good morning friends lovely to have this opportunity to be
here with you um i feel delighted to be taking
gill's place this week and to spend a little time with you
gil i'm susie harrington if you turned on your screen and expected to see gil you
now have a new person and i'll be doing the
guided meditation in dharmet this week and gil
invited me to come he specifically was hoping that i would offer some
guidance some instruction around practice in nature since
although i'm also a residential retreat teacher i particularly
enjoy and am committed to practicing outdoors and sharing that
with people in the natural world so there's
probably like many of you i spent i spend a lot of time outside when i can
and i spent years as a backcountry ranger and a lot of time hiking
and through those years i noticed something that i was outside i
was in the natural world i really loved being there
but there was still some distance some disconnect my mind still sort of ran the
show and the stories would still go in my mind and there was a
contactfulness with nature that i didn't i felt like it sort
of came in glimpses but wasn't there a lot of the time and so as i
developed my dharma practice and as i developed as a
teacher one of the things that became very important to me was this
was a curio this ongoing inquiry about how does the natural world how is
it collaborator friend participant teacher
and the the buddhist
practice is very very rooted in the natural world the buddha
was born outside became enlightened under a tree taught for
the many decades outside died outside all of those things
so it this is nothing new
this isn't something different that i'm suggesting it's that
uh bringing it into our practice as we do it now and what are the
opportunities there and how can we explore this and one of the clearest and most direct
ways in that the buddha mentioned a lot is through the practice of working with
the elements and you may be familiar with the fact that that's in the sati patana suta he
mentions the elements practice is one of the foundational practices
and he uses the elements in many other places as well
so this is the way that i'm going to explore it and offer it this week
so before we go into the guided meditation i want to read one quote that is
a lovely quote of the buddha talking to his son rahula
and making a suggested a suggestion to him about
his practice his meditation practice and this is what he says
rahula develop meditation that is like the earth
for then agreeable and disagreeable sensory impressions will not take charge
of your mind just as when people throw what is clean and unclean on the earth excrement urine
saliva pus or blood the earth is not horrified humiliated or
disgusted by it in the same way agreeable and disagreeable sensory impressions will
not take charge of your mind when you develop meditation like the earth
so as we begin to sit this is the first aspect of doing the
elements and today i'm going to introduce and work with the earth element and this is the first aspect of
it that i'd like to offer and that we can explore in our practice is this sense of stability
the groundedness we often use that phrase i wish i i feel grounded i don't
feel grounded i wish i felt more grounded and i think there's something in that what we're commenting is how
earth contactful do we feel how stable on the ground with our root with our feet as
roots in the ground that we can hold steady when what is difficult comes along
so this first practice this week will be an earth element
meditation so go ahead and find your meditation posture make yourself
comfortable and find a nice upright
posture that has a sense of dignity with it
and allow yourself to relax allow yourself to soften
relaxation in the shoulders
relaxation around the eyes
and as you settle into your posture allow yourself
to feel the contact with the ground
perhaps your feet perhaps your legs
certainly your buttocks in contact with the cushion or the
chair and whether you're literally on the ground or 10 stories up you're still in contact
with the density of the earth all the way
wherever you are it's reaching up and pulling down to you gravity is like the hug of the earth
pulling us towards it themselves
feel the pressure and the contact of that
giving yourself a few moments here at the start of the practice
to really land where you are
whatever you've already done today setting that aside
and as you land in this spot allow yourself to sense
the environment around you the space the room or the outdoors that you're in
and as we settle in i want to invite you to feel the earthiness
of yourself to feel the hardness the density that you carry
around as part of your body your body is made of earth element
so feeling perhaps first the hardness of your teeth
the hardness of your bones this skeleton that is allowing you to
sit upright we have these very dense core aspects of
us that are like a kind of mineralized rock in fact
and where this hardness meets the pull of the earth
you can feel pressure
this is the earth element earth contacting earth
your flesh too not just the bones has lots of earth element
when we eat food and digest it we're bringing in
earth moving it around changing it incorporating it in our bodies
we take in the earth and we become we are part of the earth
we come from the earth and we will return to the earth
feel the density the hardness
the pressure
of your own body sitting here and feel the contact it's making with
the earth feel how you are not so different than a boulder sitting on earth
and as you sit there realizing that you're made of earth that you're part of the earth
allow your attention to take in more fully the earth below you
have a sense also of its density its vastness and abundance
you might feel it flowing down below you almost as if you had a tap root going
down into the earth or perhaps your roots are more spreading
spreading out in all directions
let your attention flow down to the ground
perhaps even you might notice that you could grow roots down into the ground
you might even imagine that your breath comes up out of the
earth through those roots breathing up taking in the nourishment
of the earth and as you exhale letting your breath
flow back down through these roots down below you
out into the ground
feel your own weight you too are dust soil
mineral earth sitting on earth
you are earth breathing what a miraculous thing
breathing for the earth
allowing your attention to flow down
and to come back
earth sitting on earth sitting like a mountain
can you be steady feel
this stability this contactfulness with the ground
this vast and expansive and supportive ground
the earth is a vast lap of belonging
you belong here
simply because you are of this earth
it could never be otherwise
allow yourself to receive this hug this pull of the earth
relaxing the body trusting the structure
of your own skeleton this uprightness of earth sitting on
earth
you
allow yourself to rest knowing that you belong
that you are part of this earth an active walking breathing
sitting [Music] expression of earth
you
feel the density of your body the contactfulness of the pressure
the contact with ground
feel the supportive and vast density of the earth
letting your roots grow deep your breath
enlivening and further contacting
this earth
[Music]
so continuing from that earth element
and hopefully you felt as you were sitting one of the ways that we can
contact the earth earth element this way of
sensing the stability i mentioned the word contact fullness a
lot it's like we all want contact and you know we might look to other
people for contact or to situations but the contact is built right into us
we're right here in contact with ground with earth with the earth in us
all the time and in that contact with the earth
with this earth element we're also in contact with a very
this groundedness a deep equanimity
a right here-ness
so this is one of the aspects of the earth element that we can take into our
practice and we can do it practice it as we did here you can practice it when you're
walking you know if you're doing walking meditation you can feel the contact
fullness with the ground and let yourself touch
and uh let the roots of your feet go down into
the ground as if when you were walking
as if when you were walking you had you were plant moving walking
another aspect of the earth element that's very important and this is true of all the elements
is a very fundamental teaching of the buddha around not-self
and here's what he says about practicing with the earth element internal and external
he said internal and external are simply earth element
and that should be seen as it actually is with proper wisdom thus
this is not mine this i am not this is not myself
this is a very important aspect of the elements and you
heard me just touching on this in the guided meditation this recognition
that earth element is flowing through us
that we eat and we digest and it becomes part of us and
then it flows out we either shed it off our skin or we
leave it in the toilet or ultimately it all goes from our bodies when we pass
that all of the earth element that is here is only temporarily borrowed
and we can recognize oh look this is just flowing through this
is not mine this is not me there is no inside
outside it's simply earth element moving around and i'm part of the place it moves to
and when i go for a walk it's earth element going for a walk
and in this we can sense that we're part of a flow a continuity
that we are earth come alive
but we haven't separated and this is so important
we are we live in a world that is in the trauma of separation
and how do we release that belief that idea that
somehow we're separate that nature is outside earth is outside other
people are outside because when we think we're separate
that sets us up of course to abuse the
earth to view the earth as somehow something to be extracted from
to like separate and this is also leads to
separation of other people of other creatures
and otherness and so this oh look we're all made of the same
thing it's all just earth element moving around
dropping the ownership the colonial mindset that makes us think
we can own a piece of land actually the land owns us
we belong to it
another aspect so we're working on this journey towards dropping the separation and one
of the doorways to that is recognizing
the generosity the exchange is not just uh
there's not just a mechanical there's a generosity of exchange happening here
when we eat we're eating this incredible abundance of the earth
i love walking through my garden and right now there's strawberries out there
and they there's not so many that um i can pick a big basket of them but
there's just the right number that every time i walk by i can lean down and pick
one and be reminded of the abundance of the earth
and i i noticed that this is one of the things i love walking
around in the world in the natural world it's like when there's berries and you pick a raspberry
or a huckleberry or perhaps the mountains near here got a lot of
rain this summer and it's to go and look at the mushrooms and to pick the few
mushrooms that are actually edible and to just be amazed that these things come
up out of the ground and then they come into this body and we're involved in this
generous exchange and then there's simpler ways i was just
out leading a river retreat out on the river and it was hot
and the simplicity of sitting beside a boulder in the shade of it
the generosity of the boulder's shade the generosity of a tree and sitting
under it the generosity of the breeze moving the
leaves the leaves or earth element being flicked
in the breeze we can receive the generosity and the abundance
of the earth in so many ways and as we do that
we naturally have this desire to want to give back to it
to realize we're in this flow and this leads to another way
that we can recognize and participate in our earthiness
that we are the that we can take care
of the earth and everybody's felt that like when you
go out and you you know the simplest way is out in a garden or with plants
but when you make compost if you've ever done that it's quite miraculous
that you can take all these different things and you put them in a pile and they get all hot and then they
turn into the soil and earth ready to grow again
the reciprocity of taking care of places that we know
simple things picking up trash that isn't there or perhaps you write letters
or enact actively defend places
edward abbey a person from here from this area that i live in moab utah
have once said the wilderness needs no defense just more defenders
and we all can participate the generosity flowing in and flowing
out it's a reciprocal relationship
i'm going to end by reading you a short poem from rabbidranath tagore
the same stream of life that runs through my veins night and day
runs through the world and dances in rhythmic measures it is the same life that shoots in joy
through the dust of the earth in numberless blades of grass and breaks into tumultuous waves of
leaves and flowers it is the same life that is rocked
in the ocean cradle of birth and of death in ebb and in flow
[Music] i feel my limbs are made glorious by the touch of this world of life
and my pride is from the life throb of ages dancing in my blood this moment
i invite you on this day to feel your earthiness
feel your contact with the ground
feel the abundance and aliveness of being earth walking on earth
of earth breathing of belonging
of you are earth belonging to earth
thank you for coming this morning it's lovely to see i see a number of
familiar faces here in zoom and to see others and i look forward to seeing you
tomorrow if you'd like to join again thank you