so hello and welcome everyone happy hour it's lovely to be with you
this makes me happy to be uh sitting with you all and and seeing your
faces actually some of your faces this week as some of you may know i've
been uh subbing for gil for the seven a.m on youtube and it's lovely on youtube to
see the hellos from everyone though it's youtube so i don't get to see people's faces whereas on zoom and on youtube i
get to see the hellos on youtube and i see get to see your faces on zoom it just
gives me lots of delight so thank you for showing up on zoom um and supporting your own practice and
giving me delight makes me happy to see you so
so so for practice today and happy hour we
we engage with exploring meta and compassion and joy and
and equanimity in these various practices of the heart and one practice i want to invite us is
something that actually i invited folks to explore this morning and it felt so juicy i thought oh i want to
bring into the happy hour sangha also for us to explore
and whether you showed up this morning and this will be you can explore it again and deepen it or whether this is
new for you so so
so [Music] the idea of joy taking joy delight gladness gladdening
our hearts so one thing that happens often when we
are new in our practice especially when we are newer in our
practice but it can happen if we've been practicing for a while too is
is um and and then one you know the light bulb goes off one
realizes this pattern which is not a very helpful pattern and the pattern is see if you recognize
it in your own practice or from the past or present it doesn't matter no judgment
many of us do as all of us do it when we start practicing actually let's put it this way
and for a long time so the pattern is we're sitting
we're bringing our mind to the breath to the body to the object of our awareness
maybe it's mental we bring kind awareness and then
the mind like a little puppy like mark's puppy
wanders away wanders away that's what puppies do that's what minds do they
wonders away and in the little bit we find our mind resting on the thought on a memory on
the plan what to have for dinner and what we're gonna have for breakfast
it's off and then when we notice we often go bad bad mind bad puppy you
were away you were thinking come back ouch ouch
so that moment of hitting that moment of self-judgment judging our minds it takes
a while to see that it often takes a while to see that we keep doing it habitually and if we keep
doing that it actually can make the practice of meditation um
contractive can make it seem like a chore like i just don't want to meditate anymore meditation is hard and it's not
meditation that's hard it's because we keep hitting ourselves with a big stick
every time we see our mind has wandered so if you keep hitting a puppy the puppy becomes traumatized and scared like oh
so that's what happens to our mind oh i don't want to meditate anymore you keep hitting me every time
you know i wander off so so so the thing to notice every time the
mind wanders let let there be a release let there be
first of all a delight that yay yay there's a moment of wakefulness yay
yes one moment of being alert awake mindful is better
infinitely better than zero moments so yay celebrating that moment of
realizing that the mind has wandered great now i realize that the mind isn't here anymore yay
so it can be a moment of joy a moment of celebration that's one moment that one
that's one hit of joy and celebration and then there can be a second one and
here's the nuance the nuance is as we
let go as we gently release gently release and
let go kindly let that release that letting go
let that feel like an offering it's a letting go it's
it's an act of generosity it's an act of release
and celebrate that release yay as if you're offering a gift of your
release your release your letting go is a gift that you're putting on the
altar of humanity hey i let go i let go of
something that wasn't helpful in this moment yay here offering you can see it
as an art making and offering to the altar of humanity alter of your practice
it's just this gift of generosity your practice becomes an act of generosity
in that way with each release it's so each release letting go becomes a celebration a double
celebration once realizing that oh yes i'm awake yes i'm here i'm here in the second
celebration of letting go so is that clear
i'm gonna before we actually start meditating i'm just gonna pause and make sure the instructions are clear actually
you know i will say it again during the guided meditation so so in this way
the invitation is to explore delight joy
of the heart of the heart releasing of the heart letting go the first time
mind heart awakening to that oh yes yes i'm awake i'm here i'm mindful i
know that the mind is thinking about something yes yay
one moment of wakefulness is better than being lost the whole time so celebrating
taking join that number two that release that letting go is to be
celebrated it's an act of generosity of letting go of what is not helpful in
this moment so as much as this makes sense try it on for size and if it doesn't
it's okay too you can just simply be with the breath and the body and
take delight in being present as much as you are present with
in in this moments in this moment being here so
so all of that let's practice together let's try this on for size
so landing arriving arriving in your chair
on your cushions
arriving in the body
awareness
awareness loving awareness
with loving interest turned inward
with gentleness turned
to the contact points of this body and the earth
letting your bottom
feel the cushion
the support
your feet feeling the earth your legs
feeling the earth if you're on the cushion
taking time to feel this body all the contact points all the sensations that
draw your attention in your own time
all the nooks and crannies let the breath visit all the tight nooks and
crannies from your feet from your toes up to the
top of your head
as if you're a pop-up balloon or a pop-up doll that's out of air
breath coming in the breath with awareness inflating
filling all the areas
of the body filling you up with loving awareness
anywhere there is tension especially or tightness
breathed into a beach ball being inflated
not crinkly contracted
anymore
feeling the deflated pop up doll of your body
ah with the breath with loving awareness and all the
nooks and crannies in your own time
fingers toes foreign
maybe i'll name some sections your head your face
all the areas
each breath
felt enlivened
maybe you notice the creases on your forehead smooth out
your face your head your neck feels more filled out with awareness loving
awareness
let yourself enjoy this process it's kind of fun
brushing each area with loving awareness from the inside
as if breathing life into it
your chest build up
breathe in
your arms your wrists your hands your fingers
back to your trunk your chest and your abdomen lower abdomen
do
from your lower abdomen feeling breathing breathed into
your sit bones your groin area
your upper lips breathe into
enlivened loving awareness
your knees
lower legs and feet
a beach ball becoming inflated
enlivened hmm
filled with life of awareness
letting the mind and heart feel expensive the entire body
enjoying [Music] being breathed
each breath
and at any point if you notice the mind is resting
and a thought memory plan entanglement entangled
celebrate that yeah i noticed yes i'm noticing though
i'm awake in this moment
i'm aware taking delight
the brightness of awareness
as you gently relinquish let go
release as you release
the entanglement
celebrating not letting go it's like a generosity
celebrating that release
and putting it on the altar of your practice yay another moment of release awareness
and release to rejoice in to celebrate in my
training
with the mind is calm spacious delighting and rejoicing
feeling of awareness and presence in this moment if the mind wanders off
rejoicing and delighting becoming aware
whenever you do delighting in the release
noticing how you feel lighter the heart feels lighter
the mind feels lighter with each release each letting go
to be celebrated
each moment of your practice as an offering to yourself and others
a gift
this
so if you were tuning a radio can you tune into the joy the delight
of sitting being breathed perhaps there is a level of peace
available that's joyous comforting
delightful or if the mind gets
carried away here and there tune into the release the joy of letting go
oh and how much lighter the heart the mind feels every time you let go how
delightful that is tuning into the delight the joy
the pleasantness of this of different aspects of this practice
you
remember to stay embodied feeling the sensations of the body
not to get too top heavy center of gravity being
down in your lower abdomen or sit bones not in your head
notice the delight and the release the lightness
the happiness of letting go
especially if there are judgments you can't do this you're distracted this
is terrible i'm bored if you gently notice these
delight that you've seen them then release
ah just let go
if you're releasing a balloon see how much lighter you feel releasing
releasing unkind
contracted entanglements
and for the last moment of this practice
appreciating yourself delighting that you showed up
if there are any judgments releasing them releasing
letting go seeing how much lighter the heart and mind can feel and delighting in this
release let's release this letting go
is a generosity to yourself and offering
the altar of your practice may our practice be of service of
benefit to all beings everywhere including ourselves may all beings be free may all beings be happy
thank you for your practice everyone
so so much here
so today we began with settling arriving [Music]
slightly differently embodiment bringing in a sense of embodiment
with as if we were breathing as if we're being breathed
this as if loving awareness is a breath kind of bringing those two ideas
together breathing into our bodies i brought up the image of a pop-up doll
that's deflated and little by little areas of the body get get inflated
um with the breath with loving awareness
and um and so that was the first part and
and finding the delight the joy that ease of just feeling
oh this energetically this body that's full of breath and
life energy so i'm curious how that was for you if you'd like to share about that part
also um there then we transitioned if there was
thoughts distractions entanglements in the mind to number one
notice them and take delight in noticing not judge yourself for having been lost
but yay i'm noticing now celebrating that moment of awakeness
and number two when you release noticing the
lightness the delight the joy of release it's just this act of generosity to
yourself this this gift of practice feeling lighter so
so i can say more but i'd love to hear from you especially if you haven't spoken for a while please file it
hey nikki hi um i had
very strong very challenging emotions come up during this set
i think a lot because just sitting down and being quiet a lot
of stuff that had accumulated over the day over the week over the months came up
and the perspective of like
finding joy or delight in it it's like there was joy in just having
an emotion or having a sensation like in and of itself was like
wow i'm able to feel sad like i have a body that feels this emotion like
that's nice like that's a nice thing it's preferable to feel something than to not
feel anything um it's it feels nice to have a big feeling as opposed to like
most of my life which is having small feelings and then a lot of like tension and contraction and holding
to keep it small and to not let it get big um [Music] and then
even just like crying i mean crying is kind of physically
pleasurable in some ways like tears in eyes on cheeks like it kind of feels nice like
there's some there's some joy and physical pleasure in that too so
i liked that sort of permission and container of joy
for fear and sadness and range and the other stuff so thank you
thank you violet thank you so much for sharing such beautiful
touching profound report of your practice and it's absolutely profound i hope you
realize how profound this shift in perspective is that you've
cultivated holding your practice holding what arises
with appreciation oh yes it's it's lovely to feel it's it's defining
the delight the pleasure in the tears all of that is is just profound to make space for all of it to
be as it is the challenging emotions and all you're not pushing anything aside i
didn't hear that holding it all and tuning into the delight the the gift that it is to feel
and i am so touched inspired with with the beautiful
profound profound profundity of what you're sharing in your practice violet thank
you it's beautiful thank you
any other reflections please especially if you haven't shared for a
while you can also type in chat or raise your hand kneel please
so you said all right that when you become aware you should you know
take joy that you're awake first not being awake and then i think you said something about offering making an offering
um could you yeah i'm not quite sure what you meant by that
yeah yeah so so two parts of this practice i'm suggesting
so the first is as you named taking delight that yes you're awake now yay that's part one
and part two is as the mind releases as the mind lets go
right there's a movement internal movement that you're familiar with like okay this is not profitable not helpful
ah release release ah notice in that release
right in that release there's there is an open-handedness there is this aspect
of generosity opening up letting go in the let's say in that letting go
there is a delight there is a lightness the mind feels lighter heart feels
lighter okay and in that release when you really when you let go of something that's not
helpful that letting go is is an offering it's a gift it's like yay here i am cultivating
that cultivating my heart my mind in goodness so that's the offering that release that
letting go is the offering is the act of generosity for yourself for others
and i was imagining putting that on the altar of of humanity or practice here it is my
gift of releasing yay does that make sense think so
great yeah thank you thank you lovely i'm so glad you asked though that
i get the chance to clarify even more it's it can be very profound practice
there are lots of pieces to it little pieces to it but it's it can be so much fun
both the lightness the lightness of the heart when the release happens and yay this delight
like wow celebrating that so
so dear ones the time has come for us to
to turn into small groups practice together in
in small communities of size three roughly on zoom and
um and i create the rooms in the moment and
the invitation is to um again start with 15 seconds of meta silent meta for
yourselves for each other and then share as little or as much as you'd like
to share about this practice about both parts of them and you know there's no right or wrong it was i was confused or
i was sleepy or it was lovely it was profound it's all good you hold each
other with care the support of the sangha is in this beautiful sangha so
so i'm opening the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other here we go
okay and all the rooms are closed everyone welcome back
and we have a few minutes for any reflections comments questions
um yeah
so
so please don't be shy would love to hear your reflections questions comments
anything that came up
yes please um see i see don and i see lisa don since
you more recently spoke than lisa lisa you went away what happened
okay here you go we'll take lisa and then don
i'm here hello yes hear you yes um
i noticed that yeah i was really distracted but then
i just kept going into thoughts and it felt kind of thick like up here
but then i noticed it was like your voice came and was like oh hi distracted mind
and then i noticed all of my the rest of my body that was here and seemed to not have a problem
with it i was like wait my leg is just there and it seems fine like it's not
wanting to be somewhere else or thinking about anything my hands are there and they're okay and i was like wow
because it felt like it was here i was like there's so much of my body that just seems fine right now to just like
be here and it was kind of like a light moment and i had never like thought that way
before about it so thank you thank you lisa that's that's wonderful i
love the way this this whole different way of seeing which it is unusual and and it's
profound like oh yes there's this embodiment there's this sense of stability of the body the body is here
it grounds and it's here it doesn't want to go anywhere it's it's the sense of groundedness that comes through as if
the body has its own wisdom and is speaking to you hello we're here no need to go anywhere
so it's that's lovely that that's a rising for you as a shift as a way to be grounded in your body
lovely thank you for that and jerry says it was great to see loving kindness within the loving
kindness towards the person trying to do loving kindness that's great
so many levels and don do you want to quickly make your comment i'll make a minute for you where did you go
i don't see your hand anymore i can't unmute you if i don't see you uh so tell you what you're welcome to unmute
yourself if you want or if you want to pass that's okay too
okay all right so i hear that you're passing so with that let's uh
let's bring our time together to a close thank you all
thank you for your practice thank you for showing up for supporting
each other yourself stepping forward stepping back that's also very wise
thank you all may ah our practice support the awakening of
ourselves and all beings everywhere may be of service may all beings be well may all beings be happy
thank you