so the reference point for these early morning
teachings are the 16 steps of
mindfulness of breathing
and these 16 steps appear linear
without any indication that there are difficulties or
challenges or bumps on the road as we do this practice
it also gives the impression that the beginning of them the first few steps
might be beginnings they might be for beginners and the idea is as a good practitioner you
would matter factually linearly move step by step through the 16 steps and
and then wonder step 16 what's next
but in some ways the first few steps certainly are beginning steps but they also are
advanced steps for people who live a human life with all its
vagaries all its ups and downs and all its challenges
and this practice of mindfulness is not meant to be a avoidance of being a full human being
with all the emotions and concerns that human being encounters
but rather to be able to face anything
with wisdom and so these first steps of anapanasati
are also a way of not avoiding things but also not
be caught in their grip not by not be lost in them
so to breathe mindfully in the middle of what's actually happening for us
maybe in the beginning being somewhat simple and
with the breathing not to avoid but to
prepare the ground to be present without
preoccupation in the steps three and four steps three is feeling the whole body
and this i think is so important when we start feeling the whole body we
feel the physical expressions of all our troubles
how they're actually registered or expressed or processed in the body
if we're feeling sad or angry we can feel it in the body if we're
excited or lethargic we can feel it in the body
if we're spinning around in all kinds of thoughts and concerns and fantasies and
memories and plans there's an art to feeling that in the
body what's the physical feeling with the physic physical sensations
that come with that and so to feel the body as we breathe it
will be an encounter being present for all the challenges we
have and all the joys we have in how they're felt in the body
i think of it sometimes as whatever the challenges might be how is it for the body
and let the body compost them let the body process them
we don't have to figure it out we don't have to solve things when we meditate
but to trust and rely on being present for whatever is
happening in its bodily physical expression
which is always in the present moment
and then to breathe with that to breathe through it to continue breathing in and breathing
out and this is a little bit of a protection and why it's an advanced practice
a protection from getting swept off in thoughts reactions
needing to do something about things just letting it be in the body feel it
breathe with it and when the time is right
to also relax around what's happening relax with what's going on
not to get rid of it but to settle in with it more deeply
so to take your meditation posture and to close your eyes
and to take a moment before doing anything else in checking in with yourself
how are you
and uh and whatever way you are whatever way you answer the question how are you
how is that in the body
how's that expressed how's that felt
what's the physical what's physically is
activated and to take a few moments to feel that
the body body side
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths right into the middle of it
as if you're breathing right in the middle of how you are maybe feeling it more fully
as you breathe in and relaxing as you exhale
and if how you are is something positive feel that as you
breathe in spread it as you exhale
if something what you're you're feeling something challenging
feel that as in your body as you breathe in
and then as you exhale bring some ease ease up
soften around the challenge
and as we sit here this morning is today
regularly refer back to your body for whatever is happening for you if you're involved in thoughts
caught up in feelings emotions just keep coming back and feel it
through your body from the vantage point of your body what
is this is what is this experience like and breathe with that
breathe through it breathe with it
sooner or later noticing also the physical feelings of thinking or
physical feelings of mental activity and then be content to just feel it
and breathe with it everything in your body
feel it there
and as you sit here meditating if it's possible put aside
any hint any feeling idea atmosphere
that you're not doing it quite right and substitute it with the atmosphere
the mood the idea that you're doing just fine
and then settle into your body breathing
refer everything to your body and breathe with that
breathing with whatever is happening for you whatever way you are
breathing through it breathing with it
gently feeling it at all in your body
letting the body receive your life
there's a way in which the physical experience is
quiet in that in and of itself it doesn't involve thing does not involve
thinking and to feel the quiet
of whatever manifests in the body
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to whatever degree it's easy for you continue to rest your attention
in the quiet of the body
the physicality the physical feelings this the sensations of your body
breathing with them sitting with them
that aspect of them which are physical experiences not thinking
and thoughts and ideas not even reactions to them
but in the simplicity of how your body experiences itself
how the body expresses
whatever years going on for you thoughts and feelings reactions
make room in your body to feel it
and then in the same way that you make a room for yourself
stay with your body but open your body and your mind your
awareness to the world around you
to the room you're sitting in the building you're in the neighborhood
the district the town or province county
and one of the great gifts we can give to others is our ability to be present for them
with all of who we are just as we being present for ourselves
to allow ourselves to feel physically empathy
to feel physically how people impact us
what happens for us in our body without contracting necessarily or
wanting it to be different
and then from this settled place to gaze upon all things kindly
to know how to be in your body and to be still insensitive
and gaze upon all things with good will
to allow our gaze of our eyes to allow the sensitivity of our hearts
warmth of our hearts
to be concerned with the welfare and happiness of others
to be well wishing for others
be still and gaze upon all things kindly
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
so
so i think it's fairly well known for many people that one of the core
in the buddhist view one of the core sources of suffering has to do with clinging or
craving and that clinging is described many ways sometimes it's simply called a
stickiness that we there's a stickiness a glue that keeps us attached to things sometimes it's called
a knot uh you knot it up in things it's sometimes called the fetter in the
translation for the pali word but it literally means a not to be knotted up and we say that colloquially
in english it was all knotted up in something and the uh
the uh expression rather from a japanese teacher that i really liked was um uh the fist in the heart
or the fist in the mind and that we're trying to open the fist of the heart so it's not all fisted up
or closed up tightened up and so there's many many languages for this many many ways of
talking about this way we cling or crave and part of the function of practice is
to reveal the ways that we cling the ways that we are knotted up and sometimes it's pretty
evident right away sometimes as we go further and further along in the practice
we start seeing aspects of being knotted up being caught by things in ways that um
we didn't know at all maybe more subtle or deeper somehow inside and
in some ways the the the movement through the path of practice is a continual movement of encountering
and then releasing encountering and untying all the different ways that
things are sticky with things we hold on to things or cling to things or resist things
and and so when we run into these things in ourselves it's you know some people have this
instinct to feel bad about themselves or criticize themselves it's also possible to see it as oh good
this is what it this is the path forward knowing these things is part of the path it's how we go
forward and that's one interpretation i have for why this practice of anapanasati
is so simple in its explanation is that it's not meant to avoid
or not recognize that we're attached or clinging or there's all these challenges we kind of come along the way
but it's not supposed to avoid it but it's offering us a very simple way of moving through it
without making a big deal of it because they're not mentioned and rather than getting caught up in the
stories or the idea of me myself and mine in relationship to it
that is to be really really simple of course those things are there
and uh and uh and then how simple can we be in a way that's
genuine beneficial honest
and healing or freeing as we go through and so i i see the simplicity of the way
this beginning of anapanasati works as a way of really addressing all these
clinging all the challenges all the strong feelings emotions we have all the ways in which the mind
gets knotted up fisted up caught up in things and concerned with things
and but without uh without kind of getting involved
getting entangled with it even further so to just simply stay breathing
through it all whatever's going on breathe and i think i said this yesterday that there's something about hanging in
there with the rhythm of breathing that keeps them i call it sometimes the great lubricator
it keeps things lubricated so they don't get rusted up or or squeaky or or something frozen up
or it's a massage that we're massaging stuff for it's um it's a way of kind of by staying
with that gentle rhythm of breathing it's a little bit easier for the mind not to get caught by something
because if you're cut caught you've lost touch with the breathing but if you were touched with the breathing then there's something we're
taking being with that's kind of this lubricant or this massage the concerns the feelings we have
haven't gone away necessarily but it's the knotted up the stickiness the preoccupation with them
that's loosened up and then something else begins to happen if we free our concerns our emotions our
challenges even our suffering if we free it from our preoccupation
from our resistance the stories the opinions the predictions about it what it means
that it's there are pushing it away or validating it or
justifying it or apologizing for it all these complicated things we do all those perpetuated somehow
and if we just could learn to leave it alone but without denying it just leave it
alone let it be there and leave it alone from all this extra stuff we had
the heart knows how to heal the mind knows how to unfold in the same way that if
you cut your finger with a kitchen knife for example chopping vegetables
it's a complicated physiological process to heal that cut but we don't have to worry
about that the body heals itself if all we have to do is keep the cut clean
so so much of the angst the suffering the challenge the grief that we have to respect it deeply
not to and in really respected leave it alone without
stickiness without clinging without being knotted to it and this mindfulness of breathing uh
the implicit idea in this practice is that actually that mindfulness of breathing allows that freedom leaves allows us to
leave things alone and then as the practice goes along to
feel the mental formations of the the fit the bodily formations to feel the physical
activity expressions manifestations of the mind manifestations over responses or
thoughts or feelings it's such a powerful thing it's a way again of
being present for the all the difficulties and joys of life but to be present for it physically
without the stickiness without being four against in the clinging and it's a way of kind of begin to
loosen up the stickiness just to feel it in your body the body is not a story and so much of
the stickiness has to do with the story making mind the opinions the ideas predictions
and then on top of that the panasonic says relax or tranquilize make tranquil this
body and for me this idea of relaxing calming the body
is not really meant to avoid anything but it's beginning to relax the ways in which we
hold things the way we hold on or knotted up it's the knots that we're
letting go of and as the knots get let go the entanglements let go then
what we're feeling inside the challenges we have can begin to move and resolve themselves
and relax and it can be very different perspective
and sometimes we don't solve our problems but we dissolve them in this way some of the external
problems we have in life the real things that we have to take care of don't go away this way but we can put
ourselves in a much better position more creative more intelligent more wise
more loving to address them when we go through this deep process of letting go of the stickiness the craving
that we have so i think it's kind of a radical thing
with this practice that it actually doesn't talk about these challenges directly
because we don't have to address them directly if we do this steps of anapanasati
they just kind of get taken care of on the side or get taken care of because we're making
space to in releasing the stickiness the knots that we have
and that process continues into the second set of four instructions where we become
aware of the mental formations the mental activities the thoughts that we have and then we
calm those down and calming means let go of the stickiness like oh the tightness the
constrictions that are there the pressure that's there it can't be done all at once and all of
it but the beginning is process of letting go of the stickiness of settling the mind
and this also is not to avoid the mental problems but to but to let go of the stickiness
the fetters that are there so
to repeat myself i think it's a radical thing that this anapanasati does not talk address directly the challenges we
have in practice but it's not because they're being ignored
it's i would like to propose is because it's offering a very realistic very
effective process by which they can be resolved or dissolved or
we can find our way with them without having to address them directly when you know as in the usual ways the
mind wants to do that our heart wants to do that so um so as you practice
and when you find yourself with these challenges that could happen
no the practice is a response to it this ways of addressing it and perhaps being
content and willing to do so indirectly and for some of us it's a radical thing
to not feel like we have to fix and address everything directly but we can
just relax settle back and trust the process as we go move along
on this path so thank you and i look forward to
being again with you tomorrow