and offer my warm greetings
and and
one of the things to appreciate as we do
buddhist meditation
to buddhist practice is liberation
itself and freedom
and liberation freedom takes many forms
some of them we don't associate with the
grand
words like liberation and and
freedom and the
so things like relaxation calming
but as we relax the body and relax the
mind as we comment
these things there is a letting go we're
releasing of ways that the body and mind
has been tight been clinging been
contracted
and that's a variation of the
more more
i don't know to say some more
significant forms of releasing of
clinging
which is the buddhist liberation
to become liberated to become
enlightened is to really have very deep
letting go
a deep releasing of clinging right down
to the core of our being
and um and so it's all a variation it's
all
a range a spectrum of releasing
something
that we're talking about here and so we
relax the body and we
and then to appreciate don't just relax
the body as we
start to meditate but appreciate the
consequences of the relaxation
the the the relief the openness the ease
the space the
the likeness uh the
the release of vitality that might come
with relaxation
uh when we relax the mental formations
relax the mental activity the tensions
and the contractions of the mind
uh it's not just a matter of relaxing it
it's also appreciating the consequence
of that
greater ease or lightness or space or or
openness that might be there and so
also when we let go of thinking that
that some people let go of thinking and
immediately go back to the breathing
as if but just take a few moments
to let go of thinking and to appreciate
whatever goodness that comes from the
space the openness the
lack of contraction lacks of tightness
the
lack of compulsion that might be there
in the letting go
of the thoughts and so one of the ways
of practicing meditation then at some
point as we settle in further
is to just appreciate letting go letting
go
letting go of anything the mind wants to
pick up on or get involved in
and just let go any kind of attention to
any kind of pulling attention to
emotions and thoughts
as much as we respect these and include
them as part of meditation
there is an art to also letting go of
any
preoccupation with them any
prioritization of them any
extra interest or even any in interest
in them
everything is allowed to be as it is
we're not dismissing anything what we're
really letting go of
is the clinging to things the tightening
and the tension around
what's happening so at some point
meditation just the process of letting
go
letting go letting go
and and uh so
assuming a meditation posture
and
i often suggest closing the eyes at the
beginning of meditation
and as you do so you might take a moment
to see if you can appreciate how the
relief for the eyes
not to be engaged in looking and seeing
maybe there's a that gives a kind of a
rest for the eyes
and if the eyes are not don't feel
restful
maybe it's possible to
um to
let the eyes eyes rest in their sockets
almost as if you're looking down
and backwards and then taking a few
somewhat deeper breaths so you can
really
let go and relax on the exhale
really emphasizing softening the body
calming the agitations of the body
and then letting the breath return to
normal
and then to
as you exhale to continue to relax
the body calm the body
but to take a few moments to feel
the goodness whatever nice feelings this
greater vitality that come from relaxing
feel the resulting calmness tranquility
in that part of your body
relaxing the shoulders the belly
the face
sometimes it's possible to relax the
whole body
and sometimes it's possible to calm
a body-wide feeling of agitation
a calming
wave through the body with as you exhale
and also gently tenderly as you exhale
to relax any agitation
calm any agitation in the mind the
mental activity
letting go relaxing any tension or
contraction
in the mind or in the or in that part of
the body associated with your mental
activity
to calm
the agitation of the mind
and then to let go of your thoughts
or at least let go of your involvement
with your thinking
they appreciate
that there's more space in the mind to
be aware
when we let go of our thinking
and let that space of awareness
be filled with the experience of
breathing
breathing in and breathing out
and then as we continue sitting this
morning
with every exhale
say the word letting go
let go not as a command
but as a invitation
for us to let go of something
that the mind is has taken up
to let go of the energy of holding on
or picking up or being involved in
anything at all
just let go
and on the inhale appreciate
the goodness the spaciousness the
openness
of that letting go
letting go and the exhale
appreciating
the good results of letting go
and just keep letting go
as if for these minutes meditation
everything that arises
everything that you know nurses known
is another thing to let go of
to be open and fresh for the next moment
just let go
let go
let go as if letting go is the most
important thing to do nothing to hold on
to
nothing to be concerned about
just let go
so
what are you not letting go of
what can you still let go of to be
thorough
and letting go
um
so
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting
perhaps to appreciate
the greater letting go there is
the more space there is
for love
the more space there is for good will
kindness
tenderness
the more there is the opposite of love
the less room
there is for love
the more time and space is taken up with
clinging
and reacting and being preoccupied
they're less time there is less space
there is for friendliness
not the love or friendliness that
is an obligation or something we have to
muster up
but rather something deeper more
simple and that comes out of the
tenderness
gentleness
of our hearts our minds
to let go
so that without work and without
obligation
we can receive other people into our
hearts
in the place where there's tender
friendliness
sometimes in buddhism there's an
expression
tender compassion
and again without any obligations or
is there a place in your heart
in the simplicity of being here having
let go
where your heart's tender good will
could if it wanted to be expressed in
the words
may others be
happy
may others be safe
may others be peaceful
may others be free
and may i live a life
that supports that to happen
may this meditation practice we've done
together today
may it be so that we can live a life
that benefits
and supports the welfare and happiness
of all beings
may all beings be happy
and free
[Music]
you