so good day and good evening
good morning to everyone and it's a
it's a funny thing to be sharing here and now with
different time zones and different places it's a wonderful way that here can be
at different time zones or now can be at different time zones at the
same time something like that so um
i think it's uh maybe useful to i think that
human beings are using their imagination all the time
and imagination is more subtle than
flights of fantasy and this but rather it's the little uh images
that we have of what's going to happen what did happen imaginings when we
we imagine people when we meet them we imagine things about them we imagine what's going to happen
tomorrow and and sometimes these imaginings are detrimental they undermine us
especially if they're they are kind of frightening or disturbing
imaginations that we do over and over and over again they kind of slowly kind of begin to
create a mood a disposition and almost maybe sometimes
even a personality by this the constancy of what we imagine
and so meditation practice is certainly a wonderful time to learn how to put
down some of the imaginings that we do so when we let go of thoughts we are also letting go of imaginations
when we come back into the present moment we're letting go of or what we imagine or assume will be
tomorrow or other times other places but we can also use imagination to give us a
kind of a little edge a little clear clarity about uh um stay here be present
write this out and uh you know so i've used the lots of
analogies over time and these analogies are all acts of imagination it gives us a sense a feeling for
kinesthetic and association that can we give a better sense of what it means like to stay with something
continuously than if the instructions are okay sit down and stay with your breath and don't leave it
but this idea of riding a scooter and and every time that your mind
wanders off we come we push back into the present moment and then we coast along on the present
moment until we need to kind of come back again and push again
or if we're staying with the breathing the imagination that we are it's like waves
and as i've done frequently and or like we're surfing on the waves the in-breath
is the lifting of the lifting us up and on the wave and then the out breath we're surfing the front of it
going down or maybe not surfing just simply kind of gently being lifted
and falling when my son was quite small had trouble sleeping i
sometimes had him imagine that he was an author floating on its back to sleep at
night and top of a wonderful peaceful sea and the kelp forest all
around underneath and that the and the gentle kind of swells would come up and down and that with his
breathing he was the otter that was being lifted and settled lifted and settled with
each wave and generally then after a while he'd fall asleep
and so all these little acts of imagination that not to put us asleep here but to
encourage us to stay here this is what it's like so as i said yesterday the buddha gave
one for uh for breath meditation
which is that of a lathe worker holding the lathe knife i guess or the
chisel so that against the wood that's going around in the lathe
and in order to cut the wood properly the chisel has to be in continuous contact with the wood
that's how it it chisels away and so i guess this idea of a lathe
turning around and around was the buddha's analogy for the cycles of in-breath and out-breath
and the awareness somehow is like the chisel where the kind of the point of awareness
is really centered someplace with the breathing and then it doesn't leave it just stays
there stays there and stays connected so this goes around and around
and um and if that kind of image doesn't mean much for you an image that
when i was when i was in college i took a massage course and the instruction was that if we had
to get more oil to put on more you know for the massage to continue with the massage
to never lose physical contact with the person getting the massage so you have to always keep one hand on
this you know touching the person's arm or something as you reach for the oil and put it on your hand and so this idea of
always staying in touch and contact and contact and touch i interpret to be
the physicality of breathing the physical experience just stay there with
your chisel or stay there with your hand stay there on the waves riding up and down
so don't be busy with all those images but these are images that can be used
one of them maybe speaks to you and uh if using the image is better than the
alternative meaning that you it's you're less likely to wander off into thoughts and
imaginations which are not supportive for you then stay with the image until the image
no longer is needed and you're able to stay there with the with the breathing
so taking a meditation posture and gently closing your eyes
and even saying the word gently closing your eyes and hadn't thought about it but also
evokes the imagination the idea of gentle gentling
and maybe has value that travels beyond just the eyes
and then sitting quietly and gently the body
shifting gears so that you are settling down into your body your embodied experience
and taking a few long slow deep breaths big swells big waves that lift you up
expand you and then down the other side of the wave
as you exhale relaxing your body
and letting your breathing return to normal
and then softening relaxing parts of your body and as each parts of your body relax
imagine it's becoming soft like a cotton ball
relaxing the muscles of the face
softening the shoulders
and softening the belly
and also as you exhale softening the mind
quieting the mind
distilling the mind into a soft
place and if any part of your body mind feels
hard brittle maybe it's your awareness which is like
a soft cotton ball it gently supports or holds
whatever is hard challenging
and then to settle into the body's experience of
breathing
and feeling the sensations physical sensations that come into play as you breathe
the sensations of inhale are different than the sensations of exhaling
and then settling in to stay with the sensations of breathing
and so some continuity like you would a chisel against the bowl being lathed
or like the continuous contact of the waves is once flowed someone's
back on the gentle swells of the ocean lifting up and lifting down
or the continuous stroke of a masseuse yes as we receive a massage from the
inside as the lungs expand and contract as a
diaphragm pushes and releases
and settling in gently steadily
see if you can have continuity
with the breathing letting the thinking mind become quieter
softer stiller
so the center of gravity of attention shifts from thinking
to breathing
as if breathing is the center of the
universe if breathing is
home for these minutes that we're meditating
riding the waves of breathing
letting go of imaginary futures imaginary
other places the imagination
of things which are not here and now and to use the imagination instead
to be intimate with our lived experience of here
allowing yourself to feel whatever satisfaction or gladness
that comes from not being lost in thought so much
not perpetuating thoughts which are undermine you
trouble you glad to be intimate here now
perhaps even allowing yourself to feel the joy
of just being alive breathing just content sitting here breathing
feeling embodying yourself
the more that we are preoccupied in thought distracted by thinking
the more that we're lost in imagination
the less in touch we are with others
the less we are distracted the less we're preoccupied
the better what's best in us can come forth to meet other people
love gratitude
compassion friendliness all shine all flow most easily
most manifest when we are not distracted
not preoccupied when we are present for others
that's the vehicle that's the channels by which our positive attitudes
manifest and may it be that to whatever degree
that you're more settled more intimate with yourself
calmer clear from this meditation
may that register for you may you take that in feel that
and imagine how you can stay this way
or stay close to it so that your warmth for others
can be palpable expressed your love your compassion
your kindness can better flow
may it be that what you learn about being non-distracted
supports you
in greater goodwill for the people around you
known and unknown strangers and intimates
may it be that what you learn through this
practice is a means by which you live a life that
betters the life of others in small ways in big ways
in intentional ways and unintentional ways
may the benefit of the merit of our practice together be for the welfare and
and support of all beings everywhere may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
so we've taken a little bit of a pause of moving through the next steps
of the 16 steps of mindfulness or breathing to
really look a little bit more deeply at this particular way in which the mind works
the use of imagination in the mind and i'll talk a little bit more about
specifically the buddha's use of this word imagination and i've read sometimes people say that
there's no poly word for imagination but there actually is it's a little bit
of translator's choice but i think there's a good argument i'll talk about it tomorrow
the words that have to do with it and they have a lot to do with um they also relate to this idea of
self and not self which is so important in buddhism but for
today i want to uh so this is kind of pausing to look imagination is a is a preparation for next week when we
start looking at um the mind more carefully and what goes on in the mind the mental
activity but to create the right conditions for supporting
investigation and a deeper letting go in the mind is part of the function of this earlier
parts of anapanasati mindfulness of breathing and to to the more sense of well-being
that can come in meditation the easier it's going to be to really work with the mind
there's a i've told the story many times but i love the story
of when my son was in kindergarten
once a week they would play with beeswax with a little wax and um
and uh when it was time for them to play they would actually been sitting up on the shelf and it would be um usually when
the form or whatever animal they made the week before and they would it would be hard and
being hard it would be brittle and the only thing you can do with any of it would be to break it and a little animal legs can be broken
off easy enough for something but what they would be instructed to do every week would be
to put the little the piece of wax they had in the palm between the palms of their two hands and just hold it there
while the teacher told the story and by the time the story was over
the warmth of their hands had softened the beeswax so that the or whatever kind of wax it
was and so that they um then they would then they could make these beautiful little figures animal figures or
whatever it was they made but you had to have the warmth to soften it so the same thing with the mind and
the heart in order to make it into something beautiful to move it towards freedom
it helps to soften it and warm it up and the the the the good feelings the
calmness the joy the happiness the well-being the contentment the calmness that we sit
in um are all the kind of creating the right conditions
to begin softening the mind so the mind can be more pliable more
flexible more malleable in the best possible way so that the healthy mind the healthy
functioning of the mind can operate smoothly and easily
so on the way to do that the cultivation of these deeper states of well-being that
come in meditation the the mind is actually used to do that
the mind is always being used the mind is being used to apply the attention uh to sustain the attention
but it's also used to it can be used supported by the imagination and the
buddha uses a lot of similes and and rather than thinking about them as being
active and intentional uses of imagination when we sit down to meditate it's more like we learn those similes
internalize them well enough so that they're kind of in the background of the mind so the mind associates meditation with
those similes in a kind of a natural way the similes create kind of a positive kind of view
orientation that supports us to be present now it's very easy
to have lots of uh imagination which is
not so helpful we can carry a lot of unconscious and conscious associations
bias fears projections onto our experience so that
it's we kind of are creating kind of an unhealthy or unsupportive environment
for our practice the simple imagination that i'm a lousy meditator
i can never do this that's also kind of an imagination it's kind of an
idea a thought that creates a certain atmosphere which is a little bit something in
extreme forms is a self-fulfilling prophet prophecy if we're completely preoccupied by the
idea that i cannot meditate then you probably can't because of because of that preoccupation
and and so there's you know there's also fear like there's people who uh there's fear
what's gonna happen if i open my heart in meditation if i relax and really feel what's here and there might be some good reasons to
have some caution but um to have chronic anxiety and then kind of vague imaginary ideas of
why or what's going to happen um it doesn't it's not really supportive for the process of deepening and meditation
we have to be wise about that anxiety and caution not not feel not not feel bad about having it it's
there for reasons but we want to try to work with it and find another way of being
so when the buddha offers all these similes he's uh providing he's kind of seeding
in the mind associations and imaginary associations which then begin
to create a different atmosphere for what we're doing and what meditation is about
so whether we bring up these these imaginations actively or we just let them sit there
in the background both of those are supported by really knowing these similes knowing these
imaginary kind of scenarios
so this comes into particular play with the deepening of concentration what's called genres
deepening states of absorption that really kind of really kind of settling in and really being present
in a clear continuous way almost like there's a state shift so that oh now i'm here i'm present it's
clear i'm here and the buddha doesn't give a lot of in descriptions
kind of prose descriptions of these states he describes a little bit but
but to really get a feel for what the buddha is talking about he provides similes almost ever many
times he talks about describes what they are he then follows up with a simile for each of the four of these absorptions
and these similes if you kind of feel your way into it and and kind of um let it kind of live
in the feeling of it or the sense of it or almost imagine that you are the simile in some way
then something begins to be kind of an atmosphere and a context is being formed
an association that awakens something inside of us that's not the imagination but rather
the felt sense of what the buddha is pointing to so the imaginations for
uh these similes for deep states of concentration where there's a lot of well-being
um use three of them use water as part of the
simile and often in the kind of symbolism of the buddha
water represents the mind and and perhaps the clarity of the mind or
the awareness itself of the mind i think maybe awareness maybe more than the mind
and um and so we're getting a sense of how to work with awareness or how to
relate to the awareness or how to notice uh qualities or aspects of awareness as we settle in into the
practice and um so um so there are four of these and i want to
read the the similes for you and maybe you could kind of let it sink in
for you and kind of imagine that you're somehow this you can feel this with your body or
feel it with inside the first one begins with an assembly
that's very much with in modern world maybe we would associate it with making dough with flour where you
sprinkle water onto the dough until and and and knead the the water in
until it's the all the whole all the flour is moist and in the ancient world it has to do
with making a certain kind of powder soap powder that they had and making that into a kind of a bald
so just as a skilled bath person or a bath person's
apprentice heaps bath powder in a metal basin
and sprinkling it sprinkling it gradually with water kneads it until the moisture wets one's
ball of bath powder soaks its and pervades it inside and out yet the ball itself does
not ooze so too a practitioner makes the joy and happiness born of seclusion
drench steep fill and pervade this very body so there's no part of one's whole body
unpervaded with a joy and happiness born of seclusion so here there's awareness in kind of my
kind of description that's that's that comes along with joy and happiness
so with sitting in meditation there's feelings of well-being and then one big gently kind of needs it
massages it or or spreads it or expands it through the whole body so no part of the
body is not moist with this goodness of joy and
happiness so so it implies that there's a kind of
engagement with the process so not just opening and allowing well-being there but in a certain kind of way gently
lovingly kind of maybe each time we breathe kind of opening and filling opening stretching letting it
kind of ooze or letting it like spread through the body so there's a little more active involvement and
and and this is where the mind is a little bit more involved in staying there stay present be with it work on work on
the breath the in-breaths and the out-breaths as the mind gets stiller and quieter
there's no more needing no more work is needed to stay present no more work to spread anything or
cultivating it and so the next uh uh level of
absorption so just as though there were a lake
whose waters welled up from below and it has no inflow from east west
north or south and would not be replenished from time to time by showers of rain
so there's no streams flowing in from any direction into the lake from the top it's only an
upwelling of a spring from below then that cool fount of underwater water
flowing up in the lake would make the cool water suffuse fill completely fill and pervade the
lake so there's no part of the whole lake unpervaded
by the cool water um in this way
one suffuses and fills and completely fills and pervades this very body with the joy and
happiness born of samadhi no part of the body is unpervaded with joy and happiness born
of samadhi the third absorption just
as in a pond of blue or red or white lotuses some lotuses
that are born and grow in the water thrive immersed in the water without rising
out of it and cool water suffuses feels completely fills and pervades
these lotuses to their tips and their roots so that there is no part of all these
lotuses unpervaded by cold water
so one experiences happiness in same way one experiences happiness with the body
that the noble ones describe when abides abides with happiness of one who is equanimous and mindful
one suffuses feels completely fills and pervades this very body with happiness no part of the body is
unpervaded with happiness so the joy has stopped which is more active and energetic and now it's just
happiness and then the final one
is um
just as though a person were sitting covered from the head down with white
cloth so that there's no part of one's whole body enclosed
um not enclosed by the white cloth
so once it fuses and fills it completely fills and
pervades this very body with mental purity mental clarity
no part of the body is unpervaded with mental clarity just as a so
um the the idea of surrounded by a white cloth and no part
of the body is not touched by this white cloth is the idea that
there's no outside stimulus anymore and there's no clear defined body anymore it's kind of
you can't quite see it but it's there it's it's covered and and it's a softness to
it the soft clean cloth that touches it everywhere so we go from working the working the
joy through the body to feeling the joy uh so being a very peaceful quiet lake with
whatever we've experienced kind of floating in this stillness of awareness happy awareness to um
to becoming so quiet and still that the body begins to recede and very
peaceful safe quiet equanimous and characterized by a kind of mental purity mental
clarity or cleanliness that's there so this is the closest we get to the
buddha really describing or these met these states of
concentration and i don't know if they mean something for you or whether you kind of evoke some imagination for you but if
they evoke your imagination then these are things to kind of take in and and
internalize a certain way some people memorize these descriptions and and then they're there
in the background for the mind to kind of
perfume itself or perfume meditation with dissociation and associations which
might be a lot better than some of the other ways in which your imagination is
influencing your experience so thank you and and
may you enjoy and may your joy and happiness
have a chance have the opportunity to spread and prevail and soak your
whole body don't get so distracted that you don't allow your well-being
happiness and joy a real chance to really be felt and be experienced in this body that we have
so until tomorrow thank you