so welcome all uh it's sweet to see uh
the the names uh names streaming through
so um yeah happy too uh happy to be with you
and uh that's uh that's it
just as you take your your posture
sense of of your body remembering all the practice you've done
all the goodness you've nurtured
all the letting go and the patience the equanimity
all the stillness
all the determination just getting a little sense of
the wholeness of that karmic stream
and of course we can trace that back further not just our life but we're here
because of the the lineage of
of understanding of love of compassion
where beneficiaries and also will be causes
for more goodness in this uh stream
of dhamma
just feeling into the the blessings of this path
it could have been otherwise we could have lived
a whole life never
listening to
the voices of uh of longing within us longing to be free
as we we contemplate this kind of blessing gratitude
things get quiet still
perhaps you make the soundscape the field of
sound and silence the
objective attention
there are all the outer sounds sounds from
wherever you are sound of my voice
but also the inner sounds that we usually just call thinking
let me just make the entire soundscape one field
not distinguishing so much inner sounds outer sounds
and also those moments of silence
the heart cannot rest and it's clinging
so we relax we surrender to the
imperfection the human condition
we find ways of giving the heart some rest
because so macha is asked of our heart
it's not indulgent or self-serving
to that at rest
[Music]
so welcome once again
so the last last
reflection in this series on on equanimity
um
so i saw saw a couple um
bumper stickers recently um that i liked a lot uh
the first one was on a station wagon and it was uh
black background white letters and it just said uh i used to be cool
um what does that have to do with equanimity i don't know not not much that doesn't really tie in
maybe to yesterday's theme but there's more just i like that bumper sticker and
just wanted to share that with you the other one this one is very relevant
for today it said um cynicism is obedience
cynicism is obedience
one of the most most common misconceptions
about equanimity is that it's a a form of indifference or passivity
or maybe even cynicism but
equanimity is not about the future
in a sense it's not even really about the presence it's it's about accepting
what has already arisen what has come to pass
yeah that that moment of the very recent past that is here
can we open to that that this is the fruit of this moment
and a moment of deep equanimity
now does not imply passivity in the next moment
passivity or action that is really another
question it's not actually so closely linked to the question of
equanimity the practice of equanimity again shinzon young equanimity involves
non-interference with the natural flow of sensory experience apathy
implies indifference to the controllable outcome of objective events
now this is an important clarification
and some of the confusion comes because
we extrapolate meditation instructions as instructions for life
right so some meditation instructions some of the
things we say during a guided meditation are indeed instructions for living but
some aren't yeah so in guided meditations
i never say okay now breathe out
and at the end of your exhale scratch anything
and everything that itches yeah that's not an instruction
we tend to give but if i were life if i were doing some life coaching i would tell you yeah most
of the time when you have an itch scratch it yeah
um meditation instructions are they're a training ground you know
and um they're a cultivation of of uh these
beautiful qualities of the heart but they can't be not all of them can be easily
extrapolated to all conditions the complexities of being human
and so we we you know when we're teaching we say we're desperate we'll say whatever we can to
support non-clinging love determination
yeah and um and there those instructions they have
uh uh obviously a place an important place we gather here to practice
together but they can't be traced out in a linear way to all of life you know
so when when it matures when
equanimity matures it it enlivens rather than dampens our
commitments to to alleviating suffering
and the the poignancy of feeling that i
described a couple days ago that that sticks to our bones yeah
this way that that equanimity is a kind of um in in the cauldron of experience the
equanimity meeting dukkha that um our life becomes much less melodramatic
but more and more poignant and
it's like there's a lot of feeling the heart moves easily
but it's it's surrounded by the tranquilizing factors yeah
the depth of feeling occurs in a kind of ambiance of
of years of tranquility of equanimity
the the buddha was worried about nihilism
you know and there there are experiences there are meditative experiences
that can tend towards that way experiences where where everything
everything all sensory impressions have one taste
and you know it's like
the world is like a gust of wind and we're like a gust of wind
all phenomena just kind of blowing through a kind of
space blowing through emptiness and
one might get the impression amidst that that um
it's all the same and in this way nothing matters
but the buddha found the middle path between extremes between
everything means everything and nothing means anything
when uh when everything means everything you
you can't stop caring you can't stop worrying you can't stop giving
you can't justify even a moment's rest
and when nothing means anything love love dissolves and
all goodness is at risk so
equanimity it really um one way of thinking about it is that it
purifies our compassion purifies our compassion
it makes it less compulsive it makes it less
codependent less grandiose less self-righteous
equanimity purifies our compassion our care
and we see that that actions arising from equanimity
from this non-interference with with what has arisen
um those actions arising from liquidity are more potent have greater moral force
than actions arising from clinging
our heart it needs to rest
it uh can't always be in a state of openness
it can't you know like a blossom it cannot stay open for all seasons
and when we feel like too much might be asked of our heart we shut
down yeah when we feel like uh the demands
are too much we actually shut down and so
shown one child who's hungry we humans get very generous
shown a thousand we start to shut down
and of course i'm here to uh
to tell you there are a thousand a thousand
thousand and can we can we open to this
can can compassion meet that fully
full-heartedly radically their pain
permeating our heart their pain
spurring action their pain being moralized being a
concern for us even though we might be separated
by space or by time
but um we can only open to the depth of need we
can only open with compassion when we also trust
that the heart can rest in equanimity too
we are less intimidated by the enormity of
of dukkha yeah we're more
willing to spend our our well-being to spend our love on
others because we know there's peace too
and we know that peace is the only state that doesn't
fatigue the heart peace is the only state that doesn't
need its seasons
and so we have a place to rest
and then we open again we love deeply again we leave
it all on the floor and then rest again
the philosopher dark parfait
if we are the only rational beings in the universe as some
evidence suggests it matters even more whether we shall
have descendants or successors during the billions of years in which that
would be possible some of our successors might live lives
and create worlds that though failing to justify past
suffering would give us all including some of those
who have suffered reasons to be glad that the universe exists
yeah reasons to be glad that the universe exists
yeah maybe we may we find those reasons yeah may we may we uh love well and uh rest deeply
yeah so thank you uh thank you all thank you
for this uh week your practice your practice many of you over not just this week but
months year plus yeah and uh
yeah i'm honored to have been uh been with you and uh nurturing for my own heart to
reflect on these themes so uh yeah i wish you uh i wish you all
well uh you'll be back uh plan plan is for
monday okay thank you all and thank you kevin for for uh djing the whole thing and
yeah i'll see you around the dharma campus somewhere