so
so as a way of continuing the
discussion of the buddha's teachings
on anapanasati
mindfulness of breathing
the buddha is presenting these 16 steps
for mindfulness of breathing
and then clearly showing their
connection
to two other important teachings
meditation teachings he has and one is
the teachings on the four
what's usually called the four
foundations of mindfulness
and what's usually called the seven
factors of awakening
and um it's really wonderful the way
that
rather than many people will feel that
you know that practice is practicing
those who know about the practicing the
four foundations of mindfulness
we'll see them as a very different
practice than
practicing mindfulness of breathing
and certainly the way they're taught is
often the case
but they also come together
especially in mindfulness of breathing
really becomes
some point or enters into the same
domain the same area of life as the four
foundations of mindfulness
and um and the way the buddha does this
is that
there's four tetrads in the 16 steps of
aleppanasati and each tetrad he says
corresponds to one of the foundations of
mindfulness
so as it usually said the foundation of
mindfulness that's
based on the body corresponds to the
first four steps of
breathing being aware of the long breath
bring where the short breath being aware
of the whole body as you breathe
and then being aware of the body calming
and relaxing
as you breathe so it's all about the
body
and when that becomes really well
established all four of these steps and
really awareness has become strong
then the awareness is based on
the body in the first
and the first foundation of mindfulness
it's really about establishing awareness
on the basis of the body and classically
there's a series of exercises to giving
or different ways of practicing
mindfulness practice
all for the purpose of establishing a
strong
mindfulness awareness in the body
in the second tetrad steps
five to eight
they are that corresponds to the second
foundation of mindfulness the foundation
of mindfulness on feelings
and so the second tetrad of anapanasati
is experiencing as we breathe feeling
joy
as we breathe feeling happiness as we
breathe
experiencing the mental activity
and then relaxing the mental activity
and this expert experiencing
could also be translated as feeling it
has the same word that we translate as
feeling
is embodied in the word experiencing the
way the pali
grammar is or l the words are used
and so ex feeling
joy feeling happiness feeling uh
the whole the mental activity and then
relaxing the mental activity
so this corresponds to this the
foundation of mindfulness on feeling
the third that threat has to do all
about the mind
and the third foundation is all about
the mind
so in the breathing exercises it's
experiencing
the mind not just the activity the whole
mind
gladdening the mind settling
stabilizing the mind concentrating the
mind
and then liberating the mind in the four
foundations of mindfulness
the it's
in part understanding really high
quality states of mind
maybe first the mind itself in some
certain ways particular
ways and then these high qualities of
mind
that correspond with gladdening roughly
of course by gladdening
concentrating and liberating the mind
and then the last tetrad uh is
observing all about observing observing
impermanence observing
fading away cessation and relinquishment
and these are the insights deep insights
and the fourth foundation of mindfulness
is also about about insights
it's really uh insight also into seeing
the arising and passing
how hindrances arise and they go and
seeing the suffering our suffering comes
and goes
and now that's the first of the
observations of the fourth tetrad
observing in constancy or change
and and the others follow in the wake of
that
so the buddha corresponds these two
these the four foundations are equal to
the four tetrads
but not just automatically it's when
awareness is well established
in each of these areas when it's when
when
when we're really grounded and centered
and present in a full way without being
distracted or
thinking a lot about the past and the
future this precious
precious thing that we have being aware
being able to really experience the
present moment
sense the present moment feel the
know the present moment in all its all
the dimensions of knowing
not just know it fleetingly but to feel
that
now we're centered we're at rooted we're
grounded
here and this feeling of being really
here definitely be grounded resting here
it's kind of like the difference between
maybe
being in a row but being tossed around
the sea
and then coming up on dry land now you
feel like it's stable and strong
here we are and there's a qualitatively
shift a quantum shift that can happen
inside when boom we're here
we don't have to work at being here and
come back
and come back and remember to be here
and present
we're not liable to wander off and the
awareness then becomes strong
and uh and that awareness is established
and uh so the translation i like for the
four foundations of mindfulness is
uh is the four ways the four basis
for establishing uh awareness
and um and then in the when the buddha
correlates these four these
these foundations and the four tetrads
and the fourth one he says then
mindfulness of the
ma of the dharmas is well established
so there's a strong level of equanimity
and this is one of the kind of
directions the practice goes when
there's a stability
boom we're here that then we're here in
such a strong way
that we're not easily tossed around by
the changing circumstances of our life
we're not easily losing our equanimity
our balance our
peacefulness when
difficult thought arises it just rise
and they go
when there's difficult painful
sensations in the body arise and
we just can feel them and know them and
and but mind doesn't get agitated or
disturbed
and this is called equanimity a lack of
agitation and lack of
being disturbed and
so both these practices the four
foundations of mindfulness whatever way
you've been taught to do them
and there's many ways that be possible
mindfulness is taught
or the mindfulness of breathing one of
the ways of doing this
whatever those practices are they're all
for the purpose
ultimately in buddhist practice to
come to a kind of dwelling resting
abiding aware in the present moment
without any tendency to leave that
and wander off from that and
some people then will use the
kind of the expression lucid awareness
when awareness is not ruffled when
our sense of mindfulness not ruffled by
what we know
that knowing becomes
free and independent
of what is known we can't separate what
we know from knowing
completely but but
the knowing is not ruffled it's not
agitated
it's not entangled it's not
clinging to what is known and this idea
of
knowing something and that kind of
freedom that equanimity
is then um the um
the the really the place where all the
different practices of mindfulness all
the different ways might be past our
practice
come together and and set the stage
for uh for awakening
so then tomorrow i'll talk about how
this goes to
is connected to the seven factors of
awakening
and i love this because um if there's
kind of a creating of a harmony or unity
in in the buddhist teachings we start
seeing how they all come together
as a whole and
in the way that this discourse on
anapanasati begins
where it begins with the
senior disciples of the buddha coming
together
with all their disciples and living
together for
a period of months in unity and in
harmony
receiving the buddhist teaching so
to have that sense of unity in harmony
with all the different sides of who we
are
that we could all come together and live
under the full moon of our
lucid awareness
so um thank you and
and we'll continue along this path of
the anapanasati
and tomorrow's the seven factors of
awakening and then we'll see
by thursday how the seven factors of
awakening
are practiced the practice changes
when a person has not just learned how
to be stably aware here
but has experienced a degree of real
liberation freedom from clinging
and how the practice of changes at that
point
so so we continue and we're almost at
the end of this
anapanasati series thank you