so welcome everyone lovely to sit with you this
friday or saturday for some of you such as murray christine in australia
joining us lovely to sit with you in this moment in
time whatever the time might be
so for today's practice i'd like to invite us to um
to sit to to explore to to simmer to let let
the fourth phrase of meta really um simmer hang out with the fourth
phrase of meta given that it's friday i like to
say less today and have a lot more space for quiet and just for
unwinding unwinding i've noticed that's a nice
space nice beat for friday or friday practice to leave more space but i'll say just a
few words to set the container
so with metaphases the four traditional metaphases the
first one being about safety may i may you be safe feel safe
the second may i may you may we may they
may all beings be happy so having to do with mental happiness
the third phrase having to do with physical happiness i.e health may i
you they all beings be healthy and strong and the fourth phrase
may i have ease may you have ease having to do with ease
our lives unfolding with with ease may there be ease in our
lives may we take our care of ourselves happily so the fourth phrase has to do with
how our lives unfold in the world and
we've this we've discussed explored the previous three phrases in the previous
days and last week so if you're curious about those please there are all on youtube and
audio dharma and now today we'll explore the fourth one
and of course whatever wherever you jump in doesn't matter
so so don't feel like you've missed out there's it's not like they're building on each other each each exploration
is beautiful and and worthwhile in and of itself
so so today let's wish his fourth wish for
our lives unfolding with ease what does that even mean so
so maybe we consider the opposite for a moment that there are times that perhaps life feels hard things feel hard
it's at times there's a sense of ease we take care of ourselves happily
feels like life is humming along for us or for others and that's the wish that's the
wish oh kind of like there would be there to be uh grease in the in the crankshaft and then
the wheels that you know like oh everything just kind of like runs smoothly
that idea of oh may may i take care of myself happily
may my livelihood for example unfold with ease
so it has to do with our worldly ways of being the way we are in the world or the
conditions so so may there be ease peace
ease so
as a gift so if we consider these wishes these blessings these phrases of
meta as these generosities of heart generosities of heart
that we offer ourselves and we offer others it's just a wish it's just a wish and
it could be that there are areas in our lives or for others that there is
no ease it's tight it's hard it's there's ah there is contraction and
it's okay similar to the other three wishes of
meta phrases of meta we're not offering this phrase to make it go away
where it's it's not attachment to outcome because if there
is attachment to arkham we keep saying okay may i have ease may i have e's may i have ease and feel
tight about may i have ease ah do i have easy at ouch and you see how it kind of gets a
little strange whereas we offer it with generosity
as if we're blessing ourselves may there be ease in my life
ah no fully well knowing that there might be areas that there is no ease
and it's okay we still offer this wish we still offer this wish this blessing
fully well knowing their areas with with no ease maybe there will be ease maybe
there may not be ease knowing that conditions of life are impermanent
and ease comes and goes and it's not something we can hang
on to because if we try to hang on to to ease we get rope burn
rope burn is similarly for for like trying to hang on to
impermanence when the row keeps running ouch ouch out and you try to hang on you can't
hang on you let go you let your heart release and yet this wish is
offered with generosity to yourself if we're doing meta for ourselves
generosity for others may you have ease dear one may you have ease dear human being may
you have ease dear stranger so
again fully well knowing that life is impermanent and things there might be ease or not
but just offering this as a cultivation of our own heart
so i've said plenty we'll start this practice by
settling in our breath in our body and inviting the mind
to settle and then we'll turn to the practice so
so let's let's start let's start our practice formally and i'll invite you to
ah get into your meditation posture whatever that is if you need to sit
differently a different implement or lie down
it's all okay see what your body needs in this moment
see how this body
can express ease
can be held in ease in this moment
as much as it is available right now
you might be surprised how much is available
can the forehead the tightness of the forehead release into ease
the eyes resting in their socket can they relax
ah into ease
muscles of the face behind the face
neck and shoulders arms and hands
release into ease
just chest abdomen
as they expand and contract with the breath
ah whole upper body
releasing releasing more and more and more into ease
the lower abdomen
the sit bones
the contact points between the bottom and the cushion ah
dropping dropping their weight
into the cushion
releasing [Music]
upper legs lower legs and feet
the whole body released into ease
ah with each breath
nowhere to go nothing to do
in this moment but to just be
breathed
and if thoughts arise for this moment of practice can they be
released into ease
gentle releasing gently opening the hand as if holding
[Music] the string of helium balloons
releasing to the big sky
of awareness with ease
letting inviting the lower abdomen
to be breathed to be breathing the breath in and out
ease breathed into the lower abdomen
ease breathed out
as if happening on its own no doing forcing required
and if you notice any resistance or forcing tightness in the body in the mind
can there be a fluffy cloud of ease
that can hold gently softly
wherever there is lack of ease
with breath being breathed around it providing this fluffy
cushion it's okay it doesn't have to go away it can just
be held this lack of ease if any
may my life unfold with ease
dropping this phrase in [Music] lightly
may my life unfold with you as if a blessing
sacred blessing just dropped in may this life of mine
made unfold with ease as much as
possible
may i have peace may i have ease see what version works better for
you
i wish ease for this person who is me
may this person may this being
take care of themselves himself herself happily
if you like you can imagine someone who cares about you
or an archetype of care and love
unconditional love wishing you wishing you ease and you just receiving
it
this person this being says may you take care of yourself happily
may you have ease in your life
or whatever version works for you
maybe they wish you spaciousness in your heart and your mind
lightness
brightness in your heart
the sense of presence to how your life [Music]
unfolds aware of the miracle that it is
in each moment
receiving these gifts these blessings
as if sacred gifts
from this loving caring being
without attachment to outcomes
letting your heart your body relax receiving each blessing
this
may i have ease may this life of mine unfold with ease
may there be ease in my life my heart and my mind
my livelihood
the unfolding of my life
either wishing for yourself or receiving it from the caring being or both
may there be ease may there be
now considering someone that you care about
and you would like to wish them ease in their life
turning the meta outward externally
bringing the image the felt sense of this being this friend
this being wishing them ease may you have ease
may your life unfold with ease dear being i wish you ease
offering these wishes like blessings without attachment to outcome offering
them freely with generosity of heart
as if you're sprinkling [Music]
good wishes of ease all around them all over them
like magic dust may you have ease
with generosity of art
and now internally and externally
may we both have ease
in our lives may there be ease may there be ease
for the last moment of this practice
letting there be ease
the way you consider this practice period let there be ease no judgment whether
the mind was distracted sleepy whether there was
lack of ease it's all okay let there be ease
let there be ease holding supporting spaciously
with each breath holding the lack of
ease let there be ease
let there be ease
may all beings everywhere including us have ease
thank you thanks everyone for your
practice so
i wonder if you feel more ease in your body and your heart and your mind
or maybe less ease
so we have time for reflections what do you notice what you learned you can raise your hand
if you wish you can type them to me if they're typed privately i will not
read your name if they're typed to everyone i will say your name out loud
and one reflection that just came in is thank you
your warmth oh your warmth is so wonderful you're so welcome thank you for your practice so mirage
please
i want to thank you from the depth of my heart for your nurturing presence and guidance
and everyone for your presence i have been going through challenges in
my practice today on my retreat and this is so beautiful
such a beautiful synchronicity that i decided to show up today actually in person instead of doing
youtube with you because this is the topic exactly of my challenge of being too
hard on myself and i knew it on the mind level i was aware
of my mind being very strict and of a harsh inner
dialogue but today i was able to drop onto my body level and
experience that heart ache and that pain of years of pushing my stuff and almost
like everything i did was because i was pushing myself too hard
and it's so beautiful to just release that and cry and i was laying down
and hugging myself for the practice and i felt i was being held by all of you
with your awareness so thank you so much
my eyes are feeling moist mirage thank you so much for the grace of your presence and
your practice and sharing yourself
holding and feeling held what a gift thank you so much
[Music] thank you
paul please
thank you nikki and everyone one thing that emerged in this practice
today was the image of how
ease interacts with exertion or intention
and for example in health practices
doing something challenging becomes easier as we hydrate ourselves as we eat well as we
sleep there's this whole set of practices that can make exertion and ease come together in a flow
and it's almost like that resistance get gets worn away by water flowing over it and wearing it
over time and i feel the challenge for me is you know so often called into
work that is transformational whether it's sustainability or social justice where there's this
inherent resistance in the work it's a work of
changing something that is stuck in a way that it is and the challenge for me is always that
i absorb that uh resistance into myself and it creates a lack of ease in me
because i feel like i'm fighting against the very nature of intention for transformation is pushing against
something that is a way that you want it to be different and so what came up for me today was how
to create that same sense of ease in effort or ease in transformation that
the water flowing over these resistances through practice and not knowing
necessarily what all those practices can be that lead to that but by
doing the meditation in the way that you were guiding today just instead of trying to figure out
what practices are what to do just being open to looking for
and exploring and receiving that ease as i put myself in a place of
resistance in order to be part of change so thank you
thank you paul thank you and hearing what the beautiful reflection you brought in
with ah resistance inside this this external this wanting to make change happen and
then this contraction actually coming inside and wondering okay what could be those conditions to actually
support it so i have a suggestion and invitation for you to explore and it's very simple so the invitation
is this notice when there is contraction inside and you know what i mean when i say
contraction inside yes notice when there is contraction inside
and just gently ask oh can there be ease can there be ease
holding this it doesn't have to open can there be ease and maybe the answer will be yes maybe
the answer will be no but just ask just gently humbly ask can there be ease can there be can there
be ease and you might be surprised
thank you thank you
thank you all
yeah one reflection on youtube you are so very welcome yeah
glad it was impactful so um let's turn
to practicing in community from internal as i was inviting us to external how can
we wish others ease while we're holding ourselves with ease and if you notice contraction in the way
you're relating oh can there be ease can there be ease in this little sandbox if you
notice yourself you know the ego wanting to prop itself up or feeling small or like
oh sweetie can there be ease can there be ease can can this contraction be let go
into ease so you can practice with that in this field which is
great because it's just a little tiny bit more challenging than sitting quietly but not as challenging
as practicing with people who are not practicing so here in the sandbox i invite you so
the invitation is to start with um 30 seconds of silent meta
actually let's make it 15 seconds 15 seconds of silent wishing ease for each other whoever is
in the room you wish them ease and then um
and then yeah sharing whatever you like and notice if there is ease when you're
discussing or if there's tightness if you're discussing and yeah practice with it in okay
welcome back everyone the rooms are closed so we have a couple of minutes for
reflections um what what did you notice in community practice especially if you
haven't spoken today or in a while would love to hear from you what
what did you notice with this practice of ease especially
internally externally we'd love to hear your insights or questions or challenges anything
yes please richard
can you hear me yeah oh a friend of mine um
compared ease or ease of well-being with equanimity i wondered if you uh
sync up with that what was the last part that you said
about whether or not that that makes sense to you oh ease and equanimity
um it's i think there there is a relationship
yeah um i would yeah this is how i would say it's an equanimity i think of as
equipoise as a sense of ease with the comings and goings of things
right it's ease with conditions just as they are with comings goings
etc there's a sense of ease so yes in that way i'll
i'll sign up for that one thank you richard that's great
any other reflections you can also type them if you wish
oh and it's seven so oh well i guess we have come to the end of our time
together it time flies when you're having fun with ease so thank you all thank you so
much for showing up and practicing not just for yourself but for all those
whose lives yours touches directly or indirectly
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
thanks everyone and