warm hello from inside meditation center in redwood city
and uh
it's so wonderful that you're here to go along with us in this meditation
thank you so
the topic is thinking and
it's an important thing to become wise about when you're a meditator
and you don't become wise by batting it away and you don't become wise by indulging in it
you become wise by looking at it seeing it clearly
where the emphasis should be on the word clear seeing it really clearly
clear seeing and i think that um i think
the um some people are so identified
with their thinking that they are synonymous with their thinking
their identity their sense of who they are they're very beingness
is is associated with thinking and it gives thinking a lot of authority
because sometimes in thinking whatever i think is part of who i am and therefore it
needs to be true it is true my opinions my views my everything
so i am therefore i think is the famous french philosophers
saying and buddhism wouldn't say that
thinking is just one part of the vast world of our
psychophysical functioning and it's not any more warrants
identifying with as being mine as your finger clipping once you've
clipped your fingers you hold up your finger clipping and say this is me this is me look here there
here i am i'm going to keep it close maybe thoughts once they've been
thought out once they've appeared in consciousness are simply the finger clippings of the
mental processes we have we give them a lot of credibility a lot
of importance so one of the ways
of sitting with meditation with thinking is to when we think
to turn the attention fully onto the thinking
and look thinking right in the eye to really observe thinking
without justifying it without condemning it without being for it or against it
but taking it as a fully fully warranting attention as anything else
if there was a wonderful bird singing outside the bird song coming through the window
some people might take that as a delightful object of meditation just kind of just
listening for listening in the same way we can just watch listen
look at directly oh this is thinking
one delightful kind of way of that looking
is to imagine that you're sitting on a big boulder safe and sound and content
in a river where the middle of the river draw high and dry
but either side of you the river's just flowing just flowing by
and you don't pick it up you don't get involved you don't dip your hand in it you just watch the flow by
to step back or stand on a dress and sit on a dry rock
and just watch the thoughts come and go and watch the tendency to get on them to get
into the river the old analogy of thoughts are like
trains train cars going by and suddenly you find yourself in the train
car
just watch just watch teso and if if you want to identify with something as being you
for the purpose of this meditation don't have it be your thinking have it be the observation of thinking
settle back relax and just observe and see if thinking is not predominant stay with
your breathing meditate as usual but then when thinking
picks up do this exercise of just turning and looking directly at it recognizing what
this is thinking as if the thinking is
apart from you not really you
if anything the observers you just see it let it let it
run by you like you let a river run by flow by
so taking an upright meditation posture either
literally or metaphorically one that has a little bit of
energy in it a little bit alertness in the posture
maybe being a little careful with the spine so that the spine feels a little alert
you're aware of the spine the aliveness of it
lowering your gaze
and if it's comfortable gently closing your eyes
and then taking a few long slow deep breaths
on the exhale letting go of your thoughts and your concerns
let go and let go into your body
deep breath in relaxing the body
letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale relax your body
maybe in the inhale feel some part of your body where there's holding or tension
anywhere it is in the body on the exhale relax
and then taking them a few moments here to allow yourself to think
but look thinking right in the eye
calmly clearly recognize your thinking
the thinking then gets quiet being watched this way
feel notice what that quiet feels
like notice the space or the stillness the quiet
notice if there's a location for it
is there any attention associated with it
if there is relax
and if thinking stays away then begin again with your breathing
if thinking stays there is even more activated than before
breathe with it breathe through it and see if you can
find the place to sit on the boulder in the river
so that the river of thought just flows right by
and you are not involved with it
and looking clearly at thinking and stepping away and being on that dry
boulder it can be helpful to label the thinking
as thinking thinking or remembering
talking planning
the label is not so important what's important is the way the label
helps you step away and not be so glued to the thinking
and then taking a few moments to feel any tension that exists in your
body any holding tightness
notice it in a relaxed way no need to judge it or yourself
just notice if there's any tension
and then in the next three exhales see if you can relax that tension and
any tension right down to the core of your being
relax and let the thinking mind become quiet
peaceful as you feel your way to
whatever relaxation there's here
and then
there are times when thinking is heavy
and sometimes when it's very light
it's heavy when we identify with it and lighter when we let it be
and lightly see if you can allow for some light thoughts
almost not thinking at all but the light thoughts that arise
or might arise in the wake of these words that i will
speak
we all have a capacity
to have well wishing for others
we all have the capacity to be generous
we all have the capacity to be kind friendly
we all have the capacity to love
even if it's ever so slightly
and to make room for that capacity for these last couple of minutes to
trust that capacity and allow perhaps there to bubble up
very simple light thoughts of goodwill
it could be they take the form of just appreciating how wonderful would it would be
if others were happy peaceful and safe
may it be that all beings are happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and without any burden any sense of weight but rather with a light as a feather
may it float from us the wish to contribute to that as a
possibility may we go through the day
doing whatever is easy and light
for the welfare and happiness and well-being of others
may all beings be habeam
[Music]
thank you
so we continue with the topic of mindfulness of thinking
today it's the topic is restoration and what i mean by that is the restoring
of a healthy way of being that um we
the ways that clinging and attachment and fear and the resistance
inhibit the natural healthy functioning of our psychophysical being
so the
as we kind of no longer are carrying the burden of our attachments
and carrying the burden of our responsibilities you can still have response abilities
but to to be weighed down by them
to be able to shed a lot of the attachments that we have in preoccupations
is a way to allow a healthy and so meditation operates
for some people a little bit like a you know if you're dirty
you take a shower and you're clean and so meditation is a way of cleansing
the mind the spirit the heart excuse me for a minute
so um so how does this relate to thinking
uh there's there can be a restoration of healthy thinking um
or thinking which is beneficial thinking which is light clear
easy and
so one of the steps towards that is as i've talked about is to respect
thinking but here's a way of looking at it
is that um
everything that we are is made up of parts
and so thinking is made up of parts it's part emotions part physical tensions far
apart motivations apart our memories and our associations
and um sometimes thoughts are motivational they're
trying to get something done sometimes they're simply uh very relaxed
memories or relaxed pleasant anticipations so all kinds of
there's relaxed reflections as we
begin respecting the different component parts of the complex of thinking
it's possible to recognize there's tension there's heaviness there's tightness contraction
and that's our contribution to it there's a way in which we're involved or identified or
represents some attachment we have independent of whether it's appropriate
to be thinking of whatever you're thinking about the weight the contraction the tightness
is not necessary in fact we usually think much better
more creatively more efficiently if there is no tension
if there is no tightness and heaviness and preoccupation
and and so to begin letting go and allowing thinking to
to be free of our
reactivity to them or cotness in them allows a thinking to operate to be
restored to a kind of healthiness to think without fear
to think without hate to think without um
desire wanting something it's maybe unimaginable
because if those are so much important parts of our thinking to have thinking occur
but not to have it glued to our sense of self me myself and
mine my opinions my stories it's really remarkable how much thinking
from some of us that we're somehow a central character in our thoughts
one way or the other and as uh we become lighter and freer we're
thinking the thoughts don't have us at the center of them anymore
and so thoughts just float up and one of the ways one of the
remarkable things that can happen in meditation if you do it meditate long enough or deep enough
is that with time thinking is not so heavy and thick
it's not so solid sometimes when we're really caught up in something
thinking can be the most solid thing in the universe it's so dense so serious so important so much energy
behind it and when that when the content of the thoughts
are negative negative about ourselves negative about the world the heaviness and the
and the contraction around the thoughts can be quite debilitating they say that the leading one of the
leading causes of depression is rumination just kind of
churning away with the same kind of thoughts over and over again that are negative negative self-talk
so to begin to put that to rest to not identify with him not be involved in it
and there might still be unfortunate kinds of thinking going on but uh because we're not logged
latched onto it or reactive to it or taking it so seriously we're just sitting on the boulder in the
river and just letting the water right run by not identifying with it
over time the thinking becomes thinner and thinner lighter and lighter
it's remarkable process by which thinking has its lightness to it it's like a thin thin veil maybe
or it's like a clouds drifting across an open sky
and clouds have no weight almost thoughts have no weight
in and of themselves they're very very light they don't interfere with anything like a cloud kind doesn't interfere with
anything you just put your hand in a cloud and your hand goes right through um
so that the thoughts feel like they're getting thinner and thinner lighter and lighter
more and more relaxed and and they just kind of feeling of them floating
through floating by and at this point some people find
that their thinking becomes creative i certainly found that when i was
um when i meditate a fair amount generally outside of meditation
my thinking is very easy and relaxed and creative i'm more likely to write poetry
when i have this kind of very light thin thinking going on
i'm also more likely to think about things more clearly i often will find that after i've
meditated in the morning that i go back to some thing i'm trying to figure out or do a right or something
and there's much more clarity and it's ease i think there's coming out it's almost like the
forcefulness that trying really hard to think or do something interferes with this natural creativity intelligence
that exists within us so one of the possibilities with
mindfulness of thinking is to understand the territory of thinking the ecology of
thinking to recognize the different component parts of it
and understand which parts we don't have to be involved in which parts we can let go of
it might not be letting go of thoughts themselves it might be letting go of all the tension associated with them
or it might be that maybe there's certain motivations connected to those thoughts which are
not something if you realize what the motivations are you know i don't need that you can let go of the motivation what they're trying
to do with their thoughts or it could be that there's a lot of physical tension
connected to thinking and so you let go of that you relax that and
and uh or maybe the emotions that are connected need real attention
that's what needs your love and your care and your presence so you and by recognizing the component
parts then we start separating that suffering that away it becomes easier to
look at thinking right in the eye and just see it
and it's fascinating to do that sometimes when we do that thinking just fades away
partly because thinking continues through time by our feeding it
and if we're just watching it then we're not feeding it and then it kind of kind of dissipates
and but then what's interesting is when it dissipates and we're relaxed
at some point maybe after meditation if you stay relaxed don't rush back into the thoughts and
concerns of the day that there's this restoration of a healthy way of thinking
and healthy wholesome useful there's a there's a way of being when
we're deeply relaxed and at peace we have a reference point for what health is what being healthy is
and it's not healthy to start getting preoccupied again or
starting to get caught again in the preoccupation concerns of the day
we do have concerns we do have things to take care of but the wonderful thing to discover
is we take care of them better if we're not tight if we're not rushing if we're not
pushing we're not barreling ahead we you know we can get up out of meditation some of us and like okay
gotta get to work and that attitude then
is a kind of leaning then into thinking leaning getting involved and thinking or the thinking itself gets revved up
and it's not that's it maybe it's not necessary
maybe there's a way of trusting that healthy way of being with thoughts where they're light and
soft and gentle maybe or just kind of you know
not weighty and not pushing us that um
that we have a sense oh that's healthy that's what's useful
so here restoration it means restoration of kind of a healthy thinking
and they have the ability to know what that is and uh the more ease more peaceful more
relaxed you can become in meditation the more you'll discover this reference point of a peaceful baby
a healthy way to be with the world of thinking we don't have to only let go of thoughts
there are times when it's completely appropriate to be thinking and even in uh and even wonderful to be
thinking thinking can be a gift you can be friends with your thoughts
but you can be friends with relating to the thoughts in a very healthy way
the thoughts themselves can just feel healthy and it's actually possible to have thoughts which feel nourishing
that feel supportive that feel onward leading to greater peace
so um thank you we have one more day on thinking
and and then tomorrow i'll talk a little bit about the plan for next week and
kind of how to continue this series so
may you today discover something
new about healthy thinking thank you