so
some people are fond of reading books
about buddhism
and if they want to learn about
meditation they might go find a book
or maybe nowadays some people go find an
audio recording
for the book people
the book we're trying to read is
found within ourselves we're learning to
read
ourselves read the signposts the
symptoms the movements the
process of meditation that unfolds
within us
that's the book to read or that's the
audio recording to listen to really
listen deeply into what's happening here
and sooner or later
all that we are to discover in buddhism
is meant to be discovered here in our
own body in our own experience
so to learn to read the signposts to
read the
to you know to leave to read what's
happening is part of with the skill
and uh for samadhi for developing
concentration
they the stability this composure this
unification of mind
there are signposts and
the pali word for signposts
usually translated into english as signs
is nimita n-i-m-i-t-a
and it's it's used in
very different way different ways down
to the history of buddhism
it has different meanings what this is
sometimes it's
reduced in meaning to being a visual
image that some people will see when
their concentration gets strong
maybe they're seeing a light maybe a
white light or yellow light this this
it kind of lights up as they get
concentrated and so the the
image is called the nimita but in the
early buddhist tradition animata is any
kind of sign
or indicator of the presence of
something or that something is about to
happen
and uh and so the the buddha said that
the nourishment
for samadhi what feeds and supports
somebody
is uh is two of these tasks two
of these signposts that we can find and
we can read we can recognize in
ourselves
and one of them is this
word samata sam s-a-m-a-t-h-a
and which means tranquility or calm or
quietude
and the other is a word that means
something like
non-dispersal or non-fragment
or non-um agitation of our thinking mind
and so as part of this unification
process
this gathering together being centered
here
we're not being de-centered by spinning
out
and and
i think the pali word that's translated
as non-dispersal
could maybe uh be read as a
non-decentered
uh as a as a
you know so and so so these these are
nimeta so as as we start getting
concentrated as we start getting settled
in sort of steadiness of mind then
to recognize these signposts to
recognize that there is a quietude or a
tranquility
or serenity however we want to translate
this word
samata and and to recognize we're
starting to be non-decentered
we're starting to be not scattered or
dispersed in our minds and
the mind's not jumping around and
chasing every thought that comes along
and
we're wandering off for minutes at a
time in our fantasies or our thoughts
but there's a real feeling now of being
gathered in
being non-dispersed being here and uh
that doesn't have to that neither one of
these have to be very strong at first
and this is where learning to reckon
know that these are signposts
they're kind of pointing the way so
there might be a lot of agitation there
might be a lot of dispersal of the mind
but if we keep focusing on those we
it's too easy to reinforce those
and the nourishment for somali is to
take in
to allow our son to experience to
experience or to
be supported by tranquility and
non-dispersal of the mind
this centeredness of the mind and
and so this and so even if there's a lot
of agitation
uh to recognize maybe in the cracks of
it
behind it in the back room of it in the
attic and the basement
somewhere inside to recognize oh there's
a little bit there
yes i'm agitated but in fact
a little bit in my sternum there's a
little feeling of tranquility there
a little bit in my hands my hands feel
steady
and confident and a little bit uh
calm tranquil and so to find where it
might be
don't manufacture it and don't worry too
much if you can't find it
we're talking about now as meditation
deepens and deepens
not just from you know just sitting down
and boom there you have to be able to do
this
but as you begin feeling yourself
settling and feeling yourself getting
more and more here and calmer than you
were before
that's when you start feeling that's
where the to appreciate
to affirm to validate these signs
these signposts this is good this is the
path forward this is the direction to go
this is the
now i'm now i've picked up the book
where the chapter where i left it
this is where where you know now i'm
picking up again where
you know the place where my practice is
really deepening
and and so to recognize these um
um
you know these these signposts so i see
there's a for the other
uh nimita there's two nimitas in pali
what is samata
and the other one is
a v y a g g a
and aga could mean like center and
and the vui is divided or separated
and a means not not separated from the
center
so this idea being centered um
so there are other signposts for samadhi
there's a lot of them
and so over time you might learn these
different ones
that um that uh
can support us oh this is good now that
we're in the territory
this is the direction forward because uh
to recognize it not so much to
be a not at all to be attached to it or
try to engineer and work too hard to get
concentrated
but simply to not
for the mind to begin recognizing that
this is the way forward this is the path
in the forest
as opposed to being distracted by every
little
troll and bird and insect and butterfly
off into the forest and we go chasing
after it and we lose the trail
so to gather ourselves together
to start feeling and recognizing these
signposts so
some of the other ones are as some
people feel have the physical sensations
that shift and change that show they're
getting concentrated
there can be tingling feeling of
lightness a feeling of
warmth the glow the feeling there might
be
some people there's a strong feeling of
physical pleasure
sometimes a little bit of pressure
vibration that begins
happening someplace some sometimes in
the forehead the people feel it there
sometimes in the chest
sometimes the belly
and sometimes parts of our body like the
arms
start feeling so light and maybe even
they seem to disappear because
things are so tranquil so peaceful there
or other parts of the body
the there might be a
visual signpost like i said there might
be
uh the field of vision starts it might
get completely
white or some other color sometimes
there are
some people when they get concentrated
will see little shapes
in their field of vision sometimes
geometrical shapes
and um it's important not to get
distracted by these things by the by the
visual
uh images especially if there's like
geometrical
signs or shapes or something but they
are
supportive and so to take them kind of
like
in the background of your experience oh
i'm on track i'm getting this is this
this is a signpost that i'm getting
concentrated that i'm
deepening here and uh
and is is
and then there are um what could be
considered may be more mental
signposts or emotional signposts a
common one is joy
and feeling a joy welling up
delight the kind of pleasure sometimes
it's even a sense of rapture
when the samadhi gets strong but there's
a feeling of delight of gladness
of relief that might be there and um
sometimes uh it's a deep sense of
happiness
something is more sublime more subtle
more more of a sense of contentment a
deep contentment in the quietude
here and sometimes a sign of getting
concentrated is that the mindfulness
gets clearer and clearer
the awareness gets clearer and clearer
and there becomes more equanimity
in that clear awareness which is
equanimous we're less likely to be
reactive to things
and feeling that equanimity feels so
good
and so don't expect all these things to
happen at once
and maybe don't even memorize don't even
try to memorize and look for all the
things i've said
i've talked about the two things that
buddha
emphasized as nimitas was this
tranquility
or calm quietude
or this non-de-centeredness the
non-dispersal non-scatterness of the
mind
the mind being composed and both of
those are supported by the two
actions verbs that buddha used
when he instructed us for what in
english we might say
become concentrated he didn't use the
english word concentrated because he
didn't speak english
he used two words one was the word um
to settle and the other is to steady
to settle on something and to steady
oneself on something
so the those four can be your signposts
uh um
settle settle the settling on the
breathing or in your experience
a steadiness with your breathing a
delightful warm
content of quietude tranquility
and and and a non-de-centeredness
a feeling ah this is good to really be
here not scattered anymore
and perhaps you can read the read at the
inner book
read yourself and see if you can find
the you know that supports you and
guides you and
gives you kind of more something to
in the good sense of the term hold on to
as you're developing concentration and
and or be cheerleaders or support from
the side to stay there
be there this is good this is keep
opening to this keep opening to this
and if you're not ready for that or if
you're not you know
if it didn't it doesn't work because
you're trying too hard or you're not
you know it's too much work just put it
aside
but sooner or later hopefully you begin
begin recognizing
your signposts for what it means when
the goodness of samadhi goodness of
being settled
and unified begins to come into play
and then to appreciate that to validate
that to
affirm that so the mind knows
this is what's important this is what's
valuable
thinking about trolls and butterflies
and all the other
things are useful sometimes but not for
the purpose of meditation
so thank you all very much
and and we'll continue tomorrow