so welcome uh welcome all uh it's nice to uh
see the the uh morning uh greetings uh over on the the uh chat
stream and um yeah happy to uh to again be with you
and yeah we'll uh we'll settle settle in and
practice together so um
yeah finding a posture that feels feels sustainable
and maybe maybe i was a little premature in the whole uh silence and stillness thing if
you need to check which friends are here go ahead check the uh the chat forget about that whole
silence and stillness thing i see stinson beach is uh in the house boise
yeah welcome welcome to uh to all of you
so
just sensing the the the presence of of others
the the jewel of sangha
just softening your your face
we wear the self on the face
in other words a certain kind of self-consciousness creates tension
in our face
relaxing all of that tension relaxing
self-consciousness relaxing the the
grip of self
relaxing the shoulders
your belly
hands
we sit undefended
but there's a deep dignity in being undefended
the game of fixing optimizing this moment
shoring up our resources
maybe it feels safe enough
to put all of that down
to rest in the good will of sangha
the goodwill of buddha dhamma
to truly make peace with this moment
we just keep blessing experience with uh
awareness love
non-equanimity arises as a kind of density friction
and it's as if the awareness gets blown into that solidity
everything becoming
less dense more like space
giving up all our fights
wherever the story or narratives
of
time of our autobiography the story of this meditation
as that accumulates and we notice and we just breathe
awareness into all of it
somewhere between suppression and entanglement
so so welcome muay always struck you can kind of say
welcome before sitting but then the the welcome after sitting
feels like a sort of true true welcome you know
um so i'm happy to uh to be with you and be
continuing this exploration around around equanimity
so
it's uh it's said that um
all of biology is evolutionary biology
um we we humans we don't just
come from animals sometimes we say that we come from animals
let you in on a little secret we uh we are animals
and um sometimes i think that uh you know the
the word human the name human maybe that's just like another
vanity of our of our species
and i say this because if we forget that we're animals we start to
uh maybe hate parts of ourselves and
when we hate parts of ourselves we
can't really train ourselves we can't really learn it's harder to train
ourselves when we have this kind of moralistic idea
of what it is to be human and
one element of equanimity is becoming uh non-moralistic
about experience and
i've always remembered that teacher's sharing that one of the the kind of
honorific names for the buddha was uh the unexcelled trainer of the animal
within the human uh this uh path of practice is very much
about our status as animals embodied
and the kind of um vulnerability of that
so in in in neuroscience there's um [Music]
there's a model model of the brain as
basically a hypothesis testing organ yeah
you make a hypothesis you do the experiment you get the data
you revise the view and this is very
different this idea of the brain as a prediction machine as a hypothesis
testing organ this is different from the normal
stimulus response there's a sound i have a response
in this way of thinking this approach um we're not really reflecting the world as
it is we're it's more like we're testing hypotheses about now
based on what happens next yeah
like we're constantly generating and testing predictions
and then adjusting based on the feedback and so in in a way our very sense of now
of what's happening now depends on what happens next
so to make a concrete like is this sensation in my knee is this just a
harmless ache or a sign of tissue damage of injury
well have to see what's next make a hypothesis
see what's next and
from this perspective perception is a
is a process of optimizing beliefs
about the causes of my knee sensations
and the driving concern in all of this
the knee sensation or the sound the driving concern in all of this as
animals is safety protection
very innocent longing
and the scientist k
tai she says um just made this kind of offhand comment she said like fear
fear has an authoritarian command over the rest of the brain
yeah fear has an authoritarian command over
the rest of the brain this this longing to be protected to be
safe yeah and this way in which where
we're figuring out the present based on what happens next
making predictions testing them gathering the data revising minimizing
our errors and so maybe you have a question like why why
am i talking about this uh well
i'm talking about it because it gives us an actual sense of
the power and the gravitational pull of the future
and so we say you know just relax into the present or the shirt
that says be present yeah and it sounds simple um
but um [Music] it's actually
very uh quite radical yeah to be present it's an act
of letting go to really be present
because in some sense to to be present
is to be open to that vulnerability
to our mortality to be undefended against the future
to begin to put down some of this habit of generating
hypotheses about the next moment the next moment
we we don't always recognize yet to be
open to the present moment this is like a
profoundly unguarded state there's a dignity in it and a power and as we'll
see a safety in it but it is a profoundly unguarded state
and in this mix as we're trying to
ensure our safety in this mix
as we're modeling our inner world trying to understand
what does this mean inside me what does this sensation mean what does that mean in all of this
maybe the most important signal the most important
that has the most salience is something like pain
something unexpected something unpleasant and so we get very preoccupied with pain
and because it it seems to mean a lot
and it gets us moving into this mode of what is this hypothesizing
checking this moment against the next moment
and so all of this is to say is that equanimity is vital if we're to step out
of this loop of preoccupation with the next moment
to actually for the heart not to be spun by pain
for us not to over interpret pain you know like often
it just pain means too much to us we over interpret it yeah
because we're animals because we're patrolling our borders because we are
surveilling yeah to see is everything okay
and um and so even little pains you know little bits of dukkha
feel as i was saying yesterday they feel like these freak accidents
rather than just woven into the fabric of our universe the fabric of our biology
and so we become so vigilant
and equanimity with pain creates a deeper
sense of safety we're not tracking
threats in the same way our vigilance starts to let down the
belly gets soft
experience feels less dense and we settle into the moment in a more
profound way a way that feels
nourishing and the waves the waves of pain or
discomfort the signals of threat rise up the contraction or the
pressures the tingling the sharpness the dullness all of this rises up
and then that itself brings on a kind of cascade of emotion
and then the mind goes scrambling what is this what do i do what can i do what does this mean about now what does this
mean about me what does this mean about the trajectory of my life
and we just bring it all down into the present moment
with this equanimous heart
even um even small pains can create a sense of desperation when
we really look yeah just this this itch on my face
we can sense the builds into a certain kind of
desperation and so we stay
we we feel our way through it we keep
our chest open we breathe we breathe into it
yeah we rest in the the triple gem
we have confidence in this buddhist path and we open to the whole body
and as this kind of the momentum of equanimity builds
this makes us less afraid less preoccupied with the
future and we start to settle into the present
moment a moment that um that doesn't feel sandwiched between
past and future some kinds of present feel like
the you know sandwiched yeah
i was that here's what it where we are and this is coming next
as we develop equanimity we don't feel uh sandwiched in that way
yeah we drop into a deeper kind of presence and
totally exposed but
the equanimity creating a sense of of refuge
so i offer this for your consideration
and that's good to think of you
out there all the places and uh
look forward to uh to being being together tomorrow continuing the theme
so yeah thank you all