so
in these
almost 70 sessions we've gone through
the
16 steps of mindfulness of breathing
and the most famous discourse
where i have where these
16 steps occur is actually in a
discourse that has much more in it
and it has a second half where
the practice is discussed as how it
follows up how it continues
after we're being well established in
the 16 steps
or it continues and describes
part of the wider kind of unfolding
that happens while we're doing the 16
steps
and somehow the second half presents
more richness and fullness
to it and partly it does so by
harmonizing
bringing together and showing how other
aspects of early buddhist practice
come into play in doing mindfulness or
breathing
and in particular there's two and that
is the four foundations of mindfulness
how they how the four foundations of
mindfulness are fulfilled through this
breathing meditation and how it leads to
the seven factors of awakening
and um inherent in this discussion
that here's you know this second half of
the
instructions or this description of
practice
is uh is something that's called the
onward leading nature of the dharma
there's a very famous description of the
dharma
where it says that it's immediate
inviting inspection onward leading
to be known for oneself
and um but this onward leading
uh the word for onward leading could
also imply
kind of like it carries it carries us
along
so it isn't so much that we're the agent
of developing and growing in the
practice
as as we enter the dharma stream
we enter the stream of meditation and
somehow the meditation
the dharma carries us along
and a kind of very simple way of
understanding that this
in one aspect is that most people
spend their days preoccupied maybe with
tension
and attachment wanting and their mind
racing and spinning
and afraid or or
angry resentful all kinds of ways in
which we're caught
and phenomenal and activities and
and so there's a lot of tension physical
tension emotional tension
mental tension and if we begin to relax
that all that preoccupation all that
entanglement with everything
then um it isn't just that we then
nothing happens but it starts to being
an unwinding a dissolving of fading away
of attachment and that fading away
that's
a dissolving of attachment begins to
change there's an onward movement
onward moving phenomenon and that as we
change
things open up within us that qualities
and capacities we have
that were submerged or repressed by our
fears our attachments our
preoccupations or entanglements
have a chance to begin showing
themselves and they become
stronger and stronger and it isn't so
much that we're
trying to make them become stronger but
they begin unfolding and moving
and uh and we it's wonderful to feel
in meditation slowly day by day or
whatever way we might feel it that
there's a kind of an opening
a kind of releasing a growing and
maturing
of something quite beautiful inside that
uh
it's kind of like a plant that has
finally
come into the sun sunlight it's been in
the dark for a long long time
and the plant grows and it just flowers
and this natural uh kind of that
description
of a flower coming to full blossom
is part of it is inherent
is inherent in the in the teachings of
the buddha
where there's kind of over and over
again a reference to
an organic movement growth unfolding
flowing a phenomenon as we enter into
this dermapath
the one of them is in fact the growth of
a plant
we can cultivate the plant but we don't
tug on it to make it grow
a frequent frequent metaphor is that of
a
of a river or stream coming down from a
mountain
if it rains in the mountaintop the rain
rains enough
then the rain the raindrops start to
flow down the side of the mountain
they join together and form little
streamlets the streamlets become streams
the streams become rivers the rivers
become
you know bigger and bigger until finally
they come down to the plains
and become wide big silent rivers
just flowing along into the ocean and
that water has its natural flow and flow
of gravity
and that metaphor is used for the if
we're getting into the stream the flow
of the dharma
it will carry us along and as we kind of
go into the dharma these
qualities become bigger and bigger
something inside of us becomes bigger
and stronger
and also much more silent and the
metaphor of silence
is the silence that happens within when
there's no conceit
when we're not no longer caught up and
preoccupied with me myself and mine
it isn't doesn't mean that we're
physically silent
but it means that there's a silencing of
this kind of extra agitation
that spills over into the world in all
kinds of
noisy ways and so
this flow down the river
that uh entering the stream is one of
the metaphors
that uh with the first experience of
real liberation
real freedom a person is changed forever
because now they know what the stream is
they know where the current is they know
the
both directions and how to be in that
current
that's going to carry us onward to full
liberation
and so um the onward leading nature
of the dharma in the anapan assad and
there's one way that concentration
practices onward leading
and another way that uh
insight practice is onward leading and
the two go together
and the concentration practice is
armored leading is described
as the there's the arising of gladness
when we're no longer caught up in the
hindrances
no longer the mind is no longer
distracted all the time
and the glad that we're finally present
that gladness
is the condition out of which flows
joy and if we really feel that joy
it's a condition that out of which flows
a deeper tranquility
relaxing a calming
and with that deeper calming there is
happiness
and with happiness there arises
concentration
and the way that this these five
gladness joy
tranquility happiness and concentration
are talked about in the suit dozen in
buddha's teaching
they are not something that the
meditator is doing
and making happen directly but rather
we're creating the conditions where this
onward leading movement
through gladness joy tranquility
happiness and concentration
can unfold on its own and
and and then that's the concentration
path
the inside path as described best i
think by the last
four steps of the
mindfulness of breathing that there is
insight observation observing
inconstancy there's a fading away
of attachments that depend on things
having more constancy
there's the ending cessation of
certain attachments and then there's the
letting go the relinquishing
of you know of our investment
belief in those attachments and so this
that also is described more of a natural
flow it's not something we do
but something we're observing and
watching happen
and so in anapanasati the
flow of practice moves through
concentration
and then leads this insight of deep
observation observing
and the but the what the meditator does
all along
mostly is just staying with a breath
being with a breath and there's a little
intentionality
to just stay focused stay focused on the
breath
which is expressed in the repeated way
in which the
grammar of the phrase is
having to do with being mindful of
breathing occurs
it says one trains
two says and then there's a quotation
like this is what i'm doing and saying
to myself
i will breathe in
when trains i will breathe out
when we'll engage over and over again no
matter what happens as we go through all
these 16 stages
we're not getting sidetracked by
anything we're allowing all the other
things to happen in the onward leading
nature
and we're recognizing allowing the the
tranquility
the relaxation the joy the happiness the
gladness the concentration the
liberations the observations that happen
but each all along the dedication is
simplicity of just staying with a breath
i will breathe in i will breathe out
i will stay connected to it this is
where the home is
for people doing mindfulness or
breathing it's not
exclusive the attention is open and
aware
so that this wider field is allowed to
manifest and to grow the dharma that's
onward leading can appear
but to keep us relaxed and not caught in
anything
not preoccupied we keep staying with the
breath in a relaxed
open committed way not clinging to it
but just kind of staying open but
staying there
so we don't get drift off and get caught
in other things
and if we have this relaxed open uh
steady continuous dedication
love for devotion for just breathing one
breath at a time
and of course we'll get distracted but
just whenever we can to come back i will
stay here with the breathing
this is what i'm doing then this we
start entering into
the dharma which is onward leading the
flow that begins to unfold
and and one of the things that it
unfolds into
this is uh
the the the core aspect
of the four foundations of mindfulness
and
um and how this mindfulness of breathing
connects with four foundations will be
the topic for tomorrow
so uh thank you so much
and then i hope that
you will be open to
not being the agent of change not to be
the one in charge of making things
happen
and fixing things all the time but you
go through the day
with some room to allow things to unfold
to allow yourself to unfold
to make room for yourself and room for
the dharma
that you can't do if you're just
constantly caught up in
being in charge or being the agent or
being the subject
of your preoccupations so
thank you