hello everyone and welcome to our morning on meditation and
maybe for some of us to be productively uncomfortable or wisely uncomfortable
because sometimes in meditation things are uncomfortable and to learn how to sit quietly
peacefully non-reactively with our discomfort is
one of the great values of meditation
people often think meditation has to do with becoming calm and peaceful
and that's the end of the story but we're probably more important is to learn how
to be wisely present attentive to whatever is happening in
our life so that no matter where we go we can find a wise way of being present
and maybe that means there's a kind of calmness and peacefulness in the
attentiveness or maybe it's we've learned how to rest
in a certain kind of way in our discomfort things that are difficult
so we will meditate
and if anything feels uncomfortable
maybe avoid if you can
seeing that as being unfortunate in some ways it might be
but maybe there's no other perspective that would be useful for this period of time
and maybe the perspective that would be useful is that maybe for now maybe there's a way of
resting in the discomfort breathing with the discomfort
that will teach you something that will serve you throughout the day
throughout your life maybe even so assuming a up upright
meditation posture
and it doesn't necessarily doesn't necessarily mean physically upright but a posture in which you will not collapse
that you will somehow stay present and open [Music]
in lowering your gaze softening
your focus and if it's comfortable gently closing
your eyes
and taking a few moments here to familiarize yourself with how you are right now
and perhaps becoming aware of how you are in your body
and if you're uncomfortable maybe at the beginning here if there are simple ways of shifting
your posture so that it's more comfortable please do
and then if there are ways now that you're uncomfortable in your body
let it be and gently lovingly
breathe through it breathe with it as if the breath lovingly accompanies
the discomfort while allowing it to be there
taking a few long slow deep breaths
as you breathe in deeply maybe take feel your body globally
feel whatever is pleasant unpleasant comfortable uncomfortable
take it all in
and as you exhale long quiet exhale
let it all settle let it all settle together
here
letting your breathing return to normal
and in whatever way it's easy as you breathe
have a sense that you're breathing aware of your whole body
global awareness of body with breathing in the middle
the movements of the chest the belly
a global awareness of what's comfortable and uncomfortable
pleasant and unpleasant all held in a kind of global awareness
with breathing accompanying it all
a global awareness where you're not defined by what's pleasant
and not defined by what's unpleasant not focused on one or the other
exclusively but for now a global broad
panoramic awareness of your body
breathing with it
and then whatever is most comfortable for you letting your attention become
more focused on a particular place in your body where you're breathing
or have it focus in a particular place in the body where that's calling your attention
or continuing with a global awareness
that holds it all openly calmly
without prioritizing what's comfortable or uncomfortable
but takes it all in in the cycles of breathing
[Music]
so
and as we come to the end of the sitting
to once again have a global
experience of your body whatever way that's easy
wide angle lens for your embodied experience
aware of the movements of breathing as it moves through your body
the chest the belly the shoulders
the rib cage front and back
a global experience of the body
and to whatever degree you're able to
see if you can rest in this body
maybe a feeling that attention settles and rests throughout the body
letting go of tension holding
and then staying in this global body
relaxed as you can turn your attention outward now
to the people you'll encounter today the work you'll do activities of the day
and become aware of it all remember it all while staying
rooted in your body relaxed in your body
the best you can
and from a place of goodness within place of warmth or kindness
a place where you care your care is born
to awaken a well-wishing for all the
people you'll encounter all the activities you'll do and for yourself in those
activities and offer words of well-wishing
may all these people all of us
be happy free of stress and strife
may all of us be safe free of hostility and
ill-will
may all of us be peaceful free of agitation
conflict and may all of us be free
free of compulsivity and oppression
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
and may we be messengers of this into the world
[Music]
so again good morning and this week we're
exploring the topic of discomfort that is a
common experience of life and becoming wiser about it
so discomfort so one of the things about discomfort that's useful to practice
is to make a distinction see the distinction between the discomfort which is
physical pure and simply physical and that which is more emotional or
mental and the reason for the distinction is that um
if it's physical discomfort if that's the one of the primary characteristics of
the discomfort or if you see the physical discomfort as the
the um you know the most obvious part of it
then uh what what we can do is rest in the discomfort
and this might seem paradoxical but to find where the discomfort is in the body
maybe the stomach is uh in knots or maybe the chest is uh swirling and
agitation or tight whatever it might be there's a restlessness that we feel in
our arms and our legs our hands and wherever it might be the physical
symptoms of being uncomfortable is um
you know you might be in pain is uh to see if it's possible to have
the attention or have your yourself rest into the discomfort
and um so that the discomfort is not a source for agitation
but rather is the basis where we kind of we stop to really
rest in it to be with it to allow it to be there
but not allowing it to be there um to do whatever it wants
but allowing it so something inside of us stays close to it and rests in it
it's kind of like a friend of ours might be really upset and agitated about something difficult that just happened
and maybe obviously very uncomfortable and um and you might come over and just
sit next to your friend or you might come over next to your friend and and uh and hold their hand
and you're the calm presence you kind of rest calmly with the with a person
so to feel the physical restlessness or the discomfort and
breathe with it feel it in your body center yourself on it and
find a way of being grounded or centered through it
not around it and uh you know by avoiding it and
so partly what this is doing is learning
to not give in to the reactivity of the discomfort the subject of yesterday's talk all the different ways
we might react to it but rather to not allow the reactivity to take over but to find how to rest in
it and sometimes this physical discomfort if we do that we'll begin
relaxing itself and it also allows for a
the second part of stopping and that is seeing and there's this pairing in buddhism of
stopping and seeing we stop we slow down we calm down
in order to see more clearly and when we're uncomfortable and agitated by that there's not going to be
a lot of clear seeing so to find find find out where that is in the
body and rest in it and breathe with it and so if it's
a social discomfort rather than spitting out in the mind and
the thoughts about what's happening socially find the physical discomfort and rest in it or stand in it or
open to it or breathe with it and that's a this is an art form or it's a skill to learn
this skill of turning towards a discomfort and resting in it um and
you'll probably you might find that there's a kind of rest there's a kind of calmness that can be found in the middle of the
storm by resting attention and just being with it for what this is uncomfortable in
being with it if it's a emotional or psychological discomfort a
social discomfort what has to do with the ideas and thoughts and experiences that happen interpersonally
if it is a if there's physical manifestations of that then
it's really useful to rest in that to stop and really feel it it might be the simplest way the easiest
way to begin relaxing and not being caught in the grip of the social uh
emotional discomfort that might be there the discomfort doesn't have to go away
so that's a little bit of a trap to think you're trying to get rid of it but there's a way of resting in it
that gives us a vantage point in which to see more clearly to not be
seeing through the reactivity we might have so not of course not all social
situations we find ourselves give us a time to do that but there are some where we can just
take take our time which is okay i'm really uncomfortable here let me feel it and be with it
occasionally there's a there's something that's uncomfortable that's not so much physical but
primarily mental or emotional and then it's interesting to also come
to your body and find uh you know find the little remnants of or
little places where traces of that discomfort in your body even though the primary thing is psychological
and and maybe it's easy to relax that way or maybe we find the body
becomes the the holder or the grounding from by which we're not caught or
trapped by the thoughts the stories the judgments that are involved in the
social discomfort we have or if there's uncomfortable things
happening around us we're not so much we're not taking it in as deeply
uh if we feel the body the body becomes more porous or balanced or that sometimes the body becomes more of
a shield even from the social discomfort coming into
the mind or into the heart so to uh to find some place of rest
and in the body in relationship to discomfort
get grounded get stabilized in the body and sometimes that can involve changing
your posture if you're standing stand and stand in such a way that
you're kind of like a that really balanced and strong in the posture like you're both feet they're
firmly on the ground and you're standing tall and maybe even if you can if it allows the situation allows it close
your eyes and really feel be with the body if you're sitting in a chair
uh they're also make sure you don't you're not in a posture that collapses or a posture that is overly tense
but take a balanced kind of upright posture uh that where the body
support the body supports embodied awareness
so they keep coming back to the body and then the second part of it is the seeing
to stop to rest in to stop for the discomfort really feel it
in such a way that the mind quiets down just enough that there is space to really now
study what is really going on here and maybe we can look at all discomfort as a
messenger and the question is what is the message what is it to learn here in the
situation and there's many things that can make us uneasy and sometimes the uneasiness discomfort
is actually a wise thing to listen to there's some real message here something is wrong here something is off and maybe
i need to listen to this maybe i need to pay more careful attention what is going on here and many times in my life i felt
uncomfortable about by about something and it didn't really stop to look at it or take it take it in
and so i i overrid overwrote it and did something or said something that
or participated in something that later i regretted where initially there was the warning this is this doesn't feel
right and now that not feeling right is part of this discom why is discomfort
in other times where my discomfort was limiting me i was afraid and
and so i was uncomfortable because i was somehow neurotically anxious about something
about what was happening and i felt myself pulling back or shutting down and limited by the discomfort
and and i learned that if i stopped and really brought presence to it attention to it
that i could see oh here i am holding myself back i'm anxious i'm i'm afraid
do i need to be afraid should i give into the fear
sometimes it's appropriate to override the fear or open up to the situation be willing to be vulnerable
like for example if it's uh someone is you know has a lot of warmth a lot of
kindness and care and love it can be it can be frightening sometimes to have
someone really love love us but is it necessary to be frightened is it possible to open
what's the message what is the discomfort about and and so sometimes we stop we learn to
rest in the discomfort rest in the physicality of it so we can begin
investigating considering what is the message of discomfort what is it telling us what
is it how is it useful to know and what is the useful way of being
with it is it to open up is it to heed it this is to to
step back is to stay quiet is it to step forward is it to understand ourselves
better is to investigate what is happening here for me so
this willingness this ability to stop for discomfort and to rest in it kind of resting
in the agitation resting in the unresting discomfort is a kind of something is not
really at ease and so resting in the unease
and see what happens discover what happens what opens up and so this resting in discomfort
is a stepping stone to begin being able to ask ourselves what's the message here
what is it to learn here is this discomfort useful and wise is it
not useful is it unwise and we can answer that question much better if we've stopped and figure out
learn how to rest in it and make room for it in space for it and chances are
is that chances are that uh more often than not
there will be at the time you'll have the time the space maybe even just a minute or a few seconds to
step back and and rest in the discomfort and rest in the body the physicality of it and see
what happens see what opens see what you learn see what might relax
so um
and uh so i wish you well some of you will be traveling and going in places where
maybe lots of joy and might also be a fair amount of discomfort as well and
gatherings that might be happening and so maybe it'd be a wonderful laboratory
to explore your discomfort and develop greater wisdom and
self-understanding around this territory of discomfort and maybe
these next days will go easier for you thank you