warm greetings from redwood city in imc and
and delights me to be able to spread these greetings to around the globe to people so many
different places so welcome everyone
and now start with the meditation and i want to mention first that one of
the advantages that can come from sitting meditating a lot
you know meaning perhaps meditating every day day in and day out through whatever
ups and downs that happen in our lives just there's a constant thread the constancy through it all kind of like a
ballast perhaps of a boat that keeps everything balanced is meditation just kind of
that's what we're doing and no question about it and we're literally learned to be with
be mindful of meditate with whatever circumstance of our life that our life might have and slowly
as we are meditating like this regularly through all the ups and downs
there's a very interesting shift that can happen and that is that instead of
at being identified with whatever mood or emotional state that we have
for example to identify with it is to is to say you know i'm afraid or i'm angry
or i'm happy and i've had all those and then not only have i had them and
identified myself with it but uh various times have thought i'll always be this way
i'll always be afraid i'll always be angry and there were once in my life where i thought oh wow i haven't made i'll always be happy
and that didn't last long but i remember having it and uh the um so this identifying like
so being i'm afraid at some point that shifts
and with the regularity of meditation sitting in stability of meditation just sitting there day in and day out
and just kind of watching it all come through at some point instead of identifying
with these emotions and moods we recognize we have these states
so oh there is fear fear is here my old friend fear has returned there is
here is fear or anger is here or
happiness is here or sadness is here there is sadness there is joy
and and there can be a huge difference between being somehow identified defined by the mood
and state somehow it casts it says something about who we are
versus not making it as a definition of who we are our identity or
even our worth maybe it just it's a phenomenon it's here it's
happening to me it's here and and now and that gives a whole different possibility of relating
it to a different way we can then relate to it i think a little bit more respectfully
that's a little hard to do when we're kind of glued to it or enmeshed in it you can kind of step back
away from it and say oh i see you my dear friend i know you're there and i'll spend some
time breathing with you or accompanying you or you're welcome to accompany me
as i as i ride then inhales and exhales
and and we can start to study it or see it we can befriend
our emotions we can explore them we can
allow them in a certain kind of way because they're not us we're not in danger of being influenced
by them and saying and doing things that they were caught in their grip
and maybe we can even release them and they're releasable because they're not us so
as we do this meditation maybe something will come through maybe not
some emotion that's common for you and maybe you'll try out viewing it as
there's the emotion there it is it's present as opposed to i am this way
so taking a comfortable alert posture
and gently closing your eyes
and taking uh just a few moments now to feel your body here
if you felt your body from the inside out what stands out as being predominant
sensations feelings in your body
and then to take a few long deep breaths maybe loving breaths
tender breaths maybe three quarters full
and then a lot maybe longer than the inhale long slow exhale
maybe three quarters complete the exhale not so far that it's a strain
and it's a little ritual of
having your body and mind connect together here they are partners in being present
in the here and now taking these deep breaths
and then letting your breathings return to normal
and also to help you arrive here and be present it can be helpful to relax different
parts of the body we might relax the muscles of the face
soften around the forehead and the temple
letting the eyes rest in their sockets
perhaps softening relaxing the shoulders
perhaps adjusting the position of your hands to make it a little easier for the
shoulders to relax
and then to soften the chest
and soften the belly
and then become aware of the rhythm the natural rhythm of your body
breathing in and breathing out
the rhythm of expansion of the torso as you inhale
the contraction of the torso as you
exhale
taking a few moments to feel whatever stillness or quiet there is
here in your body and mind
even if you're agitated maybe there is still somewhere in the corner of your being
some quiet and stillness
and maybe you can breathe with that sit quietly and still
and if as you're sitting here something occurs in emotion or mood
or sensations of your body comfort and discomfort
or even thoughts perhaps rather than identifying with
them and see them as visitors
there is here now there's this emotion for now there's this since these
sensations for now these thoughts these visitors
that soon enough will change and not be here
but the breathing remains always the breathing
breathing in and breathing out a kind of constancy
running through all things
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps to appreciate that when you're sitting
with some stillness and meditation your posture is not changing so much
that whatever emotion or mood that you have that comes through
is not being expressed in your posture in your body it's allowed to be there
but it doesn't we're not engaged or involved with it
with our body the body just sits upright and still
there's a stability that can arise
that's able to stay stable regardless of what we're feeling
and it's from such a stability where we're not identified with our emotions
involved with our feelings
that all the different flavors of kindness and goodwill and care
can flow and there can be a stability
in which we turn our kind gaze out into the world
we look upon the world kindly we look upon the world in a friendly way
we look upon the world with appreciation at the wonder in the beauty
and the preciousness of all life
from our stability we can look upon the world with care
with good will that's wishing for the welfare and happiness of all
beings maybe even having a vision
of how people would be and how beings would be if they were safe and free and happy
and to wish people well to wish life on this planet well
is a form of generosity and respect and love to wish the best for all beings
may we as we end this sitting gaze upon the world beyond our meditation
with well-wishing may all beings
be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
do
so good day and
welcome to this dharma talk and today i would like to talk about
fear and part of the motivation to talk about it
is that it's a very common state for many people for everyone's some point or
other and also because um i'm finishing up a
year-long program that i'm co-teaching which in experimental is kind of like an experimental program that just
that will probably offer some more in the future some point that's called a path of fearlessness
where we spent uh seven months or so looking at fear and considering it practicing with it and it
comes to a conclusion this week and so it's this bringing this topic for this program to a conclusion
uh has it on my mind and it's what i so this is what i have to talk about
today and
so one thing to it's very important to
i'll say it this way that that as for people who meditate
regularly and uh really familiar with their
of meditating being present for experience and they're familiar with themselves so that
all kinds of things their life comes along when they meditate so
when they're upset they sit down to meditate and they feel the upsetness when they're afraid they sit down to
meditate and their fears there when they're angry they sit down they get to experience the anger when they're
happy or joyful or peaceful or calm they sit down to be with that and
sometimes as we sit some of these things shift and maybe become calmer more settled more stable
and then we might be sitting there quietly and then something suddenly appears out of nowhere and a
thought and memory comes up and there's anger memory comes up and we're
we're remembering what's going to happen tomorrow and there's anxiety that comes up
and so over time it's not a surprise when an emotion appears while we're
meditating and and there can be a
phenomenal shift that happens when we shift from identifying with the
emotion to just recognizing that it's part of what's happening
so to identify means to define oneself by it so if one's angry to assume i'm an
angry person people now are going to relate to me and as if i'm an angry person that defines
who i am and how people will judge me and um
the same thing with fear when becomes one feels like i am afraid boy am i afraid and uh and
when it's kind of leaning into the fear or or being captivated by the fear so
thoroughly so fully it we're kind of assuming it's all of who we are
same thing with happiness and joy but a shift happens in meditation that
at some point that rather than saying oh i'm afraid now
the meditator will say there is fear now there is anger now there is happiness
now and there's not anything there's no inclination to define oneself by it as if it's a
it's a well-worn coat that we're putting on for another time and uh it's just a phenomena just a part
and parcel of what's happening it might be strong and it might be coursing through the
body even but there is a stability of mind that recognizes
there is joy there is sadness there is happiness there is fear
and uh and this ability then to to just see it as a phenomenon
gives rise to a that's present gives rise to a very important
possibilities and this is really when the mindfulness work
can really kind of begin becoming stronger deeper more penetrating
it's a little bit hard to penetrate phenomena if we identify it if we define ourselves by it
because it's almost like we've so fully defined by it it's like we can't normally without a
mirror we can't see the eyes that see we see through the eyes but we don't
turn back and look at the eyes and see them and if we're really defined by something by an emotional state
we might know it's there we might recognize that i'm angry or sad or happy or afraid
but it's kind of like it's the filter through which we see so it's not really quite accessible for
clearly seeing and really recognizing there it is but when it comes to time when we can
say oh fear is here this gives birth to new possibilities
and um and so i'd like to talk about four categories of
possibilities with how we can be with fear once we can just see it that it's present
and not not defined by it or identified by it and and i you know
i thought it was fun maybe to come up with an acronym with the letters for fear and
and so the first thing we can do is now that it's become a verb
thanks to facebook i think we can friend our fear we can befriend it and
and this idea of becoming a friend for our fear is a really powerful thing to
do it's the opposite of being afraid of fear it's the opposite of being a versus it's
very radically different being aversive to fear and angry at fear or ashamed of fear or
trying to fix fear or attacking fear or trying to analyze it or
or figure out what's going on it's um it's kind of like if you're with a
friend you don't want to do all those things with your friend you want to be present for your friend
and hear what's going on with a friend you haven't seen the friend for a while you want to hear what's happening what's going on and
and be with them in a way that's respectful and caring for them
and it's possible to do that with fear it's harder to do it when we are defined by it but it's easier to do
if we recognize it that it's just there in a kind of way i'm here and fear is there
fear fear is part of me and but it's not quite me so i can look at
it without it kind of being a filter through which i see
and the value of becoming a friend to it is uh similar to um it's not quite just i'm jumping
around a little bit but if um you know if a young child is
afraid we don't get angry at it we don't run away from it we don't get all flustered and confused
and running around in circles when the kids sitting on the floor being afraid
you don't berate the kid you sit down with the kid and maybe put this
kid is small enough you put the kid on your lap or you hold it and you're there with it
so there's all these ways we say that when once we kind of kind of identify recognize that fear is there
we want to first friend the fear and one of the great values of friending
it is that the fear feels safe
the fear doesn't feel like it's being shamed or pushed away or denied or unwanted
and which is hard just like would be hard for a little child and it's one of the fascinating and
wonderful tasks of mindfulness is to help our fear feel safe
and now it's a little counter-intuitive you know some people never thought about helping their fear feel safe and
and if we are afraid if they were defined by like then it's hard to offer anything to the
fear but when we come to that point in practice when we can recognize
fear is present and we're not so inclined to say i am afraid
then we have something we can offer the fear and we become the one who offers
safety offers stability who offers kindness who makes space for it to be there and uh
and and start to listen and look more deeply what's here
and that's the e of fear and that's to explore the fear so rather than recoil from the
fear it's to step in a sense towards it to explore it to be with it to feel it
more fully and and one of the first things we can do
in exploring it is we can try to assess whether the fear is appropriate or not
we can try to see is this a appropriate fear to have or is it not is it a real fear or is it
not is it a healthy fear to have or is it not healthy
or my favorite pairing is it helpful fear or is it not helpful
and some fear clearly is helpful to have it protects us and and sometimes we need
protection if we there are
times when i'm driving my car or walking on a street where i feel a little bit afraid
there's a little bit of fear there that's kind of kind of inseparable inside of me from a
sense of caution and the you know it's something sometimes it is a little bit
scary maybe if i was different than who i who i am i wouldn't be afraid of certain kind of
traffic situations but i don't think it's necessarily wrong because they're it's uh death can be instantaneous in
some of these crossing some sidewalks some some crosswalks uh the way some drivers drive and and um
so the fear protects us is look before you walk across the crosswalk or something
and and so and so in buddhism one of the appropriate fears is the fear
of doing something of oneself doing something that injures one's own
integrity that injures one's own sensitivity to
compassion to kindness to honesty
once to harms one's sensitivity or one's orientation to live a life that doesn't cause harm
to anyone else and um and to into when we feel like
we're in the danger of saying something to someone that's very unkind and hurtful
to feel that fear no this is dangerous i don't think i should say this i should be careful here the mood that
i'm in right now is not a this is a little dangerous mood i'm in
i could easily snap at someone and later regret what i've done what i would have said
so i'm afraid of myself a little bit because of this mood i see what i've done before
and so i'm going to be cautious maybe i'm going to learn to hold my tongue or maybe i'm even going to avoid certain
stressful situations when i'm in this mood if i can avoid them so the idea of
we have something to protect here also we're afraid to hurt people and they
if the simple fear of not wanting to hurt others is a very healthy i think
fear to have and um and uh and so this kind of
and they say in the ancient world in the teachings of the buddha that people or practitioners have fear
for causing the slightest fault slightest harm
and and hopefully this is not seen as a debilitating fear a fear which diminishes who we are
but actually it's a fear that protects what's the best in us and allows it to grow
so buddhism recognizes healthy fear but there's also unhelpful fear the fear that is
debilitating the fear that does uh freeze us in the way or or inhibits us
or keeps us from living a full life or engaged properly in the world sometimes it's fear that causes us to
harm others sometimes it's fear that causes us to harm ourselves because it's we're so afraid of
the alternative and so we we keep ourselves in check and close down because of it or collapse
so as we explore fear we can recognize when it seems helpful and when it
seems not helpful we can uh and even when it's principle fear can be
helpful the strength of the fear or the way that we engage in the fear or take in the fear
can be debilitating can be limiting and so to this idea of exploring the
fear what's going on here what's happening here for me is a wonderful stance wonderful
kind of sense of inner strength that begins to operate from the stability of practice
of mindfulness what is this what's going on here
and one of the things we can ask is what we're afraid of so this question of
the study of exploring fear i see it as a movement of respect
that we respect the fear we're not belittling fear or or deleting ourselves because we are
fear and i like to think that all every fear that we have should be respected because it's a
messenger sometimes it's a messenger that there is in fact the danger
but sometimes it's a messenger that something inside of us feels threatened and it's possible to
feel and so so sometimes it's important to look and see what's the real danger
explore is there a danger right now and sometimes in the here and now what we're afraid of
is not present and that's a fascinating thing to realize
that what we're afraid of is partly a product of our imagination
and some people have said that anxiety is completely an issue of imagination
it might be a real imagination but it's imagining what's going to happen in the future it's predicting something sometimes it's
a it's a wise prediction but um then it has a kind of anxiety it kind of lives in and
simmers inside that
but some people have chronic anxiety that it just kind of almost stands
they've learned there's been so much pain and so much danger for them in their life that it becomes kind of habitual and to
be expected there's always a threat always something's going to happen that's dangerous and we don't know what
it is there's nothing concrete right here and now but in that sense it's imaginary it's a potentially
something here so to
so we can see clearly you know that and to see that is not present maybe can give a breathing room that
here and now maybe it's not as if not as dangerous as we thought and there could be some relaxation
also we can look at um so we can look at what's what we're
afraid of but for dharma practice a very significant
exploration of fear is to look and see what's being threatened
what is it that's really going on here with inside of me and that i'm afraid that's going to be
hurt or damaged or what's what is it that feels threatened and
and sometimes what's being threatened is real enough integrity is kind of real enough important enough to protect
but sometimes what's being protected doesn't really have
such a strong real basis sometimes what's being protected what's
being threatened are the constructs that we live under uh the constructs of self the ideas the
what we had how we've identified us how we've constructed our idea of who we are
so for example if a person that constructs the idea of themselves
as they need to be wise and funny all the time then
anything that uh that uh if they feel fear maybe it's because they're with their how other people see
them is being threatened that their idea their identity as being a wise and funny
person is threatened but that the idea being there's no need to be a wise and funny person
that's a constructed particular notion idea without that idea there's that can't be
threatened the idea that we have to be someone that everyone likes
that we have to be someone who we we are someone or with what's being threatened is that
um we're we're somehow an undesirable person and so we're constantly being
threatened by everyone because we're afraid we're going to be pushed away by people or rejected by people
and so it gets a little more complicated when when the what's being threatened is
a little bit of a imagination a concept an idea
a construct and it maybe doesn't quite exactly have to be there
maybe we're stuck on some idea that it doesn't have to be there like i know
when i was younger i thought it was a life and death matter
almost you know whether uh someone liked me or didn't like me
and so uh i was had a lot of fear about social fear about then you know i was
constantly assessing and wondering and hoping that people would like me and and
it was a big revelation to me they realized that um everyone everyone doesn't have to like
me it's okay if some people don't like me and and i don't have to constantly be
concerned about it and to see that begin to kind of shed and drop away create a lot more peace inside of me
social peace and ease and in fact sometimes people don't like me
and that's okay they're they're allowed to do that and and sometimes people do and that's nice
too so this idea of exploring there's a
whole series of things that can be explored around fear but but the important principle is
um to not be caught by the fear uh so that we can't and one way not to be
caught by it is to explore it take the initiative okay let's let's discover what's going on here and
there's all these different ways of discovery and you can have your own way and but just keep looking and feeling and getting to
know the a of fear is um
is to really allow it to be there the more we can discover it more we can
explore it and then we really allow it and but not allow it to run us and tell
us what to do and how to see things but this is really now a continuation of this
there is fear here i'm not the fear but there is fear here
with me in me and so and then to discover how it experi how
to know and discover it how it appears physically what's the physical manifestation of fear
and then allow that physicality of fear to be there almost as if you get out of the way from
it and sometimes it's best to do this in short bouts especially when there's a
terror or very strong a very strong fear that is connected to all this it's better not
to explore it and be with it for very long but just to touch into it for a while
and then pull away and come back to another day and slowly slowly kind of befriend it slowly
get to know it but at some point the beautiful art of mindfulness
is to really allow it to be there and allow it without our reactivity
around it without our needing it to be different so it's just a little bit an extension of
befriending the fear and allowing it and part of the value of that
is that our inner life knows how to take care of itself knows
how to unwind knows how to release knows how to morph into what needs to happen next and so if we learn to learn the art
of just allowing the fear to be there it's impressive what can happen and
that's also a hard skill to learn when we when the habit is we have to
analyze it or we have to engineer a change or we have to fix it or something like that
and to learn how to allow it in meditation is a wonderful skill because some fears
maybe we maybe we can't get rid of it or it will always be with us but with the art of allowing it
befriending it knowing it's there exploring it and allowing it can mean
that we might be able to have the fear be present but not
be inhibited or limited by it we bring it along it sits on our left shoulder
and it's there with us we know it's there but we're not going to stop what we're doing it's not going to get us to cower or
shut down or not live the life our life as we want to live it but we allow that the fear comes along
and accompanies us and it's there we recognize it's present
but we know how to allow it so that it does it can just be there and not interfere
and then they are of fear is to is to release as that's the freedom part
of fear and and that has different com different sides of release
sometimes the fear is released and it's no longer there that especially if the underlying thing
that was threatened i know no longer is there or they realize that what was threatened doesn't
really exist it doesn't has no real kind of substantial existence
and and so the constructs of self and the self definitions we have
when we learn to be at peace without a self definition be at peace without a self construct
we're trying to build up or defend or protect or hide from people then
that fear that that thing that there's nothing there threatened around self-identity
and so people all kinds of things people can do they might you know they can't hurt that identity
because we're not holding on to that identity we're not defining ourselves by that and it just
goes right through um and so we're free of it and sometimes
what's being released is not the fear but rather is uh
the um our pre our clinging or attachment or selfing or
identification with the fear and we release ourself from the fear
the fear is still there but we are released from it and then it's much easier to have the
fear be present and then just live our life as we want to or as
is appropriate so to friend the fear to explore the fear
to allow the fear and to release in relationship to the
fear these are four things to explore but
the emphasis for this talk is this is meant for people who have
capable of having some disidentification from fear not disassociation from it
but this identification the sense that they don't define themselves by their fear but they're able to sit be quiet and
breathe easily perhaps and recognize oh there is fear
fear is present i'm not the fear but boy is there fear present that fear
is strong but you know i'm not the fear and then that allows for this interesting
phenomena interesting practice of friend the fear explore the fear
allow the fear and release the fear and then fear has become
a four-fold practice that we engage in so next time you feel fear you might
remember that fear is an acronym for a practice
that we look fear where we respect the fear by getting to know it well
it's a messenger do we understand what the message is
so thank you very much and may you explore your fear
and discover the wonderful place inside where there is no fear because
it's a place that cannot be threatened so thank you