hello and welcome everyone lovely to be with you this time and space
as violet said here and now whatever the time zone might be whatever the weather internally and
externally might be so for our practice today we're
going to continue with this beautiful practice of equanimity cultivating equanemity upeka
um the fourth brahmavihara the fourth heavenly abode practice and
upeka the word in pali equanimity translated as equanimity
equipoise has the sense of
large view having this expansiveness of you seeing over seeing
fully so yesterday we practiced as
we're going through these concentric circles traditionally all these practices you cultivate them
expand your heart little by little starting where it's easy expanding a little by little towards
more challenging so yesterday the concentric circle we extended ourselves to
was the benefactor and tonight it's the next traditional category which
is the good friend dear friend or just friend someone
whom we care about we're friendly um relationship we have a friend
relationship with them and um and what we'll do
today as always we'll spend some time at the beginning of our practice
to settle in with our bodies with the breath just arriving settling settling arriving
the body embodiment embodiment i'll say that trillion times how
important embodiment really coming to the body sensing the body stability is
and then we'll open up as i'll invite you with guidance
with practice practicing equanimity cultivating equanimity
um offering some reflections some sentences
some phrases of meta which also if you're on the happy hour google groups
you receive them earlier this week and neil sent them out so they're
already there if you want to go back and or if you want to to sign up now that you have the link
and see what entire list of different phrases of of equanimity of upeka what different
options are i'll offer a few today so anything else i want to say oh yes
one last thing to always say is is uh if you're a beginner great
welcome to happy hour whatever you need to know will be shared with you so no previous experience necessary and
just to also say that the near enemy the what what massacre
raids as equanimity is aloofness not caring and if you see that in
yourself oh then my invitation is to try to connect a little more
with your sense of care friendliness with with your friend the person you'll be
bringing up in your heart your care for them so that you there's a sense of care
presence as well as holding it with a lot of spaciousness
[Music] okay let's begin all right so
ah let's settle let's settle into our
bodies our meditation posture whether you need to lie down
or sit up straighter see what your body needs right now check
in with your body if your body needs to move and shift a little bit it gets to settle
your sit bone center of gravity it's it's okay too
so landing arriving
feeling your feet on the ground if you're sitting on the
cushion your legs
and your set bones your bottom on the cushion on the chair feeling these contact
points just taking a moment to feel connected
inviting inviting your abdomen to relax
for any tightness or tension in the lower abdomen groin area
your bottom to be dropped to dropped ah falling
into the cushion onto the earth
and inviting your chest to soften your heart
you're hard to relax feeling safe it's okay to your heart it's okay
entering a judgment-free zone
for the period of this practice whatever arises is fine you're doing your best
letting your heart feel safe relaxed
dropping your neck shoulders
your arms your hands
as if any tension as if all tension is dripping dripping
away down from the arms shoulders
hands
your entire lower body
and your face hold muscles
loosening the forehead the jaw and the muscles from the inside
behind your cheeks
behind your forehead connecting your ears your jaw
at all those muscles drop relax drop their weight their tension
and let the breath be received in this relaxed soft body
in the abdomen
and if thoughts are arising gently kindly ask
do i need to be thinking this right now
is it really necessary
with lightness with a sense of humor without judgment
letting it go it's okay it's important enough it'll come back
later coming back to the body to the breath
in this moment taking refuge in the simplicity of just
sitting and being breathed
intimately intimately connecting with the breath the entirety of the in-breath and the
out breath in the abdomen not from afar not from the control tower
of the head but as if your abdomen was an
organ of perception receiving the breath
the abdomen has the organ of perception
sensing the in-breath and the out-breath
now allowing the whole body to feel
as if it's an organ of perception
your hands receiving sensations of contact
coolness warmth
your lower body receiving the contact points sense of touch
connected rooted to the earth
sensations of the breath fell in the abdomen or wherever they're felt
whatever sensations are felt in and of themselves again not from the
control tower of the head
say with the hands as if your mind was in the hands in your hand sensing
sensations of contact
letting the sense of stability
of the body presence breathing connected
the earth element earth on earth the body is earth element
a sense of solidity of sensations contact points
sitting on earth
and just as a well-rooted tree with roots through the earth
doesn't topple over in a wind no windstorm
with gentleness just as the bodies both relaxed and soft
and grounded rooted
just like a buddha statue
sitting on a platform stable grounded
this body this amazing magnificent body
that is yours and not yours as your very own buddha statue here
sitting on earth stable
stability equanimity equipoise
caring connected
present here
and not easily tupled over
well rooted connected to the earth
just being breathed stable spacious grounded
and now i'd like to invite you as you feel connected to your body
sensing feeling this organ of perception sensing itself
bring up someone who serves as a friend for you in the
easy category and when you think of them there's a
sense of ease safety care for them
maybe you feel their sense of care too
not losing contact with embodiment of each breath
bringing up a felt sense
an image as if they were in front of you
best good friend this dear friend
could be someone you haven't seen for a long time there is a sense of
friendliness
again it doesn't have to be every aspect of your life or their life that's connected but
there's a sense of connection and ease and care
bringing them to your mind's eye
feeling connected to them as if you're having a conversation with them
if you're having a zoom call with them or facetime just seeing seeing them
feeling them hearing them whatever senses are most accessible for you
notice what happens for you in your body maybe a sense of ease care connection
maybe a smile shows up
this place of stability in your body and connected to your care
warmth meta for this person for this friend
connecting to their goodness
to their care for you
to your appreciation for for them for their humanity
for their goodness
and now connected to this friend your sense of care
good will friendliness meta for them
and a sense of stability in your body
now bringing to mind one aspect of your friend's
life that has some challenges
and first letting yourself connect to your sense of care
before this friend
of the challenge they're going through
meeting meeting the friend and the challenge with care with worms
and now as you stay connected with this friend and their challenge
opening up to the practice of equanimity equipoise
knowing that you do care about this friend
but their well-being
what they're going through right now that's challenging for them you care for them
and without turning away and without falling into neither turning away
nor falling into the challenge acknowledging that they have
their own journey you care about them you wish them well
you wish them goodness happiness freedom from suffering
and you can't make their choices for
them
i care about you
and your happiness and unhappiness depends on your actions not my wishes for you
i wish you ease and may you accept
and have equanimity with things as they are right now
staying connected embodied with each breath
and connected to this friend their goodness your care for them their care for you
and holding their journey both in care with a lot of space
spaciousness
i care for you
i care for you and i can't make your choices for you
i care for you and i acknowledge you like all beings
have your own journey
hey you may i may we
have peace with the comings and goings of things
with things as they are
i care for you and whether i understand it or not
things are unfolding according to a lawful nature
may i accept what is may you accept what is with ease and equanimity and balance
and for the last moments of this practice period
opening up equipoise equanimity for whatever arose
or did not arise during this practice
period sense of peace ease openness to the unfolding
just as it happened without resisting judging
pushing away grasping
freedom freedom of heart freedom of heart
letting it be just as it was just as it arose
with peace
may all beings everywhere
be at peace
may all beings everywhere be free in their hearts and minds
including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so we have some time for reflections
for questions for reports from the field of your
experience reports from the field that can be
supportive not just for yourself as you verbalize them but also supportive for
the entire community
so what did you notice what a rose and especially if you haven't shared for a
while or spoken you are invited to please share you can raise your hand
your zoom hand or type in chat and if you type
privately to me i won't say your name and if you type to everyone i will
read it out loud with your name
jessie please all right thank you yeah so
a question that's coming up for me is because you had mentioned that aloofness is uh one of the enemies
near afar i'm not i forget uh yeah okay thank you yeah so what that
brings up for me is um just a question about curiosity and investigation
and how much because i find that uh you know to i don't want to be
distant i want to be engaged and but it just strikes me that too much
engagement or curiosity or investigation seems to kind of go to another
side where it's uh it doesn't feel autonomous anymore i'm wondering if you could uh comment on
that yeah thank you so much for raising this because this is so important that
balance so yes too much investigation too much kind of being in it like this thing that's
happening to you actually you can tell me if that's what's coming up what do you mean by
investigation there is that what you mean or do you mean something different yeah exactly i just like i guess i feel
like i i don't want to get too wrapped up in whatever is arising the hindrance or
the aversion or the correct grasping whatever it might be right but uh uh not too aloof
either yeah yeah perfect so so actually your question what you're
raising here is is a perfect opportunity to to talk a little more about and tease out
not just the near enemy but the far enemy which is the opposite the far enemy is the opposite i love this
archaic language fire enemy is the opposite near enemy is the masquerade or something that feels like it aloofness
often is what it feels like and then the opposite is um aversion or entanglement what you
were describing like oh and and it's okay follow you you notice you're
investigating well this is how it happens i fall into the the far enemy becomes the opposite it's
not equipoise holding it all it's too too entangled with this friend and their
suffering or it's like oh i don't like it make it go away right so so that's exactly that so the the the
invitation i have is great you've noticed that the first thing is to notice instead of
practicing practice the thinking we're practicing equanimity but we're actually entangled in there or we're having a lot of aversion so
without any judgment noticing oh this is what's happening okay here it is the
are i knew you were going to show up at some point okay now i get to practice with you and kind of find my way on my way with this practice
so so noticing it and what what can support that is the sense of
uh connection and care is kind of spacious you know you care for someone but you're
not in there trying to fix their problems you care for them and you're giving them
so much space there's so much space it's almost like loving someone from afar
you care for them and you know that this is their journey and
it is part of your journey too so there's that's where you can still be connected the sense of care
but with a lot of space giving them space does that does that help jesse tell me what's coming up for
you yeah that's great i guess because something you said was that uh
equanimity has a quality of warmth to it and i guess i'm finding that it also
has a quality of kind of a gentle action you know not not just ignoring things
but yeah the application of wisdom so yeah that's great yeah yeah great yeah thank you yeah it's
it's and the gentle action is is it's ac the gentle action of inaction
in a way like giving the action is not getting entangled giving a lot of
space staying engaged i mean that's the parts that the action you're talking about
it's beautiful because it's a way of staying present staying present and
and one one image that comes up for me is at the deathbed of someone you care for and love and knowing that it is at
the end and you can't get in there and try to fix it and you can't hate it just holding presents holding press
you're engaged you're breathing with them and there's a sense of yeah this is this is the
journey that needs to happen thank you so much for for bringing that
up jesse very very helpful thank you yeah and linda says i had to make myself
the friend odd but beneficial great great that's
that's terrific it all works what however doing the practice works for you
in this way you can be your own friend in fact i often think of ourselves
where we can both be our benefactor our good friend we can be our difficult person sometimes
neutral person like person we don't quite know really we think we know so we can work with
ourselves with all of those categories and forrest says equanimity seems to be
much subtler than the other brahmaviharas and i often find i have a hard time identifying is this
it or tapping into it yeah thank you forrest um equanimity is subtler
absolutely glad you're calling it out which is why it's the fourth one we kind of build up to it with practicing the
other three um and and um
the the um questioning is this id is this not
um there's a sense of you know equipoise kind of both
there's a care but there's an openness so um and you will know when you're in
it when you fall out of it so that's the invitation i have for you first kind of when you feel like ah this feels like a
looseness or too much attachment and then you go into equanimity oh this is more refined the lens of perception becomes uh more
attuned and jerry asks is it the process
also of setting boundaries um [Applause]
it it could be i mean this is a slightly different language and different uh per
different lens setting boundaries but in in some ways is giving them their own
boundary giving them space right you can uh maybe it's a boundary of spacious right
it's somehow yes you can think of it as boundary but somehow setting a boundary
seems that you don't care anymore i mean you are still caring you're still and yet you it's so um
i don't know how helpful it is to use the that terminology might be maybe not but maybe i'll just leave it at that
yeah thank you all right so very rich um
reflections and conversation so let's
take our practice on the road question mark road and practice it in
instead of just silently with ourselves with our eyes closed now in the field of interpersonal
relationships with people who uh are practitioners with you in this field
so in small groups let's start with 30 seconds of
award-less meta for each other knowing that other people are wishing goodwill for
you and then sharing however little or much you like to share about
your practice and this way of connecting with equanimity um and ease so i'm going to
create the uh rooms here here we go
okay so almost there
okay ready opening opening them now okay welcome back everyone the rooms
are closed and we have a couple minutes for reflections what did you notice what did
you find out and especially if you haven't shared or are new um
i'd love to hear from you what came up for you
and if you raise your physical hand i may not see you
anything you notice that came up especially when you were discussing with others parents please
i just feel so supported in this practice and this is subtle and you know not always sure that we're
in the right vein and i just really really support this or or
i'm so grateful for this uh venue of practice
very good thank you thank you
thank you thank you thank you parents for for your words and for
also for you being here and supporting others with your practice with your
it just presence me that you feel supported yay and may we all feel supported in our
practice and in our lives so
and sarah says i second that a deep sense of gratitude towards everyone here in nikki
ah thank you sarah thank you for seconding that and and for your presence here
supporting yourself in this practice and supporting the sangha and all of you for showing up so i want
to thank you all for showing up for practicing both for your own sake and the sake of
all those whose lives you touch within the sangha outside the
sangha in your life your colleagues the world so
thank you all may all beings be free in their heart
may all beings have peace and ease and equanimity
thank you i'd delight to share with you