your dharma great so so hello and welcome everyone welcome to
happy hour wonderful to be with you wonderful to see you
so so for the theme of today practicing together
i wanted to bring in the the support of of practicing loving
kindness called cultivating the sense of safety
and care and goodness in our heart and how that can actually be a support for letting go
and diana and i just taught a retreat that ended yesterday sunday
on the theme of we called it um released into love so there was about
letting go letting go releasing and about
love spaciousness peace ease so many things that we let go
into so letting go isn't just this this bleak thing that the heart does let
go into nothing but it's letting go into more peace more ease more freedom
and and love and many of you actually i see you were part of the retreat yay good to
see you again long time no see since yesterday so so with that um
[Music] yeah so what else do i want to say
before practicing together well okay i'll say that um
if you are new to happy hour welcome anything everything you need to know
will be shared with you and we always start um i'll start the
guided meditation with some settling just bringing some
attention awareness to the body to the breath to till the soil till the
soil of the mind just settle arrive and then there'll be some invitations
to try something on for size cultivation of kindness good will maybe
exploring something that we want to release or being with it gently saying if it wants
to be let go of so we'll see what happens we'll enter all of this with the spirit of
curiosity exploration and humility
so let's give our hearts to cultivation to goodness
and see what wants to arise what what needs to arise in this moment
so let's start together ah so i'd like to invite you
settle into your meditation posture you need to move and shift
maybe you need to move your body a little bit before settling finding your sit bones
maybe you need to move to lie down or move to a chair or cushion it's all okay
see how you can be comfortable how you can be comfortable for this practice
comfortable while your spine is is straight whether sitting or lying
down having an integrity in your posture
and then landing arriving
ah arriving in the body
in this moment
i'm inviting inviting yourself to let go
of any thoughts preoccupations that you might have had just minutes ago
and also let go of all the words that just came before this endangered in the
introduction letting go letting go it's okay ah
let me go into some the simplicity of this moment with this breath
taking refuge
in just being
however it shows up in this moment
the mystery the magic of the breath being breathed
on its own
with each out breath
ah releasing releasing [Music]
into the body releasing any tightness
or holding tension
any tension in the forehead in the face
with the next out breath
asking can it be released
as if gently posing the question ever so gently
dear darling forehead
dear jaw ah
would you like to let go of any tension
that's being held around you in you
similarly at the next outbreath
now seeing the neck and shoulders ah where we often carry
a lot of tightness
dear hard working neck and shoulders holding up this head
ah is there any tension you like to let go
of at the next out breath
similarly moving the attention down the arms the hands
inviting to release to soften
dividing the chest the abdomen the lower back
the upper back
to relax
the lower abdomen
the next out breath releasing
the sit bones the contact points of our bottom with the cushion or the
chair ah releasing into the chair
into the earth the upper legs
the lower legs and feet
giving their weight releasing their weight onto the earth letting gravity
pull down [Music] ah and the whole body and all the
muscles
no extra effort needed to hold ourselves up
letting the body relax let go of any extra unneeded effort
letting the breath be breathed you don't have to make breathing into a project
notice that happens on its own it's been happening for years on its own
simply notice the breath is breathing
itself
and as thoughts arise as they inevitably do
for the sake of our training together our practice together
can they be released in this moment kindly gently as if opening your hands
holding helium balloons letting them go
it's okay you might need to
release them many times it's okay do it gently during this period of
practice gently gently
letting awareness loving awareness
receive the breath in the lower abdomen
as if the breath
moving on its own meet awareness
in the abdomen not in the control tower of the head
as if the lower abdomen is an organ of perception receiving the breath
if you're thinking about something
it's okay notice notice the balloons of thought that are being
held being clung to it's okay
can they gently be released in this moment for the sake of this practice this training letting them go
ah feeling lighter landing in the body
with the calming soothing in breath and out breath
and now i'd like to invite you
to bring to mind as if sitting in front of you a good friend
someone you care about with whom you don't have a complicated
relationship could also be a benefactor
someone who's been there for you or even a child or a pet
someone about whom you have warm feelings
and care and good will
maybe when you think of them you feel safe sense of ease
overcomes you maybe a smile shows up on your face connecting
the felt sense of this being maybe what they look like if you're
[Music] visual
or their felt sense or how they sound if you're auditory
getting a felt sense of them so you're talking to them interacting with them
or having a facetime or the zoom call with them just contouring
their presence up and how you feel about them
wishing them well wanting them to be
happy
and from a sense of connection
staying connected to this being [Music] you can say the metaphrases you have or
i'll offer the traditional ones four phrases may you be safe
may you be safe dear one
sharing it as an offering it's a blessing as if your heart is
gifting gifting these good wishes releasing gifting these good wishes
to this being may you be safe
i wish you safety
may you be happy
giving a gift from your heart
your wish for happiness may you be happy dear friend dear one
may you be happy
may you be healthy i wish you health
as if offering them this wish of well-being goodness giving them a gift
maybe giving them a flower petals whatever imagery works for you
is offering of goodness
and the fourth meant to wish may you have ease
may you have ease dear one gifting this gift giving this
gift of generosity of spirit may you be filled with ease
may your life unfold with ease
may you be safe
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you have ease
feeling each phrase as an act of generosity giving
a good wish wish of goodness may you be safe
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you have these
feel the rhythm of your breath
with the words calming and serving
this gift-giving
safe happy
healthy
ease
imagining that with each phrase you're giving them a gift of goodness
offering giving away offering up
goodness
if you find your mind is filled with thoughts see if you can let go the same
letting go same act of release that your heart has been practicing with
this gift-giving giving of blessings is it release
is it giving is it letting go not keeping goodness just for yourself
but sharing it with others same embodiment of a hand releasing
the same way see if thoughts preoccupations ruminations could be
released ah let go of
as if put on the altar here buddha dear quranian
embodiment of compassion hold this one for me please i'll put it on the altar i offer it up
i offer it up i release it i let go of it
and inviting your awareness your attention back to offer phrases of goodness
meta friendliness good will dear friend
benefactor whomever you've chosen
giving gifts releasing goodness onto them
same practice same movement of the heart
may you be safe dear one
i offer you wish of safety in my mind in my heart
may you be happy dear one
may you be healthy dear one
imagining visioning an act of giving of goodness
may you have ease dearly
and for the last minutes of this practice period
connecting connecting with this movement of the heart
she's releasing giving away giving a gift a blessing is generosity
every release the other side of the coin is an act of generosity
giving connecting with this movement of the heart and giving
goodness good will friendliness giving it away
and noticing if your heart feels any brighter or happier
for having given it away having released it
to know it's also the same movement of the heart when we release thoughts judgments
preoccupations
emotions when they're ready same letting go
and now letting go releasing into appreciation whatever this practice
period was like
if the mind was sleepy distracted it's okay you did your best
you showed up as best as you were able to do to show up in this moment
appreciating that you showed up
did your best cultivating seeds of goodness and kindness
for yourself and all beings everywhere
may all beings be free all beings be happy including ourselves
thank you everyone thank you for your practice so
so what i wanted to bring attention to is how
this act of releasing this movement of releasing or giving giving
this movement of giving giving blessings giving goodness
sharing meta sharing good wishes
that also is is the same as the release when we
release when we let go as i mentioned the thought of preoccupation
and there is this beautiful word chaga that i mentioned on the retreat which is
both means release relinquishment giving away and also it means generosity
and with generosity we have this association of brightness there is a sense of gladness
generosity ah what a bright beautiful sense it's the same movement of the heart
releasing giving away and the heart gladdens it feels fuller it feels happy
and chaga generosity is a precondition for happiness
in buddhist teachings a heart that is generous that doesn't cling to
you name it doesn't cling to bitterness doesn't cling to preoccupation doesn't cling
to stuff it's it's a generous heart it's a happy heart
and one more thing to say is there's plenty of research about how our
cognition is embodied embodied cognition embodied cognition so these words that
we use release really there were based on actions activities so if you're wondering well
how do i let go how do i let go if that's a question that comes over you then practice
giving things away practice that physical tangible giving away to give gifts
give smiles give give things away that's our same it's the same it's the same action
either physically or emotionally mentally so so
plenty to work with and practice with so we have some time
for reflections or questions what you might have noticed that came up for you
you can raise your zoom hand or you can type them in chat and if you type them
to me alone i will not say your names will be private if you type them to everyone
then i'll say your name you'll be public so reflections
eric please
thanks nikki i guess the difference for me that made it hard to connect the
two was that giving somebody a gift of peace or happiness seemed nice and
giving away all my ruminations didn't seem like anyone would want those or something bad to give away so yeah
[Music] yeah yeah i appreciate you bringing that up eric and that's something that comes
up a lot so so the invitation as i brought it during the guided meditation
is is imagine that you're releasing them first of all releasing
them into goodness because whenever something is released if there's a sense of freedom you know when you're
freeing their ruminations there's a goodness that's being generated and yet with the question that you're asking well nobody would want the
the bastard of the pain the sorrow the roommates imagine you're putting them on the lap of the buddha or kuan yin
embodiment of compassion or whatever figure that represents compassion for you and they're strong enough their
heart is so big they'll hold it with you they'll hold it for you here the sorrow
hold it with me please will you i'll put it on your lap i'll release it sort of like my it's like ah it's not
personal let's it's more universal it's a part of the human condition so that's the invitation i have for you
to consider how does that sound derek
i'll try it thank you great thank you eric
other questions or reflections that came up for you why did you notice
did any of you notice your heart was happier more glad there was more lightness
from actually this act of offering this generosity of giving someone else in your mind goodness
yes i see nicolas says yay has a celebratory nicholas do you want
to say more oh um yeah just uh
feeling into the presence of the person is very supportive and um yeah i was i was
playing with there was tension in my shoulders and neck and there was
warmth towards the person and kind of feeling the the interplay between those and i mean there's warmth as there's release
it was fun to build that physically a little bit that was really great nice so so the sense of just the warmth
and the heart and releasing some tension in the back and the interplay of of of this release and that release is
is that what you were saying did i hear that right and i muted on accident yes exactly so
there's kind of a sense of bringing some attention to the tension and then naturally it settles out a bit
and then there's a little bit more space to feel good will there's the into that space there's a little bit more room
towards the person yeah oh sweet so what i'm hearing is kind of being have being with the goodwill and
then bringing attention to this tightness it's like oh it released a little bit there was a little more space and then there was more space for the
goodwill and then there was more goodwill and then there was more space for the tension to release so it was a virtuous cycle it's a
virtuous cycle ah lovely beautiful observation yes that's how it works yes the virtual
cycle that's lovely yeah that's the yeah and it and it's it's the same release i'm so glad you
you brought this up because it's the same gift it's the same release it's kind of like the same it's like way the tightness oh yeah just
a little bit of release oh here there's a gifting so thank you for reporting that because
it's the same movement of the heart one more reflection is that uh yeah just like it also helps because i'm more okay
with not forcing release of tension but there's a sense of forcing goodwill so it kind of informed both ways because
it was like oh i don't force or release the tension that lets go and in the same way oh i didn't have to kind of press the gas pedal
it filled the space that it was given brilliant oh i i love that that they
both informed each other yeah but the gentleness of the release of this like
oh yeah this could just be gentle to just be an offering it's kind of like opening the same way that you kind of invite the
um you know the tension ah do you like to release oh yes it's it's safe it's kind it's nice it wants
to release it in the same way would you like to offer kindness and goodwill in this moment oh yes i feel
i like this person i do want to offer goodwill yeah great thank you so much nicholas
lovely and jerry says it was helpful to start the focus
on the abdomen than the mind yes well i would say that
maybe i would shift that because and say focus on the abdomen instead of
the head because where is your mind embodied mind your mind might be your mind is in your abdomen jerry
so you are focusing on your mind it's just that it's in the abdomen
love that love that so dear all let's uh so eva hold that for
when we come back from small conversations because i want to make sure we have time for that so i'd
love to hear from you is that okay well so yeah great thank you so
now the invitation is in small groups practicing in sangha in small groups of three which
many of you love and many of you at this point think ah i'm gonna get off so so if if you like
to stretch yourself just a little bit and the idea here is it's just six minutes seven minutes of
uh speaking with like-minded practitioners and we start with 30 seconds of
meta just silent meta goodwill for each other and you receive it also may you be well may you be happy
and then sharing whatever you like to say about your practice and holding others holding you you holding them in
safety and in care it can be so powerful to connect and practice with others and anything you say is
is fine there's no right or wrong but speak from your own practice what do you experience even it was confused or
or distracted it's okay just showed up like this in this moment it's all fine so with that
i invite us all to be in practice me groups and
[Music] let's see oh i need to sorry i need to
create okay so ready about to open
here we go okay hi everyone welcome back the rooms
are closed so we've got a couple of minutes for reflections and and eva had a hand up eve
it's still relevant if you would raise your hand again so i can see you and ask you to unmute please there you
are fantastic okay
um i shared what i was about to share in
my small group basically what i shared was that uh this
is my second time coming to the happy hour and uh the very first time i joined
the group in the small group uh you've asked us to start with 30 seconds
of sending meta to each other and that feels very awkward
and i feel very awkward and that was the first time that i was asked to do that but then
uh today this is second time and then uh after practicing the
you know uh releasing the stress and then you know uh actually sending
the good wishes to uh everyone and i all of a sudden
remembered you know that instruction you gave us the first time my first time and
i actually was conscious about each one of these
you know we are on the zoom squares but um actually these old people right now
sending the good wishes to me and i'm receiving on the end and when i'm
practicing alone the world seems really tight and small and especially colbert we're not seeing
each other and alone but then all of a sudden it's expanded and then wow
we are doing this together and everyone's actually sending me the
mentor right now and that really you know my world
expanded and felt connected and uh that's what i shared in a small group
and that's what i wanted to say earlier so thank you
oh beautiful thank you eva thank you so much for sharing
what a beautiful note to end our session together on what a heart
heartwarming note and i see lots of loves people are oh yes their
heart signs are showing up hard yes oh lovely sweet and neil says i'm honored to be
part of your expanded world eva oh sweet we're all honored to be part of your extend expanded world eva
yeah the sense of connection that just it's here and it pops up so thank you so
much for being part of this all of you thank you for being part of happier
thank you for showing up for your practice for cultivating your heart to serve both this being
and all beings everywhere thank you may all beings be happy may all beings
be free [Music]
thank you everyone