so
then we come to the 12th step
of the 16 steps of anapanasati
the practice of mindfulness breathing in
and mindfully
breathing out
and the 12 step is breathing in
one liberates the mind
breathing out one liberates the mind
and um so it's the 12th step of the 16th
so it's usually said not to be the full
complete possibility of liberation that
buddhism
champions but it is a significant
experience of freedom of liberation
of letting go that
that
that makes an impression on the mind
makes an impression on us it's
educational
it's opening it's inspiring it kind of
begins
pointing the way oh now we know
something we didn't know before
and um the
so the um
uh now remember it's a 12 step
so what that means is that um
the first 11 steps are in a sense
a preparation for this step if we simply
heard
the only instruction for buddhism is to
let go
let go let go i don't know if that would
be so useful for people to hear
and also it might not give the right
idea of what letting go is about it
might feel like oh
just let go of everything i have and
have nothing as a result and
be impoverished impoverished in some way
and if i let go there's nothing left and
i'll just be kind of depressed and
miserable or
something
the letting go happens after the first
11 steps
which are preparing the ground and
opening the field
and setting up a sense of well-being
where letting go has a very wonderful
context and we understand the tremendous
value of letting go
because of the wholesomeness the
beneficial states that we're
experiencing
so so to kind of review this little bit
how to contact how context is set up for
letting go
so the practice begins with just simply
mindfully breathing in and out
helping the mind calm down helping the
mind get focused
helping us to show up and be present for
our experience
and i think for most people that's where
the bulk of the practice is
even people who practice for a long time
they sit down to meditate
and they're they're at step one and two
and uh and uh this idea that there's a
progress you're supposed to always be at
the
growing edge of this 12 16 steps
is a kind of uh just a
unnecessary source of stress and
misunderstanding and it's easy easy than
to
miss ourselves in the process and not
really connect to ourselves
the idea in mindfulness practice is to
really become ourselves be ourselves
really
be honest about what's here and learn
how to rest and be present for it
and this idea of just breathing in and
out through it all
is a way of supporting us to not resist
not
try to escape not try to avoid what is
here but to really
be present and face what's here and work
through it
and just breathe with it and relax and
heal and open up
and and release the things that have to
be released
and but as we do this practice then at
some point we begin feeling
recognizing that we can relax the body
sometimes the body just relaxes itself
in meditation
often you don't have to do the relaxing
but the mind body becomes more tranquil
more calm
and and that's a feels like a good thing
and the more we practice the more calm
and relaxed the body becomes
as the body becomes calmer and more
relaxed let go some of the tension we
have
some of the feelings of well-being can
well up the
sense of contentment ease relaxation
itself is
can bring a kind of joy and happiness
and so the practice begins kind of
inching its way into feeling some joy
happiness contentment well-being
that sets the stage to better
appreciate the tensions of the mind the
mental activity how there's the stresses
that are there
and so then the practice when we start
seeing that we start relaxing the mental
activities
calming the agitation of the mind
relaxing the mind relaxing the mental
uh muscle the thinking muscle and
um and so the mental activities which
can be swirling around and be fragmented
and
be going off in different directions
begin to settle down
and the mental activity starts coming
into harmony with itself
and in in harmony and unity with the
settling process of meditation
and then we come into the third tetrad
all having to do with the mind the
chitta
and the cheetah can be understood as the
heart mind
it's kind of like our inner life
you know it's uh not would not be
appropriate buddhist term
but it maybe for a way some people some
modern people use the word soul
um kind of the deepest kind of places
inside our
insider psyche inside of ourselves it
might also be the soul
kind of them but the the mind the heart
the mind heart
it is you know what buddhists talk about
and uh so we start recognizing that we
have this inner life
this inner mind this inner quality of
life the mood
state that's inside and we start
becoming the caretaker of that
and because of the earlier steps of
panasati
this begins to feel good to be connected
to this deep
you know if i use the western word soul
to really
for some people i think it really kind
of feels like a homecoming more than if
you
say mind or heart but uh
does heart mind really feel like this is
good this inner state the state of being
and there can be a gladness of
satisfaction deep satisfaction deep
contentment
of being home being connected to
something deep that's not kind of
spinning around on the surface of our
thoughts and ideas and
scattered in her mind but we're really
starting to feel whole
and unified and that process of becoming
unified and
unscattered undispersed continues into
the
11th step with with samadhi with
unification we're studying
this whole mind state comes and gets
gathered together and
and there's a lot of well-being that can
come some of the greatest forms of joy
and happiness
come from samadhi from a mind that's
unified and settled and connected
so by the time we get to the step 12
letting go liberating the mind
the um there's just a tremendous amount
of
of well-being there's a feeling of being
really at home
connected and so rather than letting go
being an impoverishment the diminishment
of ourselves
it's we start really seeing that what
we're letting go of
is in fact what diminishes us
is in fact what impoverishes us that
there's something about the mind
getting caught and preoccupied
obsessing about things spinning around
in thoughts and ideas
holding on to fear oddly enough we can
cling to fear
uh clinging to uh to resistance clinging
to
all kinds of things that we resist and
hold on to and cling for dear life
clinging to self and self image
clinging to hurt all kinds of things
that
people will cling to
but it's seen on this reservoir on this
foundation
of well-being of goodness of freedom or
clarity and so it's really clear that
that clinging
is is a separation from that well-being
letting go just feels like of course
i'll let go
the letting go so obviously a
diminishment so obviously a source of
suffering so obviously a source of
stress of course i'll let go and so
sometimes the letting go
the liberation that happens here is uh
so
innate that it's not something we have
to do
we just keep staying present breathing
with the experience
and and just letting things be letting
things be
and something will just let go by itself
because it takes a certain kind of
mental involvement
to remain clinging and if we just let
things be
let things be even our clinging it will
self-liberate
at some point the self-liberating
capacity of all things and so
um so we come to the
the 12th step and we come to
the time of liberation of letting go and
it's at this point where some people
find it just
really a wonderful thing to just
sometimes when you sit down to meditate
just let go
let go let go just whatever arises let
it go
let it be let it be don't be involved
don't pick it up
don't get reactive to it don't pull away
just let go let it be let it be let it
go
and um and
you know and so we let go of everything
let go of even we let go of even
mindfulness being aware we let go of
self we get
let go of knowing we let go of
even letting go at some point just let
go
and don't and let go of being the agent
of it
let go of having an agenda let go of
trying to be complete
or getting enlightened even just let go
let go there's some that's as if that's
all there is
let go of um
of uh needing to let go even uh just
wherever it is possible the next moment
let go of this let go of this
and so
so this twelfth step of anapanasati
breathing in liberating the mind
breathing out
liberating the mind so that's um
and that is the is the entry way
to the last four steps of anupanasati
and so letting go and liberation here is
not in
you know the end of the story but in
some ways it's the beginning of the
story
and they say that some sometimes it said
in kind of
folklore buddhism that the buddhist path
really begins
when we have a qualitatively experience
of letting go of liberation
that we know oh this is what it's about
this
is what freedom is possible this is what
really feels good and feels inspiring
and feels
this is worth and this is such a
qual qualitatively good
experience such a rich experience such
an experience that's filled with
potential for
compassion and love and freedom and
goodness and
lack of causing harm wanting to cause
harm in the world
this is a good thing
so so
that's where we are on this process and
we'll continue it
um on monday and
and and over this weekend uh
why don't you uh talk to some friends
about
what they've learned about how letting
go is useful
and when letting go is useful have
conversations about
the benefits of letting go and how
letting go can be done
in wise ways and and look for
opportunities to let go
look to look and really start to explore
all the different dimensions that you
can find
of when and how and where letting go
operates for you or can operate for you
and if we do that then
we'll have a better foundation for our
continuing our adventure
on next week monday thank you