so
good evening or night or morning
i think many of us know that the essence
of mindfulness practice
is to notice things in our experience
and when we first start paying attention
to our body and our emotions and our
thoughts
we discover all kinds of things that
were
there anyway but that we weren't
noticing before
sometimes people tell me
that they wish they hadn't started
mindfulness practice because
as soon as they started looking they saw
some things that they
didn't want to see or you know weren't
so excited about seeing
various speech or actions going on that
maybe they didn't want to know that they
were doing but i tend to take this with
a
a bit of a grain of salt a bit lightly
because i think people really really do
want to see
these things about themselves
and as we as we practice further
we may start to notice that we have
a favorite set of storylines
and ways of thinking and
[Music]
habits of speech that we use in our life
for example
we could call all these things patterns
you know we have various patterns that
come frequently in our experience
it's quite common that we see that and
often
there's a sense that these kind of are
going on their own you know because they
were there
before we were noticing them so they
have they run
on their own under certain conditions
okay and often
what they're about is rehearsing
and refining and reinforcing
uh the story of our life or the story of
me
if you will so this aspect of our
experience is what could be called
samsara in buddhism there's this
term samsara that means these
habitual karmic kinds of patterns that
are going on in the background
pretty much by themselves many of them
are a form of dukkha because effectively
they're just reactive
they they're just going on in the
background
they tend to deviate from what's
actually unfolding in experience and
and kind of take on a life of their own
like when something happens and we start
it reminds us of a challenge that we're
having and suddenly we're no longer
paying attention to what's happening
we've moved into our thoughts about oh
that's like that difficulty and then we
go off on that and we've deviated from
the present moment
that's how we often discover these
things in meditation is there the ways
that we
fall away from present moment
mindfulness so that's essentially
a kind of dukkha of being disconnected
from
the ongoing flow of experience and these
have
um they're said to have a deadening
effect on the mind
tamapada verse 21 says
the heedless or those who are not paying
attention the hebrews are as if
already dead wow so we're starting out
on kind of a
you know
the part of mindfulness that isn't as
attractive but i want to then say oh
the other thing that we'll notice as we
start practicing
and we'll notice it more and more
because it's enabled through mindfulness
practice
is that we aren't only reacting there
are actions
that are more in the realm of freedom
they're unique in the moment responses
to what's happening
that come from paying attention so we
start to see more and more
also as we practice mindfulness that
there is a freshness and an aliveness
to the way we meet the moment
the mind can be vibrant alive connected
to what's going on
sometimes we surprise ourselves that we
say something
quite wise simply because we were paying
attention
more carefully than we had been up till
now
so it's quite um kind of exciting to see
those things to know that the mind has
this
capacity to really meet experience some
of the time
so it's important in our practice to
start being able to discern the
difference between what we could call
pattern behavior and free behavior so
we start to learn what it feels like
when the mind is just
doing its habitual thing and what it
feels like
when it's um attentive and responsive
and
doing things that are appropriate to the
to the situation
so then we start seeing that there's
that contrast
those are the sort of two main ways that
we could operate
then we might start to get curious what
am i not seeing so you know what
what i'm not seeing could hold me back
you know what i'm not paying attention
to
these patterns that run and i don't
notice when they slip
in so i can start to wonder what am i
missing here
or how can i see what i don't see
it's the question i want to address
tonight how can we learn to see
what it is that we're not seeing about
our
speech actions thoughts the very things
that mindfulness was
intended to see we weren't seeing
certain things before we started what
else might we not be seeing at this
point
so it's an interesting question in
spiritual practice
how could we see what we're not seeing
so this is the realm of ignorance
ignorance isn't some kind of stupidity
or something or we didn't
read enough or learn enough about it
ignorance is what we're ignoring
it's what we're habitually not seeing
and so um it's difficult to let go of
things that we don't even know are there
we can sometimes but often it's helpful
if we're able to have some way
of directing our mind toward being able
to see
the things that we're not seeing of
course there are plenty of times when
what we're not seeing will come and find
us
you don't have to worry it will that
will happen but
it can be interesting to have some
techniques for looking into what it is
that we may not be seeing
so i want to offer three places tonight
that we can look for
what we're not seeing to see what we
don't see
okay so the first one is
to take the direct approach and
literally try to notice
things that we have not been noticing so
we can try to identify areas that we're
not paying attention to
sometimes it's possible to literally ask
about this
to spiritual friends there's there's a
wonderful story in the sutures
that's a conversation between two monks
between aniruddha and sariputa
who are friends they've been practicing
together for a long time
and anuruddha comments to sarikuta
that he knows that he has attained
clairvoyance
and he has excellent energy and
concentration
and yet he is not awakened
so this may not be the realm that we're
practicing in but
this is where anuruddha was so even when
you're close to awakening you may still
know that you don't know things
and so he's kind of puzzled you know he
comes to sariputta and he says i know
i'm not seeing something i've got
all this good stuff happening in my
practice
and yet i'm not awakened you know what
is it that's
going on and so sorry puta is a good
spiritual friend
and he deftly points out that anuruda's
attitude toward his accomplishments is
revealing certain things about his mind
so for example he's
revealing that his mind still contains
some conceit and some restlessness
and some remorse and so it would be good
if he would abandon these things and so
anuruda is grateful that his friend
pointed
out what he was not seeing and he
practices in line with that
and becomes an arahant becomes awakened
as these
stories go but it's it's kind of a sweet
suit up because it demonstrates
that one of the things that our
spiritual friends can do
for us is that they might be able to see
what we haven't yet let go of and find
the right way to
encourage us so it can be useful
at the right time of course to reveal
to our spiritual friends where we think
we're stuck
and actually ask for some advice about
that
you can do this with teachers also so
that's kind of the direct approach
it may also be that we sometimes have to
try to discern what we're not noticing
in a more indirect way and we can do
that
by just observing what other people
are noticing like our teacher our
friends our partner
our colleagues i'll give an example
there was a time very early in my
practice when i was at a
buddhist gathering and there was a cart
being passed around the group for a
sangha member who was ill
and the group wanted to support her by
sending her a card
so i didn't i was pretty new to the
group i didn't really know
all the people but i remember thinking
that
uh noticing that this was nice
you know and thinking oh this is the
kind of group that sends cards to people
and i thought about the person a little
bit that i knew her
and so i was kind of on a pragmatic
practical level like that that was what
i noticed about the
situation and then as the card was
passed around
um one of the people in the group um
looked at the card and exclaimed with um
put her her hand to her heart and said
this is such a beautiful buddha
on this card it was like she was really
touched by the beautiful buddha image
that was on the card and i realized at
that moment
card had already gone by me that i
hadn't even really noticed the picture
on the card i just i didn't even look at
that
aspect of it and so i was intrigued that
she had seen this
and maybe at that time i was pretty new
to practice i don't know that i would
have called a buddha image beautiful
you know it was a buddha but i would
recognize it but
but to sort of put my hand to my heart
and say it was beautiful
i don't know that i would have done that
and so that
um kind of that little incident was one
of the triggers for
an investigation in my own practice into
the quality of faith
which is something that i had not been
paying really any attention to it sort
of wasn't my style
but because of that i wondered you know
what am i missing here and so i looked
into that and i i learned quite a bit
about faith by trying to open to it
and now i have this buddha which i think
is very beautiful
so things change over time
when we notice new things so this is um
important to be intrigued by what other
people notice that we don't notice
so that's one area where we can
look is you know what is it that i'm not
noticing
so then the second area that we might
look at
is what we don't question
okay well we don't question so this has
two different aspects to it the first
is there might be areas
where we simply don't think to question
more deeply
you know it's like we just don't think
to ask any questions
and again there's a story in the suntes
there's a story about an elderly man
whose name was nakula pita
and he comes to see the buddha
and he points out to the buddha when he
arrives
that it's quite a rare event
for him to be able to come and see the
buddha
so he says i am old venerable sir
aged burdened with years advanced in
life
come to the last stage afflicted in body
often ill i rarely get to see
the blessed one and the biggus worthy of
esteem
the monks worthy of esteem let the
blessed one
exhort me venerable sir let him instruct
me
since that would lead to my welfare and
happiness for a long time
so it's special for him to get to see
the buddha
and because he's kind of old and often
sick and it's probably hard for him to
get there
so the buddha first of all agrees with
him
that this is indeed a rare event and he
gives him a teaching so the buddha says
so it is householder so it is
this body of yours is afflicted weighed
down
encumbered if anyone carrying around
this body
were to claim to be healthy even for a
moment
what is that due to other than
foolishness
it's quite straightforward so then he
says
therefore householder you should train
yourself thus
even though i am afflicted in body my
mind will be unafflicted
thus you should train yourself so he
gives a pretty concise
teaching even though i'm afflicted in
body my mind will be unafflicted
it's a great teaching by the way one
that can be unfolded for a long time
and so nakula it is said delighted
in the teaching of the buddha he was
very happy and he departs
and then later as he's leaving um
he comes across sarikuta the same monk
who was uh giving anuruda advice
in the last example and he comes upon
sorry putta who comments how he looks
very serene
and you know wow householder your
faculties are serene he says and
says oh yes and he repeats his whole
conversation with the buddha
and sorry puta admonishes him
actually and he says didn't it occur to
you householder
to question the blessed one further as
to
how one is afflicted in body and mind
and
how one is afflicted in body but not
afflicted in mind
didn't you think to ask what it means to
be
afflicted or unafflicted in mind when
your body is afflicted
and nikula peta says well um
no i didn't think to ask that actually
and so then he um asks for further
instruction from sariputa
so uh which sorry puta then
gives a whole discourse on unfolding the
the meaning of this very
concise teaching that the buddha gave so
um
it may be that um there are areas of the
teachings where we're just sort of
passively taking them in
but we are actually meant to engage with
the teachings
and either by literally asking questions
or by at least investigating in our
practice and trying them out and
hoping and prodding and seeing if they
work and how they work for us
so we're not really meant to
let's say swallow things whole um
and that doesn't mean that we need to be
asking questions all the time you know
things do
unfold at their own pace um but it's
you know there might be areas where we
have some some question you know we
never really
understood that teaching about dependent
origination
or not really sure what not self is
about
you know instead of continuing to just
hear these teachings we could
ask some questions about them dig a
little deeper sometimes
so sometimes what we don't question can
reveal
areas that we have not been paying very
much attention to
in our practice then there's a deeper
or a second aspect of what we don't
question
and that points toward the assumptions
that we're living by which can be
serious blocks in our practice and
they're very hard to see
it's actually quite hard to see the
assumptions that we're living by
you know the kind of the lenses that we
have over our eyes over our practice
over our way of being in the world there
are certain things that we're just
not questioning about that so
assumptions
lurk in generally in our thinking and in
our
interpretation of events
and one way that we can reveal them is
to
ask questions so i'm going to give i'll
give a specific
example suppose that we are
angry about something and we could
you know it's fairly common that we get
irritated at least or sometimes we
actually get angry about something and
we know that
you know that's something that's really
bothering us
and so we could just say mindfulness of
anger
anger feel it in the body
anger and then wait for it to go away
eventually
but we could also do some some
investigation of that and we might
you know we might look a little bit more
carefully or of course what we might do
is just justify the anger and say well
i don't have to look into that anger
that's obviously justified that person
is clearly in the wrong that social
situation is clearly unjust
no need to question further however
if you're interested here's a um
a train of thinking and asking that can
be quite revealing
so if we're angry we are typically
in opposition to something that's kind
of what the state of anger is about it's
an opposition
so we may not even know what or we may
or why we assume that that's useful so
when we're feeling angry or oppositional
it can be interesting to ask
a set of three questions so the first
one
is what am i opposing
and it might be that we think sort of
casually think that we know what we're
opposing i'm opposing my sister
or something but it's not exactly your
whole sister that you're opposing
what precisely is it that you're
opposing and
look a little bit more carefully and
then um
you'll check into that and then the
second question is
do i need to oppose it
so i need to oppose that
so then that calls into a question this
stance of opposition
it doesn't say that you're not going to
do anything or that you should approve
of it
instead it only says do i need to oppose
it
which then just automatically opens up
oh
might there be other responses or might
there be
other avenues to bring about
what i would like to see changed
as opposed to as opposed to opposition
so you know might there be other
possibilities
for this situation we hadn't ever
questioned that we might not have ever
thought there was any option besides
simply
opposing this thing that i don't like
that is unpleasant
so then the third question
is opposing even called for here
you might still think that you need to
oppose it is opposing even called for
here
so then we're sort of calling into
question whether
opposing could have uh positive results
usually opposing creates more conflict
actually
that tends to be its nature
so these questions can help to you know
they're not meant to
say that you're wrong or that the other
person is actually
good or that you know the whole there
doesn't need to be anything
done it's just a way of teasing into
what we might not be questioning
about our way of being in the world we
could do this in
all kinds of i picked out anger but all
kinds of dukkha so cases of desire
what am i desiring do i need to desire
it
is desiring even called for here
or cases of confusion or other
such things any kind of dukkha really so
don't be satisfied with surface answers
to these questions
and kind of see if you can go deeper
so another approach that people have
to discovering about their thinking
is a set of repeating questions
so you can ask why is that
important if you think something is
important it's up you're
obsessing about it thinking about it i
can ask why is that important
and you'll get an answer and it's
probably true but then you ask
and why is that important and you'll get
another answer
and you ask and why is that important
and it
draws the mind down toward the values
that we
have and what it is that is really
important to us in that situation
and that can help a lot in understanding
first of all how we're thinking about
situation and what it is that's really
driving that obsessive thinking we can
learn a lot about our practice and our
mind
some things that we weren't noticing
before
so we have what we don't notice
but we don't question and then the third
way of approaching seeing what we don't
see
is what we don't laugh about
so what we don't find funny tends to
reveal where our identity is invested
it is not that everything should be
humorous but
if we can't find any lightness in some
area
it's worth investigating to see if
there's some kind of sticking point
there for us it's likely a place where
we're identified
the buddha points out in um similarly of
the snake suta majima 22
that any form of identification
is dukkha it will eventually
bring dukkha that may or may not be
clear to us
but it's worth investigating these areas
that we
can't find anything light or humorous in
so it's very worthwhile to develop a
sense of humor
in our practice many things in the mind
are actually kind of funny
including many of our patterns we can
have a little lightness and say uh
there's that one again yes
um that can be very helpful sylvia
borstein says
that we need three things in practice
gentleness
precision and humor and i think she's on
to something
you know we need to be so gentle with
this habituated
stressed mind but also precise
about questioning its assumptions
and in the end we have to find it
somewhat humorous
about how recalcitrant it is to be
changed
and how tricky it is about reasserting
its
graspings and identity we don't have a
sense of humor we may not have the
patience to
continue to work with the mind
there's a wonderful there was a
wonderful 20th century
thai forest teacher named ajahn
bhunatasa
who was a boxer before he became a monk
so that was his first profession is that
he was a professional boxer
and then he ordained and he um practiced
for a while and eventually he became a
well-known teacher and had his own
monastery and
trained a lot of people including some
of the western teachers that we now have
in our tradition here
and but because he was a boxer earlier
he retained a somewhat belliger
belligerent
heir let's say about him so he could
sometimes come across
as rough or blunt he didn't really
oppose
in the way that i was just talking about
in the previous example
but still he had that kind of roughness
about him
and sometimes um sometimes people would
take offense at it in certain ways and
think that
a spiritual teacher should only be kind
and gentle and warm and
so forth and if somebody challenged his
demeanor sometimes
autumn budadasa would just roar with
laughter
and he would say oh that's just my
personality
so he had learned in his own heart to
make peace with just the way
his mind was still kind of a boxer in
certain ways now he was of course quite
free inside
and wasn't caught up in that identity
but he recognized that his personality
still had that and had a certain amount
of likeness about
just how he was that that air and that
helped other people to lighten up then
you know if they were concerned about
that and he just laughed and
was gentle about it then they would say
oh okay
it's just his personality
so i teach from the suttas fairly
frequently and
one thing that i look for in people as
they develop in their practice and
in their study is sometimes or often
there will be a point where people
realize that the sutas are hilarious
some of them some of the suitors are
hilarious
you get to the point where you can
imagine the scene
going on and there's somebody asking
this question or
questioning the buddha in a certain way
or misunderstanding what he's saying in
a certain way
you just you can just imagine the scene
you think ah
wow you know it must have been funny to
be there
so i thought about trying to give an
example of this but then i decided that
it's something that we really have to
come to on our own
but if you've never thought of the
polycannon as funny
i recommend trying it and and just
seeing some of the lightness in the
exchanges that the buddha has
with people so it's clear to me at least
that the people who compiled the
discourses
had some sense of humor and how it got
presented
so we've talked tonight about
trying to have some way of seeing what
we don't see
of opening up our practice so that we
can notice
more which is what mindfulness is about
it's about noticing more things noticing
different things
seeing the mind in different ways so
that we can continue to
untangle the knots that com that
bind our heart in various ways so
looking into what we don't notice
looking into what we don't question and
looking into what we don't
laugh about can be wonderful ways
of broadening and also deepening
our practice and also keeping it fresh
and alive
so this is talk is especially if you're
feeling a little stale in your practice
or like it's always the same or you're a
little stuck or dry
we go through periods like that it's
normal but
it's good to have some ways of finding
new areas of the mind to to look into
so i hope this is giving you some some
sense of that
i wish you a very good evening and
ongoing practice
well everyone