there's a dharma teaching that expresses the activity
of awareness with with it it says there are three
factors the first factor gil was talking about
yesterday confidence in the
the dharma bird in pali is sada in in sanskrit shraddha
and it it covers the territory between trust and confidence
maybe the way when you are very thirsty and you drink some water
and you taste how drinking water quenches thirst
you trust that activity
so we in awareness
sati mindfulness zazen [Music]
the activity of being aware
we entrust attention to the activity of the moment
and we discover we realize
that when it's met with non-grasping when it's allowed to be
what it is something trustable
in that form of experiencing rises
second teaching second attribute of this threefold teaching of the
activity of awareness is resolve
when our intention
ripens it finds expression and activity
through resolve
and and the third attribute often called benzene
great doubt but maybe another way to understand it is
inquiry that doesn't conceptualize
what's experienced in that inquiry
allows it to be dynamic
it allows it to be we could even call it the truth of the
moment the truth of the moment this appears to
be happening
so confidence trust resolve and this kind of
inquiry
this is how it is in this moment and it's dynamic
so as we start to sit
the confidence the trust in your own body
its stability finding the stability of posture
quite literally you know arranging your cushion your seat
how you're sitting
and then letting your body rest
on how you're sitting and letting your body
become upright take its place in the world of being
within uprightness and openness
you know so be it this body
is part of all being [Music]
sitting in the midst of all being
and when we trust what's happening would be trust own
being we have nothing to prove
there isn't anything in particular that we need to assert become
we just trusted as it is
and when we trust the breath
we let it happen
and such as the nature of the breath we can notice as we allow the breath
how is that how is it to allow the body to breathe
it has a physical expression
and as we contact the sensations of the breath in the body
they instruct us those sensations instruct us
on the activity of allah
candid nostrils in the area behind the nose
can it soften and open
can the throat relax
can the chest
open can the abdomen soften
sometimes it's helpful in the first breaths
like one one teaching you can try on you can experiment if you breathe
in fully you hold the inhale and you just gently push down
with the diaphragm it's almost like you're opening up the
[Music] abdomen
and then release and you can experiment doing that a couple of times
and then allow the breath and just notice
is there any change maybe there is maybe there isn't
but trusting the body and breath to find their own rhythm
it's in the realm of sensations the thinking mind doesn't have to take
charge knowing what should happen
it's like trusting the being that we are in a very visceral way
there's resolve but in many ways
it's gentle perceptive and steady
and as we trust the breath to breathe the body we we're introducing those factors
the factors are resolved
it's gentle it's consistent persistent
with the steadiness
as we open all the senses
seeing hearing
sensations in the body maybe smelling and tasting too
as if we're enlivening
the world of awareness
but not resisting the constructs
of conditioned being
how it will present
thoughts memories images
anticipations
that ripple through us reverberate in our conditioned being
can there be a non-grasping inquiry
the activity of awareness expressed as
in inquiry what's happening now
before i expressed it as notice acknowledge
not so much as a doing as an opening to
being similar to how the breathing bees in the
body
[Music]
um
okay
so
can attentiveness illuminate what's being constructed
by the senses by thought and feeling
non-grasping inquiry and attention
[Music]
can the resolve express itself
as a confident invitation to awareness
there is nothing to prove trusts what is
[Music]
the inquiry of awareness
has an energy to it
that's balanced by the trusting
what's happening now
nothing to prove
assert
[Music] accomplish
[Music]
so
how is the interplay between awareness
and the activities of the self how is that interplay right now
the expression of awareness definitive are the expression
of constructed self with all its issues
and intrigues
can they dance together with nothing to prove
or accomplish
in a moment i'll ring the bell
play a game with yourself try to track
as carefully as possible isabelle rings
something in your disposition shifts how is it all
what's happening
so [Music]
[Music]
so this interplay between the world of awareness
and the world of constructed being
the deeply habituated world of constructed being
and this maybe we could even say revered
world of awareness
and then as we're discovering in practice
part of the challenge is is not to stop the world of constructed being
but to not let it make invisible to dissipate the world of awareness
and that interplay
you know the challenge of our practice is to make the interplay between the two
harmonious you know just the same way we we call this intensive the harmony
of vipassana in zen like right in the title there's
[Music] clues about what the challenge we're
picking up is you know the interplay between the world of awareness
and the world of the self
and then as buddhism developed their developed a uh
different aspects of practice
we're acknowledged as their own the term would be its own kind of buddha field
or another term would be a kaya a realm of existence
so the world of the karmic self is its own realm of existence
and the world of awareness is its own realm of existence
and the world of the interplay between the two is its own realm of existence
and so a few days ago i wrote i i mentioned zen's story
with the monk asked the teacher duncan he asked some which of those realms of
existence do you uh live in
or do you you know you attend to
dongshan says that's the inquiry
that i stay close to you know the inquiry that's exploring
what's happening now you know is the world of the self dominant
in fact is it totally convincing and dictating
what is is the world of awareness sort of
in its demeanor rebuking the world of the self
monkey mind you know self-centered all caught up in yourself
and and these three realms in buddhism each of them was acknowledged as kind of
buddha field and then they had their own buddha
they had their own name as a significant realm of experience
[Music] and then they each had their own
designated attribute the realm of awareness
went beyond any fixed ideas
the realm of itself was definite objective
the this is how the stuff of being becomes tangible
you know and then very interestingly the interplay of the rule of the two
was designated as the realm of bliss the realm of ease the realm of
harmonious existence
the interplay between the karmic and the dharmic is the realm of harmony
and as we bring awareness to the self
not not simply an awareness oh there i go doing my stuff again you know
or maybe we flip it and and we we become puffed up
well i think my ideas are
the awareness helps us bring some very supportive qualities into the realm
of the self
it helps us start to see the way we think and feel
and interact
and that's an enormous teacher for us there's so much to learn i mean we've
learned about our own conditioned self and we learn about the human condition
each of us is a specimen of the human condition
there's a repertoire of emotions that each of us
plays jazz with you know we take that repertoire and we create
all sorts of amazing and wonderful uh variations on a theme
each of us in our ingenious of creativity
you know adds value significance
to different ways of thinking about the self about life you know
and when there's awareness of it it's so instructive
sometimes it's helpful to say to ourselves after there's been a significant
experience in our life what did i learn from that
you know like in a way we're inviting the noticing and the acknowledging and
the inquiry what did i learn from that not so much to grasp that okay now i know but more
that's really helping me see the interplay between awareness and self
so it tutors our conceptual mind and then there's an
another extraordinary valuable thing as we feel it
and rather than have the emotions um sort of extend out
objectify the world and attribute emotions to it
we feel the emotions and as we feel them and
acknowledge them there's a kind of integration
it's kind of like an emotional integration oh anger
oh sadness oh gratitude
oh love [Music]
and we can feel how some emotions have a kind of disturbing contraction
and some emotions have a soothing expansion
i once heard someone describe god as opening the greater being
you know and how certain emotions
open us to greater being
and maybe if we're inclined we call it a religious experience
or maybe we're just grateful
and then the teachings that the mind is being given and the
teachings that the heart the emotions and the integration you know they stimulate
our trust in the buddha dharma they stimulate our trust in the practice of awareness
and yet almost paradoxically
[Music] they invite us not to cling
to what's being revealed what's being illuminated
they invite us and remind us that it's an activity
not a fixed state that you attain and then you own it and then you have a
better me you know you have a me that's so wonderful that
it can conquer the very process of being alive you know
in some ways rather than attaining and having that the process stimulates
us in a confident and trusting way to give over
okay this is how it is this dynamic interplay
of the stuff of being human
in the mysterious wonderful way of being aware
and learning how to harmonize yeah learning how to be patient
with your own clinging and diversions and others clinging in aversions
ah this is a human condition
each of us trying to navigate and sustain our very life
in this moment this is this person's best effort at
being alive
i don't know why they're so angry are so afraid
but i can bring patience i can bring
a acceptance a permission
and i can bring positive attributes this is the resolve
no the energy of attention
and commitment and engagement
and dongshan stays i stay close to that i stay close to studying all that
you know and maybe all i'm trying to say is this
that it's an activity yeah
it's not like do this and then everything in your life
will be perfect
and i would suggest you that would be kind of boring
you know you know if it takes on
a kind of steady state you know
and yet the constant activity of life
it is a challenge
and it asks something of us but asking something obvious
is part of what keeps us alive
just imagine if you had a good friend and they never asked anything of you
[Music] versus how each of us our life goes up
and down sometimes we're the giver sometimes we're the receiver
and that's what enhances the
relationship so dangshan's saying i stay close to this
this is what i'm attending to this is what i'm engaging
this dynamic interplay okay sorry i've run over
thank you very much and enjoy your day your evening
and may you have wonderful discoveries