so hello everyone who is here today with the youtube and
listening maybe into the future as well
and then some ways we span
geography across the globe and we also spend time into the future with how these
recordings work it's kind of an amazing thing that we share and feel a connection to so much
there are some maybe some of you have heard me say many times i like to divide our experience of life
what goes on in our with our life moment by moment into two
areas there is what is happening and there is how we are with what is
happening or our relationship to what's happening and mindfulness practice i put in the
lighter camp mindfulness is a practice of showing up and being attentive to what is happening
and to engage in mindfulness with equanimity
has the function of um staying with the mindfulness staying
with a relaxed dedicated sincere attention to this moment attention to
nexus being present being available for the flow of the present moment as it keeps
appearing and arising for us moment by moment and and one thing that helps to have
equanimity to just stay present stay with the mindfulness moment by moment
is to not think that you are unique that uh not think that your that
but your experiences is unique enough that it's an exception to
what humans experience not to dismiss what you have what's happening to you or make
it not to make it kind of unimportant everything is important you're important
but what's also important is the steadiness of how we are the steadiness of mindfulness
when we're practicing mindfulness to not it's kind of like we have the bumper sticker that says
um i stop for nothing when i practice mindfulness meaning i don't get involved and get entangled and start
thinking about things and just a bear recognition oh this is what's happening now
this is what's happening and or available to experience this is what's experiencing this is what's known now
this is what's being experienced now just steady steady steady
like when i went on a walking pilgrimage a good number of years ago and it was only two weeks but
the idea was just keep walking when we walked just keep walking and walking and walking
didn't matter what the ex experience around us was just you walk and you walk so we
are mindful we're aware we're aware with equanimity that allows us to just
continue without getting sidetracked without getting stopping for something and getting
entangled and retro retrospective thinking so
to begin this pilgrimage of mindfulness
pilgrimage where we don't we don't walk we sit
we remain stationary in a stationary posture that works for you
and to tenderly close your eyes
and maybe tenderly in your heart open to yourself
closing your eyes and opening your heart
and taking a few moments to appreciate yourself and value yourself
that perhaps that is why we're meditating because we value our well-being
and this is a way of finding a valuable important form of
well-being happiness freedom from suffering
to take a few long slow deep breaths
and exhales really settling in here with yourself in yourself
for yourself here in this body
here in this heart
here in this belly
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and because of maybe with a sense of self-care self-appreciation
to as you exhale to continue to relax what can be relaxed in your body
face shoulders stomach belly
and then letting then settling in just to your breathing
no walking pilgrimage it's the feet that walk
it is a stationary pilgrimage of meditation
can you it's your breathing breathing in and breathing out
and to have the simplicity of breathing be something that we
allow to come into our awareness
a simple sea of breathing is where awareness lands
two metaphors for awareness awareness which receives allows
awareness which lands connects whichever is
most useful for you and then with equanimity
that doesn't get alarmed or caught up or annoyed or
think that something is unique and not part of the practice
everything is part of practice everything is for the next moment of
awareness to trust it's enough
just to be aware to trust to just take the next moment
for what it is even if it's very similar to the previous one
just stay stay
the equanimity that allows a steady continuation of the practice
come back to that continuity and if things are challenging
breathe with it so that your awareness
rides on the currents of breathing
relaxed available present for the experience without getting entangled
as you meditate nothing is extraordinary enough
to stop to think about or get involved in everything is ordinary enough
it is just one more thing to be aware of to be mindful of
in a steady ongoing receptivity of awareness to what is one breath
at a time
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to tenderly calmly
open up to the sufferings of the world
and to do so equanimously
meaning that we care
we feel for the suffering we're concerned with it
and there's no need to give up this steadiness of our mindfulness
steadiness and confidence in remaining rooted in awareness
so that we don't get pulled into our reactivity our thinking our predictions
our sense of obligations and should and what shouldn't be
in equanimity it allows us to stay open
so that care and good will respect and kindness
can flow through that awareness through the field of mindfulness
and may it be that as we learn how to be more aware and mindfulness
more mindful with equanimity with calm with balance
may it be that we can show up for the challenges of this world
and stay close to our goodwill well-wishing kindness friendliness
compassion may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
peaceful and free
and may my heart and mind
have this good will this well wishing for others
so that in some way or other it spreads from me spreads from each of us
into the world that we encounter today
may our love and compassion
spread from this meditation session out into our communities and out into
the world may all beings be happy
[Music]
so today is the part two of the equanimity factor of awakening
and um you know it's also part of this series
on mindfulness of breathing which the buddha presented a little bit like a path
that as we stay present for our breath that we're cultivating and deepening the
meditation practice um with a deep relaxation of the body a deep relaxation of the mind until
we're not just focused on the details of our life the particular activities of the body
or the mind but we start becoming aware of the mind state the state of mind the
quality of our mind the feeling of kind of the gestalt or
the wholeness of awareness that can just be here holding it all
and it's a fairly you know mature place in meditation that we might fall
into occasionally where the the the mind state is more salient
more prominent than the particular details of what's happening in our body or the details what's happening in our mind
all of these all of the all of the above are important but to be more holistic
in the practice to some point to get a sense of that the whole the mind as a whole the mood mind state
that we have and those mind states have various characteristics uh when we get more and more settled
when the mind feels more whole or expansive or clear the greater clarity and mindfulness
and the seven factors awakening are part of that and the last one equanimity is part that
when the mind when we're really stable in a strong awareness with a strong
sense of being aware in this in our mind state a healthy wholesome mind state
it tends to come with a strong sense of equanimity and equanimity being very simply not
getting caught in the reactivity of the mind of being for and against things and
um and it's a wonderful uh capacity we still might be for and
against things might have those thoughts or impulses a little bit but equanimity we
just simply don't pick it up we don't get involved they just pass through they're just fleeting kind of impulses of the moment
that come and they go and and we don't we don't pick it up we don't get involved
and it can lead to a tremendous social good
because when we don't respond socially into the world by our
reactivity by the quick impulses of being foreign against things then uh we're more likely to be
impartial in a really healthy understanding of impartiality where we
treat everyone equally or we don't treat people through the filter of
our desires and our aversions kind of leaning into and wanting or pulling back because we don't want or
something we don't so easily get pulled into our preferences
and so a sense of justice a sense of impartiality sense of being someone who's safe for other people
um becomes more and more more stronger the the more we have this equanimity
this ability to not get caught up in our reactivity or or these impulses of being foreign
against all kinds of things there might still be wise being foreign against things
but that wisdom builds on equanimity on being stable and settled is not
impulsive there's a clarity and a wholesomeness in how we respond to the world so
equanimity is both something for deep meditation and for
everyday life it's a really a great boon for life in deeper and
deeper meditation um that's some place where some people can really feel
this state of equanimity in a very powerful way that gives us a feeling for it and then
a support of what it's like to bring that into our daily life but in the anapanasati process it's very
much the reference point for it is in meditation and so in meditation
the equanimity is what allows the mindfulness to be uninterrupted to just stay in the
flow of awareness here here and we don't find ourselves drifting off in thought and coming back
to three minutes later we don't find ourselves getting caught and preoccupied by what's
happening now we might be very attentive to what's happening but we're not caught by it
and so the steadiness of mindfulness it just kills the course holds the course keeps walking keeps
engaging step by step equanimity sort of allows that steadiness and continuity of awareness
and equanimity that upekka as i said yesterday has a lot to do with
wisdom so having an overview of the situation and it's not a wisdom that's acquired knowledge that we bring with us
and apply but rather something that we deeply understand as we go along and there's a variety of things one can
be that it's not worthwhile getting being reactive it's not being worthwhile being
caught up in in thoughts or thought up in our reactivity it's just not valuable for us and we can feel that and sense
that directly the other is that we can have a clear
sense feeling for the impermanence of phenomena the inconstancy of how things come and go and change and
to really understand that means we don't then relate to things as if they're going to be there forever
or if they're you know something that's fixed that has to be fixed something fixed that has to
be fixed and uh and so having a clear sense oh this is impermanent this is change as
well can let us set back and just be willing just be present be aware
the wisdom of not taking all these things personally that i'm not unique that my experience is not unique that
many people have meditation probably all the experiences we've had in one way or the other others have had as well and it's one of
the primary roles of sometimes of a meditation teacher is to normalize
people's experiences and for the most part to normalize just make it ordinary it's
okay it's just part of the process so we can keep coming back to the equanimous mindfulness steady
mindfulness that doesn't get perturbed or agitated by no matter what is happening no matter the
fear or the pain or the suffering or the experiencing and meditation it's all
normalized in a certain way so not taking it personally is one of those ways
and so there's a variety of kind of wisdoms that come into play that's really supports this ability
to stay equanimous balanced unagitated in our experience the
but also this equanimity comes from a sense of balance and balance has something to do with
inner strength to be cultivate when there's a strength of mindfulness a strength of
concentration strength of stability then it's kind of like we have
a a you know a stability we have a
something that holds us down keeps us grounded allows us to withstand the winds of the
mind the winds of change and things that come and go and to develop
that strength by the continuity of meditation meditating maybe almost every day and regularly and
developing this the mind is an instrument that can be developed and strengthened and trained
and um not everyone develops their mind everyone trains their mind to be a
strong um be strong and part of what ongoing regular meditation practice is
about is not just showing up and being mindful of stuff and accepting of stuff but also developing an inner strength
a capacity to let go a capacity to really stay present and be steady with experience and not
wander off in all kinds of things a a strength of concentration
as strength or even joy so as we get stronger and stronger we're
not buffeted so much by the winds of change the winds of what goes on and so we're more able to kind of hold
the course and hold the course and so as the uh as the ninth step
of this mindfulness of the mind is to um start
experiencing and sensing that we have this amazing resource this amazing
thing called chitta called mind that we want to care for that's a reference point for
a well-being a wholeness that any kind of suffering we have is a subset of and so when the mind is
really spacious and open expansive present we're aware of the cheetah in a more
bigger way it's much harder to take our greeds or attachments or lusts or addictions or
hates hostilities regrets resentments our fears as being all there is
they all become a piece of the puzzle they're not the whole puzzle the whole puzzle feels more like the
mind that can be aware of it all and and there's a lot can be uh
feeling of great goodness great rightness great kind of in that kind of sense of a
mind or this inner life which is whole and and so whether it's completely whole
or feels completely kind of as satisfying as i'm saying here that keeps coming now as we continue the
practice of sati step 10 is gladdening the mind or feeling the
satisfaction of the mind of being connected to this mind that feels more whole and then the the 11th step
is samadhi is concentrating the mind or unifying the mind which we'll talk about soon enough and
that's what makes the mind even more whole so it's a fantastic process here and
and i know that it's not easy to experience all these things i'm talking about but
part of the confidence in practice is to know that you're on a good path and
and part of the equanimity that comes with practice is the confidence this is a good path to be on i can just
walk this path steadily keep going i don't have to be too concerned about how far i've gotten
because i know i'm in a good path and i'll keep walking so
thank you for today and i look for forward as i almost every day do now
of coming and sitting and teaching here with you thank you