hello everyone and it's delightful to sit down here and
into this posture that's so so rich for me and connotations
associations and in uh what gets evoked and
it's centered in this meditation posture for decades and it's kind of like a
homecoming and to do it together with community to do it together with all of you and adds a certain depth or
width and breadth and wonderfulness to this beginning of meditation
so thank you and
so we're working in meditation and mindfulness with attention our capacity to be aware
and one of the and freedom is a hallmark of buddhism one way to
understand freedom is that we're setting our awareness free freeing our attention
from the way that our habits of mind um take it over and direct it
the habits of mind of wanting or not wanting pushing or pushing away or holding on or
being being preoccupied with certain thoughts and ideas concerns
emotions these habits of mind then propel attention
in the direction of the concern and uh propel them the attention into the world
of thoughts or feelings or what's happening and in a sense they
the attention is not free the attention is being directed it's being
utilized some people might say that attention is being uh hijacked
and so to set attention awareness free
is one of the great pleasures joys of life and it's almost like we can live a
different life then there's room for something different to occur to
animate us to motivate us to to connect us to the world
when the awareness has been set free it's almost like a door has been a wide open
that was closed or almost like a light has been turned on where it's been turned
you know it's off in the dark so i want to give a little analogy for
this if um
so uh if a person lives maybe in a very crowded room for a long time
maybe a hoarder and almost no space in the room to walk around in perhaps that uh if uh
or i mean and then if a person walks out into a very large room
uh comfortable nice safe looking room where there's lots of space there might
be things furniture and chairs and things different things there but immediately what becomes
obvious is how much open space there is and in fact for most rooms there is more
space than there are things in the room and if we're only focused on the things then
sometimes we can miss the open space i've been in places where there's high ceilings and here at imc there's a very
high ceiling over me and it's easy to spend a long period of time focusing on what's at eye level and
but to look up and see the high ceiling these places kind of uh space kate's room
opens things up in a certain way and so it's possible to shift one's attention from the objects in a room
to the space in the room in the same way it's possible to be claustrophobic in one's own mind and
be maybe an equivalent of a hoarder of the mind just collecting things and wanting things and
fantasizing and and going you know one fantasy one
thought train overlapping with the next and with you know almost breathless between them
and it's possible then to open the metaphorical inner eyes or a sense
of awareness we can open it up we can look around
and we see that there's actually more space in the mind than there are objects
there's more space in our capacity for awareness the field of awareness then there is
the things we're preoccupied with or caught in it and if you can look around a little
bit in your mind to see the space the openness that some people might experience with the stillness
in the mind quiet in the mind or a silence in the mind rather than space
and there's actually together with the objects in the room there is the space
together with the concerns we have there's also space there's also silence there's
also stillness and to let awareness
relax into that to take that in and see that in that space in that stillness
there is a freedom an awareness there can find its freedom where it isn't
being directed as much and the sweetness of awareness is set
free so assuming a meditation posture
and tenderly closing your eyes
and giving a little bit more attention maybe than usual in sitting with a spine or body that
is feels attentive for people sitting upright it's maybe sitting a little bit more upright
for people lying down it might be adjusting the shoulder blades a little bit and that upper back
so that the shoulder blades maybe come in a little bit and and the chest is allowed to be more
open
and then ex become attuned to the body's experience of breathing
aware from the inside out
and gently tenderly as you exhale relax your body soften
maybe letting there be a gentling of your body together with
keeping the alertness of the body
and then you can stop relaxing the body
but as you exhale now see if you can relax the mind
maybe that means to quiet the mind may have your thinking becomes quieter
slower calm thinking
as you exhale to relax any tension pressure to think
or to fantasize or any other way the mind is tense or
contracted narrow
allowing the mind to become
wide and open
appreciating whatever stillness there is in the mind
if you throw a rock through empty space
through the air nothing if nothing is disturbed by the
rock
if you play music the notes travel through the air without
disturbing anything
so when we center ourselves in awareness
all kinds of things can arise thoughts and feelings and emotions
there's nothing we have to do except experience them allow them to
appear and travel through
the space of awareness
without having them disturb anything and without us disturbing them getting
involved in them
perhaps becoming aware that beyond the edges of your concerns your sensations your
feelings
there's lots of space lots of room
and allow whatever particular experiences arise
allow them as if they're floating through all the space of the mind that's here
instead of attention being directed by our concerns
our concerns are held in a wide open free awareness
relaxed mindfulness
you
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting is there some deeper way fuller way that you can relax
if you are more in touch with your body or your mind from this sitting
more settled you have access to some way to relax more fully
maybe softening relaxing at your core inside
in your heart or your mind
not to do this ambitiously but just a little bit more
and then if there is some calm or relaxation or subtleness seeing if you can maintain
it as we now turn our attention
to the people of this world the animals of this world all the living beings
that we share this planet with
in a sense that we're in a family with
some some of these creatures we share the planet with are distant relatives
into in this relaxed settled way to gaze upon others with kind eyes
with a kind regard to gaze upon all beings
with the generosity of heart
and perhaps after a session of meditation it is possible to look upon others
in a qualitatively different way than if you're preoccupied and caught up in things
maybe you have access to a simple kindness and well-wishing
and if so it's useful healthy health-making
to give a simple expression to this kind this well-wishing without ambition
or obligation wishing maybe even saying to yourself
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we live as if we're related to all living beings
because somewhere of some way or other we actually are
may all beings be happy
so before i give my talk today a couple of announcements one is
that next week i'm going be away
and so matthew bren silver will come and
teach these early morning 7 a.m here in california teachings matthew is a wonderful teacher and i
think you'll be delighted by his teaching and his presence and
very happy to have him fill in for me and the other is that our retreat center
the irc insight retreat center we were going to open at the end of august
but now we decided to delay that probably till the middle of november and and the retreats that we were
scheduled to do in person now will be online and which means that we can accept more
people so if some of you are interested in a chance to do an online retreat and
you can go i think you can go onto irc's website and see what's available now or i think it's all been converted now um
and um to online retreats and and um and uh these online retreats are quite
wonderful it's one of the surprises of the pandemic is how how well the benefits beneficial is for
people to do them and so anyway so that's available
so this today this last talk on this five part series on
delusion it's also the last talk in the now the three-week series on the three
roots of unwholesome behavior the three sometimes called the poisons
greed hatred and delusion and so in conclusion i'd like to
kind of paraphrase the buddha when he said that he said kind of emphatically
or enthusiastically he said if it was not possible to bring greed
hatred and delusion to an end i would not instruct you to do so
but it is possible to put an end to greed hatred and delusion and so this is my instruction
so maybe for many people it's inconceivable that they can give up these very strong forces in the mind but
this is what buddhist practice is sets out to do and it's a phenomenally
beneficial and dignified and valuable path to be on to
first alleviate decrease and then to have an experience of the absence of
great hatred delusion and that absence is followed by coming to a time where
the tendency to create hatred and delusion is comes to an end and
and one of the things that's quite wonderful about this is that greed hatred and delusion are the roots
for all unethical behavior or say it differently all behavior that causes intentional or
conscious harm to others and even to ourselves
and it's a phenomenal thing to become a person who has cleansed themselves or freed themselves
from these powerful forces the consequences of which we can read in the newspaper every day
of how people treat each other and the impact we have on others and the environment and all over
and it's some you know the hope is that there are some people who appreciate the human capacity to
become free and uh and our model then or
a beacon for others it's possible to be on this path maybe in this lifetime we're not going
to go all the way to the complete ending of all greed hatred and delusion but the diminishing of it
and to have greater and greater periods of time when we're free of it before it comes back
is really marvelous for the buddha he teaches what he teaches called the
dharma and and sometimes his dharma that he teaches is said to be
visible here and now directly perceivable in the present moment it's not something
esoteric and distant uh you know but rather something that's available here
and one of the inspiring ways in which he makes it so available maybe it's hard to do this but
so kind of you know in in our lives is that the dharma that when the dharma
is visible here and now when we have had the experience
of greed hatred and delusion and we experience the mind the heart free of
it without it and that distinction between what it's like to have a mind of with
great hatred and delusion and what it's like to have one without that is where we can see the dharma in a
very profound way but it really takes both so part of this
study of greed hatred delusion is a willingness to see it in ourselves to admit it
to ourselves to become familiar with all the tricks all the ways that great hatred and
delusion operate for us not to uh feel bad about ourselves or
or be depressed by it but the more familiar we become then that when when it's not there
we're able to recognize that in a clearer way it's like going from a crowded room full of things and um because we really
know what that's like the experience of an open room that's free of a lot of
crowded things just feels so different and we really appreciate it in
fact if the room is spacious and clean and peaceful enough it can feel nourishing and
delightful to be in it and so to be familiar with great heightened delusion
to better appreciate um and and be nourished by the
absence of it that is to see the dharma here and now and so it's not understanding you know
great profound teachings on emptiness or great states of consciousness or
transcendental states as much as it is this clear kind of ordinary recognition
that's possible uh the presence and the absence of these things
as we become familiar with greed hatred and delusion and this week it's the topic is delusion we begin
to appreciate that all of these in delusion as well have a common characteristic
and maybe we can call it a common denominator and that is they all involve
clinging or grasping and clinging uh some people like to think of it as
like uh you know plastic cling wrap that uh it just sticks to us we stick to
it and and sometimes you can't get rid of it or you can't unfold it or something
and it just accompanies us but grasping is a more powerful
clinging maybe some people are synonymous grasping when people would cling with p to people
with our hands or with our hearts or our minds we grasp on we don't let go we claw
sometimes it feels like they're clawing onto what we want and to other people or something
so all greed hate and delusion has a share having clinging and grasping as part of
it and something we're grasping something we're clinging to
and the experience of becoming really free is the uh opening up of that
grasping hand it's the relaxing of the clawing hand it's the softening of the
fist or the resisting hand there's a deep deep kind of letting go of a knot
inside of us deep letting go of a contraction a coagulation of
that exists within the field of awareness and um and uh
and so to to move in that direction to have a sense oh this is possible and
to begin to experience this release of clinging release of grasping
first in small little experiences in life even the smallest letting go relaxing
around something is a foretaste or is or partakes in part
with the liberation of a buddha it's just a matter of degree and so we're not so different from the
buddha if we begin to appreciate the small degrees it which we live without greed hatred
delusion the small degrees in which we can let go of it and relax around it um small degrees we can let go of
clinging and grasping and the appreciating that seeing that
and valuing it and valuing ourselves for being on this path
supports the growing growing capacity to let go more deeply to relax more deeply and it
isn't so much we're letting go of things in the world which some people protest that you know just means that we live a lot in life of
radical renunciation just let go of everything that there's some value to that for sure
but um but uh it's not letting go of things that's the
object of buddhist practice it's letting go of the clinging to things it's letting go of the grasping
in the mind and whether or not we let go of things or even people sometimes
um is uh is secondary it's that that we use our wisdom to know what's best to do
there but it doesn't take much wisdom to appreciate that we're better off not having clinging or
grasping in the mind and the people we do cling to
they really appreciate it many times when we can be with them and love them without clinging to them so if you learn
to let go of the clinging life becomes a whole different game and
importantly that as we learn not to cling this absence of this activity of
clinging of grasping this non-doing of clinging and grasping that um where it
lowers the tendency to be caught in delusion and hatred and in greed and we begin
seeing how the movement towards delusion towards greed towards hatred
comes along with a with a activity of the mind activity of the heart of contraction of tightness of clinging
of tension that is just not good for us and to really feel and recognize that
because we're really in touch with ourselves it gives us the opportunity to recognize something different
the absence of clinging and how good that is and how our view of the world changes
if we're seeing the world through the lens of non-clinging rather than seeing it through the lens
of clinging seeing in the world through the lens of non-greed
non-hatred and non-delusion it is possible to do this and
it's uh more valuable to it to do this than a lot of other human pursuits more
valuable than becoming rich more valuable than having i don't know
popularity and all kinds of things so i wish you much much happiness
and peace and well-being and and i know that the greatest happiness
and peace that's available to you will come when you when you really
let go and release the clinging and grasping in the mind and free yourself of greed hatred and
delusion and may it be so so thank you
for this series and being part of this and listening and i look forward to being back with
you in two weeks so thank you