so hello and welcome
to this uh 30 minutes now of mindfulness meditation
and sometimes i think that there are two
mutually supportive aspects of mindfulness meditation
that they are and that they can work together
so the first is uh to relax
to release whatever tension that might be held in the mind or the body
or the heart and if there is no tension this
discerned then of course one should not keep relaxing some point relaxation
doesn't really become relevant
and and the relaxation is not the same thing as slumping or collapsing there is an
alertness and uprightness which is related to the second aspect
and that is the practice of clear recognition
the the uh to where there's a quality of attentiveness
that is a little bit more uh maybe acute then in everyday life
where there's a clarity to our experience of the present moment
that allows us to register or see or experience know
what is happening in the present moment in a particular way
and and different times it's more being aware more feeling more experiencing more
knowing more what some people will call a recognition and that special way is to
be aware without interfering with what we are aware of so
not to tighten up hold on not to have expectations not try to make something
happen not try to pull away or push away
but there's a quality of freedom in the clear recognition so this idea of
relaxing and kind of relaxing and opening the awareness up to really be
here with what's here part of this clear awareness can be
expressed that it's to allow whatever we know to be here so there's no
pushing or denying anything pushing away or denying and there's no holding on and clinging
to anything and there's a kind of deep respect to all things it's a deep kind of allowance
and one of the things that leads to is uh discovering that it's trustable
to allow the dharma to move through us to allow phenomena as they arise and pass to come
and go and evolve and change and process but the key to it is a clear recognition
where we kind of get out of the way we're not kind of you know we're not the
the agenda of the self doesn't come into play so this relaxing makes helps the
clear knowing be relaxed and useful
and the clear recognition helps us to stay alert and clear it also helps us to
recognize when what needs to be clearly recognized
is the tension we have because if it's not easy to relax then we shouldn't spend a
lot of time trying to do it but rather bring this loving careful attention
to what's going on here and then and sometimes what we learn to relax is
not the tensions in our body but we relax the tensions in the mind in
relationship to that so these two things to relax
and have clear recognition and discover how to be aware that gets out of the way and allows the
dharma to move through us so to take a upright posture or a
posture that allows you to be a little bit more alert
maybe there's a little energy in the posture for people who lie down on their back
sometimes that's uh found by um the
the forearm is uh the upper arm might be parallel to the
bed or the floor but the upper arms are pointing straight up towards the ceiling
one of them or both of them and that not only gives a little energy but also
gives the indication when we're starting to lose that um you know it falls over the arm
and gently closing the eyes
and perhaps using a few deep breaths to really relax the larger
tensions and holdings of the body
breathing in deeply and then a long exhale that really allows the shoulders and the
belly and to relax and let go
sometimes if there's a long exhale it's like progressive relaxation of the
shoulders just step by step it kind of like a little bit a little bit more
and then letting the breathing return to normal and still it's useful to relax to soften
softening in the face
softening relaxing the shoulders
maybe the area of the shoulder blades
maybe you can open up
your chest a bit and then see how you can relax your shoulders
and softening the belly
and then maybe relaxing softening the
mind imagining the mind is like the surface of a choppy
waters and the wind dies down and the surface of the lake the waters
spreads out wide and still and quiet
and then perhaps inside the mind somewhere inside
is the place from which you know or aware or you experience things
often the location for where we our sense of self might be
and as you exhale maybe soften relax
dissolve that center into the wide
field of the mind
and as you exhale at the end of the exhale
soften relax a little bit into the paws between the exhale and
inhale the ever so slight momentary pause
so that you can allow for the inhale to arise on its own
out of that pause and you receive it
awareness receives
clear recognition receives the inhale
clear recognition allows the
exhale
and and continuing clear awareness of
breathing but if something else occurs in the body the mind the heart
that's more compelling than the breathing
see if there's some way you can relax about its presence
and practice clear awareness non-interfering attention
as if it has permission to be there no problem
and you practice clear awareness of it until you're ready to begin again on
your breathing
if you are floating away and thinking practice clear recognition of
thinking
and see if there's any tension involved or pressure
in thinking that can be relaxed
and perhaps renew your practice of clear recognition clear
awareness of the present moment and begin again with your breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to imagine what relaxed clear recognition would be like
when gazing upon the joys and sorrows of the world
what would be like if you're able to stay relaxed clearly recognizing
the great bodhisattva of compassion the great embodiment of compassion
is sometimes named the one who sees the suffering of the world
and to see to gaze upon
the sorrows and joys of the world with relaxed clear recognition
and in so doing maybe the channels of recognition
can touch the tenderness and the warmth the places of care in our hearts
the place that where the heart is nourished nurtured by the goodness of the world
by our own goodness and from this place of being touched
to consider how wonderful it would be if the suffering of the world could be
transformed so that people are freed of that suffering
freed of oppression injustice
afraid of greed and hatred
and may it be so as we end the sitting wishing
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we learn to share this happiness safety peace and freedom with each other
[Music]
so today is the second talk on dosa which is uh
can be translated as hatred or hostility
and so we're following a sequence here of this week that yesterday i introduced
the concept of non-hatred as a significant state of uh well-being that
involves love and patience calmness peace
not just simply the absence of hatred but a reference point of uh of a significant healthy
state of being that highlights the the uh unsatisfactoriness of hatred
that highlights how it's um it's a form of stress and tension and and
pain for for the individual who has it when we can really see the contrast to
being in a state that's that's not hateful not full of hatred
and today i want to talk about just this idea of dosa itself and then i'll talk about
tomorrow i'll be practicing with it thursday will be um composting hatred
the transformation of it and friday will be the liberation from
hatred and what's possible with that liberation
so um the it's important to appreciate that
this word hatred uh dosa means hostility uh
it's ancient texts talk about it being a wanting to harm
and it can also involve intense dislike a kind of intense opposition to others
where that dislike and opposition is a form of harm making that others feel somehow belittled or
boxed in or oppressed or disrespected in some big way
when they dislike the the uh the aversion is so strong
and um now there can be kind of simple
dislike of things and people even in direct maybe dislike of their activities what they do
but it doesn't have to translate to any kind disrespect for others
it doesn't have to even diminish our love for others possible to have a kind of a heartfelt warmth
towards others even if we dislike some of the things that they do but the intensity of it um
even if we don't think we hate someone or feel hostility and the intensity of like we don't feel
like we want to harm them the intensity of the dislike is a form of hatred
and what it what it's not or what it overlaps with and sometimes
includes and sometimes doesn't is anger and this is important because if we
treat anger and this dosa hostility is the same thing then all anger is seen as being a problem or
being a source of suffering but if we see it as
sometimes anger is a very passioned sense of no sense of this is injust
this is not right and the intensity of it might look like something
that resembles hostility but there doesn't have to be any hostility in it i've been on the receiving end and of
what i call the white anger where i felt there was zero hostility
but uh and in fact i felt i don't know if i felt friendship from
the person but i felt no hostility i felt safe though the anger was intense and
the one occur the occurrence i'm thinking about it the intensity was in the message
of no don't do that again and as soon as the message was delivered
i could feel the person just kind of let it go and and it was an appropriate message
and uh it was received and i was inspired by the cle how clean it was that's
intensity of no so it was kind of an anger but there was no hostility as part of it
so this has the way in which we have hostility and our this movement of hatred can harm
is a way of we harm ourselves and that's why the reference point of
non-hatred is so useful because we see how we're harming ourselves
that it's like a a wood fire where the the
the wood is both uh uh the fire is arising out of the wood and
it's the fire is burning the wood so in the same way the heat of hatred burns the one who's
on fire with it harms it generally when there's hatred this dosa
the attention of the mind is externally directed is directed to the object of the
hostility and um and some people it takes a form of blame
sometimes sometimes takes the form of being hypercritical and unwillingness to
see anything good about the other person and only sees that aspect which is bad and or problematic um sometimes there's a
a recoiling from our own pain by blaming by finding something outside
of us to either blame or attack or to be hostile towards
sometimes as a deflection from being willing to experience our personal
pain and suffering and and somehow
redirecting that pain in a sense outward and sometimes it's clearly to cause
other people other people should feel pain i'm feeling pain so other people should feel pain
and so to recognize how hostility has this uh and also if there can be
hostility towards oneself uh maybe some people hate themselves or some aspect of themselves
and there also there's a kind it's not exactly externally focused but there's a kind of objectification of
something that the mind is directed towards and anytime there's this objectification
then there is an alienation both an alienation from the other person that we
might feel that towards or the other thing we feel that before we're no longer there present to be able
to see and feel experience fully what's there we're now seeing it through
a particular filter the filter of hate and hostility aversion and uh and every
and everything is seen in that light everything is wrong everything is and we
just pick up all the problems and um but also and so that's an alienation we don't really there fully
for the person it's also an alienation towards oneself that uh because we're involved in kind
of an intense objectification of something we're involved in a thought an idea a concept of something that um
the attention is kind of towards that object and towards thinking about it that we lose touch with ourselves
and so when there is uh intense hostility um then uh it does not be intense but
there's hostility it comes with all these different aspects it comes with a burning a
tension a tightening a stressful state to be in it comes with an objectification of
something that is alienating that disconnecting
and also see tomorrow the task of mindfulness is to re-establish the connection
overcome the alienation both towards others and towards oneself by opening up and really being present
part of because hostility and hatred is so compelling at times uh sometimes it's
um it produces its own um you know it produces its own fire
that hurts that that hurt of the stress or the alienation
produces more of the same and it kind of like it keeps looking
outwards for more things to hate or more things to feel bad about to be critical of and so there's a loop
that of hate sometimes where it's difficult sometimes to get out of because to do not
to not have the object of the hate or the is to allow us allow oneself to feel what's
happening here and that's just too difficult sometimes intense hatred comes from uh
maybe from good reasons within uh you know it could be that there's an intense protectiveness
maybe there's fear for good reason there are people who cause harm and um and so then it's easy to
uh justify the hatred because it's a form of protection from justifiable things we should you
know just viable reasons to be protected and and but the question is that really
the best way to protect ourselves and i can't i'm not going to answer that question for any individual
but because circumstances are so complex that i don't want to say that never have
hatred if that's what protects you from the harm that other people are doing but i believe that it's possible to be
trained or be reflective or be have a presence of mind that allows us to protect ourselves
in other ways besides using um returning hatred with hatred returning
harm with harm and but you know how to find that that's a
you know interesting that's an important topic but the beginning of it
is to have a willingness to study our own hatred to really uh our
hostility to really stop and take a look at it and if um and maybe the words hatred and
hostility are you know such such intense words that maybe you feel this doesn't relate
to you often but hostility and uh and hatred um are also very subtle forms of
aversion subtle forms of dislike and opposition to something um subtle subtle sometimes there's a
biting humor we use to kind of get back at people sometimes we say cutting things because
you know we're upset with someone we want to kind of step you know st have verbal daggers and stab them a little bit
there's all kinds of subtle and subtle ways in which we express um hostility or
say things which we don't believe we're wanting to harm anyone but there is a kind of subtle kind of
kind of attack that's happening so to become sensitive to this to become
aware of this and spend some time being willing to look at personal hostility
aversion that sometimes takes the form of prejudice and bias
sometimes takes the form of of turning away walking away shutting down
ignoring um where we feel like i'm not hostile but
we've kind of shut someone out of our hearts and and it is a kind of hostile act
and so but to study it to really get to know it and it's a worthwhile exercise to do and
even if it's just for these next 24 hours is to kind of review
how this dosa both mild and intense
has been part of your life and and how it's part of your life still and when it manifests and what are the
conditions to bring about and then what your relationship to it is do you
hate it do you are you distraught that you have this within you
do you justify it quickly right almost automatically how is it
and see if you can practice this clear recognition is to kind of relax with it and
and find a time and place where you can relax and just kind of allow it to be there so you can start seeing it clearly
without the interference of hating or hate being distraught over our hate being critical of our hate
turning away from it trying to fix it right away spend time getting to know it it's the
really getting to know and understanding how it is for us that lays the foundation for practicing with
it well and moving on towards freedom and because in buddhism
the freedom from great hatred and delusion is the definition is one of the primary definitions for
what full liberation is uh it's a well worth
to spend some time with each of these but this week with uh with hostility hatred uh dislike
and really kind of understanding how it works for you and hopefully you don't get discouraged or depressed
hopefully you feel in a certain way encouraged that this is the way forward this is a
wise and mature thing to do and then tomorrow we'll talk about practicing with it
so thank you and and may this all be for the purpose
of non-hatred thank you