here
[Music]
so
so today we're going to touch into that
tenth step of anapanasati breathing in
one
delights the mind breathing out one
delights the mind
and and this word mind cheetah
appears in step 8 9 and 10.
in 8 it's
calming the
activities of the mind
then step nine it's uh
experiencing the mind and then
in step now ten it's
delighting the mind
and and so there's the light
the word that's translated i'm
translating now is the light
sometimes can be translated as pleasing
the mind or satisfying the mind
and it rather than it being an active
verb that what we're doing
we might understand it as being
recognizing or allowing for
a certain sense of deep satisfaction
deep
being pleased a deep kind of very glad
gladness in the mind
and that comes from meditation practice
and there's a number of ways to
understand this and there are different
ways to experience this
one of the classic ones that the
tradition talks about
is um finally
the mind is no longer out of control
or say differently finally the mind
doesn't have a mind of its own
and and where the mind were led around
jumping around agitated trashing about
in the mind with our thoughts but we
feel like now we've really come home or
we're settled we're back to in ourselves
the mind is under control or the mind is
not
just doing whatever it wants wandering
around and picking up thoughts and
chasing thoughts and
but we're really settled here and we've
come home to ourselves the mind is
settled and present
it's a word and the word that's often
used in the ancient tradition is mind is
now
tamed i suspect a lot of us
in the modern west don't really like the
idea of taming ourselves
so if a tame mind doesn't really inspire
but but the opposite of that
you know having a mind which is no
longer
untamed or out of control maybe
just feels better to appreciate that or
value that
and one of the metaphors for an
out of control mind in the ancient world
is
like a fish trashing about in a very
shallow puddle of water
you know just flap flapping around and
so sometimes the mind just flaps and
does its things and
jumps around and chases one thought
after the other and
and and we have no control or no
say over the mind and but to get
the mental activities to quiet down to
settle
and a feeling that we're not really
going to wander off into the past in the
future anymore we're not really going to
get lost in thought anymore we are now
really here
and and feel that sense of it's deeply
satisfying
to start feeling really connected here
and
and at peace here or settled here
and there's a kind of a satisfaction of
not having the agitation or the
energetics of the mind jumping around
moving out
going here and there and it allows the
mind to be
start becoming peaceful or being a deep
rest they're just
here and it can feel like very
solid or very centered i can
hear and the mind is in the present
moment
and any tendency to leave that present
moment by going off
into thought it just it just doesn't go
very far it hardly goes anywhere at all
it's like
a rubber band attached to their thoughts
and they just get pulled right back to
the present
or we just like no you know why bother
it's really good to be here and
this movement of the experiencing the
mind
this way is a movement towards wholeness
to becoming more whole that's only
possible
if we're in the present moment
by almost by i don't know if definition
is the right word but
by definition if we're lost in the
future
caught up in future concerns or past
concerns
we are partial we're involved and
focused on the future and we're not
really connected to what's here
or if we're involved in fantasy it's no
matter how
wonderful and nice the fantasy might
feel
a fantasy is only a small part of who we
are and there's a disconnect even in
dissociation
in extreme forms with our body our mind
states and it's really what's happening
right here
and so as we start settling and able to
be here in the present moment in a
rooted way grounded way
it allows begins allowing for this
of a process of feeling whole
becoming um and a whole
is is a process also
of a lot of the sharp boundaries we have
time and space begins to fall away
or sharp boundaries between
the body and the mind or sharp
boundaries between
the edges of our body and the space
around us
a lot of the
sense of wholeness starts moving into
what some people would call
altered states of consciousness altered
states of mind
but that suggests that somehow it's
non-nor
like not normal or and well maybe it's
not so normal because
we don't go into those states very much
but um
uh to in in meditation we start feeling
this settled in the present moment and
start opening up to a whole
feeling of wholeness of being here
it starts feeling like this is natural
this is a homecoming this is what should
be ordinary
ordinary states of consciousness
ordinary states of mind
are fragmented narrow limited
bounded and
frazzled and even though they might be
familiar with us
and that sense comfortable for us to
really experience starts feeling a
settled wholeness it starts feeling oh
this is health this is healthy
healthy mind this is um
you know it's the altered states of mind
are daily mind states those are the ones
are altered and
and strange and preoccupied and things
like that
but you know a subtle feeling of
wholeness
that feels good some people
when they meditate are struggling with
a distractible mind you know being
caught by the hindrances
and uh caught the desires and aversions
of all kinds
and they're coming back and coming back
and working with that
to finally have those quiet down
and the mind is able to finally be
present
it's like the mind has found itself
it provides a deep satisfaction a
delight a joy a pleasure
and this is what we're talking about in
this tenth step
of delighting the mind or pleasing the
mind or
gladdening the mind allowing the mind to
feel a deep satisfaction
and i offer all these different words
because different people will
find different words speak to what their
own flavor of
all this might be in their meditation
and
and uh but the important thing here is
that we're allowed to
feel the goodness of that we're allowed
to feel the delight and the joy and the
satisfaction
certainly not to cling to and hold on to
and congratulate ourselves for in some
egotistical way
but we're not supposed to ignore the joy
the happiness the well-being
the pleasure the satisfaction of
meditation
in fact feeling that is there's a way of
feeling a way of experiencing it
that allows us to continue this process
of settling in
quieting the mind expanding the sense of
wholeness
that we're moving into and in doing so
we open up to states of mind qualities
of mind
that are coterminous that are
intimately part of
this feeling of a wholeness or a broad
awareness or
centeredness clear knowing clarity of
mind
that are uh that are considered a form
of wealth
in fact for the buddha the greatest
wealth a person
can have and acquire is the
wealth that comes from a settled
clear and open mind the sense of
wholeness so
the seven factors of awakening that i
mentioned yesterday
mindfulness investigation effort
joy tranquility samadhi
and equanimity these all kind of belong
to the realm of this
settled wholeness that comes with it as
the awareness the attention gets full
and complete
and and and so it isn't just like we're
losing something
by settling down and really letting go
of the distracted mind and really being
present
we gain so much and and it's called
an inner wealth if you want to be
wealthy develop your inner life
and it's uh and it's a wealth that i
mean it qualifies as a wealth because
it provides some of the greatest
pleasure and
safety and happiness and
that that's available to us and
certainly greater happiness than any
material wealth can ever produce
so so
breathing in delighting the mind
breathing out delighting the mind
you can't do that too early you can't
just sit down decide to do that
it comes when when meditation is really
settle down and settle down settle down
so remember it's now we're talking about
the 10th stage of the 16 stages
but when it happens to you that you get
that you start feeling inklings of
kind of this kind of delight
satisfaction pleasure
being pleased by what's happening deep
satisfaction
open to it allow for it let it spread
wide and broad
throughout your being be nourished by it
and and let it be something you
appreciate and enjoy
and that sets a stage for the next step
amanapanasati which we really won't do
for a couple of weeks
which is samadhi which is the
unification of the mind the
concentration of the mind and until then
we're going to spend next week with the
seven factors of awakening
and maybe this will support experiencing
the mind and
experiencing the delight in the mind to
really kind of spend some time with
these
seven factors of awakening and they'll
also serve
for the 11th step the samadhi