so i think it's
fairly well known for many people that
one of the core
in the buddhist view one of the core
sources of
suffering has to do with clinging or
craving
and that clinging is described many ways
sometimes it's simply called a
stickiness that we there's a stickiness
a glue
that keeps us attached to things
sometimes it's called a knot you knot
nodded up in things
uh it's uh sometimes called the fetter
in the translation for the pali word but
it literally means a not to be knotted
up and we say that colloquially in
english i was all knotted up in
something
and um the uh
the uh expression from a japanese
teacher that i really liked was
the fist in the heart or the fist in the
mind
and that we're trying to open the fist
of the heart
so it's not all fisted up or closed up
tightened up
and so there's many many languages for
this
many many ways of talking about this way
we cling or crave
and part of the function of practice is
to
reveal the ways that we cling the ways
that we are
knotted up and sometimes it's pretty
evident right away
sometimes as we go further and further
along in the practice
we start seeing aspects of being knotted
up being caught by things
in ways that
we didn't know at all maybe he's more
subtle or deeper somehow inside
and in some ways the the the movement
through the path of practice
is a continual movement of encountering
and then uh releasing and countering and
untying
all the different ways that things are
sticky with things we hold on to things
or cling to things or resist things
and and so when we run into these things
in ourselves
it's you know some people have this
instinct to feel bad about themselves or
criticize themselves
it's also possible to see it as oh good
this is what it this is the path forward
knowing these things
is part of the path it's how we go
forward
and that's one interpretation i have for
why this practice of anapanasati
is so simple in its explanation
is that um it's not meant to avoid
or not recognize that we're attached or
clinging or
there's all these challenges we kind of
come along the way
but it's not supposed to avoid it but
it's offering us a very
simple way of moving through it
without making a big deal of it because
they're not mentioned
and rather than getting caught up in the
stories
or the idea of me myself and mine in
relationship to it
that he has to be really really simple
of course those things are there
and and uh and then
how simple can we be in a way that's
genuine
uh uh beneficial honest
and healing or freeing as we go through
and so i i see the simplicity of the way
this beginning of anapanasati works
as a way of really addressing all these
clinging all the challenges all the
strong feelings emotions we have all the
ways in which the mind
gets knotted up fisted up caught up in
things and
concerned with things and um and um
but without uh without kind of getting
involved
getting it entangled with it even
further
so to just simply stay breathing
through it all whatever's going on
breathe i think i said this yesterday
that there's something about hanging in
there with the rhythm of breathing
that keeps them i call it sometimes the
great lubricator
it keeps things lubricated so they don't
get rusted up or
or squeaky or or something frozen up
or it's a massage that we're massaging
stuff for
it's um it's a way of kind of by staying
with that gentle rhythm of breathing
it's a little bit easier for the mind
not to get caught by something
because if you're cut caught you've lost
touch with the breathing
but if you're touched with the breathing
then there's something we're taking
being with that's kind of this lubricant
or this massage
the concerns the feelings we have
haven't gone away necessarily
but it's the knotted up the stickiness
the preoccupation with them
that's loosened up and then something
else begins to happen
if we free our concerns our emotions our
challenges
even our suffering if we free it
from our preoccupation from our
resistance the stories the opinions the
predictions about it what it means that
it's there
are pushing it away or validating it or
justifying it or apologizing for it
all these complicated things we do all
those
perpetuate it somehow and if we just
could learn to leave it alone
but without denying it just leave it
alone let it be there
and leave it alone from all this extra
stuff we had
the heart knows how to heal the mind
knows
how to unfold in the same way that if
you cut your finger with a kitchen knife
for example
chopping vegetables it's a complicated
physiological process to heal
that cut but we don't have to worry
about that
the body heals itself if all we have to
do is keep the cut clean
so so much of the angst the suffering
the challenge the grief
that we have to respect it deeply
not to and really respect it
leave it alone without
stickiness without clinging without
being nodded to it
and this mindfulness of breathing the
implicit idea
in this practice is that actually that
mindfulness of breathing
allows that freedom leaves allows us to
leave things alone
and then as the practice goes along to
feel
the mental formations the the
bodily formations to feel the physical
activity expressions
manifestations of the mind
manifestations over responses or
thoughts or feelings
it's such a powerful thing it's a way
again of
being present for the all the
difficulties and joys of life
but to be present for it physically
without the stickiness without being
four against in the clinging
and it's a way of kind of begin to
loosen up the stickiness just to feel it
in your body
the body is not a story and so much of
the stickiness has to do with the story
making mind
the opinions the ideas predictions
and then on top of that the panasonic
says
relax or tranquilize make tranquil this
body
and for me this idea of relaxing calming
the body
is not really meant to avoid anything
but it's beginning to relax the ways in
which we hold things
the way we hold on or knotted up it's
the knots that we're
letting go of and as the knots get let
go
the entanglements let go then uh
what we're feeling inside the challenges
we have
can begin to move and resolve themselves
and relax
and it can be a very different
perspective
and sometimes we don't solve our
problems but we dissolve them
in this way some of the external
problems we have in life the real things
that we have to take care of
don't go away this way but we can put
ourselves in a much better position
more creative more intelligent more wise
more loving
to address them when we go through this
deep process of
letting go of the stickiness the craving
that we have
so i think it's kind of a radical thing
with this practice
that it actually doesn't talk about
these challenges directly
because we don't have to address them
directly
if we do this steps of anapanasati
they just kind of get taken care of on
the side or
get taken care of because we're making
space
to in releasing the stickiness the knots
that we have
and that process continues into the
second
set of four instructions where we become
aware
of the mental formations the mental
activities
the thoughts that we have and then we
calm those down
and calming means let go of the
stickiness like oh the tightness the
constrictions that are there the
pressure that's there
it can't be done all at once and all of
it but the beginning is process
of letting go of the stickiness of
settling the mind
and this also is not to avoid the mental
problems
but to but to let go of the stickiness
the fetters
that are there so
to repeat myself i think it's a radical
thing that this anapanasati does not
talk address directly the challenges we
have in practice
but it's not because they're being
ignored
it's i would like to propose is because
it's offering a very realistic very
effective
process by which they can be resolved or
dissolved or
we can find our way with them without
having to address them directly
uh when you know as in the usual ways
the mind wants to do that our heart
wants to do that
so um so as you practice and
when you find yourself with these
challenges that could happen
no the practice is a response to it this
ways of addressing it and perhaps being
content and willing to do so indirectly
and for some of us it's a radical thing
to not
feel like we have to fix and address
everything directly
but we can just relax settle back and
trust the process
as we go move along on this path
so thank you and i look forward to
being again with you tomorrow