so here we are at the beginning of a new
week and happy to start the week with uh
overall an expert exploration of delusion and but for now for this morning sitting
one of the hallmarks of the pasta practice is simplicity
and if there was a menindraji any
indian teacher that some of us knew i had the practice with
he um would say that if it's not simple it's not vipassana practice
and the relationship between the two can be in the meaning of vipassana as clear
seeing if there is not simplicity in the
perceptions then there's a
you know we don't perceive clearly if we don't see clearly there is no
wisdom and in fact some of the wisdom that we
practice with is wisdom about simplicity the tremendous value of of not getting
involved in planning or analyzing or trying to
figure out or trying to fix engineer or practice
even if something is doesn't seem to be going right in practice rather than spending a lot of time
trying to make it right the kind of the paradigm shift of the
pasta practice is to say well what would be the simplest way of
knowing this just knowing it and to have the wisdom to some way step
away and find some freedom some kind of independence
in the clear seeing and the beauty of it that and really the
word beauty is is really meant it's part of the tradition we'll talk about it later
the beauty is in the clarity of the seeing and the simplicity of the perception
the the clearness of the knowing and it's possible to know clearly for
example that i'm confused there's confusion here
this this is an experience that's complicated
i don't know what's happening
my mind seems to want to fix it run away or attack it or analyze it
and each of those little recognitions can be in itself have this beauty of clarities the beauty of simplicity
just knowing this just knowing this
so
we begin with the posture meditation posture and ideally
it's a simple posture over time practicing the same meditation
posture over and over again and the body makes small adjustments and
finds its way to a posture that is relatively easy to maintain
and become simple
so taking a little bit of time maybe swaying forward and back
left to right and it kind of until you find a kind of
center place where there's a balance
and then from if you're sitting upright from the sitting bones up the spine
making small adjustments
to have the weight of your body your torso centered on the vertebrae
and as they travel up the spine you come to where they're
neck last vertebrae connects with the skull
maybe you can create a little space there by lifting the head up or pulling the back of the head
slightly up and the chin slightly down
and then gently closing your eyes
and to establish a renewed connection familiarity
grounding in the breathing taking a few long slow deep breaths
three quarters full and gently breathing long breathing out
longer than you normally would not by forcing the breath out
but by releasing letting go
and letting your breathing return to normal
and scan through your body and as you exhale
if there's places in your body that you can relax muscles held in ways that you can
release relax the muscles
also you can see if you can exhale
relax the mind the thinking mind
and part of relaxing the mind is allowing the mind for these minutes of the meditation
to be simple simply with the present moment
and perhaps you can begin practicing a simple clear awareness
with your breathing
not being ambitious with your breathing or
trying to make anything happen except being with your breathing
with clarity and knowing with simplicity of attention
as if the fog has cleared and you can see clearly
as if the light has been turned on and you can see clearly
not what you think you should be seeing but whatever is easy
to experience in the breathing being content with what is easy
just as a place to be in the present appreciating simple
awareness
and if anything occurs that makes it difficult or it takes you away from breathing
experiment with how simple you can know it
so simple that you're not entangled with it
for or against it maybe more like a
feeling of awe or wonder
from the lack of complications lack of being for and against
just simple knowing
and after knowing it for a little bit begin again with your breathing
being simple in the attention to breathing in
and breathing out
what is the simplest way you can know what's happening now
and then to keep it that simple
take refuge in that simplicity
simple knowing of what's happening
can provide wisdom one wisdom
is that getting more complicated about what's
happening loses some of that simplicity
loses some of the clarity
loses some of the absence of entanglement
the simpler the awareness the more clearly we can see how we lose
that simplicity that clarity
and as we come to the end of the sitting
the simplicity of being present can also reveal
the complexity that takes us away from our good will
our simplest basic human kindness
simplicity of knowing clarity of knowing
enables basic human kindness
to have a chance to be present gives it
a room and time and space
so it too can be available for how we meet the
world and so as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps in whatever simplicity and clarity you have to open your heart
to the world and gaze upon the world
with kindness with goodwill
a generosity of spirit
wishing may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may there be something from this morning's meditation
that supports each of us to contribute to that as a possibility
may we all live for the welfare and happiness of all beings
[Music]
so this week's theme following up on the last two weeks
is the third of the three unwholesome roots sometimes given the dramatic
name of the three poisons sometimes describes the three ways that
when firewood burns it burns itself so that these three fires sometimes are
called the three fires they arise out of us they burn from
us while they also burn us so these are greed hatred and delusion
or greed ill will and confusion we'll stay with for now with
the translation delusion and um
excuse me for a minute
so we'll state it now for now with a translation of delusion for mohawk m-o-h-a but as the pattern has been for
these last two weeks this first talk will not be about
unwholesome root of delusion but rather the opposite
and the tradition calls the opposite non-delusion
and it takes for many forms it's not just simply the absence of
something but think of it as the absence that allows the opposite to appear
and those many things are kind of the opposite so for example wisdom discernment vision clarity
understanding the tradition also has penetration
as the opposite so we'll talk a little bit more about this but for now i want to emphasize clarity
that rather than wisdom being necessarily a sophisticated under
understanding of things certainly understanding is part of it but so much of it
arises out of clarity clear seeing clear knowing clear perception
and and so this is something to really appreciate a
lot and celebrate it's such a sense of refreshment
and openness or peacefulness or simplicity or
brightness that that comes with non-delusion
um the maybe the most dramatic or the most powerful image or idea for
this idea of non-delusion is the idea of being awake and the word buddhism
could be translated more literally into english as awake-ism it's the ism it's the
religion of being awake of being non-deluded and
often often there's a strong association with um awakening is the ending of ignorance
it's a variation of delusion so um
the tradition talks about because these wonderful kind of analogies for non-delusion
one of them is um turning on the light that uh you we're in the dark and then
the light goes on and then we see clearly what's around us
the other is um
this non-delusion is not a passive thing but it becomes like a skilled guide that
leads us through the forest through the jungle someone who knows the forest the jungle
really well and they can just guide us through so the non-delusion
has a function of helping us to see the path of practice it shows us
you know where to practice where the practice is where the path is found
and the other analogy that's given is that of an arrow an a skilled archer who can shoot an
arrow and it penetrates whatever it is that is shot so that the idea of a skilled archer is
one who has really good eyesight really precise kind of ability to really
calmly stay present and see what's there and then really see through it see kind
of not just the projections not the bias not the preferences we have but to see through
all that penetrate all that so we see things clearly for what they are themselves
and i love this analogy of an archer because of a story that i maybe i've told this before
there was here in california a wonderful zen teacher who came from japan in the late 1960s
named koben chino and apparently in japan he'd studied the japanese art of archery
and so one day he was going to demonstrate his ritual or the practice of archery
at a retreat center on the coast here called eslan and eslin was kind of has big kind of
grass lawn or something on the edge of a cliff that overlooks the
pacific and so there are people gathered on the lawn to watch cole bencino
do his thing and he took a long time to get all ready and a lot of the ritual and all was the preparation of
getting himself centered and balanced and the feet just grounded and the spine straight and the head in the
right position and putting the the the arrow and the bow just the right way
and it took apparently a very long time to all the preparations getting ready
and and but he had such focus and such stillness and such quiet and such uh poise
that i think everyone felt concentrated everyone got pulled in everyone got very quiet
like this was a demonstration of i don't know
skillful elegance skillful concentration presence stillness
and then when he had the target clearly in his sight
he let the arrow go and it flew through the air
and it hit and penetrated his target perfectly bullseye
he had aimed for the pacific ocean and the arrow landed perfectly in it
but this idea of being poised and still in the archer who pen and pencil see is
clearly so there are these different words that associated with
non-delusion and one of them is to have discernment to really kind of make
distinction between what is uh wholesome and unwholesome skillful and unskillful what is helpful
and not helpful um or to say it you know to keep it so it's really simple
between what is harmful and what's beneficial and of course not also
easy to discern this but the greater the wisdom the more clearly that's discernible
and in the the in much of buddhist practice as we get wiser and
wiser or less and less delusion it's more obvious right in the moment
where the benefit is and where the non-benefit is so this ability to see that and that
also gives birth to the ability to have a vision for where the path is the
path of practice and it's to follow what's wholesome what's beneficial to
follow where the non-attachment is and the freedom is and uh and to have a vision for that
this part of this clarity this non-delusion and um it gives life a
kind of a kind of a purpose a kind of direction a kind of that can be quite powerful quite
meaningful partly because it's so freeing and so valuable
the um so this factor of wisdom
discernment vision understanding is said to be a beautiful state of mind
so in its when it's there it's not obscured or or fogged over
by confusion and guessing and analyzing and trying to figure out
in and of itself the state of this clear awareness of wisdom is a beautiful
state of mind so whether there's brightness or clarity or illumination
simplicity all these things associated with it
as we practice uh buddhism it's sooner or later and sometimes maybe
it's later or sometimes it's sooner and later and in between we begin to slowly wake
up slowly discern see recognize this the mind's capacity for simplicity
for clarity for wisdom for understanding for discernment
not in a complicated way but it's obvious it's right there and one of the ways to see that and why
i'm starting the week on with this topic is that at some point we see the distinction
between a simple clarity a simple presence simple being aware of the present moment
and and a way of being that's more complicated maybe much more complicated
maybe we lose the present moment for entanglement in the past and the future
maybe we lose the simplicity because we've gotten very caught in our preferences with what
should be in the present moment or we're caught up in our fears and our analysis and securities around it
or we're caught up in our ill will our projections our bias in relationship to whatever we're
present for and but if we have a reference point
of clarity of wakefulness of wisdom
in all its many forms and some in one of its many forms any of its forms there's a reference point to see
how we lose that and we see that getting
pulled into delusion pulled into projections and biases and and
kind of an overlay of opinions and uh on top of whatever we're seeing
including seeing ourselves and seeing other people that there's a loss there there's a
diminishment there there's a the the light gets turned off the um
we don't have this we lose our calm and we become agitated we lose
our guide we lose our ability to see where the path is and so then it becomes obvious
what much more obvious easier to see what delusion is easier to see
the disadvantage because we feel we see we recognize what we've lost we've lost
that clarity to start with a you know to try to see
and understand delusion um you know just just without any practice
at all then it becomes an analytical exercise it becomes like getting a clear definition of it
and applying that and looking at our mind and trying to say well this this is delusion that's what they're talking about and i'm not supposed to have it
and it's almost like you know getting complicated to free ourselves from the complication
of delusion but if we have if we're settled calm peaceful non-agitated there's a
basic clarity of mind then we have a very different reference point for recognizing
delusion including the reference point the understanding that we don't have to get be feel
ashamed or feel angry or feel upset by the movement
to into delusion all we have to do is to recognize it as delusion
and the simple recognition the clear recognition oh this is delusion brings us back to some of
that clarity and so it's not a moralistic critique of delusion it's it's a clear recognition
knowing clear knowing of the disadvantage of being pulled into it and we know that the alternative not
being diluted is so much better so much more satisfying
so the wisdom so
it gives us the opportunity to have uh have non-delusion about delusion
to have wisdom about delusion and in some ways this is
central to the buddhism enterprise so it's not wisdom about wisdom so much
but freedom is found in wisdom about delusion and that'll be the topic for tomorrow so
thank you all very much and look forward to our time tomorrow