hello and welcome warm welcome wherever you are in the world and how
ever the weather is externally and internally happy to be practicing together warms my
heart so for the practice today the theme i
wanted to invite us to explore is um practicing
meta cultivating goodwill generosity of heart this gift of the heart meta
kindness good will whatever we call that arose by any name is just as fragrant
and sweet mata when we cultivate metta this
this sense of goodwill friendliness for others it's actually a gift to ourselves it
really makes us happy it makes us calm it makes us there's a sense of
peace and ease and beauty that our heart revels in and i especially want to
invite this practice if the internal weather at times is
gray or say you're lying in bed and you're having a hard time falling asleep there
there are challenges so this um
this practice i mean there's some so many different forms of this practice but this practice the way
i'd like to invite us to explore it is just offering it's offering gifts of
generosity gifts of meta gifts of kindness as if you were as if you were you
discovered oh you're santa claus and you have this bag of gifts and it's
goodness and it's never ending it's a never ending bag of
goodness blessings kindness that you didn't even know you
had and the more you give it the more it gets filled up the more it gets so there's
it's not like oh if i give away these goodness these blessings these wishes for other people's well-being there
won't be enough for me it's like oh no there will be more there will be more i can just go and bless people with these
gifts of kindness so so that's one image we can work with
and another image is you can imagine you're a your lofarian's going around and it's just
very dusty and you know you're blessing people with with this these wishes of goodness so there's
different imagery that we're going to to invite today a skillful means see
what works for you and the object really the purpose here
is to cultivate our hearts in generosity of goodwill
for others and what we will discover is that we are the ones that feel
happy and healthy we feel safe happy healthy ease you know the sense of the
four wishes that we kind of went with with meta we share with others we have a sense of goodness
um that that we the sense of brightness
um and and i'll share with you some some nights ago i was having
trouble falling asleep and this is the practice i did i just sharing goodness just sharing
a meta for others in my imagination people i knew imaginary beings all over the world
people near far my challenging categories my people i care about you know just
just gifts of goodness and soon enough there was a sense of gladness bliss
happiness in my heart and that night actually i had very happy dreams there were just the
sense of gladness the sense of abundance of the heart
continued it just continued in the dream space so i invite you to
to explore this not just here as we will explore it together but but maybe tonight when we're about
to to fall asleep when you're lying in bed practice it and see what happens so
and one last thing to say to set the stage before we start is we do all this practice as always
without attachment to outcome yes we know that the world is
uncertain there's there's impermanence we know there is love and permanence um
so as we wish well for others it's not with a sense of clinging to outcome we want you to be
happy now why aren't you happy yet it's more a sense of cultivating our own
heart without attachment to outcome um it's a cultivation of generosity the
way we show up in the world so this is practice so that when we actually interact with
others oh we realize wow there's a lot of kindness there's a lot of generosity there's a lot of good
will it's like athletes who imagine doing a stroke or a particular
uh game and then there's research actually
suggesting that in when we do these um imaginary these practices in our
minds um physical the same those muscles those physical muscles actually get stronger
it's as if we have exercise so this is the same way with with these muscles of quote-unquote
muscles of the heart these practices of kindness generosity good will
gladness that we share and we just become more glad you probably know this by now already
having practiced with happier you've been coming for a while all right let's get started without
further ado so [Music] [Applause]
i'd like to invite you to
ah to land in your body
to arrive to arrive
letting go letting go of all the words
letting go of whatever has come before
ah just a moment of quiet silent refuge in this body with this breath
settling receiving one breath at a time
letting go letting go letting go [Music]
letting go of tightness tension [Music]
the legs letting their weight drop into the earth
into the cushion
letting go the weight the sit bones
your abdomen
dropping dropping into the chair into the cushion
from the inside
dropping dropping the weight
ah your whole trunk the chest
arms the hands offering their weight
to the earth
neck and shoulders the head
this whole body this whole body
offering its weight to the earth
earth sitting on earth
letting each breath be received
in the abdomen
softening relaxing letting go more deeply with each out
breath
spend a few minutes just settling taking refuge
this moment
if thoughts arise letting them go for now
not now not now
so much more nourishing to be with the breath and the body in this moment
than lost in thought
now i'd like to invite you to bring to mind
someone about whom
your care your good will flows with ease can be a child or a pet
a friend benefactor
so when you easily wish them well
you would like them to be happy healthy
have natural good will for them
it doesn't have to be big overpowering just
you like this person maybe when you think of them you feel safe
comfortable
now imagine like santa claus you have
you have a bag that's filled with goodness bright goodness
goodness blessings imagine you reach into the bag
and you spread you shower this person with goodness
and the more you do this the more you share
the more goodness becomes available in your bag
more you spread it the more there is to spread the more you give there is
the more there is to give
now if you wish imagining other people whom you know
and you have an easy relationship with
spreading [Music] blessing then with this the contents of
this bag
spreading goodness spreading well-being your wishes or will
be giving it away for free generously noticing the more there is
magically didn't realize you had so much goodwill to go to give away but here it is
it's kind of fun
to be spreading so much gold dust happiness dust fitness dust
imagining just for the purpose of this practice again without attachment to outcome
but as you spread this happiness dust ah it touches it touches
people and brings them well-being
sharing spreading well-being
and yes of course you can throw some on yourself
spread it into the air and let it drop on you and wow ah nice
being showered with goodness dust
like gold dust
spreading more spreading
imagining your neighbors
people you don't know
each and every one of them children spreading
blessing them with this goodness this blessing this meta dust
meta dust
meta sprinkles may you be safe may you be happy
may you be healthy may you have ease
sharing the cemented dust blessing people who are different from you
different gender identity [Music] different race age
ability size be creative
and know the more you give the more you spread the more there is in the bag and the more there is in your heart
the more gets automatically spread upon yourself the hand that spreads it
spreads this metadusk
has a lot of metadust on it
your own time using your imagination skillful means
spreading this metadust to whatever beings you wish human beings
people you know you care about people with you with whom you have some
entanglement if that comes easily
yourself now and then people in other continents countries
animals
all beings have fun with spreading meta
and if it works it can also say the phrases why you spread
the metaphases may you be safe may there be safety for you
may there be happiness joy for you
may there be health
strength for your body may there be ease for you may your life
flow with ease
sprinkling all over the earth have fun make it joyous
and spread yourself now and then there's plenty to go around
you can sprinkle metal over all categories different categories if you wish
sprinkling metal we're all creatures
who fly even more specifically sprinkling metta
over all the bees that pollinate
overall ducts
etc etc let yourself have fun
as we approach the last couple minutes of this practice period
sprinkling spreading [Music] meta sprinkles this ever growing bag
for all those who are practicing together with us
in the zoom room on youtube
and audio dharma all fellow practitioners in this moment
future and the past
sharing wishes of well-being goodness
giving it away freely
letting ourselves letting our own heart
be sprinkled quenched
the generosity of the mental wishes well-being
feeling gladness and well-being in having spread
having cultivated friendliness goodwill
mata
if there are any judgments coming up oh this wasn't good enough
the mind was distracted sleepy anxious whatever it's okay
spread spread some good will reach into the bag and spread some good will over
the judgments some friendliness
may all beings all beings everywhere
be well and be free
thank you so much everyone thank you for your practice
so spreading metta spreading goodwill
and realizing the more we spread it the more there is for us
so we'd love to hear your reflections
what did you discover what happened
what worked what was challenging questions love to hear your insights you can
either raise your hand your zoom hand or you can
um type in chat and if you type publicly i'll say your name out loud if
it's just to me it'll be um private so bill
[Music] hello hi um
i was thinking about what you said about um focusing doing meta at bedtime and i've tried that before
and it's for me it's it's not sleep inducing it tends to be more emotional i don't
think i'm clinging i don't at least i don't think i am um i just didn't know if that was anyway
that's that's what i'm sharing so there you go yeah yeah an interesting bill so so actually
in um the 11 benefits of meta in the suttas
one of the benef one of the 11 is that you fall asleep you sleep you sleep happily so it
is supposed to be actually one of the benefits and you have happy dreams so these two items which are reported
are actually part of the meta benefit so it would be interesting to actually
have bring some more curiosity bill to your practice to your meta practice to see why
is there clinging is there attachment to arkham because if you're saying well i don't think there is well maybe that's a pointer
there maybe that's what's maybe that's what's agitating the mind really wanting instead of just
really giving it away because it's just such and this just feels so light and as manohar says on on youtube
it felt much uh it felt much light feels so lighter and relaxing you know there's a
sense of lightness in this practice you're just giving goodness away wow you
feel lighter relaxed and the mind the heart falls asleep with happiness with
gladness so please bring some uh curiosity um to
to what's happening what's what's causing that yeah great because it's it's not exactly
supposed to be that way so something is kind of yeah
um yeah something is probably causing contraction jerry says very lifting and allowed me
to calm and focus meta towards others lovely thank you
and i see our ma now one more uh uh that was so much fun so worthwhile
thank you and good night says mark on youtube great i'm glad it was fun mark i had fun too so armando i see your hand
please i have a question like when there are hindrances
present could be like restless or worry or any of the other
hindrances um do you think it's a good idea to first
like sort of like you know take care of that hindrance or the hindrances and then do mata
or maybe mata can be a way of actually sort of helping with the hindrances because
i mean i sometimes if the hindrances are strong it may be difficult to do mata i think i
mean you know in some situations i believe i mean i feel that right so yeah exactly yeah that's a that's a
great question um so you can experiment with
with either and both depending on a given situation and see so with the you know if the
entrances is so strong that meta is feeling really challenging then turning
then turning the attention the awareness to the hindrance either with wisdom
practice and you know you know what the wisdom practices are with um or with or um or with meta
entirely turning well actually i guess i'm including meta here too entirely turning to the hindrance if
it's very strong if it's not very strong then you can continue the practice and just let the hindrance be be there
without having to push it away just kind of let it be there let it feel supported so i guess
four options the first the like decision tree the first decision is is it really strong or is it
kind of weak hindrance if it's very strong then you turn attention to it um and then if it's weak then you can
kind of continue the meta so that's the first decision and then let it and then not try to push it away
but let it feel included let it let it be included yeah i know you're here restlessness or
it's okay sweetie it's okay we're just gonna do this and you can come along you can come along so so if that's
possible if it's mild so now if it's really strong then decision tree now we're down to
okay so if it's really strong then you can turn towards it with with um wisdom practices
as as you know or if you turn towards it holy with meta
one thing i would warn against is to is not try to get rid of the hindrance with meta
that can become um conflictual and and if you're doing meta
in order to get rid of it it's not really meta so giving it space
with a sense of okay restlessness worry okay ah
letting there be a lot of space a lot of let your let your hindrance feel safe
is let your hindrance feel safe like it's okay it's okay if you're holding a a child
that's that's uh kind of crabby and crying it's like you don't try to like okay
shut up no be quiet i'm trying to do meta it's like oh sweetie okay what's going on it's all right it's okay it's okay you turn towards it with metta
so be be mindful of that thank you thank you yeah and
last quick comment from ben before we go into groups yes
hey uh yeah thanks um i was listening to a dharma talk the
other day on yeah generosity as you know uh a transformational tool for
the way the attitude we bring to the world specifically that it's a great remedy to
the feeling that there's you know not enough for me um and that sort of
that attitude can often be accompanied by a certain kind of uh um unhelpful degree of sense of self
and i'm all for that that makes a lot of sense to me and particularly this teacher was saying
you know that implies the following instruction if you feel like there's not enough for
you give and like that's that's if if that's
doable that sounds great but i don't know for me personally that's like exactly when i don't feel like i can
make that first reach into my pocket to get yeah so i strap myself up yeah so so i
hear where you're going and i think what i want to connect with with the practice we did tonight is that in this cultivation this
imagination this bag is never ending back so you don't have to imagine a situation
where oh there's a scarcity mindset so this is actually what can cultivate train your mind where there's so much
goodness there's just so much goodness there's plenty to go around so my invitation would be to use this
practice as a stepping stone because there's no way you can imagine that okay i've given goodness away and
there isn't uh there isn't anything anything left
does that make sense ben um it it it makes sense in
in concept but i think that to really get the energetic feeling that that stuff in the bag
is resource i think i would still just sort of have the problem with it i i think you're you're thinking too
hard so so so do this for this practice as invited just this imagining that it just
the more you give the more there is because that is the case with generosity and kindness with
goodwill so start it here and don't try to say well well if if you try to stop yourself before
you actually go there it's it's you're shooting yourself in the foot in the imagination space like
there's nothing that can stop you so so anyway i'm saying this from experience having
tried it so it's like it's not nothing yeah i i appreciate that and at this
point this is all i have to offer which is to hang in there with it um so okay
so thank you ben and so i like to invite us now to practice in
small groups because time is running out and we may not have enough time right now with small groups so there
might they'll be shorter today so i've just created the the uh the rooms
and the invitation is to start with 15 seconds of silent meta
and then to um yeah to um
yeah the sense of generosity the sense of generosity of heart um can can you feel it for yourself and
can you feel it for others so here we go with the rooms
i'm trying to create them quickly here we go all right
the rooms are open hello everyone and welcome back so the rooms are closed
and we have just about a minute for one final reflection or comment so if you haven't spoken
for a while please we'd love to hear from you what did you discover what did you notice
and how was it to do this practice of generosity in community terrance
i found it extremely supportive the little group interaction i had just and
delightful and um helpful in many ways
thank you thank you would it be possible to perhaps tease out one thing
to share well well we both we we didn't go with your back thing
all good whatever the bag of goodness so you know we were we were joined together
and poo pooing your bag idea [Laughter]
so what worked for you so what was important for you tell me oh just i had a kind of a natural
flowing of generosity toward myself i've been taking medications lately that
that for pain medication and part of me typically in the past would have said no this is not good you don't
want to take very much of that but i'm doing what the doctor said i'm taking a full load and you know kind of
unpleasantly dedicated and it's okay i'm being generous with myself nice so whatever brings up a sense of
generosity terence yay i celebrate that with you with mudita
so fantastic whether it's a bag doesn't have to be a bag it could be actually
just a sense of general whatever brings up a sense of generosity flowing um whatever imagery whatever skillful
means and for many people it could just be beaming of generosity sense of light or sense of
whatever it might be so what whatever made it work for you yay fantastic for you and others so
thank you all for your practice for doing this work not just for yourself for all beings
everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free
thank you