so warm greetings from redwood city
and looks like it's going to be a beautiful
blue day blue sky
and uh the vast blue sky
with no clouds in it is sometimes seen as a synonym metaphor
analogy for our mind
and to begin appreciating the sense of settleness wholeness
clarity that can come through meditation practice
arouses arouses evokes
a sense of delight or satisfaction or being pleased
in this opportunity to sit with oneself to sit and meditate
and and that is the 10th step of these 16 steps
is being pleased or steeply satisfied or delighted the word can mean rejoice
and there's something about stepping back a little bit and appreciating this opportunity to
meditate and then as the meditation as we become more
centered in the moment with ourselves becoming more whole more whole here then
there is um
hopefully some deep sense of beings of satisfaction in this process
so here we are and
we've been doing this some of us for a while now and so to take your usual meditation
posture or the one that is the right
for now and gently close your eyes
and even if you're agitated about something if you're sitting in your regular
meditation posture is there um
something comforting about doing so
something settling or something familiar that's
feels good to be in this posture
if you've been doing this little ritual of taking a few deep breaths at the
beginning is that also something becoming a little bit comforting or settling or familiar
that you can get settled into so taking a few long slow deep
breaths and as you exhale
to relax maybe a long slow deep long slow exhale
settling in here
the deep inhale is a chance to feel the fullness of the body the
width and breadth of the body or the wholeness of the body that's always more whole than the parts
always greater than the particular places of discomfort or distress that we might have to take a
deep breath in that spreads the awareness through the body so the awareness is
more encompasses more than any particular issues we have
and to exhale to let go of this intensity of some of
the thoughts and concerns soften and quiet the mind
soften and quiet the heart and the inner your inner life
settling in
and then taking breathing normally
and to some degree the process of meditation is a process of coming to a kind of wholeness
where all things are kind of held together without any
and divide within us everything has a place
and the relaxing of the body moves in that direction
on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the shoulder
on the exhale relaxing in the chest
and on the exhale relaxing the belly softening the belly
and perhaps on the exhale there's a way of releasing the whole body
releasing the way we might be bracing ourselves we're releasing the way we're
leaning ahead of ourselves
and then feeling the breathing
for a few moments familiarizing yourself
with your breathing the experience of it
and then whatever pleasure or joy
well-being that might be here even if it's in the cracks between
other things breathe with a pleasure breathe with a
well-being tingling in the body a warmth the glow
feeling of pleasure and the breathing maybe
or as you relax a kind of spread of
energy through the body that has a pleasant quality
breathe with a pleasant
and as you exhale relax the mental activity
quieting your thinking
relaxing any tension or contraction in the thinking mind
maybe relaxing the thinking mind on the exhale
and letting the mind become broader wider quieter
kind of like the waves on a vast lake the waves quiet down and the top of the
lake becomes still quiet the flatness the calm
stretching wide out towards the horizon so the mind gets quieter
and then be breathing with your mind state noticing the general mind
mood the atmosphere of your inner life
breathing with it allowing it to be the way it is
but being mindful of it as you breathe
maybe appreciating
that a mood or a state is broad wide
maybe has no boundaries
his soft transparent translucent
the mind state is not a solid thing it has no weight
maybe no color
maybe appreciating
the insubstantiality of mind state
breathing with it breathing through it
and rather than letting your mind drift off in thought
let your mind be concerned more with the breathing
breathing in the middle of this wider hole of body and feelings
and mind state
appreciating the breadth and the width of this whole
and then is there anything about sitting here now if you really settle in really connect
to the direct experience of meditating that has a feeling of satisfaction or
goodness to it something that's pleasing or something that makes you feel glad
or delighted being delighted in the being on the path
of practice having a practice being settled
not caught up in the busyness of the day
breathe with what is pleasing not so much the ideas of it
but maybe the ideas give rise to
an embodied feeling of satisfaction joy delight
in this experience of becoming moving towards wholeness or subtleness
or ease more peacefulness
and breathe with that satisfaction that delight and breathe with it in a way
that helps the mind become more quiet
a quiet breathing
with the inner delight and satisfaction
of being here now
instead of caught up in activities and concerns and thoughts
the goodness of just being here meditating
stepped hand of anapanasati is breathing in
delighting the mind breathing out delighting the mind
and how might you look out onto the world with eyes of the light
how might you look upon the world with eyes of kindness and
love how might you look out from your heart
sharing delight sharing joy as if it's food
for the for the hungry
as if it is missing resource in our lives
to no delight to no joy
and to look upon others having delight in them
appreciating others with respect and love and and may it be
that our delight and appreciation and respect for others
that we concern us ourselves with their happiness
their safety
their capacity to be at peace in this world their freedom and may our delight
our joy and others our appreciation of their beauty and their the wonder wonderfulness of
others be contagious and support others
so that all beings may be happy
all beings may be safe so that all beings
may be peaceful so that all beings may be free
and may our delight and in the existence of others support that
so so today we're going to touch into the
10th step of anapanasati breathing in one
delights the mind breathing out one delights the mind
and and this word mind cheetah appears in step 8 9 and 10.
in 8 it's calming the
activities of the mind then step nine it's
experiencing the mind and then in step now 10 it's
um delighting the mind and um and so this is the light
the word that's translated i'm translating now is the light can be translated as pleasing the mind
or satisfying the mind and it rather than it being an active verb that
what we're doing we might understand it as being recognizing or allowing for a certain
sense of deep satisfaction deep being pleased a deep kind of very glad gladness
in the mind and that comes from meditation practice
and there's a number of ways to understand this and there are different ways to experience this
one of the classic ones that the tradition talks about is um finally
the mind is no longer out of control or to say differently finally the mind
doesn't have a mind of its own and and where the mind were led around
jumping around agitated trashing about in the mind with our thoughts but we
feel like now we've really come home or we're settled we're back to in ourselves
the mind is under control or the mind is not um
just doing whatever it wants wandering around and picking up thoughts and chasing thoughts and
but we're really settled here and we've come home to ourselves the mind is settled and present
it's a word and the word that's often used in the ancient tradition is mind is now tamed i suspect a lot of us in the
modern west don't really like the idea of taming ourselves so that if a tame mind doesn't really
inspire but but the opposite of that you know having
a mind which is no longer untamed or out of control
maybe just feels better to appreciate that or value that and um one of the metaphors for an
out of control mind in the ancient world is um like a fish trashing about in a very
shallow puddle of water you know just flap flapping around and
so sometimes the mind just flaps and does its things and jumps around and chases one thought
after the other and and um and we have no control or no say
over the mind and but to get the mental activities to quiet down
to settle and a feeling that we're not really going to wander off into the past and the future anymore we're not really
going to get lost in thought anymore we are now really here and um and feel that sense of it's
deeply satisfying to start feeling really connected here and
and at peace here or settled here and and there's a kind of a satisfaction
of not having the agitation or the energetics of the mind jumping around moving out going here and there
and it allows the mind to be start becoming peaceful or being a deep rest or just here and it can feel like very
solid or very centered it can hear and the mind is in the present
moment and any tendency to leave that present moment by going off into thought
it just it just doesn't go very far it hardly goes anywhere at all it's like a rubber band attached to their thoughts
and they just get pulled right back to the present or we just like no you know why bother
it's really good to be here and this movement of the experiencing the
mind this way is a movement towards wholeness to becoming more whole that's only
possible if we're in the present moment by almost by i don't know if definition is
the right word but by definition if we're lost in the future caught up in future concerns or past
concerns we are partial we're involved and focused on the future and we're not
really connected to what's here or if we're involved in fantasy it's no
matter how wonderful and nice the fantasy might feel a fantasy is only a small part of who we
are and there's a disconnect even dissociation in extreme forms with our body our mind states and it's
really what's happening right here and so as we start settling and able to be here in the present moment in a
rooted way grounded way it allows begins allowing for this
of a process of feeling whole becoming um and a whole
is is a process also of a lot of the sharp boundaries we have
time and space begins to fall away or sharp boundaries between um
the body and the mind or sharp boundaries between the edges of our body and the space
around us a lot of um the um
a sense of wholeness starts moving into what some people would call
altered states of consciousness altered states of mind but that suggests that somehow it's
non-nor like not normal or and well maybe it's not so normal because
we don't go into those states very much but um
in in meditation we start feeling this settled in the present moment and start opening up to a whole
feeling of wholeness of being here it starts feeling like this is natural
this is a homecoming this is what should be ordinary ordinary states of consciousness
ordinary states of mind are fragmented narrow limited
bounded and frazzled and even though they might be
familiar with us in that sense comfortable for us to really experience starts feeling a
settled wholeness it starts feeling oh this is health this is healthy
healthy mind this is um you know it's the altered states of mind
are daily mind states those are the ones are altered and and strange and preoccupied and things
like that but you know a subtle feeling of wholeness that feels good some people uh
when they um meditate are struggling with a distractible mind you know being
caught by the hindrances and caught in desires and aversions of
all kinds and they're coming back and coming back and working with that to finally have those quiet down
and the mind is able to finally be present it's like the mind has found itself
it provides a deep satisfaction a delight a joy a pleasure
and this is what we're talking about in this tenth step of delighting the mind or pleasing the
mind or gladdening the mind allowing the mind to feel a deep satisfaction
and i offer all these different words because different people will find different words speak to what their
own flavor of all this might be in their meditation and
and but the important thing here is that we're allowed to feel the goodness of that we're allowed to
feel the delight and the joy and the satisfaction certainly not to cling to and hold on to
and congratulate ourselves for in some egotistical way but we're not supposed to ignore the joy
the happiness the well-being the pleasure the satisfaction of meditation in fact feeling that is there's a way of
feeling a way of experiencing it that allows us to continue this process of settling in
quieting the mind expanding the sense of wholeness that we're moving into and in doing so
we open up to states of mind qualities of mind that are coterminous that are
intimately part of this feeling of a wholeness or a broad
awareness or centeredness clear knowing clarity of mind
that are that are considered a form of wealth in fact for the buddha the greatest
wealth a person can have and acquire is the wealth that
comes from a settled clear and open mind the sense of wholeness so the seven
factors awakening that i mentioned yesterday mindfulness investigation effort
joy tranquility samadhi and equanimity these all kind of belong
to the realm of this settled wholeness that comes with it as the awareness the attention gets full
and complete and um and uh and so it isn't just like we're losing something
by settling down and really letting go of the distracted mind and really being present we gain so much and um and it's called
an inner wealth if you want to be wealthy develop your inner life and it's uh it's a wealth that i mean it
qualifies as a wealth because um it provides some of the greatest pleasure and
safety and happiness and that that's available to us and
certainly greater happiness than any material wealth can ever produce
so so
breathing in delighting the mind breathing out delighting the mind you
can't do that too early you can't just sit down and decide to do that it comes when
when meditation is really settle down and settle down settle down so remember it's now we're talking about
the 10th stage of the 16 stages but when it happens to you that you get
that you start feeling inklings of kind of this kind of delight satisfaction pleasure
being pleased by what's happening deep satisfaction open to it allow for it let it spread
wide and broad throughout your being be nourished by it
and and let it be something you appreciate and enjoy and that sets the stage for the next
step amanapanasati which we really won't do for a couple of weeks which is samadhi which is the
unification of the mind this concentration of the mind and until then we're going
to spend next week with the seven factors of awakening
and maybe this will support experiencing the mind and experiencing the delight in
the mind to really kind of spend some time with these seven factors of awakening
and they'll also serve for the 11th step the samadhi