so good morning and welcome
and um so this week
when i'm entitled to kind of mindfulness of mind is not the same as uh what we did some
weeks ago with we did the third foundation of mindfulness where that was also mindfulness of mind
it's a mindfulness mind is kind of like a little sometimes used these days as a
almost synonymous with mindfulness of awareness it has other meanings as well
but uh the ability to notice awareness
not just the objects of awareness is uh one of the great delights that can
come along with this practice and uh it's also uh very helpful for
kind of feeling your way to freedom freedom from clinging to the objects of awareness
and so there's a kind of a paradigm shift that goes on in meditation
and it's a little bit like this that um
or very much like this is starting to become aware of the
silence of awareness or the spaciousness
the vast space of awareness or the stillness of awareness and these are kind of metaphors so it's
not exactly we are kind of experiencing it but we don't want to make it into something too
solid or fixed ideas but for example
when you taste a strawberry
and it's the taste the tasting on the tongue
is very distinct from the idea of strawberry the ideas of liking the
strawberry the taste is the tasting
has no words as part of the tasting the words come as
a response to the taste and so sometimes when we really want to taste something well
we let we even close our eyes we reduce our senses and we even let the thinking mind become
quiet so we can really sense what's happening
the tasting is silent but the mind might not might not be there might
be immediately a cascade of thoughts about wanting more strawberries
when we see the seeing itself is silent
the words and stories ideas and the mind are secondary they come after the seeing
but the seeing itself happens in silence
uh the um if you uh
or spend a cold day and
then maybe working hard outdoors and you come home and take a warm bath and really want to feel the
wonderfulness of the warm bath and really let it soak in and relax
the sensations of the body the relaxation the warmth this comfort
the sensing there in the body is silent of chatter of thoughts of ideas
and there again if you want to really feel this the pleasure the comfort the relaxation of
the path you might even kind of put aside all your thoughts and concerns for a few
moments and just really luxuriate in the silence of it and the silent mind
so there is this paradigm shift where we are capable of meditation to also sense
and feel things in silence it's also possible to be aware
by thinking about it by having cognition and thoughts and
labels recognitions oh this is warmth this is a strawberry and this is also this in a simple way
this is also part of mindfulness but
mindfulness of awareness is closer to
being aware of the silence in which we're aware the space in which we're aware the
stillness in which we're aware and it's a radical shift
from being concerned with the content of our thoughts
with the things we're thinking about or things we are aware of so even if you're aware of your body
there's a shift to not only being aware of the sensations but being aware of the
awareness that is aware an awareness which is
coterminous with stillness with silence with spaciousness
so i hope this makes some sense and if not don't worry about it
except that it might be good to file this away because someday it might be relevant
so to assume a meditation posture and to
relax your gaze lower your gaze
and to gently close your eyes
and to appreciate the sensations of your body
whatever they might be and how the body experience them
experiences them silently the body is not a thought
the body feels and senses
and to gently take a few long slow deep breaths
and relax let go as you exhale
into and then let your breathing return to normal
and become aware of the silent way in which the body senses breathing
in and of itself there's no thoughts in the lungs in the diaphragm and the
belly but there are sensations
that maybe become a little bit more vivid when the thinking mind becomes quiet
or more with vivid as we feel the silence
around those sensations
and then as you exhale to relax some more
throughout your body wherever it feels good to relax relax and soften
relaxing your thinking mind
softening the pressure the tension associated with thinking
gently as you exhale allowing the agitation of thinking
to settle down
and is there a silent way of noticing thinking
a silent knowing or sensing
the mind involved in its thoughts
and then again feeling your breathing
and perhaps a silent awareness of breathing
silent that's free of wanting and not wanting anything
silent silent from ideas of time before and after
the silence that allows us to just sense
feel the breathing of the moment
and if you feel any silence quiet
quietness that silence is inseparable
from a certain kind of awareness a silent awareness
the silent knowing
that's receptive
it has space for breathing to arise within
and the practice is the meeting of the breathing
in the silent awareness and as my thinking mind gets quieter and
more focused each of these becomes more vivid
the breathing becomes more vivid in the body and the awareness that silently is aware
of breathing becomes more vivid to the meeting of these two
breathing and awareness stay there
let the rhythm of breathing keep you connected
to awareness
like the waves on the ocean wash up across the sandy shore
back and forth
foreign
sometimes our attention is directed
sometimes attention is receptive
when there's a lot of thinking a lot of desires and
efforts to do attention tends to be directed
but sometimes it's nice to meet our friends our family our neighbors
strangers with the receptive awareness
one that's not carrying a lot of judgments ideas bias
history
maybe even awareness that's a little bit silent
of thoughts just present
open available to feel to sense
to be aware and kind of silent awareness of another person of others
sometimes that's a way of experiencing others
more fully without
the limitations of our preconceived ideas
it's respectful of others to be receptive of how they are in their
own terms rather than coming with our preconceived ideas
and may it be that this practice that we do fosters this kind of respect
the respect that we allow people to be themselves
at least until we've taken them in the fullness of who they are
in a receptive awareness maybe even a kind of silent awareness
silent of agendas
and maybe it's in this fuller awareness of others
that our care is born our love
our generosity our kindness
and maybe our kindness is transmitted more fully
in a mind that's not filled with preconceived ideas
a mind that is quieter and receptive
may it be that through this meditation practice
that we have a more vivid awareness of others
and in doing so may we contribute to their welfare and
happiness may we contribute to the welfare and
happiness of the whole world
may it be that this meditation practice we do supports
the happiness safety peace and freedom of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
thank you for letting me know so we have lots of silence
and uh the um
all these buttons to push let's see still there's messages of no sound maybe
see if you start hearing me
so still no sound maybe there's just a lot of people who typed in it takes a while for it to upload
so you should be hearing me now there we go thank you
so sometimes just being quietly
in the present moment i'm not tracking everything so all these
buttons to push so sorry about that
so to this morning the perspective for the topic is that of respect
and as probably you've heard me say many times that i really like the word respect
actually inspired by it partly because of its etymological meaning that it means to
look again to inspect again in the latin roots and this idea of having a willingness to
not just barrel ahead into the future and keep doing and doing but to
um but to also um uh
you know take a deeper look maybe our life our experience
is warrants a second look a better look sustained attention what is really
happening here so we don't take the first impression of things but we really kind of take time
to experience and feel it more deeply and then as we do this one of the
benefits of it is we begin appreciating um the looking itself
the the ability to give a second look that there's something
about looking again looking seeing in a relaxed and open receptive way
that's a little bit free or very free of our preconceived ideas our agendas our
preferences our bias all kinds of things that so easily comes along if we just go rapidly from one
thing to another but this thing of consciously deciding let me look more carefully here let me
take be more open let me take in this experience more fully
that's a kind of sidestepping or kind of putting aside slightly
the automatic preconceived ideas that kind of get carried along
ideas and thoughts and agendas that are directing attention often i want this i want that i want this
and that some of us can experience kind of acutely if we're surfing on the web on the computer just kind of going from
one thing to the other seeing this and that and looking and there's its mind is being directed all
the time but to step back and and be willing to look again look more
carefully at some point the looking becomes the fact that we're looking the
act of looking becomes kind of special you know i've been in places where
wonderful vistas great vistas you know maybe high up in the mountains with the great fist views of the
landscape or below or on on the beach looking out across the ocean
and for me at least there's something about the panoramic view of lots of space and
openness and then kind of relaxed looking that i just enjoy looking
and after a while certainly i'm appreciating what i see but i also appreciate the relaxed open
kind of receptive just looking and gazing and it's almost like they're
they're both they're both separate and not so separate the looking and what's being seen
but how they're separate is that looking now uh stands out and highlights oh
there's seeing happening and that seeing is so relaxed and spacious and open and i could just stay
here looking at these clouds drifting the sky for a long time or looking at the river
flowing by i can just look and look and just feel so relaxed and settling to do this looking
and as opposed to writing every cloud and saying well that cloud
is a little bit too big it has too much of a bump here or that one is a nice shape and i like to keep it that way
and work you know let me find a better cloud to look at because this one's getting kind of boring um you know to constantly be involved in
this directedness it's a very different exp tends to we lose sight of the fact that we're looking
we look more at our preferences the cloud should be that way not this way and
and so this respect looking again and again is partly what we're doing in
mindfulness practice we're learning not to ride the waves of our
preferences our agendas what we always want but step back take a look at we do that
but when we step back take another look take another look at some point
the looking the mindfulness begins to stand out and highlight oh it's so good to be mindful in being mindful there's
freedom there's spaciousness there's a relaxation there's an ease and that
this is good and we start becoming aware of awareness itself
now this topic of awareness is a big topic and um
and uh i think that uh i kind of like you to use the word
as a vague word because different people have different reference point for what awareness means
and so some people when you talk about awareness
for them the way they know things is much more through their thinking and so it they're thinking about things
that's how they're aware some people it's more a sensing they're aware to come through their body
and their sensing some people it's more of a silent knowing
where they don't not really aware of any active cognitive movement of the mind to
know but there's a silence just they know kind of intuitively or something so there's many ways to know
and um and uh in the mindfulness tradition
one of the there's a variety of different kinds of knowing that operate at different times but what
can happen with each one of them regardless of what your way of knowing is you're what you think awareness is
for yourself at some point it gets it gets highlighted it stands out a
little bit and highlight oh here is something this is the uh this is not the object or
what i'm thinking about this is the receptivity or the the experience of knowing it
and and then we can become aware of the attitudes like we talked about yesterday
that go along with it desires the contractions the that kind of
a part of being aware but then we take a second look
in a second look until we begin seeing experiencing awareness knowing sensing
feeling observing whatever it might be kind of uh at ease open
a certain kind of silence a certain kind of spaciousness
even when there's thinking there can be a silence that knows it
one of my first entry points to uh the world of kind of spiritual life
was spending a week in solitude and uh it was a beautiful place and a
farm and nature and um and in the course it wasn't meditating
but in the course of the week because i had no social contact no talking with anyone it was kind of like
being on a meditation retreat without being on one and um
and i became acutely aware of myself thinking and i had no thought that i had
judgments about the fact that i was thinking but i had it was that the clarity
by which i knew i was thinking that clarity oh there's a thought it was like really
it's just like wow it's kind of there's a beauty there's a clarity there's a cleanliness there's a openness
there's a distinctness that i'd never seen before it was kind of like uh the old days the
radio would be out of tune and then suddenly it came into uh a tune you're tuning in the radio
station and you got it into tune and then suddenly it would become clear so it's kind of like that oh suddenly
the wavelength i found the wavelength my mind and i was clearly aware i knew
and that clarity of knowing that clarity that
is kind of what for some people the clarity is they call awareness
and it's not different than awareness but it's not exactly awareness but it's coterminous with awareness
and the clarity is so beautiful so wonderful
and the clear so i became aware of this clarity that let me see my my my cognitive thoughts my words my
mind was such clarity and i appreciated the freedom the ease that was there
so to respect to be mindful mindful of awareness mindful of
the process of being aware is one of the ways supports of coming to
a place of clarity in the meditation just now i talked about silence
and that's another word i think so it's you know even though i was thinking when i was alone that week
um and that thinking became kind of acutely acutely clear each thought
i was aware of it in kind of a larger silence sometimes
what's this mindfulness awareness associated for some people is stillness
the awareness that's uh vividly softly wonderfully velvety
still or sometimes it's spaciousness just lots of space for it
and um and it isn't so much like that's so
the ultimate thing space or stillness or silence or clarity
but it's how it helps us to relax more deeply it's how it teaches us about non-clinging
how it helps us to see where the remaining clinging is and and you get a feeling for freedom
there's freedom in the clarity of awareness there's freedom in the stillness the silence of awareness
and so oh you get to feel like a little hint the smell the doors open for that's where freedom
is found so um finally i'll give you another analogy
that from my childhood that maybe for some of you if you're old
enough and did this kind of thing
when i was a little kid sometimes my parents would take their car to a car wash
and it was such that you could go in through the in the stay in the cars it
went through the car wash you know and pulled along and and all these uh
water and suds and brushes are spraying and it was kind of chaotic
outside the car and coming against the windows but inside the car
it felt so safe and quiet and peaceful and the contrast
was so that was one of the reasons i loved going through these car washes because i felt it so acutely
the highlighted the peace the quiet the stillness the safety there being inside the car
with the chaos outside and so that's a reference point for me of how it can be in the mind sometimes
where i'm resting in awareness and there's a peace there's a quiet there's an openness
and independent of the chaos that might be happening around me
carry our peace with us so um
it's a little bit esoteric a little bit you know what i'm talking about today and
and i'm trusting that for those of you who don't quite understand what i'm saying which i wouldn't of when i was
first introduced to meditation that um just relax with it and but keep it in
mind keep it filed away and at some point you might have an experience oh that's what gill is
talking about and that might help you appreciate it and and get the benefits of that kind of
experience so thank you very much and
i look forward to continuing this tomorrow