okay hello and welcome everyone to this
edition of happy hour as we come together to practice
so for inspiration for tonight's practice uh i'd like to read
a um a translation uh from the udana of the verses in udana
um translated uh by taniser bhikkhu and udana is
from the original poly canon so so here is um here is the
um the quote and so the buddha says
searching in all directions with your awareness you find no one dearer
than yourself in the same way others are thickly dear to themselves
so you shouldn't hurt others if you love yourself
quite profound so two different parts to this let me read it
one more time searching in all directions with your
awareness you find no one dearer than yourself
in the same way others are thickly dear to themselves so you shouldn't hurt others if you love
yourself ah interesting there's a lot to unpack
there as a practice right so looking in all directions you find no one dearer than yourself
so that's kind of taken for granted that first part that oh yes that no one is dearer than you
to yourself than you are okay that's that's part number one and then yes of course
it's the same for others so if you love yourself you wouldn't
hurt others so some invitations that
yes it is okay the buddha is actually um saying that as you look around
uh searching in all directions with your awareness you find no one dearer than yourself yeah
interesting and the second part that there is something about
self-love if we dearly love ourselves so the base the baseline the the conditions
um for us really dearly loving ourselves accepting ourselves um holding this
being who is me showing up in this way with all the gifts and challenges and
uh idiosyncrasities and i can even say that word which is kind
of interesting but anyway so so with all the idiosyncratic ways i show up in the world okay that's better
um and all the funny ways and all the gifts and all the beauties that i show up
if i really truly love myself and hold myself dear
that is the base that is the platform for considering that yes other people
hold themselves dear their lives are dear to them not just human beings but animals
so that can become a precondition a basis of treating others just as we want
to be treated just as we hold ourselves dear so a lot to unpack here
so without jumping into a dharma talk
let's just practice together and draw on this as inspiration for us
practicing self like to invite you to get into your meditation posture
ah whatever is comfortable for you
landing in this body
sitting [Music] standing or lying down
first as always we start by just settling
[Music] settling with awareness into this breath this
body calming arriving
letting the breath breathe you
settling arriving
more fully more completely more wholeheartedly with each
out breath landing
and if thoughts memories plans are arising
noticing noticing with awareness what's happening
and calming soothing ourselves with the next out breath
ah landing in this moment right here lovingly
for this being who is us
out of care out of concern
putting down putting aside what doesn't need to be thought
or figured out right now
here here just here
right here this breath
this moment
nowhere to go nothing to do
just to give our hearts to itself in this moment
to recognize the goodness the beauty
in suchness of just being aware
turning the gaze inward
searching in all directions with your awareness
you find no one dearer than yourself
no one dearer than yourself
what if we imagine that with our awareness we're searching in all directions
and we find this being we find this person ourselves
whom we perhaps forsaken for others
what if we truly recognize honor love not from
a selfish egoistic place
but from the perspective with truth is saying
unconditionally loving
this being who is us
perhaps
imagining our favorite love song
when we have sung for others in our minds and our hearts or wish that somebody else some other
person would see us would really see us and love us
and sing that favorite love song for us
what if we sing it to ourselves
loving ourselves our beloved other
giving our heart
lowly fully wholeheartedly to itself
an infinite echoing and mirroring
of love
see how this practice might work for you
maybe receiving it easier is easier for you can imagine yourself receiving
this love poem love song from yourself
or maybe it's easier to give it from the embodied seat giving it to this
being stepping outside of yourself see whether giving or receiving embodied
works better for you or maybe both
if unsure maybe try imagining yourself receiving this poem or love song
serenade it to you
by yourself
for some maybe a younger version of yourself
might help be supported
to see love protect care
for a younger self
searching in all directions with your awareness you find no one dearer than yourself
the same way others are thickly dear to themselves
so you shouldn't hurt others if you love yourself
so as we've been considering
how dear we are to ourselves loving caring maybe with the image of a younger
version of ourselves caring for this younger version
maybe they are sitting on our lap we hold them hug them
ask them if they need rest
food sleep love protection safety
offering that wholeheartedly to ourselves
realizing all beings may be starting with all the beings
we're practicing with right now on zoom and youtube all these beings
with the younger version of themselves sitting on their lap metaphorically they hold themselves dear
their lives are dear to them they don't want to suffer
so just as we care for ourselves hold ourselves dear and precious the
part of ourselves all of ourselves recognizing that
is true for everyone else just like me just like me
and i am just like them no different
it's natural to hold ourselves there
and the support for non-harming
others
how can we hurt others if we hold ourselves dear we truly love ourselves
we know how much it hurts to be hurt
how can we inflict that upon others wish them ill
just as we wish ourselves well just as we want to be safe happy
healthy and have ease
may all beings all beings be safe
happy healthy and happy
may all beings be well
may all beings be free
thank you for your practice everyone
so i'll change the settings for the chat so if you like to share your reflections
in chat if you type them just to me i won't say your name out loud if it's to everyone
i'll read the name you can also raise your zoom hand to share your questions reflections
what came up for you we have folks joining on youtube also hi
you're welcome to share your reflections as well so yeah how was this for you what did
you notice in your practice in your practice this
teaching from the udana
it's all welcome especially if you haven't spoken for a while we'd love to hear from you
while i wait for you to raise your hand and type i'll share something that came
up for me which was kind of sweet so as an example
um some point an image of a younger version of me came up sitting on my lap
and i shared that with you as an invitation and and also a song came up
there is a song by peter gabriel called the book of love
and there's a line in there says i love it when you read to me
and you can read me anything so that came up for me as a younger version of
myself saying oh i love it when you read to me so i guess i like reading books to
myself so and you just wanted to share that because that sense of the visualization the sense of tenderness giving
whether through words through song through just all of these are skillful means for us to really connect with
ourselves so what happened for you whether it was challenging or easy and what you noticed
janie i see your name your hand physical hand for a change here please
thank you thank you thank you yeah i had a hard time at first getting my mind quiet and um but when you said the
child i recently had run across a picture of myself you know 70 years ago and um
and i saw that child in my mind's eye and i could um have her on my knee and you know just
be there with her and tell her i loved her and you know all because some good things and so that
changed it for me lovely thank you genie it's lovely to
hear what what was supportive and what worked is this image of our younger self great thanks for
bringing that in did that work for anyone else you're welcome to share or if that didn't work or something else did
tell us share your practice it's helpful for the whole sangha
challenges and what works
one reflection coming privately for me it was hard because the only
person i feel like i've loved unconditionally was my daughter when she was a baby
a young child great actually that is fantastic so um
the the invitation there is to um imagine in in your meditation
to bring an image of your daughter when she was a baby as a young child and
have the sense of meta she's on your lap and then and then skillful means
bait and switch then you're the baby on your lap and the feeling of meta is going to continue unconditionally for this
being that is myself and then you will run dry after a while then you'll bring your daughter young daughter back and
says oh it's unconditional when she was a baby and just fragile and sweet and then again hold
some bait and switch and then you're the one and you'll notice actually the the unconditional meta will flow for a while
so may i invite you to explore that yeah great thanks so much for bringing
that in appreciate it helpful for everyone anything else
any other observations and maybe it was just challenging period and that's okay
too anything about the very end when we
turned to actually notice all beings that they're just like us
just as we hold ourselves dear now says for me it was a reflection on
how everyone is at the center of their own story
yeah we are we are the center we yeah
yeah yeah and it's interesting because there are two different ways we can see that and then what you're saying is
absolutely true it's all about me self and yet we are dear to ourselves there's a sense of
dearness so so um i think i think both recognitions are important
uh and and in that way we also realize how much we are in the center of our own story we're the star of our story we're
the victim of the story or the protagonist we're
it's all about me maybe and and yet you know it's kind of interesting
because as i say this it almost seems like the teachings on not-self it almost seems like they're orthogonal
here but they aren't actually because the selfishness um sometimes actually comes from a sense
of scarcity as if there is not enough there there's not enough love there's not enough
goodness there isn't enough needs i need to prove myself i need to be bp so
so when actually there is a sense of contentment um and fulfillment like yes
it's yes it's okay that the sense of self actually drops
which is why the um the full expression of love the full expression of love
is is not self and emptiness and the full expression of emptiness is
love and compassion it might seem counterintuitive but actually
there's no um um they're not orthogonal so so much to say
about this and i'm thinking it might be good actually now to turn our attention to practice in
small groups and see what might come up and as you discuss with each other what
was challenging what was easy and um yeah practice discussions can be
quite quite juicy and productive in this way so like to invite us to um
offer ourselves offer our heart recognizing that we're all dear to we're
so dear to ourselves everybody's dear to themselves so when you are in a practice meeting with two
other people recognize that you're dear to yourself and they are dear to themselves so so i'll create the groups let's start
with 15 seconds of meta for yourself and others and see what comes up
the rooms are open enjoy
okay the rooms are closed everyone is back welcome back everyone so we have a few minutes for any
reflections that came up while you were in groups take it away why did you notice
i think diane wants to talk or diana diana you're welcome to unmute
yourself diana um this um meditation was really lovely
this particular subject as always but it brought up something for me where i finally have a
chance to ask a question because every time the idea of holding the child
or being around myself as a child comes up it just brings sadness because i i don't i didn't have a happy
childhood and so i find myself then focus on something
where it's not where i want to be and is if the idea is to to
bring warmth and a lovely and a loving feeling then then do we
bring in something else that makes us happy uh like our cat or something or another
person if that is it similar to other because bringing up the child is is not
um the law it would be a long distraction for me i i hear that i hear
that and thank you so much for bringing that that in so so a couple of different things one is
um the idea of bringing
you know which a a a someone you care about a cat a dog that's that's great
you know for for meta um it might still be helpful unless the
childhood has was so traumatic and there isn't really any any space um
to to be with that but even if there's a little bit of space in the long term of practice in the long
run it can actually be helpful to re-parent in a way of reparenting yourself in
to repairing to yourself little by little by little um like sweetie i'm here for you yes i
know it was sad i know it was hard and now i'm the adult and and
i i protect you i love you nobody's gonna hurt you now so there's a way of reparenting
ourselves in our hearts which can be so wholesome really healing
in this process um so i invite you yeah yeah i hear so just try a little
bit even though it might be sad but i'm understanding what you're saying yeah but i think the
love can be bigger than the sadness that's what i'm bringing in because the love from the adult view
can be bigger than the you know there is some there's some nuance there's some
maneuvering so don't shy away from it just because it's meet the sadness with love it becomes a
practice of compassion and it can be very powerful
okay thank you you're welcome thank you so much for bringing that in what a great
great question yeah so dear ones as you all hold yourselves
dear we all hold ourselves dear thank you for your practice thank you
for your practice thank you for coming to happy hour cultivating your heart for your own sake
and sake of all beings whose lives we touch may all beings be happy
may all beings be well
thank you now i