so a warm-hearted welcome to all of you wherever you are in this
moment in this world of ours this being human
whatever the weather whatever the weather externally whatever the weather internally whatever is happening
here we are together practicing so as we've been practicing
i'm going through the categories of of karuna compassion together
we're lingering a little longer with self-compassion karuna for because you
can never have enough karuna for self compassion for self filling our own cup so tonight
we'll we'll continue with that and there's so many different ways to do this practice there is no right or wrong
these are all skillful means you can try different methods see what works
and um and one thing i wanted to bring up
today in our exploration for the practice is to explore the relationship
between self-compassion and resilience
well you might wonder hmm okay what's the relationship between self
compassion and resilience some aspects might be obvious some may
not be i'll offer a couple of thoughts and then we'll just explore and experiment on our
own so one thought one reflection about
resilience is the sense of when something challenging happens in life it doesn't
so much mean that you don't get knocked over yes you do get knocked over but how quickly you stand up
how quickly you get up how quickly you write yourself
and there are studies supporting that this
practice mindfulness meditation and this practice in general it increases resilience in this way in
this way of getting knocked over getting up more quickly whereas something would happen perhaps
you would berate yourself or be upset or depressed for days or
weeks [Music] you bounce back more quickly and you may
have already observed this about yourself if you've been practicing for a while
there are areas of your life that don't get you down as much or as long
as they used to now one thing to consider about practice of
self-compassion and the relationship with resilience is when you're more compassionate to
yourself there is a sense of soothing there is a
soothing self that supports you to stand up to get up more quickly it's a sense of support sense of
empowerment imagining compassion to be weak actually it's it's a powerful expression
of our own strength and love for ourselves to hold ourselves with care
to hold our difficulties with with care and love so there is a sense
of resilience um instead of being down especially if we
keep being down with self-recognition with self-judgment it will keep us down
it will keep us miserable and depressed but with a sense of self-compassion can
actually take responsibility okay okay i did my best
given all the cause and conditions didn't turn out as as well as i aspire to but it's okay
sweetie i forgive you i love you i care for you ah and let's
aspire to to uh to our values to show up in in the way
that we really want to instead of oh you're terrible you're a loser you're awful so
it can really support us in resilience in that way not to give us a free past
that's not the idea but to support us in resilience so without further ado
let's practice together so i'd like to invite you
to get into your meditation posture
landing in this body with this breath spending a few minutes just settling and
arriving and taking refuge
the simplicity of this moment in this breath
okay
invite you to feel your body
your entire body
as the breath is breathed into it both physically and energetically
sense of the body billowing with air
and as if your body extended a few inches beyond
your skin
relaxing into this energetic sense of your body
ah letting go into it
and feeling the body energetically breathe
expanding and contracting
feeling your whole body physically and
energetically be breathed energized
relaxed
and feeling your chest your heart center fill
[Music] through the breath both physically and
energetically feeling bright more filled more awake
more full
appreciating appreciating this body
it's body breathing
and all the functions of this body
how it does its best to support you in breathing
and digesting in healing you get cuts and wounds as best as it
can and moving
seeing hearing understanding
[Music] perceiving processing information
this amazing miraculous body
should take for granted both yours and not yours
deeply appreciating this body breathing
deep appreciation
it does so much it has done so much for us for you throughout your life
and often taken for granted or even berated for not being the right shape or size or
not functioning or or hurting
oh dear body oh dear dear body
as if you were bowing
in your heart with appreciation and love and care
as if this body is miraculous
this miracle of nature your body as if it were a beloved
as if it were a beloved other thank you to your body
can there be
appreciation care love
this dear beloved other this good friend it's been taken for granted
now you decide oh darling
let me connect with you let me see you appreciate you love you
relating connecting perceiving
this body
with appreciation care
love
and as if you were sitting and caring for a dear beloved friend having tea with them
telling your dear friend
sweetheart tell me how are you what's been challenging for you
are you hurting have you been hurting
and being open to holding to receiving
the challenges the pains the aches the difficulties the suffering of the
body with love with compassion with care
this beloved other
and this body beloved body may speak to you about
either physical pains or heartache emotional challenges
that are also felt in the body experienced in the body
making space for those two oh darling this is hard this is hard
and it's okay i love you i care for you i hold you
dear i don't and i won't berate you
in this moment it's safe it's okay to just be
not feel you have to be in any particular shape or form or way
you're accepted and loved just as you are with all the challenges that you're
holding
physically energetically emotionally
the empowerment of love and compassion for yourself
powerful loving stance
connecting with yourself physically emotionally energetically with your
heart however way it's appropriate for you in this moment
connect with this beloved other in your own way in time
are there ways that you underestimate yourself
diminish yourself
see yourself with not enough
depth perspective dimensionality
grace and beauty such that
this being that is you actually is a beloved other you don't completely
know or understand
they are far more unfathomable
there be love and compassion for this
beloved other and their beauty
and challenges
and for the last few minutes of this practice
see what's needed
never feels appropriate opening the circle of care and compassion
to all those who are practicing with you with their physical
energetic emotional challenges and all beings everywhere in your own time
all beings everywhere all beings in this zoom room and on
youtube practicing with you as these beloved others
you only get a sense of them perhaps a limited sense in the small groups
but they are far more complex
not reducible to either our or their conceptions of
themselves wishing all beings everywhere
goodness may all beings be free
and happy and then peace
[Music]
thank you for your practice everyone
so the idea of ourselves our bodies our hearts this being who's us
as a beloved other the way we would treat a beloved friend the beloved being
treating ourselves in the same way same way that we give them the benefit
of the doubt and allow them
to have their their complexity not let them be reduced
to a limited understanding doing the same for ourselves and holding
ourselves with compassion care so we'd love to
invite you if you like to share something about your practice something
that came up an observation maybe something that was challenging
also if you'd like to share the wisdom of of that how you worked with that or
how you were stuck with that it's all okay you can either raise your hand if you haven't shared
in a while uh or ever or you can type it in chat
ben says the benefit of the faith i'm not quite sure what you mean by that
ben you're welcome to raise your hand to extend
benefit of the doubt oh benefit of the doubt okay
play on words i see yeah i like that benefit of the doubt
benefit of the faith bill asks what did you mean when you use the word
energetically that's a great question
so it's something to open up to and explore
um that often as as we sit and we practice for a
while or also for some people when they're new
to practice there's a sense of physical the physicality of the body
the physical sense of the body there's also kind of an energetic sense of the body
that the body is breathing there is um as i was describing the
meditation as if the edge of your body is is a few inches beyond your skin there's
a sense of ah you've you know have you here's a simple way to to relate to it have you ever felt like
you're buoyant you can walk on air you feel so good energetically wow you feel expansive and
light and sometimes you feel heavy and just ah contracted so
it doesn't just feel physical at those times there's an energetic sense of buoyancy
so that's what i'm inviting you to you to become more sensitive to
and tune into there is so much to discover about ourselves does that make
sense bill
and yeah
and susan please see your hand raised
yeah um i noticed that sometimes i feel some confusion with
accepting like um so i have some challenging health issues
so accepting my body and loving my body
but yet wanting to heal and get better and not get
caught in identifying with the illness does that make sense so sometimes i have a problem of like when i go into wanting
to love my body yeah and telling myself it belongs all of it belongs the pain whatever i'm
feeling belongs that i'm then allowed i'm allowing that all to be there
and i'm identifying with it and then i won't get better i won't heal i have some
does that make sense that can i'm saying that confusion yeah yeah it does i hear that this conflict
sort so let me reflect reflect back there's a sense of when when you get into meditation trying to
love the body and and all the ways it is suffering and accepting the pain feeling it belongs
then feeling like oh if you accept that then you're not going to get better because you're allowing it all to be
yeah and i'm identifying with the pain like right you know so so here's exactly so
here's the slight shift in perspective i'm going to suggest susan so instead of identifying with the pain
as as you're turning to to love and appreciate the body appreciate and love all the ways the
body is hurting not the pain but all the ways the body is struggling is trying to heal
and it's having a hard time like a good friend who's really doing its way so so in that way
you're not identifying with the pain but identifying with the body hurting and just having a hard time
aligning itself with health so in that way you're accepting and there's an inspiration for health
does that make sense that shift yeah i think so it's like yeah not
identifying with the illness and i'm just using pain as an overall yeah
because it's easier for people to identify with so it's like not identifying with the illness
but just being really kind and loving with my body and all the sensations and my
feeling and and um giving that that care and love and
compassion and knowing that that probably is the most healing thing from my body that's exactly right right on yeah
thank you so much thank you susan thank you for that
the other reflections questions realizations came up for you in this practice
mara christine says it makes me think our practice needs to be proactive
help tell me what you mean by that amari christina uh if you could um
see if you could kind if you would like to unmute yourself if you wish you're
welcome to if not that's okay as opposed to being um passive recipients we're quite
in the process of um how we feel about our body and where how
our mind inclines yes oh absolutely yes yes yes i see what
you're saying there's yeah and the way that i i would i say that usually in
nikki's wording is you know um we our act of perception the way we're
perceiving creates our world every
act of perception is a weaver of worlds so the way we perceive is really weaving
a particular kind so in this proactivity that you're naming is the way we choose to perceive we choose there's so
many different perceptions we can have so yeah thank you
other reflections are there especially if you haven't shared for a while
i was how is the idea of the body as the beloved other connecting with this friend the
unfathomability the dimensionality
or anything else i'll take one more
pause
okay so having taken one beat so we'll leave some time for the other
side when we come back ben says i've only recently started
playing paying down the debt of love i didn't know to give my body growing up ah that is
sweet that's yeah the debt of love it's it's wonderful to pay it to pay it down
whenever ben it's i appreciate your your use of words they're beautiful
makes me makes me happy so the invitation for tonight here hear it
before you jump off those who think of groups so one way one invitation which is a
really unique way to relate to other human beings and take this as a
practice as a little sandbox that then you can take to
people in your life to practice with them the invitation is in the group
to see if you can see them as people who you know you're getting just
this small two-dimensional one-dimensional three-dimensional perspective of who
they are and what they're saying but there's so much more to them so much more to them so can you listen
to them and can you listen to yourself appreciating this this uniqueness that
you haven't quite explored about yourself or about the other people really giving them the benefit of the
doubt or benefit of the faith as as ben was saying just really opening up
to each other and seeing what what it feels like if you held the other people in this way what what
might switch do it as an experiment as if you're scientist of your own
mind nothing might happen but something profound might happen so i'd like to invite you to to relate in
that way with each other and start with 30 seconds of silence holding each other these amazing beings that you are each
of you with so many talents and capacities and
and challenges too so i'm going to create the breakout rooms
and [Music] uh here we go
okay here we go all right i'm going to open them okay the rooms are closed welcome back
everyone so we have a couple minutes if you like to share what what was that like
you can raise your hand if you like or type in chat especially if you haven't shared for a while
would love to hear from you
i see smiles but i don't see any hands raised
especially if you haven't ever shared it would be lovely to hear your perspective
especially if you're new or we're kind of not sure about the group thing
i would love to hear from you yes i'm speaking to you
yes parents i i love your perspective of considering
the body the precious other that's that's brilliant
you know everything out there is the other right
this is other two yeah very good thank you tense
thank you thank you
kim says my co-group member said it was heartwarming and i agree it was oh sweet heartwarming
sweet yeah any last quick reflections before we close
yeah yeah yeah i i hear that i hear that it was
challenging to to share some challenging and difficulties with
with your group um whenever you reflected and that's completely understandable it can feel
very very very vulnerable to share something that's very challenging right now sadness
depression to share with the group and feel vulnerable and i hope you felt supported in that and i'm happy
to stay a couple of minutes afterwards if it would be helpful to reflect that the person who
sent me that message privately i'm happy to stay a couple of minutes
so so dear ones thank you all thank you for your
practice for showing up for practicing for yourself
and for all those whose lives you touch directly or indirectly
may we all be safe happy healthy
and free and may all beings everywhere be free safe happy healthy and have ease
thank you sanga you are awesome i love you beloved others