so
as i've said already that with the 13
step of mindfulness of breathing we
enter into the territory of insight
of bipasuna and
before this meditation practice can be
characterized by practicing mindfulness
after all this is called mindfulness of
breathing in and breathing out
and mindfulness and vipassana are two
different things classically in the
early tradition
in the modern english kind of scene
people will use the word vipassana and
mindfulness sometimes synonymously
and sometimes the word vipassana refers
to the vipassana tradition
or vipassana meditation and it's used
kind of as a
you know to a general term
but in the teachings of the buddha the
word vipassana
doesn't refer to any kind of practice
but rather the results of practice so
it's the result of doing
mindfulness the result of doing
concentration
the result of doing mindfulness and
concentration practice together
which is one of the benefits of
mindfulness of breathing that they
they stay with the breath all the time
there is a concentration factor that
builds
as but we're also practicing mindfulness
of is staying aware of what's going on
where the the mindfulness is present
when those become both become
sufficiently strong the mindfulness and
concentration
then we start having insights we start
seeing
observing in ways that we don't usually
observe in everyday life you start
observing in deeper and deeper way or
with greater clarity
into the moment-to-moment experience and
that's when
insights begin and the insights
of the insight meditation practice
are not i i like to think of them
insights with capital i
there's lots of insights with a small
eye all
can be very significant but the
difference in my vocabulary and why i'm
using him now
is the small eye insights are the ones
that are
big aha moments where we see something
about
ourselves that's unique to ourselves so
for example
we understand something about the
conditions that led us to become who we
are today or
we see clearly our particular beliefs
that we're operating under maybe they
were
deluded or not really true ah and then
we put that down or we see
something about ourselves that we never
saw before and
and i said wow that explains why i
behave this way because oh there's that
anxiety or fear or something
memory that i have that keeps kind of
filtering my experience
so there's all kinds of very important
personal insights
that help us become freer and freer
but the insight with a capital i the
insight of
that inside meditation is really
focusing
focusing on are seeing things which are
universal uni uh that are common
denominators
of all experiences
and so it's it's true whether it's a
personal experience it's only unique to
oneself
and it's true for uh and
for everybody and so sometimes they're
called universal characteristics of
all experience and
and and in the buddha called these
perceptions so they're they're qualities
or aspects of how we perceive
all things that we we take in or
character characterize the perceptions
that
of all things so there's something
universal so they're transpersonal maybe
or
or um you know they're more encompassing
than anything
we see is personally whereas the
personal insights are important
going deeper down into the common
denominator of all experiences
the common characteristics of all
experiences this
it puts us down at the deeper foundation
from which
we build the cathedrals of
the citadels of our conceptual world
the world of self and self in the world
of others and
we we kind of build this world and
philosophy and beliefs and feelings and
all that
based on uh things that are uh uh
have this foundation of these common
characteristics common pers
ways of perceiving and
and the primary one that uh
is the buddha emphasizes uh is a
quality of all experiences
is something called anicha in pali it's
a-n-i-c-c-a
it's commonly translated into english as
impermanence
and and uh
probably not the best translation and
i'll get to that in a few moments
but i want to emphasize that what we're
focusing on here
is what can be called experience
in philosophical terms uh buddhism is
epistemological or it would be possible
this practice we're doing is
epistemological
i think what that means is that it's a
nature of how we ex
how we know something or the nature of
the experience we have itself
and so as opposed to ontological which
is
having some understanding or belief or
interpretation
about the nature of reality so
many people want to assume or believe
that insight practice brings us a deep
insight into the nature of reality
and it can be very reassuring to feel
like we have that kind of deep powerful
understanding the buddha seemed very
reluctant to make any ontological
statements about the nature of reality
he was not an early physicist who
understood the physics you know in my
nuclear physics of what was really going
on
he was a scientist he was a scientist he
was a scientist of perception
of how the nature of perception nature
of how we experience things
which is uh an interface of what it's a
meeting place
of what's happening in the world out
there
and and our perceptions how the mind
takes it in
and so it's a nature of experience now
this can be a little bit
feel complicated a little bit
discouraging because we want to have
certainty about the world out there
but everything we know about the world
happens through the
filter through the the avenue
of our experience how we experience
something
it's kind of like if there's an
hourglass the
one wide end end of the wire that when
you know broad
cup of the hourglass is the expanded
world outside of us
and the other end of it expanded
kind of cone of the hourglass is the
huge inner world
that we have but the the
the neck of the hourglass is
what we see through our eyes what we
hear through our ears
smell through our nose taste through our
tongue feel through our body
and then what is known
about what's happening in the mind the
knowing the experience of knowing
or recognizing what's happening in the
mind one way or the other
everything that we know has gone through
those six kind of hourglasses of
perception
and then with that the inner world can
make
it complicated and we can invent new
ideas and stories and
connections and all kinds of things so
but we don't we don't
remember or don't recognize that
it all had its genesis in that realm
of hearing seeing so for example
language
and concepts and words for things had to
we had to have some
you know that had to come through
hearing someone speak
those words or reading those words
and so the buddha made tremendous
emphasis
on this kind of in a sense this narrow
neck of the hourglass where everything
is coming in
and rather than seeing it as an
hourglass we see it as the foundation
upon which everything is built inside
and sometimes outside as well
and and so what is it that is the common
characteristic
of experience and it's anita
that all the experiences
are coming and going they're changing
their they appear and they disappear
the details the fingerprints of
experience
appear and disappear moment by moment
and sometimes it's because what's out
there
is passing by really quickly and
or not so quickly but clearly passes by
we have here i think some of you can
hear that
sometimes the train whistles going by
they come
and they go they come and they go and
and so it's pretty easy to notice that
those come and go
but but also the way as i said yesterday
the way that we they bring attention to
something
we very rarely fixate the attention in
some solid hard way
because if we do that it tends to be
strainful it's stress
stressful but that very gently the mind
the awareness
is kind of moving around and taking in
different details
and it's fascinating to do this with
physical pain where pain can you know
can feel from a distance like it's just
solid and
we're really kind of connected
we're connected to it and uh
and then uh we will um
the um um
but if we really pay careful attention
this observing way
we see the experience of pain is a
kaleidoscope of all kinds of sensations
going on arising and passing
and this arising and passing is
repetitive
so some things come and they go and they
return they come and they go
and um and so that can give
lend a sense of continuity and even a
sense of
permanence like they're not stopping
they're continuously there
but as we drop deeper and deeper into
this deep subtleness
of meditation and able to observe
intimately and closely everything
without
without the mind making the leap
making the constructing the idea of
continuity
then we just see the arising and passing
of phenomena
and the repetitive nature of it the
inconstant nature of it
and and so
the word anicha a-n-i-c-c-a
comes from the the root nicha
which means uh it can mean something
like constant
continuous and also sometimes maybe
permanent
and the a is is a negative prefix so not
constant not continuous not permanent
when we translate this as impermanent as
done often in english
it suggests that uh very many people
hear that as meaning
it's not going to last it's going to
come to an end
and it's kind of you know to be
constantly reminded everything's going
to come to an end
it maybe can be even depressing or and
also it kind of misses the boat
because um we have to then we just
expect and wait some things take a while
to end
and while it can be wise to be
understanding and recognize that things
will end there's a lot of wisdom to that
it's not the full story or it's not
really what the buddha is pointing to
as an insight the core insight of
insight meditation is to see the
inconstancy
of experience moment by moment how it it
arises and disappears arises and
disappears
so anitcha as as one of the core
insights
is probably better translated as
inconstancy
to the inconstant arising of passing a
phenomenon
that there might be continuous a
continuous constant
inconstancy constant continuous things
being inconstant like a river is
constant it's continually flowing but
it's also
never the same there's been inconstant
about it as well
and um so
nice enough for now so um
so we're entering into this deep world
of insight now
and um and uh and hopefully you'll begin
appreciating the observation of
inconstancy
thank you