so maybe we just sit quietly
for we have about 10 minutes or so and
we'll just sit and meditate and then
we'll
continue as usual
so then as we come to the end of this
sitting
the idea of refuge
is incomparable to the idea of saying
yes
to a way of being
that's not caught in
anxiety or caught in
distractions or desires or what if or it
should be different
or caught in
aversion or
ill will or disappointment or
discouragement
a way of being a yes to a big yes to a
way of being
it is not taking us away from ourselves
but a yes to the possibility of
being really here without agitation
and the confidence in that
makes a huge difference
an antidote to a kind of unconscious
confidence
in agitation and all the way different
forms it takes
and that's a big yes
that can allow us to
give us room in the heart and the mind
to have an unagitated
attention presence connection
with others
to have an unagitated
space to look upon others with
out our agitation being contagious
without our ill will hostility
frustration disappointment
desires expectations
unduly challenging others
instead we can be
someone for whom it's comfortable to be
around
we offer people a refuge
a safety
a peaceful and calm presence perhaps
or maybe just a attention a focus
of safety
and may it be that through this
meditation practice
that we become
a refuge for others
may it be that we are able to
breathe and live and walk and speak
in ways that promote the welfare and
happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so thank you for those of you who have
persisted to keep coming back and coming
back
it's a very like meditation we keep
coming back
and starting over so we kept
needing to refresh and refresh and come
back
i think the issue was in the end i
believe the issue
was uh either with our internet service
provider
or with the router to the service
we have two
wi-fi systems here at imc and so i
switched to the one that we usually
don't use
that's kind of the backup and the backup
seems to be holding strong
so why what happened i don't know
but i'm glad that it's working now and
um
so
so continuing on this topic of refuge
the primary kind of
and the most well-known aspect of refuge
in buddhism
is the idea of going for refuge in the
buddha the dharma and the sangha
and the word foregoing
gotcha me and pali literally means to
walk
but to go i think it's just a perfectly
good translation
but i like walking because it implies
that
when we walk we bring all of ourselves
along
and and so this idea of that
going for refuge is to bring all of
ourselves
into the refuge and
and so it's something that's deeply
personal and very
individual and involves a real
commitment a real dedication
to really step forward step into
something
and um and that uh
and so it is um both something personal
the eye
there's something that uh involving a
certain intentionality or commitment or
sense of purpose uh going
and then going to the buddha the dharma
and the sangha
and and it's i think it's useful to
consider
that there's two versions of buddha
dharma in the sangha
there's the external ones and the
internal ones
and external are what most people think
about it's a literal meaning of these
words buddha dharma sangha and the
internal
has to do with how we find uh
the reference point for those or
recognize these
somehow in ourselves and
so the external buddha is
is the historical buddha who functions
uh
probably one of the most important
functions of the buddha
for practitioners is he's an exemplar
he's an example of what's possible that
it's possible to become free it's
possible to
really to uh shed
thoroughly completely fully uh
all the different forces of agitation
of attachments of fear
of hostility ill will
that lives within us and
and so the buddha represents that he's
an exemplar of that
and and that's inspiring because unless
we have exemplars of what
this dharma is about then we have no
proof it's possible
and i think of a little bit like the uh
in the 1950s when there was the first
person who broke the four minute mile
running and it was said bef that that
can't be done it wasn't humanly possible
to
run uh a mile faster than four minutes
but once someone broke that barrier that
line then
many other people followed and so
um uh so once the buddha
you know showed it was possible attained
what's possible
many people have followed his example
and have attained the same degree
of liberation as he has
the and so to have him as an example and
be inspired by that be guided by that
and
you know have sense oh it is possible
and it doesn't that doesn't involve the
blind faith or allegiance to the buddha
the buddha then becomes a mirror for
ourselves
to engage in the practice this is
possible for me as well
the external dharma is his teachings
his the truths the practices the
the what flowed out of him
uh as a way of pointing us
to our own potential and they're a
remarkable set of teachings the
teachings of the buddha
and i still find them there's a vast uh
corpus of text that uh claimed to
represent the records of his teachings
it's a fascinating body of text it's a
little bit hard to get into
but it's so multi-dimensional and so
rich and it's kind of care in which it
really
addresses the issues of practice and
philosophy
or views and self
and all these things that we really want
to kind of shine light on
to really understand and find our own
freedom
a lot of what he has to teach is meant
to be practically
applicable in fact one time in one place
it says that
when someone teaches a dharma it should
be practical
and and then the dharma the sangha
are the community of witnesses those who
have witnessed
what he teaches who've attained a
similar
you know the similar form of liberation
as the buddha
and and to know that there are these
people who
not just not the buddha's not the only
example there's lots of examples down
through
time and even in our our our time
there's many many people who really
tasted some of the fruit
of what the buddha was pointing to
and and
they're there to guide us and support us
and to teach us
in our own idiom in our own cultural
form
maybe adapting the teachings according
to what's appropriate in different
environments and
different countries and different you
know cultures
and um so um
that's the external the internal
buddha is uh to re is when we see in
ourselves
the qualities of freedom inner freedom
and the qualities of compassion or care
or love
that that the buddha had
and dharma is to
recognize that some of the values and
some of the practices
that come that come out of that freedom
or to lead to that freedom
also is found in us one of the primary
characteristics of the dharma
is non-harming and so
to recognize in ourselves that there is
a force there is a
reference point for really not wanting
to harm
any living being at all a reference
point of feeling a sense
that where there's integrity where
there's wholeness
is not to lie uh not to harm
and not to steal the
not because it's the ethical thing to do
in the sense of abstract ethics or
morality
but because um it something lives in us
that feeling a sense of integrity
that's the dharma that's living in us
and there's a the dharma that's internal
is the dharma that
uh of practicing of saying yes and
bringing mindfulness and showing up and
being settled and
keep coming back to these qualities of
practice
that begin feeling like this is
this is a valuable and important way of
being
this is where home is this is where
to not be here it feels a loss
feels like a a um a diminishment of my
life to be caught in agitation
caught in desires and expectations and
frustrations and disappointments and
resentments and envy and jealousy and
um you know uh acquisition
well i wanted to acquire um
just you can feel how we come out of
harmony or we kind of
a little bit uh out of kilter when we
end up in these kinds of unless
unnecessary
and agitated states and
and to begin to really recognize these
settle state wholesome states
nourishing states peaceful states within
is to recognize the dharma and to
recognize the sangha
is to recognize that the inner sangha is
to recognize
how we in our personal way live in
relationship to other people
that we live in relationship to others
who
not necessarily are buddhists but
certainly buddhists are included
who share some of these values who
resonate with us with those values
who guide us or support us or encourage
us to live by these values by this
attention this unagitated place of peace
and wholeness that
the dharm liberation the dharma points
to
and then we live in a relationship to
that to others and in that relationship
then there are certain relational
motivations qualities that they're part
of this refuge and sangha
generosity friendliness good will
compassion honesty that have to do with
our
relationship with each other that's to
take refuge in the inner sangha
and and both external
and inner and the inner sangha are
valuable and some people orient one to
one more than
no the other at different times
and but ultimately the
idea is to have something within
that we recognize oh that's what the
buddha is
not that we have all the full qualities
of a buddha for sure
but some things all this is what the
buddha was talking about
this is what the dharma is this is where
where you know the sangha is found or
awakened or connected to
and uh and so we're talking about an
inner transformation that happens in
practice
and at some point as people practice
there's a recognition that
of a way of being that is valuable
a way of being that is more valuable
than almost anything else and for some
people they'd say it's the most
important thing for them not as i said
yesterday because other things that are
important
have become less important but rather
let the people in our lives there's some
of that
purposes we have that we live our lives
form some things can be
remain just as important as they always
have been
but maybe sometimes the dharma the
practice
the refuges become the most important
because they're the very thing that
feeds into a healthy way of really
beneficial way of relating to all the
other things that are important as well
it's like the common denominator or the
source from which
flows out a way of being that
really brings benefit to what we love
and people we love and
what's important for us
so to take refuge in the buddha the
dharma the sangha
it's not a passive thing it involves
understanding knowing something for
oneself
and so with practice deepens to learn to
appreciate what we're getting to know
and then what we're knowing and
recognizing
to let that live as a kind of big yes
this is important this is inspiring
um and it's an orientation it's like
this is the direction i want to go
it's an intentionality and orientation
the refugees are kind of a guide
oh yes this is the way and um
and they're an inspiration there's
something that's can be very heartfelt
and for some people it's quite emotional
that's a very deep emotional connection
so it's something intellectual something
intentional and something emotional
it's very rich this going for refuge
so
finally i like to say that
in some places in buddhism the maybe
some of our own
buddhist circles that what gets
emphasized a lot
is the goals of liberation and freedom
awakening
and and certainly that's important
but for many people
comparably of comparable importance a
comp
comparable magnitude of impact and
transformation and and a real kind of
turning point in a life that's you know
as valuable almost as liberation itself
is when there were really clearly
a change inside that is represented by
refuge it's a big kind of yes this
is what my what i what i'm dedicated to
this is important this is where my faith
is
and so this refuge is a very can be for
some a very important turning
decision turning point
that though this is important
and it said that when that happens for
people
that it gives their life a sense of
purpose meaning
it gives a certain order or
understanding for
all of our how we live our lives so it's
it's
and with that it can give a lot of peace
and reassurance
that that
we found a way to be in this difficult
world
so thank you all very much and
we'll continue on this topic tomorrow