so good day everyone and welcome
so the topic overall for this week is to take a good look and at
dosa dosa a pali word that i think today i'll translate a little
differently than hatred or hostility but as ill will
and it uh that translation works well as a contrast or as a partner in a sense
through good will and it's easy to set up these in opposition to each other
and to feel like it should be either one or the other and but one of the wonderful things about
practice is the way we can bring things together and nothing's excluded everything has a
certain kind of place in the field of awareness and learning what that place is
is uh part of the art of mindfulness
of practice and one of the ways of holding these together is when there is ill-will
whether it's to another person or to oneself or some particular aspect of our experience even in meditation
some ill will to the medic meditation cushion we're sitting on because it's too hard or
or too anything that uh to bring it together like
you know left and a right hand coming together to hold each other bring them together of goodwill together
with ill will meet the ill will with goodwill
to sit in a field of certain generosity of heart
that is willing to gaze upon all things kindly including our unkindness
including the ways in which we might have an ill will
cynicism maybe even or snideness or or a certain kind of judgmentalism which
is kind of like stabbing at people or ourselves
but instead to meet ill will with good will it doesn't mean condoning it it doesn't
mean you know encouraging it to continue and do what it wants to do
but it is a way of not being in opposition with it that allows the ill will that we carry
to be held in a in a field in a embrace
that allows something in the ill will to relax ill will hostility hatred does represent
tension contraction tightness a certain kind of forcefulness
sometimes a certain kind of assertion of power
and good will is a different kind of power that's never assertive but
many people say that love was always more powerful than hate
and so as we sit here today you might consider what it'd be like to be mindful to be
present for your breathing for your body for your experience for your emotions
and whatever ill will might arise would it be like if it's met or held or
gazed upon with good will with kindness or friendliness or
a generosity of heart that doesn't condem but also doesn't
condone and but allow something deep
over time something deep inside to relax that would be good to relax
so assuming a meditation posture
and perhaps for this sitting maybe some care could be given to a
posture that expresses a good will to your body
that's caring for your body
adjusting your legs your arms your torso your head
just kind of all the little subtle and big ways in which you can kind of care for it and put it into a
posture that is is supportive and helpful for you
to meditate with goodwill
some people when they want to evoke goodwill will put their hand over their hearts
somehow the human touch contact and to feel the warmth that comes in
that space of contact and if there is warmth there to allow it
to kind of settle in be received by the heart area
and to gently close your eyes
into maybe ever so slightly just to write for you take some
deeper breaths that express goodwill to yourself
care so this life-giving air that you take in
is done in a way that feels caring or nourishing
in a way of caring for yourself as you exhale to relax in your body
soften settling in and grounding here
in this body
and letting your breathing return to normal
is it possible to establish an attitude of goodwill of kindness
metta as the attitude of it carries or
supports the meditation today
perhaps it's experienced as a kind of tenderness a warmth
a caring a well-wishing
and to have with that attitude to settle into the experience of the
body breathing
relaxing and softening
and if as you're sitting with your breathing something that arises that's challenging
for you or difficult see if you can
meet it or be aware of it with good will
maybe with the idea that this is difficult
and i wish this part of me i wish this whatever it is i do wish it to be well
i do wish that it knows that it's cared for and
in a world where ill will is so common good will can be revolutionary
it even changes the paradigm
and perhaps as we sit here now to let the paradigm be a simple
gentle goodwill
breathing in and breathing out settling into your breathing to the
present moment
you
if you are wondering often thought is there something underneath or part of
the thinking that you can touch with kindness
with good will then relax let go of your thinking
you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
we do a very variation of a common buddhist practice
which is to dedicate the merit of our practice
dedicate the benefits that we've had for practicing for the welfare of others
and there's a kind of a wonderful dynamic with dedication of
merit is to offer up the benefits we receive
for others for the whole world creates more merit we benefit from doing so
if we dedicate our practice for the welfare and happiness of others
and appreciate that the deepest or the fullest welfare and happiness that people can experience
is a freedom from attachments freedom from greed hatred and delusion
and so when we wish even difficult people in our lives that they be happy and safe and
peaceful and free if that actually is the case
we benefit because they'll be in the world without great hatred and delusion
it's this wonderful chemistry or dynamic of goodwill generosity
it's healthy for all of us in all directions
to practice lots of it so now as we end the sitting
may whatever benefit that has come from this practice today
may we find ways in which to enact it
to express it for the happiness of others
for the safety of others for the peace of others and for their
freedom may all beings be happy
may all beings be free
[Music]
you
i'm sorry about that that i kept the mic on while i was drinking and you had to hear the swallowing
so um
so so the topic this week is a dosa
that i've been translating as hatred or hostility it's also translated as ill will
which has the benefit of being feeling like it can include a wider range
including um things that are even very mild and
there can be feeling there's a little bit of ill will in it and um and that you might not identify as
having hatred or hostility so it might be as simple as um you know
someone uh this crowds you a little bit too much in
the supermarket line uh maybe instead of six feet away they stand four feet away in
and you know and far enough you don't feel like you can say something but you really don't like it and and there's
so you feel this kind of little ill will like a little to that person
is that you know but is that necessary to have the ill will and
not hatred it's not hostility but it is kind of kind of an unkind attitude
so we will uh so today the topic is how to practice with ill will
and uh and this is a big topic practicing with it and uh and i want to kind of maybe try
to do it from the kind of a wide perspective first and then
bring it in closer and closer to the mindfulness practice with it and a wider perspective of it is that if
you want to practice with the ill will if you want to get a handle on ill will that you have and become wise
about it and even become free um
of it from it even if it's remains it's the kind of freedom you can find around it so you're not caught in its grip
one of the things to do is to live to is to reflect on it for a while think about it
contemplate uh talk to friends about it and to see if you can begin understanding what your relationship to
it is what attitude do you have towards ill will it do you have ill will towards it ill
will do you tend to regularly justify it and uh and hold on to it and
do you tend to feel shame because you have it do you tend to ignore it
and deny it and push it away all those are kind of common enough attitudes that people can have towards
ill will that they have and there's lots of other things but what is that relationship you have
what's the attitude and what are your beliefs about it do you believe that it's always wrong do
you believe it's always for you it's always justified and that's a tricky one because in some
ways maybe it is justified given how difficult
the experiences are that are happening to you and what people are doing but maybe it's easy to justify but
it's not really still the most strategic way of living your life
in the face of challenges maybe there are better ways and so anyway to look at the attitude we
have and the relationship and then to consider also
if you act on the ill will what happens what's the consequences of
that uh are the consequences in the world really beneficial or not
and um and maybe you sometimes expressing strong ill will to someone
you you it can be strategic in the moment to get what you want
but it maybe it doesn't really set up conditions for the long term that are very healthy or useful
and and so what are the dangers associated with the ill will
and um and then what happened what's it like for you when you walk around with ill will and
uh what are what are the what are the things that come with it um so anyway so there's all these
questions and to relive a reflective contemplative life and and to kind of question it
and consider it it's often helpful to do that with a friend a wise friend and even sometimes to engage your friend and
say you know can you ask i'd like to explore ill will and my relationship to it would you be willing to just kind of be
with me as i explore it maybe ask me questions and help out the benefit of that kind of reflection
is when you sit down to meditate you're wiser about the ill will you can recognize
some of the attitudes that come up some of the common strategies you have in relationship beliefs you have in relationship to ill
will that interfere with the ability to really be present for it
another thing that can be helpful before even before you meditate or during meditation
is to have some familiarity with metta some familiarity with some of the uh
emotions of kindness and compassion and care that we that can live inside of us and to
consider and this can be reflective also maybe conversation with friends what is the
relationship with ill good will to ill will and how is it how is there appropriate ways to bring
good will to ill will and have good will meet the ill will and or to touch ill will and i use those
words carefully meet and touch ill will because it's different than fixing and getting rid of
and i've had you know ill will and tried to use my practice to kind of blast it out
of existence it was kind of an ill will to ill will and but a touch touch it and so to
kind of begin exploring this world of ours in relationship to our to to goodwill and how do we what is
goodwill and where does that live in our lives and and um and uh so this is a reflective life a
contemplative life that lets things deepen and fill out for us so when we come to meditate for example
that's in the background that's there's a foundation that's a support for the mindfulness practice itself so
in mindfulness practice whether it's on the cushion it's meditation or in regular life mindfulness practice
entails in a sense stopping and looking
so we have ill will we want to stop and take a good look and the stopping is um means we don't
just barrel ahead be busy in our life but if the situation allows it
to uh maybe even pause and um and so that you really reckon oh this
is what's happening now sometimes there can be a kind of a general simple understanding that there's ill will
there but um and then we kind of may some people might be content well that's kind of mindfulness
but it's not really stopping and pausing and really taking an honest good look and seeing
this is what's happening there's ill will here and then having stopped to take a really look at
it take the time to familiarize yourself with it to be in the present moment with the experience
which is what the seeing is and and begin seeing it more fully with eyes
that maybe have a little good will or eyes that are not inten
not caring with it all our attitudes that we have about it that make it so much complicated but to
see to stop and look at the ill will
with eyes that are simple present without hostility without condoning it
without justifying it without feeling shame about it or critical about it
just to kind of look at it just for itself for what it is as if ill will
it there is a rightness appropriateness to really stop and take a look at the
experience of ill will in and of itself as if it has permission to be there
but because you've stopped there's no danger that you're going to act on it in
harmful ways you're just going to look at it and really get to know it and one
of the ways with many things in meditation expressed is to feel it in your body what's how is it
experienced where is the center of it where is it expressed most in the body where is the tension where is the heat
where's the pressure uh where's the place that wants to do something and act
and to feel it in the body and one of the advantages of really feeling
it in the body is the body is not a story and one of the things that fuels ill
will is a story making mind she said he said they said
and and so instead of kind of continuing with the stories and
the conversations we're kind of dropping in and letting the body be the place that
we feel what's actually happening there's something very significant about the feeling ill will in the body
is that the body has an ability to process difficult emotions that's a very
different way than the con the cognitive mind the mind that thinks about things and
analyzes things and um imagines things the body has a tremendous healing power
and to drop down and feel the body is part part of this healing potential
we have and one way that healing happens is that just as soon as you're feeling in your
body you can feel the tensions and those tensions can begin to melt away
and that changes the whole relationship to ill will because some of the fuel power that ill will has comes from the
tension we hold in our body or in our mind in our hearts and so
um it might also be useful to notice what other emotions come along with ill
will there might be underlying emotions that are really the ill will it's just a symptom of deeper
emotions there might be fear there might be hurt there might also be
deep inside a sense of conceit a sense of self that we're contracted around
and to drop in and start feeling carefully those underlying attitudes feelings
emotions contractions sense of self sometimes is much more useful than just paying attention to the ill will
and i find it very helpful sometimes to think of ill will it's just a si messenger don't kill the messenger
what's the message what's what's going on more deeply and then to feel and be mindful of that
it's not an analysis but it's feeling our way into what's deeper what's really going on here
and and then sometimes with ill will there is a mindfulness of the stories we do the beliefs we have
and the fascinating thing there is to see them just as thoughts to be able to be quiet still
enough to have stopped enough just to observe a belief come up a thought there
without believing it without picking it up or being involved and like almost
like you step back and you know you watch
you know you could maybe if you could watch a thought bubble rise up above the head of a friend
maybe you know it's like a little bit or a stranger you're a little bit detached you're a little bit removed you're not entangled
with it um so sometimes we kind of step back and watch the thoughts the story of making
mind that sometimes is so important for perpetuating the ill will
and um and then uh always finding some way to uh maybe relax to find the places
where there's tension and if it's easy enough to relax it and settle
so to practice with it to be present for it to be mindful of it
and and uh and all along if you have some interest and and value
in goodwill to do this whole practice of practicing with ill will with an
attitude of goodwill that you're doing this even though it's difficult you're doing it for your own
welfare and happiness for the long term happiness it might be difficult in the moment
but the more familiarity and the more wisdom and the more capacity we have to be mindful and
present with ill will the more that will slowly begin to build and create
a more and more a greater and greater wise way of living with it until ill will you'll discover one day
has less and less hold on you with less and less power over you it might still arise but instead of
being alarmed or going along with it you say oh there's my old friend ill will it's okay
you can kind of just stay there and i'm not going to get involved with that and later we'll practice with you or
we'll sit down so um in these few minutes that i have
that's what i have to say about practicing with ill will and
um it's a well worthwhile i think it's part of a responsible life
is to um is to really learn the art the ability to be mindful of ill
will so that it doesn't get the upper hand and so we don't cause harm in this world
so thank you and um and so one of the things you might think of doing in practicing with
ill will even the slightest for this next day is to maybe see in what way does ill
will contract you into yourself so that the sense of self or conceit or something is
there is highlighted or if to what what degree does ill will
create an unhealthy separation from other people and both directions are possible
you see the the difficulty in yourself to have ill will and you see the difficulty it creates
socially so you might see how that operates
thank you very much