so hello hello everyone hello and welcome
to this edition of happy hour so so
for for those of us who have been practicing uh meta
loving kindness for a while um we know
we trust we have a sense of the shift and changes
that happen over time when we practice both for ourselves the way we relate to
others and
and uh there have also been studies on loving kindness practice
um research studies psychological studies etc etc and sometimes it's kind of nice to see
things that we already know again verified oh yeah we know this
already and yet here it is it's kind of fun you know we don't necessarily need
validation from science and yet it's kind of fun when both come through and as a as a scientist myself you know
there are times that um anyway that's a much longer conversation i will get into that but
just to say so something i want to bring in tonight is um
is a study that was done in 2008 and
it has a pretty cool title so the title is loving-kindness meditation
increases social connectedness increases social connectedness
and it's a study done by hutcherson
emotion various places and basically let's just say a few were since i brought it in they brought
people into the lab they had them do a short loving kindness meditation
and then they measure the sense of you know
their their sense of friendliness or connection towards
others towards strangers and so so um
so one sentence that they have at the end which i particularly like especially at the time of kovit
at the time of many of us being socially isolated all of us having less social connections
than we did a couple years ago the sentence says the results suggest
that this easily implemented technique may help to increase positive social
emotions and decrease social isolation ah
kind of fun and yet this is what we know already we know that when we practice meta when we
practice loving kindness for ourselves for others even if we don't see our loved ones
there is a sense of being connected to ourselves being connected to others being connected to life there's this
sense of connection because again we know again from other studies and
our own experience that when we imagine something that imagination if you imagine
you are hitting a golf ball or you're imagining doing a particular exercise
actually there's some more recent research that that shows that if you imagine doing
for example some weight training actually your muscles get slightly more toned
you don't actually have to be weight lifting those weights so so this act of
bringing something to our imagination whether it's physical exercise which
amazingly actually changes the structure of our body our physical
muscles and not so different in terms of our psychology for imagining in our hearts
in our minds being connected with others wishing them well wishing them well wishing them well
there is a sense of connection we feel less lonely we feel less alone
um so and the opposite way if we don't
practice or if there's a sense of lack of
meta lack of good will or say ill will towards ourselves ill will towards
others you might have noticed there is more sense of alienation we
feel more alienated from ourselves we feel more alienated from others
as if we don't belong as if there's a sense of this social
uh fabric gets disconnected when there's a sense of ill will
so so we know this already we know we know
this and i bring this this one study for example as a way to remind us to remind
us remind us of what we already know in a different way
so coming together practicing in the sangha with a happy hour sangha and also there
is a sense of social connection of coming together in sangha whether on zoom or youtube
so as we practice loving kindness tonight um
for ourselves for others sense of how
tuning in tuning into the sense of social connection that
it actually fosters in the way of well-being both for ourselves and the way we show
up for others so
so that is the setup for tonight
let's get started in our formal practice so
i'd like to invite you to land in your body to arrive
to settle to connect
to invite your heart to your mind your awareness
to connect with this body with yourself
hello body
hello breath
greeting ourselves creating the sensations
of this moment's experience inviting the body to relax
to let go of any tightness or tension
nothing needed in this moment nothing to do nowhere to go
just relaxing all the muscles ah
receiving
taking refuge in this moment
unlike thoughts to be put down
thank you not now
receiving each in-breath the entirety of the opera
settling arriving landing
one breath at a time
this
spending a few more minutes to just arrive and settle
with the breath and the body
and let's begin our meta practice
by extending good wealth to this being who is me
greeting this person who might be tired
might be distracted [Music] it had ups and downs today which we
intimately know their challenges
meeting with friendliness with kindness
wishing well for the being who is me
myself
may i meet this moment with ease
may i have ease in my life
as an expression of our meta goodwill
may i meet this moment with ease
may my life unfold with ease
may i hold myself with friendliness and good will
may i love and accept myself just as i am
not a better version not the perfection i imagine
just just this
just this imperfect human being that does their best
may i love and accept myself just as i am
i invite you to experiment with putting palm of your hand
the middle of your chest your proverbial heart center just to connect with yourself connecting
the physicality of your palm with your chest
just connecting with this person with this being who's you holding yourself
so if you're holding yourself maybe love and accept
myself just as i am experiment see what happens
to connect with yourself physically not just with words
and now if you like you can stay with it's yourself who is you
or if you wish you can invite
someone who's dear to you you have an easy relationship with them
a child or a pet is okay
bring them to your mind's eye into your heart space
and extending your good will from yourself
to include this being may you
meet moments of your life with ease may you have ease
i wish you well
whatever phrases work for you or without phrases
may you be safe
may you be happy may you be healthy dear one
may you have ease
see if you can include yourself if it's easy for you to continue to include this
being who is you in this
good will
may both of us may both of us have ease
love and cherish ourselves just as we are
may we have happiness and well-being both of us
myself and your dear easy being
imagining both of you perhaps being together sitting together
at times your awareness might shift more towards them sometimes more
towards you sometimes equally including both of you in your loving kindness
it's okay
you're welcome to stay with yourself and your dear being for the entirety of the time
[Music] if you wish you can also invite other
friends other beings into your circle of meta and include them
your choice see what's best for you today
if you choose to invite more friends more relatives more beings into your circle of meta
may all of us may all of us have yeast may all of us be well
may all of us be filled with well-being or whatever phrases you like
that express your good will your care your warm-heartedness
perhaps imagining that the light of your meta
your is the shining light your goodwill the shining light
shining out of your heart your chest
touching you first and then touching outward
your friends your dear ones may all of us be well
i always have goodness
shining out touching your sangha your community of practitioners
on this path practicing with you may all of us practicing
may all of us have ease and goodness
i'm shining far beyond on its own you don't have to push it out
may all beings have goodness be well
be safe happy and healthy
have ease
including myself
different beings may come to your minds i wish them well
may you be well whoever
comes feeling your sense of connection with so many beings so many humans
whether you know them personally or indirectly connected
large web of interconnected humanity may all beings be well including myself
thank you everyone thank you for your practice
so we have some time for reflections
for questions comments what did you notice
especially with the theme of connection interconnection
with meta feeling less isolated lonely but feeling more
connected you're welcome to share in chat
if you just send it to my to me i won't read your name if it's to everyone i'll read your
name and reflection and if you haven't shared verbally for a while you're welcome to
raise your zoom pad
as i wait for your reflections i'll share something that
i noticed that for me today practicing that
the beginning you know i'm pretty tired tonight and i was tired and as the practice continued
i found myself smiling and smiling more and more sharing meta for
for dear ones and including myself and expanding the circle and it just became
so joyful but i had so much gratitude i felt so much
gratitude for doing this practice i'm happier than
than before we started so that's my practice report
what did you notice eric please
everyone i just noticed um when i got distracted
near the end of the sitting it was i just went back to the practice without
kind of scolding myself being distracted and i've been doing a lot of concentration practice and i wonder if
since i did meta practice this time that it just kind of primed me to not need to scold myself the
more generous nice nice
thank you for sharing that eric and i know it's actually very significant is
um you know that metta is also a concentration practice
is isham at the practice you know that um and
also that your if you're you know you might be practicing anapanasati
mindfulness of the breath as your practice concentration practice just so
you know you already know this but so that you you hear it again if you don't scold yourself there also
the mind will settle and become absorbed and settled and calm
much more quickly so this practice of meta can be really helpful with mindfulness of the breath
practice also so yeah yes beautiful that you discovered you were not
scolding yourself yay that is yeah very significant thank you for that
jamie please um well nikki first off i just want to
thank you for um you're saying that um i accept myself and love myself just as
i am that was just such a wonderful thing to to say to myself um i mean it was just
like a gift thank you um and yeah i just wonder if you have
any comments on um sex and sexual energy as part of meditation and i'll tell you
why um i thought about my dear one today was a friend who's who's kind of recently
revisited and redefined her sexual orientation and um i as i thought about her i um
my wish for her i said may you have sex that makes you feel more alive more connected
to your partner and more joyous and after saying that to her
i thought i want that and it was really easy to extend to
other friends and people i know and to the whole world because i thought everyone will be better with that
and i i have to admit i have like i become aware of my own sexual energy
sometimes during meditation it's just not a topic i've ever heard discussed in my uh still budding practice so i wonder if
you have any suggestions or response to that yeah thank you for
bringing that in very important um so with respect to this particular
because sexual energy is such a big topic but i'll keep my comment in this
case um specific to what you asked and what you came what came up for you regarding your
friend and your wish and it felt really genuine and joyous that you're wishing them well given the transition
yay may you have well-being in this area of your life that must have been confusing and challenging for you dear
friend and then and then oh i may i have that too and may so many people have that yay
so so in the way that i'm hearing that and also us being lay people
um to me the way it sounds to me it feels like your wish of well-being may you
have wholesome well-being experience that brings you joy that's how i'm hearing it so yay beautiful
and now bringing a little bit of historical context these practices most of the practices that are
taught are taught to monastics and monastics are celibate
so sexuality and sexual energy is something that they renounce renounce
when they enter uh monastic life which is not the case for our us lay
people so and and um so
just to put the historical context you know traditionally you would not see or hear this like that but you know it
would be kind of funny for monks to be wishing that for themselves or others it's like feels right and
given that again they've given it up or announced it and yet given [Music] that we are lay people and the spirit
with which you shared this jaime it feels like a good will wish may
you have happiness in different areas of your life you know the way we wish may you be happy or may
you have happiness in this sexual area of your life with with partnership so
um sounds good to me if that brings you joy this is there's a way of way for you to
express your good will then it feels wholesome to me in this context thank you very for bringing that
up thank you thank you
and we have a reflection from dawn the research is really
interesting i feel disconnected at times so good to hear about this as a means to
feel more connected thanks for sharing this you are very welcome and in fact i will share the the link
in the chat when you come back so so given that today's theme is about
connection and interconnection especially if you are on zoom and these
are the times that you think okay we're going to do small groups bye bye if you can stay
given that it is about connection interconnection challenge yourself gently gently to stay
to stay see what happens if you have connection especially if there have been any moments of lack of connection or
loneliness throughout your day see what happens if you stay you don't have to say anything brilliant just show up and
just be silent but just show up in the small group that's my invitation and if you absolutely have to go because of the
commitment no judgment but please don't jump off just out of fear
of connecting with other human beings so with that we're going to turn our
attention now into small groups um and practicing together
would be groups of maybe three or four and feel free to share anything you like
about your practice we'll start with 15 seconds of silent meta
for yourself for each other and the rooms are created and i'm going to
open them up and here you go take care of yourself take care of each other
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed
so we have just a couple of minutes for any reflections uh oh and also i'll post the
information about the study uh violet please
hey so um so yesterday i was
walking alone in berkeley in a residential neighborhood and a man came up to me and
basically harassed me tried to touch me like sort of like walked after me
and i did you know my usual defensive practices that most women know how to do in those situations
and he came up for me during the meditation tonight in the form of like connection
of like feeling connected to this man in some way and just like my
heart was breaking for his loneliness and his lack of connection
like how deluded must he be that that's his only way that he even
knows how to reach out to people or like is trying to get some kind of connection with people and it
yeah and it just it broke my heart in like a really sort of lovely and scary way to feel
connected to him
thank you violet i feel so touched and i see others are
too by by sharing your practice
it's it's amazing right it's amazing and of course you did what
was appropriate to the defensive at the time and yet not to carry that as a
resentment and hatred but ah to feel a sense of compassion for
this person who must be so isolated and disconnected just really speaks to the beauty and
transformation of your heart thank you violet thank you so much for sharing this
what a beautiful note to end on it what a beautiful note to end on tonight
thank you violet and thank you everyone thank you
everyone for your practice and jerry says kindness and vulnerability in the small
group was so nurturing for all of us beautiful and earlier deborah had talked about
stealth meta which we have talked about before and this um [Music]
at happy hour which is walking down the street and just sharing menta giving
meta for others and feeling a sense of connection with everyone so
so thank you all thank you for showing up thank you for practicing for your own sake and the
sake of everyone whose life yours touches directly or
indirectly may we all be free from hatred from ill
will may we all feel connected to ourselves
into this beautiful mysterious web of humanity may all beings be well may all
beings be free
thanks everyone