so warm greetings
and happy to have this hour to meditate and
talk about the dharma together
and the idea of relaxing the body and then relaxing the mental
activities is um might as might seem to be
a not a particular spiritual thing to do
or so significant but it is quite meaningful
in many ways it
gives us a feeling for a sense of what's possible as we go deeper and deeper the deeper
tranquility the deeper forms of letting go and freedom
it's also a significant in that is not just an issue of relaxing
but also the issue of feeling the consequence of relaxing or
calming or letting go feeling the influence it has on us
sometimes when we relax parts of our body areas around the area
respond sometimes the um
if you occasionally if you relax if you're sitting upright and you relax the belly
something then lifts in response sometimes there's a lifting of the torso
that goes together with relaxing sometimes relaxing the shoulders
there can be a lifting then of the the neck and the head and the
upper spine
relaxing the elbows and this can have a nice effect down to the hands
relaxing the face can have an uplifting feeling in the mind
or in relaxing there might be a feeling of lightness
or even vitality that comes something gets released as we relax
when we're really tense there's a lot of energy in tension but energy and the tension is
all kind of contracted and there can be a wonderful very subtle feeling of
what's as the tense tension is released so there's a freedom of a certain kind
of vitality openness ease
lightness
so as we do this relaxation that we often do at the beginning of a sitting
you might see what's subtle and it might be quite subtle influence that has what's the
what's left over what good things follow the relaxation
and you can appreciate it if it's pleasant or enjoyable
spend a few moments appreciating that taking it in the joy the lightness the pleasure of it
so sitting upright and closing your eyes
and gently taking a few somewhat deeper breaths
steep enough so you feel like you are expanding stretching good
part of your torso and as you exhale
to release and relax
the torso
whatever in your body feels easy to
relax
um
and then letting your breathing return to normal
then starting with a belly relaxing the belly softening around the belly
and feeling whatever is pleasant or enjoyable or good
about that relaxation
the influence the relaxation has around that the belly
relaxing as you exhale relaxing the chest
softening in the chest
and if it there's relaxation feeling whatever pleasure or lightness or openness that results
yeah feeling your shoulders as you breathe in
relaxing your shoulders as you exhale
and then there's the muscles of your face as you exhale softening in the face
letting the muscles fall away from the skull and then feeling the vitality
or the openness the peacefulness that follows
and then bringing your attention to where in your body you most associate
with thinking if there's any physical feeling
sensation associated with mental activity maybe in the area on your head
but it could be somewhere else
and as you exhale relax your mental activity relax your thinking
soften in the mind and feel whatever goodness
or pleasure vitality or peace that
seems to result from that however subtle
and then feeling the whole global body
wide feeling of being here in your body
and with the exhale release the body
relax the whole body and feel the influence that has
on the body
feel the mind kind of the global mind
if that's available to you and then release
the whole mind and feel the influence of that release
and when there's relaxation more room to feel
contentment
to feel some peace
to feel a kind of healthy vitality just being alive and breathing
that might even have some joy or well-being as part of it
so then as we now continue with breathing breathing in and breathing out
breathe with whatever is pleasant pleasure
pleasurable enjoyable
peaceful that's here in the wake
of letting go relaxing
letting go into the present moment relaxing into the body
releasing the mind whatever influence
that remains from having settled in and just being here
breathe with that good influence let it support you to quiet the mind
even more quieting a stilling
of an active mind and a contracted body
just here
as you relax or get calmer more subtle than the sitting
feel the goodness of that feel the pleasure or the
what's positive about that even if it's subtle
feel the influence of that throughout your being
without focusing on it so much include it as the atmosphere
as you breathe in and breathe out
even if there are difficulties in the peripheral attention
breathe with whatever goodness is here
whatever pleasure contentment peace
the atmosphere within which breathing occurs
so
hmm
um
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to consider that your ability to relax be calm have some tranquility
is a gift to others
especially if you consider that when we relax
there's an influence on that on us there's a impact or a result
that it allows us to be present
with less clinging
with less of the movements of mind and heart that
come with clinging less assertive less
forceful on people less
projecting our expectation demands
our bias prejudice our preferences
and instead when we're relaxed some of the good qualities that we have are more available
care attention for others kindness and friendliness generosity
so not just to feel not just to relax for its own sake
not to get calm for its own sake as if it's just for us
but appreciate the impact there the results the influence that has on us
in a way that lets us participate in our social world in a better way
and may it be that we reflect on how this meditation practice
does in fact help us participate in the world in a better way
both consciously and unconsciously intentionally and unintentionally
may the influence of our practice spread benefits out into the world
may all beings benefit from our meditation
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and if we notice how our goodness can benefit the people and beings around
us may we have the wisdom to do so
may we have the inspiration to do so
[Music]
so
in doing uh this buddhist path doing meditation practice
it's certainly helpful to relax
to calm the places that are over activated to relax the places that are
overly tense to bring tranquility to the ways in
which we're anxious or agitated
and sometimes then the emphasis emphasis is on the relaxation on the rely on the calming
but one of the things that's very important to develop on this path of practice
is a skill is a heightened sensitivity to the tension to the agitation
to the the ways in which we
get tense and the reason for that is that we want
to become skilled at we want to be able to recognize it well and clearly so that it becomes something
we pick up early as it begins or so that we become more aware of the
more subtle ways in which we get caught and cling if we're only
focusing on the relaxation and the calm we might not become experts at
perceiving attention now all the tensions we feel tension in
the body not maybe i shouldn't say all but most of it um probably represents
some way that the mind is clinging to something it's fixated on something it's pushing on something
in the mind and the much of the physical tension that we have represents
something deeper in the mind and the surface tensions of the mind
that we might feel when we're really you know anxious or upset or tense around something also represents
probably something deeper in the mind some deeper place of holding of clinging of attachment
and so even though it may be talking about physical relaxation
what we're relaxing is something that has its source in the mind deep in the mind the
clinging in the mind and so the idea is to start becoming more sensitive
to clinging to tension and that has many benefits one is that it can help us go further
and further and deeper and deeper into practice because we've gotten used to we've gotten familiar with all little ways
that that clinging appears in our body and mind and heart but also we can um
it's also a protection for ourselves that it protects our practice because
it's very easy to practice with tension practice with attachment
and we don't see it so i mean paradoxically a person could get the instructions just relax
your tension and they get so serious about the relaxing and that they tense up around let's do that let's
have to really do it well here the teacher says to relax and by golly i'm going to relax i'm going to be the
best relaxer anywhere and then we relax certainly we relax part of the body but the mind has
gotten tense in the effort to push anything any instruction people get in
practice we can get attached to the instruction any idea of what might happen in
practice we get attached to wanting that to happen or attached to somehow clinging
kind of a negative clinging to oh that's not happening to me it's not possible for me that doesn't relate to me
or that's not right so there can be this tension is holding on to that in a
way that limits our freedom and so if we start becoming skilled
at recognizing tension then we recognize the very tension that's involved in
how we practice what we're looking for wanting to have happen in practice and so it becomes a protection that
we're not ahead of ourselves in practice that we're not trying to make something happen or expect something to happen that's not
actually what is happening the default is always to come back to
what is happening and in doing that again we recognize
maybe how we're tense recognize the pushing the striving the
contraction that might be there and then as we let go of that then there's an influence that has on us
and part of this recognizing tension deeper and deeper is that we can
recognize what is not tension we can recognize the impact that has on
us to let go to soften to relax and we can recognize that there's more
happening here than the tension i've certainly had the experience of
being overly concerned with my tension in my body and mind
concerned with something i was supposed to do like focus on the breathing that i didn't notice that in the wider
picture of what's going on there was in fact some subtleness some calmness some
peacefulness some actually some some very subtle kind of delight and just being here
and i was so fixate and concerned with my preoccupation and so this idea of relaxing and opening
the attention to feel the influence of relaxation the influence of tranquility
allows us to feel some of the other goodness that's here some of the other things that are
actually going well for us and
and this is um the um because as as this anapan asate deepens
we want to uh broaden the attention to take in the bigger picture as well of what's happening so
the joy and the happiness of practice the contentment belongs to this kind of little bit
bigger picture and it might be subtle nothing dramatic and we might
then get fixated get attached to having joy attached to having happiness and or
disappointed that we don't have it and that's tension and if we
again if we are skilled at looking at tension we'll catch it right away so it doesn't trip us up oh there's
tension maybe rather than looking for joy i should look for i should really spend
time feeling that tension so he can relax it can soften or let me not be limited by the tension
let me kind of open up the attention wide or not in a fixated way
but in an open relaxed way and so the
uh and then but then as we open if we do feel some of the goodness of
the relaxation some of the goodness of the practice that's occurring i think of
it as the atmosphere uh the or the mood of a room or the
atmosphere of a situation we're in we we can go into i've gone into some places and the atmosphere is clearly
peaceful and i feel like i'm being washed in peacefulness i go into other atmospheres of your
social atmospheres and just feel immediately feels very tense the whole thing so the kind of the atmosphere within us
and and take in the atmosphere of the goodness even if it's subtle and breathe with
that not to deny other things not to lose our ability to notice when we get tense or
tight or contracted or resistant or all the different expressions of
clinging but as a way of creating a nice atmosphere that supports
the further letting go of clinging that gives us confidence that gives us some sense of the rightness of the moment as
opposed to it's so easy to focus on the wrongness of the moment some people are really experts at this
and and this is not to make a polyanis view everything is good but it's to create an atmosphere that
allows us to hold and be with the difficulties in a way that we don't get fixated or
cling to them or resist them too tightly
so all this is a way of saying that part of what we were doing in this practice is becoming an expert on tension
and so even though if the emphasis might be on relaxing
don't become tense because you're trying to relax or because you can't relax keep remembering that recognizing and
learning the feel sense and becoming more of a connoisseur all the different flavors and textures
of tension of clinging of holding of attachment is actually a very important part of the
practice and the so you want to take some time to feel it and get to know it and
and not be in a hurry to relax or not not in a hurry to to get rid of anything
that's uncomfortable because the lesson of what you what you learn
by really feeling it fully you learn how to be prepared better for
next time how to catch it earlier how to protect yourself from being caught in it
next time so part of this buddhist path is to become
skilled intention not skilled in tensing
because we don't want to be you know learn better how to tense but skilled in recognizing tension
and seeing it when it's there seeing it sometimes almost when it's beginning and the last thing i'll say about this
is that importance of not confusing tension with intentness
sometimes there's an intentness that has a certain energy and engagement
that and wholeheartedness that doesn't have the quality of limitation or
or debilitation that tension or clinging has
but it's really present there can be intenseness of the body and tentness
of the mind i'm here this is what i'm doing i'm i'm involved in this but there's no
tension there's maybe a tautness but no contraction or tentness
and so because sometimes people when they hear relax relax their intentness they relax their
healthy tautness and they become moved towards becoming just a slouch just kind of move towards
becoming just a you know too limp to really let the vitality of practice operate
so certainly relaxing calming becoming tranquil
peaceful is a support for this practice but don't overlook the important work of
becoming skilled at recognizing tension and maybe take some delight and
satisfaction as you become more and more connoisseur
of all the different ways that you're tense and rather being disappointed when you see it you say
oh fantastic i get to study this and get to know it better
it's not so pleasant right now to the tension in and of itself but in the long term i'm much better off
to really become the student of tension before i
focus too much on relaxing so thank you and
uh so uh tomorrow morning as well we'll have this
uh 6 45 64 45 sitting and a little talk at 7 30.
and tomorrow diana clark will lead it she's my co-teacher for this retreat i'm
teaching this week and and i'll take the morning that early morning off and
and she'll come in and now offer something for the sitting and and then we'll continue with this
anapanasati with step nine moving forward now
on monday thank you