so good day everyone
and welcome to our meditation time together and beginning of the week
and as a very brief overview of this practice of mindfulness of breathing
it begins with a training in attention and in a sense attention or
awareness sits at the middle of this practice
and that establishing this attention this mindfulness then in helping establish it more
consistently more thoroughly more fully
that awareness is centered on breathing breathing stays at the center attention
and breathing attention on breathing stays at the center and as the capacity to stay more in the
present moment more continuously with the breathing then either
intentionally or as a byproduct of that settling of attention
the attention begins to expand and open up to include more and it includes then the body
and the feelings of the body and eventually the mind and there's a kind of a natural order to
it that kind of moves outwards all along we're staying with the breathing we're
keeping breathing at the center it's like having a a home base or having
a secure place from which to be free to not get wrapped up in things
cotton things and to stay with the natural rhythm of breathing where we have to let go constantly and
and accept the new in-breath and let go of the old breath we're learning to kind of keep
the mind the heart relax soft free as we begin to open up into areas
of our life that might be more difficult and we're more likely to get caught in and entangled in
so the continuity of saying with the breath is a way of having an effective attention to the
rest of our minds and the rest of our being attention to the body being centered in
the body makes it easier to be attention attentive to the mind and so forth
and so with this week we'll begin with uh moving into more more closely into
aspects of the mind and um so to begin
to uh establish oneself in your place of meditation
really take a few moments to really feel maybe sway back and forth rock a little bit
to really feel the contact where your body is supported
from the pull of gravity and to be in that contact in a way that feels
supportive and solid
and then to gently close the eyes
and because attention and intention can be closely related
it's helpful at the very beginning to do some intentional breathing just for a little bit not the whole time
not really loud or anything but just a way of beginning to orient oneself to the breathing and
beginning to let go of other things so very gently maybe
let yourself breathe more deeply maybe three quarters full
they don't know how to fill your lungs entirely two-thirds full three-quarters full
whatever feels kind of easy for you to do but to take a fuller breath than usual but
not too much and then as you exhale
exhale slowly not too slowly but just exhale slowly so
the exhale is longer than the inhale
and as you inhale a little more deeply fully let the attention let that filling of
the lungs also be kind of a feeling of attention
in different places of your body where there is tension
in the long slower exhale let that be a draining of that tension
so letting your attention roam around your body as you breathe in
filling awareness into places of tension or holding
and relaxing as long exhale
especially can be useful to soften the
shoulders
and the belly so the belly hangs out tanks forward a
little bit forward and maybe down
and also as you exhale
maybe there can be a global relaxation of the whole body
and then continuing with taking an in-breath which is maybe a little bit
more full than usual doesn't have to be two-thirds full or
three-quarters full just a little bit more and with an exhale that's a little bit
more intentionally slow and long just a little bit
and then begin to count your exhales up to 10.
and as you count one two the difference for each one number for
each exhale
maybe you can say that number in the way that you would delightfully
and happily say the word yes to something
that tone of voice softly quietly but kind of an uplifting
happy intonation of one one
two and if you lose count no worry just
start over again at one and doing this counting is a way of
beginning to settle the attention down into the experience of breathing
and the counting is a way of giving the thinking mind something to think
so the rest of your thinking can become quieter
can fall away
and then if you'd like you continue with the counting but let the breathing be now really
natural or you can let go of the counting
and as you breathe feel the whole body as you breathe
in whatever way the global experience of body is easy to experience
it doesn't literally have to be all of it just as globally as is available
maybe as if breathing is a massage that moves through this global body
and as you experience the global body become aware also of any
thing that's pleasant or enjoyable
that comes from doing the meditation and it could be very mild
sometimes in meditation there's nothing but if there is
breathe with that include that in the breathing
the breathing that moves through the global body
breathe with the pleasure the enjoyment
feeling a present moment well-being that encourages the mind to become quieter
thinking less and more able to experience
what's happening here and now in the body
breathing breathing with the contentment of the
body the calmness
and then as you're breathing now on this basis of being rooted in your
body maybe feeling some well-being
also now become aware of the sensations associated with
the mind with the activities of the mind
in particular with thinking so there might be some sensations of
tension or pressure contraction
maybe an ache or maybe it's agitation or excitement
or maybe the mental activities is characterized by some emotion or mood
whatever sensations characterizes the mind
how the mind is active and involved let it completely be that way
no need to make it any different but let that be known
as you breathe with it stay rooted in your breathing
and in a simple easy way know the sensations connected to the
thinking mind
breathing through those sensations
staying rooted in your breathing breathing with the sensations
of body and mind being unconcerned with the details of
what you're thinking or what you're feeling any concern with the
why just for these simple minutes
breathe with the sensations the physical sensations of thinking and
feeling and emoting as if those sensations have complete
permission to be there and you just breathe with it
instead of thinking about or fixing anything with
mindfulness or breathing is just to breathe with what's here with a kind of intimacy or closeness
a calm careful willingness to just breathe with what is
here trusting that that's enough
for these few minutes just breathing with the sensations of body sensations of
mind
and then as we come to the end of the sitting and turn our attention
to the world outside of us ourselves
one of the profound things we can do for others
is to accompany them and if we learn to accompany ourselves
just breathing with our experience allowing our experience so whatever it
might be to be there
to unfold itself the way it wants to unfold but just accompany it
maybe it also teaches us how to accompany others without getting tense
or activated
to be able to offer a kind supportive presence
that allows others to relax cause others to be themselves
it allows others to be more attuned to themselves
so that they can move to greater health
and may it be that as we end this meditation that we dedicate the benefit and merit
of this practice to accompanying others
with our goodness our calmness
our friendship
without being too complicated or
too ambitious about what we can do for others company it can be one of the great gifts
and as we learn to accompany ourselves may we better accompany others
with the wish the aspiration that all beings may be happy
all beings may be safe
all beings may feel respected
beings may be peaceful
and that all beings everywhere may be free
so
so before we move into the talk i would like to
make a few announcements and first
is that
that on friday i said i would post we would post
some of the things that i read last week the simile for the jhanas for the states of absorption
samadhi and also i posted the little passage from the buddha's teachings
with the 16 steps of anupanasati and the easy place to find that is at
on imc's home page on the home page there's a little
in the bottom right corner in what's new section and in there there's a little
line for reflections from gill and in there that's where you'll find
those passages and
and the other is that next week so starting from next monday the plan is to have for one week have
this early morning sittings be 45 minutes meditation be 45 minutes rather than 30
minutes and we'll start 15 minutes early so we'll start at
you know whatever time your time zone is 15 minutes before the hour in california at 6 45
and you're welcome to join at seven if that early time doesn't work for you uh just that you know um you should
probably um tiptoe into the meditation room when you when you join us and
and the reason for this longer sitting is i think that it would be after all this time of sitting some of you've been sitting for months this way
with me in the morning i feel like we're kind of deepening and going further
and to be able to sit longer is one of the ways to experience more the benefits of this
path to kind of let it unfold more deeply in the course of of the sitting so we'll try it next week
and maybe in a few weeks we'll do it again next time i do a retreat
panasati practice involves 16 steps of mindfulness of breathing in and
mindfulness of breathing out and the eighth step between the eighth
and ninth there's kind of a transition that goes on and the transition is we go into the ninth
we're staying in the first eight we're still staying very closely in
intimately involved with our embodied experience and uh and then uh that's always a
foundation for the the second eighth but um now we're in the second eighth we're going to open up
more to the uh realm of experience which maybe is not so
directly related to the body to work related to the mind and and so we're still in this
body section of the first half and so in the first tetrad
it's about just learning to develop a continuity with the breathing and beginning to experience and sense
the body and the and especially how the body is activated by the mind
the tensions of the body and to learn to relax that as that relaxes it frees up a good kind
of energy in the body and as the concentration deepens it also awakens a kind of um
meditative joy and happiness well-being that comes with calmness subtleness
contentment that comes just sitting here and being here and with that as a foundation a certain
kind of meditative well-being it's only then that this instructions
then is opens up to becoming aware of
um becoming aware of um
aspects of the mind and uh so in the step seven the instructions
are breathing in one experiences the mental formation
breathing out one experiences the mental formation so a few things about
this the word experience the pali word for it as maybe the english does has a lot to
do with the uh the physical direct experience of the sensation and it's almost like this word that's
translated as experience could be translated as one senses when senses for oneself
the sensations of the mind of the mental formation and here it's a singular the mental
formation so it's not necessarily going and looking at the detail little detailed
aspects of uh the mental formation but the whole the whole thing somehow how
it's experienced so the mental formation are
those experiences associated with the mind mental activity that we can sense and feel so it's the
mental activity that has some impact
on the body that senses i think of sensation as being very much part of the
body and and so the sensations of the mind also
so it could be for example something is clearly physical that if we're afraid our shoulders might
be up it may be tense and tight and that's a physical formation but if
our if we're if we're afraid and our mind feels contracted
feels small or tight that's the mental formations the mental expression of the fear
of that activated state so it's feeling the mental activity
so if particularly associated with thinking if we're thinking very intensely we
might feel it physically as you know maybe the forehead is all bunched up and scrunched together
and that would be the bodily formation but if you look kind of more deeply into the area around where we're
thinking if we think in the area of the brain for example you might feel that kind of
behind the forehead in this in the area of the brain that's not particularly associated with muscles
that have tightened up there's still sensations uh there's might be a feeling of
contraction there might be a headache there might be
agitation there might be a sense of pressure or pushing there might sometimes i feel like there's a magnetic pull
gravitational pull for me towards thinking or thinking towards me and there's some
something that feels like a pull or a tug going on that's
in relationship to the thoughts there's a leaning in in the mind sometimes the center of
gravity of my thinking is a little bit ahead of my body
somehow i'm like i'm leaning forward into the future a little bit so it's possible to start feeling
something that resembles or is sensation like associated with the mental activity we
do and that's those will be called mental the mental formations the mental
activities that we can feel and and so then
um the um so what's interesting here is a variety
of things is certainly we have a lot of mental activity let's look at thinking for example thinking is a mental activity and the
instructions here are to feel that the physical the kind of the physical experience of thinking
and and it's only feeling the feeling it it's not thinking better or
understanding what we're thinking or analyzing what we're thinking it's not about recognizing even what
we're thinking it's simply recognizing the physicality or the sensation level
of the thinking itself so in the shorthand i like to think of this
as feeling the the thinking muscle
and and so the ways in which we feel i'm thinking it feels energetic or tight
or constricted or there's pressure or there's a hurry or there's a kind of
low energy uh there's sometimes you feel swampy in the mind it can't lack of clarity there's um uh
you know so so a whole realm of things that are how it feels for us as opposed to what
it's about and partly this is a wonderful support and aid
to not get caught up with permission during meditation to not have to fix our thoughts fix the
world understand what's going on analyze what's going on we're here we're
only asked to feel it and feel an aspect of what
the mind is doing the mind is very important but a particular aspect which is the
sensation level of it so we're connected to it but we're not
being pulled into the storyline in a sense and so and we're trying to do this
based on the foundation of the of step
5 and 6 which is feeling this sense of well-being so until we have
some feeling of well-being then we don't really start actively taking in
what is going on in the mind what the mental activity is about
perhaps so that there's a container there's a context of well-being for looking at an area of our life which
is often quite difficult and so we're not you know trying to do a spiritual bypass we're not trying to
avoid our inner suffering or challenges that we have
but maybe we're touching it with a breath with an awareness with a
with emotions that are supportive that have a goodness to them that have a
calmness or kindness in them that have a kind of generosity to them
some something like that it's on the building on the foundation of what's been done earlier
in these these steps of mindfulness of breathing and so the context for becoming now
aware of the mental activity is one of kindness of goodwill
or even joy it's one of the great um maybe peridot
wonderful paradoxes when i first discovered it that one can exp one can experience suffering
in oneself and suffering in the world and at the same time have a lot of joy and in fact my ability
to go deeply into the practice of vipassana where there are times we experience a lot of our
personal suffering was was supported by having cultivated meditative joy that
could hold that suffering so it isn't one or the other but it can be both there and all this is
it involves a disidentification from being locked in or
overly preoccupied with what we're thinking and what we're emoting and doing like that so that we
can just hold it and be present for it in a different way than we usually are and that's one of the opportunities
here with with with
this anapanasati is mindfulness of breathing so breathing in one experiences
the mental formation one isn't even trying to parse out the details of it
just the whole gestalt the global feeling the sensations of what they're going on in the mind
breathing out one experience of the mental and then because we're breathing
in and breathing out this is again like a support for not getting wrapped up in not being caught
by as long as the breathing stays relaxed and smooth we tend to have a more
open freer relationship to what we're including in that awareness to what we're accompanying with the
breathing so i hope that makes sense uh and we'll do more of this over the next few days
so if it didn't make full sense don't worry about it too much and and just maybe there's just enough that
when i go on for the next days and become clearer so so for now
uh maybe you can spend the day this next 24 hours reflecting practicing this idea of
accompaniment that we're accompanying things we're accompanying ourselves
we're accompanying our hearts our minds and we're accompanying other people what does that mean to be a companion
that way so thank you and i look forward to
tomorrow