happy to be here with all of you and this gathering of
people and also gathering of our of our minds of our attention
so um when i was uh living in the zen monastery
i had been there for maybe about nine months or so
and content to be practicing and doing the meditation that was a regular part of that life
and then one day they told me that i was going to be assigned to the kitchen and to be one of the cooks
i never really cooked before so and i'd come for do a lot of meditation i knew that the cooks didn't meditate a
lot so i was a little bit uh dismayed by this
but any case i went into the kitchen the first day i was supposed to be there and i walked in i was alone in this kitchen
a monastery kitchen and and i looked around
and the kitchen seemed kind of
huge like overwhelming for me exactly a year later when i finished my
stint in the kitchen i had i had just found myself in the same situation alone in the kitchen
and it seemed very small and the first day i it seems it seemed big
and i seemed small the last day the kitchen this building hadn't changed but now it felt small and
i felt large so there was a kind of shift of perception that went on partly with my
familiarity and my confidence of being there so a little bit something like that can
happen in meditation as well and other things begin happening that are we experience start
experiencing our minds differently it's perceived differently and some of it has to do with
familiarity with it and comfort with it where the mind starts feeling big
in a confident way and in a certain kind of way the world seems not i don't know if not as big but
not as daunting or difficult because the mind is big enough to hold it all
or as the mind as we begin to become a little bit freer in meditation
and less devoted to um to our thoughts devoted to our ideas
devoted to our emotions and devoted also in a negative way kind of devoted to being aversive to it or
reactive to it or all this complicated way we have with our our lived experience
as we start stop stop being so glued to it so committed to it
it actually frees up the space in the mind and the mind starts feeling large
or awareness starts feeling spacious expansive
and when i first started studying zen they talked about big mind and as we practiced this experience of
having this big mind in this early tradition that we're practicing out of
the buddha had the similar term that could be said big mind and
might sometimes it's called an expanded mind
but the word is a big or large maha and uh
and so this maha great mind and so as mindfulness
meets experience but it doesn't the attention doesn't get narrowed in some kind of
it doesn't get contracted around it or gets lost in it but gets relaxed around experience
then um things begin the mind begins to open up it's kind of like
if my if my i bring attention to my left hand with my attention can be like a little laser
like this it gets all wrapped up around it or attention can be like a big wide open
hand and it just it has lots of space for the experience of the other hand there's lots of room
for it to roam around and be experienced so something begins shifting
in the mind or with attention that it starts feeling large or spacious
open expanded sometimes as if it has no boundaries
it's not it's larger than our body in a sense larger than the some people have the experience of their
attention has a certain kind of funny way where it's larger than anything that's known within
it so of course you know here i'm sitting in this room here and of course the room is bigger than me
but i only know the room through the
medium of my awareness of it and so it's it's uh
the seeing the awareness of it is kind of a way in which perception is constructed
in the mind and then we know what's going on so in a certain kind of way awareness is larger than the room
and uh it can feel that way and and not that this is accurate for what
the mind is who knows what the mind is but it's how it's experienced when the mind
starts getting relaxed and spacious and not caught in things
so to sit quietly now to see if
you could notice how large your mind is
how small it is how much space there is an awareness
so to take a meditation posture
and close your eyes
and without anything more right now
what's if if you had to kind of
notice the size of your mind or the size of awareness
how large is it as large as your skull
smaller than your skull larger than your skull
for some of you maybe this question doesn't compute
it's perplexing but what is it that knows being
perplexed
that which knows
does it have any boundaries edges
so now taking a few long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale let all things settle
relax
letting your breath return to normal then gently
relaxedly on the exhale
further do some further relaxing of the body of places where things are held tight
softening in the face
softening in the shoulders
softening in the belly
and also as you exhale to soften the mind
especially any physical sensations connected to thinking and
trying to figure things out or any tension
pressure contraction in the mind in the brain
as you exhale imagine that the
mind spreads out horizontally like a vast
large still lake of water
and without knowing exactly or even approximately
what your mind is
does your mind have any boundaries is there an edge to the mind
is there that which is inside the mind and that which is outside the mind
and if there is what's the shape of that boundary
and if you relax the mind further relax trying looking seeking
just allowing your mind to relax and be
allowing awareness to be and does your awareness have enough
space in it to become aware of your breathing
and as you exhale to let there be a quieting of the mind
so the mind is pulled pulled or settles towards
an inner silence quiet
and as you inhale
let there be a receptive quality receiving the inhale
receiving the inhale and the vastness of the mind
and if there are thoughts and feelings and body sensations
that become predominant experiment with knowing it
in the vastness of the mind
know it with an awareness that has large
unpreoccupied
the less reactivity the more we experience the mind
as something that's open and relaxed
perhaps vast the vast mind
which has space for all things within it
the mind becomes larger when it's not limited by our concerns
it doesn't when it doesn't become narrow with our
trying to get something or make something happen or figure something out
letting the mind relax letting awareness be relaxed
open wide and clearly receptive
for the meeting between awareness and our experience
and coming to the end of this sitting
what has shifted in your mind in the course of the sitting
not in terms of the content of the mind the concerns
but the state of your mind
is there more calm or subtleness
are things quieter
is there greater understanding or clarity about
what's going on in the mind
does the mind in any kind of way feel more expanded larger
does the metaphor of space relate to
maybe feeling spacious in the mind
or a spacious awareness
and whether you feel it or you can imagine it imagine your mind is
as large as the room you're sitting in
imagine that it's as large as the building you're in
imagine it's as large as the
town you might be sitting in or the area you're
in imagine that your mind is vast and open and
extends out into the world
and in the vastness of the mind there's a room for all things
and so too in your mind's eye imagination imagining
some way the whole world with all its beings and
all its joys and sorrows lots of room in your mind or your heart
that you welcome all things you're ready to be a witness
to be a safe presence for all things in your mind
relaxed open receptive
and perhaps allowing this openness holding all beings
to gaze upon it all kindly to gaze upon all of it
with a feeling of caring and compassion
kindness and love or a friendliness
that wants if once the wants the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy and may whatever benefits that come from
this meditation may it support that happiness of others
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may that safety and peace and freedom that others can experience
may it begin in my own mind may they exist peacefully in my own mind
safely safe from me peaceful with me and free
with me may all beings
be free
[Music]
so here on the fourth talk on mindfulness of the mind mind state
um kind of a little bit now maybe trying to explain a little bit more about what
that guided meditation was about so the
when the buddha teaches the classic teachings on mindfulness practice the four foundations of
mindfulness the third foundation has to do with mindfulness of the mind
the state of mind in that description of how to practice that
there's the instructions to notice eight pairs of mental states
and the first four have a lot to do with noticing the presence of
how we relate to the world how we get involved in the world so there can be desire greed there can
be ill will or hostility hatred there can be delusion
and also there can be ways of relating that without those and so the mind somehow is still in
involved in in the world and thoughts and feelings and all this and uh and it's possible meditation to
feel that that shifts and changes that the contractions of and the tightness the tension of great
hatred delusion begin to abate and a whole other motivations come how to relate to the world generosity and
love also um in how we relate to the world or
confused about the world or begin kind of not quite knowing whether to be involved in the world or
connected and preoccupied or not the mind goes through a transition where sometimes it just doesn't know
whether to collapse and get tired and fall asleep or doesn't know to get over excited and
doesn't know where to land or what to focus on but it's agitated the mind can get kind of contracted in
itself so i can get it get get scattered in all kinds of ways but it's still kind of a mind that's concerned with things
in some way as mindfulness gets stronger as our ability to be present and rooted and
here in the present moment as we not so inclined to get caught in our thoughts
and preoccupations then the experience of the mind shifts
to a kind of mind state kind of mind way of operating that's not so
incessantly concerned with relating to things
if you're involved in thought swept away in thoughts you're relating to the thought to the ideas of the
thought if you're preoccupied with your feelings uh
you're you know then the mind is kind of involved in that and focused on it so so when we stop focusing on this
stuff then the mind starts to become freer from its preoccupations
and then we start experiencing the mind more as its own thing its own state
it's very hard to talk about what the mind is and so to call it a mind state or
something i've been calling a state of being the quality of our inner life some people might call it the heart the
quality of the heart and you know exactly what the mind is we don't know
but we don't have to know for the purposes of meditation we just have to recognize something
about how awareness consciousness feels what we might call
the gestalt the totality of our mental activity the state of our mentality
this inner kind of world of knowing of being conscious of being
aware of mindfulness and start feeling the quality of it this
and when it's no longer preoccupied with things then the mind starts feeling
um more peaceful more calm and one some people find the mind feels
more expanded and uh it feels large large mind big
mind expanded mind and and uh
and it's a little bit you know it's possible it's a little bit of an imagination because you know what the mind is in part
is a reconstructing apparatus it takes in all the data
that comes in from the senses and from our memory and all kinds of places
and it kind of shapes it constructs it in some kind of way um understands it it's an understanding
apparatus that we have and so whether there's actually space in the mind
that we're making or just feels that way we close our eyes and just feels like
there's a vast kind of maybe luminous darkness or light that might be there
or just uh without a sense of seeing just a felt sense of perception
being expansive and taking in things that are beyond the edges of our
body um not in some telepathic way but just kind of like the sensing that awareness is
open uh it and and it's not like focusing on anything at
all it's the absence of being concerned with anything that awareness the conscience still operates
but it's not eclipsed by our concerns
and so the mind that's not always relating to things is a mind that starts feeling
qualitatively different there's a deeper level of peace deeper level of calm
ease spaciousness stillness silence that
starts to be a shift when the mind is not always incessantly relating to something
and so to learn to recognize that shift and for each person will be different and so hopefully giving enough different
words that some of you will find different words work better than others but there is a shift
from uh from to something that feels more healthy more satisfying more free partly because
a lot of the unhealthy not all everything but a lot of the unhealthy ways in which the mind
operates the ways that we suffer and feel anxiety and feel
you know caught in desire and ill will and confusion
a lot of that the condition that makes that happen is our rumination our preoccupation and
things and it kind of we're spinning tales stories ideas
telling ourselves things that are kind of uh
deflating to tell ourselves things these same things over and over again and
reminding ourselves of stories that are painful and ideas that are painful but when we stop doing that
stop being in the world of thoughts and ideas and aboutness
then the mind doesn't have that stress anymore and it turns out the mind without stress
feels very satisfying very peaceful nothing has to change in the world
except how we relate to everything and um and how we hold things
in the mind in awareness so there becomes a radical shift as we begin recognizing the quality of the
mind at some point we can recognize the quality of the mind that's not
preoccupied not focused on things and being always relating to things
and this mind then is some people say it's receptive open receptive mind open
mind open awareness the the mind now is maybe not the mind
people say it's more like awareness more like consciousness more like um you know
and they can feel boundless they can feel like it has no limit
so the buddha says one can know that the mind is large
or we could know that it's not large but that it's that it's small still maybe because it's preoccupied but at
some point you can actually watch it sometimes uh oscillate between becoming large and we're not stable in that
settled mind and so then we some wonderful thought arises and we
get involved in it and then when there's a wherewithal you can actually feel and see how things got contracted and narrow
again maybe some people even find it darker the light goes out as we get involved in these thoughts
but if we're pretty settled it might be easy to let go of it and then we come back to this larger more luminous and
spacious mind as this develops further
the buddha says that in its instructions he talks about a mind that is
that that feels as if it has some it's with a ultimate feeling
kind of ultimate state it feels this or maybe the ultimate maybe not the right word but it could also mean higher
now we're into a higher state of being a higher state of mind something that's really
exalted or special or maybe special is good and now it's with something special
and um and and the mind feels really good and we know it there's a clear knowing of that wow this is there's a
purity there's a clarity there's a crispness there's a freedom there's a piece here that is qualitatively
different so now this this is a mind with a high quality
however with how the traditional understanding of this is there can be a
wonderful feeling sense that as as high as quality of mind as
this is it's not the highest potential and the highest potential is a mind
which is called unsurpassable and this is when
when there's no duality or no separation between
knowing the mind is special and
and and no separate from the knowing of it and the special mind itself they become
one and the same almost that the knowing is so special and is no different than
what the mind is so all this ability in the third
foundation to really get into it it's a
it's a description of what happens when the mind is settled and concentrated and mindfulness is
strong and so uh don't feel like you have to be there or this is you you're you know
you're you're a poor meditator if you don't know what i'm recognize what i'm talking about
but it's good to know the description of the of the map of what can happen in meditation
because some point you might touch into something like this oh this is what the text is talking about ah now i
understand now i i see it rather than being like what's this and what do i do with this
so the mind the heart consciousness
it's one of the precious things and the the our whole there's a paradigm shift
in how we live fully and completely in this life when we know
there's a new game in town the old game was always to be concerned about things and always relating to
things as if that's the only game in town it's a fine game at times and we're not rejecting it
but now we know there's another game there's another paradigm of how to be and it's possible to be
a mind that's receptive aware conscious for sure but it's not locking into things lobbing on it's not
organizing itself to be focused and relating to things all the time but it is receptive and can still know
and it allows for some deeper response from within than can happen if we're only responding
from the paradigm of relating relating and relatedness
so uh hopefully this makes sense and if not just store it away and someday maybe it
will and so we'll have one more day on this teach buddhist teachings on the third
foundation and i look forward to our time tomorrow
thank you