so good morning good day good evening hello everyone
and here we are to do this morning meditation or
together and a little bit the topic of
theme of this session of mindfulness meditation
is what's called investigation or exploration a process of discovery
and as one of the seven factors of awakening it's sometimes said to be the most
important one for the purpose of awakening
for the purpose of freedom and there's something about
choosing to explore to discover
to investigate what our experience is which is
an expression or a manifestation of freedom
no matter how difficult something might be to choose to take
take another look at this to step in a sense step towards it to
see it better or sometimes we step away from it
to get a better view of it it's always to discover to see to investigate
and when we do that we're not a victim of experience
when we do that we're not under the control of experiences around us within
us when we do that we are
our attention is not being hijacked by our hindrances or
our neurosis or our fears whatever it might be
and so this ability to decide okay what what is this what is this
experience i'm having and not to answer that question with words
not to answer that question with an explanation but to answer the answer it with
um with
a clear seeing to answer it with a clear
perception feeling for what's happening
so taking a meditation posture
and in some sense this expression of freedom which is to take a
good look begins with caring for your posture
choosing to use this wonderful resource of attention
to scan through your posture
and to
make small adjustments
that not only help you be more settled and more relaxed
but also a little bit more alert physically alert
ready to discover ready to see what's here
and then to take a few moments to discover your own breathing
without doing any different breathing just notice how it is for you to be breathing
to explore it to feel it and as you do
so maybe you can notice a difference between being entangled with your breathing and
wanting to be different or concerned about it or and simply discovering it
simply becoming familiar oh this is how it is now
without being for or against
without being analytical and
preferences just discover it in its own way how the breathing is
and then having done so now to take a few long slow deep breaths
as a way of establishing yourself in this body
here and now
and then as you exhale long exhale
relaxing settling in releasing yourself
the tensions of the body
and then to
let your breathing return to normal a little bit more it's useful to release
and relax the holdings of the body as you exhale
and often enough the tensions and holdings of our body
give pressure or give yeah maybe a kind of pressure to the
mind to keep thinking about things being preoccupied and as we relax the
body there is less of that pressure to think
softening the face around the eyes
softening around the shoulders
releasing the shoulders maybe adjusting your hands a little elbows so the whole arm is a little bit
more at ease
and perhaps softening the belly
and then settling into your body breathing in whatever way breathing is most
compelling or easiest most pleasant for you to attend to
in the belly in the chest and the nostrils
wherever it might be
and then very simply
choose to be with your breathing
to discover how it actually is now distinct from how you want it to be
in a sense to explore it to discover it to investigate it
feeling the freedom in that choice
that you're exercising your your ability
to direct your attention to discover and feel and get to know
better
noticing the difference between the bodily experience of inhaling
and exhaling
noticing a difference between the experiences of breathing where there's some tightness or
constriction and where there's some looseness and releasing
to investigate it to explore it means to let feel it on its own terms
step towards it to just get to know it better without it needing to be different
without trying to fix it just know constriction here looseness here
and discovering a little bit what it's like for you to be aware of
your breathing what it's like for you to explore
investigate the experience of breathing
not to make anything right or wrong but how is it for you
to discover the kind of discovery that
of a naturalist
simply discovering something in nature patiently observing it as a natural
phenomena noticing how you are in relationship to
mindfulness or breathing as a natural phenomena
if there's resistance or reluctance eagerness
if they're straining or complacency whatever it might be
discover it notice it and let it be that simple
the simpler the discovery is the more freedom there is
freedom to let things just be as they are freedom from our internal reactions of
things just being aware discovering
seeing and then returning to the breathing
maybe seeing how simple the discovery can be just discovery just seeing
not seeing anything special or hidden but just how it appears
just how it shows itself to you
if you get lost in thought that's just another natural phenomena
and you the naturalist that's studying it seeing it
this is how it is
and then settling back into your breathing
a silent discovery a silent dis investigation of breathing
where there's an intimacy or a clarity
about the different sensations that come into play as you breathe
and to follow along
to observe in the distinct sensations of breathing in and breathing
out distinct sensations of
the beginning middle and end of the inhale beginning middle and end of the exhale
discovering your breathing
and very easily with ease
maybe you can feel the freedom the independence that you bring to your
experience by choosing to discover it to see
it more fully
more clearly without it needing to be anything
different
even when our thinking is pleasant if we get preoccupied and lost in
thought there is also a loss of freedom
but to wake up our capacity to discover
what's happening here
is to enact our freedom
and asking the question what's happening here is not to be answered per se
but to encourage taking a gentle clear
look what is happening here just seeing and feeling
just what's obvious no need to
think or probe just discover
what is showing itself to us now
to investigate does not need to involve a contraction or a
tightening of attention or the mind
it's more useful to have it be involved in opening an expansion of attention of awareness
of the mind it's open and receptive
and you know and it's possible to let this investigation factor
come to its fullness in simply being mindful of the breathing
breathing with greater intimacy and
clarity discovering
the obvious experiences of breathing in and breathing out
with clarity and
distinctions
with a quiet mind a mind that gets quieter
the more we discover
so to bring this sitting to an end
to use your freedom and investigation
your ability to discover be open be available
to you see if you can use it to have that freedom of openness of
discovery for others to allow them to be
as they are because you are free
so and i see that you could hear my phone
calls with my wife so perhaps you can hold all this in investigation and freedom
and simple discovery how it is and in so in doing so
may all beings be free may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be safe and may all beings everywhere
be happy
you