good evening and i always feel like i want to say
good morning good afternoon whoops whenever it might be that you're
listening to this so
it's nice to practice with others so welcome welcome
as you know we start with a guided meditation
so just taking an alert upright posture
settling into a posture that supports your intention
to
meditate
that includes some balance as well as some ease
feeling centered grounded
i like this saying to sit and know that you're sitting
feeling the pressure of whatever you're sitting on perhaps against the back with the back
side putting the pressure against the legs
whatever the feet are touching
and to help support the arriving
and a sense of ease we can also check in with
other areas of the body the face
and the eyes the jaw the mouth
the shoulders allowing the shoulder blades to slide
down the back have the shoulders be away from the ears
maybe tucking the chin just a tiny bit just a really small movement that
opens up the back of the neck
relaxing the chest maybe another really small movement
of opening the chest maybe the shoulders go back
and relaxing the belly
and relaxing or bringing awareness to the hands
what are they touching is it smooth or rough
is it warm or cool
and bringing that same attention
to the sensations of breathing
feeling the movement of the chest or the belly
abdomen or the feeling of air going in and out of the nose
noticing the in-breaths and out breaths
or when the mind wanders we just very simply gently
begin again with those sensations of breathing
feeling into the experience of breathing the expansion
stretching pulling
when the mind and body are settled a little bit
it can be helpful to turn towards our thinking
rather than believing that we have to get rid of our thoughts
we just turn them into objects of
meditation and we can turn towards them
with an inquiry about the process the experience of thinking
not the content of the thoughts but are the thoughts pictures
little videos or are they more like sounds word
sentences
are they colorful are they loud so the
quality of thinking the process of thinking the experience
of thinking not the content
having the intention to notice this can disrupt some of the momentum
of thinking
it can be really helpful to notice
oh yeah this is a little movie
planning what i'm going to do or remembering something
or maybe it's a voice
maybe it's your own voice
you can also inquire is there a location
in which this movie is playing that is is there a movie screen
as their location for the movie screen is their location for the loudspeaker
the point is to be curious and have an inquiry
which can interrupt the thinking the purpose is not so much that we have
to find and dig for the answer
we don't have to get rid of our thoughts we just fold them in into our practice
it's worthwhile to notice thinking or
thoughts without getting lost in them
have such a big influence on us whether we are aware of them or not
and being more aware of our thinking disrupting it
not getting lost in it all the time
there's a way that helps us to be here
and attentive to what's here and now
in such a way that can support others
be available for others
so that we can create the conditions in which they can
be the best versions of themselves
just like we're practicing to create the conditions so that we can be the best versions of
ourselves
so may all beings be safe and may all beings be free
from suffering and may our practice in perhaps some
really small way but may our practice contribute
to the ending of suffering
[Music]
good evening
i i want to say it's nice to be here with you all because in my mind i'm meditating with other people even
though i am alone in this room but i feel the sense i can see the chats
that um there's others with us here others with me here
so tonight i'd wanna i would like to talk a little bit about
how we can bring our mindfulness practice even to thinking or thoughts or mental activity
or often with mindfulness there's an emphasis on being with breathing
being with the body but of course we can also be with the mind
and that our mental activity has such an impact on our lives it's worthwhile to become more aware of
it and and to interrupt some of the momentum it might have some of the compulsive
quality it might have some of the feeling of getting stuck going round and round
and because it's so easy to just to get lost into story and mental activity
it's abundantly easy to do that we often don't fold in mindfulness of
mental activity mental states until there's a certain amount of
stability and steadiness so it might be for a lot of our
meditation that we are just settling and calming down and
so it's primarily spent with a mindfulness of breathing and mindfulness of bodily sensations
but when we feel like there's a certain amount of stability and this might not happen until we're on
retreat or some other extended opportunity an opportunity for extended meditation
periods but whenever we do feel like there is some stability
then we can turn towards the thinking and the thoughts
without getting completely swept away in them because of course
this um in order to be mindful of thinking we need to
not be lost in thought maybe that goes without saying but we see both in the satipatana suta
and the anapanasati suta so these two discourses some of the primary discourses
that talk about mindfulness both of them include mindfulness of breathing and the
body before the mind
so with this quality of stepping back being able to see the thoughts without
getting lost into them or to see anything really the bodily
sensations or emotions or is this so being able to step back
in some kind of ways just a characteristic in general of how we can go a little bit deeper
with our meditation and how we can a little bit more steadiness
or solidity or something like this so this idea of knowing what is taking
place rather than just being immersed in it sometimes in guided meditation i talk
about to sit and know you're sitting there's a certain pulling back when we know that we're
sitting so there's a few ways that we can
look at i'm using this word mental activity mental state and i like to maybe like tease apart three
different aspects of this and the first one is not so common and
maybe it's a little bit debatable but i'll offer it and that is in the
satipatana suta that is the discourse on the establishments of mindfulness
there's some qualities of the mind that it says is good to notice helpful
to notice and one is whether the mind is surpassable
or not surpassable so the presence or absence of
surpassability if that's a word what does this mean so
there's some hints we might get if we look at the parallels that are preserved
in chinese for the satipatana suta and there the word gets translated as cultivated
or not cultivated so one way we might understand this are
probably a few ways but one way we might understand this is whether this is our usual state of mind
or a more mindful state of mind sometimes i think about this or refer to
this as it's more like street consciousness i'm just making up this term what i use
is kind of walking around not being mindful versus being mindful
we i don't know how to describe this but i think you know what i mean like we know when we're being mindful
when we're not being mindful we don't know of course we don't know
so not only that to know whether we're being mindful but to also know
is there a general feeling like oh yeah okay i recognize this mental state this is
what it feels like to be more settled
or this is what it feels like at the beginning of a meditation period and after i've been sitting for a little
while i believe it'll be different so is it surpassable or not surpassable
that is is this the edge of our meditation practice
or is it the beginning or is it ways we're in still in the process of getting settled
so is this familiar territory or new territory and this not so much that we have to
always be inquiring um do i have some attainment am i in
in some new place all the time but so it's not an obsession with our
progress or our development or how far we've gotten but it's just this recognizing where we
are so that we can
know what what to expect maybe what comes next or how we might if we know that there's
some it's possible to get deeper more settled i'm using these
words more settled deeper then we might know that oh yeah there's
can be a little bit more letting go that can happen there can be a little bit more quieting
that can happen so that we can walk this middle way
between not having this excessive expectations like but it's supposed to be a
particular way but also we don't want to have any disdain
for using reference points that we have with our practice or maybe even some aspirations
we might have for our practice so that might be the first aspect
of our mental activity or mental state is just this very gentle maybe
it's not even worth them highlighting but to acknowledge there's a gentle acknowledgement
of where we are in the territory in the landscape of
meditation so to speak a second way that we might notice
the interior experience the mental state is to
be aware of this state of mind or we could use the expression mental state
so not the content of the mind so much but the
quality of the mind the mood of the mind the state of the mind maybe the attitude
i know sometimes um i have this just general even even when not meditating i have
this state of mind like oh yeah i just can't quite think i think for whatever reason i don't know
why exactly maybe i'm tired or um feeling frazzled or something like this
and the mental acuity isn't quite there but just the general kind of state of the mind
and so to step back from the details and to notice the greater context or the
mellow in which our mental experiences happening
so mental states are subtle and diffuse they're not we can't
pinpoint them necessarily and say it's here exactly this it's more of a
vague kind of idea or experience
so this again in some ways can be an interesting exploration because we might
have this assumption that to be mindful of something means
that there's some precision there's some delineation
i'm mindful of this and it has edges and it's clear and it looks exactly like
this again this is implicit probably we don't have that explicit
but i'd like to suggest that we can also be mindful of things that are diffuse and vague
maybe foggy maybe they're just known in the periphery of our awareness not in
the center of our awareness a certain a different type of knowing if you will
and maybe we could use as an example that when you're looking at a window
and you realize that the window is reflecting back so you can see whatever is being
reflected in the window and you just shift your gaze or a little bit and you can also see
out the window so there's two different views that are possible and
to notice that it's light inside and dark outside for example
and that's why the window is reflecting so it's the noticing that it's light
often when you notice that it's not so much that you are pointing to one particular
experience or object but there's a knowing of light
i'm not sure if this is a good example but it's something like to explore
that there's can be a general feeling or mood or attitude
the classical teachings use words like the mind is constricted or expanded
that is scattered or concentrated
or colored with greed hatred or delusion or not colored with greed hatred and
delusion or fettered or unfettered
so maybe we might use language like appreciative or wanting more
or calm versus tense or light-hearted versus critical
or maybe i um an example i gave earlier feeling like i can't quite think
clearly i can't feel like i'm maybe there's just a feeling of not
a lot of mental acuity and sometimes there is some mental acuity and then even that whole
idea well what exactly is mental acuity so just pointing to the general feeling
of the mind and to recognize that these states of mind have a more pervasive and enduring quality
than just particular thoughts that is we might um have angry thoughts
that appear but they the angry thoughts might just arise and then pass away but there isn't a general mood of anger
there might just be a flicker of irritation in contrast when we're when we are in in
an angry mood they're just everything we feel just a little bit
cranky and irritated with everything this just general sense but we're not
really angry with everything because in the midst of that we might be having thoughts of
oh gee i wonder what's uh for lunch where are my glasses is it time for
me to get onto that zoom call you know we're having all kinds of completely neutral thoughts
even though there might be this general mood of anger that
might be colored by anger so it's possible to completely ignore
the mind state we don't have to pay attention to it of course but i think we all notice when we wake up on
the wrong side of the bed kind of gives us a general mood that it does have an
impact on us and often the more aware that we are of what's influencing our thinking
our behavior the more we can make decisions
about how authoritative we're going to take to be
our thoughts are we going to believe everything or are we just going to notice yeah i'm cranky right now
maybe if you're that half of the human population that hormone cycle and monthly
it might be noticing yeah okay having these types of thoughts right now they don't have to be
so authoritative i don't have to believe them or give them as much weight as i might at other times
when my hormones are in a different state
so that's the second way it's just this kind of vague mood or color of the mind
state that tends to be a little bit uh maybe um
not obvious and enduring and then a
third aspect of the of what's in the mind we might call
generally mental activity or maybe more specifically thoughts but there's a
whole range of things that we fall under the word uh mental activity
or maybe even thoughts kind of lump them together but
there's a range in terms of how compelling they are how
lost we are in them and maybe the energy or the movement that's behind
them that we might get really might be a pressure really to think about them there's also a whole
range into terms of the wholesome or unwholesomeness
some things that are clearly if we're having a lot of thoughts of wanting to cause harm
there's it's very different of wishing to end the suffering of somebody thoughts
of how you might help them find greater peace and freedom
and then there's a whole range in the middle
so mental activities yet one more way that we can pay attention and this these are
associated with the best of the human experience and the worst of the human experience
and when unattended just like our mental state our mental activity can
have such a big impact on us
so i'm making this distinction between mental state and mental activity some could argue that
maybe we don't need to but i find it helpful in meditation practice to make this
distinction but notice that often the instruction is
to settle or let go or calm mental activity there isn't the instruction that we have
to get rid of eliminate mental activity
because meditation doesn't always require that we have this thought free mind a thought-free mind is
possible but that happens but usually in a retreat setting when the mind is
really settled really quiet
so it doesn't have to make the fact that there are thoughts doesn't have to be a problem we
can let go of this idea that somehow we have to be getting rid of our thoughts
and instead just how can we work with them if they're arising how can we disrupt some of their momentum how can
we disrupt some of the unwholesomeness if if they are there
and sometimes just simply paying attention to the experience of thinking
that is as i did in the guided meditation are these thoughts are they images or
are they sounds and just having that gentle inquiry
can be a way that takes some of the momentum away from the thoughts and that might be
sufficient to allow the thoughts to just arise and pass away like thoughts do
another way is to bring awareness to the sensations of the
body and when and or
any sensations that are pleasant there might be a feeling of ease or openness or
some sense of well-being or okayness that's anchored in the body
so i'm talking about okayness and ease and one could argue that there those also
can be mental states and if one can rest in them by all means
we can do that but often it's easier to rest in physical
experiences of ease and well-being and certainly in the as i
mentioned in the anapanasati suta as well as the satipatanas mindfulness
of breathing or foundations of mindfulness
they is this instructions on mindfulness of the body and mindfulness
of breathing before the mind so we can always just go back to
mindfulness of the body or mindfulness of breathing
if we find that our thoughts have a lot of energy behind them or find that they're
unwholesome maybe we can disrupt them or undermine some of the
energy underneath them by just being with sensations of the body
especially if there's any some sensations that are associated with well-being or happiness or some contentment
so maybe just an emphasis um on rather than having to get rid of our thoughts we can just have a focus
on what's helpful and what's unhelpful what's wholesome and what's unwholesome
what's skillful and unskillful and maybe to steer the
thoughts steer some of the mental energy towards what might be more wholesome
more helpful so in order to do this there might be a
few tools we can use and the buddhahi uses a simile
which i appreciate that there might be a peg that is in some wood
but we might imagine that it's and the buddha says you might want to remove this peg
and in my mind i'm thinking those dowels like when you're using ikea furniture
that you're using to um join different uh pieces together so something like that
and this buddha simile says that if you want to replace a peg that is in wood that you use a
smaller peg and you can tap it out so if you if the dowel of the peg is
rotting and you want to replace it if you want to not have rotting peg
anymore you can replace it with one that is fresher and the word in the
similar uses to replace a coarse one use a finer one so if you were doing the
dowels with ikea furniture of course you would use a little bit of a smaller dough to
tap out using a hammer tap out the the coarser one maybe that was a
complicated explanation of what was obvious and didn't need that explanation but the point here
is to replace thoughts replace unwholesome
thoughts with more wholesome ones
so one might be to
chant the refuges and precepts if you find that your thoughts just feel like they
have this a lot of energy and there's a
you're feeling stuck with this compulsive going round and around not really going anywhere
let me change the refuges and precepts that can be uplifting and gives the mind something to do and
really can support a sense of openness and ease of course don't do it if it doesn't
support a sense of openness and ease
if you find that there are some thoughts of ill will revenge or wanting to
give somebody a piece of your mind or something like this something that i've done is chanting the
meta suit in my mind i memorized it and it was a great
support to use it as a tool to to be chanting the metasuta
and just the practice of memorizing it was really helpful so
i offer this as something that can be helpful to kind of replace some unwholesome thoughts
or if not chanting the mata suta then to just do some loving kindness
practice bring to mind the phrases of loving-kindness and to do them in a way that is um
easy and available and accessible
that is not towards the person for whom you're having some ill will but towards a
lovable being send some good will some benevolence to a lovable being
so those are some thoughts of some ways in which you might replace some
unwholesome thoughts associated with um ill will if you're finding that you're stuck with
some lustful thoughts some sensual desire that is
just not helpful we can do meditation on body parts this is what
the buddha recommends for the monastics right to have a life of celibacy
and i can imagine it's not always easy to be celibate so help them and to help all of us if we're
having some thoughts that are unhelpful and unwise of sensual thoughts to think about body
parts so usually when we think about people's appearances we think about that as a whole
this person's attractive this person is attractive but be they become
less attractive if we consider their body parts for example
from somebody who's a model for
shampoo for example and has beautiful lustrous hair it becomes
less attractive if you imagine that it's chopped off and on your dining room
table it's the same hair but just to consider
it by itself kind of shifts our relationship to it so many of you may know that this is
practice of doing the 32 parts of the body it starts with head hairs body hairs
nails teeth skin flesh spleen phlegm spittle snot and urine and it continues
so right when you start considering all these things of a person then that really can shift your
relationship to them so this is another practice somebody might want to consider
something else that we might do rather than to replace our thoughts is just to say
you know i'm going to think about this later right now i'm meditating
and it might need to have some energy behind it no i'm not going to do this right now
right now i'm going to meditate i'm going to bring my attention to the breath for example and just to say
later later not that we're never going to think about it
but just now is not the time
so now that's a the third way we can think about mental
activity and mental states is to notice our thoughts and then not so much that we have to get
rid of them but can we encourage thoughts that are wholesome and supportive
and one way to do that is to replace thoughts to use a tool and of course if it's
not helpful we don't use tools not to use it so these are things just to if we
find that we're stuck and we need something other than just returning to the breath
we need something other than just being with the body
so i just offer this as some ways to work with our interior
experience or mental experience to notice the mind state as well as to
notice where we are in our settling process in our meditation process as supports
that supports for more ease more freedom so that
can support our being present not only for ourselves but for others
so that our practice can be for the benefit of perhaps in one small way
for the benefit of all beings everywhere thank you