okay welcome to imc's monday night
sitting and uh dharma talk
all right i assume that things are going okay so um uh we're going to begin
this session with about half an hour of a guided
meditation and then i'll share some reflections
based on a topic and that i bring in today
so let's begin the sitting
maybe take a moment and to find a posture that's supportive of meditative practice
i'm aware that today is the first night right after the full moon
night since yesterday yesterday was a full moon night
and so in some sense this is kind of an auspicious auspicious night and so
um may we all have an excellent night or an auspicious night
sitting together practicing together
so maybe just take a few moments to settle in into wherever
you're meditating in
the first few moments just to allow the body and mind to arrive
arrive into here and now
it's often useful to begin by taking some long deep breath
as you breathe out just allow the body to relax
feeling the connection of your legs and feet
with the ground the floor and the chairs or the cushions
having a sense of groundedness grounded on earth
as the lower half of the body began to settle and rest on earth
allow the upper half of the body
to rest and settle as well
can you feel the weight of the arms
hands
let the arms hang naturally
maybe the torso is upright
and neck is aligned
with the spine like an extension of the spine
allow the muscles on the face to soften
feel sensations on the top of the head
on the back of the head
just do a quick scan from the top of the head all the way down to
the bottom of your feet inviting ease
inviting relaxation
and softening
and then momentarily if you're ready
can turn our awareness
to the movements of our breathing
that maybe is rising and falling of the belly
or the expansion and contraction of the chest
foreign
resting your attention on the movements of a breathing
without trying too hard
simply resting like a putting a gentle [Music]
hand i'm petting the little baby
stroking the baby
soft gentle awareness on the breath
the concerns of the past and future
maybe can be faded into the background
allow the foreground to be filled with the experience that's happening
here and now in this body
maybe tinkling on the feet
warmth in your palms
coolness of the breath
it's a secret life force unfolding right here
right now
now you can rest your attention your awareness
right here in the whole body
it's as if the awareness is
filled imbued in the body itself
there is nothing to do to be aware
simply receiving the experience of the body
and experience of the mind in the restful field of awareness
maybe the sound is known
sound of my voice
ambience sound
silence in between
vibrations in the belly
a thought
tightness on the forehead
everything everything that's happening
can simply be received and known
and pleasant experience
unpleasant experience
a moment of doubt
a moment of wanting grasping
everything can happen on their own terms
it's kind gentle awareness
simply receiving
no need to fix
boundless allowing
some experience may be extremely challenging
getting to know this through the embodied experience
persistent swirling emotions
how does it feel in the body
are you aware
if the mind wandered away it's never too late to start again
right now this moment
mindfulness front and center right now
if the mind wandered away just know that this temple of this body
always has a door wide open for you
always welcome
to enter and return to the temple of this body
in this last few moments of our sitting
i'm going to read this poem versus from a middle length discourses
the title of this poem is an auspicious day
maybe you can listen to those words while you're you sit
allow this words to drop into your awareness
however it might touch you connect with you
allow it to be received in the wide open field of awareness
and if something bubbles up receive that too
an auspicious night this is translated by gil fransto
the buddha said don't chase the past or long for the future
the past is left behind the future is not yet reached
right where it is have insight into whatever phenomena is present
not fattering and not agitated
by knowing it one develops the mind
ardently do what should be done today who knows death may come tomorrow
there is no bargaining with mortality and his great army
whoever dwells thus ardent active day and night
is says the peaceful sage one who has an auspicious day
and the other translation of the auspicious day is a single excellent
night
[Music]
you