so greetings and uh welcome to the continuation of our
exploration of mindfulness of breathing and by now i think you'll understand
that mindfulness of breathing involves much more than breathing but that breathing mindfulness
of breathing is kind of a foundation in which we begin to open up our
awareness to more and more of our experience
and at some point this you know as we open up to our body our feelings our mindset our
mind activities mind states and so there's a kind of expansion
opening the metaphor i like to use and so it's not narrowly focused only on
the breathing and at some point as we do this the
the very idea of opening the feeling of opening the experience of opening becomes more and more salient and more
and more experienced experientiable that more and
more this stands out the sense of opening and in contrast to that it's possible to
feel the closing and this movement is that i'm calling
opening and closing can be represented by many words many ideas
and the buddha used the word as a word obstructing that sometimes
we cover over and we give certain activities of mind obstruct and others remove the obstruction
and has more expansion and openness of attention and we can see that i think relatively
easy in some circumstances in life where in know very quickly we can suddenly get
completely caught up in some concern completely you know the mind attention
everything gets focused very tightly around a preoccupation someone says
something to us which is maybe disrespectful and the whole universe
collapses around that disrespect our feelings our ideas our thoughts or maybe our
fears resentments whatever it might be and where it gets swimming and that's the story of it and
and so maybe there's not much openness anymore to take a bird's-eye view of the
situation and what just happened and what's happening with us and then
other times we have that bird's eye view we have this broad field of awareness and we're
relaxed and open and someone might do the same thing say something disrespectful
but we don't close down in fact maybe we do the opposite we actually open even more and like oh
what's going on here what's happening here let's let's uh i don't even know i don't
i don't quite understand all this but this is a time to be present and open and take in the full
range of what's happening myself the context the other person and there's a clear feeling of opening
being preoccupied caught up in things is something that the buddha says brings
blindness and a lack of wisdom this movement towards opening is
movement towards wisdom and vision
and so getting starting to get a sense of this difference is an important part of this practice
and this has this becomes more relevant when in the process and this is in the
process of mindfulness of breathing we become more attuned to the state of mind because
it's the state of mind that shifts and changes and so to uh so we certainly can know
that we're preoccupied with resentment or or uh caught up in our or hurt or
whatever it might be and um the uh or in our desires and we lose touch with
everything else around us and we can know that we're involved in that but to appreciate the impact that
preoccupation has how it shifts the mind state it shifts the quality of awareness the openness of
awareness the ease and receptivity of awareness that becomes interesting
and and so to notice this movement between closing down and opening up
covering over preoccupied versus kind of available attention that's open and
available because it's not preoccupied as practice goes along
there's a shift of attention from the details of our life the stories
of our life the history of our life a shift little
bit even from our beliefs and ideas desires aversions
opinions and to the quality of the mind state and we become the
custodians of that quality no one else can be the
custodian of our inner the quality of our inner life and so to begin finding a relaxed easy
way to to track it and know it and be able to gently keep opening
keep finding the way of peace keep finding the way where the mind state is receptive and open
with wisdom with real wisdom so that we're safe in the situation and can take care of ourselves
so that's kind of the background for this meditation so if you can
begin by assuming a meditation posture
and if it's possible to do a posture that already in the posture
expresses a kind of openness availability
to life to experience
for me sitting cross-legged i sometimes really like taking my hands on either side of my
hips on the floor or mouth next to me and lift myself almost off the cushion
like i'm doing now and so i'm lifting up and then as i'm lifted up then i roll my
shoulders back a little bit and release and if i do that the shoulders roll back a little bit and
the chest kind of naturally kind of feels more open and that openness of the chest can be
one or the reference point for being open
and then gently closing your eyes
and this idea of openness we can be open-handed
and you might take a few moments to relax your hands and maybe even
turn your hands to palms upward so the hands are open and available
sometimes expressing openness in the posture is supportive for the heart and the mind
to do so become open
and perhaps you can as you exhale
relax the shoulders soften in the shoulders
and whatever softening release that happens in the shoulders let that travel down into your chest
and whatever reference point you have for being open hearted
see if you can establish yourself as openhearted
open chested
and then as you exhale relaxing in the muscles of your face sometimes those
muscles are very intimately connected to what's happening in the mind
the tightness scrunching up the pulling in very subtly the micro
muscles of the face it's as if there's
the mind is a puppeteer with strings that go into the micro muscles of the face
to relax the face
around the eyes the forehead and temple
the cheeks and the jaw might even be helpful to open your mouth
slightly so the jaw is not clenched
and then gently softly float
the teeth back together the mouth back together so there's a light touch with your lips
and whatever reference point you have for this as you exhale can you allow your mind to
become open to be open-minded
to your experience now
open-handed open-hearted open-minded
and taking a few moments also to set your body at ease
be easy with how things are in your body
maybe easing up if there's any heaviness or contraction
resistance in your body
see if you can find some even a slight sense of ease
being present for your body
and if possible set yourself at ease in your heart with your emotions
ease up on how you're feeling be easy with it
and then set your mind at ease
in whatever way it's you can a little bit ease up on what's
in the mind or be easy with it
so the awareness becomes a little broader
more available to receive
awareness is not recruited
to help us focus on our thoughts and desires and aversions fantasies
instead of being recruited to close down and narrow its attention
letting the awareness be at ease and open
receptive
and then within whatever openness that's here
whatever ease that's here
to attune yourself to the breathing
the in-breath and the out-breath breathing through or with
open awareness ease full awareness
as you exhale letting go of your thoughts
and as you do so also see if there can be a
opening to a wider awareness or opening to opening
allowing the mind to have more space and room to silently
be aware of breathing body
appreciating any sense of openness or ease or
in the state of mind state of heart
breathing with it and notice the small and big movements
of losing that openness contracting
getting caught up in something
nothing you have to be feel bad about or criticize yourself for
but simply to be sensitive to that distinction
sensitive to the way the mind moves can move from being open to being more closed
relax to being contracted
preoccupied or being available and open
breathing with it all being easy with it all
but clearly aware of the difference and how the mind can move
around to different degrees of openness and less openness
no need to analyze or figure anything out or
stay very simple with appreciating if the mind gets more open
or more closed appreciate which direction mental activity is
taking you and see if you can keep choosing to stay
open move more it's very forgiving
it doesn't require a lot of understanding of what's happening
or justifying or criticizing it's just a very simple movement
opening or closing and when you can choose the opening
choose awareness
being upset about the mind closing down
is to do even more closing
be equanimous about the mind closing down is to contribute more opening
as we become more aware and simply recognize what's happening
allowing the recognition to be wide and
open
uh
ah
[Music]
and then in the last minutes of this sitting maybe knowing it's the last minutes
you could let yourself become more open
maybe quiet the mind more and open up in a way that the heart mind is
broad and silently receptive
whatever degree of ease just being here
in a certain way nothing to do nothing to be nothing to prove
just here with awareness open relaxed
maybe even soft
and perhaps trying to keep it that way and see or see what happens
bring to mind some person that has been part of your life lately or
will be today and see if you can hold the image the
idea of this person in your mind without closing
without getting caught up in thoughts and stories and feelings
just for a few moments let the persons the idea the person float
in the openness of the mind
and in doing so does that make it possible to have more
wisdom more clarity about something about yourself and them
might it make little bit more room for a simple good will
friendliness or generosity of heart
and if so maybe softly gently
give expression to that good will with these words
may this person be happy
may this person be safe
may this person be peaceful
may this person be free
and may you in staying open and at ease
in some ways contribute to this being possible
in some simple ways can you contribute to their happiness safety peacefulness
and freedom so at least they're safe from you
and then to expand that goodwill out into the world more widely
but without closing down
the air on the side of staying open and simple
and in that openness may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
okay