so
warm greetings and welcome to our meditation session
together and
the basic practice we're doing here is mindfulness mindfulness practice and um
yeah i think i've said this recently it's a common enough expression or cliche that
mindfulness is easy what is difficult is remembering to do
it and the idea of staying in the flow
of present moment experience by being aware of it is at the heart of
mindfulness practice and and being aware means many things
maybe people are aware in different ways but there's different different aspects of awareness
and one of the aspects of awareness one quality characteristic
way of being aware is to know is to recognize what is happening in the
moment and the art of mindfulness is to keep
that recognition simple to have to recognize what is obvious
or observable in the moment so it's not a matter of digging and
looking for something special or the underlying cause of something
but when we practice mindfulness practice it's just staying with the obvious what's what appears to us what's
observable in any of our senses perceivable in the moment but then to know it
to recognize it and one of the things you might try on this meditation session
is to emphasize the recognition part and it's often done with this single
word uh if you're breathing in you recognize you recognize it as in so it's not like automatic pilot
it's not like that um you're directing yourself to inhale by saying in it's almost as if
the inhale begins and then because it's perceivable we recognize it inhale or just in
as a shorthand if there's an itch then
don't have to analyze the itch and why it's there and you know and wonder if you have poison
oak it's just to notice itch the simplicity
of recognition so it can be
easy to overlook how powerful it is this simple act of recognition
and it is
hence but in this meditation you might try to see if you can discover how simple an act of recognition can be
and how it supports you in being rooted in the present moment
so if there's a thought not just know your thinking but have a
clear maybe maybe crisp or clear or definitive
recognition oh that almost like you use a sentence that is thinking there is thinking now
it doesn't have to be that long it could just be thinking but the equivalent of that you know like oh i really see
this oh that's what's happening even if it's completely mundane you hear
a sound that's a sound and it's the the fullness or the clarity or the or the
uh all okay how to say that we really give ourselves over
to that recognition something frees up something becomes more spacious
something we're less preoccupied and caught in our concerns we're less in the stream of thinking
again and again and it's like it's like almost like we take a pause to recognize this
we take a pause to recognize the next thing there's no hurry to recognize as many
things as you need to it's more the quality of clear recognition
how does that work for you and how can you do it so it doesn't feel like work it doesn't
feel like it's um a strain to do it it's actually kind of
you feel the benefits of it you feel how it puts you in the present moment more fully uh that's the
task of this meditation and if you find that that doing the exercise is
agitating then you clearly recognize oh that is agitation
and but you recognize it there's a calming in their recognition
there's a spaciousness there's a even a freedom in the clear recognition
it's kind of like oh that's what it is and we make room
and then the next thing that's what it is then it might be the same thing over and over again but clear recognition
so to set the ground for that to assume a meditation posture
may be one that's familiar with you for you
so that the familiarity supports
a welcoming feeling of being here and present
and you might close your eyes
and to take a few of those long deep relaxed breaths
breathing in and relaxing as you exhale
breathing in and settling in to your body as you exhale
letting your breathing return to normal
and relax the shoulders soften
on the exhale softening the shoulder blades
maybe if letting relaxing so the shoulder blades
can roll down the back slide down
relaxing and softening the belly
and then to begin the practice of clear recognition
recognize in the simplest way you can the most direct and obvious way
how you are right now
and recognize it a few times and see if there's something about how you recognize
that's not a duty it's not forced or work
it's simply a very simple act of recognizing pausing
pausing and recognizing almost as an act of generosity
it allows each thing that's recognized to be itself
recognizing how you are in your body
recognizing the predominant sensations of your body as you're here
now
and recognizing the sensations of breathing
and if you use a single word for that recognition
it's a recognition that if you do it kind of clearly and fully
hopefully is a quieting of the thinking mind
not triggering of more thoughts
and continue with your breathing and if something else becomes predominant
recognize it recognizing how it's obvious
observable and in a way that recognition
is beneficial for your meditation one observation after another
if you are involved with the flow of thoughts
you probably are not recognizing the moment
clear recognition
[Music]
and then as we come to the end of the setting
perhaps there can be a clear recognition
of goodwill a clear recognition of a place inside of
you
that's the location for or the source for kindness
friendliness care love compassion
and even if you don't feel it at the moment perhaps you can clearly recognize
the place the location within
a tenderness a gentleness a warmth
and openness
that if you open if you direct that openness and tenderness to the world
perhaps you can see the world with kind eyes
to look upon the world
with a kind regard
generous in your eyesight and considering that we're coming to the
end of the meditation
to aspire to in some way small maybe small maybe
spig some way that on this day
you contribute to the simple welfare and well-being and happiness of
others not in big dramatic ways but maybe just with
simple gestures a smile greeting
an inquiry into how they are into your ability to listen
listen well as they answer may it be that this meditation practice
we do spreads from our meditation community
out into the communities around us in the form of welfare and goodwill for
all beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free and may we contribute to the welfare and
happiness of this world
you
so good day on this monday end of june and
the theme that i want to discussed this week is
clear comprehension the pali word is sam pajana ajana
in this context means to know and uh and the paw of
pajana it's kind of an emphatic prefix so it's kind of like to really
know and some my belief means here means something like
with so with clear knowing with really knowing
and the
and so uh it's an important quality of mindfulness practice
sometimes it's translated as clear comprehension sometimes clear knowing clear recognition
the clear being the emphatic kind of idea behind it and um but to really know and
uh it's part of the art of mindfulness is to learn the power of recognition
in some cultures i've been to that people won't talk tell each other
tell other people strangers their birth name they have another name kind of like a nickname that they go by
because it said that their their birth name is has some there's some power to it and if you give
it too easily to other people then somehow they can have power of you or something it's something you want to
be very careful for the and sometimes many of us can have
the experience of the english expression is um to name something i'd like to name
something or you know it's just naming what's
naming what's happening is to very simply describe or characterize what's
happening the moment other people aren't noticing and ah maybe oh that's what's happening oh i see
that's how it is and uh sometimes we do that for ourselves i've kind of felt
off sometimes and i didn't know quite why i felt off or something was quite not quite right
and then i recognized at some point i recognized that i was
sad about something and in recognizing the sadness oh that's what's happening i'm sad and with
this with their clear recognitions like the clouds parted and something becomes obvious and clear and
the kind of the way in which things are cloudy or murky uh clears up oh that's what's happening
and so mindfulness practice involves two primary attentional faculties
and and others as well but the two primary ones is sati and sampajana
and sati which is often translated as mindfulness i think it's maybe more useful to
translate it as awareness and some pajama as clear recognition
and that mindfulness practice is the combination of those two to be really present have a sense of
really a present moment awareness present moment attunement uh to being aware of what's
happening here and now so ability to receive to perceive for the senses sense doors to
be open so the senses the eyes the ears the nose the tongue the tactile senses
and also the mind door is all open so that we can receive
what's going on or perceive what's going on in a way that is not so thoughtful it
doesn't necessarily involve recognition it's almost like pre-recognition just the experience being with the experience
that's sati and uh and then the clear recognition is the
clear knowing of what that is and now the combination of those two is
what didn't i think often in the modern definitions of mindfulness are presented
um you know so that sometimes what's called clear recognition knowing
what's happening in a non-reactive way is often called mindfulness sati but
it's closer to this thing called sampajana clear recognition
and as i said in the guided meditation it's a really or implied at least a very invaluable
art to learn how to uh call forth our capacity to clearly
recognize uh even what is most obvious and and sometimes it can be dismissed
it's easy to be dismissive of what's obvious like that in-breath that out breath that we feel tingling or warm in our
body these are little details that seem like they don't warrant much attention
but what's warrants that warren's attention and engagement is this capacity we have
to clearly recognize where the clear recognition
is closely related to freedom freedom from preoccupation freedom from
reactivity freedom from closing down around something because we that recognition is kind of a bias a
judgment but rather the recognition is opening um to possibility opening to being
present and so this is the art of figuring out the art of recognition
so it's very very simple so uh to recognize that i feel
i feel warm and tingly and just to to recognize it not with a lot of
baggage and association of what it means but to recognize it as a kind of like pausing to open to
experience it more oh warm and tingly what's that like ah
it's like that um seeing like right now i'm seeing the camera
that you're all behind and and so there's a moment of seeing of
recognition that i've been here now for you know over half an hour kind of looking in the direction at
times with the camera but until this moment i hadn't really clearly recognized it it's like
oh so it stands out a little bit in highlight and it's more like oh look at that as
opposed to oh no the camera or something so oh it's a camera and then i have a
monitor in front of underneath it so i can see what's happening here on the chats and stuff so so you know i see the
light and the color and and things and um and now i feel thirsty so to clearly
recognize the thirst and and then maybe do something about it
and so there's a story in my book the book of
stories called the monastery within and it's a story about a very famous
sage who lives deep deep in the mountains and there's no roads that take you there
and just some trails mountain trails and the person seems to ha has a reputation
of having just the right thing for everybody if you go tell this person your troubles and
your challenges and uh he seems to always have the right everyone leaves satisfied like that was
perfect for me and and um this you know you must have great
intuition great understanding and so people would do the trick it sometimes would take three days of hiking into the mountains
and three days out and because people some people were really desperate to find out you know support help for their challenges in
their life they made that trek and when they found him the the sage
would sit and listen sometimes they'd listen for 15 minutes sometimes an hour or
something hours as people kind of unloaded and told the stories that they were concerned with and the sage didn't say
much but uh just took it all in and then at some point the sage
the person would stop talking and then sage would nod and okay indicated this age now really
wanted to think deeply about this and really reflect and come come up with some really wise thing
but before before uh he would say his words there was always a requirement that the
person who was asking for support guidance whatever he said
would not be told to anyone else so just very personal for that person
and it turns out the person always said the same thing to everyone
it's the same thing and that's the thing that he said we always said
what are you not paying attention to what are you not recognizing and then
people some people are often disappointed that's what he has to say but okay gave him the benefit of the doubt and
then they leave but they had to spend three days hiking out of the mountain and it would echo in their mind
what are you not recognizing and over those three days all kinds of
possibility all kinds of things they hadn't been noticing came up and came up and by the time they
came out of the mountains they were transformed they had received something powerful that had changed them
for the better so this power of recognition
to really when we sit and meditate to clearly not only be present
for the experience but to recognize it um and to do it in a way that's relaxing
that's calming as opposed to agitating but do it in a way that is so clear that we're
no longer being swept along in the mind stream of thoughts or we're no longer admired or absorbed
in the world of emotions it's almost like taking a step back out of the
mud out of the mire out of the preoccupation stepping
out of it and looking back at it and saying oh preoccupation thinking oh this
is thinking or anger sadness this is anger this is sadness
and and the art of is is to kind of explore and use the word the recognition until you really feel
the kind of freedom the kind of separation not aloofness not kind of distance
but separations were not caught in something the release and then and then
then mindfulness uh the awareness that being present has a whole different quality of
of of of movement and then mindfulness can do its work it
can unfold best when we're not kind of lost in the stream of thought or stream
of emotion so clear recognition that's the theme for this week and i'll talk about different aspects of
clear recognition and for these next 24 hours you might experiment
with uh seeing if you can discover some of the power of recognition of how it's supportive
and helpful and look how you can recognize what's happening even what's obvious even what you already know
but you haven't really recognized it what it's like to really stop pause and recognize
and if you care too you could also explore carry with you the sages
question what are you not recognizing and see if
that's interesting for you so thank you all very much
and i look forward to this week together with you
you