so good day and uh it's actually feel quite wonderful to be
here with you all and not only is there an opportunity to
meditate and talk about the dharma it's also remarkable to
feel the good will and the warmth and the gratitude that uh comes through the chat
and i'm sure represents many other people who don't participate in the chat
and for all of us to be sharing in this together quite remarkable and maybe it's
almost uh certainly adds the richness of the meditation we do to feel like
we're doing it in such a friendly community so thank you very much
and um
when doing meditation it's really best not to try to be a perfectionist
any attempt at perfection probably goes in the opposite direction
it makes it harder we strain more and maybe it gets more brittle
and i think that the idea is to be at ease with how things are
not how we think they're supposed to be to be at ease with how things are not
with what we think they're supposed to be and to have that and then and to have
that ease not be perfect so that not looking for perfect ease and what
this means is that we're partly
learning to hold [Music]
ourselves be mindful of ourselves without it needing to be all one way
but we have an ease with holding things together that are maybe some good and some not so
good some some pleasant some not pleasant some uh you know what we think this what we is
what's happening is what we think is supposed to be happening what's happening is not what we think was happening all these things can co-exist so for
example people associate meditation with a quiet mind not thinking so much or not
thinking at all and so people some people that are trying to have that no thinking state
i think it's better to be at ease with the mind that thinks certainly it's nice to let go of
thoughts and quiet the mind and it's nice to come to a place where the mind is not thinking so much
but even better is not to be disturbed by your thoughts and to be at ease with them and
in that way it's possible to let some thinking just recede into the background
and rather than being preoccupied by with the idea of having no thoughts at all
it's um it's uh we could just um let some you know some thinking can just
go on in the background and we can kind of know what we're thinking or maybe not as long as
in the foreground we're just staying with the breathing or staying with our present moment experience and
so these two can coexist and uh and so but it when thinking comes
into the foreground then we learn to practice with it but even then the idea is to be at ease with
it and the same with uh discomforts in the body some people have like a homing
instinct uh maybe because of fear to just kind of really tune into
uncomfortable painful sensations the body be worried concerned um but you know and expecting they're
supposed to be completely comfortable all the time but also comfort and uncomfortability
can co-exist and sometimes it's just fine to have a certain
level of pain discomfort also be kind of in the background or just be part of the overall environment
and not needing to zero in on it and focus on it and that allows us to kind of open up
and focus on all this allows us to then gently focus on what is
onward leading what is really supportive of us to develop the meditation further it's
supportive to focus on that part of our experience where we're not thinking a lot where we're feeling and quietly calmly
feeling the experience letting the thoughts be in the background at some point in meditation
it's onward leading um to uh to become aware of the pleasant
sensations that um they're not there because of some we're getting you know some wonderful ex
sensual experience but rather uh as we settle as we settle and feel
more content here more then then we feel uh kind of the meditative
contentment meditative comfort and pleasant pleasantness of the experience and that is a useful
thing to open to and in the background there might be discomfort but if it can just be in the
background don't worry about it too much and gently open to the pleasant to the
meditative pleasure joy contentment that might be there or the feeling of rightness the feeling
of this is good to be here so there's a wide range of kind of
pleasant enjoyable or right feelings that might come as we meditate
and to open to those and let them spread or i like the notion of just opening the body to them and
so they they fill us more or they expand more
so taking a meditation posture and gently closing your eyes
and and kind of settling into your posture
and here also we don't want perfection with a posture i like the expression just good enough
just good enough for you to be here and settle settling in
and then if you can set yourself at ease
set yourself at ease in your body
and that can mean to be easy be easy with what's happening in your
body ease up a bit around the body
and then as you exhale settle and relax the body further
and then set yourself at ease in your heart in your emotional life
let yourself be easy with whatever feelings and emotions you might have
ease up on them a bit not to make them go away or make them different but ease up
be easy with it all an easy
relationship
and then set yourself at ease in your mind with the things you're thinking about or
concerned with see if you can let yourself be easy
with the activities of your mind
easing up the pressure easing up the heaviness the contraction
around the concerns
and then as you exhale to relax your emotional
being relax and soften in your heart
as you exhale relax and soften in the thinking mind
maybe the notion that you're making lots of space for your thinking mind
so you start feeling the peacefulness or the calmness of the space around it
and then settling into your body and feeling your body
globally in whatever easy way there's
maybe a broad awareness baby awareness that gently slowly
roams around the body to touch into things to be aware of the body
as you exhale softening the shoulders
as you exhale softening the belly
as you exhale settling in to your body your posture your place
here
and then to if it's possible if it's available
perhaps you can feel some modicum of contentment
or allow yourself yourself to feel some degree of contentment
to just be sitting here quietly peacefully
aware of whatever is here for you whether it's comfortable or
uncomfortable pleasant or unpleasant
it's very significant and valuable to be aware of how things are
and to be content with just this opportunity to be quiet enough
to be aware of it all pleasant and unpleasant
difficult and easy it's all okay just to be here aware
maybe letting go of perfection that things have to be just so
and then feeling your breathing more fully
being at ease with whatever way you're
breathing being easy with your breath even if it's labored or tight
be easy ease up
not needing the breathing to be perfect it's okay for it to be unpleasant
if you're feeling it
it's okay for it to be pleasant if you know it
and maybe there's a little bit of both with breathing
as you go through the cycles of in-breath and out-breath some of the experiences of breathing a
little bit more pleasant some are a little more
unpleasant
offering yourself the gift of knowing just knowing how it is and just knowing
is enough as you go through the cycle of in and out expanding and contracting
inhaling and exhaling
settling in to breathing
and in the breathing itself as you exhale relax
and let go soften go with the releasing
like you would let go of at the top of a slide just like to slide down
let go with the exhale sliding down the
length of the exhale
let go
and then as you inhale receive the full inhale
allow your body space to breathe in
and then as you're breathing breathe with whatever is
pleasant letting the unpleasant be there but not focusing on it so much
any feelings of contentment or comfort or pleasure
delight or joy happiness or well-being
maybe a subtle glow or a subtle warmth or a brightness
tingling or vibration
or maybe a pleasant energy that seems to come along with breathing through the
body
sliding down the exhale allowing for the inhale
sliding down what is pleasant
allowing for what is pleasant the joy the happiness well-being
letting the thinking mind become quieter so you can better feel the goodness of
just being here breathing
allowing that goodness the pleasure to fill you to spread throughout everywhere
even the places where there that are uncomfortable let those be touched and filled
by whatever degree of well-being that might come meditating
so as we sit here to remember that things don't have to be
all one way or we don't have to focus on just one aspect of our experience
there's a way in which we can be at ease and inclusive of all of it the pleasant and the
unpleasant but then open more to the pleasant side
not at the exclusion of what's difficult but to better more bowel in a more
balanced way to hold it and be with it
and if we turn our attention now to the suffering of the world suffering of people you know and
suffering of this covet time and
so many people challenged
there can be a strong tendency to focus on the suffering
exclusively to feel the suffering the pain of the world or of other people
and think that caring about it means you have to really focus on it exclusively
i believe that compassion is richer fuller
more compassionate if it doesn't exclusively focus on
the suffering but realize there's always more there's
always the pleasant the non-suffering that's happening at the same time
and to include what is good and what is
healthy and has sense of well-being to it or
goodness in it and to have a broader field of attention
so we the suffering can be held together with or inside of
a sense of well-being or sense of subtleness or ease
and so we can better recognize that the people were thinking about or focused on
they're more than just suffering people
and you are more than someone who just focuses on suffering
there's a wider context in that wider context of well-being and
wellness and not wellness allows compassion to be fuller and
more penetrating and more pointing to the end of suffering
so as we end this meditation now may it be that our ability to be
inclusive of it all allow us to meet the suffering of the
world with greater care and kindness and compassion
may it be that the meditation we do is a direct support for us to enter the
world with compassion for all
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
you