okay so we'll go ahead and get started nice to see everyone there
welcome so just settling in for
today's meditation yesterday we talked about
four qualities that are the basis of spiritual friendship
and are also forms of inner wealth and so i'm going to pick out one of
those today to provide some of the background for our
meditation at the beginning and then we'll settle in again with a period of silence
so we're going to focus on generosity but first let's just
begin by settling in closing the eyes
allowing the attention to come inward
sensing the posture that you're sitting in or maybe lying down in
and just checking in that you're in a balanced posture
if you're sitting upright it's one where you don't have to exert a lot of effort
the body feels naturally upright and straight
relaxed if you're lying down you can still have
a sense of straightness in the body balance in whatever posture you're lying
down in
it can help to sense where you're sitting
what's supporting you and just you know even rocking back and forth a little bit or forward and back
just to find that middle point where you're the most balanced that you
can be in this posture
you can even think of resting in your sitting spot
as a way of giving yourself to the support
instead of trying somehow to do it all ourselves hold ourselves up
give your weight to what you're sitting on and ultimately to the earth
let it support you
and then softening into this balanced posture
softening the eyes and the eye sockets often looking at a screen you can get a
little tense in the eyes
even softening behind the eyes as if we could relax
a muscle in the head
relax the brain
softening the neck and letting the shoulders drop
releasing down the arms and hands
and just inviting some openness through the chest and the belly area
[Music] checking in while you're there if you
have any sense of tension
make background emotions just to know how you are
inviting some eaves
i'm releasing any bracing in the legs
just letting the legs be natural the muscle's soft
letting the in-breath encourage a straightening
of the central part of the body and letting the out breath encourage a
softening forward way around that straight center
just in a gentle way
so i'm going to drop in a short quote from the
tsutas from buddhist teachings
and the invitation is just to let it resonate inside like
ripples in water or like an echo and there will be
some ripple and then you can just let it fade out naturally and go back to the
breath or the body
so the buddha said if beings knew as i know
the results of giving and sharing [Music] they would not eat without having given
even if it were their last morsel their last mouthful they would not eat without
having shared it if there were someone to share it with
and as it fades out just turning the mindfulness back to the breath
the body
so we'll have two more brief connections with generosity
and the second one is just a simple reflection
in the mind so i'll ask you to recall
a time of simple unentangled giving
when you were able to give something just simply it was easy it was natural
it flowed i'll just remember that time and how it
was
you could let images arise in your mind
or a recollection of the feeling you had or how the person looked when you gave
something
and maybe notice how it brings some joy into the mind
and you can also let that fade away let the mind settle back into
your usual mindfulness
and now the invitation is to feel directly and deeply into the
body how it is when the mind is imbued with
the quality of generosity so you can re-evoke memory
or you can recall the quote
that beings would not eat their last morsel without giving
if there were someone to share it with
and really take that feeling deeply into the body where we have the
direct experience of a body and mind imbued with
generosity and rest in that feeling
what is the energy of generosity like
does it move
does it have lightness heaviness
certain location [Music] does it extend outside the body
there are no expected answers to this just
getting to know that quality
through our own experience
so we've encountered this quality of generosity through
hearing the teaching on it through
reflecting thinking about how that matches our own
experience through directly sensing
that quality in the mind the experience of it
these are different ways to encounter equality like generosity
so now we'll have a period of silence sitting for a little while
just allowing it to resonate settle out move into your usual mindfulness
practice
foreign
so as we continue to sit for a few more minutes
we may consider how wholesome qualities
feel in the body in the mind
how even the thought you know thinking the thing that we
think isn't so good during meditation but even thinking about wholesome
qualities has a certain impact on the body
different from thoughts that are
less good
thoughts of generosity have an easier impact on the body than
thoughts of anger for example
and how even hearing passively hearing a quote about
a wholesome quality something that we might resonate with
impacts the mind-body system so we can start to be
wise maybe sensing internally how these
wholesome qualities feel so that when we're doing actions out in
our life acts of giving [Music] or more neutral acts of speaking or
preparing food walking around we can notice
how that feels in the mind and the body so that we can keep our
mind directed well throughout the day
and also in a more nuanced way if we are
giving something or sharing something there are ways that we can
do that from a mind that isn't totally wholesome
for example it's possible to give out of fear or give out of a sense of duty or
obligation with some heaviness and we'd be able to feel that
we would be able to feel that it was different from that very simple unentangled giving that i asked you to
remember so our direct experience can also
help us throughout the day
to do things from the most wholesome intention that's available at that moment
it's a very practical skill
so this might be an interesting thing to remember as you go forward today is
how wholesomeness feels and how just tuning into that naturally
quietly simply can help others
through the way that you talk and speak and hear and act
always helpful to include that internal dimension when we can
[Music]
hmm
okay so today we are continuing
with the dharma of uncommon lists and so that means that today we will
explore a list of three and
i want to talk about the three kinds of wisdom that are mentioned in the suttas
wisdom is such an important quality in the buddhist buddhist teachings that maybe it's not surprising that it's
considered multi-dimensional and
these three are sometimes mentioned in dharma talks but not often in much
detail and usually the first two of them are minimized
but i like to think of these three kinds of wisdom as forming a kind of ecology in the heart
and mind where we need each one to support the others
so all three are important there is one that of course is more liberating than the others that's why
the other two get minimized but i see them as an ecology that are that are all of them should be there
so the first is called the wisdom of hearing or listening
so this is a kind of understanding or wisdom that comes from
listening listening to teachings generally so it's good to
listen to things that are worth listening to for at least part of our day
so you know that means here in the dharma we can listen to audio dharma
we can come to talks like this in these days i think listening probably
includes reading where we take things in also through the linguistic part of our
mind um and we can also maybe include talking with wise friends as i'm hearing
listening to what they say so sometimes people want to discount the
wisdom of hearing or listening as you know just the first step you know
but nonetheless hearing the dharma is actually listed as one of the factors
for reaching the first stage of awakening it said that we need wise attention and
the voice of another so i assume that means we need to hear the dharma most of
us so this form of wisdom is called
sutamaya panya panya being the word for wisdom and then
suta that's not the teachings the sutas that's s-u-t-t-a
this is s-u-t-a it's a different word and it it means what is heard
so suta means what is heard and in other contexts this word suta
is used to mean learning or one who has learned
so it has to do also with learning i think that's kind of interesting because
anything that involves thinking tends to get short shrift in the dharma
world and certainly it's true that we you know spending a lot of time thinking on the
cushion is distracting but across the teachings it would be hard to ignore that the buddha did
emphasize the importance of learning and so i want a quote from a suta that
talks about learning as a form of wealth it says this way
and what is the wealth of learning here a noble disciple has learned much
remembers what they have learned and accumulates what they have learned those teachings that are good in the
beginning good in the middle and good in the end with the right meaning and phrasing which proclaim the perfectly
complete and pure spiritual life such teachings as these they have
learned much of retained in mind recited verbally mentally investigated and
penetrated well by view so that's kind of a lot