hello and welcome to happier everyone dear sangha lovely to be with you i'm
happy already just sitting in community sitting in community both the zoom
community youtube community and the sangha leader
you will join us on audiodharma
so [Music] for today
the invitation is to consider that metta could be explored in so many different
ways of course the practice of meta cultivating loving kindness as
many of you have witnessed both with happy hour so many different ways i
explore it i offer it in creative ways as well as diana offers it
and also different teachers so there's so many different ways there's not one way to practice metta
and sometimes creativity is a good thing and sometimes being settled in just the
continuity of breath body the the utterances the phrases might be helpful
so using our judgment using our clarity
um we can tell we can discern actually the word i want to use isn't judgment is
discernment i think that's a better word here because judgment can be misconstrued as judgment and self-judgment but
discernment using clear comprehension some pagania
discernment we can discern what is the appropriate way
perhaps for a given time to which tool in the tool bag
to to use for both different practices and different practices of metta so the
particular practice that i want to to highlight tonight is meta
as non-doing interesting what does she mean meta as
non-doing how can non-doing be meta it can be so
in the following way so sometimes and again it really depends on
our discernment discerning what is appropriate so
so think of times when you've been with a friend perhaps
and maybe the friend has been upset or we're suffering and um
[Music] and all they want you to do is for you to listen
just hold presents listen just hold presence with patience with metta with care
not to rush it to give him advice to make it better to make it go away because sometimes that
impulse to make it go away is actually our own fear
our own fear of discomfort because when somebody else is uncomfortable it can make us uncomfortable so notice
if that's the reason like okay jumping to do something instead of first the non-doing
the meta of non-doing the meta of holding space
similarly for ourselves there are times that maybe a
challenge a difficulty comes up in the body in the mind in the heart let's say
it's a challenging emotion and
something and and notice if the mind wants to whip up active meta active meta
may you be well maybe happy maybe well make it go away make it all better
see if there is if there might be sometimes
this this conflictual relationship make it go away this is not good this is bad
this is so there's so much doing there's so much forcing and i hear that's from so many
practitioners that they discover that after a while they've been practicing meta that they're they've been perhaps
doing jackhammer meta or or hammer metals like they're just
hammering this difficulty away like okay
so it's it's good to be aware to know with
discernment what is appropriate sometimes it is appropriate to just be
to just be with what is give it space don't push it force it
away the same way that if there's a little child crying
um you know say okay stop stop it's uh it's fine it's it stop stop crying like it's okay sweetie it's okay you hold
them you hold them you can't be rushed you hold them
it's the meta that shows up with patience with non-doing with clear awareness clear presence
so i said plenty that's the frame for today's practice
so let's do some non-doing together
let's let's non-do together let's begin
landing releasing
in this body and this breath nowhere to go nothing to do in this
moment opening up
opening up to awareness
just holding presence
awareness
the sensations this body the breath
not doing the breath or the breathing
relax let the breathing unfold on its own the body knows how to breathe
don't get in the way
as if you were thawing as if your body was thawing
ah
awareness
permeating through the body and the breath
knowing simply knowing
whatever is arising in this moment
settling the breath with the body
awareness
expansively holding the entire body
the breath whatever's pleasant unpleasant thoughts are rising and passing
ah it can all be can all be
awareness patient kind expansive
if you find the mind as resting on thoughts entangled in
thoughts that's okay that's okay
let whatever is arising whatever thought entanglement
sadness memory dukkha whatever it might be let it be clearly known
with kindness oh yes yes this this too this too is arising in this moment
let it be held in kind awareness doesn't have to go
away it doesn't have to be jackhammered away
kind awareness can be soothing expansive just enough
plenty
and you may come back to this realization
to this kind awareness rekindle it a hundred times it's okay do it every
time smilingly it's not a problem it's the bare bones of this practice
it's okay give thanks every time you come back
smilingly because after all
you never leave it's just the metaphor it's always here
ready to be recognized to be invoked
let it be a non-doing non-effortful
invocation recognition it's just there
it's just here
kindly spaciously knowing
if judgmental thoughts doubting thoughts arise i don't know what i'm doing
maybe simply know this
thought with kindness ah shine the light
shine the light of kind awareness ah
give it space it's a lot of space
for it to just be known
it's like this
see if this way of kind awareness practice
gentle non-forced can be nourishing
with a heart and mind whatever is painful or difficult right
now it can hold it without pushing it away or falling into
it
so
this non-doing meta could also be expressed
with an inner smile just holding
knowing experience with good will of smile friendliness
you can also wear an outer smile to encourage an inner smile
as if you are sitting in space spacious kindness
sphere everything your body your breath
thoughts everything is held
in this kind awareness
a whole experience that is known
and this moment is okay held with mental
doesn't need to be pushed away
now turning the practice outward
imagining you're with a friend maybe someone from this saga
they want you to just be present old present just listen
with kindness with care
this moment it's not for you to fix it and just
hold presents with menta with care with good will
with patience
maybe you're breathing mental with every breath for them maybe you say the phrases for them it's
your choice see what feels right
this
you're invited to invite more friends
more dear beings
in your circle of meta a holding presence
and for the last minutes of this practice period
see if you can open up a sense of holding presence with meta
with care with knowing with awareness not turning away
for the world
and notice if this feels similar in some ways to the practice of equanimity for
you or different
if it gets too heady you can drop that comparison just open it up
for all beings
may all beings everywhere
be safe
may they be well
may they have ease
[Music]
thank you for this practice for your practice
so
way of practicing this met us holding presence non-doing
can be very healing and soothing um you can also
also for some for many different times can also be not having enough of an
anchor not having the phrases as an anchor not having the
other being so much as an anchor so so mind can can wander a little more but
it's okay it's all held it's all okay it's all okay so it's just a different way of practicing
um so if your experience was that oh yeah the mind was a little more distracted and
that's okay that's a part of this way of practicing it comes with this more open
spacious awareness of being
so we have time for reflections
questions comments complaints it's all okay it's all
welcome smiling at all everything is welcome so you're welcome
to raise your zoom hand if you like or if it's typed in chat if it's only to me
i'll only read your your uh your reflection and if it's time to everyone then
i'll read your name also
so and also please know that when you offer your
reflection what you discovered or the question what was challenging
it's of benefit it's it's your offering to serve others to other practitioners
not from place of ego hey here see my practice it's not that it's like hell here i offer this
to the altar of of this community may it be of service to others what i discovered or
what was challenging for me
reflections coming on youtube appreciation thank you all
and gratitude for this peace filled embracing practice
thank you richard
many more reflections questions about this practice before we turn in
turn to our practice oh debra says i think this is the best
i've felt all day oh the power of your practice the power of meta
it's lovely thanks for sharing that
yeah as i read your reflection and as i tune in like oh yeah me too i feel
calm and happy and restored i had a really really full busy day
and now it's oh yes ah smiling
sarah says i felt like i could slow everything down which was very calming
oh lovely nice
practicing your super powers nicholas i missed nicholas
felt a sense of generosity giving each experience the gift of being known
beautiful love that sense of generosity giving each
experience the gift of being known beautiful oh i'm so inspired by all of your
practice everyone all your reflections those who are sharing and those who are not sharing and just hanging in here
with however it was ups and downs of it
one more reflection i felt like i could let go of the effort of preventing my heart from being hurt
ah what an insight
the effort the effort of preventing your heart from being hurt yeah so so much effort
and metta can be so calming soothing effortless beautiful
another reflection very calming yeah meta has this kind of impact right just
calming soothing nourishing
[Music] nice
and you're quiet i haven't seen any any zoom hands for
speaking of course you're welcome to
and if not that's okay
and susan it's nice to sit with you also tonight joining on youtube lovely
all right we have neil please whoops yes there you go
so i found this to be very soothing um
all right i know you weren't here last night but dawn did something on
loving interest um which you know this seemed to dovetail with that you know just
wonderfully um it's sort of you know i found you know really on both
nights just you know just you know just to be able
to sit there and watch what was happening and you know you know be okay with it
you know at one point in time i'm like oh yeah that's a version you know and i was just like you know
aversing or whatever the ing form of of that is you know and i just you know
it was not really an experience i can recall having had before um you know it was
you know you know and it yeah it was very soothing and lovely and yeah
thank you thank you neil beautiful and thank you so much for sharing that insight in
particular this new experience of oh aversion is here oh yes for a version to be known
instead of more evolution on top of a version yay what an opening what an opening thank
you for sharing that beautiful yeah deborah please
i uh i haven't done a lot of loving-kindness meditation or at least
for a long time and so tonight i was really present to um how the giving is off is also
receiving and how i was just sort of i don't know delighted might be
too strong it's not exactly what i was but anyway i was somewhat delighted
at just thinking of all these people as i went through
and some of them especially with covet you know some of them i haven't talked with or seen and
um yeah so anyway there was just this yeah the gift of it
not just the soothing it was very soothing and very calming as i said earlier and i feel really
you know wonderful now but there was a gift of uh just giving
and even the heart kept opening and yeah yeah even the difficult people yeah
beautiful beautiful thanks so much for sharing that deborah minta is a gift of giving receiving i'm
so grateful that you verbalize that broad that's that into the
the space it is it feels like oh we're giving but it's not a giving it's a giving receiving it's it's
a and it's a non-doing giving and receiving in a way it can enter another space lovely thank you and claire will
make this last quick um reflection before we go into groups please
sorry i actually texted you or chatted with you but that's okay i was just commenting i
i'm having some health issues and the calm and the peacefulness of this is was
absolutely perfect for soothing my body
letting it rest it's a perfect medicine
thanks for sharing that yeah i'm delighted to hear that yeah me too
it's um so so happy to hear that thank you claire
ah you're getting thumbs up on that too it's beautiful so dear ones
let's turn to hold space old
non-doing meta filled aware space for each other
in small groups so small groups of roughly size three
and we'll start with 15 seconds of silent meta take care of yourselves
take care of each other and
yeah let's see what arises as you hold space for yourselves and each other the rooms
are created here we go
welcome back everyone we've got a couple of minutes for any reflections
uh observations that might have arisen from practicing in small groups small sangha
together so don't be shy you can raise your hand or type in chat
if you haven't spoken or shared or if you're new would love to hear from you
was it helpful to discuss with others jerry i do see your hand i usually don't
but let's see if i okay there can i mute yourself
uh there we go so i we were at the end of the small group um talking about how
we're getting uh increasingly very attached to this sangha and uh
very nurtured and uh i look forward each night to
going on line for my sake it was just before 10 here
in the east coast so it's a nice way to go to bed and for those who are just
beginning their evening a nice way to set the evening away from work so that was the comment
oh thanks for sharing that jerry thank you so much for sharing that
um yeah the the experience for you and and and people in your group
and i feel the same for this the sangha is such a gift it's such a gift really
we it's a gift we give and we receive as as deborah was talking earlier about the gift of meta
giving and receiving this this song i feel the same our participation is a gift to others is a
gift to ourselves we give and we receive myself included so with that beautiful
note thank you jerry i thank you all for your practice for your wholehearted
practice and showing up for yourself for one another may all beings including
ourselves be happy may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you all