so good morning good day
and here we are here you are in your place
and the idea is to kind of be definitively clearly
in the here that you are meditation is to rest here
established here now
and in that this week has been the week of touching into the role of imagination
and meditation one of the similes the buddha uses for
the state of clarity that
gives rise to awakening or that it kind of represents maybe
awakening is that of a clear
very clear lake here in the mountains in california there are some very clear alpine lakes
where you can look down into the water quite far and see clearly what's on the bottom
and uh so a very clear lake and a person who stands on the edge of
that lake the buddha says can look into that lake and see the fish swimming around can see
the pebbles the little shellfish that might be there and
each thing stands out distinctly but these things each thing is kind of swimming or
existing in this a context of domain
this space of clear water
and the water is often a symbol for awakening or the awakening but the mind for awareness
and and so the awareness that becomes clear
and so clear like this clear mountain lake in which all things can be seen but the
idea of standing on the the edge of the lake looking in the fish and the little rocks
the person who's looking is not interfering with anything it's not being foreign against anything
particularly just kind of just letting each thing be independent and free
and i love this idea because there's such a strong emphasis or strong tendency for people to look at
buddhist practice their own experience in meditation through the lens of me myself and mine
in my experience what i have to do and all this and and uh and so then you know the
ideas and the liberation means i will become liberated uh
look at me i'm liberated i'm free another way of understanding it which is just as valid
is that as we become free we are liberating everything else
from us and that way liberation awakening is a gift we give to
everything where everything has become free of our attachment our clinging our expectations our
judgments all the stuff that we put on top of it and uh and so they're standing on the
lake edge of the lake and looking in the clear water the fish the rocks the shell shellfish
whatever's there is allowed to be theirs free of our entanglement or trying to grab it or
do something with it so that kind of clarity of mind that allows
each thing gives each thing its freedom its independence every experience in meditation
has this permission to be there provided it's seen in clarity
and so that's the kind of the key thing
recognized clearly so it's possible to be very foggy in one's mind
confused but that can be known clearly i'm foggy this is fogginess fogginess is
known this is chaos confusion chaos is known
confusion is recognized oh so um
so the um and so that's kind of the vision the
imaginational vision that the buddha is giving of where we're going with mindfulness practice
and it's not so much an experience of bliss and joy and happiness which is the subject right now in the
series of anapanasati but rather it's clarity
so with that as a background image for this meditation
to assume a meditation posture and to
gently close your eyes
and taking a deep breath in in a long exhale
and exhale that you relax your body
as if relax as if
you're draining out all the mud in the lake
as if there's a little outlet to the edge of the lake where the
mud can just drain away so as you relax your shoulders
let the tension drain away
as you soften your belly on the exhale the tensions of your belly
drain away
whatever attention you can easily let go of or relax let it drain away so you have
room within for clarity for seeing
as if you're making your body a receptacle
for clear kind of an empty receptacle empty of tension
so it can be the
the abode of clarity
letting your breathing return to normal
and taking a few moments as you exhale
to drain away the tensions or pressures in your mind the area of your brain
any tension in the forehead or in the temples
even any any little bit of contraction
that has a location for awareness
it's okay to have a location but the contraction associated with is not necessary
as you exhale let it drain away
and then to settle in here more fully in the body
entering into your body
regardless of how much comfort or discomfort you have in
your body from the inside out
that you your body is the buddha's body
certainly you're having a lot of experiences that he had when he meditated
certainly not all of them but the basic physical experience of the body
from the inside out your buddha body
to settle in be present here
and within this body to become aware of your breathing
regardless how you're breathing the buddha certainly breathed like you
at some point or other some of the same sensations you're experiencing
the buddha felt from within
here you are your buddha body breathing in and breathing out
and then
searching around in your mind or in your awareness
to find where and how can your awareness your mindfulness of
breathing have some degree of clarity
the clarity of standing on the edge of a lake looking in
without interfering with anything allowing things to be as they are
each things in its simplicity
nothing to do nothing to change
except have clear seeing
of the body breathing
and whatever else arises that's compelling
clear seeing clear knowing this is happening
this is what is recognized
reach it with each in-breath and each out-breath
the mud and the lake settle and gradually
there's more clarity
about what's happening in the moment here and now breathing
breathing in a vast expanse of awareness
so
[Music]
when we can let go of our preoccupations
it's kind of like emptying the lake of
debris and bud
and it makes us a vesicle for clarity kind of like it helps us become
gloriously empty spacious open
and then where there's space and openness for there to be well-being
is in room for gladness joy delight happiness
when the mind is crowded and claustrophobic with anxiety and thoughts and concerns
there's no room for well-being and joy
letting your tensions and preoccupations drain away
and give room for whatever well-being is here for you now
and with whatever embodiment that's available for you
feel the embodiment of well-being in whatever way it is for you however
small the embodiment of contentment
stillness calm
and breathe with the well-being
as if the well-being
shows the mind that it's okay to relax and dwell in clarity
clearly recognizing here
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to open and extend your well-being
in your consideration contemplation of the world around you
the people you know people you know about and the many
people you don't
and to sit here for a little few seconds as if you can share your well-being
with them whatever however small it might be
as if you're a little bit like a heater that's spreading its heat outwards to
the world around it so if you can sit content in your well-being
and open it to the world imagine that you're warming up the world
with well-being
and consider how wonderful it would be if in fact your well-being one way or
other known or unknown could reach and touch all the beings of
this world
may it be that the practice of meditation this this day
is a condition for bringing welfare and happiness
to beings everywhere may the goodness and merit of this
practice be dedicated to the happiness well-being
joy peace and freedom of all beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings
be peaceful
may all beings be free
you