so um
what i had in mind to share today
tonight
um is that i finished
a chanting retreat last week
there was still quite a lot of energy
reverberating in me
from this chanting retreat
so i thought i'd share some reflections
on one of the things
that stood out for me that is
taking refuge in the buddha
dharma and sangha
and that is often called the triple jam
some of you probably know this and then
probably have done this multiple times
and i just want to um maybe just chant
to this apolly chant
right now for everyone and
maybe share a little reflection about
the sense of taking refuges
in the buddha dharma and sangha
and so the pali chant goes like this
[Music]
uh
and it often times get translated as
i take refuge in the buddha
i take refuge in the dharma
and i take refuge in the sangha
and this um the typical form
is to chant this three times
and so on as a chanting retreat
and we chanted this multiple times
and taking those refugees are often done
formally
in a ceremony when one commits
to become a buddhist
to walk the dharma path
a teacher may initiate the ceremony
enchanting this refugees
taking refugees is part of the ceremony
and for me when i did this
ceremony a long time ago
i i felt like a turning point in my life
i felt some deep sense of sense of
surrendering
into this dermal path
and so nowadays uh in many
dharma centers or retreat centers in
particular
i know in inside retreat center our
retreat center here
in scotts valley california
usually at the beginning of the retreat
and the group
would initiate the whole retreat process
by taking refugees in the buddha dharma
and sangha
together in monastic settings
and many lay buddhist communities
take refugees very often sometimes on
daily basis
so what does this really mean taking
refuge
in the buddha dharma and sangha
it's quite worth reflecting um
for me i was i was i feel like i'm
very fond of the chinese translation
of buddha gancia me this polychant
in particular on the chinese translation
of ganciami
is that of return and
rely and so under
a chinese version of
taking refuge is something like this
and to the to the buddha i return
and rely to the sun
to the dharma i return and rely
and to the sangha i return
and rely
i like the sense of returning a lot
and the chinese character used for
returning
it often relates to the sense of
returning home
or coming back you know sometimes when
someone has been staying oversea
in some other places when they go back
home and this is the character that's
being used
which is this returning so what does it
mean by returning to the buddha
coming home to the buddha this
orientation
the sense of returning and to me
is that it's not necessarily going out
to somewhere
out there but rather
it's just turning inward and coming back
right here somewhere within us
the home of this being with this life
and so in this way there's a sense of
i return and rely
um it's not appointing to
something of worshipping
something out there
rather something deeply inside of us
in the pali
recollection chance and often times in
the monasteries
there are this form of chantings that
monastics do on very regular basis
called the recollections there is a
particular chant around the recollection
of the triple gm
that is a one is to remember and be
reminded of
the qualities of the buddha dharma and
sangha
and the um the qualities of the buddha
in this recollection chant
um is that
the buddha is the one who is an arahant
who is completely free from
great hatred and delusion and
he's someone was rid of this kind of
forces completely
and totally incapable of great hatred
delusion
and another quality that's often being
remembered or recollected
is this um term called
charana sampano
that is one whose wisdom and compassion
are in perfect harmony
one is wise and compassionate
and the another quality and is that
the buddha is the one who trains those
who wish to be
trained like
us and wish to be trained
and buddha serves to teach those who
wish to be trained
so there's a sense of taking refuge in
the buddha
is like returning home to this kind of
qualities finding true
safety and security in this kind of
qualities
relying on non-greed non-hatred
a non-delusion to live our lives
instead of relying on i don't know
money status relationships
power you know many things
that um we may
rely on are actually quite unreliable
um in the dharma teachings
and it's really possible through the
practice and to cultivate this kind of
qualities
as if it's not that the buddha would not
have taught for over 45 years
and by wandering all around
in different parts of india
by foot
so personally the sense of taking refuge
in the buddha evokes the sense of
surrendering oneself
to this possibility to this possibility
to become free
from great hatred delusion and this
possibility to be wise
and compassionate the possibility of
serving oneself and serving others
and oftentimes through it's
through cultivation of
mindfulness concentration
ethical conducts
that this kind of quality began to
become
possible or accessible
within us and through the teachings of
the buddha
and this tools of mindfulness
the tools of cultivating concentration
the tools of of abiding sila
can allow us to
clean out the stuff that
hinders the access to this kind of
beautiful qualities
and this leads to maybe the the second
refuge which is a refuge in and the
dharma
returning and relying on the dharma
so what does this mean returning and
relying on the dharma
in the recollection of the triple gm
the dharma is said to be here
and now always present
timeless
inviting investigation
and dharma leads
is leading inward or leading towards
liberation
and dharma is to be individually
experienced
by the wise
and so you hear this kind of qualities
that describe the dharma
something that's right here and right
now
it's present right here it's not
found in you know long-winded memories
or fantasies in the future
but it's something that we can touch
into right here
maybe in the breath we breathe in
and breathe out and in the sensations of
the body
in the sand that's traveling through
something that's unfolding right here
right now
in front of us and it's said to
invite investigation
invites us to see pay careful attention
to this
quite a secret unfolding of our lives
right here
and it's by this form of quite
deeply intimate seeing
and clear seeing of
the phenomenon that's unfolding in front
of us
and liberating insights can arise
the insides into anicha dukkha
anata that is impermanence
stress and unsatisfactoriness
and not self
and this insights can really lead can
lead
to the freedom of grasping
lead from lead us into the freedom from
great hatred delusion
and so it's through this returning again
and again to the immediacy of
our lived experience
we can begin to see clearly what is
going on
as i was reflecting about
what we usually rely on
or return to
you know what we are when we i didn't
when i didn't
start practicing dharma
i there's lots of external things
that i'm thinking that i would depend on
or rely on that it would make me feel
okay i feel safe you know maybe the
weather
needs to be good or the neighborhood
needs to be nice and the shelter is
comfortable
and somehow one way or another family
members are in harmony
and our bodies are healthy enough
um or maybe you know no one is saying
think anything bad about you or no one
is looking down on you
maybe you have a good job lots of those
kind of things
and that one can put
a lot of efforts in
to try to get them all lined up so that
we can feel
a sense of okayness or feel a sense of
safety but after we try
for some years maybe many years
we begin to see it's pretty difficult
right so no matter what we do
somehow um maybe they're always someone
who's not particularly happy with
what you said what you did
things are not always coming together
harmoniously
so putting a lot of effort on trying to
sort out
all of this external uh
reliances
may not really work out
so this taking refuge in the dharma
is a calling for us to look in a
different way
not outside but deeply inside of us
and also something that happens here and
now
not in the past and not in the future
and i also say that um
when we when we follow the
buddha's teachings cultivating our mind
and heart
we don't do this alone
as i was reflecting on the vast
transmission the collection and the and
the translations of these teachings that
came from more than
2 600 years ago
countless individuals have walked to the
path
countless individuals have been
cultivating
their heart and mind in the past and
right now
just look at all of us here together
practicing together
and there will be this kind
of forces happening in the future too
in the way we are the direct
beneficiaries
of the stream and currents of the wisdom
and compassion
from so many people before us
i'm feeling that even in our virtual
meditation hall or dharma hall
a group of us are joining
the current of the practice the current
of the sangha
so here the community of the
practitioners
who practice well is the home to return
to
i'm fond of this particular suta where
ananda
said it to the buddha one time that
half of the holy life is a sangha
but the buddha corrected him and buddha
said
no no ananda don't say that
the whole of the holy life is sangha
because if the sangha practices the
noble eightfold path
you will do so as well
isn't that true and so if
all of you are practicing noble
eightfold path
i will be doing this no doubt
as part of the sangha
and so for me personally at some point
of my dharma journey
dharma practice journey i had a
realization that the dharmapath
can't be claimed as mine
because i'm constantly influenced
shaped inspired and moved
by people like you
by my teachers by the dharma bodies
by the sangha i'm part of
and when i'm returning to the home of
sangha there is no doubt
that these currents were drawing force
and the practice will unfold will move
each other
now i remember sometimes if i get caught
up in the things
of the world i don't know worldly wings
um but when i'm
entering into a group of practitioners
for a sit offer a dharma talk
or for an event together
often i have the sense of coming home
there is a real sense of safety here
i can trust the collective conscience
collective goodwill kindness
and the beautiful wholesome qualities
that the the sangha cultivates together
so this returning and relying
on the goodness of the sangha is a real
refuge
a real home
and so um i wanted to maybe
um just feeling this and
chanting retreat energy i wanted to
end today's talk maybe by chanting
for a few minutes on this particular
chant
that touched me quite deeply and this is
paying respect to the buddha dharma and
sangha
and the the chant is in poly
um and it's actually quite a simple
chant
and if you wish and definitely join me
and join me and it's a repeat so
hopefully as you follow along and a
couple of times
you'll be able to join in and on this
chant
in this chant it goes on like this
[Music]
means
reverence or to revere
and so what this chant is saying
is to revere
the buddha to revere the dharma
and to revere the sangha
and so i'm going to begin and
if you like to join me and after maybe
listen
on a couple of times and feel free to
just
join along our chant for a few minutes
together before we end
[Music]
day
oh
[Music]
a
one day
[Music]
uh
so
so allow the vibration to ripple through
you
thank you all friends for being here
have a wonderful night for those who are
in
evenings or um have a great day
otherwise for those who are in different
time zones and
take great care