good morning it's good to see you
i thought you start with a sit here since that is your tradition and i'll do a little bit of guidance
so glad you're here with me so i don't have to sort of look at a screen by myself um i like to start my
sits with a pawn because i have found that i think
constantly every time i sit down to meditate and so i have trained myself
that if i'm going to think about something i want to think about the last thing that was that i heard or the last thing and if
it's a poem it kind of helps me allow the thinking
to help me settle more and so uh i'm going to start by reading this
little poem with you and um and then i'll read it at the end
before the bell so i'll read a poem ring a bell we'll sit i'll do a little bit of guidance
and then i'll ring the read the form at the end of a half hour so this poem is uh entitled blackbirds
by julie codwadler stop and this is what julie says
i am 52 years old and have spent truly the better part of my life
out of doors but yesterday i heard a new sound above my head
a rustling ruffling quietness in the spring air and when i turned
my face upward i saw a flock of black birds rounding a curve i didn't know was there
and the sound was simply all those wings all those feathers
against air against gravity and such a beautiful whining the whole flock
taking a long wide turn as if one body in one mind
how do they do that if we lived only in human society what a
puny existence that would be but instead we live and
move and have our being here in this carving and soaring world that is not
our own so that when mercy and tenderness triumph in our lives and when even
more rarely we unite and move together towards a common good
we can think to ourselves ah yes this is how it is meant to be
that's what we're going to think of remember that this is how it is meant to be
so whatever is happening in your sick this this we spent the better part of our
lives sitting but in this moment something might be a new
all right so let us get started here
let's find ourselves a comfortable place
when you're ready you can close your eyes
just let whatever sounds happen to be around you just come to the foreground
here where i'm at i can still hear the uh resonance of the bell and
it's very faint i have a fan on i can hear that
i hear little creaks in the house
and i hear silence
see if you can just tune into what you hear without the judgment of it just
curing we're just sitting here hearing
allowing the ears to do what ears do on their own without our help we don't need to do anything
we can just notice
gradually you can notice the body sitting it's like shifting your attention from
the hearing to the body just sitting here the posturing
maybe noticing how heavy the body is
the skin and the flesh of the body just sitting here wherever you're at or lying down just
the weight that felt sense of the weight of the body
and if you sense that you're
maybe holding yourself up see if you can just let the weight of
your body be as it is release the belly
release the arms maybe the tightening of our torso
release our thighs and our legs and just let the weight of the body
be held by whatever you are sitting on
maybe notice the weight of your arms from the underside of your arms or the weight of your legs
from the underside of your arm where you philip moffat points to
you just hear this heavy body there may be a sense of hardness
you can feel the bones in the body the bones of the feet connecting with the softness of a
socks or carpet or
the floor you can feel that hardness even the sit bones sitting in a cushion
or chair you still feel the hardness of bone bones on the arms and
the body torso head
just arriving in this moment here and now preparation
for our sit the poem of being interested in whatever is
happening right now is a new experience the way it's
supposed to be
getting grounded in our seat here and now
and allowing the experience of this moment to unfold however it unfolds
could be thinking talking could be irritation unpleasantness
pleasantness it doesn't matter what it
is when you establish a sense of groundedness in this moment
point your view towards curiosity and interest
just sit with whatever devices
now you might notice the breath body breathing
you might also notice the mind just getting lost in a lot of thought
so use this anchor of this arriving in this moment it could
be the anchor of sound that helps you remember where you're at
it could be the anger of sitting here feeling the heavy body just sitting here
hard steady it could be the movement of breath in
and out up and down
whichever anchor works for you helps you remember to come back to this
present moment
we can steady our attention like in the poem so that we can
see something unusual see something unique
and see something real and experience something for the first time
so we'll sit here and now maybe every so often just
drop in a little reminder
and trust that what you're seeing what you're experiencing
what you're noticing is all part of the process
nothing to get away from of things something to be understood to be noticed
so
don't forget remember the sound
remember the body remember the stainless of the body of
the movement of the breath to anchor and keep your fear tethered
to now
this
so
allowing the moment to unfold however it unfolds
our little mantra this is who they meant to be
i just want to know that we know what is arising
so
i'd like to read the poem again now that we've had 30 minutes of quiet
to kind of settle ourselves
i'm 52 years old and have spent truly the better part of
my life outdoors but yesterday i heard a new
sound above my head a rustling ruffling quietness in the spring
air and when i turned my face upward i saw a flock of black birds
rounding a curve i didn't know was there
and the sound was simply all those wings all those feathers
against air against gravity such a beautiful whining whole fly
taking a long wide turn as if of one body and one line
how do they do that if we lived only in human society
what a puny existence that would be but instead we live and move and have
our being here in this curving and soaring world
that is not our own so that when mercy and tenderness triumph in our lives
and when even more rarely we unite and move together towards a
common good we can think to ourselves
oh yes this is how it's meant to be
you