i want to start today with uh three little vignettes
that were important for me in my life and the first one was when i was a
relatively new zen student i was living at a zen center san francisco zen center
and i was back in the 1970s and there were not very many zen masters
in the united states at that time but they decided to have a
meeting among themselves a gathering to talk about whatever they had in common or issues they had or something
and and so they gathered for i think two or three days and had these private
meetings with monkeys themselves but then one evening they offered to be available as a panel
to maybe take questions from the students who lived there and students who were taking care of them and hosting
them and all that so that was nice and so i was in the audience and they were kind of when i
laid out they were all kind of sitting behind this long tables um this seven or nine of them
and uh it was kind of for me as a young and impressionable was a pretty formidable
group of teachers sitting there but i was watching them
and at some point someone came along to give them tea or water each of them maybe came with a tray or something and
and came up from behind them like a good server i guess and kind of reached over and put the cup they had
in front of them so they have something to drink and and they all kind of were kind of
just accepted it that there was no the zen teachers had no they just received it and was there they didn't react or
respond to receiving it at all except for one and one of them when the server came to
offer it turned completely around to the server acknowledge the server was there
and thanked the person who brought it and the contrast between the ones who kind of just like you know were almost
like oblivious the person offering and the one who took the time to really like that person was the most important
person at that moment and so the person that the teacher was going to turn and really be there and
see and recognize and and uh and thank the person i was so impressed by that oh that's quite
something what are the other people doing i thought so that inspired me
so that was one vignette the other vignette was in the same zen center some years later
there was a visiting monk from japan who uh we were sitting at sashim a seven day retreat and he was sitting next to
me in the hall and the way that it worked then is that um
every afternoon during the retreat in the meditation hall
we've been sitting like i'm sitting up here on the stage they'll be kind of sitting in facing the middle of
the room everyone's around the edges of the room and and people would come in and offer us
tea and a cookie but the first day of the retreat first afternoon they also came with a tray of
cups and we kept our each of us kept our own cup next to our seeds for the week
at the end of the retreat we were all supposed to uh they came in to gather the cups we've been using so
they gave us tea they gave us a cookie and when that was finished they came to collect all the used cups and used for a
week so the visiting japanese monk who was sitting next to me you know it's all choreographed in zen
you're supposed to exactly when you're supposed to bow and chant and stand up and sit down it's all kind of like you
know choreographed on schedule so if you someone said something is a little bit out of the usual it stands
out so we were he was sitting next to me and his uh
his cup was on the on the platform in front of him and before the server came
he bowed to the cup and that wow
that's a respecting appreciating having gratitude for the cup i don't know what he was expressing but
i think i thought it was kind of partly gratitude but the fact that you would express this to a cup
that was inspiring as well not just people that you'd respect not just people you would
thank or express something but to a cup that was the second vignette
the third was when i was in graduate school i was studying religious studies buddhist studies at religious studies
department but i took a class from the history department i think i think the class was some like the history of japanese
buddhism maybe it had to do with japanese history and
and so uh somehow we were learning all these facts about
history and uh uh uh
there was some little fact that was told and we were preparing for the finals or
something and so i i said to the professor um
so this spectacular thing is not so important right that we have to know this
and uh and he looked at me and he said gil everything is important
and that wow that that was quite something so oh everything is important
so there this idea that you know when you're studying history use everything has its value and but i kind of
it kind of echoed my mind all kinds of situations everything is important everything is respect worthy
so i think what they have in common these three stories is the idea of respect
and uh and i respect is a very important attitude
behavior that that in many societies many religious many people
it uh i have never heard a dharma talk about respect i've been listening to dharma's talks for
almost 50 years and i've never heard one about respect i've never seen anybody actually writing
about respect there must be someone but i'm not that well written read you know so
and uh but if you go back to look at the teachings of the buddha
the concept of respect is uh is all over
it's kind of like sprinkled in all over however it's not on any list
so if you're going to like to teach lists it's not there it's not i described as having any role
for the path of awakening because that's a very specific kind of listing of practices and
mental experiences that happen on that path but respect is not listed there so the things that
you know that people often use for dharma talks they're talking about important things
things that are important you know understood those things that stand out the things you'd read an introduction to buddhism book and there
it is you know this is what it's all about or something and uh respect doesn't uh rise to the
surface high enough to be talked about an introduction to buddhism texts you know or entered a buddhism
dharma talks in all kinds of places that i've heard maybe some of you heard differently
and however it sprinkled it all over and the impression i have is that respect it was
just an assumed important quality maybe of a society at the time of the buddha but
just assumed there's a very important quality people have that you didn't have to teach it specially you just mentioned it
and in fact it gets mentioned in all kinds of places uh one place is that it's mentioned
together with gratitude and contentment and i think also something there's
something that i've been translating english as deference yeah so uh respect deference contentment and
gratitude are great treasures or great blessings
the and in the this course on loving
kindness there's an emphasis on respect and uh and one of wonderful teachings about it
where it's connected to a day of respect is connected directly with love
pia the love or chair or appreciation or deep
deep regard for other things and and then it's also connected with um
social cohesion non-dispute concord and unity
so those wonderful things are all connected somehow in association with respect and the buddha teaches six things
uh actually four four things that are conducive to this love respect
cohesion non-dispute concord and unity and these are uh loving kindness
or friendliness kindness that if we live a life of kindness and
that conduces to love and respect if uh
generosity if we live a life that's generous that also is conducive to
love and respect and so forth and if we live an ethical life
that also is conducive to love and respect and finally
developing the insight that's that leads to awakening liberating insight
having that insight having that experience of liberation that also
our being on the path of that also is conducive to love and respect
and so i think when you meet someone who is very mature in the dharma practice it tends to kind
of bring up a certain level of respect that appreciation of that person
there's a fascinating story of the buddha after his soon after he was enlightened
he said to himself that someone uh will live
an unpleasant life for an uncomfortable life if they don't have
respect and deference and a certain kind of reliance on others
and uh so it's an interesting idea so he's so so then he looked around and he said
well actually there's no one who is more realized than i am
so it doesn't make sense for me to have respect indeference or to rely on them to have certain kind dependence on them
because you know you know i'm i'm complete i'm complete in my awakening
so what should i have respect for then if it's not a if not a person
and he said i'll have respect for the dharma by which i was awakened i will he
actually said respect homage or honoring
and reliance so the idea of respect honoring and
reliance not a person but some some the the
the uh the dharma the teachings the truth the
processes of awakening that exist within each of us so here also the idea of respect appears
so respect is a fascinating social attitude it's complicated because it means so many different things
in english we use the word respect and sometimes it has you know it's more has more to do with fear
than it is you know that then it's not really respect but we might say you know i have respect for
something but this person who's saying i fear it but
the but uh as as an attitude
of appreciation of others an attitude of valuing another person
seeing their worth or their importance every everything's important including each person
and so to have an appreciation for the value of others
it when there's respect it's a very interesting
mental kind of process to do respect
to have respect as many of you know involves that i like that it involves um
seeing again taking a deeper look at what's going on there's a latin uh respect like
spectator or spectacle or something to look and then to re it means again to look again
so something is respect worthy we want to take a deeper look at it
but a deeper look is also deeper listening like this thing is whatever this person is
is worthy of me paying attention to it's not only about
me myself and mine it's not only about what i want or what i'm afraid of
or how it supports my self-centeredness or something there's a kind of a dropping of self-centeredness dropping of
my likes my preferences in order to hear or listen or take in
the other person in a good way there is a kind of kind of a healthy i think deference to
others when you have respect there's a putting yourself aside slightly
in order to take in to let the person to register the person to make space for the person to to there's that kind of
difference even just to listen to someone what they have to say is the kind of difference
we put aside me myself and mine a little bit so respect involves a kind of attitude
where other people are important enough that we do kind of put ourselves
some part of ourselves aside and it has to do
the focus becomes on the person the object that we have respect for
but it's not a giving up of oneself because at the same time
when we have respect for someone else we're the agent of the respect
where they we're the one who's empowering the respect we're the ones who is living their respect
and so uh it is a it comes from a place of certain kind of
confidence certain kind hopefully certain kind of ability to offer something here
so ourselves are the subject of the respect as the person who has respect part of
who we are is put aside our preferences and our likes our our self-centeredness so we can take
in and really register the other person but part of us comes forward the ability
to do that and the ability to appreciate somebody else to to value
them and this is a mental movement this is not just a casual thing just kind of
stumbling along and you know bumped into someone
and it takes really a certain kind of stopping and taking in and registering and having a kind of
mental process that values appreciates and values the person that we're with
that you wouldn't get that message that's important when people or dharma teachers for example teach
about some of the higher reaches of dharma practice where they talk about not-self
you know you know you're supposed to everything itself disappears completely or sometimes you talk about
it knows that there's a no separate self and some idea of merging or disappearing
of the self and the other person respect doesn't it is not doesn't involve that respect involves a very
clear distinction between you as the subject and the person is the
object for that respect and the advantage of that is that some there's a synthesis of that
or the the chemistry of that there's something beautiful that can happen in
there can be love there can be
respect there can be appreciation there can be
a dropping of certain kind of self-centeredness the dropping of self-preoccupation
and the strengthening of a kind of confidence i would like to propose that
healthy respect involves a healthy confidence
to offer respect and have no confidence the respect might be more of a
of a belittling of oneself making oneself small
in relationship to the other person almost like subservient sometimes but i think that the
the the the more confident we are in ourselves
the more value there is in our respect
the more we belittle ourselves the less power or less energy of there
is in the respect itself so does respect have a role in buddhist
practice and apparently it does it's kind of
you know at least for the buddha it may be it's it's so fundamental he doesn't have to say it's part of buddhist practice it's just assumed as a
foundation and uh and i find that
having respect for my teachers has been it was very important for me there was a time where i felt like i'm
not really going to study with that teacher anymore but but uh i still had tremendous respect
and deference to them if some of my teachers told me um i gave i gave my teachers this authority over
me i said if they ever come to me and say gil you have to stop teaching i would have said okay
that you know there's a few people who would if they told me that i would i wouldn't question it i was okay
because i had that respect and that reliance that dependence on their on on them that felt
important for me to have so that i wasn't just being barreling ahead with my own
you know self-centered orientation around all this and there was someone who was my i was accountable to or that
someone that i was willing to listen to and hear from it
but more even more significant for me is the respect i have for the dharma
for the practice that it it also is not and the dharma
the practice and also karma uh i've learned through my life experiences
that these are powerful forces in the human heart human mind and that are not
related to not how to say this that are kind of uh non-personal
but how i personally live affects it so it's to connect it to the
personal but it's somehow bigger than or it's a larger process too and so for me trusting the dharma or
trusting meditation or respecting it is to respect this this this process or this force or this
this uh these natural processes
that uh in order to that are valuable and important and profound
that i i get out of the way for if i respect my meditation respect my
dharma it's here also i put aside my preferences and my
likes and dislikes what i want in order to allow some make room for
something deeper to happen to allow for myself to listen and hear
and sort of see something that's happening here that is different
than uh than me myself and mine and i've learned i've seen this over and
over again this transformation you know this movement this change that happens in meditation
where sometimes it's only in meditation i realize i've been spending the last
hours somehow caught up in my thoughts or caught up in some personal concern
and then to watch and see it melt away or drop away or or to be able to meditation seed through it to the other
kind of on the other side of it there's more going on here than what i was allowing myself to tap
into when i was going around my life to caring for things
so to have this respect for that process respect for meditation
respect for dharma so when we show up to meditate there is a kind of
both putting ourselves aside and kind of bringing ourselves forward
at the same time putting ourselves aside because it's not about me myself and
mine only it's not about my i keep saying my likes and dislikes my preferences
what i want so that's putting that aside but it's also about coming forward more
fully because i'm here to listen i'm here to really wake up and see
to to let allow life to show itself allow myself to
receive allow myself to be impacted by the dharma
the dharma is operating here let me let me show up and be available for it
and so this wonderful combination and this dance between this of uh
of uh letting go of self and bringing self into the picture
that i think is uh expressed very well with the word respect at least the way i'm talking
about it today and and perhaps there's a wonderful place for respect in our
dharma practice and maybe dharma practice would has a different
kind of confidence in it
and a kind of freedom in it when respect is uh brought along and bearing
attention so maybe you have have thought about this a lot
and uh but maybe if those of you who haven't maybe it will uh was well worth
some kind of uh deeper reflection about your relationship to re respect
and uh and uh in what way for you
does respect involve valuing what you respect what kind of valuing
what does it mean to see something as worthy and what if everything is important
what if uh every teacup is to be respected
what if everyone about if every everyone who you run into is someone who
warrants respect wouldn't you like to live that way
respecting everyone and who would benefit the most from that
you or those people being respected it'd be nice if it was equal
from both so respect that doesn't diminish us it
certainly doesn't diminish us but a respect that brings forth some of the best qualities of who
we are that is conducive to love cohesion non-dispute concord and unity
very nice thing so those are my thoughts for today
so uh do you have any uh
things you'd like to say about respect thoughts about it and
when you uh say where's yeah if you can bring it to him and then
uh if you can please say your name and and then
hi my name is barry i was thinking about mutual respect
that that is maybe the substrate of connection
mutual mutual respect yes yes uh and that
feeling respected by another makes it easier to respect them and vice versa
i was thinking about your story about talking to your teachers in a respectful manner respecting their opinions and
i was imagining that they were respecting you too as a teach as a student
yes thank you yes right here
good morning my name is jill and i'm sitting here with two
two thoughts that are struggling to come out as one question and i can't quite get there and the first thought is um
perhaps the um there's no teaching actual teaching
of respect in
the sutras it is it could it possibly be a matter of translation i know we
struggle with so many words maybe there's some little nugget in there that didn't quite make it to english
translation that combined with the fact that the word respect in our western culture
has so much baggage with it
when i was raised the phrase it always was used with the word show
you are to show respect and showing respect is very different than what we've spoken of
today so somehow i'm i'm kind of rolling through those two things together which
may mean that we just don't have a common language about it yet yeah i think that's very nice what
you're saying that the word respect is so complicated because all the different meanings of it and there's like a whole slew of
meanings and so some of them are not so so healthy and showing respect if it's only a show
that's why i was calling it an attitude at the beginning rather than a show
and uh but whether it's an issue of translation i don't know it's hard very hard to know
how properly to translate these words but that's why
but there's a slew there's a bunch of words which are closely related that sometimes appear in lists
and in english they get translated as respect reverence veneration and homage
so that's the family that we're talking about exactly what the you know exactly what it means in the different ones
and also there's the word that sometimes translates as difference is
is sometimes could also mean something like
being a gentle things like that and
the what's interesting about that how often they translate as differences if you read modern psychology's
philosophy about respect deference is often considered closely related
uh kind of goes along with it and so when i first saw that i had what deference that doesn't seem like a good
thing but uh but i think maybe maybe it is a good thing in a certain way or it can be a
good thing and so all these things part of the task is to discover how to do these things
not as a duty an obligation but how to do them in a way that's healthy that's supportive and beneficial and that's the
task of each person and that's what i think how mindfulness can help give us the inner
information we need in order to understand when we're doing things in a healthy way and when not and not in a
healthy way so what there's one more thing where
respect appears in the suttas and it's another thing so i said that respect is kind of maybe it's just
assumed maybe because it's a cultural value of the buddha he doesn't really teach it especially
but another another thing that's also found has the same thing very foundational
and he doesn't teach about it particularly and so it tends to be overlooked very
often in the suture gets mistranslated and that's taught about now a number of times anu kampa
which i translate as care and uh and
sometimes it gets translated as compassion but compassion requires someone to suffer technically
you know the dictionary definition so there has to be suffering to whether to be compassion or some reference to
suffering and wanting to alleviate that suffering but care
can be involved it can can involve a caring for people who aren't suffering
and the the caregiving emotion that buddha uses repeatedly is this word anu kampa
karuna the common buddhist word for compassion the buddha never uses as a
caregiving emotion in his in his teachings it's always this anu kampa
and so but then the question is what motivates anu kampa what motivates care and there's very little said about this
but when there is a couple of places where there's disgust it's motivated by respect
by respect reverence veneration and homage in one place another place just respect
and so these two fundamental things respect and care are hooked together
and then we care for people not because we have compassion for them our love for them we care for them because we have respect
and maybe respect is a kind of a more universal or more foundational or broader or
more you know it's like it love and compassion is wonderful and
profound but it does require a more active uh engagement maybe
respect is uh more basic and we can respect people that we don't love we can respect people we don't have
compassion for and anyway so that the our care of each
other comes from respect is one of them seems to be one of the teachings of the
buddha so i don't know if that was addressing your your two two thoughts
very helpful thank you so much
hi uh this is shawnee i think you were just getting starting to get to my question but i'm
also struggling a little bit with a different what i perceive as a different definitions of respect
i can understand kind of care as an attitude and
towards maybe everything and not worrying so much about what the object is but for respect it seems with some of
the words you're saying like difference or you know veneration or these words
it seems like there's a positive connotation towards the object so if there's um you know a difficult person
or a violent person or things i really don't agree with how would you approach respect in those
situations some people say what you do is you separate out their behavior from the from the person
and so that for the you you you someone who's difficult even maybe even dangerous
it's possible to respect their humanity but not their behavior and the behavior has to be addressed in a
particular way but you never lose sight of the respect for that person so the person feels all along
you just call the police on them but uh but boy that person did it in
such a respectful way he told me they were called the police you know
you know this is not really good and i wish you well but you know i would like to support you but this
can't continue so i'll call the police but i'll stay here while the police come and make sure they treat you well
something i don't know so so uh i don't know just making up a scenario but
uh i like to believe that we can find a way to have respect for the humanity of
people that's not dependent on their behavior
thank you
hi everyone my name is jan
what came to my mind was also since we barry and i have been
leading the sangha group after the talks um
how much i respect the sangha and have learned from the sangha
no matter how long people have been practicing it seems like there's always something to value and learn about
what someone is experiencing through the practice and also i was thinking about something
related to this from a talk that tunisia gave recently and the climate crisis
about how
consumerism really comes from a feeling of disconnection and not feeling like we
belong to each other and how important it is to value and
respect our connection to others in addition you know to the dharma
and the teachings of the buddha nice and this connection to others is related to the way in which self-respect and
respecting others are connected to each other and um you know disrespecting the
humanity of others is you know that's one way of talking about it but another way of talking about it
is that if you have self-respect you wouldn't want to have any disrespect for anyone else
because the act of disrespect is a way of diminishing oneself
so uh of course you'll have respect because if you have self-respect because that's what you're left with is respect for
others because the to not appreciate others is to is somehow i see it as a
as a uh not as a neutrality but as a kind of a
movement of disrespect
so what else anything else
i'm tanya and um yes i was just kind of imagining um you
know how the buddha often defines things by their opposite so i was thinking
i didn't find the word disrespect very visually imaginably helpful for me but i
was thinking about the word respect or we look and that to respect or we look right
and the opposite of that is to not look to not see to not regard to not take in
and how that's uh that's very painful and that's sort of
like the crime climate crisis not looking not seeing not respecting so
what comes to mind is that uh is that if you're calm and present for things
of course you'll take another look and so uh not looking is a kind of disregard
not looking is a kind of turning away and uh maybe respect involves we mean
means we never turn away or never turn our back on someone or
on the planet okay and so i hope this was nice for you and
uh i've never given a talk on this topic but lately i've been uh it's been on my mind my heart quite a
bit and i kind of find it kind of meaningful to spend time
reflecting on this topic so maybe you will too so thank you all very much
bye