so warm greetings for our meditation time
together and um
as i sit down to be here with you all and i'm thinking about
two things that uh and that is sacred presence
that which is present that feels deeply respect worthy inspiring
meaningful and sacred absence the absence which is
special respect worthy inspiring
and in this practice uh there's a very important role of absence what i call today's sacred
absence and to recognize the absence of
clinging attachment hate preoccupation
and to recognize that absence is special respect worthy inspiring
it really helps open up this path of meditation and then with that sacred absence
the way that we are aware of what is present can have a sacred quality
maybe not exactly because what we're attending to is maybe sacred in
some way but the way that we're present for it our sacred presence our presence our attention
has qualities that are sacred and special and not to be overlooked
and there's always something here as we meditate which is absent
and uh if you go back even you know over your recent life there have probably been things that
you've been caught up in reacting to consumed with driven by
troubled by that those troubles and those preoccupations maybe they've faded away and they're not
here anymore and it's possible to somehow be aware of
their absence and in that absence
to have more room for awareness for attention in that absence to receive
more fully the experience of breathing in that absence to connect more fully to
breathing and even in the much short term
if you're thinking about something in meditation and you're able to let go of it
there's the absence of that thinking there might be the absence of the drive
to think or the desire or the resentment or the whatever it was inspiring the thinking
to start recognizing the absence is a very important part of the deeper
dimensions of this anapanasati
and then not just to recognize the absence but recognize it as an opportunity to
bring have a sacred awareness a greater awareness and for the purpose
of this meditation for our breathing simply aware and
kind of committed to breathing in and breathing out
with awareness awaringly
wearingly so to take a assume a meditation posture
and close your eyes
and and here we are there's a lot of things
absent just being used to meditate
for the time being the absence of maybe the busyness of the day or the
concerns that we have to things we have to do during the day
physically those things are not here now in our body working them
maybe some other concerns that you have for the day you can put up on a shelf and put aside for now
and let them be absent because they'll be picked up later
to help let go of things to be here to take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe three quarters full as you breathe in
and four fifths emptying the lungs as you exhale
and as you exhale to relax the body the whole frame
letting your breathing return to normal and relaxing
some more on the exhale and not only feeling the release of tension and holding
but to appreciate the absence of that holding
so to soften the belly
perhaps you can soften your chest
yeah relaxing and softening your shoulders
and calming the muscles of your face
and cooling down the
agitation associated with thinking
calming the thinking mind
and then appreciating absence not so much that you have to think about
what is absent but maybe there's some way you could intuit
the absence space the absence the freed up time the freedom thinking
the freedom attention that's not preoccupied with
the things that you have been preoccupied with
and here to allow this absence to become fuller
letting go of thoughts ideas
an absence which is related to the simplicity of this moment
just here now in
the sacred absence in which you
make room for your body's
breathing allowing in a sense the experience of breathing
to fill the space of awareness
a sacred absence that allows for sacred presence
a sacred attention
and when you find yourself thinking and you let go of it appreciate
whatever absence of thinking that then follows
and allow the breathing into that absence
so breathing begins to fill more and more
your field of awareness as if awareness fills the universe just
breathing
keep filling the absence with your breathing your experience body's experience of
breathing so that this sacred absence is not filled with
something else filled with thinking and wanting fantasy
so
whatever you're caught up in and thinking about beyond the edges of it is also
sacred absence
let go of your thoughts and preoccupations your tensions your holdings
let go into the great absence and
fill that absence with the experience of breathing
allowing yourself to become very simple and quiet just breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
one form of sacred absence
is to make the heart as wide as the world
make lots of space in your heart in your care and your love and your
good will so there's a place inside of you
for all beings
and so to clear the space within
so that there's room for you to consider relate to
hold in your care others
and for them to fill the space of your heart
means to be very simple allowing them to be as they are
maybe a sacred presence
that everyone is respect worthy everyone in some way may be
independent or even how they're behaving some way deep inside something beautiful
and inspiring even if it's just a seed that's waiting to germinate
in sacred absence within you that allows you to receive
and be present in a fuller caring way for others
and you don't have to say these words but maybe a care and a good will
that these words express or touch on
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we live caring for the welfare and happiness
of those around us
may this meditation practice
provide inspiration and ability
to walk through the world with care and good will may all beings be
well
so we're continuing now with the last steps of last of the sixteen steps of mindfulness
of breathing and we're coming now to the the
fifteenth step and uh which is uh the the poly word
that it represents that that's been being used is niroda
and um in the 14th step the pali word is v raga niroda spelled n-i-r-o-d-h-a
and and it's sometimes it's nice to just use the pali words because
in the original context and in india these words have really rich connotations in fact the
these the iraga and eurota are sometimes listed almost as as synonyms or almost
as synonyms for liberation itself and so they have a very kind of almost sacred or special
quality that the english word for viraga which i've said sometimes translated as
fading away and sometimes as dispassion it doesn't really capture the richness of the
the disassociations or the the way it feels in pali to the raga
and then same thing with niroda such a rich world word that in the original context
i think that really felt like a heartwarming idea that you don't get from the english
translations the most common translation for niurota is
cessation and cessation just end you know ending doesn't really
bring for most of us doesn't bring much heartfelt feeling inspiration delight joy just cessation is like just seems
like okay it's not the ending of something the word niroda comes from the
prefix knee which means without not
free from and rhoda which means obstruction so it's being without
obstruction so cessation is a very different feeling than free of obstruction and maybe the
cessation of obstructions cessation of blockages or clinging or
contraction or what gets in the way of freedom and so
the 13 the 14th step the fading away the dispassion is the involves the fading away in the
ceasing the ending of attachments of cravings of conceits of
the driveness compulsive ways of being that have an uh definitely a feeling of
stress and maybe even pain associated with their drive with their presence and that the the
the pain of those the stress of those becomes more and more apparent
the more wonderfully and beautifully quiet and still the mind becomes a
meditation the more calm we are the more they stand out and highlight as being oh this is kind of
uncomfortable to feel this way that in ordinary street consciousness we might not feel and so i can even say what's
the big deal it's okay to have a little bit of irritation but in deep meditation a
little bit irritation it doesn't feel like a little bit it feels like a real disruption and more importantly an obstruction
to a deeper peace deeper freedom so the 15th step is one trains
observing cessation one will breathe in observing
cessation won't breathe out observing non-obstruction when we'll breathe in observing
non-obstruction one will breathe out and and so
uh as we get deeper and deeper at some point we observe
sacred absence we observe the absence of something and the absence that was really
strong is really noteworthy it's like
deeply inspiring so with watching in constancy in constancy
we're watching things come and go they arise and they pass and this and being in the river the flow of
transiency but as we do that we begin to the attachment to reaching into that river of change
begins to give up can still relax and with that something ceases something
stops something is no longer there to obstruct the freedom and that uh and that absence is not just
a temporary absence like it fades and then comes back a second later or fades away and comes back a minute
later or something but it there's a way in which the cessation the ending of it the absence of it is really
impactful for the mind and the heart wow it's possible
to really be free of cynicism wow this is right you know i've been sin
cynical for decades wow this is possible or i've been always you know
preoccupied and self-preoccupied with self wow this preoccupation with me myself
and mine has fallen away and it's not here i can look around where is it it's not there wow
it's it's absent it's ceased it there's a non-obstruction now that i realize that self-preoccupation was a
kind of a obstruction or wind drag or something
um jealousy doubt hatred resentment
all kinds of desires that sometimes are there kind of in the structure of how
our mind works so embedded fear
and wow this has ceased for now it might come back the next day it might come back at the end of the meditation
but there's something about the thoroughness of that absence which makes an
impression and then this i know is possible i had no idea this was possible and
of course this is like coming home or this is health or this is my birthright
or this is worthwhile this you know it's worth this is is fantastic
and any movement away from it any way of picking up the compulsion that's a diminishment that's not really
worth it anymore and that's not the direction to go that's not the way i want to live
this is how i want to live without this obstructions this kind of stress of
these kinds of things and when this sense of absence is really
impactful and strong enough when it's really a very very deep thorough absence then
a person will never be the same again it's almost as if that absence is a living memory or presence
or something that as a guide oh this is where freedom is this is where peace says this is
where truth is not truth propositional truth but just the true way of being a certain way and
and and then it becomes an orientation for how to live our life or to say it in
different way the tradition what the tradition says when then has entered into the current
the good current the current that takes us to full freedom so we're in the river of change the
river of in transiency but we've now discovered that there's an
uh a place that's not in the eddies that's not in the in the brambles that are growing
into the side of the river but where notice maybe in the center of the river there's a beautiful current
that if we stay in that current it'll carry us to the tradition talks use uses this
analogy to the ocean of liberation and freedom and so this so i call this the sacred
absence the absence of uh and to recognize the value of absence
and this is a hard thing for many people to appreciate that absence has importance
the uh in a sense you can watch the mind and see as soon as there's a quiet
moment in the mind sometimes it seems like a mind just reaches out for the next thing to think about or we have certain problems and as soon
as that problem is solved the mind just goes on to the next thing and the next thing and the next things the mind is filling itself all the time
but but to appreciate absence cessation this deep sacred pause or
stopping um and let it impact us wow
it's true so that it's possible to be free so it's a little disappointing for
people who always want to have something that's be reassuring
something that's a confirmation that they're important they're valuable that they're on the right track that
they can have the badge to tell their friends look i have this beautiful thing the spiritual quality or something and
but and an absence is not a badge you can put on absence is not the presence of something
there might be our ability to be present for things of the world become stronger
but freedom is not something tangible it's not something that in a sense that
the mind can focus on as an object of attention in a usual way that things we can
see and touch and feel and so it's very easy to overlook
absences or to diminish their importance in fact in in history of buddhism in the ancient
world there were debates and big concerns about some people some great buddhist teachers
couldn't understand how in absence could be
that the ultimate goal the ultimate freedom of buddhism was somehow represented by an absence
it had to be a thing it had to be some something and they posited a variety of different kinds of transcen transcendent kind of
states and experiences because it had to be a thing so whether
that's true or not is besides the point what i'm trying to say now in the 15 steps of mindfulness of breathing it
becomes it's at observing absence observing cessation
observing a space of non-obstruction uh observing how with the fading away of
of these you know passion for this lust for clinging for craving
at some point the stopping the cessation is so full and sometimes it happens like like
a like a quantum shift wow and sometimes it happens slowly or fading away
but um something and um and it might be just one thing it might be cynicism or it might be
doubt but something has been plaguing us for a long time boom wow we notice
this is possible and it is possible and the buddha made this great statement
if it was not possible if it's not possible to kind of paraphrasing him if it's not
possible to bring an end to our unwholesome mental qualities
i wouldn't teach you to bring them to an end but it is possible to bring unwholesome
mental qualities to an end to cessation
and so i teach you that this is possible
so this 15th step is an encouragement to appreciate
absence to appreciate the sacred absence take time recognizing when a
preoccupation when greed when anger when desire when lust when anything like all these things that
the mind involved mind contracting the heart contracting and notice uh know it appreciate when
it's not there and that appreciation will allow to grow or
allow you to feel some confidence about this and keep making space in sacred space sacred openness of
attention to be more present and more here that supports this whole process of of
furthering along onward leading aspect of this path of practice
so breathing in observing cessation
breathing out observing cessation so um thank you all and
may you appreciate the all the absences that occurred to you
today that will enliven you or say it maybe or
just just delight you benefit you open you free you and there's probably much more
absences that are the door to step through today than you realize
may you appreciate the sacred absence today thank you