warm greetings to our meditation time together
and as a way of introducing this meditation
i want to use as an analogy something i witnessed
some days ago at a local park there were some people who were flying
remote control airplanes little airplanes in the field
but one of them was a helicopter a little drone helicopter with four
propellers and i was just kind of it was zipping through the air and
flipping around and doing all kinds of things and it was actually kind of hard to follow its
jagged path and it's kind of following it looking around and i felt a little bit discombobulated
trying to find it and looking for there it is now it's gone and it was zipping around and then at some
point it started to return back to
you know back where the person was who was controlling it and uh there was a clear spot on the
ground a little three four inch little disc that it was
going to land on and so it started coming in and it was easy to follow it and it kind of zipped back and forth a little
bit over around that disc kind of oh like then it was easy for me to watch and stay with it
and it's and then at some point it came right above the disc slow slow down slow down came right
above the disc and it hovered above the disc right above it and it was kind of delight to kind of
feel the delight and joyful to just see it hovering there and it was so
much more relaxing for my attention not to be searching for it in the sky and i was just there just watching it
hovers like my mind hovered and it was kind of like a little bit of a thrill to see it just a few inches above the
ground and then it just went straight down
on top of that disc and rested on the ground and something in my mind just rested ah
and the kind of thrill a little kind of excitement of just having it hover vanished my mind and i just my mind kind
of settled it's almost like my my mind got grounded oh
so i just see that the zoom folks didn't
weren't hearing me because i had them to mute on so so those of you on
youtube hopefully you'll be patient with me and i tell this little story again and then we'll start going going going
again everyone welcome to the meditation
and i'd like to begin by a little analogy of what happened a
few days ago in a park where there was a people flying
remote control little airplanes over the field and there was one drone helicopter with
four propellers they were zipping around in the sky and it was a curiosity thing for me to see
it but it was very hard to follow was see it for a moment it would zip away and
a very jagged trajectory and path and so i was kind of busy my mom was kind of
active busy looking searching it was a lot of work at some point it
started the helicopter started coming back to where it was going to land and then i could start seeing it again
very easily without having to search for it and then it clearly was a spot in the
ground where it was going to land a little round disk and and i um
and then it was kind of like went back and forth a little bit looking to be close to that spot above
it and it's easy to watch it kind of glide and slide back and forth it was kind of nice to see it
it's little gentle movements and then it came to a place just a few inches above the disc and it was
completely still hovering in the air and it was such a pleasure to watch it hovers like
it was a little bit of a thrill like just kind of defying gravity just being really still just right there and i felt a certain
kind of joy and delight and my mind got really still like oh what's happening here
just kind of being still with that hovering and then the
the the helicopter just kind of landed on the ground and just was
atlantic got still subtle on the ground and i could feel my mind just get still
and the little bit of thrill or kind of the hovering feeling in my mind which was a little bit of energy rested
and my mind something in my mind ah and it rested there
so this is an analogy for samadhi for the development of this wonderful thing
called samadhi sometimes called concentration some translators
translated as serenity and and it's you know if you're if your
mind is a helicopter then sometimes your mind is zipping
around and it's hard to even find it wherever the mind goes it's trajectory is not so clear it jumps around
and so you know for a mindfulness practitioner it can be a lot of work kind of like where'd it go now and
finding it and keeping up with it and remembering to look for it and be
present but then as as we start getting settled
more more subtle than meditation the mind doesn't flit around so much
doesn't jump around so much and it begins to kind of still not quite in the present moment here
but maybe it's with the breathing some it's kind of in the territory and it's kind of a little bit moving back and forth
getting close in and out and sometimes there times i'm not but it doesn't go very far and you kind of know where the mind is
but it's just kind of looking for its landing spot and then at some point it's really there
in the present moment here in our experience in our body maybe with our breathing and it just
kind of a little bit hovering and it just feels so good to kind of to have a certain kind of stillness but
also to have a certain kind of well maybe i don't know if weightless feeling or hovering feeling of just
there but it's kind of a bit of a thrill and it's so nice a little bit wonderful and delightful
and then it's it doesn't go anywhere except it settles further down onto the
landing spot and for the mind to land here in the present moment a
landing spot on the ground where it's still peaceful
unmoving and then our mind just comes to our deep rest it just
rests there it's not searching for anything it's not chasing for anything
it's not bouncing around and even the even the delight of finally
just kind of being in a spot hovering is ah that settles as we come
to town and just up just here stillness quiet
peacefulness and settled here
and one of the descriptions of samadhi is a settledness of mind the mind is
settled and the deeper the subtleness is the stiller the mind comes
and a stillness that's not just a stillness of a particular spot within us
but as if everything is still because the awareness has become still
so assuming a meditation posture
that can be both your landing spot here in this body
and your helicopter your mind here
and if your mind is
dashing about after this thought and that thought just know that
you also have the remote control
to direct it back to its landing spot
gently lovingly still letting the mind know come back come back home
be here this is where rest is this is where safety is
don't need to flit around so much
and maybe one of the remote control signals for the mind to
settle down is taking a few long slow deep breaths
a deep breath about three quarters full without without any strain in the
in-breath and then an exhale that's maybe twice as
long as usual again without any strain
and exhale where there's more letting go at the end of the exhale
more release at the end of the exhale
and then letting your breathing settle down quiet down as if the breathing now can
begin landing here in your body
as you exhale softening and relaxing the body
and part of the relaxing of the muscles is to help the body come to a greater
stillness
as we soften the muscles of the face relax them
it's letting go of the activity of tension and holding
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders and if the shoulders are being held up
it's activity and action
that interferes with the deep settling into stillness
and the same thing with a belly softening relaxing the belly
and sometimes there you can feel the greater stillness sometimes not if it's difficult to be
relaxed
perhaps or some way to bring the entire body to stillness to relax let go
in the hands the arms the chest the legs
and then to begin bringing the mind the awareness
home to the landing spot of the body breathing
and you might not quite be there yet might be close by you might fly by and come back and
circle around close to the breath but not quite there that's okay
that's that might be needed to kind of locate the place to land
you're with the breathing for a few breaths or half a breath off you go again
and rather than being discouraged be encouraged that
this is part of the process of coming to landing
and you are getting closer
maybe less off in the distant sky fleeting around coming here to your
breathing
and maybe for a while you hover over the breath almost as if
the in-breath is a dr upward draft that you catch and kind of hovering in
gliding on
and the exhale is kind of a
provide support to glide along slide along on the exhale
and for the mind to really land in the breathing
the mind needs to become stiller
mind needs to be quieter which might be held by relaxing the
thinking mind relaxing any muscular tension
associated with thinking worrying and wanting
tension that might be in the forehead or behind it around the eyes or jaws
in a slight leaning forward or pulling being pulled or like pulling back
a more subtle relaxation of the body that corresponds to a settling of the
mind allows the mind to settle and get
quieter
and feeling more in the breathing the body breathing
and what would it be like for you to be right there with a breathing
hovering over it gently quietly
putting in just enough energy for your mind your attention
to hover over the in-breaths and out-breaths
so the mind is not wandering off and into thought so much but right there
breathing in and breathing out
and not so much like there's a laser focus like you're in the control tower looking
at the breathing but more like the whole body is
gently vibrating hovering over the breathing or with the breathing
right there breathing in and breathing out
they're kind of hovering where there's a stillness and a tranquility not a lot of movement
and then to let the mind
land in the breathing to land in the present moment
so that the engine can go off and
has deep stillness groundedness
safety having landed
and stable here on the ground of the body breathing
aground the earth
wide and expansive and quiet earth
where the mind can feel secure and enough to be still quiet
resting on the body breathing
whenever the mind is wandered off lot come back to first hovering with the
breath with breathing and then with a relaxation letting go
land on the breath land inside of it
come to a stillness of mind in the middle of the moving experience
of breathing
do
finding a place that of stillness within
and allowing the mind to become still
quiet maybe even unmoving
together with the inner stillness
so
and then coming to the end of this sitting
and thinking about how samadhi operates in our interpersonal
relationships it is not a concentrated focus on others
but rather it's a deep settledness in ourselves
to be deeply settled without any fear
agendas without any leaning forward or pulling
back without being pushed by desires or
pulled by aversion just a deep subtleness
and to be with others in this settled way
so settled that of course you'll be aware of the other person
you don't need to intently focus of course you're open and available and
aware of the other and from this subtle place may be of
peaceful place
here there can be a kind of deep love and
positive regard and offering of goodwill of safety
a deep respect of others because you're not interfering with them
or needing them to be different you're simply settled with them
settled on yourself
this settled samadhi factor
can give a wonderful perspective
for how to be with people with care with love with friendliness with good will
that is not so much work or an obligation or a transaction
it just is
it may be that our ability to be still in meditation
may it also be for the for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be settled in them on themselves
may all beings be nourished by an inner stillness and safety
may all beings know inner peace
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
you