good evening let's see this microphone doesn't feel
quite right there we go
good evening welcome welcome
so i'll do a little guide in meditation
here
and just settling in
to this experience right now
i remember somebody once describing it as
getting the mind and the body in the same place
and to do that it can be really helpful to
feel into the body the bodily experience
just in general how does it feel in the body right now
maybe there's some tiredness some restlessness some achiness
as best we can we welcome these experiences
maybe not welcome in terms of invitation but they're already here
so acknowledging what's here
and feeling the body breathing
the movements associated with in-breaths and out-breaths
maybe you feel that in the belly in the chest
maybe sometimes the ribs even around the back
or maybe the air going in and out of the
nose
and when the mind wanders we just very gently simply
begin again
and if we notice an uncomfortable sensation in the body
can we make room for it as best we can that is
not hating it or trying to shove it away
but to somehow recognize that it's actually there
and can we befriend it or
somehow allow it to be there
because it is there
and if we can bring our awareness to our experience
even if it's an uncomfortable one
and somehow we don't get lost or swept away
or carried away when we're with bringing awareness to
our experience
accompanying our experience in some way
and each time we accompany or bring awareness
to an uncomfortable experience
we learn something
we learn it's possible
to bring our awareness
to that which perhaps we want to avoid
and we also learn that somehow it's okay
after we bring our awareness like we survive in some kind of way there's a
little bit of confidence or
familiarity
of being with difficult experiences so even if
at that particular time the particular instance we bring
awareness to an uncomfortable experience
maybe it seems insignificant
but this is exactly exact precisely how
we grow our capacity to be with difficulties and
gain confidence to be with difficulties
and as we gain familiarity
with being with difficulties as we gain confidence
being with difficulties just by
being with difficulties in meditation even minor ones feeling that
itch rather than scratching it
noticing our reaction to the neighbor's dog barking
these simile seemingly small little movements
really make a difference as we train so to speak the mind and
heart to be able to hold
these difficulties
because all of our lives have difficulties and if we can hold them more and more of
them not only does our life unfold
differently but it enables us to help others
maybe to recognize when they are in difficulty or to be an exemplar of
how to show up in difficulties
so may our practice together be for the benefit of all beings
everywhere without exception
good evening good evening welcome welcome wherever you are whatever time it is
whether it's evening when you're listening to this or not
so today i just um finished the last class of a course
called the path of fearlessness so this topic of fear
as something that i've been thinking about it's on my mind and on my heart a little bit
this how how we work with fear how we are with fear how fear shows up
and of course there are different types of fear one is uh due to imminent danger
that is uh seeing a rattlesnake while we're out for a walk or a car that's veering over into our lane
or something like that so some real imminent danger there's that type of a fear like some bodily harm might happen
soon and then there's also maybe i'll say and i'm not talking about that so much
that's a natural response and it's important and helps keep us alive
it's uh an appropriate response but we also might have some fears that
are less pressing don't have a fee not so much associated with some imminent danger maybe just a fear of
public speaking is not so uncommon or
fear of being seen a particular way you know not doing the right thing or something
and also we and so maybe i'll talk a little bit about that today sorry and but also
there is we could distinguish between fear and anxiety and there's a number of
different ways in which we might make these distinctions but one way
is to say that fear has a clear object i'm afraid of public
speaking and i feel this dryness in my mouth or jitteriness in the body or something
like this maybe it's a little aside i'll say
that there was a time in which my head this really increased heart rate
would be beating really fast and before i really understood it i just assumed that it
meant that i was afraid and so then i started making up all these things that i was afraid of
but then when i when that kind of got taken care of i realized oh it was i was misinterpreting
this rapid heartbeat as i was afraid
so there is fear that has this bodily experience
most often our hearts don't beat quickly for no reason but to distinguish between fear and
anxiety anxiety also can have an increased heart rate or
but anxiety tends to not have any particular i shouldn't say this maybe it's a more
diffuse maybe it's not so clear what we're anxious about
anxiety tends to be maybe a little bit more pervasive or a little bit more
um touching different areas of our life but maybe not you know maybe in some
ways that those distinctions are artificial but maybe it's an invitation for you
to discover for yourself the relationship between fear and anxiety
and so i would like to talk a little bit about fear this evening and
and some of the ways in which working with fear can be really beneficial and not
only because it's a difficult experience and not only because i don't think anybody wants to feel
afraid so for the most part it's something that we're trying to manage so that it'll go away but
there can be something really valuable about working with fear
in addition to learning how to be with difficult experiences and in the guided meditation
i was suggesting that when we do look when we do gain capacity to be with
difficult experiences it really can be a great support for our life and i would say fear in particular
as something that can be a support for us but i would say it really can be a
support provided where it's not overwhelming
if it's overwhelming then of course we need to take care of that and one way to
stop feeling overwhelmed is to feel the experience of fear in the body maybe
it's rapid heartbeat maybe it's a dry mouth whatever it might
be and as best we can to allow the fear to be there
and in some ways maybe even allow the fear to be
okay to be there as best we can as best we can
and then if we can allow the fear to be there maybe we can become curious about it
and learn a little bit and investigate it not so much that we have to figure
everything out while we're in meditation but at other times when we're off the
cushion perhaps to get curious about it
so to help us explore fear again this is maybe not so much on meditation
during meditation and not so much when we're feeling overwhelmed by it
but in other areas of our life to help this exploration i'd like to share a poem
and i'm just going to share the first part of this poem this poem kind of unfolds as a
short story so the first part of this poem this poem is called hello fear
it's by rosemary trauma and the first part of the poem goes like this
there i was making tea in my kitchen when fear hit me like a school bus
i didn't need a scientist or therapist to tell me it hurt i screamed ah i shouted
no but after smashing into me fear just opened the folding
glass door of the bus yanked me on then plopped me into a green
vinyl seat i love this i think it's very um evocative this idea of you know fear is
never invited right we never really wanted it just comes careening in and
and i think it's uh this poet she's choosing to use a school bus as kind of like the vehicle
i'd like to suggest that we might use examining being curious about investigating fear
as a vehicle and i'll unpack this a little bit as we go but i think that the poet rosemary trummer
we can think about his school bus maybe in some ways we were younger
we were children when we were on school buses so there's a part of us that feels young
and vulnerable when we feel fear but also buses carry a lot of
people so we don't know how many other people are on this bus but
maybe there's a whole lot of people when we get pulled onto this bus of fear
and maybe we don't notice them at the time because we're feeling fear but
might there be a way in which we can imagine connect to this common humanity that
fear is something that humans experience it's a good thing it's helpful for us it
keeps us aware of the rattlesnakes and the car veering drifting into our lane
but also to just maybe there's some support and knowing that there's others and
maybe the others that can accompany us with our fears
and also i appreciate in this poem that the fear just arrives
the bus with fear on it arrives and they get yanked on they open the door of the bus and we get yanked on
sometimes we feel that way right when we have difficult experiences we feel like whether we want to or not
like we get whisks whisked away and off we go
so that the poem continues so she's on the bus on the green vinyl
seats i'm laughing because that's my memory of school buses also with green vinyl seats
i don't know if they still do but so the poem continues i'm scared
i said yeah fear said because i'm scary yeah
i squealed as the bus careened through the couch through my bedroom through the
splintering dining room table so in this poem the school bus is
carrying fear with our protagonists the poet perhaps or maybe ourselves and going through all
the areas of a person's life the couch the bedroom the splintering
dining room table and in the same way i'd like to suggest that working with fear
can take us to many areas of our lives sure we might experience fear in all
areas of our lives but i want to suggest that working with fear being curious about it
investigating learning how to be with it can also touch so many different areas
of our lives in fact maybe it provides a window working with fear
provides a window into our inner life maybe some emotions that have been
tucked away that we've been kind of afraid to feel or maybe
if we work with fear we start to notice some of the stories that we've created about who we think we
are or the purpose of our lives or what we value because when we start to work with
fear we get a view of what are we trying to protect often fear fear arises when we feel
threatened so what what are we trying to protect so examining fear is a way in which we
might gain some clarity about some of our inner life and what's important to us
and maybe some ways in which what we're really holding on to isn't so helpful
working with fear also helps us to realize the way in which our fears might be limiting our
freedom in ways that we didn't appreciate we
might not be aware of the role fear has until we are asked to really examine it
i know for me that i noticed for quite some time early in my meditation practice there was an awful lot of planning going
on you know as soon as you know i was just spending my time planning you name it i was planning it what i was going to do
next and what i was going to eat next and what i was going to get at the grocery store
you know all these things the emails i was supposed to be sending all this stuff right maybe some of you can relate to this or
recognize this and it wasn't until that i really started to
examine i started to see oh there's fear underneath this planning i'm trying to
make myself be safe i have this idea as long as i just plan everything i'll be safe
i see this showing up sometimes in my dharma talks too that i try to plan them and then you know
maybe i get a little too stiff then but just the ways that we try to be plan
or prepare or take care of just because there's a little bit of
fear there somehow just recognizing the fear makes it a little
i don't know it shifts our relationship just if we're aware with it then maybe
we're okay i heard that earlier today if we bring some awareness to what's
happening then there's some confidence that can be there
so working with fear can also reveal some of our underlying beliefs some additional underlying beliefs may be
that we have these beliefs that were only validated through the eyes of others
so it's so important how others see us and we're afraid that we won't be seen in a complementary way or
maybe we have the belief that it's dangerous to be strong and competent
so examining fear might highlight some of these things that otherwise maybe we wouldn't get
illuminated we wouldn't notice them we might notice some of our patterns of
reactivity oh yeah i get i'm a little bit afraid when
the refrigerator doesn't have is running out of food i feel like you know this sense of lack and i won't
have enough for i don't know we we we all have our own things that
we have some patterns of reactivity or second arrows we might notice oh yeah
fear shows up here or maybe anxiety shows up here
if we start to investigate fear we also might notice how there's this vicious cycle of fear and
clinging and fear leads to clinging
through identification clinging to a sense of self or clinging
to wanting to have things a particular way that's why we're planning right that things have to be a particular way
so that we can feel safe and then with this clinging through
identification and then with identification this leads back to fear
as we observe the objects of our identification under threat because of
course they are changing so whatever we're identifying with doesn't stay constant it doesn't stay
steady it's not as predictable as we wish it were so fear and clinging fear
and clinging is this vicious cycle we know that clinging is a source of
suffering but maybe sometimes it's helpful to look at clinging like from the side view
and maybe one way is to look at fear again not when we're feeling overwhelmed
and not when maybe in our meditation practice maybe it's just enough to notice there's
fear but maybe outside of meditation to talk about it think about it journal about it kind of get curious
about the role fear has in our lives
maybe i'll say some other areas of our life that working with fear might travel
through is our relationship with death this of
course is a natural fear that humans have
but to if we are looking at fear we could look at our relationship to death
we are all going to die we know this intellectually all of us know this
but maybe we can start to reflect on death in a way that allows us to
approach the dying process in a way that's sacred in a way that's liberating
and perhaps when we examine our fears and we look at our fear of death maybe
we decide that we'd like to do some death contemplation practice marina sati practice
a highly esteemed well-established practice in the buddhist tradition of contemplating our death
not in a morbid way it turns out to be really beautiful and touching practice
i'm not going to talk about it here some of you are familiar with it i'll say i know that nikki mercafori has
taught some death contemplation practices but allow us to kind of reclaim that
part of ourselves that's afraid of death and instead kind of experience the peace
and ease of the wholeness that comes when we can
no longer fee be afraid of the fear of death have the fear of the fear
and also the peace and calmness that can come when we align ourselves with the truth of
reality we know things that have the nature to be born have the nature to die
but somehow it's part of the human experience that we don't really think
about it so inclu so that leads me to the next
section of the poem so here the poet or the protagonist is
um speaking to fear and she says
what if i lose everything i said to fear yeah said fear what if you do
and who will i be when everything changes yeah said fear who will you be
then he opened the door and shoved me off the bus and i was standing again beside the
familiar green counter teacup in hand not a drop
spelled so the person finds herself at the
beginning right she was making tea in the kitchen when the this bus
arrived but working with fear like builds some
self-confidence i think um once we realize that
yes we can be with fear and we can examine our fears then that we don't
maybe the the fear of fear starts to diminish we realize oh yeah
okay it's uncomfortable perhaps but we can do this we learn to like trust the
practice trust the awareness trust having some curiosity
about what's happening what our experience with fear is and this uh expands into wider and wider
circles in the world how we are in the world the confidence that we gain from having working with
fear and then no longer fearing the fear starts to leak out
in different um areas of our life in so many different ways
and maybe we can also be inspired by um had the buddha
he worked with fear some of you know and part of the stories he talked about how he had fear
before he was awakened i think i talked about this in a dharma talk a number of months ago
and he said when he felt fear he just kept practicing
until the fear went away and then after awakening
the buddha is not somebody who is afraid he speaks with confidence
and he speaks about he's confident in his knowledge he he knows he has seen and
knows and he wants to share it with others so it's possible to go from somebody
who's experiences fear to having some confidence we might also think of the nuns
from ancient india and they're liberation poems that are captured in the tarikata
some of you are familiar with this and these um and these nuns they express
themselves with warmth and calmness and with confidence
even though they also in some of their poems are describing some really difficult emotions
and some fear but they found their way to some
confidence and more freedom
so then the this poem continues building on this
who will you be he shouted so fear is shouting to the protagonist
who will you be he shouted from the half open window
i took a deep breath ah not knowing how to answer
good fear said as if uncertainty were a gift
and who fear said as the bus peeled away who are you now
who are you really
good fear said as if uncertainty were a gift
so pointing to that working with fear
helps us not only to gain confidence where things are uncertain and that
maybe to trust the practice and some of those experiences but also to recognize
that uncertainty that is to be open
to what's actually happening to have some flexibility some fluidity
with how things are and with how we are
one of the key buddhist teachings of course is that there isn't a solid stable permanent self
instead actually there's uncertainty there's impermanence things are changing
there's the uncomfortableness that goes with that but there isn't a solid self
and i talked earlier about this vicious cycle of fear and clinging and identification
that some way identification we could say is a way in which we're creating a self i'm the one who has this
experience or i'm the one that has to get rid of this experience
so we can just notice how fear and clinging identification and maybe like a
sense of self that feels really tight and are really separate from everybody else they go
together so if we can relax our fear we can relax
our separateness this sense of separateness
and being fearless
can be a profound gift to the people around us
the willingness to have the difficult conversations the willingness to be with people who are
dying or really sick or the willingness to not know to not know the answer to have
uncertainty and and instead of being dogmatic or having
really strong views that we have to trumpet everywhere say loudly
but just to instead have some openness some uncertainty and have some
fearlessness that allows us to just be with what is
so fear as a vehicle working with fear can be just a really
great way that can complement a meditation practice and might help support us discovering more and
more things about ourselves and can bring these beautiful fruits
not only to our lives but to those around us as our fearlessness grows
so when you find yourself on this school bus careening around
with fear maybe you might notice there's other people on the bus with you and maybe that diminishes some
of your fear or maybe you the fear just asks
or he dropped her off after she said what if i lose everything and he said yeah
what if you do and she said well who will i be when everything changes and fear said yeah
who will you be and that's what brought this bus to a
stop so working with fear
may you find some of the benefits and fruits of working with fear thank you