so welcome welcome it's good to be with you
i saw a uh a cartoon and uh
like two people on a beach sort of i in chairs looking out on the the water
and uh and one person says to the other um i'm relaxed enough that i've stopped
thinking about the drive here but not so relaxed that i'm not thinking
about the drive back
so um topic for this morning is uh
is thinking um thinking mindlessness mindfulness rumination
and and want to try to
in a sense parse different forms of non-mindfulness
yeah then maybe not all forms of non-mindfulness are created
equal yeah so
the patterns of uh of thinking they they do change uh i think kind of dramatically
over the course of a practice life that
we come to contemplate the dharma to think about
the dharma a lot in a sense more and more
reminds us of the dharma and so this becomes a kind of active
point of reflection of contemplation
and uh and there are other changes there are um
i think real reductions in certain species of self-related
thinking yeah and it's not that all thoughts of self-reference drop out
of consciousness entirely maybe maybe
not not for me but
but there are certain kind of self-referential
ruminative thought of who we are what we're like where we're
going what people think what the future looks like for me
who i will become what i will acquire
that fades quite a bit
this kind of movement of of really taking
taking the self as an object and pondering it
that's a [Music] a very congealed
mode of thinking and
i think that fades but not all
non-mindfulness is the same not all thinking is the same not all
forms of autopilot are equally destructive
and you know we
okay thanks um
we meditators um we're almost um
tend to be like a little embarrassed that we think you know
that um uh the when the guided meditation kicks in
right and we're in the middle of some
wild something you know or we're wondering what that
knocking is that's fairly persistent for the wrong door
[Music] you know but that moment of just like okay we get called back to whatever to
the breathing or something and um and
um it's it's you know jarring and there's a sense of just almost like a
child being caught doing something wrong or something yeah
and um and of course thinking is is not the enemy and the mind is just another sense
gate yeah it's just another sense gate like hearing or feeling
and i remember a teacher saying you know you would never um
try to plug your ears with cotton in order to get enlightened yeah
but uh we do that we have those same fantasies whatever the equivalent of plugging the ears with cotton would be
for our thinking yeah and
i remember during a retreat uh michelle mcdonald said
you know if you broadcast what everyone was thinking
in the hall you know if you just broadcast at all hundred
right which she said it would break your heart you know
it would break your heart
we're learning about um about thinking and about silence and
in a way if we're ashamed of anything inside us it short circuits
investigation yeah if it feels like we may discover
something about ourselves about our conditioning that could break us we
don't look yeah so
um a researcher uh kalina kristoff brain
brain researcher she does a lot of very interesting things
and is interested in mindfulness meditation stuff and among other things and
in one one research approach she had
participants do this think aloud
paradigm you know like 10 minutes in a room
it's kind of like just speak out the papancha in your mind
the mental proliferation just say it out loud don't censor yourself
10 minutes just go right and
um and then research assistants you know transcribed it and then coded
it you know to sort of deciphering it into different categories and chunks and um
and so she kristoff gave one you know just one line um hopefully i'll get the new job because i really want it
i'm tired of my old job um i miss my dog i haven't seen her in a
long time yeah so it's just that ten minutes just that right
and uh you gotta you gotta kind of lift a glass
to the research assistance there too that's the no joke that job yeah
um but they gathered all of this kind of like
they're trying to parse this what is happening in people's minds yeah
and so it was 1300 words yeah on average that in
and 30 discrete chunks of thought you know where there is including 20
major transitions so that that example of i'm tired of my old job i miss my dog
that's a major transition yeah 20 of those in the course of the 10 minutes
and and she was looking as i'll get back to later about the valance yeah
the the kind of the vedna sort of like um
neg positive you know positive negative neutral yeah and then the continuities
and discontinuities and so
just seeing seeing that is like okay 1300 words 30 discrete chunks of thought
20 20 breaks in continuity and that is 10 minutes and we kind of live in that
yeah and a question of like why has evolution
conserved those habits so exquisitely is it just to like humiliate
us as meditators right it feels like that sometimes you know
uh but it's probably useful for staying alive yeah like that that we heard the door
knocking and there is some like sense of a little vigilance or
question what is that we did not stay with our breath you did not keep listening to me right
all of a sudden there was something else yeah and
and so yeah single pointedness is uh
is there's a certain kind of defenselessness about it yeah
to just sit and to relinquish the kind of vigilance and the the orientation and the tracking
of threat and opportunity that
entails some measure of trust some measure of safety some measure this is part of why we take the precepts
on retreat yet to know that we have each other's backs to know
that we are formally committed to non-harming yeah so that some of the
vigilance might be released yeah and this may allow us to settle into the
moment in a deeper way and so
yeah those habits the habits of fragmentation of discontinuity of
narrating our life has evolutionary value for i'm sure
but um our happiness was not at the top of evolution's to-do list
yeah it's like this is why some of this path
is against the stream so
sometimes it's said that that mindfulness is the only factor
that you can't get enough of you can sort of overdo
anything else you can overdo the effort the energy the compassion the equanimity
that can put you out of balance but one of the classical views is that
there is there's no such thing as too much mindfulness that can never actually put us out of balance which is an
interesting yeah and
i was reflecting on this and and feel like oh yeah i agree if if we're aspiring
for awakening in every moment mindfulness is vital
mindfulness is vital and when we're really practicing
we can sense even a short burst of unconsciousness carries a
certain kind of hangover yeah
there's like a hangover from unconsciousness
and in the context of like some deep aspiration around
enlightenment or something like this there's there's you're kind of like
kindling a fire you know and moments of unconsciousness sort of douse
the glowing embers you can actually start to feel it yeah
and the the kind of uh way that
yeah just unconsciousness diffuses diffuses the energy of insight of
samadhi that's when we're
dedicating each moment to freedom but
if we're honest at best we're aspiring for enlightenment
some of the time
not all the time right let's be honest
some of the time the rest of the time i just like to be comfortable you know
right
so i want to put in a plug for um
for mindlessness yeah this is not a retreat talk by the way some talks you could give
on a sunday morning or in a retreat this one you do not give on a retreat this is
it is different yeah so um this is different yeah this is kind of
like all right how do we be nuanced about mindlessness and you know
i this portion of the talk is uh sponsored by netflix just
interest of full disclosure uh so um
when the attention is engaged consistently it requires effort and energy
yeah just there are times when we just develop so much momentum that it's
the image gill uses of just coast the mindfulness is just like coasting down
water with you know there's there's wind at your back there's some current at your back
but a lot of times to attend to move the attention to the breathing for example entails a measure of energy
it's like attentional energy
that has some fatiguing effects yeah
now part of why we practice part of why we practice moments of mindfulness is
such that we elevate the trait level of
mindfulness the dispositional level of mindfulness the mindfulness
that we're at when we're not trying to be mindful
yeah that that changes over time right and so it makes it such that we
don't actually have to marshal all this energy can i be mindful can i remember can i remember
the cruising altitude of our awareness is is is clearer
but that's a whole process and it i don't think it ever stops really
and in the meantime it takes energy yeah to devote the attention to
the breathing or to a book or to
anything a person to work
and there can be a kind of backlash or a certain kind of depletion
or fatigue and sometimes you see it in in retreat you're sort of like exerting
a lot of energy and then you just hit a wall yeah how many people have done residential retreat uh in here okay
it's hopeful so you may be familiar with those those
like the energy just sags and it just gets chaotic and
very difficult to focus or to kind of feel even connected to the whole
path of practice yeah the energy flags and
and maybe in our lives just we've been through something intense yeah
and it might be some significant life event for you something in the larger culture covet
all of this it might be just a day of work or a day caring for
a child or a parent or something and there's a sense of
oh yeah the the the attention has flagged in some way it like needs to go
slack and we see this again after retreat
sometimes people have maybe a maybe a really rich retreat and then get home
and it's like this backlash of unconsciousness yeah
where it's like oh you know it's like the attention needs to go like fully
slack yeah that's how it feels at least
and we seek something that is like utterly
undemanding attentionally speaking yeah like that we seek the path of least
resistance we seek the activity with like zero
attentional caloric burn yeah
right like running is a thousand calories an hour and rowing or whatever
you know like we're looking for zero what is zero calories burned attentionally speaking
in some moments yeah and
it's worth examining like our own patterns around this what
what what are the low low calorie attention habits yeah like
how do we try to soothe around that what are the rhythms of exertion
and going slack and
and maybe sometimes sometimes maybe we could say like oh i'm just feeling lazy
or something but other times it actually feels like
no there's something uh i don't know i was almost going to say
the word wholesome maybe that's too much but it's like there's something
needed to restore the attentional balance where there's a sense of needing
to go slack attentionally to burn zero attention calories yeah
and uh and maybe sleep is part of this and
zoning out in different ways for sure is part of that thirst that we have
and our days are really punctuated by this rhythm of like giving attention and
conserving it yeah of giving it and rebuilding it
and um i almost thought of like again this parallel of exercise of like the
interval training that people do they'll run really fast for a little bit and then walk slowly and run really fast and
and it's worth investigating like how do we how does our attention economy
function inside and uh
some of our work is is examining like what are what the intervals should be
yeah and to be careful also
what we're consuming on our attentional breaks because
um we're pretty porous kind of defenseless
in that time and things you know tiknot han's vision of the
the precept around non-uh you know not taking intoxicants includes
like entertainment or things because it sort of like gets in deeply
and we want to be sensitive to when we've had our fill when the attention has gone
slack and there's some kind of wholesome restoration process happening
but then we sort of keep going there's some kind of momentum of the
unconsciousness and we keep going even when we've actually like really had
our fill even when the attention has been kind of replenished
we can keep going in this kind of zero attentional caloric burn mode
and that is um you can start to feel that that feels
different that feels different than the restoration mode is it making sense yeah
so so summing up uh where we are so far um you don't need to
be engaging the attention all the time but be careful be careful in the sort of
doses of mindlessness what's consumed the intervals between engaging
and releasing attention
so this has been a kind of like oh yeah i'm trying to maybe dignify certain forms of
non-mindfulness yeah other species of non-mindfulness are
more corrosive yeah more problematic where we're
we're really kind of actively marinating in the defilements
yeah it's just like the forces of greed hate and delusion
were like actively marinating in them now maybe the traditional view would say any
mindlessness is marinating in the defilements i i don't know but i i
want to just illuminate a distinction that feels real to me
um that that there are other species of being
lost that are more problematic than that kind of
attention just going slack and so
the wellspring of of suffering greed hate and delusion great aversion delusion
um we're very familiar with what greed looks like with what aversion or hate
looks like delusion is slippy more slippery you know and
sometimes delusion itself is defined as just being lost in thought
being lost in thought
when mindfulness collapses we truly are on a train ride
and we never
get to decide where we're going our habits good and bad
make that call they're the conductor yeah
and when when um the the kind of we noticed this the
movement from like okay we were attending to the breathing the movement
from the breathing to being identified with thought is itself thoroughly encased in
unconsciousness yeah it's not like
okay now maybe i'll get lost in some
thoughts of dragons or whatever right
it's just like no we there's this collapse and this move into
off the the breathing and into some thought realm
and then we live in that bubble and we are kind of severed from the
dharma yeah like there there is a very precipitous
collapse that happens in that and
the nature of mindlessness is that it is um
it's a kind of perfect identification with the content of
thought perfect identification with the content of thought
it's this utter collapse of knowing yeah
this is a philosopher metzinger
the beginning of every mind-wandering episode
is marked exactly by the collapse of our epistemic
agent model i'll say unpack this metzinger always talks like this so
the the beginning of every mind wandering episode is marked by the collapse of our epistemic agent model a
conscious representation of now possessing the ability
for epistemic self-control for knowing yeah and the end of every episode of mind
wandering is marked by the re-emergence of a new epistemic agent model the
meta-aware self the self that is then aware the meditator
that then can know uh lost and thought now here
i think it could be fruitful to analyze mind wandering as a loss of mental
autonomy goes on to say
when we're not identified with thought we have a model of ourselves like an
implicit model of ourselves where we can direct our attention we can
direct our thinking we can direct the attention to the breathing or to the body more broadly
or to feeling tone or to the mind right we can do this we have a sense of a model
of where we can exercise attentional control yeah
and when we get lost the epistemic and this is the
word around the the knowing the capacity for knowing
that epistemic agent something capable of knowing collapses
very precipitously yeah in a sense no one's been there to notice
that there's just we just
collapse yeah that model collapses and we become perfectly identified with the
thought and it's literally like like we
become the protagonist of the thought world
and we forget it's just a character yeah
and so we do we truly lose sense of of mental autonomy
and wherever that train is going that's where we're headed
yeah maybe headed to heaven or hell
we are not conducting yeah
in those moments um we are
the dharma feels kind of remote yeah
the default assumptions of that mode of living of being identified with thought
is not full of dhamma
and the moment of coming back is the kind of the re-emergence of
meta m-e-t-a awareness mind some kind of mindfulness
it's the re-emergence that is a moment of mindfulness as every teacher says that's a moment of mindfulness
and once again we we are aware of phenomena as phenomena
yeah we're aware of the body as phenomena the breath as phenomena everything is phenomena again
but that was really deeply forgotten in that collapse of the knowing the
collapse of the epistemic agent
one species of this collapse that
deserves note is is a rumination
yeah so and this brings us back to kalina kristoff yeah
the the rumination the brooding this kind of obsessional
very abstract very deeply lost mode of thinking
is uh is not so good for us yeah
so kristoff writes instead of freely moving from one topic to another individuals prone to riemannation
exhibited longer negative thoughts and negative content
in ruminative individuals was linked to a narrowing in conceptual scope
yeah over time suggested by higher levels of semantic
so higher like the in the ruminative modes
there's less it's this narrowing yeah but we can feel it when we get in those
modes it literally feels claustrophobic yeah the mind feels claustrophobic it feels
narrow we're perseverating about something we're chewing on something and we're
like and there's more similarities with
semantic similarity encoding the words there's more similarity yeah
this is a very congealed sense of self
yeah very congealed and
in the dream of rumination
we've really almost completely forgotten the three characteristics yeah
dukkha anicha natta that
suffering unreliability not self
in our ruminations in that state of deep loss
we fantasize about a durable pleasure that might structure our lives
we fervently hope to tie up all the loose ends of being human and hold the
world still we try to game out uncertainty and find
the path through the labyrinth of a nietzsche of uncertainty on reliability
and we fantasize about taking a refuge in an identity of finally finding our
home in some sense of this is me this is self
all of that are different kinds of dead ends
but we're so earnest in our rumination in our laws
and really the we're trying i think often with
rumination we're trying to solve an affective emotional problem with
thoughts yeah we trust thinking we sort of like it's
the kind of main tool in our problem-solving arsenal
and we over trust it
the word me itself means chewing yeah and um
to ruminate and it's like we're trying to to digest our problem with our thought
yeah and we're just kind of like going to chew
until we feel better but usually wind up feeling worse
and that is because that mode of thinking maybe thoughts generally like
they do not function well as uh
digestive enzymes yeah they just don't
maybe certain kinds of you know speech with one another that can
function that way but when we're in deep in our own heads often
in this ruminative mode things are not being digested it's quicksand
and to enter that realm is to lose
and so the invitation is to go to the body to go to the engine
of feeling i was alluding to this in the in the sit uh
to go to that's like thinking is only
it's it's clinging necessitates thinking yeah
i i don't know that all thinking is a function of clinging but a lot is
and when we find ourselves clinging we
thinking becomes vital yeah we we just feel compelled to think to think our way
to the object of our clinging and so instead of instead of taking that
approach we we go to the body to the engine the engine
of feeling and the thoughts that come off like like exhaust on on off an engine
we we go to the body okay we're willing to feel badly
yeah equanimity with unpleasantness doesn't feel good
yeah there is there is a subtle taste of relief in it
but at least initially it does not feel good but we cannot try to solve
the affect of you know challenges with the thought
itself yeah so we go to the body
and we're we practice patience and equanimity and
begin to release some of the energy of clinging it begins to take some of the
thorns of our thinking the thorns of rumination out
and this reconnects us to the dharma to what
we know to our own wisdom to our goodness
to the path to the buddha
so i offer this for consideration should sit for a moment together
so
so thank you that's uh
i appreciate the opportunity to uh to be with you this morning and
please pick up what is uh useful and leave whatever is uh
all the rest leave that behind
yeah okay i'll uh i'll hang around for a bit if uh you want to chat about anything
so uh thank you thank you all yeah yeah