so good morning everyone good day and i'm happy to be here with
you and to share this sunday time and um
it's a wonderful thing to sit in meditation a chance to show up and be present for
our experience and one of the qualities of meditation that maybe
aselda mentioned is the value of bringing some strength
tapping into or calling on whatever native strength we have
to not to assert ourselves but to really be rooted here to be
present in a full dedicated way to this doing this practice so we're
giving a bit of whatever inner strength we have to let
that strength be activated so that we are stronger
than the mind that wants to wander away not in conflict with that mind but
simply that [Music] the our bill our strength of attention
our attention is given more value more importance and that there's really
kind of a engagement with it that naturally then becomes stronger than our wandering
away distracted mind analogy the buddha often gave is that of the sun
when the sun becomes strong the stars disappear so in the same way when the sun of
awareness gets strong then then you know the distractions tend
to vanish so to take a to assume a meditation posture
and to gently close your eyes
and to as you know in assuming your posture
whether it's it you know there's there's considered before dignified postures
sitting standing walking and lying down
and whichever these postures that's close to how you are
perhaps to assume at least some form of inner
strength or vitality to that posture and one way to do that
is to be clearly here in this posture
clearly here in this body
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
that can be part of the movement towards becoming
rooted here to enter into fully and in a strong way
here and as you exhale
to relax the tensions the holdings of the muscles
softening the shoulders
softening the belly
softening the muscles of the face
and there's a heart to relaxing and softening
which a lot which makes room and space for an inner vitality
and inner aliveness to flow through us more fully in a sense
physical tension constricts her vitality
the deeper fuller the relaxation the more that vitality begins to flow
a vitality that i can have a certain kind of strength maybe a sweet strength or a peaceful
strength
letting your breath return to normal
breathing in and breathing out
one of the strongest muscles in the body is the diaphragm
there is a kind of a strength perseverance
inherent in breathing
to allow the breathing to breathe you
allow breathing to breathe itself
and letting your breathing
be the way that your the strength of your attention
is is rooted here in the present moment in the present
moment breathing breathing at the center of all
things
so
most things that you think about in meditation
you've probably thought about them before and will think about them again
more likely most likely it's not particularly useful to think
about them now there's no need
and so to realize that clearly
and choose again to be with your breathing
with an atten an attention that has a little bit of strength to it
a little bit of investing yourself this is important this is the time
to ride on the waves of breathing
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
it's often considered a special occasion
to sit in meditation to have the time the inclination
to spend time connecting to the dharma practice this way
and at the end of a practice session like this
it's an opportune time to spend a minute or two reflecting
on how this is this practice that we've been doing can be a basis a support
for living in a way that betters the world for others
that we don't meditate in isolation just for me myself and mine
but we meditate open and available and caring for the world around us our
friends our family neighbors and people in our communities
far and wide
and to have the aspiration that whatever benefit we receive from the
meditation spreads outwards into that wider world
may all beings benefit from the goodness of this practice
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
and then before switching over to the dharma talk the
um the announcement is that starting
tomorrow morning for seven days from monday through sunday morning
uh the seven a.m meditation that we've been doing now for about nine months
will be outside of a 30-minute meditation will be 45 minutes
it'll start at uh in california at 6 45 15 minutes to the hour
and uh and the idea is that i think that it's coinciding or doing
being being done together with a week-long retreat i'm teaching and um and also the idea is that uh
for those of you who have been coming in the morning that a longer sitting is might be nice to stretch yourself or to
have a fuller experience to especially for this practice of anapanasati that we're doing
during this time so you're all welcome to come
and then also next week because i'm on the retreat i won't be here to teach the sunday
morning talk and a wonderful new dharma teacher new on our scene
named salah who's the guiding teacher up in
the seattle light in seattle inside meditation center
will be here to give the talk and i'm delighted that you get to meet this wonderful teacher
so
the so i want to share with you some of my
reflections from this weekend and maybe you'll permit me not to
give a dharma talk but maybe a dharma chat since um maybe they're not so well
formulated but the topic is an important one and one that
is i think seldom talked about and maybe even uh there's some
reluctance to teach it here in the united states because that the topic is um is easily something that
is off-putting for people or can it come across as something which is maybe even dangerous
and that is the topic of strength uh that the developing
inner strength and inner power even through this practice of ours
that that is part of what we're doing here in this practice and um i think much of the
way that the inside meditation practice practices taught in the modern west
maybe that's implicit but it's explicitly more language of
acceptance more language of just being with your experience not trying to fix your experience
the idea of personal agency that you have some control some power some
in your ex practice is not really get emphasized
and i think that sometimes maybe it's a shortcoming that we don't do that and
that really developing becoming strong people
is actually one of the benefits of developing and practice becoming a strong person that develops
strong inner core or capacity of various kinds
and it's important because certainly we wanted to have enough strength
to not succumb to our defilements not succumb to greed hate and delusion
not to come to unwholesome unhealthy fear
and one of the things that people are can be afraid of is they can be afraid of themselves
and uh and so certainly be afraid of things out in the world but they can be afraid of themselves
afraid of what they're going to say what they're going to do what they're going to think and what they're going to
feel and so there's a kind of an avoidance of really connecting here
because of this self fear that that can exist now uh but that and that self fear then
also what it does it can easily dampen uh personal strength in fact some people
are afraid of their strength they're afraid that if they are strong that they will
harm someone that they will cause trouble for other people other people be uncomfortable
that somehow they'll be seen as conceited or seen as being somehow assertive too much
in a way that's maybe considered unacceptable in the scenes the situation we're in
and and and then also sometimes this fear of
one's own strength can be related to a fear an idea
that we don't really um have a full right to exist or we're not
really worthy enough to be strong that somehow we're diminished we're less than others
or we should really what what's you know we should really kind of keep small stay small or stay
unnoticed or stay in the back row and somehow diminish ourselves because to
not diminish ourselves sometimes is socially disruptive for the scene that we're in
and sometimes in some families and even some cultures that there's a preference for somehow
not being a little bit
self-effacing a little bit not assertive and certainly that can be quite valuable
and at times of quite healthy and appropriate but it can lend itself for support go
along with a tendency of people to be afraid of their own strength or reluctant to embody it or engage it or
not to realize or appreciate they can be developed and and grow some people are kind of looking
for something that's going to fix them some insight
some in experience something that's going to be their savior from the
difficulties they have and so they're kind of a little bit looking outside of themselves
for a and and one of the things about strength as strength and practice
develops there's something that grows from the inside out that is little bit has the effect of
of not solving problems not providing an answer per se but we grow
in such a way that like the snake that grows the skin gets shed
the old skin gets shed and there's something about cultivating developing a strong inner strength or
sense of power or powers or strengths maybe in the plural
that makes us grow and old things just get shed they fall fall off us
rather than needing to be solved so to spend too much time trying to solve problems sometimes as a
dead end solve our inner turmoils and challenges sometimes it's actually more useful to
develop a strength so for example a strength in mindfulness a strength and concentration
as strength and ethics integrity a strength in impatience and strength in telling the
truth and being truthful to oneself or maybe to others as really a strength of presence really
to and sometimes that can be done physically in fact so much of what can be developed in
practice develops stronger develops more more more effectively
if there's a kind of embodied association or embodied
connection to actually doing this embodied mindfulness embodied
presence embodied truth so um clearly the buddha wanted people
to be strong and in buddhist practice develops inner strength
and as i said ideally we become stronger than our defilements so we don't cause problems in the world
or problems for ourselves and some of the language the buddha used in his teachings
are language words that i associate with strength the words like ardency with practice in an ardent way to
the word that's often translated as effort which kind of it the word effort is a
fine word but it's kind of a neutral neutral word just effort it doesn't carry any
strength in it and the word that's often translated as effort is viria and viria probably more
appropriately should be translated as something like courageous effort um that the word vira
that viri is part of is a word for hero i've been told that in modern india
it's the word for a soldier and so a heroic effort i think is sometimes the
way it's translated in maybe in tibetan buddhism where they use the word hero that
in related terms the idea of courageous effort and
and then also the word power itself and that is used and and as people
develop in freedom in buddhism greater freedom including a freedom from conceit
they are frequently depicted as being coming powerful language and symbolism of mature
practitioners is often with uh represented by images of power
so for example there's a delightful suta where someone who develops uh
some degree of freedom initial degree of freedom um together with the seven five seven
powers of awakening seven factors of awakening is described as be having a
great self a large self and it's a little bit surprising to hear
this language of self use in such a definitive way a great self a large self and that great
self and large self is uh represented or is the
analogy for it is a kind of a great mythic being that develops that grows in the great
himalayan mountains that's a it's kind of a river spirit a river serpent
and uh and so it's called the naga and uh in this case naga means many
things but one of the things these river spirit uh serpents and that a person a person develops some
initial taste of freedom uh becomes one of these great
nagas of with uh who are of a great self and a large self
expansive self is one translation the um and one of the also delightful
uh expressions of the power the strength that a practitioner can have is uh in what's
called the lion's roar it was something that the people the time of the buddha the buddha did this
and other people did it as well they would declare their full awakening when someone came and told the buddha
that they had then now they were fully awakened that was referred to their lions roar
and i don't know if you've ever been close to a lion that roared but i have fortunately it for me
at the zoo maybe not fortunately for the lion but i was probably only standing only
four or five feet away from the lion and with bars between us
and the roar that it uh directed in my direction was one that commanded a tremendous
amount of respect it had felt it had a primordial feeling that the like the whole bowels of the
earth were kind of roaring at me and and i thought the only respectful the
only proper thing to do with that war was to walk away
so the lions roar not that we're supposed to walk away from in lines enlightened people but it's a it's a
expression that conveys great confidence and great strength so so one of the things that are called
powers in buddhism and here we see the powers are not meant to be powers that we on other people
but rather inner capacities that we have the five powers are the five faculties
when they're strong and these are faith or confidence to have a
conf the power of confidence of faith the power of this courageous effort that
the courageous effort has now become something a real strength that we carry with us the power of mindfulness the power of
samadhi usually translates concentration and the power of wisdom what a great power to have wisdom be
wise in a way that has a real strength that we carry with us
another place where we seek i associate with powers what's called the four resolves and
the pali word is aditana which is a means could almost more literally be
translated in english as taking a stand the etymology of the word
and but usually as resolves and and so what we have resolved for is what
there's a power there's a strength behind us in doing it and and so these are also interesting
lists again it's not power over others so it's um the first one resolve is
not neglecting wisdom the second one is um
is um
preserving protecting the truth the third is cultivating the capacity to
let go to relinquish and the fourth is to train in peace train peacefully
train to become more peaceful to so to develop a strength of being
peaceful sometimes we don't associate i think power and peacefulness together it's
almost like peacefulness is is an alternative to being powerful but the power the resolve
of being peaceful so living in a confident committed and
dignified fashion is are some of the associations with this developing this power this
capacity to be and so there's not in itself if there's not a there's a there's
it doesn't look from the outside like some developed practitioner is self-effacing
at least not in how they carry and hold themselves but it is in terms of not having any
conceit or arrogance letting go of being self-centered at the same time as being
strongly centered no egotistical center but a strong
centered in our lived vital experience of being here and present
one of the ways we might understand this is to live in a manner where there's no
need to apologize for ourselves i think there's a strong tendency in the
united states for some people to constantly want to say they're sorry to apologize to
to kind of diminish themselves for exerting themselves or being even being and i think that to live in a
way that we don't have to apologize not regularly of course not regularly not as a policy not as a
second nature thing to always feel sorry or apologize and the way to do that in buddhism is to
live what the buddha called the blameless life a life the blamelessness that is meant to
bring a certain kind of joy the strength of a blameless life and this is to live a life
that adheres to the precepts to not harm people not intentionally be
involved in causing hurt or harm through killing and stealing and sexual misconduct and lying and
and using intoxicants and to really have confidence that one is living this way
um to the end we end up living a life we don't apologize for ourselves
to be blameless and uh i don't think it's second nature for many of the people here in this country
but um it's uh but if you can live that way then you're encouraged to feel the joy
of that the joy and the power of a blameless life an unapologetic life
in the dhammapada there's wonderful descriptions of of strong
people that they don't use the word strong but i think we can substitute it
reasonably enough and there's a whole chapter called the brahmana the brahmanas were kind of the the
priests of the brahmanical religion they're also a hereditary role so there
were families there were brahmanical families and they thought thought of themselves as being the top
class in society and the dominant class and often they were
had a lot of authority sometimes and owned a lot of land had a lot of wealth
and they're responsible for the religious rituals of the brahmanical religion and um there was often a kind of not
just in buddhism but in other areas of india as well a kind of jockeying for
position or um you know but who was it really should be dominant
or what kind of kind of critique of the dominance of the brahmanas and the buddha he did this by
redefining what it means to be a brahmana and he defined a brahmana as someone who
has some degree of spiritual awakening and so so here are some examples of
these ways which he says this this is a verse from the dhammapada
who has no clinging who has nothing i call the brahmana
so at first no clinging having nothing that doesn't really seem like a
situation of power or strength or you know an important class of people in society or
some someone to revere or something who has no clinging who has
nothing i call the brahmin whoever is most excellent a bull
a hero a great sage a conqueror free of craving cleansed
awakened i call a brahmana so here now that's all these are all synonyms for
the same person all kind of describing the same kind of person here they're talking about excellence a
bull which is a powerful uh animal a hero which has
strength to it and a conqueror now this can be quite off-putting for
many people in the west to have these kind of masculine seeming words or concepts associated
with it but but there is clearly a show associated with
non-clinging freedom from craving inner cleanliness
it's not an assertiveness or a dominance the idea of conquering being a conqueror
is really becoming conquer of one's own defilements one's own inner attachments and clinging one
conquers oneself in a sense not others so we get this
clear example in other verses that this power strength of a
practitioner is not meant to be over other people it's really over themselves
in these verses having given up violence towards beings both timid and
strong whoever neither kills or causes others to kill
i call a brahmana i call i say is strong whoever is not
adversarial among those who are peaceful among those who are violent not clinging
among those who cling i call a brahmana whoever lets passion
hostility conceit and hypocrisy fall away like a mustard seed from the tip of an
all i call a brahmana who speaks
what is true informative and not harsh who gives offenses offense to no one
i call a brahmana so for me in in these
these verses all this emphasis on non-harming is presented in a way that prevents a
real strength of people there's a dedication a community this definitively this is what a person is
this idea of a blameless life that doesn't cause harm in any kind of way to do that with strength and be able to
stand up in a dignified to be in dignified confident way
to carry oneself in the world with confidence to no one sells well enough to know all
the forces of fear self-belittlement self-fear
the ways that we self-criticize ourself or and kind of become less than who we are
and to learn to shed those to learn to not have them diminish us us so that our native
strength we don't we're not it's not assertive strength it's not like puffing ourselves up in
some arrogant macho but rather the native strength of who we
are can be there in a simple natural full way it's not we don't
we don't diminish it we don't apologize for it we don't you know
hide it or hide from it that somehow we're allowed to be
strong we're allowed to be present fully embodied in here in a clear definitive
way we are worthy of that in fact one of the the meaning for our our heart someone is fully awakened
literally means a worthy one and uh i i kind of like to translate to
interpret that i mean they're worthy of really being present to being here and alive and full
so that one of the goals of buddhist practice is to become fearless and and part of that is to stop
undermining ourselves through fear and the fear that i wanted to emphasize
today in this chat is self fear how we are afraid of ourselves
and therefore diminish ourselves and and kind of undermine our strength
so to do this it helps to take stock of our fear of how we're afraid of ourselves including
our fear of being strong this then allows us to address these
fears and develop growing confidence in our capacity to live intentionally without
harming anyone including ourselves so um i hope that
these ideas that i've presented here uh are meaningful enough for you for you
to reflect and consider a little bit how it is that um it's a pro how in what appropriate way
can you step up and uh and allow for yourself
to have a native power native strength of someone who metaphorically
stands their ground speaks speaks freely and confidently
what they feel like they have to say can talk honestly can doesn't diminish themselves but just
as they're allowed to be present and fully there and have a voice and show up and um
and that uh that is i think one of the great benefits from doing mindfulness practice
the mindfulness practice that helps us to let go of any force within us
that diminishes us that undermines our native natural strength that's here
and in doing so um we might end up looking like strong people
in the eyes of others but in our in our own inner sense we won't
necessarily feel that we are now strong but the inner sense is feeling now we're
free and but to be free from the outside will look as if we become strong so
i hope that you will think about this and reflect on it and so hopefully there's something of what i said today
that will be useful for you and i would love to meet each of you in your
strength so thank you all very much