so hello everyone and
and perhaps i can welcome you to the beginning of the week start of a new
week for many of us and
it's nice to start it here so um one of the
sometimes it said that one of the first lessons that are useful to learn if you start
meditating is the importance of patience
and sooner or later meditators learn patience
learn a variety of different ways by which to
not give in to forces of stress or judgment or
frustration or discouragement or
because sooner or later we'll find that the mind has a mind of its own that it
has strong impulses strong patterns of thinking that
and and rather than fighting it there is some sooner or later a patience
a willingness to steadily calmly work with it practice with it
not to collapse around what we discover what happens with our emotions our thoughts or
our attitudes our challenges we have and there's many different forms of
patients and uh discovering some of the different
flavors of patients is part of what can be quite wonderful
as we practice over a long extended period of time
so today to sit with patients sit with patients with all things that
are unresolved in your life to be patient with
the challenges that you could show up as you meditate not to
have a version to it or disrespect it to dismiss it but not to succumb to stress
around having it not to succumb to aversion
or not to succumb to pressure to change it and fix it
but rather the patience that allows us to be still and quiet and attentive
attentively quietly recognizing what is actually happening
for us what is it we have what is it that we is happening
that gives us reason for patience and to sit quietly in the middle of that
breathe with it sense it feel it without getting caught up in fixing and thinking
and analyzing just as quiet abiding in the midst of what's actually
happening a serious recognition serious
engagement with our life through this wonderful avenue
of quiet abiding in the midst of what arises
so assuming a meditation posture
and
perhaps relaxing your gaze
maybe letting your eyes gaze downward
and relaxed soft
and if it's comfortable to close your eyes you could close
gently
and if it's comfortable to take some gentle but deeper
breaths that expands the rib cage
maybe deep enough that it lifts the shoulders a bit
deep enough that if you have a back rest or your back is up
against some surface you feel the pressure
if you breathe in against that surface the back ribcage
and letting your breathing return to normal
on the exhale
to relax whatever's tension or stress that's easy to soften relax
unwind
a kind of releasing throughout the body as you exhale
perhaps if it's comfortable for you you can imagine that as you breathe
that the breathing the energy of breathing the sensations
are breathing move through the whole body
maybe as if you're not breathing through the nose or the mouth but you're breathing through the whole
body in and out
and as you exhale softening the mind
relaxing the pressure to think the contraction of
thinking
if you think in words slowing the words down in the mind
if you think in images slowing the images
and if there's a lot of feelings emotions maybe there's some place like the heart
maybe the hands the belly
that you can relax a bit soften
and now to center yourself on the breathing
the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
and perhaps the ongoing rhythm of breathing
staying close to it will help you
to be patient
with whatever goes on during meditation
that might be difficult perhaps staying close to your breathing
and breathing through it
or staying centered and grounded with breathing
remembering to be patient with all things one breath at a time
um
what could you be patient about now
that would support you to be here quieter stiller
attentive not reactive
and perhaps the gentle rhythm of breathing can support you to be patient
so then as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps we can dedicate some of the benefit from sitting and meditating
the known benefits and the unknown benefits dedicated for the welfare of the world
for the benefit of others perhaps if we're more patient for
meditating
we can be more patient with other people
more patient with their shortcomings their challenges
more patient as they find their way in this difficult life
they're kind of giving more room for people to be without them being the recipient
of our stress of our reactivity
our impatience
may it be through this practice that patience is much more than patience
it's a gift
in being able to be present for people as they are
free of our projections our needs our reactions
may through this practice of mindfulness may our attention to others
be a gift
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may our patients support that possibility
[Music]
thank you
so here we are first day of the week monday
first day for our next series and uh for these five days
i would like to uh spend our time reflecting thinking about focusing on
patients the poly word for patients kanti
h a t k h a n t i
um shanti in sanskrit
it's a really rich word and perhaps as rich as the word patience
but it's multifaceted and it's a relevant
the very start of doing buddhist practice as i said
meditation you have to if you don't learn patience quickly meditation is going to be much harder
than it needs to be and uh it's also uh
characterizes some of the deepest insights some of the deepest places to abide in to dwell in
in meditation but there's a kind of a something that's called kanti something that's called patience
and so there's many forms of patience and i'll talk about different ones
and over these five days and um
the um but patience is needed
not because it's just a virtue you always just practice it because it's good to do
but patience is a response or a practice to things that are challenging
and so when we get reactive in ways that are unhealthy for us and
not healthy for others sometimes patience is a better um
better response than anger or resentment or being stressed or
being kind of getting tense around what's happening and so this capacity to appreciate the
value of patients and understand how it enhances us brings out the best in us as opposed to
patients with a damp it dampens us down or represses us in some way and
and uh is actually adds stress to the system rather than freeze it to it
so um today i want to talk a little bit about um
i'll tell you the five themes of patients for the week the first today is going to be
um patience which is being staying true
under stress staying true to ourselves under stress
tomorrow it's gentle perseverance under
difficulties under challenges wednesday will be
patients under insult things that happen in the in our life how people treat us
to be patient with the insults and so what does that mean and then
thursday will be forgiveness
when insulted and so how's that healthy how is that done in a healthy way
and then um friday is the kind of the deepest form of patience and the word kanti is used for this and
whether patience is the right word in english or not but this has to do with a certain
very deep patience with the some of the deepest truths that we
can touch into through buddhist practice some of the deepest realization insights
that are you know it sounds wonderful to have insights um deep realizations but
some of them are challenging to have and so to develop patients around these these
these things which are phenomenally true but but you know it's challenging to do
so for example we can realize at some point i have insight and realization at some
point of the possibility of not clinging to anything
but then we end up clinging a lot so how do we and and uh and it can be frightening this idea that let go of to
really not cling and so to be patient to be accepting to be
somehow some kind of healthy tolerance for this truth that clinging is not
worthwhile so today the topic is being true under stress
and what i mean by this and this is particularly meant for people who i'm thinking in my mind i'm thinking about
people have some kind of ongoing spiritual practice like meditation practice
that at some point we start uh having access or
start experiencing a way of being that feels true feels truer
than being greedy being hateful being tense a lot being afraid a lot
is truer than kind of being lost in fantasy and spinning around in thoughts
and when when the thoughts quiet down when we feel more connected to ourselves more subtle on ourselves when we're not
ahead of ourselves not behind ourselves we're not not when we're not kind of carrying the weight of
the world on our shoulders um that then we can feel like oh now i'm more
myself i'm more alive i'm more connected there's something here which feels true
and honest and so to connect to this honesty to this true way of being
so it could just be maybe i'm talking a little bit in grand terms it could be
that something like meditation just helps us to be calmer a little bit and then uh and that feels right to not
to the calm feels a little bit commerce feels better than being agitated
and so there's a reference point something that feels healthy and good and desirable a way of being
and so to be patient is this for people have access to that
is to stay true to it in stressful situations and um
there's a lot of you know infinite number of situations we might find ourselves in that are stressful
it could be the most mundane it could be that we're late for the dentist
and and so we feel we have to rush and be anxious and worry but we know that when we rush and worry
that way that we actually lose touch with what's true about ourselves something that's true or connected or
real or valuable way of being and so maybe so to be patient
is to not give in to that rush not give in to the the thoughts of worry that are spinning
stories and stories but to be patient with ourselves
is to stay true to what we know is there and what this means is that for people who don't have access to some way of
being that feels like right way of being or better or satisfying way of being
then patience might seem like just a a um a you know i don't know
an obligation it's like a work you know now i have to work at this too being patient and
and it's just kind of a drag because it's just like imposing a certain kind of virtue on top of us
but if we know something that's valuable if we know a way of being that's healthy and good
then to be patient is not to give that up
easily and not to easily succumb to the temptation to be angry the temptation to be worried
temptation to want things to be different and the impulse strong kind of movements of
impatience that might be there and so to give give let go of the impatience
so that we can stay closer to what we feel is valuable and at ease
and and uh and so
and sometimes this idea of patience has less to do with a way of being
patient as it is letting go of the impatience whatever that
is the forces of impatience so that we can be something that feels innate and healthy
and good not to hold on to it not to construct something but let go into something deeper that we have
so one of the exercises you might think of that goes along with what i'm saying today
is when you meditate and maybe you want to maybe meditate a little extra this week
so you can do this exercise it doesn't have to be long a 10-minute meditation and
is to um when you finish your meditation if you're a little calmer or more subtle
than you were before more connected then
get up from that meditation and stay very carefully attentive
to when you begin losing that calm losing that subtleness
and when you do stop in your tracks and
maybe can you close your eyes and check in with yourself and see what just happened here
and did anything happen here that was a symptom of impatience
and what would it and maybe could i come back since it just happened
just a few moments ago that i started to get tense or hurried can i settle back
into this place of calm or subtleness what i'm calling
and this is what i call being true under stress so there might be good
reasons to start hurrying and rushing and getting tense but it's not necessarily the best thing
to do even if the reasons are there the results of being stressful is stressed
and doing these reactive things is we're less wise we're less involved more forgetful more easy to make mistakes
and sometimes when we don't have to redo things uh because we stay calm and do them carefully the first time
it's actually more efficient so try this exercise when you come out of
meditation maybe even today and after this talk
is notice when you begin losing some subtleness or calm
and then see what would it be like to be patient would it be like to be true to yourself
under stress so first type of patience
being true on staying true under stress
so um i hope that as we go through um these
five different kinds of patients that uh it's kind of a little journey for all of us into kind of a deeper and
deeper dimension of of um this parts of our lives
so thank you and i look forward to being here tomorrow