recording recording okay so so now a formal form well hello and
welcome so the theme for today um
we're going to continue with um [Music] the theme of gratitude which we started
on friday and it was so um rich so
rich that there was a sense i felt in the sangha that oh yeah let's continue with this there are many many more
explorations and a few of you free of you said that so so we will
explore we'll continue with the exploration of gratitude
in pali those who like the pali words and in happy hour for those
who've been listening for a while and coming for a while you know that we each time we try to take a slightly
different new perspective on these practices and explore as a scientist of our own
mind to discover something new something slightly different
with a spirit of curiosity as an experiment and an experiment is always successful
because you learn something you learn about what works for you what doesn't work etc you learn something about
the practice as well as this as well as cultivation there's always
cultivation happening so so the perspective that we'll
take tonight with gratitude is one of simplicity of the moment
so as always we'll start by settling the mind and heart with a few minutes of
of calm abiding calming the mind and then starting with just simplicity
with the simplicity of gratitude or appreciation for
this mystery called life and the invitation the invitation to
play around with is to imagine you are a young
child if you have been around young children lately or ever for especially if they're
you know one or two years old there is this sense of wonder there's a sense of joy there's a sense
of everything is new everything is amazing there is no
good bad future past it's just amazing there's this sense of awe for
the mystery of being alive being here i had the
privilege to be around a year and a half old this weekend and
it was lovely to to observe the way this little girl was eating up the world
the waves of the ocean dipping her waves in the cold waves and just wow this is fun it's cold i'm totally
wet i'm shivering and yet this is interesting the sense of
awe wonder oh wonder and with that sense of appreciation
gratitude there's no good there's no bad it's just amazing in this
impermanent life that is ours
flash of lightning across this vast sky of
being you just show up it's all an amazing show and from that perspective
all our worries and fears and trepidations and
insecurities and want this don't have that greed hatred and delusion
it's a way to step out of ourselves into appreciation so so having set the stage
let's begin let's begin by settling into our bodies
ah landing landing
whether you're sitting or lying down deciding what works best for you for
your body in this moment whatever posture
and arriving with each in-breath
each out breath exhaling long settled
here
feeling contact points feet
at the floor
your sit bones on the cushion
the chair
and with each out breath landing landing into her lower body
ah letting go of any tightness or holding
connecting connecting with each breath in the lower abdomen each breath
cleansing settling
soothing
just taking our time to settle and arrive
in this body this amazing body that knows how to breathe
fully present here turning our gaze inward
greeting ourselves
greeting ourselves with friendliness
each in breath each out breath long exhale
a friendly greeting
just this breath just this one
not the next one not the previous one
just this moment simple
welcoming settling peace and quiet as much as
it is available in this moment
and if thoughts plans memories are arising
it's okay no need to judge oneself simply
acknowledging thank you thought but right now i'm
giving my heart to this practice
please come back later smilingly turning
ah to take refuge in just the simplicity of this moment
as we till the soil and prepare
for our next practice
as each breath is breathed in
to the abdomen the lower part of your body
noticing
noticing sense of immediacy
the freshness
what can be called the now-ness the now-ness
fleeting nowness
as if your awareness
is standing at a revolving door
awareness
not going through the door past present staying at the revolving door
as the new experiences keep arriving
new breath arrives rises crests
like a wave rising falling always
awareness
fresh standing at this revolving door
the point the point of view of nowness
even if the mind can stabilize then this viewpoint for a moment
or if it can simply set up an easy chair and just rest here
hanging out
knowing observing experience as it arises and passes away
almost feels like a miracle
this knowing is awareness
and whatever experience is coming through the revolving door coming and going
whether it's the sensations of the breath this wavelength
sensation or sensations so many of them
fell through the abdomen
chest the whole body
whatever else is arising
this revolving door of experience being known
in this nowness
other sensations in the body
quite miraculous
whatever experiences arising
and the knowing of it
or sounds arising right here at this moment heard
arising and passing
this now-ness experience are rising and passing
through this pinhole of knowing
quite miraculous this whole show
to have a first row seat this conscious experience
this mind this heart this being
the only one
looking through this pinhole of experience and this nowness
having these experiences of life
in its particularities yes we're all humans and yet
in its particularities the way it's showing up in this moment
for me so intimate
not taking it for granted
so fascinating
experience of being human
is miracle mystery
we each have a front row seat
too in this moment
just observing with interest curiosity for it to reveal itself
with patience with appreciation
with this perspective in the present moment appreciating
really waking up to this mystery
passing every moment
all amazing
even what we usually call unpleasant
perhaps an unpleasant sensation or pain in the body or a loud noise
it all becomes fascinating from this perspective
amazing sensations wow interesting
interesting sounds rising and passing
sense of gratitude and appreciation
for having this conscious experience
knowing it's all impermanent
moving through the pinhole of experience the revolving door just here
just now
i will read the poem by e.e cummings let it wash over you
i thank you god for most this amazing day
for the leaping greenly spirits of trees
and the blue true dream of sky
and for everything which is natural which is infinite which is yes
i who have died i'm alive again today
and this is the son's birthday
this is the birth day of life and of love and wings
and of the gray of the gay great happening illimitably
earth how should tasting
touching hearing seeing breathing
any lifted from the know of all nothing human merely being
doubt unimaginable you now the ears of my ears
[Music] awake and now the eyes of my eyes are opened
for the last few minutes notice what is it in your experience in this
nowness seeing hearing touching [Music]
breathing tasting
being
this amazing experience of just being
witch the many have you have i been taking for granted
what if it wasn't here
this sense didn't exist
and letting go letting go of any
judgments however this practice period was or wasn't
appreciating appreciating
having shown up and even if there was
awareness mindfulness connecting this moment even for a moment giving
thanks giving thanks
thank you all thank you for your practice
so welcome back
so before i open
the floor for reflection and to ask you for a moment
to look around your space just look around the room you're in
with fresh eyes there's any new appreciation with fresh eyes really take your time
maybe look at one object either the process of looking or the object itself
with fresh eyes
of appreciation of just seeing the object being seen
before turning your gaze back so so we have a few minutes for
reflections questions comments what you discovered complaints it's all welcome
for the benefit of the sangha what did you discover
what a rows for you questions are okay too and if you type them in chat if they're
typed just to me i won't say your name i'll just read the reflection privately if it's typed to everyone then
i'll read it all publicly you can also raise your zoom hand
[Music] and i'll have you a new
question coming do you feel a somatic difference in your body between feeling meta and
feeling gratitude um yes
i do that's a good question how about you the person who's asked
this question i wonder if you like to comment um if you'd like to say more you're
welcome to unmute yourself now and if not it's okay
you can or you can also ask me to elaborate okay yeah so yeah for me there is a
difference um maybe
where do you feel it ah um
all right so it's interesting i've never been asked this question so let me tune in so so
with gratitude what i sense um is is
um you know it's gratitude and joy i think yeah gratitude they're they're
nuances of joy when when i when i practice gratitude there is
whereas meta can can have gladness can but it's more
turned towards towards others towards myself so there's friendliness but but
gratitude has has more joy in it has more brightness in it
that's the best i can describe it right now but then again don't take my word for it see what works for you and i would be
curious about your your report
bill says it's hard to stay still in front of the revolving door yes that is true it is it's a it's a
practice exactly but as long as we if you're able to even stay for a moment it can be
so amazing um to even try to stay there and be there for
a little bit nicholas says today was a lovely opportunity to sit with discomfort and unpleasant
sensations in the body ah i love how you put that nicholas a lovely opportunity to sit with
discomfort and unpleasant sensations in the body and nicholas you're welcome to raise
your hand if you i would love to hear you explore expand a little more
if you would with that the sitting with those sensations and this kind of so i'm
going to ask mark uh tell you what now actually i'll ask nicholas to continue with that and then i'll go to mario christine so
nicholas you're up yeah the the chest
was was not aligned very well and so there was just a lot of tightness and sharpness and it was
moving around and uh it was
yeah i felt the the the push to try to meta it away it's
like oh there's some aversion here oh there's some like why is it contracted it's like oh maybe meta will push it away and
there's a few minutes of that and then they kind of yeah there was this this nice moment of
oh it's uncomfortable to be in this body right now oh like what is that like
and it kind of yeah it just shifted the discomfort didn't go away for the whole set it was an uncomfortable sit but
there was that kind of falling back into being annoyed and hoping it goes away and then
coming back and recognizing that a version is there and just kind of feeling the the
back and forth um and yeah it was it was lovely in its own way
yeah thank you nicholas this is fantastic and i want to highlight what you said
um for for benefit of the sangha because what you described was so and so
beautifully you mindfully observed in your practice that there's this desire to meta it away
we often do that like okay so there's aversions like okay i'm going to
meta this thing away this unpleasantness whereas when when that falls away and you fell
into like the revolving door this is what's showing up right now this this this unpleasant weight enough
feeling tone and ex this is what's showing up oh
this is this and that too can feel amazing and incredible and
just mysterious and it's which you're smiling so i think it
sounds like you got a taste of that yeah yeah yes it's
there's there's an ease that holds the unpleasantness it's still unpleasant but there's a sense of it's not the maybe the
urgency of like needing it to go away somehow that thirst kind of settles down i don't
it's hard to describe it's hard to describe but that's it there's the ease that holds the unplug it's it's it it's the ease that holds it
it's it's it's still here it's not gone away but it's held with ease
that's exactly it that's an important insight remember this nicholas
thank you for sharing thank you awesome mari christine please
oops wait you're still muted you're still muted my christine there okay for me meta is something that
happened happens outwardly from me to the outside world whereas gratitude is what
comes in i don't know if that makes sense of course it does absolutely yeah thank
you for describing how it shows up for you that's lovely yeah thank you
yeah yeah great now there's one more example of that of of and this
is an invitation for all of you to now explore this this beautiful question that came through
yeah nice yeah and i think this uh this reflection i
think from here was meant for everyone uh came to me it is wondrous to sit alone in my sanctuary
with all of you worldwide sangha well that's beautiful thank you it's lovely so glad you're joining us
and eric make this the last reflection before we turn to small groups
i had this experience when i was sick the last time i was asking myself like what if this
were to continue forever uh would i be okay with this is there a way i could be okay with this
and i didn't know i was like i don't know it seems pretty bad
i kind of had a similar experience today
yeah so so help me understand so
yeah i guess i just wasn't able to tap into like a gratitude nicholas was saying
like how he found like an ease around the unpleasantness yeah yeah yeah i just wasn't able to
find that yeah so you're saying there was some discomfort in the body
is that oh yes so there was some discomfort in the body and and then did the question come up
that what if this continues and there wasn't ease with it there was a sense of overwhelms
some helped me connect the dots eric yeah i felt uh
i couldn't find gratitude for it yeah yeah yeah yeah so
and that's okay that's perfectly fine it's you know the insights don't always arise
so so one way to work towards that the invitation it would be
this would be to [Music]
pull back first into calm into spaciousness and breathe
around the difficulty and see if there can be breathing
around this pain this difficulty kind of breathing around it right not breathing it away and not
making it all okay but just kind of like it can it be here and can i breathe around it can i breathe around
it can i breathe peace around it that would that could be a way
to gently you know build a little yellow blick brick road using a
different uh metaphor towards it does that make sense what i'm talking about breathing
peace and space around the difficulty it does it does yeah so that would be my
invitation eric if that arises again yeah thank you for that really appreciate you
bringing that up yeah so dear ones
let's turn to practicing into small um groups together for
six seven minutes and the invitation today is we will start with um
15 seconds of uh silent meta when we go into the small
rooms of three or four and then after the let's say 15 seconds of meta
then sharing as little or as much as you like with each other about your practice your insights and
caring for yourselves caring for each other and um yeah so the rooms are open
take care of yourselves take care of each other with metta and here we go
okay well welcome back everyone um so we've got a minute or two
if you have any reflections would love to hear your reflections especially if you haven't spoken and
shared in a while so please feel free to raise your hand or type in chat what did you
discover why did you discover especially being groups together you know as i'll wait for your hand to
raise or your your comments to come in chat um i wanted to say
earlier when bill said that oh being at the revolving door is is not easy i wanted to say yes
this is this is kind of advanced practice and you guys are game you guys are jumping in with me so this
is this is not beginner's practice and yet it it even if if it's accessible for a moment
or two if and and actually i would be curious if if it was accessible for you even for a split second or even for a
second to be in this this revolving door um use your would you use your reactions and
tight and and click choose yes the check mark
um [Music] let's see seven eight nine okay i see
all right for a bunch of pk great great thank you for that cool yeah great so let's see a couple of
uh reflections a private question came through yes the answer is yes to
that and then casey says learned a lot today thank you nicholas and eric for your chairs oh that's great
patricia thank you breakout room it was brief but lovely sharing oh that's very sweet
so all right dear ones it seems like this is it we have come to the end of
our time somebody's see yes i think that was a clap not a question i take it i don't know who that
was but anyway it's 701 and um i will stay a few minutes
extra and um wanted to thank you all for showing up
and sharing of yourself sharing your practice cultivating your heart
and mind may all beings be free may all beings be happy including ourselves
thank you