so hello hello and welcome to this edition of happy hour everyone
so for today's practice um i'd like to invite us to consider
[Music] this practice of granting others autonomy granting others their autonomy
in our hearts and our minds with a sense of well good will for them so
[Music] it's a practice of i think one way to think
of this practice is the practice of but maybe tonight i'd like to invite us
to lean into it as you know you care for someone a friend a relative
um maybe a child in this i've heard comes
up a lot for adult children especially when they're all grown up and yet um you care for them so much they can
also come up with parents when we grow up and we want to care for our parents there's such a sense of
care and love and menta and oh
we just wish it would be different right for them we just wish
um gosh that would make different decisions or or if it wasn't so hard at this point we
somehow want to make it all better make it go away make the pain go away make
the difficulty go and we really want that we care for for this friend for this child for this
parent for this for this other being but this other being could could
also be a pet could be a four-legged friend or an animal so we want so
much um to make it all go away and yet and yet and yet we know that
by really wanting to make it all better it doesn't work for them it doesn't work
for us we can step on their toes they might feel belittled
as if they don't have a sense of autonomy and so how to manage how to manage holding
with a sense of care and love not with aloofness not with oh okay i'll just turn away and not
look at all the the sense of care and yet respecting respecting
their autonomy that every being all beings have their own journeys
and their lives equal unfold their lives our lives all of our lives
unfold according to causes and conditions that have been set in
motion when long before we arrived with our genes with our experiences and
of course the decisions that we make are part of those causes and conditions but
not the entire picture so so this is an invitation to nitrix to
practice engage with this practice in the way of continuing to love and care
for this being and also honor appreciate their path that need
they need to go through as it needs to unfold for them to
perhaps learn the lessons they need to learn um through the challenge through the
difficulty through the dukkha through the suffering that might be presenting itself
at this moment and continue to care continue to care
so so with that as the frame
like to invite us to engage in this practice so let us
let us begin let us settle as always into our bodies
to this moment arriving
first arriving arriving arriving letting go of all the words
becoming tuned sensitive to what is here right now
relaxing softening the body
to become more aware more present more attuned
to what's here with the breath with the sensations of the body here
now
letting the breath be received
in the abdomen sensations of the breath
lowering the center of the gravity from the head to the abdomen
letting go letting go of thoughts as they come up
let go of thoughting thinking [Music] thank you thank you
so it's not now not needed right now
please please come back later
leaning leaning into
the sense of being present aware here
the body and the breath
here just here deliciously just here
now
receiving the breath received in the abdomen
just connecting connecting as if it's a cleansing
as if it's a cleansing of the heart the mind the body to connect with age
and breath each out breath purifying
refreshing
noticing the sense of well-being with each and every breath
as much well-being as there may be maybe a tiny bit
or might be if founded received
and now bringing to mind if you want bringing to mind
inviting to your heart space it being
whom you care about an object of your affection
perhaps is going through a challenging time there or there are some challenges in
their lives and part of you wish you could make it all go away
bringing that being into your mind into your heart space
and first first appreciating with gratitude
the goodness the friendship you've had a relationship you've had
just the goodness that this person
has brought into your life for this being could be a pet
just taking time first to appreciate
your connection the goodness of it
choosing to focus on the good of course relationships are always a
mixed bag choosing to focus on the good in this moment
bring forth the goodness
appreciating their good qualities
appreciating the sense of care good will
kindness warmth you have for them however it shows up for you maybe it's love
however it shows up for you tuning into this goodness
this care this meta for them
it's feeling coming forth from a sense of appreciation for them
and now allow this sense of care this meta to meet the challenge they're going
through in their life right now
allowing metta this care to be expressed as compassion when good you will meets
pain suffering it becomes compassion oh dear one may you be free may you be
free from what is challenging right now i wish you well i wish you
ease i care i care for your pain i care for your
sorrow i care for your sadness disappointment
you hold your suffering with ease
allowing compassion to arise
from metta which which itself arose from appreciation
i hold you with care may you have ease
may you have well-being yes in the midst of this challenge
and now
allowing practice of compassion karuna
to transition to practice of equanimity upeka
bringing to heart letting the heart still be warm with care
and appreciating appreciating that this being
appreciating that this being
the unfolding the unfolding of their life right now
is happening according
to causes and conditions
which you may or may not understand which actually you may not we do not
understand all the causes and conditions the buddha said
that's one of the imponderables if you try to understand all the causes and conditions your head will explode
so keeping this person this being in mind with care i care for you
i care for you and i cannot
take away all the suffering
may i accept and see that all beings have their own journey
all beings all beings have their own journey
i care for you i care for you
but i'm not in control of your happiness and unhappiness
i wish you happiness i wish you well
but i have not been able to and i cannot make your choices for you
i wish you well i care for you
whether or not i understand it
whether i understand it or not things are unfolding according to a
lawful nature according to causes and conditions
i care for you and i offer you autonomy
i gift you in my heart i gift you a sense of
autonomy to grow to learn
to have your own journey
and i continue to hold you with care
may i accept that things are as they are for you right now
continue to care there and accept things as they are
any of these phrases or nuances that work for you you're welcome to use
i care for you but i cannot make your choices for you
i care for you and i offer you autonomy on your journey
on this human journey that we're both on
i care for you and in my heart i offer you autonomy
for the journey you're on
i care for you and i respect
that all beings have their own journey
for the last moments of this practice period
feeling failing into our care our meta for this being
a sense of spaciousness it's not a contracted care it's a spacious care
they're happy where they're sad we care
this care is so spacious it's enough space
to hold the conditions of their life present unmoving
stable equanimous radiating care
a sense of spaciousness in our heart stability in our heart body and mind
so we can be more available to support the care without being contracted
for this being we care about
may all beings everywhere
taste goodness and freedom ease
feel cared for
including ourselves
thank you all thank you for your practice
ah so [Music]
so what we did was we started
started with appreciation well actually we started first by
arriving landing with the breath with the body i invited to feel to the breath the
sense of nourishing cleansing refreshing to really connect with the in-breath and
out-breath i wonder how that worked for you if anybody wants to comment on that and then we
brought in someone we care about might be going through a hard time and with that being we start it with
appreciation with gratitude as a way to prime the heart prime the heart
with goodness and then with that appreciation then we
opened up to mehta to care the good will for this being
and from there the meta touching into the challenge
they're going through right now meta plus suffering equals compassion
practice turned into compassion practice karuna practice
feeling feeling holding the suffering the pain with
with well-being with a sense of good will and from that we turned into our final
destination and hung out there for a while which was practice of equanimity
offering autonomy continue to care to love to be present
for the being and offer them autonomy so
so many so many different a unique path we took
this evening and different from the path we've ever taken
through this practice before and knew always a new path right isn't it fun always a new practice
never a dull moment of happy hour so we'd like to invite you if something
opened up if you um something you discovered in your practice you like to offer this insight
this gift into to the sangha or if there's a question if something didn't work
um so it's all good you're invited especially if you haven't spoken for a while
um you can raise your zoom hand or you can type in chat if you type to me alone i
won't read your name if you type to everyone then i'll read your name or
if you don't even want me to read your reflection you can say private as you type it to me alone
claire please thank you so much i had to get my hand
up this is very personal and i don't know if it will interest anybody but me but you uh
gave me an answer to something that i've been worrying about all day i
in the early in the morning i ran into someone as a dear friend who has cancer
and i listened to her and talked to her and then i left and as i left and right
after i left i thought you know i really should invite her to meditate because i believe it will
help her but i got busy with other things anyway it came back to mine later in the day but i
have learned and it's related to this in the last year that i have tended to be
not overbearing but too involved with people's problems and they don't like it actually it pushes
them away and so i thought to myself no you know you're just repeating that old pattern
so maybe you better not and you know you just reinforced what i had sort of gotten to
that this was would not be helpful to her even though it would be helpful to me
but not to her and it was just beautiful i mean it was absolutely perfect so
thank you beautiful thank you claire thank you so much for this it's beautiful and and i love how you said
yeah it's helpful to me because then it feels like it reduces and that's the case for us right right because it
reduces our anxiety when they are when they feel less bad like oh yeah you meditate oh you feel better i feel
better but can we be okay with our stress arduca our concern for them and
and and offer them autonomy exactly oh beautiful
thank you claire and i saw hearts in the chat yeah appreciating what you shared
beautiful thank you right on time i heard you this morning claire
it's great um
lydia says i often find nikki's guidance so timely oh that's that's sweet isn't
that uh it's pretty wild right things i
i have to say i've often found in a various times when i've listened to dharma talks myself and various um
offerings just things can be timely so i appreciate that but it does feel timely
both for claire and lydia thank you thank you for those gifts
and the floor is open if any other reflections questions
any other discoveries
abraham hi thanks um
for many years uh my brother has been the source of much dukkha for me
and uh and i've done a lot of loving kindness for him and it's been really wonderful
and uh it's just i went to see him today so
um for various reasons causes and conditions he is very separated from the
rest of the family i'm the only one who goes to see him and it's hard and the previous time that i went to see him i
was just really going like wow i don't know how much longer i can do this um
what do you get out of meditation why do you go on retreat you don't do anything that kind of a misanthrope a real grump
and uh so just to do equanimity you know um i
see your suffering he's really suffering and just connect with my compassion for
him and just leave it be at that was very timely today so
thank you for doing equanimity i needed it thank you abraham thank you so much for
sharing the the story of your practice with with your kin with your sibling
with so much heart yeah thank you beautiful oh look at all those hearts going yeah
and so beautiful oh thank you sanga
so with the practice of equanimity and care
because equanimity is not aloof it definitely has a sense of care
and and well-being we're going to turn into practice into small groups oh one more reflection
elaine says i really like them i really like to mentally say to myself
the phrase i cannot make your choices for you this is really helpful when i am doing my
best to care for others great beautiful yeah and so many uh phrases and and see which
one really works for you for for this particular person or being
could be unique and and that's the one that really connects so thank you elaine for showing the one um sharing the one
that's connecting for you right now i cannot make your choices for you when you're doing best the best to care so
so with that we are all invited dear friends
to practice in small groups in groups of roughly size three
and we'll start with 15 seconds of meta for another
and then um to share as much as little as you wish from
what came up for you as a gift to your fellow practitioners and um care for yourself care for each
other and yeah i think that's all i want to say so
um the rooms are open take care of yourselves take care of each other here
you go okay everyone the rooms are closed
everyone is back and we have just a few minutes for any
reflections um questions comments complaints especially
if you haven't spoken in a while or tonight it's all
welcome what might be of support
what did you discover in the practice or in the conversations
mary please so for me um the person who came to mind
was my long-term partner and how much i
really believe that i can keep him healthy and happy and he will not die
before i do and that is just you know i'm obsessed with it and i always have been and we have great
humor about it but i encountered how it equanimity about his dying is worse
it is harder for me than equanimity about my own dying it's like no i want to go before you
and and to have compassion for myself in that
stuck place
oh dear heart dear heart yes dear heart your mind
wants to control right yes you control life who wants to control death
i want it this way make it all oh dear heart dear heart yeah
yeah yeah it's part of the human condition we want that right of course especially
with the big things especially with the big things especially with me the one you named
yes this is i want to go before you or just yeah of course
so common so common
thank you for gosh thank you for bringing that in mary thank you for sharing that and also
the humor and the compassion for yourself yeah thank you yeah and thanks for letting it
be witnessed um thank you yeah
so powerful it's really the um
both with mary's comment and and every time a any of you really share something
about your practice and allowing others to witness it both supports others and there is such a beauty and grace to
being witnessed by other human beings by other caring consciousnesses like yes
yes we see you we see your gift we see your beauty we see your challenge it's just it's
um it's so different from practicing on our own alone with our own stuff when we
share it just something shifts something profound happens so so thank you for
for offering sharing jerry says it is so freeing to sit in
equanimity especially at the end of the day of work yes ah what a great
point common to end on after a day of work sitting in equanimity there's a sense of
ease right we're flow but i feel too having practice with you because of
course i always practice with you when i lead these practices so so thank you all thank you for the gift
of your practice the gift of your being and cultivating your heart your mind your
being for the sake of yourself and all beings who come in contact with you
directly and indirectly may you all be well and you all be free and happy
thank you