good day warm greetings from imc it feels to me like it's been a
while since i've been here and um happy to be sitting here and and
somehow in my heart feeling a warmth and a connection to this wide
youtube audience all of you so thank you for being here
the um
one of the
underappreciated aspects of meditation is that right from the very
beginning even the beginning of someone who's starting a meditation practice for the first time
the the there are
hints or clues for where this practice is going and now
what's being developed and to start tuning in or recognizing
these hints these little traces of the goal in a sense from the beginning can be very helpful
and it kind of is as maybe a guide maybe a simple guide for
the path of meditation and so for example
if you sit down to meditate and
you're sitting or lying down to be still and not moving that
right there there is no longer the engagement with all the movements of a
lifetime movements of speech movements of action
spinning around concerns with movement fidgeting that might go on and in that
stillness of the body there can be a kind of a release from all the
activities that might feel kind of good like wow it's like taking a rest if you sit down to
meditate and you sit and take your posture and then you relax your shoulders
in that relaxation there is this hint of the whole whole path of meditation that um
that in the relaxation there is a release a release in the shoulder maybe even a
release in the mind because of the close way in which the mind and body are connected
and there is a release right there and um and with that release there can also be
some shift in the mind there might the mind might become subtle more settled maybe
a little bit more something settles in the mind just as the shoulders settle also it uh
something can um become clear there's on this little
moment of clarity with the relaxation and so this release and clarity
however small it is when you first sit down that is the
way forward that's what meditation is kind of opening to and opening to and and
expanding and growing and so to feel it right there at the beginning
and to kind of feel there's there's the way forward not to try too hard to always release
and always be clear the basic idea is just to see clearly what's going on
but when there are releases when we're no longer caught up in our thoughts and concerns
our story making mind when we let go of a thought
in that letting go is a feeling of release there's a feeling of openness
feeling of space feeling of non-preoccupation
and that without feeling that sense that experience of non-preoccupation of release
that's the way forward that to be appreciated to feel that rather than quickly going
on to the next thing let go of your thoughts and then you have a duty to go into your breath and like let's go
get to work so to appreciate the the goodness that happens the value
the benefit the goal that's right here of freedom
each little moment take a few moments to appreciate
the good impact the good consequences of relaxing the shoulders relaxing the belly
letting go of the thought relaxing the mind and that is getting a sense of that and
appreciating it points the way forward so assuming a stationary
posture posture that you can be still in for this 30 minutes
and to help you even maybe it's easier to become quieter and still in the
posture if you do kind of maybe sway back and forth a bit or a little bit gently
rock yourself a teeny bit maybe sway around so that you can kind of better
find the center and come to a place of balance
so your whole body somehow is finding here to be still and quiet
and then coming into stillness with your body
appreciating whatever lack of
work frenetic energy busy doing that we can be caught up in
to come into a posture that represents peace and quiet
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe three quarters full
and as you exhale relax your shoulders
perhaps appreciating whatever softening of the shoulders there's there
the release
and letting your breathing return to normal
taking a few moments to now relax different parts of your body
and each time if you're able to soften relax settle in your body to appreciate
what that feels like the goodness or the rightness or the release that happens
you might soften relax your belly
appreciating if the belly softens how the lack of tightness contraction
holding provides a release a sense of freedom or ease
as you exhale relaxing in the chest
around the heart
on the exhale releasing the shoulders
maybe the parts of the tight shoulders don't release at all but
maybe there's a little softening around the tightness
and as you exhale to relax muscles of your face
and also any contraction or tightness in the mind
any pressure you feel in the mind or tightness
as you exhale can that be softened relaxed
released and however small the release is
to appreciate
what's nice about that release
letting go of your thinking
appreciating maybe the more spacious feeling that can
come with not being preoccupied even if it's just
for a couple of moments
and then as we continue this meditation whenever you notice there's contraction
or pressure tightness
this grasping or clinging to anything or
relax let go and appreciate
whatever feels good about no longer being caught up in a
contracted state or pressured state
now in the lack of contraction maybe it's easier to for the awareness
to be clearer
clear awareness of what is
releasing all concerns and
preoccupations
let go of your thoughts and appreciate
that release and opening and quieting
of a thinking mind perhaps noticing if then without the
thinking there's more clarity in your awareness
clarity about here and now
can you relax your body further
and in the relaxation feel the release
feel a certain kind of freedom or ease
can you relax your mind
settle it quiet and in doing so appreciate
the absence of busyness the absence of chasing thoughts
the pressure to think
so
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to once again let go of your thoughts
release and relax whatever holdings you have in your body and your mind
appreciate how doing so might allow you to be more present for
other people more present for the tasks at hand
that the more you're at ease the more that you're not preoccupied and
have the pressures of agitations of greed and hatred
fear that there's a potential for
attention clarity availability of
seeing clearly what's here maybe with an open heart
and that meditation is not only for our own benefit
but also sets the stage for ways that we can be
more caring more present for others that's a stage for us to
have the heart respond to others with care and kindness
with compassion and appreciation
with generosity
so may it be that this meditation that we've done today may it serve us
may it serve others in our ability to be present attentive
present to to see and understand and
appreciate other people whether in person or other ways
may it be that as we free ourselves
that freedom
is expressed in a greater care and love and benefit
for the world around us may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be free
and may we contribute to that possibility
[Music]
so the buddha gave an analogy which i would like to adapt for
this talk today he talked about a forester someone who
worked in the forest who roamed around the forest for their work and
one day came across the traces of an ancient road
that had maybe been mostly overgrown and difficult to see but he saw a trace of it and he
cleared the cleared a little bit and started following the road and clearing
it and following it and finding his way through it until he came to a ancient capital
that had long since been overgrown and been abandoned and and so then uh the forester went back to
the monarchs of the lands and explained what had been found
and the monarchs came then to clear the road fully and to reinhabit the great capital
so um partly what this analogy is used for in the teachings of the buddha is to
suggest that what the buddha had to teach is
ancient he didn't invent it he didn't just you know dis invent something or make something
that hadn't already been there but it was there available for everyone except it was
overgrown with our preoccupations our attachments our
contractions our clinging our graspings our fears our hatreds our delusions
and uh so forth and that um the uh
and so he's rediscovered this ancient potential is the ancient
possibility for all of us and the task is to kind of clear the road and to
reinhabit this beautiful place that has always been there for us waiting for
us in a sense so so the question is what is the trace
that we can find if we are the forester what is the trace uh what's the hint that shows us the
path forward and this idea of a road or a path is such a big metaphor in buddhism
about the journey of practice the way that we grow and develop in the dharma and
i just love the idea of being on a journey that has an arc as a beginning middle end as an
unfolding over time and i think partly why i love it is that
it's so so organic so part of the human condition that there's always change there's
always a movement going on and we see it with young children
that if you haven't been around a child for some time you see that they've grown physically and they've grown
mentally and capacities and all kinds of things and that with the right conditions they
grow beautifully and and you can't really stop them from
you know without a lot of effort the natural process of their growth the change that they
unfold the maturation and so the same way our maturation
psychological and maturation that we have doesn't end when we're 18 or 21
but that continues into adulthood and right up until the time we die and many of you can probably recognize
that in some ways you're wiser than you were 10 20 30 40 50 years ago
things that uh disturbed you tremendously or things that you were afraid of or you resisted or that
you really were grasping onto and clinging to there might be some things you no longer do
that you've changed and you're let go you're wiser you see clay more clearly and you know they're better off options for
you or what you used to have no you don't see the allure of it anymore
so um there is kind of a natural movement and people who don't do any buddhist practice at all
go go through a changing unfolding of it sometimes there are
challenges or things that um interfere with uh them the
maturation of wisdom and in that process and people get stuck they get disappointed
they get betrayed they have disappointments they somehow they get uh closed down um shut down
and uh and so then are not available for the continued maturation process which is pretty a natural process
and so buddhism is going along with that process and then setting the conditions
in place that that really brings out the best in us that brings out
that freedom freedom from being shut down closed down being having the heart
covered over with mud or with overgrow overgrown overgrown with
all kinds of vines and shrubs and stuff that it doesn't allow the heart to radiate or
shine and so this idea of a path then a
journey of that maturation process is often talked about in buddhism so
what is that what is that traces we can find and what i'd like to
say is that those traces are available at the very first beginning of meditation
the first even before meditation even the first teachings or ideas of
meditation where there's a maybe a recognition that oh these teachings point to something i can
feel i can sense i can to it that there is some freedom some ease
some absence of stress that is possible for me
and that is the beginning that's the clue that's the first traces of that road
and what that means is that the traces and the road itself are not complicated metaphysics they're
not uh complicated beliefs and philosophy but something experiential something we can
see and feel and experience for ourselves i in the simplicity of that's as simple
as if you hold your hand in a tight fist it begins being a problem
but if you release the fist it becomes a lot easier it's a fist feels freer and more comfortable so
we have all these fists of the heart fists in the mind we have all these ways we contract or
there might be strong resistance or strong pressure that lives inside of us
that kind of obscures it gets in the way of our sense of ease
or peace or freedom there might be a strong desire you need to have something now you need to have
this now and and without this i can't be happy and the very intensity of the desire is
the very thing that keeps us from being happy rather than the thing is going to make us happy
it's that intensity of wanting that uh obscures our natural capacity to kind of
for the good heart to just kind of manifest to show itself to relax to open that
doesn't need much but space doesn't need much but quiet and freedom
to do so to be to express itself and so um and so it's this
experiential sense of this the difference between being stressed and being not stressed being contracted and not
contracted being in bondage to something versus being freed from it
being feeling under pressure and then the
release of the pressure to feel the weight of the world and the release of that weight to feel um a strong kind of shutting
down of resistance and then the release of that resistance so there's all kinds of things like that that those are
the traces of the path that's that's what we're clearing
so when we first sit down to meditate then the shoulders relax in that relaxing the shoulders is the
very is the first maybe trace or hint of what buddhism what this buddhist
practice is all about and so rather than thinking that relaxing your shoulders is a
you know preliminary practice or a you know kindergarten practice of
buddhism it's it itself is a little movement
towards that ease towards that freedom and so rather than just relaxing the shoulders and then quickly moving on to
the whatever practice you're going to do to take some time to appreciate to feel
ah oh yes it's a little bit more easy there now more relaxed more open
a little softer or sometimes when i relax my shoulders
it feels like i feel ah that's good but when i do so what i feel what's left
is a little bit the underlying tension and holding that might be there and and i feel that's good oh this is
good too to know this to be aware of it and to be close to it
to feel it because that's the way forward and to go back to being tight so the
underlying tension is kind of masked that's not desirable it's really it's
good to relax to feel what's going on here oh yes it's like this
and then that allows for over time so deeper relaxation deeper release
and um so something as simple as relaxing the shoulders you i've been you know in
social situations where i noticed my shoulders were tense or my stomach was tight and then i relaxed it and
and it's not like something to write home to your you know you know write home about and
say look what great thing i did um you know if i attain the fulfillment
of buddhist practice you know it's kind of silly to do it that way but
in talking that way i am pointing to that there's a trace there there's a this is the path this is where
the way forward this is what it takes it isn't like you relax your shoulders so that now you can go read some big
tome of buddhist philosophy you relax your shoulder so that's the
the door that's the book we're reading we're reading the book of softening releasing opening
together with clarity and uh and um
there can be with relaxation a little sense maybe a minor sense of
clarity the awareness becomes a little clearer and these two together
release and clarity those are the the primary things that we're
appreciating valuing opening to uh remembering to do as we do this
meditation buddhist practice letting that grow these grow and develop
and doing so then allows for this maturation allows for the greater clearing of the road until we
come to this great capital at some point but it gets uncovered so that's one kind
of analogy the analogy of you know a path that we go but it's just an analogy and
another way of saying this is that we are going from one place to another we're going
from here or self-suffering to there we're not suffering at all that's the
kind of the the over overall kind of simple description of the buddhist path
and so it but however it's not a geographical journey it's not like we're traveling anywhere
in the world it's all about what happens right here and and each step along the way
is not about doing something so that you can get some
place in the future but each step along the way is itself a fulfillment of the
of clearing that clearing the road or the expressing or finding even a small degree of what the whole
path is about the freedom from suffering from stress from contraction from pressure from resistance from fear
and so to really appreciate this that it's just right here and right now
what we're doing in this regard it's sometimes said in buddhism
that the fast fastest way to go from a to b
is to be fully at a so not to be so involved in getting
anywhere but really take and really be here with what's happening now
and and that's very much the same process because if you you sit down just anybody
you know they sit down to start paying attention to what's going on they might find that there's a lot of
physical agitation they don't want to sit there they want to they have a lot of things they have a long to do list and they're anxious to do it all and
there's all this restless nervous energy in the body to do and and because there's all this restless
nervous energy it actually feels better to enact it or act out the energy that is
sit still and feel it and makes us busy again and keeps people spinning until they're exhausted
but so notice this energy of wanting to do and then maybe settle back and relax the body and
until there's some ease and presence just things can unwind and then we notice that the mind is not
here and now with in the past in the future thinking about things and so then there's a process of
releasing and letting go of that to be here and then we notice that we're
here okay but we spend a lot of time analyzing and telling stories about here and what's
happening and what where we're going and what's happening and so we see what these all this story making mind and all
this analysis of what and plans about what to do about that's
also keeping me from being here at a really present so then we let go
of the stories we let go of the plans we let go of the analysis of what's happening because
it keeps us removed from the experience and so we find this a we kind of keep
shedding letting go releasing all the things that keep us from being present in a very good high
quality way and and it's not about getting any plays
as it is really arriving and being here in a fuller and fuller way so in that
sense we're learning to be fully at a but in doing so we are shedding releasing understanding
all the things that help the process of maturation unfold the process of inner growth the
process of movement towards freedom to wisd towards wisdom towards compassion and love
all those things now have space and room to unfold and grow and so there is that kind of a going
from a to b simultaneously we're becoming transformed and changed in that process
and even if you don't want to be transformed in that process
you can't help human change we're all changing psychologically we're all changing physically
day by day hour by hour through this lifetime but what we can do is create really good
conditions for that change to happen in in a way that's beneficial
and if we continue to live under stress if we continue to live not really
connected to ourselves uh spinning out with desire and agitation and
wanting the next thing and making the next plans and or always hiding and and closing down
and not really being honest and present for what's happening those are powerful conditions that uh
influence the direction of our maturation and it can be a direction which is not so good
and but if we meet ourselves our life with courage with
goodness with presence with love with letting go
opening up and then that creates a very different set of conditions where things start feeling safe inside
where there starts feeling a fearlessness inside whether starts feeling um it gives it as
appreciation and love and care for what's here and those are very different influence
on how we change and mature over time and so simultaneously to the practice
being fully here at a nowhere but here
we are putting ourselves in a process that uh has us go from a to b
has us go from who we are today to what we can become as we become freer
and more compassionate more more liberated in this whole process
and but whether you're looking at it from going a to b
the road in the forest that's overgrown and you're clearing it or it's simply that you are already at
the palace and there's nowhere to go nowhere to be however the palace is overgrown the
capital is overgrown with lots of shrubs and trees and vines and dirt and
so it's not a matter of getting anywhere but it's a matter of clearing all the
overgrowth so the capital can be inhabited and so either way the met whatever
metaphor analogy that you prefer or both of them but they're both the same process
and a process that develops the more we can appreciate the benefit
of each moment of release we can appreciate the value or the goodness of letting go
of opening up of not resisting not chasing desires and wishes and not being
agitated and swirling around in stories not caught in the grip of resentments
and anger hostility all these things that are kind of the overgrowth
that prevent us from seeing this wonderfulness that waits for us inside this and what's
quite beautiful and um and that we can inhabit the beauty that we can inhabit
and maybe this inner beauty this inner freedom and peace that can be where we take up residency
and whether it's a path from a to b to get there
eventually we're there and we're taking a presidency in this wonderful beauty
or if it's just being at a fully nowhere to go
no road to it no path we also end up taking up residency
to a beautified heart that he has become free and compassionate
so um so recognize even at the smallest
initial steps of the path of release relaxation opening up
seeing clearly what's here oh stopping to look oh this is what's happening in in the
relaxation in the stopping to look and see clearly recognize the best you can
the whole goal of the practice is found traces of it
you're already there you have it you can you have what it takes
and now keep doing it keep opening to it keep practicing it repeatedly over and
over again so this can really make space and grow and develop and and there's a wonderful word
in the teachings of the buddha it's
means to make it abundant so and he says by repeated practice
we make it abundant so make your freedom make your peace make your
beautiful qualities of art become abundant for you
by just continuing to practice over and over again what is available
for a beginner at the very start of their practice
so thank you very much and for today and
and it's very good