hello everyone and welcome to imc in redwood city
and
and we're here to meditate together and i'm happy for this gathering thank
you
the word vipassana that's uh
the kind of word for the kind of meditation in which we do mindfulness
vipassana is is how we translate is the word it gives us the word insight
for insight meditation center it comes from the holy word pasana which means
to see and the prefix vi is a
intensifier and so to intensely see though i don't know if we want to use the word
intense so it's often used clear seeing to see clearly
to see well and in one of the little slogans
in this vipassanai insight movement is that vipassana is not about seeing
something new but seeing in a new way and
as a slogan it only goes so far but it does point to something important that
seeing in a new way and one of those new ways is to
be present for our experience breathing our body whatever aware of in the present moment
sent to ourselves in the present moment and do so without
referring it to our concepts of self
the ideas of identity that we might have about ourselves the idea of me myself and mine
the idea all the kind of orbit of ideas that circle around the central idea of self
what the self needs what it wants what's going to happen what it means to me
and then to shift and to see it see our experience some people talk about just as nature
as nature seeing itself and
i'm kind of fond of the idea that this idea of where nature is seeing
itself that out of the cosmic soup
the formation of the solar system and this planet and then out of the elements of all this
there arose life and life arose in such a way that at some point it became
conscious aware and and it's a the natural world which has
formed these conscious beings that can see that aren't part of nature that can see
nature so rather than seeing everything from the reference points of of myself and my
ego and things to see oh this too is part of the natural world
that rather than being caught up in responsibility and measuring everything about you know
point of view of my life today and what it means to see things perhaps as
our experience the thought we have maybe the feelings we have as the product of
5 billion 14 billion years of
development evolution tremendous amount of cause and effect had to come into play
phenomenal that at this particular moment you're thinking about what should i have for lunch
and it's not a simple thing that the universe organized itself so you could have the thought what should i
have for lunch and so to see in a new way
is to see kind of in amazement and with interest in this new way without
centering the seeing on what it means for me myself and not to
judge what's happening judge myself for what's happening just allow things to be and see them in
their particular it's just part of the continued
flow of life of experience of the universe that we just happen to be conscious of and it happens to be a lot
of the experience that is arising and passing in this psychophysical being that we are
and this is a new way of seeing and it's not the only way to see
but it's a certainly fascinating way to see and it it
gives us access to a different way of experiencing ourselves and the world
that is said to be liberating so to assume a meditation posture
that um with this body of ours
a body that's made up of 100 recycled material from this cosmic soup
probably been involved in many these elements of
our body have been in all kinds of other life forms and situations over these billions of years
and now they've come together here so to feel to sense the body
perhaps get take a downward gaze and relax your eyes
and if it's comfortable to close your eyes
and take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe three quarters full and then exhale that's maybe
one and a half times longer than you usually do
relaxing letting go on the on the end of the exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal
take a few moments to relax this body
for whatever the causes and conditions that have come together maybe the shoulders are tight and tense
no need to make a story of it or define oneself by it
just tension and allowing
the tension to relax a bit
feeling the sensations of your belly the belt is tight or held in
perhaps you also don't have to make it about yourself and that it means something about you
it's just nature who knows why it's tight you don't need
to know it for the purposes of this meditation but if it's easy enough to relax
the belly
and to also feel the muscles of your face
either any tension or clenching or tightness
anywhere in the face see it
matter-of-factly like you're a naturalist in the wild you're studying
some fascinating plant that you've never seen before it's just nature
the tension and if it's easy enough relax the
muscles of your face
and if there's any tension pressure and your thinking mind
associated with thinking
to also see that as nature
no need to use it to make any commentary about yourself and
it's just phenomenal happening tension happening thoughts happening
nature unfolding but if the tension of thinking can be
relaxed on the exhale relax
the thinking muscle
and then centering yourself on your breathing
wherever the breathing the body breathing is most clearly
experienced known
center yourself there steady yourself there
and allow yourself to experience the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out okay
creatures of all kinds many kinds breathe
breathing is a natural phenomenon and the rhythm of breathing is like the
rhythm of the waves washing up and down on the shore
it goes on and on to relax and simply observe
this also natural process of breathing
without needing to make any judgments or conclusions
about you yourself just the breathing
and if you do control the breathing that's also natural
let it be and just say wow this too
and then as we continue meditating see if you can do this seeing in a new
way without the overlay
of self and self concerns and if those concerns come up
maybe you can be amazed that five billion years of evolution
should somehow have given birth to self-concern
and maybe you can see for a few moments self-concern is just as much part of the nature
as everything else it's all nature
seeing in a new way
uh
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
a wonderful aspects of this natural world
somewhat like we are nature [Music]
looking upon nature so we can also be nature caring for
nature just as we have the ability to perceive
the world we have the ability to care for the world
and if we're relaxed at ease feel safe
and don't see through the filter of me myself and mine
there can be the simple wonderful
capacity to care for others for their welfare for their happiness
it doesn't have to be dramatic it doesn't have to be great compassion
and it can be ordinary care and support
valuing appreciating people
and it's useful at the end of a meditation to bring forth this part of who we are
caring for others to do so at the end of the meditation
it brings a much greater value to the meditation we've had
even if meditation has been difficult we benefit from practicing with the
difficulties if we practice seeing in a new way
and in our care for others let the benefits that we've had from this practice
may it be directed through our care into the world
simple ordinary care simple ordinary directed to the world around
us with a wish may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all beings
be free and may it be that we have occasion
to help make this possible to help support others to be happy safe peaceful
and free
[Music]
thank you
so before i offer this talk today
uh i think there's one announcement maybe a couple but
and that is that um we are beginning to make plans to begin
a slow opening for imc it's possible it could be as soon as in
a couple of weeks and it depends whether we can put together
the protocol that we would like to have to feel safe coming here
and we'll have more kind of care given to it than we were planning to during the
summer and so the next next sunday
after this 10 o'clock arma talk the plan is to have a community meeting
for the imc community and one of the things we'll do is talk about that a little bit and
describe the protocol and we'll start by opening small
probably on a sunday and maybe with 25 people coming and
and people who register ahead of time and and then we'll see how that feels and how that goes and then maybe
will slowly start to increase and maybe have more programs um so
so that's for next week a community meeting then there's and the zoom link will be up but
posted in what's new and then some days before and also i'll post it uh in the calendar for this
event for that event in the imc calendar and so those are the two places you can get it and i'll probably post it also
here on the chat so that um on youtube so if you're on youtube you can just
maybe just jump over
so
and then when we open on sundays we'll still do the sunday morning on youtube
we were doing that before the pandemic and we'll continue after
so
so to do vipassana the practice of clear seeing
is to see in a new way
and in a new way that begins opening up a whole other possibility for how we can
grow and develop and unfold our life can unfold and it's a marvelous thing to learn a
new way and then to give ourselves to that new way and let that new way really develop
and grow and and um and change us from the inside out in a useful way
and that's the uh um you know what the buddhist path involves
and initially the new way of seeing is learned initially it's maybe even provisionally that we hear something and
then we try it out okay we've heard that there's a new way of seeing um i get i kind of get a sense of it
i'll do my best and see how it is and then over time maybe we'll have uh
evidence that this is actually works really well it's actually a very useful framework for
living our lives and so that it grows and grows and this growing of the momentum around
a new way of seeing new way of living is
there's a lot of analogies that buddha gives that have analogies of movement
so movement of a stream entering a stream and being carried by the stream
or water rain water falling on a hillside and the mountainside
and then the drops roll down and become bigger drops and they flow into little creek lits
and and those little creek lits flow into little pools and the pools overflow
with enough water and they flow into little streams and the streams keep
flowing to larger ponds when they ever flow that flows further down into
becomes rivers and the rivers flow into bigger lakes and when those overflow the water just
keeps getting bigger and bigger and stronger and stronger and keeps going downhill until eventually it makes its
way all the way to the ocean and so this is a movement that we're entering in this movement of
growth and development and flow and the the rainwater analogy
is fascinating because it has two different meanings uh it points both to the growth
something's growing in strength and capacity and it's also flowing down waters
following gravity rather than resisting gravity following gravity in a natural way
all the way to the ocean where it it doesn't have to flow anymore it can
come to a rest of sorts and and this new way of seeing
uh that is encouraged uh one way of describing it is a very
simple mindfulness just very simple ordinary seeing things in their
own in how they are as they appear as they exist in the moment
without you know as we do mindfulness practice without reference to the past to the future and without reference to
um and this is more difficult without reference to the egoistic self without
refuge to ref reference to the ideas we build up around who we are
and what we need and who we aren't and the judgments we have about ourselves the ways we undermine ourselves with
negative self-talk the way that we have delusions of grandeur about how
wonderful we are and we just allow experience to just be
itself without any reference to itself but we see it clearly now this isn't necessarily how we're
supposed to live our life the whole time past and future are valuable and
enriched enriches life as well but in meditation that's not what we're
trying to do meditation is trying to really discover something very radically new and allow this stream inside of us
to get bigger and flow and to be carried along by it the dharma stream
and so uh it does involve seeing in a new way and um
and a fascinating way of presenting this is that uh it involves seeing our
suffering in a new way and some of you probably are tired of
buddhists always talking about suffering suffering this suffering that and maybe you even kind of
tune out a little bit as soon as you hear the word suffering it's repeated so much what's fascinating is that the word pali
word for suffering the literal meaning of it is not suffering
the literal meaning of it is pain and we often and
and it's by kind of by interpretation by application it involves kind of psychological pain
and emotional pain that we would like to call suffering
and um but it's useful to think of it as pain and what happens if we see
so-called suffering or the big sufferings of our life as pain rather than suffering
it begins to maybe take remove a little bit the hegemony of
self the ways in which self will
invest in the self in this we get invested in the pay in the pain
we get interested in pain we get infatuated with the pain we get
all these ways we get involved with the pain but one of the ways we get involved in it is we overlay
attachments and reactivity on top of whatever pain we're looking at
so that there might be emotional pain there might be psychological pain there might be physical pain existential pain
all kinds of pains come along with being alive and then
we or we have we overlay our ideas on top of it it shouldn't be there this means that i'm living life the
wrong way i'm doing something wrong that i feel pain um i i need to be the one who now gets
rid of it who this is happening to me i'm the victim of the of it all
um there is um there's a pain of loss
and then we we refer that loss to all the ways in which
i thought i was going to live my life and build up my wonderful life is not possible now
it's sad and it's you know that this happens but there can be a lot of extra investment of self what it's in for me
myself and mine which is separate from the pain of the loss now it's the pain of losing a future
which is a little different that we imagined than just the particular loss we have
so the the grief sometimes can get quite complicated what it involves
there can be anguish over the pain
because we add so much meaning to it and so much
projections into the future this is always going to be this way it's always been this way i'll never make it never
figure it out this is too much for me and no one's caring for me no one's taking care of me
and i feel so lonely in my dismay and my despair
so i don't want to be little or how difficult it is to have human suffering it's quite challenging
but i want to try to get across the idea that there are certain layers
overlay over overlaying certain degree of extra baggage on top of it or
reactivity or commentary and maybe that's very maybe just a veneer on top of it and so maybe it's
not very much but for some people it's actually not so you know
the overlay is actually the primary quality of what makes the pain suffering
and so the suggestion is to see a new way and maybe it's a
outrageous suggestion is that to see our suffering whatever we have whatever we call it
but uh to don't not call it suffering not call it grief not call it anguish not call it dismay
or depression or or anxiety and all these things that we now
have gotten used to calling it um it's it's valuable to see it that way i'm not you know i don't want to
diminish the importance of seeing clearly but uh when we say to meditate it might
be a time in our life where we can let it be very simple and just see it as pain
and make it that simple and seeing it just as pain might help us
to begin relaxing the mental work activity of these
overlays we put on top of it the way we bill helps us build the story of me
myself and mine and we might start seeing that
that some of those layers lighten up the pain is still there but it's not as
intense it's not as debilitating it has a whole different quality of it
so i'll give you a simple example i don't want to again i don't want to belittle how difficult life is to give a
simple example but simple makes maybe clearer that that i learned was very powerful
learning for me so that's why i like telling it that when i first started meditating
i was practicing zen where you weren't supposed to move during the 40 minutes of meditation but my body had not been conditioned to
sit in this posture and so my knees were on fire they hurt a lot
but i wasn't supposed to move and and so i had a lot of intense
suffering around this i felt self-pity i felt fear i felt
upset i was angry with myself i was angry at others i was
feeling is impossible why me and
you know and very impatient frustrated all kinds of layers of things were
happening and and because i kept sitting this way i slowly began to notice
that there was a difference between experiencing the pain in and of itself
and experiencing the pain with the self-pity and all the different aspects of it
and if i was able and if i had all this extra stuff the self-pity the impatience the frustration
then then it was you know intense psychological suffering emotional suffering
but if i drop the self-pity the pain remained but it didn't become
as bad it like had space had breathing room it eased up and
sometimes the pain would become quite manageable until i kind of
forgot about kind of putting aside the self-pity he would come roaring back
and the knee pain would get intense again and i saw over and over again
how much overlay i put on it and slowly began to kind of simplify and simplify and not add all
these layers on top so that to me was incredibly inspiring
and it gave or gave gave birth to a kind of
inspiration of faith trust a confidence
that this was a useful to shift how i saw the pain
and so the this radical idea from this talk today is whenever you have suffering and
you're going to try to do take a dharmic approach to it like in meditation
see what the shift is if you stop calling it depression
anxiety despair grief sadness without any diminishing of it without
any disrespect for it of how what's happening for you but simply shift the
orientation to see it as just as pain and then breathe with that and see if
some of the layers that are extra the baggage on it begins to settle
if you get inspired like i i i was by that or have trust or confidence in it
that gives birth that's similar to what the buddha said that learning to see pain
suffering in a new way through practice through the eyes of the
past not clear seeing in this way he said that gives birth
to faith to confidence a kind of inspiration if then you
don't just get inspired but with that faith that confidence to us okay now i'm going to start
practicing this new way of seeing i'm going to stabilize it i'm going to use it more
and really kind of give myself to develop this new way of seeing
that's when the stream begins to flow and at first it might be just a trickling little stream up in the
mountain but if we want to get this stream to be to grow and develop we have to practice
it and so then we keep start practicing we have this inspiration
and uh and if the inspiration can fuel the practice the the confident confusion
fuel the practice rather than continually falling back into the old patterns
that can give rise to gladness to a delight that we have a practice wow this is cool
i didn't know that i could live this new way it's hard it's challenging i doubt it at times but there are times when
it's really great and i think i'm on a path so the buddha said that once that faith
is there and we and we continue to practice without the practice probably nothing will happen
then with the practice then there comes a delight a gladness or a
satisfaction or a feeling this is right as that practice continues
and you start getting more evidence that this works as we get into the flow of the stream of practice
and it becomes we are feeling this stream getting bigger and the stream starts to have a little bit more
momentum and initially it seems like we're doing the work but with time it just seems
like oh now it's it's it's that practice is doing me i'm kind of flowing along
here and and um and that being involved and being really engaged having been able to put
aside a lot of the distracted mind and the undistracted mind is really into
doing this practice seeing in a new way there's a kind of
physiological delight joy that comes and the buddha said that
if we keep practicing with the light with the uh from the delight there grows a joy
as we keep practicing and settle into this and really start feelings the beginning the fruit of this is really
works this is good the practice begins kind of growing
the stream gets uh lands into a large lake that's calm and
very tranquil and um and tranquility sets in it's like there's an ease a certain like oh
i have something here that really works i don't have to be so agitated or so anxious anymore because i have this
practice the practice really helps me to see in a new way i can't always do it but just knowing i
have the practice can make us less agitated
we keep practicing and that tranquility fills up it goes over the banks and beca creates
a different um river that's a smoother remember this big rivers get bigger and come down off
the mountain into the rivers and the plains they get big rivers can be very quiet
whereas in the mountains it's quite noisy rapids and boulders go over
so it gets quieter it becomes something called uh happiness and a pleasure or a deep sublime feeling
it just feels so good to be in the flow that the buddha said gives birth to
concentration to really be present really be really here
that the buddha that the buddha said gives birth to seeing things as they are
which is now to get confirmation a real kind of qualitative
different kind of affirmation confirmation of the value of seeing in this new way
and now you see directly the evidence oh this really is significant
and uh to see things because things are constantly flowing and changing this natural world
to really see this flow and moving along and seeing how nothing gets stuck and nothing
nothing um gets frozen unless
we bring the baggage and the self and the attachments to it then things get solidified
but to see that without that baggage without that overlays that things just flow natural flow the
natural inconsistency of movement and so not only do we feel like
we're in the stream of practice but now we see the stream we see the flow
this feels so good so right so much clarity that there starts to be what the buddha
said gets more goats gets born is now a disinterest or a disenchantment
with the old way of seeing and now the old way of seeing through the ego egoist egoistically or
self-centeredly or with all the baggage and concerns and and or even some of the old cultural ways
familial ways we've learned to always see our life are seen you know maybe that's
not so accurate or not so useful to that lens and so we start becoming a disinterested
disenchanted with it and it begins to relax and fade away and that gives birth to the
further this fading away so seeing
things as they are gives birth to a disinterest a disenchantment which gives birth to
this movement of fading away of our attachments and when the attachments have faded away
enough then who knows when enough is enough but when they're enough
something lets go and we have liberation
liberation then flows further into a deep understanding of what this liberation is all about
and uh and one of things is about is now uh not just a confirmation
of the seeing in a new way but now inhabiting the new way of seeing
in a whole different like it becomes like who we are rather than something that we introduce
into our life so remarkably 2500 years ago
the buddha and the people around him who were practicing this you know really looking at their minds to understanding
their minds and understanding how to practice with these minds and hearts we have discovered this amazing
uh tools and capacities of the mind that then they described in i think
quite inspiring ways and uh and the
description i use today is something called liberative dependent arising
how liberation comes dependent on certain conditions being in place
and there's 12 steps and they are born on the basis of seeing suffering in a
new way that gives birth to faith
faith gives birth to delight the light gives birth to joy
joy gives birth to tranquility tranquility gives birth to
happiness happiness gives birth to concentration samadhi
samadhi gives birth to seeing things as they are seeing things as they are gives birth to
disinterest in attachments disinterest or this disenchantment gives
birth to fading away of attachments
the fading wave attachments is the condition that leads to the ending of attachments which is called
liberation and once there's liberation that's not the story doesn't end there
but then there's understanding what has happened and really understanding now we're living in the
world with new eyes seeing in a new way
and all this depends on itself the whole list depends on practicing
the practice we do is what uh that's the rain
uh that's and i love the analogy of rain because it's just drops little drops moment by moment that we're adding and
those drops are not inconsequential moments of mindfulness but the continuity of it
more and more over and over again so that it's you know not just the occasional drop
but it becomes a kind of a you know lots of rain falling on the parched ground
and uh and then overflowing and and building up the
the volume that allows the river to get bigger and bigger and bigger
so practice based on seeing in a new way
and so you might consider is there a new way to see
that you could try out is there a new way of seeing you'll do provisionally
meaning you don't have to accept it this is the absolute true way of seeing things but maybe it's just a different
orientation and different perspective and to see without any reference to me
myself and i without reference in past and future just see
pain see suffering just as pain very simply and see if that begins to loosen up the
crust the solidification of all this extra baggage extra layers that we add on top
of the difficulties of this human life and if we
those difficulties don't have all these extra layers maybe it's easier
and maybe we'll be inspired to practice because it's really worthwhile once we
get the start getting a glit glimpse of this new way of seeing it's really worthwhile to do what it
takes to let this glimpse become a bigger and more irregular part of our
life so um to see in a new way be passionate
may you see in a new way and may we as a community and uh
share that with each other and see each other in this new way and i think that
we'll end up with tremendous delight appreciation
for each other thank you very much