so
for those of you who came to the
meditation just now
thank you for those of you who came at
the 15 minutes earlier and
had this longer sitting and thank you
for those of you who might have joined
at the regular time
or anytime it's always what you're
welcome to come
and what's wonderful about
this electronic medium for meditation
together is that
it's uh everyone enters the meditation
room and
in a sense quietly
so um
so some of you will find i see that the
idea that
the 15 minutes extra meditation is a lot
longer
and certainly if you're used to one
length of time it takes a while to
kind of get used to the the longer
period
uh and once after a while it becomes
normal the longer period it can seem to
go quite quickly and
and anything shorter feels like we're
not quite
you know finished maybe
so it's well worth doing the stretch
so hopefully this week is is um
nice for you and if it's not nice i hope
that it's educational
you learn something about yourself that
you wouldn't have learned otherwise
so
you know in the overall series on this
mindfulness of breathing
we're halfway through the 16 steps
but we're kind of taking this week to
kind of review or just kind of begin
over again in a certain way
and beginning over again is not really
starting over completely
but meditation it's often useful to
think we're always beginning over
that often you know our lives are ups
and downs we've
been active in our life and we sit down
to meditate and we don't
sell them we just drop into you know the
depths of where we were before
but rather it's always kind of a
beginning over
and now learning how to be a beginner
learning how to engage in it
in a in a way that is harmonious with
meditation or
supports the enjoyable settling in
is part of this art and not to be in a
hurry
not to be striving but to be diligent
and to be you know wholehearted
and showing up in a way that ah this is
really good to be here
and in the instructions the buddha gives
the preparation for
the first step is the is the
instruction to establish mindfulness
and this idea of establishing awareness
i i like the expression awareness
establishing attention here
i've asked a number of people how they
understand this idea of establishing
awareness
and many people respond that it for them
it means
to allow for it to enable it
awareness or attention is a kind of a
capacity that
in all our conscious moments is
operating
and to establish it is to open up more
fully to what's already here
and and maybe to center oneself in that
awareness to be rooted in here
some scholars have said that the pali
word for establish
could also mean to stand next to or
stand close to
it's to to really accompany something
and now this idea of having awareness uh
established like it's like it's really
rooted here in the present moment
and to do that a fair amount of what we
have to do is to let go
we have to let go of the ways that
thinking
preoccupier so much that we don't even
know we're aware
we get pulled into its drama as its
stories its concerns
and there's something about letting go
enough
of the storylines the thoughts the ideas
the preoccupations
so that we're clearly cognizant that i'm
here in the present moment
and something as simple as uh i'm here
in this body i'm here in this place
begins to establish
and um and so the question is uh you
know more fully for you
what does it mean for you to establish
yourself here
in awareness and attention and how do
you do that establishment
that that you're finding a place that's
wholesome
finding a place that's a healthy or
helpful or even
healing a way of being really being here
in the midst of what's going on it might
be that there's a lot of emotional
turmoil or difficulty in physical pain
there might be challenges that go on
there might be challenges around you in
the environment
but if it's appropriate to be meditating
what does it mean to establish yourself
peacefully or another way of saying
which i like quite a bit for myself is
the idea of
becoming sitting and practicing without
being in conflict with anything
and what does it mean to sit here uh
without conflict and so then you know
we're kind of looking around and seeing
where is their conflict
where am i caught up in responsibilities
or desires or
resentments and what are these
and not necessarily to make them go away
or to let go of them if it's not easy to
do so
but what is it like to be sitting in the
middle of it
established and uh
so this image of sitting in the middle
and just being present for the
experience
i think i've said this recently my son
when he was
he went into kindergarten and he was
kind of young for
kind of in the younger end of i forget
exactly what he was but i think he was
still four or something
and four and a half maybe and
and he went to kindergarten and and uh
the first month or two he would find a
small little kids chair
and place it right in the middle where
all the kids were playing in the
classroom
and he would just sit there and watch
everything that was going on
and it was only after a couple of months
that he left his chair and started
interacting and playing with the kids
and
no one ever felt that he was troubled or
upset or afraid
he was just that's what he did he just
sat right there
confidently in the middle and just took
it all in and this whole new environment
and so he established himself in the
room of
you know probably chaos kids
kindergarten kids playing and running
around
and so
to establish oneself to root oneself
here to i know some teachers who have
emphasized
that simply no having your two feet
rooted
you know firmly on the ground or in the
cushion meditating
your butt firmly on the seat that's you
know
that's really where the heart of it is
really here established here
i had one one teacher who
gave this wonderful teaching and he said
that a successful period of meditation
sometimes sometimes because it can be so
wild and
so maybe agitating or
what's going on within as we meditate
that a definition of a successful
period of meditation is that we did not
leave
our seat and he said sometimes like the
rodeo but you stay in your seat
stay on the saddle and
and the reason he called it a success is
that
we don't give into it we don't give up
because of it
and sometimes just simply hanging in
there and staying
it doesn't look like it's a wonderful
meditative experience
but it takes a we're cultivating a lot
of strength
a lot of stability and the ability to to
keep our seat
to hold our ground here i'm staying here
and and so
what's the nature of how we establish
awareness what's the nature of the way
that we practice awareness practice
attention
and this took me a long time to
understand for myself
because i had a lot of agendas sometimes
when i was practicing like
sometimes i had the agenda to get
concentrated and i was pushing and
straining
and trying my best and judging myself
and
and comparing myself to the when i was
meditating in a room with other people
kind of part of me was comparing myself
with others those you know and
trying to catch up or be as concentrated
as them or
be as mindful as them or so or as still
as them or something
and all this swirl of comparative mind
swirl of
needing to accomplish something needing
to prove myself
and then there was a the attitudes of
not liking what i saw in myself and
being upset with this and that
that happened and the mindfulness then
had a sting to it
that it wasn't just being mindful of
something but there was little barbs
like
i was like poking at myself or
criticizing myself
kind of together with being mindful
and slowly to learn to simplify
and simplify and simplify the awareness
all this extra stuff that we bring along
so much so that some people can would
say that the whole process of meditation
like the whole process of the 16 steps
of anapanasati
is a process of simplifying awareness
so it becomes comes into its pristine
purity
or its pristine simplicity just aware
to see clearly without the seeing
having any filters without the seeing
having any obstructions to it
and just to see just to see
and to trust that that's enough is
supported with the idea
that the actions how we take care of
things that will come later
first we're learning this ability to see
in this clear
simple way and that allows us to see
better what can be done and what should
be said or can be said
there's more wisdom that way
so finally this is a quest for
simple awareness tranquil awareness that
is committed and
established just stays here with
experience
maybe it's inspiring for you to remember
the little saying
that if you want wisdom the wisdom of
how to live in this world
become tranquil have your awareness
established in its simplicity
and learn how to be content with that
that's enough
that in them for now just enough to
sit here and be present later
can come the action the response
so establishing awareness
so thank you very much and
let's all of us continue with our
awareness
practice thank you