as i talked about yesterday
the fourth tetrad
the fourth and final group of four
practices or steps to
mindfulness of breathing
involve observing
and to settle back and observe our
experience
and part of a big part of the ability to
observe what's being implied here
is not to be assertive or not to be
doing things interpreting
changing fixing escaping
our experience but learning have the
stability
and the ease and the strength of
awareness
to settle back and just really see
clearly what is happening here
to observe clearly the moment
and and when we don't overlay
our ideas and our concepts what we see
is change we see things are much
are changing all the time and
it doesn't take a lot to appreciate i
think that
even aside from any ways in which we
think things are unchanging
that moment by moment there's always
change
that the day changes the lighting
changes slowly over time maybe
sometimes imperceptible if you're in a
city the sounds of the city are
constantly changing and um
the sensations of your body are changing
through the day
and you could watch the changes as we
get hungry
and we eat and we don't feel hungry we
feel uncomfortable we
we engage our body in different ways
different muscles are used at different
times and therefore different sensations
come into play
there's a constantly shifting changing
landscape
of where attention focuses and what it
takes in and
even things that don't necessarily
change themselves
what's changing constantly is how we're
perceiving it
how we see it if i look at the wall
that's opposite me here
that the natural thing when i'm relaxed
is to have my eyes kind of not fixate on
a spot
but just kind of roam around and even
though the wall is not changing
what's changing is the the uh where my
left my where my eyes land on or
the flowing of this of perception of the
wall
so whether it's something that's
constantly shifting like a river flowing
and we're watching it or whether or it's
the the act of perception is constantly
shifting and moving
and going around what we experience
is a constantly shifting landscape of
change
and it turns out that this is central
to the deeper insights of
buddhist meditation so in this in the
fourth
step of anapanasati the fourth tetrad
it begins when trains
experience observing in
in constancy i
breathe in
one trains ex
observing in constancy
i breathe out
and um so in constancy here is one of
the words for
change and
and things uh and so here is to see
really begin appreciating and seeing
the depth of how things are changing all
the time
and one of the reasons why buddhism puts
such a strong emphasis
on being present in having a present
moment attention
is that that's where change happens that
uh
if we're thinking about the past the
past in certain kind of way is not
changing anymore
except in how we remember it perhaps the
futures may be
it doesn't really exist to change it's
just kind of a projection of our
imagination
and and the
the um but in the present moments where
we see
the change it's kind of like where
that's where the river flows by of
change and all that and everything is
changing is according to the buddha
everything is inconstant and
this is not necessarily obvious in
ordinary consciousness and
ordinary ways of being but
but it's really central to what happens
in deeper and deeper meditation
in meditation itself where we're kind of
no longer paying attention to the wall
that's in the opposite side of the room
or a mountain and saying well the
mountain's not changing
and then we have to use our logic and
say well it's slowly being worn down and
eroding
but in meditation with the eyes closed
sitting here
that as we begin to
really open up to the present moment
experience and really feel it
sense it experience it observe it
what we experience in that kind of
context of meditation
is a constantly shifting of flow of
phenomenon
it's experienced after developing strong
stability
and part of the paradox is that
in meditation the more still the more
stable the mind is
the more the mind observes change and
impermanence
the more unstable the mind is the more
scattered and preoccupied the mind is
the more unsettled the more we tend to
impute permanence the more we tend to
get caught up in our ideas and thoughts
and stories
which have often carry with them a
feeling of things are
constant or permanent this is the way
things are
and and i've certainly have fallen into
the
delusion of permanence without
you know it being kind of unconsciously
even
and if i think about it of course i
don't believe what i'm feeling
but uh the way i'm acting sometimes
remember one day
many years ago having a difficult day
with my child
and and my wife and i were kind of like
hovering over him and
trying to manage with this highly
spirited child
and and then my wife just looked up at
me and said
we're having one of those kinds of days
and as soon as she said that then i
realized that i was kind of emotionally
operating as if
this is it we're always going to be this
way it's not going to change
of course i if i thought about it i
wouldn't
have been that way unknown that to
thought that but the emotional feeling
of it was a perm this is it and as soon
as you said that we're having one of
those kinds of days
then i relaxed and like you know okay
this is it's the manifestation of the
moment this is how it is now
and it will change it'll be we'll have a
different day tomorrow and something
so this imputing of permanence even
emotional feeling like this is it
interferes with our ability to step back
and benefit from the wisdom of change
and the wisdom of how things
move and constantly shifting and this is
one of the
key insights of the buddha
it doesn't say it this particular way
but this is
my interpretation that things are always
changing
and change is not random
change happens because of the conditions
that precede
what's happening now they can as
conditions shift and changes
the direction of change how things
change unfolds accordingly
that um that
generally we don't have rain without
clouds the clouds are the condition for
the changing weather of rain happening
and and so
when when i feel cold
then perhaps it's harder to get
sometimes harder for me to get
concentrated when i meditate i've
meditated sometimes in very cold weather
and i haven't really you know the
conditions were not there for me to get
settled and calm
there was still change happening and
things were being in all kinds of
different ways but it wasn't one that
supported
becoming concentrated and there are
times when the weather has been
comfortable or been bundled up nicely
and my body is not you know coping with
you know cold and shivering that
that i have different conditions of
being cozy and settled
and it's easier than to the conditions
are there
to allow the changing of into a
concentrated state of meditation
so depending on the conditions that are
present
change go and go in different directions
and the key one
that uh really central to the buddhist
teachings
is that things can go either
in a helpful direction or unhelpful
direction in a wholesome nourishing
direction or an
un helpful unnourishing direction
and the and so we're a little bit
responsible for putting the conditions
in place to support the directionality
of change we can't control it absolutely
we can't
make things be a certain way but we can
put the conditions in place to support a
tendency
in healthy directions beneficial ways
and and so
so a deep appreciation of change
shows us that also things are malleable
things are changeable
because they're always changing and we
have a little role to play
in the direction of that change if we're
floating in the river down a current in
the river
we understand that you know we're being
carried by the
flowing change of the river but we also
understand
that that which part of the current
we're in
how we avoid the eddies how we avoid the
parts of the current that takes us
up against the shore and we can gently
kind of guide ourselves
in that river in a way that keeps us in
the central current and we keep flowing
down the river
and um the um
um so
being attuned to change
is part of this uh uh
13th step of the sixteen steps of
mindfulness a twelve step
well thirteen for thirteen step of
mindfulness of breathing
and um the um
and it's to um observe
in the word is inconstancy and i'll talk
more about that tomorrow
but it's a part of this family of
concepts that relate to change things
becoming different
um and and
impermanence so
so to observe in constancy observe
change
and to find some degree of freedom
in the same kind of freedom that we
would have
if we're floating in the river there's a
freedom and being carried and
but then we're also careful about what
current we go in
how we're where we're floating the river
maybe even which river we're floating in
and so this might be the theme for this
next 24 hours for you
is to notice change
and notice how change arises
changes in ways depending on conditions
and how
and also how your role and where you
find yourself in your change your
relationship to change
and how you relate to that change
puts you on different currents if you're
resisting change or if you're fighting
change or if you're
attached to a change that puts you in a
different river
than one that is with change in an open
relaxed way
so um so there's different words
different concepts different ways of
kind of talking about the same thing the
buddha used different words
and now for now i'm using the word in
constancy and
and are focusing mostly on change and
tomorrow
we'll pick up this idea of inconstancy
more directly and
a word that is in polis
often or in english is often translated
as impermanence
but that we'll see tomorrow that in
constancy
might be a better translation
so so thank you all
very much and i look forward to tomorrow