so welcome
and a warm hello to all of you and uh
sometimes when seeing all the locations where people are sending in their greetings on the chat
i have a kind of very kind of vague imagination of
having a globe in front of me and having lines drawn between all the places that are
named and take into account all the places that are not named and it would be quite a net quite a
a interconnected net of community of people with similar
interests sitting here to meditate and doing a practice which i believe brings
out the best in people and so it's a wonderful act of
imagination and and that is the topic for this week
the ways in which imagination can support meditation rather than detract from it
a certain kind of way if we don't use our imagination then we get used by it but
and but it's not just our own imagination we get used by but there's a lot of people who
are trying to hijack our imagination or plant images and ideas in our mind
advertisers politicians you know all people who are providing us
with imagination imaginary scenarios that sometimes are done very cleverly to really kind of penetrate
deep inside of us and then they remain and and we're used by them or influenced
by them and it's also possible to use our imagination creatively or
and use it for the purpose of meditation and it takes wisdom to do that takes
skill to do it in a way that's actually supports the mind to wake up to be present to become stable
and and then at different levels of stability of stillness different forms of imagination might
come into play so that if you hear different instructions for imagination
some of them might not work for you because either because you don't have a reference point for them or because
they belong to different degree of stability either than you have
maybe less or more something but the buddha certainly
was his teachings are filled with what could be called images of the imagination images of
similes ideas and a basic one for meditation
is um the idea of sitting with the sitting as stable as
the earth or sitting as firm as a pillar
that it's planted deep in the ground so it's not going to wobble at all or being as calm as a surface of a still
lake and there's it goes on and on these kinds of uh images that buddha uses
which are tapping into the imagination and i'll say this later but part of the
purpose of this tapping into the imagination is because the imagination itself is
tapped into so many different aspects of our inner life the to our emotional life
for physical life kinesthetic life to our motivational life to
to our thoughts and memories and things and so imagination somehow has a
capacity to contribute to the unification the integration that is samadhi as we're getting more
present and more collected in meditation the process of meditation is a process of collectedness
or unification or some people like to use language of becoming whole
and imagination can be in the service of that because of what it evokes within us
it's certainly not true for everyone and everyone if people have different ranges of
relationship with imagination but for this week we're looking at the
building on the buddha's use of imagination in order to cultivate stability
but also presence but also gladness to have gladness or a certain degree of
joy in meditation so to take an upright
meditation posture and to adjust your posture
so it begins to feel stable
one of the advantages of sitting cross-legged is the stability of the legs and the buttocks on the on your cushion a
broad wide foundation anything that supports you the weight of
your body can provide a foundation of stability
and to imagine this body that you're sitting in is here like
a mountain
stable strong
unfazed by the wind that flows by or the clouds that wash over
imagining that the mind is like a clear quiet lake calm wind not blowing
water still and the mind is broad and wide
like the wide broad lake
and imagining the moon the heart is like a full moon
fully exposed fully open fully here
the heart shines its light peacefully on all things
and then the buddha uses an image for tuning into the breathing that one
tunes into breathing like a woodworker does on a on a with a chisel
on a lathe carving a piece of wood or maybe we would say a potter
turning clay on a wheel and to make this contact
with something which is moving around in a circle the cycles of in-breath and out-breath
and this image of a someone working a lathe or working
clay on a wheel is partly an image of making contact and
keeping the contact there
so to take a gently with his contact with the body breathing
taking a few long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale maybe like a dam which has opened its doors so water
can flow out to relax your body
so there can be a flow of vitality flow of ease calmness from the places where you relax
to relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the arms and the elbows hands
relaxing the chest the belly
and breathing easily maybe naturally
as if the piece of clay now has become smooth and round
bowl and the wheel and it just feels light and smooth and
easy to allow the turning of breathing in
and breathing out
your whole body is the bowl awareness is feeling
as you breathe breathing in and breathing out
that kind of intimacy with the body breathing
and as you're sitting here bring to mind
gently quietly whatever sense of goodness or
gladness that comes from the simplicity of being here
meditating where you're somehow what's absent
is the busyness of the day
what's absence is the challenges of the
day the crowds of people
driving in traffic
and if you can stay quietly focused on the breathing
and not giving in to thoughts of desire thoughts of ill will
thoughts of anxiety and regrets thoughts of doubt
this begins to feel like similar to being free of
debt or free of an illness
free of oppression
free of being lost in thought
and these ideas of this freedom from these things for the buddha is meant to be a source
of gladness to take a few moments to appreciate
what is not here right now that feels good to have put aside
and which gives you an intimacy and a peacefulness even if it's mildly so
with here and now and being present
feeling the goodness of this maybe being glad to have these moments
to be free of these things
so
perhaps making a small half smile
that maybe supports a gladness or a contentment
that's willing to be just here in whatever goodness whatever
pleasure or contentment that is available
as you turn the wheel of breathing in and breathing
out in a sense smoothing out the bowl of
your body the bowl of clay on the wheel
with the image of a mountain feeling whatever stability is here in
your body resting in that stability as if you're a
mountain
as if your mind is a broad peaceful lake
feel whatever ways the mind might be that way
broad and still even if there are some waves on it
and then whatever way the heart feels like a full moon
exposed open floating in the air in the sky in space
feel that luminosity and freedom of the heart
and they're breathing like a gentle breeze
that blows here and there through the body through the mind through the heart
connecting you to stability and stillness
in freedom of the heart
and staying centered here in this mountain-like body
still mind an open heart
open the awareness up out into the world
as if the stability spreads out from the place you're sitting out across the
surface of the lands
as if a peaceful stillness spreads from your mind out across the
air and across the seas
and as if the freedom and luminosity of the full moon heart
shines all over the globe and you
for a few moments undisturbed by the suffering of the world
but in this undisturbed way perhaps you can tap into a heartfelt
wish of compassion care wish for the welfare of all beings
may all beings be happy
may all beings be free of suffering
may all beings be safe from all forms of harm
physical mental emotional
may all beings be peaceful
sharing as we share our peacefulness with them
and may all beings be free
as we do not limit them box them in with our ideas and
desires expectations
may the benefit of this meditation together spread out into the world for the
welfare and benefit of all beings
and they do so through our deeds of body speech and mind
may today be a day for spreading for caring for the welfare
of others
[Music]
you