okay so good evening
i wanted to talk tonight
about beginning well
so wherever you are in the world it's
clear
that this pandemic that we're all living
with
is entering a new phase there's an
increased
availability of vaccines and all the
complications that come with
different variants
but nonetheless it's clear enough that
things are starting to shift a bit and
sometime later this year will be will be
different
so as we move toward
whatever post-pandemic life looks like
it is helpful to consider
how to pick up new activities
well so in this case we actually have
the luxury of time of considering
what it is and how it is that we might
want to pick things up
as we go forward in some sense we don't
ever really have
this time it's just an illusion because
every moment right
experience is arising it's arriving and
arising
and we're meeting it and so there's
always beginning
every moment there's a continual process
of beginning
but nonetheless there are some times
when we can
imagine that we have a beginning that we
can think about or move toward in some
intentional way so it is worthwhile
when we have this time to
begin things well to begin things well
so when this is done when we begin well
then experience unfolds more naturally
and also we're in a better position to
learn from experience as it comes and
also to make
uh the necessary adjustments to to
staying on course
all of that a lot of that depends on
beginning well
in some way so what is this you know
what does this mean
what do the buddhist teachings say about
beginnings we hear a lot about endings
about
cessation and letting go and
being free you sort of imply something
dropping away maybe ending suffering the
end of suffering is the aim of the path
but what about the beginnings
the buddha did talk about beginnings and
how to do it well
and the teachings mostly focus in three
areas
our understanding our intention
and our effort so we'll talk about
those things tonight
i think it's no surprise that we are
instructed to pay attention to the mind
as we are beginning things you know
that's considered
a really important place to to notice as
we go forward
there's the well-known opening stanza of
the dhammapada that begins
mind is the forerunner of all things
so that's pretty clear that the
how we are in the mind is going to have
a major impact on what happens as things
go forward
and then more specifically there are
other teachings um
there's one in the major that says quite
directly
right view comes first right view comes
first so this is about our understanding
uh it doesn't mean let me unpack that a
little bit
the right view doesn't mean that we are
sort of
passively applying a view that we
receive
from the teachings or from our teacher
or something
um and just sort of sticking it on okay
here's the
here's the belief i need to apply in
order to begin
it's actually more subtle than that so
whatever view we're using and there
always is one
we always have some kind of a view
coming in that's going to provide
the context or the orientation for
what follows so then
what write means about right view is
that we should adopt
an orientation or a view or an
understanding
that is appropriate for the task at hand
for what it is that we're beginning so
in practice and this is the context for
that quote right view comes first
if the task is walking the buddhist path
to the end of suffering to peace to
liberation
then what we would choose is what is
called right view
which means an appropriate view for
doing
that and you know this generally has
two forms because it's this right view
is useful for whatever we undertake to
make it part of our path
so the two forms of this appropriate
or right view
the first one is the understanding that
actions have results and that we have
some choice about that
so we live in a world that has laws of
cause and effect
in going on you know they may be
more complex than we can exactly see all
the details of and they may operate in
different ways
at different times but generally
speaking actions will have
consequences and we have some choice
about that so
in particular actions that come from a
mind that's oriented toward
harm will lead to our own
suffering our own dukkha and
in contrast actions that come from a
mind oriented toward peace or toward
non-harm
will tend to bring happiness to us this
is one of these of these some of these
basic
laws of action and consequence so even
if we have kind of no
idea about the long-term
or large picture of what we're doing we
can at least in this moment choose to
do actions from an orientation of
non-harming
and that will be good in some sense
and so um people can feel great relief
at having this at a as a guide you don't
actually have to have it all figured out
in the whole big picture because things
are complex especially in
something like this pandemic or in a
complex interconnected world like we
live in
so we can you know make some attempt to
think about our views and our
orientation in the bigger picture but
what matters really is that right now
we come from a place of non-harming that
will have
good consequences for us for our
happiness and and those around us
so that's one wise orientation
wise view and then the second dimension
of
of right view or appropriate view which
is actually not so different
is to see things specifically in terms
of dukkha
and its ant or suffering in its end
or stress in its end so we can notice
um in a situation what feels
stressful or tense or somehow
unsatisfactory we can notice that attune
to that
and then move toward its release
so if i'm entering a room and i feel
some tension
in my chest i can notice that and then
take care of that in some way notice am
i feeling afraid in some way
or in what you know what might i do
maybe just being mindful of the fear
sufficient or something else but
tuning toward dukkha and its end
is a way of orienting toward the four
noble truths
toward what is it that's challenging
right now
how am i somehow holding on
wanting something in order that that's
coming about
how could i apply something i know from
practice
to somehow ease or release some of that
suffering
you know without making it complex but
this orientation of dukkha and its
release
is very much in line with what we're
doing on the path so that's
a good guide for our actions as we
as we undertake things
so even you know just another everyday
example
is if i'm beginning a work project with
somebody
and i'm going to talk with them about
this project so
it's a beginning how do i orient i could
orient toward cultivating kindness
active listening a healthy relationship
with this person that i'm going to be
working with
or i could practice mindfulness of not
drifting off into my own thoughts but
actually
staying on task and being clear about
what's happening in the conversation
those are both forms of this appropriate
view that i just talked about
and those are very different than say
orienting toward
okay i've got to convince this person to
do it my way i've got to get my point
across and make sure that
i stay in control of this thing as it's
starting
that's very different right so that's
going to have a major
impact on how things unfold so
and this works on the cushion too we did
it in the guided meditation he said if
we sit down and we orient toward
bringing some ease to the body some ease
to the mind
some sense of what we're doing that will
have a different effect than if we
don't do those things to orient at the
beginning of our sit
these simple acts can have very
important
results for how the meditation proceeds
so in general we're asking
how can this be wholesome or supportive
of the path as i go forward
now how can i reduce stuka through this
beginning
so all of this amounts to right view our
understanding and our orientation as we
begin a task go into something
so right view as you may recall from the
steps of the eightfold path
it feeds into the next step which is
called right intention
and that is actually the crux the sort
of key point the crucial point
of how we engage skillfully with
beginnings i would say that's
the key one so classically there are
three wholesome intentions that we
orient around as we go forward
each of which is set up to counteract
some kind of unwholesome intention that
we might have in the mind
some sort of tendency so the intention
the first intention is typically called
renunciation
people don't always connect with that
word
so we could also call it letting go or
even being at ease if we you know wanted
to
extend it a little bit so it counteracts
the unskillful pursuit
of sense pleasure you know just wanting
to grasp at the pleasant part wanting to
get things that are
good and pleasant and useful for me
you know these sorts of graspy kinds of
orientations
um the the intention of being generous
or renouncing the need for those things
is is this first orientation and it's
it has a an effect of coming in with an
open hand with an open heart with an
open mind
and then the the second and third of
these
right intentions or wise intentions are
stated
as clear counteractions so they're
stated as non-ill will
and non-cruelty so we also come in with
a mind that isn't oriented in a negative
or aversive
or oppositional
way as we move into things or if they're
named
more in the positive it could be named
as
good will or as compassion
so these are um essentially these three
set the tone of our engagement with
things
so um and the tone the tone that we're
setting in life
matters so much that's
worry that's based in our intention
so i guess i'm thinking about work
projects today because another i'm
thinking of another time that i
was beginning a work project and i was
sending an
email to one of my colleagues about
about the project and i noticed that um
i kept wanting to include some kind of
comment
about um
their experience with this and a little
bit derogatory like you know
i know you don't have so much experience
with this or something like that i
i don't know um but i noticed that there
was a slight feeling of tension around
that and i realized that i was kind of
trying to question my colleagues level
experience of experience in order to
elevate my own
and therefore show that you know i was
going to be able to
contribute very well to this project or
something so
but i i caught this you know luckily as
an intention of ill will
and i um instead changed what i wanted
to write to something that was more
inclusive more connecting at the
beginning of this project
not highlighting their lack of
experience or my
experience which was a little bit
delusional to think that way
and i'm certain that that set a much
better tone
than if i hadn't done hadn't made that
change
would have changed the relationship
right at the beginning of the project
we can also set the tone
in advance of an experience or a
situation that we're going into
and then just trust that it will carry
us
in so for example if we're about to go
into
a meeting or even a social encounter or
a party of some kind
we can as we're walking toward the door
or
sitting in the car before we go in we
can set an intention
of goodwill or of mindfulness
or something like that and just orient
the mind that way
and then you know you don't have to
constantly think about it and bring it
to mind and
be distracted by it during the counter
you just um
you just set it and then walk in and
trust that it will carry through in some
way
it may not carry you know entirely
through the entire
encounter or it may but
generally this is a good thing to do
with the mind just to orient it well
when you're starting i remember a
friend of mine went to practice in
asia and she was doing
intensive retreat practice but even in
that setting
the abbott of the monastery used to ask
the
people who were practicing there that in
the morning when they
woke up before they got out of bed
to start their day that they spend a few
minutes doing loving-kindness practice
and the way he said it was this will set
the tone
for everything else you do and then you
know the rest of the day they were doing
mindfulness practice vipassana
concentration you know sort of more
traditional
wisdom practices but he wanted them to
do this
loving kindness at the very beginning to
set the tone
for the for the rest of the day so you
might try this also
see what you can remember to do in the
morning
before you get out of bed just to meet
the day well
so in general we're aiming to
act and speak and even think
from a place of non-greed non-hatred
and non-delusion that's the
overall picture and so the three right
intentions
that i just named are
very clearly covering the first two of
non-greed and non-hatred
so renunciation for example would cover
non-greed
and non-ill will and non-cruelty
would cover non-hatred so it encounters
those first
two you know clear defilements of the
mind
but then we might ask you know where is
non-delusion
in terms of orienting ourselves
sometimes people have
questions about the second step of the
path because it doesn't seem
to include non-grade non-hatred where's
the non-delusion
it turns out that that is covered by
right view by what we talked about first
so um you know having the correct
view that we're moving towards suffering
in the end of suffering
and that our actions have consequences
and we have some choice
that is non-delusion knowing those
things
so this three-fold purity of volition
if you will non-greed non-hatred
non-delusion
is the fundal mental way to begin and
also to proceed and also to end
the buddha says very clearly in a
different suta that
volition or caitanya lies at the heart
of action
of kama so that strongly influences the
results that we experience
so that covers a lot of the territory
but um all of that is kind of the
prep in the mind and so there's also the
actual active beginning
you know what what else do we need to
begin well
the third thing that i area that i named
is that there's something to do with our
energy
as we actually engage with the
beginning of a task and so let's
let's talk also about this area of
energy
the buddha talks about the importance of
generating
wholesome energy or iberia
that's the word for energy or effort as
we undertake a task
so in particular this is a very stock or
standard phrase you'll find in sutas
like
it goes like this one generates desire
makes an effort arouses energy applies
one's mind
and strives so
i know that that sometimes sounds a
little too energetic for
those of us in the west who are a little
bit uh
action-oriented and result oriented in
some word we're told not to strive quite
so strongly
but that phrase is very common in the
sutures
one generates desire makes an effort
arouses energy
applies one's mind and strives so we
might just encapsulate all of that into
that middle
phrase arouses energy so that's uh
viria ar rubity that's the polyphrase
and arabity means to
engage with or to undertake in a sense
so we should be willing to put forth
some effort for things to go well as
we're
beginning so we orient our mind and then
we bring forth this kind of wholesome
energy
to get it going in a sense so instead of
being a little bit more passive or
lackluster about how we get started on
things
later when there's momentum then we're
encouraged to back off
and be a little bit more effortless you
might have heard that phrase effortless
effort
and we did that a little bit in the
meditation where at the beginning
we were a little bit more attentive and
then
at the end relaxed our effort and just
allowed
experience to unfold that's often a good
way to
think about the energy in a project so
wise effort
means the right amount of effort and
that's one aspect of it is to bring the
right amount of effort not too much
and not too little and at the beginning
when we're just starting things out
sometimes for beginnings a fair amount
of effort is needed because we're trying
to
generate momentum or else change
direction
of momentum that we already had so you
might think of beginnings as requiring a
little bit more
energy a little bit more focused effort
to get going in a good direction
so
considering beginnings i've been kind of
orienting us around
beginnings in daily life
in particularly also in this bigger
picture of beginning what's going to
happen as things start to open up and
people come into more
contact with each other and maybe we
start
interacting with more people than we
have been these things would be very
good to keep in mind but actually there
is um
quite a bit about beginnings that
happens on the cushion
too and i also alluded to this in the
meditation
there's a stage of inside practice where
we become
very attuned to beginnings um
i asked you to do it consciously during
the sit but it
there's a time when it just comes
without
needing to be deliberate about it so the
mind um
gets really interested in beginnings
it's a very it's an interesting
fun time of practice because mindfulness
gets really sharp
because you're you're catching the first
moment of things it's like oh
you see the the breath come into
being from a moment before when there
wasn't one
and you see uh you know the in-breath
tails off
and then the out breath begins we see
that first moment when there starts to
be
uh the air exiting instead of entering
and it's exciting and maybe we see um
the first
shift in a mood you know where we're
feeling angry or irritated and but we're
we're don't get caught up in it we're
mindful
and then there comes a moment when it's
like it's like the mind sort of
turns away from that and we feel
something else come in a sense of relief
or
or joy or peace or many other things
we see that first moment we know ah
there's the moment where the anger
turned and we might also see
um the first moment of a thought
you know we're sitting it's not that
there's absolutely zero
thoughts but we're kind of between
thoughts and we're not
really noticing thoughts at that moment
and then we'll see a little spark
like the mind starts to form an idea and
we see it kind of arising out of the
matrix of the mind this idea
we can see oh that's going to be a
thought in one more instant
it's going to break the surface and i'm
going to know what those words are
and every once in a while one of those
will come
and we'll be mindful of it and it will
just dissipate
before it ever forms into the image or
the word
and we wonder what was that thought
gonna be
you'll never know but it's a fun time of
practice
seeing these beginnings um
there's a lot of wisdom in this to see
and feel
beginnings means that we can also see
and feel the very first moment of
clinging
we were peaceful calm mindful
and then the mind started to
form an identity or attached to
something or hold on no
don't let that go and we see that we see
that little grip and we
can feel that the moment that we begin
to cling is the moment of the arising of
suffering
we see the second noble truth is that
clinging and suffering
are identical and we can only be sure of
that
if we see them begin and end together
so it's important and so then we can
start to get wise about
how we engage with beginnings because
stuff is coming every moment
we see if we grasp it we're going to
suffer so we learn not to we learn
to let it arise as it is
to let it be itself as it comes into
being
without grasping it as mine without
putting it in a box so i know what that
is and immediately
labeling it without controlling it
letting it arise and have its life
whether it's going to be big or small
can we just trust
that it can come into being as it is
so we start to we start to see this and
there's a lot of wisdom that comes from
getting intimate with
beginnings and with how we relate to
beginnings
on the cushion and then that will of
course feed into
how we do it in life also when things
come in that are surprising
as happens all the time our partner we
don't know what her partner is going to
say next
can we meet it can we just let that be
there
we turn the corner and see something
unexpected can we open to that
or do we close off or get scared
or try to control it or try to make it
what we want it to be
we'll see again and again how we're
relating to life
when we start to see on the cushion how
we relate to things coming in
beginnings coming into our mind and our
body
so this is an important area of practice
beginnings and as we learn to begin well
and engage in ways that are
open and connecting and
filled with peace good will all those
right intentions
that too will help us learn to end well
to let go
to let things cease to let them end
to not cling so
all of this is feeding into our wisdom
and our compassion so i wish you well
in exploring a very interesting area
and also with whatever is beginning in
your life beginning in
this springtime maybe it's autumn if
you're in the southern hemisphere
beginning with things opening
beginning with seeing more people
whenever that occurs
you might consider how to meet that well
so many blessings for your practice
take care