so welcome to this meditation session
and to
evoke a theme for this meditation
some of you may have seen that it's not it's fairly common for statues of the buddha
for the buddha to have a small smile on his face
it's not dramatic just a little upturn of the lips
and while he's sitting in a posture that represents both alertness
and tranquility and i think of this smile the buddha
to be a tranquil smile represented tranquil joy
or a joyful tranquility
and so to sit with tranquility to sit calmly is often associated with
meditation and one of the ways of
supporting tranquility and meditation is to recognize the tranquility that's
here the buddha said that the nourishment for tranquility
is tranquility that might seem
making it impossible if you don't feel any tranquility at all how can you
benefit from tranquility which is absent
but i suspect that
if you take your meditation posture that you will
if you search around find something within you that feels like it's
calm or tranquil or it could just be a hint
and that can be the basis for the growth of more tranquility
so assuming a meditation posture
one that maybe will support the body
to be tranquil calm
certainly not with the agitation of running around
and to
gently close your eyes
and to feel as you sit here is there within you
any physical tranquility anything that qualifies as physical
calmness maybe already a bit of relaxation
where in your body do you feel that calmness or tranquility the most
even if much of you is agitated
where is at least agitated
take a few moments to breathe with the place of calmness of
tranquility breathe through it breathe with it
just so you can feel the calmness more fully
and is there some simple way to allow that calmness to expand outwards
into more of your body
maybe there's relaxing around the calmness
maybe even a small adjustment in your posture
allows the calmness to spread a bit
and is there some way that whatever calmness or tranquility you have however small
that it could also be found or expressed in your breathing
is there any any part of your cycle of breathing
that has some quality of relaxation relaxer relaxing
tranquility peace calm
is there any part of the cycle of breathing that qualifies as being the most
calm the most at ease
the end of the exhale maybe
the end of the inhale
if there's a pause between the exhale and inhale
there's something about that pause that feels tranquil and calm
or is there something about the tempo of breathing
that feels easy and calm even if there's only a little hint of it
and as you exhale now to relax your body
soften
tranquility of the body is associated with the softness of body
in a lightness a body feels light
and as you exhale relaxing the body to soften
the edges of it
to ease up on the heaviness of the body
to feel a lightness
relaxing releasing the muscles of the face
relaxing releasing tension in your shoulders
softening the belly
and similarly can you find any hints of tranquility in your mind
even if the mind is agitated underneath the agitation behind it
to the side the mind or at the heart the center of the mind
is there any feelings of calm
he's
the tranquility of the mind is also associated with the softness soft mind
and a lightness of mind
and if there's a if you recognize any tranquility of mind
can you allow that to expand as you
breathe relaxing the mind
quieting it quieting the thinking
as you exhale relaxing any tension or pressure associated with
thinking so that the calmness of mind
can spread
i associate calmness with a very still
lake at dawn with no wind hardly
very peaceful surface of the lake air is clear and still
quiet before the activities of the day have begun
and for the body and mind to be tranquil like that
and the breathing to be maybe a very gentle breeze
that touches down across the surface of that lake
like a light feather it brushes
the surface of the lake that breeze doesn't disturb the lake
the movements are breathing soft and light like a feather
breathing with whatever tranquility of body and mind that's here
not worrying about the agitation that there might be
making room to feel and experience whatever peacefulness that's here
breathing with it letting it have its time
to expand to grow to nourish you
the nourishment of tranquility and peace
if there is any tranquility for you let there also be a willingness
to feel the tranquility and openness to it
receptivity
as you breathe with the tranquility of mind and body
if the mind is starting to get activated and thinking a lot
calmly recognize that's the that's the case
let your mindfulness be calm and tranquil about what it knows
there's no hurry in mindfulness
calmly bring what's happening into focus
and then recognize whatever tranquility and calmness that's present
in return to breathing breathing
together with whatever calmness is here
with whatever nourishing nourishment there is
in being peaceful and tranquil
and as the body feels tranquil and peaceful
might there be hints of some happiness
or some sense of contentment or ease
happiness or contentment in the body
and if there is hints of that let that expand
let that open to that
breathe with the contentment the happiness the ease
that might be there with the tranquility
a happiness contentment
that makes it easier to quiet the mind more
a still quiet tranquil mind
might itself have a mental contentment and happiness
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
may it be that this meditation is a support for the world
that the benefits of sitting and meditating will spread out from
us individually and us collectively
among those who are agitated
may we spread tranquility
among those who are in conflict may we provide peace
among those who are tense may we provide relaxation
among those who are discontented may we provide contentment
and for those who need reassurance may we be reassuring
that it's good to be at rest and at peace in one's own heart
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and in this way may all beings feel deeply at home
in this world of ours and in their own hearts
may all beings be happy
[Music]
so continuing to discuss the seven factors of awakening
following the joy factor of awakening comes the tranquility factor of
awakening and
in the teachings of the buddha that pattern repeats itself many times
that first there's joy and then there's tranquility
and one of the common phrases in the suttas
is that when the mind is joyful the body becomes tranquil
and when the body is tranquil there arises happiness
so exactly how this works i can't tell you it depends a little bit of what we think
joy is but i think it's in part something that's
very reassuring that somehow to begin experiencing some
feeling of delight joy happiness goodness
in meditation then it's reassuring something can
release something and relax oh this is good i'm here i'm starting to be home
this is a good place to be it's okay not to be running around
searching wanting fighting resisting hoping
it's okay to kind of be reassuring just to be here and settled and relaxed
and and the function of this tranquility in
the buddhist path of meditation is not tranquility for its own sake
but tranquility for the sake of happiness
that joy precedes tranquility and then that opens
up the possibility for a deeper happiness and exactly what we mean by
happiness maybe is each of us will have a different idea but it's something that opens up
throughout the body it's often considered to be an embodied feeling of contentment or
happiness warmth goodness
that the tranquility enables because tranquility
kind of is something that's meant to spread through your body open your body so the tensions of your body are not
holding things in check and so as the body opens up more and more and
and we get feel and open to the body then there's more room for a well-being
an embodied sense of well-being that doesn't really depend on what's
happening in the world it doesn't really depend on having our desires met or
having you know an evaluation doesn't depend on someone praising us or
having worldly success but comes from the state of mind
and body that we've kind of settled into in a meditative way
it's not easy to experience this and um so this is in terms of the factors of awakening
you know this tranquility is now step five and uh
i think that uh just with on as with anapanasati you know we're all
whether we consciously know it or not we're all kind of moving through these factors uh different days and different ones are
salient and but i think that percentage-wise but
average meditator spends much more time on the first one mindfulness
a little bit and then somewhat less time with investigation somewhat less time with maybe with i
don't know if the effort took outfits but less time with feeling joy and less time with feeling tranquility
and less time feeling to see that good happiness and then samadhi concentration and then
equanimity so i'm saying this so we don't set ourselves up and think that it has to be
linear it has to be like more and more of the good good stuff
you know the meditation is a lot to do with starting over and working with you know
working with what's we have and what's going on and then slowly you know that
we might find ourselves developing and moving into the direction of that these seven factors awakening
are pointing to but tranquility
in mid-1970s when the first
american vipassana teachers in our lineage who kind of establishing vipassana in the united
states they were going to look for a retreat center to have
first retreat center and they came across a
i guess it was a closed monastery kind of place in a place called barry massachusetts
small little town and as they were driving through town to see the place
in the middle of town there's a little statue or little yeah i think it's a statue from the kind of commemorating the colonial times
or the clone the revolutionary war or something something like that maybe but anyway had
the the motto of the town is tranquil and alert
and they said oh this is our place this is the place from meditation center
tranquil and alert so certainly the tranquility that comes
along with alertness not bright energetic alertness but the kind of clarity and simplicity
of alertness it's really here present so not a tranquility where we get lethargic or dull or start falling
asleep which is a little bit the danger with tranquility it's easy to
linger in it rest in it it's easy to indulge in it in such a way that we kind of it
actually becomes soperific it puts us asleep and the art of meditation is to be able to
stay alert and clear while being this deep tranquility
and that's why i like this myself this this lake metaphor image for tranquility
that early in the morning when the air is completely still and quiet and very clear
at dawn and everything and that surface of the lake is so still and quiet and peaceful
but completely um clears like and so this clarity
that comes with tranquility so it's about it's important when there's a lot of tranquility
to kind of bring into balance these factors of awakening so it might be a little more energy is
needed to keep that clarity or that's maybe the part of the function of the joy is to keep a little bit
brightness there so the mind can be soft
light and bright at the same time and so we're kind of tracking ourselves
and and so it's very important in any kind of meditation state when there's some nourishing qualities that are
present uh to not um kind of it's
the art of not indulging in it or resting it in a certain kind of way or
savoring it in a way that um but also allowing ourselves to be nourished by it
allowing us ourselves to feel the goodness of it without leaning into it or holding on to it or or becoming
complacent i think as people get calmer in
meditation and a lot of their tensions and anxieties and different things settle
down it's very easy to fall into a complacency and um and just kind of just be content
to kind of feel calm and relaxed and the mind wanders off and fall asleep and
because there's not really the little brightness of practice of engagement
so this bright tranquility this bright serenity or peace
that comes along and um right you know
tranquil and alert and then uh as i've maybe said already
that for the buddha each of these factors of awakening have something that
nourishes them and then in the case of tranquility tranquility nourishes tranquility
so if you want to be tranquil go find something for fine tranquility
because that tranquility feeds us or influence us or something so it could be mean you know going into
some people find have tranquil places they go there are places believe it or not
buildings that are tranquil buildings i used to go sometimes into some of the
churches in europe when i lived there i just sit quietly some of them were quite tranquil and peaceful and just
it was wonderful to go you know hustle and bustle of town come across this wonderful little church and go in and be
so peaceful and just sit there for a while and take it in and it felt like nourishing to take it
in the um many people associated with places in
nature even if it's a very small little park
you know that can be a tranquil place so yesterday i was in a park and
and there was a piece of the park just a few trees that thought this is a peaceful place it was nice just to be
there and take it in or maybe a tranquility can be found with a cup of
tea it doesn't you know just to contentedly drink the tea to drink
the tea as if this is meant to be a place to
drink tranquility it's a little bit
a footnote that the word pity p-i-t-i that's the word for joy also in pali means to drink
so nourishment drinking in something
and then and then when you sit meditate
can you support yourself with tranquility as you meditate um do you just take it to chance you
just gamble that today i'm gonna sit down and maybe it'll be some tranquility or do you sit down in a place that's
tranquil sometimes people find that just straightening out their room before they
meditate it just seems to kind of support a little more tranquility rather than a
messy room and a clean place
and then to take some time to value tranquility try calmness
and so to sit down and see if there's any any of it here
so tranquility nourishes tranquility so the ability to recognize it and allow
ourselves to feel it when it is there than to avail ourselves of that and and i love the term nourishment
to be nourished by this it goes along with translating
kusala the word for skillful or wholesome translating as wholesome
because one of the things wholesomes mean i think in english is a kind of something which is healthy for us it's
nourishing for us like wholesome bread or something and
and so this idea that what we're doing this buddhist path is we're nourishing
ourselves with what's wholesome and that's a very different paradigm
for meditation practice in buddhist practice than the acquisitive paradigm
and i got to do it and i gotta work at it and you know get concentrated and
make something happen and get something to happen to me and you know it's it's a there can be a lot
of um uh unhealthy unnourishing attitudes that we bring to meditation
so is there a nourishing attitude is there an attitude is kind of
touch and do this practice engage in our life live our life so the very way that we live our life
feels nourishing feels wholesome feels supportive that is onward leading
just to these each of these factors of awakening is onward leading tranquility when you practice is not a
dead end when you're practicing mindfulness and sincerely tranquility itself is onward leading its
support to go it to um to kind of happiness and contentment
which then becomes a support for samadhi for concentration and if we take samadhi to be a
unification of mind where we're feeling of becoming whole then this tranquility that allows us to
kind of be at ease in our whole body and mind that kind of that supports us to be
kind of really centered in here in a deep way without the tensions and the conflicts and the divisions that
that um you know prevents us from feeling a wholeness then we understand how this tranquility
being tranquil is a support for the wholeness feeling of wholeness or unification
that comes with samadhi which will be the topic for these
early morning tomorrow and
and so for now
you're left with tranquility can't be that bad
thank you