so
before i begin this talk
i want to mention that
the way i calculate and uh
next monday it'll be one year
anniversary of having done these
early morning in california these uh
daily sittings weekday sittings
meditations and teachings
kind of remarkable that it's lasted a
year and
and remarkable
for how for many of us how wonderful
it's been to do this
so i thought that next monday we could
do
a community meeting to
acknowledge celebrate this one-year mark
and we haven't done it for a long time
and
my own personal life has meant that i
can't it's been hard to do
add more things like that but i can do
it next monday
and so we can um
so it'll be there'll be a zoom meeting
so after
uh we finish here at about 7 45
you'll be given access to a zoom link
and then we'll switch over to the zoom
and
and be able to meet and hang out and
talk and
maybe break up maybe break into little
groups and so you can chat a little bit
with uh
this youtube community and maybe meet
some of the people whose names appear
on you know in the chat
and then we can also talk a little bit
about some of the maybe some of the
questions and issues around our little
community and this meetings and
the continuation of it and all that
planning to continue
and so
so next monday the 15th
so um
of the foundational cornerstone
teachings
of the buddha is that intimately
connects to both meditation and living a
daily life
is the idea of wholesome and unwholesome
sometimes it's translated skillful and
unskillful
more informally i like to translate it
as helpful and unhelpful
that that there is a uh
way of of uh and it has to do with the
actions what we do
that we and some of those actions don't
really maybe in english we don't think
of them as in actions but
more like states wholesome states but
they still have a kind of a little bit
they're an activity of the mind in the
background somehow
and so um these are these are
states of mind actions of the mind
activities of the mind
ways of being that feel like as if
they're nourishing
and that word nourishing is a is a word
that the buddha used that's
different things different mental states
and mental activities
operated as food as nourishment for
ourselves
so it isn't just simply generosity's
generosity generosity is a wholesome
state healthy state
that is nourishing that has a good
influence on us
so uh loving-kindness is that
mindfulness is considered a wholesome
state that is nourishing
and and has a good influence on us
tranquility is a wholesome state
wholesome way of being that is as a
nourishing it nourishes us nourishes
more tranquility
and and so this idea of
both of nourishment wholesomeness
comes into play now in the third tetrat
of the sixteen steps of anapanasati
in a number of ways the
tenth step is gladdening the mind
and this gliding the mind some people's
translated as satisfying the mind or
or enjoying the mind
and this comes with the ability to feel
the goodness
the delight the enjoyment not just of
pleasure
but of this nourishment this
wholesomeness that can happen
and this comes with as we no longer
fixate or focus
on the details of our inner life
but begin looking at the big picture and
that's what uh
being experiencing the mind as a whole
we're not preoccupied with the past
preoccupied by the future our desires
are focusing on particular emotions that
we have that are really troublesome for
us
all reasonable things to do at times but
to
um but as we go deeper and deeper into
meditation
we're relaxing and letting go and not
fixating on things
that there's a softening and a deepening
and an opening
that begins happening that we've become
aware of the
the general the quality of our inner
life
and another way i'd like to translate
chitta the mind or the heart
the whole the holistic a whole quality
of the inner life
and as we let go a lot and going through
these deeper states of meditation
we tap into um
we tap into a sense of wholesomeness a
goodness
and some nourishing nourishment
something it feels very satisfying just
to be here
and now this becomes a valuable
thing to experience this becomes
something to imbibe
to feel to allow itself to be influenced
by
and so and so to understand that the
buddhist teachings is based on this
movement towards the wholesome and to
the degree to which we do
what's wholesome do wholesome things in
our life
skillful things do things which are
ethically wholesome
that is psychologically wholesome that
leads to
a sense of being whole rather than being
fragmented
a sense of being inclusive rather than
holding things at bay and holding things
in check
this becomes very important as we start
moving into
developing samadhi or unification the
eleventh step of anupanasati
breathing in one unifies the mind
breathing out one unifies the mind
another translator
breathing in one steadys the mind
breathing out one steadies the mind
another translator breathing in one
concentrates the mind
breathing out one concentrates the mind
so these words
unify steady concentrate are all
in the domain of this
fourth this third tetrad one experiences
the mind
one gladdens or satisfies the mind and
then
one concentrates unifies the mind
and this sequence points to the fact
that
it's a lot easier for the mind to get
unified to gather together to get
organized to get settled to be steady
when there's a feeling of when the mind
feels like a satisfying place an
enjoyable place to be
the heart is wholesome and good
and so we're not recoiling from inner
pain or struggle or
angst we're not afraid of ourselves and
in trying to avoid parts of ourselves
we've come to the place where we're now
inclusive the mind we associate more
with the inclusivity of the big mind
rather than the particular details we
might still have particular details that
are difficult for sure
but it's not where we're locked into or
what we're preoccupied with
we respect it but where now the mind
holds it all
in a more expansive open way and then
expansive open mind
that is is where we begin feeling uh
something allows for something wholesome
and satisfying and deep to happen
and so rather than huffing and puffing
to get concentrated
it's more like da this is good
the mind wants to settle the mind wants
to
go into uh
into uh you know be more more subtle
doesn't want to be scattered
in fact to be scattered to go into the
past and the future to be caught up in
thoughts
to become narrow again or
locked into something again it just
starts feeling not doesn't really feel
interesting it's not like
it's like why would you and there's not
much juice much energy to
to be distracted because it feels so
good
to be here right here so maybe my way
i'm talking is kind of grand and
grandiose a little bit seems like a
little bit beyond what's possible for
you
but what i want to emphasize is
that we are kind of moving in the
direction
of an inner goodness and inner
wholesomeness and inner
some kind of way that inner life feels
satisfying
and i like to use the word we feel at
home in ourselves
oh i'm home it's so good to be here of
course i want to be here
and it's with this mind this way of
being
that when we connect to our breathing
that we do it in a way that feels
satisfying tender
caring we appreciate the opportunity to
start again
rather than being a burden and rather
being dejected or dismayed that we
wandered off and thought
we feel ah yes i come home this is good
and then when we sustain the attention
it's not because we're struggling to do
it or holding things at bay
it's because we are ah this is good i'm
home and
this feels nice to be here in the
present moment
so the um it's called the initial
application of attention
this connecting and the sustained
application of attention is
sustaining attention ideally it's all
you
all kind of nourishing and maybe each of
you can
have a different um
reference point or example that supports
you for this
i used in the meditation idea of doing
tai chi
tai chi of the mind coming back to your
breathing
hanging in there with the breathing
those gentle
flowing movements of tai chi where the
point isn't to get to the end of the tai
chi movements as quickly as you can
the point is there's an action we're
doing tai chi
but we're each moment we're just is
complete in itself is we're really into
that part of the movement
for some of you might be gardening maybe
you love gardening and just
being and weeding and planting just
doing it
there's not you're not in a hurry to do
it it's just tender it's nourishing it's
maybe it's kind of a parental feeling of
your plan so just kind of tending and
caring maybe it's a craft maybe it's
caring for
someone who's sick that you do do it in
a loving way
so you might think about what example
you have
in your life of doing something which
has qualities of
wholesomeness nourishment
satisfaction inner goodness
that is the that represents for you the
movement we're going
the downhill slope the pull of gravity
of meditation
this is where we go going and
and with that we cultivate unification
we cultivate a steadiness a deep
subtleness
and what some people call concentration
so enjoy yourself
enjoy your mind and or provide your mind
with a way of being that
the mind enjoys let your inner actions
inner attitudes thoughts and feelings
be something the mind really appreciates
that the mind feels ah
this is good the mind says oh i like
being with this person
i like being here i don't feel like i
need to run off anymore
because the way this is operating for
this person this is really good
and maybe your mind will stick around
and
stick around for your breathing and for
your meditation in the present moment
so thank you all very much and i look
forward to tomorrow