warm hellos from redwood city
and uh i appreciate all the good mornings and the warmth that it comes
kind of radiating out of the chat here so thank you for those who are making
the greetings and and thanks to all those of you who have those kinds of
greetings in your heart so we're continuing with mindfulness of
breathing and one of the functions one of the wonderful functions or
potentials of mindfulness of breathing is a combination of doing both mindfulness and
concentration practice that we are both developing a steadiness of mind to stay on the breath
to really rest in the breathing or stay kind of immersed in the world of
breathing without being pulled into extraneous thoughts and ideas and
feelings and it can be a real delight to simplify the mind even our life in a
certain way and be absorbed in one thing in this case the breathing
and it's not necessarily the breathing is so wonderful and as it is the absorption the really
kind of intimacy with it that intimacy and connection continuity opens up a whole different inner world of
possibility and one of those possibilities is to observe
carefully the experience of breathing which is really where the passana practice practice of insight
begins opening up and to distinguish to highlight what observing means
we can distinguish between
looking seeing and observing looking is an active function
we if we look at if we say look look look at look for look for the needle and the haystack
then there's a kind of steering that might go on you might kind of really
actively engage the eyes to see and try to find the thing that we've been asked to look for and so it's an
it might be very active engaged and and even the head might go forward
and the eyes may be you know more fixated as it kind of really searches the terrain
uh to see uh in the more passive sense of the word or
there's less active senses of the word it's just the i see there doesn't have to be an intention to
see determination to see any effort to find anything or look anything particular
there's a seeing happens and we might not even choose what we see it's just new things come in and and you
just see that for now and uh and it's more receptive quality
than the active quality of looking and observing has a little bit
of both qualities observing uh has uh the the receptive quality of just
seeing not interfering not trying so hard not staring at anything fixating on
something but it is also a little bit intentional gentle loving determination
intentionality to be intimate with the experience to really get closer and really
feel and sense and experience it in a more precise way and a little bit like you're still
seeing within that kind of receptive mode but you've placed a magnifying glass or you're
still seeing but you've gotten really close so i've had a history of being
nearsighted and that's a little bit changing now with cataract surgery in one eye but uh still
my right eye is nearsighted and if i keep my eye my hand you know three feet away from my
myself i see that i have a hand but i don't see many details at all it's a little bit fuzzy but as i bring
it closer i can see really all the lines and the fingerprints and i can see the details
of my hand very nicely and and so i can still just seeing
but there's a things get highlighted and clear and clear so it's a little bit like that
the observing that we're building or finding discovering
that comes with being settled and immersed in the world of breathing is to now begin seeing this the
subtlety or the details the fingerprints almost of each little in-breath and out
breath each little experience of breathing and so the observing has a little bit more of
a little bit more maybe kind of intimacy than just seeing might have but not the
active kind of looking forward and reaching for out that that looking would have so to
observe so that's kind of the so to take a comfortable meditation posture
and gently close your eyes
and relax let go soften your body
tune into your body see your body feel your body
and then within this body take a few long slow deep breaths
the purpose of which is to remind yourself now you're going to be
with your breathing that you're offering to accompany your
breathing and your breathing and ascent is going to accompany you
hand in hand you will go
and here you are you're saying hello to your breathing with these big breaths
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as a way of settling into your breathing more
you might relax your shoulders and as you relax your shoulders
almost as if you're relaxing into the body breathing
easing up some of the muscles and that are surrounding
the bodies engagement and breathing
and the same thing with a belly to relax the belly as you breathe
so that there's a greater connection to breathing and freedom to breathing
and maybe there's also a softening in the chest the solar plexus area
and as you relax the chest it's almost like you're able to settle in more to the experience of the body
breathing
if you experience the breathing mostly in the nostrils maybe there's a way of softening
relaxing your face so that you settle more into
the place where you feel the breathing
there as you exhale
to relax your thinking
calm your thinking a little bit
reassuring the mind that things are okay at this moment just for now here
as you exhale letting go of your thoughts
as you let go of your thoughts let go into your breathing
and in the beginning of this sitting keep returning to your breathing as
often as necessary but do so gently lovingly
do so in which in a way that the returning the beginning again
is pleasant the returning the beginning again itself
is done in a way that's calming relaxing
maybe a mental tai chi
where you flow awareness back into your breathing
and then stay intimate with the inhales with the exhales
as if there's a wonderful tai chi dance between breathing and your
awareness why the breathe awareness mirrors the
breathing follows the breathing
rides the breathing
and relaxing the mind's ability to be aware
so that the awareness of breathing is more receptive
then active but receptivity that
is committed to the intimacy between awareness and
breathing
hmm
and then with a little bit more intimacy
awareness getting really close to the inhales and the exhales
begin to experience the details of sensations that come into play
as you breathe in that come into play as you breathe out
breathing in breathing out intimately
letting things letting the sensations that are connected to breathing
begin to stand out and highlight
in the clarity of awareness that's
not swept away in thinking and thoughts
but becomes more like a soft relaxed magnifying glass that just
feels and senses intimately
the beginning the middle the end of the inhale
the beginning the middle and the end of the exhale
observing
observing the particular detail of your breathing
particular detail of all the sensations that come into play as you breathe
and that is those sensations are changing
no need to look at the details in any a different way
but begin observing in a relaxed receptive way
how every sensation that comes into play as you breathe
changes by fading away or turning into something
else
maybe the way that waves washing up on a shore are constantly changing
as they wash up and roll back on the sand
immerse yourself in that changing landscape of breathing
observing in a relaxed but careful way
not only noticing how the sensations change
notice that some appear and disappear
an ongoing sequence of sensations that appear and disappear
throughout the inhale throughout the exhale
no need to think about it or be involved with them
but allow those sensations to be known as coming and going
as we observe the breathing allowing the sensations to come and go
on their own there is a giving of freedom
to those sensations there's allowing each of them to be its
own self as they arises as it passes
in this way in which observing grants freedom
from our involvement our entanglement our fixing and wanting it's a wonderful lesson
for how to be with others
to allow others to be as they are
to have the ability to be present and maybe even a certain intimacy or
closeness or attentiveness
we allow others to be who they are where others become free
of our desires our needs our expectations our fixing our wanting
our bias and interpretations
and to allow to let the deep capacity to observe this way
be registered deeply in the mind and the heart
and to stay close to it so we begin to find wise ways
of offering this freedom to others the freedom from what our minds does
and may it be that this meditation practice that we do
offers a lot of freedom for others to be as they are
they might not recognize that you're granting them freedom because it's really a freedom that
within which how they are seen and received in ourselves
and it's a freedom that then also makes more room for the heart's tenderness
kindness love for others to shine forth
in a way this freedom that the mind grants to others
allows for space for more love care
and may it be that what we learn here
can be expressed in the words may others be happy
may others be safe
may others be peaceful
may others be free
and may others be included in my circle of care
a care that is characterized by freedom
the giving of freedom to others so they can be
be themselves in some deep way may all beings everywhere
be free and safe
uh
so as i've said already that with the 13
step of mindfulness of breathing we enter into the territory of insight
of bipasuna and
before this meditation practice can be characterized by practicing
mindfulness after all this is called mindfulness of breathing in and breathing out
and mindfulness and vipassana are two different things classically in the early tradition in
the modern english kind of scene people will use the word vipassana and mindfulness sometimes synonymously
and sometimes the word vipassana refers to the vipassana tradition or vipassana meditation and it's used
kind of as a you know to a general term
but in the teachings of the buddha the word vipassana doesn't refer to any kind of practice
but rather the results of practice so it's the result of doing mindfulness the result of doing
concentration the result of doing mindfulness and concentration practice together which is one of the benefits of
mindfulness of breathing that they they stay with the breath all the time
there is a concentration factor that builds as but we're also practicing mindfulness of
staying aware of what's going on where the the mindfulness is present when those become both become
sufficiently strong the mindfulness and concentration then we start having insights we start
seeing observing in ways that we don't usually observe in everyday life you start
observing in deeper and deeper way or with greater clarity into the moment-to-moment experience and
that's when insights begin and the insights of the insight meditation practice
are not i i like to think of them insights with capital i there's lots of insights with a small
eye all can be very significant but the difference in my vocabulary and why i'm
using them now is the small eye insights are the ones that are a big aha
moments where we see something about ourselves that unique to ourselves
so for example we understand something about the conditions that led us to become who we are today or we
see clearly our particular beliefs that were operating under maybe they were deluded or not really true so ah and
then we put that down or we see something about ourselves that we never saw before and
and say wow that explains why i behave this way because oh there's that anxiety or fear or
something memory that i have that keeps kind of filtering my experience so there's all kinds of very important
personal insights that help us become freer and freer
but the insight with a capital i the insight of that inside meditation is really
focusing focusing on are seeing things which are universal uni uh that are common
denominators of all experiences and so it's it's true whether it's a
personal experience it's only unique to oneself and it's true for uh you know
for everybody and so sometimes they're called universal characteristics of all experience and um
and and uh and in the buddha called these perceptions so they're they're qualities
or aspects of how we perceive all things that we we take in or character characterize
the perceptions that of all things so there's something universal so they're transpersonal maybe
or or um you know they're more encompassing than anything we see personally whereas the personal insights
are important going deeper down into the common denominator of all experiences
the common characteristics of all experiences it puts us down at the deeper foundation
from which we build the cathedrals of
the citadels of our conceptual world the the world of self and self in the world
of others and we we kind of build this world and philosophy and beliefs and feelings and
all that based on uh things that are have this foundation
of these common characteristics common per ways of perceiving and
and the primary one that is the buddha emphasizes is a
quality of all experiences
is something called anicha in pali it's a-n-i-c-c-a
it's commonly translated into english as impermanence and and
probably not the best translation and i'll get to that in a few moments but i want to emphasize that what we're
focusing on here is what can be called experience
in philosophical terms buddhism is epistemological or vipassana this
practice we're doing is epistemological i think what that means is that it's a nature of how we ex
how we know something or the nature of the experience we have itself and so as opposed to ontological which
is uh having some understanding or belief or interpretation about the nature of reality so
many people want to assume or believe that insight practice brings us a deep
insight into the nature of reality it can be very reassuring to feel like
we have that kind of deep powerful understanding the buddha seemed very
reluctant to make any ontological statements about the nature of reality he was not an early physicist who
understood the physics you know in my nuclear physics of what was really going on he was a scientist he was a scientist he
was a scientist of perception of how the nature of perception nature
of how we experience things which is uh an interface of what
it's a meeting place of what's happening in the world out there and and our perceptions how
the mind takes it in and so it's a nature of experience now this can be a little bit
feel complicated a little bit discouraging because we want to have certainty about the world out there
but everything we know about the world happens through the filter through the the
avenue of our experience how we experience something
it's kind of like if there's an hourglass the one wide end end of the wire when you're
broad cup of the hourglass is the expanded world outside of us
and the other end of it uh expanded kind of cone of the hourglass is the
huge inner world that we have but the the the neck of the hourglass
is what we see through our eyes what we hear through our ears smell
through our nose taste through our tongue feel through our body and then what is known uh
about what's happening in the mind the knowing the experience of knowing or recognizing what's happening in the
mind one way or the other everything that we know has gone through
those six kind of hourglasses of perception and then with that the inner world can
make it complicated and we can invent new ideas and stories and connections and all kinds of things so
but we don't we don't remember or don't recognize that it all had its genesis in that realm of
hearing seeing so for example language and concepts and words for things had to we had to have
some you know that had to come through hearing someone speak those words or
reading those words and so the buddha made tremendous emphasis on
this kind of in a sense this narrow
neck of the hourglass where everything is coming in and rather than seeing it as an
hourglass we see it as the foundation upon which everything is built inside
and sometimes outside as well and and so what is it that
is the common characteristic of experience and it's anitcha that all experiences
are coming and going they're changing they're they appear and they disappear
the details the fingerprints of experience appear and disappear moment by moment
and sometimes it's because what's out there is passing by really quickly and
or not so quickly but clearly passes by we have here i think some of you can hear that
sometimes the train whistles going by they come and they go they come and they go and uh
and so it's pretty easy to notice that those come and go but um but also the way as i said
yesterday the way that we pay bring attention to something
we very rarely fixate the attention in some solid hard way because if we do that it tends to be
strainful it's stress stressful but that's very gently the the
mind the awareness is kind of moving around and taking in different details and it's fascinating to do this with
physical pain where pain can you know can feel from a distance like it's just solid and
we're really kind of connected
we're connected to it and uh and then we will um
the um
but if we really pay careful attention this observing way we see the experience of pain is a
kaleidoscope of all kinds of sensations going on arising and passing and this arising and
passing is repetitive so some things come and they go and they return they come and
they go and and so that can give lend a sense of continuity and even a
sense of permanence like they're not stopping they're continuously there
but as we drop deeper and deeper into this deep subtleness of meditation and able to observe
intimately and closely everything without without the mind making the leap making
the constructing the idea of continuity then we just see the arising and passing
a phenomena and the repetitive nature of it the inconstant nature of it
and um and so the word anicha a n i c
c a comes from the the root nicha which means it can mean something
like constant continuous and also sometimes may be permanent and the a
is a negative prefix so not constant not continuous not permanent
when we translate this as impermanent as done often in english it suggests that very many people hear
that is meaning it's not going to last it's going to come to an end and it's kind of you know to be
constantly reminded everything's going to come to an end it maybe can be even depressing or and
also it kind of misses the boat because we have to then we just expect
and wait some things take a while to end and while it can be wise to be
understanding and recognize that things will end there's a lot of wisdom to that
it's not the full story or it's not really what the buddha is pointing to as an insight the core insight of
insight meditation is to see the inconstancy of experience
moment by moment how it arises and disappears or rises and disappears
so anisha as as one of the core insights is probably better translated
as inconstancy to the inconstant arising of passing a phenomenon
that there might be continuous a continuous constant inconsistency constant continuous things
being inconstant like a river is constant is continually flowing but it's
also never the same there's being inconstant about it as well and so that's enough for now
so um so we're entering into this deep world of insight
now and and hopefully you'll begin appreciating the observation of
inconstancy thank you