okay so good morning or afternoon or
evening it's nice to be here with all of you for this week
and why don't we go ahead and get started with the meditation and then i'll i'll
say a bit more afterwards about what we'll be doing together this week
so please find a posture that is upright and also
someone where you can have some ease in your body
and just feel yourself settling in and letting go of whatever it was you
were doing before arriving just having the sense
internally that you have arrived
if it's comfortable to do so you can gently close your eyes
otherwise just have a soft gaze downward
and just bring the attention internally
perhaps feeling first into the place where you're sitting so
your seat against the cushion or the chair
or the bench or the bed maybe you're even doing standing
meditation
so feeling the support under you and just allowing
your body to find some balance sometimes i even
rock back and forth slightly or forward and back just to find that center point
where the body can be supported with minimal effort
from the muscles
and when that balance point is found it may feel like the body naturally
straightens or extends upward
almost as if there were a little string from the top of the head
it just feels
natural and then we can invite some ease
throughout the body especially places where we tend to be
habitually tightened so softening the muscles of the face
like in the forehead and around the eyes the jaw
softening the eyes and the eye sockets
releasing all the little muscles around the scalp
down through the throat
and into the shoulders letting the shoulders just naturally settle
out maybe thinking of the shoulder blades sliding down the back
and letting the arms soften down through the hands
then down into the torso softening the chest area the upper back
maybe sensing the ribcage front the back the sides
and down into the belly
inviting some softness just whatever is willing to release
down through the hips
sinking a little deeper into the support
groin muscles the thigh muscles
all the way down through the calves and the ankle joints and the feet
it can be helpful at the beginning of a meditation just to briefly scan through the body
and all we do is invite some ease
there are parts of the body that are still tense or that we couldn't connect with
particularly that's fine
the body is fine as it is
and then as the body gets a bit more still even just a little bit
often it's easier to connect with the sensations of breathing
so we're just allowing that simple
connection of the body breathing in and breathing out
just naturally not changing anything about how that happens to be right now
just bringing that into the field of mindfulness
we may begin to notice that breathing is a whole body process
there's of course the we may know anatomically where the lungs
are but as you tune into the breathing in a
meditative way it may be possible to
sense the way the breath affects other parts of the body
the shoulders rise and fall slightly
the belly down underneath the lungs the belly is moving
maybe there's even a slight feeling in the arms and the legs or the head
we don't need to push for that but i'm just inviting
an opening up of our understanding of the breath
so we can connect in with very simple sensations
not even really the idea of breathing in breathing out
but sensations more like tingling
or pressure heat
the brushing of the clothing against the skin as the body shifts
even very subtle sensations that would be hard to put a word onto
so i call these elemental sensations
they occur throughout the body
i would invite in this meditation to use these simple
breath or full body sensations as the object
if it works for you you can see them as an observer you can
imagine that you are watching them with some interest maybe the way a
child watches waves on the beach
that's fine it's also possible to
enter into the sensations directly
as if the mindfulness is getting very close to these sensations
that feels supportive or interesting
so i'm just connecting with this
world of body sensations for a little while and if the mind gets
distracted which of course it will it's no problem just
immediately open again to these simple
sensations either as an observer
or entering into them directly
okay
when working with the body it can be helpful
from time to time to just quickly scan through again
and soften any places that may have become tense
sometimes the eyes get tense because we
are trying to look at these sensations
we might just not notice that we're building up some tension in the shoulders or
the belly and that's fine when we just turn
attention briefly back to the ease and the body and we can
identify those tight spots and soften them and
on with our direct connection to this world of the body
if there are sensations that feel particularly
strong or
dominating the awareness it's fine to
focus on something else more often this observer stance of
being separate from that but watching it is a good way to just maintain the
balance of the mind
so being sensitive to how you're relating to this particular
meditation
taking care to just stay in something simple
you may notice also that there is change
the body is continually blowing changing
even sensations that seem relatively constant
have changed since the beginning of the sit for example
so being aware also that there is inconstancy and
shifting and changing dynamism in the body
and continuing to rest with that
so as we continue on [Music] just bringing in one more
element is to consider the knowing
the knowing quality that is allowing you to be mindful at this moment
there are different aspects or kinds of knowing
and what we've emphasized in this sit
is this kind of bodily knowing
it may seem like a subtle difference but consider that the bodily kind of knowing
is it's different from thought isn't it
it's different from emotion
it's different from knowledge that other people have told you
about the knowing of these direct body sensations is one form of what's called
direct knowing direct knowledge
very clear and distinct
and completely unique to you
always available
so just being aware of that direct knowing quality
of body sensations
so there's a lot of information in the body
a lot of signals coming in
and they're always in the present moment what is known through the body is always
in the present moment whereas the mind can go out to other
things that's in other times and places
so maybe just as we're going about our days this week
we can consider that having this intimate
direct connection to what's going on in our body can actually help us
in our daily life it may not be as subtle as we have
during meditation but we can
use it as a way to know that we're being present that we're in the present moment
we may be able to notice if we have times of tension or times of ease
the body can help us to stay mindful and to
stay in a wholesome state of mind so when we're with others we're
more likely to remember our arnetta or our patients
so this is actually very practical
helpful information to have sometimes i just feel my feet on the
floor or what's going on in my belly and that's
you know that's enough i maybe that's all i can bring into my attention while i'm also with someone
else but it's very helpful so i am quite
experimenting with that
may it be that we can stay with the present moment so that we can be present for
others as well as ourselves
may what we've learned is in this meditation be of service to all beings
[Music]
okay so
many of you know me i'm kim allen and
i saw one comment asking about gil because apparently he had to cancel
the meditation yesterday um just to let you know he is fine
that was just a complication where he wasn't able to be there but everything is okay
so i'll be here with you this week
so as you likely know there are a lot of lists in buddhism and
i think they're quite helpful but i was recently reminded of some
items from a different set of lists in the 12 days of christmas
and the last set goes like this five gold rings four calling birds three
french hens two turtle doves and a partridge in a pear tree it's an interesting list
and it turns out that buddhism has some unusual lists also so i was inspired to consider some of
the less well-known lists in the buddhist teachings and that is going to be the
theme for this week so today we'll have a list of five tomorrow a list of four
and so on down to one item on friday and we'll see that there's some deep
dharma in these somewhat less common teachings and i also chose them to apply to this
year end time when some of us are in the midst of family and maybe others of us might be having a
more reflective or contemplative time or maybe maybe some of us are doing both
that's good so i hope you'll indulge me in this exploration this week
so today's list of five might be called
five ways of ascertaining truth and then also how we can uh preserve
that truth while we're talking so
somewhat like what i alluded to in the meditation how is it that you know something
how is it that you know something and i i mean that is a sort of a question to explore
so consider you know how do you know your dog's name or how to drive a car or what to say to
your child's teacher the first time you meet them or what about
more spiritual truths how do you know the deeper movements of the heart or the more universal
qualities of a of a human life so without attempting in a whole
epistemological catalog we can observe i think that it's that we
have many different modes of knowing we have facts that are memorized and stored in
our brains we have emotional understanding we have cultural norms
we have logical deductions [Music] i used to work
long ago at a lab where i was running complex machines and i would if i hadn't
used one for a while i would go to use it and sometimes i would remember how to use it because my hand would move
toward a certain knob i had some kind of a body memory about how to use that
machine and then you know kinds of knowing where we can't quite pin down what it is we
tend to just call intuition so we have a lot of different ways of knowing
why is this interesting or important well how we know does matter because
some types of knowing are more reliable than others right so the buddha in one of the sutas
um 95 he talks about how we know
spiritual or religious truth and he comments and the reason he's giving this teaching is that he comments
that very often people will make assertions about this kind of truth that amount to saying
only this is true everything else is wrong you know so we have a
an idea where we're asserting a certain thing as fact and that everything else must be wrong
but then he he gives a little more nuance to how it is that we know things and he points out five common ways of
knowing that are not actually fully reliable
so he i'll list the five so he says um faith or
yeah faith or trust in something um the second one is liking something
gill translates it as it is pleasing so we like something it sounds good
makes you know feels feels right um and then the third one is oral or cultural tradition
something that our culture has just always known is true
the fourth one is logical reasoning something where we've deduced it for
ourselves by thinking about it and the fifth one is called reflective acceptance of a view so that means we've
heard from somebody else we've thought it through and decided that that's a correct assessment so those are the
five um the buddha says that each one of these the way the suta says is it is that they
can turn out in two different ways so that that means that we could have faith in
something complete faith in it but it's actually false or
we could not have faith in something but it is actually true
and the same for all the others and we could reason something out very carefully but we'd come to the wrong
conclusion or we could not accept the logic of something but it
is actually correct so it's interesting to consider that yes
it's true i can't really say that any one of these five is absolutely 100
uh reliable all the time now of course we use all five of these
throughout the day and and we might notice also that uh the
first two are in the emotional realm so having faith in something or
finding it pleasing kind of in the affective realm uh the middle one is in the cultural
realm what what society tells us and then the last two the reasoning or
the reflective acceptance are logical cognitive
so then one might ask also what's left so he's he's eliminated
large swaths of our uh you know realm of experience as not totally reliable ways
of knowing so the buddha doesn't say in this suta to just throw out anything any of these
ways of knowing he just says to be clearly aware that they're not definitive
and what what is reliable according to this teaching is to know something through direct experience
that's kind of remember he's talking mostly about religious or spiritual truth so instead of asserting things or
deducing them or just having blind faith in them we should actually experience things through our
through our practice [Music] so it's pretty interesting list right
so then um he goes on after this to
describe a path for discovering spiritual truth that actually makes use
of several of these unreliable methods along the way so that gives at least some assurance that it's okay to be
using them he suggests that we should have some kind of faith in in a teacher or in the teachings in order to be able
to walk the path and he also says that we should use reflective acceptance of what we've
learned you know when you hear teachings like like this one that i'm giving don't just believe what i say you know
please think about it does that make sense have i seen that in my life um yeah and so he
considers that those are actually good and reliable well
helpful ways to approach the path and so with care we can use these ways of
knowing skillfully in order to get to the place where we can directly know things through our own experience
like what i pointed to in the meditation where we have bodily knowledge is quite direct
so then um he focuses then on how we can know how we can talk about
what it is that we know and this is now practical for our holiday time if we're discussing
ideas and facts and views and opinions with relatives for example
so the buddha talks in the suta about preserving or safeguarding the truth by
clearly stating how it is that we know something so we have to notice then how we know it
um and so then when we make declarative statements we can say from what basis
we're speaking so for example if you thought some think through logically you can say i've
reasoned my way through this and i think such and such or because of xyz it follows that such
and such so you're being clear about the fact that this is coming from logic
or if you have faith in something you can say my faith is that such and such is true
or i trust that such and such is true so this provides some honesty and clarity
around the statements that we're putting out into the world and so what we don't want to slip into
is only this is true everything else is wrong you know that doesn't usually land very well for other people
so we have to be careful about making declarative statements you might find that this
helps in conversations with others in order not to get into so many disputes
so maybe i'll just give an example of um kind of the difference between these
typical ways of knowing and the more reliable experiential one
i was trying to kind of discern if i had one experience where i could
show several of them and i thought about one time that i went on a ropes course
i don't know if you've been on one of those there are various ropes and suspended planks and nets and
other things meaning uh sort of gaps between platforms and they're all about
50 feet up up over the ground right so you're moving on ropes and nets and
logs and other things that have been constructed high up and you wear a harness
so that you know you can't actually fall but it's it's as if you're
climbing around on these things and of course they're constructed so that they swing and sway and they're
generally unstable so um i can say that you know the intellectual knowledge that i couldn't
fall wasn't very useful to me you know i had the harness on and so i you know
suspended securely by a cable but it didn't really help my body's visceral reaction was wow i'm
50 feet off the ground i'm i'm afraid of moving on these unstable things but i
sort of you know picked my way across a number of these gaps walked along some
of the ropes and so forth and you know i used mindfulness to feel
okay fear you know i'm not sure about doing this and that
was okay i gained some measure of confidence because i actually learned that i could negotiate my way through
this and i could be with the fear and that was fine um but so that you know the the
emotional realm and the logical realm were operating but still not completely
not completely assuring my my being but what reduced the fear most
effectively was when i actually fell off and and then i was caught by the harness
and so i knew actually i had a direct experience that i actually wouldn't fall
and after that i became much more confident um walking around on the the nets and swaying logs and so forth
and interestingly i didn't fall again after that because i somehow had enough confidence
that i could actually do it physically so it's interesting experience so maybe
you've had something similar you know where you've worried about it thought about it been mindful of the fear but
what actually worked was to to do it and have the direct understanding
and the buddha's point toward that in more subtle ways in this suta where we um
you know we we might talk logically about what we know about the teachings or we might have an emotional feeling
about them but in the end when we have a direct understanding in our own body and our own being and it becomes kind of
incorporated into how we are somebody once said about visiting their
relatives they they don't like it when i'm a buddhist but they love it when i'm a
buddha so maybe this will help in some way
so then also just to exercise the you know how we talk about it i'm teaching you from this
why am i making these statements from coming from this teaching it's because of a combination of
experiential understanding that i know from my years of practice that these
teachings do point toward what is true and also out of faith or confidence that the things that i haven't verified yet
for myself are likely also to be true so
speaking from a combination of experience and faith and also the fact that i've logically thought through them
so i'm preserving or safe regarding the truth by telling you about how i'm
relating to the suta and then passing it on to you so i hope that that gives you
some sense this list of five ways of knowing i'll repeat them
faith finding something pleasing
cultural tradition logical reasoning and reflective acceptance of a view
i hope you might consider how it is that you use these five to negotiate your life how it is that you
know things that you are confident in doing things and also what things you know directly from your own experience
and maybe finding ways to talk about those with other people such that we aren't
making declarative statements that aren't backed up by how it is that we know them
so hopefully that was interesting um and tomorrow we'll be on to a list of four
and so forth down through the week so wishing you very well and see you again
tomorrow if you can come in
thank you