so
warm greetings to our meditation time together
and i want to start with a principle of meditation that
is not well appreciated i think or taught and that is that
in some of the challenges we have for meditation the art is rather than fighting the
challenge is uh transforming the challenge into something that helps us to be
present and to enter into the meditation space and um the um
so for example if there's a lot of thinking going on and you really can't stop the thinking
and just like you know really obsessing about something or other and think you know and you try to come back
but just it's hard or you keep spinning out then rather than struggling with your
thinking you might reorient your thinking
to think about meditation think about what's actually happening in the present moment
and thinking about meditation is not the same as meditation exactly
but it's certainly better than the alternative because you're pointing the thinking
into the present to what's actually happening what you're dedicated towards and so a variation of this has to do
with the imagination that um if we're thinking about the past or the future
it's partly an act of imagination we're thinking thoughts of fantasy it's
imagination especially when there's visualizations going on we're visualizing things
and to some degree imagination is at play with a lot of the ways in which we drift off in thought and that's one of
the reasons why it can be so compelling and so it's also possible then to use
imagination to be present to point us back into the present moment
and and ideally for the purposes of meditation this would be a very simple act of
meditation of imagination imaginations which support the settling
and concentrating and uh becoming more attentive to the present moment but to harness the
power of imagination to be present is um something that the
buddha never taught explicitly but in his teachings it's kind of
implicit and i'll talk about that later so i'll offer you some simple
i'll offer you some simple acts of imagination that maybe can help you gather yourself
together and become focused and present here in the moment and so if you hear as you hear these
little exercises and imagination keep in mind this is this is the purpose of them to help us really be
here in the present moment so to begin to
take some care for your meditation posture
and the attention to the posture is the
beginning of mindfulness meditation being mindful of
the posture making mindful adjustments
and as you exhale mindfully relaxing and softening parts of your body
close your eyes and to begin the process of
being present in the place you're at here in this body this time
slowly maybe tenderly take a few long slow deep breaths
breathing in and deeply and maybe lovingly exhale long exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and then one more time one more round of going through your body
and on the exhale relaxing the parts of your body that are
easy to relax
and as you relax relax into the pull of gravity
and then sitting here quietly
meditating quietly in your meditation place evoke your imagination
that with your eyes closed imagine yourself sitting meditating where you're
meditating imagine yourself in this space
imagine yourself on your spot imagine you're seeing yourself in your
meditation posture
in a sense you're using your imagination to imagine what is actually happening here
but it is an act of imagination a little bit removed from the
direct experience imagining
your spine your back
have a picture in your mind perhaps of what's happening with your hands
your legs
if you have an easy ability to visualize maybe visualize yourself sitting here
quietly peacefully just here
and then imagine that side by side with you is a person
who really inspires you in in the dharma
maybe the buddha sits next to you or kuan yin available
or some teacher that greatly inspires you
and they're meditating next to you and what would it be like to have this
inspiring meditator side by side with you sharing with you
in the meditation in your space
and then imagine that see in sitting here in your own
experience you're sharing a lot of experiences with this companion of yours
both of you feel the temperature of the room
both of you who hear the same sounds around you
in this inspiring person next to you imagine how this person feels the
temperature hears the sounds
and like you this person is breathing
and while there might be differences between your breath and theirs there's also a lot of
similarities they also experience their rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
and maybe imagine how this person would sit peacefully and
feel that rhythm and the sensations of breathing
and like you this person feels their body maybe there are some
differences but a lot of similarities to be in this body to feel it and sense
it and imagining how this person meditates
and holds and relates to their body from the inside out maybe with peacefulness or calmness or
ease
and as you're sitting with yourself here can you feel or intuit
within yourself some degree of calmness or peace
embodied calmness settledness
which receives your breathing the experience of breathing
imagine what it'd be like for you to be peaceful maybe you're not peaceful
particularly but imagine what it'd be like
maybe remembering a time that you were peaceful or contented
settled at ease
remembering what it was like at that time physically the actual experience from
the point of view of your body what was it like in your body to be peaceful and settled
at ease
and then to let go of the imagination of your companion
of some other time and place where you felt peaceful even imagination of yourself sitting
here but allow there to linger some of the
qualities of peace or calmness
and gently tenderly you know allow the experience of breathing
to be received in whatever calmness or peacefulness that there is
receiving the experience of inhale
allowing for exhaling
letting there be an ever so short pause before you inhale
pause where the mind can get quiet
in which then you can just receive the inhale when it wants to begin
an ever so short pause at the before the exhale
so that you can feel more fully how good it is to allow
for the release the exhale
imagining that all around you and all within you is lots and lots of space
lots of room and breathing
has lots of breathing room room with space which is peaceful
expansive easeful
and breathing in and breathing out
allowing and releasing
is intimate with all the space and room peace
that's also present here
imagining the mind what it would be like if it were there
was a refreshing silence in the mind
a silence which was maybe that maybe spread through all the space
that's here
silence that makes your thinking
not so important
silence that allows the thinking to relax and dissolve
diffused into the silence
breathing in and breathing out in space and silence
having a very teeny pause at the end of the out breath
the end of the in-breath
relaxed pause can be a little protection
from being caught up in your thoughts or your imagination
little reminder stay here with the direct experience of breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
take a few moments to imagine some of the people that you you'll encounter today or
communicate with today or maybe think about today
and imagine what it would be like if you could encounter them
being peaceful having a simple good will
without any animosity or anxiety
or any strong desire that expectation for anything
imagine what it'd be like to meet them in a peaceful goodwill
that is not so strong to
disturb them but just nice for you
imagining that possibility and then wishing aspiring
that whatever benefit and goodness that's come from this meditation
then it might be translated in your body in your heart and the mind
to walking through the world in a way that brings benefit to others whether seen
or unseen whether you know knowingly or unknowingly
may it be that the merit the benefits the goodness of our meditation together
spreads into the world with kind actions supportive actions
generous activity for the welfare and happiness of all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be
free
you
so my friends that the
kind of subject for this week is the fifth and sixth step of mindfulness
of breathing which is to experience joy and happiness in meditation
and it's certainly not easy to experience that and you can't just do it just because the
instructions say so you should do so but uh to explore this territory of joy
and happiness meditative well-being and some of the conditions that support it some of the
things that bring it about can be very helpful and so that's a topic for today this
week and so um so there's uh the precursor
often often the suttas for joy and happiness is gladness and uh the word is pamoja
p-a-m-o-j-j-a and pamoja comes from the
the kind of the root word we don't never know if the root or the etymology is that important
for the people who spoke it but it's certainly a fun game to play
and uh so the paw is the prefix can mean either outward or upward and uh
the moja comes from the word for face mukka and so
the the uh the idea of you know something of the
face uplifting face a face that's rising up or maybe a mouth sometimes the mouth is
closely associated with this word from for face and it's the uplifting of the lifting of
the mouth i think of it as uh up lifting up the corners of the mouth to make a smile
so is that which and lit makes a smile or a kind of maybe a beatific kind of
out upward gazing at what inspires us and in fact and for the buddha the
the uh he encouraged people when there's difficulties in meditation
to think about or imagine an inspiring something that's inspiring or
but inspiring not in a way that's activating because the word for inspiring also has the meaning for
confidence or peacefulness or kind of brightness so that which brings brightness or
confidence or or peacefulness kind of a peaceful confident brightness
maybe so we'd say in simply in english kind of inspired
and and and to be inspired when we sit down to meditate involves
activating the imagination and and we find that imagination
is regularly referenced in the teachings of the buddha in relationship to meditation
and this was certainly very different than how i was introduced to both vipassana practice and zen practice
where the explicit and the implicit instructions was not to not to be involved in
thinking so much and now certainly not to be involved in imagination this was the meditation practice about
just being present for things as they directly are unmediated by concepts unmediated by the
imagination just the experience in and of itself and
the direct sensations direct contact with things and and and that's definitely true
but it becomes it becomes true as the meditation gets more and more centered in the present moment
and but to get ourselves centered in the present moment and centered in the present moment with some
joy some well-being imagination can be
harnessed can be utilized for that purpose and and so uh the buddha i encourage
people to think of an inspiring topic and some of the things that he um talked about that were inspiring
was to think about that the buddha himself think about someone who you're really
inspired by their practice by their being how they are in their life in a way that kind of
is inspiring enough to really want to sit here and be here and kind of kind of puts to rest other
thoughts and concerns that keep you distracted and um or
to uh the encouragement is to be inspired by your own virtue
and of course that requires us to be virtuous and but the word virtue
has really means virtuous conduct so you don't have to be inspired by what
you're feeling on the inside the buddha's teachings are be inspired
by how you act in the world and if you're acting in a world without causing harm if you're not you haven't
stolen any money from the bank lately or you know it killed any of your neighbors late recently
or uh you know done all kinds of things then that's a source of being inspired
and it doesn't mean you have to be a hundred percent virtuous but uh to recognize the way that we
are living a virtuous life even if it's just for today
not to be burdened by the past so much and but rather be inspired by what is good and
beneficial and so to be inspired by one's own virtue maybe that's a hard thing for many
people to imagine to experience but it's certainly one of the teachings of the buddha and one of the purposes of being
virtuous is to create the inner context to be inspired and gladdened and
uplifted so we're more so it's easier to stay present
and the other thing that the buddha makes explicit about what's inspiring
is his mudita
the appreciative joy to think about the things in the world that bring you a
wholesome nourishing kind of joy like so to share in the joy of others who are doing wonderful things
and and be inspired by that and so this idea of being inspired
uh by things is um uh is not meant to take us away from the
present moment or to be a spiritual bypass it is not meant for us to dwell there
just kind of keep thinking about thinking about and fantasizing about it but rather to do it just enough that
it really orient us to the present moment it brings this uplifting kind of
feelings and goodness that we're capable of then feeling and then riding those feelings into the
present moment it's sometimes easier to be present if there's some modicum of well-being that's here as well and
it's not meant to be again an overriding or a bypass of the challenges we have or the
suffering we have but it is helping to create a context where it's
easier to be with the challenges to work through them and meditate with them breathe with them
and so the principle here that i think that supports this idea of using the imagination
for something that's inspiring is that is that to to to do it when the
alternative is worse human beings spend a lot of
time in their imagination imagine the future what's going to happen the terrible things are going to happen
imagining the past remembering you know some percentage of our memory
is uh fantasy we it's well known that we don't necessarily remember accurately
what happened in the past we're telling ourselves a story we spin it a certain way we spin it around the things that really
have a charge for us whether it's good or bad and we kind of kind of stretching
certain parts of the story the memory to fill the space of memory
in a way that not completely accurate and uh and so sometimes that can be very
depressing and agitating uh certain fantasies can be not helpful at all and uh so if the if
we're doing that anyway in the imagination then uh it's possible to use the imagination
don't fight the imagination then and try which might not be working but harness the imagination to help you
be here in the present moment to gather together and
and then when you're here enough then you can let go of the imagination
and then sit here and be present so you know i've in the course of this teachings i've offered some imagination
imaginary kind of scenarios images to help for example
as i love this image for breathing of the of the waves of the ocean washing up on
the sandy shore and kind of i have this image of myself of of the especially when the waves once they're
washed ashore they're washing up across the sand and making the sand wet for a while
and then the receding and then as it recedes it's the sand is wet but then the the water
kind of that's the surface kind of gets pulled into the underneath the sand and so you get a
whole different texture feeling of receding and absorbing
and this image of this of then of like the i use it different ways in meditation but
imagining the breathing experience of breathing are the waves and my body is the sand
or the experience of breathing the sensations that come and go the
cycles of upswelling and and receding
with the exhale is washing across the shore the sand of awareness and it kind of
that image kind of keeps me there and involved i've known some people who have
one person in particular who used um the image of a large bird maybe a
i don't know some large wonderful majestic bird flying in the sky and the inhales and
the exhales were the where they uh the flapping of the wings the slow long just flapping in
the wings of the bird and uh and that kind of kept her engaged and involved and
flying along and um so to use the imagination
to help us be connected and then uh to use it to help us be inspired
uh and and to know as i've said how not to overuse it how to use it so
it's onwardly leading in the direction i talked about yesterday that we're going towards
uh doing less and less activity to quiet or still or states of mind and to more
from coarser to the more refined more active to the more peaceful and so we use these things to support
that process knowing at some point we have to let go of it not relying on it too much not
overdoing it not depending on it not using it as a antidote so we don't have to face our
difficulties or work through them but rather as a way so that we can be present
in an effective way so so to
particularly i want to end now with the idea of inspiration with that which brings a brightness and
uplift a delight brings confidence brings trust brings a willingness to
engage in practice and this idea of an inspiring things
and i would encourage you for the next 24 hours to consider what inspires you
and stay close to thinking about it and visiting it being with it somehow be
connected to it or maybe there's many things maybe you can talk to others
friends or anybody who you strangers about you have this assignment to talk
about what inspires you and and you'd like to share a little bit and hear from them what inspires them and
and maybe in ways that are spiritual in nature or has to do with some of the fundamentals
of what gives her life purpose or value and in doing so i hope that you have
some wonderful conversations and and some wonderful um time
thinking time with yourself what is it that inspires you and maybe
that you can stay close to that so thank you very much and we'll continue
a little bit this uh the way the buddha uses imagination for meditation tomorrow thank you