hello everyone and
happy to be here to uh share this meditation time with you
and i have been thinking this morning how meditation is um maybe it's helpful to think of
meditation as a way of both stepping into the middle
of our lives right smack in the middle as it is and also stepping out of our lives to take a very
different perspective for what's happening and one way to bring those two together is the idea
that we sit in the middle of our lives to
unstick ourselves from our lives to so we don't we don't get caught
caught or stuck in whatever is happening in our lives and meditation is an
unsticking process de-sticking ourselves and this thinking doesn't mean
that we reject anything but it does mean that we're simply not stuck we're not glued to it
and that process of de-sticking helps if we think of meditation as not
being business as usual not going along with however it is that we
usually are the attitude the approach the focus the orientation
and to be willing to have be open to a different way of being
so sitting in meditation
and taking a posture assuming a posture
that as if you're sitting in the middle of your life
everything is included
and if it's comfortable for you to gently close your eyes
and then to relax a little bit initially maybe taking a
few long deep breaths and really letting go and relaxing on the exhale
so we're letting go of some of the preoccupations and concerns and tensions we have
so we can better sit in the middle of it all we can feel ourselves really here in this body
in this heart this mind without the centrifugal force outwards
into thoughts and concerns
and then letting your breathing be normal again and continue for a minute or so
a process of physically relaxing
especially on the exhale softening the face
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
and softening the belly
and perhaps to do things a little different than usual
feel your way into your heart your mind your body especially maybe your body
to a place that you associate with well-being
a place you associate with contentment and ease
maybe joy and happiness
maybe kind of a well-being that feels deeply satisfying quiet contented
and even if you don't feel that now where in your body do you most associate
with those feelings
and if you breathe with that place breathe through it
maybe even feeling some of the contentment or ease or well-being
even if it's just hints of it
and if you even if you don't feel it to be have the breathing arise
out of the place that you associate with well-being
or have the breathing move through it or accompany it
so as you breathe in the middle of your life sit here in the middle of your life as
it is you're breathing
maybe arises out of a place of well-being
your breathing somehow breathes through it or with it
perhaps it's a quiet place of tenderness of contentment
of a simple ease or peacefulness
well-being
and with that as a gentle reference point for breathing
the rhythm of breathing breathing in and breathing out
can help you unstick help you sit in the middle of your life
and let go of the stickiness the grasping the holding on gravitational pull
and the breathing with well-being breathing with contentment
as a support that helps the heart the mind to dissolve
the stickiness of preoccupations concerns
resentments and fears desires and expectations
here content to breathe in the middle of it all
making your home be the breathing breathing from the place of
contentment and well-being in the midst
whatever discontent you might feel
not being not setting the two up in opposition
but breathing sitting at the middle of it
and every time you return to your breathing every time you ride your breath
it's like a massage
for dissolving the stickiness of life the holding the clinging the resistance
softening opening relaxing further here
and now
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
are you in some ways have you in some ways unstuck yourself through the meditation
have you loosened up a little bit the momentum of the mind the clinging
no wanting the spinning have you dissolved or softened the glue
the stickiness keeping you wedded to preoccupations and
concerns
and what is it like what would it be like to be unstuck no
stickiness and to bring into your heart now
the people of your life those you know those you don't know personally
neighbors and store clerks and people in the streets
and just the whole range of people that you might encounter or think about
and what would be like to just take bring these people to mind
at the end of the meditation and to continue to unstick
de-stick yourself
to loosen the ties the entanglements just to breathe with others breathe with
the people the beings around you
nothing to do and nothing to you need to say for these few minutes
just to breathe with these people
and in such a simple way can you now maybe
have thoughts of goodwill thoughts of well-wishing for others
from this from your inner sense of care and
kindness compassion
to have thoughts about how wonderful it would be if others could be happy and safe
peaceful and free
and the less sticky we are in those relationship
the more we're going to support the happiness and well-being and peacefulness
of others and the more sticky we are
the more complicated these relationships
become in whatever way that you have
more unstuck may the benefit of that be
shared with others so you engage and talk and communicate
with others with less stickiness
less entanglement more contentment more ease
more breathing with others
so that you don't so easily get stuck again
may all beings be happy and free
[Music]
so a couple of announcements before i begin the talk first is that um
i'll have a community meeting on zoom tomorrow morning after the 7 a.m sitting in dharma talks it'll be
at 7 45 or so and it's partly to commemorate the one
year anniversary of of uh starting the seven a.m sittings
and it's also for many of us marx commemorates also the one-year anniversary of
sheltering in place where our life has changed dramatically
a year ago and different places of course went into shelter at different times but at least here in california
to a year ago it's been a big year and i almost was going to give a talk today
about grief and maybe i'll do that in a couple of weeks but
i wasn't quite ready for that and and then next week i won't be here
next week a wonderful teacher amana johnson is going to speak she is
she graduated a year and a half ago from the teacher training for at spirit rock so she's a local
dharma teacher and um and uh very happy to have her come
and and spend sunday morning with you
so imagine
that you're in a beautiful place in nature that maybe someplace you've been
and found inspiring and maybe far away from buildings and roads and a lot of people
and it's just an expanse of a natural setting beautiful comfortable
safe inspiring place to be and maybe it's so inspiring maybe you
visit regularly to appreciate and feel the freedom of just roaming around and
the trees and the skies and the hills and the rivers and the lakes
whatever it might be just a vast space that's wonderful to be in
and um so after visiting many times you think this is special and you want to
kind of mark the specialness of it some some nice way and creative way and so uh
you bring a um with you into the wilderness a glass door with a frame
it's a bit of an effort to bring it in there and you install that door right in the middle of
the wilderness this glass door swings open very nicely at its frame
and there it is this door middle of the wilderness some people might think it's an art
installation and but it's your door and uh
kind of marks that this space this place is so special for you it's kind of like marking it as being special
and and that uh you know symbolically it's a door into a different landscape and different place and but
now when you go visit in this big vast open space there in the middle there's a door
and and you put happen to put it right in the middle of a trail so that when you go in the trail you
have to open the door and step through and so the door is there and
you like this door and sometimes it gets locked by mistake and you have to go home and get the key to unlock it and
sometimes it gets rusty being in the weather and you have to oil it so that it can open and close and
some being a glass door sometimes it gets dirty and you have to clean it and you care for this door and after a
while you think of this door as your door and um and you want to protect your door
and so you because the door represents this openness to
into this wilderness and this freedom that's there and so you decide that the thing to do is to put a fence around the door to
really protect it so the moose doesn't come along and knock it down and and break the glass so you put the fence
around it and you come out there and you feel my door is protected and after a while
the um you start feeling you look around say well this incl incl this place where i enclosed the
feds it's not really big enough for me it's that you know really you know i'd like more space to be able to come in
and and just kind of be spacious and open and and so you expand the fence make it
bigger and bigger and after a while you don't want to really see the fence you make the fence
really big and goes around the hills and outside of you and so you go inside you
know just you and the door and the doors kind of maybe sometimes
gets branches fall on it and break it and you fix it and
all kinds of things happen to the door and eventually you would wonder about
the door and then you remove the door
and then there's vast open space again then you remove the fence and it's just like it was before it's
still beautiful beautiful location inspiring a peaceful wonder wonder wonderful to roam around in
and then you think what was i doing with the door what was i doing with a fence
so this may be a little silly story is introduction to the topic today
which is the buddha's teachings on selfishness
the earliest teachings of the buddha as best we know he did not teach anything about not-self
this you know famous teachings of of the buddha
it wasn't his focus but rather he was focused on
talking about their problems and their suffering around being selfish and how a wise person let go selfishness
and as he developed his teaching he described three different ways of being
selfish or self-focused or self-preoccupied in some way and one
was through craving one was through conceit and the other is through
metaphysical opinions and views beliefs that we hold on to
so the craving uh idea of selfishness he associates with possessiveness
possessing things these are mine this is mine the conceit
is associated with the idea of i am um
you know that i am something that i am this i am that so it's a row identities that we take on
and hold on to and um and the third is um um
um this is myself that this is a true self now i know what
the self is and this is what the self is what my true self is my essence is
and in pali these little expressions appear a lot in the suttas it's
me and eso
eso and it's kind of close to what we say in
english of me myself and mine he kind of says it in reverse this is
mine this i am and this is myself
this is the self so um and the reason to
notice this and pay attention to it it's the domain the the qualities of selfishness of being
caught up in excessive excessive preoccupation with oneself a strong attachment clinging
self-centeredness that can happen and and this movement towards selfing and
getting holding on to self is uh is uh limits our freedom
it uh does something which is not really necessary to cling to the self that is a
comparable to this idea if you will if you allow me of putting this door right in
the middle of the wilderness the wilderness was beautiful and wonderful by itself and it was a wonderful place to visit
and peaceful and relaxing and it was so much more less complicated to be there when
you didn't have to take care of the door and protect the door and repair the door and build fences
around the door and um so the same thing the natural
kind of a natural state of being that um can be quite open and peaceful
and inspiring to experience for oneself uh that um it doesn't require
placing uh something in the middle this is mine this is who i am this is myself
that movement is kind of an extra movement that that places something in the natural
setting which more often than not does not need it especially if what we're doing is
clinging and holding on to to these things so conventionally that we might say
things are mine and um and you know it's a lot we say
it's so you know things are mine things are legally mined there's ownership there's things which
we allow each other to have but but the selfishness around that
is when we cling to mind we hold on to it for dear life like it has to be this way
and this movement towards possessiveness and claiming things as mine but this belongs to me is a recipe for
suffering the uh one famous kind of
origin story in buddhism that the beginning of the one of the beginnings of the downturn of
the of society was private property and then people started uh
hoarding in their private property and stealing and things got out of hand in
this mythic story so the idea of it's mine and holding
holding it tight not realizing that possession possessions of all kinds anything we can
say is mine is fragile it's temporary is uh there's no guarantee that it's
going to stay around that i read recently about a
meteorite or asteroid that kind of landed in the driveway of someone in i think in scotland i think it was
or somewhere and um the rare rare mineral that
came in this asteroid and um but there's no you know guarantee that lighting's not going to strike us
or strike our things like our car or bicycle and asteroid's not going to fall and something we
own and then we don't own it anymore it's gone you know it just becomes a squash piece of
burnt stuff and uh the idea that it is me myself and that
it's mine has disappeared um the um you know i've
recently i broke a bowl ceramic bowl that my son had made
and beautiful bowl and i broke it in the kitchen and it was ours belonged to our family but
as soon as i was broken i didn't really think about think of it anymore as mine or i didn't think of it as belong to my
family i rather unceremoniously just kind of put it in the trash and
off it went and um
the the um
so mine as i love the story that's suzuki roshi i've told him many times of
suzuki roshi is um there's a photograph of him actually
saying this taken just as he was saying it so it's kind of more poignant he was photographing him
holding up his glasses like this and he says these are not my glasses
but you know about my old tired eyes so you let me use them so that's a very different relationship
to my glasses and so
certainly it's convenient to have things that we use and know they're there and they're reliably going to be there next
day when we find them and so we're seeing their mind but you might reflect a little bit
about how much extra attachment there might be possesses in this fear fear of safety
fear of not being safe attachment to to status attachment to all kinds of
things that come we say something is mine it gets more kind of interesting when you look at
that we take as mine of traits of our personality or
qualities of our physique and our body and ways that we are in the world
opinions my opinions and and if we hold on to those and cling
to those and think they're unchanging we'll suffer so there's suffering of taking things as
mine and for the buddha it's very explicit even taking this body
as mine is a recipe for more suffering and and so you know isn't it natural and
normal take this body as mine i think it's natural normal conventionally to take it as mine my
body but uh but to do so with an open hand not clinging to it just
lightly provisionally but as soon as you say my body that i you know them then i have to be
in charge of it and i can't change and it has to always stay the same
maybe the second form of selfishness is conceit and this
is the idea of over evaluating oneself it has to do
with how we value ourselves in relationship to other people and the common way in english the word
conceit refers to thinking that we're somehow have a higher value than others
we are better than others in some ways and and so it's a form of comparative
thinking and as soon as we get involved in comparative thinking with other people this is really a amazing source of
suffering uh comparative thinking um you know things are constantly shifting in the
social world and between us and our abilities and other people's abilities and so
um you know if we expect to always have a higher evaluation other people will meet someone else who's going to be
better if you know i'm pretty good at basketball for someone who you know compared to
the six-year-old next door but not compared to most adult men at this
point and so do i hold on to that do i have a conceit around i'm a good basketball
player better than everyone else uh you know i'll probably just suffer
around that kind of idea and so this comparative thinking is
an unnecessary glass door in the wilderness in the natural setting
it uh it mars the situation it limits it it becomes something then that we need
to protect we put fences around it we want more and more fences and control for it
and now it actually is a form of of limiting ourselves rather than
freeing ourselves there's a wonderful cartoon from calvin and hobbes
where calvin is um in the snow building a fort and it can make him feel safe in this
fort and he's building up the wall so it just goes above his head and and he's making it really tight and
compact and and he surrounds himself with all the snow to make a good safe fort for himself but it's uh
basically he's made a round little cone around himself and once it's all finished he's trapped
inside and he says help help because he can't get out anymore
so so this idea of conceit is a can become a trap we've kind of
protected too much and we kind of can't breathe even me myself and mine
the conceit of being better than and in the ancient buddhist language
buddhist teachings a word which was closely related to
mano mana the word for conceit is the word mada and the
means to be intoxicated totally confused and wrapped up in things and sometimes
it's translated as pride but the english word pride maybe has a variety of different
meanings these days and sometimes they're positive but since the original meaning of in
talks of this word mada is pride is intoxication
one translation of ancient abhidhamma text is to list all kinds of things people
are intoxicated intoxicated by so in intoxicated by
their birth by their caste basically intoxicated by their clan
intoxicated by their health by youth intoxicated with life
itself intoxicated with gain and acquisitions intoxicated with honor
with being respected with fame with having followers with wealth
with skin color with learning with intelligence with not being despised accomplishments
popularity with being ethical with meditation attainments and the list
goes on and on but each of these is seen as a kind of pride they kind of conceit
and conceit that we get intoxicated by or get caught by and it's so much easier
to be in life in the world without getting caught by these comparative
thinking with others one form of comparative thinking that in the buddhist idea of
conceit is also the idea of thinking that we're less than other people that we have less value than others in
some way and that's also a conceit because it's also an attachment to an idea of self
attachment to a comparative way of thinking and and the solution is not to figure
out a better way to compare and even the idea of comparing ourselves as equals to others
and buddhism is considered to be partly are you still playing the comparison game but rather freedom is found by not
comparing by allowing ourselves and others to be just as they are
and much more and so removing the door and the fences in the middle of the wilderness and letting that
natural setting be itself the third kind of conceit
is the conceit of views of philosophical opinions beliefs about
what is the true self the essential self and the buddha said there's he he knew
of his time no belief in an essential self a true self
that doesn't bring suffering and i don't haven't done the analysis myself to see if that's really the case
but it's certainly a provocative idea that um and certainly we can say that anytime we
crave or cling to something we will suffer and so if we're clinging and claiming
craving clinging or craving to a view an idea my true self is my soul my true self is
my is my you know inner goodness my true self is my is my
um you know whatever it might be my consciousness
um is that going to give birth to suffering does it bring suffering when we're not
in touch with that true self when it's not evident and present does it just remain
an idea that we have and so the idea needs to be reinforced needs to be reasserted in order to keep
staying in touch with it because maybe you can't be really feel and felt
and experienced or what about deep meditation whenever we feel or experience as
the essence of who we are falls away then some people get really frightened
by this um because the deep deep peace of meditation where things just let go we
let go of all clinging it's remarkable how wonderful that
that piece is i want remarkable how liberating it can be and how ordinary reference points for
anything we have as we experience as myself dissolve and then if but some people get
really frightened because that's who they think they are i am this and i have to be this
so so selfishness
and the antidote to selfishness in buddhism it certainly
is to see the suffering of it and sometimes it's only by seeing how painful it is and how
fragile it is and how much energy goes into being selfish that people begin to loosen up and let
go but the other the other antidote
is happiness is uh to experience deep abiding sense of
happiness well-being contentment that doesn't require being selfish and so to
that's one of the functions of meditation practice is not only to become calm not only be mindful but to acquire a
sense of deeper contentment satisfaction ease
to be able to breathe easily freely without any clinging to selfishness any kind of
idea of me myself and mine at least to give ourselves a radical break from it
so we don't come into meditation and hold on to these ideas of me myself and mine
often the the source the fuel for a lot of our preoccupied thinking is
me myself and mine and to let go of that so we can experience something really wonderful
and to value this wonderful beautiful natural setting that we have
the natural capacity for ease and freedom and peace and to learn how to wander freely openly
in our own hearts and our own minds and our own life without the glass door in the middle of
it all without the fences all around it so it's unobstructed by it all
where we don't need to advertise ourselves or promote ourselves or should explain to people who we are and
and assert ourselves on people as a form of clinging
and a sense of well-being and one of the benefits of discovering
such kind of well-being and peace and ease and letting go of all this is that
then it also might be easier to
to stand up for oneself when society around you
defines you when society around you says you can't be that how you how you are
you have to be different or you are in this kind of way if we don't get
if we have our own stability inside and peace inside that we know and we're not wrapped up
around our identity issues and then in the way that this clinging is involves clinging
then it can be quite powerful to stand up for ourselves and say no to people not not go along
with what people are how people are defining us how other people's me myself and mine
you yourself and and yours is really oppressive for many people
and and so the idea of really looking deeply at selfishness
and how it works with me myself and mine is also a gift so that we don't
project you yourself and yours onto others in ways that makes
makes them oppressed imagine if we can live in a world where
we don't put any fences around anyone we don't put any glass doors that block
anyone's path where we allow the
the people to be how they are we allow the natural world to unfold in a
beautiful way without the limitations
and the problems of our clinging especially the clinging to selfishness
may it be that this meditation practice shows us the limitations
shows us the suffering of our selfishness so that we become
more open more free more generous more kind more forgiving
and more in a certain kind of way natural the
kind of naturalness is there when there's no clinging so i hope that gives you something to
think about and to reflect on and and hopefully you're forgiving of
yourself if you happen to have some conceit or some me myself and mine
but you might want to take a deeper look at this this this topic and make it a study for the week and
and it's this is uh this list that i read from the ancient texts
about intoxicated intoxicated when i saw this list i was kind of delighted
that they being intoxicated preoccupied caught up in things like health and youth and
gain honor being respected fame having followers our learning
accomplishments popularity all kinds of things it's been going on for thousands of
years this is kind of what humans tend to do especially when they come together
so if you have if you're involved in some of it as well you have a lot of company and you have
the company of the buddha of freedom you have the company of yourself
perhaps in meditation where you're beginning to loosen up and unstick yourselves from all forms of
selfishness may you be may you let go of selfishness
and find out how to be really happy in this life thank you