good morning or for some of you might
be afternoon or evening but wherever you are and whatever time
it is even if it's sometime in the future you're listening to this recorded i'm sending
warm wishes your way it's such a wonderful thing to be able
to practice together to practice with others for me it is
it's very meaningful so a really warm welcome a warm welcome
wherever you are
so before we formally
settle in or maybe it's part of the settling in process
for our meditation it can be really helpful to set our intention
why are we practicing so not in a heavy-handed way not in a
way that feels oppressive but in a manner that feels it's supportive to just do a
brief reflection why are we doing this meditation thing anyway
might be something i'm engaging in this practice so that i might discover more freedom
so that i might discover more ease
so that i might understand myself better so that i might feel better
so that i might have a develop cultivate a a refuge a respite
get re-energized in some way
whatever the reason might be it can be helpful to periodically
just reflect on that put it into context of why we do this practice
and to be sure sometimes it feels too clunky and
awkward to do this reflection and what feels most natural and useful is just to
sit and there might be times in which doing this reflection can be a real support
can help bring us to the cushion and when we're on the cushion to help stay
there so to speak
i am engaging in this practice because i
wish to have access to more and more freedom
and then as we begin to get settled
just taking a moment to see how the body
feels having a general sense of
how you are right now
tuning in to the experiences of this moment
having the intention to bring awareness to this moment
i'm sure as many of you know the body can be a tremendous support
for feeling settled tuning in to this moment
rather than the memories of the past or fantasies of the future
so as you settle in you might notice any sensations that are present
in the body
maybe feeling the pressure of the chair the cushion the bench
the bed the couch feeling the pressure of whatever it is that you're sitting on
against the body or if you're lying down whatever you're
lying on laying on lying on
and getting a sense of how the body feels
in general maybe a little bit in particular with the pressure
against the body and more in general
sometimes we bring a lot of effort and expectation
to what we're doing whether it's in our daily life or in our
meditation practice
and this kind of effort is often motivated by wanting and striving
can we soften any of those kind of movements
wanting striving
and practice in a way that feels relaxed
a certain amount of ease
that feels sustainable
and of course this doesn't mean cavalier or half-hearted
but with ease and purpose
you might notice the relative ease of simply feeling the pressure points in
the body feeling the chair cushion against the body
simply inclining the mind
actually takes very little effort
feeling whatever the hands are touching
inclining the mind that direction
we might think of awareness
as having a receptive quality it's more about receiving
the experiences rather than going out and getting them
receiving the experiences of breathing
feeling the sensations associated with the movement of the
chest or the belly
or the sensations coming in through the
nose
in this way we might notice
what we sometimes call effortless effort
there's a certain effortlessness and receiving sensations
but maybe there's a little bit of effort in setting the intention
set in that direction
the intention to be aware of the sensations of breathing
or perhaps the sensations in the body more generally
without grabbing onto them
without clinging or pushing away or pulling in
so
and it's natural that our minds will wander
we just very simply gently begin again
no need to make it a problem
wish it were different chastise ourselves
we just begin again
this is part of the art of practice
it's just having enough intention
a little bit of effort but not too much
to be going a particular direction
without a strong sense that i should be there by now
to find the middle way
between aimlessness and drivenness
between being disconnected
and being tightly bound
the middle way between no effort whatsoever
and extreme effort
and to recognize and appreciate
that middle way can be different every moment
letting go of the idea that there's one perfect middle way
let me just have to find it and then we can relax
we're always finding the middle way
allowing the experiences to show
themselves
rather than pouncing on them
and part of our reflection of why we practice
can be not only to support our own lives
finding more freedom finding more ease but the lives of others
so that we can be a factor an element of good in this
world that we can help others find more ease
more freedom
so that we practice for the benefit of all beings
everywhere [Music]
so
so again a really warm welcome
to everybody wherever you might be whomever you might be
so today i'd like to talk a little bit about um this
uh there's a brief asuta maybe not talk so much about the sutta
itself but something in there that the buddha says and he says there are two powers
two powers in some ways that can't even feels powerful to even talk about two powers
some of you might know that there's this list of the five powers that is similar to the not similar it's
almost pretty much exactly the same as the five faculties and that's not what i'm talking about
and this idea of two powers and we might think of well what is meant by this word power
and we could consider it's the ability to do something or to act in a particular way
is to have a certain amount of power you might might also think that or the same word
strength is there and this word impali bala
that's getting translated as powersome some translators use this word strength
two strengths two powers we might also think that uh power or
strength is the ability to influence influence ourselves make ourselves get
to make ourselves do things or influence others
and we might also think of powers like you know something is powerful when it really touches us when
it moves us we often talk about powerful movies books
dharma talks when it affects some change or some experience in somebody so
tough power is also to maybe touch somebody whether it's ourselves or
others and to be sure power can also have
negative uses and connotations
the oppression of people and justice these terrible things and that's not
what i'm talking about the buddha here is talking about power maybe maybe strength is a better word
and i was reflecting like what about this word power why why would the buddha talk about
power and i thought well maybe it's because it's to counteract this idea of
powerlessness sometimes we begin a meditation practice
we begin any spiritual practice because we have this feeling of powerlessness in a way
that is um takes the wind out of our sails so to speak or maybe we
feel stuck and like we can't find our way
we can't make ourselves quote unquote do what we know should be done or
something like that so maybe it's an antidote or a counteract something about this feeling
of powerlessness maybe also this word power is kind of
associated with this the idea the experience of being empowered
to feel to experience to have the capacity
to affect change to do something to have some agency
so the buddha talked about these two powers and what are they so one
is the power of reflection and the second is the power of
cultivation and sometimes we might think like oh really
i was hoping it'd be something a little bit more inspiring than reflection and cultivation but but we might
use these two powers these two strengths something like the power of reflection
we might consider it something like choosing a trail on a map
a hiking trail that we want to go on and that's the reflection where do i
want to go and then while we're on that trail like
while we're hiking like to reflect am i on the trail am i on the right trail
my for some reason my map reading skills are not the best this is something i have a
little difficulty with so i'm often wondering am i on the right trail
so just this reflection and then cultivation might be the actual going on
the trail the actual walking it a little bit of effort required there
so the strengths of reflection and cultivation and where do i want to go and am i going
there it's a reflection and the cultivation is just going
so i'll just say a few words about the second one cultivation first because i think that this is
something that we're familiar with and there's probably been countless dharma talks about
cultivation especially in this tradition there's a real emphasis on this sense of
development and to be sure that sutas are filled with the buddha talking about to develop
and cultivate develop and cultivate our ethical
actions our integrity how we show up in the world
we can never be too ethical like that doesn't even exist
so to reflect on is this the right thing to do
what is the right thing to do and to do the right thing
so to cultivate to cultivate our sensitivity to ethics and then to do the ethical
thing the buddha also talked about the to cultivate
having a steady mind that's why we have a meditation practice is to help the
mind be steady or settled so that we might see things more clearly
so that we might understand things more clearly
and also there's to cultivate a warm heart
the brahmavihara practice so that we can increase our capacity
with difficulties if we have some brahmaviharas some love
some compassion joy happiness when others are happy it's an
equanimity some steadiness when things aren't going the way that we expected or
even though we might love somebody dearly we of course can't force them to do what we think well is
the most helpful so to have some equanimity
and more specifically the buddha also talked about cultivating the seven factors of awakening
i'm not going to talk about these this morning but many of you know mindfulness
investigation energy joy tranquility concentration and
wisdom
so in some ways this the power of cultivation
for our practice is not that different than how it is for maybe an agricultural
simile or agricultural metaphor that we don't
make plants grow they grow themselves
but we create the conditions helping them with water
with sun fertilizer or a good quality soil
so in the same way cultivation is about creating the conditions and
recognizing that we don't make these things happen things we just put the conditions in
place as best we can as best we can
so that's one of the powers of cultivation just to remind you of probably what
you've heard in many different dharma talks now i'd like to talk a little bit more about this idea of
the power of reflection because sometimes it's easy to be dismissive
of this capacity that humans have to reflect
so what does it mean to reflect maybe one way to think about it is to put our
experience whatever it is that we're having into a larger context
and importantly to do it in a warm-hearted way
so not only are we putting our experience in a larger context seeing the bigger picture
but we're not doing that in such a way that it creates the conditions for us to beat
ourselves up we don't want to activate this inner critic or to have this
oppressive feeling like i should be this way that should be that way or whatever it
might be because this reflection loses its power
we could think if it's coupled with this heavy oppressive sense of how things
should be but instead can we just have this gentle
inquiry this reflection does what i'm doing right now support my
life does it support my practice is it
going in the direction is it that i want my life and my practice to
go not in a heavy-handed and not in a
clunky awkward way but just to periodically just
check in some practices have this idea of check the attitude
so maybe in the same way we can kind of like check in the our attitude often is
um has an effect that we don't see if we don't notice it so
of course if we want to eat better
more vegetables whatever it might be
could just periodically reflect while we're eating opening up that bag of cookies
does this is this ref support my life this direction i want to go
in the same way if our practice with ethics our practice with studying
the mind or cultivation of some warm-heartedness just the way that i'm
speaking with others does the way that i'm approaching my meditation practice
does this support my life does it support my practice
and so one way we can do this is to reflect on our reason for practicing
why do we have a meditation practice why do we work on our ethical practice the way we
show up in the world interact with others
when we know why we're doing something it can be a tremendous support it helps us put it in that bigger context and
helps us to know which direction we're going what is the purpose
what do you want to experience what do you want to have more of in your
life or what would you like to understand better or what would you like to penetrate more
deeply or what would you like to open yourself up to or
maybe what would you like to touch more intimately in your experiences
again to have this reflection in a way that is in a relaxed easy manner and not in a
way that is a disguised inner critic
but just have some clarity of the direction we're going
and this idea of periodically reflecting of the purpose of why we're doing this
there's a story that's told by john c maxwell about a person who sees some bricklayers
who are working perhaps you've heard this story and this person goes up to the first
brick layer and says what are you doing and the person responds i'm laying
bricks okay simple enough and then the person goes up to the
second brick layer and asks what are you doing and the second brick layer says i'm putting
up a wall okay so a little bit bigger context there's a purpose for what the bricklayer is doing
but then the person goes up to the third bricklayer and asks what are you doing and the
third bricklayer says i'm building a cathedral
even a bigger context than a way that feels inspiring or so we can say that maybe the first
bricklayer and it might be completely appropriate at times to just notice i'm just putting
one brick here and not have to go the bigger context
but just to have this here but there also could be a way in which that feels
could be a little bit half-hearted i'm just laying bricks you know without a sense of purpose or a
sense of a direction in which they're going it could feel like
it's never-ending and it doesn't matter the quality or how i do it
to the second bricklayer that's talking about building a wall maybe they have a sense of com they want
to have a sense of completion if there's a succinct or defined um
objective that they have they can say okay well i'm gonna stay with laying bricks until
this wall is built but then the third brick layer this idea
of building a cathedral there's a way in which they the bricklayer might put
their whole heart into the practice
and that's they feel inspired that they're part of this big beautiful thing that will be of
service to others service to themselves can help others
connect to the divine perhaps or
so to reflect on occasion what is the purpose of what we're doing and to recognize that how we answer it
that it might affect the attitude in which we're approaching what we're doing
so not only setting the direction in terms of where we're going but also
influencing the attitude and then this attitude
i'm using this word might whether we're doing it wholeheartedly or maybe we could say
whether we're doing it cavalierly or casually or whether we're just bringing ourselves
to it and feel inspired and open to the possibilities like this third brick layer
so maybe i'll just say that i know this there's a story of somebody
who wanted to lose weight a significant amount of weight a lot of weight and this person did
and then was sharing with others how he had done it and you know some of
his secrets secrets quote unquote and when he was asked uh why he had
done it in the first place he tells the story of that he wanted to
um fit into a star wars costume like a really serious star wars costume you know one
that's like might have actually been used on the star wars set he wanted to be thin enough so that he
can fit into one of those uh costumes of a character now i don't remember the
character's name and the reason why he wanted to fit into one of those
character costumes is because his nephew a young child had cancer
and was being treated for cancer and he wanted to show up in this star wars
uniform for the birthday party that was coming up for this little boy that had cancer
somehow that feels inspiring and we can imagine that it's so much easier to do something that is difficult
if we have a purpose and if we're imagining that it could really benefit
somebody so this is something that we might use as a support for our own meditation
practice because let's be honest sometimes it's not easy to get to the
cushion or if we do get to the cushion the mind and the body are
feeling restless and it's not so easy to stay on the cushion
but we can see we're having a reflection of why we're doing this
and to have a the why be something that allows us to have an attitude of open-heartedness
wholeheartedness can be really powerful it can be a power
to support us in our practice
but this idea of a reflection not only can help support
why we're doing something but it also can help us with uh discover
if we the way that we're practicing is going to help us go the direction we
wish to go recognizing that the goal
and the means are so interrelated
do we have the goal to have more freedom then is the way that we're practicing a
way that brings freedom into our practice a certain amount of ease or or is there
a constricted sense of i have to do this i should do this
if we if the goal quote-unquote the direction we're
heading the purpose is to understand things more clearly
understand ourselves then are we meeting each moment with a
sense of curiosity and openness oh what's this
or do we have a sense of like just noting and going off to go into the next thing because we have
to get to understanding and i'm not going to bother with the sensations
on the my body with the cushion or the sound or whatever it is
so to reflect in the way in which we are practicing and to recognize that the means and the
goal are intimately tied together and so it's the manner in which we're
practicing supportive so this brings this this that maybe this idea of the art of
practice is then coupling these two [Music] notions that is
maybe discovering the middle way between having some clarity about why we are practicing the
direction we're going and allowing the practice to unfold
finding the middle way between having this idea we wanted to go here but not
forcing it to go there not making it not white knuckling our way
through not using a sledgehammer with our practice but instead creating the conditions in
which the practice can unfold so this is really the art of practice is
maybe it's not going the direction that we think we would like it to go that we have set
as our purpose but at the same time we could see oh
there's some understanding here there's some freedom here there's some ease here
and the way it's unfolding i didn't think it was going to unfold this way it wasn't my preference for it to unfold this way
but i can bring the direction i want to go into this moment
this really is the art of practice of having an intention having a direction
and allowing it to unfold
and finding this middle way is something that we do over and over again in practice
so we can even reflect on our relationship between this idea of doing i have to make things go a
particular way and being quote unquote just allowing things to be
you could just do a general reflection which do we feel more comfortable with
doing making things happen or being just allowing things and to recognize that
practice requires both a certain amount of doing a certain amount of being
and are we privileging one over the other or are we not even recognizing
that there's times for both
so part of our reflection can be is this balance between doing and being
i'm using doing and being as these kind of generic words about the amount of effort that we're
doing that's being applied or maybe even the amount of self
that's uh having a sense of agency of one who is making things happen
so that could be another reflection is this balance and our what are our ideas of
how practice works quote unquote like what uh propels or moves
uh practice forward towards greater and greater ease greater greater free freedom and
understanding and to reflect in our conceptions our assumptions
about the amount of effort that might be needed
and then of course to reflect on the potential and the actual consequences
of our actions all of our actions reflection can be enormously powerful if
we are reflecting is this going to cause harm
for myself for others for both might this be harmful
of course we don't know everything but we can just do a quick reflection
is this is there a way in which this might unfold and that it's harmful
i think many of us know i've heard this story where the buddha is teaching his son rahula to reflect
before during and after every action of body speech and mind
is this for harm will it harm myself will it harm others or it will it harm
both myself and others and of course if it's going to cause harm we don't do it
and of course there'll be times on which we are mistaken we didn't think it was going to cause
harm and then it ends up causing harm and then we make amends as best we can
and then move forward so this power of reflection of where
we're going this attitude that we have towards going
there including our relationship between being and doing this can be such a fruitful
place to reflect and to recognize whether we have a preference for one or the other but
rather than having to choose like oh i should all have to make things happen or no it's just about allowing
can we recognize that part of navigating part of balancing part of finding the
middle way is to have a little bit of being a
little bit of doing at the right time in the right dose and then of course to reflect
on the consequences of any action we might have so when we think about it this way you
could see why the buddha talked about the power of reflection can you imagine
if there was no reflection none of those considerations it was just
mindlessly so to speak doing anything and everything willy-nilly allowing ourselves to be
pushed around by our preferences or pushed around by what others are saying
or what we're experiencing at that moment
so instead the power of reflection and the power of cultivation these two
powers that allow our lives and our practice to unfold in a way that
not only don't harm ourselves or harm others but might benefit ourselves and benefit others
so that we might be a force of good in this lord in this life and in this
world that needs it we need all the good so
thank you very much