hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour
hi so we have a couple of minutes before we
formally get started and let's say
some hellos and i'll start by saying hi i'm nikki i'm in mountain view
california on seated territory of the ohlone tribe
and let's see the weather it's still light outside the days are getting longer here in
california today was mild in the 60s today who's here who wants to say hi
you can unmute yourself if you like and say hello
hello bill from dallas comfy temperature glad you're not freezing bill
[Laughter] mark christine says peek-a-boo from
sydney mild in sydney 21 degrees celsius ah nice mild summer sweet
and hi neil from new hampshire how's how's the weather in new hampshire
nice it's warming up no no no snow no
only on your cam only your background it's the only snow right now i know i'm
sure that's great
and romina says hello on youtube and and from
from also from texas and and kevin says hello from middlebury california
and er says namaste hello folks on youtube yay nice to have you with us anybody
else wants to say hi before we get started it's nice to hear your voices
i hear claire's key clicks but i don't hear her there is her laugh
here i am who types claire from new york city hello
oh it's a fluffy it's a fluffy sweet guest oh yeah four legged oh
that's great so sweet here's my bed
great so let's get started let's formally get
started so thank you neil for
sharing information about the google groups happy hour google groups where folks can share information
information with each other and and contact the community
offline and also information about nick about diana and myself teaching a
retreat a four-day retreat in april is is there
uh in the chat also so so i changed the settings always at this
time so that uh uh the unmuting ability will go away for
the duration of guided meditation chats will just come to host only and i start the recording now for
the sake of audio dharma here we go okay
great so a warm welcome wherever you are in the world whatever time zone
you're in so nice to come together and practice
together how sweet it is i've been looking forward to coming together and practicing together
today so um so for the theme of today's practice i have to say
i've been really relishing the the mudita practice really getting to
the habit of it and usually in happy hour you know before we started this regular
theme of going through the one brahmavihara like metta and then we did compassion
and then beta we would you know do different things different night but it's the consistency is nice to explore
one uh practice for a period of time and kind of explore it
for the heart to get um some footing in it if there are challenges which is fine so
so if you've had challenges with with vicarious joy empathic and pathetic
joy um it's and you think oh we're gonna do more pathetic joy
actually let it be yay we're gonna do a more pathetic job because you get to explore it you really get to explore
what can work for you what is challenging so instead of just doing
it for you know one session and then moving on to the next it's like when you're traveling if
you're you know there are these tours where each day you know you're in a different city so
you kind of get a little bit of it i don't know real wind experience so but it's kind of nice to explore
walk the walk the city the walls really get a sense of it so this is just like that so so
um so we'll explore the practice of vicarious joy one more time and and a show of hands
would be helpful who is new either to happier or to or to this practice of vicarious joy and
you can click on reactions and then raise your hand which is below on the bottom of
the various things so i get a sense of how many people are new to this practice of vicarious joy mudita
i'm not seeing anyone raise their hand so seems like you've all showed up in the
past few days and practiced before okay great so
it's helpful to know so um one more thing i want to say before we
start about this practice is um
yeah given that you've all practiced with this before
as none of you raised your hand we've been doing it now for about a week a couple of weeks
um yeah while you're doing it also be a scientist of your own mind
see what are the ways that you can really connect with happiness of others happiness of yourself
and and in what ways um
yeah what what are the challenges and try to be gentle with yourself and working with those challenges and
maybe what aspects bring up jealousy if any or envy and just be both be a practitioner and also
a scientist observer of what's happening and kevin on youtube says uh they're new
great and so is jonathan great so yeah you we can all also
uh attend to this practice as if that's the other aspect of it even
though many of you have done this before attend to it with a beginner's mind
as suzuki roshi said in beginner's mind there are lots of possibilities it's
open to possibilities it's open to exploring open to being surprised
open to learning whereas the expert mind oh i've done
this practice before i know what's going to happen oh it's closed to the possibilities it's
close to the surprises they're always surprises so
i'm inviting all of us including myself to have a beginner's mind
today with the practice of vicarious joy and at the end i'll ask you did you
notice something did you observe anything that surprised you about your practice tonight so
so this will be yeah so let's bring a sense of curiosity
newness beginner's mind to our practice today just one more thing to say about the
practice of vicarious joy it's about cultivating joy
it's about turning our hearts to joy happiness for our own happiness and happiness for
the happiness of others and it's a happy making practice
especially supporting us to have more joy in our hearts and in our life not as
a way to avoid and turn away from challenges but as a way to make more space
to be more available to have more resilience to think about it that way okay so enough
introduction let's do it so i'd like to invite us all
i'd like to invite us all to get into our meditation posture
landing landing in your bodies
landing arriving in this moment
ah relaxing softening
intentionally putting aside
all thoughts all preoccupations that have come before
intentionally bowing to them saying thank you
setting them aside ever so gently and intending to give yourself give your
heart fully give your heart fully to this practice in this moment
ah landing with your whole body
resting in this moment
inviting your feet your legs
to let go of any holding and tightness
your sit bones
your lower abdomen your groin area ah to release to relax from the inside
your hands to drop on your lap
your neck and shoulders to release
drop
your facial muscles
your jaw
to soften let go of any tension release
let your forehead be smooth
let the inner muscles of your face behind your eyes
behind your cheeks behind your chin behind your ears
fight all the muscles internal in your face
ah to let go
resting the attention resting in the belly
noticing each in breath and out breathe
as you let go of any tension in the body
letting the tension drop
with each out breath relaxing softening even more
and if your thoughts are rising
with each outbreak letting them go [Music] releasing your hand as if they're helium
balloons letting them float away gently coming back to the breath
in the belly just settle in the right
attending paying attention gently
to the breath in the abdomen with a beginner's mind as if this
is a new breath it is a new breath you don't you haven't
met this one see see how this in-breath this out
breath is new is a little different
made it fresh right here in the moment
no preconceptions
beginner's mind fresh
the thoughts are arising in this moment ask yourself
whatever i'm thinking is it necessary to think about this right now
now the sense of humor about it kind of laugh at yourself it's okay let it go
no judgment ah see how this works so much better
than chastising yourself
the smile coming back to the breath and the body to settle
and let's start
our sympathic and pathetic pathetic joy practice by bringing
to mind someone for whom your care
flows easily you care for them
maybe when you think of them the smile shows up there's just a sense of ease safety with this
this being and that you naturally feel happy when they're happy you feel
happy for them for their good fortune bringing up bringing to mind this
this deer this deer being either human or pet or a child
and feeling [Music] their presence and bringing to mind
something they're happy about something that's a good fortune in their life
a blessing something they cherish they take
delighted and know that not every aspect of their life needs to be happy
they could have plenty of challenges but this aspect
they're happy about they're grateful for and you feel happy for them
[Music] you celebrate it with them
start where it's easy where it's really easy
not a complicated relationship
and seeing this being happy delighting grateful for this blessing in their life
for this goodness and you as a person who cares about them
loves them sharing sharing their happiness
i'm happy for your good fortune i'm happy for your happiness
dear one
you can say this phrase silently
or this other phrase may your happiness
goodness good fortune may it continue
made increase may never end
whatever version of these works for you or simply silently connecting
with their gladness and feeling happy for them as if it were
your own as if you were the one
cherishing taking delight
in this goodness
let yourself have beginner's mind see how you can connect
how you can be your inner dharma coach to connect with gladness
happiness for another person's happiness
i feel happy for them what do you need to how do you need to
modify if needed this practice a different being a different blessing
really conjuring up their sense their happiness
your love and care for them their love and care for you
to connect with happiness for them see for yourself
explore
i'm happy for your happiness dear one dear friend
your being
my heart is gladdened but you
are happy
i take delight in your good fortune and your blessing [Music] as if it were my own
and staying with staying with this person this being this blessing
continue mr mind wanders bring their image their felt sense more
vividly up for yourself to connect
and now just as this dear
being has blessings in their life they're happy about they celebrate turning the attention to
yourself and noticing something good some
blessing in your life yes there may be plenty of challenges
difficulties yes and in this moment choosing choosing
intending yes we can intend to turn your mind to something
that's good in your life right now
that you feel grateful for that you feel happy about
let yourself relish
really savor this goodness in your life
your heart delighting your heart shining in gladness beaming
with happiness for this blessing
not the time to play small let your heart sing
with joy for your own happiness
for this blessing this goodness
and you're welcome to let in other blessings if they want to come into your heart to
be celebrated stay with each for a few breaths
savor them long enough to have honored them
before moving on to the next
letting your heart expand enjoy gladness for your own gladness
and notice something perhaps surprising or new about the way
this practice is unfolding for you in this moment
or something some way you need to relate to it for it to expand
and connect
perhaps notice also how gladness for your own good fortune
naturally turns to a sense of gratitude even if we don't call it that
that's what it becomes naturally
now bringing to mind
again your dear being [Music] inviting them back
and this being who also cares about you
to see them happy for your your happiness see them delight
celebrate reflecting your joy
happiness for your good fortune
let yourself receive this reflected joy your joy reflected in someone else
who cares about you
notice if there are aspects of this reflection back and forth that are nuanced
and new and interesting to land into
perhaps see them looking at you with happy eyes
celebrating what you're glad about
even if it's something small or subtle saying their gladness for you
may not be as big as a celebration but just simple quietness
and now as if joining their gladness for your
gladness joining your own gladness for you all
for your very own happiness both of you happy for your happiness
for this goodness
as if both of you are dancing with joy for this goodness in your heart
in your life
and see how you need to modify what blessing you need to consider
for this practice to really connect for you
and for the last moments considering that everyone practicing with you in this
zoom room on youtube the future
the past on an audio dharma etc all practitioners
all beings they have something they're grateful for we all have challenges yes
we do and we all have blessings
we feel happy and grateful for them feeling happy celebrating goodness in
the world yours others whoever
whether you know them or not you've met them or not
may there be goodness happiness gladness in the world
may all the happiness and gladness may it continue made increase may never end
celebrating all joys and blessings
as if they were your own no boundaries
celebrating goodness happiness in the world experienced by anyone
may all beings be happy may all beings
be free
thank you thank you all for your practice
so wondering what you noticed with your beginner's mind and your practice tonight
i noticed so much joy expanses as if my heart was beaming with
bright light in this practice and also the reflection which we hadn't done
the past few nights this reflection of one's own gladness in somebody else reflected that
adds more nuance more delight more celebration really celebratory mirroring reflecting and
mirroring that was just lovely so that's what i noticed and would love
to hear what you notice you can raise your hand you can type it in chat
if you type directly to me i won't say your name it'll be private if you type to everyone
i'll say it out loud and of course you are invited to raise your head and share what you noticed
what worked what was challenging it's all good so
take it away
yes please carlo and shivani is it carla or giovanni
great carla please i noticed today um there was still some uh some
tightness that i hadn't had in the last couple days it was more euphoric the last couple days but i noticed i
could still go from tightness to feeling joy and
happiness and go back and it would come back and then go back so it was like it didn't
it didn't go all one way but it didn't go all the other way so i could balance kind of between the two which
was kind of nice i didn't get lost in one tightness for me it was exact opposite
it was easy today and i felt like i'm feeling warm
like i was excited and like a whole body warmth sort of like heat not even warmth but
heat kind of came i still have it so yeah it was exciting today
lovely beautiful thank you both for your reflections i i feel warmed by
by both of your reflections this is lovely i have one question for you carlo
when noticing the tightness and and then the the the gladness the joy of the
practice and then ah the tightness would come back uh and there was gladness of not being lost or
just in the tightness did you notice was there something that mediated
or or or brought the tightness back or in anything you noticed curious and if
you didn't it's all good um i
i don't think it was a thought that brought the tightness back i think it was just
um yes and just sensations of of tightness kind of being
disconnected from my my heart and then get reconnected again be up in
my head not just even in thinking just sensorially so it was kind of that um
dance i see okay okay great i appreciate the clarity of the
observation so so one invitation for you and others who would kind of notice the
oh the titan is somewhere maybe it's in the head it's higher up it's not quite connected to the heart center or this
feeling which is what i'm picking up you say did i pick that up correctly yeah so one is what um
one is to actually try to to settle into your body some more and try
to expand the sense of subtleness of the heart center and in the in the abdomen kind of settle in and
expand and if the tightness kind of is is kind of expand to if
land into this more in order to for the tightness to be included for it
not to be separate okay does that make sense what i'm pointing to yeah i think i'll have to try it and
yeah great great awesome great thank you so much thanks to both of you sweet emily says the practice felt so
nourishing today i feel very grateful to have tuned in yay [Music]
it expanded the impact of the blessings by bringing my attention to them lovely
thank you emily it's lovely the way you've put it expanded the impact of the blessings
because they're there but it expands the impact when we bring our attention to them beautifully put thank you and one more
reflection uh noticed much gratitude and caring exchange with others oh that's lovely
that's lovely gratitude and caring exchange with others that's lovely
so so dear ones this is a great time to bring our practice into
this sense of gladness and gratitude that can actually feel even bigger when we
practice in real time with others so this is the invitation for tonight and don't hop off just yet
for those of you who are a little shy about practicing with others in the small groups what what you guys
have shared is the 30 seconds of silent joy silent modita for each other just
seeing each other's um images on screen and feeling happy for
each other's blessings you don't yet know what they are but everybody has blessings just feeling
happy may happiness continue and see what it feels like when you do that in real time for
someone you don't know or you've just met maybe um and then after the 30 seconds of silence
then again let's go one round each of you sharing some some blessing in your life something
you're grateful for maybe today and then others practicing real time
mudita yay may your happiness continue and see what that feels like you've done it with your eyes
closed in your heart but now see what it feels like real time because in this way you
can actually take it to the real world when somebody at work when somebody a
friend when then some stranger says something then yay
you can feel happy in real time and wow what a nice burst of happiness to
have in life to have access to that so that's the invitation for building this muscle
in small groups so so i will actually invite you to
start practicing by looking at each other on the screen feeling happy for each
other's happiness while i set up the groups it'll take me a moment to do that uh
and and okay and um
let's see it's a little okay it's taking more than a moment okay here
we go all right all made rooms are open enjoy
your practice take delight in it here we go
nice meeting both of you thank you you too hi everyone welcome back hi
welcome back all the rooms are closed great i love this the zoom uh
uh glitch those are who on the phone they don't get muted when they leave the room so it's kind of sweet to say lovely to
meet you it's it's sweet it warms my heart
like i catch the tail end of some of your your warm-hearted connection and conversation it's sweet
so so we have a minute uh if you like to um share
share reflections uh yeah yeah bill says i find this practice more
challenging than just meta but i don't understand why um yeah i um it can be
this can be more it can be a little more complicated than than meta there's more happening here
it's not just good will but it's it's meeting um good um
the good fortune of others with good will so there is more there that can come up and it is a purification
practice so yes it is a little more challenging in general it's more complicated different things can come up
so and and it's good to stay with it even if intellectually don't quite understand
what's going on both for you and others who are finding this a little more difficult stay with it gently gently gently
remember that maybe with the times you found bento challenging if any of you did like oh yeah through
practice it becomes a little easier and i see neil's hand is up so yes neil please
so you know i i find this very difficult too right i find
generally i just lose focus right which you know i mean happens of course all the time when i meditate but
i seem to do it much better when i'm practicing mudita um you know and i'm wondering you know
sort of what practices i should do going forward you know to try to you know try to overcome this difficulty
yeah yeah so i think one aspect of it might be
i mean as you said you'd mind wandering but one but given that this
specific practice there the the mind doesn't want it finds it challenging so when something is
challenging the minds like to do might be more fun to kind of think about something and plans and
so so that's really where where it is so i suggest you start this practice you continue
this practice where it's really easy whether it's your own blessings
dear person a child a pet whoever just start where it's
really easy so it's not hard so the mind doesn't go like oh my god this is hard work i rather think about what i'm going
to have for lunch tomorrow so just kind of stay where it's really really easy
then the mind goes oh actually i'm liking this is fun i can i can do deal with this
and then go to the slightly more difficult category maybe just four percent difficult four percent more
difficult where the mind is like okay i'm on the edge and i choose yeah i'm just on the
edge of like yeah i can still it's not so challenging that okay i'm out of here and it's not so it's not it's
never boring but it's not so challenging that's out of so that's what i would recommend neil or sticking with this
practice as you practice on your own excellent question both of you so
we have come to the end of another happy hour together a happy happy edition of happy hour
celebrating happiness so thank you all thank you for your practice for showing up
for doing this practice not just for yourself but for all those whose lives you touch
and i really mean that may all beings be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves thank you merci so
i am going to uh stop the recording oops i know oh the
recording was paused i never reached