so good day hello from redwood city
where there's been lightning storms and teeny sprinklings of rain
and uh nice to be here
so the
subject of this week's
dharma talks has been mindfulness of the mind and or the mind state
and we have to appreciate that we have many mind states you know or many minds
many qualities of minds and the task of
in the basic teaching of mindfulness is to become familiar with them get to
know it and there's something powerful that happens as we know as we recognize become
familiar where there's the meeting of just knowing awareness
and the state of our mind the quality of our inner life and some of it has to do with learning
how to how to be mindful how to have that recognition that knowing
be really simple without an agenda without
you know analysis fixing but and part of that is a willingness
to become familiar take your time and get to know it and as
soon as you choose to take your time to become familiar you're shifting the inner ecology
you're kind of no longer going to be swept away caught and
reactive to what's happening you're adding a whole other ingredient to the local mental ecology
and that is a place of strength of maturity of freedom of agency
of care there's all these qualities that come when we choose to say okay i'm not going
to fix anything here or change anything but i do choose to be present for it to be here
as we become aware of the mind state we become aware of different kinds of mind states
and i want to mention three very general categories
first is become familiar with how the mind mind state is when it's
active when there's a agitated that's very active when it's moving
when the mind gets moved around goes here and there when there's activity in the mind
the other thing to become familiar with is when the mind is stable steady
when it's gathered together it's not fragmented and moving around but it's become familiar with what this settled
mind is like and that and part of the advantage of really getting to know the settled mind
is that it sets a stage for something to give away
something that we've been holding on to and just kind of can give away it's kind of like
like i said what i'm doing with my hands right now we steady them so that something can fall away
it's just something you know and um so so what is it that we don't know you
can't really know the task is just become familiar with a steady mind at rest at ease with
it peaceful about it peaceful with it and then at some point
just like you maybe sometimes you go to bed you can't make yourself sleep but you can lay there at some point you're
asleep at some points when the mind is at rest and we're at peace with that
and not trying to make anything happen something can something has a chance to
let go so assuming a meditation posture
and
and i often say take a posture that's a combination of alert and relaxed
and maybe today i'll say that take a posture that expresses expresses a degree of respect
for you and your meditation you meditating a
respectful posture so that you enter into this world of
meditation with respect for the meditation for yourself
and for your mind
and gently closing your eyes
and noticing become familiar with the state of your mind
just familiar as if nothing needs to change it's just a matter of familiarizing yourself
is it agitated is it jumping around is it energized or
is it tired and slow
such an important part of mindfulness is that agency we choose
to have to just meet the mind as it is
allowing it to be as it is but knowing it
so how's your mind state and what happens to it when you have this very simple
attention to your mind state
and now from within the body within it all taking a few long slow deep breaths
exhaling and releasing letting go
if you're sleepy and tired emphasize the inhale
how it energizes if you're
over energized excited emphasize the exhale
emphasizing being pay more attention to be receptive to allow it
and letting your breathing return to normal and continuing for a couple minutes this
process of relaxing
and the more familiar you are with relaxing different parts of your body
the more deep and more subtle the relaxation becomes
at some point it's called it's even micro relaxing
and then letting your breathing be the center of your attention
and take a few minutes now just to become attuned
to breathing
and as you exhale let go of your thoughts
and let go into the exhale
and then as you're sitting now what is the quality of your mind
what state of mind do you have how much movement activity is there
how much stillness and quiet is there
maybe the two can coexist
or maybe there's a degree of both
as you breathe breathe with the stillness of the mind
breathe through how the mind is stable quiet
letting the movements and activities of the mind the thinking of the mind
recede to the background
becoming familiar with any ways the mind might be stable and
steady hard to see if we identify
with our thinking or the agitation
but if the mind if the mindfulness is simple simple knowing
see if you can see if you can know the stability of mind the steadiness of
the mind the composure of the mind
stillness of mind
and if you're aware of the steadiness stillness of the mind
and you're less agitated now or less activity of the mind
gently know the absence of that activity that agitation
to the degree to which some of the active agitated mind is quiet
notice the absence of that that which is absent
and as you continue as you breathe exhale
just let go of the mind let go into that absence
of agitation and as you let go
let the mind rest be still be quiet
letting go
the mind lets go of itself
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
checking in again with your state of your mind
with a simple task of becoming familiar with it as if it's okay to be the way you are
just to know it feel it sense it recognize your state of mind
it may be appreciating your capacity to
know to recognize
appreciating it that it's a form of independence
autonomy
it's a form of maturity and strength that does nothing needs to change
but inevitably things do change when we know
and then with your knowing awareness
your ability to gaze upon things to be familiar with them to know what
they are to recognize clearly
let your now your attention gaze out upon the world
gaze outward and the joys and sorrows of the world
but become in a sense familiar with it from this place of
knowing recognition not leaning in and
not taking it in identifying with it just knowing it
where the channel of knowing is a
valuable challenge a channel for our care and our kindness
that sense of autonomy or agency or freedom that comes with knowing
is a wonderful place from which to love the world
compassion for the world to care for the world
and so to
express that care with dedication of merit at the end of the sitting
may it be that any benefit and well-being and happiness
that comes from this meditations
may we share it with others may the benefit be a
source from which we can benefit others may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
so in this fifth week the fifth day of mindfulness of the mind i want to emphasize that
there's many things that we can notice about the mind it's multifaceted and we can spend you know endless time
in the labyrinth of the mind being mindful of all the things but in offering these teachings of
mindfulness i believe i like to interpret them that the buddha is pointing our attention to
what is most useful to notice and and what is in a sense onward leading to
freedom to peace and so these eight categories that he talks
about in mindfulness of the mind are are divided into two general categories two
general divisions one has to do with the mind that's relating to things
and so a greedy mind relates to things a mind of generosity relates to something
and this is the mind that is kind of involved with the world and that's an important part of the mind and we want
to find a way to come to a mind which is wholesome and healthy
and at some point the meditation as it settles there's a shift
and what becomes more important is not what the mind is relating to or how the mind's relating or the relating mind
but rather it's the mind that is at ease and at peace so it's not actively involved in
relating that part of the mind that our awareness that begins to be um
spacious settled um and uh
and um and so to start noticing i like to think of it as the mind in and
of itself independent of what the mind knows so the quality of
the quality of awareness so we might be aware of something but at some point we become more
interested in the quality of awareness than what we're aware of certainly it can possibly be
disassociated in unhealthy ways if we don't notice what's happening and but to start noticing
the the quality of the mind and then that is what allows the mind to
begin to settle more deeply so the second to the last of these eight
categories is to know a settled mind as a settled mind
and to know an unsettled mind as an unsettled mind so here we're beginning to track how well
the mind is settled or not settled sometimes the translation here is
no a concentrated mind is a concentrated mind but the word is not being translated is
not samadhi the usual word for concentration but it's
a m a long a h-i-t-a which means to be a settle to compose
to be um unified to be stable so at some point we start feeling that
this in degrees that the mind is starting to get settled starting to get
composed unified stable and we start feeling the mind become it
doesn't move so much you know if there's a sound then we get
interested in it the mind moves kind of to notice what that is um we say the mind wanders away into
thought uh direct your mind to the breathing and the you know place your mind in your you
know in your in your torso as you feel the breathing so all these expressions involve
movement but at some point the mind doesn't need to move anymore it can be aware
and be very still it becomes like an a big open space
where things arise in the space and are known but the mind doesn't have to go anywhere
because it's happening within within the space and so things are known but they arise
within the mind in a sense in awareness and so awareness doesn't have to go anywhere or move anywhere or turn
anywhere it's just very still very spacious very open
and that mind becomes some people you know it's settled uh composed stable
it depends how we want to translate these terms different people orient a little differently to different ones
and it's possible to know when the mind is not stable and steady and that's the task is to know that
difference and to know that difference makes a world of difference and
the instructions here are just to know just to be familiar with it it doesn't
say adjust it change it make it better there's something very powerful begins happening when we just meet the
experience with knowing mind we're just there to be with it to recognize it
and so to recognize when the mind is not settled the more subtle the mind becomes
the more we'll recognize how the mind is unsettled and you know sometimes we can feel that
my mind is really settled and then some other time in meditation we realize oh
it's possible even more settled and then what was settled is seen as for
being more a little bit unsettled and this often can be kind of step in
step where we think we've reached some level of peace and you know what this piece is really it
and then later we find oh no that's the greater potential for peace
that's possible and this simply becoming familiar with how it is
allows something to deepen to open to relax and
the idea of familiarity of just knowing just knowing very very simply
the kind of the goal is to just be not don't be excited by the mind state
if it's exalted and big and wonderful and lots of joy and rapture or lots of
peace and equanimity or or lots of agitation lots of difficulty in the mind
the idea is to become very aquanomous about or easeful with it especially when the meditation goes
deeper and deeper and then um
um and the idea is to become kind of like as as uh
uh as familiar whether it's easy with it as brushing your teeth
you know it's it's that ordinary it becomes you know just okay no nothing exciting it's wonderful but not exciting the mind
doesn't move or get excited by uh by itself and its state
and and this uh this ability to discover not necessarily it's not necessarily
having a particular mind state that's important what becomes more important is the
knowing of whatever the mind state is the mind states begins to change
and settle as it's known
but you don't get enamored with the mind state we stay appreciating the
significance of the knowing and as we learned that knowing can be
more and more equanimous and peaceful then something let's go and then it's the last
state of mind that in this list and that's a liberated mind one knows a liberated mind as a
liberated mind and then one also recognizes what an unliberated mind is like
and so something let's go and in the wake of letting go we know something new about the mind
we know the mind that has let go and and the deeper that letting go
you know that also has stages of letting go and we might let go deeply and think wow that was full
and then later we discovered there's deeper levels more lovers letting go and the more we let go
the more we'll recognize when we haven't let go when the mind is not liberated
and and that's actually quite important because uh whatever degree of liberation letting
go we have of the mind that becomes a support a guide
to highlight where there's still practice to be done where there's where we still cling and
get caught and rather than being disappointed that's really an encourage a useful
thing that's where the path of practice is found becoming familiar and seeing
how we're caught and we go through the cycle again until the mind settles and gets
and something lets go more deeply and more deeply so mindfulness of the mind
and sometimes we're aware of the agitated mind as agitated
sometimes we're aware of a settled stable mind as a subtle stapled mind
and sometimes we'll know a liberated mind as a liberated mind and
and we'll cycle through all these and remembering
that it's not the state of the mind that's so important it's the knowing of it
that's where something really significant happens
so thank you very much