okay so hello hello hi and a formal formal
very formal welcome warm welcome to happy hour lovely to see you all
and for our practice theme for today we've been practicing the past week with
the third of what's called the brahmaviharas the practices of the heart the heavenly
abode and the third one is empathetic joy translated as sympathetic joy um
also different ways is translated but basically this translation of the word mudita
in pauli m-u-d-i-t-a it's about cultivating our heart and generosity of
happiness for other people's happiness to feel happy for other people's
happiness and they can be just a lovely practice of
of feeling happy for good fortune of others or ourselves it's a very happy
making joyous practice as many of you have noted it can be difficult and challenging at times too
we acknowledge that in different ways it can be challenging and this is a purification practice and challenges
come up that we didn't know were there we work with them
so we have made our way working through the categories uh little by little this these
concentric circles that we practice with in
the brahmaviharas with loving-kindness compassion vicarious joy
sympathetic joy from where it's easy we extend extend extend extend extend to
include more and more beings extend our heart and we have made our way to this
category of all beings everywhere feeling for the good fortune
feeling happy for the happiness of all beings everywhere so
say a couple of words before we get started before we do the practice together the meditation
so in many ways we've been working up to this in the past few days and even
if you're joining for the first time tonight is your first time no problem no worries all you need to
know will be shared with you all good so the invitation will be as
as i will invite you in the meditation gently little by little is to
feel that beings all beings they have some good fortune they have
all have challenges we all have challenges and we also have something we're grateful for
something we're happy about and can we celebrate can we celebrate other beings
happiness and good fortune whether it's another human being who's happy for some reason for whatever
gift they have or another being could be a pet
a dog or a cat who is well loved well taken care of or could be some
some bird who can imagine that who's got a yummy meal and is celebrating but can
we be happy for other beings good fortune and happiness and again if the mind turns too well but not
everything is okay in the world and while they're going extinct yes yes yes that is
absolutely true and and in this break we'll save that for compassion practice so
so we'll turn our mind to to that with kindness when we're doing compassion practice and here we choose to
again i'm going to emphasize this underline it we choose to turn
our hearts to the goodness to the good fortune very well knowing that there is plenty
of challenges and all that in the world but right now we choose to turn our minds
to the goodness and cultivate our heart in the gladness in the goodness of others knowing that
yes there is a time and place for different practices and this is an
intentional practice that we cultivate we choose to and again if you find your
mind going other places you can very gently lovingly bring it back okay sweetie it's
all right let's let's stay here and if it becomes too challenging and too conflictual just turn to it with
kindness just hold yourself or hold whatever is coming up with kindness with warmth with
compassion and that's okay too no problem so those are the
invitations and they'll guide us oh piece by piece so that's the preamble
so let's get started let's get into meditation posture
ah need to sit taller if you need to relax and soften
into your body if you need to shift posture or lie down
that's okay too
see what your body needs
and just landing just arriving
for the breath
the sensations of the body
it's a moment that is fresh and new
has never been here and will never be repeated
relaxing into this moment of being alive
this moment of being breathed
intimately intimately as if you were folding onto yourself giving yourself a hug comforting
yourself the soft blanket of kindness
now now sweetie now now let's just sit
ah and comfort and care
of this heart this moment and be
breathed
and your thoughts are rising you find mind is a monkey mind in this moment
it's okay it's all right
hello dear monkey hi good to see you
and invite invite the monkey to come and settle
settle in your lap as you breathe body relaxed
as if you're holding and caressing this monkey mind
it's okay it's okay you can rest it's safe here it's okay and relax
settling and arriving with each breath in the body
inviting your gaze to be turned inward
observing witnessing the breath
the body from the inside
just arriving settling tilling the soil
for now
feeling your feet on the ground your legs your sit bones
your hands touching each other your lap feeling your body breathing and
connected to the earth
hmm
and now let us bring to mind
something about your life in this very moment
as you're sitting breathing being breathed that is a blessing for you
it's a source of happiness it could be just as simple as
ah how nice it is to sit after a busy day quiet silently
just be breathed meditate with fellow practitioners
just simply feeling into the goodness of that how nice to have this opportunity
feeling this goodness this happiness this gladness
whatever it is
and let your heart celebrate let your heart take delight
expand shine relishing
[Music] this goodness
now if you like to consider another blessing
letting your heart celebrate relish this blessing in your life
this goodness
and see if the celebration for this blessing this gift this goodness
is good fortune in your life it automatically feels like gratitude
celebration happiness for our own good fortune
expressed as gratitude relishing relishing celebrating
if you find your mind going to a place of fear of in the future not having this blessing
it's okay bring the mind back to the present just this moment right now stay right
here intend to stay in the present
intend to let go of the future
we have a lot of power with our intention to turn the mind our attention
our will stay right here relishing
celebrating
this is all we know right now
now i'd like to invite you
as if your little fairy traveling flying with little wings
around the earth
going to some humans maybe for some humans around where you
live and seeing these beings
these humans
they have blessings too which they feel grateful for that they make them happy
you can imagine maybe there's a mother who's holding her young child
just happy in the embrace ah feeling happy for their happiness
for her happiness or a young child who's well cared for
and happily playing
giggling happy happy for their happiness
your mind you can imagine beings with different blessings
and let your heart celebrate their happiness as if you're
as if they were your own as if they were your own happiness
maybe you imagine someone who's been looking for work and now just got some work
yay they're happy celebrating with their good fortune
and in your heart you celebrate with them i'm happy for your happiness as if it
were my own
these humans who are just like you they have a complex in their life
just like you do their life is dear to
them they want to be happy
joyous celebrate goodness
knowing each being has some blessing turning your heart
your mind intently to goodness just as everyone has challenges everyone
has blessings everyone choose to turn your mind to advert
your mind the goodness in this world in people's lives
celebrating with them
now expanding expanding this circle to include all beings
all human beings
all animals
two-legged four-legged flying swimming
all beings born and yet to be born
seen and unseen
and if opening up to all beings
is too vast let yourself connect with particular beings or particular categories
maybe all beings yet to be born
you have the blessing of happily gestating
in this moment the blessing
have a life to be born
for all beings in the sea
are all human beings
short or tall medium small large
may your good fortune may your blessing continue
may it increase may it never end knowing there is impermanence of course
and yet turning our heart to generosity of good will
wishing them well wishing them continued happiness continued blessing
or simply reciting i'm happy for your happiness
may your goodness continue may you continue to be happy
and blessed in this way feeling in your own heart and
body this sense of generosity of
heart happiness for others happiness
knowing that you are included in this category of all beings
happy for your own happiness for all happiness
all good fortune in the world no matter who it belongs to
or seemingly belongs to happy for happiness without boundaries
mine yours theirs
celebrating goodness good fortune happiness
of any being anywhere
exploring your own way in your own time
using your own creativity
for what works for you discover in this practice
may the good fortune of all beings all beings everywhere
continue made increase may it never end
all right take joy i take delight i'm happy for all beings
everywhere or anywhere will have any goodness good fortune happiness as if it were my
own
radical generosity of heart
if it gets too vague you're welcome to connect with individual beings
the last moment touching into getting your own good
fortune of practice connection community
whatever it might be showing up in this moment
taking delight and being right here right now the goodness
that is present here
and gladness for whatever goodness showed up during this period of practice
and also for challenges
gladness for those two that open your heart open your mind open you up
to possibility of growth
[Music]
thank you all for your practice
so let's take a few minutes for reflections questions
what came up for you you're welcome to type in chat either
privately to me in which case i won't say your name or publicly to everyone in which case
i'll say your name or you can raise your hand your zoom
hand uh to share your reflections your questions your comments your
complaints what worked what didn't what did you discover how was this practice for you and
it's all okay this can be a challenging practice can bring up various emotions to work
with and it can also be happy making an exuberant it's just a lovely
practice of not being you won't be able to smile at some point just doing this
practice you can be very happy making him joyous so it's all good so if you like to share
reflections your wisdom your yourself with the sangha here is the invitation
especially if you haven't shared recently
says i often struggle with being emotionally porous like if i speak to someone who's sad or
anxious i feel their sadness or anxiety as if it's my own so your instruction to
feel someone else's happiness as if it were your own seems like a slippery slope to me
is the point to be selective about it ah violet i'm going to ask you to unmute
yourself if you would i want to ask you a little more detail about
what you mean uh fury oh so
yes can you can you unmute yourself please hi hi um so one example of this
one time i was meditating feeling good and i felt or i heard someone outside my
door anxious because they spilled something and i got this like hit of anxiety to my
chest like in my chest in my throat like i'm not anxious i don't care about this thing that they spilled but now it's
like in me and it's mine even though it's not yeah yeah yeah great great
that's a great question so
so yes and so yes and this practice does make you
more more resonant with other people it does and that's a beautiful thing
about it and there is how to work with it so that it's not overwhelming which is
where you're leading into like wow if i feel if i resonate with everybody's anxiety then
wow i'll be a nervous wreck every day yeah so so the beauty of it
that you become more resonant you become more i would say more sensitive i think that's a better way to say you
become more sensitive so feeling somebody's cry or anxiety oh yes you're sensing instead of your heart being closed like
no feelings here like yeah we don't want to live that way to having a wall
up like you can't touch my heart it's not going to resonate so it is beautiful for our heart to be
sensitive and that's the first part of it now the second part is okay how do we
work with that and it's resonating with joy it's lovely yes we feel their joy and when it's sadness
that's when we bring the all the other practices so we bring the stability of equanimity
as a as a bedrock and physicality of the body for example
to can support it so as i keep talking about ground in your body ground in your body
settled in your bodies and that can support with a sense of equanimity to hold what's coming up and then turning
kindness to it turning kindness if it's challenge your suffering okay then becomes compassion
holding it with kindness and stability so that this resonance the sensitivity doesn't topple you over but
you can be stay resonant to your own suffering and to other people's suffering with care with compassion so that
is how all of these practices now are connecting together does that make sense violet
so it's like you're simultaneously building increased sensitivity with like increased groundedness or
strength exactly and as we talked about it uh when we were working with compassion
last week's there's a sense of stability and strength and compassion it's not weak or
there's a sense of empowerment and compassion so exactly yes we're building all of those together
yeah it's it's a more alive way of being in the world sensitive
and stable and empowered thank you for that question many many
resonated with you thanks susan [Music]
thanks um thanks everybody and nikki thank you um
and violet wow that was really helpful i appreciate this topic being being raised i've been
working with this well for a while and i'm so happy to know the term toppled
because that's what happens and i've been aware of how i can get toppled it like the
sadness can topple me but lately i've been tripping on
how with mudita i've been aware that like due to my
trauma i'm sometimes too leaned out forward
and i'm too it'll blow my nervous system out like i get so excited like a little
kid about some something going on that i'm really aware oh dear i've gone too far um
but yeah so it's just really nice to have people who understand this process
because it's weird a little bit thanks yeah thank you susan i am so glad that you
said that articulated that as clearly as you did just now
because that is i think some previous times maybe people are asking about this what's called the near enemy
of modita that i said is exuberance and people say well what does that feel like
and you described it beautifully that is the near enemy of modita when it's toppled it's just like too much it's
just too exuberant it's not it's not stable it's not grounded and that's what you're describing um
when he loses its stability becomes the near enemy it's not the far enemy which is envy which is the opposite but the near enemy
like it masquerades as the real thing but it's not the real thing because it doesn't have the stability of
equanimity to hold it yeah so thanks for that description susan
perfect right okay all right dear one so
the invitation for our practice together in community which is
so can be so joyous so joyous so please hear before you jump off
um if it's your edge to practicing if in
community you have to go you have something to do perfectly okay but if it's your edge to practice in
small groups and community i really invite you to work with your edge to
to kind of stretch it tonight and the invitation is when
at first in the small groups for 30 seconds let's have silent
mudita for each other's joys just silently looking at the other two people in the group with
you and feeling joy for their joy for joy for your joy
and then as you on um on you start to speak let's go one
round each of you share something that you're grateful for something some blessing in your life so that other
people can feel happy for you and you can feel happy for them practice mudita
in action mudita in real time see what it's like you've been doing it silently in your heart
and now do it in real time see what it feels like when you actually feel happy for somebody else's happiness how
how profound that is and then you can share whatever you like about your practice
so so those are the invitations and i will create the
break out rooms and it will be here we let's see here
no it's one more time okay so i'm gonna open the rooms here we go
okay welcome back everyone and we have a couple minutes if any
questions or comments and i just saw
actually something typed by um by aria
about when i feel good with the lot of others i feel sad for people who are
poor sick and sad is there any way to balance this i think that what comes up as i was inviting you
is is both turning into intentionally turning into the goodness
and and also you could then if it becomes overwhelming then practice compassion for for
the challenge and difficulty that you feel for others but also working with intention
of choosing to do this practice right now and you can practice compassion there we have um that's that would be
what i would invite you leena yes
thanks nikki as usual it was fantastic and i'm so grateful that uh in our one
of the gentlemen shared his very personal grief and i'm so happy
that their friends and family to take care of him and and we're all so happy that we are
in this group where we can share our personal stories get supporting each other
my question to you was nikki is there any way if people do want to share their emails
and numbers is it possible to do that so that if somebody really wants to reach out to someone
and vice versa then we can do that that's the google groups that's what neo shared at the beginning
i couldn't actually i joined that but i still uh it didn't work for me so
you can you can join that and then reach out to people individually you know yeah through that did that that
is the way lena that's the way we have exactly for the question you asked so that people can join and then reach
out to each other through there and make connection through through the google groups
so i did join that last time i will get the emails there i mean i
joined that and i left that okay yeah so go yeah check out the workings of the google groups
both for you and others work that basically the answer to your questions are all in the google groups yeah thank you lena
yes thank you and so we have come to the end of another
happy hour practice um together
and ira asks for the google groups address and i'm going to ask if you would kindly kneel if you
would share it um that would be lovely
again you shared it at the beginning and maybe some people who were late maybe they hadn't
uh joined it yeah great thank you neil so there it is that's the link for the iimc happy hour
um google groups so thank you all for your practice
for doing this practice not just for your own sake not
not just your own heart and awakening but all of those whose lives yours touches may all
beings be happy may all beings be well including ourselves thank you