so good morning good day hello everyone
and uh thank you for being part of this
so um one of the
important things to study or to be learn about in doing meditation practice
is uh desires how our desires work
and uh how we get pulled into them the allure of them the the um
the propensity we have to get caught in them and to believe them and
follow them and uh how not to and not to be involved in desires
or to be involved in the desires that are healthy for us and appropriate for us
to be able to choose a healthy desire for meditation and then be able to stay
with it have a commitment to it or engagement with it and there is a kind of desire
in meditation to meditate to be present
and it's a maybe a very simple one some people it's not simple and there can be a lot of greed and
and attachment involved in that desire to attain certain states or have something happen prove something
but it also there can be a very simple desire to be present to be with one's breathing
as an antidote to being caught up in green antidote to be caught up swept away by other desires
it's a desire to become free of compulsive desires
so we sit no so if we sit
um with um
we said to meditate if you use the breathing as your primary anchor for your attention in the present
moment there can be a very simple desire to do so
without that desire of you know there can be a kind of like instructions to do it than one thinks that one's supposed
to do it and we'll try to do it but uh maybe the desire is not there
and maybe never thought about having a desire it's like okay i have to follow the instructions
in a sense the desire is to follow the instructions but it helps a lot if you have a simple
relaxed but clear desire
like a this decision desire that leads to a decision that this is what i want to do so no no
question about it it still might be difficult but there's a big difference between a
decisiveness and a desire to be present versus um kind of
not really having decided and and kind of like it sounds like a good idea i'll try it but you know
easy come easy go or something and it can be the desire to stay with
the breathing it then has to be monitored a little bit to make sure that it's not greed or
it isn't with expectation
as you meditate i teach here to do so with the anchored in the in the
breathing as you do so the mind will wander off
and when it does before you return to your breathing see if you can see this recognize
if that wandering of mind involves any kind of desire
if you start thinking about a meal there's maybe a desire for food if you
start thinking about you know planning the day there's a kind of desire for
the planning there's a wanting something there's engaging in something and don't make it a big complicated
project is very simple kind of obvious and if you don't see a desire that's okay just let go and come back to your
breathing but notice how often you're thinking involves uh
maybe he's fueled by a desire for something
for something or desire for something not to be and
and then and then reestablish your desire for being with breathing
and letting go of those thoughts
so this brings a kind of more clarity more wisdom understanding about the mechanism
by which we wander off that often the wandering off is is aided
by the desire that goes along with it and you might discover the desire for a
meal or whatever you're thinking about has some kind of greater psychological strength and desire to meditate
and then maybe relax relax deeply remember that now is the time to meditate
there's always time for other desires so
assuming a meditation posture
with the desire for a posture that will allow you to meditate for the
duration but also a posture that
since there's a desire for clarity and certain relaxed alertness
what posture supports relaxed alertness
and then lowering your gaze
you might close your eyes
and with a desire to settle in and relax
taking a few long slow deep breaths and relaxing into your body as you
exhale a clear desire wish
to let the whole system soften relax
letting your breathing return to normal and now before centering yourself on the
breathing check in with yourself and see if how you feel
what your mind is concerned with really and also what you might be feeling
emotionally or in terms of a mood is there any way which those represent
or come along with an active desire
is there a subtle desire behind the background or in the foreground around your thought streams
how you feel
um
and then with a see if you can establish a desire
to be present for the ongoing rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
a desire to be present for your breathing
experience or breathing in the body
it doesn't have to be any tension or expectation of success
but there can be a decisiveness in the decision the desire okay
this is in fact what i'd like to do now
settling into your breathing
maybe relaxing a bit with the exhale
and if you mind wonders away from breathing notice
if any desire is involved in that or can be is representative of that
movement of mind or movement of feelings
acknowledge the desire and then return to wanting to be with your breathing
and settle in again one breath at a time
letting your thinking mind become quieter as you exhale
mind moves towards stillness quiet
so you're just breathing in breathing out
most thinking involves desire of some kind or other
even if it's just the the desire to think
but often it's the desire for something
for what we're thinking about or something in relationship to it
desire is the fuel for thinking
can you recognize the desire and let go of it or put it aside
and return to the desire to be with your breathing the desire to be here meditating
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
turning your attention outward into the world
world of other people and animals and creatures of all kinds
and do you have can you find in yourself a simple
maybe almost like the simplest kind of uncomplicated desire
for the well-being of all living beings
a simple wish uncomplicated by
expectations and obligations and
even uncomplicated by the need to act on it at least for now
and to wish for the welfare and happiness of others
what a good idea would be how great that would be if everyone could be happy
and then to give voice
to this desire even if the desire is
the desire to have the desire maybe you could silently repeat after me
these words may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and then if you would like you can add a desire to that
and that is the desire that for this day next 24 hours
may you contribute to that in some way no matter how small
may all beings benefit from our community
thank you
so hello and for this monday for this week
i would like to discuss the fourth foundation of mindfulness
the kind of the foundational teachings on mindfulness
practice comes from a text by the buddha that's sometimes called the four foundations of
mindfulness and and it has these four different areas in
which to cultivate this clear awareness of mindfulness
and uh over this last four months or so i've given weeks on each of the first
three maybe starting in june maybe one june one july or august and um
and so in this today i would like to do the fourth foundation and uh if uh some of you have been there
for the others and and uh if you're interested in this topic you could always go back and
listen to those the fourth foundation of mindfulness is
is called the foundation of the dhammas the
dharmas and it's commonly said that the word dharma has many meanings and
in relationship to this fourth foundation people have struggled to figure out what the proper
meaning is here my proposal is to call it um the
action or activities one of the meanings of dharma among the many is it mean it can mean actions
and um and but not just actions of uh that we do actively but just activities
but actions of the activities of the mind here and um
and we're and here what we're doing in the fourth foundation is building on the foundation of the
previous three we're now taking an interest in the activities of the mind
that either keep us in bondage or which set us free
either those that keep us in the karmic stream or those that lead us into the dharm extreme following the
topic for last week's talks and um
and these five layout are laid out as many things are
in the suttos progressively almost like a little map of practice as we go along
and it begins with the five hindrances the five hindrances are something that
uh used to be i don't know still the case but uh used to be uh standard talk to be given at week-long
or 10-day long insight meditation retreats usually the second day or so there's a talk given on
the hindrances and um and uh it's really invaluable
to understand how these work these are five forces in the mind
that act as kind of like like black holes like a black hole star that
is so gravitational force is so strong that light doesn't come out of it in our
case as a pull is so strong that awareness doesn't come out our awareness
gets sucked in and we get involved in this sort of lost in this in a way that's unproductive for clear
awareness and uh these five are uh
sensual desire ill will
sloth and resistance sloth and torpor restlessness and remorse regrets
and then doubt or uncertainty and
so it begins with central desires and uh and then one of the reasons it's taught
that these to be possible retreats it's like the uh the coarsest or the often the first line
of mental activity that gets in the way of getting settled in meditation
and it has a lot to do with desire for things uh in fact
the whole first three parts of this fourth foundation can be seen as expressions of desire or
manifestations of desire but in particular for these hindrances
the desire for sensual pleasures the desire for getting rid of something pushing it away
there is sloth intorpur sloth and resistance especially when you call the resistance is the kind of a desire to
not participate or shut down or or
you know kind of go numb and and so sloth and torpor isn't just innocent being tired it's kind of like
uh wanting not to pay attention not to be here in some way and being deflated
and um maybe deflated because our desires we can't fulfill them and we're not being satisfied
with our desires and then uh the fourth one is um this uh restlessness
and kind of regrets and agitation restlessness can often come because
unfulfilled desires and we don't know how to fulfill our desires and regrets can often come when
when we had a desire that we that was not fulfilled or we didn't do
what we had hoped to do or we did something that we in retrospect realized we wish we
hadn't done and because our desires were a little bit askew a little bit off
and then doubt is you're not sure what to do in relationship to all this so we get pulled into the world of
objects the world of things of experiences of people and these five can be the fuel for getting lost in that
world sometimes for decades and um and so mindfulness practice is to
so if we settle that down then we go then we are
then we're ready to take and take on something more subtle that keeps us distracted or keeps us
from getting really settled and that has to do with uh various kinds of attachments or
identifications uh as self and so we're working through this kind of ideas and and deeper ideas of self
and this is called the five aggregates the third one when that's settled uh
there's a simpler kind of desire that goes on that's left when attachment to self is no longer there and that's just
simple uh desires for anything and everything just us simple
experiences in the moment we hear a sound and there's a movement for against it or a taste or whatever it
might be and this is called the mindfulness of the sense fears of how we
experience in the moment uh is the sense experience at all the different
scent stores and once we kind of quiet that down
then the dharma extreme has a chance to surface and then there can be the arising of
seven factors of awakening seven uh wonderful qualities of this darm extreme
that begin coursing through us like a stream almost when it gets strong and when and those uh and this is kind
of like it's a core um
states of meditation that are setting the foundation for a quiet calm steady mind
that then can see the fifth part of the fourth foundation which is um
um the four noble truths the inside having the insights that lead to liberation
and uh so these are kind of progressive and we can go through them um and so today we'll talk a little bit
briefly about the hindrances and then we'll go through the other four so it's kind of a whirlwind tour of
these big topics and and you know in these few minutes i'm going
to talk about the hindrances i could also say that i have given classes on the hindrances that are on
audiodharma and um and uh i've covered this before so you
could go and look it up and if you want to catch up more and more more depth around them which i strongly
encourage i'd like to think that uh the pasta students should become experts
on the hindrances and think of the pasta practice especially in the early period of one's practice
as kind of a de facto study um to get a phd in the hindrances to
really understand them to see them coming to be able to recognize them to know how to work with them
the um in the way that uh the buddha discusses in this text the four foundations of
mindfulness he says very simply uh when there is one of these hindrances
when that it's there when recognized it's it's there when it's not there when recognized it's
not there when it when before one has arisen
if something hasn't come occurred yet hindrance when is there present enough
and bright and clear enough to recognize its arising and this idea of seeing the beginning of
something the arising of something is we'll talk more about this as we go along but is phenomenally important it's
only possible if the mind is steady and stable so that we can see the arising of things
and and then we see we recognize that we've abandoned it we recognize that it's gone
away um and uh and then we recognize yeah it's really gone it's not coming back
wow so as the mindfulness and concentration gets stronger one has the ability to let go easily
and seeing it go is um is a meant to envir inspire faith and
confidence in this practice that we don't have to we're not stuck in these hindrances we have some agency
around them and and we should exercise that there is this healthy desire
to let go of the hindrances it's not easy to do and that's why i say we want to do a big study you know get
it the equivalent of a phd and the hindrances so we really understand well how to do this
and how to prepare the grounds so that we can avoid getting caught in the hindrances
so one learns to let go of it and then one recognizes there comes a time when
the mind is so stable and so beginning to have a feeling of freedom
that one recognizes that hindrance is not going to arise again i mean in the short term at least in in this state
that we're in it might later come back but uh it's such a nice feeling so good oh
especially if someone's been caught in the entrances for a long time and struggling with them
it's such a relief to have them you know
go away and then feel confident that for now they're not here
the word that we're translating as hindrances nivarana is
is literally means a covering so the hindrances of what covers over
uh the depth of who of what goes on for us covers over our freedom covers over
um like clarity and covers over wisdom and part of the
function of reason to practice with hindrances and and have them quiet down
is so that we can see clearly and wisdom can begin operating in relationship to what goes on
and part of that wisdom is to begin to understand the nature of desires
and know which desires are healthy to have and
and how to have healthy desires in a healthy way and
and so i no longer get pulled into the world of desires of the hindrances
then we can start uh have more freedom more ability to have this healthy desire
to yes what i'm going to do is to practice mindfulness what i want to do is to be present here
yes recognizing what's happening at present moment is better than not recognizing
and wandering off in the highways and byways of my mind
so um so the five hindrances the fourth
foundation of mindfulness a journey from our
contracted difficult states to liberation
so thank you