hello everyone and it's good to be here and i hope that
it's good to be here there where you are
and um it is a day for celebrating the earth appreciating the
earth valuing it and um
sometimes uh you know in that today's topic for the meditation is
mindfulness of thinking i sometimes reflect on
imagine long before human beings appeared on the planet and started
naming things and dividing up the lands in different ways that there were no boundaries between
countries there were no countries with boundaries and no states with boundaries provinces
you know just no property lines in a sense the earth was seamless
in a sense uh just a con one one large continuity of sorts of the natural world
and that the divisions that we live under boundaries and all kinds they're the product of
thinking and what happens when we see it as such
really see the clarity that this is thinking these are thoughts that were
created and then live our life based on them
so thinking one of the
important instructions i received in meditation or in life when i was living at the zen
center's monastery tasahara i don't remember who told me this or
what the lineage of this particular teaching was it might have been originally from
suzuki roshi and that was that the instruction
to not be bothered by your thinking
and and that was really insightful i thought this don't be bothered by your thinking
and with that little piece of advice with time i learned that when i was bothered by my thinking
i was actually fueling my thinking that there's something about
the reactivity of being bothered being troubled by thinking that itself is kind of a food for more
thought or is itself a kind of agitated thinking and that
not to be bothered by thinking was a paradoxically actually a way to for the thinking to quiet down to
not be the fire of thinking too quiet and still
and um and i learned that uh not to be at war with thinking not to
try to get rid of thinking that thinking is a
fine thing to do it takes care of itself as long as i don't get
wrapped up in it or preoccupied with it troubled by it or attached to it
and so sitting in meditation is a means as a way to discover one of
the places to discover how to leave thoughts alone and
and not be entangled with them or not to live in them sometimes i had the sense
that when i you know get caught up in thoughts that
i'm actually taking up residency in my thinking it's kind of like the center of gravity that
i think therefore i am and uh and when i don't take up residency
there if i take up residency in my body or in an awareness that's maybe
free of thinking then things are so much easier and so much
more pleasant and freer an interesting question to ask
is to be to ask who are you
when you don't use thoughts to answer the question
who are you if you don't use thoughts to answer the question
and what happens to you what do you become aware of then that's not and doesn't involve thinking
doesn't involve labels ideas
explanations maybe doesn't involve the past and the future
because those come with thoughts and ideas and memories
so today we'll do a little guided instructions on thinking
and so one little further introduction to this topic
that the general generally thoughts whether they're
verbal thoughts or images that we see visual thoughts um there's usually
a content through the to them they're about something they're about
ourselves about someone else about the future about what happened what's going to happen about fantasy
there's a world of aboutness and the more we live in thinking the more we live in this world of
aboutness as opposed to living in the world that's more here and now
more direct and the task of mindfulness of thinking
is not to get away from thinking but to be
present for thinking in in ways that are in the parts of
thinking that are not the content of your thoughts
it's more like the process of thinking rather than what you're thinking how you're thinking
more than what how what the experience of thinking is
like instead of why you're thinking so i'll guide you with this
so entering into a stable alert
meditation posture
where there's a adequate stability that you can now relax into this posture
perhaps taking a few long slow in-breaths and out-breaths
relaxing on the exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and then as you exhale relax the muscles of your face
around your eyes
cheeks in the jaws
as you exhale soften your shoulders release the holding that might be there
and you might also soften your belly
allowing the belly to hang forward and maybe down
and then as you exhale feeling the body's experience of
exhaling
maybe a global experience of breathing the different parts of the body that get
activated with breathing in and breathing out
and on the exhale at the end of the exhale maybe there also there can be a relaxing
letting go releasing that allows the exhale to continue just a little longer
and continue this way for a longer doing this but as you relax through the exhale
see if you can let go of your thinking or if you can't let go of it
quiet your thinking a little bit
let go of your thoughts acquired your thoughts so there's more attention available
for the experience of exhaling
and now we'll do a shift in attention
and shifting the attention away from the breathing in a sense
and let the center of attention be a direct awareness of your
self-thinking for this exercise
you're allowed to think no need to let go of it
but look thinking directly in the eye be directly aware this is thinking
kind of like you were involved in a
you know strong active conversation with a group of people and then you stepped away 10 feet and
looked back at them and you observe the fact that they're talking
but you're not in that in the conversation so step back and allow yourself to think
but observe it
and if thinking quiets down
disappears even then you can begin again with your breathing until thinking returns
but when thinking is there become aware of do you think
more in images or more in words
and is your thinking localized someplace in your body or in space
or does thinking seem to be unlocalized
in other words is there a place in your within you
where the voice that thinks
resides or the a projector screen
upon which the images appear
the place for that
and if there is a location that's associated with thinking
is it have a relaxed feeling or a contracted feeling
is there a lot of energy or is it very peaceful and calm
is there any pressure associated with thinking strong desire
tension and everything is okay
whatever you're experiencing as you think the exercise is just to know it just to
be aware maybe silently aware
is there any emotion that's connected to the thinking that pervades it or
fuels it
and if so for a few moments hold that awareness
gently tenderly in your awareness
no need to be for it or against it just aware of it
is there a tone of voice
that comes along with your thinking or is there a mood music that comes
along with the images
the mood
and then as you're aware of your thinking are you bothered by it
is there a strong pull into it to be involved in it and
swept away in it
is there resistance to stepping away from it or letting go of it
and then beyond the edges of your thinking can you be aware of a stillness and
spaciousness or is your whole universe filled with
thinking or is thinking just a small little
corner of the universe surrounded by space and
stillness even by silence
rest back in that spaciousness
aware through the spaciousness
now if you'd like you can return to your breathing
gently peacefully quietly
a light touch with your breathing
but if thinking predominates
then bring this light touch awareness to look thinking right in the eye
thinking i see you there you are and take a few moments to feel the
experience of breathing without any interest in the content of
what you're thinking
and as we come to the end of this sitting
it might be interesting to consider how in a very in a room crowded with
people everyone talking loudly it's hard to really hear anyone
but if the everyone gets quiet and one person speaks it might be easy
to hear that person
if our mind is crowded with lots of conversations and lots of thoughts and
ideas if we're giving a lot of attention pulled into the world of our thinking
we might not be able to be present for others to hear what they say both what they say
and hear what is deeper in them than their words
at the end of a meditation session when we consider how we can bring benefit to the world
from our meditation this is one of the reflections is that
now maybe i can listen more deeply to others
i can allow myself to be touched to be moved
by the living beating heart of another person
a form of respect and care for others
to take them in fully or as fully as we can
because we know how to be quieter in the mind
we know not to be swept away in our thoughts
and perhaps if we allow ourselves to really listen deeply to others
we can also then allow ours to we can also listen to ourselves deeply
not to our thoughts maybe but to the seat of kindness the place inside
where there can be respect and good will
compassion and care for others friendliness
and even if we don't feel friendly or kind there can be the aspiration
that someday we will be friendly we will have goodwill
the aspiration that someday we can live by these wishes
may all beings be happy
may all beings be free of suffering
may all beings live at peace
may all beings be free of oppression
may all beings be free and may it be
that in a loving way that we contribute to this possibility
[Music]
so i was introduced to the pasta practice in
southeast asia first in thailand and then a bit in nepal and then in in burma
quite a bit and then i came back united states and began participating in
the vipassana practice that was taught here by western teachers
and one of the differences was that
the western teachers when they talked retreats would have this systematic way in the
first days of the retreat of laying out the instructions much like how i've done it this week so
far they would begin the first day with mindfulness of breathing second day mindfulness of the body the
third day mindfulness of emotions and the fourth day mindfulness of thinking like today
and and then maybe a little bit more days of something at some point the instructions were
to bring all those together into a seamless hole
and uh and it turned out that these instructions in the beginning were kind of like learning the alphabet
once you learn the alphabet then you can put them together into words and sentences and
communicate and say to people write to people you know i love you or i apologize or
i forgive you all kinds of profound things we can say we can write once we know how to put those words
together those letters together so in
in in asia though it wasn't laid out in this kind of step-by-step way you would go to the
monastery and you were given the instructions in rel relatively quickly
maybe 15-20 minutes was and the basic idea was you sit down and you're present for
whatever is the most dominant predominant experience of the moment and if there
was nothing that was particularly predominant more predominant in the breathing then you would focus on the breathing
and that was a default that was the anchor to the present moment that keep you tethered to the present to
stay with the breath stay with the breath but the idea was not to hold everything
else at bay but rather if something else arose that was predominant meaning it
was kind of compelling and it got your attention
then the instruction was actually let go of the breath and bring your attention to this new
experience so if it was a compelling experience in the body
your knees hurt for example or a pleasant sensation arose then you would let go of the breathing
and you would take your mindfulness awareness and offer it to be present for this new
experience and just take that in if it was an emotion the same thing if it's thinking the same
thing and no matter what it was you would just bring that attention to it
when i was a relatively new zen student i had this colon this question that
i was very curious about i don't think i was perplexed exactly but i didn't really have an answer but
it was maybe i didn't need an answer it was kind of like
enlivening to have this question but it felt like there was something really true here in this question
and then i asked when my teacher said i think it was this way i said um
you know it's easy to see that how everything is different the rug in this room is different than
the wall it's different than the ceiling and the lamps that are here each of these are different things but
how are they all the same was my question and um and i never you know i never
try too hard to actively think about it you know logically what how they're all the same
i believe what was happening was that the sameness of them all
was somehow associated with how i was aware of them
that i was aware of everything with a certain kind of equanimity or openness or
respect for each thing each thing deserves its own respect for me
and um and so in this idea of wells in this vipassana practice
when you have when you know the alphabet and you put it all together then it becomes a seamless whole
and there's no part of human life human experience which is considered to be outside the
domain of the practice so no matter what we're experiencing
it is included yet this too is for my presence for my mindfulness and
um and so what i valued so much about the instructions of vipassana was the clear
instructions around doing that with things that like emotions and doing it for thinking
things that these are things i mostly ignored when i was practicing zen and sometimes to my detriment
because there was all these emotions that i had that i wasn't really aware of and didn't really know to pay attention to them
but in the seamless whole that i learned where everything is allowed to be
included and there's an element of respect that goes into this
uh this touching awareness touching the experience with awareness
really taking it in and letting it kind of register and almost as if you're allowing it to
be felt in a deep way and known in a deep way as if it's a it's a valuable thing it's
a everything's allowed to be there and they have this idea in zen which was very important for me
of uh the suchness of experience the thus-ness of experience each thing is in its own suchness
can exist uh and uh there's suchness how i understood this is is was kind of
how that whatever is being experienced thing how it's been how it has experienced before
the judgments before that ideas are being for or against it
before all the kind of clear what clearly can be seen as the mind's kind of response reactions
ideas about it just the experience in its own pristine
simplicity so this can be done with something like thinking so rather than
thinking that thinking is bad the thinking is the problem because thinking is what is the reaction to
things thinking is what doesn't allow things to be in their pristine suchness the um
rather than kind of having that attitude towards thinking it's rather this a wonderful thing of
turning the attention 180 degrees around and when there's thinking is a really strong
or predominant to really be mindful of thinking
and in a sense the you know pristine suchness of thinking and have you ever thought
about what a have you ever considered what a thought is
have you ever kind of held the thought in your hand palm of your hand to feel its weight
or if you ever try to touch a thought and see you know how flexible is it how pliant
is it can you push it and it gives or is it hard or do you go right through it with your
your thought have you ever considered what color your thoughts are or
how large they are how small they are for some some of us when we have these
kinds of thoughts the whole relationship to thinking begins to shift
because a lot of the substance of thinking has to do with our involvement with it
our desperation or anger or desires or intensity around how we think and
you know carrying the burden of the world on our shoulders has a lot to do with our relationship to
thinking how intensely we're involved in all these thoughts and ideas
and um and uh this question you know how much is thinking away
is one of the ways for some of us to shift back out of being so glued and glammed on to
thinking that you know we're carrying it so heavily or it's claustrophobic in our minds because of it all and
and and then start creating space and a very common experience for people
as they meditate if they're able to get settled is the thinking mind
doesn't necessarily go away but it stops being one thought after another or the
thoughts the thoughts stop feeling so heavy or so dense so
so compelling and they get lighter and lighter and thinner and thinner and softer and softer and
they can be just as profound as before but there's all this extra way in which we
infuse them with weight infuse them with intensity begins to quiet down so if we turn
attention around to really look at thinking to be present for thought just the way we be present for thinking
with a light touch with a you know just seeing if what it is part of what we're seeing also looking
at is the way that we relate to thinking what is our involvement with thoughts
and the pristine suchness of seeing our involvement
it's very easy to say well now it's okay i learned i don't want to get rid of my thoughts they're not my enemy
but i'm not supposed to be so attached to them or so involved in them and then now i'm a bad meditator in
vipassana practice and in zen practice i believe there's no sustain as a bad meditator
is just one more thing to experience in in its pristine simplicity
oh this is me chasing my thoughts this is me
kind of contracting around this set of thoughts this is me being so interested in this
particular concern oh this is what it is this is what it is and then as we do
vipassana practice we learn more and more this seamless hole where we bring this
quiet light touch presence to anything that is happening
anything that's compelling in the moment and with time we get a sense that because
the attention now the awareness now is inclusive that nothing is left out
it becomes sacred or the world becomes sacred because the awareness and the world are
not exactly two different things we have an awareness which is includes has a sense that includes
everything not actively in the moment but it's ready to include everything
as soon as awareness as a something that's outside of what's acceptable for
awareness what we're not supposed to pay attention to then this my sense of this sacred
sacredness disappears but when there's no outside and everything is included there's no
outside then maybe there's no inside either it's just this seamless hole that we're
able to sit in not being bothered by anything but ready
to respect and care for everything
so um may you that in these next 24 hours
may be interesting for you to look at your relationship to thinking
and consider is there some way a wiser way to relate to thinking is
there a useful vantage point in which to experience and
know that you're thinking that that kind of suggests to you something
about the sacred dimension of this world that comes through the
medium of being aware so thank you all very much