so um let's uh let's sit together here
had a yoga teacher sometimes say uh what what is
what does light make heavy what is heavy make light
yeah in a posture and an asana what is light make heavy what is heavy make light
pointing to this gesture of uh
smoothing out smoothing out body mind
evening out the energies of body mind
we can use the the breath
as a way of unifying smoothing
energies of the moment
so what is hyped up hyperactive
bring the soothing breath to
ah that constellation of feeling in my chest let
me breathe into that
soon that
maybe there are places of of numbness or fatigue sloth
and we breathe life into it
spine reaching upwards to the sky
the rest of the body hanging loosely
just unifying the field with the breathing feeling the breath in your whole body
what would we do if we weren't busy clinging
clinging is inherently agitating
complicating
it's so easy to repeat our habits of greed
version as we said
and yet practice is practicing
non-clinging and i use that word practicing in the
same sense that one might practice a free throw
playing basketball
or clinging was like a little whirlpool
of energy somewhere in body mind
what does light make heavy what is heavy make light we smooth out
the energy especially of our body
and rather than acting out greed we practice
practice equanimity with longing
rather than act out aversion
we practice equanimity with imperfection
this way
our moment starts to get very simple
clinging is complicated
letting go feels very simple
simplifies
the moment can get very simple
sacred really
sense of the dharma coursing through it
and just to rest there is no
my
sometimes i i'd say like that it um
it feels like the the first
noble truth contains the other three yeah
that somehow uh if we can open the dukkha yeah
that's there's no joke and um
it's easy to get familiar with with suffering in a way and say oh yeah i get
i get the truth of dukkha but um but do we realize it
in the sense that sedgwick talked about realization of making
something real
a friend who who recently
finished a long retreat said during during this time
sometimes the memory of the suffering of a pet from
decades ago would just like pierce her heart
and there's a bumper sticker that says i break for suffering
but the question is like would we
would we ever hit the accelerator right
it's a major project to open to one's own suffering
major but sometimes the the suffering of the other is even more evocative
yeah it can be evocative in ways that open us
to deep compassion yeah so we see the suffering of a loved
one and the heart just naturally opens
and sometimes of course our care gets tangled up
with our clinging and our control
and with our preferences or our needs
and we have entrusted our our heart to
another by choice or by birth and
what that means is that in a sense all of their suffering feels
like our business yeah
as a child the the suffering or imperfection of a
parent has huge implications for our sense of of uh safety of protection
and so their pain their confusion their greed their hate
is itself destabilizing for
for the child right for ourselves as children
and there's a kind of yeah there's a deep wobble that can
happen in our own heart when we see
loved ones in pain or we see loved ones
acting acting out their own defilements
and in a sense their neurosis
could be just a kind of opportunity for our own care compassion
but their neurosis usually interacts with our neurosis it's like
they're clinging tangles with our clinging
friend teacher was was telling me that
you know at a family gathering i kind of you know this is pre-coveted
family gathering with the uh you know his family his wife's family
and he says to his wife like uh you know can you believe how my mom's acting i'm
sorry and his wife says no no no your mom is
fine can you believe how my mom's acting right
sort of like oh yeah something particular gets evoked in us
along these lines of of connection of love of clinging
and um you know researchers have uh
have done um brain imaging you know when one person
is seeing a loved one suffer you know in some way do a pain task actually
some way of of um of knowing that a loved one is is um
you know uh is is uncomfortable there's they're actually part of the research is for the
other one too to be in some pain
and a lot of our brain lights up regions uh associated with understanding the
state of the other but also a kind of affective resonance
and some of the same things happen in our brain as if we were in pain
um kitty sorrow and tenisra beloved
teachers in this lineage were monastics for for many years and
then left the monastic lineage and where i've been a couple for a long
time now and still you know very
obviously serious practitioners teachers and they're asked at one point like what's
it like to be in relationship and um and kirisara said it's like two people
under one robe yeah referring to the monastic experience two
people under one robe their goodness their suffering
all under one robe and when we when we see suffering in our
own life it can get us just naturally scrambling to re-order
circumstances yeah and when we see suffering of someone
close to us it kind of does the same thing
we habitually move into this mode of just we're trying to reorder
circumstances but that often means we're trying to reorder them
who they are and so the compassion the care becomes
entangled it becomes
it's no longer free and our aversion or our fear
or that's what's driving the show we get
frustrated get controlling and then we try to change them through
our own frustration and
you know when i think about what what do i want in all my relationships
well really i want them all to be our hearts
yeah to be fully enlightened i get to be
a basket of defilements but they better be
deeply enlightened right and
the greed the aversion the delusion the non-enlightenment i perceived in loved
ones is especially evocative for me it spins me
and on the one hand i know if i respond to my own suffering in that way it's
totally unproductive but it's somehow harder to resist
interpersonally yeah for their greed aversion delusion not to spin me
in a way i know is unproductive so yeah may they all be enlightened
right but then again in the end
even if i lived with the buddha i know i would get irritated by
something you know
honey you know uh lord buddha
can't you see i'm angry yeah why are you so calm
yeah there was a an interview with a writer who was asked if literature changes
people and uh the writer said
i don't think people change very much to the extent that people change at all
it's because of some encounter that has love in it
it's hard to uh hard to change it's hard to grow we know
that yeah sometimes it happens in a flash but a lot of times
it's very incremental it's hard to grow it's hard to change
and if we're gonna do it for sure love will be involved
yeah and the irony the
the people we most want to change are the ones
we tend to be most enraged by yeah
even if that frustration is subtle you know
and yet we know anger anger aversion that is the single
worst way to support someone in their change in
their evolution
so we're going to have to tolerate some ambivalent and
we're going to have to open our heart to the imperfection of the other
just in the same way we open our heart to the imperfection of ourselves
compassion is not an insistence that someone change
it's not an insistence that someone changed
deep deep acceptance
forgiveness it doesn't mean condoning harm but
forgiveness and what is forgiveness other than
really just understanding understanding their inner life
so we investigate uh what does the
the pain or the neurosis of the other do to your mind
what happens in your heart what is evoked in perceiving
their own dukkah and what way is does our care and
our dependence uh
express itself as compassion as a kind of generosity of heart and what ways
do the impulses of control get born
last album of uh his life uh leonard cohen uh saying uh
i wish there was a treaty we could sign i do not care who takes this bloody hill
i'm angry and i'm tired all the time i wish there was a treaty
i wish there was a treaty between
your love and mine
so may we may we practice well
see you uh see you tomorrow
you