so
in this process of anapanasati
mindfulness of breathing in
mindfulness of breathing out
we've come to the core heart of it
the insight aspect of it
and and the purpose of insight
is to liberate us to free us and it
involves a very clear
centering ourselves in the core
dynamism core aspect of how this life is
and all the
steps before in a sense are preparing us
and preparing us and i don't want to
i want to emphasize how important this
preparation
is certainly preparation for
what we're doing in the last steps
but what we're doing the last steps is
also
preparing ourselves or willingness to
meet this world as it is
the ability to really be in this
suffering world
and to be prepared for that to have
really developed the qualities of
attention and concentration
and persistence and and uh
and well-being and purified ourselves
got to work through
some of the hindrances all the
hindrances work through or
are the attitudes and the
places that we're where we
kind of can you need to be healed and
and settled
and this is a beautiful and profound
process and we need this for it to be
available
to be available to care for this
suffering world
and so then we come to this 13th step
where we're experiencing
observing impermanence or in constancy
and this has three different aspects
that things
are changing and inconstant one is there
is loss
things disappear but also the very fact
that
things change allows for new beginnings
the fall gives birth to the winter the
winter bring gives birth to the
spring things pass away in the fall die
away and then
get reborn in the spring and now
we need this cycle is what we need
and so we live in a world of tremendous
suffering
and so much that we've experienced in
the news now for so long
and you know the amount of hate that
gets expressed in violence and killing
is astounding and um
and it's been going on since the time of
the buddha
and so how do we address this how do we
meet this and so anapanasati is this
beautiful practice
of profound practice maybe i shouldn't
use beautiful in this context but
profound
helpful and healing practice that
just to stay the stay constant with the
inconstancy of breathing the rhythm of
breathing
frees us from this the
contractions the resistance the fears
the preoccupations the distractions of
the mind
it allows something to be settled and
and to be
come into kind of harmony and ease
that allows for the self-healing
qualities of this human body and heart
to operate it makes room for some of the
most beautiful qualities of who we are
to surface and come forward
and so to really be able to dip into the
inconstancy and the changing nature of
it
is to have a direct confrontation with
what's most difficult with human life
but also with what's most wonderful and
healing in this human life as well
and and because things have changed not
only is it until there's loss and
there's also the disappearing of things
which are
not useful or that are that are painful
and difficult
suffering disappears as well and so part
of the
inconstancy and the changing and
permanent nature of all this
is a rich rich world of so many things
that we enter into sometimes
simultaneously
where there is loss but with loss
there's also a gain
we or in the sense that we also lose our
suffering at times
um and uh with the new arising of things
appearing of things some things that are
pure are not good
but also there's possibility of good
things and then the teachings of the
buddha
to really see and feel and be in this
current of change
gives us some agency
to shape how we experience and how we
are in this world and we certainly can't
change the world dramatically most of us
but we can't change our immediate world
we can't change ourselves
and the practice has a lot to do with uh
with understanding
change and finding a way to harmonize
with it
and work with it so that we cultivate
ourselves we develop ourselves
to become better people so to prepare
ourselves for
this world so that we have resiliency we
have
open heartedness we have non-clinging we
have non-hostility
it's a um it's a powerful thing
to uh you know to work with
the changing nature of this world in the
in vipassana practice
we're working with that changing nature
of the world all the time
but it's not often emphasized but now on
this 13th step of anapanasati
this is the part of the world that we're
really working with this
is the we're entering into this flow and
the change
and it's easy it may be easy to at least
for a teacher to say what i'm about to
say
but maybe much more difficult to do it
and that is that to really enter into
this
this part of what the buddha was
emphasizing to really uh to really
observe
in constancy means that we're no longer
in the sway or caught in or seeing
the reality through the lens
of our concepts and ideas
our stories and all
those also are part of the inconstant
world changing world
and and stories come and go they arise
and they pass
there's all this change and flow and
movement
in the story making mind and the concept
concept making mind
everything is flowing and changing and
so how do we really
get to really get into that and and
really rest in it
the buddha taught that because it's
liberating that's where freedom is found
and it's a the core insight of the
buddhist teachings
over and over again is to see in
constancy
is to see change is to see
maybe we can say the word impermanence
and and it represented by
a number of things kind of
the first person who was enlightened
after the buddha was
hearing the buddhist teachings exclaimed
kind of
proclaimed his awakening with the
statement
everything that has the nature to arise
has the nature to pass away
everything that arises passes away
the buddha explained that everything is
inconstant
everything that is an experience
concepts might not be and the ancient
greeks
you know had a lot of
controversy debates about the nature of
impermanence and change and constancy in
this world it's a common topic for
philosophers
and the famous philosopher plato wasn't
that comfortable with that everything
was changing
and he wanted to have something that was
permanent and i believe
a little bit i know about him that he
settled on this idea's platonic concepts
there is
ideas that are unchanging
but the ideas are not direct experience
and the buddha over and over again was
placing ourselves
in direct experience breathing with it
being mindful of it feeling it and
really
entering into this inconstant world
to know it because that is the way to
freedom so i said
the first person was enlightened said
that everything has
everything that has a nature to arise is
the nature of passing away
there's something about that insight
that was liberating
the when the buddha died the the final
statement
that um the first statement i believe
one of the first statements someone said
when he died it became kind of the
funeral chant for buddhists
it also became it's said to be the the
um
the sayings or the affirm the
saying the the saying of the
arhat saying of the fully enlightened
one
and it goes to chant in pali it's anicia
domino
suko
all things are inconstant they have the
nature of arising and passing away
those who see deeply into this truth
experience happiness
so but the happiness not of
you know being totally delighted and
happy all the time
but a deeper happiness
or contentment or satisfaction or
intimacy or something that we are
in touch with what is real in this real
world of ours
so even if we this world is full of
suffering which it is and
the violence against the asian americans
lately and
the shootings and so many
places in this country but most recently
in boulder
is um
you can't say we're happy in the
relationship to that
but there can be a feeling of rightness
that yes if this happens in the world
we want to be present for it we want to
know it we want to it's right
to be aware of it even if it's painful
even if it's what touches some of the
deepest strings in our hearts
but to have the capacity that's if this
is what's happening
yes let's be present for it let's
breathe with it
and all the steps of anapanasati can be
relevant for this
the feeling that pain but to feel that
pain
is not the same as i feel suffering
and this freedom of this practice the
rightness of this practice to feel this
world be present of this world
without suffering but willingly feeling
the pain of this world
so that we can also have compassion for
it and care
so we prepare ourselves for all that
what this world has to offer
so that we can offer ourselves as
someone who is
loving compassionate caring
and that we live in this world in a way
that
supports the betterment of all beings
out everywhere
may all beings everywhere
be free thank you