so good morning and i think i have the technology set up a
little more complicated today
we're going to be working with the breathing that's what the anapanasati is where the simple rhythm of breathing
in and breathing out is used as the through line
as the thread that goes through uh all our experience it's kind of like the the um
the beat of the song that's always there or it's the kind of like the ballast of a boat that
keeps the boat steady it's a the breathing is a
the rhythm of breathing and the coming and going of breathing so can support the mind to both have
developed a stability and also not to hold on to anything
and in fact this part of the stability of the mind it comes maybe seems like a
paradox comes from not holding on to anything it's when holding on
to things being preoccupied being churning away ruminating on things that
the mind becomes more unstable because it has an unstable basis on the
unstable foundation and and so the rhythm of breathing
coming and going it's a con there's continuity there there's a constancy there that supports
us it's always there for us and because the inhale disappears the exhale disappears
it's like a wave like coming and going it's you can't really hold on to the
breathing and so it both provides us with this constancy this stability
and a kind of massage or support to not get caught in anything we still might have thoughts there might
be sensations all kinds of things might happen and we can be aware of them but with the
breathing kind of at the center or the breathing as support as a foundation
it comes and goes they it's a little bit more difficult to mind get fixated
or caught on its preoccupations and whatever's going on the emotions that are happening
and so it can be very it can be a gentling effect it can be a nurturing effect it can be a
tranquilizing effect to do this and for this meditation
i'd like to offer you something a little bit extra to pay attention to with the breathing particular quality of
it and that is the transition between breathing out and breathing in
the transition between breathing in and breathing out
and this is a place where um
just a little extra attention to and there's different things that might happen there
and so this is where you can literally pay attention to how it is for you and it might change over time
that on the in that uh the end of the out uh exhale uh
there might be just a very s automatic quick automatic um
transition between breathing out and breathing in just just boom boom breathe out and then
immediately the in-breath begins and that can be noticed how it happens one happens immediately after the other
it might be a the transition might be not so quick it might feel more like
it's gradual the exhale gradually ends and the inhale gradually begins
or it might feel like there's a sense a pause between the exhale
and then the beginning of the inhale and each of these has its advantages each of
these is part of the you know you know part of what we can notice but there's something about noticing
that transition in a relaxed and open way without expectation that completes the cycle of attention of
breathing in and breathing out and so
and so we'll bring some careful gentle attention to this as we go
through the breathing so to take a comfortable
alert posture and
gently close your eyes
and perhaps taking a few long slow deep breaths full breaths three quarters
full and then as you exhale a little longer
exhale than you would just on your own
breathing in deeply deeply and then relaxing on the exhale
releasing and letting go
letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale you go through the
little almost like a ritual of relaxing the body
and as you relax see if you can feel
some quality of tranquility or peacefulness in the area that you're
relaxed so as you exhale relaxing the muscles of
the face
around the eyes
the cheeks jaw
and if it's you're able to relax those muscles
is there any evidence any little even partial sense of tranquility
as part of that
then as you exhale to soften the shoulders release the
shoulders
and as the shoulders relax in the shoulders is there any sense of
greater calmness or tranquility
as you exhale relaxing the chest
the area around your heart
and even if there's agitation in that part of your body if you're able to relax a little bit or
soften are there any even hints of tranquility calmness
and then on the exhale relaxing the
belly letting the belly hang forward or
settle down deeper into
sometimes when we exhale sometimes when we relax the belly
they can also support a relaxation of
other areas of the body and you might as you exhale both relax
the belly and see if you can relax at the same time
release the shoulders the hands
arms
release the whole body
and then feel is there any physical tranquility or calmness
that you can pick up in your body as a whole
even if you do feel some thing opposite to calmness
see if you can be attuned to that which does feel tranquil and calm
and as you exhale relax with that calmness
and then becoming more centered on the experience of breathing
and in relationship to breathing itself is there any tranquility or calmness
or maybe around the experience of breathing underneath it behind it
some feeling of calm or peace
that's there associated with the breathing
and as you breathe breathe with that calmness breathe with the tranquility
and very calmly without thinking about it too much
appreciate or notice how the physical experience of inhaling
is different than the experience of
exhaling
and then letting go of noticing the difference between them
let the inhale just be the inhale allow the exhale to just be the exhale
as if it's the only thing that's here
and notice as you inhale the inhale inhale has an
end an end that fades away or an end which
comes abruptly and don't just notice and
feel the physical experience of that ending of the inhale
and then observe the transition to exhaling
maybe a little bit like you're
driving in a car and on a flat road and then there comes
a little hill a little bump that you gently lift up and then over the the crest and you go
down kind of ride
the end of the inhale to the beginning of the exhale the
releasing
and then the same thing for the end of the exhale beginning of the inhale
maybe like driving along and there's a gentle dip in the road in the car it goes into
the dip and then slowly comes up
or maybe the transitions are sudden almost like a switch
that goes on and off switching from inhale to exhale exhale to inhale
both ways are fine gently observe how it is for you
and perhaps in doing this careful sensing observing
maybe you can feel a quiet intimacy with the experience of
breathing
feeling whatever calmness or tranquility that's here
a tranquility that allows breathing to be as it is
comfortable or uncomfortable
but you just follow along in this rhythm
of breathing
seeing if you can feel any tranquility or calmness
associated with any part of the
breathing
and perhaps you can notice any calmness might be there in the transition
between breathing in and out between out and in
a calmness that's closely related to allowing
allowing that transition to do itself
with an intimacy with awareness breathing in breathing out
calmly receive the inhale
in the body
calmly release the exhale
and ride along in the transitions between these
a continuous intimacy tranquility
with your awareness of breathing
if you find yourself involved in thinking what happens to your thinking
when you place the rhythm of breathing back in the middle of your experience
and for these few minutes we have together trust your breathing
more than you trust your thinking
center yourself on breathing in the body
releasing into tranquility as you exhale
receiving the inhale in your calmness as you breathe in
so
[Music] so
and before bringing this to an end
scan through your body to notice what is it and where in your
body is there some tranquility calmness
even if there's places that are agitated notice the places that are calm or quiet
for a few minutes here breathe with that tranquility breathe through it
breathe along with
tranquility calmness
peacefulness
as if it's a gentle vapor that you can
blow through your body spread outwards throughout your whole
body as you breathe
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
perhaps in a world that's so agitated
our calmness
can be so that we don't fuel that agitation further
may it be that we don't add to people's anxiety
may it be that we don't contribute to restlessness
maybe that we don't reinforce
agitation of any kind
and may it be that whatever goodness benefit that we received from this
sitting may we dedicate it
to the benefit of others
may in our calmness may our benefits and merit
spread out across the lands so that all beings be happy
so that all beings might be safe
so that all beings might be peaceful
so that all beings might be free
may all being everywhere be free of all that oppresses
may all beings be happy
[Music] you