so
i thought that before kind of going
further with anapanasati with this
practice of mindfulness of breathing
to kind of kind of start over again in a
little bit way
if maybe a little different way and stay
more with the basic
most basic aspect of the practice
and over these weeks that i've been
doing this i've offered a variety of
maybe subtly different ways of being
with the breath
and breathing and different ways
different little different little
different each time
and it isn't that you have to remember
all those ways and
and but rather maybe some of them
work for you inspire you in some way
and it can be a basis of how you
practice and so
the wider range that i give perhaps the
more likely you'll find something
and maybe you'll piece together parts of
it the subtle different ways of
being with the breathing and work with
the breathing and the meditation and
breath
um and i also wanted to kind of just
stay real basic today rather rather than
moving
further along the steps um as i said
yesterday in some ways as we're going
through slowly in some ways we're going
through it very fast and
you know maybe it would be ideal to
spend a year going through the steps
and so
it's on monday you know we'll start then
a little bit further and the next
stages of the next steps of it are quite
fascinating or very
very significant for this working with
this meditation practice but before we
go on that way
i wanted to um um
uh maybe take some questions from you
we've been doing this
breath meditation now for a few weeks
and maybe it'd be nice if you had a
chance a few of you had a chance to ask
some questions and
if you can put them in the chat and then
i'll try to respond and maybe
the questions that i pick out of the
chat
hopefully they are relevant for many of
you and be interesting to kind of
have some this interesting for me to get
some feedback or some
hearing about learning a little bit
about the kind of questions you have or
challenges you have with it or joys you
have with it or something
and the um
and the ways you know there are a lot of
chat questions uh
sometimes i can't really follow them in
order and they're in place because they
passed by so quickly and
i i try to do a little bit that way but
maybe we can think of it more as i'm
pulling questions out of the hat
then doing it in sequence
and
so someone said i experienced
anxiety um and um
there's no question but it's interesting
that anxiety
is a i think it comes from a greek word
to choke
and like choke to not really be able to
breathe fully in
so this kind of working the edge of
where the breathing is held or resisted
or
it sometimes can be helpful with anxiety
kind of expanding it relaxing that
how can this help with the severe
chronic pain
the um it might not help i mean i
i can't promise you that this will help
but there are plenty of people who find
that
um breath meditation helps can help with
severe pain uh certainly i've had lots
of severe pain in meditation but not
chronic
but certainly severe at times and
one of the surprises is to discover that
it's possible to feel joy
and pain at the same time it's possible
to have become
and feel pain at the same time it's kind
of like two different sides two
different parts different aspects of the
of our being and often if we identify
too much with the pain or we
too preoccupied with it or too caught up
in it
then that influences kind of the inner
state of how we are
but if we don't identify two with it or
aren't too preoccupied with it it's
there
we don't ignore it um but um
then their inner interstate inner state
of our emotional state our mood and all
that
doesn't have to be tied to it and so the
interstate can be
peaceful or calm and that doesn't
necessarily make the pain go away
but it creates a different context for
being with the pain
so that the pain isn't the primary
influence on us but there's some
other something inside which is an
influence that might actually influence
the pain in some way
i've also when i've had severe pain
and meditation or in life i sometimes
have um
just breathe through it and around the
place of pain
and it depends a little bit probably
what kind of pain it is
but sometimes uh just breathing through
it and
and and or with it i don't identify with
it so much and just
little sense of relaxation little sense
of something releases then and
if nothing what releases is that my
preoccupation with it
there's much more to be said about pain
but for now
have you experienced all 16 sure
and sometimes i've experienced them
sequentially one to the other usually
but sometimes it's more random you know
sit down to meditate
and i find myself some points different
points of the
of the steps or i'll jump ahead or seems
like i go through it quickly and
and one of the steps becomes more the
predominant one for the day
and so so you know
but yeah um
oh what does it mean when the body
disappears and there's no question mark
so
that's already disappeared too
generally when the body disappears in
meditation it means we're concentrated
it means the the thinking mind has
become quiet quiet enough
that that we're not conceptualizing
about the body
it turns out that it's a little hard to
imagine you know if you have never
experienced it
but it turns out that a lot of the ways
in which we experience the body
is mediated through our thoughts and
ideas
through the activity of the mind that
constructs the body
and so
so for example with eyesight from seeing
we have all these little photon light
particles
travel into the eye they get turned
upside down in the eye
and go against the retina and um
and then there's these electrical
signals the nerves that
send these signals up into the brain and
then the brain
reconstructs the signals
into something which is a simile of the
world out there the world that was seen
and sometimes that reconstruction is not
accurate
as when you know you see a twig on the
ground and you
first you see it as a snake and um
or i've seen people the distance in a
crowd strangers
but uh for a moment i thought it was a
friend of mine because there was enough
similarity
and then i filled in the blank to kind
of see my friend and then i looked more
carefully no it's not my friend
so the reconstruction process is is an
activity the mind does
as the mind gets calmer it's not
reconstructing so much
and as it doesn't reconstruct it doesn't
it's not taking the signals or doesn't
have the signals from the body
to reconstruct and it just and it feels
like the body is disappearing
and sometimes it disappears entirely and
i've actually
sometimes thought you know had to open
my eyes in meditation to make sure that
i was still here because
it just felt so you know empty
sometimes there's an intermediate stage
where um
we're still the mind is still
reconstructing
uh sensations but it's not really doing
it accurately anymore
and so sometimes people's uh in
meditations they'll feel really like
they get elongated like they're about to
touch the ceiling or they feel really
squat
their hands feel like they're getting
really big usually it's not particularly
you know you know you know
unusual it's just kind of little
perceptual distortion
and it's usually a particular stage and
when people go d
just it also doesn't last for too long
and and then after a while
the capacity to settle and get more
concentrated settles in and
and that perceptual distortion stops
um
is it important to follow the steps in
order
like i just said no sometimes it's
helpful to do so because it if
it can't help the concentration just
you're on task
and you're just going to do it and
sometimes it's not to do it on tasks and
do a technique and kind of follow
something makes the mind too busy
and um and sometimes what happens is we
start with the first one we just start
with breath meditation and getting
settled in
and then rather than following this you
know implying and following the steps
exactly we are we're recognizing as we
deepen the practice
we recognize the steps we recognize
where we are
and because we can recognize it maybe it
becomes a little fuller
and we can let it become fuller and more
complete and then it just on its own
it moves into the next step into the
next step and i prefer that way rather
than kind of intentionally moving ahead
when
you know it's a time to move ahead now
it's more like you do your practice and
you just kind of allow it to unfold
in its own way and sometimes it jumps
around it doesn't have to be the same
linear steps
how to work with controlling breath this
is really common
the i think the
the most useful thing to do is um
uh not worry about it and
don't be bothered by it allow yourself
to have a controlled breath
and and you can cultivate just a strong
mindfulness and concentration with a
controlled breath
with the breath that's not controlled
it's not the breath that
is the main issue it's really the main
issues the quality of the attention you
bring
also if you're not bothered with it
you're more likely to get out of its way
when we're bothered by a controlled
breath we actually in some subtle way
reinforce it and it makes it more
difficult to let go
also it can be very interesting to
become a connoisseur of the controlled
breath
just be content to have a control breath
and then get to know it really well like
where exactly is the sense of control
where's the tightness the resistance
the pushing what are the emotions that
are connected to it
are there anything anything emotional
any beliefs connected to it
just really get to know it inside and
out and sometimes that really getting to
know it
sometimes is a little trick because
after a while focusing on that way
directly
kind of disarms the control and
sometimes you discover something
interesting that needs to be
relaxed and released then then becomes
easier to
to to do it so that's one of the things
i would do
another thing that i've done you know
i've done so much of this over the years
that i've
depending on times i've done different
things sometimes with that when i had a
controlled breath
i imagine that uh i was bringing my
attention
uh from the back forward like going in
through the back door
my back rib cage and just feeling it in
the back ribcage where there's very
little sense of control in the back
ribcage
and i felt the breath there for a while
and then that
kind of relax the control in the front
and then i slowly
move my attention forward gingerly
without kind of
triggering the control
um
i have a challenge in the out breath
smaller
and belly tight your suggestion
observing the end of the in-breath
at the end of the out breath is helpful
since i
do get anxious there so any thoughts
about that
i think a little bit same as with the
control you know it's very
very significant just simply to
recognize and observe what we're
actually doing
and and there's a tendency when we see
something about ourselves
to have judgments or reactions or think
it should be different
but don't underestimate how very
significant is that you're just
observing it and seeing it
and it might be all you need to do and
i've had all kinds of ways in which you
know i've been anxious or
tight in my breathing controlling my
breathing all kinds of things about it
that i just allowed myself to feel it
know it
and there's continued with the breathing
kind of like the breathing is just a
massage for it
and i find it interesting that as a
massage
some point in the in-breath is more like
the
the heart of the massage and then like
pushing it and then relaxing
sometimes the top of the in-breath
sometimes the end of the out breath
depends what's going on and just kind of
like
be with the rhythm be and and find a way
to be really content like you're in it
for the long term like
you're not trying to fix it you're not
you know pre-concerned about it
not just okay just recognize oh i'm
you know it's uh it's unpleasant it's
tight it's
controlled there's anxiety and i just
breathe with it
you know and and we're going to be
friends and just breathe and breathe
and that kind of attitude sometimes is a
very effective way
to over time the things just settle
without us being involved in
all kinds of mental uh preoccupations
and that often just kind of
stir it up even more sometimes
yes let's do another zoom soon to chat
with sangha yeah we'll do it
maybe we can do it next week it depends
a little bit about
you know it depends whether i have time
and right now i have
a number of um
it thinks i'm having to take care of my
life that makes it a little harder
any idea for trauma survivors and
disassociation sometimes
i may think i'm concentrated maybe i'm
disassociated
yeah i mean certainly
trauma survivors have their own path and
and the care that's needed for breath
meditation and for meditation in general
and it's a it's a noble path it's a
dignified path for
people who've had trauma to work through
and work with
their trauma in meditation and and all
that
but it often needs a little different
kind of attention than
uh the kind of the basic usual you know
instructions that i would give
the
the you know it usually uh what's really
good is a lot of compassion and a lot of
care a lot of generosity to oneself and
a lot of patience with it all
and and permission to not have to go
headlong into the trauma or the fear or
something
it's fine to be at the edges of it and
and and it's fine to avoid it if
or it's fine to breathe with it without
fixing it or doing anything with it
so you can find exactly or to pull out
when trauma responses arises in
meditation a very helpful skill to
develop
is to kind of end the meditation or kind
of
come out of that state and revive
oneself or come back to normal a little
bit
and develop that skill so there's
confidence that
as you go into it that you if you ever
if you really wanted to you could come
out
so at some point if you want to explore
and go further with the sensations of
trauma
that you do so with a lot of confidence
at a moment's notice you can pull
yourself out
and and maybe there is disassociation
and sometimes you know it's not it's not
there's not a
you know it's not a it's not nothing you
know
not a crime to be disassociated uh so
it's okay to within reason and um
and so if it just happens in meditation
maybe it also has an
helpful function sometimes there's a
break or there is a kind of relaxation
that
can happen with some disassociation so
not to be in a hurry to make it wrong to
do that
and then but if it starts being a
problem or you suspect
that it is a problem then
you know the really the focus focus on
the body
i find is one way to kind of work
through disassociation because
dissociation is very
more often than not i associated with
not being connected to the body
and so
and then getting professional help i
think is good if you really think it's a
big issue it's really good to
find a professional help there are now
in some areas you know therapists who
know about
mindfulness and buddhism and meditation
and you know that can be particularly
helpful
for people meditating
um
after the 16th step this would be the
last one after the 16 steps would you
make
letting go the next theme yeah that that
certainly can be uh
the um but we'll see it letting go is
built into the anapanasati
and so next week we'll get to the end of
each tetrad
there is some quality of letting go in
the family of letting go
and so um we'll see next week when we
get to the eighth step that
has letting go and the first step
uh the end the first tetrad is relaxing
or tranquilizing
the bodily formations and that's that's
in the family of letting go
and so at the end of each tetrad there's
a letting go kind of
quality so we'll do some of that here
well thank you for your questions and
i'll read the rest of the questions and
so i get some sense of your concerns and
and i appreciate this chance to
be this way with you and i look forward
to uh
next week and continuing on this process
thank you very much