okay welcome to imc's monday night sitting and dharma talk
all right i assume that things are going okay so um uh we're going to begin
this uh session uh with um about half an hour of a guided
meditation and then um i'll share some reflections
um based on a topic and that i bring in today
so let's begin the sitting
maybe take a moment and to find a posture that's supportive of meditative practice
i'm aware that today is the first night right after the full moon
night since yesterday yesterday was a full moon night
and so in some sense this is kind of an auspicious auspicious night and so
on may we all have an excellent night or an auspicious night
sitting together practicing together
so maybe just take a few moments to settle in into wherever you're
meditating in
the first few moments just to allow the body and mind to arrive
arrive into here and now
so often useful to begin by taking some long deep breath
as you breathe out just allow the body to relax
feeling the connection of your legs and feet
with the ground the floor and the chairs or the cushions
having a sense of groundedness grounded on earth
as the lower half of the body began to settle and rest on earth
allow the upper half of the body
to rest and settle as well
can you feel the weight of the arms
hands
let the arms hang naturally
maybe the torso is upright
and neck is aligned
with the spine like an extension of the
spine
allow the muscles on the face to soften
feel sensations on the top of the head
on the back of the head
just do a quick scan from the top of the head all the way down to
the bottom of your feet inviting ease
inviting relaxation
and softening
and then momentarily if you're ready
can turn our awareness
to the movements of our breathing
that maybe is rising and falling of the belly
or the expansion and contraction of the chest
resting your attention on the movements of a breathing
without trying too hard
simply resting like putting a gentle hand
i'm petting the little baby
stroking the baby
soft gentle awareness on the breath
the concerns of the past and future
maybe can be faded into the background
allow the foreground to be filled with the experience that's happening
here and now in this body
maybe tinkling on the feet
warmth in your palms
coolness of the breath
there's a secret life force unfolding right here
right now
now you can rest your attention your awareness
right here in the whole body
it's as if the awareness is
filled imbued in the body itself
there is nothing to do to be aware
by simply receiving the experience of the body
and experience of the mind in the restful field of awareness
maybe the sound is known
sound of my voice
ambience sound
silence in between
vibrations in the belly
i thought
tightness on the forehead
everything everything that's happening can simply be received at known
and pleasant experience
unpleasant experience
a moment of doubt
a moment of wanting
grasping
everything can happen on their own terms
this kind gentle awareness
simply receiving
no need to fix
boundless allowing
some experience may be extremely challenging
getting to know this through the embodied experience
persistent swirling emotions
how does it feel in the body
are you aware
if the mind wandered away it's never too late to start again
right now this moment
mindfulness front and center right now
if the mind wandered away just know that this temple of this body
always has a door wide open for you
always welcome
to enter and return
to the temple of his body
seriously
in this last few moments of our sitting
i'm going to read this poem versus from a middle length discourses
in the title of this poem is an auspicious day
maybe you can listen to those words while you're you sit
allows words to drop into your awareness
however it might touch you connect with you
allow it to be received in the wide open field of awareness
and if something bubbles up receive that too
an auspicious night this is a translated by gil fransto
the buddha said don't chase the past or long for the future
the past is left behind the future is not yet reached
right where it is have insight into whatever phenomena is present
not fartering and not agitated
by knowing it one develops the mind
ardently do what should be done today who knows death may come tomorrow
there is no bargaining with mortality and his great army
whoever dwells thus ardent active day and night
is says the peaceful sage one who has an auspicious day
and the other translation of the auspicious day is a single excellent night
[Music]
so welcome to our monday night dharma talk
and so what i had in mind today is to maybe unpack this poem um
a little bit together and just reflect upon this poem that i just
i read
so i said that this poem sometimes and the title is translated as a single
excellent night or an auspicious day
the first time when i read this poem and i was very touched
without knowing anything about this poem the context of it and the significance of it i took this
poem with me to various locations i read this poem to
the dharma system who's in the in the hospital bed
and i took this poem and read it at a memorial service
and i took this poem to my heart i memorized it and reflected upon this
and so maybe i'll read the discipline one more time and then we'll kind of unpack this
together and i'll unpack one stanza at a time
it's an auspicious day the buddha said don't chase the past
or long for the future the past is left behind the future is not yet
reached right where it is have insight into whatever phenomenon
is present not fattering and not agitated by knowing it
one develops the mind ardently do what should be done today
who knows death may come tomorrow there is no bargaining with
mortality and his great army whoever dwells thus ardent
active day and night is says the peaceful sage
one who has an auspicious day
so so what does this mean to not chase the past or long for
the future past is left behind the future is not
yet reached
we all probably have experiences of this and where we might be chasing the past or lying for
you for the future right and for me
right away and what becomes a vivid is you know for
most of us when we are getting older and older
we chase the youth that we used to have
and we really long for the use where we had before
and name is pandemic it's probably not hard to feel this kind of
lying for the past are the future and the vacation
the vacations that you used to have where you can travel to different places
and we can be chasing the past in this way you know whatever
accomplishments that we may have had in our earlier careers and work and job
family or maybe even you know you were the dance champion in
high school and so in the suta and this is the
majimanika yeah 1-1 and let me see 131
where this poem shows up and the buddha explained this
how does one chase after the past and he said one gets carried away
with the delight of in the past i had such a form or such a
body in the past i had such a feeling in the past i had such a perception in
the past i had such a thought fabrication or mental formation
in the past i had such a consciousness this is called chasing after the past
i don't know if everyone is familiar with this particular formula
in that the buddha is pointing at how one gets stuck
in the past and getting carried away by it in this ways that are related to
ourselves through this this list that's called the five aggregates
these are the things that we often identify as ourselves
i mean mine this is me
and i'm struck by the key word that's been used here by the buddha and that
is and he defines how one chases the past
by that one would take delight in the past
in this form of a taking delight it could be you know and really getting um
consumed by the past in that you know that maybe pleasant experiences
we had before and who we were before in the past
and this taking delight could also happen even when it's
unpleasant it experiences unpleasant history
we could be defined by those and when we're being defined by them
we get hooked by the past
even when we do not like them
you know sometimes i can see you know and sometimes i had a certain
recognition that you know i used to be this way i really didn't didn't like it but somehow being really
annoyed by it i actually get hooked by how i and how i get myself identified
with those and so this is taking delight in
the past this way or that way that we how we are and how does one
not chase after the past and the buddha continued by saying well
if one does not get get carried away with the delight in the past in that
and i in the past i had this kind of a form or the feelings and perception or the
mental formations or the consciousness and then this is called not chasing after the past
and so the formula is quite simple you know if we stop being consumed to stop taking delight
in the past and we no longer have that kind of um
[Music] uh force in us to begin to chase the past
anymore so so there's a recognition that there is a possibility there is a
choice not to get swept away in the past
so how do we really do that
in our meditation practice in our mindfulness practice
when i began to notice that one is being hooked
by the memory and by the history by the stories that were lived in the past and that's when we began to
have a choice well we see wow you know here
here i am but i'm hooked by this story and i recognize this is
happening when we begin to recognize that this is happening
this is where um detaching from
being taking delight in them or detaching from being
attracted by the past the story of the past
we can begin to loosen the hook with it
and often what happens is when we're being mindful
we can for example rest our attention in the body shifting from the stories of
the past to what's happening in our body then the memory and the images that came
from the past can simply become kind of a
ripple that to flow through in our awareness
there's no need for the story of the memory and the past to take a foot
in us so it's possible that you know our mind may have a thoughts of
the past or the stories but they don't have to be a problem
it's when we begin to take delight in them and really being consumed by them that we get swept away
but when we're aware we can see the memories as simply memories
they flow through like clouds in the wide open sky
and similarly how does one long for the future a buddha used a
similar language no one one gets carried away with the delight
in the future you know i might become this way i might become that way
and that this is becoming this is what in the suta it says this is called
placing expectations on the future
we all have this kind of experience in our own lived experience right
and maybe um
there are lots of examples that we can take
when we're not comfortable with what is happening here and now sometimes
we construct a future in our head
and then we hook onto and this kind of constructed experience and we
really go after that and to pull us out of what is happening in the present
experience
and so there's a form of uh expectations in the future here's a construction of
um it is a form of a mental construction
and we can believe in them so strongly that they become almost real for us
and similarly the buddha kind of explained you know how not to place expectations
in the future and and the the same formula was
prescribed by not do not get carried away with the delight
in the future
and it's easier said and then dumb you know we all know that and it's very
easy to fall into this a form of taking delight but what it takes is to become
recognized that this is happening you know maybe expect expectation or
projection is happening and allow ourselves to then rest into the
field of awareness to simply notice
projection being projection
and planning being planning our expectations being expectations
sometimes they're really momentary maybe they're just one or two thoughts they come and go
just like a snap of the finger but if a feed onto them you know
continue to plan and tell our stories and
and this can become something really big take us away
but when we began to see
this expectations the simply being expectations the thoughts as the thoughts and there
is a real sense of lightness in all of this experiences
and so the next stanza the buddha brought us back to where where it is here and now
why right where it is have insight into whatever phenomena is present
not fattering and not agitated by knowing it one develops mine
and disappointing at this is this moment is where we live
the present moment the present experience the present phenomenon is
where we live and this is where insight
can happen and this is where we practice this is the field of our practice
but very interesting though in the susuta it says that even in this
practicing with the present experience there can be two ways
and one way is a skillful and one way is not very skillful
so when i first direct this i was kind of puzzled wow you know i thought being present was you know what would be all
good and fine um but there can be a way that one will be being present and
we there can be still unskillfulness in there so how is that possible
and so let's let's take a look at this so what happens is with respect to the
present experiences the present qualities an unskilled person can take whatever
is arising as i me my
so what happened so whatever is happening
[Music] in one way an unskillful way
is that we take that this is me for example right now if there is a
little moment of a sadness that happened in the field of emotion
one way to relate to this sadness momentary sadness said
i'm a sad person i've always been sad there is so much sorrow in me
now what happens we began to construct
myself in this simple moment of sadness
a moment of grief
oh my god i am really miserable i've always been
very miserable i don't know how to get out of this
and this is what the buddha is pointing at we can make self out of the momentary
experience that's happening and when we do this what happens is we get
hardened into this experiences
and this becomes more permanent than what it is
and most of the time our emotions flows up and down this way and that way
throughout the day but we can oftentimes pick on to hook onto
certain forms of emotion and make it ourselves i remember
um gail fransto sometimes would teach that it is more skillful
to be situational centric rather than
self-centric or you know in another word in this particular suta maybe we can say
it's a phenomenon centric rather than self-centric whatever phenomena a situation that
comes about in our present lived experience
we simply see this as the situation or the phenomena
and this is a skillful way of being with our experiences
and the self-centric approach would be turning everything that is happening into something related to
i me and mine
and for example you know if you drop a plate on the floor
maybe the immediate the reaction would be i am so sloppy
but is it is it really all about you i use it to just oh this is a situation
that just happened
so i get identified with the situation what happens is there can be a lot
of dukkha a lot of stress that comes along with it
our experiences can become stuck and no longer flows
like the clouds in the in the sky
and so the opposite and that if if we're not taking this phenomenon
and the situations as i mean mine and there can be simple transient
changing experiences are rising and passing
and when this happens there can be a quality of not being wavered or shaken
by agitation by fartering the agitation happens when there is a
center like the center of the self
when there is no center of self the agitation cannot shake anything
there's nothing to shake
so when one develops the mind in this way
mind will no longer be shaky or restless
and so the poem goes on by encouraging this
and so the the next stanza says ardently do what should be done today
who knows death may come tomorrow there's no bargaining with mortality
and his great army
i don't know what more is to be said about this particular line because it is true
we don't know we don't know when death may come
it may not even be tomorrow maybe next moment
and i know this can be can sound
untrue unreal but we really don't know
you know oftentimes you know our intellectual mind understands that you
know when everybody gets born and death will be part of it i think
and one of my teachers philip moffat sometimes would like to quote his
teacher john sumato and that birth
has a death as life sentence and it's it's true and yet
we often live our lives with the complete denial that this might happen to us it might
happen anytime
and so the buddha knows this and knows the preciousness of a
practicing in this moment here and now
and so argently do what should be done today ardently do what should be done right
now because we don't know
and the poem ended with this line whoever dwells thus ardent
active day and night yes says the peaceful sage
one who has an auspicious day
i love this definition because oftentimes we associate auspicious day with some
i don't know special days like yesterday i know it's a full moon day
and even in the buddhist tradition and maybe many different spiritual
traditions full moon days is considered to be auspicious day
but the buddha had a different definition for this
whoever dwells thus ardent active day and night practicing ardently
day and night this
says the peaceful sage is the one who has an auspicious day
i love it because this makes um the practice very accessible we don't
have to wait for some special day in order to practice
this day if you practice here and now it's an auspicious day
the other translation a single excellent night or an excellent day
and so we just need to become become fully present become aware
of what is happening cultivating our mind skillfully
seeing what's true right in front of us
and this is where the piece lies and this is where the freedom is found
i'm gonna close tonight by just reading this poem one more time maybe by now the few lines
even sinked in in you in some way
the buddha said don't chase the past or long for the future the past
is left behind the future is not yet reached
right where it is have insight into whatever phenomenon is present
not fattering and not agitated by knowing it one develops the mind
ardently do what should be done today who knows death may come tomorrow there is
no bargaining with mortality and his great army whoever
dwells thus ardent active day and night is
says the peaceful sage one who has an auspicious day
may you all have an excellent night
so take good care
[Music]
you