okay all right so formal hello and welcome to all of you
dear friends wherever in the world you are whatever the time zone might be
happy to be with you happy that the sangha is assembled
and we get to practice together how sweet how special how special
so so for the theme for uh today's practice
um yeah i wanted to um
invite us to consider the juxtaposition of
the times which is what's happening with the new varian the omicron variant and
the world being on edge and again seems like we're heading into
another period of challenge in the world so and we are we've already been in the
midst of a challenging period and it's about to get even more challenging so not to turn away from that not to turn
away from that and also to acknowledge that meta
loving kindness good will for ourselves and others is a resource in tough times is a
resource is a refuge is there refuge that soothes and calms the heart and
mind for ourselves and for others so that we can be more
available for ourselves and for others so it's at both end it's a both end
so that's the theme [Music] like the consideration i'd like to bring in for
for our practice this evening not to turn away from the challenges in the world
and yet knowing that trusting that our practice of mental good will for ourselves and
for others is is refreshing is is renewing is a
refuge really it's it's it's a our hearts refuge and we can offer that
stability that care that warmth both to ourselves and to everyone else in the world even
if we may not we many people we might have contact with and speak with and they might be ah
very upset and in challenging times um experiencing challenges and for us to
just be stable with with kindness just the sense
of stability ah openheartedness with kindness
so so that's the setting that's the background
so let's let's delve in dear ones let's delve in together so i'd like to
invite you to land to arrive
allah arrive more fully arrive in this moment in this body
taking refuge the simplicity of this moment letting go
of whatever has come whatever might have come before this
whatever busyness whatever stress or worry just for a
moment bowing to it saying thank you i'm going to take
some minutes of refuge to refresh my heart to refresh myself
to connect more deeply with my humanity
to connect the capacity of this heart
to be tender
to be vulnerable if it needs to be to be held with care and love
and rest
landing landing in the body
feeling our feet on the ground
grounded well-rooted
as if our feet are kissing the earth
as far as if our feet are kissing the earth
i am here this blessed earth this
these blessed feet
it's magic of this life
here here
letting the sit bones embrace
cushion the chair
letting go of the weight
ah releasing releasing
releasing what you're holding
you're holding onto in your thoughts
ah releasing arriving more fully here i'm here
giving giving yourself fully to this moment of refuge
to this beautiful [Music] amazing
now-ness right here
mystery
relaxing releasing into
this river this river it's always now time passes and yet it's always now
as if you're releasing relaxing floating
being held
by healing nourishing waters
let the stream carry you lovingly nothing you need to do
or be
let the soft animal of your body relax
let your heart relax
receiving the lullaby of the breath
in the lower abdomen
floating floating
if thoughts judgments
whatever is not helpful right now arises
release it release it into this healing river
opening your hand don't need to hold on to any of them
ah yourself be nourished and held
just this breath being received
soft in a soft relaxed body
healing waters healing waters
healing waters of meta nourishing feeling health
the more you soak
perfect temperature of the waters
more tightness tension [Music] challenging thoughts
the more they wash away gently gently the more you soak
there is a simile called the simile of the cloth in the teachings of the buddha
like a cloth
it's being soaked with stains slowly slowly
feeling water seep in
as if as if supporting nourishing every cell
every cell of your body your heart your mind
it's okay it's okay
i am held
it's okay i'm held i'm health and kindness
and care and safety
realizing knowing
this healing soothing waters the river flowing
outside is also flowing inside
nature outside nature inside
inside this body heart mind
nourished from the healing waters there is a river that runs through you
a river that runs through me
a nourishing loving caring river
it soothes
nourishes cares for
here here now now it's okay
wherever internally in the body the mind the
heart
there are challenges maybe no challenges in this moment
the river flows
let it flow don't get in its way
let it flow you don't have to make it flow
it does so on itself simply don't get in the way
relax release
let this body this heart this mind be held
externally internally in good will
mental care
if the phrasing support you're staying with the feeling of menta
please bring them in if you like to stay with the feeling
alone that's fine too
allow for one round of the phrases
may i may this being who is me
be safe safe and protected
from inner and outer harm
fully well-knowing that events
life so many of them are uncontrollable beyond my control
ungovernable and yet i wish myself with kindness this safety
without attaching to it offering it to myself as a gift
may i be safe
may i be happy and have joy in my heart
may i be healthy and strong as much as it may be available to me
offering this gift this wish to myself
wishing myself well
and may my life unfold with ease
feeling the river of care nourishing river of menta
flowing flowing through your heart through your body through your mind
nourishing enlivening healing soothing
river inside river outside
knowing trusting that water is this cooling something is hot or burning
water cools something is cold shivering water warms
brings comfort
see what is needed see what is needed
now if you wish
bringing to mind
some beings in your life for whom it's easy for you to feel meta and care
as if you were sharing these healing waters from your heart
that are both inside outside no difference
between the meta that's inside and outside
maybe they too are joining you in this healing body of water
whatever works for you whatever imagery it could be a river
could be a lake it could be a safe healing ocean with
undulating waves warm [Music]
soothing whatever whatever might work for you
or maybe a warm bath
the healing the soothing the meta the river running through you
is fed by this body of water and also it feeds it feeds this body of water
that your loved ones are held in
don't try too hard let it be whatever is easiest
may you all may all of us be safe
may all of us including yourself together with
people who are dear to you may all of us
be happy
may all of us be healthy
may all of us have ease
for the last minute or two of this practice period
and bodies of water rivers evaporate into the air
they become clouds they become rain [Music]
continuing with the healing waters metaphor imagining is
soothing healing [Music] meta-filled rain [Music]
all over the ears for all beings everywhere
this planet of ours hurting
so many beings hurting the pandemic
climate change etc etc
so many being soothed
cared for with this meta reign
yourself included may all beings everywhere
including ourselves
[Music] the refuge
of a loving [Music] kind heart
a peaceful heart may all beings including ourselves
be free
[Music] foreign
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so we have some time
for reflections questions comments
and new reports from the field how the practice was for you
how you're doing what worked what didn't work
it's all welcome the invitation is for you to share your
practice as a gift to others when you share your insights or challenges
as you well know by now it supports others
mima please
thank you um i thought it was so appropriate tonight with this meditation because
you see what's going on in the world and sometimes
hearing people speak you know i know i hurt for them
and i felt reminded of mehta being the antidote to suffering
and uh that's kind of what i was floating and bathing in
um as an antidote to what we see going on in the world right now so i thought it was
a very appropriate thing for tonight thank you thank you mima yeah
and with so much suffering you know meta trans gets transformed into compassion
compassion holds compassion can hold the suffering it
just it's uh it becomes um it's
as you're using the word antidote it's yes that it's the medicine maybe that's
what i would use it's the medicine yeah the medicine it doesn't negate it but it just it's the medicine it's the self
beautiful thank you mima yeah ah i appreciate your reflections
louisa on youtube appreciates the beautiful water meditation
she went to a beautiful waterfall she says and was very synchronistic for her with
gratitude feeling held in peace lovely thank you
bill says thank you for for the peace of mind ah delighted to hear there's a sense of
peace so
how about we turn since i don't see any comments coming
how about we turn to uh small groups
uh small sangha practice and um
we when we come back we'll have some more time for reflections so
you know by now how precious how important it is to have
a community to have sangha even if it may be
spending just a few minutes checking in with fellow travelers it is so
um important it is so nourishing it's it's um to be to to feed them with the river
of our meta and to be nourished by their river of mettas so take care of yourselves take care of
each other and and i'll open the rooms in a moment
and if you can't stay please do and if you have to go not out of fear of talking with other folks but if you have
to go it's okay to take care of yourselves take care of each other okay
so i'm opening the rooms now here we go the rooms will close in about 10 seconds
so we'll wait for everyone to come back
okay everyone is back welcome back folks so
[Music] so we have some more time for reflections
questions comments what came up um please
i would love to hear [Laughter]
bill says our group was too relaxed to talk [Laughter] i love it i love it
[Laughter]
you know that's what happens when you soak in healing waters like you've been soaking it's like wow i've just been to
the hot tub of metal oh my goodness christine says ours too
oh did i did i just put you all into a yeah
what what should i call it a meditative kind of oh that that is too cute that is too
sweet hey parker so dave says that's what i
was saying oh my god we talked about cat videos oh my god
this is too funny you guys would anybody like to to to share this they put their
voice put their voice into um into the room or just be in chat maybe
you don't feel like talking i don't blame you i'm pretty chilled myself now
[Music]
you know we might just end early tonight and go take a bath a really you know a meta bath and continue to
practice meta in in the bath being held in healing waters and feeling your own
healing and and loving energy of meta any takers for any any last minute
comments or reflections besides that you're too chilled to talk
jerry please the comment uh filming on what's been said but the word
that struck me was the lullaby of the breath that when you said that uh
uh combined with letting go of various
perhaps what ifs and butts clubs uh you might call it um
it particularly struck me the lullaby of the breath which i hadn't sort of thought about
and i was just like oh it's like a chiropractic moment just like oh i can
let go of this stuff and so it speaks to what everyone else was i
thought wow this is a powerful thought a lullaby of a breath so
that's about to say thank you jerry thanks for reflecting that back and highlighting that the
lullaby of the breath yeah you caught that yes and others too
it feels like that right it can feel when you tune into it there's just
lullaby quality the soothing calming
just so nourishing yeah it's all right here
yeah what did you say though but if what was it bud ifs and something
else club
oh you're still on me well i heard a patient say to me that what ifs and
butts club what ifs and butts club i like that what's this
butt you know uh so i like that that what if some butts club so i thought let
go of the what is some butts club and just fall into the lullaby of the breath wow i think that that's a great quote
let go of the what ifs in butts club and let that go into release into the
lullaby of the breath all right i'm gonna write that down i love it we co-created that jerry or
fall into the lullaby like instead of like a hammock you know i had
a hammock okay i want to go take a nap now
for those of you on the east coast this is perfect timing
it's sweet thanks jerry thanks so much any other last
minute reflections before we bring our session to our close we've got a couple minutes
thank you thank you for that message fred um so thank you walt
let's bring our lovely session to a close it's so nice
to see you it's so nice to be with you again i've missed you
um it just gives me so much joy and delight to be back together
practicing what a lovely community yay
every single one of you every single one of us is
is important your presence makes this community so
thank you deep deep bows of appreciation so may you all be well safe happy
may all beings everywhere be free
thank you