so the topic of today is the samadhi
factor of awakening
and
tomorrow's topic monday will be
equanimity
and we are one day behind because of the
technological glitch that happened on
tuesday
and um we will
um and then
for the youtube we'll be back meeting
again at 7 00 a.m
california time tomorrow
so samadhi is uh commonly translated as
concentration in english
the the prolific translator
tanissero tunisirobiku
an american who lives in san diego
he um translates it as serenity
and so it's a very different feeling
between
concentration and serenity
when it's translated as serenity it then
raises the question how's that different
than tranquility
the fact of awakening that's listed just
before
samadhi
and i see that um
that samadhi is characterized by
stillness
serenity for me is characterized so i
don't know if the english
english word serenity and tranquility
are maybe
almost complete synonyms of each other
but if you look at the pali words the
ancient language words
that um pasadi the word for
tranquility i think has more of a
connotations of
brightness of
of a kind of a bright quality a soft
quality
a very light feeling the body can feel
very light and soft when there's
tranquility
whereas in samadhi the
the the when the primary characteristic
could be more a stillness than samadhi
there's a very of deep stillness things
have gotten very still
the greater the samadhi the more
stillness there is
and um and also with with somebody it's
a very clear
the stillness of it this sometimes can
feel very strong
there's a strength can be a strength to
it at times
and the mind has is not destructible
mind won't wander away at all just
it's like the mind is kind of sometimes
there's a feeling people describe as
being
locked in in samadhi it's so strong and
the stillness was
boom we're locked in and then the mind's
not going to move anywhere
into anything whereas in a tranquility
the mind
very tranquil and peaceful but it's not
really 100
still maybe i associate um
tranquility as i did mentioned yesterday
about with
a quiet very peaceful morning lake
completely placid and still not a ripple
of wind on it
and um and the morning you know the
morning light is just very clear and
bright and still
very stillness in the air the birds
haven't come out yet
and um and so this but this body of
water it's very flat
and um and so
so tranquility is you know
it's kind of like a body of water and i
associate it with
much more with the body than the mind
somehow
and then um in samadhi
um at least for me it is it's uh it can
be very embodied
feeling that comes with it but it's much
more like
the stillness of the mind there it's not
like a body of water
but it's more like the stillness of
space
and then where there's
you know everything is still in in space
space in and of itself is stillness
uh kind of and uh and there's but
there's
space like if you look up at the scott
knight at the sky you know space has no
boundaries it
goes on forever it's you can you don't
you can say that space is soft i guess
but
you know it's not a quality that has
softness or lightness as part of it
it's more porous or just
it's the openness or something so the my
and i associate samadhi a little bit
more with the mind becoming still
and porous open has no boundaries to it
and um but you know definitely it's
landed it's here
and then it landed here and then
sometimes the place sense of a landing
place disappears
it's just here but with this openness
kind of an openness and it's not exactly
embodied
body sometimes disappears in deep
samadhi
so the primary function of samadhi
one of the primary functions of
tranquility here is to support samadhi
and so when the body is tranquil
it really supports the mind to become
stiller
it's kind of like if you try to land
that
you know drone on top of a moving train
that's going along fast
it's you know it's a little hard but if
the train stops
then you can land it on the roof of the
train perhaps
so the same thing if you try to land in
a body that's all agitated
it's hard for the mind to land and be
here
so that tranquility supports it creates
a nice home and nourishment and support
for this to be settled to be
settled on our experience more than
being focused on our experience
the idea of of focus in samadhi
sometimes this idea of one pointedness
maybe that's a good metaphor a good good
for some people that really works today
okay i'm really going to be focused one
pointed on something
but i think of it this this so-called
one-pointedness
as a gathering together so all of
ourselves
are all of us is centered on something
it's being centered on the breathing
and so uh rather than being one pointed
with the mind
it's coming to rest at the center point
of the concentric circles of our life
and we're just really right here so with
the breath completely with a breath for
example if the
focus is the breath but there's more
feeling of
being centered on it than it is being
focused on it at least that's how it is
for me
the buddha said that the nourishment
for samadhi
is serenity and the word there now is
samatha
so it's not the same word as samadhi but
samatha in particular has that i
in my rudimentary understanding of
poly etymology is that it's um
even closer to the city of stillness of
landings
stan taking a stand where we're really
still and quiet
so it so it's a kind of serenity of
stillness not the serenity of us
of of softness and lightness
and so the nourishment of samadhi is
is stillness and that means that uh
to be nourish yourself with stillness
so to notice the places where the you
are still where there is stillness
and um and perhaps that's within
there's a woman nearby a local woman who
wrote a
compose this she's a mindfulness teacher
and she did a little cd for children
called the still
quiet place within i love that little
title
the still quiet place within and so to
uh to recognize and find a place of
stillness
but not that we're being held still or
kind of a trapped being still but
something that actually feels nourishing
it feels wholesome
and if you're able to touch into that
inner place of
nourishing stillness allow yourself to
be nourished by it
and this is one of the wonderful
characteristics of these teachings of
the buddha around meditation
it's not just kind of this dreary
dry you know focus on the breath and
stay with the breath and count the
breath just
you know zero in on the breath and and
um
like a little technique of you know of
i don't know of mental focus
it's a it's uh it's a
it's a settling into allowing and
touching
into all kinds of ways in which we feel
nourished wholesome feel the
wholesomeness of something feels a
nourishment of something
feel the goodness of something allow
ourselves to
we're allowed to feel joy we're allowed
to feel happiness
and one of the characteristics of the
the buddhist community in the time of
the buddha that apparently was a little
bit
unusual for the religious circles of his
time
was that the buddhist disciples were
smiling a lot always kind of kind of a
joyful group
so it's not meant to be a grim practice
this meditation
don't take meditation too seriously
meditation is much too
important to take seriously because
uh if you take it too seriously i think
you kind of like squeeze some of the
life out of it and
makes it harder to feel the nourishment
and the and the
wholesomeness and the joy the pleasure
of it all
not to indulge in those things and not
to hold on to them and expect them and
huff and puff for it but
in the very even in the smallest ways
in the course of a day or in the course
of meditation
you're allowed to tap in and discover
the places that feel wholesome
places field where there's inner
goodness nourishment
each of the seven factors has a
nourishment for it
and um so um
so what how would it what how does
samadhi come about
if that's the orientation not this one
pointed focus
but rather imbibing
the nourishment that's here even if it's
just like if
one percent of yourself feels has this
good
nourishing quality um
then um maybe that's worth a lot more
than the five percent of your of who you
are that's neurotic
but if you give a hundred percent of
your attention
to your five percent that's neurotic
then you're not going to be nourished
but if you give
a hundred percent of your attention to
the one percent that's
wholesome then you can be nourished by
that and then things begin to relax and
open
and something like that i don't know
what percentage you are
of all these things but uh
chances are that if you're a regular
human being
that you probably give more attention to
what's not nourishing
than to what is nourishing and
so sit down meditate in the nourishing
stillness
the nourishing awareness the nourishing
tranquility the nourishing joy
the nourishing mindfulness
so samadhi the samadhi factor of
awakening
and when that it becomes well developed
meaning they're well nourished by it
supported by it to feel the goodness of
it
that creates the wonderful conditions
for the mind to have equanimity
to develop equanimity so it's not
enforced equanimity where you hold
yourself still
but it's an equineme that comes because
there's a feeling of being really
settled and
at ease and in this nourishing place of
stillness
so the so the samadhi factor of
awakening
so until we do equanimity tomorrow those
of you coming back
for that you might
spend some extra time today
seeing if you can become more familiar
with whatever capacity whatever
ability you have to discover
a nourishing inner stillness quiet
unwaveringness unagitatedness
within and see what it's like to
let yourself enjoy it and be nourished
may samadhi be a delight for you
thank you