so it's one of the i think
wonderful things that simplicity
is one of the
hallmarks or one of the characteristics
of this meditation practice
and sometimes that's not quite seen
because
sometimes teachings teachers like me
might give all kinds of instructions and
it might seem like there's a lot of
instructions to keep in mind
a teacher i i knew when i was in india
named
manindra menindraji he was a student of
many of the early western
practitioners of vipassona
he had many wonderful sayings and one of
them was
if it's not simple it's not vipasuna
and and so the idea is to keep it simple
so how is it that this practice is
simple
it's simple by relying on
the simplicity of how we can be aware of
something and
to be aware maybe in the simplest
possible way
and and uh and for each of us
and each of us at different times what
it means to be aware
will be different and so that this part
of the fascination of it all is to see
how the uh what what we call attention
or awareness
shifts and changes um depending on how
settled we are how focused we are
and and the kind of attention that's
useful in any given moment
but the guideline is to always keep it
simple
and partly that means not to be
striving for it to be different
not to be trying to engineer your
meditation to get it just right
it's partly to partly means to
not be trying to avoid experience and
get away from something
is not trying to overthink the
experience or think our way into
something and
trying to figure out analytically even
what's the right way
and it's also not trying to do too much
at once
the idea is to kind of
be content with just being
now just being is not the end game of
meditation
but there's kind of a reference point
for keeping it simple
rather than a lot of doing there's a lot
of being
and in that being in the simplicity to
allow
of whatever the native awareness is
allows us to know that we're in the
present moment to
be there and surface and show itself
because the mind drifts off in thought a
lot and is caught up in thought
that then to
one of the things that many people find
useful and it's not necessarily useful
for everyone
and then teachers can give other
instructions
but um is to the simplicity of breathing
and uh the breathing is kind of like the
the
sometimes you use like the the anchor
line or the
tether or the support for staying in the
present moment
breathing is always in the present
moment it has a rhythm to it
it's not a fixed experience it's a
flowing or moving or
changing experience and there's
something about attention
following a moving changing phenomena
that makes it easier to be relaxed in
the present moment
kind of like if we're watching a uh
we're sitting
under under a tree relaxing
in the shade of a warm day watching
maybe the river go by
and we're kind of just watching the
ripples and the little wavelets and
the currents this flow and flow and
we're not
studying it intensely we're just kind of
allowing the experience to come we see
it maybe clearly
and there's something about that
movement where the mind doesn't fixate
on something but just allows things to
flow
it keeps the eyes soft and relaxed and
kind of moving along with it
that part of the reason why it can be
very relaxing and people can spend
long periods of time just watching a
river go that by or
watching the waves on the beach come and
go
or watch a fire just a burn in the
changing patterns of the flames as we
watch the
little fire the fireplace perhaps
and so it's that movement of breathing
the coming and going of the inhale
they're coming and going in the exhale
that that can can work for some people a
very nice way
of just keeping us in the present moment
and then of course for many of us
especially if you're starting that can
be we start getting
more complicated than we need to be and
and part of simplicity is to relax
around making it complicated you don't
don't hold up simplicity as is something
to strive for and
and to engineer into but rather
kind of take yourself as you are in a
certain way
meditation is a come as your party so
come as you
are and sit down and allow yourself to
be how you are
and and that allowing
and settle into it and that and uh and
the art is not to
let yourself be as you are and continue
and have your thoughts galloping away
but allow yourself to be as you are and
then really settle
into the the direct experience the
embody the living experience
of how you are so there's a turning of
attention
inward to the body and and what is the
embodied experience of all this
what's the embodied experience of our
mood our emotional state our mental
state or
physical state and
and because it's the simplicity of being
has a lot to do with what our experience
here and now in the present moment the
body is always in the present moment
the breathing is always in the present
moment
so coming here and settling into it and
then as we settle into it
at some point to tune it
become attuned to or align ourselves
with the experience of breathing
and and to be with that simply
sometimes we're controlling the breath
sometimes the breath feels tight and
constricted or held in some ways
not particularly comfortable and so the
experience of simplicity is just
allow that to be and breathe with that
breathe through it
uh make room for it to be uncomfortable
or controlled
because that making a room for giving
breathing room
is part of the way of keeping things
simple and allowing
something inside which is not yourself
your own engineering efforts your own
kind of try mechanisms of trying to fix
and change
something inside of you will begin to
unfold
um begin to unwind will begin to release
begin to kind of find itself and
so that's one of the things that
the in the principle of simplicity
is uh trust the simplicity of just being
with experience
trust trust your experience if you're
present for it
even it's even if it's not necessarily
ideal or comfortable or something
and then something within begins to open
unravel relax
on its own there's a very strong
momentum in our body
in our in our whole being
towards the release of tension
towards the release of holding and
tension and pushing and pressure
and and so part of this giving breathing
room
to ourselves and allowing things to be
is in fact this movement towards
allowing for this settling this
releasing this
freeing that can happen
when we just keep showing up and being
present
so maybe what i've said this morning
that was already too complicated
so i apologize but it's all
kind of an effort to try to point to
just being simple and maybe the
breathing can help you with that
simplicity just be
with the breathing trust the breathing
i like the expression entrust yourself
with breathing
and uh and um and then it doesn't have
to you know it doesn't make me doesn't
look so sophisticated doesn't look so
wonderfully spiritual but to keep it
simple
and in that simplicity uh of being with
experience being with the simplicity of
it um
feeling the embodied experience of
breathing
that something will begin to settle
something will begin to open
something will happen that um is the
journey of meditation practice
so um
so thank you all very much for today and
we'll continue these 45-minute sittings
uh this week
all the way through to um through sunday
so
seven days not just the weekday days and
for those of you who are available to
come on the weekend
we'll continue and
may you have a wonderful day and may the
simplicity
of meditation support you
in giving the gift of simplicity to
those people that you encounter today
thank you
foreign