so good morning everyone and welcome to this
monday as we begin our week on the theme of mindfulness of emotions
and it's one of the very important areas of mind of
mindfulness to beware to be mindful of our own emotions and to be mindful aware of the emotions
of others as well and to
learn the art the skill of recognizing emotions
knowing how to be mindful of emotions and learning how to discover what liberation
is in relationship to emotions so for now i'd like to say that i
i think of emotions as as a belonging to a place in human beings
that can be quite tender and that uh the
careful attention careful caring attention taking time to slow down and
be with these things that are to say the moods the emotions the
mental states that kind of kind of have a huge influence on our lives
that we slow down and really start recognizing more deeply what's going on with them and
where they arise from from under the surface and and where they um
it's a tender place and so as we begin this week on emotions
remember that and remember to hold yourself with care with compassion
and and generosity lots of generosity to how you feel
and slowly through this practice of mindfulness of emotions we are
increasing our capacity to be with emotions the whole range of
them difficult ones and beautiful ones and and also
increasing our capacity to be with them in a way that's free
a kind of freedom that allows the best of the emotions to thrive inside of us
and allows that which is difficult and maybe debilitating around emotions to
relax to settle away to no longer be limiting us in our lives
so today's topic is uh relaxation
and what we learn about relaxation of the body
has a lot to do with our ability to relax with emotions around emotions
and it isn't so much today that i'm going to emphasize relaxing emotions like maybe to make
them relax away but rather to relax around them to soften the boundaries of them and
any reactivity or holding or preferences we have in relationship to
them so so entering into your meditation posture
and maybe spending a little time swaying rocking around
and so you can kind of slowly come into a still place that feels balanced
aligned and to lower your gaze
and have a loose focus in your gaze you're not really looking at anything in particular
letting the eyes relax and then if it's comfortable for you to
gently close your eyes
and is as if you're caring for something tender within
taking a few long slow deep breaths three quarters full hour full is
comfortable for you and an extended x cell
and in that exhale to allow your body to relax and settle in
and then letting your breathing return to normal and continuing on the exhale to relax
your body part of the value of relaxing is that
there's greater bodily sensitivity to feel when we are relaxed
on the exhale to soften and relax the muscles of the face
around the eyes cheeks
then if you feel any activated energy or
in the face tightening in the face
as you exhale maybe you can allow it to get cooler
the coolness across your face
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the belly softening the belly
and if there's any way that the thighs are tight or gripping
maybe you can also relax the thighs
and then becoming aware of how you feel
what's the emotional state that's most present or mood
state of mind that's present for you
and it could just be that you're sleepy calm
it might be
see if you can feel how it manifests in the body
the feeling of your emotional state or your mood
is it kind of mostly felt or ex
in the head the face the chest the arms
the belly all of the above
is there a location that seems to be the center of how you
feel
and then as you exhale to relax the physical place where you
feel your mood your emotions allow the physical softening
or in other ways relax around how you feel
if the mind is preoccupied in some way or caught in
on the exhale softening the mind relaxing the thinking muscle
and then coming back to your breathing and just settle into the rhythm of your
breathing
if there's ways in which your mood or emotional state can be gathered in to support you
to stay with the breathing
make use of that support or you can just let your mood emotional
state receive to the background as you stay with the rhythm of breathing
but if what seems most predominant is your mood your emotional state
see if you can find where it's most expressed in your body
and relax there relax around it
relax the physicality of it
and then begin again with your breathing
is there any attention associated with how you feel
if so can you relax it
if what you feel is pretty nice and relaxed itself
can you relax other parts of your body around it
to allow the good mood or state to spread through your body
recognizing whatever mood or emotional state you have
and relaxing with it relaxing around it
relaxing through it softening
the edges and breathing with it
wherever your emotional state mood state of mind is located in your body
as you exhale soften relax
or if you have some place in your body like you're around your heart
that is your emotional center
soften relax
and as we come to the end of this sitting
maybe for the next two or three breaths relax again
on the exhale and on the inhale
open your mind's gaze out into the world
your world of people you'll encounter and engage in communicate with
and how is it that relaxing in your body relaxing around your
emotional states how is it that that helps you be more
prepared for meeting other people
relating to to other people
in whatever ways we benefit from doing this meditation practice
to trust that that we do it not only for ourselves but for others as well
that these benefits the ways we benefit
allow us to be in a better place to care with
to connect with others
and may we think about and consider how with the foundation of meditation
that we can now engage in the world in a more useful way
perhaps in a more generous way or empathic way
may whatever ability you have to relax with your emotions
it awaken a care and sympathy for others
so we have space and time to consider
how to speak how to act and even how to think
in ways that is for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
so i begin these five-part series on mindfulness of emotions
and the structure of these five talks will be the first one will be about relaxation
the second about recognition the third about respect
the fourth about restoration and the fifth about release
and um all these ways are ways of aspects of
mindfulness that uh ways to practice mindfulness ways of
mind ways that mindfulness practices us just to be this careful attention to
what's happening tends to evoke or bring about these kinds of
relationships to our emotional life and
as for today it's to relax so one of the remarkable things about
mindfulness meditation is that you're allowed to have your emotions
in many places in public life at work or other places sometimes if we have very strong
emotions and feelings it maybe isn't so appropriate to show them
if we get angry at someone at work at our boss for example maybe we want to be a little careful how
we express it or some i mean i remember when i was a
relatively new parent there were some times where i felt angry what was going on with the children
but i could see that it was mostly my own inner struggles not really about them
and so i found it best not to express the anger and you know sometimes i even left the room
and came back a few minutes later when i'd cooled down so there's many places you know in some
some families some cultures the idea of expressing emotions is not
really so welcome and it might feel that you know that you have to kind of keep
it in check it's something internal that we process but not something we're allowed to
talk about even in mindfulness meditation you are allowed to have any emotional state that
you have you're allowed to feel whatever feelings that are there
and partly especially when we're doing mindfulness in meditation
meditation is a wonderful laboratory for investigating getting to know and understanding our inner emotional life
and that laboratory works best if we allow ourselves to feel whatever
emotions are present as if meditation is like this special time
where you're allowed to feel anything at all you can have murderous rage
and as long as you stay in your meditation that you don't move and you know go out to
hit anyone just don't move don't speak
then to discover what it's like to let the anger course through you and relax
with it relax around it i'm very fond of the idea that the word
emotion comes kind of from a latin root and the motion means movement and the e
means out moving out and all emotions are processes
they are not things they are things that are in process they're ways in which we process our lives the ways in which we respond to
life the ways in which we understand what's happening in life the ways which we express ourselves
they're very important part of our life some of them are
afflictive some of them are suffering producing and some of them are not some of them
are actually part of the the wonderfulness of the lies the joy the happiness the well-being
uh the beautiful feelings that can arise are the non-afflictive ones sometimes
called beautiful emotional states and there's a very interesting phenomena
that the afflictive emotional states come with tension
come with stress come with some kind of contraction or tightness some kind of
directedness that we kind of lose a certain kind of freedom and peacefulness
sometimes the directedness and the power of inflictive emotions can be seductive
uh the the power that can feel it comes with anger for example or the or the um
the allure and the promise of uh lust
can be quite you know quite compelling but if you're mindful deeply mindful
this is why meditation is such a good place for this you can feel how it's also
afflictive how it's also stressful to have it and so the idea of relaxing around the
afflictive emotions begins to settle some of that stress some of that tension
and uh the other hand the non-afflictive emotions
in in their essence or in their kind of in their simplest form
before we react to them or or have agendas of what to do with them just in love themselves
tend to be nourishing uh tend to be
um comforting tend to be warm tend to be comfortable
tend to have a nice feeling to it and there if we relax
this simple aspect of this non-afflictive emotions there tends to be more space for them to grow into
they tend to be able to be more open and and more settled in a nice way
except if the positive emotions the beautiful emotional states
if we're attached to them if we're clinging to them
then then they don't necessarily grow when we relax
they um because what we might be relaxing is the extra fuel we're giving them by our
agendas our attachments our desires are what we're you know trying to feed it
and pump it up and so as we meditate that pumping them
up might relax and so you person might feel like now they're much less emotional
and in fact they might be less emotional in an expressive way but hopefully as we settle and allow for
the emotions to be there in their simplicity we actually feel them more fully they
become more exquisite they become more embodied more
opening to a deeper sensitivity to what's happening that can't be there if we're spending a
lot of time celebrating your joy or or indulging in emotional pleasures
the idea in meditation is to neither indulge
nor push away neither celebrate
nor condemn neither before emotions or against them
and so when we relax around emotions one of the things we're relaxing is this ways in which we get caught in them
indulging getting involved jumping on board justifying them
holding on or resisting and pushing away or condemning or being angry or feeling shame or
embarrassment for it there's all these kind of secondary reactivities we have
it's those secondary reactions that we learn to relax
and one of the ways to relax is to uh if we can feel
the emotional the physical expression of our emotions
uh it's sometimes been said that all emotions have a physical expression physical
corollary that's part of it and that without having some physical
basis for feeling or emotions we might not know what the emotion actually is
so whether that's always true or not i can't tell you but certainly i found that that's you know predominantly true
regularly very true and i make it a regular practice when i feel some emotions or especially in
meditation to find the location where it is in the body so i might feel fear in my belly at
tightening or butterflies there i might feel some kind of aversion a little bit and
tightening in the face and upwelding kind of tightening in the
back of my neck i might feel a love as a kind of warmth
and warmth in my heart area or a softness in my in my cheeks that might come along
in easing up of the tension in my eyes so it's all kinds of all kinds of little
subtle changes that happen in the body and part of that maybe is because emotions are meant to help us engage and
be actively involved in life so they're kind of in some ways
adjusting the body for some new way of being and so but
that new way of being might not be healthy for us it might be misplaced
it might be the wrong you know it might not be a healthy way of relating to what's happening
so finding out where the emotion is in the body and uh and then you know breathe with
that area feel it and sense it and see if there's any tension or any tightening
in that place that can relax if it's easy to relax it relax the
tension soften it if it's not easy to do the tension itself maybe it's possible to
relax around it to soften around it sometimes the resistance we have to fear
might be uh that where we can relax we can't necessarily relax the fear
or something like whatever it might be and or maybe it's just kind of a
softness around it a softness of that comes maybe in allowing ourselves to
feel what we're feeling and okay okay i'm just here with this is what's happening now i'm here with it
now i'm meditating i'm not going to cause any problems in the world without feeling so
this is the time to just allow for it and be mindful of it
and sometimes it's not not possible to relax the tension or tightening around emotions
but if we simply breathe with it and allow it to be there accompany it with our breathing
it kind of removes some it has attention removing some maybe
even subconscious way in which we're reacting to the emotions presence
and just shifting our focus to breathing rather than feeling but breathing through it so we're not
ignoring it can sometimes allow something to settle and relax
and if it's afflictive emotions they might dissipate
if it's something beautiful a beautiful emotion and there's no extra
attachment we overlay on top of it then you might find something delicious
happens with those they might grow and swell and expand through the body in
some nice way or they might might transform into something that's a different emotion or mind state mood
that has maybe a little different or kind of a wonderful different expression that's not what you
were feeling first but now it's something something very different that's beautiful
so the theme for here today is relaxing with your emotions relaxing through your emotions
around your emotions and the more you can do so physically if you have a physical location for it i
think the more effective this this can be but i would encourage you through today
next 24 hours to when you have a strong enough emotion
that you feel it um practice relaxation and see what happens
in the wake of that relaxation and if you have the opportunity to meditate or just
stand still close your eyes sit down close your eyes and do this relaxation
in a kind of this kind of attentive way meditative way all the better
and and developing the skill of this kind of relaxation will help a lot with the
further deepening our relationship to emotions that we'll talk about these next days
so thank you may you enjoy your emotional life