so a warm hello from imc
in redwood city and uh appreciate
how far spread and how close in this youtube community is and
that we've gathered together here and i like to think of as in a wide circle
sitting together to meditate thank you one of the
for me one of the surprising aspects of buddhist meditation was how much it involved the body
and so much that i think sometimes that mindfulness the
word sati translated into english as mindfulness maybe should have been translated as body fullness
because it plays such a central role in attention awareness sensing feeling
and um but one of the surprising things is how much
the focus is not on the bot the corporal body not the body that will be left when
you're a corpse but rather the animate body
the body that is is animated
with uh certainly with life with but more than that it's animated also
with the um the functioning of the mind
and this body-mind thing in buddhism are not so separate sometimes we consider them to be kind of working together
inseparably and so much of our the way in which we experience our body
is mediated with with how the state the quality the activities of the mind
and that as we dip deeper into the body there's a reciprocal relationship between the body
and the mind the mind and the body and so as the mind changes so does our
experience of the body the animate body the experience body
the way that we experience the body it's not the same thing as the corporal body
experience is mediated partly through our perceptions our orientations our states of mind we
have and it's remarkable how the body shifts and changes as we become more embodied
more present and and the mind becomes more healthy more
settled more at ease and anyway so this was a huge surprise
for me in my practice and i'm hoping that uh for many of you it is or has been or will be
a um a similar kind of delight and surprise and of a profound nature
to appreciate the body in a deep way the experienced body the animate body
so one of the ways to that this reciprocal relationship works between the mind and the body
is that when the body is relaxed
it has a huge impact on the mind the more tense the body the more it supports the tension in the
mind the more relaxed the body is the more it supports the mental tension to soften
and relax so um so today the focus will be relaxing the
body so taking a
posture being careful with your posture
kind of align adjust your posture so that it's most
balanced and open and you're sitting upright most upright
so that when it relaxes the body doesn't collapse or slump
so that when it relaxes um it um
it kind of is relaxing into a support
and aliveness
so then begin by lowering your gaze and relaxing your eyes
and gently closing your eyes
and when i take deep breaths at the beginning of the meditation i imagine that
the movement of the inhale begins deep inside and expands outward like a big massage
stretching moving expanding the torso chest so taking a deep deep breath
and as you relax exhale relaxing into the body
deep deep
breathing and then relax
and letting your breathing return to normal and on the exhale
progressively relax the body from the bottom up
so maybe just exhale to soften any tension or holding in your
legs around the knees
the thighs
as you exhale to relax the whole area around your hips your hip joints
where your bottom connects with your cushion
the floor relax
on the exhale relaxing the belly
letting the belly soften as you exhale
maybe as it softens it settles down
into the lower torso to create some more stability
a ground a floor for the upper torso to rest on
and then relaxing the upper torso the chest rib cage back and forth forward and
behind
and then the exhale relaxing the shoulders
allowing the shoulders to give into the gentle pull of gravity
relaxing the arms the hands the fingers
and relaxing the muscles of the face softening around the mouth
sometimes helped by gently very slightly
opening your lips the middle of the lips apart a little bit
at least so the lips aren't pressing against each other
softening the jaws
and softening around the eyes
letting the eyes rest in the sockets and if it's more restful
even with your eyes closed let any gaze looking that the eyes are trying to do
be it gentle looking backwards down into the body so the eyes aren't reaching out
and softening the forehead
and then if there's any tension or pressure in the mind
in the brain area or anywhere else you associate with the mind
let the mind relax soften
[Music]
and then through the soft attention settle your awareness on your breathing
feeling the inhales and the exhales
and on the inhale feel your body in whatever way
it shows itself
and on the exhale relax your body
in whatever places there can be release
breathing in breathing out
feeling the body relaxing the body
and as we approach the end of this sitting perhaps now you can do another round of
relaxation of the body as you exhale to relax
deep at the core
the core of the body
the way that you might be held in check or closed or
held back just for the last minutes to relax that
to relax again around the face deep in the mind
and as we come to the end of the sitting to bring to mind a saying
that in times of crisis one person who stays calm
can keep everyone come
i don't know if it's always true but it's a wonderful principle
and may it be that as we go out into the world today the next 24 hours
that may be our gift is to
keep our body relaxed a calm body a calm presence
people carry so much tension chronic tension
and some of that tension
is a response to being around other tense people
if we can turn that around and find a way to be relaxed
and let that be the gift so other people can relax
can feel at ease you can let go of some other tension and
anxiety
you might see what ways being relaxed in body
is beneficial for the people around you
being relaxed and being relaxed maybe it's easier to be
have our hearts concerned be the welfare and happiness of others
maybe we live this day caring for others
so they can be happier safer
more peaceful and more free may all beings everywhere be happy
peaceful and free
thank you
so this day this week the focus is on
that part of the mindfulness instruction that has to do with mindfulness of the body
of course the mindfulness of the body practice begins is
with mindfulness or breathing the focus for last week the breathing is
is a completely embodied part of our experience and now it's it kind of
begins opening and helping open us to the rest of the body
the simplest instructions for mindfulness that we teach here at imc
is that when you know to use the breathing as the basis as the home base
for meditation if as a default just if you are wondering where to
have your attention have your attention with your breathing so just just a default just automatic you know think
about it but if something else becomes more compelling
there used to be the teaching when something else becomes becomes predominant
then then the idea is to you can two things you
can either let go of the breathing entirely focusing on it and bring your full attention
to this if the if it's in your this other thing that's predominant so for now it's going
to be the body so if something becomes more predominant in the body then
we practice mindfulness of the body mindfulness of that place
if someone and the other option is to stay with the
breathing but in a sense maybe through the imagination slightly is to imagine you're breathing through
or with the strong sensations in your body sooner and later the body will speak up
with strong sensations for beginners in meditation taking a meditation posture is quickly
uncomfortable and slowly over time
the body adjusts and stretches and opens and gets stronger so that there's some ease in this yogic posture of meditation
and it's really a well worth to work through that time but you don't don't need to
strain yourself meditating you don't to force yourself to stay with discomfort if some discomfort becomes too strong
then change your posture you know you don't have to if it feels like you're getting stressed by the
meditation itself then don't stay with uncomfortable things
and um but there's also this turning towards what's there in the body
and today's the kind of topic is relaxation
to relax the body in a deep way so one one
early time where i started learning the value of relaxation was when i was a zen student
and there are times that my knees hurt a lot from sitting we saddled we meditated a lot and we
weren't in zen you weren't really supposed to move while you're meditating during meditation so if you're
uncomfortable you have to kind of bear it and so um i noticed some point
that around the knee pain there would be subtle micro tensions in
the muscles around it like resistance of maybe kind of expert was an expression of resistance
to the pain and that contract around it but that tightness actually made the pain worse
and if i relax those micro tensions the pain got better got less
and it was just enough there was a difference from being overwhelmed to managing fine with it but i had to be
very attentive because if i didn't pay attention then the reactivity i had would creep in
kind of kind of unknowingly and um and then the muscles would be
tight again so i learned to kind of stay there and feel feel that since the the
the sensations there the tightness and relax them relax them they
i learned also that i had sometimes subtle tension in my fingers and they looked ever so slightly pulled
in and it was an expression of some kind of uh feeling of like i had to work hard here
i had to engage now in doing this meditation thing and so i learned to recognize that subtle
tension in the fingers and relax it and keep it relaxed and that had a reciprocal relationship or in
relationship to that attitude i had to work hard here and as i relaxed the fingers that attitude would soften
unknowingly the attitude would return and the fingers would get tense again
and uh and so i learned to do a regular part of the check-in as i meditated was to make sure my fingers were relaxed and
it was something that was relatively easy to do for me um it was a micro relaxation it
wasn't a big deal so microattention same thing with the belly
in the early years of meditation practice i had a lot of tension in my belly my belly was always
tightened up and held in and i didn't make it a big project but probably
two or three times in the course of meditation beginning in the middle near the end or something
i would relax the belly and from it often times in the beginning it would just tighten right up again
and i didn't make much to do with it i just kind of periodically relaxed but over time over the months of doing
this the belly learned what it was like to be relaxed and as the belly became more familiar with
it and more at home in it i could feel you know it would became more of a regular place easier to be
there in a relaxed belly but also the anxiety
that seemed to be the genesis of that stomach tension began to loosen again to
recognize it i hadn't recognized it until i started kind of hanging out with the belly and
feeling the tension there so as you do mindfulness of the body
it's helpful to keep an eye out for where the tension is where the holding patterns are the tightness
and and not to make it a big project or very be very ambitious about the relaxation
but it is helpful to relax so as many of you know you know i teach here
on this these 7 a.m meditations to relax at the beginning always to relax at the
beginning but as the meditation goes along it's useful to kind of check in
is there some tension there any attention crept in uh in some of my longest retreats that i
met sat where i sat in very deep states of meditation i developed a
practice of i would sit for sometimes for a few hours at a time and i would pull myself out of the
meditation uh you know with my mind i would still look like i was meditating but i would kind of pull out of the
concentrated state and and look around for a few seconds
to see um and any tension crept in and if there was then i would relax
that tension and often the relaxation had to do with something in the upper head that was connected to um trying a
little bit too hard to be focused a little too hard to concentrate and to be a little contraction there so i'd relax
and with the relaxation the consciousness softened and then i would dip back into medit
into the in the deep place of meditation i found it so useful to always kind of
come out and check and some people as they get concentrated to get tension in their face and
and come out of the concentrated state relaxed relax the tension and then
and then see if you can get concentrated without that tension building up
um some people find that in meditation even if they don't try to do a lot of
relaxation actively that just meditation is relaxing uh
the genesis of a lot of tension it has to do with the
the tense way we think and the tense things we think about and as in meditation that the thinking
quiets down that source of tension begins to
lessen and become weaker and weaker and so some people find just simply staying with the breath
focusing on the breath letting their attention kind of ride the breath be with their breath
then there's not so much attention available to all these thinking that are stress producing
and so just that then people find themselves relaxing sometimes
progressively and sometimes they realize after the fact boy am i relaxed
without trying so it's important also not to try too much to relax
there are times when i try to relax my body and i made it a project and you know i couldn't quite do it i
could do a little bit and i'd try some more do a little bit and just kept me busy in meditation
and and then i i wouldn't try to relax
and i would just stay focused and be with my breathing and get constipated breathing and lo and behold that part of
my body relaxed um so you we don't always want to do kind of frontal assault on our attention
sometimes we have to just accept it and and allow it to be there and just do the practice and
trust that it will relax on its own
the um and then finally an interesting thing to
do with relaxation of the body if you feel there's tension somewhere in the body
that doesn't want to relax don't worry about it but sometimes it's very interesting to relax around it
relax the attitude towards it relax the and this outer layer
of reactivity perhaps around like my knee pain i tighten up around it
so you know if the shoulders are very tense so the belly is tense and it can't relax don't worry about it
but maybe it's possible to relax something a little bit a wider circle in the body
just around it there might be a softening that can happen
and so today's theme is relaxation
and relaxation is just uh i think of it as kind of like the entry-level
uh variation empty level kind of taste of
of the deep letting go that in buddhism is called liberation and
it partakes relaxation shares some of the goodness and some of the qualities of
deep deep relaxation freedom liberation that comes and so we're kind of getting a hang of
it and feel for it the body gets a sense and it helps prepare the ground for
deeper and deeper letting go and relaxation as meditation proceeds
so thank you for today and uh
you might spend the next 24 hours um familiarizing yourself
with the tensions in your body the times and places and ways in which you
tighten up and it might be just a fascinating to see how much it goes on
and then but also are there simple ways you can relax that what happens if you stay
and don't allow relaxed or don't allow the tensions to build how does your how does that affect your
day so thank you very much