good morning welcome all of you from all these places
wherever you are i'm at green gulch farm in marin county california so i want to
welcome you however to the insight meditation center uh where i am a guest of your teacher gil
fransdale my good dharma friend um i'm foo schrader and uh gil and myself and another good
friend paul haller have been enjoying three weeks of an intensive called the harmony of zen
and vipassana and so there is
so during this first half hour i'm going to offer a brief meditation instruction for about 20 minutes just silent sitting
which is a kind of hallmark of soto-zen and then i'm going to talk a bit about
the buddha's teaching of right conduct which is the primary focus of our conversation during this
week the first week of our intensive gil and paul and i discussed meditation jana
parmita and last week the buddhist wisdom teachings
and tomorrow the last day of our intensive we are going to talk a little more about the inconceivable vow to save all
beings from suffering so the paramitas in the mahayana
tradition are seen as the basis for training for those who seek to realize the full
complete perfect enlightenment of a buddha some anutara samyak sambhodi
anutara samyak so when you all feel ready please settle yourselves into a
comfortable seated position while i give a few reminders about how to best care for your body
as you do so so begin by bringing your attention to your ankles and your
knees your thighs and your hips in order to create a stable base to support
your upper body as you begin to settle into a
comfortable position explore whatever might be blocking you from a restful
and yet energetic upright posture and if you're able then let whatever it
is go sitting practice is the mainstay of both
zen and papasana traditions when we sit we are making the same shape with our bodies that the young prince
made with his the shoulders are relaxed the spine is elongated
upward toward the top of the head the back of the head is in alignment with the base of the
spine in the zen tradition we keep our eyes
open with our gaze downward allowing the breath to flow naturally from deep in our belly
out through the nose and then back in again
it helps to begin with a couple of very deep breaths through the mouth you know taking in as much air as you
can kind of exaggerating the inhalation filling your chest and your abdomen
like a billows and then exhaling again with some energy letting all that
air go and do that a couple of times and then after that you know just go back to breathing naturally
through your nose
so one simple instruction it's quite basic and and i think common to all buddhist traditions is
the practice of counting your breathing from one to ten so if you choose to do
so you're welcome to try um i usually begin counting from
the in impulse to inhale which is i find in my abdomen so that kind of mysterious impulse to
take a breath on the inhalation is a one
exhaling and then inhaling again the two exhaling
and so on to ten if you can it's not so easy actually as
it turns out we often you know go off course from counting and find ourselves in the past or in our
plans for tomorrow so when you do when you see that which is already inside then come back to your breathing
back to one
so when we take this posture like the buddha to be we're opening ours
we are opening ourselves to the silence and the stillness that is at the core of our human life
to a world of deep connection and mutual support the earth upholding our weight the sky
upholding our breath and the land and the water upholding the animals and the plants
that we depend on to survive
as we enter ever more deeply into the roots of that connection the living roots of an unbroken line
through time and space we find ourselves right here
where this exact moment this exact breath becomes this exact wish to let go
completely of every loss every pain and everything other than this
just this this is a gift that has been given to
you to me to each of us alone we didn't earn it we can't pay for it
and we can't make it ourselves it's given to us and all we need to do is say thank you
so here's a poem for this occasion by billy collins from a book called the poetry of
impermanence mindfulness and joy this poem is called aimless love
this morning i walked along the lakeshore i fell in love with a rem
and later in the day with a mouse that the cat had dropped under the dining room table in the shadows of an autumn
evening i fell for a seamstress still at her machine in the tailor's window
and later for a bowl of broth street steam rising like the smoke from a naval battle
this is the best kind of love i thought without recompense without gifts or unkind words without
suspicion or silence on the telephone the love of the chestnut the jazz cap
and one hand on the wheel no lust no slam of the door the love of a
miniature orange tree the clean white shirt the hot evening showers
the highway that cuts across florida no waiting no huffiness or rancor just a
twinge every now and then for the ren who had built her nest on a low branch overhanging the water
or for the dead mouse still dressed in its light brown suit but my heart is always propped up in a
field on its tripod ready for the next arrow after i carried
the mouse by the tail to a pile of leaves in the woods i found myself standing at the bathroom
sink gazing down affectionately at the soap so patient and soluble
so at home in its pale green soap dish i could feel myself falling again as i
felt its turning in my wet hands and caught the scent of lavender and
stone
[Applause]
i was having a little trouble i'm muting myself right then so i'm sorry [Music]
if you were wondering what i was doing uh so i've gathered a few thoughts to share
with you for the next few minutes and
these last three days i've been talking about some practices that have been given to us by the buddha
in support of an ethical life in the buddhist tradition a person who
is devoted to the welfare of others is called a bodhisattva or an awakening being
and as i've been mentioning to those of you who've been joining for the last few days
the guidance system for an awakening being is called are called the 16 bodhisattva
so among the 16 precepts the first three are the refuges i take refuge in buddha and dharma and
sangha and the next three are called the pure precepts and those are basically a summary of the
whole of the whole thing of all 16. the pure precepts are do good avoid evil or unwholesome
conduct and purify the mind so that's what i'm going to talk about this morning beginning with a story
about a zen master by the name of bird nest roshi so burden s roshi as he came to be
called was famous for sitting meditation high up in a tree when a monk came to
visit he called up to the teacher and asked what is the secret of buddhist practice
the rashi replied do good avoid evil and purify the mind the monk then said
well that's easy even a three-year-old child can understand that
to which bird nest replied a child of three may understand it
but a person of 80 years may not be able to practice it
so many years ago i took a number of zen students with me on a field trip to the asian art museum in san francisco
and as we entered into the beautiful collection of chinese buddhist art i saw this wonderful trio
of standing figures in the center was shakimuni buddha and on one side of him ananda known as
the guardian of the dharma on the other side mahakashapa known as the foremost
in ascetic practices and then later on i was reflecting on these stat these standing figures and i
thought that together they very nicely represent the three pure precepts
so mahakashapa avoiding evil you know unwholesome conduct ananda doing good and shaky many buddha
purifying the mind and then as a trio saving all beings from suffering
so this first pure precept avoiding evil often connected to the idea of
asceticism basically re refers to a wise and a and at times a severe restraint
regarding the actions of our body of our speech and of our minds
asceticism basically supports us in not getting carried away by the extremes of what the dalai lama
calls the three pathological emotions the pathology of attachment
greed i have got to have it the pathology of revulsion hatred i have got to get rid of it both
of which are grounded in the pathology of delusion about the true nature of reality
so in his very first sermon the buddha mentions the extremes of asceticism many of them familiar to us because of
the practices that the buddha himself as a young prince had undertaken in his initial quest for freedom from
suffering he nearly starved himself to death he lived outside without shelter
he didn't bathe he held his breath so long that he got a terrible headache and he engaged in long hours of
meditative trance and yet it was through such severe practices that siddhartha
came to realize what he called the middle way a path between extremes of asceticism on one
hand and indulgence in sensory pleasure on the other such as the childhood that he had spent
in the palace so because of that insight was called his darshana
the buddha declared in his first sermon that the middle way avoiding the extremes is the most
beneficial path for the development of a truly mature human being
a being who is awakened moment after moment by this very life a life that is filled with
mysteries with wonder and of service to others and yet asceticism
as represented by mahakashapa has remained an important part of the buddhist
training program as it does here at zen center but the question is to what degree and
to what end and it's always a good question for us and it's been a question throughout
the history of not only buddhism but i would say of all other religious traditions as well
how far do we humans need to go and more importantly perhaps go where the
song asks fayyang where are you going fayan said around on pilgrimage ditsan said
what is the purpose of pilgrimage fayang said i don't know. disand said
not knowing is nearest so for those who go too far there's
ananda standing on the other side of the buddha ananda was the buddha's cousin and
lifelong attendant whose name means joy or bliss and who's characterized in the earliest
teachings as kind unselfish and thoughtful towards others
and also as very popular ananda enjoyed playing with children and
spending time with women he was also portrayed as a large body
person unlike mahakashapa who was as thin as a rail ananda for the most part was a
happy man he too is a perfect model for spiritually satisfying life
and the second pure precept as well doing all good ananda also became famous for
beseeching the buddha to allow women such as his aunt his mother and his sisters to enter and train in the sangha as
fully ordained nuns albeit with a few extra regulations
to contend with and which they still contend with to this very day
following the buddha's death ananda was severely criticized by his new teacher mahakashapa not only for speaking on
behalf of women but for a great number of other things relating to play
so for me these two mahakashapa representing asceticism and ananda representing
pleasure are simply the guard rails on the path to awakening you know each one personifies the
extremes by which we navigate the middle way first we slide too far to one side and
then we slide too far back the other way and so it goes so this reminds us once
again that our practice is not a thing it's a process you know it's a living process
a 10 000 mile long iron road down which we sometimes move merrily
along and sometimes not as the case may be in the zen tradition mahakashapa's
transmission as dharma's successor to the buddha is said to have occurred when the buddha held up a white flower
and twirled it in his hand the other disciples looked on without knowing how to react
but mahakashapa smiled faintly and that was it
then dharma flower turns the dharma flower i've always thought it was interesting
that the buddha according to zen would pick mahakashapa as the first ancestor and ananda as the second and then as i
thought about it it occurred to me that really it is important it's an important sequence for
each of us to follow and to understand why that's so
so in my view the first thing that we do as practitioners is to commit to a
period of ascetic discipline you know the first pure precept avoiding evil
unwholesome actions in order to remove the habit body so deeply ingrained in us through a
realization of selflessness you know vipassana and then the second pure precept doing
good becoming free from selfishness and then seeing the beauty and the joy that runs through all things
and therein a natural wish to show that same beauty and joy to others
a wish to benefit them and the entire world so then there's the third pure precept
by which we transform the body and the mind to whatever is needed for the welfare of all beings
mrs kuan yin with her thousands of hands and arms
unfortunately our usual habit as humans is to try and capture that joy that runs through all things
we try to grasp it and possess it and thereby we lose touch with its transient nature lose touch
with the transiency of seasons of hours and of moments
without which there would be only absolute silence as you all have heard many times
the cause of human suffering is this futile effort of the illusory self to capture illusory things and that the
pursuit of the transient by the transient is the very core of human suffering it's basically
a kind of madness and so we must practice together in order to
reveal in fine detail the depth and the breadth of our insanity and then
we must stop suzuki roshi once said that practicing together is like putting unpolished
stones into a tumbler and as they knock around hitting each other their rough edges get knocked off this
is a very courageous thing to do you know very courageous service that we offer to one another
as we must and this is because none of us here at the zen center or anywhere
else for that matter is lacking the emotional and psychological conditioning
for becoming excessively angry lustful or confused and as my therapist often
said to me when as a zen student i would complain of some kind of personal upset
human first so for this reason human first i do believe that all of us
have come to this practice in order to face the facts of our ancient conditioning
which leads us to enact our pathological emotions we have come to consider how we might
alter the outcome of our habitual response towards self-defense self-righteousness and worst of all
self-loathing so this is the third pure precept to purify the mind
meaning as one of my teachers once said to save all the beings that you are the precepts are a way of learning
the truth about ourself and about our relationship to the world and to other people which is basically and ultimately
that there is no self and there are no other people just as the buddha saw on the morning of
his awakening he saw a world that was not separate or outside of himself
and he knew for the first time that he wasn't alone that there was no thing and no one
outside of himself no alone only all one and he was happy
he was so happy he almost stayed right there under the tree but lucky for us he changed his mind and
so can we may all beings be happy may they be joyous and free from
suffering and may they live in peace thank you very much
would you like to uh take a couple questions sure happy to okay
so if anyone has uh questions go ahead and put them in chat
i think there was an earlier question about uh the poem and the poet you read earlier yeah billy collins
he's wonderful it's a wonderful book a friend gave it to me as a gift i think you can read it without the
words being backwards it's called the poetry of impermanence mindfulness and joy by john
brem and john brown is a practitioner who was listening to a lot of dharma talks and he said
you teachers need some more poems so he put this wonderful collection of
chinese and japanese and american poets together under these headings the first section
is impermanence the second section the poem is about mindfulness and the third
about joy and i don't know if you can see the picture but there's a wonderful image of it an
elephant standing on top of some china wear some teacups and improbable
but there it is and i think there's another question uh
what are the two truths well does the ultimate truth which
basically is inconceivable the inconceivable nature of reality itself it can't be broken into parts you know
reality doesn't come apart it's just all at once right here and we are all
that just this is it as a declaration of the ultimate truth
and the relative truth is the other truth which is the truth about our relationships and it's pretty much about
language how we have we as clever little primates have created language
to take the world apart you know into many many parts
in fact i was reading this book sapiens which is quite fascinating about the origins of language and how
with language humans were able to begin to say things that were simply not true
like that that god up in heaven loves our people better than any others you know
it's like where'd that come from but you know we all know these things have been said so uh language allows us to lie
and all kinds of terrible things so being conscious of language the relative
truth and there's a wonderful series of books by some scholars led by jay garfield from back east
tibetan teacher uh called taking the relatives seriously
i think all of us who come into spiritual practice are often drawn to the ultimate we want the ultimate truth we want to
you know have that big bang experience of enlightenment you know once and for all
um however the ultimate truth is that there is no ultimate truth everything shows up for us as in
relative terms you know these truths are about the this one reality it's not about you
know two separate realities so it's really the truth about the one thing you know
about each object and uh it's a fascinating study i highly recommend
all of you you can even just wikipedia as a really good description of the two truths if you want to uh read a little bit
about it hey thank you phu and uh what was the name of the book again
that you showed with the elephant yeah the poetry of the poetry of impermanence
mindfulness and joy john brem b-r-e-h-m
and we'll take one question from youtube there was a question about please explain think of
no thoughts is it a coin uh-huh definitely that's the question
you know dogan says he's quoting some other teacher previously think not thinking so this is the
dualistic proposition the relative truth comes in twos you know is
isn't me you right wrong that's do a lot dualistic thinking based in language
so we think in in twos but there's no twos you can't find the tooth
so think not thinking how do you think not thinking
non-thinking together this is the essential art of zazen not
splitting the word world into half into twos the big one being self and other
you know that's the one that hurts us the most think not thinking how do you think not thinking
non thinking the essential art of life really of zazen we say zazen but that
just means everything
okay fool thank you very much yeah thank you all thank you so much and please have a a good day a safe day and
take care