so
continuing on the topic of samadhi
and um
the 11th step of mindfulness of
breathing
and samadhi is
sometimes the word samadhi is sometimes
the
generic word or general word for
meditation
or the meditation
and cultivating our mind our body
cultivating ourselves
in the meditation practice and then
when we look kind of within this
universe of samadhi
there's all kinds of things that where
we are gathering together reunifying
we're coming together
that to develop and grow and enhance
our experience and samadhi is not meant
to be
an experience that diminishes us that
makes us less and deprives us
but is actually the opposite it's one of
the richest ways of experiencing
ourselves
enhances fulfill for very fulfilling
very filling
very nourishing and it's developing
these
beautiful wholesome qualities these
beautiful wholesome states of mind
but in doing so it's also kind of
getting out of the way
uh of our without adding all this extra
tension and stress
that uh can exist in the mind and moves
us to less and less stressful states of
mind
or states of being less and less
activated
places of agitation and moving to deeper
and deeper peace
and as we do so even wholesome states of
mind wholesome activities of mind
that are more energetic than need to be
begin to be shed or relaxed or settled
and it's a movement from more energetic
states
to quieter and stiller states and not
that quiet
think some people have very negative
relate experiences of quiet and
stillness and silence
so we have to kind of try to put those
associations aside
and somehow realize that the quietness
and the stillness
silence that we're developing is letting
go letting go
it's kind of like filling us with
feelings of
real goodness and contentment and
fulfillment
satisfaction but there is this movement
towards
uh less and less agitation less energy
energetic
movements and things that in that in
that context
of the mind getting peace more and more
peaceful things that were wholesome
and wonderful before can be felt now
they feel like they're a little bit too
agitating
they're a little bit stressful to be
there so for example one of the
things that happens in samadhi is there
can be a lot of joy
but joy at some point seems like it's
too much it's too agitating
and even though at the beginning it
feels like this is the best that anybody
could ever experience
and but as we get more familiar with it
it's
the energy of it seems like too much and
then
we
and then we settle down more and more
into
um into
you know peace or more quiet place that
feels even more satisfying
so this movement and this is kind of the
general trajectory
of deepening samadhi developing samadhi
is this movement for more agitated more
energetic states
to less energetic states that i feel
more and more satisfying as we go into
them
and so i say this because it's a guiding
principle
for tuning into our practice that
that the the kind of the way to see the
path forward in samadhi
is to appreciate at some point that
really feel at some point that what felt
really wonderful
at one one stage of practice we're ready
now to
let go of it or let it become quieter
and move to a less energetic less
activated
state and uh and that's the movement
that's the direction that the practice
is going
and um and uh and then there are
various um landmarks along the way
that stand out uh as we do this process
of settling and settling and settling
that goes on more peace that happens but
the principle is removing in this
direction
and it's helpful to keep that principle
in mind
because sometimes when people read about
samadhi
they learn about like four stages of
jhana four stages of deep absorption and
it becomes a little bit mechanical or
technical like am i in the right place
am i at the first john i'm at the second
genre and there's a kind of like
samadhi my numbers that goes on which
can get overdone sometimes and people
are too preoccupied about
the technical definitions and aspects of
this
rather than living in the organic flow
of samadhi
that we can and just allowing things to
unfold
and not be so concerned about the
numbers and stages
and how far we've gotten and
it's easier to do that if you understand
that principle that we're going from
more activated states to less activated
more stressful to less stressful more
from more agitation to less agitation
and so there is a kind of a trajectory
kind of a path and some of the landmarks
of that
are
is first is a real appreciation
for no longer any kind of relief from no
longer being
actively engaged in unwholesome ways of
thinking
so if we have spent a lot of time with
resentment and just like why did that
person do that
or desire just really want something
hostility fantasy and you after a while
we feel the flatness of it the
two-dimensionality of it the
way in which it keeps us stressed and so
with somalia with developing meditation
we're starting to let go
of those things and when we really are
become separate from
it's temporarily put aside or
deactivated those apps of greed hate and
delusion
the unwholesome it's such a relief
and there's a kind of a gladness and joy
that wells up
but more important as this relief and
the goodness the
happiness of this relief now the
meditation can really begin
to do our gentle work of practice
staying present applying the mind and
staying there
and this idea of the gentle work of just
okay stay here be with us
hang in there come back be here
um now it's done without the stress of
having to
struggle against unwholesome
distractions and difficulties of mine
but there is a kind of gentle work of
you stay here
that can be represented by what happens
on the in-breath
uh we have to the in the beginning then
breath is a whole new experience
the mind has to connect to that and then
we stay there for the full in-breath
then we connect again to the beginning
of the out breath and stay there for the
whole time
it's a very gentle some people don't
even notice that they're doing it
but there is a kind of little movement
to these two movements of the mind
little working massaging kneading
the dough kind of experience
but it comes along with the relief and
the happiness
of not being distracted anymore finally
being able to be here and do this
as we settle in and we at the stead
we land and and there's a steadiness
and the um we there's less and less of
this need to make the work
of connecting and staying it becomes
second nature the mind is just starting
to become
stable and we're just able just to rest
in the breathing and just stay there's
very little tendency to wander off
just there we're here we're finally here
and that gives birth to a different kind
of joy
of just being really now being able to
put aside that extra work
of connecting and being and there's a
kind of a gliding
soaring um sliding
on the experience of of and so
it kind of feels like it's like petting
the cat the pet begins to purr
we're kind of there
being touched in some deep way and
it's kind of like the pleasure principle
where we're just kind of being touched
this beautiful feeling
of just staying with the breath and
being there and being
that a different kind of joy arises
and that can be quite strong and
energetic at times and after a while
that joy
it feels like it's too much and so then
uh it's ready to kind of
to let go of that level of agitation
activation and by tuning into
there's actually a deeper satisfaction
feeling of contentment
and um feeling of mindfulness
feeling of clear comprehension a simple
awareness
simple recognition of what's happening
simple awareness of what's happening
and the goodness and contentment of just
being in this happiness or
this deeper sense of pleasure and we let
go of the joy because
and then as we go deeper in that
happiness
feels i don't know if it feels like it's
too much but
the happiness begins feeling begins to
soften and relax
and it falls away into something that's
much more
satisfying which is a deep sense of
tranquility equanimity
and where the awareness is very pure
um very pure awareness sometimes it
depends how we translate the pali the
buddhist
teaching zone is but its awareness is
very closely connected to equanimity
that its awareness which is purified by
equanimity
and so the awareness is very peaceful
very aware
and and uh very still and because
there's so little mental activity so
little stressful activity
much of our ordinary way of experiencing
ourself has temporarily fallen away
people even have the sense of not really
being in their
having a body the body edges fall away
and no sense of being in a body
it's not being disassociated it's
actually the opposite
we're so connected that uh and so still
that we don't need the reference points
we usually have
so um
so the principle of this movement to
less and less activity
as we go into samadhi and part of the
purpose of this
is to clarify
our gaze our ability to see to observe
so it doesn't have a lot of agitation or
filters
or disturbances of
unwholesome thinking but even our
thinking and projections and ideas and
concepts
that we overlay even if the concepts are
accurate enough
to no longer be overlaying concepts on
our experience
and and so it isn't that samadhi we're
doing it for its own sake
but for the way in which there's a
cleans
the our perception cleans
purifies awareness so we can start
seeing in a deeper and deeper way
for the purpose of liberation