so good day greetings and uh happy sitting here seeing the greetings
on the chat and the names and so thank you all
and so the topic is still
samadhi and i like to sometimes translate this word as to be composed
and that's a wonderful i think concept that brings together some of the qualities of samadhi of
landing on some place being established being calm and
centered being steady with the experience that we're focusing
on if um we go i've gone into the wilderness like up in the mountains
where there was no trails but there were cairns there were these little piles of stones that people had
built that indicated where more or less where the direction was to walk
and so we would hike along and we would look for the cairns and uh and then we'd find our way
but if we hadn't looked you know if i hadn't known about karen's and also just was fascinated by everything up there and
and um and was looking at everything equally i wouldn't have found uh you know the way forward if i was
if i was really scared about running into trolls up in the high sierras in california
um and was constantly looking out for trolls i also wouldn't have found my way because i wouldn't have seen the cairns
even if i knew there to look for them but if we know to look for karen's then we know how to find the way so the same
thing with meditation we can be afraid of trolls and spend our time looking for trolls we can be
um searching for long-lost treasures in the world lottery
tickets and we don't really pay attention to what's really here
and but there are karen's there are these markers these signposts that for samadhi it's helpful
to recognize them and in recognizing them that's how we find our way
and and there's many signposts but i would like to emphasize two of
them now one is um a
to be steady a certain kind of steady composure with the experience and if when we're
steady when we hold ourselves steady when the the gaze is steady when the
when the our composure is steady when our attention is steady
or that part of our attention is steady so we're looking for that part of our attention that
is steady or can be steady and we're steadying ourselves in that the other is
a quietude a tranquility maybe it's a a a serenity
and um and even if we're agitated we might be able to just pick
out the corners of the mind the heart the body where there is some tranquility uh some quietude
and uh and then to include that to kind of orient ourselves oh this is the place
this is the way forward here in this part and um and but if we don't recognize that
quietude that tranquility then we don't uh we know we don't see the signposts
and the third is um to so composure quietude tranquilly and
third is non-destructibility a kind of a non-dispersal of the mind non-uh
distractedness of the mind and even if we're you know 99 distracted
uh we might kind of pick up uh the signpost of that way in which the mind
is not distracted is not dispersed not spinning out and centrifugal force so kind of just
scattered and all kinds of thoughts and ideas and as the as samadhi begins becoming stronger
there's a stronger and stronger feeling of the mind not being dispersed not being scattered not jumping around not being
fragmented the mind starts feeling composed quiet
centered and it is just a feeling like the mind is really here now it's
not just non-distracted or non-dispersed kind of feeling and
and and so
so these are three signposts that we can follow so to take an upright
meditation posture and if you're lying down then upright means
laying with a certain dignity and vitality or openness some way that
maybe expresses
an integrity or a wholeness or confidence in being here
and gently closing your eyes
and being a little bit delightfully serious at the beginning of a meditation
to prepare yourself to so that you can really be here and the sacredness of the present
moment so you're preparing yourself and so you take a few long slow deep
breaths and the deep inhale is a
for affirmation that indeed you are here that you've showed up
here i am i'm showing up for this deep breath filling the torso with
not just air but with sensations and expansion and maybe even
confidence here i am
and then to exhale along gentle exhale letting all of that go
letting go of it tension and holding and
and then letting your breathing return to normal and we prepare the mind and the heart by
relaxing the body all these are very closely connected
so relaxing the muscles of the face
around the eyes the jaw
and to soften and release the shoulders
the area around the shoulder blades perhaps
perhaps the outer edge of your shoulders as the shoulders turn around to go down the arm
the very top of the upper arms
perhaps relaxing the chest softening in the chest
and then relaxing the belly in such a way the belly the weight of the belly
gets lower
settles into a foundation the lower torso
and then with your attention your mind gently
placing it on your breathing wherever you're going
to be primarily focusing on breathing imagine that attention is gently placed
on that area
but clearly kind of settling into your breathing
again affirmation that here is where you're going to walk here's where you're going to be present
if you can make some small adjustments in your breathing to make it more comfortable
relaxing some part of the musculature breathing
breathing a little slower a little faster a little deeper or shallower
whatever makes it comfortable for you
and adjusting how you are with your attention
is there some way that your attention can be less forceful or strained
less up in the control tower trying to stare at the breathing
and more that the attention the awareness is within the breathing itself
in the sensations of breathing
and then noticing whatever's quietude or tranquility there might be
here even if it's in the cracks between any agitation
or in the side or deeper inside
that's right letting them thinking mind become quieter
slower maybe the thinking mind can even be more
gentle so it's easier to notice the quietude
the tranquility
that and let that tranquility be part of the
atmosphere within which
you're mindful of your breathing
and notice whatever degree of
stability or steadiness
you can establish with your breathing
whatever steadiness on breathing that's here for you
and then also notice any way that you are
non-distracted the mind is not scattering out into all kinds of
thoughts and even if you are doing that look for
the signposts look for that part of you which is not that way
that's capable of being undistracted
with your breathing
relaxed calm
steady undistracted
these are the signposts
that point you to samadhi to staying present
to being intimate with the experience of breathing
one breath at a time
when you notice yourself thinking a lot look for the quiet and tranquility here
let that tranquility of mind spread
open up further so it's easier to stay with your
breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
you could begin by remembering that we're still meditating
there's nothing you have to say to anyone or do for anyone for this few next two minutes
there's no responsibility and obligation to for to do anything but sit here quietly
and in the privacy of just sitting here with nothing you have to do
can you somehow let the your heart open
your kindness open
to think of people around you and here on this youtube
sitting together or in your homes or communities places of
work think of them with
good will very private goodwill they don't have to
know about it you don't have to do anything
just opening your kindness goodwill
in a sense
being aware of these people around you
within the quietude the tranquility that might be here
and without needing to bring them into your bring too close to you
just there in the privacy of your own heart
perhaps you can feel or sense or extend
the sentiments of these words
may you be happy
may you be safe
may you be peaceful
may you be free
and if in the safety and privacy of meditation
in your own heart if it's possible easier than to have
good will for others
stay close to that maybe you don't have to confuse it with
what you actually do
or feel obligated to do stay close to that place where it's private
maybe even secret trusting
that having good will for others will some way or other spread from you
with benefits for the world
may whatever benefits that come from this practice this morning
spread from us like the scent of a rose spreads out
into the garden so may this benefits that we've had today
laughed out into the world for the welfare and happiness of all beings everywhere may all beings
be happy
um