good morning good afternoon good evening good day everyone dear sangha from
around the world i'm delighted to be with you today supporting
supporting our practice and gil taking a vacation um a hiking vacation
with his wife so delighted to be here practicing with you today thank you for the warm welcomes
so [Music] so another week another week another
opportunity to cultivate our hearts and minds
so let us begin to practice together and i will introduce the theme for
this week gently in the guidance
and talk more about it during the dharma so so let us begin
so i invite you to settle in your seat to land
in your body
ah arriving arriving in this moment
fully inhabiting [Music] fully inhabiting [Music]
this moment with whatever is arising
let's start by acknowledging whatever is here
whether it's body aches
the mind that is calm or distracted or anxious or sadness in the heart or
gladness in the heart expectation disappointment joy
whatever is arising in the heart and the mind and the body
let's greet it first let's greet it with a smile
it's like this right now
and smilingly smilingly bowing to everything that is
present in this world internally in this world
externally bowing
appreciating what is even if it's a crowd of sorrows
and inviting the thoughts
the heartache whatever there might be to be here they don't have to be pushed away go
away but is it okay for them to just settle and allow yourself and allow you to give
your heart to stillness in silence for just
a few minutes
taking taking time taking a moment of refuge
in this fathom-long body taking a moment of refuge
turning our gaze inward
greeting simplicity
the feet simply touching the earth the ground
ah feeling feeling the simplicity the joy
receiving receiving this groundedness
receiving receiving
sensations of your bottom on the cushion
connecting rooted landed on the earth
receiving the sensations of the hand
touching each other and touching your lap
coolest swarms
the uncountably many contact points
no the next in-breath receiving ease
with the breath ah and with the out breath
letting go letting go of any tension tightness holding in the
muscles in the body and landing
more deeply connecting more to yourself in this moment in time this morning
afternoon evening this precious moment in time
that has never been and never will be again
like this the gift of this moment
like this gift of this moment of our lives
receiving receiving receiving the in-breath
magnificent amazing to be alive
this body knowing how to breathe itself
or letting go letting go the out breath
into this moment
into the unique wakefulness of this moment
can we receive what is offered just as it is offered
can receive the breath just as it is offered
deep shallow whatever it is
with graciousness
can receive each gift the entirety of each gift
the entirety of each breath beginning middle and end
of the inbre beginning middle and end of the out breath
can we receive this body sensations of the body
whatever is presenting itself with an open heart with an open heart
not picking and choosing but with an open heart wholeheartedness
opening the gates of our hearts
just for this period it's okay you can close it later if it doesn't feel safe but if you can
experiment just this period see what it feels like
to try on this attitude of openness
and generosity of perspective for yourself
it's a huge breath each sensation even each ache in the body was a gift
it's a gift to teach us something to point something out and if only we
would open up our hearts or generously receive
even if it's challenging conditions
of course there can be joys ten thousand joys
as well as the ten thousand sorrows can we receive
can we receive can we receive not go out and get for this moment
betraying our hearts our minds in just receiving
relaxing the body relaxing and receiving
and imagine the next period of time is a gift to yourself
you've made a gift to yourself nothing needs to happen
you're not supposed to accomplish or do anything even do meditation no
it's a gift it's a gift of time just sit and receive
just sit and receive
see how this shift in attitude can change your body your breath
and the ease of being here
just relax and receive this gift
if you notice the mind wandering thinking come back to your mind come back sweetie nothing to do right now
this is a gift of time to just relax in this body
and be just receive being the gift of being
relaxing receiving
receiving the breath in breath letting go of the outbreak
what else are we receiving in this moment
besides the breath
a chair or cushion that's supporting us
a roof over our head likely some food that we have eaten that's
giving us energy in this moment
so so many things technology with which we can be together in sangha and
practice
the works of uncountably many people who have contributed
to our well-being to support us in this moment we are receiving so much in this
moment connected through this web of humanity
not to be overwhelmed
just to sit just to sit in this web
in this web of receiving and giving
relaxing into it just
graciously smilingly received
and for the last moments of this practice period together
whatever arose or did not arise during this period
to have kindness generosity
in our attitude towards ourselves it's okay it's okay it's okay letting go
letting go of any judgment relinquishing releasing any judgment
and trusting that there is goodness generated
from our coming together showing up showing up and practicing that there's goodness
generated
and to generously share that
sprinkling as if sprinkling this goodness all over the world
made the goodness generated be shared with all beings be a cause and
condition for their well-being in ways i cannot
fathom may this goodness be a cause and
condition for my well-being the well-being of all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
thank you for your practice
finish
so nice to sit and so nice to sit in sangha
and receive each other's presence in this interconnected web of humanity
so so friends
you might have already guessed the topic for our exploration
for this week i'll give you some cues we'll make this a little interactive even though it's
kind of awkward right i don't see you or not in the same room i'm actually on zoom
i'm not at imc for those who already know this is virtual background
this audio is going through zoom etc
so we'll try to make it all interactive so so you might have already guessed
perhaps from the theme
of the guided meditation i'll say a few more the theme for this week
the theme for this week is one that
the buddha taught first and foremost and emphasized
especially especially for for us lay people
emphasized and it's a practice that he taught first
before he taught sila before he taught ethics so
the found this topic which i'm not naming yet just see if you can guess it
um this it's so important that he taught this first and when it
was firmly established when the mind when the heart really had this
down only then did he uh teach
uh ethics and only then after that did he teach what's called
bhavana cultivation of the mind meditation
above on a cultivation meditation cultivation of the mind and heart so
this comes first in the trilogy before sila ethical teachings
and before bhavana meditation and
any guesses i'll wait in chat for a moment you probably already have it
and um also i'll say one thing that for me
in my own practice when i was younger i was primarily interested in meditation
it's bhavana yes and as as i've become older and and
hopefully a little wiser the importance of these other two
factors of course of course silas so important of course ethical conduct and
this other factor that i'm not naming yet has become even more important in my
practice somebody guessed it yes generosity donna exactly
dhana sila bhavana dhana silabao and adana
generosity i realized that in my own practice in my own
and when i say practice it's not just an outward practice of giving it's so much more than that it is so
much more than that and i think when i was younger i was mistaking generosity as as just the outward act of giving yes
it is that too of course it is that but it is so much more than that it's
it's really an internal practice it's really a practice
of cultivating generosity towards ourselves towards others towards our
mind towards our bodies towards our life generosity of attitude generosity in in
the way we treat others the way we give the way we receive it's it's such an
important practice um and as i was saying just a little early as
i've become a little older i re and and as practice becomes
life as as you know after a while many of you already know you have been
practicing for a long time life becomes practice practice becomes
life so your practice is not just something that you do on the cushion
in the morning or in the evening or sometime and then you go and live your life it doesn't work that way maybe at
the beginning it felt like oh yes i'm meditating and then after a while your life becomes your
practice your life becomes your practice the way you live your life the way you
show up the way you treat yourself the way you treat others the moments of your of your living
become become your practice so in this way generosity is not just something that
you do you just give something to someone oh yes generous i'm being generous
it becomes it infuses infuses your heart your mind
generosity towards yourself towards others and it's related to
to many path factors we have four other days so i i'm so excited i
need to pace myself part of me wants to just share all the teachings all the
all the [Music] teachings i am so excited about i want
to teach them in one go but slowly slowly slowly so there's
i'm thrilled for us to be discussing this for the next
few days and not just discussing but to let our hearts and minds swim in
in generosity what what is it to have a generous heart or or notice moments
where there is no generosity and i've done this practice before to have my mind swim in generosity
for days as a practice and it's been hap happy making and also very opening so so
that's the topic it's a long way of introducing the topic so
so to place um
as i already mentioned with with dhana sila bhavana dhana being
first donna this word for generosity or giving
in fact um the word dhana is both giving and what
is given in pali the word is d-a-n-a
it's both what is given and the act of generosity
and uh and in an article written by upandita
he called dhana sila acts that purify our existence i love
that acts that purify our existence
what a beautiful way to relate to it acts these are acts that purify our
existence so they have internal dimensions not just external
dimensions of of benefiting others but internal dimensions of purifying and also
other dimensions that are even above and beyond our perception our understanding
to just open to the beauty and the mystery of this giving and receiving
in in life we're always receiving we're always giving in our
lives [Music]
so i'd like to invite us to start today as we already did with our
guided meditation in to start with ourselves to start with
ourselves so in some way similar to the practice of meta loving kindness
where we start with in smaller concentric circles start with ourselves and then go out out out
and we cultivate kindness good will for ourselves and with meta may i be safe
may i be happy may i be well etc so that when our cup feels full then we
can share it with others we don't have a needy sense love me love me love me
right when our heart is full when our cup is full with our own kindness
it's less needy we can offer it to others so drawing a parallel here let's try
this on for size drawing a parallel in order for us
of course for many might be an easy step from receiving to giving but
but to appreciate and acknowledge receiving acknowledge receiving acknowledge
that we are the recipient of so much goodness so many gifts so much generosity all
around us i mentioned a few
items in our guided meditation the the breath
the air you are breathing in this life this body it's ours and it's not so ours nothing
is really ours even things that we own own
quote-unquote own [Music] aren't really ours we are a traveler in this life
we're just passing through and we use these items for a while for a while
you know after i'm long gone this this beautiful tibetan bell will still be
here for now i'm i'm it's um owner or i'm it's a custodian that's it
i'm it's custodian but when i'm gone it's it'll still be here so so acknowledging acknowledging
so much that we receive so much goodness this being that is living this life is receiving
is receiving as a way to open our hearts to the to the awareness of oh letting go
letting go letting go generosity letting go
so an invitation that i have there's so much i want to say and we're already at
time i have to save it for the next days so an invitation i like to have and
tomorrow i'll exp i'll explore more the relationship between
letting go chaga which is another beautiful practice another beautiful term relating to dhana generosity of
heart and attitude of generosity chaga which relates to dhana this act of
giving the two going together as beautiful practices so but for today the invitation i have
um is as you go through the day as you go through your day
notice if you um what what am i receiving in this moment
what gift am i receiving this moment what gift am i receiving this moment
and can i receive it wholeheartedly can i receive it graciously can i receive it
with gratitude can i receive it with openheartedness
for example if you receive a compliment today right can can i receive it with graciousness
and simply say okay they say nice shirt oh thank you instead of oh this old thing oh yeah
like instead of like you know pushing it away can you receive it with graciousness
it's a gift someone is giving giving you can you receive generosity
of spirit can you receive generosity from others [Music]
or from yourself from the universe with graciousness with openheartedness
with delight because that act of graciousness openheartedness
opens our heart to turn around and share its its own generosity share
the generosity of our hearts with others when our heart feels abundant like wow
i'm receiving so much so
thank you for your kind attention i feel like i'm receiving so much from
you with your presence with your practice with you participating with you showing up
so thank you so much and i look forward to continuing to let our hearts and minds swim in this
beautiful topic of donna generosity tomorrow
take good care be well