[Music]
so good morning everyone and welcome
nice to have you all here in person and nice to have everyone who's on youtube
present as well i have the chat open thank you and uh
so one of the hallmarks of
of this practice of ours is simplicity
and you might want to keep that word close by when you do this kind of practice simple keep it simple
stay simple if it's not simple it's probably not mindfulness
and that's not meant to be a big complicated engineering job of mindfulness
complicated thing to figure out or to follow and make or make our way
certainly we enter into a complex world sometimes with mindfulness
complex inner lives and one way that i've made that simple
is i use the label chaos it's just chaos
i'm sitting in chaos and that's like the big overview kind of label that
then i'm not lost in the details trying to figure it out just oh it's just
another big wonderful label is confusion whoa that's all that's all it is simple i'm
i'm confused
so okay okay and then you can hopefully oh now that i know it's confusion
i'll just sit with confusion i don't it doesn't keep it simple maybe i don't have to be
unconfused maybe it's okay to be confused just just confusion
and and as soon as i make those labels like that you know chaos or confusion
i've kind of begun to make sense of it or just kind of beginning to kind of find my bearings or
like a toehold or a landing place for it and then it's not quite chaos or
confusion anymore and because now like with confusion
i'm not confused but being confused i know i know i'm confused
so it's like it's beginning to shift and then what would be simple way of
being with confusion or chaos let's be let's be embodiedly present so
let's be present in the body with it and then what is like it for the body for this chaos or this body to be
confused and suppose energy and agitation and so it's getting narrower and kind of more defined where the attention goes no
i'm not not confused about this now i'm not confused that my body's agitated
is my little toe agitated no it's mostly in my torso
it's mostly in the front of my torso so it's just because it started to get kind of more and more
you know like sense or clarity of what's happening
but the principle for doing so is to be simple keep it simple
so ideally you would take a simple posture
and sitting upright literally or metaphorically
and gently closing your eyes
and if it seems too too complicated take some deep breaths and you don't you don't have to but
if you can take some deeper breath in a simple way that's appropriate for you and your body
your lungs partly as a ritual of
simplification just being here for this body this place
maybe a longer exhale can partly be
letting go of the complexity of
there and then past and future exhaling into now
here
letting the breathing return to normal
there can be a continued simplification process that as you exhale
to relax your body
relaxing the body sometimes relax the mind
relaxing the body sometimes relax the heart
relax the muscles of the face
softening in the belly
softening the shoulders
and then the question for each of you is
what would it be like for you to be simply here
that kind of simplicity doesn't need anything to change
but you're simple with how things are for you
and maybe it has a process of simplifying
maybe it's enough just to breathe with what's happening
breathing in and breathing out
so
having it be the question of the meditation session
or the word simple simply being with what is
simply breathing with what is
simply breathing allowing yourself to be simple
allowing yourself to allowing things to simplify
here and now
[Music]
and then coming to the end
coming to the end of this sitting
to let the world come back in
allow yourself to remember
the rest of your life today people in your life
in your community and your neighbors and
family and circles of connection that we have to people that we know and
don't know
and to imagine that the simplicity of your
kindness simplicity of your care
travels in unseen ways out into the world
and then it begins with looking upon others
kindly
to see if you can look now onto your world kindly
and wish that in the scene in unseen ways that your kindness can travel
that your well-wishing follows those channels
those currents and wish well-being for this wider world
that we live in wish it and also
offer a little bit of yourself behind that wish
that you yourself will offer
some way to contribute to the welfare and happiness of others even if it's the smallest possible way
may all beings be happy may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe
may all beings everywhere be free
okay
so hello everyone and welcome nice to have you here
and uh hopefully it's also nice for these those of you who are here that it's nice nice to be with people
and uh some of us it's been an unusual thing to do to welcome and for those of you on youtube
i hope that someday we could be together someday you'll have maybe
far away you'll visit come here time see we have people who do that periodically
they it used to be before the pandemic seemed like almost every sunday someone would come up and say i'm visiting i've been
listening for a long time so it's not very nice
so the topic for today is
a little bit following up in a talk i gave maybe four or five weeks ago on sunday
that was in preparation for the seven a.m sittings i was doing which was uh
focusing on these different asp basic aspects of instructions for
mindfulness meditation that we teach here and
at that time i said that uh something like that
that the basic instructions are not only basic for beginners
but they're also basic for people who would like to consider themselves advanced
and for those who are in between the two that the basic instructions of the
practice is the same in fact the buddha when he talked about
this kind of thing he said that before the first
level of first experience of realization the first level of awakening that people can experience
and after the practice is the same that what what we're doing the basic practice
doesn't change and so in a sense if in order doing the
practice it doesn't matter whether you're enlightened or not
uh it's still the same practice and he even goes so far as to say when people become fully enlightened even
buddhas they still do the same practice
for their in order to be able to be at ease in this world call it a pleasant abiding here and now
and also to encourage other people to practice
so the practice is the same before and after enlightenment isn't that kind of nice so you don't have to worry about
enlightenment when you're practicing because you know what god is going to do you you have to do the practice anyway
be warned after you do it and uh but it does you just it does some some
good at the practice and uh uh
when when when someone has a certain degree
clarity of letting go of releasing is something that's been
they've been attached to for a long time and it's clear enough and strong enough
then after that they have a reference point for the practice that's different so the
practice is the same but the reference point for the practice changes
and then the ancient language the language is um well now uh what the practice is based
on this reference point and there are three reference points
that they talk about that can happen and uh and this is where the difficulty of
translating words from an indic language to english
because the words in india are really rich i mean there's a long
history of it and and i think there are inspiring words in not just in indian buddhism but in
indian language even to the modern world sometimes
they're rich in association whereas when you take and translate it literally into english
most of people who only know english are not going to feel oh wow yeah this is
cool this is wonderful they're going to go what what
you know sometimes at the best of it right it could be different so um i'll tell you the words in pali
the indic language first and you most of you won't have any mean any sense of this but some of you might have an
indian background so um it's um
v becca v raga
and niroda so the practice becomes based on those
three viveka v raga niroda
so uh so the way that they translated usually into english that does not come to inspire you i think maybe maybe you will
i shouldn't be speaking for you so maybe you'll be really jazzed to hear this
seclusion dispassion and cessation
is that kind of okay or is that like wow you know you're paying attention like this is like fantastic
seclusion i can't wait more seclusion the pandemic has been
good not good you know that hasn't been long long enough let's go really do it
it just justifies you know the pandemic seclusion so so so um
so i don't think it really works in english to get a sense of how inspiring this is
and to hear that after some level of spiritual maturity in buddhism your practice gets based on those three
i think in english speakers doesn't really work but i think that what might work that i
think is not a literal translation but i think is a fair translation for these three terms
is independence
freedom and peace that i think in english has some people
have some people even have emotional relationship to those two those three and that they speak a little bit more to
people you know in english speaking maybe grew up in an english-speaking culture
and uh and some of those words you know they're quite powerful united states
and then when i when i was growing up there was a party i think it still exists right the peace and freedom party
and uh and then independence i mean maybe there's problems sometimes because
it lends itself to uh you know sometimes it aligns itself with the kind of
individualism that is that is selfish whereas you know to be too independent
from everything else and just be myself and mine so uh but independent you know this
country is like the united states is kind of you know it's like one of the
almost religiously politically religiously political ideals you know in my independence also
it has it but it you know it's a beautiful thing sometimes i've thought that this word
viveka that i'm translating here as you know the seclusion i'm translating as independence i've also i like the term
english word autonomy and in sometimes
to give people the autonomy to make their own medical decisions in this country is a really i mean it's a
central feature of medical ethics and
so the seclusion is to be secluded
from attachments from being uh
enmeshed in the world of things and people and experiences and feelings
then we might have the thoughts and ideals and judgments we have and so we're secluded from that
entanglement but another way of saying is we become independent from it
or something inside of us is independent from it something inside of us has become autonomous
autonomous from us there's an autonomy so
say you have a thought that goes through your mind and maybe it's not a wonderful thought
and then you judge yourself oh i'm a bad person i shouldn't have done that i hope there's no one mind reading here at imc
because that'd be rather embarrassing that i had that thought
that reaction is an entanglement we're caught in its web we're involved in it and reacting to it
and having preferences around it to be autonomous or to be independent
from our thinking is to see that thought arise and just see it arise and
wave as it goes by you know or not wave just let it just have no reaction to it
because there's some place inside the place of knowing of recognition of awareness
that clearly is aware that this is happening but it doesn't pick it up it doesn't
react to it it does it's not for or against it doesn't use it to re to
define oneself oh there was a there was this terrible thought that i
am a lousy person because i had that thought as opposed to the simplicity of
look there was a that was a lousy thought wow okay lousy thoughts come lousy thoughts go
and there's no attachment so there's a seclusion there's a autonomy there's an independence from
those kinds of things that kind of thought same thing with feelings
and uh this time we'll use a positive thing just to challenge you some more
and that is um maybe there's a really happy feeling coming up
now who wants to be independent of that but they but a happy feeling comes up
and there's an autonomy we're aware of it we're present for it but there's an autonomy and independence
from the happy feeling the happy feeling is allowed to be there but we don't define ourselves by it
look at me i got it made you know i hope they notice how happy i am because now i'm a good buddhist or
something and um because heaven forbid that you're depressed because then how can you be a
good buddhist it doesn't matter what feelings are depressed happy
in this place of autonomy independence and it has a lot to do with the autonomy
independence of knowing being aware we know we there's a place inside almost
almost like a place inside where we know what's happening and i want to stress
this idea of knowing that there's not there's not shutting out the world we know
and the knowing is free the knowing is independent
so that comes to the second quality which is i translate as uh or render it
as as freedom so independence is the first one or autonomy and the second one is freedom
which is usually translated as dispassion but what a dispassion means in the ancient language is no longer
having attachments and uh the clinging and uh
and uh it's kind of the word raga which translates as passion here has some of the negative connotations
that we can have sometimes in english around the word passion um you know there's sometimes having too
much passion you know you have passion for his anger whoa please
that's not good or passion for money or passion for status or wealth we might talk that way sometimes
in california maybe i don't know where else in english-speaking world and the passion is kind of considered all good
you're supposed to have on your passion for life so to talk about this passion it kind of
doesn't quite work in this kind of in in the new fashion used to mean suffering in the
old days that's from latins suffer that the passion of christ was the suffering of christ
so uh but so but freedom and its freedom from uh
from uh clinging from grasping greed it's freedom from
ill will and hatred and it's freedom from delusion
and delusion has a lot to do with the projections we put on the world
and then we believe those projections and we you know there's human beings are kind of projecting machines
people you know walking and talking projectors you know we have all these ideas that we
overlay onto the world and and others so some of those are diluted
and so as we develop this independent way of knowing this autonomy of seeing of being aware
and we're no longer so enmeshed in the experience we can actually see
thoughts interpretations projections arise in the mind and we say oh that's just a projection
that's just you know who knows what that is so you guys are all wearing masks
and i can you know i bet you all have nice mustaches
yeah that's you know that's what it's you know so i would love to see your mustaches and probably some more handlebar mustaches and who knows
and i'm just seeing mustaches on you know all your faces you know because i can't see you know so
i'm making up a story so i can see mustache story arising
and it's just a story it's just an idea and i don't know you know it's so easy
to live in that story and assume that i'm seeing accurately so the more more independent we become
from this aware place that we have fantastic vantage point to see the birth the arising
of an idea and we can put a question mark behind it is it true
so this dispassion is this uh they're fading away or becoming free
from clinging so some people would say it's a little
bit you know a different way of talking about the first one but here we're talking we really feel
the freedom when we feel kind of independent
and now we feel there's freedom oh what a relief it's so great to have this freedom so great to not be caught
there's a joy there's a delight there's a sense of well-being there's an appreciation of how great that is
and the third one the nirona translated as usually technically
translated as cessation means the stopping of something it's a stopping of the agitation
so calling it peace kind of works there's a place of peace that we have because we know something about peace
in fact peace is always present
believe it or not it's just that if we're agitated we can't notice it
there's more peace in this world than there is agitation
but we don't notice it because we're caught up in our swirls and thoughts and fears and
you know ways and so when someone has reached deep
enough letting go let go something let go of their
their self-preoccupation and let go of their clingings and attachments
uh let go enough so that agitation has abated
and they have an experience of themselves being unagitated when it's been strong enough
uh that they that it becomes ever available it's always there if you turn towards it
and see it oh it's there i might be agitated but there's also peace i might still be entangled but there's
also a place of independence where i see it that i'm entangled
i still have these these passions these attachments but i'm seeing it from a place that's not attached
so they kind of the two work together as opposed to just being completely immersed in the world of attachment
immerse the world of self definition and selfing and all that
and so at that so so the um so the practice is the same
it's a spirit mindfulness practice is very simple it's just to be present clearly for
what's happening in the moment and i like to think that this mindfulness practice has a light touch
to it there's a it's a light practice it has no weight
but i certainly add weight to it i bear down i'm trying hard i'm trying to desperately make it work i'm
trying to kind of sometimes i have to have the the bazooka approach to mindfulness you
know you know i don't like what's happening and i'm going to just blast it out of existence
i used to do that with knee pain you know like i sneak paid if i just get really concentrated i could just kind of
like go beyond it i blasted away or something i could bear down
and uh or you know his mind is so agitated like you know this is terrible i should meet this way and okay i'm
gonna really kind of be mindful of my agitated mind and not just gonna
make it go away or blast it away so that's when there's a lot of weight a
lot of intensity and tension but the mindfulness has this very light touch that has no weight it clearly sees
clearly knows but it's not reacting but doing so learning that
i like to think that mindfulness practice is very simple we always try to keep to keep things simple
so being aware thinking i'm thinking just thinking
and then we do it again thinking thinking really see it and then we might see that we're tense
around our thoughts we see tense we see we have preferences around thinking preference
see that we're recoiling from our thoughts oh rick this is recoiling
and and then we say you know then then we notice oh i'm breathing you know
in addition to all these thoughts i'm having oh it's just breathing and then there might be a choice i think
that rather than thinking about these things what if i just stay with my breath
and just stay and you can stay two or three breaths that was nice and then my mind wanders off
at some point you notice that the mind wanders off and then it's just a wandering of mind
and then there's breathing again breathing in and breathing out breathing in and bringing out and then now i can
stay longer with their breath and and then it occurs to me you know if i kind of relax in my torso and my belly
i think i can stay with the breath longer and so we stay longer and longer and so
slowly things kind of come together and at some point this process of
simplification comes to a place where something releases something let's go enough
something quiet enough or stills enough that we discover this place or is no no
that place is not really the right language we discover something that feels
independent free and peaceful
wow now one option then is to cling to that i want that more of that i'll hold on to
this so then you then the simple practice of mindfulness you notice wanting
tension headache arising because of peace and freedom
you know then um you know how much loss of peace that happens as we cling
and want more of the peace and try to make it come back or something so we learned how to learn all these
tricks of the mind we learn what the mind does to all this that makes it more complicated than it needs to be
but you know if we come together and we practice and so so someone who has some
level of maturity in buddhism the practice is the same as someone
who's a beginner but they have this reference point they can kind of feel or sense or know
or remember that there's this
potential this capacity to know well well the in the knowing there's
this independence freedom in this piece
and it's and so the practice with the practice of mindfulness is the same it's just a
reference point for it the support for it the context for doing it shifts so
that's that's the big change and so sometimes it said that um
and when you do mindfulness practice little slogan that says it's not seeing something new but seeing
in a new way so it's not necessarily that we live in a world and see the world differently
but we see with these eyes or with perception that doesn't um cling
we see with these eyes that it feels independent it's not enmeshed
with or tangled with so it's independent we see with perceived with a capacity
that's there's just freedom in the being being with something not caught in it
and there's peace rather than agitation as we see the eyes that see are calm
as opposed to darting around and you know being afraid or something or wanting
and so uh and so that's a that's that's the big
shift and um and then you have you begin you have some hint of that
it feels traces of that and and then this is to be appreciated and valued
some people don't hear that message and so they just think it's always the same practice
and so they will keep focusing on what's happening in the moment
not in understanding that how they focus how they're aware
is actually more important than what they're aware of you have to be aware of something
in this world of ours usually as we go about our life but how we're aware of it and how we are
be independent free and and peaceful
and if it can't be which it often isn't can hell you know that
be independent free and peaceful and you keep stepping back you keep
saying where can i find that place where can i can i step back and just see okay this is how it is
so in terms of mindfulness meditation then it's always like when we actually do meditation it's always the same
practice but the practice what we're aware of also shifts as we practice
if there's a simplification process that goes on and the buddha talked about this
simplification process that leads us to simpler and simpler and simpler and
then we get turned inside out and this is my language inside out
so that we can when we come back into the world we're back
in the world in a simply this simple way uh but we're free
and so again it's not a rejection of the world it's a kind of a learning how to be in the world in a whole different way
so this there's a one there's one uh discourse that's called the lesser discourse on emptiness
which i think i should be trying to translate the lesser discourse on emptying
because there is a process of simplifying simplifying that goes on so i wanted to
give you a little try to do a little example of this so this morning before i came down to
imc um
my mind was thinking about being here at imc this morning you know we had this covet protocol and
i'm going off to teach retreat today and so i had to get some things from here i had to want to be here early enough just
make sure that everything was in place there was some my responsibilities here had to be fulfilled take care of things before i
left and um and then there was this uh talk i was supposed to give and
who's going to come and do i have the right mask and you know and it's a i was a kind of it was i was comfortable
and peaceful enough about it but my mind was in this complicated world thinking ahead planning ahead what i have to do
with a list of things and and that was the complicated world i was living in kind of a little bit coming down here
once i came here i didn't have to be thinking about what am i going to do tonight when i get to imc
i was at imc and so now i just went around started taking care of the things i had to do
and i still was thinking ahead a little bit you know what's next and i have time to do everything and
and so but i was you know then it was much it was simpler just doing them i was here and
and just you know it was just a simpler world than the complicated projections of that
and so i was taking care of things it was nice and then uh at some point i could meditate with all of you
and then you know then okay things a lot of things were taken care of and yeah there are things to do afterwards as well but
now i don't have to think about that anymore and now i could feel that i'm still the momentum of having all those thinking
was still going on but that momentum just feels like energy a little agitation little tightness someplace in my chest
it's okay i'll just breathe with it and be with it and feel it and and then i could feel there started
to be a shift and my thinking got quieter and i started i stopped thinking about
imc and the tasks i had to do and i started in fact even after the eyes closed the
fact that i was even sitting in imc in this building kind of receded occasionally had thoughts about when do
i have to ring the bell should i look at the clock
i finally did and i was late and um
and so um you know so a little bit things came through but things got simpler and simpler and then and then
after a while i could feel the shift inside and and uh there it came i kind of dropped
into my body and it was more with my body and the simplicity of just breathing and there
was very little thought going on just breathing and simple and that process if it continued it
could get more and more simple and you know after a while i've had you know something maybe the breathing would have
kind of got quieter and calmer that i couldn't even feel the breathing and it was just more feeling sensations
in my body after a while sometimes when i meditate the sense of the boundaries of the body
the sense of it being in a body as a bounded thing it disappears and the body just feels porous to the environment or
you know boundary-less almost there were times when i've my body's disappeared in meditation and
i i kind of felt so much like i didn't i was i was invisible and i when the first times it happened i
opened my eyes to make sure i was still here yep it hadn't gone anywhere
but there's simplification simplifications implication that goes on
and one of the and then it's not valuable just to have it that simple except that it's kind of relaxed
and calm what's valuable is what it teaches us about non-clinging he said oh because if i was cl you know
when it's more complicated it tends to be more clinging more attachment and stuff but you kind of all those get shed and get quieter quieter
and it takes a lot to trust have this deep trust that it's okay to let go the things we're attached to let
go in terms of meditation let go of thinking about it being concerned about it it takes a lot of uh
love and care not to criticize yourself if you can't let go
and you know your mind is just taking swirling and whirling by itself and probably that's a time we probably need
a lot of compassion and care and love and kindness and generosity and
and trust it's okay and that trusting it's okay to be agitated
is a great help for getting calm so this trusting in finding finding finding ourselves
and so there as ways to trust and relax and just trust the present moment just this enough just to be alive in the present
moment breathing and being at some point you get a sense of
independence we get a sense of freedom we get a sense
of peace and if that experience is uh impactful enough strong enough
some remnant of it some traces of it some memory of it remains there
so we so and then the buddha said this is when this this course lesser discourse and
emptiness you go through this whole process of emptying simplifying becoming less
and then he takes us back into the world and he it's as if
it seems like he's going to more and more reified sublime kind of meditation
states but then he says that it kind of basically says and the most
ultimate the really the most ultimate thing is to
be back in the world with hearing seeing tasting and touching
being aware of your thoughts what goes on in the mind just being in the world
any clinging and then you're just aware that your
practice is the same aware of your thoughts your what you see what you hear what you feel what you sense what you
taste what you're thinking what you're feeling you know all these things are still there
but then there's a different reference point
so it's possible that some of you already have a reference point for that
maybe something happened for you time in your life there was independent outside of meditation
maybe you were in some setting some situation where you had some profound experience of
being at peace being at home being at ease some people have it
in a natural setting in a park or by the ocean or in the mountains or something
some people have it with other people sometimes in lovemaking some people will have that without experience
some people's listening to music you know in some kind of nice way maybe at home alone or some people it's through
playing music or dance or exercise or or
having a good nap and waking up a peaceful setting
so you know i i you know so many different ways but maybe if you've had some kind of maybe you've had some
experience an experience that i had a number of experience a few experiences as a child
growing up that kind of remained for me kind of like as a touchstone
and one of them was it was um we had this i guess a relatively small
dining room table and sometimes i would take these white bed sheets that we have
and put it over the the table and then i was little kid so i would crawl underneath inside
and the light from the sun would be coming into the kitchen and the light was so sublime beautiful
and clear and kind of i don't know clean or something coming through the white sheet and i'd feel so cozy and
safe from the world protected secluded
and and it's such a nice way and i just like to spend i still feel it
in my body this physical sense of kind of well-being that came from that kind of
way of being and the buddha also had a childhood
story like that that wasn't under the kitchen table but it was a
similar kind of childhood experience that became his reference point
for how he then followed followed the path to his awakening
so maybe you have a reference point already maybe something happened to you maybe something from when you were five
i think that's how old i was maybe with the kitchen thing
and uh some some reference point for what we're talking about here so that when you practice you that reference
point is close by it's kind of like a little reminder or a little
uh you know pointer to oh that's possible that's a way of being with this
as opposed to when i was in japan and the zen monasteries
sometimes the abbot would bark like a drill sergeant
concentrate concentrate concentrate as if your head's on fire
die die now
you know if i took that as the only reference point for the attitude for how
to sit and meditate i probably would have given myself a headache
and so you know some people grew up with taskmasters teachers or parents or somebody that kind of
imbued a certain kind of attitude that became became the reference point
for how to be that not so not so healthy so
i think what buddhism is suggesting is that there is a way a
healthy way to have reference points of experiences
we've had in life that are really healthy and wholesome and good
and not try to desperately have it again engineer it again
but to kind of um intuit it or kind of remember the quality of the mind the
attention the heart so that when you start doing mindfulness practice
you that's kind of the tone that's the feeling that's the way
that we this light touch in which we use mindfulness that the mindfulness the attention is
somehow somehow you know oriented a little bit
to be that way or oh it's like a north star where it's like a reminder
you don't have to be so tense you don't have to be trying so hard you don't have to be so
confused to confuse mindfulness with uh judgments
with preferences just because it's okay to be simple
it's okay to be really simple and i think it's good and then i'll end
by saying that it's a beautiful thing to
be be independent free and peaceful
because then there's generosity in our way of being with the world
a particular generosity and that is the generosity of uh granting everything else its
freedom so they were with someone we're not meeting them with
them you know being entangled with them or them needing them to be a certain way or wanting them to be a certain way or
or imposing upon them our agitation or our agendas
we can do being able to be with someone fully and kindly and presently
with the degree of independence so they can be independent
with freedom our inner freedom so that we we're not
complicating their life and taking their freedom away so that we are
uh peaceful so that there's a possibility for them to be peaceful our agitation is not necessarily
agitating them and that's true with people it's true with things and animals and beings and
everything we grant everything it's freedom isn't that nice
in the end maybe you don't get liberated maybe you've liberated everything from
you and that's your gift
so thank you all very much for today and uh
and then we will so next week max erdstein is coming to speak
and uh very happy to have him come and
be here and i'll be back the following week and uh and then the week after that
matthew bryn silver will come and give the talk here in person so i don't know if any of you will sign up but to come for that
but and then and then i want to say that um
depending on what direction this uh covet infections go
if it goes in a good direction then we'll probably start we'll change a little bit the registration
what we do here maybe have a few more people come on sundays or or
we might change something we might change the sunday schedule a little bit so that the first sitting starts at 8 30 rather than
at eight so some people might want to come then because it's a little bit later
and so you have to be sure you read you all get the announcement i guess to sign up
and so you have to be sure you you read that that's where we'll explain how it changes i think the beginning of each
month will probably change what we're doing
and then those of you on youtube if you live locally in order to get that email with instructions about how to come here
in person you have to register your covet card to show us that you're vaccinated and you'll find that information on the
what's new on imc website so thank you very much everyone