so
breathing in one
concentrates breathing out
one concentrates the mind
breathing in one steadys the mind
breathing out one steadys the mind
breathing in one unifies the mind
breathing out one unifies the mind
so all these words concentrate steady
unify are all kind of
uh facets of
the same thing of developing and
deepening meditation practice
and it can be helpful in the deepening
of practice
to have some landmarks so have some
signposts some some kind of sense of
where we're going or what we're looking
for what we're valuing
as we develop meditation practice
because
the um
you know subconsciously unconsciously
the mind is valuing all kinds of things
and um and that's why the mind
the thoughts go off thinking about the
past future fantasy
what we're worrying about what we want
because we
value we have we we prioritize or we
put value into those concerns
but if we have value in the process of
meditation and the signposts the
experiences of meditation
and enough to recognize them then we
make space for them to grow
we they we make space for them to
nourish us
and support us and provide more
confidence more reassurance oh this is
good
this is the right thing to do so it's
easier to put down our preoccupations
and so with this deepening of the
practice
there's uh things like the mind becomes
stiller
quieter the mind the body becomes softer
more malleable there becomes a sense of
well-being of different kinds joy and
happiness
subtleness the
the there can be a
sense of joy and happiness there can be
equanimity
there can be a sense of being really
embodied
could not really feel the vitality of
our life coursing through us
and really feeling present and whole or
settled
ah it feels so good to be at home in
this body
and the same thing with the mind the
mind can feel have assurance to it be
peaceful
the mind can start feeling expansive as
if the mind has a room
for all the little details all the
dramas of our life all the
concerns we have all the little
experiences
the details anything that's a detail
can be held now in your mind that's
really broad and wide
like a very large large room that can
hold
all the everyone everything everybody
inside in a
peaceful spacious way so this expansive
mind open mind
there can be for some people a sense of
brightness even light
that comes on that feels really good
but i wanted to provide you with the
three
similes analogies that the buddha uses
for this deepening of meditation
practice
and the advantage of of similes
or analogies is that each person kind of
uh interpreted or find themselves in it
more easily than with a
clear kind of technical description of
what might supposed to be happening in
meditation
uh similarly analogies are a little
black poetry they're evocative
they touch our kind of imagination maybe
even our emotions a little bit
um they these things also have a little
bit kinesthetic or somatic sometimes the
these images so that our somatic
uh involvement with associations come
into play as well
and um and uh and there's a lot of room
for
personal uniqueness so our own way of
finding ourselves
in these analogies so i want to offer
three of them
and they're kind of three progressive
and now uh deepening stages of
meditation
and the first uh and they all have to
use the they all have
they all use water in the analogies
and it's never been explained to me
why water keeps being used in these
similes analogies what it represents
but i take it to represent the mind or
awareness itself
and that's the medium in which we're
operating right now or the mind the
awareness
and and so this awareness begins
takes different shapes different forms
as it practice deepens
so the first uh simile is
water being sprinkled into
in our modern equivalent into flour
and as the water gets sprinkled in the
water gets
folded in kneaded in
stirred into the flour until the flour
becomes dough
you know to make bread and so what's
important is that
all the all the water that's being
sprinkled in gets kneaded in
and spread out evenly throughout the
dough
and so part of the kneading of the bread
is kneading of the flour the dough is to
get that
uh spread out the the you know equally
around
so that the dough kind of could hold the
flour can hold together into one hole
so that's the analogy and uh
and um in a sense the
the flower is the body and the
and the water is the awareness or the
mind and we want to bring these together
so the awareness
is immersed in or penetrates throughout
the body so the body and mind are to be
in the same place at the same time
if the mind is thinking about other
times in other places
then the body and mind are separated
but if the mind starts focusing
awareness starts entering into the
bodiness present for the body like for
the breathing
then the mind is kind of in the same
place in the same time
as the body and uh and
by doing that uh what we're looking for
is the body and mind to end up
in in a kind of harmony with each other
um a kind of unification and
harmonious working together where there
can be real
experience feelings of health and
healthfulness healthiness and
wholesomeness that can't be felt
if there's a real dichotomy real
separation between these two
parts of ourselves and
um and so we take awareness and uh
we bring it into our breathing and
and we're working it's kind of nice the
breathing itself is kind of a massage a
kind of a kneading
but we bring our awareness and we place
it we sprinkle it into
something like our breathing and then we
want to knead it we want to stay there
with the breathing
and those are two different movements
that i talked about yesterday
the contact the placing of attention
somewhere like with the breathing
and then keeping it there and keeping it
there is not holding it necessarily
steady but a gentle kind of working it
and staying there
staying there be there and then we have
to do it again because the mind wanders
off
we come back and connect and stay there
and stay there
and and that's a sprinkling of awareness
into our breathing into our body and
we're kneading it in we're kneading it
in and so there's a massage there's a
rhythm of coming back and applying
yourself staying there
um reconnecting and so for every
beginning of the inhale and begin the
exhale there's a kind of gentle
reconnecting that goes on there
and then it's staying there stay there
be there to the massage
and so slowly um we're beginning to
uh penetrate awareness into the whole
experience of breathing so it's
continuous and
and fills the experience of breathing
wherever that might be in the body
and then and then there's a kind of as
we get a hang and we're doing this hang
of doing this and
feel like this is going well there can
be a rising
gladness certainly the gladness and
happiness
of relief of not being lost and
preoccupied in some of these thoughts
that
thinking that we have that maybe not for
some of you but for
many of us you know is not so much fun
it's not a great thing sometimes to
spend a lot of time
caught up in thoughts and ruminations
and stuff
and what a relief it is to have the
thoughts received enough and
not be pulled into their orbit and be
settled in here
so there's a there's work involved
there's this kneading the sprinkling in
coming here
the next analogy is that what i used in
meditation
is that now the is the mountains
mountain lake
with the underwater spring that flows
through it
and now in a sense awareness has become
very stable and expansive and big
and kind of penetrates or is resting or
is maybe coterminous with the body
that somehow now awareness in the body
are not so distinct
but we really feel the
fullness the vitality the aliveness of
the body
where the sensing the sensory apparatus
of the body
sense endings of the body are part of
the awareness system
and so awareness is not just cognitive
mental observing or knowing but there's
a
broader feeling of sensing and aliveness
that's part of awareness
and so the body and mind now are are
there together as partners
and then within that the
the concentration the steadiness the
real kind of
intimacy with just breathing
is um if he has this inner goodness and
nourishment to it
that there's a welding up of a kind of
joy or well-being or delight
that's not evaluative it's not like we
have to think ourselves into being happy
it's almost like some people say that
their
joy hormones or serotonin and endorphins
they get released
in this steady massaging staying with
a focus of concentration a sense of
well-being wells up
and there's a flow of vitality that
feels like it comes from the inside out
the joy that comes from the inside like
a spring going forth
the last analogy is now
the deeper meditation the sense of flow
and vitality and joy
settles away into a very deep satisfying
peacefulness
and the analogy is that of a of
a the lake has now become or lake has
become really
still unmoving and there's lotus is
growing in it
meaning it's not a cold mountain lake or
something but now it's a very
nice temperature lake that's very
comfortable to be in
and this beautiful uh lotus many
different colored lotus flowers
submerged in the lake floating on the
lake and
and the sense of everything is very
peaceful
everything is calm very still
and everything that's known within that
calmness
even though conventionally it might be
something that's not
maybe a little bit of i don't know
something not not so nice maybe
but everything that is touched by
awareness now touched by the water
is like beautiful lotus flowers floating
there peacefully in space
in the in the water so
additionally there's work in the
with the kneading of the dough and then
there's no more work
and it's just a flow that's happening
we're being carried by the flow
and then the flow comes down
and we're just kind of in this very
peaceful place very still place
where everything just feels beautiful
and there's
and it's in that and in these states
where there's a lot of reassurance a lot
of confidence a lot of equanimity
um and it's a beautiful thing to tap
into this capacity for deep
confidence deep serenity deep
reassurance
it does the heart a tremendous amount of
good to have it
and it does not depend
on the things in the world around us
being just right being fixed um
it's uh this very private inner place
inside
that uh becomes a resource for which we
can kind of enter into the world
in a wonderful way
so maybe those analogies are
interesting for you to play with and
work with and
maybe this topic of inner reassurance
assurance and confidence
is something that you can
explore how that lives in you as you go
through the next day
and i look forward to seeing you
tomorrow thank you
and then to mention again that um
monday we'll have a community meeting
after our
our um you know
seven o'clock sitting in the dharma talk
so around 7 45
i'll post a zoom link a variety of
places
on the imc calendar for this event and
the imc
um what's new section and also i'll put
it on the
on the chat here for the youtube as well
and we'll have that meeting as a kind of
uh marking our one year
of doing these uh seven a.m sittings
so i look forward to those of you who
will come thank you