so warm hello here at the beginning of our
week and happy to be back with all of you and have this chance to
share the dharma the teachings the meditation
so one of the i would say most central
features of early buddhism the buddhism that you find in the
teachings of the buddha as saved in that the tradition we're in the therabad and
buddhism this penitential feature is this idea of
on one hand not causing harm and the other hand doing what is
doing what is wholesome and and kind of
everything the whole tradition kind of centers on this and and i'll talk more about
that in a little while but for the meditation uh this is also an orientation that
we're sitting here really to care care for the world
but in particular we're learning how to care for the world by first foremost in a sense caring for
ourselves in meditation is a is a
way of learning how not to harm
and instead to learning how to do what's beneficial and wholesome
and there's something about the uh heightened attention
sensitivity to the details of our direct immediate experience
that gives us a new information but maybe better information about how to
orient ourselves to towards avoiding harming ourselves
and instead bringing benefit so if this is the
as a fundamental principle or purpose of this early buddhist meditation practice everything one does
in meditation can be evaluated through that point of view
is what i'm doing now beneficial is it harmful
and sometimes it's not always clear if that's the one or the other so then we just kind of keep following
the instructions and doing it but it also implies to how we're
practicing that is how we're doing the instructions are we doing it in a way that is harmful
in a way it is beneficial and harmful can be
too high expectations or being critical of oneself and
if one kind of wanders often thought to be angry with oneself
those are all ways of harming oneself or having high expectations and insisting i have to have a certain
experience in pushing and having greed for meditation experiences any kind of greed
or attachment to what we're going to attain is a kind of self-harm if it's not
obvious now what part of what happens in meditation practice is we have
a higher and higher sensitivity to what is where the harm is where the
stress is and we learn to slowly let go of that and and be able to come into greater and
greater beneficial states um and it's transformative to do so
the um and we realize that the harmful ways in which the mind operates
the heart operates are really not necessary
and that's expanding expending unnecessary energy and that it's quite wonderful and
appropriate to move into states of being that are
beneficial and if we want to care for the world it turns out that the more we can learn
to do this for ourselves the more we have the more we have to offer the world the more we have
a way of meeting the world that does the same thing
so
to begin with a meditation posture
that seems um
i see some some messages of the sound is low yeah i'll try to speak a little louder and there might be some setting that
later on we can adjust here i don't know so assume a meditation posture
that um
you think will be beneficial for you
and what's beneficial includes what helps you to be attentive
aware present
so there's a kind of attention through the body
so [Music] gently closing your eyes
and then i usually instruct to take a few long slow deep breaths but as you do so
can you do it in a way that just feels beneficial feels like a good thing for you to do
not overdoing it deep inhale
appreciating the full
breath in
appreciating the release of the breath the exhale
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and perhaps you find it beneficial a way of even caring for yourself
too quietly as you exhale
relax different parts of your body
perhaps you can soften around the forehead and the eyes
the eyes don't have to do any looking when we sit in meditation
the organ of perception we use more than seeing is sensing and feeling
through the body
as you exhale to relax the other muscles of your face
in the long term it's beneficial to let go of tension in the body
and if you can relax your shoulders
or soften some of the muscles around the
shoulder
perhaps softening the belly relaxing
perhaps as you exhale to release tension in the arms and the hands
as you exhale maybe releasing the thighs
legs any holding or gripping there
and then turning your attention more fully to the experience of the body breathing
breathing there are many circumstances in life
where one of the best things we can do for ourselves is to breathe consciously
with awareness it can be grounding and settling
he can protect us from wandering off into thoughts and mind states which are not
beneficial even harmful sometimes
the buddha said that mindfulness of breathing brings great benefit
and perhaps as a way of getting closer and
more intimate with the body's experience of breathing
maybe a quad may let the thinking mind become quieter
and perhaps there can be a deep appreciation
of breathing maybe even a love
of this body of ours which has been breathing and keeping us alive
for many years and in a sense returning
the favor
by being present acknowledging experiencing fully
the body breathing
and letting go of your thoughts every exhale so you can better
settle yourself when breathing in and breathing out
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
whatever we learn in meditation about not harming ourselves
is directly learning something about not harming others
whatever we learn about benefiting
ourselves orienting ourselves to wholesome states
of mind is directly related to our ability to
have wholesome states of mind as we encounter other people
states of mind which are beneficial for them as well
and appreciating that these two are mutual and almost
maybe not exactly the same but closely related benefiting oneself and
benefiting others to understand that meditation is not
only done for oneself but knowingly and or unknowingly
it also brings benefit to the world
and one of the ways to benefit oneself
is to wish to bring benefit to the world
to have well-wishing good will
a simple care and so as we come to the end of the
sitting allow yourself to be still and quiet as
possible and gaze upon the world with kind eyes
with a caring heart
and perhaps we can all wish that the benefits of this meditation practice
spreads out from the meditation into the world which we encounter today
may it be that the benefits of this meditation
brings benefit and welfare to others may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
and may we contribute to this
[Music] possibility [Music]
you
uh
um
okay so now their sound sorry
forgot to turn it on again after taking my drink of water
so the um
so i'm going to tell a semi-story there's a beginning of this and
um i call it a semi-story because what we often find in the discourses of the buddha is we find
the context is set up for the buddha to teach and that context is a little story about
who the buddha encounters in their situation what they ask him and and then the buddha responds and so
it's not really a full-blown story but exactly but but so the semi-story that
begins up begins this teaching that initiates this teaching
is uh the people of kalama the buddha has this
very famous text called the kalama suta and some for some people it's their
absolute favorite discourse of the buddha and there was a
wonderful zen teacher by the name of yvonne rand who is now dead but
she was very much involved in trying to address the ethical issues in
western buddhism in the united states here in the 70s 80s
90s a very ethical wonderful teacher and she made a rather dramatic statement
that this particular discourse the the kalama sutra
should everyone should have a tattooed on the inside of their eye eyelids so she wanted it to people to
always know it and have it close by and one of the reasons for this is that
what i'm going to teach in a moment is a protection against
some of the more dangerous ways that people can adhere to religious teachings
it doesn't have to be dangerous but historically in human history there's people that are here for these reasons
can create tremendous problems so um
anyway the buddha is in the territory of the kalamas and they come out to see him and they
ask him a question they say in our town lots of different religious teachers of
different kinds come through and they all kind of are saying this is the truth this is the truth and whatever
everybody else is saying is not true and how is it buddha that we can
discern know which of these teachers is teaching the truth and which of them
is not so what criteria can we use for for understanding who's teaching the truth
or not and and so um
the buddha first offers criteria that we should not use for this purpose and
and then he does a very interesting thing he changes
directions or he he puts aside this question about truth and untruth to
offer something which for him is more primary so anyway so the criteria that you should not go by
you should not use for deciding what is true and and false is to go by
tradition the religious tradition that you're part of the teaching lineage so you shouldn't go
because it's traditional the lineage you know your particular teacher lin your teacher and your teacher's teacher
just because you're adhered to this particular lineage political party or whatever it might be
don't take that as automatically is true don't go back to true because it's popular it's the
common view of the times don't go don't take it as true because
it's in the scriptures sacred texts don't take it as a criteria criteria for
what is true because it's logical you've worked it out logically and therefore it must be this way
used reason don't go by
intuition preferences and don't go by the reason of confidence
of the speaker so a speaker who's very competent and eloquent and clear and and seems to really understand
what's happening don't just simply believe it because you think that speaker knows
and then finally i don't believe something's true or untrue because the
person saying it is your teacher so at this moment i'm your teacher
in a sense i'm teaching and you're listening so please don't take what i'm saying
as either true or false just because i say it is not a reliable source of to to really know for yourself this
is true or false and and in replying this way before you
replies this way the buddha says to the kalamas
it's reasonable that you should have doubts about what is true and not true so he really appreciates them they're coming to him with this question
so he gives this list of things but not to go by and then um he um
he offers his own criteria and so here not the criteria for what is maybe what
is true or not true but maybe this is implied but probably what the buddha is doing here is he's if that's the case
he's changing the whole either changing what is defined what he means what's meant by
truth or he's he's has his own idea of what truth is which he doesn't explain in a text
or he's simply
changing the the flow of the conversation to be what he emphasizes instead of
focusing on what is true and not true that what is religiously true and religiously not
true as statements as beliefs or something that's a little bit outside of oneself that that's not his interest
and um and rather he says that um here's
the buddha's criteria is that is it harmful or beneficial
both in in and of itself and also he says does it lead to harm or does it lead to welfare
is it wholesome or unwholesome
and and do the people who you think are wise are they critical of this or not
critical in this so it doesn't mean that you take what the wise say as being true
but you do have respect for what they their point of view and if they're critical of something
then maybe it's time to look more carefully and and pause
and is it praised by the wise and then maybe you don't necessarily
believe it then either but maybe then it's worthy of further investigation
so but the core the core thing here is it uh is it harmful or beneficial
and i can't underscore how much and how i think wonderfully this is the central kind of
pivot or orientation that the buddha has he's not so
interested in religious truth religious doctrine but rather he's
interested in what we can know for ourselves
that is harmful that brings harm or brings welfare
and to it's a radical thing to fully brought
all forms of harming to an end in ourselves i mean what a fantastic
thing you look at what read the newspapers and see how much harm human beings are
inflicting on each other and then there's you know the ass mounts more harm that
never makes it into the newspapers into the news
and um and to to be a person who doesn't inflict harm
on themselves or someone else is a phenomenal thing i think it's like you know a gymnast at
the gymnastics you know some it's such a beautiful such an amazing thing to have worked through and
found a way where there's no inclination no tendency to cause harm
and maybe the opposite we are inclined to do what's beneficial
what brings welfare to ourselves and to someone else and so there are all kinds of lofty
religious states we can attain there's all kinds of wonderful perspectives on life and ex experiences
we can have that people say are spiritual or religious and these aren't to be devalued
in and of themselves but i think in this criteria the buddha has one wants to be careful not to assume
that that gives us a privileged access to what is true and what is false
unless it has taught us something from the buddhist point of view be very careful
for the buddha those states also are evaluated looked at what does this teach
us about how to live a life that is beneficial
that avoids harm over and over again that's what the buddha is interested in
so you could in modern english ideas say the buddha is more interested in
ethics than he is in religion he's interested in how people act and how people behave
and and and and to do so both behave with our
bodies our speech and also in our minds that don't cause any harm but what makes
it kind of beyond ethics is that is the thoroughness in which the buddha points to that's
possible to do this that the the level of peace the level of
of well-being and happiness the level of freedom that's possible when there's no
inclination to cause any harm is a in his experience of radical
non-clinging non-compulsion of freedom and liberation
and so this potential this possibility which is kind of a phenomenal uh human capacity and
possibility but it doesn't matter if we so much if
we take the buddha's path all the way to its end what matters is that we're practicing a
life of doing what is beneficial avoiding what is harmful and to do it
in a beneficial way so part of this teaching then also
is not only beneficial and harmful but also to really make a distinction between
what is unwholesome and wholesome and that is going to be the theme for the next couple of weeks
on these 7 a.m sittings and teachings is i want to look at this
very important topic that the buddha concept of the buddha of wholesome wholesomeness and
unwholesomeness and this week it'll be that
and there's an alternative translation for this pali word kusala k-u-s-u-u-l-a
so sometimes it's translated as wholesome and unwholesome and sometimes it's translated as skillful and unskillful
and for this first week i want to look at the it as wholesome and unwholesome and next week is skillful and unskillful
and this is a a um pivotal orientation for
all of the buddha's teachings and to really understand uh this idea of kusala and akusala and
understand it well gives you access to really begin kind of it's like the key to understanding so
much of what the buddha is about and if you understand these two the two things together
the avoidance of harm and doing what is beneficial and the notion of wholesome and
unwholesome then you're well on the way to discover what the buddha is all about independent
of feeling that you have to know what is ultimately religiously and doctrinally
true you're on the way to become a person who is true true in that they're free
of the causes of harm and filled with these beneficial ways of being in
the world so that's an introduction for what's coming up and
i look forward to our time together and thank you