so hello and welcome dear sangha to
to this edition of happy hour today
whatever the time might be in the time zone you're in around the world
so um [Music]
the theme for today's practice is um
meta and impermanent meta and impermanence
so so
impermanence i want to say a couple of words about that so impermanence
it's a fact of life nothing nothing that's challenging
stays ever the same everything will change everything that is quote good or quote bad in our
lives whatever experience everything changes everything changes
and sometimes we feel that um impermanence is on our side when
something is challenging and we know it's going to shift and change even though our minds think oh this will
never change will always be the same but of course they will shift and of course
if if there is a period of ease enjoy it because
it will shift it will change not to grasp not to cling because
clinging to it can cause um undo
undue pain so it's wise to realize everything shifts and changes part of this life so
so matter and impermanence so can we love can we love what is
knowing that it will shift and change especially knowing that it will shift
and change ourselves situations
people in our lives can we lean into meta
good will care love especially in light of impermanence in
the light of shifting nature of life that's just the way it is
on this dimension of being human and i want to offer a poem
as our inspiration
so the poem is called eternity
which is interesting because it's actually talks about impermanence it's by william blake
and here's the poem many of you probably already know it
he who binds to himself a joy does the winged
life destroy he who kisses the joy as it flies
lives in eternity's sunrise i'll read it one more time an apologies
it's gendered language but he lives from 1757 to 1827
so you can change the gender as it works for you but i'll read it as he has written it
he who binds to himself a joy does the winged
life destroy he who kisses the joy as it flies
lives in eternity's sunrise so this idea of impermanence
it's it's joy as it flies can we kiss the joy can we kiss the joy as it flies
instead of binding ourselves to it
destroying by by binding ourselves by the sense of clinging
destroying ourselves destroying it destroying the joy as it flies
so can we kiss it as it flies can we have good will meta love
for whatever the circumstances are as they're flying as they're flying they're changing all the time
changing all the time so can we live in eternity sunrise
by appreciating with love with gratitude with with meta the impermanent nature of
all things so that is that is the loose theme of
tonight's practice so let's settle let's begin together
so let's arrive in our meditation
posture whatever it might be supportive for you in this moment
sitting standing lying down
or maybe walking for those who might listen to this later on adiodharma
and for most of us right now sitting sitting feeling [Music]
our sit bones on the cushion on the chair
landing
in this moment in the impermanence the fleeting nature of this moment
kissing this moment as it fly ah
letting our feet the bottom of our feet
sense feel [Music] their contact with the earth
i am here
just as the buddha touched the earth
with his hand the night of his enlightenment
does earth be my witness touching the earth
with our feet with our body
with our bottom and the cushion i am here
allowing the breath to move
any weight wishes in and out of the body
received felt in the lower abdomen
just receiving this breath this in-breath this outbreak
with appreciation if it's available right now
this impermanent moment as it flies
just tilling the soil calming inviting the mind to settle to
be calmed with each breath
in the body received in the body
each breath
received in breath received
out breath received the abdomen
embracing appreciating
as if each breath is a winged life a winged life
in the poem
as a butterfly
appreciating
turning our kind awareness
receiving with kind awareness
each breath as it passes through
now let us turn our kind awareness
to this being who is us who is myself
this impermanent being who's of course impermanent
in the big picture but also shifts and changes
aches and pains energy of the body this body keeps
shifting and changing every hour every day
moves emotions thoughts coming and going
this dear dear being with
arising and passing [Music] sensations thoughts emotions
so much influx this being is in flux
and hardly impermanent oh dear dear being who is me
oh
holding [Music] this being
shifting changing
being with mentor with love with care with friendliness
any phrases of meta work for you feel free to use the phrases
any phrases you have i'll offer
some typical phrases may i be safe
from inner and outer harm [Music]
knowing fully well that there is no complete safety in the world
we're just expressing a wish
out of kindness for safety for ourselves may i be safe
may i be happy and joyful
may i be healthy and strong
may i meet every changing moment with ease
may i be safe as the conditions internally and
externally change all the time
may i be happy and joyful in the changing world
internally changing externally changing
may i enjoy as much health as possible with shifting circumstances
internally externally
and may i meet with ease every changing moment
the phrases adapted for our theme today
you can shorten them if you wish
safe happy
healthy ease
perhaps with the rhythm of the breath
synchronized
safe happy
healthy ease
now if you wish opening up
opening up our kind awareness or loving awareness
appreciation
from internal to the external
all the beings in our life
all the circumstances in our life
all shifting changing impermanent
and let's start with the beings
beings in her life
sharing meta sharing our goodwill the understanding
that they too are impermanent and the circumstances
now their lives their bodies their minds their emotions it's all
in flux wishing well for these shifting changing
winged winged life worms dear beings all around us
okay baby safe
safe as possible in the shifting nature internally externally
happy
healthy
and have ease with it every shifting moment
changing moment of experience
and opening further opening further for all beings
all beings everywhere all impermanent beings
and their circumstances impermanent too wishing all wings beings well
including ourselves this impermanent being
with impermanent circumstances internally externally
and for the last moments of this practice period
can we meet the passing circumstances of our lives with friendliness with metta
internal external circumstances these flavin conditions
can we befriend them meet them with friendliness
whether easy or challenging
they too shall pass this too shall pass
this too shall pass meeting this passing moment
with friendliness
so
thank you thank you for your practice
meta and impermanence
so we have time for reflections
or questions comments and always remember that you sharing
your your insights what came up whether it was challenging or something
interesting was realized it's really a gift to the community
so that's the spirit in which i invite you
to please feel free to raise your hand or or type in chat and if you type and chat
your reflections if on soon we have the option to be anonymous you can just send them to me
in which case i'll only read the reflection mark i see your hand
i usually don't see everyone's but you i see please
two years ago i had three dogs two golden retrievers
and i've lost all of them at early ages this last one
this last saturday night and unexpectedly
a few weeks though came to me the opportunity to have the golden retriever puppy
which i got and even though it diluted the
passing of the last one and
then there's obviously the definition of cute and
i've been working on the meditation question what does love without attachment look
like it's really you have answered with
this entire practice tonight with the blank poem and everything since
to appreciate each moment having this puppy i found to my surprise
it was very anxiety producing that i would lose it an eagle would swoop down and grab it
and take off and eat it if something would happen one would lose it
and as you say so very truthfully
that each moment must be met with ease
and that if the puppy was gone tomorrow that i enjoyed it and loved it today
and i meet tomorrow with as much ease and
love as i can for that miraculous moment
thank you please thank you mark thank you so much for
your reflection
oh and thank you for sharing your puppy the image that was so sweet to see you
all here he is the definition of cute he really is oh my god brings up so much meta
oh yeah and
merry christine is also loving your puppy in in in chat he who says he who loves in the
present moment lives always in love
he who stands alone in the present moment is eternally lonely interesting thank you
one more reflection because i have a relationship with this william blake poem i've created an art series inspired
by it i felt a wave of gladness and excitement when you read it anchoring on the breath helped me stay
grounded it was a wonderful combination thank you you are so welcome beautiful
reflection and i see wayne your hand is up please
um well i'm in my 13th hour here sitting in school
and uh i'm because of the
emails from the principal demanding that all the teachers get their google slides together for tomorrow's
parent back to school thing on zoom i'm working and i'm thinking
all i could do was besides hearing the noises and i'm
sort of this year i'm i'm adding a whole lot of and i'm learning myself because i needed of executive functioning skills
for my students and i was just pondering
what would the buddha say about executive functioning skills but then the more i think about it it's
like yes they can be they can be applied to my life and my practice
um [Music] i'm certainly no expert i don't god
knows you must have heard a lot about that living in silicon valley but
i don't know i'll ponder it but in seriousness i realize you know about not wasting time and being organized in my
daily tasks and my meditation periods and my zoom
sitting groups and teaching acquires requires
executive functioning that i need to work on yeah thank you wayne and bless you for
doing for being part of the community of teachers and your 13th
hour in the classroom preparing and serving and supporting so many students
so what i would say is is just one couple of words briefly is
you know executive function is not a term or concept that they put up
talked about however one thing that might be helpful to to consider is perhaps refining it as
wisdom how can you be wise with your time how can you be wise with
your purpose how can you be wise with the way you spend your time uh and serve your students so i'll just
leave you with that reframe thank you thank you thanks
so dear ones dear dear impermanent beings in impermanent conditions of our
lives internally and externally we are going to now
change everything changes so we now are going to shift and change from
[Music] being in the larger community and turning into small
groups of size 3 to support to share our practice with
each other practice in small breakout groups
so and as always we'll start with um 15 seconds of meta
for ourselves for the other people and um
then we will turn to sharing saying as little or as much as you wish about
impermanence and meta what came up for you so the rooms are formed
and here we go take care of yourselves take care of each other
so we have just a few minutes for reflections comments questions what
what came up what you realized so please don't be shy especially if you
haven't shared spoken for a while
[Music]
jerry says the poems at the moment is there it was just something specific
also that came up in the group that you mean the moment in the group or the moment for the for the meditation jerry
you're welcome i'm mute if you like you don't have to um i i both actually
uh at the very end the timing was get and i said oh this is a fleeting moment we need to say goodbye
and it was a moment of real and real moments because it was a very enjoyable uh
period to be with another member and the group but um but
the other part that we talked about uh because both of us were reflecting on one hand everyone's in a lot of pain
uh you know jill has mentioned in his talks that well it will change the pain
will never going to be constant there's always a nuance and then of course i reflected on the other side that when
you're in joy there's a tendency to want to cling to it and not let it go but in both places
it's that space of trying to recognize things are always changing and
i gave the example of a cardinal that i buried that i saw the other day i took a picture and sent it
to the neighbor said it was good but i many times just see the bird and absorb that moment and enjoy it recognizing
it's going to go without having a sense of loss but you can get into a sense of loss when you're in a period of joy
right exactly exactly and you're bringing this up as as also mark brought it up earlier with
with the puppy like oh enjoying this puppy i love the puppy so much i love this this bird flying so much
oh what if it goes away that that sense of angst so so befriending befriending
the oh befriending that that that impermanent because that too is impermanent that sense of
grasping and clinging so all of that yeah beautiful thank you and thank you all for your
practice such rich practice with this theme um can also also one last thing quickly i
want to bring in is is um jerry as you're talking about pain physical pain uh
realizing everything is perfect is impermanent can bring a sense of sweetness a sense of befriending for
what is only here for a limited amount of time whether challenging or more pleasant and
henry on youtube says hello in breath goodbye out breath thanks so that that's
another way to summarize our practice so thank you all thank you so much for your practice
for showing up for yourself for each other for all whose lives yours
touches may all beings be well may all things be free including ourselves
thank you