so a
couple of announcements before i
begin the talk first is that um
i'll have a community meeting on zoom
tomorrow morning after the
7 am sitting in dharma talks it'll be at
45 or so and it's partly to commemorate
the one year anniversary of of
starting the 7am sittings
and it's also for many of us marx
commemorates also the
one-year anniversary of
sheltering in place where our life has
changed dramatically
a year ago and different places of
course went into shelter at different
times but at least here in california
to a year ago it's been a big year and
i almost was going to give a talk today
about grief
and maybe i'll do that in a couple of
weeks but
i wasn't quite ready for that
and um and then next week i won't be
here
next week a wonderful teacher uh
amanda johnson is going to speak she is
um
she graduated a year and a half ago from
the teacher training
for at spirit rock so she's a local
dharma teacher
and and very happy to have her come
and and spend sunday morning with you
some
so imagine
that uh you're in a beautiful place in
nature that maybe some place you've been
and
found inspiring and maybe far away from
buildings and roads and a lot of people
and it's just an expanse of
a natural setting beautiful comfortable
safe inspiring place to be
and maybe it's so inspiring maybe you
visit regularly to appreciate
and feel the freedom of just roaming
around and
the trees and the skies and
the hills and the rivers and the lakes
whatever it might be just a vast space
that's
wonderful to be in
and so after visiting many times you
think this is special and you want to
kind of
mark the specialness of some some nice
way and
creative way and so uh
you bring a um with you into the
wilderness
a glass door with a frame it's a
bit of an effort to bring it in there
and you
install that door right in the middle of
the wilderness this glass door
swings open very nicely at its frame and
and there it is this door middle of the
wilderness
some people might think it's an art
installation
and but it's your door and uh
kind of marks that this space this place
is so special for you it's kind of like
marking it
as being special and and that
you know symbolically it's a door into a
different landscape
and different place and but now when you
go visit
in this big vast open space
there in the middle there's a door
and and you put happen to put it right
in the middle of a trail
so that when you go in the trail you
have to open the door and step through
and so the door is there and
you like this door and sometimes it gets
locked by mistake and you have to go
home and get the key to unlock it and
sometimes it gets rusty being in the
weather and you have to oil it so that
it can open and close
and some being a glass door sometimes it
gets dirty and you
have to clean it and you care for the
store
and after a while you think of this door
as your door
and and you want to protect your door
and so
you because the door represents this
openness to into this wilderness and
this freedom that's there
and so you decide that the thing to do
is to put a fence around the door to
really protect it so the moose doesn't
come along and knock it down and
and break the glass so you put the fence
around it
and you come out there and you feel my
door is protected and
after a while the um you start peeling
you look around say well
this incl this place where i enclosed
the feds it's not really big enough for
me it's
it's you know really you know i'd like
more space to
be able to come in and and just kind of
be spacious and open and
and so you expand the fence make it
bigger and bigger
and after a while you don't want to
really see the fence you make the fence
really big
and goes around the hills and outside of
you and
so you go inside you know just you and
the door and
the doors kind of maybe sometimes gets
branches fall on it and break it and you
fix it and
all kinds of things happen to the door
and um eventually you'd wonder about the
door
and then you remove the door
and then there's vast open space again
then you remove the fence
and it's just like it was before it's
still
beautiful beautiful location inspiring
and peaceful wonder wonder wonderful to
roam around in and then you think what
was i doing with the door
what was i doing with a fence
so this may be a little silly story
uh is um introduction to the topic today
which is uh the buddha's teachings
on selfishness
the earliest teachings of the buddha as
best we know
he did not teach anything about not-self
this
you know famous teachings of
of the buddha it wasn't his focus but
rather he
was focused on
talking about the problems and the
suffering around being selfish
and how a wise person let go selfishness
and as he developed his teaching he
described three different ways of being
selfish or self-focused or
self-preoccupied in some way
and one was through craving
one was through conceit and the other is
through
metaphysical opinions and views beliefs
that we hold onto
so the craving uh idea of selfishness
he associates with possessiveness
possessing things these are mine this is
mine
the conceit
is associated with the idea of i am
um you know that i am something
that i am this i am that so it's a role
identities that we take on and hold on
to and
and the third is um
this is myself that this is the true
self
now i know what the self is and this is
what the self is what my true self is my
essence is
and in pali these little expressions
appear a lot in asus it's
[Music]
and it's kind of close to what we say in
english of me myself and mine mind
he kind of says it in reverse this is
mine
this i am and this is myself
this is the self so
um and the reason to
notice this and pay attention to it it's
the domain
that the qualities of selfishness are
being caught up in
excessive excessive preoccupation with
oneself
a strong attachment clinging
self-centeredness
that can happen and
and this movement towards selfing and
getting holding on to self
is uh is limits our freedom
it does something which is not really
necessary
to cling to the self that is a
comparable to this idea if you will if
you
allow me of putting this door right in
the middle of the wilderness
the wilderness was beautiful and
wonderful by itself
and it was a wonderful place to visit
and peaceful and relaxing
and it was so much more less complicated
to be there
when you didn't have to take care of the
door and protect the door and
repair the door and build fences around
the door
and so the same thing the natural
kind of a natural state of being
that can be quite open and peaceful
and inspiring to experience for oneself
that it doesn't require placing
something in the middle this is mine
this
is who i am this is myself
that movement is kind of an extra
movement that
that places something in the natural
setting
which more often than not does not need
it especially if what we're doing is
clinging
and holding on to uh to these things
so conventionally we might say things
are mine
and and you know it's a lot we say
it's you know things are mine things are
legally mined
there's ownership there's things which
we allow each other to have
but but the selfishness around that
is when we cling to mind we hold on to
it for dear life like it has to be this
way
and this movement towards possessiveness
and claiming things as mine
this belongs to me is a recipe for
suffering
the uh one famous kind of uh
origin story in buddhism that um the
beginning of the
one of the beginnings of the downturn of
the of society
was private property and then people
started
uh
hoarding in their private property and
stealing and things got out of hand in
this mythic story
so the idea of it's mine and holding
holding it tight
not realizing that possession
possessions of all kinds
anything we can say is mine is fragile
it's temporary is uh there's no
guarantee that it's going to stay around
that um i read recently about a
meteorite or asteroid that kind of
landed in the driveway of someone in i
think in scotland i think it was
or somewhere and the rare rare
mineral that came in this asteroid
and um but there's no you know guarantee
that lighting's not going to strike us
or strike our things like our car or
bicycle
and asteroid's not going to fall and
something we own
and then we don't own it anymore it's
gone you know it just becomes a squash
piece of
burnt stuff and
the idea that it is me myself and that
it's mine
has disappeared
the um you know i've
recently i broke a
bowl ceramic bowl that my son had made
and beautiful bowl and i broke it in the
kitchen and
it was ours belonged to our family but
soon as it was broken
i didn't really think about think of it
anymore as mine or
i didn't think of it as belonging to my
family i
rather unser ceremoniously just kind of
put it in the trash and
off it went and um
the the um
um so mine
as i love the story that's suzuki roshi
i've told it many times of
suzuki roshi is um
there's a photograph of him actually
saying this that taken just as he was
saying it so it's kind of
more poignant he was photographing him
holding up his glasses like this
and he says these are not my glasses
but you know about my old tired eyes so
you let me use them
so that's a very different relationship
to my glasses
and so
certainly it's convenient to have things
that we use and know they're there and
they're reliably going to be there next
day when we find them and so we're
seeing their mind
but you might reflect a little bit about
how much extra
attachment there might be possesses in
this fear fear of safety
fear of not being safe attachment to
to status attachment to all kinds of
things that come
we say something is mine it gets more
kind of interesting when you look at
that we take as mine of traits of our
personality or
qualities of our physique and our body
and
ways that we are in the world opinions
my opinions and
and if we hold on to those and cling to
those and think they're unchanging
will suffer so they're suffering of
taking things
as mine and for the buddha it's very
explicit even taking this body as mine
is a recipe for more suffering and
and so you know isn't it natural and
normal take this body as mine
i think it's a natural normal
conventionally to take it as mine my
body
but uh but to do so with an open hand
not
clinging to it just lightly
provisionally
but as soon as you say my body that i
you know them
then i have to be in charge of it and it
can't change and
it has to always stay the same
maybe the second uh form of selfishness
is conceit and um this is um
the idea of over evaluating oneself it
has to do with
how we value ourselves in relationship
to other people
and the common way in english the word
conceit refers to
thinking that we're somehow have a
higher value than others
we are better than others in some ways
and
and so it's a form of comparative
thinking
and as soon as we get involved in
comparative thinking with other people
this is really a amazing uh source of
suffering
comparative thinking um uh you know
things are constantly shifting in the
social world and between us and our
abilities and
other people's abilities and so um you
know if we expect to always
have a higher evaluation other people
will meet someone else who's going to be
better if
you know i'm pretty good at basketball
for someone who you know compared to
the six-year-old next door but
not compared to most adult men at this
point
and so do i hold on to that do i have a
conceit around
i'm a good basketball player better than
everyone else
you know i'll probably just suffer
around that kind of idea
and so this comparative thinking
is an unnecessary glass door
in the wilderness in the natural setting
it uh
it mars the situation it limits it it
becomes something then that we need to
protect we put fences around it
we want more and more fences and control
for it
and now it actually is a form of
of limiting ourselves rather than
freeing ourselves
there's a wonderful cartoon from calvin
and hobbes
where calvin is in the snow building a
fort
and to make him feel safe in this fort
and he's building up the wall so it just
goes above his head
and he's making it really tight and
compact and
and he surrounds himself with all the
snow to make a good
safe fort for himself but it's uh
basically he's
made a round little cone around himself
and once it's all finished he's trapped
inside
and he says help help because he can't
get out anymore
so um so this idea of conceit
is uh can become a trap we've kind of
protected too much and we kind of can't
breathe even
me myself and mine the conceit of being
better than
and in the ancient buddhist language
buddhist teachings
a word which was closely related to
mano mana the word for conceit
is the word mada and the
means to be intoxicated totally confused
and wrapped up in things
and sometimes it's translated as pride
but the english word pride maybe has a
variety of different
meanings these days and sometimes
they're positive
but since the original meaning of in
talks of this word mada is
pride is intoxication
one translation of ancient abhidhamma
text
is um to list all kinds of things people
are intoxicated
intoxicated by so in intoxicated by
their birth by their caste basically
intoxicated by their clan
intoxicated by their health
by youth intoxicated with life
itself intoxicated with gain
and acquisitions intoxicated with honor
with being respected with fame
with having followers with wealth
with skin color with learning with
intelligence
with not being despised
accomplishments popularity
with being ethical with meditation
attainments
and the list goes on and on but each of
these
is seen as a kind of pride they kind of
conceit
and conceit that we get intoxicated by
or get
caught by and it's so much easier
to be in life in the world without
getting caught by these comparative
thinking
with others one form of comparative
thinking that
in the buddhist idea of conceit is also
the idea of thinking that we're less
than other people
that we have less value than others in
some way
and that's also conceit because it's
also an attachment to an idea of self
attachment to a comparative way of
thinking
and and the solution is not to figure
out a better way to compare
um and even the idea of comparing
ourselves as equals to others
and buddhism is considered to be partly
still playing the comparison game
but rather freedom is found by not
comparing
by allowing ourselves and others to be
just as they are
and much more and so removing the door
and the fences in the middle of the
wilderness and letting that
natural setting be itself the third kind
of conceit
is um the conceit of views
of philosophical opinions beliefs about
what is the true self the essential self
and the buddha said there's he he knew
of his time
no belief in an essential self a true
self
that doesn't bring suffering and i don't
haven't done the analysis myself to see
if that's really the case
but it's certainly a provocative idea
that
and certainly we can say that anytime we
crave or cling to something
we will suffer and so if we're clinging
and claiming
craving clinging or craving to a view an
idea
my true self is my soul my true self is
my
is my you know inner goodness my true
self is my
is my um you know whatever it might be
my consciousness um
is that going to give birth to suffering
does it bring suffering when we're not
in touch with that true self when it's
not
evident and present does it just remain
an idea
that we have and so the idea needs to be
reinforced
needs to be reasserted in order to keep
staying in touch with it because
maybe it can't be really feel and felt
and experienced
or what about deep meditation when
whatever we feel or experience as
the essence of who we are falls away
then some people get really frightened
by this
um because the deep deep piece of
meditation where things just let go we
let go of all clinging
it's remarkable how wonderful that
that piece is i want remarkable how
liberating it can be
and how ordinary reference points for
anything we have as we experience as
myself
dissolve you know and then if but some
people get really frightened because
that's who they think they are
i am this and i have to be this
so so selfishness
and the antidote
to selfishness in buddhism is certainly
is to see
the suffering of it and sometimes it's
only by seeing how painful it is and how
fragile it is and how much energy goes
into being selfish
that uh people begin to loosen up and
let go
but the other um the other antidote
is happiness is uh
to experience deep abiding sense of
happiness well-being
contentment that doesn't require
being selfish and so to
that's one of the functions of
meditation practice is not only to
become calm
not only be mindful but to acquire a
sense of
deeper contentment satisfaction ease
to be able to breathe easily freely
without
any clinging to selfishness any kind of
idea of me
myself and mine at least to give
ourselves a radical break from it
so we don't come into meditation and
hold on to these ideas of me myself and
mine
often the the the source the fuel
for a lot of our preoccupied thinking is
me myself and mine
and to let go of that so we can
experience something really wonderful
and to value this wonderful beautiful
natural setting that we have
the natural capacity for ease and
freedom and peace and to learn how to
wander freely openly in our own hearts
and our own minds and our own life
without the glass door in the middle of
it all
without the fences all around it
so it's unobstructed by it all
where we don't need to advertise
ourselves or promote ourselves or
deficit explain to people who we are and
and assert ourselves on people
as a form of clinging
and a sense of well-being
and one of the benefits of discovering
such kind of well-being and peace
and ease and letting go of all this is
that
then it also might be easier to
to stand up for oneself
when society around you
defines you when society around you says
you can't be that how you how you are
you have to be different or you are
in this kind of way if we don't get
if we have our own stability inside and
peace inside
that we know and we're not wrapped up
around our identity issues
and then in the way that this clinging
is involves clinging
then it can be quite powerful to stand
up for ourselves
and say no to people not not go along
with what people are how people are
defining us
how other peoples me myself and mine
you yourself and and yours
is really oppressive for many people
and and so the idea of
really looking deeply at selfishness
and how it works with me myself and mine
is also a gift so that we don't
project you yourself
and yours onto others in ways that makes
makes them oppressed
imagine if we can live in a world where
we don't put any fences around anyone
we don't put any glass doors that block
anyone's path
where we allow the the people to be how
they are
we allow the natural world to unfold in
a beautiful way
without the limitations
and the problems of our clinging
especially the clinging to selfishness
may it be that this meditation practice
shows us the limitations
shows us the suffering of our
selfishness
so that we become
more open more free more generous more
kind
more forgiving
and more
in a certain kind of way natural the
kind of naturalness is there when
there's no clinging
so i hope that gives you something to
think about and to reflect on and
and hopefully you're forgiving of
yourself if you
happen to have some conceit or some me
myself in mind
but you might want to take a deeper look
at this this topic and make it a study
for the week and
and it's this is uh this
list that i read from the ancient texts
about intoxicated
toxicated when i saw this list i was
kind of delighted
that they being intoxicated preoccupied
caught up in
things like health and youth and
gain honor being respected fame
having followers our learning
accomplishments popularity all kinds of
things
it's been going on for thousands of
years
this is kind of what humans tend to do
especially when they come together
so if you have if you're involved in
some of it as well
you have a lot of company and you have
the company
of the buddha the freedom you have the
company of yourself perhaps in
meditation
where you're beginning to loosen up and
unstick yourselves
from all forms of selfishness
may you be may you let go of selfishness
and find out how to be really happy
in this life thank you