welcome welcome good evening good evening or maybe it's not evening when you're
listening to this so whenever it is a really warm welcome
so we'll begin with a guided meditation
i'm just taking our seat our meditation posture
and it's worthwhile taking some a little bit of time to get the
seat in a way that we feel balanced and
supported
and allowing this sense of balance and support to
maybe infuse our mood our experience of being here at this
moment
so we can sit and know that we're sitting
checking in with the body
can we have a warm welcome for whatever
experiences we're having at this moment doesn't mean they're pleasant
it just means that we're not slamming the door in the face of these experiences
maybe there's some tension in the neck or the shoulders
can bring our awareness and see if that allows some of the tension to dissipate to
soften of course without making it a project
that it has to go away
bringing attention to our jaw and the area around our eyes
other places where we often hold tension
and then to rest our awareness on the sensations of breathing
feeling the sensations maybe with the movement of the chest or
the belly
maybe feeling the air going in and out of the nose
it might be that when we first sit down there's
just a cascading waterfall of
thoughts and we only every now and then catch our breath so
to speak remember that we're oh yeah i'm supposed to be meditating
that's okay we just begin again with the sensations of breathing
it absolutely doesn't matter how many times we have to begin again
each time we do we're strengthening the capacity
with the mind to turn away from thoughts
and towards something else in this case the breath
maybe we find that we're more with the idea of the breath
rather than the actual sensations
that's okay we don't have to make it a problem
but the movement is towards actually feeling the expansion the contraction with breathing
the stretching with breathing
not so much the idea but the experience
and it can be helpful to support our being with the sensations
of breathing it can be helpful to
set the intention okay i'm going to be with the entirety
of the in-breath
setting the intention to be with the beginning middle and end
maybe we set the intention supports our practice for a few breaths and then
maybe the mind drifts away doesn't have to be a problem
we just again set the intention
to be with the entirety of the in-breath
of course we can enlarge our intention to be
with the in-breath and the out-breath
we can use setting an intention as a gentle way of
helping us connect with the sensations of breathing
without using a sledgehammer or
pouncing on the breath just simply setting an intention
to support just a little bit more connection just a little bit more effort
so we can use this practice of setting an intention
in a relaxed easy way and not a
ambitious intention necessarily
but to set the intention as a way of just applying a little bit more effort
so that our [Music] mindfulness can be a little bit more
connected with the sensations not so much just about the thinking or
the thoughts or the ideas
setting an intention as a way of making effort
[Music]
so welcome welcome welcome everybody it's nice to be here practicing together
so tonight i wanted to talk a little bit about effort
and this recognition that some type of effort is required if this path is
going to become something more than just theoretical i remember when i heard gil use this
expression of a book stand buddhists i think that's what he said but this idea of you know just reading
lots of buddha's philosophy just great but it's not the same right of course as
practicing it's the if we want to make this transition or
this movement or bridge the gap between aspiring
to and actually living this path of practice
this path of greater wisdom greater compassion then some effort
is needed some energy some activity right there's some doing
that needs to happen because certainly it takes effort to go
against the stream of our habits to go against the
stream of these patterns of that we have of body and mind that we've
been cultivating for a a lifetime and these patterns of our relationships
these patterns of social structures right that kind of like keep us in a groove
and if we want to do something a little bit different or a lot different
then it's going to require some energy some effort some activity
and we might say that right effort that is the sixth step on the
eight-fold path many of you are familiar with this we use this expression right effort we
could also say wise effort i first learned it as right effort and somehow that just that expression stays
in my mind samavayama so right effort we could say is swimming
against the stream perhaps but swimming towards the wholesome
and away from the unwholesome that's maybe one way that
we could think of right effort and this way that we can make our aspirations
be transformational and to for whatever it is whether it's the
buddhist path or learning calligraphy or pottery or
tennis or bringing along some changes in our
social world working for justice and peace all these things right
take effort and of course effort depends on energy
and we could say that or maybe i'll define for myself here that effort is like at the application of energy
is this way in which we are you a particular way in which we're using our energy but what
is energy we can think of energy we can be something that we can feel in the body
is maybe it's the sense of vitality a
maybe a really fine vibration [Music] i don't know i don't know really how to
ex explain it maybe you have your own words that you might say when you feel energetic or you
feel like you have energy how that feels and in the mind we might say that energy
is associated with a little bit of maybe glee gladness
or also with that being engaged with material with whatever material it is
we're looking at whatever media whether it's just what the senses are bringing us what we're seeing smelling
tasting etc or whatever that is that is arising
so some energy in the mind is being engaged and connected with what's happening as well as maybe
some happiness so but we don't always feel like we have
energy of course so what are some things that can support some energy one is
bringing attention to this experience of energy so maybe we feel like we don't
have quite enough but maybe we can bring to mind or feel into
sometimes we feel energy with our hands there might be a little bit of tingling or something there
or maybe there might be a way in which we can sit upright and that takes a little bit of energy so
tuning into that because just like everything else
when we bring our attention to it it brings some energy
so if we bring our attention to energy it's likely that the energy will
increase if we can do this in a way bring our attention in a way that
is not demanding that the energy be there it's not uh requiring things to be
wavered so it's not um have some secret aversion tied up with it but just resting our attention on the experience
of energy whether we have that in our mind or body is one way to bring to increase it
another way is just recognizing especially like with meditation practice or this buddhist path is to practice
with others whether that's virtually
as we are right now those of you who are on youtube with me there's something that's helpful
to sit with others we're you know irc we're offering these uh meditation
retreats online this recognition that it helps to be together even if we're not
physically together it kind of helps the energy there's a sense maybe encouragement
and the creating a container or maybe some inspiration maybe we're
inspired by somebody else's practice so it's another way in which we might
increase energy is to be with others whether physically or virtually
another way is when energy is aroused when we play at the edge of our comfort
zone that is when we get out a little bit of our grooves of these habits
but instead we touch into something a little bit different or maybe it's just a glimpse
of another possibility like oh oh what was that oh there's something
here this direction i know for me that's often has happened
that when meditation practice and often i feel like when stumbling into some new territory i know i've had this
experience a number of times like oh that was different and then this kind of tends to be a
little bit more engagement so whether it's with our meditation practice with our daily life
but i like this word kind of play play at the edge of our comfort zone
using this word comfort zone but we could also say the edge of what's familiar
or edge of kind of these grooves sometimes we get in so just explore
and then buna talked about um arousing energy not so much how to well maybe it is a
little bit about how to but also um some encouragement and this is just an
excerpt from a suta that's longer and has more elements to it but
i don't know why i kind of get a kick out of this so this uh suta goes like this
well here again here's just an excerpt a mendicant a biku a practitioner
somebody who's practicing amending kent has some work to do and they think i have some work to do
but while doing it my body will get tired
so let me lie down so they lie down and don't rouse energy
for attaining the unattained for achieving the unachieved and for realizing the
unrealized so this idea just thinking about doing work things like okay that's going to make me
tired i better lie down and then the buddha of course he contrasts this well
a mendicant has some work to do and they think i have some work to do
while working it's not easy to focus on the instruction of the buddhas
so i better preemptively rouse up some energy for attaining the unattained
for achieving the unachieved for realizing the unrealized
so they're seeing like oh okay i'm not going to be able to practice i won't
awakening i don't expect is going to happen in the next moment because i'll be working so
let me uh work let me apply energy effort towards my practice
now rather than lying down
there's a few more but um has work to do furthermore is to go on a journey
um i have to go on a journey but while walking my body will get tired
so let me lie down and they lay down and they don't rouse energy and then in contrast
a mendicant has to go on a journey while walking it's not easy to focus on
the instructions of the buddha i better preemptively browse up energy
and the suta goes on with six other cases i'm going for alms rounds not having
enough food and having finished work and some other things but i appreciate very
much kind of the buddha recognizing yeah we often do this i better conserve my
energy there i'm not going to practice or it's i have other things to do that
are pressing i can't practice while i'm doing that i i have this either or
idea and instead the buddha is saying no we don't have
to believe these ideas that we have that that we can't practice while we're doing
something or that we can't use these as encouragement to practice some of these
other responsibilities that we have they can be a support for practice as opposed
to a distraction so an opportunity to rouse energy
i think um yeah so maybe that's not language that i would use but you know just to bring up
a little bit more energy so we can have some effort
and so right effort is about
yeah i'm sorry about that having to cough kind of uh with some urgency there
the right effort as swimming towards the wholesome and away from the unwholesome
so gregory kramer he uh summarizes this uh as this practice of right effort as out
with the bad and in with the good whereas we could say the bad refers to
those actions that bring harm either to ourselves or others or those
mental qualities that keep us from settling down and seeing clearly headed towards more wisdom
so this classic core of what is abandoned or i'm just going to
name a list of lists here many of you will be familiar with this
these five hindrances maybe the three unwholesome roots that
is greed hatred and delusion the taints
this uh intoxication with sense pleasures intoxication with self-making and ignorance
so these are the some of the things that we're abandoning of course we're abandoning clinging
upadana clinging to the aggregates clinging to this conceit of i am
clinging to views so this is so much like buddhist practice right
it's like abandoning what is unwholesome and cultivating what is wholesome and
often we give dharma talks just on one little aspect of this
but just many of you are familiar with this kind of these are some of the unwholesome qualities that we're
abandoning and then of course on the other side the wholesome ones the seven factors of awakening
the wholesome roots of non-greed generosity
non-hatred which is love and non-delusion which is wisdom
we cultivate the five faculties we cultivate the brahman faharas the pyramids i had all these lists so i'm
just giving you a list of lists just to help maybe kind of
sometimes for me it's helpful to have like really that 10 000 foot view like
okay sometimes we're abandoning things sometimes we're cultivating things but
of course there's this interrelationship between abandoning the unwholesome and
cultivating the wholesome it's not like they're completely independent sometimes it's helpful to
organize our thoughts thinking that there's that which to be abandoned in that which to be cultivated
but there's this dynamic process or this dynamism between
these two and we can work with us so of course we notice
that when we're cultivating calm with our meditation practice
then some agitation is getting abandoned
when we're cultivating loving-kindness it will
is getting abandoned
so we can use this when we this want to abandon the hindrance of desire
we work with the entrances often by just bringing our attention to them
as we abandon the hindrance we can see that
more settledness arises more able to be present
so this inter-relationship between them and sometimes it might be that
what's unwholesome is really predominant in our mind predominant in our experience
and that's what we work with maybe we're already a little bit more settled and able to cultivate
some of these other qualities whether it's the brahma vahrehs the paramis the
factors of awakening just simple mindfulness or concentration
but there's if we're going to be applying effort on either of these ways of abandoning or
cultivating but there's also the way the manner in which we do it like how we
do it one thing is the direction where we're going but another is how we do it
because it's really easy to conflate effort like this word effort with this
kind of uh intense maybe we want to say over intense like focus kind of like a
bearing down sometimes i use this expression of a sledgehammer there's this feeling of you
know i'm going to do this now and there's this sledgehammer with our attention or
with our focus perhaps or maybe we have some kind of dharma
ambition which is beautiful to have these inspirations but this dharma ambition for greater peace
and freedom gets translated into this over-striving and
efforting in such a way that is not sustainable
and ends up being unhelpful i i learned this the hard way probably
it's the only way to learn it i would say i'll say that at one retreat um in a
practice discussion with one of the teachers the teachers said to me that i'm a striver and i was
like quite offended i am not a striver
of course later i saw i was driving so much but you know i didn't realize it
and i have certainly spent many of retreats where you know kind of like this real bearing down on trying to get
concentrated and certainly i could get concentrated but there was a brittleness to it there was a kind of a little bit
of a unhealthiness to this like kind of this aversion almost a hatred towards
everything that wasn't supporting my getting concentrated so there can definitely be this
over efforting over striving in a way that isn't healthy but at the same time especially with
meditation practice or any of the buddhist practice that we do if we don't apply enough effort
if we're a little bit cavalier
lexidasical perhaps then this just leads to discouragement because we don't see the fruits of
effort if we're not really placing effort and then this leads to doubt
often like does this work does this practice work do these teachers work teachings work what about
these teachers do they know what they're talking about so if we don't we have to apply some
amount of effort in order to see some of the fruits
so and just maybe some different levels of effort are needed at different times
and again uh gregory kramer he says that sometimes right effort is like the
strenuous effort required to turn the soil and plant our gardens
let's work to turn the soil and plant the gardens
and then he continues at other times right effort is like the steady application of the sun's heat
as it slowly penetrates the soil and warms the seeds
if we want to see the fruit of our efforts both are required turning the soil planting the seed
letting them have sun letting them have water just soaking up the water
so discerning which type of effort is needed for whatever we're doing is part
of this practice of right effort and i would say is also part of the art of
practice is knowing how much effort and not only knowing how much but how to
turn the dial like how can we back off and how can we apply more
and so notice one way we can do this is to practice during meditation
with a mindfulness of breathing
as i did in the guided meditation we can just first allow the attention to
if we notice that they were lost in thought a lot just allow the attention to begin again so the kind of the energy
is to like just begin again with the sensations of breathing in this example
and then when we starting to feel like okay there's a little bit more attention to breathing there's a little
bit more capacity or a little bit more ability to be with the breath
then we can look at what is the effort that we're applying and just
ask ourselves this question in a really gentle relaxed way
not in a demanding voice but what is the effort and we can as i had said in the
guided meditation we can use intention to help turn up the effort if
we feel like we need it so we could see
are we pouncing on the breath are we like really holding on to it straining
or perhaps there's another way in which we're kind of mindful like yeah okay
i'll get around to it i know the breath is there but this thought is very
provocative and i'll kind of do both at the same time there's this kind of mindfulness where yeah we know we're
breathing but we're also kind of simultaneously thinking
and because there isn't a lot of clarity it feels like there's two parallel tracks going on and because we have
mindfulness of the breath we feel like we're mindful actually what's happening if we had a little bit more focus we could see that
it's mindful of the breath and then a thought and then the breath and then thought we're like the mind is actually wavering back and forth
so we don't need a lot we don't need strong effort but sometimes we might need just a
little bit more effort and with great meditation we can set the
intention it's one way of just dialing up the effort a little bit setting the intention okay i'm going to
be mindful for the entirety of the in-breath so it's not a very ambitious intention
but it's something in which we can do setting the intention is a way in which
we can it makes it more likely that in fact that will be with all of the in-breath
and chances are we'll be with a number of in-breaths and then the
the mindfulness will start to wane and when we notice that we can set the attention
again and so
we might if we need to lessen the effort during the meditation if we find that we
really are kind of really tight and this often can happen when we're trying to get concentrated we might have
this idea that we really have to i think gill uses this expression bear down
this real way we have to strive strain maybe
so one way to lessen the effort is to open up the awareness
so one way to open up the awareness is if we're being with the breath is maybe to just be more broadly with the body
sometimes we i say that expression to sit to know we're sitting maybe that's one way maybe that's too
broad maybe just to choose some contact of the body where
it's touching the seat where your feet are touching what your hands are touching
as well as the sensations of breathing so not such a small point
but a little bit larger or another way to broaden our awareness is to bring it to
sounds kind of like open up the awareness to sounds and just allowing sounds to arise
so we're still being mindful but not bearing down and straining quite so much
so that's one way in which we might be able to decrease the effort
but we might also have this fear of and resistance to
the application of this energy or this some exertion or zeal
sometimes in this who does those of you are familiar with this that language this seal
exertion and i think even this language often gets translated as strive
so we might have this fear of this or this real resistance to that might feel
like the last thing we want is somebody telling us to strive this feeling of a having a
what is that you know kind of like the the whip but can we come to an understanding
of right effort that's helps helpful and wholesome
that recognizes that there there can be a joy that's associated with a heartfelt
commitment commitment to something that's wholesome
and and like this joy arises when the it's the effort isn't too much
but instead is more like a commitment yes i am committing myself to this practice
for this next hour or maybe buddhist for this next half hour however long you're sitting
or for just buddhist practice more in general taking the refuges
and can we also allow ourselves to apply ourselves with
confidence like that we can back off if it's too much effort and we
can turn it up if it's not quite enough effort
can we come to this understanding of applying effort through investigation through exploration through noticing
in which we can appreciate that applying effort to this practice is
such a beautiful way in which we can get out of the streams of our habits
the streams of our social structures and our relationships and help us to find more and more
freedom more and more ease while we are
abandoning the unwholesome and cultivating the wholesome
so may our effort be a support for us not feel something burdensome something that we have to do
not something that is overly taxing so that it is not sustainable
but instead that allows us to have this commitment to practice this commitment to
non-harming this commitment to greater peace this commitment to
discovering more freedom so that those we come in contact with and
spreading out from there so that our practice and the way we apply effort
can be a support not only for ourselves but for all beings everywhere
thank you