good morning and uh this is
the first couple days i hadn't figured out outside my range how to see the
chat that people are sharing that are on the youtube stream and i
have to say that i can see it i can't read it all while i'm
talking but i can see it and it's quite lovely it's really i can feel the sangha
this spread all over and quite beautiful and i realize there's many of you that
have have this as your regular practice that you're committed to being here every day
and just want to celebrate that with you that this has been made possible
and sort of one of the gifts that's come out of these
very difficult recent times
so beginning today with air we've talked about
earth and water and fire and now moving on to include air
and this last year [Music] has been
particularly poignant the year and a half really around air
we've seen sort of this and we've gained so much understanding
about how connected we are and it's come through our awareness of
breath so there's um you know i really
uh last summer and with george floyd the eye can't
breathe and how deeply we were all affected by that
and rightly so and how that phrase
like got us right where we where we live and where we die
and raised consciousness in a huge way in a way that was really good
and in the midst of that we have
covid which is has made us so aware
of how connected we all are by breath that this
thing this virus that is carried on the breath has traveled the entire world
we it's it's sort of a a terrible and yet
clarifying
unfolding of how clearly our breath is intimately
connected everyone you can't be left out of this
and then again in a another way with the smoke and you know
when the smoke from the california fires reaches all the way to the east coast
and it's like oh right the air we breathe it moves everywhere
so there's something so intimate about this
and sometimes challenging i want to acknowledge that part too
but the breath we start our practice with our breath that's where we begin
and there's so much in that there's so much potency available if we
start to connect with this universal breath that we all share
so we'll begin our practice i'll offer a poem to start
and i'll offer a few different ways to connect with this
element of air
beginning with a poem as you're settling into your meditation spot
finding your ground this is from dana faults
walk slowly it only takes a reminder to breathe
a moment to be still and just like that something in me settles softens
makes space for imperfection the harsh voice of judgment drops to a
whisper and i remember again that life isn't a relay race that we will all cross the
finish line that waking up to life is what we were born for
as many times as i forget catch myself charging forward without even knowing where i'm going
that many times i can make the choice to stop to breathe
and be and walk slowly into the mystery
so as you settle into your posture feeling your connection with the ground
feel the pressure of your buttocks on the chair the cushion
feel your feet in contact with the ground
allow yourself to feel the spine rising up
and then the muscles softening responding to the pull of gravity
softening in the shoulders
letting the eyes soften
and allow yourself to tune in a little bit to the
place where you are recognizing that even if you're in a building
but just outside there's trees
there's plants there's other beings
and allow yourself to feel how these other beings just acknowledging perhaps
conceptually and then just sensing it a little that these other beings
are breathing that the trees are breathing
they breathe out carbon dioxide and breathe in oxygen
the algae of the ocean are breathing in great quantities
the deep forests the tropical forest the boreal forests
all breathing and as we breathe in we breathe with
them
and the breath is carried on the wind through the air
spreading everywhere
and as you breathe feel this breath
as it comes into your body
through this open door of the throat
feel the breath in the area of the diaphragm the solar plexus
as it comes in and fills you here
as you breathe it [Music]
as you breathe in let the breath be felt in the lower belly
sense it from the inside the world coming in through the throat
all this breathing coming right into your lower belly just notice you don't need to change the
breath to feel it there just notice that you can feel it
let yourself feel the breath all the way to the base of the body
in the perineum into the joints of the hips it'll become subtler there
but it's still affected we can still sense the breath
here
perhaps noticing that you can feel it even along the back along the lower
lumbar and the sacrum
notice if you can have even some sense that the breath flows down your legs
the slight ripple of movement we know that in fact the breath
the oxygen is being transported through our blood down
to every cell but can you sense it just the subtle energetic movement
of breath flowing down into your legs perhaps you can tell part way down your
legs or fully whatever you can feel
or sense
this nourishment of breath
perhaps noticing the whole body from the waist down
that it's breathing
it's being breathed no effort required
letting yourself sense up into the chest area
you can feel it most clearly to the front but notice that you can feel the breath also along
the back the ribs expanding just a little
the breath along the sides of the ribs
then feeling the breath in the upper chest and both in the front in the back
under the whole region of the collar girdle shoulder girdle
feel the breath in the right shoulder
see if you can notice this sensation of breath traveling
and including your right arm breath
nourishment the molecules of the amazon and the ocean
algae breathing in flowing down your arms
and the left shoulder
sometimes the shoulders the body has to soften some to allow
more this sense of air to be filled
and be nourished letting the breath flow down the left arm
feeling your body from the neck down one
full breathing body
the blessing of breath coming in and flowing to every corner
every cell
and letting this sense of the breath
fill your head as well the neck filling all the way through all your
sinuses filling your brain
breath nourishing deep inside the skull
feeling the whole body breathing
being breathed aliveness
notice this air element may have some aspect of vibration or lightness
we can't see this air we can see its effect we can feel it
move in the body
you might notice that thoughts when they come are much like this element of air
they have this air quality they appear ephemeral
cannot really be touched directly and then they just drift away disappear
right back in to the empty space they came from
allow your thoughts to come and go
like the air
drifting in and out like rustling leaves
and as you breathe you don't need to exclude anything sound comes through the air
sensations arise thoughts come and go
all to be breathed in and allowed to breathe out
foreign
feeling the whole body breathing and in those moments where we start to
latch onto a thought where we cling to some
thing that's arisen just notice that there's a way the breath there's a constriction a contraction we
lose contact with the fullness of the breath and then we remember
that we're being breathed and we can rest in this breath
and the relaxation [Music] the fullness is available again
let yourself notice any coming and going
every cell in your body being awoken
alive with the breath of the world this thin
layer of air covering the surface
this living alive breath that we share
[Music] you are part of it
you too are breathing breathing with the whole world
no inside no outside simply breath
coming and going
breath perfading your whole body the space around you
inside each living being
rest and allow yourself to be held great sacred breath
foreign
it's fun to realize that in spite of our distance and the spread and the way we
just sort of appear as i appear as a voice and you maybe as a
typing or on zoom as a box but we're all still breathing together
it's all still moving around and this breath is so important in our
sangha i mean in our practice it's and in our sangha but in our practice the
buddha started his instructions on the four foundations with pay
attention to the breath does it come in short does it come in long
how does it feel and many of us are very intimate with
our breath sometimes our breath can be challenging and we can go to the places of constriction or
places where it's difficult and i always appreciate the the instruction of go to where there's
ease and pleasure in the breath go to where you can find it
this uh connection aspect of it it's so interesting we start with the
breath we are connected to it and yet it has this insubstantial
it's it's a doorway it's starting to move into this mysterious earth is so here solid right
there and the water we can touch and now as we're moving towards the air we're
starting to move into this area of the mysterious and it's interesting the word spirit
in greek was breath wind and that word turned into our western in
our languages into the word spirit and anima comes from latin
air breath to animate animal
this connection that has been there in our language is intuitively known by us that the breath
the spirit the animation the aliveness
are all so intimately connected and to let ourselves feel that
this animation that comes this spirit
in some indigenous traditions when they talk about the great spirit
the that's the translation we get they're talking at least in the ones i know the dna
that it they're speaking specifically to the wind to the air
that that is the spirit the great spirit that connects
the dna say that's uh the navajo they call themselves the dna
the wind within one is in no way autonomous for it is in a continual
process of interchange with the various winds that surrounds one and indeed is entirely a part of the
holy wind itself it's a quote from david abrams book
a spell with the sensuous and he doesn't name the particular individual so that's why i didn't say
this idea that the spirit is moving around this aliveness and coming into us
and then adding to that that our breath is our
speech that when we speak we are
speaking with this sacred breath that comes out of us
and what is our speech this connection this possibility this opportunity for
truth and beauty and then how it gets distorted and
confused but we can come back and this is often
in spiritual traditions and certainly in ours singing and chanting
are part of the tradition we join our breath together in speaking and feeling
the sacred
there's a play here happening i hope you can hear it between the scene and the
unseen that happens through the breath through the wind and we see it all
around us you know when the when the leaves move on the tree we see the
result of it when the clouds move we see this sort of
wind air made tangible for a moment and then dissipating or being moved
and we live in this world of breath
in the body as we feel it and just as i talk even keep noticing see if you can
feel your breath perhaps even the words that i'm saying can you breathe them in
what is that like to let them come in and be felt in your body
to stay connected to this breath and breath has a
lightness to it in some ways you might say it's the balancing with the earth
element it brings up and it's often talked about in the
buddhist tradition as having the vibration quality and i think of that as kind of this aliveness that we feel in
us you know there's something that it's almost hard to pin down what
it is but when you feel into your body you can feel a certain aliveness here
this is the air element as we recognize it right here in us
and as i mentioned in the meditation the the thoughts are understood to be an
expression of the air element and that makes sense doesn't it the way
that thoughts just sort of appear out of nothing they have this sort of temporary
quality and then they disappear
dissipate into nothing once again and when we can understand and sense
the way the thoughts are this air element it can help us
become less be less attached less clinging to them as if they were solid
right that's where we get in trouble when we start believing that our thoughts are solid and real in the final
word on everything and instead recognizing oh they come and
they go and even the words that we say they're sacred on one side
and on another way they just disappear into nothing
and we're doing all of this in communion
with the algae the plants that breathe one a practice that i
offer to you that's something that i like to do is i go out in the where there's trees or a plant and i go
out and i sit with it and i breathe with it and what is it to breathe with this
other being that's so different in some ways than us and yet it too is
breathing i started out very early on in
high school being fascinated with plants and the soma that are breathing and
taking in the those are that's their their breathing mechanism
and us too we're all being breathed
feel your breath let yourself breathe
i want to end with a poem from
rumi called in every breath
in every breath if you're the center of your own desires you'll lose the grace
of your beloved but if in every breath you blow away your self-claim
the ecstasy of love will soon arrive in every breath if you're the center of
your own thoughts the sadness of autumn will fall on you but if in every breath you strip naked
just like a winter the joy of spring will grow from within
all your patients come from the push for gain of patience let go of the effort and peace will
arrive all your unfulfilled desires are from your greed for gain of fulfillments let
go of them all and they will be sent as gifts fall in love with the agony of love not
the ecstasy then the beloved will fall in love with you
i want to offer today as a practice allow yourself to feel the generosity of
the world of all the beings that are participating in this breath
the generosity of all the plants and as you breathe out
as you breathe out others breathe in feel it in your body right now
and whenever you remember today not just your breath not just the breath
but that you're breathing with no inside no outside
all of us breathing together breathing breathing alive animated
thank you all