[Music]
foreign [Music]
i [Music]
me [Music]
[Music]
good morning or afternoon wherever you are in the
world welcome this morning i hope you all were able to settle in
and enjoy that chant by the venerable rena sakhar
it sets such a lovely tone for the sacredness of our time
and of our being and prepares us for settling in my name is amana
and i will be guiding you in the meditation and and offer a few
reflections today so at this time i invite you to
come into a comfortable posture one that suits your unique frame
and needs of your body
disregard any notion of
the posture that you feel you should have
and allow yourself to be a student of the body
and for it to inform what will bring you ease
for when the body is at ease the mind is better able to settle
i invite you now to sense into the parts of your body
that create the foundation of your posture
the touch points of the earth where you connect perhaps the soles of
the feet on the back of the thighs and butter
or if you're in a laying posture if that is what suits your body
the whole of the backside
take these initial moments now to feel into the connection
your connection to the earth
earth resting on earth
and since the energetic exchange
you may choose to take in a few deep breaths if that's available to you
and slowly exhale out anything that's not needed in this moment
and i invite you to slowly scan the body
from your foundation the soles of the
feet your seat upward
with kind attention to release any tension
or holding that you may encounter breathing spaciousness there
and take your time
and when you feel complete in offering the deepest peace
to your body heart mind
allow yourself to bring your awareness to your anchor whatever it may be
the breath sound touch
and his thoughts arise do not push them away in aversion or judgment
simply allow the witness in you to notice
the arising and passing away
and at that moment at that very second that you
recognize thoughts have arisen or that you may
even be caught in thought celebrate that moment turn your full
attention to that second
for it is the time that mindfulness has returned
offer your full awareness to mindfulness
the invitation now is to continue to practice in this way
should there be recurring thoughts
difficult thoughts
turn your attention there
notice the quality
offer it your kind attention
and release it back to your anchor
knowing that that recognition of his presence
is the moment mindfulness has returned
[Music]
hmm
this is the miracle of practice settling the mind heart body
i would like to offer at this time just a few minutes bio break
let's come back at 10 05.
[Music]
so [Music]
m [Music]
me [Music]
[Music]
you [Music]
i
[Music]
me [Music]
foreign [Music]
[Music]
me
hi thank you uh we'd like to welcome amana to our imc sunday dharma talk
and a little bit about romano amana brembi johnson is a core teacher at the east bay meditation
center in oakland california and a guiding teacher for the center's
spiritual teacher and leadership training four decades of contemplative practice in multiple
traditions contributes to a form of teaching meditation guidance and mentoring
that offers a diverse range of access to practice amana's life work emerges from the
intersections of spirituality social justice body awareness and
intuitive creativity thank you for joining us
thank you kevin and welcome everyone
and thank you for putting the chant back on during the break it's so soothing i loved hearing it
again so
as we come together today i'd like to take a moment to acknowledge
the land where we are and the indigenous the indigenous people who live
on this land i acknowledge that i am on traditional
unseated land of the first people of oakland the lausanne ohlone people both
past and present who speak the church in your language
i'd also like to offer a lineage acknowledgement of our practice of
buddhism which is an asian heritage and tradition
a tribute attributed and and and it comes to us
through 500 years of written language
of unwritten language and was recorded in sanskrit and pali before other
language translations and let it be acknowledged that these
practices were preserved nurtured and handed down for millennia
before reaching western shores and western languages
that in many ways the people and cultures of origin
can and in many instances have been erased in much the same way
that the people who originally inhabited inhabited these lands have been
erased so let us remember our ancestors
and the ancestors of this land who survived pandemics
the destruction of their known world and their ways of living
may we hold their names dearly in our hearts and minds
and may this acknowledgement serve as a reminder of our inextricable connection to the practices
we share and the places we inhabit
as well as a reminder of our connection to the earth
across species and across time
before i go into the talk i'd like to share with you an excerpt from a public notice sent
from the east bay meditation center in regards to the rash of violence against asian and american
asian pacific islander communities
the east bay meditation center expresses our collective grief
an outrage at the ongoing violent targeting of asian and
asian americans and in the wake of the most recent tragic attack in atlanta
we stand in solidarity with asian and asian americans in beloved community
these violent acts of hatred are arising due to the current and
historical oppression of asian americans in the u.s
they are the direct result of our nation's deep roots in white supremacy
imperialism and xenophobia
i'd like to invite you all to participate in a moment of silence
as i recite the names of the beings whose lives have been senselessly taken during the atlanta
mass murdering spree which happened just on tuesday
you may choose to place your hand over your heart or slide the eyes closed
or simply just be present
soon chung park yoon jung grant
delina ashley young paul andre michels
xiao ji tan [Music]
and those whose names i do not know names that have not been spoken
or names that have been forgotten
[Music] uh
and even in the midst of all this it's so important
to focus and bring to mind the beautiful qualities that exist in our lives
and it's a pleasure to be here with you today and to share my experience of the dharma
on this first day of spring it's a day of great significance as a
time of birth and rebirth of renewal and awakening
with hope may may it mark the dawning of a new day that follows a difficult period of
isolation massive death and deep
internal grief we've been living in a difficult time of disease and
hatred living in a triple pandemic really on many levels
the most obvious is the coronavirus that has plagued the earth with a cloak of
illness and death the more disguised virus of white
supremacy that has infected the infrastructure of systems
and institutions all around the world with hatred of difference and the loathing
for the natural diversity of life itself and a third pandemic of
untruths lacking why speech
a blatant spreading of deceptions that have blinded and wrecked a scourge
of mass confusion and metastasized delusion for so
very many we've been living in a time of massive individual and communal grief
and what is fortunate is that the dharma is immensely vast and far-reaching
that it touches into every aspect of our lives the scene and the unseen acknowledging
the known the unknown and the unknowable
there are many paths to enter the dharma some resonate sweetly within our hearts
and others present difficult challenges to overcome
the undoing of our harmful conditioning
you know life has always been hard to pin down but lately the reality that we are not
in control of our lives our futures
our circumstances has been even more apparent
right now we're living in a liminal realm a transitional groundless place
here nothing is certain we're at the threshold of an unknown
the threshold of an unknown this invisible cloak of delusion
the delusion of predictability it's been pulled back to reveal the truth of uncertainty our
lives today have brought into the open the instantaneous
passing of each moment
and this truth has been there all along yet these current circumstances have
forced an entire world to not only face but to embody
the truth of the moment-to-moment change in every breath of our unpredictable
lives the buddha states that every life
is marked by three characteristics of existence
impermanence anichah the pali word
suffering or dissatisfaction dukkha
and egolessness sometimes referred to as not self anata
our intuitive understanding and somewhat forced embodiment
of a nietzsche impermanence is the characteristic that opens the
door to our release from attachments which is the true
source of personal internal liberation from suffering
to release to let go
to settle to feel into the emptiness
of this existence and as the truth of the unreliability
of life continues to unfold we can choose to embrace tremendous
suffering by clinging on to old habits and familiar comforts
or we can welcome the stillness within us that holds the power of awakening
intellectually we know that nothing in this life
in this world will last forever and that the longer we live we will
certainly see everything that we have come to know and love wither die
vanish into the intangible
however true understanding of impermanence is non-cognizable
we can only know the truth of it in the unnamable experiential terrain of our
bodies where there is a resonance of memory
that is a part of our very being
sati to remember
to remember it's there within us you know the ancestors are not out there
somewhere those who have come before us they live within us
they move through our bloodstream they're in the marrow of our bones
the chain of dna in our bodies that gets passed on from generation to generation the
memories are there
not only of experience of loves and hurts and pains and traumas
but the memory of what we are it is there
but these these memories are easily forgotten because we live in and are conditioned by a culture of
memory loss and dwell in the immediate gratification of short-term memory and distraction
we move about barely present to the moment enchanted by a a world of rapid
information bites the media technology and corporate
marketing schemes that create a culture of attention
deficit beings and now that the wheels have all but
grind it to a stop we are even more susceptible to the
enticements of distraction being out of our comfort zone
being able to move about in the ways that we've always moved
the deep insight necessary to cultivate an easeful and fulfilled life in the
midst of chaos and horror and the enchantments of delusion
arise when the mind is still silent
and unencumbered aware
it's quiet you that allows us to see the trappings that lead to our own
destruction it is stillness that throws open the doors to our
discerning internal wisdom a wisdom that is unempirical and immaterial
unquantifiable when the loud noise of want and desire
and dislike have been quieted the unspoken wisdom
contained in the deepest recesses of the body arises the wisdom of ancient knowing the wisdom
of all that has gone before us the wisdom held in the whispering earth
all become available to the conscious mind
this is a wisdom that reminds us remembers to us
that we are all a web of connection that is unseen and unbroken
that there's really no space between us that we are part of the space the
air the void that we are the pause
this is a time for remembering what it is that we have forgotten
connecting with the memory contained within the body
mindfulness of the body is no accident the first door to awakening
the first of the foundations of mindfulness
our cultural default is wired to do too many things move too fast take on too many projects
and juggle too many jobs in our endless efforts to make ends meet or to acquire
the things that we have been told and conditioned we need for a fulfilled life
and accompanying this normalized way of life are deeply seated feelings of overwhelm
overload fatigue sleep deprivation
these are all systems and mental states that keep us from remembering
that we are sacred in our very flesh that we are light beings of infinite
energy living forth just a brief
whisper of a moment on this material plane
that we are interconnected to all around us both animate and
what is seemingly inanimate i read just the other day that
it's been noticed that trees have a heartbeat
so spaced out that it's not hardly at all perceptible
everything we touch vibrates with the energetic charge of life the same charge of life that is apparent
in our senses when we allow the mind to settle and be
with what is
constantly juggling the balls where do we find the time to reflect
upon the moment when do we stop to take in the effects
of that incident that arose today yesterday on tuesday
and before that where do we tuck away the horror story
that we witnessed or the daily infractions that got stuffed down
packed on top of the other the other the other unresolved stories now
absorbed in the body awaiting their time when attention will be turned in that
direction you know living like this is to
constantly stub the toe and not take the time to attend to it
in the rush of getting to the next task
today in the quiet of our homes for those of us who have homes
we get to turn over this rock where the slippery lizard of privilege
remains hidden from sight you know lately we've heard a lot about
white privilege but privilege is not only white
each one of us has a degree of privilege that others do
not have if we are listening the current
circumstances can help us tremendously to bring our
awareness to where we fall on that scale
where do we stand when placed amongst those who experience these circumstances these dire
circumstances as a continuation of the threat of death that has always
been there
you know before the pandemic hit i said oh good goodness
there are more and larger tint cities everywhere all over the place
as i turned the key to come into my home that i've made
comfortable and a beautiful refuge safe from the outside world
and now on the few times that i leave the house and drive down the street
the ten cities are still there but they're much smaller
what does that mean
i think it means that i've had the privilege of being
sheltered away sheltered away from death and disease
for a few moments and that there are many who had no
shelter no shelter in place no access to medicine
these words that i'm sharing with you are about memory and what it means to remember what it
means to turn a kind attention
to all about us all around us to wake up to see
to remember all that it is that we have forgotten
as the vaccines take hold in our lives begin to open up a bit
can we can we remember what it was like to stop
and bring awareness to our stub toe
will we choose to return to the abnormal life of rushing to make plans and
cramming as many tasks as possible into the time frame of each moment
will we examine the ways in which we ourselves contribute to systems of harm
in the world through our livelihood and our speech
and through our actions
and should we choose to engage in those examinations will we ask ourselves for forgiveness
for the ways we've been complacent and contributing to systems
and institutions and ways of life that are harmful
to all beings and to the earth we all have a part in this
perhaps as our world reopens little by little we will be we will welcome with open arms
the innate compassion that has been waiting to fully emerge from within
have you felt the beautiful qualities knocking at your heart's door
qualities that have been waiting to be shared with others
even those beings outside of our chosen beloved communities
maybe this life experience this trial just maybe has shaken us up
just a bit out of our conditioned trance in a way that we might
cherish the pure gold of this breath of this time this very brief
time of our lives
maybe we will deepen the practices necessary to explore the essential parts of our
being the time is now
it's always now the time is always now but the time is now to draw upon
our deepest most precious resources that we have been practicing and saving
up especially for this occasion
what have we been practicing for
to re-imagine to draw upon all of our intuitive
wisdom to remember the wisdom of the ages that flows through our veins we recognize
the truth when we hear it it resonates in our bodies
it perks us up because it's there
this is the time to re-imagine a new world
not a remaking of the old world but something never before seen to envision how we can live
in the deepest most beautiful way possible
you know i want to share this quote from clarissa pinkola estes my friends
do not lose heart we were made for these times
i have heard it from so many recently
who are deeply and properly bewildered
they're concerned about the state of affairs in our world now ours
is a time of almost daily astonishment and righteous rage over the latest
degradations of what matters most to civilized visionary people
you are right in your assessments the lustre and hubris some have aspired to while
endorsing acts so heinous against children
elders everyday people the poor the unguarded the health the help the
the helpless is breathtaking yet i urge you gentle you
to please not spend your spirit dry by bewelling these difficult
times especially did not lose hope
most particularly because the fact is that we were made for these times
she goes on to say that when a great ship is in harbor and
moored it is safe there is no doubt
but that is not what great ships are built for
let us not forget that we are great ships
so on this first day of spring
let us join the prayers of many in the northern hemisphere who honor the
spring equinox and plant during the time of the growing
moon and set a collective intention to create
to fashion a better world
with our words with our actions with our deeds to bring the ethics of the dharma of our
practice into these areas of our lives
to create a world free of hatred and the violence of terrorism
this starts in here because we are the contents of the world
it is an internal as as sylvia borstein says it's an inside job
thank you for your kind attention i'd like to just take a moment to
let the words fall away to bring your awareness to the resonance
in your body to notice what is activated or what has
arisen there to drop the story lines
the questioning the judgment the interrogation
to free ourselves of any anything that we don't need
and simply listen to the wisdom of our bodies
[Music]
and as we close
i'd like to bring a dedication of merit
today we have generated good deeds that entitle us to a spiritual reward
as an act of generosity we offer the merit generated from our actions today
to radiate outward into the world at large and to land upon and rest with those who are less
fortunate than we are may it reach its long tentacles through
the illusion of space between all that there is and defeat the
enemy of wrongdoing may it land in the hearts and minds of
those who are steeped in suffering those who are stalked
and hunted those who are hungry and imprisoned in the trance of
ignorance we offer the fruits of our merit to all
living beings who crawl on the earth and swim in the waters of this world
all who fly and hop who walk and climb
all those who see without eyes and hear without ears we offer the merit of our practice
to all creatures above us below us to the right and the left seen in the
unseen the known the unknown in the unknowable
may all beings all beings
be free
[Music] so
you