foreign
warm greetings from imc in redwood city california
and uh i have a delightful feeling of the goodwill that uh somehow
circles uh the spot that i'm in with through all the youtube kind of spreading out in all
directions and i hope that each of you maybe can feel the same thing that
from your spot their circles of goodwill as this community gathers around the globe
and so this week i'm offering little
exercises mindfulness exercises that go along with the darmette them the teachings that i'm
doing and so the idea is to do continue with your
mindfulness practice as you do it but then this little exercise might
be relevant that you could do as you go along and now this one
has to do with the idea that something happens
and then we react to it of course we don't always react but there are reactions
there's a a difficult sound outside uncomfortable
sound and then we react to it we get involved in it we get
for and against it we start thinking about it it might not be a perfect match for the
our english idea of react reaction but the buddha
used the word not entanglement sometimes it's translated into english
as fetter so a knot getting knotted up in something
and so this idea of getting caught maybe we use in english
but uh you know if you get caught in a spider web the spider web is kind of responsible uh when we get knotted up
we're the ones who create the knot we tie ourselves up
and so as you go along in this meditation i want to say one more thing that
this way in which we get knotted up with things caught in things is
not always so conscious uh it kind of happens a little bit but not not necessarily in the unconscious
but it happens kind of under the radar we're busy focusing on whatever we do
and we don't notice some of the more subtle ways we get entangled and caught
so at this exercise as you we go along doing the basic mindfulness practice
and uh whatever you notice whatever you're noticing whatever like
if you're noticing the in-breath of the out breath you're noticing a sound a body sensation a feeling whatever it is
that comes into awareness if there is a
if you're caught in it reacting to it and tangled with it
then use the word label not k-n-o-t
and i kind of lighten this label because uh it can also be spelled n-o-t
so in other words uh not this let's not let's not get entangled let's not get knotted up
so you say very gently lovingly calmly not not
there's a knot recognizing there's a knot and a little subliminal kind of feeling or maybe not maybe i don't need
to so just not and just notice so if you start thinking about something
start thinking about your breath in a subtle way maybe without any discomfort you are kind of not in the
buddhist language you're not knotted up in it you're now involved in it so maybe involved is an english
word for this but um knotted up and um
so if this seems like too much or you know you know you don't care for this you please you don't have to do it
but um but it might be interesting to notice how often
in some way or other you get involved in what's happening and uh interested in might be
interesting to see what happens if you just quietly uh recognize it as a not not
so taking a
meditative posture
establishing posture that's upright or alert or supportive for you
and the one that also allows you to relax
to relax to
make room for yourself to become for calmer calmness to be here as well
even if you're agitated there could be a
a wave of calmness or a envelope of calmness around it
gently closing your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
with the idea that these deeper breaths are calming you bringing some calm some subtleness
especially as you exhale a calming peaceful effect
breathing in breathing out
letting your breathing return to normal and on the exhale for a little while
relax your body different parts of your body with the idea that each little micro
relaxation is a gentle calming settling
and steadying yourself on a normal breath
calming yourself into an attention centered on breathing
maybe the exhale has a little peacemaking movement
a wave of calming settling
and allow yourself to feel the calming soothing
impact of exhaling even if it's just at the very near the
end of the exhale letting go of thoughts
every every exhale letting go of thoughts
and if you find yourself involved with anything if you're in the present moment
distra thinking feelings body sensations sounds
any concern anything that we call be called a concern because you're caught up in it they're involved
gently lovingly say the word not recognize it as a
a knot an entanglement
and see what happens in the wake of simply recognizing it as
such no need to let go of it just recognize oh there's a knot
and then continue with your breathing
if you are involved in thinking you probably have a knot
entanglement
it can feel innocent enough to be involved in thinking
but when it takes us out of the flow of the present moment
we would call it a knot
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to turn your attention outward to the people community that
you somehow are touched with contact with interact with
and consider what it would be like to be present with them
without being reactive without being entangled
without a knot being knotted up
maybe consider the peace or the calm or the
ease it might provide you to be present
unentangled just present available
attentive and what it would be like for them
to be able to experience themselves without being entangled with anything
with themselves with others with their things
they can still be attentive and engaged engaged but not entangled
and if we have some experience of disentanglement
and the benefits of it we can know more
about the kind of happiness and peace and ease that's possible for human beings
and for whatever peace and well-being and happiness that we know is
possible may we wish it for others
may we be inspired that this be a possibility for others to experience
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings
be disentangled
[Music]
so before i begin this talk of announcement
the so there is starting to be plans there are plans now to try to reopen imc
sometime in the next few weeks with kind of a covet era protocol different
types including only being open for people who are vaccinated
um so um
there'll be more announcements about this and information about that will appear on their website
but the announcement now is that this sunday after the 10 o'clock dharma talk sunday morning
we'll have a community meeting on zoom to discuss the opening and questions
concerns similar to what we did in i think in july when we were thinking about opening
back then and uh so if anybody'd like to come you're welcome to come even if you don't
plan to not relevant for you because you're not not planning to come in person but it might be interesting just
come along and uh the information for that is um in the calendar
imc's calendar and also in the what's new section of
the website the home page of the website imc website there's on the bottom right there's a section called what's new and
there there's an announcement about the community meeting with the link the zoom link and it's password
protected so and the password is there but the password is meta m-e-t-t-a
so
so this week i'm going through the five x mindfulness exercises
that are taught in discourse on the four foundations of mindfulness
and these are i call them exercises these are ways of practicing in order to develop
a heightened sense of mindfulness so that mindfulness is established and
so it's kind of a means and the means to be mindful is in a sense to be mindful
but there are in particular ways or emphasises that are given and uh in the fourth foundation is
beginning to pay attention to either the way we get entangled in things get caught up and attached or the
process by which we get free and liberated
and um and so the there are three exercises around being
entangled being caught and uh they're going going from coarser maybe more activated more
conceptual more story-centered more more
complex world that we live in to the simpler and simpler and so it started off with
the complex world of our attachments to to our desires and
aversions uh and to the things where we desire and have aversions towards and that could be
anything complicated things in the world and ideas and and
things like get along once we stop getting so concerned in the world
of objects and things in a sense including our own comfort then we settle down
and there's a next layer i talked about yesterday which is the ways which we identify
the way we get involved with things based on me myself and mine
as we get quieter still and there's less coarser this more subtle and there's
less baggage less complicated ideas and concepts no concepts of self anymore
we're left to with simple sense experience in the present moment
we're not thinking about the future in the past we're just really present here and we hear a sound
we feel a body sensation we recognize there's a thought and these are all considered very simple
sense recognitions and we don't usually think of the mind doors being a
sense but whatever ability we have to recognize the simplest recognition was happening
in the mind before the complexities around it and reactions to it is it called you know
the a sense experience and so with uh the eye
there's the object of the eye that's things we see and then the buddha talked about the
entanglement between them the knot that gets formed how we get knotted up with it
so there are three things happening there's the eyesight there's the ability to see the eye
the eyesight that sees there's a thing that we see and then kind of imagine that between
the object of sight and and the eye there's things get knotted up
of course the knot is in our brain and our mind but we get involved we get attached to
we get caught up in we get sticky we start thinking about it wanting it reacting to it and
it's not the complicated ideas of the world
like winning the lottery it's just in the moment as we go about
it's something very simple there is a sound and and then we recognize the sound as a car
and then we might get entangled with it we might start thinking of thinking about the sound
and or not liking it because it's unpleasant or liking it because it's pleasant and wanting more of it or
wanting less of it and so getting knotted up and the in the
most english translations they translate this word as fetter
and i don't use the word feder in my ordinary english life i don't know if maybe some of you do
but uh the pali word has the meaning of being knotted up
not and um so i'd like to i like just knotted up
and um and so it's now recognizing that there's always there can be two things there's
the experience we're having and there's the way that we relate to it and that way we relate to it might be
not free it might be free of any entanglement we can engage in it we can
think about it we can care for things without being entangled
but we also can be a entangled there can be attachment and it can be very very subtle
if you just simply simply start in meditation simply start thinking about something that's happening
you've left the flow of the present moment and you now become um you know you're kind of gonna
maybe maybe the word like not or entanglement seems too big but um we've gotten it's gotten sticky
we got leaning into it and we kind of lost something in the process of thinking about it we
lost our mindfulness in our present moment experience so um
so the buddha says that talks about how in this exercise when one is aware
that there's seeing when aware one is aware of what is being
seen and then aware of what that relationship is the entanglement in particular how
we're caught by it or reactive to it and um and then uh
and so we know when it's present the fetter the the knot we know what
it's like when it's not there and this distinction between recognizing the presence of something
and the absence something of something is very important in um mindfulness meditation we often
emphasize being recognizing what's happening in the present which kind of always gives a subject
something is happening that we're aware of but in fact sometimes it's important to be mindful of absence
not all the time but when we've been attached to something
it's valuable to take some time to experience what it's like to be unattached the freedom that comes
so to be knotted up and then know the experience of being unknotted the ease the
we breathe more easily there's more sense of openness spaciousness lightness all kinds of whatever way it
might be experienced so that it registers and we kind of begin to
those channels too that kind of unentanglement starts becoming more available to us because we let it
register more deeply and so the buddha talked about noticing the
presence of these knots the absence of them no and then being present enough in the
moment that we can see that a knot that hasn't arisen yet
does arise we notice the arising of it oh here i get knotted up and that takes
a sharp mindfulness to really be here and say oh i can watch the process
we don't wait until we find ourselves knotted up we watch the process and this is what a benefit can come
when the mindfulness gets established well enough in the present moment that there's a kind of sense of flow
uh in the present a sense of rising and passing appearing and disappearing
the river of experience that's happening here and now that as we stay present for that
we notice when we leave the flow when we get involved in something and we
can watch the beginning of that because it's part of the flow originally
and then and he talked also about then knowing
that the knot has been abandoned let go of he doesn't say to let go of it but i
think maybe it's implied but um
we're aware of it and letting go of it as well that it's gone we've let go of it it's
not there so that we can benefit from experiencing the absence of it
so there is some uh so i like to say that if it's easy to let go of something
like a knot let go of the knot we're not necessarily letting going things in the world we're letting go of
that entanglement that's between us and the thing and then take time to be aware
of what that absence of entanglement is like if we do this regularly and strongly
a special time will come where in practice where we have a clear sense
that the entanglement is not going to arise again at least not in this meditation or in
this state of mind this kind of presence we have and and this clarity and confidence wow
i'm so settled i'm so present i'm so so much peace and and self-awareness
awareness going on here that no way am i going to get entangled
that requires a kind of a coarser activity a kind of choice and involvement that i'm simply
not inclined to do now and to really feel that wow
i i you know i'm not inclined to to get in entangled again it's like
now i'm safe at least for this meditation for this next few minutes
and to feel that possibility to know that this is possible is can be life-changing because we know
that life doesn't require attachment doesn't require being entangled
so um at first we're we're disentangling ourselves from the coarser
big ideas of the world the things we want and don't want that involve stories and ideas and complicated concepts and
that are you know that are the hindrances and then we do something more subtle
which is the whole way in which we attach to self and then we get more subtle in uh in
just our relationship to sense contact and um it might seem uninteresting it might
seem not so valuable to be aware at this more base level of of
sense contact but it turns out that some of the deepest attachments we have
arise out of the attachment to these basic sense contacts it sets the stage for all the other attachments and
sufferings we have so it's very powerful to kind of settled enough to really track it
and and as we start getting more sensitive and aware of the entanglements and the absence of them
then we're poised to be aware of some of the benefits that come on the path to disentanglement on the
path to really becoming free and that's a topic for tomorrow and so for the next 24 hours
you maybe use this concept of a knot or an entanglement
and go through the day recognizing as much as you can your entanglements
either while you're doing it also afterwards you might kind of reflect back over the day and say well where was
i entangled and caught sometimes it's hard to see in the present moment but sometimes
retrospectively we can see oh i see and and see what you learned about yourself
in that process so thank you