hello greetings international sangha
dear friends dear siblings in the dharma inhabiting our
shared planet earth and i greet you in this moment in time from mountain
view california from my home uh from virtual imc
a virtual background i'm actually using zoom to youtube hence the difference in audio
and why i can beam in um without needing to sit as usually guild
does so hence the explanation so so um so
let's continue our practice together we've been exploring various
supportive conditions supportive practices for samadhi for calming the mind
for settling the mind for unification for concentration
so just a quick review of the techniques we're building upon
we started with relinquishing relinquishing what is not helpful putting aside what is not needed
and then the other side of the coin of relinquishment is turning our attention
our wise attention to what is actually here what's already here not
the distractions outside but what is
joyful what is delightful what is wonderful in the simplicity of the present moment
right here right now so instead of the stick the carrot what is delicious here to
have contentment and peace with what is already here to recognize
what is already here and we continued with the invitation to
relax to soften the body to open up the body
so that the mind can relax can and can settle a relaxed
sati a relaxed mode of mindfulness drawing inspiration from the buddha
under the rose apple tree as well as um the
uh the simile of the the cow herder under the tree
when the harvest has been done so their sense of relaxed spatial awareness so we'll bring
all of these in today in addition to the new theme today
that we'll be adding all of these are interrelated all of them depend on one
another [Music] is gentle perseverance
gentle persistence coming back keep coming back keep coming back you
need to relinquish it's okay keep coming back relax the body
notice the the simple delight joy of the pleasant moment keep
coming back keep coming back but gently atapi is one of my favorite words
in the sitters especially shows up in
the four foundations of mindfulness the four establishments of mindfulness
gentle perseverance so it's not a forceful it's it's not a jackhammer
like okay bring the mind back yank it back bad mind it's not like that
it's the force of a feather but it's repeated bring the feather back
bring it back bring it back gently kindly patiently a thousand times
maybe more during a 30 minute set without
grudges without judgment self-recommendation just gently okay all right
distracted buddha in this moment okay gently back a tapi gentle persistence
gentle persistence so with the basis of everything we have been cultivating
turning our attention to this week and now today special attention to this gentle
persistence coming back and i'll say more about both this and vitaka and vichara
which are essential and to translate them initial application of the mind with the
breath with the object and sustained application so initial application
as if you touch the breath you gently bring back the attention touch the breath and
sustained attention as if you're rubbing a ball because if you're rubbing a ball with a cloth
you rub the breath with your attention gently coming back initial application
sustained application until the the attention drops drops away and then
again again and again so a day for cultivating
cultivating gentle gentle persistence and patience joyfully
so let us begin
blending landing in our posture
in our meditation posture whether sitting or lying down
and inviting inviting the body to relax
the forehead to soften
for the eyes to rest back in their socket
for the jaw
perhaps to open up just a little bit
ah and then settle into a comfortable position
inviting the neck and shoulders to give their weight to the earth the arms
the hands to drop
the chest the abdomen
letting go at the next out breath ah
and the sit bones
the lower part of the abdomen connecting to the sit bones
dropping dropping their weight onto the earth in lieu of the chair
the cushion
letting go of the weight the lower legs upper legs and feet to
the earth bringing attention to the entire body
relaxed soft
breathing being breathed
the in-breath
the out breath
connecting attention awareness satay
[Music] connecting with the in-breath
or the out-breath in their entirety as much as possible
relinquishing what is not helpful in this moment
nothing wrong with thinking per se but in this moment
we choose to give our hearts fully
our minds wholeheartedly
to this moment this moment's cultivation and goodness
hear the simple joy of just being here
simply sitting and breathing
with gentle gentle persistence
connecting connecting with the breath
as if awareness lands on the breath connects with the
breath
and serves serves
the breath joyfully
the attention surfing the breath joyfully for as long as possible
and if and when it drops the attention drops it's okay
gently relinquishing without judgment
smiling
coming back gentle persistence coming back
connecting tension awareness connecting with the breath
continuing to surf to be with the breath joyfully
for as long as available no problem
again and again this is our practice
this is our training of our mind
every now and then [Music]
as you notice the mind is resting on something else and you relinquish
without judgment with e smilingly check to see the body is relaxed
if any tension has crept in ah release relax
with the next out breath
and connect with the breath
surfing the wave
returning again and again to the joy of surfing the breath
surfing as long as possible
if we're dropping off
and however our practice was in this moment
trusting there is goodness generated trusting
that are coming together aligned with our intentions
our actions for cultivation that goodness is generated
for ourselves for others around us and the whole world
and offering sharing with generosity that goodness that is ours and not
ours sharing it generously with the whole world
may our cultivation may this merit generate this goodness
okay cause and condition for freedom
liberation of all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free
including ourselves
thank you for the grace of your practice
greetings greetings everyone
so our fourth day of exploration with supportive practices supportive
tools for cultivating samadhi translated often
as concentration but perhaps better translated as unification of the mind
settling of the mind calm abiding
so today's theme
one is atapi as i mentioned this favorite word of mine that shows up
a lot uh especially in the four foundations for establishments of
mindfulness
where the buddha in the refrain that repeats so many times in that suta
says to come back with atapi with gentle persistence gentle persistence there's a sense of
gentle persistence that we cultivate and
what's really important to keep in mind here is the persistence
we keep coming back we keep coming back we keep coming back and yet there is the
gentleness because if the coming back is like a sledgehammer
it becomes exhausting it becomes painful very soon if every time
the mind and the mind is a puppy we are training this sweet darling
beloved puppy of our mind and it just just as puppies like to run around
it's in their nature it's in the nature of our minds to like to think and go here and there
etc so so training this beloved puppy of the mind you don't want to
yank it back traumatize the puppy every time he comes back come back sit sit and beat
up the poor puppy beat up the poor mind gentle come back sweetie come back
come back you may do it a thousand times come back gently it's okay it's okay or run away
it's okay come back come back with bad level of gentleness
training caring for a beloved puppy another simile that i mentioned is
is um the pressure of a feather pressure of a feather not a sledgehammer
so it's persistent it happens over and over and over and over and over again
without without the problem not make it into a problem yes
this is the nature of the mind oh yeah it's the millionth time this morning in the 30 minutes i'm
coming back it's okay just calling oh today the busy buddha is showing up on this
question the busy buddha that happens for me many times in fact i remember once i was teaching a retreat
and there's so much planning going on and i'm sitting on the on the dice and realizing wow the mind
is going everywhere okay all right busy busy buddha is showing up
in this moment busy buddha ah and the mind that the heart can settle with that
can settle with that with that gentleness of okay it's like this it doesn't become conflictual and yet
there is persistence yet there is persistence after you say okay it's the busy buddha
all right sweetie okay come back all right yeah it's the busy buddha today yes
come back come back this beautiful word in pali my one of my
favorites and the other couple of concepts i like
to bring in today is vitaca and vichara
which are two of the five gianic factors so vittaka means initial application
and vichara is sustained application so one simile is that imagine you have a
bowl and here i have a bowl and you have a cloth and vitaca is like okay
the cloth touching the bow this is vittaka the initial application the initial contact
the initial connection and then vichara is the sustained application is as if
you're rubbing the bowl with the claw then at some point
so so the cloth is awareness and the bowl is your breath
is the object is the object of your attention which could be many different objects there are 40 different
samadhi objects in the visudi maga in higher teachings but
here we're using anapanasati the breath as our object so this in this
case for our practice today is the breath it could be again many different things
could be sounds sensations etc but here's the breath so attention being the clock initial
application the contact when we make contact we we grok
we grab we get on the wave um if we're surfing i'll talk about
that analogy a little more and then vitaka and then vichara sustained application sustained
application we rub the bowl attention rubs stays on the
breath the entirety of the breath as if touching the breath touching the entirety of the breath
before at some point at some point it will fall off it's okay with atapi with gentle persistence we come back
we make contact vitaka and then we sustain the attention
vichara we sustain the attention for as long as possible before he drops off again then when it
drops off no judgment just that's the puppy it just drops off that's what happens okay
with atapi we come back initial application sustained application so
so whichever of these metaphors work for you and the another metaphor that i invited
you to consider today is is being a surfer and those of
you who are surfers maybe can easily connect with the joy and even
though i'm not a surfer but having watched surfers there is so much joy
watching surfers when they catch away when they connect with the wave and then they stay on the wave as long
as possible there's such joy so for us to connect
with the with the wave with the breath initial application to to connect with
it and then ride the breath surf
serve the breath for as long as possible and joy arises joy arises with the
out breath in breath the pauses the breath oh it's pausing pausing oh
and then there's another breath you can continue to surf it so this is a lovely metaphor
i just came up with today so it's it's new fresh off of my practice here it is enjoy
surf enjoy surfing and there's also this joy of the delight of this this idea of
surfing the breath really connecting into somebody the mind doesn't want to go anywhere else surfing
the breath is so much fun why would i get out of the water this is so much fun
so the joy which we talked about a couple days ago can actually be part of this metaphor part of this way
of working and i want to end with
saying making a distinction many of you might already know this but
but might also might be helpful as this week we are working with
samadhi and you might think what is the difference between samadhi concentration practice
and vipassana insight practice often translated as inside practice
so this can be a long long lecture and there are many similarities and
differences but in terms of technique um one thing to keep in mind
is and this is giving credit to um the similes giving credit to steve
armstrong um a teacher a senior teaching the trivada
i learned this from him a couple of decades ago he would say that
vipassana is like serial monogamy for the attention
so the attention is with the breath and then um and then there's a sound so
the attention can go to the sound and be with that but really there's monogamy you're really
dedicating giving yourself staying with that object and then um maybe a sensation arises in
the body then you go to that then you're monogamous but it's serial you go
from one object to another to another insight an insight opening up to all
these different objects after the mind has settled with
samadhi now samadhi concentration on the other hand is
in his words absolute monogamy it's just the breath you come back to the
breath and you're just with the breath absolutely monogamous faithful to one object whatever the
object of your concentration of your practice is just with the breath and often
one thing that actually might sound confusing is that we often in the practice of vipassana we start
with a few minutes or a period of uh samadhi practice to settle the
mind we keep coming back to the breath with this sense of oh just a breath just a breath and then when the mind is
settled with some concentration samadhi practice at the beginning of
inside practice then we can open up usually we open
up the attention this fear of attention so that when the mind is settled then it
can stay with the sound oh yes impermanence the sound is coming and
going oh the sensations oh notice the vedana in the sensations
so there is that malleability that flexibility so i just wanted to offer these and i
realized this was kind of brief i hope it was helpful and made sense um
there's so much more here to cover there's so much more dharma and to be a scientist of your own mind
so explore explore for yourself today what is the nature of gentle
perseverance gentle perseverance in your daily activities
gentle perseveres without judgment coming back coming back initial application
sustained application enjoying enjoying really tuning into the joy of surfing the wave
of whatever it is you're doing so thank you all for your practice may you
be well and see you tomorrow