warm greetings to everyone and Welcome to our meditation session
together and there are many ways of talking about mindfulness
meditation one way is to see that it has three component parts or three aspects
to it they can be done SE separately each or they can be done Al together in
whatever combination and sequence but the first uh is to
accompany to really accompany our experience to attend with our experience
to be a companion to our experience it's a little bit different
than being our experience um and but to company and to
be accompanied by our experience the second is to know our
experience uh and to be known by our experience to be known to know our
experience to really let it register be fully acknowledged be really really
known and really known doesn't necessarily mean only in some conceptual
way but really known in some real clear way this is here this is what what's
happening there's an intimacy and the third is
liberating liberating our experience and um we could say
liberating ourselves but I think it's more kind of to the heart of the issue
really the heart of what really happens is we're we're liberating our experience so that all our experiences
are not entangled with self and desires and preoccupation and resistance and
running away and burying to liberate our
experience so to accompany to know and to liberate and um so in that way we'll sit
today and one of those three might be just the right one for you they each have their their time and place and each
of them feel just right um can feel just
right so to begin by assuming
a meditation posture that's appropriate for you with some care that that's it's
in a a posture that supports you to be
alert to be clear and present
a [Music] posture that supports you to
accompany your present moment
experience gently closing your
eyes and if you are going to accompany your experience What's Happening Here in
the present moment for you not the reason why you're experiencing ing what's here not your predictions of
what's going to happen but just the experience in and of itself with no need for it to have a
past or a future just to be present together with
what's here what would you be present
for and to ACC compy part of the richness of that word is that it's a
noninterfering attending to what's happening
it's it's a non-judgmental way of being with what is we're just here to be with
it
and then you might take a few long slow deep breaths right in the middle of how you
are as if you're massaging how you
are really meeting how you are
and as you exhale to relax your
body to relax around how you
are and letting your breathing return to normal and still as you exhale
just look around the body and see where can you
relax can be particularly useful to relax the
belly over and over again how much do we
hold against life resist life keep from feeling what we're
feeling by tightening the belly
relax the belly and maybe there's more to a
company more that we can be a companion to feel
softening in the shoulders relaxing the
shoulders and relaxing and softening the face
sometimes the muscles of the face can be tired from all the Expressions that we're holding
there and letting the face
rest and then dropping deeper into your
breathing to accompany your breathing
perhaps relaxing around your
breathing and then knowing your
breathing let it be a deeper maybe even silent knowing
recognition registering that you're
breathing an intimacy with breathing
and then liberating your breathing from judgments ideas of how it should be
or shouldn't be or wanting it different
and ideas that is not quite right that you liberating how your body is
breathing so you it can just be
itself and as we sit here there might be other experiences that come come that
become predominant and then you might see if you can practice mindfulness by
[Music] accompanying what's happening knowing what's
happening and liberating what's
happening
e
for
e for
letting go of thoughts and thinking so you can be a better
accompanier of your experience so there's more attention
available awareness available for
breathing for your present moment experience
for
e e
e
for
e for
for for
for
e
for e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting these three parts of mindfulness
accompanying knowing
liberating is something we can offer to other
people from kindness we can accompany others
with love we can know others and with generosity we can
liberate others to accompany people others in
their lives is a is always a
gift to really know someone else not necessarily their history or
everything about them them but to really when we're with them to know them
then and there to really be attuned to who they
what's happening how they're feeling and to liberate
others we can't get them to liberate themselves but we can liberate them from
our judgments our criticisms our
attachments even our needs and
expectations to accompany to know and to
liberate are a way
to act on the wish may all beings be
happy may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
safe may all beings be free
and may it be that the goodness benefits of this meditation
session supports us to contribute to this being possible for this world of
ours may may we support the happiness and well-being of all
beings may all beings be free
[Music]
for e
the topic for this uh talk
is grief and maybe the talk can be titled
liberating grief and what motivates this talk is in
big part is that the one-year anniversary of many of us going into
Sheltering in place and the dramatic way in which our whole world
has much of the world as 99% of it has been turned upside down down or inside
out or radically Changed by the pandemic and in marking this one-year
anniversary uh it feels important to acknowledge and make room for and bring
forth the grief that has been part of this
year and that um grief is not something that should be shied away from or be
embarrassed about but is actually a very important part of human beings and our human life and and
it should be acknowledged it should be understood and seen and um and what's uh significant I
think for many of us recognizes that the griefs of uh the last year have been
wide ranging I mean certainly there are some of them are huge I mean uh many
around the world millions of people have died in the United States well over 500,000 people have died directly from
the disease and the illness and then there's been many who have been seriously sick and uh some
with with the long-termers like Long Haul people people who there symptoms that continue for months and months and
maybe it'll be for years and so there's a grief of the loss
of so many things loss of people loss of family members friends from death than
sickness and then there's the grief of just loss of connections of people we've been regularly connected to are
Sheltering and place themselves and there's not much communication
and um the grief of not being social in the same way we were
before there's all these small griefs that goes along uh that uh we experience
of all the things we can't do that we're used to doing and that we value you doing and all the small ways in which
we've gotten energized and inspired about life and ready to go out and do it are not available and some people find
there's a slow slow steady attrition of energy of inspiration of motivation
partly from uh the slow kind of Drip by dripping of little griefs and sorrows
and sadness as that go on and then there's uh the things that
happen in our society the challenges the grief Bel the sorrow the sadness about
politics and about racial Injustice and economic Injustice and and um um
nowadays you know we were aware of medical Injustice and environmental Injustice and um and uh you know and
violence and hatred the violence against asian-americans is you know is
heartbreaking the violence against black Americans is
heartbreaking and um and the hatred that exists in our society that people go
around shooting each other so all these things together you know are forms of
sadness and grief and and uh that kind of accumulate or can accumulate if
they're not acknowledged and not known and not liberated so there's three ways of being
with grief there's accompanying grief there is knowing
grief and there's liberating grief and what I like about these words
accompanying knowing and liberating that grammatically they can both be a verb
and an adjective so knowing accompanying grief
means we are the companions of it we bring ourselves to be present for it and be with it but uh it also it the grief
that does the accompanying it's a grief accompanying grief can also be the grief that
accompanies us and it's a mutual relationship uh you and your grief and
to feel and experience that mutuality is really really to allow the accompanying to be
full there is a knowing grief where we can know it but there's also the grief
that knows something uh grief is not just uh ignorant or dumb or you know uh
uninformed grief is something that's really well informed about something very important and what is it that grief
knows and so when we know grief we're also learning what does grief
know and then uh liberating grief is both you know we can Liberate the grief
perhaps but also there's the idea that there's a grief that is liberating
and uh and how can you know something as painful and difficult as grief can be at times how can that be liberating as well
and and to even to say those words or suggest that idea can feel like a
betrayal or to the grief we have or can feel like a insult to the degree of pain
we can experience the grief so grief uh such an important topic for us
and I had this in mind and that that we could uh somehow uh do this uh talk together that
not just me talking but maybe those of you who have access to the chat we can have a little bit uh do this as in
teamwork the um so accompanying
grief grief is an ordinary part of human beings lives there's it's to be expected
that we'll have grief it's not a mistake to have grief if we're living and paying attention and caring about life and
caring about things there'll be grief there'll be sorrow there'll be
sadness and uh and so to spend time with that and allow ourselves to feel it to
trust it to be with it um and people who do mindfulness practices can really
maybe appreciate this how valuable it is to be with something be all this partly because we start feeling that um to not
be with it is to not be with ourselves that as we learn to be really
present for our experience present in ourselves and being opening up to all of
who we are there's a feeling of coming home to ourselves or feeling whole in
ourselves uh complete in ourselves or no part left out and it's uh in doing so we
become a refuge to ourselves we become the a refuge a a place of um of support
a place of Freedom a place of being we're allowed to be full and complete
and as soon as we have something like grief that's too painful for us or too embarrassing for us or too uh something
we want to push away or ignore or repress then uh we are dividing
ourselves we're no longer whole we're no longer able able to come back into our hearts and feel at home there and so to
um and to to accompany ourselves accompany the grief is a means to kind
of learn to stay whole learn to stay complete or learn to be a refuge to
ourselves no matter how big and strong the pain is there's good reason why people want
to avoid grief and that is because it can be painful acute grief you know is
SE in is you know it's just like everything is torn apart and and um you
know kind of the world the fabric of the world is torn apart and it can be
excruciating to feel some griefs so it's very painful and so the idea of accompanying
grief is to accompany our pain and if we don't do that then uh P
the grief and the pain remains but maybe it goes underground it gets repressed or gets
kind of ignored and um but it still operates it's still there
festering and uh and it's there if it hasn't really been dealt with fully
or with uh dignity or nobility then it can come back and come back in
unexpected and maybe unhealthy ways in terms of anger or excessive fear or um
or being too closed and numb from what's going on so to accompany all this is to accompany
the ways we go numb to accompany also the ways we get angry the ways we get feel helpless and hopeless to uh just
accompany ourselves in the pain so I did that this last week uh to
some degree uh for me personally it was a very uh touching experience time for
me where um I uh moved my mother into
memory care home and um and uh I think the most
poignant part of it was walking across the parking lot of um of the you know
the memory care place to bring her to the door and because of covid we can't come in someone comes out and receives
her and and accompanies her in where I stay behind so here I was walking across
the parking lot very acutely aware of uh what was painful for me over 60
years ago and that was one of the earliest memories I have of my mother was uh her accompanying me when I was
about four years old across a school uh playground I was holding her hand and I
was crying because I was going to the first day of school in a foreign country
in a language I didn't speak in Geneva where they spoke French and I didn't speak French and um and going to a
Catholic that's best my memory kindergarten maybe uh something like
that um uh that uh was run by nuns and I
was uh so I was she was walking me across I was holding my head and I was crying and now over 60 years later um
you know the roles were reversed and and uh her memory was not such that she
quite understood what was going on but I did and and so that came back and I'm
accomp I made space for it and then after I took her there I went for a long walk in the hills around here just to
accompany my grief accompany my sadness of what was going on and it was kind of kind of the
richness of it partly was the leftover of a certain pain the memory of pain
from over 60 years ago that speaks to a principle that that uh uh uh sometimes
our our griefs are previous griefs and even more so if the griefs are unresolved or un somehow have been
pushed down or ignored um they get reawakened with new griefs and so the
new griefs can be much more acute because of the how it can be with um
with um you know that uh the legacy of griefs that we've had so to accompany
grief is to accompan any pain and and for people who mindfulness practice we
begin discovering that there's a difference between pain and suffering
and this makes a world of difference and this is really what the heart of Buddhist practice is about is uh to if
we can see that difference then we can maybe learn to let go of the suffering and then learn
to with nobility with with uh compassion uh accompany the pain that's
part of human life the suffering is when we uh contract around the pain when we
close the heart around the pain when we cover over the pain when we resist the
pain when we are afraid of the pain all these other ways that we contract and
get wrapped up and in it is the suffering but uh the pain doesn't you
know and that's what we're liberating in in Buddhist practice all that kind of
complicated reactivity to the pain and it's uh but just to live with a pain and
make space for it be open to it be a refuge for the pain help the pain feel
safe safe in us and to learn that art to learn that ability to accompany our pain
so it begins by you know recognizing what the pain is naming it so that we
can see what what's been going on and what's been happening and and so for
this pandemic and marking this anniversary there's been um big big uh
griefs uh big things to grieve and small things to Grieves and all these teeny
incidental things that some people say would shouldn't count you know I should be not up to handling that and dealing
with that but the accumulation of all these small little things and that have been challenging and losses over this
year they add up to a lot and one of the lessons of grief is never discount any
grief never feel that because other people's grief is so much bigger mine
shouldn't count every grief counts every grief is something to accompany to know
and to liberate because if we don't do that then slowly incrementally We Begin
closing down or pushing under and and the Vitality the fullness of being here
uh you know is going to be diminished so if you're willing um maybe
if you could write some of you would be willing to write in the chat maybe one or two or three words or whatever you
want um um of what you have grieved this last year that has to do with this
pandemic and uh it' be nice to have some names Associated not um not necessarily
to people but n you know to these different kinds of griefs named
here and um so what have what have you griefed
over this last
year grieving hugs lost hugs the absence of intimacy and physical contact with
people not seeing a grandson going to school and seeing my
friends not being able to see my parents death of 20
clients loss of relationships I can't read them all but
Community lost distorted social connection sad many P have many past griefs have
resurfaced being in class with my students isolation nourishing human
touch family visits not being with grandchildren loss
of Grandmother sitting in community connecting with many
friends ant dying High School son's loss of his senior year
yeah no hugs loss of the world and freedom as it
was being alone so much Miss celebrations loss of sense of
safety our cat that died this year after 15 years as our
companion yeah these these loss of pets can be huge huge grief loss of closest
friend also not being in s with distant
relatives I think moments even of Freedom From
Fear not attending to a dear friend's father's funeral illness isolation political
corruption PTSD isolation dad's funeral yeah it's a big
thing I've have not seen my daughter and grandchildren for more than a year loss
of Truth and compassion from leadership music
jams lost my ability to understand my loved ones changing
friendships so thank you all for writing all those things it's a big deal so
these are the things to accompany these are things to name and to be with and
and sometimes it's helpful to have help support and accompaniment that's what
sometimes having friends you can talk to about the griefs we have and not to fix not to solve but just to help to have an
to be a have a companionship in the grief and some griefs are so difficult
to be our own companion to that uh having someone else who can support us
in that process there are like grief counselors for example and they're
useful in many ways but one way is that um they know how to be Companions and
accompany and be present for and so it's easier for us to then to be our own
companions for our grief because we have someone who really knows how to do it and can do it with care and compassion
and acceptance and um and then learning how
to be willing learning how to be comfortable if that's the right word
with feeling pain learning how to be open to feeling pain
uh learning the wisdom of being with pain the more we love something that
we've lost more we love something that we lost um that love doesn't go away and
that something is precious if we what is is to really really kind of listen
deeply get to know deeply what's going on here and that's a second step of this
three-step process knowing grief really getting to know what it is is this grief
what is this pain being willing to really tend to it because there's a
tendency sometimes when we're really some situation we're in a lot of pain um
and hurt and feel of betrayal to get angry and push things
away and and be hostile or something and U which is natural enough it's a way of
avoiding sometimes the pain um but to uh but to really get to
know the pain because the degree to which we love something to that degree
our Capac our beautiful capacity for love our beautiful capacity for something good is is there buried in the
pain is found together with the pain pain isn't all necessarily all
bad um and so to really get to know grief and no pain to know that part of
the grief that kind of that suffering as opposed to pain to be able to make that
distinction between the contractions we have and the resistance the shoulds and the shouldn't I shouldn't be feeling grief I
should be over it by now uh I'm supposed to go through grief perfectly I'm supposed to resolve my grief I'm
supposed to heal my grief I don't know if we're supposed to heal grief or some people heal grief but I don't know if
we're supposed to or required always or we're supposed to resolve grief some of
us never healed in a sense that the pain pain never goes away but we can make
more space for it it's part of our deep Humanity to feel the pain of living life
Freedom real Freedom can coexist with pain Freedom does not coexist with
suffering suffering is the loss of freedom and so to make to just keep
opening the heart and allow it to be broken allow it to have space for the
pain that we feel um is part of it and sometimes that
grief can be so strong that any words about it like the words I'm doing today
uh can feel just uh impossible and too difficult to listen to and doesn't make
any sense occasionally grief has to go we have to reach rock rock bottom for
something to finally give out or it just seems like so impossible and so to
really company really know know how impossible it is and stay there with it
stay there with it is part of least what this mindfulness practice
teaches the um to be with pain to be with it
all and I just I'm just remembering some of the things that I was thinking about we
grieve um I've grieved um in my my life I've grieved um anticipated futures the
future the now that won't happen because my friend died we grieve uh what happened in the
past we grieve what didn't happen in the past what should have happened in the
past so all these you know it's layers and layers of grief that we can
feel so this knowing grief in vasna practice has a lot to do with the direct
experience in the moment which is to feel it in your body how is what is the
manifestation of grief here and now in the body what parts of the body are touched and moved and ache with grief
and we can find identify how it is physically here and now then that becomes a place the very location where
we begin opening up to it where we open the heart we open the mind we open
attention and make make see how big the awareness could be so we can hold that
place and be with it if it's not located sometimes in the body it just seems like it's just
overwhelming but sometimes when we locate in the body it has a kind of locus it has a kind of location to be
close with or intimate with or to touch or to connect to so um maybe here in the chat again
would some of you be willing to write um where how and where in the body do you
experience grief some of of locations and places for
that our wonderful bodies that carry so much I have difficulty swallowing
stomach and chest digestion mostly in heart upper chest throat right below the
heart my face throat chest tightening of my chest my heartaches heart and lungs
my heart area in my chest upper chest and
throat right behind the sternum throat throat absolutely in the
chest and throat eyes and forehead breath in the
smile less easy to turn up the angle up R my eyes I squint a lot torso upper
neck hot teary eyes tightness of belly broken
heart in the chest and heart like a vacuum in my heart breath tightens tightness in the
brain jaw tightens shoulders so thank you for all that
headache from Angry thoughts brain core of my being center of my
body water flowing out yeah lots of
Tears headache lower
back in The Voice
yeah so so many ways it manifests in the body darkness in the head in the entire
being so these are the places that we bring our compassion and Care these are the places we hold these are places
where you want to bring a sense of safety to in the pit of my stomach we to mindfulness is to bring a
sense of safety to these places in the body that ache and hurt and are contracted and tight
and there's a way in which to trust that to trust feeling it and sensing it and being with it it can be very very hard
one of the things that makes grief particularly difficult is when there
when we feel helpless or hopeless with their grief and um and uh the sense of
helplessness is a can for some people especially if it's chronic is really
debilitating and the ability to accompany and to know and to feel and
connect and and to make space for and to hold in the body is a way that over
starts overcoming this feeling of helplessness we can help ourselves there
is hope for ourselves through this practice of mindfulness we have something we can
do we have we can't we might be helpless in terms of uh for for those who are
dead are gone or losses we have for them to come back but it doesn't leave us as
a helpless person we can engage with agency with sense of purpose and uh it's
a profound thing very profound to learn the ability to hold our pain and not to
add layers of suffering on top of it there's no shame in adding suffering on
top of our pain because sometimes what we need to accompany what we need to open to is a
clear seeing knowing and experiencing of those layers of reactivity we have and
without that we don't have a hope of really experiencing what Charlie Brown called I think he called we good
grief good grief is the grief that is simple is unentangled we don't have all
these layers of shoulds and shouldn't on top of it it should be different we should be over it by now or I don't
deserve to be grieving because other people's have grief so much more all these things we
do and then finally there's liberating grief and um and this is kind of what
I'm saying all along is liberating the grief not from getting rid of the grief
not from not no longer having grief but liberating it from how the grief all the
suffering on top of the grief all the reactivity all the judgments all the uh
angers all the pushing away the resistance all the ways in which we
divide ourselves by shutting out part of who we are because it's too painful to
be with uh to liberate is to become whole
liberate is no part left out all of who we are is allowed to be there not
because we are justifi in or celebrating it or condoning it
necessarily but so that we can open up and um and have it all be part of the
whole the whole is always greater than the parts and grief is one of the parts
they can feel like it's the whole thing when it's really intense but it's always
part a piece of a part of the whole and to make room for it and to hold hold it
and be with it it might be that the liberated person
might cry um because the pure Simplicity of
the pain brings along tears tears are not a sign of being unliberated they
might be sign of actually we're beginning to liberate ourselves that's
where the Liberation happens I love the idea I love the the the ways in which it's possible to cry
and meditation because there's something about the meditation posture where we
it's a posture in which we never collapse we never sink we never give up
we never succumb to it but we stay simple relaxed up if you're upright
upright and let the tears flow so there's not the self-pity or the giving
up or something and there's freedom and just crying there's Freedom there's
Liberation found in that sometimes so um liberating our grief
without needing it to go away so that we can go through our life continuing to
experience the griefs that will come there's no there's no final freedom from
grief and sadness but to go through life and be free in the midst of it is to
allow ourselves to feel it the vital ality the fullness of life with the grief and with the joys and with the
love and with all that's here um and this is not resolving grief
in terms of it going away it's not finally it's over it's uh it's the grief has its own
life and so liberating our grief is to uh be generous to our grief so the
grief can have its freedom the grief can do what it needs to do and
to learn to trust the heart knows what to do the heart knows what to do with grief if we've liberated it if we if we
know it accompany it and we get out of its way and we've Li liberated from
ourselves our hearts our grief knows what to do and sometimes we have to be
patient it takes time so liberating our grief so some of you maybe have had some
experience of grief liberated in the way I've descri I've talked about here and how
does it feel how do you know that Lea has grief has been liberated how do you
know uh how how's that experienced in you how's experiencing your body what's
it like to have grief maybe even still present but really feel it's been
liberated so um let's see
here there can be a purity to the feeling of grief and strong emotion maybe that's part of The Liberation
yes and
um part of uh what it feels like for me is a
willingness The Liberation of grief comes along with a willingness a willing willingness to grieve a willingness to
have
pain breaking away and lifting of weight I feel like I'm cared and safe
when I let it go I felt more here and connected to others compassion sense and
grief emerging sense of Peace feeling Joy along with the sorrow getting in
touch with the raw emotion and being with it forgiveness there's truth in the Deep
sorrow and grief lifted weight of grief more love and accompanying grief
relaxation and gratitude I feel lighter it feels cleansing forgiveness more
peace and openness acceptance of experience at peace with it putting down a large Rock
grief from childhood became compassion for my parents heart opens and I cry
more with the connection grief is a necessary part of moving on from the loss feeling the joy
right next to it great thank you for all this very
much feeling the love behind an inside of grief and feeling grateful for such
love Fe feel like I'm moving again
relief the heart knows what to do with grief when it has been liberated I will always carry this incredibly wise
statement thank you oh it's a quote quoting so um thank
you so accompanying our grief knowing our knowing grief and
liberating grief uh three different ways of being with grief at different times different
ones ones of them are appropriate and um it's a profound part of our human
life and it's been important part I know important is the right word a very
significant part of this last year and um and as we begin the second year of
covid with whatever changes might be coming that um that uh to acknowledge
little bit what happened this last year and to have spend time really
accompanying knowing and liberating this grief hopefully will let us go into this new world New
Year U more capable more willing more wise and how to continue to meet the
griefs that will come one way or the other will still have griefs where even
when the pandemic's over will have griefs this is part of human life and there's no Liberation without being
liberated in relationship to our grief as well we are grieving beings just as
much as we're are loving beings compassionate beings forgiving beings
we're also beings that can experience pain so
um thank you very much for this and um I'm aware that grief is a huge well
abyss of pain sometimes very difficult and to bringing it up today and evoking
it this way might be very hard for some of you and I'd encourage you to spend some time um today caring for yourself
if that's the case maybe talk to friends go for walks uh if you have no one to talk to
journal about it write about it so it's so you you give it some
expression and but do take care of yourself and and um and uh if this talk
is particularly difficult um maybe in a few days listen to it again there might be some something moving and bubbling
inside of you from it um but I wish you well and I offer you
this talk with a lot of desire and care and compassion for your welfare and happiness and and for
all of us as we go forward together in this new new next year that uh may all
of us uh support each other in this process thank you all very much