so mindfulness of body something i have in mind to share
tonight and so in poly canon text and the buddha often
and talks about the mindfulness of body
he says the mindfulness of the body one cultivated and developed is of a
great fruit and a benefit
so i thought i'd share a little bit of the teachings of a mindfulness body based on the poly canon text
specifically and this uh suta and the title of the
suta is mindfulness of the body and the susuta can be found
and in machu nikaya 119 for those who you know might be
interesting looking it up so much money kayla 1 19.
so mindfulness of body is also often uh emphasized um
in secular mind mindfulness meditation teachings
and in secular mindfulness teachings and often the teachers would start with
mindfulness of body for example mindfulness of breath or becoming aware of
and the sensations in the body and through this kind of awareness of what
is happening in this lived experience in the body we began to cultivate our capacity
to live in the present moment with more clarity
the mindfulness body however in the poly canon teaching
is much more um extended expansive and has a profound
implications and so uh buddha on one buddha taught
mindfulness of a body and the whole sequence of the practices that's introduced
in mindfulness of body are meant to lead all the way to full awakening liberation
in addition to many other benefits and that may be a bit available to
oneself and so i want to share a little bit
about this sequence of practices that the susuta talked about
and some of them are not very
not often taught in secular mindfulness teachings
however they can be quite profound and so this mindfulness of body teaching
consists of seven different practices and that are ordered in a particular
sequence i can be thought as a progressive sequence
to cultivate mindfulness in somebody and through which through the sequence
of a practice one can have a great clarity
into the very nature of this body which is according to the three key
insights anicha dukkha and that is an impermanence non-satisfactoriness
of this body and that cannot be identified as self anata
so through these forms of insights it becomes possible to have a complete destruction
of defilements and that leads to full awakening
so what are the seven different practices
so i'm going to give you this list of the seven first and so you maybe orient your mind a
little bit to this list of seven and then i'll walk through each of this
and in some form of a sequence and to say a few words about each of them
so this list of the seven uh in poly canon text it starts with
mindfulness of breathing and however in the chinese parallel
of the poly canon text mindfulness breathing actually is number
three in this sequence um which i'll say a few words and um uh the sequencing
a little bit later but i just started with the list number one mindfulness breathing the
second one is awareness of the four postures that is walking standing sitting down
and lying down the third is awareness of the bodily
activity and that is if you're bending down
you know you're bending down if you're eating you know you're eating if you're cooking you know you're
cooking and so whatever you're doing in terms of bodily activities
and you know that this is happening so that's number three awareness of the
bodily activities number four is the contemplation of the
anatomical parts as a different parts of the body
contemplation of that this body is made up of different parts component parts
number five is contemplation of the four elements earth water fire
and air in other suitors it also talks about um the fifth element which is space
but not in this particular suta and number six is the corpse
contemplation contemplation of the different stages of decay
of the dead body corpse number seven is the four jhanas which is
the four stages of samadhi
and so it's very interesting to look at this sequence to see what is happening with this
sequence and then for me it made a little more
sense that the mindfulness of breathing is number three and the whole sequence starts with um
something that is relatively easy to know very simple intuitive and
quite global and so for most of the folks who began to practice engage in
a mindfulness of body practice there's the first to feel are relatively easy easily accessible
so for example being aware of our postures and we all know that we
have some sort of posture and we're aware of it and so the practice is to simply know
that oh you know i'm standing right here i'm standing or on
if you're lying down just aware that you're lying down very light weight noticing just know
and then uh the awareness of a body activities um it's also something very
um relatable and maybe comparing to the first practice it has a
little more detail and so you are you're now paying attention to different
activities as you uh go about your daily life and so
um it's maybe has a little more detail than adjusted the four postures
and then after that mindfulness a briefing so now we're settling down to a more
settled state of being where we begin to pay attention to some
details of the activity and as this whole sequence of seven unfolds
and you get a sense that there is a growing sense of settledness
and the subtlety and collectedness and so the
strength of samadhi and mindfulness began to build up as we
practice in this way starting from the first practice mindfulness of
awareness of the posture awareness of the bodily activities
and yet you know the practice doesn't have to go uh in sequence exactly like this you know
for most of us and we may practice in one particular one uh in different situations and then just
practice with that for quite some time so for example becoming aware of
on the bodily postures and bodily activities and was a
you know a practice that i engaged in for quite some time and especially at the beginning of my um
meditation practice i didn't have a regular formal
meditation sitting but i was
still interested in cultivating mindfulness and so i incorporated just noticing
my activities as i go about on kind of living my life in daily life
and it has an effect because becoming aware of our coarser level um
postures and body activities in action it began to cultivate and tone our mind
from this muscle and as we actually sit down
when we begin to sit down if we had cultivated this mindfulness
in our daily life by noticing various activities as we
we do them on the sitting meditation can be more
easily um uh settling so one can settle down but much more quickly
but if you know during the day um you know whatever you're doing you're
very preoccupied with thinking this thinking that and and you
know for example if you're cooking uh instead of noticing that you're cooking and you
know taking this spatula or flipping the pancakes and you're simply thinking
about all kinds of things and then we have last opportunities to really begin to
atone our mindfulness muscle and as we sit down and to do our formal meditation
our mind can still have this momentum to jump here and there i'm busy engaging in all kinds of
mental activities so this first few a couple of mindful body
practices can be a great way to really set the conditions up for us
and to go into more formal meditation practice
but they they can also be complementary to formal meditation practice
and some people do formal walking meditation on retreats or daily life and that
itself can be a very meditative meditative process as well
and then as this process goes on the next um practice that's being
introduced is mindfulness of in and out breathing
in this particular suta mindfulness of a breathing and that's being described here uh
includes the four steps of mindfulness breathing that is
noticing in and out breathing as it is and as you breathe in and out
begin to come and settle the body and so in our meditation before this
talk we did a little bit of that and kind of as we began to
uh breathe in and out this process itself can begin to settle the body
and allow the body to become quieter and calmer
and some of you may know that um mindfulness breathing itself and
can be a a whole system a comprehensive process of its own that leads to full
awakening and that process consists of the 16 steps
that go through mindfulness breathing that allows the body to come calm down
and then allow the mind to settle and then um go through the process to
cultivate joy and tranquil tranquility and and also leading to seeing
the insight and the nature of our experiences
and so that that itself is a 16 step of a process in this suta
it's the first four steps and that are related to calming and easing the body
that's being brought here
and then but it has an effect because as we go through on this mindfulness
breathing process when our bodies become to come
down the next few practices that are introduced become
more relevant to become more available to us and so for example the next uh practice
that's been introduced in the susuta is the contemplation of the analytical parts
so this is a a contemplation that is
not taught often in secular mindfulness some teachers also teach contemplation
of analytical parts but it's not very popular and and yet in and the mindfulness of
body teaching and it's a quite a significant
practice of its own so what you can and one way to understand this
particular teaching is that as we become calmer in relationship to our body we can begin
to see this body in a bit more raw form rather than a bigger conceptual
framework of what this body is you know whether it's beautiful or ugly kind of all these other conceptual
things began to kind of fade out but we can begin to see this body
as it is in terms of its componentary and parts
and so the classic teaching and is to see this a body in terms of the 32 parts
or 31 parts starting from the exterior part of our body
you know body hairs and skin the nails and then go through this
process and and begin to contemplating internal of the body also
and all the way to on you know our flesh bones fat um and the body
liquids even including our your urine and um so you you know you ask
why why do we do this contemplation and that's probably not very popular
because if we begin to look at this body in this way often our immediate reaction
could be you as some form of aversion of repulsiveness
and so maybe that that's kind of why it's not very popular teaching uh in
contemplation of our mindfulness of the body teachings
but the buddha prescribed this specific teaching um as a way to really
point at some strong forces of craving in us
in particular craving for essential pressures it's not very hard to see that
you know many people and most of us probably have a strong claiming to our
bodies one way or another and i'm aware and that even for
kids when they are very young they will begin to have some sense of how they wanted to be
seen from the image or perspective what to wear and
how long a hair is and as the kids grow older you know in teenage
years young adults body images you know can be become so defining for
who we are i can certainly relate it to this myself
and as we get older uh we we can get very obsessed with our health
our the aging process
and so it's not hard to see that you know there can be a lot of cleaning and grasping
in relationship to this body and the buddha has um really seen this
um that in you know kind of the human psyche and so he prescribed to this kind
of contemplation to begin to see this as is
not something to be clinged to as you know beautiful
or repulsive against as ugly but just as this is what
what is what the body is made up of
and yet you know as we um began to engage in a practice like this the
contemplation of the analytical part there can also be some danger because
for those who do have a very negative and repulsive relationship
with one's own body and this form of practice can can lead to
um i don't know depression or it maybe even self-harm
and so it's a wise to really tune in to what kind of attitude we may have
and maybe even work with the teachers and to engage with this kind of practices so
that one can move with this practice move into this practice
with a more balanced mind in the suta and the simile that is being
used to describe this particular form of practice is that asia for one is looking into
a bag of mixed lentils and mixed rice and knows that you know the red lintel
is red lentil black lentil is a black lentil and and this is the way to look at you know
here the body has all those different parts just like you know the bag of lentils
and rice mixed up here and so there's no attitude of indulging
or attitude of pushing away and so it's a very neutral
way of looking at things as is
and so that's contemplation of the analytical parts
now moving from there the next practice that's being introduced in this
sequence is the contemplation of the four elements
and so what is happening is um in this stage now uh one
once um contemplation of reflection or observing of this body
is now moving into more of a felt sense of what this body is
now this may not be very obvious if one just began to practice
mindfulness body because it's not very uh common for one to relate to this
body at this level which can be not very intuitive
or hard to be accessible at the beginning but if we practiced
as and the sequence unfolds we began to see that once mindfulness
maybe began to grow i might one is able to let go of some of the higher level
concepts and ideas but now one is able to drop into
the raw and felt sense of what this body feels like
so the elemental natures of this body the firmness of the earthy part of the
body and the air and movements of the
of the body and then the space all around us inside us
and so contemplation of the four elements allow us to begin to cultivate even
further what this body is in the elemental level the raw level
and so this particular practice based on the contemplation of the four
elements and can also cultivate a strong sense of
ease unsettledness and so this allows the next
practice to begin to become accessible so the next practice is
a corpse contemplation again this may be something kind of a
provocative in our modern
secular my mindfulness teachings and rarely you would hear people talk
about corpse contemplation um yet the corpse contemplation
serve um very um how do i say it
very critical step in this cultivation and that is it's moving into a different
form of a perceiving the nature of this body
usually when we come to uh the notion of a death
most of us most people will have some sense of a denial even though we
all know that the death would happen but one would refuse to see it but through this
a process of cultivating how we see our bodies in this sequence of our
practices when it gets to corpse contemplation a mind may be more centered and began to
be waving to see oh this body is of nature to
age of the nature to be sick and of the nature to die
and even when this dead body [Music]
even when the death happens this dead body go through its own decomposition process will
eventually go back to earth go back to nature
and since through seeing that this it can lead oneself to an insight into impermanence
unsatisfactoriness of this body and the not self nature of this
this body is not something that we can hang on it's not something permanent
and so this corpse contemplation began to bring in kind of front and
center this inside way of seeing inside way of seeing
the nature of this body anitja dukkha and anata
and when we began to be able to see this body in this way there can be
a profound sense of letting go as well
and so in this sequence and the seventh practice is that of the four genres
it's a cultivation of the four stages of samadhi
and this is impossible because when um when we began to see the nature of
this body there can be a strong sense of letting go letting go of grasping and
cleaning and when the clinging and grasping are let go of
a deeper sense of well-being can bubble up joy tranquility equanimity can become
available and that can become a platform for us to lead into
full liberation awakening and so this process um that's described
uh prescribed by um this particular suta that includes um you know from a very
simple lightweight practice of being aware of our body postures body
activities to our breath and to noticing and reflecting
contemplating that this body has made component parts and all the way to begin to notice
that there is a felt sense of this body which is very uh elemental nature of
this body through this then the the
samadhi becomes available to us and this can lead to lead to
destruction of defilements so this is really kind of a holistic
system and that covers the uh the entire spectrum
spectrum of our practice and this practice has a lot of benefits
and the suta itself i have highlighted 10 different benefits you know ranging
from no longer being a victim of a desire and a discontent no longer being a
victim of a fear and dread and have a stronger capacity to endure
the vicissitudes of climate and hunger and disagreed and disagreeable
conditions all the way to destruction of
the defilements as i mentioned before and it's a very profound teaching
and so um i do hope that tonight's practice and
and this dharma talk is a bit of an inspiration for us to engage
in this practice with a lot of curiosity and
maybe some dedication and so may this mindfulness body practice
bring much benefit to all of us and to all beings thank you for being
here tonight and i wish you all a wonderful evening
or a wonderful day wherever you are so thank you