so good morning and welcome to
the first meditation session of the retreat that some of you are doing and for those
of you on youtube good morning and good day and
welcome to this monday morning meditation
and for this morning's meditation i would
like to emphasize the word awareness
sometimes i like to think of the word awareness as a synonym or for mindfulness or
and i'll talk more about that but what's interesting about awareness
is we talk about being aware we don't talk about doing aware
someone doesn't say i'm a wearing they say i am aware
and i associate being aware or awareness
to something like hearing versus listening hearing
is something that we can just hear those of us who have the ability to hear we can hear
something without intending to hear it the sound arises in the ear maybe a loud
sound nearby and we hear it if we're curious about it
then we turn our attention to it and we listen to it and listening
being the active and the intentional quality of what we do with our capacity to hear
and um i am so so i am aware
is equivalent to the hearing we can be aware without intending to be
aware we can be aware without directing the
attention with our interest in our intentionality
and when we practice mindfulness we're bridging the world bridging these
two aspects the non-intentional and the intentional the directed and the non-directed
the doing and then not doing and the word awareness
gives a little bit more emphasis on the on just allowing awareness to operate
so rather than doing awareness we
are being aware
and as such awareness is closer to
a state of mind than it is to an activity of mind
in particular mental action
as important as mental actions can be
are just a subset of what awareness can be aware of
and so with this anapanasati mindfulness of breathing
as it develops as we settle in
we're getting closer to the state of awareness than we are to
moments of knowing moments of what sometimes is called mindfulness
so taking a meditation posture
and finding a posture
adjusting your body to a posture that is suitable for you
to be aware in a calm and relaxed way
for this purpose it's helpful if the posture is relatively comfortable relatively
relaxed
and then it's helpful to
settle into your body and one of the ways of doing that
is to take a few long slow deep breaths at the beginning of a sitting
and the deep inhales are maybe three quarters full three-quarters of a full in-breath
nothing that would tire you out or strain you but something that would allow you
to feel your body more fully breathing in and that
full breath not only feels your body
but a little bit energizes it in a good way
and then taking letting your breath return to normal
and feeling
your body letting your awareness your attention
roam around your body maybe in its own way
to the places where there are some tensions or holdings
and as you exhale relax soften the places of holding
perhaps it's a little bit in the muscles of the
belly softening the belly
maybe there's some softening around the front of the chest
softening in the shoulders
and softening in the face
perhaps also there's a some possibility on the exhale to relax the thinking mind
maybe around where the brain is
or are there places in the body where thinking has its tentacles
and as you exhale to quiet the thinking mind
allow the thinking mind maybe to think slower
there's no hurry here in meditation
there's no requirement to think of anything else besides the meditation
and if you're thinking about what the meditation maybe you can do so quietly
calmly slowly
in ways that are clearly supportive of the meditation
so maybe the thinking is kind thoughts about
now turning the attention to the
breathing thoughts about experiencing
being present for how the body experiences breathing
simple thoughts of receiving the inhale
thoughts are being present for the inhale just as it begins
and letting there be a receptive quality where the the body's ability to be aware
to sense and to feel receives the inhale
maybe receives it as an upwelling feeling of energy of movement
of sensations
and then as you exhale to release with the exhale
there is a letting go in the exhale allow yourself to exhale
allowing the release
inhaling and receiving the inhale
in awareness
allowing the exhale
to release within awareness
so not so much focusing on the breathing
but more allowing breathing to focus itself in the middle of awareness
as if breathing
is received it's like the waves received by the beach
in which the beach then releases or allows to wash back
roll back back into the ocean
across the beach of awareness comes the waves of in inhaling and exhaling
and regardless now of what you're thinking about what you're thinking about is less
important than noticing the
it as activity of the mind
whatever the activity the actions the energy
energetics of the mind are see if you can let that relax
as the activities of the mind relax into a calmness of the mind
set a place of subtleness
a calm body a calm mind
and then we are always aware we're we're always conscious
there's always some degree of awareness going on
see if you can allow for a state of being aware or state of awareness that is more
naturally there it doesn't require a
doing but more an allowing to be aware
allowing awareness is close to being in a receptive state
receiving experiences as they occur in the present
and with breathing at the center of it all
a receptive awareness that also receives breathing
receives the experience of inhaling and
exhaling
breathing is a rhythm
that reminds us
to be receptive in the awareness
not to fixate on anything or get caught in thought
the rhythm of breathing received an awareness
in a sense a rhythm that keeps awareness open and
receptive
so we stay closer to a place of quiet receptivity
a state not dominated by thinking a state more characterized
by receptive awareness of what is
a state of awareness
that we repeatedly allow for repeatedly return to
resting in receptive awareness
there is a way of being aware where awaring is not doing
but more being more a state that we're in a state of awareness
and within that state we can register be aware of many
different things that occur but those things can occur
without intentionality from us without desire without
making something happen
and to relax allow for that form of the state of awareness
allow yourself to be aware
in that allowing allow the experience of breathing
to remind you to stay receptive
to be allowing of what is
if we can recognize awareness as a state state of awareness
like a state of mind or state of being
that allows us to
be content in that state or to be to rest in that state
to allow ourselves to be receptive in that state of awareness
perhaps a state of awareness where we're not actively involved with what we know
we're not for things or against things
we're not trying to fix things or get away from anything
that there's a willingness to just be aware of whatever is happening
a state of awareness
that's receptive and open
and with a state of awareness resting in it content in it
you might bring to mind or include in that awareness now
some of the people that will be part of your life today
the community of people on the retreat or those are not on the retreat
in whatever communities you might be in today
whether personally or on some form of communication technology
and for a few moments to allow for a sensitivity of awareness
of those people
that's only possible if we rest in awareness allow them to exist in awareness
while we rest in the awareness or remain receptive in that awareness
where we can be we can be aware of people without doing anything or
needing to respond act just
aware
and that being staying close to this way of being receptively aware of others
just being aware of them
not paying attention to them but being aware simple awareness
that perhaps there in that awareness you can now tap into your good will
for others or your wish for their welfare your well-wishing of others
and to let that well-wishing radiate from you glow from you
flow from you may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
you