okay so so warm hello and welcome
wherever you are whatever time zone and for
the practice today i'd like to invite us to explore the
practice of equanimity and entering into it yet in a different
way on monday we explored equanimity
entering into it in one way as i described
noticing the coming and goings etc in our lives and then sense of
spaciousness so tonight we'll try something else yet another doorway
into equanimity and um see what do i want to say about it
before we start yeah maybe what i will say is there are so many different ways to
practice this beautiful practice of equanimity the crown jewel of buddhist practice
and maybe i will also say that the near enemy
or or what masquerade sometimes as as equanimity is aloofness not
not caring kind of uh turning our mind or our our hearts away
whereas equanimity is a sense of caring stability it holds presence
so we'll explore that another aspect we'll explore is there are so many different
perceptions so many different perspectives that we can play
with so many wholesome perspectives that we can invite and play with so
we will play with one perception a perspective of
on our life from a compassionate being from someone who cares and and take on
their perspective of both care and equanimity for us so that's kind of the territory
where we're going and let's just practice together and see what happens so i'd like to invite us
all to get into our meditation posture ah landing landing
[Music] landing in the body you need to shift
to lie down that's okay or sit up straighter
see what this body needs right now in this moment
and just landing glanding in the body arriving with the breath
spending some time to settle in a relaxed soft
present connected body grounded deeply rooted
will take a few minutes to just settle and arrive
the breath receiving the breath in the abdomen
in breath and opera
inviting your body to relax and soften
with the breath
nowhere to go nothing to accomplish
then to just simply inhabit this moment here
however it's showing up
noticing the sensations of the breath and the abdomen
noticing any sensations anywhere in the body that
calls to you letting the sensations be felt be sensed
whether pleasant or unpleasant the comings and goings of the sea of
sensations
just witnessed known now trying to fix push away
simply known
the rivers are sensation some pleasant some unpleasant
can also open up the awareness
to include the river of sounds the soundscape
coming and going arising and passing
not falling into not wanting more not pushing away just
knowing a rising passing of all the sounds the river of sounds
there can be peace ease the heart can be relaxed
the comings and goings of sensations
and sounds
not taking any sounds personally they come and they go can we have
equanimity equipoise with all the sounds
the same with the sensations
coming and going
being witnessed
spacious open allowing the comings and
goings not turning away not personalizing
and now also opening up to the comings and goings of thoughts
goings of comings and goings of emotions
perhaps labeling not my emotions but emotions
maybe sadness joy whatever it might be with each breath
witnessed not owned not clunked to
similar with thoughts like clouds in the sky
i'm getting entangled in the content
like watching the clouds and the sky
it's easy to have equanimity with clouds in the sky that come and go not me not
mine born out of causes and conditions
now you can stay with this or if you like continue with the next invitation
to imagine a kind compassionate presence
who is witnessing [Music]
with you all the comings and goings the rivers of sensations
pleasant and unpleasant
the sounds the emotions the thoughts like clouds in the sky
this kind compassionate presence who cares
witnessing knowing as if a good friend sitting next to you
watching being aware of this these rivers flowing
and they care they care about you and they have a lot of wisdom
they're both wise and compassionate
they have vast vast wisdom of the causes and conditions they're not
caught they care
and yet as they observe as they witness with you these comings and goings of your life
they have a sense of caring stability in their perspective
they care
and they are not toppled over they watch they sense they notice they
know that's happening for you intimately
and with a lot of equanimity
with their perspective of care and wisdom
then is it possible to witness yourself witness your own life
from the perspective of this wise and compassionate presence
you're welcome to imagine it as a friend sitting next to you or maybe non-localized
just a knowing that's wise and compassionate
see what works best for you
letting the body be relaxed make sure you're not trying too hard
if you notice it's the body has become tight or the breath
has become tight just relaxed just soften
and let the breath and body be known keep it simple
all the rivers of sensations thoughts sounds emotions just coming and going
known witnessed with care stability without pushing away or
falling into the vast wisdom spaciousness
with equipoise
equanimity
comings and goings of sense and events internally
and externally in the world
some pleasant some unpleasant all witnessed
all witnessed spaciously with equanimity
equipoise
all the comings and goings witnessed
from the perspective expanse of perspective of deep wisdom and compassion
far beyond
what we give ourselves credit for
but from a knowing a presence that compassionate
and wise from that arises deep deep equanimity
to hold all that arises and passes
perspective we can peek through
at our own life and others
and for the last
minutes of this practice together
allowing the river of thoughts sensations sounds
that this period of practice was
letting it be held witnessed from this expanse perspective of equanimity
caring stability
not judging not pushing away not berating
it flowed exactly as it needed to flow given the causes and conditions
and appreciating that we showed up and we did our best to practice
appreciating if we if our perspective managed to connect
even for a split second with the perspective of equanimity vast
equanimity stable caring witnessing the comings and
goings with care and wisdom
[Music]
thank you for your practice
so we have some time for reflections
questions you're invited to share your wisdom with
the community as they can be very supportive
and you can raise your [Music] zoom hand if you wish or type it in chat
and if you type in chat just to me i won't say your name
it'll be anonymous and if you type it to everyone then i will say your name so what did you notice in
this practice what did you notice in this way of practicing equanimity
maybe as i wait for you to form your reflections your questions
your complaints i will say that [Music]
it is said that with the four brahmaviharas the first one being metta love
loving kindness second one being mudita vicarious joy sorry second one being compassion karuna
third one being vicarious joy and the fourth one being equinemedi
upeka so it is said that
[Music] compassion is the love child of
suffering plus when love meets suffering it expresses itself
as compassion and i just thought that actually uh equanimity the fourth brahma vihara
is the love child of metta love child of love with um
wisdom with wisdom wisdom that sees all causes and conditions so when you
have love caring meta meets wisdom the two of them they express
themselves as equanimity so it's stable it's caring it's holding
witness it's not turning away and yet has
vast vast wisdom as a part of it
so so reflections why did you notice how was this for you
i'd love to take a couple of reflections from you
how are you finding yourself right now compared to before we're starting this
practice
mark please
i really enjoyed the practice i was just going to say not a super deep
reflection i just finished the book of joy which i'd heard about when you did this
series based on it and so my compassionate being was the dalai lama
and so the meditation was kind of like what would the dalai lama do like how would he hold whatever's coming
up which was fine because sometimes it was like laughter and just being silly sometimes it was compassion
and sometimes it was just sort of like peaceful like you said sort of vast wisdom that
doesn't get hung up on things so it was fun it's lovely thanks clark thanks for
sharing that i i love worth hearing that you're inspired to read the book of joy which i
think is wonderful based on the series we did together and also that your compassionate presence was dalai lama and
was playful because he tends to be a playful person especially as it comes through the book
the book of joy he's just he's having a fun time with desmond tutu and they're
joking and making fun of each other and just just such lighthearted compassionate joyful presence together
with a lot of wisdom of course so yay i so appreciate you bringing that
in clark that's lovely that's great
and question comes from mitra can you say a few words about equanimity and right effort
being okay with what is and making effort to stay with mindfulness
um [Music] vitrogen let me ask you some uh what uh
what would be helpful what because there's so many directions i can go so it would be helpful to hear a little
more about what would be what's coming up for you that this question is becoming relevant
so yeah um in regards to
meditation um i tend to be very upset with myself when
i can stay mindful or i lose my
mindfulness and how do i and i i see the benefit of trying to be
more economists with that but how do i gauge it so i'm not too
easy on myself yeah yeah that's a really good question
so um so it's it's i'll also so i understand
the question thanks for for elaborating um so
i'll say a couple of words about wise effort or wise engagement the word effort
brings a lot of we can bring oh tightness so why is engagement what is wise engagement they're not related to
to equanimity so so with wise engagement
the buddha likens it to tuning a bow a bowed instrument so sometimes it will be too tight like
are you trying too hard oh i miss that breath oh i missed that thought bad bad bad that's a little too tight
ouch and then too loose would be daydreaming for the entire 45 minutes
and then it would be the last you know if it's the 45 minutes or in this case the 30 minutes you know
uh they drew me for 35. oh i'm daydreaming it's fine noticing that you're daydreaming
and not doing anything about it that's too loose right in the middle you're like i'm daydreaming but it's fine this is so
fun i don't really want to follow that meditate so that would be too loose so okay so those are the ends okay
so from what you've described it sounds like you're closer to the tight to the to the efforting right it's like
bad you missed that oh instead of so so it's okay so go you so so in order to
find what is the the appropriate level of engagement you need to loosen you will be
you get you will get too loose at some point and then you'll get a little tight at some point and then lose some so you
you'll just do this until you how you develop a discernment for
what is appropriate so don't expect to be right on all the time but from what i'm hearing from you is that
you're too tight so loosen it have more ease like oh i just noticed i
i was daydreaming for five five minutes ah it's okay i'll start again
so a sense of ease a sense of ease of letting go um so and and that's how actually
equanimity can come in here because then you're not fighting it you're not trying because it's past it's gone anyway there's a
sense of ease of spaciousness oh maybe the mind is really busy because
these are the causes and conditions that's the that's how the wisdom comes in like these are the causes and conditions
of this body right now it's very distracted and another um
thing that i've heard and i use is distracted buddha or thinking buddha is
what you can say and i've used that a lot of times i've you know i've sat and my mind has been
really really all over the place like oh today the mind is busy i'm showing up as the busy buddha
busy mind buddha as the distracted buddha this is these are the causes and conditions that are
showing up and having just as much ease that's a training too having just as much ease so because you
know and recognize you had the intention i had the intention um but being
equanimous with with what arises because that's really what we're trying to
cultivate anyway it's a sense of peace with all causes and conditions so if we can't have peace
because the conditions of our minds right if we're then
we're trying to get somewhere that we're just going the opposite way how can we get there when we're going this way
you see so having more peace with
i love thinking about causes and conditions i mean that that kind of loosens
the the harshness is also thank you thank you
thank you dear thanks for bringing that in and olivia oops uh okay never mind
i'll skip i'll look at that comment another time um so uh
i realized it was just it was directed to me so i didn't want to say the name so
olivia if you want to stay later i'll i'll read that and and we'll um address this together sorry uh wanted
to keep it anonymous oh well okay so matthew i see you're oh actually tell you what matthew let's uh if it's
okay let's do the groups uh and come back and come i'll come back
to your comment because time is flying by so keep that thought please so so
let's turn our attention to small practice in small groups in small
breakout groups and we'll come back and reserve some time for reflections at the end
so here we go creating the rooms and look let us start
with um 30 seconds of silent meta for each other and then you're
welcome to share anything you wish okay here we go i'm going gonna open the rooms
here we go okay okay welcome back everyone we have
about a minute left and uh matthew you had your handle up so please if you would kindly unmute
yourself hi uh i haven't been here in a few weeks uh the last time i was here i think was
for mutita and for me it's easier that i find like mudita or meta are a little bit
less subtle like they're a bit easier to bring up for me and i was wondering if
there's kind of a way to maybe like go from one of those into equanimity or if if that's kind of
normal the economy is like a little bit less easy to kind of just feel straight
away yeah yeah equanimity tends to be
more subtle than the other ones which is why it's number four because all the teachings of the buddha if you've noticed they go from the
grosser to more and more subtle um so um
yeah so so um so yeah so if you're finding it more subtle you're not alone i've heard this from
many other people that oh yeah this is a little more subtle wait a minute like ah um so hang in there hang in there
and and it's it's nature to be a little more subtle it's just it's it's part of the kind of nature of
equanimity to be a little more subtle right it's not in your head over you know it's like oh
my god it's more like ah it's more kind of a subtle way of holding there's some care so um so with that you
can either get into it from meta where there's a little some care some care and there's and then opening to
wisdom with all causes and conditions or or getting into it from compassion like ah i care for you i hold
you and may um it is what it is and i guess also the
other thing to say is that um at the beginning you said that um you haven't been to happy hour since
uh mutita and then after murita we did a week of uh of equanimity and
and there was a lot more uh methodical i use the phrases and sometimes the phrases can help
people so so that's it matthew you might want to go back and look at the archives of the week of equanimity
when there were five or six or sessions or something and much more methodical and yeah and play
around with those yeah great i am glad you brought this up thank you thank you thanks so
dear ones the time has come for us to end with equanimity to let go to this hour of
practicing equanimity together so thank you all for your practice for this cultivation that
you do not just for yourself but for all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings
be free thank you