so hello and welcome everyone to happy hour
so for the theme for this practice for us
this um sitting together um
two themes i like to bring in one is the theme of of wisdom
imbue imbuing meta imbuing uh kindness and kindness imbuing
awareness which is a theme that those of you on retreat for a week that's
one theme from the retreat that the people reported were very um nourishing
different different way of practicing in many ways for many people
so that's one thing i like to bring in because really meta is so it doesn't need to be
different from wisdom practices and with wisdom practices where we pay attention
where we become aware of what's arising what's passing awareness awareness awareness this
awareness can be imbued with
ah kindness care warmth acceptance
love so many different nuances of meta who are different for different
occasions but basically knowing knowing intertwined
with ah sense of e sense of care love um so for example when judgmental
thoughts arise knowing them but not pushing them away oh you stop it right now
that never works because if you try to to punish yourself if you try to um if you try to um
work with aversion with a version doesn't doesn't really help it just
becomes more conflictual so noticing with ah
noticing with being becoming aware with curiosity with acceptance with love
like oh judgmental thought okay let me be curious about this let me
open up to it and understand it a little more so awareness can be impeded with this
imbued with the spirit of meta spirit of openness acceptance um so
that's one theme i like uh to invite us to sit with to explore in the guided meditation and
um the other theme is we'll be primarily working uh with
with ourselves ourselves body thoughts the the realm kind of the internal
realm not so much going external with other beings as as we sometimes do in concentric
widening circles of meta but as the buddha said if you search the whole world
you won't find any more worthy of your own love
your own care your own affection your own mental
so that's all i want to say to set up the framework and let's
do let's get into it together or not do whatever might be appropriate but let's
transition into our practice space
so inviting you to shift move if you need to
change position if you need to lie down if you need to sit up a little
straighter whatever this body needs notice what
this body needs right now
and arriving arriving and landing
greeting creating this body greeting not just the body but also the
space in which the body sitting
is being held becoming aware
of the body
earth element body with heaviness weight
earth on earth and aware of the air element inside the
breath
that moves through the body
while noticing the body grounded stable shifting
allowing the shifting of awareness shifting of your weight
ah to be moved down
your sit bones to your legs to your feet
the earth element grounded
[Music] stable
inviting the whole body to relax your hands your arms your shoulders
let them drop their weight
fighting your legs to give their weight to the earth
feeling supported
dividing your whole trunk your sit bones
to let go [Music] to release any tension
that you might be aware of holding
the same for the face muscles of the forehead the jaw
muscles inside the face
inviting them fighting the muscles to release let go
of any tension
holding
let awareness
expand to feel the entire body hold the entire body
with each out breath dropping in
dropping more releasing more tension
notice that this body earth alone earth on earth grounded rooted
is breathing it's being breathed
noticing aware of the air moving in and out
on its own
the body being breathed
it's not so much that we are breathing consciously let the
unconscious parasympathetic nervous system knows how
to do this perfectly well
simply relaxing and letting it be known
and as awareness is turned internal
intimately knowing the breath the entire in-breath entire opera
can the knowing be tinged imbued with friendliness as if you're greeting
a friend who's visiting
every moment a new arrival
awareness grieving
knowing with friendliness
whatever comes in contact with
whatever is known the breath
sensations
and as thoughts arise maybe thoughts of judgment
oh you're not doing this well oh you're getting distracted
can awareness meet these visitors too
with openness of heart with friendliness they're just
visitors
even if aversion arises not liking wanting to push something away
in our bodies and our hearts and can that too be met
ah be known
with ease the relaxed open friendly attitude
if anything arises that's challenging hello challenge
hi how are you
how's it going or aversion to something stop
go away ah and they're wanting to stop go away
how are you how do you feel let me know you it's okay
ah i'm open to knowing you with ease with friendliness
for some things you don't need to linger some thoughts that can be known oh it's like this
for a moment with friendliness and you can come back to knowing the
breath the sensations of the body receiving them
receiving the sensations of the breath in the body
greeting this friend this breath this one visiting this
moment this out breath visiting and now this
one getting to know
the entirety of them not just casually but really getting
to know them intimately from the moment they arrive
till the moment they leave taking care of this serving tea
and cookies this breath just this one
you might even experiment with smiling
at thoughts
especially if they're judgmental genstrom receiving them with a smile
and letting them pass greeting them and letting them be on their way
we're smiling at the breath receiving it with friendliness
smiling is such a powerful tool imbuing awareness with mental
but what would happen what may shift or change
if you smiled physically smiled
imbuing your perception
the knowing
with the friendliness of a smile please try it and if you
are hesitant or feel ridiculous try it anyway experiment like a scientist see what
happens smiling
and whatever arises in the field of experience in this moment whatever it is
deceiving receiving them all
even if they're a crowd of sorrows ah receiving them with a smile
everything sensations body breath thoughts
sounds
emotions
it is hypothesize that smiling
is an over evolutionary way to offer safety
to offer safety and friendliness to signal that to others
can we signal that friendliness safety offer it to ourselves
to whatever arises this fear of
experience
and for the last moments of this practice period
holding with appreciation offering safety and care
to yourself for having practiced for having showed up
even if there was connecting with the practice the practice for one second
knowing that you are planting seeds by continuing to show up
as best as you're able to so appreciating appreciating this being
that is me for showing up and practicing whatever arose
or did not arise it's all okay
offering safety goodwill and appreciation
may all beings be safe may all beings be
free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so we have some time for sharing reflections observations
questions sharing practice if you wish
you can raise your your uh
zoom hand or type it in chat if it's typed in chat to everyone i will
um read your name otherwise if it's just privately to me uh you only mention the comment or
question and not the name as i invite your reflections i'll share
one reflection one um one thing that came up for me practicing in this moment
in this way so interesting that any thought
any motion or or tightening um that was that was graded
that was that was created in this friendly way with this smiling uh smiling awareness
offering safe it actually it released much more easily or quickly just
released so that was an interesting observation to see that oh they were greeted and like
hi we're visiting okay now we'll go so interesting to see so what did you
notice what came up for you
[Music]
comments
did you find this an easeful way of practicing
what's the smile hi lisa hi hi um
i think one thing i'm noticing is i guess this baby pertains more to
strong emotions for me right now but saying like not now
versus like pushing away or like denying or not feeling the emotion and
noticing how i i think a lot of times my version of
engaging with the emotion is really like falling into it that empathetic distress
and so this like way that it it can actually be okay
notice like oh angers here but i'm like you know what i really want to
practice meta right now and feel good because i really need it so just like okay not now
and i think maybe it's because there's some
not kindness towards the anger i'm not sure like hopefully but that maybe makes it possible um
so it's kind of like what i've been working with i guess or i noticed today
great thanks for sharing that lisa yeah oh brilliant i love how you describe
that how you've noticed sometimes in the past falling into falling into difficult
emotions and uh kind of his empathetic distress
and here now there being this this wisdom in deciding actually hello visitor anger um
i could practice with you i could you know with rain or let you move through the body but right now
actually it's wise and i'm going to say not now later right now i'm going to choose to do this
because i i want to resource myself i want a resource and i'm kind of
tired right now and not visa so brilliant beautiful use of wisdom to know when
it's when it's appropriate uh for for challenging emotions for not to
arise to say no and and also that's something we discussed this
this week and the practice is the four skillful the four wise efforts to know to have
the skillfulness for on arisen or or arisen in this case where anger is
arisen is coming to to skillfully to say no no to let it to support it
to go away skillful and again what you're describing didn't
sound like aversion to me it wasn't like go away it was like not now i'm gonna come back later we'll work
later but now i'm giving myself to this practice brilliant brilliant thanks for sharing
that lisa love it nice
one reflection uh it has come through chat is easier to stay
focused while smiling great what a wonderful realization and please
know that that's always available to you if there's difficulty staying focused smile at whatever is
coming up it's so easy uh reflection from forest
when you said only this breath something in my heart felt really good i would remember that
oh lovely thanks for sharing that first only this breath right here
and abraham i see your hand whoops uh-oh i tried to ask you to unmute there you
go
yeah i'll click you click i'll click you click i i i clicked only once but i can hear
you now abraham lovely to hear you here you are hi nikki uh thoughts about the smile and
maybe this only works for um extroverts like myself maybe the introverts all know how to do this
already but i really resist somebody telling me to smile
and i find that if i smile in such a way that nobody can see it it
still feels like a really nice smile
so i get the benefit without feeling like i'm doing what other teachers telling me to do
[Laughter]
you crack me up i love how your you're smiling underneath oh you're smiling underneath
so i i'm absolutely delighted i have with detail my heart is joyous that the
practice of smiling underneath is working for you abraham that gives me great joy
thanks for sharing that that it shows up in this way for you that's lovely
and yay i put another chalk to the smiling practice in in again personalized
personalized however it works for a given person of course all these invitations you personalize
for yourself you see how it works for you these are all just invitations so that's
a very uh sophisticated deep meta practices smile practice
yes absolutely it is i'm joking but that's fine i like it
great so let's see um susan says um thank you lisa that was helpful ah
that's lovely and holly says i was able to uncover a fear driving the thoughts i was having
i think the smiling helped this ah thank you for sharing that
thank you for sharing that holly that's yeah there's something um evolutionary
and biologic biologically about smiling which is about offering safety
and really can use this whichever way um works for you offer offering this um
to yourself as this the practice and elizabeth says i love the idea of secret smile abraham that's great
so so dear ones let's transition to
our practice in small groups and community and
the invitation is starting with 30 seconds of meta and if you choose to smile at each
other or or is it secretly smile that's your choice you can experiment with that and
see how that feels in in interactions in on the zoom thing um
and if not that's okay just but starting with 30 seconds of meta and then you can share as much or as
little as you wish in community this time is very precious as many of you
have spoken about the time to a practicing community so so i'm
going to in a moment open the rooms
and here we go they're open
okay welcome back everyone rooms are closed
so we have just a few minutes if you would like to share uh some
reflections um but what what do you notice what came up for you what how was it please
hmm jerry says wisdom nice do you want to say more jerry
i'm always impressed by the wisdom of the group it's like
it's uh amazes me uh you know when you're in your head and then someone else is talking about
their life and just even even seeing people actively listening to what you're saying it's it's one of
the most profound things so it's uh there's a lot of profound wisdom in these groups
thank you thank you jerry thank you for that yeah great and kathleen asks
could someone put the group web address up in the chat uh this is something that uh that we
always have uh um uh neil do and and um so if somebody else can do that but
i don't have it handy come come again tomorrow kathleen probably neil will will be here
and we can share that unless somebody else has it any other reflections
i'd love to hear maybe one more reflection what did you notice about practice in this diff slightly different
way of practicing uh imbuing awareness with this kindness with with with
with metta with offering safety to what comes up internally as a way of
doing meta for ourselves holding ourselves with care offering
safety would love to hear maybe one more reflection if anybody would like to talk about
how the smiling practice perhaps was we're calling it the smiling practice now hi holly please
hi um i'm gonna have to keep doing the science experiment but i think
i think that the smiling helped um like calm me down
and i and my like anxious thoughts were less likely to
keep spiraling did that make sense absolutely yeah so i'll keep
experimenting and see if that's true yeah it's sounds like a great um
in great report of great first report first draft of your report of your experiment as a scientist that you are
of your own mind as we all are scientists of our own minds and see what works for us
how it might work and keep making discoveries and i look forward to hearing more about your
experiment holly seeing what you discover so and also thank you clark for sharing
the google groups information uh in chat so thank you all for your
practice thanks for coming together and doing this practice not just for your own
sake but for all those whose lives we touch directly and indirectly
may all beings be happy which includes us which may all beings be happy may
all beings be safe may all beings be free
thank you all you