so a formal hello and welcome to all of you to this rendition of happy hour
so for today's practice he wanted to invite us
[Music] exploring meta and gratitude
there was a question last time that came up how does metta feel how does gratitude
feel in the body and i thought we would spend some time today
again meta there's meta for oneself there's meta for others it's a big field metta but we're going
to tap into meta practice of love and kindness and then
at some point we'll turn to the practice of gratitude and we will be will serve as scientists
of our own mind and heart and say oh how do these feel differently
for for us in our bodies the embodiment
and how do they feel in our minds what's what brings up knowing observing having sati
having mindfulness becoming mindfully aware of how these practices
move through us of course it's both a practice of cultivation
both cultivating meta and loving-kindness as well as gratitude tonight as well as
awareness of how these cultivations impact us so it's a twofold cultivation
one is the cultivation itself turning our hearts our minds
so that meta and gratitude become the automatic response
of our hearts and minds to situations instead of gosh you name it instead of so many
challenging ways that the mind and heart can respond to situations why me
this is terrible or ill-will but there's so many ways the mind and heart can respond
isn't it wouldn't it be nice if the natural re reflexive if the reflexive response
is one of kindness towards ourselves towards others and one of gratitude even if things are
difficult even if things are difficult so one aspect is the cultivation
and the other aspect that i'm inviting us to turn to is aware of the impact of the
cultivation so knowing how we're shifting and changing
because it turns out that the more you are aware of what it is that's happening the more
it takes hold in your mind and your heart and your neurons whatever perspective
you take however you cut the cake so awareness of the thing supports
the things cultivation so so with that as
our setup um let's begin as always
we begin with settling in the body with the breath with some
minutes of just arriving with calm abiding
landing landing in this body
landing with this breath
landing in our seat
this being here and together
all of us practicing together quite beautiful
letting the breath breathe you in
and out
in [Music]
just this moment appreciating the delicious simplicity of
this moment the mind doesn't want to go elsewhere
just resting resting here
you know what to do letting go
of entanglements of thought turning
to your sacred intention for cultivation this moment taking refuge
the breath the body here just here settling
arriving
now like to invite you to bring to mind
someone you care about straightforward relationship with them
could be a child could be a pet or a friend or benefactor
feeling of safety comes over you may be a smile of delight
bringing this dear being to mind
your mind's eye their fountains
and noticing what comes up in your body
in your mind as you conjure them up
and from this place of goodwill friendliness gladness sharing the phrases of mitta
may you be safe darwin
may you be happy dear one
may you be healthy dear one
and may you have ease dear one
repeating the phrases silently to yourself
or just beaming friendliness good will
warmth kindness good will towards them
for them i'll say their phrases one more time
may you be safe
fully knowing that they may not be safe from everything but we're expressing your wish and
intention inclining our mind to wish them well wish them safety
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may your life unfold with ease
keeping the image the felt sense of the friend benefactor the deer went up so that the
mind doesn't wander
and using the phrases as the anchor for the feeling
if you wish
keeping the image of your dear being fresh in your mind's eye
their felt sense will support your mind not drifting
and staying with the phrases of meta the feeling of matter
noticing in the moments when meta is flowing what does it feel like in your mind in
your heart in your body becoming mindful
of the feeling of matter
now imagine your dear is looking at you
with kind eyes let yourself be seen through their
perspective the way they see you perhaps with
love admiration kindness care
letting yourself be seen receiving their care
their mental
and adding your voice to theirs
may i be safe [Music]
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i meet this moment with ease
or may my life unfold with these you prefer
may i be safe
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i have ease
keeping an image of yourself in mind felt sense of yourself so that your mind
doesn't wonder
are they connecting with your felt sense or an image or yourself
whichever works best
and noticing what wishing well for yourself feels like what does it feel like in your body your
mind and heart
a notice of becoming mindful aware becoming aware of the feelings of meta
for yourself whether it enhances a meta for yourself
intensifies brings it alive
one last minute of meta for ourselves
connecting with the felt sense of this body and image of ourselves and the phrases
may i be safe
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i have ease
and now as we continue to sit failing our bodies
being breathed sitting connecting to the earth
what is one thing you feel grateful for in this moment as you're sitting here it could be as
simple as the chair you're sitting on it's a nice comfortable chair
or that it's a chair nice thank you chair for supporting me supporting my weight
robbie or maybe for the air you breathe
or that there's a roof over your head you're safe from the element
in this moment
you've had food to eat
that this body is functioning well enough
with cognitive ability and listening and cognizing that you can
show up and practice in this moment heart beating
breathing happening all the all the amazing functions of this body
and in your own time your own time
allowing your heart to become a light with gratitude of the soul for so much
goodness that we often take for granted in this
life
ranging from just simply being aware the miracle of awareness in this moment
to be grateful for that
the limbs of the body functioning imagine if one of the limbs was broken right now
how tough your life would be caring for yourself
bathing working feeding yourself
if your leg was in a cast or an arm
and wow your arm your leg is not in the cast
what a blessing how amazing you can get up after this meditation
with as much health as is available so take your time
without making your mind too busy letting yourself linger with each item
of gratitude for a few moments
maybe even a minute or two before moving on to the next
notice how gratitude feels
your heart body and mind
and for the last few minutes of this practice period
you are welcome to stay with the practice of gratitude
with the abundance the feeling of abundance
or if you wish
you can cycle through meta for the dear being that we started with
what that feels again if it's available and then meta for yourself
feelings in the body and art you choose what's best
may all beings everywhere may they be safe happy healthy
have ease may all beings everywhere know the
abundance of their own goodness of their heart
may all beings everywhere be free including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so we have a few minutes for reflections what you discovered what was this like
for you you can either type them in chat the zoom chat and if it's just type to
me i won't say your name you'll be private it will be private and if
you type them to everyone i will read the reflections with your name you can also raise your zoom hand
especially if you haven't shared for a while would love to hear from you so what did you discover um what
i'll say a couple of things while i wait for you for your reflections
and what was interesting actually becoming aware because i
invited you to become aware of the feeling of meta first for the dear being first for
yourself and then for yourself and then for and then gratitude turning
awareness to the meta i noticed actually it did intensify the feeling of metta
and the feeling of gratitude for me and also that each
practice felt very different for me maybe i'll i'll pause until i hear from you what you
discovered anthony says grateful for the dukkha thank you anthony that is beautiful that's a
beautiful insight to be grateful for the dukkha yeah
nancy says aware of how tender my heart is today yeah thank you nancy
bill says felt more emotional when doing gratitude metta was quieter ah thank you for that
observation and violet please
so when i did meta for myself the body experience was like
tingling everywhere in my body except for my heart center so my heart center
felt like this like bubble of novocaine and then when i was doing
gratitude i decided to keep it very literal i'm holding like a very fuzzy pillow
and i love fuzzy things i was like wow so grateful for this like fuzzy pillow that i can feel on my lap
and it was so clean so that felt like like a hand was like coming out of my
heart center and like literally grabbing onto this pillow like i'm only grateful for this pillow because it's on my lap right now but the
second it's gone i'm not going to be grateful for it anymore because i won't have it anymore
but then and then i was like wow this is so self-centered like i am grateful for
what i have i have this pillow so but then i thought about when we were doing
mudita you talked about how like mudita like for yourself can be a form of gratitude
so then i zoomed out to like i'm happy for this being who is violet who has a
fuzzy pillow in her lap right now and then the tingles went back to my whole body so it went from just being in
my heart to being in the rest of my body when i did that beautiful my whole body tingles as as i
hear violet as to how yay beautiful how with
wisdom like oh yeah oh with observation oh yeah this is what this feels oh that's interesting oh how about that
shifting perspective medita for this being who is me beautiful violet i am so touched that's
lovely yay may your modita practice for yourself continue to flourish
it's lovely thank you beautiful yeah it's great
and a few other reflections here let's see um
[Music] melanie so grateful for nicki's voice and guidance and for everyone here today
as always ah thank you melanie for your gratitude for for being here and
practicing in sangha and i'm so grateful that we're all showing up together
and i'm so grateful for you that's one thing that came up when i was doing this practice i'm so grateful for this sangha
that i can support you and it supports me and it's just a beautiful thing and um another reflection
more selfing with meta gratitude was more spacious great wonderful to observe these
differences and and and the ways that we can uh find our ways through these practices
lovely and tara on youtube says
how it was easier to generate meta for dear being plus all beings okay great and that it's
interesting to notice that and uh maybe that can be a stepping stone for
generating meta for oneself and thank you patricia from ireland joining us on youtube
beautiful practice thank you and thank you for your practice patricia yeah lovely so um
any other reflections um maybe as i wait i'll tell you a few things that i noticed and again for each
person they could feel differently any given day any given time these
practices could feel different so for me what i noticed was meta for my dear being felt
felt um like beaming beaming generosity and
care and love that's what it felt like in my body just and then for me it was meta from myself
was really soothing healing just calming as if it was a salve of oh
care and and gratitude felt there was a lot of joy a lot of
abundance of ingratitude in my heart it was just kind of bubbly like wow so much goodness here
yay let's turn to it so those are some of my practice notes from today of course
every time could be different so so dear ones we can save some time on
the other end and you come out of the small practice groups because a lot of times
being in small groups really brings up more reflections you hadn't considered before like oh yes
that is true for me too when you hear other people and also when you're held witness
can be so supportive for one's practice so let's start with 15 seconds of silent
uh practice silent meta for one another when we get into
groups and um then share as much or as little as you wish
about your practice with one another taking care of yourself taking care of
each other and um here we go i'm opening the rooms
now the rooms are are closed and everyone is back welcome
back everyone and we have a few minutes for any reflections that might have come up
discussing together practicing together in sangha peter
please okay they're unmuted um so we were talking about gratitude a
little bit terrence and i and we both had the observation that
sometimes meta is difficult to get into but for both of us gratitude is somewhat
easy and there's some similarity of the feeling
and so it occurred that maybe we could if we're having trouble with murder maybe to use gratitude as a leading
a prelude to the meta yeah beautiful observation yes peter
um and absolutely actually starting with gratitude it can prime the
heart for meta and this is also something that i observed tonight at the very end when
i invited you hey after having done gratitude now you can go through and do the meta again and see
what it feels like and when i turned back to doing the other practices even though they were really
short there was a sense of wow there's so much abundance in the heart now feeling grateful that it's easier to
give it's easier to give to others so absolutely peter and terence
fantastic observation so next time it feels a little difficult to get into meta start with gratitude
beautiful beautiful thank you for bringing that in
you're welcome yeah that's some something new to practice with that has a lot of problems
yeah great yeah wonderful yeah and gratitude tends to be easier and for some again never ever
i've learned teaching the dharma to never ever generalize anything to everyone for each
person is different and i so appreciate actually before we went into groups when people were
sharing their reflections in chat you know for for one person gratitude was more emotional method was quieter
and this you know this was easier that was easier it was just like everybody's different so
really appreciating and honoring all the differences that each of us brings to this practice
and finding our way to practice with uh with these practices so no yeah thanks
thanks peter any other reflections please
a quick one before we close an end
well maybe this has been plenty already come to think of it this has been quite rich it feels like
to me also hearing you all the reflections has been a very rich
exploration tonight and gratitude and and and meta for
dear being for ourselves and also be bringing awareness which is yet another
aspect bringing awareness to how these things feel so so thank you all for showing up
for cultivating your heart to your minds for your own sake in the sake of all beings whose lives you touch and
beyond may all beings be well may all beings
be free [Music]
thank you