so welcome to our earlier
meditation session and longer meditation of 45 minutes
and i'm very happy to be doing this with you and experiencing this
and so to introduce this meditation
i would like to say that um
the difference between someone who is a beginner in meditation and someone who's
practiced a long time doesn't have to be very different
if both people are entering the practicing meditation
is simply the there's something about the
simplicity of practice which is valuable for those
who are beginning and is part of the full realization
of those who mature in the practice and there's something
wondrous about being with the breathing in a simple way
as possible it's a wonderful challenge to do so because what gets
revealed are all the ways that we make it more complicated
all the ways that we have high expectations demands for how it should be the ways in which we judge ourselves as
things aren't quite right we're doing it wrong um ideals that we're trying to live by
or things we're trying to escape and to avoid experiencing and slowly over practice uh the movement
is to greater and greater simplicity which means that when we're sitting meditating with the breathing
it is it is
very forgiving that we're allowed to be as we
are in this simplicity and the art the key is a simplicity of awareness
just to be aware and and that is enough and
so to be aware of what's happening in the moment
and and to be with your breathing anyway so that's
what i'd like to suggest this morning is a simple attention to breathing
so to assume a meditation posture
that you might be able to be stable and still
for the duration of the sitting and to gently close your eyes
and and to
then simply be aware of your body
be aware of how the body is
and then within this body take a few long slow deep breaths
partly as an embodied reminder that for this time sitting here
we're going to sit in the middle of our body allowing it to be as it is breathing
breathing in and breathing out
and as you take a deep breath in then on the exhale relax
the body in a certain way tension in the body
involves our making things more complicated than they need to be
and so if it's easy to relax the shoulders
relax let go
soften
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and again as you exhale to continue to relax places that are easy to soften
relax the belly letting the belly hang forward down
again softening some in the chest
and the shoulders
also maybe relaxing the face
and as you exhale relaxing
the mind any sensations of pressure tightness agitation
that's connected to thinking or to the brain
and then in in now just settling in to the experience of the
body breathing by finding where in your body
it seems easiest or perhaps even most pleasant
to experience breathing for some people it's in the belly
some people in the chest some people in the nostrils the air goes
in and out
and now to take the experience the experiencing of breathing for granted
experiencing breathing
is the meeting it's a place where awareness
and the body meet
it's the meeting place of awareness
and the body breathing
it's a bit wonderous the simplicity
of experiencing breathing
and then to hang in there with the breathing
to trust the simplicity of experiencing the breathing
and if anything it takes you away from that or distracts from that
maybe take a little bit deeper breath and gently lovingly begin again with
your breathing
appreciating that nothing else needs to be figured out or thought about or
that for now
meditation unfolds
with a simple experience
of the body breathing
being aware of the breathing
as you're with your breathing you might in
in a simple way for a few breaths notice
that part of the inhale where the inhale just feels like
it's doing you it's doing itself it started and it's just going to continue
natural clear way just that's what's unfolding is the inhale
maybe it doesn't start at the beginning of it but at some point the inhale just
is on a roll it's just going to happen
and when that happens allow for it the simplicity of awareness
is the simplicity of just allowing that experience to come to awareness
and notice in the exhale that point in the exhale
where exhaling is just happening and it's on on its own
it's gonna it's gonna complete itself if we allow it
allowing ourselves to be aware of breathing in and breathing out
if your mind is thinking a lot you might very very softly in your mind
say to yourself the thought in as you breathe in
and out as you breathe out just to give the thinking mind something
to do to do that keeps you on track with the
breathing
as you breathe in receive the inhale the experience of
inhale
with an attitude of allowing it to arrive allowing it to unfold
maybe noticing that part of the inhale that's doing itself
as you exhale receive the experience of exhaling
allowing it to proceed allowing that sense
that part of the exhale that's doing itself it's going to continue
to the end of exhaling
mm-hmm so
and for a few breaths as you inhale notice
the thinking mind if there's pressure or tension or energy there
notice it on the inhale on the exhale relax soften the thinking mind
so the pressure to think is not so strong
sometimes relaxing the thinking mind letting go of thoughts
can be like making more room for the breathing
and then to allow the breathing to fill that room
feel the space of awareness
and then without thinking about it in what way might you experience the
simplicity of breathing
the simplicity of awareness of breathing
relax open up and allow yourself to experience
the fullness of breathing
the fullness of how you are experiencing breathe breathing
in the simplest way without any thoughts
thinking about the experience just experiencing it feeling it
embodying awareness of breathing
and then coming to the end of this sitting
i'd like to mention that for those of you who are new
that we end this sitting with a variation what in buddhism is called dedication of
merit it's a way of
offering up whatever benefit we receive through the meditation out into the world to benefit the world
itself and it's a little bit the principle of a
song my kids saying in kindergarten that was had the refrain
now that when something like
that if you have any love give it away give it away give it away
because you'll only have more you'll end up having more
so this idea of letting go and offering to the world whatever calm or
subtleness whatever whatever known or unknown
benefits we received from meditation is opening up and letting go
releasing that continues that letting go releasing settling of
meditation itself and doing so without having any
boundaries or barriers maybe
for our good will and so directing our attention now out
into the world opening ourselves turning ourselves inside
out and may whatever benefit goodness
merit that has come from our practice together
may we share it with others both knowingly
intentionally and unintentionally may we go through the day sharing our
goodness with others our good will
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
and may we contribute to that
possibility [Music]
no sound i turned the sound off to take my glass of water and forgot to turn it on so i wanted to
say that for those of you who joined um
at seven o'clock that for this week we're starting at 6 45 so we have 45 minutes sitting
rather than 30 minutes partly so that it feels like after
doing this early morning sitting since march many of us are ready to
um to um know sit longer
and uh and also the teachings of anapanasati that we've been
doing i think probably benefit a little bit with more sitting and but you know if seven o'clock works
best for you you're quite welcome to join then just know you're joining and you know as it's already started
so
so it's one of the i think
wonderful things that simplicity is one of the
hallmarks one of the characteristics of this meditation practice and sometimes that's not quite seen
because sometimes teachings teachers like me might give all kinds of instructions and it might seem like there's a lot of
instructions to keep in mind a teacher i i knew when i was in india
named munindra menindraji he was a student of many of the early western
practitioners of vipassana he had many wonderful sayings and one of
them was if it's not simple it's not vipassana
and and so the idea is to keep it simple so how is it that this practice is
simple it's simple by relying on
the simplicity of how we can be aware of something and to be aware maybe in the simplest
possible way and and and for each of us
and in each of us at different times what it means to be aware will be different and so that part of
the fascination of it all is to see how the uh what what we call attention
or awareness shifts and changes um depending on how subtle we are how focused we are
and and the kind of attention that's useful in any given moment but the guideline is to always keep it
simple and partly that means not to be
striving for it to be different not to be trying to engineer your
meditation to get it just right it's partly to partly means to
not be trying to avoid experience and get away from something is not trying to overthink the
experience or think our way into something and trying to figure out analytically even what's the right way
and it's also not trying to do too much at once
the idea is to kind of be content with just being
now just being is not the end game of meditation but it's kind of a reference point for
keeping it simple rather than a lot of doing there's a lot of being
and in that being in the simplicity to allow whatever the native awareness is
allows us to know that we're in the present moment to be there and surface and show itself
because the mind drifts off in thought a lot and is caught up in thought that um then to
um one of the things that many people find useful and it's not necessarily
useful for everyone and then teachers can give other instructions
but is to the simplicity of breathing and the breathing is kind of like the
the sometimes you use like the the anchor line or the tether or the support for staying in the
present moment breathing is always in the present moment it has a rhythm to it
it's not a fixed experience it's a flowing or moving or changing experience and there's
something about attention following a moving changing phenomena
that makes it easier to be relaxed in the present moment kind of like if we're watching a uh
we're sitting under under a tree relaxing in the shade of a warm day watching
maybe the river go by and we're kind of just watching the ripples and the little wavelets and
the currents just flow and flow and we're not studying it intensely we're just kind of
allowing the experience to come we see it maybe clearly and there's something about that movement where the mind doesn't fixate
on something but just allows things to flow it keeps the eyes soft and relaxed and
kind of moving along with it that part of the reason why it can be very relaxing and people can spend
long periods of time just watching a river go that by or watching the waves on the beach come and go
or watch a fire just a burn and the changing patterns of the flames as we watch the
little fire the fireplace perhaps and so it's the that movement of
breathing they're coming and going of the inhale they're coming and going in the exhale
that um that can can work for some people a very nice way
of just keeping us in the present moment and then of course for many of us especially if you're starting uh that
can be we start getting more complicated than we need to be and and part of simplicity is to relax
around making it complicated you don't have don't hold up simplicity as is
something to strive for and and to engineer into but rather kind of take yourself as
you are in a certain way meditation is a come as your party
so come as you are and sit down and allow yourself to be how you are and and that allowing
and settle into it and that and uh and the art is not to let yourself be as you are and continue
and have your thoughts galloping away but allow yourself to be as you are and
then really settle into the the direct experience the embody the living experience
of how you are so there's a turning of attention inward to the body and and what is the
embodied experience of all this what's the embodied experience of our mood our emotional state our mental
state or physical state and um and because it's the simplicity
of being has a lot to do with um what our experience
here and now in the present moment the body is always in the present moment
the breathing is always in the present moment so coming here and settling into it and
then as we settle into it at some point um to tune it
become attuned to or align ourselves with the experience of breathing
and um and to be with that simply sometimes we're controlling the breath
sometimes the breath feels tight and constricted or held in some ways not particularly comfortable and so the
experience of simplicity is just allow that to be and breathe with that breathe through it
make room for it to be uncomfortable or controlled because that making a room for giving
breathing room is part of the way of keeping things simple and allowing something inside
which is not yourself your own engineering efforts your own kind of trying mechanisms of trying to
fix and change something inside of you will begin to unfold
begin to unwind will begin to release begin to kind of find itself and
so that's one of the things uh that the the in the principle of simplicity
is uh trust the simplicity of just being with experience trust trust your experience if you're
present for it even it's even if it's not necessarily ideal or comfortable or something
and then something within begins to open unravel um relax
on its own there's a very strong momentum in our body in our in our whole being
towards the release of tension towards the release of holding and tension and pushing and pressure
and and so part of this giving breathing room to ourselves and allowing things to be
is in fact this movement towards allowing for this settling this
releasing this freeing that can happen when we just keep showing up and being present
so maybe what i've said this morning that was already too complicated so i apologize but it's all
kind of an uh effort to try to point to uh just being simple and maybe the
breathing can help you with that simplicity just be with the breathing trust the breathing i like the
expression entrust yourself with breathing and uh and and then it doesn't have to
you know it doesn't make me it doesn't look so sophisticated it doesn't look so wonderfully spiritual but to keep it
simple and in that simplicity of being with experience
being with the simplicity of it feeling the embodied experience of breathing that
something will begin to settle something will begin to open something will happen that um is the
journey of meditation practice so um
so thank you all very much for today and we'll continue these 45-minute sittings
uh this week all the way through to um through sunday so seven days not just the
weekday days and for those of you who are available to come on the weekend we'll continue and
may you have a wonderful day and may the simplicity of meditation support you
in giving the gift of simplicity to those people that you encounter today
thank you