so warm greetings from inside meditation center in redwood city
and uh welcome to this meditation and welcome into this
community of people all over the country the world the
continent coming together to meditate now and also some people do it later in the day hello to them as well
so
one of the when we do mindfulness practice
sooner or later and ideally it's sooner we would come to have a deep
appreciation of our capacity
for being aware our capacity for mindfulness for clear recognition
for observing what's happening for sensing and feeling what's happening
as it's happening there's many different angles or
perspectives to this you know these different different sides of this wonderful jewel this diamond
of awareness and different times different ones are emphasized
but this jewel appreciating this tremendously valuable thing that is so overly easily overlooked
because the mind is using awareness to focus
to be absorbed in something else to obsess or to be mindfulness is the
passive awareness is the passive vehicle pass a vehicle with which we then get involved in our
thoughts or what i call the world of aboutness we're thinking about something about the
future the past about people in our lives about
events about fantasy and we can get so involved in those thoughts
those ideas those concerns maybe because we're have strong desire or fear or
aversion to it or whatever reason there might be and um and we're not really really aware
that we're aware we might know that we're thinking about something but
we're everything is kind of keeping channeled into that world of aboutness
in mindfulness practice we're stepping away from the world of aboutness
not to reject it but to know it so clearly that oh now i'm thinking about something now
i'm feeling something now i'm sensing something so clearly that we become aware
of the fact that we are aware we become aware of the the event
of being mindful so we hear a sound and rather than immediately going off
and thinking what is that sound and what should i do and what do i have to fix here to not
have the sound the the first place we go is we simply know the sound oh it's
listening hearing sound but we do it in such a way that
the awareness of sound the knowing of it the mindfulness of it
becomes the jewel stands out becomes really the main center
of our experience and so we have this jewel this treasure it's a phenomenally
powerful effective enlightening freeing to begin to appreciate
our simple capacity to awareness when we you know really
taste it or feel or know it it's kind of like
being distracted and being given clear clean refreshing mountain water from a
spring and we don't taste it we don't feel it don't we just talk away and just drink
gulp down the water or to really take it in feel oh this is
this is pure water this is you know really feels refreshing and good and
really feel the tasting of it so the the knowing of it
so and the avenue to doing that the means to doing that important part
of it is to be relaxed not trying too hard it's almost as if
the if we can be upright and the more relaxed we can be
then awareness is the natural
center of our experience awareness just begins to stand out and highlight
this treasure of ours so taking a assuming a
meditative posture that will allow you to both maintain a
postural physical alertness of some kind
and to relax your body
and gently closing your eyes and without doing anything special
around breathing become attuned to the experience of
exhaling become aware know what it feels like for
you to just as you are to exhale
and then become aware of different places in your body where there might be tension
and as you exhale ease up soften
relax the tension
in the shoulders and the belly
maybe the muscles along the sides of the spine
maybe in your fingers and hands
and as you inhale inhale into the very place that you've relaxed
as if that place can receive the inhale
as if the inhale prepares for further relaxation on the exhale
and if you're thinking about things you're in the world of aboutness
about what you're thinking and we want to be in the world of
awareness of presence
a kind of awareness and mindfulness it's closely related to a silent way of being
that allows you to sense and feel more deeply your experience
or a way of knowing recognizing
that recognizing what's really happening here in the present moment as you
breathe
as you relax the awareness can maybe be more receptive
or maybe even receptive is saying too much too much work awareness just is
and in its very is-ness
it registers it experiences it knows
and the diamond of awareness
allow it to stand out a little bit
in mindfulness of breathing
simple awareness of breathing where breathing isn't the main point of
what you're doing breathing is the means by which
awareness mindfulness is revealed is
known is experienced mind's capacity to know to be aware
to highlight awareness you might use a very simple mental note
that recognizes whatever it is you're aware of
not that the note is that important in naming the experience
it's more that the note in the wake of the note
you're more aware of being aware
recognizing an in-breath with the word in
and then in aft in the wake of saying that being more there to recognize to
experience the end the in-breath out for the out-breath
appreciating
simple
and as we come to the end of the sitting
to take a few moments to appreciate your capacity to be aware
present moment awareness not thinking about awareness to
appreciate it but knowing it as you're aware now
not trying too hard to know awareness kind of know it from the edges or from
know it from behind or underneath
though it with the kind of peripheral awareness of the mind
appreciating its simplicity
that way in which awareness can be simple just know
and in the same way love can be simple
good will friendliness compassion
can be quite simple
also not being caught in the world of aboutness
thinking about things but allowing the world to register in
the heart in the simplicity of the heart the sinful response of
love of compassion good will
and allowing it to be simple without needing to figure out anything
or act on anything just just love
just good will
kindness and perhaps there's a way in which the
following words resonate with the heart
especially if you don't try to engage the meaning of the words
completely like how to do it but just listen as if
in some way these words express the sentiment of they are the
heart may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
may the simple capacity for love for kindness
may it shine nourish you
may the nourishment of kindness spread through your body
may the goodness of goodwill
radiate through your body
and then without getting too complicated may it may it be
that your good will can be expressed today
in ways that keep you intimate connected to a relaxed
inner place of well-being and peace
and may this good will peaceful relax goodwill may it also find an expression
in the world in what you say and what you do
in small or big ways in which you
contribute to the welfare and happiness of others may this meditation practice we did
today contribute to the happiness and well-being
of the world
so this is the second talk on mohawk
usually translated as delusion and today i'll talk a little bit more
specifically what the buddhist understanding of it is
so moha moha
is considered to be one of the three roots or three origins
for everything that human beings do that's unwholesome
unhelpful harmful and now in the tradition of
early buddhism this moha is said to be present in every
in unethical act that someone does in every unwholesome
act that someone does and what unwholesome implies here is that it's unwholesome
for the person who does it and it's unhelpful and wholesome for the person who might be the recipient of the
act so if we're doing something which is not healthy for ourselves
psychologically heartfully then there's some degree of delusion in
that action in that act of speech or in that action act of act of the body
and um this the word moha delusion is related then to a lot of other kind of cluster of
concepts or mental activities that are related
and maybe the biggest one in buddhism is ignorance but ignorance that's not i don't you
don't know something you didn't you know read enough books to learn things but rather it's more like an
ignoring uh it's a little bit more volitional it's choosing almost like almost like
choosing not to know and or allowing the conditions to be
present of delusion that interferes with knowing it's related also to bewilderment
to confusion and to living the world not quite understanding what's happening and being bewildered
and it's also related to um the idea of um
and i forgot what i was going to say um the um
of foolishness and um the kind of core or the core the kind of
one of the most common ways in which the buddha talks about someone who is
mature spiritually he talks about them as being wise and those are immature are foolish
and that's that divide is not the divided between saint and sinner but rather the divide between the
foolish and the wise and some people might feel is unfortunate to make this distinction
but the difference between is uh the difference maybe between this uh sinner and a fool is sinners in the
kind of way it's often used in the west um you know there's no redemption there's no
you know the person that's what a person is but when you're a fool it's possible to become wise foolishness
is a temporary phenomena and partly what we're doing is becoming wise it's overcoming delusion
now the word delusion uh in english and and moha in pali
implies that the mind is creating ideas that are not based on reality
so we either we we have projected some false ideas some fantasies
onto how things are or or we just live
in a world of fantasy that has no connection to the world around us and so there's a it's something the mind
is doing and in terms of thoughts ideas maybe some degree of feelings are involved and
contributing to this world of delusion and one of the very useful
reference points for understanding this is the psychological word or projection
that we have ideas we have bias we have prejudice that belong to the world of ideas
sometimes very intimately connected to feelings and motivations
and these bias and prejudice that we have preferences that we have is our
projections that we put on top of our experience and in and there's a whole slew of these
ways in which the mind is actively involved in obscuring
what's actually happening in the moment because it's created an idea of what's happening
that interferes with the direct experience and socially this is very painful when
we see people through the stereotype we see people through bias or prejudice
and and sometimes we see ourselves through bias and prejudice
these ideas and mind forms and and then they're projected on others and ourselves and the world
obscuring our ability to see clearly and this this understand why ignorance
is not just not knowing but isn't ignoring that it happens when
we have these projections when we're not allowing yourself to see deeply what's really going on
now in the in the tradition one of the there's a few things which are really central to um the projections we
have one of them is that we project the hope of happiness
onto things that don't really produce happiness like if we're trying to make ourselves
happy sometimes even safe with unwholesome activities with lying and
stealing and cheating and and or with being caught up in greed
or ill will uh then we think somehow our well-being
is there to be found in engaging in unwholesome activity and that's a kind of delusion because
unwholesome activity is always harming ourselves and um and so to end that projection
then we can that allows us to see actually this is not happiness producing i projected this
hope for happiness into that activity that it was going to do something for me
and so the same thing uh so this pr idea of projecting and if we can
part of wisdom is to see the difference between what's wholesome and unwholesome what's
harmful and what's not harmful and to become finely attuned to this so we really kind of begin living in the
world of what is beneficial both for ourselves and for others
the other uh important idea of projection is the idea of um we pre
we project uh a kind of permanence in things which are not permanent and it might be
a permanence just we have for the few minutes that it's there uh like oh we
we behave kind of on kind of unconsciously perhaps as if this is forever it's always going
to be a hot day now it's always going to be you know this way or that way and
i remember that uh there was a brief period of time when i was i think about 20
where i had a wonderful summer and in the middle this wonderful summer i said to
myself i'll never be depressed again this was a delusion of permanence that
came back and kind of bit me because that fall right after that wonderful summer i was more depressed
than it ever been and then i had the thought oh i'm gonna now i'm gonna be i'm gonna be depressed forever that was the attitude i had i
didn't say those words but the weight of it all this weight of permanence this is how it is
and and it's a it can be a projection and um and to live under the weight of
that product projection it causes a lot of suffering and and it so it obscures that projection of
permanence or constancy obscures how shifting and changing our experiences
and there's a whole different way of being in the world when we see the inconstancy of it the changing shifting nature and we find
how to let go and find our peace with it there's also the projection of
identity we all have you know some kind of identity gender or nationality or
all kinds of things but but there's something about the act of
projecting it on even though maybe nominally it's accurate but the act of projecting it and holding
on to it and seeing through the lens of it can obscure can create a sense of solid
self permanent self a constant kind of
ideation of who we are and what we're caught up in and this is a and so much of what we
think of myself my identity as a projection or we're acting through a projection in
relationship to it and so that's a kind of delusion that obscures
how in some very profound way we are always more dynamic more complicated more
fluid more um more changeable more
than any projection we have on ourselves that in fact that these projections obscure uh some deeper
capacity for awareness and aliveness and freedom which is always going to be here so
uh delusion as as being an activity of the mind
it's not a passive ignorance but it's the creation of ideas which are not accurate
and then projecting that onto the world or wearing them as filters on our on our
eyes so we see the world we see the world through those interpretations through those ideas
and and it's a wonderful thing to take those filters off it's a
wonderful thing to let go of those projections the um
the cost of having living this world of projections of delusion is a lot of stress there's a
lot of tension that comes along with it and to live without projections without these
these mind creations that we see through this assumptions beliefs prejudice bias
is allows the mind to be much more relaxed than it is and and to come to that place of ease
and peace that not only is it good just peaceful and useful for the mind itself
but it allows for uh to see with the absence of delusion
the absence of mohammed and and how to get to that and how to practice with delusion and
come to the other side is the topic for tomorrow so thank you and you might
you know these next 24 hours see if you can become a little more attuned or notice
how ideas surface in the mind and then those ideas become the means by
which or the filter through which we then look and understand what's
happening and and the key of this is to see it
arise see the beginning of something then it's easier to see it as a creation of the mind and and catch
it as a kind of delusion so
thank you very much