good morning well good evening good afternoon good day greetings sangha wherever you
are in the world it's a delight to be with you and practice with you in this moment in time
so we will continue this morning with our explorations
of calming settling collecting the mind also known as
samadhi so for the theme of today's practice
i'd like to offer a quote by arjun sachito as inspiration
he says i think of enjoyment as receiving joy and samadhi
as the art of refined enjoyment i love that the art of refined
enjoyment it is the careful collecting of oneself
to the joy of the present moment joyfulness means there is no fear
no tension no ought to there isn't anything we have to do about
it so there is stillness it's just this
so the careful collecting of oneself to the joy of the present
moment so with that let's just begin
and i will share guidance as needed to invite us
to turn towards joy so settling arriving
in our bodies
in this moment just as it is
turning our minds turning our hearts
to the stability to the quiet inside as if underneath
all the waves of thought
[Music] plans
all the preoccupations
ah there is stillness there is quiet
there is peace and ease trusting even if we can't find it in this moment
trusting and as if we were to turn to tune
to tune our radio the radio of our hearts and minds
to this channel of peace which we know exists and at first it might sound crackly
but we tune we tune to it
and for tuning to this channel
we settle with the breath with the body to tune to this channel of peace
turning our attention our awareness
our gaze inward to the body
inviting the body to soften
to relax to let go of any holding a tightness
the shoulders the neck
in our face forehead jaw
the back of the eyes
to soften
inviting our chest
oh dear chest
the home of the heart and the heart center
the proverbial housing of emotions to relax
it's okay whatever is here is okay
to invite our abdomen our lower abdomen
to drop inward ah giving
away its weight the weight it's been holding to the sit bones
and for the sit bones to relax
and let go of their tightness and tension to the earth
inviting the feet to rest on the earth
feeling the contact points of the feet or the lower legs if you're
sitting on the cushion entire lower legs ah
upper legs said bones
offering their weight to gravity to the earth
receiving the breath receiving the breath however it is
whether the breath is short or long receiving the breath just as it is
allowing the breath
to fill the body
the entire body
with its life-giving nourishing
purity
allowing allowing the mind the mind heart
to tune to the breath the rhythm the flow of the breath
as if the breath is the dial
that helps us tune
the peace to the joy
underneath the waves the waves of thought preoccupation
noticing
that they're actually
is joy in the contentment
of the present moment
can we contentedly wrap ourselves
as if in a blanket comfortably
wrapped
with the breath the soothing contentment of the breath
in this moment
no matter what cacophony occurs outside
right here the contentment of just sitting and
being briefed in this moment
is enough this is enough
it is bountiful
tuning into the delight of simply sitting
and breathing
turning away from entanglements and thoughts
towards the simple joy
this is enough it is plenty
even if we're just a moment
tuning into the delicious simplicity of this moment
the mind doesn't want to go anywhere else
this simply this is enough
and as we bring this period of sitting
to a close together
your last moment tuning in to whatever level of peace
delight in the simplicity of this moment
just sitting and breathing
appreciating the goodness of even the moment of delighting in this
peace the peace and this delight
and trusting trusting there has been goodness
generated from our effort of showing up
and practicing without attachment to outcomes
we showed up we did our best
letting go of the outcome that's not entirely under
this being's control and appreciating appreciating the
goodness generated and generously sharing sharing this goodness this merit
all around
as if giving a gift to those we care about here i'm working on cultivating my heart
my mind and goodness
sharing the goodness further those we don't know
and all beings everywhere
may the goodness of our cultivation be a cause and
condition for the waking up for their freedom
of ourselves and all beings everywhere
thank you for your practice
so greetings once again
to friends all around the world
so as we continue to explore
this week different supportive aspect to establish samadhi
settling calming the mind
yesterday the invitation was to put down what's not needed to put
down windrack to put down to put down now today this is the other side of the
coin the other side of the coin one side is to put down and the other
side is to notice that actually it's lovely it's wonderful it's delightful it's
delicious the simplicity of this moment and wrapping ourselves in the simplicity of
this moment so
we often only do the putting down the thoughts arise we put them down
we put them down distractions arise we put them down and actually sometimes we
throw them down it's not so it's like the stick method stop stop being
distracted stop bad meditator bad meditator and instead so putting them
putting things down is is wise but with gentleness bowing to them thank you not now not
needed not wholesome not for my benefit and now the other side which is
the the carrot method oh wow it's actually lovely the
simplicity of this moment is delicious is
is yummy then the mind doesn't want to go away doesn't want to wander off
in fact that the putting down or this the seclusion the
relinquishment becomes not so much needed because the mind is so still
is so in love is enjoying is delighting in what is here
have you noticed when you do something that you love um a hobby whatever it might be
you don't want to stop come have a meal no let me finish this i want to finish this
puzzle gardening knitting whatever it might be this game um because there's so much joy
so much delight so tuning into that delight into that joy into that simplicity and
we often don't see it because we're so focused on okay put it down put it down come back put it down and it
becomes so much it conflictual relationship somewhat
with practice whereas if we tune into oh this is actually quite lovely and it might be subtle
[Music] and also to say a lot of times we wait we wait for that
delight that deliciousness that stillness to arise and then we tune into it after
we've done this pudding down a lot and then we realized oh wow yeah it's
pretty calm it's delicious it's lovely so the invitation is to try to tune into it
earlier to tune into it with the breath with the body
trusting that underneath the waves there is this deliciousness this
safety this calm this this piece and trusting as if you're
tuning a radio yes it's it's crackly but something is coming through there's a memory of
you know it's there it's been there you trust it's there even if you haven't experienced it yet
you've heard you've read that it's there so trusting that you're not different from
the other seven billion people it's it's there for you also trusting trusting
and coming back to to this joy i shared a
a quote at the beginning by arjun tsuchita i like to read it
again in case you some of you might have missed it earlier
and he says arjun suchito is is a a senior monk in the
arjun cha's forest tradition and he says i think of enjoyment as
receiving joy and samadhi as the art of refined
enjoyment it is the careful collecting of oneself to the joy of the
present moment i love this
samadhi as the art of refined enjoyment it doesn't say the art of okay
concentrate bring your mind to it hard work oh it's the
art of refined enjoyment it's the careful collecting of oneself
to the joy of the present moment and there is a lot of joy in the present
moment it's just that our minds are so used
to the cacophony the the busyness the the the diet of
constant stimulation constant uh sound noise
news facebook conversation this that so so if the mind
becomes tuned only sees that delight the enjoyment in thinking
or in reading or in interacting and doing and the same way that um
say a subtle subtle flavor could be lost on someone who's
tuned to just uh really complex with i'll share this with you when i was
when i was very young i only liked say rocky road
and chocolate flavored ice cream things that had a lot of flavor in them
i couldn't understand why would people ever eat or enjoy vanilla
my taste buds couldn't quite tune into the subtleness and only when i became older i realized
ah vanilla there is so much complexity in this simplicity so so
tuning our our palate tuning our mind to appreciate the delight the simplicity
the loveliness the joy in the present moment and for that
it may not only just happen if we on on the cushion so if we've been busy
busy busy doing doing doing and now we come to the question we sit it's it's as if it's we've been a
car driving at 200 miles an hour and then that's really fast okay maybe
100 miles an hour and then we come to a stop
the car would still be shaking it's it's still reverberating we need to slow
down slow down slow down so in order to when we arrive to
actually for the mind to be able to catch up with itself
to delight to to notice the the joy the delight
in the simplicity of the present moment
and to say that the path to the mind settling is through joy
is through delight is through this nourishment of ease
not through beating ourselves up okay concentrate drop it drop it drop it
in many sutas um including
in the sutta teaching on transcendent dependent origination
the path towards freedom
is through joy rapture tranquility happiness concentration
so so in this utah the it starts
with faith leading to joy joy leading to so faith sada
trust that i was talking about so trust trust trust so trust
leading to joy or actually um maybe palm or ja palmoja i'd like to
translate it not as joy but as gladness faith leading to gladness
gladness palmidja leading to pity pity is the word also translated as
rapture or also translated as joy sometimes so rapturous joy the sense of delight
really this wow yum that can come up in in meditation
and pity rapture joy leading to pasadena prasada tranquility
calm tranquility tranquility leads to sukkah
sukha's happiness is sweetness the sense of sweetness in the mind
sukkah happiness leads to samadhi concentration so so you see all
the steps before somebody before concentration are this
delight rapture joy tranquility happiness and from there leads to knowledge and
vision of things as they are to disenchantment dispassion emancipation
and knowledge of destruction of the us of us so which is awakening nibana so
from concentration then we lead then the next steps are are the
states of awakening so delight the joy of the present moment
so i'd like to invite you invite all of us throughout the day can we tune can we
tune the radio of our minds to the simplicity of the delight
in this moment the simplicity of the joy in this moment that's not
born from outside but it's born from within the simplicity of this joy
born from within oh it's actually quite lovely i don't need all these extra things can i
tune inside and notice this joy trust trust the the delight the joy
within bedley then leads to the mind calm being calmed and settled and not being agitated and
needing [Music] so much entertainment from the outside
so just an invitation to explore for yourself to be a scientist of your own mind
so thank you all thank you for your practice thank you for cultivating your hearts in goodness and
kindness in generosity to yourself
and to all beings everywhere may all beings be well may all beings be happy thank you
be well