so good morning good day
and here we are here you are in your place
and the idea is to kind of be definitively clearly
in the here that you are meditation is to rest here
established here now
and in that this week has been the week of touching into the role of imagination
and meditation one of the similes the buddha uses for
the state of clarity that
gives rise to awakening or that it kind of represents maybe
awakening is that of a clear
very clear lake here in the mountains in california there are some very clear alpine lakes
where you can look down into the water quite far and see clearly what's on the bottom
and uh so a very clear lake and a person who stands on the edge of
that lake the buddha says can look into that lake and see the fish swimming around can see
the pebbles the little shellfish that might be there and
each thing stands out distinctly but these things each thing is kind of swimming or
existing in this a context of domain
this space of clear water
and the water is often a symbol for awakening or the awakening but the mind for awareness
and and so the awareness that becomes clear
and so clear like this clear mountain lake in which all things can be seen but the
idea of standing on the the edge of the lake looking in the fish and the little rocks
the person who's looking is not interfering with anything it's not being foreign against anything
particularly just kind of just letting each thing be independent and free
and i love this idea because there's such a strong emphasis or strong tendency for people to look at
buddhist practice their own experience in meditation through the lens of me myself and mine
in my experience what i have to do and all this and and uh and so then you know the
ideas and the liberation means i will become liberated uh
look at me i'm liberated i'm free another way of understanding it which is just as valid
is that as we become free we are liberating everything else
from us and that way liberation awakening is a gift we give to
everything where everything has become free of our attachment our clinging our expectations our
judgments all the stuff that we put on top of it and uh and so they're standing on the
lake edge of the lake and looking in the clear water the fish the rocks the shell shellfish
whatever's there is allowed to be theirs free of our entanglement or trying to grab it or
do something with it so that kind of clarity of mind that allows
each thing gives each thing its freedom its independence every experience in meditation
has this permission to be there provided it's seen in clarity
and so that's the kind of the key thing
recognized clearly so it's possible to be very foggy in one's mind
confused but that can be known clearly i'm foggy this is fogginess fogginess is
known this is chaos confusion chaos is known
confusion is recognized oh so um
so the um and so that's kind of the vision the
imaginational vision that the buddha is giving of where we're going with mindfulness practice
and it's not so much an experience of bliss and joy and happiness which is the subject right now in the
series of anapanasati but rather it's clarity
so with that as a background image for this meditation
to assume a meditation posture and to
gently close your eyes
and taking a deep breath in in a long exhale
and exhale that you relax your body
as if relax as if
you're draining out all the mud in the lake
as if there's a little outlet to the edge of the lake where the
mud can just drain away so as you relax your shoulders
let the tension drain away
as you soften your belly on the exhale the tensions of your belly
drain away
whatever attention you can easily let go of or relax let it drain away so you have
room within for clarity for seeing
as if you're making your body a receptacle
for clear kind of an empty receptacle empty of tension
so it can be the
the abode of clarity
letting your breathing return to normal
and taking a few moments as you exhale
to drain away the tensions or pressures in your mind the area of your brain
any tension in the forehead or in the temples
even any any little bit of contraction
that has a location for awareness
it's okay to have a location but the contraction associated with is not necessary
as you exhale let it drain away
and then to settle in here more fully in the body
entering into your body
regardless of how much comfort or discomfort you have in
your body from the inside out
that you your body is the buddha's body
certainly you're having a lot of experiences that he had when he meditated
certainly not all of them but the basic physical experience of the body
from the inside out your buddha body
to settle in be present here
and within this body to become aware of your breathing
regardless how you're breathing the buddha certainly breathed like you
at some point or other some of the same sensations you're experiencing
the buddha felt from within
here you are your buddha body breathing in and breathing out
and then
searching around in your mind or in your awareness
to find where and how can your awareness your mindfulness of
breathing have some degree of clarity
the clarity of standing on the edge of a lake looking in
without interfering with anything allowing things to be as they are
each things in its simplicity
nothing to do nothing to change
except have clear seeing
of the body breathing
and whatever else arises that's compelling
clear seeing clear knowing this is happening
this is what is recognized
reach it with each in-breath and each out-breath
the mud and the lake settle and gradually
there's more clarity
about what's happening in the moment here and now breathing
breathing in a vast expanse of awareness
so
[Music]
when we can let go of our preoccupations
it's kind of like emptying the lake of
debris and bud
and it makes us a vesicle for clarity kind of like it helps us become
gloriously empty spacious open
and then where there's space and openness for there to be well-being
is in room for gladness joy delight happiness
when the mind is crowded and claustrophobic with anxiety and thoughts and concerns
there's no room for well-being and joy
letting your tensions and preoccupations drain away
and give room for whatever well-being is here for you now
and with whatever embodiment that's available for you
feel the embodiment of well-being in whatever way it is for you however
small the embodiment of contentment
stillness calm
and breathe with the well-being
as if the well-being
shows the mind that it's okay to relax and dwell in clarity
clearly recognizing here
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to open and extend your well-being
in your consideration contemplation of the world around you
the people you know people you know about and the many
people you don't
and to sit here for a little few seconds as if you can share your well-being
with them whatever however small it might be
as if you're a little bit like a heater that's spreading its heat outwards to
the world around it so if you can sit content in your well-being
and open it to the world imagine that you're warming up the world
with well-being
and consider how wonderful it would be if in fact your well-being one way or
other known or unknown could reach and touch all the beings of
this world
may it be that the practice of meditation this this day
is a condition for bringing welfare and happiness
to beings everywhere may the goodness and merit of this
practice be dedicated to the happiness well-being
joy peace and freedom of all beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings
be peaceful
may all beings be free
so this has been a week of emphasizing the role of imagination
in buddhist practice and it's not something that i'm making up by my own
that the buddha himself in one way or the other in a variety of ways
used imagination and evoked the imaginary powers of people
when they engaged in this practice and as the practice deepens there
is born a capacity for a particular capacity for
imagination which in english we could call maybe vision
and and to have a vision of a possibility
and it's a vision that can seem very clear and tangible and immediate and maybe it even is
in a certain kind of way it's not something which is it physically tangible or physically
seen but with the mind's eye and buddhism awakening is opening the
eye of the dharma the eye that can see and have a vision
of the potential for freedom or can see freedom
can see if the peace and the freedom of the mind that's there to some degree and then has
a vision for it becoming complete a vision of it expanding
a vision of it touching the places where we're not yet free and this idea of becoming a visionary
using the imagination to to know a possibility that um
it's nothing it's not a fantasy it's based on something real
but it's imagining the fulfillment of that so for example if i hold my hand in a
tight fist i could release one finger and hold down the other fingers tight
and then but then oh i think you know it's possible now i have a vision i see the potential
of opening the whole hand up and relaxing it and so it's a kind of a kind of an
imagination a vision of a potential and it's said sometimes in
buddhism that with the that uh awakening is an act of vision a seeing
or it awakens vision it awakens the imagination of something that's possible that then
becomes um uh the direction we go or the or what we kind of wholeheartedly
put our life energy into like this is important this is valuable to live this way
and it doesn't mean we have to leave the our world behind the regular world behind
but rather when the clear enough vision of the potential or what awakening is as freedom of clinging is
we realize that it can be the foundation for how we live our life
or the all incumbent all-encompassing container or or approach
for everything we do so it isn't so much that we have to leave our life and it's
but it's rather it's to vision that it's possible to live our life freely and to wholeheartedly
enter our life with that as a guiding principle and this is a radical thing
and so so it's not a compromising our life necessarily but it's
bringing what's best in life freedom and peace and compassion uh as the container as the context as a
foundation so a vision that's possible and then a decision
even a commitment a vow this is how i want to live my life
so uh so all these things i've been talking about this week have to do with imagination and
imagination can be both harmful can be debilitating and it could be
forward leading opening it can help us grow and develop and to be able to see those two apart is
very important a few things about the word that the buddha used words he used that i'm
translating his imagination one of them is manyati and
the uh and that uh is usually uh used
for acts of imagination which are not helpful in fact b coboti the great
translator sometimes translates this word as misconceived there's no
negative prefix in the word but it's used in such a kind of negative way in the suttas that it's
often you know can be to misimagine or badam poor imagination
and so at jackal the buddha used the word for a jackal that imagines
itself to be a lion and uh and so you know
it's a misconceived oneself as a lion the um um
so one of the very interesting places where this word um one imagines where it has negative
connotations as manyati it has to do with identification and
there's a plenty of places in the sutras where buddha emphatically talks about um
the pro the problems people have when they imagine and they imagine an identity for
themselves that they are something in relationship to other things so imagining
that they are the same as the universe so the same as the world imagining that they are in the world
imagine the world is in them imagining that they are distinct from the world
and he uses this word manyati imagine and if you really understand that and it
is often translated as conceive which has some idea doesn't quite capture the idea of imagination
and so rather than talking about the self and identity that who i am i'm this i'm that as a belief
which gets into philosophy and all that the buddha is using the word imagine
and so it's not a philosophical issue but it's an issue of what we're doing with our imagination
what are we constructing what are we fantasizing about and many of the problems around self are
not about truly exactly what we are as a self whatever that is
but rather how we imagine ourselves to be and and then we have a whole different
understanding of this kind of not self teaching there's a deci for example there's a very common
phrase important to me myself and mine that's
used in the sutures it's a little bit of mistranslation the order of it but but basically the same
and and uh imagining that um
something is mine imagining that i i have an identity imagining there is a
essential self the buddha uses the word imagine it doesn't say one believes in me myself
and mine but one is something that we're construing we're constructing we're
imagining happening and so a part of meditation practice then is to
quiet and calm this excessive over-imagination false imagination misconstruing we do
and it's not questioning or or or challenging any kind of philosophical
view of self me myself and mine in these particular teachings
and so we don't have to get involved philosophically is there is there not a self where we get involved in meditation
practice is to clarify um
let go of quiet the imaginings that are occurring
and and so so that's kind of manyati this imagining
is usually negative the word that's more positive for imagination is has the word anupasati in it
and that's one of the central words for mindfulness practice it means in mindfulness practice to
observe to see but it has the the prefix sum in front of it so some anupasati um
and the context in which it's used in the buddhas is to we can understand it to be
imagination of maybe of the form of visualization
so uh so the the similes of the hindrances i talk free of the hindrances
i talked about a few days ago to the buddha says visualizing oneself
as no longer sick visualizing oneself is no longer in debt
visualizing himself were no longer enslaved and so that visualizing has a
kind of richer feeling sometimes in imagination and and it touches into something deeper it
touches into something more emotional more embodied more tangible maybe in the mind's eye
it kind of helps us to fill out something and and that is i think one of the
functions of two functions of this imagination or visualization that buddha talks about
uses in practice uh one is to give us a visceral
kind of embodied maybe uh feeling or sense sense of what he's talking about that's
not just uh explanations it's you know more like poetry or
something that's evocative and something that opens up and it touches into
more dimensions of our life than just words it touches touches into our emotional
being our kinesthetic being some of the imagery imagery are in action and movement flowing water
and the the person working the lathe or kneading the the water into the into the
powder and also it's touches into memory
and associations we have with these things and um and our capacity for imagination our
capacity for thought and thinking and so we have here this movement support
in imagination this movement of becoming unified which means gathering together all our
different functions as human being so that we're focused and present here
for the practice of meditation we're not fragmented we're not divided and we're not leaving any part of
ourselves out rather gathering together all of ourselves to center and be here
and that we'll see we'll continue now with the steps of anapanasati on monday going on with um
steps seven and eight and this continues this process of gathering
together and settling and unifying and with supporting also the process of
also once the imagination has functioned in useful way to help that to settle as well not to
hold on to that but to go to deeper states of unification and calm that at some point imagination uh
you know is no longer supportive for so we'll start going into more deeply
into the mind next week and and then we will um
go on from there and um so thank you very very much and um
someone asked yesterday i saw on the chat at the end that they wanted to see the the you know the
written form of the similes for the for jhanas and um and i said i would do
it and i i still will do at some point and also i can also maybe uh post
my translation of this 16 steps that we're going through and once i posted it i'll let you know
where it is and hopefully i'll have time to do it over the weekend so thank you all very much and look
forward to our next time together