good day everyone and
welcome and welcome to here
wherever here is for you
so
so the theme this week for meditation especially has been their
their capacity for recognizing what's happening in the moment in the present moment
and recognizing it clearly clear recognition
and clear recognition is this uh capacity to know what's happening
in the most obvious way perhaps that's clear to us it doesn't have to be some deep
analytical way but as things are observed those things they're experienced in the simplest way
that we can know them but that knowing is clear enough
strong enough emphatic enough that the knowing the recognition itself
is its own um event it isn't that the recognition is
just casual thing on the side bystander of our life we kind of know what's going on and we recognize what's
going on but we're barreling ahead and involved in what's going on the the knowing is its own event if
anything we are resting in the knowing or where we are emphasizing knowing as
over time in meditation sometimes it's the most important thing that's happening uh rather than the usual idea of of
looking at pleasure or success or attainments or or avoiding
something or figuring something out this the activity is being important whatever where it's happening
it's the knowing which is important the activity can continue but it's like
changing the paradigm or changing the the center for uh where our life is
based at least for meditation it begins being more and more centered in the recognition
more than the experience that we're having they're recognizing the experience and this becomes particularly
significant in relationship to thinking and
to clearly clearly clearly recognize thinking is happening this is thinking
so we're not kind of writing the thoughts we're not in the thoughts we're not being swept away in the river
of thoughts we're not going to kind of know we're thinking but really what we're doing is we're centered in
our thoughts and moving along it's almost as if like we we're not like
we're stopping our thinking but it's like we're stepping on the dry riverbank and the side of the river and
seeing oh that's a river that's thinking going on with such clarity with such
you know strength in a sense calm strength relaxed a peaceful place
well that is a thought so in this meditation what i would like
to suggest you do is you give a little bit more emphasis on mindfulness of thinking
and and not just to be aware that you're thinking but see if you can um increase the
volume or the the volume or the clarity of recognizing or that is a
thought and you might even use that expression that's a thought
or just a thought and it doesn't matter if it's a true thought or a false thought or if it's a thought
about the past the future even the present doesn't matter the nature of the thought
the idea is to keep stepping away upon the dry riverbank of
peace and recognizing oh that's thinking thinking has a tremendous influence on
our attitudes our moods our uh our uh the image in which we live
our life within the projections the assumptions we have it's like very insidious how they kind
of are involved in our perceptions and to start kind of stepping back so
that's a thought that's a thought that's a thought
i clearly recognizing at that so as we do this meditation the way you might do it if it's helpful
for you you might just do it just kind of in a relaxed way and and maybe that's the primary
thing that you recognize just like instead of breathing but or
you might stay with your breathing and on every exhale recognize whatever
thought has arisen and no judgments about the nature of
thoughts no animosity criticism for them it's simply the
the clarity of oh that's a thought and maybe as i talked about yesterday
it's possible to discover a kind of freedom and peace in stepping back on the bank of the
river and watching the river go by step back away from our thinking
and recognizing it's a thought just a thought no more no less than just a thought it's
an idea it's a concept it's an image i just recognize it as such
so sitting in a posture that's supportive for you
and perhaps closing your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
a long leisurely inhale and a long leisurely exhales
long as it's comfortable
and then letting your breathing return to normal and relaxing in your body
especially as you exhale
and then set centering yourself more on the body breathing the simplicity of
breathing and as you exhale
recognize thinking if there's thinking
a kind of clear recognition that's not the same thing as letting go
of your thoughts but it's similar
in not being engaged or involved in the thinking
but rather being engaged involved in the simple recognition recognition
this is a thought and to do that over and over again
perhaps to discover a peaceful place
that is not entangled in thinking
recognize yourself thinking including how subtly thoughts will creep
in on the side or
be like in the background slipping in
recognizing one thought another has
begun some are so much part of the background
that it doesn't occur to us to recognize it
and as we come to the end of this
sitting
the ability to see clearly is the goal of vipassana practice
oftentimes it's thoughts and ideas and judgments and agendas
that get in the way of our ability to see clearly
so to see and recognize clearly your thinking
is a step towards not having those thoughts interfere
with seeing the world clearly
and to see other people with some clarity
in our ability to see others hear others
perceive others in a direct way without
a thick layers of
ideas and thoughts and judgments and fears and desires bias
memories hopes
is a gift that we give to others to simply see them as they are to be open and present
in fact to see someone clearly to listen carefully
these are forms of love when people really feel seen
there's there can be love it's difficult to have real love
if people don't see each other
and may it be that our meditation
practice prepares us for the world
prepares us so that we're more inclined or more able
to see others clearly to pause to be open to take the time
to really see and listen and may that be the vehicle a channel
for our care and our love
may the benefits of our practice together today travel from us our community out into
the world
through our ability to really be present for others
may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
and maybe we recognize that as a possibility for all of us
[Music]
so we come to the last uh talk in this five part series on clear
comprehension or clear recognition some pajama
and the um
so there are a variety of ways that we can
become or things we can become clearly clearly recognize and
clearly kind of know and see and the fourth one of the four is a
clear comprehension of non-delusion and it's kind of a mouthful and what is
what is this how do we clearly comprehend non-delusion
and i think one of the ways of understanding this that i really
appreciate and delighted and sometimes i'm amused by
is to is to have a clear comprehension of
thinking to really recognize when a thought arises as a thought
i find it interpersonally very helpful because i might have a thought about someone i'm with
and um the other day i i met someone for the first time in an unusual situation and and
given the context of situation given the something about how that person
appeared to me um i had a a predisposition or a bias
to a certain kind of stereotype oh this is that kind of person and but because i have this practice of
watching my thoughts arise i could see that thought arise
and immediately i knew oh gil this is just your thought this is
your interpretation of the situation you better kind of stay open here to find out what's really going on here
what this person is who this person is and in fact very quickly i came to see this person was
not my stereotype not what i thought the fact that i have you know this bias
or stereotype these thought these thoughts came up and assumptions that came up in person that you know i think all of us have
that that's a normal part of a mind that that is operating in the world in a way
that um uh needs to have kind of simplistic sometimes understanding of complex world
to find our way uh so it's just kind of a thing that mine
does and that thought that arose about this person i it wasn't like my thought it wasn't like i was behind
the thought or or i was attached to the thought and i didn't criticize myself for having
it i just saw immediately oh this is a stereotype this is an idea and then
could adjust accordingly and and if i'd stayed in the stereotype and
got caught in it and involved in it then i have some responsibility then it's in my court to really
you know that could cause harm that way
so in seeing the stereotype come up this idea come up and to see it as oh this is just a
thought let's be careful here let's find out let's investigate more
that was clear comprehension of non-delusion the non-delusion of questioning my
thought then stepping back and saying wait what's going on here
it was also some non-delusion and not taking it too personally oh this is just a rising of a phenomena
and just phenomenal arising and and i see it just as phenomena and
because of that clarity of seeing there's a kind of freedom from it and i
don't have to interpret it or berate myself or identify myself with having that thought
it's just a thought and so there also i can be aware this is non-delusion
to to just leave it very simple and kind of belongs to kind of an impersonal not-self world
to see it it's just a thought coming up i recognize it it's not fixed it just arose and it's just here
for a moment i don't have to get involved and pick it up it's in and of itself is a
impermanent a changing temporary phenomena to see that thought as a temporary
phenomena also is clear comprehension of non-delusion i'm not deluded by it
i see it as a certain kind of way not self i see a certain kind of way as as as temporary
if i took it as being permanent this is it this is the truth that i'm going to hang on to it and stay with it
that is delusion and so this uh ability to clearly
recognize uh our thoughts that arise uh can be quite i find it kind of
delightful and sometimes amusing more than distressing
when there's such clarity of recognition that i know i'm safe i'm safe from getting pulled into it be
involved in it or act act from these thoughts that come up
and that the light can be there even when the thoughts are true then i might with my wisdom decide
whether to act on them or not or speak them or something but even is kind of stepping back and
just oh look at that it's just there's a thought and there's a perception an assumption an idea
and that kind of distance and like wow it's kind of like uh amazing phenomena of nature looking at a
tree in a park or lately we had sunflowers growing in our
garden and these are beautiful sunflowers it's bright yellow and i just lightened them and um and so to
have that kind of delight with what gets a rise in one's own mind
um and even when things are uh there's uncomfortable to have certain thoughts there's kind of stepping back and
clearly seeing and so this clear recognition also
that the knowing the awareness is not caught is not entangled it's not
reactive to it's set to uh the thinking i'm
having to the situation i having oh this is really good to have this freedom this space
this uh interval where there's some clarity can arise and wisdom can arise
this is also a clear comprehension of non-delusion
and i love this expression non-delusion because it's the absence of delusion to say
a clear comprehension of wisdom means i have supposed to be wise i'm supposed to have good thoughts or
wise thoughts or something like that and but rather to see oh here there's no
delusion there's no clinging or aversion there's no i'm not living in the judgments i'm not living
in the thoughts and seeing the world through the thoughts there's a place of non-delusion which is
not exactly a thing or a form of wisdom or that i can propositional say this is
true exactly the non-delusion is kind of the in the nature of the stepping back and being
clear and this clear recognition this clear freedom this clear spaciousness
that allows thoughts and feelings and emotions and impulses and desires and aversions they
can all arise but there's non-delusion about them it's just a thought it's just an
aversive thought or feeling it's just a desire that arises and whether or not i act on
any of this there's space to make that choice there's an interval a time
there's ability to do that but the non-delusion sets the foundations as the context for
living a life of greater clarity greater generosity greater freedom
to come from a place of non-delusion allows us to see others better to be
better friends or better listen better to other people to be attuned to other people because
we're not seeing them through the filter of our delusion or our projections or our
assumptions our bias our stereotypes it's so useful and
and then as we meditate and we become more still and quiet
it's useful to become attuned or to recognize how subtle these thoughts creep in
even the thought you know you're sitting quietly peacefully mine is silent and you have the thought i'm not
thinking anything and then you believe that's true even though you just had that thought
and um and don't see the thought itself is kind of contradicting itself
the but all these little thoughts come in and some of them are evaluations judgments commentary but what's
happening in the present some of them are just kind of like in the background far away
quiet we're thinking about you know things in the future or fantasies or
whatever but to really kind of get quiet really get it start getting more and more sensitive
to how these thoughts arise beginning when they're there this is not meant to be a lot of work
but as we train ourselves and mindful to keep showing up and being mindful and being present for what's here and recognizing what's here
one of those things is without recognizing thoughts and if you can see a thought when it
first arises there's tremendous potential there to discover
non-delusion as well the non-delusion that the thought is temporary the non-delusion that the thought is
that of not identifying with thought and making it me myself and mine the non-delusion that is not entangled
or caught in the thought or reactive to the thought or swept away by the thought the
non-delusion that's kind of akin to space to peace to openness to uh
to non certain kind of non-involvement
but a non-involvement that's automatic and habitual and maybe even neurotic at times but rather
a non-involvement that is a whole different paradigm a whole radical different way of living
our life that's not centered in our thoughts our beliefs our assumptions our ideas
but it's centered in clarity and peace in non-delusion
so um
i hope that uh maybe you'll experiment maybe you'll try over this weekend to um
see if you can notice or for those thoughts that you notice when they first
arise the first appear see if in that in that opportunity when they first
arise whether you can find non-delusion there a non-entanglement and have certain kind
of clarity and wisdom and freedom because you see it when it arises as just a thought
so thank you and i look forward to continuing on monday on probably a different topic