that topic for this talk is
grief and maybe the talk can be titled liberating grief
and what motivates this talk is in big part is that the one-year anniversary
of many of us going into sheltering in place
and the dramatic way in which our whole world has much of the world as 99 of it has been
turned upside down or inside out or radically changed by the pandemic
and in marking this one-year anniversary it feels important to acknowledge and
make room for and bring forth the grief that has been part of this year
and that grief is not something that should be shied away from
or be embarrassed about but it's actually a very important part of human beings and our
human life and and it should be acknowledged it should be under understood and seen and
and what's uh significant i think for many of us recognize is that the griefs of the last year have been
wide-ranging certainly there are some of them are huge i mean
many around the world millions of people have died in the united states well over 500 000 people have died
directly from the disease and the illness and then there's been many who have been seriously sick
and some with with the long-termers like long-haul people people who their symptoms that continue
for months and months and maybe it'll be for years and so there's a grief of the loss of so
many things loss of people loss also family members friends
from death then sickness and then there's the grief of just loss of connections of people we've been
regularly connected to are sheltering in place themselves and there's not much communication
and the grief of not being social in the same way we were
before there's all these small griefs that goes along
that we experience of all the things we can't do or that we're used to doing and
that we value doing and all the small ways in which we've gotten energized and inspired about life and
ready to go out and do it are not available and some people find there's a slow slow steady
attrition of energy of inspiration of motivation partly from the slow kind of drip by
dripping of little griefs and sorrows and sadness as that go on
and then there's uh the things that happen in our society the challenges the griefs the sorrow the
sadness about politics and about racial injustice and economic injustice and
nowadays you know we were aware of medical injustice and environmental injustice
and um and you know and violence and hatred
the violence against asian americans is you know is heartbreaking the violence
against black americans is heartbreaking and and the hatred that exists in our
society that people go around shooting each other so all these things together
you know are forms of sadness and grief and and that kind of accumulate can
accumulate if they're not acknowledged and not known and not liberated
so there's three ways of being with grief there's accompanying grief
there is no in grief and there's liberating grief
and what i like about these words accompanying knowing and liberating that
grammatically they can both be a verb and an adjective
so knowing accompanying grief means we are the companions of it we bring
ourselves and be present for it and ex be with it but it also
it's the grief that does the accompanying it's a grief accompanying grief can also
be the grief that accompanies us and it's a mutual relationship
you and your grief and to feel and experience that mutuality is really
really to allow the accompanying to be full there is a knowing grief where we can
know it but there's also the grief that knows something
grief is not just ignorant or dumb or you know uninformed
grief is something that's really well informed about something very important and what is it that grief knows and
so when we know grief we're also learning what does grief know and then uh
liberating grief is both you know we can liberate the grief perhaps but also there's the idea that there's a
grief that is liberating and and how can you know something as
painful and difficult as grief can be at times how can that be liberating as well and
and to even to say those words or suggest that idea can feel like a
betrayal or to the grief we have or could feel like a insult to the
degree of pain we can experience the grief so grief uh such an important topic
for us and i had this in my in mind that we could uh somehow
do this talk together that not just me talking but maybe those
of you have access to the chat we can have a little bit to do this as in teamwork
they um so accompanying grief
grief is an ordinary part of human beings lives there's it's to be expected it will have
grief it's not a mistake to have grief if we're living and paying attention and
caring about life and caring about things there'll be grief there'll be sorrow there'll be sadness
and and so to spend time with that and allow ourselves to feel it to trust it
to be with it and people who do mindfulness practices can
really maybe appreciate this how valuable it is to be with something be all this partly because we start feeling
that um to not be with it is to not be with ourselves that as we
learn to be really present for our experience present in ourselves and being opening up to all of who we
are there's a feeling of coming home to ourselves or feeling whole in ourselves
uh complete in ourselves or no part left out and it's uh in doing so we become a
refuge to ourselves we become a refuge a place of um
of support a place of freedom a place of being we're allowed to be full and complete
and as soon as we have something like grief that's too painful for us or too embarrassing for us or to
something we want to push away or ignore or repress then
we are dividing ourselves we're no longer whole we're no longer able to come back into our hearts and
feel at home there and so to and to accompany ourselves
accompany the grief is a means to kind of learn to stay whole learn to stay
complete or learn to be a refuge to ourselves no matter how big and strong the pain is
there's good reason why people want to avoid grief and that is because it can be painful
acute grief you know is searing is you know it's just like everything is torn apart
and and um you know the kind of the world the fabric of the world is torn apart
and it can be excruciating to feel some griefs so it's very painful and so the idea of
accompanying grief is to accompany our pain and if we don't do that then
the grief and the pain remains but maybe it goes underground it gets repressed or gets kind of
ignored and but it still operates it's still there
festering and uh and it's there if it hasn't really been dealt with
fully or with dignity or nobility then
it can come back and come back in unexpected and maybe un healthy ways in terms of anger or
excessive fear or or being too closed and numb from what's
going on so to accompany all this is to accompany
the ways we go numb to company also the ways we get angry the ways we get feel helpless and hopeless to just
accompany ourselves in the pain so i did that this last week to some
degree for me personally it was a very touching experience
time for me where i moved my mother into a memory care home
and and i think the most poignant part of it was
walking across the parking lot of um of the you know the memory care
place to bring her to the door and because of covid like can't come in someone comes out
and receives her and any companies are in where i stay behind so here i was
walking across the parking lot very acutely aware of
what was painful for me over 60 years ago and that was one of the earliest memories i have of
my mother was her accompanying me when i was about four years old
across a school playground i was holding her hand and i was crying
because i was going to the first day of school in a foreign country in a language i didn't speak in geneva where they spoke
french and i didn't speak french and then going to a catholic
best my memory kindergarten maybe something like that that
was run by nuns and i was uh so i was just she was walking me across i was holding my hand i was crying
and now over 60 years later you know the roles were reversed and
and her memory was not such that she quite understood what was going on but i did and so that came back
and i'm a comp i made space for it and then after i took her there i went for a long walk in the hills
around here just to accompany my grief accompany my sadness of what was going on
and it was kind of kind of the richness of it partly was the leftover of a certain pain it's the
memory of the pain from over 60 years ago that speaks to a principle that
that uh sometimes our griefs are previous griefs
and even more so if the griefs are unresolved or un somehow have been pushed down or ignored um
they get reawakened with new griefs and so the new griefs can be much more
acute because of the how it can be with um with um
you know that uh with the red legacy of griefs that we've had so to accompany grief is to accompany
pain and and for people who do mindfulness practice we begin discovering
that there's a difference between pain and suffering and this makes a world of difference and
this is really what the heart of buddhist practice is about is to if we can see that difference
then we can maybe learn to let go of the suffering and then learn to with nobility with
with the compassion uh accompany the pain that's part of human
life the suffering is when we contract around the pain
when we close the heart around the pain when we cover over the pain when we resist the pain
when we are afraid of the pain all these other ways that we contract and get wrapped up in
in it is the suffering but the pain doesn't you know and that's
what we're liberating in in buddhist practice all that kind of complicated reactivity to the pain
and it's uh but just to live with the pain and make space for it be open to it
be a refuge for the pain help the pain feel safe
safe in us and to learn that art to learn that ability to accompany our pain
so it begins by you know recognizing what the pain is naming it so that we can see what
what's been going on and what's been happening and and so for this pandemic in marking this
anniversary there's been big big griefs
big things to grieve and small things to grieves and all these teeny incidental things that
some people say would shouldn't count you know i should be not up to handling that and dealing with that but the accumulation
of all these small little things and that have been challenging and losses over this year
they add up to a lot and one of the lessons of grief is never discount any grief never feel
that because other people's grief is so much bigger mind shouldn't count
every grief counts every grief is something to accompany to know and to liberate because if we don't
do that then slowly incrementally we begin closing down or pushing under
and and the vitality the fullness of being here you know is going to be diminished so if
you're willing maybe if you could write some of you would be willing to write in the chat
maybe one or two or three words or whatever you want
of what you have grieved this last year that has to do with this pandemic and uh
it'd be nice to have some names associated not um not necessarily to people but you know
that to these different kinds of griefs named here
and um so what have we what have you grieved over this last year
grieving hugs lost hugs the absence of intimacy and
physical contact with people not seeing a grandson
going to school and seeing my friends
not being able to see my parents death of 20 clients
loss of relationships i can't read them all but community
lost distorted social connection sad many pat many past griefs have
resurfaced being in class with my students
isolation nourishing human touch family visits not being with
grandchildren loss of grandmother sitting in community
connecting with many friends and dying high school
son's loss of his senior year yeah no hugs loss of the world and freedom as it was
being alone so much missed celebrations loss of sense of safety
our cut that died this year after 15 years as our companion
yeah these these loss of pets can be huge huge grief loss of closest friend also
not being in sangha with distant relatives i think moments even of freedom from
fear not attending to a dear friend's father's funeral
illness isolation political corruption ptsd isolation
dad's funeral yeah it's a big thing i've not seen my daughter and
grandchildren for more than a year loss of truth and compassion from leadership
music jams lost my ability to understand my loved
ones changing friendships
so thank you all for writing all those things it's a big deal so these are the things to accompany
these are things to name and to be with and and sometimes it's helpful to have help
support and accompaniment that's what sometimes having friends you can talk to about the griefs we have
and not to fix not to solve but just to help to to heaven to be a have a
companionship in the grief and some griefs are so difficult to be our own companion to that having
someone else who can support us in that process there are like grief counselors for example and they're
useful in many ways but one way is that they know how to be companions in a
company and be present for and so it's easier for us to then to be our own companions for our
grief because we have someone who really knows how to do it and can do it with care and compassion and acceptance
and and then learning how to be willing learning how to be comfortable
if that's the right word with feeling pain learning how to be open to feeling pain
learning the wisdom of being with pain the more we love something that we've
lost more we love something that we lost that love doesn't go away and that
something is precious if we what is is to really really kind of listen
deeply get to know deeply what's going on here and that's the second step of this three-step process knowing
grief really getting to know what is this grief what is this pain being willing to really attend to it
because there's a tendency sometimes when we're in really some situation we're in a lot of pain
and hurt and feeling of betrayal to get angry and push things away and
and be hostile or something and which is natural enough it's a way of avoiding sometimes the pain
but to uh but to really get to know the pain because the way to which we love
something to that degree our capacity our beautiful capacity for love our beautiful capacity for
something good is is there buried in the pain
is found together with the pain pain isn't all necessarily all bad
and so to really get to know grief and no pain to know that part of the grief that kind
of that suffering as opposed to pain to be able to make that distinction
between the contractions we have and the resistance the shoulds and the shouldn'ts i shouldn't be feeling grief i should be
over it by now i'm supposed to go through grief perfectly and supposed to resolve my
grief i'm supposed to heal my grief i don't know if we're supposed to heal grief or
some people heal grief but i don't know if we're supposed to or acquired always or we're supposed to resolve grief some
of us never healed in the sense that the pain never goes away but
we can make more space for it it's part of our deep humanity to feel the pain of living life freedom real
freedom it can coexist with pain freedom does not coexist with suffering
suffering is the loss of freedom and so to make to just
keep opening the heart and allow it to be broken allow it to have space for the
pain that we feel um is part of it and sometimes grief can
be so strong that any words about it like the words i'm doing today
can feel just impossible and too difficult to listen to and it doesn't
make any sense occasionally grief has to go we have to reach rock bottom for something to finally
give out or it just seems like so impossible and so to really company really know how impossible it is
and stay there with it stay there with it is part of at least what this mindfulness practice teaches
the um to be with pain to be with it all
and now just remembering some of the things that i was thinking about we grieve i've grieved
in my my life i've grieved anticipated futures the future and now
that won't happen because my friend died we grieve what happened in the past we
grieve what didn't happen in the past what should have happened in the past so
all these you know layers and layers of grief that we can feel
so this knowing grief in vipassana practice has a lot to do with the direct
experience in the moment which is to feel it in your body how is what is the manifestation of grief here
and now in the body what parts of the body are touched and moved and
ache with grief and we can find identify how it is physically here and now
then that becomes a place the very location where we begin opening up to it where we
open the heart we open the mind we open attention and make make see how big the awareness could be
so we can hold that place and be with it if it's not located sometimes in the
body it just seems like it's just overwhelming but sometimes we're located in the body
it has a kind of a locus it has a kind of location to be close with or intimate with or to touch or
to connect to so maybe here on the chat again would some
of you be willing to write where how and where in the body
do you experience grief some of the locations and places for that
there are wonderful bodies that carry so much i have difficulty
swallowing stomach and chest digestion mostly in
heart upper chest throat right below the heart my face throw chest tightening of my chest my heart
aches heart and lungs my heart area in my chest
upper chest and throat right behind the sternum throw the
throat absolutely in the chest and throat eyes and forehead breath in the smile
less easy to turn up the ankle up around my eyes i squint a lot
torso upper neck hot teary eyes tightness of belly broken heart
in the chest and heart like a vacuum in my heart breath tightens tightness in the brain
jaw tightens shoulders so thank you for all that headache from
angry thoughts brain core of my being center of my body
water flowing out yeah lots of tears
headache lower back
in the voice yeah so so many ways it manifests in the
body darkness in the head and the entire being so these are the places that we bring
our compassion and care these are the places we hold these are places where you want to bring a sense
of safety to in the pit of my stomach to mindfulness is to bring a sense of
safety to these places in the body that ache and hurt and are contracted and tight
and there's a way in which to trust that to trust feeling it and sensing it and being with
it it can be very very hard one of the things that makes grief
particularly difficult is when they're it when we feel helpless or hopeless
with their grief and and the sense of helplessness is a we
can for some people especially if it's chronic is really debilitating and the ability
to accompany and to know and to feel and connect and
and to make space for and to hold in the body is a way that over starts
overcoming this feeling of helplessness we can help ourselves there is hope for ourselves through this
practice of mindfulness we have something we can do we have we can't we might be helpless in
terms of for for those who are dead or gone or losses we have for them to come back
but it doesn't leave us as a helpless person we can engage with agency with sense of purpose
and it's a profound thing very profound to learn the ability to hold our pain
and not to add layers of suffering on top of it there's no shame in adding suffering on
top of our pain because sometimes what we need to accompany what we need to open to
is a clear exp seeing knowing and experiencing of those layers of reactivity we have
and without that we don't have a hope of really experiencing what charlie brown called i
think he called we had good grief good grief is the grief that
is simple is unentangled we don't have all these layers of
shoulds and shouldn'ts on top of it it should be different we should be over it right now or
i don't deserve to be grieving because other people's grief so much more all these things we do
and then finally there's liberating grief and and this is kind of what i'm saying
all along is liberating the grief not from getting rid of the grief
not from not no longer having grief but liberating it from how the grief
all the suffering on top of the grief all the reactivity all the judgments all the
angers all the pushing away the resistance all the ways in which we divide
ourselves by shutting out part of who we are because it's too painful to be with
uh to liberate is to become whole liberate is no part left out all of who
we are is allowed to be there not because we are justifying or
celebrating it or condoning it necessarily but so that we can open up and
and have it all be part of the whole the whole is always greater than the
parts and grief is one of the parts they can feel like it's the whole thing
when it's really intense but it's always par a piece of a part of the whole and to
make room for it and to hold it and be with it it might mean that the liberated person
might cry because the pure simplicity of the pain brings along
tears tears are not a sign of being unliberated they might be a sign of actually
we're beginning to liberate ourselves that's where the liberation happens
i love the idea i love the part they have the ways in which it's possible to cry in meditation
because there's something about the meditation posture where we it's a posture in which we
never collapse we never sink we never
give up we never succumb to it but we stay simple relaxed up if you're
upright upright and let the tears flow
so there's not the self-pity or the giving up or something and there's freedom and just crying
there's freedom there's liberation found in that sometimes so um liberating our grief
without needing it to go away so that we can go through our life
continuing to experience the griefs that will come there's no there's no final freedom from
grief and sadness but to go through life and be free in the midst of it is to allow
ourselves to feel it the vitality the fullness of life with the grief and with the joys and
with the love and with all that's here
and this is not resolving grief in terms of it going away it's not finally it's over
it's it's the grief has its own life and so liberating our grief
is to be generous to our grief so the grief can have its freedom the
grief can do what it needs to do and to learn to trust the heart knows what to do the heart knows what to do
with grief if we've liberated it if we if we know it accompany it and we get out of its
way and we've liver liberated from ourselves our hearts our grief
knows what to do and sometimes we have to be patient it takes time so liberating our grief
so some of you maybe have had some experience of grief liberated in the way
i've described talk about here and how does it feel how do you know that leaf has grief has
been liberated how do you know uh how that experienced in you how's
experience in your body what's it like to have grief maybe even still present
but really feel it's been liberated so um let's see
here there can be a purity to the feeling of grief and strong emotion maybe that's part of the liberation yes
and um
part of what it feels like for me is a willingness
the liberation of grief comes along with a willingness a willingness to grieve a willingness to
have pain
breaking away and lifting of weight i feel like i'm cared and safe
when i let it go i felt more here and connected to others compassion sense
and grief emerging sense of peace feeling joy along with the sorrow
getting in touch with the raw emotion and being with it forgiveness there is truth in the deep
sorrow and grief lifted weight of grief more love and
accompanying grief relaxation and gratitude i feel lighter it feels cleansing forgiveness
more peace and openness acceptance of experience at peace with
it putting down a large rock grief from childhood became compassion
for my parents heart opens and i cry more with the connection
grief is a necessary part of moving on from the loss feeling the joy right next to it
great thank you for all this very much feeling the love behind an inside of
grief and feeling grateful for such love if you feel like i'm moving again
relief the heart knows what to do with grief when it has been liberated
i will always carry this incredibly wise statement thank you oh it's a quote quoting so
um thank you so accompanying our grief
knowing our knowing grief and liberating grief uh three different ways of being with
grief at different times different ones one of them are appropriate and
it's a profound part of our human life and it's been an important part and importance the right
word a very significant part of this last year and and as we begin the second year
of kovid with whatever changes might be coming that um that uh to acknowledge
a little bit what happened this last year and to have spent time really accompanying
knowing and liberating this grief hopefully will let us go into this new world this new year
more capable more willing more wise and how to continue to meet
the griefs that will come one way or the other will still have griefs whether even when the pandemic's over
we'll have griefs this is part of human life and there's no liberation
without being liberated in relationship to our grief as well we are grieving beings just as much as
we're loving beings compassionate beings forgiving beings
we're also beings that can experience pain so thank you very much for this
and i'm aware that grief is a huge well abyss of pain sometimes very
difficult and bringing it up today and evoking it this way might be very hard for some of you
and i encourage you to spend some time um today caring for yourself if that's the
case maybe talk to friends go for walks
if you have no one to talk to journal about it write about it so it's so you can you
give it some expression and but do take care of yourself and and
um and uh if this talk was particularly difficult um maybe in a few days listen to it
again there might be some something moving and bubbling inside of you from it
but i wish you well and i offer you this talk with a lot of
desire and care and compassion for your welfare and happiness and and for all of us as we go forward
together in this new next year that may all of us
support each other in this process thank you all very much