okay thank you for the messages about no sound
so now i think it works so hello everyone and
welcome to our monday uh beginning of the week and also
i'm happy to be back here i was away teaching
a retreat in a way teaching retreat from this very spot online and the retreat continues this week and
but i'm very happy to be here and and
so um
when we sit and get quiet sit or try to be quiet in meditation sit and be still
one of the things that sooner or later becomes very clear is that we carry with us the momentum
of our life the momentum of our thinking our concerns
our preoccupations our desires our aversions we carry with us the momentum of the
different life experiences which have influenced us the life experience of things we've done
in our lives and still resonates or still kind of lives somehow with us
one teacher once said that when was asked you know what do you do when you meditate and she said
we confront our unresolved issues so that's certainly much more than we do
than that but sometimes that's one of the things that arises and although that whole package of
things that we come into touch with our momentum of our life is sometimes summarized in buddhism
under a simple maybe simplistic term that it's karma and i'll talk more about that
later but uh whether that's the right label for it all or not
the um the it's nice to kind of gather in a sense
in your mind gather at heart gather it all together all these influence all's momentum that we have that
from a lifetime of habits and concerns and preoccupations and influences we've
had and um and bow to it deeply
to offer our respect to have tremendous respect for this part of our lives
and bowing to it and respecting it and acknowledging it's there
maybe that can allow us to step away far enough to
ease up on our concerns with it preoccupations with it trying to fix it
trying to ameliorate it whatever and step away and
recognize us there be respectful but to for the time of the meditation
to cease picking it up c is getting pulled into
it and keeping it going with thinking and concerning and remembering and planning
and judging and criticizing and all that all those things can go on
but as we meditate we want to give breathing room for ourselves
the kind of space that sometimes is not available when we're locked into these things or caught in them
and often meditation we talk about letting go of such things so we can focus on the breathing
but it's important to also respect it and maybe in a deep respect it's easier
to let it be and for these moments not to pick it up
and one of the functions of the meditation of breath meditation is to help us
disentangle ourselves from all that influence all the momentum
it still comes through us but you can imagine that you're standing on dry
riverbank looking at the river going by the river is massive you respect the
river but you don't you know get into it
i've been in big powerful rivers with
big rapids and my way of respecting it was not to stand
right on the edge of the river but to be back maybe three feet four feet
so to be able to watch it go by without being involved
so this is one of the functions of breath meditation it takes us to dry ground
helps us to disentangle and maybe it's easier to give yourself over to breathing
after you've respected this karmic stream that is part of who we are in a sense
so assuming a posture
that maybe promotes disentangling
promotes us stable confident presence
that's not easily swept away kind of like you're standing strong
with your feet firmly rooted in the ground
so that you don't get pushed over by the wind
so taking a posture that's grounded and firm
and lowering your gaze relaxing your eyes
and perhaps closing your eyes if that's comfortable
and to begin this process of disentangling to take a few long slow deep breaths
as you exhale letting whatever
momentum that's here relax and settle away
deep breath in and as you exhale
become rooted relaxed stable rooted here in this body
letting your breathing return to normal
and sometimes by continuing to relax the body
it's a way of continuing to ease up
on the way that we're concerned about things and involved in thoughts and fantasies
he's up on our emotions that we might have
so as you exhale to relax the belly
maybe maybe even letting the belly become
a little heavy to feel the pull of gravity
on the exhale to relax the chest
and then to relax the shoulders
and then to soften the muscles of your face
and then on the exhale maybe on the inhale
feel any tension or pressure in your thinking mind
and as you exhale to soften the thinking mind
relax
and then with respect for this thoughts you have the thinking you have the
feelings you have maybe even acknowledging their presence
center your attention on the body breathing
so that this precious resource that you have your attention
is no longer involved in your karmic stream
that can just go on by itself but your precious attention
is devoted to the experience of the body breathing
as you exhale
giving yourself over to the full exhale
as you inhale receive the
inhale
feeling the rhythm of breathing in and out hanging in there is a way to make lots
of breathing room for all things
well you're rooted devoted to the simple experience of breathing
stepping away from our thoughts concerns
respectfully
disentangling and using the attention to breathing
is a way of staying on dry ground
so the river of karma can take care of itself without our needing
to do anything about it just breathing is enough
um
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
if we appreciate and respect our karmic stream
all the influences and experiences and
concerns hurts and joys and
ups and downs that somehow still have their life within us
we can appreciate maybe the that's that's the case for many other people as well
then all beings all people
the influence of this difficult life streams through them and
their karmic patterns concerns preoccupations
stored in their body mind and heart
and to have care and respect and certain kind of reverence for other
people for what they carry
their challenges they live with
at the end of the sitting to extend our care compassion our kindness
our deep respect for what people
deal with in this human life
and to offer our ability to be companions on this journey
so people are less alone less forgotten
until you turn our attention outward
considering how we can support others
in finding a way in this life may it be that through
the goodness of this practice that we do
that our attention can go outwards for the welfare and happiness of others
may we contribute support
the possibility of all beings being happy
all beings being safe all beings
being peaceful and all beings being free
may all beings everywhere be happy
[Music]
so
so hello and as we begin this series of talks
on this monday that the topic this week
is to talk about two streams of our lives
the karmic stream and the dharmic stream
and the dharm extreme for is the buddhist language to talk about uh what unfolds what can develop
when we free ourselves from the karmic stream
we free ourselves respectfully respectful of the karmic stream
and in particular the way the stream of karma contributes to our ongoing suffering
and that's one of the reasons why buddhists focus on karma the karmic stream
because of how much suffering it perpetuates it's kind of like being caught in a
perpetual renewal of suffering pain despair
challenges and but then there's this other whole stream
that is not karmic but it can be called dharmic the dharm extreme
so to give a uh and you know language like karma and darmok evoke all kinds of complicated
ideas and karma people have a lot of associations already with what it means
and i'll talk about it in a particular way this week and kind of and hopefully in a way to
normalize it as something that we can see operating in the day-to-day
activity of our life putting aside ideas of karma being
you know something influencing us over the lifetimes
so if a person went through life
with their fists clenched that's never opened up
that would influence their life in all kinds of ways
that would be very different if someone went through their life their life with their hands open
relaxed soft open ready to operate in all kinds of ways and
all the kind of ways that fingers can move and hold on and do things
and um a person who has a hand that's free to open and be used
their life will unfold very differently the person whose life is always clenched
the fist is always clenched
you know it's best not to stretch this analogy too far but just in a simple way
and then if someone is similarly
if someone is their heart is clenched their heart is closed and it's closed
for decades that life unfolds differently than if a heart is open
if the mind is closed in some way constricted narrow
that life unfolds very differently than a person whose mind is
open open-minded so
the way that we live day by day in the present moment
can influence how we live in this life
if we live a life that is uh with recurring kind of chronic
hostility or aversion that puts together certain conditions
that are very different than if we go through our life with generosity and love
if we go through our lives with greed and lust and that's the predominant mindstream that we keep flowing in
that life uh opens up or moves ahead or unfolds very differently
than someone's life who is generous and kind and and uh thinks about the welfare of
others so these very broad kind of strokes are pointing to different directions life
can go and it's certainly different directions that ways that we influence ourselves
um we are not um all these ways that we operate
consciously or unconsciously has an impact and influence on ourselves
so that if we are chronically aversive that the there's traces there's lingerings
there's uh uh feelings there's ongoing impact on ourselves because of that
if we're loving this has a very different impact if um we um
uh and one of the ways that we can see one of the powerful ways to see the operation of operation of karma
is in our thought streams and probably that's the single most
effective way to understand karma to see its influences and how it operates
day by day kind of in our lives and not to kind of be involved in the more metaphysical ideas of karma
but to see that thinking has a big influence on us
and it said that rumination is one of the leading causes of depression
if we're ruminating in such a way thinking in such a way that the thoughts are deflating the thoughts are discouraging
that thoughts are critical and kind of frightening to listen to or
discouraging to listen to and to have that discouragement and that fear kind of chronically kind of
move through our system and move through our system our whole body and mind and heart will be influenced by the
ongoingness of those thoughts and we can feel that the impact it has on us
and it's a and the kind of kind of rebirth the constant renewal
into this karmic stream is that as we feel lousy
that's kind of a fuel to continue having these kinds of difficult thoughts these
undermining thoughts the undermining thoughts make us feel worse and so it prompts
certain way of thinking and so it's cyclic it kind of gives birth to itself
over and over and over again and sometimes it's so chronic that they become almost
invisible to people it's kind of like the the this if it's true that the fish
don't see the water they swim in now we sometimes don't see the water the the mood and the attitude that we swim
in we move through because it's been reinforced and so the ongoing
and so sometimes all this karma stuff is described as habits
ongoing habits and some of the karmic habits are healthy you can be great habits of love
and generosity and and that creates a very different influence
on us ourselves and that provide a very different conditioning influence in our body and mind
but there's a stream we enter into and we participate in and and and part of that stream there's momentum
from the past that's continues into the present and then there's ways in which we keep
adding to the momentum in the present moment and what dharma practice is trying to do
is trying to free us from continuing to reinforce continuing to
add momentum to the stream to be respectful of how much it's flowing
but to step back on dry ground and watch it go by the stream go by
without adding to it and as we step back um then it's kind of
like when the hand's been closed in a cleansed fish for a
clenched fist for a long time and then it's opened uh things begin to happen there's an
unfolding that has an influence on us influence on the hand influence us it's inspiration it gives us ideas of
what we can do and um but um
but uh it starts setting emotion a goodness inside of us a movement
towards freedom we get a sense that oh the hand can be released that's nice
i bet now my shoulders can relax maybe this clenched stomach has a
possibility of relaxing and um and some there's a path that begins opening up and some of that uh
that that path as is the natural unfolding
of what could be called the dharma the dharma stream and it's the dharma stream is that
stream of releasing ourselves from our contractions our tightness our holdings
and then experiencing the goodness uh the joy the well-being the tranquility that comes flowing
from that and leads to deep insights at least a deep understanding to this world
and so uh and every day we have we're in this every moment where
kind of both streams are available and a lot of what people spend their
time with doing is living in the karmic stream and a very easy way to see it i believe
is that is to notice what you're thinking as you go about your day
and if you are thinking about something which is not in the present moment
that's the karmic stream and
and you might if you as you're sitting in that stream thinking about the future the past
fantasy anything like that you might take time to see what is that what kind of influence is
this kind of thinking having on me is it a beneficial influence is it not a
beneficial influence is it neutral what is that influence on it on it
and to stop and take that kind of look is to is to uh
beginning to stop also from reinforcing that stream
but if we just let our minds kind of flow along happily thinking about
resentments in the past or the desires we want in the future then we're
adding momentum to it keeping it flowing keeping it flowing and some people like that they want to
they justify it and the cost of that of keeping it going
is that we don't allow this other whole stream to unfold
the dharm the dharma stream so that's the topic for this week and
so this is uh the introduction to it and it's kind of setting the stage and
it's uh considered to be a very important topic in buddhism and perhaps not talked about that much
and so we'll try to talk about it this week so thank you and look forward to being here with you
tomorrow