so welcome to our meditation
and uh
so one of the key components of mindfulness meditation
is our ability to clearly recognize to clearly recognize what is happening
in the present moment and to recognize it in its simplicity
so in the way and partly that means to recognize it as a present moment
phenomena and maybe without a past or a future
of course it has that maybe but but the simplicity of just this
experience without the thoughts the ideas the associations we have
with past and future imaginations we have
a simple recognition that is independent of our preferences of course we have
preferences but we also have the capacity to know independent of them
to know clearly independent of our desires and our aversions
our plans our hopes even independent of our usual
sense of self that we operate under or we we construct or we associate with our
agency and our doing and that's maybe the most difficult part of clear knowing is to
just to allow the most natural simple inner capacity to know
to occur to be to arise and without a lot of ideas of baggage
around i'm the one who's doing it or i have to do it well or or i'm not doing it well enough just a
simple knowing and so this week we're looking at
compulsive desire compelling desire with the desire and what that we get
caught in and that can happen with this in in the ordinariness of thinking
that we start thinking about something and it doesn't take much to realize that some thoughts some trains
of thoughts there's desires that is propelling them
some of them have aversions some of them have other things but this week we're looking at desire and
there's probably much more often desire propelling thoughts than most people acknowledge sometimes
there's strong feelings in the body even emotions that have underneath them
some desire that's part of it maybe in the corners of it underneath it
maybe in the center of it somehow a desire is part of it and if those desires are compelling or
compulsive or we get caught in those desires and then there's no freedom and the
medicine is to clearly recognize clearly no
so if you know that you're caught in desire
the medicine is in that knowing it might not be there automatically but
rather than looking for a solution in the desires and the compulsive desires it's
in the knowing that there's a kind of solution kind of freedom to be found
and so this kind of stepping back and clearly knowing oh this is desire
this is being caught in desire and and there's a in that stepping back
there's freedom it's like you were you know
caught in the quicksand on the edge of a kind of lake or something and all you
have to do is take one little step just maybe a few inches away and stand
on dry ground and you can look back then on the lake on the quicksand realize oh i'm no longer in it
so to step back or to open up clear recognition oh this is compulsive
desire this is being caught in desire and then to look for where that freedom
is where that spaciousness is where the openness is where the not caughtness is
and there is a specialness that's where something sacred is happening that's where the
sacred ground is in that clear knowing that is free of so many things that usually
gets attached to how we relate to things and if you're able to find that clear recognition of
desire then uh welcome
into that clear knowing into that space that sacred ground welcome into it your breathing
as an alternative to being caught up in your desires
um the breathing is kind of very closely related to this kind of
sacred ground this ancestral territory that we can live in that we lose
when we get involved in compulsive desire so don't worry about having compulsive
desire being caught in it it's the stepping stone for clear recognition it's the means it's the
support for clear recognition find that freedoms you know to fight it
or push it away or feel bad about having it say okay hi my friend
you are the stepping stone for this clear recognition this little little
moment of simplicity of freedom um and it helps to do to do this if you
take every each moment for itself some people say that you know every day
is a good day it's a saying every moment can be a good moment if
there's a clear recognition the simplicity of the moment
so assuming a meditation posture
and closing your eyes and before doing anything else
can there be a clear recognition of here and now how you are
clear recognition of how you are and then experiment with make subtle adjustments
so that you're not caught up in how you are or reactive to how you are
for or against how you are just
knowing this is how it is
maybe it's through an opening up wide wider than how you are in a sense than
knowing it maybe it's stepping back in the mind
so you can gaze upon how you are with some freedom or independence
maybe it's knowing how you are from a quiet place within
a calm place
and then welcoming in your breathing welcome breathing into your knowing into
your awareness
especially the inhale receive the inhale
and as you exhale allow for the exhale
and as you exhale for a few exhales allow your body to relax to soften
adjusting your arms maybe if that allows your arms to be more at ease
and as you exhale to relax in the mind
to calm or soften the thinking mind
rather than letting go of your thoughts let your thinking slow down
no hurry lots of time
or perhaps as you exhale to let go of your thoughts as well
and so that the clear knowing of the exhale
is worthless
the clear experiencing of the inhale is wordless
or mostly wordless
and then as you meditate here
if you notice that you get caught up in desire even subtle desires
try not to make it a problem instead see it as a stepping stone
for the sacred ground of clear knowing
the clear awareness of the desire
that is not caught in the desire you might be caught
desire might be caught in itself but the clear knowing is not
what right now can you clearly recognize
that you're enabling or going along with without knowing
stepping back opening up wider to clearly recognize what hasn't been
recognized
in the simplicity of knowing
and then allowing the breathing to return to the
fullness of that knowing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting imagine that you're sitting in an easy
chair maybe in a very open room with open door
maybe outdoors in an outdoor lounge chair
and people come to visit and you stay relaxed settle back
in your chair welcoming them receiving them
without needing to get up without needing to do much just allowing them into the space
allowing them to take a chair as well
welcoming them so in the same way as we come to the end
of the sitting can you be relaxed open
nothing you have to do but to be welcoming but open your awareness now
your mind to the people that you'll encounter today
whether strangers on the street or in stores
or their people that you'll see on somehow on the computer
in the news the people you might think about today
and welcome them into your easy relaxed space
welcome and then i'm into a space where you offer safety
you offer warmth and kindness
a peacefulness you offer them a chair where they can sit also
welcome they mean welcoming into a space in your heart
where they also can be addressed and not demand anything of you or require
anything of you
and in this imaginary exercise of receiving people into your sacred
ground wish them well
or feel how the welcome itself is a well wishing
and may it be on this day that
coming out of our meditation and through the day that in our hearts in our minds
and maybe in our actions
that we there's a welcoming of people a well-wishing of people
looking upon people with kind and compassionate eyes
may those people we meet today be happy
safe peaceful and free
and may we contribute to that possibility
that at least in our presence they're safe we offer peace
and they're free from us from our desires and our compulsions and
our aversions may all beings be happy
you
uh
so we continue these morning talks on
on greed and uh it's maybe a little bit interesting that
i think sometimes uh in the west there's this thing called the seven deadly sins i believe and
and greed is one of them and in buddhism i don't think we really look upon
anything as being a sin but rather we look upon it as being damaging being
harmful and some things are more some things are harmful and some things
are not and things that are harming we want to stop doing
and um so the very different attitude about uh you know that there isn't that kind
of condemnation that might be there with the idea of sin but rather there's a kind of compassion
care and understanding that there is an
alternative to harming and so when we're caught in desire
uh which what that's kind of defined as greed
and what it means is that even beneficial desires desires for something good and healthy
if we're caught in that desire that cotness is harmful that cottness is not healthy
and that's an important distinction because some people might have a kind of greed or being caught up
in some very very strongly and needing to wanting to have something happen and and it's the kind of thing maybe
should happen they should have it but is it necessary to be caught in it do does it improve
the situation are we more likely to get it if we're caught in it or if we're caught up in it or tight or
constricted around the desire uh are we somehow harming ourselves both
in the moment but also in creating a disposition a habit of of constriction of tightness of
forcefulness in the desires that we have and one of the wonderful things to
discover is how to have healthy desires and have a quality of freedom have a
quality of ease or peacefulness or simplicity with them and discover
maybe we take maybe we can act on these desires so much better and more effectively when we have this
peacefulness with them lack of compulsion and also if we have the lack of
compulsion then we have the opportunity to discover the freedom and the benefits of sacred
ground of this openness this ease this peace that
oddly enough can give us often time a sense that we don't
need to fulfill our desires or all our desires even if it's a healthy desire we know
something better and then not to sacrifice it that better thing
so one of the things that can be better is this clear recognition and not a forceful recognition not a
complicated recognition of things not something that's excessively verbal
like we're pounding our thoughts out like you know desire desire in some strong way
but this kind of uh soft open quiet almost natural bubbling up of
knowing of clear recognition of what's and um and uh
and in that clear recognition in that knowing there's the treasure knowing we have
compulsive desire um is not in and of itself the treasure but within it is found a treasure so
to turn the attention away from the desire the object of the desire and
recognize something like turn the attention around 360 degrees
to be aware of the what are the quality the characteristics of this
clear knowing clear recognition and is there some way of clearly knowing where it feels really
good it feels like this is my home my ancestral land this is the place of
of ease and not to dismiss the world
not to reject it in any kind of way but to find this place from which to live in the world to know
the world it takes a while to learn this and some people it's perplexing maybe what i'm
saying that there's a treasure in the knowing so it takes a while to kind of
experiment look around experiment with different ways of knowing or being aware
until the awareness feels is really nice to be aware and be present and
awake so this idea of the core in the central
kind of way of practicing insight meditation the idea is to turn away
the attention turn the attention away from the object of desire
to what it's like to be desiring so so when we have this kind of clear
clear enough knowing and mindfulness then we can use that to feel the experience of desiring
and sometimes only by doing that we begin to disengage ourselves from the compulsion
and so one of the things to feel in the desiring the feeling of desiring
is what it feels like in the body to be desiring what it feels like in the body to be
greedy or compulsive and sometimes there's a leaning forward or a
jumping up or a kind of a tension that's uplifting like i really want this
there's a tightening sometimes around it and to really feel the physical
qualities maybe the jaw gets set relax or the eyes get set on the object we want this for
sure there's a constriction or tightness in the mind sometimes in the belly there's
like a strong urge to have and to want sometimes it's almost like when there's
a strong desire it's almost like we've been possessed like everything just wants
um uh there are some certain times when i get really famished like hungry
that uh it seems almost like there's this like whole embodied physiological kind of you know
primal kind of desire like i better get food and and it can be very compelling and
it's fascinating to practice with that it's just so interesting to discover you know these powerful forces within us
and to sit in them and discover freedom in them or discover this clear recognition can
always be there to provide us a home of freedom that allows us
more clarity to think wisely about what we're doing to not act compulsively in ways that are
harmful to ourselves or others so to feel the physio physiology of
compulsive desire and one of the interesting ways of doing this is to distinguish between a desire that
has no compulsion and a desire that does and what does that compulsion feel like what's that
extra thing and to over time become a connoisseur of these
the physiological qualities characteristics of compulsion now it isn't so we can be compulsive
better but rather the more familiar we are with the physical manifestations of desire expressions of
this compulsive desire the easier it is to become free the easier is to discover this clear
awareness that knows it rather than having that compulsive desire
infuse us with its authority because sometimes desires come with a
lot of authority and that if like this has to happen now and this is important and
you know and there might be authority based on fear if i don't get it there might be authority based on
um on and you know then everything will be okay
and i'll be successful and it might be the authority of pleasure like i really need to have some
pleasure in order to feel somehow fulfilled or satisfied so what's that authority that comes with
compulsion so to feel the physiology of it the physicalness of it then then
the it's easier to kind of disengage from the sense of authority that can come with desire
the way it's commanding us as we uh drop into the body and feel
the physicality of desire then we also may become aware of the emotionality of
desire what emotions come into play when we have desire is it fear
is it a virgin actually sometimes desires we want something to get away from something else
is it is it anticipation is it are we living in
fantasies and we um you know so there's a kind of promise of
eternal happiness or something is there a delight in the desire we have
and somehow we're caught in the delight of it that happiness that hap the promise of that
happiness it might provide so what's the emotions what's the emotional tone
and feeling of what's happening with it is a desire mostly an attempt to get away
from something uncomfortable or is a desire mostly an attempt to get to something that we think is wonderful and to notice that
clearly what's motivating it emotionally feeling wise motivational wise
is again another step towards disentangling ourselves from it to another step
towards having this clear recognition of what's happening and what's going on
and in that clear recognition finding the freedom finding the ease and then it's also possible that as we
kind of settle in and relax and open to the desire is to
also become aware a little bit of the thought train what are the beliefs that are operating
there can be beliefs that this is how i'll you know be safe this is how i'll get be happy in my
life if i have this pleasure or if this desire is fulfilled it might be that then people will like
me if i or this is how people you know there's all kinds of beliefs that come
into play and we don't have to go analyzing that deeply but as we settle down and
quieted meditation especially um then we start it's kind of like um we
start like like we're looking out of a window and a stream of different
inner events begin to become clearer and clearer it first might be that we shouldn't play we're caught in desire
and then it starts seeing oh the physicality of it and then what comes through the window
of awareness is we start seeing the emotionality that's connected to it or the motivational quality of it
and then also we might start seeing if when we get quieter and quieter the stream of thoughts related to it and
we might see that we're actually caught in a belief we're caught in a dream
of hope of expectation of fantasy and we can feel the way we lean into and
hold on to that fantasy or that dream or that that where you're living in
and that's in part of the part of the desire as well and um and each step along the way
of all this the physical just the desire itself the how it feels in the body how it
feels emotionally how what's going on in the mind to practice simple clear awareness some of us it
means making very simple mental notes tightness
anticipation fantasy to help us have that clear recognition
and then when the desire is no longer compulsive we can come back to the breathing or
if the clear recognition has become strong enough the compulsion might be there still
but we're not really involved in it anymore and then it can be useful sometimes to
simply welcome back in the healthy experience of breathing and
let breathing the healthiness of breathing fill the awareness so there's in a sense there's no room
for the compulsion anymore the compulsion is not being fed by our involvement with it
and it has a chance to just settle down so for this next day you might try when
you find even the most subtle compulsive desire like you really need to have something
now and you find um you know maybe even if it's a situation's appropriate just close your
eyes sit down and really explore and track inside what is going on
if you turn the attention 180 degrees around from the object of desire to what's
happening within you as it as you're desiring
so thank you and look forward to continuing this series tomorrow