so good day to everyone and good beginning
of the week and
here we are to sit quietly here we are to let the thinking mind
become quieter so that we're less involved in our
thinking then we are involved in our
um inner life involved with
subtleness and stillness involved with a place that it's peaceful a place of
inner happiness inner pleasure
that maybe is more available if we don't keep
flowing along in the all the rivers of thoughts the streams of thinking that we could
spin out on so to begin this
journey to a more settled place
to assume a posture that allows you to settle
whatever is works for you given your
situation and some people find it helpful to close the eyes
or if the eyes are open not really to look at anything almost as if the eyes are resting
in their sockets and the eyes are looking backwards
and down and then taking a few long slow deep
breaths and these long slow deep breaths
can be done leisurely it can be done in a way where if
possible you enjoy it it feels pleasant
so doing it at a p at a speed
and to the extent that it's nice for you to breathe in fully
and to allow the diaphragm to do its full release
the work of breathing when the diaphragm the work is done on the inhale as a diaphragm
is pushed down and the exhale is a release letting go
of that pushing down and diaphragm
releases and pulls itself upward
and on the exhale
releasing other places in your body as well relaxing
maybe a global relaxation throughout the body
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and ever so slightly can you adjust the normal breathing
so that you are so it's a little bit more pleasant to
breathe so let yourself become attuned
sensitive to any form of pleasure or nice feeling
that comes with breathing
maybe there's a little section of the inhale it feels nice
or a certain section of the exhale
and if there is any pleasure or comforting feeling with breathing allow
yourself to feel that in such a way that your thinking mind
becomes quieter or allow the thinking mind to be quieter
so you can better sense and feel the physicality of breathing
in whatever physical sensations that are
enjoyable pleasant
breathing in breathing out
as you exhale relaxing more in your body
maybe almost as if you as you relax you settle into breathing more
breathing in and breathing out
relaxing the thinking mind and dropping into whatever is pleasant
in your body just a simple pleasantness
of being alive or the vibrating body
the hum of vitality in your body
and breathe with that pleasantness even if there's other places that are
painful breathe with a pleasantness of the physicality of your body
letting the thinking mind become quieter
so you're in the stream of sensations in your body
more than the three the stream of your
thinking
being careful not to flow in the stream of thinking
even this subtle background thinking that creeps in from the sides or from the back door
and if you are thinking very quietly think about your breathing
think about the pleasant experiences that are here and now in the experience
of breathing not so you get carried away in thought
but so your thinking becomes simpler and simpler
and your awareness more and more attuned with the body breathing
you
noticing if you are flowing in the stream of thinking
or if you're grounded in your body and you're
breathing with an awareness that might be aware that you're thinking
but the awareness is not flowing along in the thinking
sometimes even the awareness present moment awareness gets lost submerged
in the river of thoughts
and as we come to the end of the sitting we can be submerged in the river of
thoughts when we're with other people so involved in thinking about what to
say or what they're saying or our concerns about the situation
or our awareness can be clear and present
so that we can really offer an attentive attention to our people we're
with so that our attention is more with the people we're with
then it is loss submerged in the flow of our thinking
and there's a way of offering attention
listening seeing to really
understand and be present for others in a fuller way
maybe sometimes offering quiet so the other person can has a chance to
express themselves and say what needs to be said
what we learn in meditation about not being swept away in thought
can translate to be more present for others
and if we're more present it's easier to care for others
to feel their humanity their suffering their joys
and may it be that this practice that we do together
allows us to offer the gift of attention to others
and from that gift maybe other thing we provide other gifts kindness
friendliness care love
may the benefits of this practice spread from us out into the world
for the welfare and happiness of all beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be free
so on this monday we have a new topic for the week and in
some ways as a continuation from a couple of weeks ago when we did the first foundation of mindfulness
mindfulness of the body this week i'd like to
talk about that they're subject to the second foundation of mindfulness that of feelings the usual english
translation of feeling tones that the pali word is a
vedana sometimes they say and it's um
sometimes thought to be really one of these central practice topics for the teachings of the
buddha that it's phenomenally important it's kind of like the the some
people kind of the linchpin or the or the foundation
for so much of the buddha dharma or for practice so it's a very important topic and
this has a whole of the four foundations it gets a whole foundation to itself
now the word in pali is vedana v-e-d-a-n-a
and it's um i believe it's a cognate it's related to
the way indo-european languages relate to each other to the english word witness
or maybe say wit sometimes someone who's clever or something they have wit
and uh in norwegian the word vet the probably all similar means to know
and so the the pali version of this is vid the root word is vid vid
which means to know or to also mean in pali to experience so vedana
refers to what is known what is experienced uh what is felt
but felt uh you know as sensations as feelings and we're focusing here on
sensations in the body and so the sensations that are known
and that are felt and exactly where the line is between knowing something and feeling sensations is not very clear
because these arise together closely connected
but we are talking about a way of knowing and as a way of knowing it's a
subjective way of knowing it's what we know subjectively
and so i want to give a um analogy that maybe can highlight or
point out at the the way in which this is so important so maybe you're responsible for a
place of a workplace maybe a factory maybe a warehouse maybe a corporate building or
someplace where many people come to work and many visitors come to this place as
well and uh people come actually from all over the world
and it's uh cove at times so you want to make sure that you keep
people at your workplace healthy and people are coming from all over they're flying in
and and there's no way of controlling who shows up so how are you going to keep your your
employees people working with you uh safe
and and so then you realize that
the only way into the workplace is through the front door and so no matter where everyone's coming
from everyone has to go through that front door and um and so what you need to do is set
up a welcoming station where you take people's temperature give them a covet test whatever it takes
and to make sure that they're safe to come into the building and if they're safe and good you know then you allow them in if
they're not safe then they can't come in and that way you keep all the people
coveted safe in your building so so there's this kind of common place
it's like a funnel like a neck or a doorway a passageway through
which everything goes and now the wide range of human
experience all the different things we can experience in the world and things can happen to us
there's they go through and the passage as they come into our experience
everything goes through the doorway of feeling or feeling tones affective tone
and that is a particular tone or quality of the things that are
known as we know things as we experience things they can be either pleasant
painful or neutral pleasant unpleasant and neutral
sometimes we say and um but the the middle word is
literally means pain but it's a there's anything from the mildest you know discomfort to intense pain
anything from the mildest pleasantness to intense pleasure are the
first two and then neutral is that which is neither pleasant or not pleasant in fact
that's the way it's worded in pauline neither pleasant nor unpleasant and for the uninitiated it can seem kind
of like what's the big deal it's kind of dull and boring just to talk to things to focus on things being pleasant
or unpleasant or neither but it turns out it's a common denominator or it's the door it's the
everything goes through that um every every experience we have has one of
those three qualities in it so if you can have if you can uh station yourself
at the door and you watch everything that comes in then you can only you could you don't
have to let in things which are not healthy for you you can let in things
which are healthy for you you can leave out what is unwholesome and bring in what is unwholesome
uh you leave out what is unwholesome bring in what is wholesome and and so it gives you a vantage point
tremendously important place to stay healthy to stay well
and it's easier to stay right there and notice the feeling tones than when things get
more complicated just like to go out into the world and analyze everything in the world all the complicated aspects of it and
think about it and figure it out you know can take a lifetime to figure out the world
or to go inward and really kind of discover the inner life it's it's also a kind of complicated
world of thoughts and memories and histories and experiences we've had and accumulated and how they'll come into play but
everything inner experiences and outer outer experiences in a sense
for us to know anything to feel anything
goes through this little door of it being either pleasant unpleasant or neither so what's the big
deal about that the big deal is that there's sometimes for the people who
don't practice or have a strong kind of mindfulness awareness practice
we often can act automatically on whether things are pleasant and
unpleasant neutral maybe not but so something is pleasant and there's
kind of an automatic desire for it for more of it things are unpleasant or
painful there's a desire to push it away or not have it there and they can be so automatic so quick
that we don't even see the two are separate we experience something that's pleasant and with that comes a feeling want that
feeling something unpleasant with that comes don't want that pushing it away but
these are actually two different movements and so when i was um
uh practicing the pasta in burma i sat a long retreat and there was a
particular moment that just that taught me this lesson in a very powerful way
and and that was i was every day i would go in to see my teacher most days six days a week for practice discussion
talk about my practice and um and he lived in a little kind of cabin and
there was kind of an entryway and just next to the entryway the door going in to the right there was a little altar
and usually were some buddhas on the altar and you know we didn't have to pay any attention to it which was
on the way in to see him and and one day because maybe it hadn't been
there before there was a new wooden buddha sitting on that little altar
so my mind was very you know fairly mindful at this point
so i was able to track things more closely than i usually can do and and so i noticed
there's a statue buddha statue
i noticed that it was beautiful and the first thing i noticed was really pleasant i felt this pleasantness the
pleasure of looking at it and then i saw there was desire to have
it but those things happen in clear
distinction from each other sequentially seeing the buddha recognizing it
as such experiencing the pleasantness of it
and then wanting it and when i saw that the experience of pleasure and the wanting
were very distinct two different activities of the mind i said i could oh
there's possibility for freedom here it's possible i don't have to pick up
the desire i don't have to get involved in it it was just like oh it's just a fleeting desire comes
and it goes but that desire arose
influenced by that sense of pleasure but because it was so clear the distinction between them
the desire had very little authority over me it had a little influence on me just oh
it's a desire and i saw that these two are different and that was the beginning of
a lot of discoverer of a lot of his paws this gap in experience where there's a
possibility of freedom it's possible to leave the pleasant alone
it's impossible to leave that what's unpleasant alone and not get involved in the reactivity
to it and now or it's possible this automatic way in which the mind can work that yes
there might you see the pleasantness clearly and it's possible to see the desires or
the aversions that have come from pleasant or unpleasant and because it's so clear it might be
possible just not get involved it's just it's just desire it's just a version
just a blip in the mind and and you let it go but if these two are yoked
together the feeling tone the vedana and our reaction response to it our desires
around it then we don't see them being two different things chances are we're already in the stream
of desire it already kind of we don't have enough strong attention to to to
you know not be pulled in and kind of automatic pilot into the desires
and now this can be quite intense you know in our lives like something very unpleasant happens and we immediately
bark at someone something very pleasant we see and immediately that's what we want and
you know it's the compulsions are so strong it isn't just simply an innocent desire
we have these desires sometimes come with tremendous compulsion and we say things and do things that
later we regret and realize that we were not free something inside of us which was not
in a sense not us or not our choice or our will our decision has taken over and
pushed us to do things maybe that we actually didn't want to do and and so to
to be able to slow down enough and notice the pleasant experiences are
pleasant the unpleasant experiences unpleasant can give us a tremendous amount of
choice freedom we can kind of stop the automatic ways in which the reactivity
arises and we have more choice that show one choice is to do nothing and just to let it be as it is
another choice is to change gears and and be careful and not automatically
give into the desires and compulsions are there and
so so for the buddha in his teachings
because vedana is at this kind of door like like like the narrow neck of the
funnel that everything goes through to start paying attention to feeling tone
is a powerful way to develop mindfulness but also to discover freedom feeling tone pleasant
unpleasantness is mostly independent of our desires it's just kind of just the nature of things
i'll talk more about that tomorrow but what but the consequence of them how
desires get evoked in response to them that's what we're trying to discover our
freedom so there's no compulsion there can be a wise desire appropriate desire
but uh no desire that we're compelled by and um compulsion is
uh you know is the um antithesis of freedom
so um that was the introduction and uh we'll talk more about this the next few
days and in the meantime you might want to see and study and reflect and have
conversations with people about what's the role or the impact or the influence
that pleasant and unpleasant experiences have on you what kind of gut reaction do you have to
them and um and uh what what kind of wisdom do you have to them
and how does it work in your life so thank you very much