so this has been a week
of emphasizing the role of imagination
in buddhist practice and it's not
something that i'm making up by my own
that
the buddha himself in one way or the
other in a variety of ways
used imagination and evoked the
imaginary powers of people
when they engaged in this practice
and as the practice deepens there
is born a
capacity for a particular capacity for
imagination which in english we could
call maybe
vision and
and to have a vision of a possibility
and it's a vision that can seem very
clear and tangible and
immediate and maybe it even is
in a certain kind of way it's not
something which
is it physically tangible or physically
seen but with the mind's eye and
buddhism awakening is opening them
the eye of the dharma the eye that can
see
and have a vision of the potential for
freedom
or can see freedom
can see the peace and the freedom of the
mind
that's there to some degree and then has
a vision
for it becoming complete vision of it
expanding a vision of it touching the
places
where we're not yet free and this idea
of becoming a visionary using the
imagination
to to know a possibility that um
it's not it's not a fantasy it's based
on something real
but it's imagining the fulfillment of
that
so for example if i hold my hand in a
tight fist
i could release one finger and hold the
other fingers tight
and then um but then oh i think you know
it's possible now
i have a vision i see the potential
of opening the whole hand up and
relaxing it
and so it's a kind of a kind of an
imagination a vision of
a potential and it said sometimes in
buddhism that with the
that awakening is an act of vision a
seeing
or it awakens vision it awakens the
imagination
of something that's possible that then
becomes
the direction we go or the or what we
kind of
wholeheartedly put our life energy into
like this is important this
is valuable to live this way
and it doesn't mean we have to leave the
our world behind the regular world
behind
but rather when the clear enough vision
of the potential or what awakening is as
freedom of clinging is
we realize that it can be the foundation
for how we live our life
or the all income inc all-encompassing
uh
container or or approach for
everything we do so it isn't so much
that we have to
leave our life uh and it's
but it's rather it's to vision that it's
possible to live our life
freely and to wholeheartedly
enter our life with that as a guiding
principle
and this is a radical thing
and so um so it's not a compromising our
life necessarily but it's
bringing what's best in life freedom and
peace and compassion
as the container as the context as a
foundation so a vision
that's possible and then a decision even
a commitment
a vow this is how i want to live my life
so uh so all these things i've been
talking about this week have to do with
imagination
and imagination can be both
harmful can be debilitating
and it could be forward leading opening
they can help us grow and develop and to
be able to see those two apart is very
important
a few things about the word that the
buddha used words he used that i'm
translating as imagination
one of them is manyati and
the uh and that
is usually uh used for
acts of imagination which are
not helpful in fact bekabodi the great
translator
sometimes translates this word as
misconceived there's no
negative prefix in the word but it's
used in such a kind of
negative way in the suttas that it's
often you know can be
to misimagine or bad in that poor
imagination
and so at jackal the buddha used the
word the word
for a jackal that imagines itself
to be a lion
and uh and so you know
it's a misconceived oneself as a lion
the um
um so one of the very interesting places
where this word
um one imagines which has negative
connotations
is manyati uh it has to do with uh
identification
and uh there's a plenty of places in the
sutures where buddha emphatically talks
about
um the pro the problems people have
when they imagine and they
imagine an identity for themselves that
they are something
in relationship to other things so
imagining that they
are the same as the universe so the same
as the world
imagining that they are in the world
imagine the world is in them
imagining that they are distinct from
the world
and he uses this word manyati imagine
and if you really understand that and
it's often translated as conceive
which has some idea doesn't quite
capture the idea of imagination
and so rather than talking about the
self and identity that who i
am i'm this i'm that as a belief
which gets into philosophy and all that
the buddha is using the word
imagine and so it's not a philosophical
issue
but it's an issue of what we're doing
with our imagination
what are we constructing what are we
fantasizing about
and many of the problems around self
are not about truly exactly
what we are as a self whatever that is
but rather
how we imagine ourselves to be and uh
and then we have a whole different
understanding of this kind of
not self teaching there's a deci
for example there's a very common phrase
important to me myself and mine that's
used in the sutures
it's a little bit of mistranslation the
order of it but
but basically the same
and um and uh imagining that um
something is mine imagining that i i
have an identity
imagining there is a essential self the
buddha uses the word imagine
it doesn't say one believes in me myself
and mine
but one is something that we're
construing we're constructing we're
imagining
happening and so
uh part of meditation practice then is
to quiet and calm
this excessive over-imagination false
imagination misconstruing we do
and it's not questioning or or or
challenging any kind of philosophical
view
of self me myself and mine in these
particular teachings
and so we don't have to get involved
philosophically is there is there not a
self
where we get involved in meditation
practice is to
clarify let go of quiet
the imaginings that are occurring
and and so
so that's kind of manyati this imagining
is usually negative
the word that's more positive for
imagination
is has the word anupasati in it
and that's one of the central words for
mindfulness practice
it means in mindfulness practice to
observe
to see but it has the the prefix sum in
front of it so
some anupasati and
the context in which it's used in the
buddhas
is to we can understand it to be
imagination
of maybe of the form of visualization
so uh so the the similes of the
hindrances i taught free of the
hindrances i talked about a few days ago
to the buddha says visualizing oneself
as um no longer sick
visualizing oneself is no longer in debt
visualizing himself were no longer
enslaved um and so that visualizing has
a kind of richer
feeling sometimes in imagination and
and it touches into something deeper it
touches into something
more emotional more embodied more
tangible maybe in the mind's eye
it kind of helps us to fill out
something
and and that is i think one of the
functions
of two functions of this imagination or
visualization the buddha talks about
uses in practice
one is to give us a visceral kind of
embodied maybe
feeling or sense sense of what he's
talking about
that's not just uh explanations it's
you know more like poetry or something
that's evocative
and something that opens up and it
touches into
more dimensions of our life than just
words
it touches touches into our emotional
being
our kinesthetic being some of the
imagery imagery
are in action and movement flowing water
and now the the person working the lathe
or needing the
the water into the into the powder
and also it's um touches into memory
and associations we have with these
things and
and our capacity for imagination our
capacity for thought and thinking and so
we have here this movement support
in imagination this movement of becoming
unified
which means gathering together all our
different functions as human being
so that we're focused and present here
for the practice of meditation we're not
fragmented we're not divided
and we're not leaving any part of
ourselves out rather gathering together
all of ourselves to center and be here
and that we'll see we'll continue now
with the steps of anapanasati
on monday going on with
steps seven and eight and this
continues this process of gathering
together and settling and unifying
and we're supporting also the process of
also once the imagination has functioned
in useful way
to help that to settle as well not to
hold on to that
but to go to deeper states of
unification and calm
that at some point imagination
you know is no longer supportive for
so we'll start going into more deeply
into the mind next week
and and then we will
go on from there and
so thank you very very much and
uh someone asked yesterday i saw on the
chat at the end that they wanted to
see the the you know the
written form of the similes for the
for janna's and um and i said i would do
it and i
i still will do at some point and also i
can also maybe
uh post uh my translation of this
16 steps that we're going through and
once i've posted it i'll let you know
where it is and
hopefully i'll have time to do it over
the weekend
so thank you all very much and look
forward to our next time together