so it said
that the greatest health is nibana
nibana being liberation from greed
hatred and delusion
and uh to have this experience of
peace of the deep non-attachment
that is not nothing but rather
is feels like certain kind of
health healthfulness healthiness
that um that
is uh has a nourishment to it a deep
satisfaction to it a deep rightness to
it
and importantly uh it demonstrates to us
or reveals to us
the ways in which uh movements away from
that piece
uh are kind of are unsatisfactory moving
away from that piece
is dukkha is stressful or is
involves tension or involves um
you know sometimes
you know what the buddhist called dukkha
suffering
and um and it's very interesting to
kind of feel this in meditation
because in daily life there might be
good reason to be engaged actively in
the world and
have the mind and the body active and
engaged and
not so peaceful and sometimes daily life
it's actually quite beautiful to
be active and there's ways of acting
vigorously in the world that can feel
very peaceful or very
harmonious and engaging if there's no
resistance and no greed is part of it
but in meditation when things get very
quiet and still in a very vital
vibrant way the mind might begin to move
into some
uh distracted thought into some
feeling some direction of holding on
clinging to something
and we can see oh this doesn't this is
not so good i'm better off without it
the better alternative is the peace so
it's not a condemnation
or a rejection exactly of of uh
being agitated being distracted or
a reactivity against it it's just
knowing there's a better alternative
peace and so
as we learn to work with ill will
hatred aversion hostility
and really learn to recognize it
and learn how we get hooked to it how we
get attached to it
and how it itself is a kind of
attachment
to have hostility we're already attached
to something
and to see that and feel that in a clear
way
and then to put it down to let go
to go to the other side of it to find
that which is deeper
and to have confidence in that peace
this is a big part of dharma practice
and then and so there is
a possibility of living without any ill
will
any hostility and
any aversion any strong kind of
biased opposition to things and um
the um and this is a this is part of the
radical message of
the buddha the buddhism that there it is
possible to bring an
end to greed hatred and delusion
and and this is what the buddha
emphasized over and over again
it's not necessarily easy and for some
people greed hatred and delusion in
subtle forms desire and aversion
is so part and parcel of living a life
it's inconceivable to not have it
but it is possible to come to the end of
it
and and we're not diminished or less
because of it we're not less able to
take care of ourselves
it's a state of health and it's a in
that health there's a wisdom
there's deeper understanding and
and so it isn't just to become mindful
of aversion ill will
and learn in the mindfulness to hold it
spaciously
and openly and and non-reactively and
not get caught by it
that's very powerful to do that but
there's another step
and that is to let go of any tendency
to ill will to aversion the
the idea being that uh aversion
is um as i said earlier
is a form of attachment so if all you're
doing
is letting go of um
of your reactivity you're holding to it
but still allowing the aversion to be
there
um we haven't gone to the depths of
freedom so it's possible to let go
so um so some people
uh are suspicious of this message
idea of letting go of ill will
in a deep way uh it's us it might be you
know it seems like it's such an
important part of life the
way of protecting ourselves taking care
of what we need and things like that
but there uh there are motivations and
ways of living
powerfully that arise out of the peace
the absence of ill will and
one of the most common reference points
for this
uh or common uh
opposites of
ill will is good will is a radical
feeling of or attitude
of friendliness some people like to call
it love or kindness
and and not because we're acting it or
pretending or
or somewhat overriding everything else
in order to be kind
it's because it's it's though that is
what
wells up from the well springs within
when there's no aversion and to then
learn to live a life of good will
learn to live a life to meet
uh the challenges of life the injustices
of life the
the in a way that um
that we are um
um clearly expressing our good will
our well-wishing our kindness our
friendliness
and maybe don't get confused by this to
think that it's
for the sake of the other people
is for the sake of not losing
health here for you not losing
your capacity to be free
your capacity to be to let the best and
the fullest part of us
to be there and be present that can't be
present
if we have hostility or ill will or
version we become
then we become partial then we become
incomplete
and the deep letting go of practice
and the absence of greed hate and
delusion is a kind of coming into a
wonderful completion
and and so to not succumb to ill will
again
is tremendously beneficial for oneself
and so to come with good will and love
and have that as a reference point for
the world
and how we act um
it's maybe more for yourself sometimes
than it is for the benefit of others
but it can be both and so one of the
for the buddha one of the
consequence of this deep liberation from
ill will greed delusion
is a life of service is a life that
is naturally dedicated to the care
and the welfare of the world and i like
to believe that it's not because it's a
duty
but because it's the best thing going
it's
it's what allows the healthy expression
of the heart to ex to manifest itself in
the world
and what it means though is that that
expression of
goodwill of service of care
if it comes out of our own hearts it's
going to be expressed
in our own particular way
and there are an infinite number of ways
in which that gets expressed some of
them are just
i don't want to say just but some of
them are in forms of
caring for our immediate family
sometimes
caring for our immediate community
sometimes it's caring for
the communities around us in the bigger
way sometimes
it's uh situational and it depends and
it's all of the above
care can be different in different days
different months different years
where our attention goes where our
service and care goes
but to have that care and service
come from our peace and our care our
peace and our
freedom is one of the best things going
and it's one of the reasons why to
really
have a deep study of hatred and get to
the bottom of it
so thank you