so hi hello and formally welcome to happy hour now that it's
being recorded for audio dharma so so for the theme of our practice
together today i'd like to invite us to explore um
in another dimension of meta which is um
fierce meta this fierce it's energetic meta can feel soft
and soothing and tender and calming and they can also feel fierce you can
also feel strong um and energetic they're different ways and
and um for example in the metasutta in the metasuta in the line where
it says even as a mother protects with her life her child her only child
so with a boundless heart should one cherish all living beings
radiating kindness over the entire world so i want to bring your attention to
this metaphor even as a mother protects with her life her child her
only child so that that image of a mother
protecting her child to me that can also bring up
well there with metaphors of course there are a lot of different things that metaphors can
can bring up and and and refer to and conjure up one thing that this metaphor
can conjure up um is the fierceness if if a mother
is protecting her only child with her love her life i suspect there will be a sense of
fierceness is that love it's the love is big it's huge it's powerful and there's a fierceness about
it so can we conjure up that same sense of love for ourselves
for the only child that is us our inner child the child that
we take for granted we we beat up usually you're not good enough you're
not working hard enough not not this being that is
us what if we had this sense of energetic powerful this mother protecting
with her life her child her only child so both the sense of love
meta care being profound but also the sense of
fierceness it's there's a strength to this powerfulness there's a powerfulness to
this love a powerfulness so can we explore that for ourselves
what does that feel like if we explore that for ourselves does that bring us
more energy more aliveness more recognition of our true nature
of the goodness within so let's explore let's explore together and
see what we discover in this way of practice being scientists of our own minds
so so with that is the preamble let's let's settle
let's arrive
landing landing arriving
in this body in this moment in time
well with a sense of uprightness whether you're sitting or lying down
can there be a sense of uprightness
a sense of integrity in the spine and the body posture
noticing perhaps that you're uplifted
uplifted vertebrae by vertebrae
if there is an invisible string connected to the top of your head
ah giving you [Music] an uplift
you don't have to try you don't have to force in fact your body can relax your muscles
can settle in this sense of integrity this uprightness
is maintained on its own with this invisible string
you're both uplifted energetically
the breath the aspiration [Music] uplifting you
while connected and deeply rooted in the earth to the earth
feeling the touch points of your feet
your legs your sit bones your bottom connected
earthed deeply rooted
as if you both have wings
uplifted and you have roots deep into the ground
the breath nourishing nourishing to natural breath
uplifting energizing
energizing especially around your heart center your chest middle of your chest
enlivening awakening
both awakening and soothing healing at the same time
both energized and calmed in this moment
rooted and uplifted with the breath
the earth element rooting connecting
settling the air element uplifting
settling and driving for a few more minutes before we turn
our attention to metta
now continuing to feel embodied
connected to the earth through the to the earth
feet said bones legs
while uplifted the spine uplifted
open with aspiration
both figuratively and literally aspiration to breath filling
the body
energizing now bringing to mind if you would
you felt sense an image of yourself of this being that is you
at a younger age
any age is fine might be that there is a photograph or
an age that you can really connect to
to parent to re-parent this younger version of ourselves
to protect to love to care for
bringing this image this felt sense
connecting taking time to connect in ways
that work for you in loving ways
that work for you
maybe you have a vivid image of a photograph
or how this child moves talks maybe plays
with their favorite toys or
or activities whatever it might be connecting connecting
conjuring up their image
and as if just as it is said in the menta
even as a mother protects with her life her child her only child
as if this child this younger version of you
in this moment in time is your child
your only child to love to protect
to cherish to soothe
the comfort
and as the mother as the parent
is the parent of this child
as the parent you have more resources
you're stronger you're capable as you breathe and you feel
the energizing of the heart center your heart with care compassion love energy
both a tender and fierce love for this child
protective protective
connecting at first with image with felt sense
holding protecting sense of uprightness and energy
strength fierceness
before this child
especially if the child is hurting in some way
either is hurt
or maybe ill if that feels relevant
feeling feeling your strength the strength the power of your love your
meta this body well rooted into the earth
your breath energizing and holding caring for this child
in this moment your only child
radiating meta radiating
radiating fears loving matter
protective protective loving meta
and if you like to add phrases of mitta you're welcome to
or use your own phrases i'll offer some alternatives
the traditional typical phrases of mitta
may you be safe from inner and utter harm
may you be happy
may you be healthy may you have ease
or alternatively i love you
i care for you i'm here for you
you are loved you are cherished
you are okay
you are beloved
whatever phrases work for you
to share to shine your protective
fierce parental meta
for this younger self
you are welcome to continue with your younger self
or see if your mind your heart would like to treat yourself your present day so
as your child your only child no difference see what your heart and
mind need in this moment
and if you do choose to move to your present-day cell
try the phrases of meta if you wish with i
may i be safe
may i be happy may i be healthy
may i have ease it can also stay with you feel free to
experiment see what works for you
expression of fears energetic meta for yourself
and what if the one loving and being loved
the fierce powerful meta-filled parent
and the child the self are one and the same
they meld they merge what if
see what might arise
and now shining this bright light a fierce meta
shining outwards it touches you first
it shines out
touching all those you care for all those you know and you don't know
radiating radiating kindness over the entire world
spreading upwards to the skies and downwards to the depths
outwards and unbounded
may all beings wake up to their true nature
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you thank you for your practice everyone
so
so you have a few minutes for reflections you can either type them in chat
have you discovered what you noticed questions comments or raise your hand bill
please hello hi hi i i got tripped up
over the word fierce and it just raised connotations in my mind and it's like
once i i i started to think about that i i couldn't put it down again
and so i didn't do that well i without making this too long a story i
think in one of earlier sessions you said that you could have meta in terms of like
falling asleep and calming and i related that i did not experience that because of the level of
excitement ferocity to me my mind indicates intensity excitement and therefore not
sleep i i'm sorry my mind is hung up on this but i just can't can't get past that sorry yeah so so
what i'm hearing is a couple of things one is that this the word fears was in the uh
you have connotations with it and and the mind got tripped up with that so with that what i would suggest is is
use a word that works for you bill see what works for you protective you know i was trying to
offer some alternatives protective there's this protective loving image
if that works for you use that so tune out the word fierce and also what i'm hearing is that that
brought up some energy for you so so if you sometimes fall asleep with
the very tender soothing calm gentle peaceful meta this was an energizing
so so um and part of that you're chalking up the
energizing to the confusion of the fears and also part of it could be that this practice and i'd love to hear from
others is is more energizing is really awakening
this is not the type of meta that makes you fall asleep it's really enlivens you you feel
powerfully loving and so that's the aspect i think you're talking about right yes i
think so so you're saying there's different types of meta yes that's exactly what i'm trying to
say not all meta needs to be sleep inducing that's exactly right okay i'm good thank
you that's exactly right we were exploring a different kind of meta tonight
that's exactly it it's a well if you don't like the word fierce it's it's an energetic energizing protective
powerful meta maybe the word powerful apparent that's really lovingly powerful like a lioness
powerful loving yeah that's exactly it bill you got it
you got it you're welcome you're so welcome so um let's see
i see reflection i see fred's hand i'll ask you to unmute in the moment
here yes there while i also read from nicholas was metta for an intentional pun or did
i miss here oh my god that's hilarious that was not intentional but i love it metta four
i love it meta four that's good that's good nicolas good catch uh neil says that was lovely the image
of loving and protecting my younger self was so dear oh that is so touching thank you
thank you for that that is dear that is dear neil thanks for sharing that
and friendly greetings from ireland from kirkel thank you nikki and sanga so nice you're
joining gurgal and graham also and tulip and others royal for joining from belgium
we have a a parallel sangha joining us on youtube very sweet so please fred
i found that very powerful i was able to
envision myself as a teenager with real clarity uh and perhaps
because i i had just finished walking around lake merritt with an old friend uh
that i knew as a teenager that we sort of rekindled a friendship during the pandemic
but i could see myself as he probably saw me when we were kids and i was able to embrace that
self with all the parental energy that i would want to bring to it
not particularly fierce that didn't really feel quite the word but adult and protective and i could
feel my younger self confident in the embrace of my older
self and getting a lot of soldiers from my my presence and advice and
encouragement thank you fred i am so touched and buoyed by that ah
beautiful thank you and protective i appreciate this this trust this trust
of this this protective parental um care and love that that you connected
with and named thank you yeah great
that's great so ah okay lovely
lovely ah gargal says this fierce lioness love goes nicely with my latin
blood brazilian and ireland here oh that's sweet i love all these metaphors as uh as nicholas pointed out
i love it so dear ones let's turn to practice
in small groups together with this protective loving um energetic
energetic meta i think that's what i'm trying to really tune into and for me there is
this sense of really feeling awakened energized there's this
powerful meta that that can shine onto the world from this practice
the other practice too from the gentle soft what um bill was calling kind of like
the sleepy method i like to call it the gentle method but also this this this energetic meta can also be very
powerful this power of this kindness radiating over the earth so just tuning into these different
frequencies it's not one thing it's not one thing let us surprise ourselves by the capacity
of the human heart and mind every time we practice instead of just doing the same thing may
you be happy maybe i'll be let us surprise ourselves with just this capacity
with humanity so so with that let's join each other
and explore and speak about what we discovered support each other in this exploration
in this experiment of being human sangha practice is so precious
so i'm creating the rooms now and let's start with 15 seconds of
silent meta okay all right here we go
okay all right welcome back everyone we've got a couple we have a couple of
minutes um for reflections what did you discover practicing together especially in sangha
if you haven't um reflected commented in a while you're especially welcome to share your
reflections so why did you notice what worked what was challenging it's
all good sharing your practice for the benefit of the sangha
and if you want to raise your zoom hand that's better option because i won't say your physical
hand if you raise it oh jerry says i like my adult life much
better than my childhood oh yeah yeah and it's and it's wonderful to be able
to reparent ourselves in this way yeah it's it's very powerful practice
actually this protective parenting re-parenting very powerful we can fill our own
cup and hence not need others to do that
says same same for me jerry oh marianne says my 13 year old self was
very happy to get the intention oh that's sweet it's very sweet and
[Music]
i just want to share that i was able to um to revisit
the moment that i was so scared and when i was young and when i was a child
that i really wanted to have some someone who's protected me but i never had it maybe i had at some point but
most of the time listen and i was able to go back that moment
and i was just parenting myself which is i was doing it before but
this time was like oh my gosh it's just like such a crap practice it
was just precious moment and um i actually shared with one of those um in a small group and the
other person also shared his experience and i just want that person's child like when it was
child i really wanted to hug that person that that gifts
so much and it just brings me a tears yeah thank you for sharing this video oh
i yeah the both reflections one is that you know how how powerful it is to actually to connect
to these tender moments in our in our past when we wanted protection and and to even going it feels like
going back in time and offering that to ourselves and also being able to see the child in each other there's
something precious and beautiful that the heart opens up the heart opens up
as you're talking you wanted to to hug the younger version of this this person is yeah
beautiful thank you thank you for that thank you for listening yeah and morgan says protective meta
could be a way to fight back from self-judgments imposed by society for example
internalized isms yes yes right on morgan yeah very very astute
observation this is really powerful practice for self-judgment
because there's the sense of protective ourselves protecting this part of us that's
oh that's hurting so very powerful practice very powerful
practice um i have more questions for you but it is seven o'clock so
let's end let's end on as i always like to end by thanking
you for your practice thank you for showing up and cultivating
your heart your mind for the benefit of yourself and all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings
be free
thank you