so monday was
self-respect
tuesday was self-understanding
wednesday was not harming oneself
and today the topic is benefiting
oneself
and
you know the buddha taught for the
benefit and welfare of others
he wanted us he wanted benefits for
people that's what his whole career his
whole dedication was for people's
welfare and well-being
and
and to be a follower of the buddha is
then to take those teachings in
so that we can better ourselves so that
we can for our own welfare and happiness
and for our benefit
and um
and uh this is something that i was a
little bit slow to come to in my
buddhist practice because of maybe
practicing in zen where this was not
emphasized
in fact maybe it was even discouraged
that when one would one would practice
for kind of a self-benefit of
experiencing happiness joy well-being
and
but somehow this sense of well-being
found me as i kept practicing
and i've come to really appreciate how
powerful it is to have a sense of
well-being
it's a kind of reconditioning
of our psyche of our
neurons of our muscles
reconditioning of our mind and heart
and not all of us have had great
conditioning in our life
that so the influences on how we think
how we understand ourselves understand
the world
how we feel
are not necessarily
that which is brings welfare and
happiness and well-being
and
and so rather than
and so one of the ingredients for
developing a really healthy sense of
well-being
is not so much doing it directly
but rather indirectly
by creating the conditions for
well-being
for
benefiting ourselves
and
classically in buddhism such a
talk would always refer to the
importance of living an ethical life
that if we can live ethically
and then
that can be nourishing for ourselves
that can that itself is a form of
nourishment as form of inspiration if it
was a form of goodness
but that's not automatically so for many
of us
and uh so for our ethical behavior to
know to be nourishing
uh we have to appreciate the underlying
goodness
of a dedication of living
wholesomely living ethically
so it might be hard to actually do it
but
but to
live one's life with that dedication
with that love for
an ethical wholesome skillful life
that is a powerful thing
and
and to appreciate that intention that
commitment
not so much that you have to do it
intellectually
but rather
ideally that that desire that wish that
movement towards living an ethical life
is itself coming from a place that of
inner goodness of inner well-being inner
something it touches something inside of
us that has a rightness to it
wholesomeness to it
and it's that wholesomeness we begin
discovering inside
that
the practice can grow and develop
to sit and many people don't discover
this through being ethical first but
rather through meditation
that the meditation
is kind of first a deconditioning
by relaxing and not being so caught up
in our mind streams of thoughts and
reactions we're beginning to um
take some of the power behind some of
our old conditioning some of the old
habits of mind that we have
and so there's a kind of a
deconditioning process and the calmer we
become stiller we become a meditation
the quieter the mind becomes in
meditation the more it's actually a
deconditioning process letting go of old
habits that the mind that are maybe not
serving us
many many ways in which we have
rumination and
way people think it's actually unhealthy
it undermines us it debilitates us it
drains us because if the thinking is so
negative or stressful
and so as the mind gets quieter and
stiller
there's a deconditioning process
and then it can be replaced with
wholesome thinking wholesome desires
nice ways of being
or to say it differently as we get
calmer and more subtle some people there
discover
um maybe first as a little seed a
glimmer
a feeling of this this if it feels
wholesome this feels this goodness in
this there's a
happiness there's a sense of well-being
that comes with just sitting here
where just being alive is enough just
sitting here breathing
and letting go of all the past
conditioning or the reactivities of the
mind
a mind doesn't have to be
fed by
the heart does not be fed by external
stimuli other people things doing things
recreational opportunities tv shows food
drink all kinds of things the mind can
be content and happy
the heart can be content and happy
without searching and wanting and
getting outside it's almost as if if we
let go of all the conditioning
the harmonious flow of energy within the
harmonious flow of the heart and the
mind
has a has a feeling of health in it
healthiness and goodness and joy and
happiness
so to start getting a feeling of that
from meditation from being from the
ethical impulse
the
and then to appreciate that glimmer of
well-being that that which is nourishing
within that which is wholesome
that which
has a quality of happiness and goodness
in it to appreciate that and value it
enough that we stay close to it
and a very important moment can happen
in buddhist practice
where
some quality
of inner some good quality of inner
inner life
and i say it that vaguely because
different people identify different
things but something that feels a good
quality of heart quality of mind
is experienced
and
one begins to see
the places where there's a choice
whether to leave that behind by getting
into a reactive mind again
or coming back and staying close to it
and nourishing and supporting it
not giving it up staying close and
allowing it to grow it is like a seed
that we want to like like a gardener to
nourish that seed to water it to
fertilize it
to um protect it so that that's that uh
delicate and fragile little plant that's
the sprout
can grow and develop
and so this point comes in buddhist
practice where we have a reference point
for this some kind of inner well-being
and uh and then the opportunity is there
to stay close to it
not uh tight not
fending off the world and shutting down
from the world and becoming a hermit
but
is just staying close and living our
life from that place going into the
world being with our people but have
that as a reference point
and one of the ways to have a reference
point is to have it this
is what i'm going to do now
undermine detract
from
this ner this nourishing place i've
discovered
or is it going to enhance it or develop
it or just keep it you know keep it
steady
it requires mindfulness it requires
a willingness to keep paying attention
to it and come back to it and stay close
and in the process we learn a lot a lot
about ourselves we learn a lot about the
subtle ways and not so subtle ways that
we lose that that we kind of
bypass it the way we pick up stress and
tension in our body and mind and heart
and
and that's a very important learning
that we have to learn that
so rather than feeling
you know bad about oneself that one gets
stressed or tense or reactive
from that nourishing place is okay here
this is what i have to work with
this is what i have to understand and
learn with i had to see this so that i
could find another way and find the
places of choice to not
give into that too easily
and so
and so we're looking for where's the
well-being
and then to do the things in our lives
that create the conditions for it to be
there
so rushing and being in a hurry
is not conducive to cultivating this
inner well-being
and just that one thing
to dedicate a life plan plan ahead plan
your days
consider your priorities
maybe
do less things
so that you can stay close to what is
nourishing and supportive for this inner
growth
if we're rushing around into too many
things that cannot be there it's kind of
like becomes eclipsed and it doesn't
have a chance to grow
and
initially that might seem like it might
seem like the other things you're doing
rushing around to do are more important
than our own welfare and well-being
but
over time you'll see that this is
probably the most important treasure you
have most valuable thing you have is
more important
than money and
relationships and jobs and
all kinds of activities you might be
doing
not to dismiss the importance of those
things and to the importance of
having them
but to not lose
not not
be involved to them at the expense of
losing
this connection to what benefits
ourselves the connection is inner
goodness this nourishment
and
and the paradox is that as this inner
goodness or nourishment or inner benefit
grows
our relationship to the external world
improves dramatically
and it becomes richer and more valuable
rather than losing the external world
the inner goodness touches the some of
the best qualities of the external world
so um
so benefiting oneself we're allowed to
benefit oneself not only we're allowed
to do it but we're encouraged to do it
in a way that's not selfish the way
that's not but that really nourishes and
supports the freedom the joy the
happiness the goodness the well-being
that uh can can can
flow from within
so um
the buddha
taught
for the benefit and welfare and
happiness
of all beings
including you
and so
it's okay for you
to
pursue your own well-being
you you're doing so you're you're
following the buddha's wishes
may you find
great well-being that you thrive in
well-being in dharmic well-being
may the dharma bring you much joy and
happiness
thank you