so hello to everyone from redwood city here at the inside meditation center
and uh i would like to uh do this meditation beginning of this
meditation a little bit differently than usual and in that i would like to um
do a little guided imagery to begin using an analogy that i very i've used many times for some of
you and i'm very fond of and uh um
just to take a couple of minutes if you would just you know maybe you can be comfortable if you'd like maybe in meditation posture
and close your eyes and and maybe just to settle in just breathe
a few moments maybe breathe deeply a few moments relax your body
settle in a bit
and then to imagine yourself sitting
against the trunk of a tree maybe or some other comfortable place next to
a river and perhaps you've
have a day off maybe you've gone for a nice walk there's nothing you need to do and
things are taken care of well enough in your life that you just sit there in a
comfortable afternoon weather and maybe in the shade or
and uh watch the river watch the current and the flow of the
water the movements of little wavelets
you're watching the flow and ongoing and it's in some ways ever changing
and forever changing a constant constancy of inconstancy change the flow
sometimes some leaves are floating on the river and float down along
sometimes the twig sometimes a boat
sometimes a duck floats down the river
and you're just observing gazing at this just taking everything in but not really
studying anything not staring at anything just relaxed and
present and you let your thoughts do what they do there's no censoring yourself
but there's also no big involvement with your thoughts and particular interest in them and because
everything feels good and easy relaxed just as nice just nice to be
here gazing at the river
and this idea of just sitting observing watching gazing
gently relaxedly at some point in meditation
when we're established well enough
in the present moment we've kind of done what needs to be done
and we can just sit back and allow the practice to unfold
by by observing watching allowing
ourselves to be aware of all the changing phenomena in our
body the river of life that is a constantly
shifting and changing panorama of sensations
perceptions thoughts feelings even if something stays for a while
you might try um
to just stay and watching the flow
and one of the places to do that is in your breathing
the breathing there is kind of like a
kind of like in in the way the river is it's a constant
flow of inconstancy in that each in-breath comes and goes
flowing into the out breath
there's a beginning of the in-breath middle and an end
the beginning middle and end of the exhale
and all that can be felt as sensations in the body so it's not so much
observing the breath as it is observing
the kaleidoscope of changing sensations in your body as you breathe
settling back relaxing as if you're leaning against a tree
watching a river observing
how the sensations are breathing
go on and on they arise and they pass
some of them spark into existence for a moment and then vanish
like a little wavelet on a river that is there for a moment and then
returns to the river
and to settle further into this watching breathing
take a few moments to relax your body more softening all over
as if you're relaxing the whole body in towards the breathing
relaxing so that the body becomes a soft foundation
for a soft
river of changing sensations
and the more relaxed the body is the more the body's
flows and changes and things come and go arise and pass
the more tense we are we have the illusion of things being tight and constant continuous
relaxing softening the body settling in
and then again
gazing kindly on your breathing
being sensitive to the aspects of breathing that are
constantly changing the sensations of breath that come and go that one morphs into
the other
relaxing the mind the more relaxed the mind is the more it
can be part of the flow of the river
the more tense the mind is the more it tends to produce the illusion of
constancy of something of being unchanging
softening the thinking mind resting in the mind's ability
to observe to perceive to sense experience
centered on your breathing all around it is also change
the changing fluxing sensations of your body
the changing experiences that come into awareness
sometimes this sometimes that
wherever there is change changing sensations experience
relax with it open with it
allow it as if you're allowing it
to relax you open you further
as if this anything that changes that comes and goes
freeze the mind further as the mind lets it pass through
so
change is an attribute of the present moment
the present moment itself is constantly changing
in more ways than we usually notice
settle back and observe how it is that the present moment is a
constantly shifting and changing phenomena represented most by the breathing
the body's experience of change as you breathe
relax into the river of change
float on all the changing aspects of the present moment
sometimes we're resting in the change observing it
and sometimes we're swept away in it our thoughts are also always changing
even if even if the same theme persists and sometimes we get carried away in the
flood of thoughts
and the idea is to come back to the
to on the ground of the body and from there observe the change
in the present
sitting quietly observing change
gaze upon all things kindly
to the best of your ability in a simple maybe even
unremarkable way gaze upon all things kindly
and the ability to do so has a lot to do with the ability to be
confident in resting in awareness
feeling safe to rest here in awareness
in this print from the safety of being aware
to gaze upon all things kindly
to gaze upon all change in a compassionate way
those who understand how things are constantly changing
are less surprised that things go and things come that
things change and being less surprised
there is more space to be kind
to have good will and generosity and compassion for this world of ours
may it be that our meditation practice together
allows us to enter into the world with gift bestowing hands
enter into the world
with a orientation that's kind and supportive and friendly
compassionate we have these beautiful qualities of
heart that can flow more easily the more we
rest in change may all beings
be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings
be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be
free
uh