oh okay all right formally started
so hi welcome to happy hour
lovely to be with you after two weeks of being away and on retreat and practicing
and and um yeah i'm i'm happy my heart is at peace i missed
you i was glad to be gone and i'm glad to be back so so for today's practice
um so many themes so many things i've been sitting in and thinking oh this is what
i can bring to happy hour this so so instead of overloading us with various practices
i want to offer actually something that is inspired from from the the holiday
that's celebrated today in the us if you're in the u.s today is memorial day a day of
honoring remembering those who have dedicated their efforts
their lives and for for
for us in this way so so to make it more personal i wanted to invite us to actually
consider doing this method stepping into another dimension we usually do it with people
who are alive here and there sometimes we we do meta
with those who have passed away and canonically canonically uh
practice of meta uh it is said that it is best not to do it with people who have
passed away for two reasons and i'll tell you and then i'll tell you why we're going to kind of change away
from that so canonically it can bring up grief if if it's very fresh if if the
challenge is very new so if one is new to the practice to avoid
someone who's passed away the second reason canotically one stays away from
someone who's deceased passed away is because the practice of meta loving kindness is
also a concentration practice where the mind can get very still and can get
into absorption what's called states of absorption stillness and it is said that if your
object of love is someone who's deceased the mind doesn't get absorbed can still
have a lot of love and really a lot of cultivation happens
but that aspect of absorption with jhanas will not happen so
classically in in for the you know for those who are interested in the visual maga and you know the abidama
those teachings that's why it is that avoid people someone who's passed away however
um someone who's been on our lives who we're indebted to we feel love for and there
isn't much grief there's just a sense of love there's a sense of love
so so the invitation if that is available to you and if not then choose someone who's alive for you who you feel
indebted for but this being memorial day we're going to step into our memory
we're going to step into another dimension of goodness another demand another
dimension which is again when we what i mean by that is when we do meta usually like may you be
healthy may you be well it's the sense of here and now this
physical being where has entry into a dimension of oh just sharing love sharing love as goodness
as gratitude as generosity as appreciation so this that's what i mean by this other
dimension it's not so much physical it's just a gift of generosity gift of the heart
and who knows maybe who feel in this dimension there it's bi-directional it's not just one
directional of giving love but one of our receiving love
being loved from the beyonds so exploring spoil it's all about a
cultivation of good will love and and seeing the
finding or meeting discovering aspects of
our heart are experienced that maybe we're not familiar with yet
and it looks like my camera just failed okay let's try that again
let's unhook and re-hook so seems like after two weeks of being away
there's some technical glitches okay let's try that again here we go oh well all good so
tell you what let's start our practice while i figure out this this problem so let's get into our
meditation posture there we go let's get into our meditation posture
ah and landing landing landing into our bodies
landing in this moment
landing into our hearts
landing into a breath
letting go letting go of words of thoughts landing into
silence
allowing the rhythm of the breath
flowing flowing on its own flowing in and out on its own
letting the flow the rhythm of the breath
be calming soothing
nothing to do nowhere to go
but just to sit and be breathed
for a few minutes
so
the in-breath the outer lower abdomen
as if the whole body is being breathed and with each breath
getting calmer settling settling more deeply settling
[Music] landing
melting arriving the thoughts
sadly
and if you find the mind is wandering getting agitated it's okay it's all
right come here sweetie it's okay
come here land sit with me
let yourself be breathed let yourself have gentleness and kindness with
your mind befriending your mind and heart
you're training and gentleness with yourself
now if your heart would like to stay would like to stay with
just breathing with gentleness that's okay
and if you like
to invite someone ever so gently ever so gently as if
you're inviting them into your space of solitude and peace
inviting their memory their presence ever so gently not pumping out
a doubles but just a gentle invitation to this person who served you
cared for you maybe loved you
or maybe it was of some benefit to you as a benefactor in some
way
maybe they're no longer in your lives or maybe they still are see what works best for you maybe a
teacher maybe a teacher you've never met
be really inspired by by their writing their words their talks
ever so gently inviting this being
into your heart space
it could also be a pet i forgot to say whoever feels like
their benefactor to you
and in this heart space
just sitting with them with appreciation
with every breath silently you're sitting with them actually just every breath
worthlessly as you breathe it feels like every breath communicates
your appreciation
perhaps feeling every breath entering and exiting the middle of your heart your heart
center connecting connecting with your heart
let your body be soft and relaxed
and each breath just simply communicates
appreciation
gratitude generosity of heart however it feels
right
maybe love is what feels appropriate in this space
you
so
r
do
if the being you have chosen is still alive and
stay in the space
but if they have passed away if you wish you're welcome to try the
next invitation try it on precise
now just as they are they've been invited they're an image
in the space of your mind your heart your heart mind
let yourself let there be an image of you
maybe a younger version of you that enters the space space of heart
mind
and could the present you have a sense of appreciation
for both this being you've chosen the object of your meta your
appreciation your love
as well as this younger version of yourself who's relating to them
to see how metta wants to express itself
in this space with these beings
do
you
and now can there be a sense of
receiving appreciation for you from this being that you are today
for your intentions for you cultivating goodness
by the being [Music] by your benefactor and by a younger
version of you
if you find criticism coming up as if you don't deserve it
you don't have to get in your own way these are just thoughts of criticism don't believe
them your mind can turn arrows into flowers
just as buddha's mind did the night of his enlightenment
arrows thrown by mara were transformed into flowers because
his mind and loving kindness
and can there be a sense of meta being given being received and clear who's giving
who's receiving is being in the field of meta all around all three of you
and if you find that other benefactors show up in the space
it's okay
to give them appreciation love and to receive
and if not they don't show up that's okay too
and for the last moment dropping this idea in
dropping in the idea that this met us love
it's not about you it's not about you at all
how good you're at it how hard it is how much your mind is wandering it's not about you at all
it's an act of service to just offer it up to just
offer it up offer your heart up
notice if something lets go something is released with this offering
c
may we all find peace and joy
in offering our hearts
thank you all thank you so much for your practice
so
like to welcome any reflections any insights any questions any
complaints you like to share you can erase your zoom hand
because i may not see your physical hand or you can type it in chat if it's typed to me privately i won't
say your name if it's typed to everyone i will read your name out loud
what was this like for you what did you discover in this practice anything that was new
and interesting in your own heart
[Music] you are welcome carolyn on youtube
i'll wait for you and i'll share as as maybe as you're typing or and
i'll share with you that towards the end as i was practicing seemed like a lot of diseased
diseased benefactors were showing up they just wanted to come and share their love and be loved it
just became a party so i wondered if that would that happened for anyone too
so so violet please
hi um i had a question about receiving appreciation um
yeah when you did the switch from like receive just receiving from the other people um
so i was looking at a teacher from high school and then my high school self and then there were like the three
of us in the room and then i was perspective shifting to me being my high school self looking at my
older self and then this um male teachers and it was like this mom dad figure so
sweet yeah it was really really touching yeah yeah it was really nice but and
then it's like um yeah
it's hard yeah it's hard to receive and it's hard to feel like um
like when there's like love on offer and somehow it's like our hearts like aren't big enough for it or not like
quite able to be totally soothed by it like that feeling of like oh there's this love coming at me but it's not
quite enough to like soothe me or comfort me or like that feeling of never being enough um does that go away
yeah good question yeah let's let's uh thanks for bringing that because that is
so so common violet what you're talking about is not uncommon at all which is why i usually bring in
something about when i offer ask for the switch and say hey if there's criticism or
like i don't deserve this that because what you're talking about is so so common and they're sometimes
different things that kind of get in the way so if it's okay let's let's hang on
hang around for a moment and see in this case what what is the conception conceptual
uh way of conceiving that oh it's never enough or it's not enough there's something there
so so coming back to this beautiful beautiful image practice that you brought up that
the younger version of yourself was giving you metta is that the or described to me that
who's um i so i was looking from the perspective of the younger self so i was
17 receiving meta from 26 year old violet and this teacher uh-huh yeah oh okay so the 17 year old
was receiving yeah yeah okay and it was the 17 year old was saying that that's not enough that's that's just is
that it was like or was it 26 year old i mean from either
perspective it would be from either yeah it would be either i see okay okay so so the so from either perspective and
then the sense is not landing because it's not enough to soothe or i don't deserve it or
or what is this thought that running around that's coming up kind of um it's
like i guess it just feels fleeting or like maybe i am feeling it but it feels
fleeting maybe that's what it is like it doesn't feel stable or reliable
okay okay okay so so in what you're describing i'll invite
i invite you to be bring a little bit of investigation there
to see because it might be touching but it might be kind of like pushed away or something that's
happening in that moment when it's coming that is kind and see what what is
happening on the receiving side bring a little bit of investigation there and it'll become more clear to you
what the feeling conceptualization is that is not letting it really land and be seeped
in whereas it feels fleeting there's something happening there that the mind is quite seeing mind is curious about but
hasn't quite is not stable enough to see do you see what i'm pointing to
like what is making it sort of just bounce off exactly exactly be curious about it next time
and you're welcome to send me email if you like and can follow up does that sound okay for
now as an investigation yeah something to be seen there thank you violence it's lovely and
i'm so inspired by what you described that sounds so juicy and lovely beautiful
thank you for your practice let's see peggy says very sweet and
compassion for times ways when love was difficult to manifest thank you peggy jerry says it was super
to direct kindness to a very kind person i ended up feeling as is extraordinary
warmth and relaxation lovely and carolyn says i sat with the indigenous children
found buried around canadian residential schools ah i am new to this practice this is
what came as i sat oh thank you carolyn thank you for bringing them in yeah
practice of compassion yeah and someone has raised i don't know
their name says iphone so yes please
i mean actually outside it might be a little noisy but um i just cried
i just cried especially thinking about benefactor who doesn't exist i mean live no longer
who's been my mentor um to teach me
um ask for what i want and go for it
and who showed me there is another big world that you can dive into
and that's why i'm here i mean i'm i'm from korea and i came here about 20 years ago
and i think that in a way i think i i'm successful um
[Music] and i feel like he was right there it's just so much appreciation about him and then
you cannot seem so proud of me
i hear a lot of love i hear a lot of love both ways and i hear
much more love and appreciation there is tenderness there is it you know there are tears and the
tears doesn't don't sound like grief to me they sound like joy is separation there's a tenderness
in the heart that could be expressed in tears and thank you for sharing that
this bi-directional beautiful love and appreciation gratitude for your
benefactor thank you so much for bringing that in i'm just oh my goodness i'm just
crying on the street it sounds like they're joyous beautiful
tears yeah thank you thank you thank you so much
thank you and neil says thank you too he says thank you
so dear all let's uh turn given that time is flying let's turn
our attention to practicing for a brief period in small groups together
okay everyone welcome back the rooms are closed so we have about a minute for
any um reflections might have come up from the groups please don't be shy
ariana oops didn't mean to hit leave room that happened [Laughter]
[Music] any reflections any any other insights
that came up either oh jeff please
oh hey everybody happy memorial day um i just wanted my insights i'll share was
that sometimes relationships end it's like just the natural course of life is relationships
sometimes end and rather than having it be this bitter angry experience of blame and it's your
fault no it's your fault there's a way in which it can just be like observing the ending of a relationship
with love and with acceptance but it's really really hard to do it
that way it's much more common to end it with anger and pointing fingers and stuff so
that's what i learned today oh beautiful beautiful i am so touched up that's
that's such a beautiful insight in in in the way of refraining
that you know of course and and maybe one thought is each relationship
is a gift and maybe it's an impermanent gift for a period of time and just really focusing
on the gift that it is for that time that it is and and with meta and love and
appreciation so focusing on that because we have a choice on what we focus on
so thank you for bringing that in that's a beautiful note to end on so thank you all for your practice thank
you for coming to happy hour cultivating your heart your mind for the benefit of all beings may all
beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you