so there has a
has been a strong tendency in the west i
think
to present the buddha's teachings in a
fairly rational way
and to emphasize the the
empirical nature of it and it's really
about seeing things as they are
in a direct way and and
in doing so sometimes we left behind
or go unnoticed the tremendous degree in
which the buddha
and the buddhist early buddhist
tradition is using its
using imagination using creativity of
images and ideas and imagination
to support the teachings but not just
the teachings
but to provide us with a uh
a different reference point for both the
teachings and the practice
than simply ideas rational ideas
logical ideas that
the buddha uses lots of similes
lots of poetry lots of images lots of
little stories
all of which touch into um
other dimensions of our inner life than
our rational cognitive understanding
and it touches into our emotional life
our kinesthetic life our
motivational life our that part of it
can be
inspired can be gladdened um
it uh ties into our memory and our
associations
and um so all these capacity and
thinking as well
all these different uh faculties that we
have
get touched get awakened get somehow
brought into into the field of
our dharma relationship with dharma
practice
and this contributes the sense of
unification
that is samadhi cultivating samadhi
developing samadhi is really an
important part
in fact the buddha said that to see
things as they are
cultivate samadhi and samadhi is
unification
and unification is the is the bringing
together of all our faculties
together in a kind of whole working
dynamic working of the whole to really
be in harmony that everything's in
harmony
so using the imagination
is a means to evoke that and elicit that
in support of the meditation practice or
support of this freedom
and um it is um
so it has to be done of course carefully
it can be overdone
and certainly people use their
imagination for all kinds of things
which are not
healthy or appropriate for dharma
practice to spend a lot of time in
fantasy
and having a feeling of uh you know
the delusions of grandeur of delusions
of
great pleasure or you know just kind of
you know kind of getting lost in the
pleasure of fantasies and imagination or
getting lost in the fantasies of
conflict and war
and that we have towards with other
people
all kinds of things you know goes you
know really takes us away from this
practice
and but the imagination that connects us
to it we have to get a feel for it does
it really connect does it really help us
be more
settled more present for experience and
it's using the imagination
to eventually go beyond the imagination
it's kind of a stepping stone and uh
and the kind of images that the buddha
seems to use
tend not to be stories or there's not
it's not whole
ongoing sagas that we're imagining
they tend to be very simple like that of
a
mountain or the earth or
a lake um
the um you know so it's not like a story
of things there's just kind of an
image and sometimes it's the dynamic
image like the image of an
underwater fountain from under a lake
the underwater
spring that's spreading spreading
goodness throughout the body
you know it's not a story it's just kind
of a dynamic image of what's happening
another image that i love i'll do this
tomorrow some of these but
so this integration process and as i
said before if
if we don't use our imagination it's all
too easy that our imagination gets
used by others we internalize the images
and imagination that
advertisements commercials politicians
other people um
make up and then we internalize them in
the way sometimes they're not beneficial
for us actually can be quite detrimental
um imagining all kinds of terrible
things that are happening the world that
that that just kind of spiral us down
and in a way that's not helpful
so it's not fantasy it's not to
avoid or deny what's going on
run away from life as it actually is
that
we use imagination and buddhism but
it's really but it's with care but
knowing how we do it so it really helps
us supports us to be present
if it doesn't help us to be present
there's no need to use it
and it isn't like you're better buddhist
if you use your imagination
but it is available to us support us to
get kind of more focused
and so
the one of the ways that the buddha
talks about developing gladness and
meditation
and gladness at least to joy joy that
leads to tranquility tranquility leads
to happiness
happiness that leads to samadhi
is uh to appreciate what's absent
as we sit and meditate and in the
the main the most common one thing that
the buddha
emphasizes is the absence of the
hindrances
so when people are meditators they are
often contending with
the hindrances the hindrance of desire
aversion
lethargy and resistance agitation and
regrets remorse
and doubt these can be very strong very
compelling
uh hooks in the mind to be caught up in
thinking about these and involved in
these
and we can get lost in desire fantasies
and aversion fantasies
and and you know caught up in resistance
and
and our regrets and anxieties
really kind of get lost in these
universes that these can create
for us and um
and so as we settle down in meditation
as we kind of start getting more focused
more relaxed more settled
and start letting go of the force of
preoccupation the
debate of all these kinds of thoughts
that take us away from the present
moment
and we're able to sit more a little bit
more and more here here
in the present moment there comes a time
when the hindrances have abated that
they're not so strong anymore
and it becomes relatively easy to stay
here
and the image i used the other day of a
bowl
large bowl maybe that's you know huge
maybe
a five foot diameter bowl that they have
in some kind of
children's museums and you put a marble
into the top
you drop a marble down the edge and that
marble will
move this way and that way and
until it momentum slows down and then
eventually it falls
through a hole at the bottom of the bowl
or rests at the bottom of the bowl
but if you put a lean into the bowl and
keep pushing the marble it keeps going
and going going
so to be caught in the hindrances is to
keep the marble spinning
but to uh to finally settle down
and let the marbles all settle at the
bottom of the bowl and rest
you can feel in meditation so good the
mind just hear
so at this at this point the buddha
talks about
having gladness that one is no longer
caught
no longer hijacked by the mind no longer
enslaved by the mind because the mind
just pulls us away and
has a mind of its own and we just pulled
along and we kind of lose a kind of
freedom
in the process and so to feel the
gladness be glad about this
and here is where the buddha uses
teaches this as an act of imagination an
act of in particular
word that he uses that's translating as
imagination here
can be a visualization
and it has the word seeing anupasana in
it
and it's some anupasana with seeing
but it's not seeing through the physical
eye but rather through
the mental eye of imagination and so he
gives five similes
for being free of um
of the hindrances to be really here the
other absence
and they are a person
in debt who has become free of debt
a person who's terribly sick who has
who is no longer sick a person who is in
prison
and bondage in prison so even not just
in prison but in bondage you know tied
down
who has become freed from prison a
person who is enslaved
who has become freed of slavery
and a person who has wandered in the
desert for a long time
dangerous desert who has come out to the
other side
and is no longer lost free of wandering
in the desert
and so it gives these five similes for
being free of the hindrances
and it is the reason for these similes
is to give a um a reference point
for something would be people would
celebrate just be so
happy you'd be so relieving so
uh joyful to be out of prison to be out
of sickness and all these things
unless we don't remember that we're
free of those things if we just like
we're free of prison we just go on to
the next
preoccupation and concern and but to
take time not just to keep going back to
the breath and back to the breath when
we're present
but take time to really appreciate
the goodness or the well-being or the
or the delight that being free of the
hindrances are being focused and present
so that the goodness of that becomes
spreads through the body or opens up
more widely or
brings a kind of a gladness that is part
of this integration process this
unification process that we're beginning
to not just
keep doing the laser focus of the mind
if we ever did it that way
and just kind of like staying focused
focused focused but there's a kind of a
mellowing and opening and settling
um experience of just softening here
that the gladness can give birth to and
as we allow this gladness to
this joy space for it we don't pump it
up strongly we
don't it's just kind of just natural
hopefully a natural kind of
joy or gladness that is available when
we take time to feel the goodness of
this
what's happening in meditation
then that is what allows the growth then
of joy
and happiness that's on the way to a
strong samadhi
so so
another talk on the use of imagination
and and it takes some wisdom to know
what kind of imagination when what to
use maybe when you first sit down
what to use when the hindrances have
abated but
and not to make a big project of it but
to note this available to us and it's
like a little
aid a little quiet support that
it is meant to support us
to to be inspired to stay in the present
moment
and to feel the goodness the well-being
that comes when we really settle down in
meditation
we're allowed to be present here and now
we're allowed to enjoy it
and and this is the stepping stone for
going deeper
and in some ways in a more powerful way
into this 16 steps of anapanasati which
we'll be coming to and but for now
i'm just trying trying to introduce you
to this territory of imagination
which uh can come into play when we
start feeling
settled in meditation that supports the
further settling
and uh and absorption in the very
practice we're doing
so thank you and i look forward to
[Music]
tomorrow