so
the eighth step of anapanasati
is one trains oneself
experience one
calms the mental activity
one relaxes the mental activity
you most english translations will use
some language of
a tranquilized which makes tranquil
the mental activity and um
and the mental activity here is usu
often translated as mental formations
the formations the activity the
constructs the constructing
aspect the doing aspect of the mind
so i think activity works relatively
well
that and we now begin to calm
the mental activity
and this doesn't have to be a big
project
if it's easy to relax and
please by all means do but it's also
recognizing this is a natural process of
settling that goes on
and as we gets more and more settled in
meditation
more focused on the breathing and and we
start shedding a lot of the
concerns of the day and we're just more
and more here
uh their tent starts being a heightened
sensitivity to
different aspects of our experience one
of them is
experiencing bodily tensions the way we
hold tensions in our body
and of course there's a feeling that
well enough the body itself wants to
relax and let go
and there's almost a natural letting go
and relaxation
just from knowing and recognizing what
goes on but we can also be participate
in that if it's easy enough and we don't
get busy
we can help ourselves relax more
so as we begin having more well-being
and more settled and
in meditation at some point also then we
develop a kind of a special sensitivity
or awareness of the mind thinking
of course we can know that earlier and
we're letting go of our thoughts coming
back to the breathing
but it uh there's more and more
sensitivity as we go along to the
unsatisfactory quality of thinking the
way that we start noticing that
when we're involved in thinking it's
almost like an alienation from ourselves
that's unimaginable for people who
identify strongly where they're thinking
like a thinking is who they are
and uh but we realize that thinking is
just in one aspect of our life
that there's a fuller range of who we
are that
really becomes apparent as big and
settled and calm and
more embodied and present here in
meditation we start seeing that thinking
is just a piece of what we are
and if we get lost in thought we
actually lose touch with the fullness
the fullness of who we are the wholeness
of who we are in a sense
there's a kind of alienation even if the
thoughts are really great and exciting
or important so called
and but we also become sensitive to the
in the
impact that thinking has so one impact
is the alienation
another impact is that
unskillful and wholesome thoughts
attract more unwholesomeness
so if we're thinking a lot of with
agitated ways
angry ways greedy ways
that those tend to kind of perpetuate
themselves and attract more of the same
agitation and preoccupation and we also
start feeling the impact it has on
very subtly sometimes on our musculature
that i could go around all day long
somewhat calm and engaged in life but
when i sit down to meditate
i realize that my thinking has somehow
created a little bit of tension around
my eyes and
just behind the forehead that i'm too
busy kind of with life
to really notice the subtlety of it but
as we settled in meditation
that subtlety of where the whole tension
and tightness
becomes more and more apparent and
and the tension associated with thinking
the pressure the agitation that's
physical almost in nature that's more
closely connected to
thinking rather than the surface muscles
that we often kind of
we can relax more actively or something
i call that the thinking muscle and
part of the meditation is to is to relax
the thinking muscle
and um and um
and so as we feel this there's a natural
tendency for the system the
psychophysical system to want to relax
the more we are mindful of tension
the more we feel like almost in the
tension itself is a momentum to relax
but we can also soften and relax
ourselves softening the mind
relaxing thinking mind and
and certainly this is very helpful
because the more the mind is calm
the more it tr that attracts more
calmness
the more the mind is calm the less we're
likely to
be so interested in being caught in our
thoughts and wonder often thoughts
it's easier to stay focused and continue
with this process of meditation
but also there's a very important
lessons that can come
about how our mind works as we get
calmer and calmer
and one of them is that there's a
certain
wonderful intelligence creativity that
can happen when the mind is calm and
settled
that's much more difficult to happen
when it's agitated
it's a little bit of a trap for some
people because sometimes they start
composing
you know the great world novel by
you know they have some great idea for
something
and the creativity and the intelligence
of the mind is really kind of
operating it just feels so good and
engaging and
and right to be involved in some
wonderful creative thoughts
and so so but it's a dead end
for the purpose of meditation it becomes
actually another way of being kind of
self-alienated even though it feels so
good
and exciting and like finally i feel
fulfilled i'm doing something very
important writing the
greatest poetry that's ever been written
and
um and um so so to not get sidetracked
by that
but the process that got us there is
showing us that there's a natural
intelligence or
creativity or wisdom that can operate
when the mind is not so active
that the in the principle that actually
the um the mind operates the best
when there's no extra energy no
unnecessary energy operating
and that's a great lesson and a
difficult lesson to really take in
that um it's so it can be so compelling
to get to worry so compelling to feel
like i have to accomplish i have to fix
something i have to do something and i
have to think my way to it
and and we get agitated and pressured
and sometimes we feel like
we have to if we're responsible we have
to engage the mind and
show ourselves and maybe even show other
people
how serious we are in thinking and
taking care of things
and that if we allow the natural quiet
calm mind
to operate then it looks like we don't
care
and looks like we know that we're just
being kind of letting things just go
you know whatever way they go but uh
what i'd like to suggest is that
our love our care responsibility even a
sense that things are really important
to take care of
even then they can be taken care of
better
if the mind is relaxed and calm
and we don't build up this extra tension
in the mind of doing and
accomplishing and fixing and thinking
about things
and to learn this this um this
shift of perspective
to learn how to trust a calm mind
and have that combined be engaged
responsibly take care of things
is a process of trust process of
familiarity of experiencing oh this
actually works
i don't have to believe in the in the
messages even from
society around us that i have to be
anxious preoccupied angry
apologetic i have to kind of engage my
mind in some way
to please other people or please myself
it's possible to stay peaceful and love
and intelligence and creativity and
responsibility all can operate when
there's no extra energy going on
so um unnecessary energy in mind
and so uh this learning to to relax and
to calm the mind
it very much depends on our ability to
recognize
how we're over efforting in the mind
where the agitation of the mind is that
tension in the mind is the pressure in
the mind
the closing down of the mind that goes
on
and and so the seventh step is to feel
that
and to feel what's going on uh and then
this eighth step is to relax it
and this has a wonderful effect where
some of our problems that we have in our
lives that we feel like we have to fix
and care and take care of
maybe some of them don't have any
solutions
but rather than solving them we can
dissolve them
so for example someone who wants to know
the meaning of life
they might have a lot of agitation
around this
even some anxiety around what's the
meaning of life
i need to know because i need to know
where i fit in this universe and what's
happening with me
and have a purpose and all this stuff
and
there's a lot of agitated thinking
around searching for the meaning of life
but if they do this meditation process
and all the agitation
and anxiety associated with this
question
abates dissolves goes away
then lo and behold they might discover
that
it still might be an interesting
question the meaning of life
but there's no personal need or
investment or desperation around it
it just becomes an abstract question and
the existential
power that held our grip around it has
dissolved
without solving it it's no longer a
problem
it just becomes in maybe an academic
interesting question
that might not have been the best
example but i'm hoping that you can just
apply that to yourself that
think about what are you concerned with
what are you preoccupied with
that maybe doesn't need to be solved
maybe more valuable is to dissolve
the underlying tension fear anxiety
pressure ambition greed that might be
the very thing that's
keeping those thoughts pumping up and
going
and to relax the mental activity
trust softening the mind
and it's a wonderful thing so this is
especially true in meditation so as
meditation
con continues to develop there comes a
stage
where periodically it comes and goes
where it's really clear
that the what's really good to do is to
trust
the calm mind and letting go of all the
unnecessary energy that's there
so thank you very much and
we'll continue this process of step
seven and eight
for another couple of days thank you