so a warm very warm hello to everyone and
it's a wonderful thing to gather together this way for meditation and as an
introduction to this meditation and also maybe as a you know coming to
the end of this long series on mindfulness of breathing
the um there are sometimes things in our life that happen that
really get our attention like wow that and our preoccupations concerns we
normally have just immediately fall away because this like well now you know we're really here with this and
um and there are some wonderful places we can go
in the world where no matter what we're doing or thinking it really
gets our um
you know our attention and for me it was uh going to a small chapel
in france when i was 18. and it was a thousand-year-old chapel on top of a hill
and i entered into it and it was the silence and the stillness that was there
that was so powerful that something happened inside of me that uh felt very intimate and warm and
connected and still silent and uh it was a quality quality that
you know it was kind of like wow and so there in terms of this path of
meditation and the maturity of it coming into full maturity of its potential
there are things that then get our attention and one of those things can be silence
and a profoundly peaceful and open and sweet silence
it can be a phenomenally profound and protective
safe feeling of stillness that is not stillness of being frozen
but stillness of a early morning dawn someplace maybe
outdoors and everything is still before before the animals the birds wake up
before the wind picks up sometimes it's spaciousness
that gets our attention that things are vastly
just seems like there's just lots of space around everything
and uh and the spaciousness is so satisfying so expansive so
almost liberating maybe that it gets our attention and these qualities of silence and
stillness and spaciousness in a certain way they're always here
silence is always here but the silence gets filled with noise
and we don't often hear it stillness is always here in some kind of way
but it gets filled with activity and spaciousness is always here
but are there's ways in which it just seems like things have gotten claustrophobic
and in the mind it can be this way silence stillness spaciousness that's so
nourishing so wonderful that it gets our attention and when in meditation
the practice deepens far enough to really feel these qualities in the heart and the mind and in awareness
it's kind of hard to put words on where it is or how it is some people will feel like it's just
everywhere and um and it when it's strong enough
and clear enough then uh there's a way in which then
afterwards we realize that those qualities are ever present
in spite of the noise there is silence here
beautiful silence in spite of the activities and busyness
there is stillness and in spite of the claustrophobic and
the things you know being crowded or a lot of things happening
there is spaciousness and when this feeling for
orientation towards the silence or the stillness or the spaciousness that's here
becoming becomes easy i don't know easy is the right word
exactly it becomes available to sense to feel to taste
to hear to feel in meditation
that can become a basis for the meditation a support for it or
orientation for it or or nourishment for it or a context for our meditation
so
entering into a posture that allows you to be still
some modicum of stillness with your body
sitting alert or present or
and allowing your body to settle into a
stillness maybe taking a few long slow deep breaths
and relaxing
into the stillness of the body
as you exhale to relax parts of your body
allowing the relaxation the relaxing muscles to relax out into the spaciousness
that's here as if there's lots of space
to receive the releasing of muscular
tension
you're relaxing the belly
the shoulders the face
and then relaxing the thinking mind or any physical tension or contraction
associated with thinking agitation
or softening quieting your thinking
so that you're also aware
of a quietness within or even a silence
between your thoughts
around your thoughts silence underneath your thoughts beneath
them
and breathing in a normal way
perhaps you can feel the space just beyond the edges
of the sensations breathing the space beyond the edges of your body
breathing
if you're aware of your torso moving as you breathe the space around that receives the
expanding chest expanding belly
and as you're sitting here aware within
of any stillness that's here
next to whatever movement and movements there might be in their body
in your mind next to it besides it underneath it
inside of it is there any place of stillness
and perhaps the breathing movements of breathing
sensations occur
within the stillness
with the stillness
beyond the edges of your body is space
with no clear feeling for the line between
the edge of your body and the space around it
their spaciousness space also within the body
breathe with the space in a spacious environment
in silence trust the silence of silent mind
a quiet place within
breathing with the sweetness
of quietness and silence within
and very gently maybe tenderly
can you also allow your awareness
your mindfulness your knowing your very way of being
have qualities of stillness
not moving towards or away from anything
awareness even sense of being has qualities of
silence
quietness maybe awareness which is not based on
thinking maybe because it's larger than thinking
more spacious than thinking can ever be
and allowing awareness itself for your very sense of beingness
to also have qualities of spaciousness openness
that may be peaceful
and it isn't that everything becomes silent and still and spacious but
rather recognize that which is silent
still impatient spacious
and as you exhale relax into that place
breathe with it
for these minutes trust the simplicity
of not being involved in what moves
what has noise in it and static
and which is contracted in spatially limited
just open here
you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
maybe in the way that silence is ever present between
and behind underneath the noise that fills it
where stillness is ever present
spaciousness as well maybe in the same way
love is ever present in all it in any of its forms
simple caringness
kindness tenderness
friendliness compassion
appreciation and perhaps if we are quiet enough for
sensitive enough we don't tr drown out
the ever-present love that's in our hearts here
and maybe it's a love or a tenderness or a kindness or
maybe if it could also take the form of respect and devotion
which is which exists or which
touches on our relationship to other
people
it exists in the mutuality of our lived lives
together
and may it be that as the meditation gets quieter and stiller and more spacious
that these beautiful heart qualities nourish ourselves
and we recognize it that the nourishment comes also
as we shine it on others
may it be that whatever known or unknown
kindness that lives within us love that lives within us
be shared with the people in our lives
people on this world in ways that
is for the benefit and welfare of all beings
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
so over these now over 70 talks
and guided meditations
i've been we've kind of gone through a particular discourse of the buddha
called the discourse on mindfulness of breathing mindfulness of breathing in and breathing out
and the heart of it is these very simple
almost like cliff notes maybe instructions on mindfulness of breathing
and the text goes on and there's more teaching the buddha gives that builds on these six or extends
these 16 steps mindfulness of breathing that also represent the
development and the growth the onward leading nature of this practice
that as we do this practice something gets born inside something begins to unfold or
express itself and a variety of things and and some of those
things are called the seven factors of awakening and the way it's presented in the text
it isn't so much that we practice the seven factors of awakening as it is
we recognize them in other places the buddha is quite explicit that in some of these factors
of awakening the very recognition of them is the nourishment the food that allows them to
keep growing so this this organic growth of something that happens as we
really have starting to learn how to give ourselves over and trust this process of being aware of our
breathing being aware being present not caught up in our thoughts and distractions and preoccupations
learning to be with ourselves in a caring way
and and so these seven factors awakening develop and they're called factors of awakening
for two reasons one reason is that they are
they set lay down the foundation or lay down the conditions upon which awakening can happen
and in the word buddha means the one who is awake it comes from word awake
and buddhism is in a sense could be translated into english as awake-ism and that it's the it's the
ism that has to do with liberation with freedom of mind of heart in such a way that
something wakes up some kind of awareness
when a person has a first taste first glimmer of this what this awakening is this liberation is
so much so that it gets their attention it really oh this is central this is
really what this practice is about or this is how this is the cen this this i want to make
this the center of my my life nothing else is as important
even the tremendously valuable love and compassion i have for others nothing compares to freedom
a freedom that allows the love and compassion to be clean and and supportive for everyone
including oneself so that we have first taste of that
that's called it's described sometimes in english as entering the stream literally the language in the pali is
entering the current of river and if you can stay in the
current it'll carry you all the way to liberation
and so learning to recognize that current uh learning to stay in it and be to be
carried by it then becomes part of the practice after the first glimmer
and um and so the text this this course on seven factors awakening
uh ends with a little section that's there's a lot of ellipsis so it's not always does not really
spelled out all the way it's very short and i think it's really easy for people reading a text to just
skip over it and not see it but what it says is it picks up at first
the it talks about the seven factors of awakening how they
rise out of the practice of mindfulness and then it goes on to talk about how
those seven factors awakening come into play and how they develop and keep growing and
and support us after awakening and that is now they are based
on something they are based on and i'm going to give you my kind of
adaptation of the pali words because the pali words
if they're translated literally into english i think doesn't mean as much for an english-speaking audience but the
kind of the the value that the um the fullness of these words are closer to maybe what in
english in the best senses of the term terms
would be now they're based on a sense of independence someone who's entered the stream enter
the current is said to be independent in the dharma now they know what the dharma is for themselves
they know and they don't need more books or more teachers or anything and they just know
and they know what the practice is about so they're in there's an independence
they're based on independence and it's based on freedom a sense of
real freedom that we're no longer in bondage or entangled in things and so there's a
sense of feeling of freedom and there's a a sense of
that all the suffering all the attachment and clinging something
conceits we have there's a there's a stopping there's a phenomenal
ending that's happened it's always here
and um and these three qualities independence freedom and kind of the
ending of is um are usually in english translated
as and we've seen them uh no no i haven't seen all of them but one of them is translating english as
seclusion the other as dispassion
or the absence of dispassion or the fading away of
clinging and the third is cessation which is and those last two the fading away
dispassion and the cessation that's in the anapanasata
step 14 and 15. but now these qualities are kind of
available to a person they've experienced a degree of independence a degree of
freedom a degree of the stopping cessation that is memorable now it's ever present
in some kind of way it's not that it's always aware of it but it's just like right there sitting on
your shoulder or close by just like in the guided meditation i talked about silence and stillness and
spaciousness kind of always here in some kind of fashion that once we have a clear
really clear experience and powerful experience of those uh maybe there's always some sense that
these are ever present as well when love is associated with this then
some people say that yes love is always present and um or when all these together maybe
uh give a sense of real peace peace is always present and um
and so so with with awakening something quality of that awakening uh remains
available or is recognizable and then it becomes a basis for doing
the practice further and so now we know what the practice is about and now the idea is
now we want to practice in harmony with that we want to practice in the with in that
spirit or in those attitude of those so that um
uh if if part of it is uh this independence seclusion
that we want to do it in a way that when we practice the awareness itself has a feeling of being independent from
what it knows independent of what we're aware of we're not entangled or caught in it
we want to recognize how to be free where the freedom is in
awareness there's no freedom in clinging and wanting more and expecting and
or no freedom in reacting so this is terrible i'm doing i'm a bad meditator or i this shouldn't
be here this is embarrassing of course there's all these ways we're still not totally free
and there's all kinds of things that arise and bubble up and the mind gets busy and distracted and
difficult states of mind might arise but it's possible that at some point that in
spite of those we don't get tricked by them we don't get pulled into them we stay independent of
them and we stay free of them so we're not caught and entangled they still arise
but because we're independent and free of them there's a disinclination of identifying with them
i was saying this is who i am this is who i and then there's this last quality of
something has ceased something has stopped and one of the things that stopped is
uh is um the preoccupation beliefs um attachments
to ideas of self ideas that tend to bring conceit and self concern and this
stopping of of self-preoccupation self-concern being self-consciousness not totally
but to have some flavor the feeling of that a taste of that and letting that be part of the
mindfulness as well where the mindfulness is not entangled or caught up in being self-conscious or
self-critical there's a clear sense that awareness itself is free of this self-concern or
self-preoccupation or self-identity kind of things that we're doing and so mindfulness then becomes a very
different quality it becomes mindfulness becomes more an expression
of the dharma moving through us then it is so much something that we are identified as the doer
or the agent of we're more the to the degree to which we're an agent we're more the enabler of
it we get out of the way of it we allow awareness to be there
and we notice uh in this field of freedom and independence and and something has
stopped there's space for everything and that's why i like to think that
liberation in buddhism is we give liberation to everything else
everything is becomes liberated from our entanglement and concern rather than i am liberated it doesn't really make
sense anymore to say i am liberated i'm free and
and so over and over again we've seen the suttos in the teachings of the buddha that the ultimate goal is described in
terms of kind of of negation a liberation is kind of a negation
of being entangled being in bondage we're free now
seclusion or independence is a kind of liberation from being dependent in an unhealthy way perhaps
and or being claustrophobic in the middle of all kinds of concerns and cessation or ending of
something is is an ending of something of suffering of clinging
so there's a strong tendency for the buddha to repeatedly give the the ultimate goal of
what practice really is taking us as defining it as an absence not as the
presence of something if he talks about the presence of something that most he seems to do
is to talk about it as in terms of peace and what's i think beautiful about this
is that even the experience of liberation you know that they can feel palpable
feeling of freedom and independence and and absence of suffering
is when we're free
there's no inclination to make it into something to make it something we hold on to
make it to say that it is something the presence of something because then that's already even even
asserting presence of something is a way of kind of a little bit grasping and clinging this is this
uncompromising attitude of just trust letting go being free
being this you know the mind not clinging to anything and in doing that there's this beautiful
way in which there's maybe a nourishing stillness silence spaciousness
maybe that's interpenetrated with love and compassion and care and wisdom
it's not being frozen it's not being disconnected but it's not exactly the same as being
connected either it's being free so the
the practice of anapanasati ends this way it ends with this
reference point of practicing based on the qualities of awakening itself
and that's about in some ways is available for everyone well before become liberated and in fact
that's often what dharma teachers are trying to do is to say practice with non-reactively
non-reactive awareness practice non-judgmental awareness practice open
awareness or um and that you know what they're doing is really trying to get these qualities of
awakening already there and so with they we grow into it and it grows and
develops and comes to fulfillment and finally
don't worry so much about this path of practice the only thing to
be concerned about and happy about exactly where you are
in your practice that's the place where practice in the dharma unfolds be
content and and happy and discover awareness
of where you're at not where you think you should be so thank you and we'll have one more
talk tomorrow on this topic and
and maybe for this next day you can look around and see if you've been
overlooking things like silence stillness spaciousness or independence freedom
cessation endings see if you can be nourished by that and supported by it thank you