so this morning i'm continuing on the
topic of
oneself
that each person
is the person responsible
for their own practice
the buddha said
i only point the way
it's up to you
to make the effort
and there's a
our agency our involvement our
engagement with practice
is
an important part
of important ingredient
in walking the path of liberation
and classically i think the path was
you know back in the ancient world was a
path you walk on
which means we have to we bring all of
ourselves
to the path
and so
one of the important ways that we
bring ourselves
is to know ourselves
is to meet ourselves
to
and the way of meeting ourselves a way
of knowing ourselves
it needs to be done with care
and i like i love the idea of
hospitality think i talked about it
yesterday that
when we offer hospitality
it's an offering it's a gift it's
something we have agency in our doing
you don't just sit stay in bed all day
and
play host to the people in your house
you're engaged in caring for them and
serving them and
whatever it takes when you're when
you're the host
and um
the um
um
and there's also a kind of uh
putting aside of our own
desires for ourselves not completely
but there is a deference or there is a
letting go of self-concern to a
healthy degree
in being a host for other people
that they're very different if you're
living alone and you just do whatever
you want and
and you don't have to take in anybody
else into account
so uh
to be a host for oneself
uh the host within the host is a
saying in zen zen
to be a host to have a great house a
hospital and hospitable environment for
oneself
so for to do that we have agency we have
to engage in some way
and one of the ways we have to engage is
to show up to be
present and the other is that we also
have to get out of the way our
selfishness has no place when we're
being a host for ourselves
if we're caught up in our desires and
our wishes are passed in the future
so we can't really offer this
hospitality to ourselves
then um
you know there's no practice we get lost
in that world
um
and
but to have hospitality towards oneself
is a kind of letting go of self-concern
self-preoccupation in order to meet
what's there to be the host for what's
here
and one of the crucial things that we're
trying to be the host for
is is to understand ourselves to have
self-understanding
and
and to have it but to have the
the
discovery of ourselves the understanding
of ourselves
come from this hospitality where we're
also learning to let go
of selfishness in the process to be
selfish you can't really be a host
and so self-understanding
is a is a is uh
aided
by things like meditation by things like
mindfulness
where we're awakening our capacity to be
attentive
to what's happening within us
what's happening here
sound of course is not limited to
ourselves but this is kind of the seat
the uh
the beginning place often time in
meditation and buddhism
is to understand oneself
and what are we understanding when we
understand ourselves
we're understanding things that are
unique to ourselves
that we are contributing to our lives we
are doing
that are
healthy
and things that are unhealthy
we begin seeing how much we're
distracted
and all distractions
involve some degree of attachment
and so if we can become have
understanding about how attachment works
and recognize it when it's there
then we and we play host to that
what happens to our involvement with
attachment
chances are if part of who we are
is the host
that part is not
involved with the attachment and there
starts to be space for the attachment
there starts to be some degree of
non-involvement with it some degree of
clarity and seeing it for what it is
and perhaps on some idea that um
you know i don't believe in the
attachment anymore this is not where i
want to be it's not where i want to put
my life energy
into these attachments
and that's not a critique of them it's
not an
aversion to them but it's a wisdom that
comes from self-understanding
but this is not where i want to be
and so there's uh but i'm the host so
there's more opening up more kind of
letting go
and to the degree to which attachment is
closely connected to selfishness
self-preoccupation and self-centeredness
the as we let go of attachment
selfishness and self-centeredness fall
away and paradoxically
we become more self-aware but less
self-centered
more self-aware but less bounded
by definitions of who we are
trying to prove who we are or hold on to
who we are
and so we begin looking
self-understanding turning inward and
understanding
um how does desires work for us when am
i caught up in desires
how do aversions uh work for me and then
to understand that and how do i caught
in the grip of those
do i spend a lot of time in in stories
do i live my life in stories
do i live my life in opinions
in what's right and wrong
do i live my life in
judgments
and to really see this
and self-understanding leads to wisdom
and
one of the maybe a little bit
um
unfortunate
aspects of all this
is that wisdom comes from familiarity
that a lot of the wisdoms we see over
and over and over again we sit down to
meditate be mindful in our life and we
say over and over again oh there's the
desire well i had no idea i was living
in stories all this time
i had no idea
that i was i'm so judgmental i'm judging
every little thing that goes on
i had no idea that i'm living and
planning mind all the time
i had no idea that i'm so
self-referential in my thinking
and by seeing that over and over and
over again
something begins to shift
we tend not to be mesmerized or
enchanted with those thoughts and those
activities we start having wisdom about
this is not the place to live
i'm not wisdom about not being committed
to it not being so interested in anymore
the wisdom that lets us see it clearly
and know an alternative
and the alternative that i'm suggesting
today is to be the host
to be hospitable
have hospitality for the stranger
so even this parts are strange about you
maybe your selfishness maybe your
attachments maybe your
story making your opinions your
self-righteousness your
fears
your
and also what's beautiful about yourself
okay here let's hold that in a
hospitable way
not to condone it
not to accept it in some way like oh
this is good and i have to just let it
be
but a kind of way to
speak space and open up
so it's kind of like a stranger who
comes into your home in a cold rainy day
and shivering
and the end is has no attention to you
and is self-concerned with her cold and
their wetness
and as the host you put them by the fire
you give them a warm blanket you bring
them warm tea
and and and this stranger begins to
relax and warm up and it turns out that
as they relax more that the stranger
becomes a
wonderful person
so the same way with what's difficult
and challenging within ourselves
just to know it to have the
self-understanding of there it is
and to have the self-understanding to
know how to be the host
and how to hold it
not exactly in acceptance but with
hospitality without conflict
so that it can relax
and perhaps all
attachments
all
selfishness self-centeredness
greed and hatred
is just a stranger
that needs the chance to relax
to warm up
and so
and to thaw
and some of these things when they relax
and thaw
turn into something else
something that may be a surprise
so an important part of
this buddhist practice of ours is
self-understanding and
so yesterday that topic was self-respect
and
so to always meet ourselves with respect
always to cultivate respect and part of
cultivating respect is cultivating
and to be able to be a host to be able
to hospitality
to be able to prioritize
self-understanding
over
self-preoccupation
spinning or spinning along with our
attachments
is a
engenders respect oh i can see
i can understand
i can be the host here
and so as we have more respect we can
have more capacity to
look at ourselves to be present to
understand to be the host that makes
more respect which supports more this
capacity to be present
be here
and be fully here
in a way that
allows for greater understanding
and at some point this grows
so that there is the self-understanding
the self part falls away
and um and we just
live mindful and aware
with awareness and understanding
available for wherever it's needed
whether it's within or without
so self-understanding
so
you are definitely
worthy
of hospitality you're definitely worthy
of understanding and seeing and knowing
and to do it in a simplest possible way
maybe without analysis and
a lot of thinking
a lot of thinking about yourself is more
attachment so what we're talking about
here is not thinking about ourselves but
really almost like a silent presence
that sees and recognizes
oh
that's what's happening i'm thinking a
lot
and then we're host to that so we can
write some something about the thinking
mind can relax and settle
so um
thank you
and um
i look forward to sitting again tomorrow
in silence with all of you and
and continuing on this topic