so
continuing the topic of anapanasati
mindfulness of breathing in and
mindfulness of breathing out
the um we're kind of moving into the
territory now
of the second tetrad where we train
to experience joy as we breathe in
experience joy as we breathe out and
then
we train to as we breathe in to
experience happiness
as we breathe out to experience
happiness
and so
all along here in all the 16 steps what
they have in common is mindfulness while
breathing in
and mindfulness of breathing out and
there's a connection to this rhythm of
breathing
in and out that goes on and um
and as we move into this the joy part
the the happiness part the
kind of the sense of wellness well-being
that comes along
uh i think it's important to remember
that we're
that how important this rhythm of
breathing in and breathing out is
so it's as i've said the the continuity
of breathing
is keeps us can keep us in the present
moment
it's a breathing is always a present
moment experience
and it keeps us going and moving along
in the present and it's also
but it's also in constant it's there's a
discontinuity
because the in-breath is only there
while you're breathing in and the out
breath is only there when you're
breathing out
and one leads to the other and there's
this rhythm of one after the other
the sensations at the beginning of the
in-breath are different than the
end of the out-breath the sensations the
beginning of the out breath are
different than the end of the out breath
and so there's a constant change of
sensations of movement experience in the
body
sometimes for focusing mostly on the
little spot of the chest or the belly
we feel the changing texture of
sensations there
if we're aware more broadly we might
feel a changing
ways and places where that are activated
with sensations
as we breathe so there's both
this constancy and this inconstancy
uh with mindfulness of breathing the
constancy of the rhythm of breathing
and the inconstancy of all the pieces of
it the subsets of it
coming and going and
and so we can't hold on to any one part
of the breathing without causing
problems
if you hold on to the exhale
you know you never inhale and so you
know then you
you know run out of breath
if you hold on to same thing with the
inhale some people
kind of prioritize really don't want to
let go at the
top it's very it's going to be very very
subtle but some people come
to the top of the inhale
and they don't really want to give up
anything they kind of have a policy of
holding everything
they don't want they want things for
themselves so there's a little subtle
resistance there
to let go some people don't start the
exhale because
it's a kind of letting go especially the
end of the exhale people get little
very very subtly people get a little bit
anxious there
or there's a very subtle attitude maybe
at the beginning of the in-breath
no i don't want to breathe in it's just
a bother just more
work and now just leave me alone there's
enough input coming my way
so there can be very subtle attitudes
in that cycles of breathing and
that kind of little bit operate when you
when we get to that
a little bit of holding perhaps a little
bit resistance
or a little bit triggering of thoughts
of fear or resistance or
or you know aversion or something and
and you can if you're really attentive
you can watch and see in that cycle
where it is that some little
psychological thing is
triggered occasionally don't don't try
too hard to look for it but
it's a little bit there and or if we
start thinking about something else
and it's really you know preoccupying
really as
a major issue you can feel the breath
gets held and
we're still breathing in and out but
maybe it's all chest breathing and
it's you know the belly's tight and and
and so there's this holding going on but
if you
just stay with the inconstancy and the
flow of breathing
uh and remembering that this is
constantly letting go
constantly opening up constantly
releasing and softening and allowing the
flow to go
that it's a protection from getting
attached to anything getting hooked too
much on things
getting caught in our thoughts caught in
reactivity whatever
it's a way of keeping us limber keeping
us relaxed or loose or not so caught
and it's by degrees and um
so i don't think it's all or nothing
again but we slowly the breathing begins
to
massage us and begins to support the
letting go
and with time as the breathing becomes
more like a flow that goes smooth and
easy
that um the the uh
watching the breath tuning into the
breathing becomes a little bit like
sitting at the edge of a river
and just watching the rippling
occurrence so the water flowing down
the river and it's kind of like looking
at a fire
sometimes we can just spend a long time
just looking at
the changing patterns of the water flow
that you know that's
not that different from each other but
it's changing and it can be just a watch
that
can be very relaxing and it we're not
necessarily trying to
quiet our mind or stop thinking about
anything but just letting that be the
you know the way the mind kind of the
attention
gets absorbed in and flowing with
something gets quite quieter and quieter
and stiller so the same thing as with
time
um as the breathing becomes more relaxed
more loose
more open more flowing and we kind of be
within constancy the
and the constancy the incontinency of
the little wavelets of breathing
on top of the constancy of just the flow
of the river of
breathing we get absorbed in it we get
pulled into it
and there's a lot of it it's not like
we're looking at the surface of uh
water we're actually um what we're doing
is
feeling sensing all the sensations that
come alive
as we breathe and and especially as we
kind of get settled in
and really begin to settle into the
present moment and
stay with that rhythm and flow of
breathing that
um there gets born uh
pleasant sensations uh and um
uh that er that kind of can take the
form of contentment
it can take the form of um pleasure it
can take the form of
a joy or delight or happiness
um a sense of goodness a glow a warmth
and i know i'm repeating my things i've
said now but i think it's worth
repeating
and also and everyone will experience a
little bit differently
some people might feel something a glow
in their chest as they settle into
breathing some people might feel it in
their belly a warmth
something good some people maybe it
feels intense
um joyful tingling and kind of a
delightful
uh in the nostrils that the air goes in
and out it gets more and more intense
the the the sharpness of the joy
of the the pleasure that's there and
it's kind of a thrill
almost it might be there's a kind of a
sense of
locationless thrill throughout the body
that comes as we really settle in
and get it get absorbed just like you'd
get absorbed and watching the river
get absorbed in in this thing
my first experience of like this of
being absorbed and feeling the goodness
of it
was when i was about 10 years old and
i would
take the public bus i was living in
italy and a little
town in italy and i would go to school
in town and we lived in the outskirts of
town and
and my my bus stop that i got off on was
right near the very end of the line
and i i learned at some point oh so
there was a driver and there was a
conductor who sold the tickets
to two people and the conductor would go
up and down and
sell tickets as people got on board but
the conductor at some point when we kind
of got outside the city enough that
really not new people were going to get
on the the conductor would sit on a
particular seat
and do the accounting of all the
different sea tickets
he'd sold you know a round trip one way
children you know senior citizens
whatever it might be
and he had his ledger he'd write on and
i learned that if i sat
in a particular seat behind his seat
and kind of looked over his shoulder and
watched him
to do his accounting in his ledger of
the different kind of tickets he got
i would just start feeling so good i
would just kind of feel so
warm my chest would kind of glow in
delight and joy
and i feel so content i felt safe and
settled and
everything was right in the universe and
just watching him and i had no idea why
i didn't ever thought about it
i just knew that if i sat there i'd have
this really good feeling
and many years later when i started
meditating
i realized that um i was getting
absorbed in this very simple thing that
he was doing maybe i was
tapping into his concentration of
working
but just the movement of his pencil on
the paper and
and his focus on it somehow i got kind
of absorbed just
and it wasn't like trying to get
concentrated i wasn't
i didn't know i was you know really
getting absorbed um
it just like my world kind of got so
content and happy and
settled and just him his pencil his
piece of paper
watching him and um
so this is the this maybe captures a
little bit the
sense of what's possible in on breath
meditation as we get into this
fifth and sixth step we're not trying
too
hard it's almost like we're just sitting
back and watching the
you know on a nice quiet day and nothing
to do nothing to be
just watching the river or the conductor
do his ledger in the on the bus
and um and uh and allowing ourselves to
include
include the good feelings that come with
that
now remember they don't come
automatically and right away the first
four steps of anapanasati are always the
default
and and the basic default is the first
two just
becoming familiar with the breathing and
and developing just kind of
developing capacity to stay a little bit
in the present moment with things
and we're always going back to the
beginning and you might go back to the
beginning during some sittings
it was one way in the beginning and then
we're kind of back
near the beginning at the end because
who knows all the ways that
things change in our mind and body and
so uh don't have some idea of linear if
it's linear don't have some idea that it
has to be a certain way don't be in a
rush
but when you're settled enough and
present enough
then at some point the fifth and sixth
steps might be relevant
and this idea of kind of gently allowing
yourself to be absorbed in that
and feeling the goodness of that and and
kind of let the breathing in
and bring out always going on that
rhythm keep you from getting attached
and
wanting keeping you loose and limber in
the mind
staying with that flow in and out and
then
letting that rhythm of breathing and out
move through
or with the goodness that's there as
well
and let that grow and be expansive and
let it grow and be expensive so it
includes
it can include all the challenges as
well
without us needing to be preoccupied
with the challenges or caught by them or
needing to fix them
they're just there in a relaxed way and
so um
so i hope that
you'll feel content
contentment and perhaps the assignment
for the next 24 hours
is maybe you can look for more
opportunities
to be have contentment in your day
and i suspect that it you you can do it
if uh even if it's a minute or so that
you'll have more opportunities if you
look for them and and
and hang out with them a little bit and
that contentment in your daily life
will maybe support you to feel this
meditative goodness
and contentment that supports a
deepening of this practice
so thank you very much and
i look forward to our time tomorrow