good evening good evening welcome welcome
wherever you might be i hope that you're doing well
and we'll do a little bit of a guided meditation here
um just settling in to
this moment to this experience
and feeling what it feels like
to be here now
how does it feel in the body
just in a global sense
how does it feel in the mind just in a
general way is the mind busy is the mind feeling sluggish
or maybe there's a brightness a
sharpness
however i might be with the body with the mind
can we welcome our experience
without pushing any of it away
without quietly demanding that it be different
but instead tuning into aligning with
the experience right now
maybe tuning in to the experience of breathing
feeling the body breathe
feeling the stretching expanding
from there contracting non-stretching
just in an easy natural rhythm
resting our attention on these sensations of breathing
it wouldn't be unusual wouldn't be surprising
if we find that the mind has some momentum and momentum with thinking
and we find ourselves perhaps lost in thought
a little bit disconnected from our breathing we don't have to make that a problem
just oh here i am meditating
very simply gently begin again with the sensations of breathing
by resting our attention on the sensations of breathing
we start to notice how much the mind
wants to be making stories or planning remembering
fantasizing chances are we would notice
if we hadn't set the intention of noticing the breathing
that's one of the functions of mindfulness of breathing
is to highlight help us notice what the mind wants to do
the momentum the inclination of the mind
it can be helpful to notice not only
these movements of the mind of planning or fantasizing remembering
but also to notice those little subtle thoughts
maybe that arise when we first become aware that we've been lost
in thought is there a little voice like oh shoot
or maybe oh that's right i'm supposed to meditate
we can notice those thoughts too
otherwise we just are hanging out with the sensations of breathing
it can be helpful to set the intention to be with the
entirety of an in-breath
and the entirety of an out breath
beginning middle and end
the entirety of the in-breaths and out-breaths and the transitions
between the types of breaths
we might notice that there are little subtle thoughts
where the intention is on the breath maybe a fleeting thought
oh i feel this more in my chest i used to
feel this more in the abdomen or maybe there's a little
fleeting thought in between the in-breath and the out breath during that transition
we don't have to make it a problem we're just noticing
so sometimes our thoughts
are subtle we don't notice them but they may have an impact on us
they may have an impact on those we come in contact with
in the sense that what we're thinking affects us maybe in ways that we don't notice
and then we're find ourselves saying things or doing
things that are in response to these subtle thoughts that perhaps we hadn't seen
so as part of our meditation to be aware of what's happening in our
minds in our
and this subtle and not so subtle ways that our minds work
not that we have to make it a problem and not that we have to make it different
but there's something about just noticing that can help us not be pushed around by
them so may this practice that we do
be for the benefit of all beings everywhere
[Music]
good evening good evening welcome welcome
a really warm welcome
so i would just like to share with you this
this verse that i stumbled upon in the suit does that i've just been thinking about and i really
appreciate for a number of different reasons so the verse goes like this and i
thought that maybe i would unpack it and we could explore it together
little thoughts subtle thoughts when followed stir up the heart
not comprehending the thoughts of the heart one runs here and there
the mind out of control but
comprehending the thoughts of the heart when followed stir up the heart
an awakened one ardent restrained and mindful
lets them go without a trace so i appreciate this
this nod to subtle thoughts little thoughts subtle thoughts
sometimes we just like this idea of thinking just gets put into one
um category like there's just one type of thoughts but i think so many of us recognize that there's the type of
thinking that's a long complicated story or that we're building up and like
maybe it's a whole novel that we're writing and sometimes i talk about this that uh
sometimes story uh sorry thoughts can be more like oh okay just a chapter before
we realize oh yeah i'm supposed to be meditating maybe it's just a paragraph
just a sentence sometimes maybe even just a word
maybe they're really loud and obvious and maybe they're not so obvious maybe
they're subtle but we could ask ourselves or we might even imagine like how many
small seemingly insignificant thoughts do we have
oh during the day and we probably don't notice them and we might follow them innocently enough
thoughts like oh i wonder what the news is i haven't checked the news yet today
and then we go when we check the news on our favorite gizmo and we find ourselves going to another
website and then to another website and maybe before we know it's right we've
much more time than we were expecting or anticipating has been spent just kind of
like surfing the way of going from one thing to the next there's nothing wrong with that right on the internet but
we might notice that somehow we're getting pushed around maybe our intention was not to spend so much time
surfing the internet or clicking on this clicking on that
but instead we notice that there's that we have this little uh
this maybe this push this drive it might be really subtle
to click one more thing one more thing and we might not be noticing kind of a
subtle the sense of lack the sense of
there's not enough sense of i need more
and somehow thinking that okay clicking on that next whatever it is somehow going to make us
feel better that we need more objects like we need to purchase this thing or
i have to consume this information over here read about this other thing or
this sense of just needing more maybe we're not even sure what it is that we need
so this sense of wanting more can be really subtle or really obvious
there was a time on a retreat i remember said uh during the meditation noticing
like the desire coming up i didn't notice it at the very beginning but then notice like oh yeah lots of desire here
kind of relaxing with it noticing it naming it and feeling kind of like the desire dampening down and
sometimes it would flare back up again like oh okay here's desire just
one of the hindrances it doesn't have to be a problem just bring some attention to it and like
soften and relax and allow it to be there so
you know and then the mind starts to settle and i notice this as it starts to settle
towards the end of that particular sit the feeling pretty settled but then the
bell rings and noticing okay this flare up again with this desire it's going to be the
midday meal was going to be next lunch but i thought okay you know i'm just
going to continue sitting and let everybody else go ahead of me in the line
noticing that little desire arise but then the mind could just settle again it was very pleasant to kind of
like notice how the desire had really abated and settled down just by making
room and being for it being with it so then i decide okay it's time i'm
going to go into the dining hall get my plate
for those of you who know have been on retreats right it's a buffet i put some on my plate oh this looks
good oh i'm gonna put some of this oh look at this this looks good oh i better get some more of that and then put some
more of this on and i hadn't even noticed how this desire was showing up in this
different way until i got to the end of the buffet alone and i had mounds of food like all
this food on my plate so this feeling like oh i need more i want more this
sense of lack had followed me and had just kind of shifted
to turn to what i wanted the food so my point here is that it can be
really subtle or it can be obvious when it was a little bit more obvious i could work with it and during the meditation
but sometimes desire in particular can ever sometimes we use this expression this a
long tail that we don't even notice
so we might not notice that there's this uh sense of desire that's there but somehow
is kind of compelling us forward wants wanting something
another type of subtle thought that we might not notice is the inner critic
that is this maybe it's almost like a sub personality inside of us that's constantly putting us down
belittling us this voice of negativity this self-judgment
that we might have blaming ourselves nagging ourselves there's so many different forms it can take
this inner critic but it often has an attitude of harshness it's not particularly kind necessarily
but can be harsh and kind of creates this inner climate this inner
environment of harshness and when the inner critic is up and
running so to speak there can be this feeling of inadequacy
i'm not enough and however i am it's not enough and
i'm not worthy or i'm inadequate or something like this and there's so much pain and
suffering associated with us but for some people it's like so prevalent
they may not even notice it they may just be one of us fall into
this category of a subtle thought they might be thinking like oh this is
just the way it is this is the way reality is
and it's hard maybe perhaps to imagine that it could be otherwise
but this this subtle feelings of lack these subtle feelings of
inadequacy these is these are experiences of dukkha
we often try to translate as suffering but we can also understand it as
something a little more subtle as stress as unsatisfactory
so some of these subtle thoughts are in fact dukkha
and we it's the sense of things are not quite right maybe maybe we don't even
have a real word for it for me i was thinking about this that
it's a little bit like sometimes um perhaps waking up in the middle of
the night but not waking up completely and just having the sense maybe it's too
warm and this feeling like oh it's just not quite right in this kind of i'm going
like this with my hand thrashing around just feel like oh get these covers off of me it's too hot
or something like this this just these gestures get this away from me but we're not quite awake
just this general feeling that things aren't quite right
so dukkha can be like that and these subtle gestures where we're not even quite awake can be this
movement this movement of the heart this movement of the mind
so of course we want to get rid of dukkha of course we respond we have this reactivity of that
we want to get rid of it we've been this is our habit to kind of like push away things that are
duca unsatisfactory not quite right we
respond out of this reactivity because of the conditions we've learned to do this
and of course it's kind of our evolution too right that we have evolved from
those individuals who managed to not have the dukkha of dying
before they passed on their genes so we have evolved from people who have
managed to escape some of the biggest dukkha so
so we are conditioned to believe that we have to remove any sense of things aren't quite right that it's not okay
have this feeling like i don't accept it this shouldn't be happening
of course this is a human response of course we all have this
but something that happens when the arises and this reactivity arises and we don't notice it there's some of these
subtle thoughts there can be this sense this attitude of
should things should be different this kind of quiet demand
that things be a particular way certainly not how they are now but in some other way and
this kind of this sense of having a should creates a type of pressure
that has this maybe this frantic search for what will satisfy this should or make
this dukkha go away or maybe it's this um
just sense of not allowing the experience to unfold but instead to kind
of shove the experience into some particular direction
so when the sense of dukkha arises there's this reactivity and then this reactivity is which is
human but we don't have to have this type of reactivity
the kind of activity that's kind of like demanding that things be a certain way or doing things that not to be a certain
way and so i described that some of this dukkha is related to the sense of lack
like something's missing or maybe a sense of inadequacy like oh yeah i i
need something more
so we often have this idea that happiness can arise from getting what we want
and the same of not getting what we don't want right two sides of the same coin of course
and what we don't see is wanting this
this craving this wanting itself is also a subtle kind of dukkha
so the dukkha arises and there's craving for it to be different but the craving itself is a type of
dukkha so there's this way that the and this can be really subtle
how the suffering the difficulty the not quite rightness can get perpetuated and can be um
a feeling of stuckness of things not being able to move without
this recognition that the craving the wanting itself
has a part of duca is this uncomfortable experience
but instead what happens very often in our lives that we have this little bit of dukkha
this feeling i want something else and something else arises and we feel a
little bit better at that moment and we just naturally assume i feel better because i got something i
obtained something there's something new now that's here
what we haven't noticed and again this is subtle is that actually the happiness
that we're feeling is not because we obtained something it's because the
craving has been let go of it's because there's no longer the
this sense of craving that it's the absence of that
that has allowed the happiness to arise so this happiness is associated with a letting go
but we tend to think that the happiness is associated with it getting so there's a letting go there's kind of
a surrendering there's no longer the wanting and
we might say well yeah there's no longer the wanting because you got what you wanted
but the same feeling of happiness the same feeling of
ease can arise when the craving ends
just because it ends it's impermanent like everything else
maybe the stimulus that was causing us to feel like we needed
something went away maybe all those if we're watching tv all those commercials about food and then we
feel like oh yeah i'm gonna go into the kitchen and see what's in there maybe we turn off the tv and
are no longer seeing all these commercials about food and we no longer have this
we feel this lessening i feel a little bit more ease
so it's not necessarily because we obtained something but it's because that the
craving or the cl the really wanting has been softened that's been let go of
and just for us to you know of course we know this but to remind ourselves that this wanting can go away
without our having gotten anything
that's not the only way in which craving or wanting goes away sometimes it goes away just because the
mind is starts becoming busy with something else something maybe there's a settling of
the mind some meditation
so this happiness of letting go is different than the then the
maybe greater ease that arises with getting something but there's also this letting go of
insisting that things go our way there's also the happiness
of aligning with what is
yeah so there's this little bit of uncomfortableness here
can let go of the idea that it has to be different so there's these deeper kinds of
happiness that are not connected with getting what we want but are connected with letting
go so suffering
many of us know this is of course associated with the first noble truth
is suffering and all these noble truths have tasks
that are associated with them and the one that's associated with the first noble truth is suffering is to be understood
so we often have the misunderstanding that i need to get something in order to
be happy in order to make this suffering go away but part of our understanding of the
suffering is that the craving is part of the suffering and the craving
and the suffering they get intermingled and feed each other and fuel each other and
make it difficult for the suffering to diminish and to go away
so can we understand this about dukkha
that craving is a second noble truth but to understand that craving is part
of it it's also the cause of it but also craving itself is dukkha
and so then this brings me to the next part of this verse the next part of this verse which
i've says not comprehending the thoughts of the heart
not comprehending the thoughts of the heart one runs here and there the mind
out of control trying to end this dukkha
in some way trying this looking there and whatever will help right there sometimes
and this can be really subtle i keep on using this word subtle it can be very quiet it can be not in the
maybe not what's obvious not what we're paying attention to but sometimes i kind
of think of it like peripheral vision it's like these kind of little thoughts
that are on the side this sense of searching maybe a little bit of restlessness of trying to find
so i spoke about we're trying to find something that's craving and this sense of lack this
sense of inadequacy so that can be one way in which the mind and the heart are running all about but
another way is with papancha many of you are familiar with this word papancha it's a polyword
often we can translate it as a mental proliferation that is there's this one thought and
then it just snowballs into maybe it's a sentence that turns into a paragraph
that turns into a chapter that turns into a big novel
so andy olinsky he says he describes uh papancha as these narrative loops that
play over and over again in the mind and the trains of thought pulling out of
the station one after another and taking us for a long ride down the track before
we even know that we're on board so i kind of like this idea right that
these trains of thought we just jump on and off we go
so that's another way that we can think about this second part of the verse not comprehending the
thoughts of the heart one runs here and there the mind out of control
so the idea is that papancha is based on thought we
in the suit does it says that what one thinks about that one mentally proliferates
so it starts with a thought and then turns into papancha but then this verse continues so there
is an escape from this the verse continues but comprehending
the thoughts of the heart when followed stir up the heart so recognizing that all thoughts whether
they are subtle or not have consequences
of course they have consequences everything has consequences and sometimes we tend to think that okay if
they're subtle they're insignificant but it turns out that actually settle is
significant i remember when i first heard shinzen young say this
that settle is significant i heard a dharma talk that he gave and i
really have that's really has stayed with me i think it's true so often these subtle thoughts for these
little subtle things that we aren't paying attention to we tend to be dismissive of them
but in fact they have consequences and maybe because they're all are subtle we
don't really notice and i appreciate the translation translator here for this
is teniserobiku and he's talking about thoughts of the heart
you know conventionally in the west we often think about thoughts or in the mind but he's talking about thoughts of
the heart so maybe the thoughts of the heart or things maybe
they show up in a different way maybe they're inclinations or
they are movements rather than clearly articulated but nevertheless
they have consequences and they impact us so then this verse ends with
an awakened one ardent restrained and mindful
lets them go without a trace so without getting tangled up with the
thoughts and awakened one we can interpret an awakened one here as
one who understands one who sees clearly one who isn't sleeping through
the subtle things that are happening but one who is paying attention an awakened one ardent restrained and
mindful ardent pointing to that it takes a little bit of energy
maybe we can't kind of just drift through our meditations but to put some a little bit of effort
in there not too much so that we're jumping onto everything
and to be restrained that is to not follow where these thoughts are going
and to be mindful of course lets them go
without a trace maybe this idea feels aspirational be
able to let them go without a trace but it's pointing to something important
it's pointing to that happiness doesn't lay with getting what we want it doesn't lay with following all our
whims and there's a practice to help us discover again and again this potential
of letting go of not following
so this verse again little thoughts subtle thoughts when
followed stir up the heart not comprehending the thoughts of the
heart one runs here and there the mind out of control
but comprehending the thoughts of the heart when followed
stir up the heart an awakened one ardent restrained and
mindful lets them go without a trace
so this bow to the power perhaps of subtle thoughts quiet
thoughts little thoughts and how they might be some forms of dukkha
and gil he i read an article recently he based on a dharma talk that he gave i
don't remember exactly year 2000 2002 something like this and he called it
intolerance of suffering and he was and he kind of was using that
word intolerance of suffering as a way to be a little bit provocative
but this idea he's pointing to the same thing here how we tolerate
some of the dukkha of this little bit of craving this little bit of inner critic
feeling inadequate we like tolerate we allow these sufferings
that might be subtle maybe familiar but the encouragement is to notice them
and not so that we can add more suffering on top and create a big long story about how we're bad
meditators because we have them but to notice the impact that they can have on
our lives to notice the way that our responding to these might be
influencing our moods our attitudes our behavior in
ways perhaps we don't notice just an encouragement to
pay attention of the thoughts and the heart or maybe even the way the heart gets
stirred up by some of these subtle thoughts
and may the way that we notice that we get stirred up with some of these subtle quiet
thoughts the way that we notice and then we can
maybe bring some compassion to the suffering for ourself
and to recognize oh the same thing happens in others maybe if some people behave in a way
that's unskillful unhelpful maybe we might consider
that they perhaps have their heart is stirred up maybe they have some of these thoughts and which they haven't noticed
that's causing them to behave in a particular way
so in this way noticing that subtle thoughts of the heart can be a benefit for ourselves
and for others those who are around us and maybe
they're having maybe received compassion or from us or
maybe some non-reactivity from us maybe others can spread that along to others
and in this way we can have more more ease and peace in the world
thank you