good morning friends welcome again to the morning
meditation and darmat and i'm happy to be having another day
with you and if you've been following along you probably
have surmised that we i'm going to talk about the fire element today
and we'll do a guided meditation with that
i wanted to start by naming especially sitting here at this moment in time and
the end of this summer the complexity
of our relationship with the elements it's not all
roses so to speak it we're very aware with the fire element
with the fires that have been burning with the amount of smoke even if you're not nearby that you've had
the people probably many of us know i do people whose houses have burned and the
vast swathes of forest and to acknowledge this these elements
are powerful the earth shakes
the waters flood the fires burn
they when we stand in face of these elements and see
the power of them there's can be it's a huge sense of awe that comes
through us and it's interesting having this the enormity of the elements the power
of them and to recognize that these same elements flow through us
we are not separate from that and a certain portion of that power is
flowing through us as well we're we're in conversation with that
and this is even more evident when we sort of feel into climate change and the
way every all the elements are being amplified and we
as human beings are very much much in relationship with that
we are an expression of the elements and we are affecting the elements
and whether we sense it on a very grand scale you know standing at the edge of
the grand canyon and looking in and seeing the power of water and earth
and the physical result of that or whether you taste a
summer tomato and feel the sun and the earth in it the elements are
expressing themselves all around us in these subtle and powerful ways
and as we touch in and practice with the elements we're being invited into this
full complexity of from the very
subtle sensations in our body to the grand expressions
that are around us i
will say for myself that i live where i do in the desert in
utah partially because i really enjoy
the dramatic expression of the elements the
fiery sun and the earth rising up dramatically and the intensity of the
wind and the storms when they come there is a
potency and aliveness when we meet that rawness of the elements
and it can be terrifying as well that word awe
includes both of those so i want to name that as we move into
practicing with the fire element the complexity and the
breadth of the experience that we have with them
so please go ahead and find your meditation your comfortable meditation
posture
and i'd like to begin by reading a quite a very wonderful quote from
john seed and joanna macy speaking about fire
fire from our sun that fuels all life drawing up plants and raising the waters
to the sky to fall again replenishing the inner furnace of our metabolism
burns with the fire of the big bang that first sent matter energy spinning
through space and time and the same fire as the lightning that
flashed in the primordial soup catalyzing the birth of organic life
you were there i was there for each cell of our bodies is descended
in an unbroken chain from that event
allowing your body sensing it
feel it in contact with the earth
scan through and find any places of tension
and let this pull this connection with the earth let it be here let yourself rest into it
you can touch in to the other elements as we begin feel
the weight and heaviness of your body feel the contact with the ground
and the ground beneath you
feel the wateriness of your body as you soften
as you bring attention to different parts of the body and the little micro movements
of the softening allowing the water element to come from frozen
into its softer more liquid form the rigidity of the body being released
letting the spine stand tall
with the earth element the solidity holding you up
and the softness of the water
and then beginning to allow yourself to come into contact with the fire element
first sensing very simply and directly the places of heat
of warmth and of cool on your body
perhaps there's places where the clothes the
warmth of certain parts that are in contact with more protection and then the exposure perhaps
feet or hands or face
letting yourself also feel internally
the warmth the warmth in your belly
the warmth in your chest
this fire element that comes
that comes from our sun the sun
heating the ground the plants photosynthesizing
the energy accumulating and as the energy accumulates
and then we eat it we take in that energy we're running on sun fuel
the warmth of the sun warming us energizing us
the warmth comes from the outside from the sun
heating the earth we can feel it on our skin and we can feel it from the inside the
sun transformed into energy taken in
used with movement and digestion
keeping it all alive and then dissipating
this element of fire is constantly changing
warm to cool cool to warm as it passes through
constantly in a state of disintegration as well this food comes in the energy is
used and dissipated released
and gone
feeling the sun in your belly
and this energy also in our heart we feel the sense of
fire of passion in our heart there's a heat a warmth
of our heart it's like there's a line
going from sun to heart to molten earth down below us
from molten to molten our hearts here in the middle
feel how you too are part as john seed has said
part of that big bang the energy of the universe
the heat of it is in your body
temporarily being expressed and just like the sun
burning itself burning itself out but burning brightly
you might also sense in yourself the urges the urge to move the urge to
do things the passion for life for things that you care about
this heatedness of us this is an expression too
of the fire element as it expresses itself in us
the sun the energy the warmth and cool flowing through us
we are part of this vast exchange of the fire element
no inside no outside simply fire element
passing through combining with other elements and being released
feel the change we're cool then heat
change directly on your skin in your belly
how it changes energetically in your heart
in the restlessness and calm with your body
if there is something in your life that is present and agitating you
or eliciting passion or compassion let yourself feel the fire aspect of it
don't need to go into the content but let yourself feel
now this too is the fire element
let yourself tune to the fire element however it's showing up most clearly to
you letting it flow and change
coming and going fire element
simply moving through
so
where do you sense warmth and cools now in your skin and your belly and your
heart
coming going changing
is there fire in some way or are you more tuned to the absence of
fire the cooling the quiet
so
[Music]
the quote from john seed and joanna macy's so wonderful that i'd like to read it to you again
fire from our sun that fuels all life drawing up plants and raising the waters
to the sky to fall again replenishing the inner furnace of our metabolism
burns with the fire of the big bang that first scent matter
energy spinning through space and time and the same fire as the lightning that
flashed in the primordial soup catalyzing the birth of organic life
you were there i was there for each cell of our bodies is descended
in an unbroken chain from that event
lovely image the lightning spark of
life bringing us all here keeping us all going
and as i shared in the meditation we're most aware of the fire element in the
essence of sun and heat and energy and if you think about the amount of
that energy is such a key component in our lives we can energy both personally
inside us with our you know every step we take is an expression
of sun of fire of energy coming through us
i move my hand and it's like that's the result of the sun expressing itself here
and this way that the fire element not unlike the other one not unlike the
other ones but we're very aware with the fire element of this transition back and forth between heat
and cool the release and movement
of energy the whole play of matter and energy is so
clear here and the central element of digestion
i'll read to you the from that suit and i think i said
yesterday to somebody when they asked it was pseudo40 and i'm sorry it's also in suta 140 but the suta i'm actually
quoting is number 62. and this is what he says about the fire
element what is the internal fire element
whatever internally belonging to oneself is fire fiery and clung to
that is that by which one is warmed ages and is consumed
and that by which what is eaten drunk consumed and tasted gets completely
digested or whatever else internally belonging to oneself is fire fiery and clung to
this is called the internal fire element now both the internal fire element and
the external fire element are simply fire element and that should be seen as it actually
is with proper wisdom thus this is not mine this i am not
this is not myself i want to point out something in this
that's a little different than the other elements he talks to
it talks about he says that by which one is warned ages and is consumed
there's a way and then he acknowledges the digestion and
but there's a way he's speaking here to this way the fire element has a also
a consuming a kind of moving from and he said ages the fact that in some
ways the fire element in us that we're burning with the fire element that it's what
um not only powers ourselves powers us but also burns us up
there's something very um
this is core to the fire element the way that it
consumes what in in its very expression it is consuming
and we can feel this also in the energy the passion of us
the warmth of the heart the fierce compassion has a desire to move to do to
express itself not just to sit or be and we feel this sometimes with the
passion of anger this consuming almost chaotic when you
watch a fire there's a chaoticness to it right there's like this
this energy that's quite uh
it's quite compelling for one thing but it's also got this
rather ferocious if you think of goddesses and in
hindu traditions and when you see fierce monsters there's that in the tibetan
tonkas they're expressing this consumptive
uh quality and one of the things here that becomes clear
is that when fire is paired with clinging
as he points out to there when it is clung to then it is associated even more directly
with this agitation with consumption with greed with wanting
with destruction with anger
there's a lack of balance when it's paired with
the with clinging and this really points to the nature
of dominant experience or nature of our culture that we are the fire element i
mean look how we're burning we're burning the fossil fuels we're
burning with speed with energy and we're burning ourselves up in doing this
there's a lack of balance and yet we have this cultural attraction towards
the fire we we want to move faster do
more and very interestingly in the buddhist
teachings when fire is paired with non-clinging
it is freedom it is nibana the bana is talked about as the cooling
the releasing of fire from that which is which it is which it clings to
read you a quote from fra john jutico a thai forest
monk he said the mind released is like fire that has gone out
the fire is not annihilated but is still there diffused in the air
it simply no longer latches on to any fuel
so this brings a query for us in our practice what is it to have this fire
this compassion of the of the heart the
warmth but not flavored with the clinging
by the greed and the wanting i had a very direct
felt experience of this releasing element of fire of
a sort of different cultural experience you might say
um i once went to burning man and the second
there's the there's a day where they burn this huge thing this man that
stands huge tall and it's fiery and energy and everybody's yelling and
screaming and there's this chaotic kind of energy
and then the next night there is a temple
that has been built some of you may have been there some of you this isn't your thing but just
imagine this huge beautiful temple all built out of wood
and it's and people over the week of burning man
have been going into this temple and you there's stairs and it's big
inside and it's raw wood and people
write on the temp inside the temple with you know like massive
invitation for graffiti they write the names
and messages to people that have passed in the previous year
so it's a temple to the impermanent passing and then on this
day it on this day after the burning of the man the temple is burned
huge fire all those names all those people
being sent and released and what was for me
incredibly dramatic about it is there were i think there's like 20 000 people
all surrounding the temple out at a distance
and it was so
quiet you could have heard a pin drop complete and utter quiet
recognizing the incredible power of fire
and release
and this is our practice release of clinging
in the silence in the stillness is the power and the
release of the power and our query as we practice
is to invite ourselves to burn with fierce compassion
for all forms and yet recognizing their ultimate empty
nature not to cling
everything is disintegrating that's it that's its nature
and in the midst of that the purity of the compassionate heart and the opportunity to meet at all
everything so fully and to know the blessing and the awe
of the world fire is an invitation
to all of this so
thank you all for joining this morning and i want to
um before you go offer you a practice for this day around fire
to see if you can feel the fire you can feel it just as heat and warmth but i
invite you to feel fire and what it's like when you cling
when there's the fire element there's passion there's the urge to move and when is it connected
and held in place with clinging and what is the essence of fire as it
moves through you in the moments when there's not clinging can you feel that difference
that's my invitation for you for today so thank you all again very much and