great so hello everyone hello and welcome
hmm makes me so happy to be with you and see you what ah what a joy what a gift for us to be
able to come together in this way even though we are
separate in space and maybe even in time for those who are listening later on
audio drama but we come together to practice we come together to practice so
this makes me also happy to see your faces on zoom yay gift to me
so so for our practice together today um the theme i'd like to invite us
to explore is um is this so in the practice
of meta cultivating loving-kindness metta
there are four traditional phrases and we offer them during happy hour and
they go something like this and there are different variations of them with by different teachers etc but basically
they go something like this may you may i be safe or may i feel safe
may i be happy may i be healthy may i have ease and then could be may you be safe
may you feel safe happy healthy ease so safe happy healthy ease
so the first one had the first wish the first cultivation having to do with with safety with feeling safe with being
safe offering safety second one with um second wish with mental happiness
and then the second the third with the physical happiness which is health and the last one overall ease
in life taking care of oneself happily um
how once how one's life flows so
tonight i'd like to focus on the first wish which is safety one of
safety and sometimes that appears actually as an odd one
i remember the first years of my practice i could get the yeah may i may you
may they be say may they be happy and healthy and have ease yeah especially the happy and
healthy one i got yep sure it's the wish but safety i wasn't quite sure and then some
teachers also put it in the order to be the second or the third after happy and healthy whereas i think
traditionally it's actually the first one so so why safety what's
what's why is this safety important let's explore that a little bit
so i'll share from my own experience that
years later when i was doing intense retreat practice it occurred to me and i was playing with
the orders and saying them in different order just exploring these sentences these
phrases these ways of cultivating meta
i realized that actually feeling safe or being safe is the precursor
of all the other ones until you feel safe until you are safe
there's a sense of basic sense of safety those other happinesses
physical mental ease they can't really happen really safety is is the basic one
is the basic need for safety almost if we thought of the um
[Music] maslow's hierarchy of needs you know it's very basic sense of having shelter and
food and just kind of the safety is very very basic very basic um
and also there is other psychological research with with bulbies attachment theory
that's safety when we feel safe there's a sense of safety that
for many of us starts with our relationship our parental relationship with our moms and the sense
of safety ah then all those other happinesses physical mental um get laid on top so
this wish for safety that we cultivate may i be safe may i feel safe may you be safe may i may you
feel safe again there are different versions of that i'll talk about that in a moment
this wish for safety cultivating or feeling into safety is really really
important really important and
often when we're practicing the sense of safety if we feel safe if our hearts feel safe it's really
hard to concentrate if you're sitting in an environment and if you're feeling scared it's really hard for the heart
to settle for the mind to settle and have any level of concentration or samadhi or stillness
there will be a lot of agitation if there is in safety so it's an important one to really bring attention to to bring
awareness to and cultivate in our wish in our turning our mind our
hearts to it just another thing i wanted to say before we start practicing and exploring
is sometimes the extended um phrases may i be safe may i feel safe
from inner and outer harm inner and outer harm and then inner harm
is what is how we harm ourselves through our thoughts our actions
emotions basically the three poisonous roots greed hatred and confusion
that take our own safety away in our own heart
and then there is external safety may i feel safe from outer arm and another aspect i want
to bring in is can we be safe can we offer safety to others
can we be a safe person for others that's really important
so that they're not scared of us they're not afraid of us
may i be safe may i be a safe haven may i be safe for others
may i be safe may others feel safe in my presence so that can be another aspect
another way that we can explore this first beautiful phrase of meta
so so i've spoken plenty tonight about this
safety thing let's practice together so i invite you to land
in your meditation posture
ah see how the sense of safety
what do you need you need to shift and move
you need to lie down if you need a blanket to wrap yourself in or a shawl and now i
feel cold okay so here i'm gonna take care of myself
what do you feel what do you need what do you need right now ah
to tap into to feel into
sense of containment contentment safety
at this present moment can the heart
relax
and relaxing softening the body
landing relaxing into the muscles
with your sit bones to your feet your legs
feeling a sense of safety that the cushion the chair is supporting you
the laws of gravity are not suddenly going to change
that you fall if there's a sense of safety trust relying
that yes the chair the cushion holds you
and it's going to continue to hold your sense of safety
in being held
in the law of gravity lawful nature
of the law of gravity letting your body relax into it
and if thoughts are rising ruminations
can we let go [Music] release trusting that
if they're important enough they'll come back trusting that right now we don't need to
be thinking this do we really
letting go ah releasing
landing in the cocoon the safety the ease
of this moment just as it is however it is it doesn't
need to be different
letting the breath be received in the lower abdomen one breath at a
[Music]
time
letting the awareness loving awareness receive each breath calming soothing
settling one breath at a time
as the breath is breathed in
can we acknowledge that in this moment
there's a roof over our head indoors
ah there's a safety from the elements
from the rain the cold the sun whatever might be happening
where you are
feeling yourself wherever you're sitting
acknowledging safety from the elements
with each breath perceived in the
abdomen
now if you would conjure up someone in whose presence
you feel safe you can be yourself you feel safe
either someone from your life someone living or even deceased is okay
as long as no grief arises or an archetype
the buddha kuan yin or archetype from any other religion
or theology that works for you just feeling safe the presence of this being this person
conjuring up their presence as clearly as possible for you
then notice how your body your heart can relax feel safe
gently drop in the phrase may i feel
safe may i feel safe
if the feelings of lack of safety come up fear perhaps worry
self-judgment in this practice can we offer those
thoughts emotion safety let your fear feel safe it doesn't have
to go away or be squashed ah or the worry
or anything else any other thoughts or emotions that are rising
offering safety through and through no part left out
may i feel safe may i be safe from inner harm
offering safety to every part of yourself
see what happens be curious
just as this compassionate being that you conjured up this kind presence in your life wants
you to be safe wishes you safety can we wish it for
ourselves as a sharing a blessing so showering ourselves with a blessing
fully well knowing that life is uncertain of course and yet we cultivate our heart
in wishing well and offering a gift of goodwill
may i feel safe may i be safe
from inner and outer harm
may this being who is me who shows up in this way in this body and this mind this
[Music] conditioning
may there is her may their heart feel safe
may their body feel safe whatever the circumstances of life
may there be sense of inner goodness and safety lack of fear fearlessness
trust that supports all goodness blossom
now if you wish you're welcome to bring in the other phrases of mitta after the one for safety or to stay with
safety
may i be safe from indoor and utter harm
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i have ease
maybe after bringing in the other phrases safeties oh even more resonant
may be safe from inner and outer arms
may this being was me may they may i
be happy and joyful
may this person knows me
may they be healthy may i be healthy as much as possible
may this being have the benefit the blessing of health
as much as available
may this being lose me have ease in their life may i have ease
may this life of mind flow with ease
may i take care of myself happily
may i be safe may i feel safe from inner and outer heart
may i be safe both for myself
how i treat myself how i speak to myself
and may i be safe for others
hey
and for the last moment of this practice
we offer ourselves safety for however this practice period was
whether there was sleepiness distractions instead of judging ourselves bereading
ourselves can we offer safety to our heart to our minds and appreciation thank you
dear thanks for showing up as best as you were able to you're safe
you showed up thank you i offer you safety i offer myself safety
and see what that feels like even for just a moment to offer ourselves safety
[Music]
thanks everyone for your practice
so so much to explore in this theme of safety what a rich theme
so we have some time love to invite you what did you discover
what came up for you if you would be willing to share something that you discovered can raise
your zoom hand please or you can type in chat
if typed in chat to me alone i won't say your name will be private
if to everyone then it will be they'll read out your name also
so what did you discover friend please
i've always been confused by this concept of safety within the
meta group and uh you're acknowledging your own initial confusion
sort of helped lead me into wondering about it as i was
exploring it and i was struck by how powerful it was to me as i
uh thought about uh two two men who when i was a young man who
had been uh both of whom have been important to me as mentors and um one dead now and the other i just
don't know if he's still living and being being with the two of them it
was a um i'm much older than they were when they were important to me as a young person
but being shoulder to shoulder with them in recollection and feeling
was uh really really comforting to me and it also
made me recognize that later in my life when i was able to play the role that
they played for me with other young men i drew a lot of that from them though
not largely conscious of it but that sense of safety just like a sense of danger can be passed
down and spread out in ways that are untraceable
thank you thank you fred thank you
for for your eloquent description of
this receiving of safety and then passing it on as a
gift what a gift thank you so much guitar please
i've been always finding that safety is a key piece to all of the meta and until i
reckoned with this it was impossible for me to have any access to the other pieces and
i learned again during this session that sometimes it it didn't help me to think of people
at all not at all and i do know that some cultures and
mine included who has been mass traumatized there is sometimes a level of
hyper vigilance and innate um
lack of safety that it's it's not reflected in one's life you can do all
kinds of courageous things and people would never know but only through meditation and those um
explorations i mean i recognize that i relate to a lot of things in my life through fear and i
would have never understood that and um interestingly what occurred to me
i was popping a candy in my mouth during the meditation and it happened to have the flavor of an ice cream i had it as a child
and that recollection somehow provided safety but no no other thing and i don't definitely
didn't expect that and um also related to that i've been
the way i've been dealing with this notion that i just described and that i've known about for a while sort of how
how it can be difficult to feel safe at a very very elemental level i've been trying to add
to my meta practice to make myself safe for my fear
and um just adding that peace and saying my fear can be a safe place i can be a
safe place for my fear even though i would have never even years ago characterized this lack of
safety as fear fear is way too big a word it's much more subtle than that but
again it's it's sort of how i feel i relate to many things in my life if i'm really honest
so that makes sense a bit convoluted oh absolutely made very clear sense
thank you so much for sharing yes of course and beautiful practice of offering
safety to your fear beautiful what what a beautiful way to acknowledge it and to
work with it offering safety to yourself and the fear and also i'm just delighted
so much modita for this serendipitous discovery of of popping this this candy and
and oh it's like proust and then madeline right it's it it just brought in back
this sense of safety and actually one um one invitation i would have
especially knowing that your your mother tongue is not english is to practice
offering your fear safety and offering yourself safety
in your mother tongue and and i know it's for me it's been transformative saying the phrases and
farsi like this sense of safety that i had when i was a child with my grandmother and my mother was like oh my
wow is powerful and something that you tapped into with with this with this candy flavor
opens that up beautiful yeah thank you guitar thank you
yeah so letting me share yeah thank you for sharing so powerful yeah thanks to both of you
for sharing your insights powerful
so let us turn to holding each other with safety
and offering safety this is an important part of tonight's practice offering safety to others offering
safety to others how can we listen offering safety to others this is an
important practice people please please if you can stay if you have to go you have commitments
but if you can't stay how can you show up and offer safety to someone else how does it look
like what does it see feel like to do that and and then notice what it feels like for others to
be doing that for you so let's start with 15 seconds of silent offering safety
may you be safe may you be safe people you'll be in a small group with and then share what you discovered and
listen with offering safety i think this can be very interesting so let's let's practice
together let's practice together in this way so creating the breakout rooms
and opening them they are open here we go okay
welcome back everyone the rooms are closed so we have a few minutes for any
reflections what did you discover what did you notice in this practice
of offering safety to yourself and others jerry says wow jerry would you like to
say more please i'm going to ask you to hear you can
unmute yourself there you go so uh i was just you asked us to uh
um how do can we provide safety to others and i was just we were reflecting as a collective about
just being here and this sangha is and participating as a way of
providing safety to others and ourselves and and the small groups as well it's just a extraordinary rich
environment so thank you for all you do and thanks to everyone here
i think that uh that's how at least right now how i'm doing it beautiful
thank you jerry thank you for your participation and everyone's participation in this
co-creation of cultivation of safety beautiful thank you
other reflections what did you discover especially if you
haven't spoken for a while would love to hear from you or if you're new what did you discover
neil please that was a lovely meditation
you know i found and certainly the people in my group seemed to also
you know had taken on like a new understanding of how important safety is
you know and you know and how important it is you know to make others feel safe
and how important it is to make ourselves feel safe it was a lovely practice it was a lovely
conversation i thank both of you yeah i mean there was some discussion
about how how you know the relationship between making somebody feel
safe and and loving them you know and that you know there
certainly is you know some you know tight relationship there
absolutely exactly that's it it's beautifully said um
it wasn't me but thanks [Laughter] beautifully explored co-created by all
of you this relationship between safety and love exactly yeah maybe we will explore
that more on on friday so we have come to the thank you neil
thank you so much and thank you to all of you thank you for your practice thank you for showing up
today and cultivating your heart in offering safety to
yourself and to all other beings may all beings be safe may all beings be
happy may all beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone