what a delight to sit with other people
to feel the energy of the people in this room has been wonderful
so so gil was unable to make it this morning
and um that's kind of a lovely thing for me as i said earlier
i haven't been here in a couple of years and that's unusual
it's an unusual circumstance even even driving here this morning i thought
how familiar it all was how familiar and how
how much it has been absent the absence of what was once so familiar i have a
i have a an electric car and it it saves addresses and imc is saved and in
defaults every every time i get in the car it defaults to coming to imc
and so for two years i've been putting up with which what has become an irritation and this morning it was true
whoa um
and sitting up here is familiar although i haven't set cross-legged since i fell
the first of september so i'm experiencing unusual hip movement so
that's just how it is you know we're we we come into this day and this is how it is
and that's what i'd like to talk with you about this morning i want to talk about impermanence and the familiar
and how they intersect and when they don't and what this means for us in our
practice so
while the teaching of the dharma has not changed over the last two years the context the context for talking about
the dharma has changed a great deal
i've noticed a lot of changes in my own personal practice i do uh online groups practice
discussion groups which if you've never tried i really invite you to try they're quite
wonderful and each time i meet with a group it is
a realization that these people are showing up in this moment with these issues with these conditions
and that each time is unique each breath is unique
there is a patina of the familiar sitting in this hall you know that's a that's that's sort of
the coding that goes over surfaces the patina this this statue has a particular
patina over the bronze that makes keeps it this color and the familiar life that we live
does the same thing we don't often think about how the familiar becomes a condition
for this moment we talk about it in different ways you know we cultivate
skillful practices so that it becomes a habit for us
but it turns out that largely we humans have kind of a plan for how the day is
going to go i'm not talking about the agenda plan i'm talking about what we expect to happen in the next moment or
the next hours or the next days or the next weeks we expect things to be a certain way
because we become accustomed to thinking about things that way we become accustomed this is this is how life
works and this is when it feels right
now sometimes that has to do with our ideals how we'd like things to be
but it's the basic assumptions that we have about how things are the assumptions we have about how things are
without noticing how they are that becomes the trap for us
we have a plan i call it an experience bias
my experience leads me to believe what i think about that experience leads me to
believe and so of course this is what it's like to sit in a hall
let me tell you how different this is never have i given a dharma talk in a mask
not only do i hear my voice and feel my hands now i'm feeling the breath inside this
mask and i it feels a little muffled and my voice sounds a little muffled and
generally it's the same but it is not the same it is
according to the conditions of this moment
we have an idea about what should be happening and then you know life happens
and we have strategies right so this morning it's not as noticeable here but where i live up by 280 there's
it's extremely foggy very dense fog and there was a bicyclist that pulled in
front of me i was going up sand hill toward 280 and there's a place where the bicyclists have to cross the
line of traffic going to san francisco to get in the bike lane to continue out sand hill
and it was so so thick i just barely saw him and i saw
the fear in his eyes you know i blinked my lights to let him know i had seen him as he was crossing
that lane of traffic but i imagined how frightening that could be
and how fortunate it was that i was actually looking for a bicyclist because
i'm familiar with the area and therefore i saw him and that that moment of uncertainty
and the the my preparedness for a bicyclist made it more likely i would see him
but it wasn't a given and one of the things that's been on my mind particularly this morning was
from the talk that gil gave last week where he was talking about time and he made a statement
that has really stuck with me and he said hurrying is an attachment going fast is
not and that we can behave in a certain way
but when we are attached to some outcome of that behaving a certain way that's when we create suffering
when we're attached to what is normal that creates suffering this folks where we are sitting now
wherever you are sitting is normal
everything else is a fantasy it may not be what we want
what we hope for what we dream about my family right now is in london
to me that's terrifying what are they doing going to london they're all multiply vaccinated and you
know they haven't seen their in-laws the other side of the family for three years and they're old
and they want to see them i get it normal for me is worrying about my
family in the context of the pandemic that is normal
if i treat it as an imposition i'm denying this is how it is
this is how it is sometimes we embrace it you know the
unexpected the not according to plan i would put winning lottery winnings in this category you know how great how
lucky can you be this is wonderful sometimes we marvel
you know i get to be a grandmother without ever having children of my own because i married someone who had
children how great how lucky for me so i get the delight of that i embrace
that the unexpected can have
pleasant outcomes or unpleasant outcomes they just are the things that happen in
life the experiences we have are just those experiences and somehow we have this idea that we
should be able to control the nature of those experiences which is denying the fact that there are
very few conditions that are conditioning this moment that we actually have any influence on much
less control over
now we can we can name things like the pandemic or the weather or taxes
but the very air we breathe we don't have control over it
what we have some measure of influence on
are the ways that we approach this moment
the attitude with which i meet this moment
we tend to think of our experiences not in increments but as a continuing stream
you know my life happened it's these things happened and they led to those things and led to those things and led to those
things and led to this moment and we have this idea that life is this stream
and we don't really think of it as packets of experience and it's this continuing stream
bias that we have that leads us to think that the familiar is what is right
that the familiar is somehow something we can navigate but we're really creating the familiar
in our minds we're creating the familiar in our minds
there are two things that that i read a lot of besides dharma things and those are
neuroscience and the pandemic and as a former scientist i spend a lot of time
reading the scientific papers and neuroscience is doing amazing things
these days and our assumptions about how the brain works how the mind works
are mostly obsolete uh so so i was reading a book by lisa
barrett and i just took this line out of it it says
every thought memory emotion or perception that you construct in your life
includes something about the state of your body
wow the book is about how in fact we don't think about our emotions and react to
our emotions but that the thinking is just justifying the emotions that are already there the emotions we actually construct
by information from our bodies and and sort of absorbing what that means
lands us right in the middle of our buddhist practice it implores us to be aware of what's
happening now because that's what's creating constructing our emotions
and that the habits of mind that we have are the ways in which we react to
what's happening but the brain is busy just gathering data
and sometimes makes decisions without the data the current data if it's it's based on what's happened in the past
these conditions are there and therefore this is what is required but it doesn't know about these
conditions we can be aware of these conditions
resistance to what we think of as normal resistance to now is not being normal
resistance to normal are all still resistance you know
if if i get in a slump because things just aren't as lively as they
used to be they aren't as oh i don't get to travel as much i don't get to i walked in the hall i saw
friends i wanted to hug i couldn't hug them what's that about
well that's the condition of now
why in order to feel affection in my heart do i need
a more familiar way of engaging people i can ignore
the rising of affection in my heart and dampen it by what i am missing
or i can just feel the delight and those choices have to do with how i
relate to what is familiar
i invite you to become well aware of what you constitute
how you influence and condition your life your body by what is familiar
which is not to say that familiar is bad it is a great joy to me that i can sit
this way on the on this dice with in meditation pose and i haven't
tried it for a couple of months and look at that it's not only possible it's very possible oh
i can be delighted at that or i can think about all those missed opportunities
which didn't exist
didn't exist when there are too many deviations from
what we think is familiar from what is familiar to us we begin to build up a set of
resistances resentments we feel a sense of betrayal
you know it's been it's very common to hear someone say well you know they promised us this would be
over by now well based on the information that was
available then that's what it looked like
okay that's not how it is how do i meet that
i can have the thought of betrayal of not fair
not fair it just feels not fair
oh what's that about i'm not feeling something not
oh i'm not getting what i expected fairness doesn't have anything to do
with it really if i if i notice that thought i don't banish the thought
i say what's where do i feel that not fairness what's what's not fair and i feel the wanting
the leaning towards something else i can feel that
is in being mindful of this notion
and saying what else is in this notion what else is here
that allows me to keep from putting something in a box i label familiar and say oh my god i'm so depressed
if we're truly in touch with impermanence with the arising and passing away of all
things we recognize that we have to disentangle from this
idea that everything is this continuous stream with a well-known past and a projected
future life appears to be a stream just as we
appear to be a continuous person even though even the cells of our body
are sloughed off every couple of months they're totally different
but you know the overall pattern the over all familiar part is well that hasn't changed has it it appears not to
change because we have this continuing stream
this continuing stream of what we think experience is and we link all our experiences together and we give them
meaning
what you notice when you contemplate this is it's all about how we think about
experience what we think about what's happening now
what we think about it's it's all of those thoughts
rearranging the experience into a pattern i'm taking all these clumps and i'm
making it look like this and it is the collage of my life
but if we can become disenchanted with our own story
we have the opportunity to just meet these experiences
these experiences of this moment fresh eyes
when we follow our breath we're not thinking about how the breath was yesterday we're really just following
our breath that practice of nowness of suchness
is not just for breathing it's about the experiences of our lives
if we can disentangle ourselves from the story of my life
then it becomes possible to more closely see what is arising in this moment
what's arising in this moment as distinct from our experiences of the
familiar this happens in unexpected ways this attachment to the familiar you know
uh i've lived with my husband for over 30 years maybe 35 years i've stopped
counting and he has some habits that irritate me
as i do from his point of view this is not a one-way street but one of
the things he does is uh he he has a much higher tolerance for
clutter than i do that clutter pervades he has his own office space
which i do not enter because i will immediately start picking things up which of course he finds very
irritating but the shared spaces i bump into
often and while we have grown to accommodate each other over the years
i can see when the conditions are right when i am maybe in a hurry
that his clutter notice that's his clutter clutter left by him
not picked up by me becomes especially irritating and i notice that irritation and that
jitteriness and and then i remind myself that it isn't about him
it's not even about me it's about attachment to an outcome that
that clutter is getting in the way of but because it has become so familiar it becomes very easy to blame him
for my attachment to some outcome and sometimes i even notice that happening
right i'll go okay this is not about him not about him
this is you wanting something and that allows me
to be consistent with one of my intentions in life which is to be kind to my husband
and in the moment that i realize this is not about him i become aware of that intention also
and my heart softens that happens
it isn't about me saying i'm not going to behave that way it's about a series of realizations that
happens in the now okay irritability irritability
not him [Music] i can feel irritability in my in my body
he's not in my body this is in me this irritation irritation
irritation it's not that my knee hurts it's irritation
because i'm rushing rushing oh i i have a plan i have something i want to do
realizing that in a moment it isn't that i'm a bad person it's that i see
attachment to some outcome and that pause
the pause created by that seeing allows me to recall my intention
of kindness and the heart softens
i don't order my heart to soften that would be a useless instruction
it happens in the course of seeing clearly
this is the real value of mindfulness and the acceptance of impermanence and
not allowing the pattern to become the defining characteristic of now
i'm influenced by the pattern i'm subject to the pattern
but if i see the pattern
other possibilities exist i'm remembering a time when
when i told my mother-in-law who is no longer with us that my next house our next house was
going to be more zen-like and she said and who will you be married to
she then apologized for not bringing him up correctly but
this is all a sense of patterns and how we think things should be how we think about our
experience becomes a condition of the experience so it becomes very important to notice
how we're thinking about what's happening to be aware of how the mind is imposing
some thought pattern on the experience and to get as closely as possible to the
rawness of that experience and not stop with the first word we come
up with to say oh this is what this is
what is closest to us try to get as close in that mindfulness as possible
what else is here what else is here
i'm restless i'm jittery well jitteriness is here if i don't
identify with the jitteriness with the restlessness i have an opportunity to see what else is present
i don't have to jump in the vat of restlessness
i can see discomfort maybe i don't have to name discomfort maybe i don't have to give it a familiar name
maybe i can just say unpleasant
now i could argue that the smell of a ripe tree cheese can be unpleasant and it can also
taste delicious
and any moment that we experience unpleasantness we can look at the unpleasantness and
the very act of seeing oh this is unpleasant allows us to
slip back and settle into a place of seeing that is a moment of ease and
equanimity maybe it's just the briefest of moments
but notice it it is the in the noticing the awareness
of what's happening that we become that we form memories and that we form other patterns
we give the brain other information that it adds to this store of information
when it's making up its vision of what familiar is and we can become familiar with the
aha in the same way when we're meditating
and we notice that the mind has gone off into a story and we say oh
that's the very moment when we are here the very moment and we can say oh i'm
here and this becomes a practice for any moment
any moment when we are aware enough to say i am here
is a moment of being awake a moment of justice of just this
experience it's not that we arrive at this place by
some magical absorption of qualities or you know
some practice that makes us all of a sudden aware of every moment
it's just this moment this moment is the only moment that we can actually be responsible for
and i can allow myself to wander off into some place or i can notice my hand drifting off
into the air and in the noticing there is a form of awareness here
that is a registering when we talk about mindfulness
we remember that there is the object there is the knowing the object
and there is knowing we know that last step
that awareness step is crucial in coming close to
what is happening in this moment now i can say i'm sitting here but unless i'm actually feeling and noticing
my bottom on this cushion i'm not really aware of sitting i know
it but i don't know that i know it i don't know what's behind me
okay that's not going to work for me so gil gave me some advice last night and he said you should have the youtube
running so you can keep track of of chat you know what people are saying
well which is good but then i don't have a computer i have an ipad and it doesn't work the same way
[Laughter] i'm unsuccessful at doing that so for anybody who has a chat item that they
want me to notice i'm just not i'm not up on it so that's not going to happen
that's that's the that's the moment okay that's not going to happen i can bemoan that or i can just say
that's not going to happen it's just this
it's just this impermanence is the arising and passing
away of all things and when we think about impermanence we mostly think about the passing away
we think about the loss we think about what's missing we think about the deterioration you know my hip is giving
me trouble because frankly i'm old and i have arthritis and i fall and you know stuff happens and as time goes on i can
become overly aware of aging or i can just say well now those are things i do and those
are things i don't do last night my husband and i went looking
for something on a trail that he had lost and it was going to be a long trip
around to get to this place and the uh it was past dusk
so it was really kind of foolish for us to be looking anyway but we were good so there was a steep rise up to the path
right where we were so i scrambled up and then slid back down because i didn't
have scrambling shoes on and then i did it again and and we made it
um not gracefully not elegantly but we made it
okay that's how that went when i left the house i didn't plan to
do any scrambling up the side of a steep path
okay we did not find what we looked for but it felt pretty good just to do that
so if if we're focused on the only uh only successful outcome was that
we would have missed the full moon that we got to see on the path over the balance
and that's the thing about mindfulness it doesn't have to be what you choose to
be mindful of it's really the blessing of mindfulness is in the unexpected
it is in the arising part of a rising and falling
this is the primary thing that i have been exploring for myself over the
last few months that impermanence is not about loss and going away
more than it is about what is arising what is arising
if it doesn't arrive it doesn't you we don't lose it in the first place it doesn't go away in the first place
this emphasis on what is arising brings me more closely into the moment and more
close and more intimate with what my experience really is
so i've adopted an infam emphasis on arising
what is arising
and i don't rush to name it i notice something about it
and say so what else
uh i got dressed this morning and i was trying to decide what to wear and i you know it's i don't know what the note on
the the web says something about it might be cold because of the high airflow and
there's these new airflow things and you know my temperature management is not as good as it used to be and how can i get
warm and anyway i got dressed and as i was sitting down to breakfast with my husband i said you know these clothes
actually feel nice i just got to realize this feels the fabric feels nice
what a delight came out of nowhere
it isn't like we're constantly searching this this this this this i'm going to be aware of everything in my
life i'm going to be awake about everything in my life it's just being open to the possibility
of discovery
open to the possibility
mindful of the suchness of the moment reminding myself it's like this
how's this damned unpleasant well oh that's an attitude where's that
coming from attitude attitude attitude attitude breath
oh breath it's still unpleasant
but i have already a fresher approach to it just by taking the breath
it is in the cultivating of the not knowing it is the cultivating of not relying on
the familiar not becoming attached to the familiar
when we sit in meditation and we're following our breath everybody has kind of a different strategy around following
their breath and what feels familiar and over the years that i've been
practicing my approach to following the breath periodically changes
because it no longer because it begins to feel like it's a rhythm and it's
too familiar and i'm not actually in the moment because it's just so familiar so
yeah the breath breath breath breath breath breath breath breath and so i choose something about the
breath that is current one of my favorites is to notice the
null spot between the in-breath and the out breath that null spot is not about the air at
all that null spot is when the muscles have changed the direction of the air flow
a breath you know a breath is sort of a construct
it's a concept that we have around breath what we're really following is the movement of air
as a result of the body's muscles opening and closing orifices
the air that we breathe in is absorbed into the body and some other
air is what's expelled and so this moment in between
where nothing is happening is kind of an interesting place to be aware of
it's not a thing it's just
a marker but it's a mental marker for me and it is just a
noticing of the stopping of the airflow and of course the airflow is still happening it's going into the blood it's
coming out of the blood we don't control that that the body just does that automatically
and even if we don't have the feeling of a bolus of air moving one direction or another there's still leaking
you know air in air out
you notice this very specifically excuse me hold on a second
you notice this very explicitly if you've ever been with someone who's dying
and we have this notion that somebody takes their last breath
sometimes that last breath is an in-breath
it's a stopping that helps me to follow the breath
i'm going to do another clear here
that allows me when i'm sitting in meditation to be aware of the
nowness of the air moving it's just air moving
and focusing on the movement of air is getting at that very thing that is
happening now is being intimate with my body
intimate with this moment that's the intimacy that we want to
cultivate with all of the experiences of our lives
that's what it means to be alive it isn't about
all of the constructs we have about how we would like to be or what we'd like to leave behind or what we think of our
children's our lovers or what we think about anything
it is noticing when i think about my lover that my heart lifts
it doesn't mean something different than that
so that my life becomes the home of being here
one of one of the the big intentions in my life has been to be openhearted
i spent a lot of time thinking about what that would look like what would be necessary
how do i cultivate that it begins with
be open it isn't about what i become
or how i get to some place be
open whoa that brings up all kinds of thinking about stuff
how open do i want to be with strangers how open do i want to be
with people in my in my immediate family what does it mean
how do i experience be open not what does it mean
how do i experience being unguarded
what is arising in this moment
what is arising
it doesn't have to be a world that is about how i need to be
it can be a world about how am i in this moment not who do i wish i was
not how do i become a better person but how where am i
at this moment of what is arising
and if it is unfamiliar how do i relate to the fact that it's unfamiliar
do i want to no do i say oh great unfamiliar i get so
excited i notice excitement
in the noticing we become less driven by the familiar
and more in the place of these conditions
and if i notice if i put my attention for example right now on my hip i can say oh you know there's pain there kind
of hurts and i can try to do something about the
pain i can go into the pain i can think about the pain i can i can manage the pain
or i can say yes the pain is here and
this is happening there are all these people in this room with me how amazing
i'm not throwing away the awareness of the pain i'm just shifting my attention from the sharp
edge around the corner and i'm aware of also this
also this and this it becomes a life of and
and not a life of either or
so i invite you
to notice the influence of the familiar on what you think is right
to notice that if for you the familiar is boring and restricting and closing
down that you notice that and don't blame it on the familiar
don't be led around by the familiar become intimate with your mindfulness
notice the rawness of your experience
try not to shield yourself by putting something in a box that misleads you
allow yourself to notice this
whether it's pleasant or unpleasant it has the virtue of being closer to seeing clearly
and in seeing clearly we do not choose to suffer
it gives us room when we are feeling full of ill will and discomfort
to notice a softening that's possible by a deep
breath not as a prescription to fix ill will but to say and this is here
and with my awareness on this is also here my mind heart is less focused on the
ill-will unhappy unpleasant things of life and i am also aware of the possibility
for delight and ease and equanimity and these are what i wish for you
may you know the joy of intimacy with the moment
of the arising part of impermanence so that joy can be
a part of your life in the most dire of circumstances
and you no longer rely on what you'd like to be true you become disentangled from what you
would like to be true to be open to the possibilities of
delight in this moment thank you very much
so uh i am open to questions if you would like
if anyone here has questions i'm not sure how our timing goes this morning martha can you give me a hint here
okay does anybody have something they'd like to say i'm afraid i went on the whole period
yes we need a microphone
thank you so much thank you
yes i'm often find myself to be afflicted or victim of misconception
when i look at something or i notice something i seem to
expect that something to be what my mind creates and very often it's wrong
can you explain that perhaps okay so um i apologize but things are a
little muffled so i'm not sure i got it but so you're aware that the mind creates
[Music] a description of what has happened and
you want to know how that works but i like to know how do i not to be victim of that misconception that i
create in my mind about something that's out there that i perhaps is not even remotely similar to what i create right
right right right so so how do we become of the aware of the
possibility of delusion or misconception or feeling getting trapped by
uh whatever the mental process is and that that's that's that happens that's
something that arises and what i've found useful is to say okay i get it and what else
and the the what else is here question often allows me to see things a little more clearly in a way that doesn't
condem the previous conclusion but allows me to see a kind of evolution
of that what the thinking is and usually that works best by
asking myself that conclusion i've come to how do i feel that in my body where do i
feel that and that very act of saying where do i feel bad i'll notice my shoulders are up
or my jaw is clenched or my belly is tight and that
noticing something in my physical body reminds me that there are many things
that have that effect of my belly clenching or my jaw clenching
and when i notice the jaw clenching it gives me the opportunity to recall
mindfulness sati also means recalling to recall oh that's not the only thing that causes
my jaw to clench it it's focusing on the body gets us out of the
head which is busy constructing these scenarios and impressions
and moves me into a place of possibility because once you focus on
the body the body changes and as soon as you say well my shoulders are cl are hunched immediately they'll
go down it's an automatic response the body wants to go hold on and and that very
act has shifted something and so it's a process so much
that is not so much of condemning the mind but saying yeah that's true maybe
and what else and it's in that being open to what else that we become not so trapped
by the the decisions that the mind makes does that help
it's it's just a process of not condemning or criticizing but what else
thank you okay anybody else
back in the corner if folks do need to leave
uh thank you how do we think about things conditions that are true
um that also involve um
loved ones who are suffering and how our loved ones who are in
trouble and you know how that suffering or or
troubledness affects others in the family
there are no families that are free of that issue we
including mine and sometimes it becomes very difficult
to not want to fix everything because the heart is moved by pain
both of the person who is troubled and the people that that person affects
and so what my practice i don't give it as a prescription
but my practice has been to realize that uh
an aspect of of equanimity practice which is despite what i may wish for you
things are as they are may i see things just as they are
may i meet the arising and passing of all things with equanimity and balance
and it reminds me that the most important thing is to not allow ill will to grow in my
heart because it is only when my heart mind is peaceful that i am able to skillfully
navigate that space and being present for someone that i wholeheartedly disapprove
of the behavior does not mean that i cannot be with them
with an open heart and i wonder what is the pain that they are
experiencing that is driving this being aware of my own pain in watching
it allows me to realize that this is coming not because the person is an evil person
but because the pain is very extreme in them and it allows me to be beside them not
in them or supporting them but to be beside them and look outward and
and that being present for them can have amazing results
not trying to convince them or change their behavior not condoning or welcoming the behavior
i don't accept the behavior on myself as a burden
but i feel it passing through i'm sorry i can't do any better than
that at the moment thank you all
may you all have a wonderful holiday season