so uh warm greetings to everyone and uh feels feels wonderful that
we're gathering here for our meditation together and
just saw a message from
i think one of our members is having heart surgery today and uh jay so we wish jay well
and hope that it all goes well and um
so we sit here
holding all of ourselves everyone in our hearts including those going to surgery and having challenges
today of all kinds and
perhaps it's a
this final step of mindfulness of breathing
is very closely associated with generosity and i'll talk more about it during the
talk but the
when we remove an obstruction for someone like say we open a door someone who
can't do it themselves and remove that obstruction just that opening a door
is an act of generosity if someone has a splinter in their foot and they can't
get it out themselves it's an act of generosity to get some tweezers and
and remove the splinter and so the removal the letting go
the stepping away from those movements of the mind which don't
serve us can be seen as an act of generosity
not as a indication that aversion or pushing things away or
or or some negative thing about anything in a sense
but rather it's just such a healthy thing to remove the splinters of our life
to move the ways that we um you know harm ourselves and we have a
clearer sense of that harm even the subtlest forms the more
settled and peaceful we become in meditation the more meditation feels a place of
freedom and love and peace
integrity wholeness the more quiet and still the thinking mind becomes
the more um we recognize movements of generosity
we move we recognize the splinters that we can take out and letting go of thoughts doesn't so
much come from aversion but comes from of course let me help out here let me let go of
these thoughts these ideas when we get contracted or caught in
desires and aversions of course here it's a generous thing to
do it's not doesn't have to be done with the obligation to let go it doesn't have
to be done with hostility towards what we're letting go of
any more than opening the door are we hostile to the door or pulling out a splinter we're hostile to
the splinter rather it's a act of generosity
so to sit today maybe with a spirit of generosity
and so to begin with a posture posture itself the care we put into our
posture maybe rocking around swaying a little bit making small adjustments
can be seen as the beginning of meditative
generosity as we give attention
to our body to ourselves
and we might take a few long slow deep
breaths and as we settle in maybe even it's a giving in
a generosity of letting go of tension and
letting ourselves give ourselves the goodness of being
stable and settled here
and with a feeling of generosity of care of goodwill towards oneself
tenderly maybe as you exhale relax the body
perhaps softening in the belly
perhaps softening and relaxing the belly with a reminder to the belly
it's okay
as you exhale relaxing in the heart a generous feeling even if the heart
aches or is challenged in some way to hold it
with a generosity good will compassion and allowing the chest and
the heart to settle and relax
relaxing the shoulders maybe even moving the hands a little bit
if it frees up the shoulders and the elbows a little bit
and as an act of generosity to your face which has muscles which are in working
for us and all day long one way or the other those
muscle little muscles are expressing themselves and generously
give those muscles a chance to rest thank you for your service and now
you can rest relaxing the face
then offering your attention to the
breathing
as if attention is a gift a precious gift that's worth giving
giving over to the breathing
as if the body breathing
loves the gift of attention
and if you notice you notice yourself thinking caught up caught up in thought lost in
thought see it as an occasion to be generous
to give up your thinking to let it go
so that you can return to a way of being that's more intimate more
connected here and now a way of being present
that is more satisfying than being lost to caught up in thoughts
generously returning yourself to yourself
in the letting go of thoughts opening the doors of the heart and the mind
pulling out the splinters in the heart
so as we sit here today if it can help you become quieter and
more focused more present
you might practice giving away your thoughts giving up
letting go releasing
relinquishing all as movements of generosity
generosity perhaps associated with a deep quiet place
inside of you
let go of your thinking generously
in that in letting go of them you can [Music] return
to some intimacy and peace some sense of stillness here
that's better than being lost in thought
giving yourself the gift of that better
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
if it is in fact a form of generosity to
give yourself the chance to settle in come to a place here in meditation that
clearly feels like it's for your own welfare and well-being
then i also might consider that this generosity towards yourself
can simultaneously be a generosity for the world
that somehow settling in in such a way the best qualities of
who you are come to the forefront or are not eclipsed
then the world can also benefit from these good qualities of yours
beginning perhaps with generosity being generous to the world around you
not necessarily generous with things but generous with your attention your
heart generously letting go of the
obstructions inside of you from having a clean presence with others
to offer them the best of who you are
and if we offer the best of who we are then we benefit others while we benefit
ourselves we are benefiting ourselves where we benefit others
when we give the best that we have coming from in a good way
then we benefit as well we better benefit further
at the end of a meditation session or a buddhist event there's dedication of
merit and it's understood that if you give away your merit
you produce much more merit for yourself
if you can in a clean appropriate way offer
the best of yourself to others the best in you can grow
may it be that any of the benefits that we receive through this meditation today
that we remove the obstructions from letting that be shared with the world around us
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings
everywhere be free
you