hello everyone and welcome and welcome to this meditation
session and um
one of the ways of maybe getting a little more feeling for
the potential of meditation is to have a very clear
bracketing putting aside of the past and the future
when you meditate now the past and the future have their
certainly have their importance in human life and in fact it's a bit of a problem if you
don't remember anything of your past in the future but there's also something very valuable
about putting it aside so that you can have a very
different experience of yourself or experience of life without that reference of the past and
the future that to understand to really experience
something qualitatively valuable about the present
and so we're not forgetting about the past but we're putting it aside for the duration of a
meditation session adam will come back thoughts will come about the past and
the future but in mindfulness meditation we're not interested in those
but we are interested in recognizing them as present moment phenomena
here is a mind that's thinking about the past here's a mind concerned with the
future here it's like this and for this it's for this it's kind of
like for the duration of the meditation you're forgiven
about whatever happened in the past whatever you did in the past you don't have to be blamed for anything
when you're meditating it's kind of a time-out zone a neutral zone
and it's like in the old days people would go into the church for sanctuary and
the legal authorities couldn't go and pull a personality was in the
sanctuary of a church so you are in the sanctuary of your meditation
and you're safe here now from the past everything is forgiven for now
you don't have to do it after the meditation and you don't have to think about the future
for time being meditation you're not responsible for the future and what will happen and don't need to plan
so that just here just this experience it's kind of like
here is a door and you walk through that door to a deeper intimacy deeper connection
to the lived experience of the moment so take so entering into this door
through your body and entering into a meditation posture
and part of the value of being intentional with the meditation posture
it's beginning this process of entering into the present more fully
and doing so through your body
and also stepping through this door of the present moment into the present
stepping out of the past and stepping out of the future to just here to take a few long slow
deep breaths
breathing in deeply
and relaxing the body as you exhale long
exhale
and if you take a long exhale a long ride into the present
let there be a momentary pause at the end of the exhale
a fuller acknowledgement here
maybe a silent acknowledgement feeling here
letting your breathing return to normal
and because the body is such a wonderful vehicle for sliding into now
as you exhale
relax your belly
and sometimes if you relax the belly all kinds of other things throughout the body will relax
as well
as you exhale relaxing the shoulders
and softening them up the face
and perhaps also calming the mind
cooling the thinking activity
quieting your thoughts
and as part of present moment experience
there is awareness of the present
awareness is always a present moment event
if you are aware the awareness is occurring here and now
and for these minutes you are allowed you have permission to put aside the
past and the future enter and to enter into the door
through the door of the present moment
not to attain anything or get anything or make anything happen
but to abide
aware mindful
of your experience as you hear
and letting the comings and goings of breathing
support you to be here as breathing is also a present moment
phenomenon
riding the breath riding the sensations of the body breathing
like riding on the present moment
so
putting aside the past putting aside the future
for now for now so you can be here
whatever the now is for you now
it'll never be exactly this way again
it's worthwhile resting awareness grounding awareness
in this unique lived experience of now
letting the thinking mind take a break
just aware just
mindful
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
from time to time when you consider other people or
even more so when you're together with them
it's useful to put aside the past
and put aside thoughts of the future
so that you can really see the person in the present
certainly there's a time and place for the past and the future to be considered
but there's also a time and place to put those aside
and to meet someone in the fullness of how they are in the
present with whatever fullness you are
in the present
to connect to the humanity of another person
as they are in the present moment with a beating heart
breathing lungs with blood coursing through their body
with their vulnerability and their strength
with their good qualities and not so good qualities
to just to be there feel and sense and be with a person
and having that capacity can be a vehicle or a means
for greater respect for the other for greater care and friendliness
a greater good will well-wishing
greater empathy maybe even a sense of shared humanity
sharing in the difficulties and the joys of this life
from time to time to put aside the past and the future
so that we may have greater goodwill and compassion and love
kindness for the people we're with in the simplicity of the moment
and may it be that this meditation practice we do
supports us to be present with others
in a fuller deeper richer way
and that we bring a heart
that is inspired by the welfare and happiness of others
may we live contributing to the happiness the safety
the peacefulness and the freedom that others can have
may this practice spread from us the benefits of this
practice spread from us for the welfare and happiness of all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy
this
um so
so as a way of continuing the discussion of the buddha's teachings
on anapanasati mindfulness of breathing
the buddha is presenting these 16 steps for mindfulness of breathing
and then clearly showing their connection to two other important teachings
meditation teachings he has and one is the teachings on the four what's
usually called the four foundations of mindfulness and what's usually called the seven factors of
awakening and um it's really wonderful the way
that rather than many people will feel that you know that practice is practicing
those who know about the practicing the four foundations of mindfulness we'll see them as a very different
practice than practicing mindfulness of breathing
and certainly the way they're taught is often the case but they also come together
especially in mindfulness of breathing really becomes some point or enters into the same
domain the same area of life as the four foundations of mindfulness
and and the way the buddha does this is that there's four tetrads in the 16 steps of
alapanasati and each tetrad he says corresponds to one of the foundations of
mindfulness so as it usually said the foundation of
mindfulness that's based on the body corresponds to the first
four steps of breathing being aware of the long breath being
where the short breath being aware of the whole body as you breathe and then being aware of
the body calming and relaxing as you breathe so it's all about the body and when that
becomes really well established all four of these steps and really awareness has become strong
then the awareness is based on the body in the first
and the first foundation of mindfulness it's really about establishing awareness
on the basis of the body and classically there's a series of exercises to giving
or different ways of practicing mindfulness practice all for the purpose of establishing a
strong mindfulness awareness in the body
in the second tetrad steps 5 to 8
they are that corresponds to the second foundation of mindfulness the foundation
of mindfulness on feelings and so the second tetrad of anapanasati
is experiencing as we breathe feeling joy as we breathe feeling happiness as we
breathe experiencing the mental activity and then relaxing the mental activity
and this expert experiencing could also be translated as feeling it has the same word that we
translate as feeling is embodied in the word experiencing the way the pali
grammar is or l the words are used and so ex feeling
joy feeling happiness feeling uh the whole the mental activity and then
relaxing the mental activity so this corresponds to this the foundation of mindfulness on feeling
the third that threat has to do all about the mind and the third foundation is all about
the mind so in the breathing exercises it's experiencing
the mind not just the activity the whole mind gladdening the mind settling
stabilizing the mind concentrating the mind and then liberating the mind in the four
foundations of mindfulness um the uh
it's in part understanding really high quality states of mind
maybe first the mind itself in some certain ways particular ways and then these high
qualities of mind that correspond with gladdening roughly corresponding gladdening
concentrating and liberating the mind and then the last tetrad is observing
all about observing observing impermanence observing fading away
cessation and relinquishment and these are the insights deep insights and the fourth foundation
of mindfulness is also about about insights it's really uh insight also into seeing the arising and
passing how hindrances arise and they go and seeing the suffering how suffering comes
and goes and now that's the first uh of the
uh observations of the fourth tetrad observing in constancy or change
and and the others follow in the wake of that so the buddha corresponds these two
these the four foundations are equal to the four tetrads but not just automatically it's when
awareness is well established in each of these areas when it's when
when when we're really grounded and centered and present in a full way without being distracted or
thinking a lot about the past and the future this precious precious thing that we have being aware
being able to really experience the present moment sense the present moment feel the
present moment know the present moment in all its all the dimensions of knowing
and not just know it fleetingly but to feel that now we're centered we're at
rooted we're grounded here and this feeling of being really here definitely be grounded resting here
it's kind of like the difference between maybe being in a rowboat being tossed around the sea and then
coming up on dry land now you feel like it's stable and strong here we are and there's a qualitatively
shift a quantum shift that can happen inside when boom we're here
we don't have to work at being here and come back and come back and remember to be here and present we're
not liable to wander off and the awareness then becomes strong
and uh and that awareness is established and uh so the translation i like for the
four foundations of mindfulness is uh is the four ways the four basis
for establishing uh awareness and um and then in the when the buddha
correlates these four these these foundations and the four tetrads
and the fourth one he says then mindfulness of the ma of the dharmas is well
established so there's a strong level of equanimity and this is one of the kind of
directions the practice goes when there's a stability boom we're here that then we're here in
such a strong way that we're not easily tossed around by
the changing circumstances of our life we're not easily losing our equanimity
our balance our peacefulness when difficult thought arises the days rise
and they go when there's difficult painful sensations in the body arise and
we just can feel them and know them and and but the mind doesn't get agitated or
disturbed and this is called equanimity and lack of agitation and lack of
being disturbed and so both these practices the four
foundations of mindfulness whatever way you've been taught to do them and there's many ways that be possible
mindfulness is taught or the mindfulness of breathing one of the ways of doing this
whatever those practices are they're all for the purpose ultimately in buddhist practice to
come to a kind of dwelling resting abiding aware in the present moment
without any tendency to leave that and wander off from that
and some people then will use the kind of the expression lucid
awareness when awareness is not ruffled when our sense of mindfulness not ruffled by
what we know that knowing becomes
free and independent of what is known we can't separate what
we know from knowing completely but but the knowing
is not ruffled it's not agitated it's not entangled it's not
clinging to what is known and this idea of knowing something and that kind of
freedom that equanimity is then um the
the the really the place where all the different practices of mindfulness all the different ways might be past
night practice come together and uh and set the stage
for uh for awakening so then tomorrow i'll talk about how
this goes to is connected to the seven factors of awakening
and i love this because um there's kind of a creating of a harmony or unity
in in the buddhist teachings we start seeing how they all come together as a whole and
in the way that this discourse on anapanasati begins where it begins with the the senior
disciples of the buddha coming together with all their disciples and living together for a period of
months in unity and in harmony receiving the buddhist teaching
so to have that sense of unity and harmony with all the different sides of who we are
that we could all come together and live under the full moon of our
lucid awareness so um thank you and um
and we'll continue along this path of the anapanasati and tomorrow's the seven factors of
awakening and then we'll see by thursday how the seven factors of awakening
are practiced the practice changes when a person has not just learned how
to be stably aware here but has experienced a degree of real liberation freedom from clinging
and how the practice of changes at that point so so we continue and we're almost at
the end of this anapanasati series thank you