so good morning everyone good day
and uh welcome to this meditation and your meditation where you have the opportunity to
meditate both to both
with yourself and with a large community and the large community is meant to
support us so that we are more inspired more content
to really sit here in our own direct experience knowing that there's a wide field of
support of mutuality of companionship
on this path and that you're not alone but
and no and knowing you're not alone the willingness to
put everything else aside the best you can to be right here not so much with
yourself but with the experience that's immediate
and current and i love the word current because it
means both in the present moment and the current of a stream a river and so here we are in the
current of time in that little window of it that's always moving
always changing always flowing that we call the present moment
so to
assume a meditation posture
and close your eyes and to give some
nice attention to the body to adjust the posture
it could be large adjustments small adjustments
just kind of get everything as best you can lined up in harmony enough to what's available to
you in your body to support being here
in the current of the present moment through the experience of the body
your body is always in the present moment your mind in a sense
seemingly wonders often thoughts about the past and
future and fantasy and in a sense is not so then grounded
here in the present moment and so here to bring the mind
into harmony with a body with your capacity for attention
with awareness not so much awareness brought to the
body but allowing for the awareness which is in the body
and then within this body taking a few long slow deep breaths to begin
attuning yourself to the rhythm of breathing the coming and goings of
the in-breaths the comings and goings of the out-breaths that here this body breathing
is where you'll be centered
and as you exhale relaxing your body is a way to
continue to center yourself here now
letting your breathing return to normal
and from the inside of the body
noticing where there's tension and holding in your body
almost as if you're do you discover the awareness that's inside the tension
and gently as you exhale to continue relaxing the body
relaxing the belly
the more relaxed the belly is the more it's part of the river of
change with no sensations frozen in time
the sensations of the belly just move and
appear and disappear flow by making room for the next one
relaxing the shoulders maybe a deep relaxation of the shoulders
the top of the shoulders shoulder joint down the arm
and feeling the vitality the pulse of life the energies that are
a little bit freed up when the muscles are not so held tight
in relaxing the muscles of the face
as if the face could sit back in an easy chair and just take a break
rest and then within this body as part of
this body become aware of how the body
experiences breathing
breathing in and breathing out
and to bring a little more careful attention to the breathing so the awareness is more continuous
with each inhale and each exhale
stay stay stay right there with the whole length of the inhale
and notice how the sensations that come into play are changing during that length of time
stay with the full length of the exhale and notice how there are changes in the
sensations connected to exhaling
and not that you're leaning into it or staring at your breathing
the more you're settling back and opening allowing receiving
the full length of the inhale the full length of the exhale it's the receiving of all the changes
that come into play as you breathe
and then notice
the path that some sensations pass away
the sensations of inhale come to an end
as we begin to exhale some of the sensations within and inhale
pass away come to an end before the end of the inhale
just settle back and without trying too much or straining just receiving
appreciate the health how sensations pass away
and if they don't don't worry about it just notice the ones that do pass that are no longer here
they might return but just noticing noticing their passing
or noticing that they're now gone
without thinking or reflecting on it you can also open your awareness more
widely to be aware of any sensation
in how it passes notice what comes to an end
passes away and maybe it starts again but just noticing the passing of it
or notice the passing of our attention on it because we attention is on one thing and
then it pulls to something else
i appreciate all that is passing away
coming to an end
as you notice that things are in the process of passing away
whereas you notice they have passed away they appreciate
that then at that moment those moments it doesn't make sense to cling to
anything to depend on something which is fading away which is gone
and see if you can appreciate that openness that non-clinging to it
the freedom and space that that provides
that in and of itself when things pass away in the passing there can be
a feeling of freedom spaciousness peacefulness
in and of itself settle back into the flow of present
moment experience appreciating all the things that are
passing sounds sensations thoughts
anything that changes is also there's part of it that's passing away
chances are the thoughts that you had at the beginning are not the same thoughts you have now
those thoughts have passed away some of the sensations of your body that
were current at the beginning of the meditation may no longer be current something else
is what you were feeling has maybe changed
it's no longer here
appreciate the absence that's left behind
when something disappears or
no longer present
don't be a hurry to feel the absence
appreciate the openness the spaciousness the
freedom that comes when there's nothing there to cling to
to hold on to or to resist because it's no longer present
and as we come to the end of the sitting if you have some sense some feeling for
the openness or freedom that comes when something passes away
and how it doesn't make sense to cling to something which has passed away in the process of
passing away will pass away and even if it's inconstant it comes and
goes and comes and goes it's going can teach
us the value of not holding on
not expecting demanding wanting but allow it to pass
and to remain open and free
for the next thing to arise
and if the next thing to arise is another person
as you go up through your day and you meet a person you communicate
with a person you think of a person
to become aware of that person in that
way of the way of non-attachment the way of openness receptivity
the freedom that can come when we don't cling to what is passed away
and then maybe we don't cling to what arises we stay open
non-clinging non-contentious without need or demand
and this can become our gift to others that we receive them and know them
without the filter of our attachments and our demands
expectations bias prejudice
that in the freedom that we learn
we meet people with an openness a peacefulness
and maybe this is one of the gifts that we can offer the world
from our meditation practice because may it be that our meditation
practice not only benefits ourselves
it benefits others maybe at some point it's even more
valuable for us to meditate when we know we do it
for the welfare and happiness of others
what a gift to be attentive and aware and present for
others without any filters of attachment
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
you