so good day and good evening
good morning to everyone and it's
a funny thing to be sharing here and now with
different time zones and different places it's a wonderful way that here can be
at different time zones or now can be at different time zones at the
same time something like that so um
i think it's uh maybe useful to i think that
human beings are using their imagination all the time and imagination is more subtle than
flights of fantasy and this but rather it's the little uh images
that we have of what's going to happen what did happen imaginings when we we imagine people
when we meet them we imagine things about them we imagine what's going to happen tomorrow
and and sometimes these imaginings are detrimental they undermine us
especially if they're they are kind of
frightening or disturbing imaginations that we do over and over and over again
they kind of slowly kind of begin to create a mood a
disposition and almost maybe sometimes even a personality by this the constancy of what we imagine
and so meditation practice is certainly a wonderful time to learn how to put
down some of the imaginings that we do so when we let go of thoughts we're also letting go of imaginations
when we come back into the present moment we're letting go of or what we imagine or assume will be
tomorrow or other times in other places but we can also use imagination to give
us a kind of a little edge a little clear clarity about uh um stay here be present
write this out and uh you know so i've used the lots of
analogies over time and these analogies are all acts of imagination it gives us a sense a feeling for
kinesthetic and association that can we give a better sense of what it means like to stay with something
continuously than if the instructions are okay sit down and stay with your breath and don't leave it
but this idea of uh riding a scooter and um and every time that your mind
wanders off we come we push back into the present moment and then we coast along on the present
moment until we need to kind of come back again and push again
or if we're staying with the breathing the imagination that we are
it's like waves and as i've done frequently and or like we're surfing on the waves the
in-breath is the lifting of the lifting us up and on the wave and then the out breath we're
surfing the front of it going down or maybe not surfing just simply kind of
gently being lifted and falling when my son was quite small had trouble
sleeping i sometimes had him imagine that he was an otter floating on its back to sleep at night
and top of a wonderful peaceful sea and the kelp forest all around
underneath and that the in the gentle kind of swells would come up and down and that with his breathing
he was the otter that was being lifted and settled lifted and settled with
each wave and generally then after a while he'd fall asleep
and so all these little acts of imagination that not to put us asleep here but to
encourage us to stay here this is what it's like so as i said yesterday the buddha gave
one for uh for breath meditation
which is that of a lathe worker holding the lathe knife i guess or the
chisel so that against the wood that's going around in the lathe
and in order to cut the wood properly the chisel has to be in continuous contact with the wood
that's how it it chisels away and so
i guess this idea of a lathe turning around and around was the buddha's analogy for the cycles of in-breath and out-breath
and the awareness somehow is like the chisel where the kind of the point of awareness is really
centered someplace with the breathing and then it doesn't leave it just stays there
stays there and stays connected so this goes around and around
and um and if that kind of image doesn't mean much for you uh an image that uh
when i was when i was in college i took a massage course and the instruction was that if we had
to get more oil to put on more to you know for massage to continue with the massage
to never lose physical contact with the person getting the massage so you have to always keep one hand on
this touching the person's arm or something as you reach for that oil and put it on your hand and so this idea of
always staying in touch and contact and contact and touch i interpret to be
the physicality of breathing the physical experience just stay there with
your chisel or stay there with your hand stay there on the waves riding up and down
so don't be busy with all those images but these are images that can be used
one of them maybe speaks to you and if using the image is better than the
alternative meaning that you it's you're less likely to wander off into thoughts and
imaginations which are not supportive for you then stay with the image until the image
no longer is needed and you're able to stay there with the with the breathing
so taking a meditation posture and gently closing your eyes
and even saying the word gently closing your eyes and hadn't thought about it but also
evokes the imagination the idea of gentle gentling
and maybe has value that travels beyond just the eyes
and then sitting quietly and gently the body
shifting gears so that you are settling down into your body your embodied experience
and taking a few long slow deep breaths big swells big waves that lift you up
expand you and then down the other side of the wave
as you exhale relaxing your body
and letting your breathing return to normal
and then softening relaxing parts of your body and as each parts of your body relax
imagine it's becoming soft like a cotton ball
relaxing the muscles of the face
softening the shoulders
and softening the belly
and also as you exhale softening the mind
quieting the mind
distilling the mind into a soft
place and if any part of your body mind feels hard brittle
maybe it's your awareness which is like a soft cotton ball
it gently supports or holds whatever is hard challenging
and then to settle into the body's experience of
breathing
and feeling the sensations physical sensations that come into play as you breathe
the sensations of inhale are different than the sensations of exhaling
and then settling in to stay with the sensations of breathing
and so some continuity like you would a chisel against the bowl being lathed
or like the continuous contact of the waves is once flowed someone's
back on the gentle swells of the ocean lifting up and lifting down
for the continuous stroke of a masseuse yes as we receive a massage from the
inside as the lungs expand and contract as a
diaphragm pushes and releases
and settling in gently steadily
see if you can have continuity
with the breathing letting the thinking mind become quieter
softer stiller
so the center of gravity of attention shifts from thinking
to breathing
as if breathing is the center of the
universe if breathing is
home for these minutes that we're meditating
riding the waves of breathing
letting go of imaginary futures imaginary
other places the imagination
of things which are not here and now and to use the imagination
instead to be intimate with our lived experience of
here
allowing yourself to feel whatever satisfaction or gladness
that comes from not being lost in thought so much
not perpetuating thoughts which are undermine you
trouble you glad to be intimate here now
perhaps even allowing yourself to feel the joy
of just being alive breathing just content sitting here breathing
feeling embodying yourself
the more that we are preoccupied in thought distracted by thinking
the more that we're lost in imagination
the less in touch we are with others
the less we are distracted the less we're preoccupied
the better what's best in us can come forth
to meet other people love gratitude
compassion friendliness all shine all flow most easily
most manifest when we are not distracted
not preoccupied when we are present for others
that's the vehicle that's the channels by which our positive attitudes
manifest and may it be that to whatever degree
that you're more settled more intimate with yourself
calmer clear from this meditation
may that register for you may you take that in feel that
and imagine how you can stay this way
or stay close to it so that your warmth for others
can be palpable expressed your love your compassion
your kindness can better flow
and may it be that what you learn about being non-distracted
supports you
in greater goodwill for the people around you
known and unknown strangers and intimates
may it be that what you learn through this
practice is a means by which you live a life that
betters the life of others in small ways in big ways in intentional
ways and unintentional ways
may the benefit of the merit of our practice together be for the welfare and
in support of all beings everywhere may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
you