so we've come to the end of this week the
series on patience and um patience
is often a a wonderful
gift that we give to ourselves and to the world
because the alternative when the alternative to patients is not so healthy or beneficial for us or for
others and
so for this morning meditation i want to
mention that in this ancient teachings of the buddha he puts a emphasis on
knowledge and vision and i'll translate this as knowing and
seeing and i'll explain this for this meditation as
the simple patient knowing of what's obvious in the experience what's obvious with the breathing
as we so focus on the breathing just knowing and then taking patient time
to perceive that to sense it to let it register the experience that
you've known so in a sense you're you you you recognize it you know what
it's there there's a simple very simple recognition it just doesn't have to be with words
uh it could just be kind of a silent knowing but when something is known
then take a brief time to let it register more fully really experience what that is
more deeply and for something that's passing quickly like the inhale it's just a fleeting moment maybe that
to really register something if it lingers a little bit longer you know it doesn't have to be more than a
second or two it's easy going relaxed and the patience
is there with the that seeing with the registering allowing it to be there
and it's not literally what i'm about to say but it's the spirit of it and that is as if you have all the time
in the world not literally because you don't linger so long you start thinking about it
but as long as there's kind of a deeper silent recognition silent registering
seeing perceiving sensing stay there let let it sink in
if it's still there and then know the next thing so know the inhale and let that be
registered and feel it then know the exhale
you know the beginning of it and then let's feel and register that more fully that experience of exhaling
if there's a pause after the exhale know it and allow yourself to let that register
or take it in or or you know feel that experience in some
way so there's knowing and then there's
buddhist language seeing but seeing replies to all the inner ways of perception of feeling sensing that goes
on so
assuming a meditation posture one that allows you to have a certain
alertness but also one which you're going to be patient
you're settling in for the long term just to be with what's here whatever it might be
not fighting it or resisting it or fixing anything
but a posture that allows you to be present
with some alertness or clarity
and then gently close your eyes
or gently lower your gaze
and taking a breath or two just to relax into your body soften in the body
relaxing into the body might give you access to more of your
body to feel and sense as you now take a few long slow deep
breaths
almost as if you're getting a massage from the inside out feel the rib cages expand
maybe the shoulders rise maybe the belly balloons out
maybe as you breathe in there's an increased pressure on the sitting bones
or if you're laying down increase pressure in the back
ribcage or if you're sitting in a chair you might feel the back rib cage too
and then letting the breathing return to normal
and take take three or four breaths to
relax in your body on the exhale
and then to
settle into your breathing
feeling the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
sensing or feeling the body's experience of breathing the sensations in the body as you
breathe the movements
and as you inhale know the inhale
let's allow the inhale to be known and then
let that experience register more deeply like almost like a physical or registering
as you sense or feel what you now know
and then as you exhale know the exhale
and in the receptive mode like as if the body is receiving the sensations
let the experience of exhale be felt sensed
the exhale is known and felt
seeing if you can be infinitely patient
with this process of knowing and then silently
feeling and sensing what is known
and so there's a rhythm of knowing and sensing
and the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
a rhythm that you feel and sense
participate in with lots of patience knowing and feeling
knowing and registering quietly calmly
and if there's a lot of thinking know that is happening
and silently register how that feels in your body your mind to
be thinking the sensations
not what you're thinking about but what the process of thinking feels
senses know it and sense it
and then begin again with your breathing
um
it's quite valuable to learn the art
of staying close to knowing and feeling
knowing and sensing
knowing and letting things register more deeply
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
this practice of knowing and sensing knowing and seeing
knowing and letting things be registered more fully
can be done outward into the world that we live in
to know the joys and the sorrows of this world
and to really know it and then take patient time
to let it register to let ourselves feel it
to be a witness to what's happening in the world
so that we're touched by it and to be touched by the world be a
witness to what's happening in the world to witness it with our hearts
is an expression of this practice
it's supported by our patients
and it becomes a gift if we can then care for the world
each in our own individual way to live a life of knowing and
seeing knowing and feeling
and then caring knowing feeling caring
and this doesn't have to be dramatic it could be an expression of our own
unique agency and abilities and situations
it might be with the people around us
may this practice that we do support us
to live for the welfare and happiness of the whole world including ourselves
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free of suffering
challenges oppression
and may we contribute to that possibility
[Music]
so patience uh today i want to talk a little bit about patience
with the practice that um
when we really settle down to doing meditation practice buddhist practice
it i think it's done best most efficiently
if we don't try to be efficient we try to be sincere
and dedicated to it but to be in a hurry to be impatient
goes in the wrong direction from the freedom from uh compulsion that we're
looking for that we're trying to develop and so
to be caught in impatience is to be caught in a world of clinging
and in moving towards non-clinging we want to kind of learn how to be patient
with the ongoingness of the path of practice and um
there's a very touching for me story that i heard secondhand from someone who was
there a few people who were there dalai lama many years ago in
in a big amphitheater in arizona apparently was giving teachings
weekend teachings and it's he took questions sometimes and a person stood up in the middle of the
auditorium and and and asked for uh the quickest way to
enlightenment and as a story he was told the dalai lama paused for a long time
just stood there without responding and then at some point a tear started going down his
cheek and then uh he said something like
how sad he felt about this drive to be quick in the practice to try to get something
to be you know to um and i don't know what was going on for the person who asked the question
but um i wonder if the dalai lama felt that there was some kind of greed or
selfishness or some kind of acquisitive relationship with the dharma for someone
to ask that kind of question and and to settle in
do the practice patiently in a sense inefficiently is often the
most efficient there's a story also that i've told of kind of a fairytale story of
a person a very capable person comes to the monastery to practices is
dedicated to practice is quite accomplished in the world has a high degree he's very very smart
clever skilled lots of lots of native ability to
manage with things and the person comes to the monastery and says i'm here to practice and if i
practice well how long will it take for me to become enlightened and the abyss says
oh it'll take you about 10 years and then the person says wait a minute
you know i'm quite capable and i can really know how to apply myself i'll really be diligent and
and and really kind of work hard and how long will it take then
and the ab has said oh then it'll take 20 years
so there's something about the patience of just accepting the situation accepting how things are
including the challenges in practice and then a steady ongoingness the
patience that allows us to go step after step to to
sprint in the practice to go really hard and push and then have to kind of recover and stop practicing
um you know or you go off and do something else you think might be efficient is very different than just
the mundane ordinary step by step this breath
this my act of mindfulness just we this is what we do step after
step after step and um and to practice that sincerely and patience for me
allows for sincerity it allows for uh offering ourselves to the practice
more fully without it being in exchange without being a transactional thing if i do this the
practice will give me this back we're just in here willingly to allow it to unfold as it
wants to i very much like the idea that um
that the dharma knows better than i do what i need to experience what need to
practice with now today anytime and and i've seen that over and over again that i might have one idea of what
i'm supposed to be doing or what's supposed to happen in practice but something else comes along and i practice with that
and and that seems in the long term and you know eventually i say oh that was really great
and immediately i don't quite understand how it's beneficial but i've learned to trust
how things unfold as i practice and just practice with it practice with a practice with this with this
patient lane patiently and there's a story that i'm very fond of and i'm sure
some of you heard me say it and that is um a friend of mine was a student of
shinrio suzuki suzuki roshi the founder of the san francisco zen center a zen master and
and my friend asked suzuki roshi once
if i practice zayn will i become enlightened and suzuki roshi answered him if your
practice is sincere it's almost as good
it's if your practice here is almost as good so rather than
rushing and forcefully and demanding or expecting this you know
enlightenment to just practice patiently sincerely and it's pretty good
and maybe you'll become enlightened but if not it's almost as good so this is
part of the benefits of patients to settle in for the long term willing to practice with what is
not being ahead of yourself not being protesting by what the dharma offers you what your
what's what arises for you in the practices the challenges that come the joys that come just steadily
very steady ongoingness practice practice practice
and then at some point when when the impatience disappears when
compulsions quiet down when greed and clinging and and anxiety settle and abate
then there's a wonderful kind of higher
special kind of patience and and that's the patience
which is not it which is non-patience and i mean it in this way
that if two people are coming into the same very trying
difficult situation that's a very stressful and
and one person kind of sits down and puts on the seat belt or something and really kind of bears down into doesn't
react and stay still but it's a lot of work to um
to you know stay patient they have to really work at it and hold and check their their obsessive compulsive kind of
reactivities and people say oh that person managed to be patient with a difficult situation
the other person is in the same situation but none of their buttons are pushed
they're stressful it's difficult but they're not reacting to it there's no inner compulsions no obsessions no
reactivity to the situation and so the person has no reactivity it just sits there calmly
and from the outside someone might say this both people look like they're both equally patient
but on the inside one person is doing patience
and the other one is you could say maybe being patient
but you could say that it's it's um the other person has no need for
patients it's a non-patience that allows them to be kind
of present for the situation without being reactive so as practice deepens
as we follow this path patiently the time will come when you start recognizing
that oh i'm patient without being patient i'm
patient without needing to do anything that i can be here and i'm not reacting
i'm present i can know what's happening clearly i can let it register and see what's happening
clearly and but i'm not reacting and when that happens then there's more
lots more room and space for us to care
to be aware in a caring way sympathetic way
and to maybe if it's appropriate to act in caring ways to care for the world
so um patience to be patient it's a i think one of the great
gifts that we can give ourselves and we do this practice and it's also a gift we can give the
world because to be impatient is not a gift for anyone
so thank you for this time and this chance to talk about
patience and i look forward to
monday when we'll start a different topic i don't know what it is yet but we'll do
something so thank you