so good morning everyone and
happy to be with you
and the topic for this week has been compulsive desires really of all kinds
and one way to turn this around and for ourselves
is to in some healthy wise way
have the attitude of wanting what you have so in meditation to not look for
something beyond or other than what's happening for you
but have an orientation like okay this is what i want now of course there are plenty of things
which are not desirable not not
that are painful difficult that might be happening as we meditate but this attitude of okay this is what's
coming so this is what i want not in order to suffer more
but to begin discovering a whole different attitude or way of being in the world
that's not driven by wanting something other than what is
and then something very different can start happening in the alchemy of the mind there can we can start becoming free
of what is so it's not celebrating or appreciating or
necessarily or or validating what is happening but rather okay this
is what's happening this is what i want so that i can become free
so that i can find this place of clear recognition
open awareness luminous presence where and it's maybe in a sense the
awareness is bigger than what the details are of what's happening
or as if the details of what's happening happen independent
of the usual ideas of self what i want what i don't want
and then something very different begins to shift and change if we just work with what is happening
practice right there with what he's here so you might to the degree to which you
find yourself distracted or caught up in desires for things to be other than they are
there are even desires to hold on to what's there what's happening see if you can shift that to a desire to
just allow this desire for what is happening
desire for what is going on including that things change and shift
including that some things stay and then in that allowing and then wanting what is happening
there you can begin finding some steadiness some calm some
peace some kind of paradigm shift
in how we are in this world that maybe is free
of compulsion and free of you know self-preoccupation referring
everything back to self so assuming a
meditative posture and gently closing your eyes
and if what i just said seems a little troublesome for you or
you have ideas that too difficult for you or if
it can't be right it's okay
maybe instead you could smile a gentle smile inner smile
at the delight
of questioning looking deeper in this whole world of desires that
human beings live in that this is a time to appreciate
yourself and appreciate the possibility
of observing desires in yourself
and ex and considering yes there is an alternative
and that alternative might be
to take a few long slow deep breaths and as you exhale
to settle in to just what's happening here now
to take a deep breath in and perhaps relax your thinking mind
soften let go of your thoughts of past and future what has happened what
might happen letting the exhale center you
here letting your breathing return to normal
in this centering process centering yourself grounding yourself here on the exhale
relaxing your face the face can carry so much of the
momentum of our desires and wanting and
trying so hard
bearing down tightening up
and give the a chance to take it easy to relax
to not always be at the service of our minds desires and
aversions softening around the eyes the jaws
on the exhale to relax the shoulders
when the shoulders are tense
they're under the control of our minds the tensions in our minds
and to give the shoulders a chance
to be free of the mind and just soften relax a bit
and the same with a belly
maybe as an act of generosity to let the belly move in the direction
of relaxation
softness
and as you exhale to soften the mind
relax the thinking muscle
letting the mind become quieter calmer
or making space broad expansive space
so the mind is not making itself claustrophobic
the mind has breathing room
and then becoming aware of the body
breathing breathing in and breathing out
and see if you can find a way to be intimate with your breathing
without clinging or pushing or strong desire
where's you simply want what's already here
want how things are right now as you're with your breathing
if you're distracted in a certain way
want that as well but not to hold on to it or
succumb to it but so you're not fighting it but rather
being mindful of it
without the need for it to be other
there's a way of wanting what's happening whatever is happening
there's a way that that can set you free
even free from any wanting
breathing in and breathing out
here
if you get distracted in your thoughts see if that represents some form of
desire that you're caught up in
see if you can let go of that desire
to return to wanting just what's here
being content with what's here so that you can be free
in the midst of life here
and then to end this setting
is there some way that you can be deeply content
just with what is happening at the moment some way that you can put aside
desires for anything else to be different
putting aside any attempt to change what is
and even imagining that you could do so is there some way that that enables you
allows you to respond to the world around you in a
new way in a way that maybe is more open
a way that is free of clinging and aversion
a way where you're not asserting
conceit asserting how it relates to me myself
and mine and in this contentment in this
willingness to abide in how things are
can that be a source for love for care
for kindness that has those qualities of non-assertiveness
non-defensiveness defensiveness
non-greed because love does not coexist
very well with greed and discontent
and as we come to the end of this sitting perhaps any way in which we can
discover the peaceful care for the world
may that care become strong
and gently motivating
and may we live for the welfare the happiness of this
world in ways that are appropriate for each of
us flowing from how we are when there's a
deep contentment and freedom
may we contribute to the happiness of others to the safety of others
to the peace of others and to the non-oppression of others
may all beings discover freedom from greed
so we come to the last talk about greed and non-greed
and i can imagine that it's a difficult topic
partly because desire is so integral to being alive as a human being
and they can feel incomprehensible to not have
the assertiveness of desire the compulsion of desire to have things be
different to want something different or it can be inconceivable not to try to hold on to
what is happening and this idea of freedom from needing
things to be different and freedom from needing things to stay the same
it's kind of maybe it sometimes doesn't compute and it's um but this is one of the
things that as meditation deepens and gets quieter we can start getting a feeling for a
sense for this kind of clear recognition clear awareness
that's settled and open that needs nothing to be different including doesn't need things to
not change from how they are
so the word greed is a umbrella term uh some people don't
relate to the word very strongly and don't identify that their impulses
of desire have any connection to greed but greed is an umbrella term for a lot of different
kind of motivations in the same family family of greed acquisitiveness
just wanting things is a form of greed miserliness not sharing not being
generous holding on tight to what one has is in this family of greed
strong biological lust uh biological passion that can feel so
natural and and uh something that we should of course just kind of give into and allow for it feels like freedom and
feels like such a wonderful pleasure to just kind of lose ourselves and perhaps
it can also be a form of greed if it's if it were being kind of compelled by it and
there's no freedom in it we give ourselves over to this force that in a sense takes over
rather than being free and having a kind of ease and a kind of
non-compulsion in how we act and how we live in the world of pleasure even
so uh in in the dharma the uh one of the kind of goals of
this practice of vipassana the practice of buddhism is to realize a
way of being or a possibility of radical and complete
non-greed non-compulsive desire and and it might be unimaginable that
this is possible but it is possible and it's deeply satisfying it feels
that level of peace well-being uh sense of freedom that comes from that
is uh pretty phenomenal and then some people you know
anticipating or thinking about this goal are worried that if i have no compulsive
desire no strong desire that pushes me you know that or no holding on tight to
what i have that somehow i won't be safe somehow
life will become very difficult and so it's maybe it might have some truth
to it it's a little bit hard to know how everybody lives their life and the conditions their challenges that they're
living under but certainly we don't want anyone to be harmed by non-greed
but non-greed has this wonderful quality that the absence of greed is the absence
of states of mind that eclipse the deeper goodness within us
they obscure the deeper movements of generosity of contentment
of love of a kind of a deep faith in the
possibility of freedom and and this this capacity for
living a generous life not because generosity we feel compelled to be
generous not because it's but rather that generosity
is the kind of generosity of if your person has two hands the generosity of the left hand washing
the right hand and the right hand washes the left hand that there's a kind of unself-consciousness
in the hands there's kind of a coming together clearly there's they
need to be two distinct hands so they can do the work but they become one and they become
somehow uh not separate and so in generosity there's a coming together of the receive
the the giver and the receiver and also the gift what's been given and so it doesn't
become something that's self-centered it doesn't become something where that creates a kind of a
hierarchical distinction between me the giver who's special and you who's the one who needs something and
you better be thankful for what you've done what i've done for you there's a kind of a softening and
letting go of any of the barriers or clingings or holding on that that gets in the way of a sense of
mutuality or sense of this kind of simplicity where just the right and left hand coming together to do the work of
cleaning and so this simplicity and naturalness almost of generosity that comes from
some deeper place that cannot come from a place of greed
and part of this is that greed the compulsive desire that
in buddhist understanding psychology it always comes together with clinging
with grasping at something with compulsion where there's no freedom
and clinging and grasping are a form of suffering there's a kind of a
tightening a constriction a tension that comes along with clinging
and grasping so greed always comes with suffering even if the promise of greed
the excitement of greed acting on greed might be pleasant or has a promise of
pleasure in it the fantasies can be pleasant there's something in and of itself in the greed
if we really to pay attention carefully that it brings suffering not only that it
brings a kind of alienation from this deeper goodness deeper wellsprings of love and
contentment and generosity that lives waiting inside of us that it's not really us uh
it's not really what we usually identify with me myself and mine it's more like in buddhist terms like
the dharma that lives within us and so it's not exactly ours but it's not apart from us
and so greed always comes with clinging and the freedom from greed comes from
the freedom from clinging the freedom from grasping and that feels so good to be free of that tension
and uh and then it gives rise to a whole other orientation of how to live in life that
maybe is really foreign to the thrust of living that most people can live in this world
so it could even feel disorienting or frightening or or you know undesirable to have this
lack of clinging because so much of how we normally live
is based on clinging and grasping the other thing that greed always comes
along with it comes along with conceit it comes along with an assertion
of self of it's you know it's it's for me or i want this or i'm going
to keep this for myself and um i'm going to you know i'm going to grab it for me
and this self-assertion into the world is also its form of suffering it's also
a form of of um of sometimes of asserting greed and desire in the world
causes a lot of harm in the world around us as well either directly we can see it but also
many of its indirect that the ripple effect of our consumerism for
example that's based on greed the ripple effect of greed the greed of
capitalism that how it affects you know so much of the world
you know as part of the suffering that greed kind of spreads out like a disease almost
and so to to learn to discover again through maybe
meditation or some other means that it's possible to live and live well and happily and
successfully without the self-assertion
without it's kind of like
i don't know what occurs to me it's it's kind of like um
having a bicycle that uh maybe one of the breaks or is kind of
always kind of misadjusted it's always rubbing against the the tire the wheel and so you have to
pedal harder and forcefully in order to get the bicycle to roll but
and that that brake that's always against the you know against the wheel is a little
bit like the self that we always carry with us and uh and so
the rubbing of that and wears the all kinds of things out
but to undo the break and allow some deeper wellsprings to come up
that are defined by the absence of greed the absence of hatred and absence of
delusion and this is a beautiful way of living
and so the absence of grace comes absence of greed maybe for some
people will feel like a kind of a grace living a life of grace
and for other people it's living a life of love or generosity some people feels like a
living a life of freedom and so it's well worth taking a deep
look at this world of greed how it works for us take a deep look at the world of
compulsive desires that drive us and move us along both in our thoughts in terms of distracted thoughts
and the momentum of thoughts in our actions what we do and also in how we speak
and and and what is it like to let
speaking thinking and acting come from someplace where there's no assertion of self no clinging
and no greed and it's one of the great pleasures of life
so thank you very much and so then next week we'll do the same kind
of uh journey through the topic of hate or hostility or aversion depending how
we translate the word and so i look forward to that
and finally i'd like to say that there's a kind of announcement about imc
uh we have announced now a few times in different places that we were kind of scheduled to begin opening again on august 1st
so it's coming up pretty soon in eight days or so and uh i i think it's probably unlikely
that we'll open then so next week there'll be some announcements and on the imc
webpage we'll post it next week to be some clarity about when you know when we
you know clarity but you know a little bit more information about our opening or not our opening
and um so just if you live locally and you have those thoughts
please keep you know check check the website
so thank you very much