so the
topic now is the third factor of
awakening
the effort factor of awakening
or the effort lim the word anga
can mean lim or part
and and so it's a
it's a part of the whole
and uh so the seven limbs of awakening
the seven
factors of electing parts of awakening
can be seen as part of four
seven different qualities or practices
or states of one
whole one whole way of being
and one of those ways of being is to
engage to to make efforts to do things
so it's not just the passivity of just
how we are but there's also an
engagement
in our practice in our world
and the word viria
that's a v-i-r-a-y-a
v-i-r-yeah a-y-a
is comes from the word hero
and so a kind of heroic effort
but all these words like effort and
heroic effort
can lend itself to being exhausted as
soon as you hear them like oh no
i have to do all this work now and
tiring work
some translators to translate this word
for
effort and effort factor of awakening as
endeavor
and i don't know if some of us if the
word endeavoring has a little bit more
nicer feeling than the word effort
we endeavor to do something it's what we
are engaged in trying to do
to make it really maybe feeling closer
in
and more less the energetics of effort
i relate this right effort with the word
choice that
it's the choices we make as we practice
and as we live our life
and choice you know a choice doesn't
necessarily imply that there's a lot of
effort or strain or work
a lot of work it's just a choice the
choice and what we're going to endeavor
in
and this uh the usual this definition or
description of these of
the effort factor of awakening is the
same description as the
effort factor of the eightfold path
and so if you take it as endeavoring
the buddha is here is teaching us what
what in this wonderful precious life
that we have
what endeavors are worthwhile to do
you know what's what should we do with
our life
what endeavors and rather than giving an
answer
for a particular project you know
particular work to do a career to do or
something
the answer is it has to do with
the consequences of what we do of how we
do it
and so those things that lead to
what is skillful or wholesome
those things choose choose those things
those things that
lead to what's unskillful to what's
unwholesome
don't do those things don't choose those
things to do
and what's most skillful in the
in the teachings of the buddha are those
things that
avoid we're avoiding things that cause
suffering
and suffering comes along with a feeling
of being
caught or trapped or constricted or
clinging to something craving the
world's gotten smaller
narrower
and we choose to do those things that
are skillful which is those things that
lead away from suffering
lead to a kind of wonderful happiness
and peace that goes along with feelings
of freedom
of openness of tranquility
of of goodness of happiness
and so it isn't just any old
happiness that we're looking for
because some happiness is like the
happiness of winning
the lottery is not really a
deep nourishing kind of wellspring of
goodness of warmth of peace of
kind of real intimacy with the
warmth and juiciness of life it's more
of a surface joy and more
exuberance and
i don't know what promise of all kinds
of exciting things
and they say that most people who win
big lotteries a year later
are less happy than they were before
they won it
so what is it that's lasting happiness
what is it that lives
lasting well-being and so begin having a
sense
of what that is not in the big picture
like
way in the future but to to recognize
this
in ourselves to recognize moment by
moment
that if i'm driving my car
and there's a light up ahead that's
green but i don't know if i'll make it
and then get contracted and focused and
tight
like you know i better get it you know i
i'll be late for my appointment of where
my life will
you know be so much more difficult if i
don't make that green light and
and then we're kind of you know getting
contracted and tight
and the feeling in the body and the mind
and the heart
maybe it's subtle but is not a very good
one it's not a nourishing one it's not
one that
inculcates goodness or warmth or
peace or love or care for others
but another choice in driving would be
you know
i see the light up there it's green
right now but
probably i can't reach it i'm not sure
rather than racing to see if i can get
it
what if i actually there's no one behind
me right in the moment
what if i actually go a little bit
slower and just kind of take it easy and
give the light a chance to turn red
and then i can kind of be connected
myself to myself in a different kind of
way and
i can kind of relax a little bit be more
open it can be more receptive to the
traffic around me
and to the environment and not so
narrowly focused
and you get it turns red and you stop
and
you sit there and turns out then you're
kind of quite contented you did a nice
thing for yourself
and and so this much some of you might
think this example is ridiculous
but we have ten thousands of these small
little
choices that we make throughout the day
and to begin endeavoring the right
effort
is to make wise choices around these ten
thousand little things we do throughout
the day
including the big choices we make the
big things we do
and this this is how we bring
mindfulness into daily life
is we bring mindfulness to all the what
we're doing
and we have not just aware of what we're
doing
we're aware of the choices we make as we
do them
and we we're aware of the options we
have
of which direction we go in the skillful
or the unskillful
and so the investigation factor of
awakening the
fact awakening that makes the sees
clearly and sees distinctions
includes seeing this distinction between
as
healthy and unhealthy skillful and
unskillful
beneficial and not beneficial leading to
entrapment or leading to freedom
and so right effort is to you know in
the
effort factor of awakening is that
factor of awakening that's
constantly turning towards the healthy
choice
but not because it's a lot of work
in fact as we get the hang of it it
feels the opposite
that's where the least work is
in some ways choosing the unskillful
thing
there can't if you're lazy or if you're
kind of
it's easier just to go along with
impulses it can feel like it's the easy
way
but generally the consequences are
require much more work later much more
repair
and stress and all that choose the
healthy approach
the skillful and it tends to be
just the consequences tend to be good in
the future and
no repair is needed no you don't have to
de-stress
afterwards recover from it
and so getting getting the habit and the
ongoingness of
being present and making these wise
choices to what's skillful and
beneficial
tends to start creating a life which has
less and less stress in it
less and less uh needing to recover from
the stress
the tensions of the life and so there's
more energy it's more vitality
for this life of ours then if we choose
the unskillful repeatedly repeatedly
and so this effort factor of awakening
uh is um is certainly the individual
practices and choices we make along this
line
but it's more of a state or a
generalized
attitude or orientation for how we live
where we're just naturally oriented
towards the skillful
naturally oriented towards these choices
which lead to our betterment to
ease to peace to ongoing well-being
and there's a kind of a momentum in that
direction there's a kind of a strength
to that
that follows in the wake of the second
factor of awakening becoming strong
this really seeing clearly so first
there's mindfulness that
places us in the present moment then
there's
investigation in a sense or exploration
or discovery
that helps us to see all the choices we
have
in the moment when we when you see the
red light green light or the red light
ahead as you drive
you see oh there's a choice here and
then there's the
effort factor of awakening which no
something inside of you
with time almost doesn't have to be a
lot of reflection and planning
and calculating and bringing up the
calculus of stress
and freedom but it's uh
just it just feels like oh that's the
natural thing to do that's the
easeful way that's where the doors are
open
that's where the freedom is found
of course we choose that and so the
choice becomes more and more effortless
more and more
delight and joyful and and
my hope for all of you is that
if you do this a day will come
that the word effort just brings you a
big smile oh i am so lucky to be able to
make effort
wow this effort thing is fantastic
wouldn't that be great and along the way
what's happening is you're beginning
to manifest your freedom your ability to
be free
to simply choose to be mindful is an
expression of freedom
to choose to discover to look more
carefully to investigate
is an engagement of your freedom
to make your choice is an engagement
enactment of freedom
and and so uh
um and that's very different than being
the victim of our experience or being
under carry the burden of the weight of
the
world on our shoulders and everything so
hard and uphill
we're being impacted we're being piled
up
piles and piles of responsibility where
there's no freedom but
to choose freedom over and over again is
not a second nature for many people
but this is what we're working with and
what how we're setting ourselves free
in the big sense as well by all these
small
movements of manifesting our freedom
in mindfulness investigation and choices
we make
so thank you and
i look forward to continuing this series