good evening good evening and warm welcome warm welcome
so we'll start with a little bit of a guided meditation
and just settling into this moment
and taking a meditative posture
a posture that expresses dignity
and resolve maybe but as well as softness and kindness
so some uprightness but without stiffness or
rigidity and feeling into the posture
does it feel balanced
does it feel supportive for meditation practice
i'm tuning in to the experiences of
sitting here feeling the pressure of the
whatever it is you're sitting on against the body
so maybe if you're sitting cross-legged on the floor
the pressure against the legs and the buttocks
you're sitting in a chair
maybe different parts of the legs or if you're sitting on a bench or a
couch
feeling the connection between what we're sitting on in the body
we're grounded we're connected here here
and hopefully the pressure against the body is not unpleasant
it might be neutral maybe a little bit pleasant
i'm sitting here on i'm not sure why but i think there are three sabutons
three of the big cushions
it's very pleasant actually
tuning in to other sensations in the
body maybe more subtle
maybe not maybe there are some uncomfortable
sensations that are anything but subtle
maybe the sensations of breathing
the movements the body makes an association with breathing
the chest the belly
maybe feeling the air going in and out of the nose
one way to simplify our experiences
so that we don't get lost in thought so much or so that they don't create more suffering
more difficulties so one way to simplify
our experience
is just to notice the feeling tone
is this experience this sensation whatever it might be
is it pleasant or unpleasant or neither or we could say neutral
sometimes it's helpful to make a label use a label something like unpleasant
unpleasant unpleasant pleasant
so something like this that whatever experience sensation
arises in the mind feeling into the the tone the texture
the flavor
these are the only three choices pleasant unpleasant neutral
if it feels like you're getting tangled up i'm not sure is this pleasant or
unpleasant or if you feel like you're playing whack-a-mole and like
really on the experiences
within slamming a label on them
is there a way that you might do this that is supportive
doesn't have to be super fast it doesn't have to be accurate so much it's just
simplifying our experience to the feeling tone
what might we learn about our experiences
if we apply these labels pleasant unpleasant neutral
what do we tend to notice the most
is the feeling turn long-lasting or fleeting
we don't have to judge it we don't have to figure it out or understand exactly why
those sensations are arising just keeping it very simple
if it feels tiresome don't have to do it all the time
so simplifying our practice by noticing pleasant unpleasant or
neutral there's a way in which there might be more ease
help us stop the tumbling into more and more suffering
and with more ease our life unfolds in a certain way
and in a way that allows us to have the bandwidth so to speak to
support others if we have more ease then we're more available not only to
take care of ourselves but to take care of others so may our
practice together be for the benefit of all beings
um so good evening again welcome
welcome wherever you are and whenever it might be sometimes it's
fun to imagine you know it might be listening to this years in advance
or years from now who knows who knows wherever you are whoever you are you're
very welcome here
so one thing i'd like to talk about tonight is feeling tone or
vedina is the polyword in the language that the
ancient literature is preserved in vedana and many of you probably know that it's
one of the foundations of mindfulness when we talk about the four foundations of mindfulness vedina is one
of them the second one and often when we talk about it or teach about it
which isn't that often more often it's about mindfulness of breathing or mindfulness
of the body or sometimes even mindfulness of the mind so the body's the first foundation
the mind is the third foundation vedana or feeling to feeling tone is in
the middle there in the second but often when we teach about it we don't really
unpack it or explore some of the depths or how it might be a support to practice
so we might just um see what happens if we take kind of like this thread and pull it a
little bit and see what gets unraveled so this thread of looking at the fade in a
feeling tone so often vedana is translated as feeling or
feelings but then it starts to feel like emotions or sounds like right we use the word
feelings for sad or lonely or hungry or
excited or something like that but rather feeling tone or
sometimes even sensation is um really what the buddha is pointing to here and over and over
he defines them as pleasant unpleasant or neither pleasant nor
unpleasant which we often just shoot shorten to neutral so feeling tone
has only three different flavors whereas you know emotions of course are
more complex and seems like there's an unlimited number of them
but feeling tone is is this sensation this experience
pleasant unpleasant or neutral pretty simple pretty simple it's
and we might notice if we um if we set um this is kind of our lens
through which we're looking through vedana looking through the all of our sensations
we're looking at feeling tone and this includes the seeing the tactile the
hearing as well as thoughts thinking remember in the buddhist tradition
thinking is one of the senses everything every experience without
exception every experience pleasant unpleasant or neutral
and so if we were to tune into this simple categorization of our experience so rather than giving
them labels about exactly what they are but just to notice the feeling tone whether it's pleasant unpleasant or
neutral it might seem dry or nitpicky
or reductionistic or i might have some of these ideas like why would i want to do that we might feel like it's
dismissive of the richness the fullness of our experience
but there can be times in which simplifying just a pleasant unpleasant or neutral
can be a tremendous support sometimes when things are um difficult it can be a little bit
overwhelming or we feel lost or we feel confused or we just feel maybe lost confused
overwhelmed or the way that we feel and then just to simplify it down to pleasant
unpleasant neutral and this is a way that kind of can not only simplify things but also
like sharpens our awareness so instead of getting lost in story making
based on the experience that this uncomfortable experience of my knee
which reminds me of that bicycle accident that i had which reminds me that that person that i was cycling with
they didn't stop fast enough and you know all these stories we might have
so kind of simplifying down to this feeling tone kind of like snips in the bud some of the story
making we might be having and it's just one way of looking at our
experience so there might be a time in which it's helpful and supportive to be
simplified things down to pleasant unpleasant and neutral and maybe there's other times when it's
makes more sense to feel the emotions but that's a different
practice so i'm just talking about one particular practice here
and so not only does it simplify our experience to do practice this way
but it helps create the conditions for more and more freedom and that's a little bit what i'd like to
talk about tonight because fade and i will notice
this is a is a key link that pleasant sensations create the
conditions for desire and clinging which then create the conditions for
suffering of course unpleasant sensations create the conditions for
dislike and aversion which is just another form of clinging and as a form of suffering
and neutral feelings also create the conditions for delusion that is just not quite connecting with
our experience at all and not even really being aware of it at all and
ignorance also leads to suffering so we can see how paying attention to
the feeling tone is a way in which if we could somehow interrupt this this connection
that goes from a pleasant feeling tone to craving to suffering as a way that in which we can diminish
our suffering so of course one of the messages that
the buddha was teaching was that the pleasures we seek no matter what those pleasures are
whether it's cookies or sexual encounters or
status enhancing experiences or something that
consumption online purchases or points in a video game whatever it might be
that some of these pleasant experiences they evaporate quickly i'm sure you've
noticed this and not only do they evaporate quickly but they leave us
thirsting for more this hedonic treadmill that even though we
might have some more pleasure pleasant experiences
then we kind of adapt to that and then we just want more and then we just want more and so we
never i shouldn't say never but we rarely are having this feeling of
contentment so we overestimate this is what human beings do we overestimate
how much happiness that pleasant sensations will bring us and how long the pleasant sensation will
last so we keep on chasing after them
but if we look at what um kind of natural selection the psychology and
biology of a natural selection we'd say that this makes perfect sense that humans would do this
that they would overestimate how much happiness pleasant sensations would bring and overestimate how long that pleasant
sensation or the happiness would last because if we look at
natural selection then the original function of eve
evolutionarily speaking of even having pleasant sensations or even having unpleasant sensations
was just uh was to support organisms um approaching those things that are
helpful and avoiding those things that aren't helpful right so that we've inherited this um genetic code
that means that we have pleasant unpleasant and neutral sensations and the reason why we do this well maybe
i'll say this that natural selection um
that there was selection pressure for us to have these experience to have these sensations
so that genes could get into the next generation right
we wouldn't designed quote unquote natural selection isn't a designer but
i could say like the selection pressure wasn't for us to be happy
so much as get genes into the next generation
and it wasn't so much that we had to see everything clearly we didn't there wasn't so much selection
pressure for absolute perfect seeing things clearly
instead we can see that natural selection would say actually it's a little bit helpful to
have a certain amount of delusion so that there's our minds and that these
perceptions and beliefs that make it more likely that our genes will get into the next generation
right that's what we've inherited our genetic code from
so some of the selection pressure some of which natural selection is
designed again quote unquote is that achieving goals
that is goals of eating impressing peers having sex should bring pleasure
and that because humans tend to pursue things that bring pleasure and the pleasure pleasure
shouldn't last forever because if the pleasure didn't subside
then we wouldn't seek it again and then we would just eat once and we would be satisfied
we would have sex once and then be satisfied never have to have it again we would uh raise our status in our
community once never have to do it again right
but then here's where the delusion part comes in and i'm getting these ideas from robert wright
in this book that he wrote why buddhism is true i think it's a very
interesting book i read it quite a number of years ago and i've just been looking at it recently again
and he's positing that not only is there selection pressure
that goals should achieve pleasure and that the pleasure should be should not be long lasting
but that there should be a little bit of delusion involved that organisms should focus on the
effect that pleasure will accompany the goal whatever it is that we want what we
desire focus on the pleasure
and we should not focus on that the pleasure will dissipate shortly
after we've experienced it they're fleeting they're impermanent
so for those of you who are listening to the guided meditation i did earlier if we notice if we're looking at the
feeling tone we see it's changing or our mind is going
maybe from one feeling tone to the next the next but maybe we get on a jag where we're just noticing unpleasant
unpleasant unpleasant we tend to those tend to be a little bit more
compelling but we're also noticing that it's not like a constant sensation
so a little bit of this delusion is that we don't quite notice in our daily life and when we're
pursuing what we desire we don't think about it and nor do we really notice
how short-lived pleasant experiences are and so this is another
way in which noticing vedana the feeling tone
can really be a support for us when we start to see oh this is really short lift it's impermanent
then we're less likely to really grab onto it identify it and make with um
make a um a whole story out of it or something like this
so we can practice with this regularly just noticing the feeling tone of our
experience either in meditation as we did in the guide meditation or we can do it in
daily life too it doesn't have to be linked there and we don't have to
analyze judge compare figure out why it's pleasant or
unpleasant or why we're noticing the pleasant ones and not the unpleasant ones or anything like
this we're just keeping it really simple pleasant unpleasant neutral
and so we often one thing that we will often notice is that um sometimes if something is
really pleasant or really unpleasant we
don't bring that into our meditative experience somehow we try to separate ourselves
from it in some particular way we will come out of minute if we're on
meditation something really unpleasant happens very often we shift our posture
or stop meditating or something like this that's one thing we might notice
something else that we might notice is that actually
it's the feeling tone that we are attached to or adverse to
rather than the objects that is we are attached
to we might think that we're attached to the fantasy that we're having or that we are averse
to the sound of the neighbor's dog barking or reverse to certain sensations in the
body but actually it's that we are more attached to
the pleasant feeling that's associated with the fantasy it's more that we are
repelled by the unpleasant that's associated with the uncomfortable
feeling in the body or the sound so it's a way in which we
might get a little bit closer to what it is that's kind of pushing us around
but to also get back to the idea of the impermanence of what's the feeling tone of how
they're just fleeting the buddha of course recognizes and this is part of his teachings
but um i've i appreciate very much this short passage here where the buddha says
just as various winds blow in the sky winds from the east winds from the west
winds from the north winds from the south dusty winds dustless winds
cold winds hot winds mild winds strong winds all kinds of different winds so too
various feeling tones arise in this body pleasant feeling arises painful feeling
arises neither painful nor pleasant feeling that is neutral arises
so this can be a real support for us in our practice to notice that actually it's these
pleasant sensations that we are often getting tangled up in and then to
really notice how they are changing really changing
so but there's also the buddha talked more about the feeling tone and in
particular he talked about the kind of some of the delusion that we might have
that natural selection kind of primed us for is that we don't notice
maybe some of the unpleasantness of pursuing what we desire we're just
focused on what we desire the pleasant experience that we are imagining that we might have
and then to support this uh there's a few colorful similes that the buddha cave so this
simile of waking up after a dream of uh sensual pleasures we can imagine
what kind of dream this might be right but uh here he gives some specifics the
buddha he says suppose a person dreamt about lovely parks lovely groves lovely meadows
and lovely lakes and on awakening they saw nothing of it
so too a practitioner considers thus sensual pleasures have been compared to
a dream by the blessed one they provide suffering and despair while the danger in them is great
so that the suffering and the despair is that when we imagine that something that we really
want we might actually get it it doesn't quite it's not satisfying it's way or if it is
satisfied it's so short-lived so there's like these broken promises
that the pursuit of sensual pleasures or any just pleasant sensation
is these broken promises of how it's going to make us happy or how it will be pleasurable for a long
time or something like this there's a another colorful simile that maybe
highlights more the the despair associated with this
so that buddha says suppose a dog overcome by hunger and weakness was
waiting by a butcher shop these poor dogs right ones that if they
weren't pets then a skilled butcher or their
apprentice would toss the dog a meatless bone smeared with blood
what do you think would that dog get rid of his hunger and weakness by gnawing on this meatless
bone smeared with blood no venerable sir eventually that dog
would reap wariness and disappointment i can imagine my gnawing on a bone
trying to get some nourishment trying to get something satisfying out
of it and just not finding it i find this very evocative we have this
expression trying to get water from a stone
in the same way trying to get nourishment from things that can't be nourishing so in some ways some of
these things that we're pursuing aren't really nourishing but we find ourselves kind of like gnawing on them
anyway but i don't want to demonize you know
pleasant experiences or sensual pleasures it's part of the
human experience and of course it's also maybe i shouldn't say of course but it's
also part of the path of practice the buddha talked about that if not all
pleasant experiences should be avoided not all pleasant experiences
bring suffering and danger and specifically he pointed to the
pleasant experiences associated with behaving ethically the bliss of
blamelessness ana suka this
and paulie i just like saying that word anava jazuka so this is when we behave in wholesome
ways and we know that we don't have any
remorse or regret that we it didn't intentionally harm anybody it doesn't
mean that unintentionally we might have harmed ourselves or others but we really were practicing
non-harming to the best of our ability without any little uh
like footnotes like yeah okay well i had to tell that lie or um
i didn't i don't know what it might be but when we have this bliss of blamelessness to know that
our behavior is appropriate that's a good feeling that's a good
feeling to not have remorse not have regret
and just by maintaining the basics of ethical conduct
and not only the bliss of blamelessness but also mindfulness itself can be experience of
happiness or can be a pleasant experience because when we're mindful that is when
we kind of have this certain arriving and experiencing the present moment
at that time that's we're not caught up in reactivity or
there's not a proliferation of thoughts of this thought train where we're
building on and then this and then that and then that you know this big complicated story
those are involved are not associated with some settledness and
ease but instead if we can be mindful it can bring a certain amount of ease
and subtleness it's subtle but there can be this little bit of joy
even ah yes okay i'm here and at this moment i'm still
breathing and things are okay at this very moment you know it doesn't
mean everything's perfect and i don't want to be a pollyanna but being mindful
may probably you've noticed this otherwise you wouldn't have a regular meditation practice right
if you haven't noticed sometimes that there is this ease and this pleasant sensation associated with it
and part of what's nice of um really noticing the happiness or the pleasant sensations associated
with mindfulness is that this subtle happiness of being in the present moment actually can be
aroused at any time it doesn't have to be just when we're on the meditation
cushion all it requires is just kind of turning
towards our experience like what's happening right now and then just remaining aware of
that experience it can be done at the same time as everything else we're doing
it doesn't have to be separate so this is a pleasant sensation a
pleasant experience that we can bring with us all day every day
then another pleasant experience that the buddha brought in and some of you might be familiar with
this is that um before the buddha was the buddha that is
when he before his awakening when he was practicing to become awakened
the tradition holds there's this story that he remembered when he was a young
boy that there was this pleasant meditative experience that he had
and then he has after the memory of that comes to his mind he asks himself why am i afraid of a
type of happiness that is apart from sensuality and unwholesome states
and this was the turning point for him that enabled him to meditate and become
awakened so this recognition that he doesn't have to be afraid of this
type of happiness or pleasant sensation maybe i'll say he's an aside sukkah
it's the opposite of dukkha it's and sometimes it gets translated as happiness and sometimes it gets
translated as pleasant sensation and usually it's whether the context of
how we um translate it so the buddha asks himself why am i
afraid why do i of this type of pleasant sensation that is apart from sensuality and
unwholesome states so this is how we can practice
can practice notice feeling tone again including noticing pleasant
sensations it's part of our human experience that we are of desire
and chasing after pleasant experiences this is natural selection created the conditions
in which we all do this is part of the human experience but then we can ask ourselves is this
helpful or not helpful pursuing this pleasant sensation
does it lead to more freedom or less freedom does it lead to more ease or less ease
and if we might find that just simplifying down to actual the feeling tone might be a way in which
we can simplify it and not get carried away and
might bring it into whatever it might be can bring it into something that is more satisfying
brings more happiness even though it is fleeting even though it is not the greatest
happiness because awakening of course is the biggest happiness
maha happiness mahasuka so vadena feeling tone and pleasant
sensations can be a really rich place for practice
and may our practice with feeling tone help us find more ease and may it support us
in supporting others thank you