my greetings my warmest greetings to all of you and here from redwood city in
california at the inside meditation center
and um the topic uh for most much of this week
is the uh important insight one of the probably the most
important insight for people doing the pastana practice and for
what we see in the teachings of the buddha is the insight into the inconstancy
of experience and in constancy means that the moment-to-moment experience that we
have there's a lot of arising and passing appearing and disappearing of our
experience that is hidden from us if we
dwell in the ideas of what is happening uh ideas have a constancy to them
in our imagination we have an image perhaps of something and and the image is not really current with
how things are changing always and uh and this inconstancy is a
repetition of just new things appearing they disappear
or they get replaced they're superseded by other things that arise and so for this meditation today i would
like to emphasize the appearing of experience the arising
of phenomena that we are aware of we perceive and
many things appear in awareness without any choice in our part or wish on our
part they just appear if there's a building in the environment where you're a sound
in the environment where you're at chances are some of those sounds are
creaking of a building or traffic outside is not something you willed or planned on having or
but it just arises it appears in awareness and then there's a recognition there's a sound and it
happens on your cheek and it wasn't there before and now it's appeared and
it was not planned it was not engineered it just appeared no choice
no choice on your part and but it's there it is and the initial appearance of many of
these things is effortless and that it's effortless on our part we don't have to make any
effort to make it appear and so as we sit and meditate there are
many things that will just appear in awareness and to settle back and just watch and
observe the appearance of things don't have to worry about how long it
stays and you don't have to worry about seeing it's passing away
but in the course of the meditation many of things that appear will in fact disappear
they'll be there for a while and and then they will pass away there may be some things that endure
don't worry about that and um but for this meditation we'll stay with
the breathing it's the kind of that's the the beat or the the base that we kind of
keep staying at um being with the breathing in breathing out but as we do that in the
breathing itself we can be aware of just new new sensations arise
um or maybe not new it might be similar to what's happened at the last in breath or last out breath but still we can
we're there to not do not necessarily experience new things arising just that things arise
arise arise arise things appear without and there can be a cascade or a rapid sequence of many
little sensations that arise on the in-breath and the out-breath but that he has to rest and stay with
the breathing stay close and intimate to the breathing but then as you do so
gently in the peripheral attention as things arise a sound a sensation your
body a thought see it as something that's arising
if your thinking is incessant then notice how the the pixels of thinking
appear in the the structure of your thinking the thoughts that
if you think in words different words appear and disappear if you think more in images different
images images changes and new things appear just be sensitive much as you can to appearing appearing
and you might even gently use the label appearing appearing as just a reminder stay here
don't strain don't be actively looking so much as settling back and allowing
like you're giving space for things to appear sensations experiences
to show themselves so taking a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes and sitting here just right away
what appears what shows up
what sensations what feelings what emotions what demon
thoughts that didn't exist before or didn't were happening just before
but then appear
the sound of my voice appears
and if you drop into your body what appears what sensations feelings
and say are there that you weren't aware of before
and if as you feel your body you feel the body's wish to relax
maybe the shoulders the arms the belly the face give into that pull of
relaxation allow it to happen
and as you do there may be new sensations arise
and if what arises as you're sitting here is unpleasant
maybe don't worry about it even if it's if it stays for a while
don't worry about it this is a meditation about being open
to the next thing that arises
the next thing that arises
and if it's a presence what arises
don't hang on to it because you want to be available for the next arising
if you find yourself straining or trying too hard to just be with the arising of
phenomena then relax and center yourself from the
breathing again simple breathing in and breathing out
and then at some point gently
not trying too hard begin noticing again
the arising of experience and it might be mostly in the breathing
or in the body around the breathing or anywhere where arising new things
come into awareness and just know it's very simply
know it as an arising and appearing
without any other need to label it or understand it
just knowing it as something that's
arising
and knowing that it is good to be aware of
the appearing of experience in awareness
as it moves through as it appears and comes
in this small little sliver of time that we call the present
moment noticing what appears
and how it appears changes
in the way that awareness operates it tends to move around
now aware of this now that sometimes following
the train of thought or feelings or
so part of things that arise in awareness arise because how awareness has shifted
were shifts
even when something is relatively constant
in the subtle details of awareness
or attention goes somewhere else and then it might return
and it's a new era and what was before arises again into awareness
to be aware of change in the arising of phenomena of experience
as if your mind your awareness is wide and receptive and open
receiving whatever arises
like the surface of the lake receives the raindrops
we're receiving the arising of sensations in your body
like the bubbles that appear in sparkling water
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
that new experiences new things arise all the time for us not so hard to understand
a new new person appears or calls or emails the email arises
maybe we'd eaten and we're satiated and full and then at some point hunger
rises again we rest well rested and then sleepiness arises again
but to see phenomena first and foremost has something that's
a risen to be right there in the present moment see oh it just appeared
there it is and to do so in a receptive way open way
to receive it in a liberated way not entangled or caught in it
but with an attitude that you could
bow to it whatever arises you bow
yes and so as you go through the day
new people will somehow or other come into your awareness maybe you'll see them
maybe they'll talk to you on the phone or send you an email
maybe you can be go through the day ready and open in the present to receive the
next arising person in such a way that you could bow to them
bow to them as a in a certain reverence or certain
deep appreciation of their capacity to have emotions and
thoughts and feelings their capacity for
goodness they have a heart a sensitive heart as
well as you
to give some care and attention to the first appearance of others into
your life today and how you are how how that's received
in your awareness in your heart and your mind
perhaps before the reactions and usual thoughts and
ideas and entanglements as if you could bow to everyone who
appears and the bowing expresses a wish
may you be happy
may you be safe
may you be peaceful
and may you be free
and then my receptive awareness of you
always ready to have those wishes may it be that i contribute to it being
so may i live this day
aware of the people who come into my awareness
living for their welfare and happiness and freedom may all beings everywhere
be happy may all beings everywhere be free
so the topic continues to be the 13th step of the mindfulness of
breathing observing one trains oneself
observing in constancy i will breathe in observing and
constancy i will breathe out just how the instructions are and this observing of
in constancy usually translated as impermanence
is really as i said yesterday is the core insight of insight meditation the core insight of
the buddha's teachings in the ancient texts and the definition of the buddha gave
repeatedly for wisdom wisdom is the perception of arising and passing the insight into
the arising and disappearing of phenomena that is noble and penetrating
and leads to the ending of suffering so it's the
experience the perception of seeing things arise and pass that leads to liberation to awakening
and uh and so the site and constancy that you the way that in constancy is understood here
is um it is the uh it's defined as over in many
different words in the ancient language that are equivalent to the english arising and passing appearing and
disappearing and
things like that and it's hard to understand to appreciate
how valuable this is to have this experience until one experiences in a very deep
subtle quiet place in meditation that's really where this deep insight is
really it's really an insight that works and it's very penetrating and noble
awakening when the mind is really ready for seeing that if an ordinary consciousness
walking around the street someone tells you just to notice the arising and passing a phenomena
it probably won't stick it probably won't be any sense of continuity with that resting in it just being open to it
because you have to take care of too many details walking on the street and figuring out what's going on and
and um but in deep meditation to be really at rest and really able to
be centered in a receptive open observing way of the the flow of
experience in awareness uh that's possible because we're not overlaying
concepts and ideas on top of things we're just there in the direct experience of
of perception and sensations and the beginning of thoughts and even with the emotions that might feel
an ordinary street consciousness as being continuous we when your mind is very quiet and
still we're beginning to feel and sense the uh how they actually kind of um are very
momentarily fleetingly coming into existence out of existence there's a coming into awareness and out of a worse
awareness the mind picks it up and doesn't pick it up and generally what happens is we sew
these all these different moments of arising and passing together into a feeling of constancy into into idea that
it's continuous but when we don't have ideas anymore just in the experience
um this arising and passing occurs and this is meant to me this is supposed
to be liberating um i mean to do this and partly it's because
when we see that things are constantly in flux that um it's hard to it doesn't make
sense to cling to them to grasp onto them it's like you're seeing the river flow
binds clearly moving and in flux and then you put your hand in there to grab the river and hold it
and you grab a handful of the river and you pull it up and by the time you open your hand to
hold the river all the water has kind of squeezed out of your fingers and run off
and you might have a little bit of drops left on your on your uh on your hand but you don't go with those
drops of water and you're in your hand and go up to your friends on the shore and say hey look
i have the river in my hand if you think you're holding the river
because you have those few little drops you know that's no longer the river the river is partly defined by
water that's flowing and those drops are no longer in that flow and so the idea
of picking something out of the flow of experience and holding on to it if we're in the
flow really centered in it then we see it you know we've actually left the flow we've
actually now kind of holding something an idea of something that's just a little drop it's
just a little maybe even i don't know what and some it turns out that so much of what
we um get attached to cling to resist is not actually reality
but uh the the idea interpretation the concept we have of reality
and so to it's hard to explain that to people in ordinary consciousness but to really be centered and quiet and see
the flow of the vibratory flow of the sparkling flow the raindrop being on
the lake appearing and disappearing a phenomenon becomes glaringly obvious
that it doesn't make sense to cling to it it doesn't make sense to resist to it but rather is to open to it and just
allow it to move through and and just allow it to flow and move
in there and generally when that happens our relationship to that experience changes
dramatically so even if it's been a very we have physical pain
which is very hard to be with i know but when we really in the ability of being
concentrated and still and feel it all is flowing sensation the pain
gets transformed into something else that doesn't really feel painful anymore it's a flow of this arising and passing
of sensations that becomes a whole different way of experiencing it but it requires the mind
being very still and focused and present and quiet to do that
so this is the core insight to see the appearing and disappearing phenomenon in the guided meditation
i was focusing mostly on the arising and at some point we'll do a meditation
just focusing on the passing away a phenomena and then arising and passing
a phenomenon that occurred together but
the so our relationship to things begins to shift
and there's a wonderful verse in the dhammapada
that where it starts with a kind of a quote that all things are inconstant so everything
is arising and passing so even things that are continuous and
from ordinary consciousness seem like they're just unchanging in some way or they're
in the mind's way of experiencing it it's the experience that's arising in passing so we want to be a little bit
careful we're not getting too wrapped up in um the thing that we're perceiving
is inconstant it's the way it's the nature of how experience happens
that's inconstant uh uh there's a momentary kind of pixelated
nature of reality or this flow of this flow of experience that comes and goes
that is built into the very nature of how we are aware how we experience things so um
so so here the buddha says all created things are inconstant and the word is sankara
which uh which uh it's i'd like to suggest that what we're talking
about is all created experiences all the ways in which the mind perceives
and takes in and constructs our reality everything everything like that is just
is inconstant it's in flux and moving and seeing this with insight
and one becomes disenchanted with suffering one becomes disenchanted
with suffering so whoever believes that they're enchanted with suffering
enchanted means and maybe it kind of means enamored it means kind of caught in this i'd like caught on the
spell of it somehow if we hate our suffering we're caught in its spell
we're in enchanted by it in a certain way i guess if that means in english to be under a
spell if we hate something we're under its spell we're caught we're entangled
and there's something about seeing the constancy of experience that helps us to disentangle ourselves
to become to break that spell to not be so caught in it
and so all things are inconstant all created things are in
constant all sankharas seeing this with insight one becomes disenchanted with suffering
this is the path of purity this is a path of purity
so it's a little bit problematic this idea of purity but just a few verses before they talk
about purity this way this is the path for purifying
one's vision purifying our awareness our vision how
we see things so it's not necessarily becoming a completely you know a saint inside that kind of purity but
rather it's um coming to a place where our capacity to
be aware is purified all the filters of thoughts ideas reactions emotions
that prevent us from seeing clearly but to really see clearly see things as
they are we want to see the inconstancy of phenomena then this the verse goes on goes on
all created things are suffering seeing this with insight one becomes
disenchanted with suffering and here we have the second of the three characteristics the three
are in constancy suffering and the
third is not self and these three characteristics are the core insights of insight
meditation it starts with arising and passing in there and in seeing the arising and passing
there's something about seeing that level of our experience that layer of our experience
that gives birth to a clear clear
insight into the in here that this translator which is me
translates as suffering the word is dukkha and for now it may be it's could be more usefully
translated in this context as stressful but we'll talk more about that on monday
and and then it goes on to say all things are not self seeing this with
insight one becomes disenchanted with suffering
so we'll continue this idea of the three characteristics which are so phenomenally important for insight
meditation that's worth spending some time with it and and this movement of seeing and
constancy observing a constancy has an impact on the meditator
and the impact is a process of disenchantment of breaking the spell
of how we're caught or entangled or clinging or attached to things and
where the allure the promise of attachment the promise that uh grasping will
somehow uh save us or do something for us begins to be broken
and um and uh so that's uh so
so you might want to today during this weekend look a little bit at um at
this idea of inconstancy and arising and passing a phenomena and see if somehow that casts any
perspective on how you might be enchanted with suffering
or caught in its spell so i have a little bit of time today
so we can stop uh formally here but if some of you would like to stay a little bit longer and put some
questions in the chat i'm happy to try to answer and i might not be able to answer them in order
but but if you would like to try i'm happy to stay and
and for a little while
and constancy is not bad news aha nice
so are the transcripts of your talks yes but they're not necessarily coming
uh right away but there's a wonderful team of people who are transcribing these talks in the
morning and i think some of the earlier ones are available now from earlier in the year or before so um
if you go on audio dharma where their the audio recording of them appear it'll say if there's a
transcription available and they're likely edited luckily so um
and um and uh and the person leading up that uh that
wonderful the project of transcribing is uh meg galler who often says hello here in the
morning so uh thank you so much meg and your team for this great work you're doing
where does awareness go when we are caught in thinking a lovely question where does it go um
where does it go well it depends what we mean by
awareness if awareness is not the same as consciousness but
awareness is conscious awareness or how to say it if there's
knowing awareness we know what we're aware of we know what's coming into consciousness there's a lot
of things we know that are come into awareness that we don't really you know clearly fully up i know that
like so for example just saying all this i was aware that i have these lights on
here and the kind of studio lights just that i was aware of this light that and then i knew oh the light is on
and uh but it wasn't the second kind of the knowing of it is different than just kind of i go
about and not paying attention i don't think about it i don't have any act of formal recognition
we're thinking our consciousness our awareness i like to think of it as it gets hijacked and held hostage by our
thinking uh we get so glued to our thinking that that kind of self-reflective
awareness that we know what's happening and what we're doing we know that we're thinking gets lost because it's so preoccupied so
glued to it so that's probably an inadequate answer and and but then we'll have to leave for
that can you say more about dealing with pain especially for those with chronic illness
yeah that's a huge topic and for now and um and um it's a very very important one
there's a lot of people who have pain and they're managing their life with pain and chronic illness and
and uh i think one of the great benefits of mindfulness meditation in circumstances like that
is to help us not add second arrows to it to the when we already have tremendous
difficulty in trying to figure out and working our life with this difficulty to not add
shame or self-incrimination or or or resentment or anger or
to not get attached to it should have been different why isn't it different i should have you
know whatever it might be the second arrows but to learn how to be
simpler and simpler and to allow ourselves to be be ill
and painful in the simplest possible way maybe even an ordinary way as if oh yes
i'm sick that's what's happening and then absolutely take care of ourselves try to try to be well
and try not to try to do what we can to heal the pain or overcome the illness
and this is not a passivity that we want to have about it but
we do what we can and sometimes we can't do much but the practice can help us then become very simple with it and breathe with it
and not add extra attention and stress to the already stressful situation
and then as the mindfulness gets stronger and more concentrated then it's possible to bring a careful
loving compassionate attention deeply into the pain and the illness to really feel the
direct experience of it and that sometimes allows to be different kinds of shifts
and beneficial shifts and i don't want to say exactly how those beneficial shifts will
look like different for different people and i don't want to set up the expectation that mindfulness
can help make the pain go completely away or the illness go away and that it's healing that way but it it can
be healing for the heart the mindfulness practice so the illness and the pain might not go away
but the heart is healed and that that's the movement of liberation and and then we become whole
in a certain way is closed captioning available for these talks
you know i believe they are through youtube but i'm not i don't really haven't tracked all this
so well i'll try to find out but i believe there's a way maybe down in the settings and on youtube you can um
they're there that way and um so
oh you know that it kind of goes by quickly so i miss i can't do
them in order i apologize um our thoughts the central mechanism
as to how we cling to these constant phenomena
i don't know if thoughts are the mechanism for clinging but at least in my experience
that mostly what we cling to what is our thoughts these are ideas and um
and it's not so obvious until you might you know you really see how this works in a deep quiet way
um so we don't really cling to physical pleasure but it's more like
we're clinging to what what the pleasures what the thoughts the ideas the
that we have about what these the pleasure is doing for us
um to get it
oh to to get to the deepest levels of insight it seems we have to let go of every to-do list in our life how can we
function in the world if we want to go into the deepest levels of insight great question
yes to get to the deepest level of freedom um you have to put aside or let go of
any clinging all clinging and but
we can still hold things without clinging so you know i can
i can be attached to the striker and i can feel i'm attached to it i'm so
you know i should therefore let go of it and i can just drop it drop it but another way of letting it's not the
thing that we necessarily have to let go of when we let go of attachment it's not the thing
unless it's you know harmful and the striker is not harmful in itself it's the clinging we let go of so then
we can go like this and we can still hold it without any grasping
so in deep meditation we want to put everything aside
and so with the to-do list you would maybe put it on a to-do list on a piece of paper
and put it up on a shelf leave it on your table and and just put it aside
and then later you come back to it and then i look at it and and hold all the things on the to-do
list with this open hand an open mind and and then go through them and have the pleasure of
checking them off but don't get uh attached to any of it or clinging to any of it
so there's you're welcome to keep your to-do list and hopefully the deep letting go and the deep wisdom
of of meditation helps you to look at that list and prioritize
in a good way and maybe few of the things on the list are not necessary a few of the things
maybe represent something you're attached to maybe
unattached to unnecessarily
there seems to be two kinds of inconstancy how our awareness flickers and then perhaps wraps
things up in a constant narrative the flickering inconsistency of phenomena itself
is that correct yeah yeah first that sounds nice um
but things are not random the inconsistency of what appears and disappears is not completely random
but it arises because of preceding conditions and and so nothing arises out of nothing
but the conditions come together and then things arise and uh
and so in dharma practice we're actually putting in place the conditions
so that uh we have more consistency so that we have uh more likely that uh
we move in a certain direction we grow in certain directions we certain kinds of arising tends to arise
more often so for example if you practice a lot of loving-kindness then that sets the conditions that when
you sit and we feel pain we're ready to feel a compassion maybe and love for ourselves
and care for ourselves then we are to be angry with ourselves or angry with
other people because what's happening to us and so it's inc there's an inconsistency but we begin to
shape that inconsistency so it tends in one direction in a beneficial direction
so would you please say more about the buddha never said no self or he had a sense of self yes so we'll
talk about that next week when we get to not self in this exploration of inconstancy
i have i have hopes it kind of goes away
i have tetanus i think it's tonight that tinnitus
tinnitus there we go oh it's an idea so where is it i was oh anyway so
anyway i guess no i missed a question but tonight is i i've had i have tinnitus so the one of the best
things for me is if no one brings up the word um because then if i'm reminded then i start hearing the
ringing in my ears so and uh there are times where i've
been really troubled by this uh you know really draw me kind of batty uh the ringing in my ears
and but now i'm not troubled by it anymore and it kind of recedes and and some people find it useful to make
it the object of meditation and um it has a kind of constant constancy
that um that is grounding for some people and uh and i found it i've never found
it particularly useful to pay attention to it and in fact some teachers actually say
this is one of the things in mindfulness practice you shouldn't pay attention to the idea is to pay attention to everything in
mindfulness but not to pay attention to that so it all depends on the person and uh
you know what's useful and not useful but um i mostly these days
um don't give in much attention and don't you know i've learned not to react to it
not to before against it and just to okay there it is and then
i'll continue with my breathing and sit there and practice and go on with other things and
and i know for some people it's really bad they just have some kind of ambient sound around and that sometimes
you know masks it hides it
it's a challenge to hold one's tongue and only observe yes this is the advanced graduate school
mindfulness to be mindful of speaking and there's so much attachment so much
force and power and desires that come into play in speaking that um but it's so beneficial
to bring mindfulness to thinking it's a window into to say it in non-buddhist dramatic terms
to really be mindful of our of our talking and what drives our talking and why
we're going to say what we're going to do and what what is the the emotional motivation for
our talking it's kind of like a dramatic window into our soul into our depth of
who we actually are so it's certainly worthwhile to learn to do that
writes closed captioning equals the oral notes on audiodharma so
oh someone says yeah closed captioning on youtube is not available live but seems to show up later on
if things are inconstant and clinging to them causes us to suffer what does that mean for choices of the
heart like marriage and career things are constantly clinging to them causes us to suffer what does it mean
for choices in the heart like marriage or a career well ideally we would
choose marriage or a career without any clinging
and in the flow of things are still make choices that uh the direction we want our lives and
the purpose of our lives the meaning of our lives and what we want to really put our heart
into more than anything else we don't have to just kind of go randomly along with whatever happens
and it's a beautiful thing for some people to have a career or have a marriage that
they want to be to devote themselves to be engaged in other people make other choices that are
just as good and valuable now with something like marriage and
maybe with careers as well if we wait until we have no clinging and
no crave no craving no attachment the buddhist idea of attachment craving clinging
before we get married and then perhaps most people wouldn't get married
because that's kind of there's you know there's kind of you know there's not a crime it's not
it's not a crime it's not in buddhism it's not a sin or a crime to be attached and to cling it just means
we're going to suffer some somewhat because of it but one way to approach something like marriage and
career or any choice we make for our lives is to fold it into our mindfulness
practice fold it into our careful care and attention and compassion for where is our clinging where's our
attachment and marriage it can be a great place to and family and kids a great place
to discover where we're attached to where our clinging cravings are that maybe it's very deep that we
wouldn't see in ourselves unless we were in this kind of intimate committed relationship
and and then to work through it and come to the other side of it so it can be folded in as a path of the
practice as opposed to we avoid all these things because we're we're clinging and
so it's probably best not to choose to go into marriage because you want to work out your
clinging but but so hopefully that answers the question
well enough what chapter verse from dhammapada did you cite oh i think it's well the
chapter is first it's like in the 170s let me see
it is verse oh 277 that what i read and it's in
chapter 20 the path yeah this is my i'm reading from my translation that i did 20 years
ago or so and and it's a little bit fascinating and a
little bit i don't know if embarrassing but a little bit of regret that
um choices english choice you know i was my poly my study of the pseudos was not
what it was now so i would translate some of this differently now and and also the use of gender pronouns
i try to avoid um in order to become more gender neutral i did many things i did in a general
neutral way but sometimes i would if there was two pairs of verses
where in the original it was the masculine pronoun i would do one with he and the other was
she and at the time i thought that was good but 20 years later you know or
10 years later i understood that it's we really want to try to be gender
neutral more fully because of how many people don't fit into the binary of he and she
and and so i regret that i left it and that i mean they didn't know enough back then to make that choice so anyway
um oh someone asks meg if um need more help
with transcription and someone else as well um
yeah so she says you can contact imc volunteer coordinator hillary borson
you can i think if you go on the imc's website there's probably a place there
for volunteering and you could just let her let hillary know and she'll be the support at all
okay maybe i'll do one more here are these deep insights only really possible with lengthy
meditation retreats have you read the harper's article about the possible dangers of this
um um no it doesn't require deep insights but
if you're if you're uh if you for many people in our tradition at least it's usually
uh in in in meditation retreats that this really settles in and
really kind of becomes digested or we see it and are impacted in a very good way these deep insights
and for most people and uh but once we have a clear sense of it
and a familiarity with it then they kind of live in a delightful and wonderful way
much more in our daily life as well and it doesn't require deep meditation anymore to really
have it be part of the landscape these insights and and affect us and um i might have read the harper's
article and i think i'm pretty familiar with the modern uh discussion
about the dangers of deep inside meditation and and
so that's you know generally people who want to go into the deeper meditation experiences it's good to work with a
teacher be close connected so you can ask questions of how it's going some of the some that can be a little bit disorienting and
but some of the real dangers that happen has a lot to do with with
the attitude and way in which people practice and the people who really strive and
push and tend to can have
real psychological problems because they're overriding they're not integrated there's not a relaxation it's
not a a nice broad unification uh
composure or collectedness that leads to that supports and so this
anapanasati practice is really a fantastic practice because it creates a really good
foundation for these insights i think some of the people who have these that end up in a little bit of
psychological trouble somehow leapfrog over creating the
foundation of practice they're in a hurry there's a gung ho and and so they experienced this
the deep experiences of inconstancy before they really have the psychological support and well-being and
stability to make good use of it and so if they already have a little bit of psychological instability can make it
more unstable so this is a known phenomenon that can happen and so one of the things that one of the
reasons why having some connection to a teacher and meditation retreats is where that can
happen we have that connection and support if something like that happens
so thank you all very much and then for this morning and your questions i appreciate
them and i'm sorry if i didn't answer answer all the questions and i value them all thank you