so warm greetings everyone and
so certainly i'm happy to be here with you all and spend this time in the practice and in
the dharma and there is a
kind of a loose principle that
agitated thoughts attract more agitated thoughts
and that tranquil thoughts attract attract more tranquil thoughts
and one of the ways of understanding this is that um that i understand it is that
just in the ordinary activities of daily life if we're a little bit busy doing things
and maybe a little bit busy and maybe feeling a little pressure about what we're doing
it's easy to do those things with a little bit of agitation or a little bit of pressure or tension as we do them
and that pressure tension agitation is kind of a magnet or an encouragement
or a catalyst for more agitated thoughts maybe on unrelated topics it's like it
predisposes us to be agitated tense anxious
and and this is one of the reasons why sitting down to meditate
can sometimes feel like such a relief because we're no longer having to do anything no
longer having to take care of the daily affairs of life or work or responsibilities or for these few
minutes all that can stop and and the relief of that stopping then
becomes a little bit of a magnet or a catalyst to begin uh shifting how
our thinking is so thinking becomes quieter becomes more tranquil and and
tranquility attracts more tranquility so perhaps for some of you you will feel
that relief of being able to sit here and and not have to be doing and making and accomplishing and
just just to be here in a very simple way and all this practice and instructions
kind of on upon asati can lend itself to the idea that there's a lot to do
and if we sit down with this kind of this agitated energy or this pressure energy
that can be carried over into how we do this practice but uh it's i think it's best to start
with a reminder that you don't have to do much
and in in a big way meditation is an undoing it's allowing ourselves to
not be so busy and doing a lot and accomplishing a lot and starting off with a contentment and
just a relief of just being here where just being alive is enough
just breathing attentively without any other activity is maybe enough
and then on that foundation then the practice builds and i say that carefully the practice
builds rather than we build on that there's something about allowing something to evolve and develop
that's very important for this practice so assuming a meditation posture
and it's often good to have a posture that feels stable
because in that stability we can maybe shed
the busyness of life shed the agitation and concerns
and needs to do kind of like water just rolls down the
sides of a mountain so the agitations and concerns begin
just kind of rolling down off us
closing the eyes and
gently maybe slowly maybe not too much
taking some fuller a few fuller breaths
just so it's comfortable and nice to really take in more air
[Music] expand the rib cage
feel the body this more solidly more the substance of the
body in the movements of the body breathing more deeply
more fully
and perhaps letting the exhale last a little bit longer
longer than the inhale
to do something that's a little different that might get your mind's attention on the breath
you can exhale through a slightly open mouth
breathing in through the nose fully and then exhale gently slowly
prolonged breathing out the mouth
breathing out of the mouth and silently in your mind saying ah
and allowing the tensions of the shoulders to drain off you
taking a rest from the holding of the belly
maybe softening the arms especially the elbows
you might flap the elbows a teeny bit to make sure that they're loose
maybe releasing any tension in the hands
and then letting your breathing return to normal
breathing maybe through your nose in and out
and bringing your attention to that part of your body where you most associate to thinking
where there might be some tension or pressure tightness associated with thinking
agitation someplace where it's energized
and as you exhale see if you can relax
soften
open
as you exhale releasing the hold on your thoughts
and resting in the space of the mind
that's wider bigger
then your thoughts and images that you have
maybe you can notice some quality of the mind
that has the ability to be receptive tranquil
calm even when you're agitated
maybe it's below the agitation or behind it
or in the cracks between it see if you can become attuned
to some quality of mental calm tranquility
peacefulness
and then as you exhale relaxing the mental activity
so it relaxes into dissolves into the calm
and then with a very relaxed way with very little energy expended
receive an awareness the experience of the body breathing
so that there's a very light touch between the body breathing and awareness
inviting the experience of breathing into whatever calm or tranquility that
might be here even if you're agitated in other ways
and for a few minutes if you can don't worry about anything
just trust entrust yourself to your breathing without measuring it
or needing it to be different or judging yourself for it
a very simple dedication trusting all you need to do
is to accompany your breathing
for a few minutes here with any without any concern with the quality of your attention or
just a dedication to breathing
and when you find yourself drifting off in thought rather than letting go of your thinking
see if what look around and see what you can relax that's associated with thinking
see what needs to be settled reassured
let the mind return to a little bit more calmness
in doing so you might find that your the strength of your thinking
decreases
the more settled we become in meditation
the more heightened awareness we have sensitivity to the mind thinking
noticing it sooner noticing the unsatisfactory
this of being involved caught up in thoughts
noticing the relief of not thinking so much
when you find yourself thinking see if you can feel or experience
the impact thinking has on your body your mind
and then relax the tension the agitation
soften the thinking mind quiet
whatever mental activity that your can be sensitive to that you can feel
see if you can relax it calming the mind
maybe as if the breathing washing a calming wave
through your whole body that includes the mind
and the mind softens opens expands
beyond its concerns there's so much more
to relax into in the particular concerns and thoughts
that we have
waves of calmness breathing through the mind
so
and then coming to the end of the
sitting the mind has greater intelligence
the mind has greater creativity when there's not so much energy poured
into thinking
the less agitation the less force in the thinking mind
the more ease there is and the more space there is for
an intelligent wise contact consideration
of others
and to turn your attention now
to other people
families friends neighbors
people in your county your state your country your province
people that you encounter in through the news or other ways
and begin by just relaxing around thinking about them quiet
soft mind soft heart
and without putting too much effort into it can you evoke a simple
tender kindness good will
friendliness for these other people
kindness begets more kindness
love attracts more love to itself
all within our own hearts
and then to see if there's an aspiration a wish
for the welfare of these people may they be well and safe
may they be happy
and to imagine yourself in their presence
with some dedication and championing
of their happiness and well-being as their advocate for happiness
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
you