so warm greetings and
one of the important aspects of a regular meditation practice
is developing more and more familiarity
with your own body more and more familiarity with your own
mind and how the mind and body work together
how they connect and meet and you know to take the same
meditation posture more or less same but maybe every day
it we develop a heightened sensitivity to the subtle distinctions differences from one
day to the next the way the body is held the tension the patterns are breathing where the
breath is maybe a little bit held and where it's easy
and so and same thing with the mind we begin developing heightened sensitivity to the
differences and how the mind is is day to day from
even minute to minute what it's uh how much energy is in it how tired it is how
distractible it is how centered is so
all kinds of things and this is not incidental to have this heightened sensitivity
it's actually very important and the more we become sensitive to the subtleties of the body
and the mind the more interesting meditation becomes and more we have a an ability to kind of
begin seeing more deeply and offering more presence to our experience
and ability to relax more deeply so
to just keep becoming familiar so taking a alert
relaxed posture and gently closing your eyes
and before you start meditating to familiarize yourself with your body
how is it now what parts of your body are
tense tight what parts seem settled and relaxed
part of the subtle familiarity with the body is familiarity with the
minute differences in posture
the alignment of the spine
the placement of the hands even half an inch difference of where
the hands are can make a difference in relaxation of the arm and even the shoulders
in the position of the head on the neck
you might try tipping your head down a teeny bit
or bring the head back slightly
and then gently ever so gently
as if you're familiarizing yourself with what happens as you do so
take a few long slow deep breaths
deep enough that you feel the fullness but not so deep
that you feel winded
long relaxation as you exhale
letting your breathing return to normal
and gently familiarize yourself with the experience
of breathing
noticing the activity level of the mind
familiarizing yourself with the activity level of the mind
noticing any way in which the mind might be contracted or tense
or agitated or dull
and like your body might relax if you sit down in a nice easy soft chair
see if you can have the same movement of your mind as a mind
settles down into the body into the breathing
the mind settled on the body breathing
st at steadying the mind the awareness on the experience of
breathing
and as the mind is steadied on breathing
as you exhale let the thinking mind become quieter and
stiller
thinking slows
and as the mind gets a little quieter stiller
let there be a heightened sense of higher sensitivity to the experience of the body breathing
with awareness centered on breathing
so
you
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to turn your attention inside out in the sense of turning now your gaze of
your attention on the world people you'll encounter
today tomorrow
into familiarize yourself
with your attitudes and feelings towards others
how is it for you
the people in your life
and without pushing away any way that you feel
to continue to turn this inside out of the heart
so the softness the peacefulness of the heart of your inner life
is the place from which you gaze upon the world of others
with a well-wishing heart a heart that has good will towards
others wish them well
may others be happy
may others be safe
may others be peaceful
may others be free
in ways in whatever ways that are easy for you today
perhaps you can contribute to that possibility may we live for the happiness and
welfare of ourselves and others may all beings be happy
[Music]
so to continue this topic of discomfort
it's a maybe a simple ordinary experience to feel discomfort
and there's so much to learn from it and there's so much
room for many of us to discover how to be freer
with our discomfort how not to be pushed around by it or react to it
how to be present for discomfort so that we see clearly what's happening
rather than being distracted by the discomfort
so one of the things to study when we study discomfort
and this is the task of this beginning of this week is to really stop and take a good look
at how you're uncomfortable when you're uncomfortable what's happening then
is to look for and see if you can understand
the unhelpful ways in which you react to discomfort
when you're somehow things are not comfortable for you whether it's socially or
physically or personally any anything at all that
what kind of unhelpful ways do you then respond to that react to that
what does what comes out of that discomfort what kind of behavior
that is not really in your best interest so there's a list in buddhism the famous
list called the five hindrances and they can be understood as five
unhelpful ways of trying to cope or deal with discomfort of any kind at all
so sometimes when there's discomfort we
go to desires we want something different we want to be sued we want to be to
escape we want to be distracted
we want things to be different and then how they are and we get pulled into this world of
wanting and desire and it can be quite strong and
sometimes in meditation you can spend a long period of times fantasizing
about something that's comfortable something that's you know an alternative to discomfort revealing
interpersonally it could be that we look to have
conversations or have activities with others that that somehow
bypass the discomfort and give us pleasure
sometimes people drink alcohol for this person this reason interpersonally the relationship is
uncomfortable and maybe there's tension between a couple
and the alcohol kind of just settles it away and
and breaks through the barriers of of the tension between them
and that and rather than staying in the discomfort and seeing the interpersonal discomfort as a
as a doorway to a deeper connection to each other to resolve something uh people go towards alcohol to kind of
just change the whole dynamics so there's all kinds of ways that things people do
watch television watches something another strategy
is hostility is to blame to be angry blame oneself blame others
be angry push things away throw things away stomp away run away out of hostility out
of anger this is i don't want this this is uncomfortable for me
and sometimes there's can be a spiral of of hostility that builds up anger
irritation that we're uncomfortable we're irritated that we're uncomfortable we indignant
that we feel uncomfortable and so then we feel more uncomfortable and there's a
pressure and it's building up inside and that makes us maybe more irritated or more aversive
and so it goes until something may be on really unhealthy happens
another strategy with discomfort is a kind of giving up a kind of collapsing around it
and maybe around the self-pity or around hopelessness or
lack of personal efficacy agency and just there's a guy and so there's a kind
of giving up that's uh characterized in buddhist languages sloth and torpor
and kind of shutting down like kind of numbing out
the the fourth strategy is uh restlessness and
anxiety restlessness and regrets anxiety and
regrets it's not so clear exactly what the classic words mean
but um there's a whole complex of things where that are energizing whereas sloth intorper is
numbing or you know makes us tired uh there's and becoming energized so
sometimes it's fear people aren't comfortable and they're afraid we're just going what's going to happen
sometimes people just get restless in it they're like a trapped deer or a rat that's kind of racist walking around
the cage and just kind of endlessly kind of looping and looping and just trying to take the energy of
restlessness and and give it some kind of expression with
you know in of um you know some kind of behavior you know that uh
chewing our to uh our fingernails or tapping a fingers or
reaching for a cigarette because it just we need something to do something that energy can go into something anything
all kinds of things and the the fifth is uh doubt
uh perplexity indecisiveness
we're kind of stuck kind of in a a hard place between knowing what to do and not to do we're not quite sure not
to hurt but here should we not be here and and who's at fault what's happening here
um and so there's kind of a swirl of confusion of delusion that goes on when we're uncomfortable
and am i allowed to take care of myself am i allowed to be comfortable and and i can't really blame someone else or
i'm supposed to be kind of you know you know supposed to be comfortable but
i'm not comfortable and what am i supposed to do here and i'm somehow wrong and i'm doing i'm
failing and something so so there's kind of a little description
of these five hindrances and perhaps somewhere in those you can see yourself occasionally
and and the task of in mindfulness practice the kind of instructions in mindfulness
is to be a connoisseur of these hindrances become a connoisseur of
how you react unhelpfully unhelpfully with uh discomfort
so when you when you're uncomfortable um so one thing is like yesterday just stop
and pay attention to it really get to know it become familiar with it and as you get more familiar with it now
see discover what your common reactive patterns are and seeing the common patterns is very
helpful because they're likely to reappear a lot and you can become you know your phd and
the entrances can be on the particular ones that are your specialty and uh and the idea serious is to really
get to know it well so that you can't be fooled by it so you can see it coming in
the distance so that you learn how to not give into it but learn how not to work with the
hindrances and it might be the discomfort you're feeling is a lot easier
if you uh tease apart or separate out the hindrances that are operating from the
discomfort itself the hindrances add power to the discomfort or add a kind of uh
um you know
kind of like they're they hinder our ability to see clearly
and so without the hindrances or with a hindrance a scene for what they are and put aside then maybe we can stay and
feel and be with the discomfort in a more direct way which we'll see in the rest of these days it's how useful that
is and what can open up so for today
um i'll become a work at work at maybe not in one day
but uh set your aim at at uh
when you get uncomfortable today look around and see what is your
unhelpful reactivity to that and then take it give yourself time don't let go
of it right away don't uh be upset with yourself for having this reaction
but rather kind of stop and take a good look so the bumper
sticker for today can be i stop for the hindrances i stop to look and study and how does it
feel in the body how does it feel emotionally why do i believe in them or why do i get
caught in them what's the dynamics there and what's the stickiness and what are the beliefs that come with
all these so um
so and if you really want to do do this kind of with some help
if you have any kind of friend or stranger or someone that you can tell them that you're doing
this exercise and uh and can you kind of share with them with you a
little with them a little bit through the day what you're discovering that might give a little bit more of
substance to the both the study and the understanding that comes from it
so um may your discomfort and your
reactions to them be the arena of mindfulness for this day
thank you