with a warm welcome good evening good evening
thank you for letting me know that there was no sound
we're all in this together i think that you can yes okay good
you can hear now
so to begin our guided meditation
just to sit and know we're sitting
feeling the pressure of the chair or cushion against the body
feeling connected here
and checking in with the sound [Laughter] check it in you can check it with the
sound or with the body
is there a way that the body might feel a little bit more balanced or
connected or here is there a warm-hearted gentle
way in which you can just finish arriving
in this moment
and it might be that there are areas in the body that have some tension some tightness
can we bring a warm-hearted awareness to those areas
some caring attention
whether it's a knee or a back
or maybe just tension in the shoulders around the eyes or in the jaw
can we allow it to be there
so often we have aversion to these uncomfortable experiences of
course we do we explore and experiment
what is it like if we don't have the aversion to uncomfortable bodily
experiences
can we greet them hello you again
bring in that same warm-hearted attention to the sensations of breathing
feeling the expansion contraction [Music]
that goes with inhales and
exhales
and when the mind wanders
again an opportunity for some warm-hearted attention
non-aversion just noticing the mind is wandered
and begin again with the sensations of
breathing
is there a way in which we can practice mindfulness with an attitude of warmth
and care whatever might be arising
can we have an openheartedness
jack cornfield describes mindfulness as loving awareness
can we practice with loving awareness
to meditate with a sense of loving awareness
having an attitude of warmth to our mindfulness
help support and nourish
not only our meditation practice but our inner life
so that we might show up in the world having this foundation of
warm-heartedness so that our practice might be for the
benefit of ourselves but also for the benefit of those
with whom we come into contact
so that all beings may be free from suffering
without exception
i feel like um tonight's a little bit of comedy of errors i didn't get the sound right and maybe you
guys didn't notice but the bell fell off of the where i'm sitting here
so welcome welcome everybody it's nice to be here
i'm saying here right of course i'm at the imc by myself and i'm imagining that soon we'll be
practicing together i don't know exactly when
there was talk that we were going to open on august 1st but now it seems that the county might
have placed some restrictions asking for mask wearing indoors
so we haven't made any changes to that plan about august 1st but we might
so keep an eye on the website if you're planning on coming we might postpone our opening for a
little bit
okay so today i'd like to continue my discussion
of the pyramids these ten qualities
that are often expressed in our daily life not exclusively but can be expressed in our daily life
as a support for awakening as support for liberation as a support
for greater peace and freedom in our lives
and so this word parameter it is related to the mean of like
taken to the far that's kind of far and paramy or related so something taken the farthest as a
sense of completeness has a sense of the highest state possible
and that's why sometimes it's translated as the perfections
sometimes i'm a little hesitant to use this expression perfections because implicit in that is imperfection
and we might like this perfection it feels like it's just such a high ideal that we might even feel
a little bit dissuaded from even working on it at all but parame as maybe instead of farthest we
could also understand it as kind of going further so developing
growing like enhancing these qualities so what are these
qualities it's a list of 10 generosity ethical behavior
renunciation wisdom energy patience truthfulness resolve
loving kindness and equanimity
in the first five so the next one should be patients but i'm not going to talk about patients
tonight i'm going to talk about loving-kindness which is the ninth parame
there's a few reasons and one of it is related to just what i was talking about how sometimes we hear this idea of
perfection maybe we don't even notice it it might be a subtle way in which there might be
this that our inner critic might roar it's itself and say oh well
i'm far from perfect and i'm not why should i even bother or something like this
but loving kindness is a way in which we can meet whatever is arising with some openness
some spaciousness some ease some warm-heartedness
so mindfulness and loving-kindness aren't exactly the same but they're related and as i go through
the talk maybe i'll highlight some of the differences
so loving-kindness as many of you know is the translation of the word meta so
it's the metta parami but loving-kindness isn't the only translation we could use goodwill
well-wishing benevolence friendliness kindness
kind fullness and i've seen a handful of them and maybe you have your own
favorite translation of meta
one way we might understand it is as a heartfelt concern for the welfare and happiness
of all living beings as a parame it's for all living beings
without discrimination without reservation and of course includes ourselves
so the pyramid is kind of like taken to the farthest the complete version is to have this
warm-hearted wish for the welfare of all living beings
but sometimes you know love and kindness it might feel like it's um associated with love
which is a beautiful beautiful quality but sometimes love we might hear this and it might
feel sappy or sentimental or saccharine
and meta isn't sappy or sentimental or saccharine
and so in fact some of you might know this that the near enemy of meta that is that which
looks like or is uh is a facsimile of or
maybe can pass as meta but isn't quite meta is
affection with attachment so it's the warm heartedness but it's uh intermingled with your
mind or or um you
this wish for things to be a certain way like i want it's not unconditional like i love you
as long as you behave properly when you don't behave properly then i have different feelings
but it's just perfectly natural that loving kindness and attachment are mixed in this
human life they're different whereas meta is an offering and
attachment is more of a holding there's this different uh movements
an opening and maybe like of a closing and we might say that the difficulties
that we have in our relationships arise from this root of attachment that
is any possessiveness or rejection or fear that we might have in our relationships
are associated with this attachment that is often intermingled with
loving-kindness it's perfectly natural to have this and it's part of the human
experience to have this intermingling so meta is a parameter
is an encouragement for us to notice where is this attachment where is there some holding
and can we also notice when there's some just pure wish for the welfare and happiness
of others this pure warm heartedness
good will well wishing so in the same way that mata is
universal it doesn't make distinctions whereas attachment is particular
attached to this person but not that person presmetta is more of a even
radiance or something like this so in this way mata is an expression of
freedom it's not an expression of clinging not an expression of attachment
and since the awakening and freedom is the guide is the measure is the goal
of parame practice again you know we can use this word goal we'll hold this lightly
but is the direction of our practice so metta parame includes those forms of
love or goodwill that are characterized by freedom
so has this quality of freedom associated with it as opposed to some
clinging or some attachment but clinging also can be expressed as
greed or hatred and loving-kindness of course is like an
antidote to hatred or if hatred is too strong a word maybe ill will or
maybe we can even say aversion we know that greed and hatred are some
of the roots of the defilement so loving-kindness manta
is some of the antidote like the opposite in the opposite direction we don't simultaneously have this
warm-hearted care for somebody at the same time that we have hostility and ill will towards them
and so the eightfold path also is has the guide and measure
and goal as freedom and it's not surprising that the
eightfold path and the parameters are towards awakening and freedom to support that
and part of the eightfold path is the second step is right intention wise intention
and part of wise intention is non-greed non-it will and non-harming
so non-greed sometimes can be understood as renunciation which is another of the pyramids it could also be
generosity perhaps but none non-ill will is often understood
as meta loving-kindness so loving-kindness as an intention
as an underlying
support for our mental activities as maybe as substratum or maybe maybe
even just a stratum of our of the direction our life is
going or when we're expressing the eightfold path when we're practicing with the
eightfold path we're not filled with ill-will instead there's manta
non-ill and then the third aspect of right intention is
non-harming which is compassion and of course compassion and mata
karuna and mehta are related that is that loving-kindness is this
warm-hearted wish for the welfare of all beings that's radiating out and it's just
natural that when the radiating out it would come into contact with individuals that are suffering
and so that sincere wish for their suffering to end is compassion so
mata plus suffering equals compassion
so in this way that love not only meta but karuna
loving-kindness and compassion are not only a part of the evil path but they work together as
part of a part of the pyramids as well this wish for the suffering to end our
own suffering and the suffering of others
but ill will also shows up in subtle ways
i'm talking about the eightfold path has the intention of you know non-ill will not having hostility not wanting to harm
others not being angry with others
sometimes when we're angry we don't have access to our best wisdom
and sometimes there that energy can feel um like it's not directed in a way
that's wholesome and helpful so the eightfold path includes non-ill non-anger
so this is maybe a more obvious way in which ill will might be expressed
but ill will can also be expressed in subtle ways
that is when we encounter suffering there's often this tendency to think if we don't have loving
kindness already there's this idea of like this needs to be different
and whether that shows up like just an uncomfortable sensation when we're meditating
i know for quite some time when i'd meditated have this sound in my ear and i could and it
wouldn't go away and i could just feel kind of like the anger that would like be arising like
dang it don't you know that i'm trying to meditate now i can't meditate with this in this
sense of um like hostility and really wanting to push it away
so when there's this when we come up with difficulties it
might start out as subtle like um i wish that weren't there or it might flare up into something
obvious like anger but when it's really a subtle it might
be of this sense of like oh this has to be different or maybe there's a sense of irritation
or fault finding or having a grudge against something so just ways kind of
the heart and the mind might lean in these directions so these are like more subtle ways
or maybe instead of the sense of like this needs to be different there's a sense of i need to be different if there's
suffering if there's something that's uncomfortable then i need to be different this is a way
also a little bit of a subtle way in which ill will shows up against ourselves
is not a sense of not being good enough this sense of inadequacy the inner critic just getting
a toehold and then often it can go running
so loving-kindness is a way that if we practice with loving-kindness and have this intention of
loving-kindness is a way in which we might be able to embed in the
i i keep on using this word substratum but i'm not sure that's the right word and the foundation in the milieu
in which um we think in our inner life is a way in which some of even these
subtle forms of ill will can be counteracted and maybe not given the
chance to flare up into something like anger or some real inner critic some self-loathing
another way in which ill will might show up and which loving kindness or meta can be a
support to counteract or to be an antidote is when there's a strong sense of us
versus them me versus you me against the world whenever there's a
strong sense of the separation there's also this subtle sense of ill-will there
with meta there's not such a strong sense of course we can make distinctions
and use discernment but there isn't that such a strong separation
me versus you us versus them
and so practicing with loving kindness practicing with menta meta as a parameter is a way in which we can
soften some of these boundaries that we are making that are being supported by a
will and instead maybe allows us to
be with the irritating without collapsing without shutting down to be with the unfair to be
with the messy so in this way meta is
also going to be a support for equanimity in which we don't lose our balance but instead can
just be with what's happening and not collapsing into making these distinct separations
or just collapsing into numbness excuse me here
make sure that i'm pushing all the right buttons here
so meta as an antidote to ill will both the obvious ways of ill will
but maybe even really the subtle ways like the aversion or the creating a strong sense of
separation and the suit does talk about how
a heart released with meta is brighter than any
axe we might do or any meritorious acts in particular
and in the time of the buddha meritorious acts that is things that were done in
order to garner merit we're definitely concerned with like separation between individuals
and maybe a little bit of attachment i'm going to do this and that i'm going to have this particular reward
so marriage is a little bit more associated with the everyday life there's nothing wrong with
gathering merit absolutely nothing wrong with it they're an integral part of the path
but at the time of the buddha merit was also associated with ritual sacrifices
not in buddhism but in one of the dominant traditions the dominant religions of the
time they would do rituals ritual sacrifices of sometimes living beings
as a way to please the gods or to garner a particular outcome
so in contrast to these things the mata and especially
the a heart released via mata some of you may know in pauli the word
for heart chitta can also be translated as mind so the mind released by mata and the
heart released by manta well so here's asuta quote
just as the radiance of all the stars does not equal a 16th part of the moon's
radiance just saying that the moon the brightness of the moon is so much
brighter than the brightness of the stars but the moon's radius surpasses them and
shines forth bright and brilliant in the same way
of all the grounds for making worldly merit none are worth a 16th part of the
heart's released by metta the hearts released by manta surpasses them and shines forth bright
and brilliant this idea of when we have this manta that it's a
beautiful thing has a luminosity it has a irradiance to it
and part of the reason we might say that there's this radiance is in the same suta as another stanza is
another verse that says one who actively develops
meta mindfully and without limit sees their attachments wane
their bonds become worn thin
so this developing of mata this cultivating of mata that mindfully and without limit
so to so it's that it's boundless and it's for all beings everywhere like
we would with a parame we see their attachments wane so things that we're attached to
there's a softening of this there's a letting go and the bonds the fetters that keep us
tied to our difficulties into suffering become thin this is the direction we want to go
right towards greater freedom so this first line one who actively
develops mata how do we develop mata there's a number of different ways
one is just in our daily life how we can
when we meet people especially as the pandemic is ending and
many of us are moving about in social situations more than we were before
just noticing how we feel when we meet people that is there a sense this inner sense
of friendliness that we're having do we have some warm-heartedness or maybe not
maybe we have some were you feeling uh reserved or a little bit held back
maybe you could have this inquiry of noticing okay what does it feel like when there's
more warm-heartedness and less open-heartedness it's perfectly natural right in our
daily life when we're not practicing loving-kindness to have more or less
so how does that feel how can you tell the difference what does love and kindness feel like
what does meta pure mata feel like what does it feel like when it's tangled up or
associated with attachment what does it feel like when there's a little bit of a version just in our daily life so that's one way
to practice developing meta is just becoming familiar how does it feel like in the mind
and in the body and is there a way in can you notice there's
ways in which it's more likely to arise so that's one way another
is the metasuta some of you might be familiar with this i'm not going to go into detail now but
this is kind of like a beloved chant in our tradition i believe it's the most common chant
certainly here at probably imc and maybe spirit rock and ims but it
might also be the most common chant in without southeast asia as well for teravata
buddhas the metasuta that's about this quality
of love and kindness and the cultivating it and showing up in the world with it and
it also talks about how it leads to freedom so in some ways like the metasuta
is in some ways a guidance of the metta parame that leads to greater freedom so one way
to practice cultivating developing meta is to practice with the metasuta chant it
to listen to it to memorize it to maybe contemplate it maybe
investigate it a little bit we don't have to make it complicated you
know there's been plenty of analysis that's done on of it if you like you could but you could also
just very simply listen there's a point online you'll find
if you just put in metasuta chant you'll find plenty of versions of it and just see how it feels so that's a
second way in which we can cultivate and develop loving kindness
and a third way maybe i'll actually just share this story this uh
when i was in chaplaincy training part of the training was um we went to our funeral home and
we found ourselves there's a group of us that were there and we found ourselves in a chapel
with um a casket but uh i had a corpse in the casket
and we were kind of surprised we didn't know that that was going to happen it
was just us there with this casket and we kind of like looked at one
another and we weren't quite sure what to do but we
wanted to honor and respect this corpse this uh
person this that used to be alive that is now here and so we chanted the mata suta it's
just kind of an expression of our well-wishing expression of our warmth expression of
i don't know a way for us to join our voices together and put something out there so maybe it
doesn't make perfect logical sense but in some way it felt like a beautiful
thing to do so there might be a way in which
learning or practicing with the metasuta it might show up in your life in a way
that's unexpected it might be a support or a a
resource yeah i'll say there were times early in
my meditation practice when i would have difficulties and i would um i had memorized the
metasuta and i would just chant the metasuta while i was meditating and they've just created a different
atmosphere different attitude in the mind so chanting the matasuta
and then of course the third one is sorry i'm gonna cough here
my apologies my apologies i'm not sure what's why my throat is uh misbehaving a little
bit here so a third way to practice with uh loving kindness
is of course to do loving-kindness meditation meta meditation chances are many of you
are familiar with this maybe i'll just say briefly there's two ways in which we can do this
one is the sense of just radiating meta
indiscriminately just sending it out
and there's a suita that talks about this and i'll just say briefly one dwells
pervading one direction with a mind imbued with metta likewise the second
direction direction likewise the third and the fourth so above below and all around
one dwells pervading everywhere and in every way the entire world with a mind imbued with
menta so just the sense of radiating goodwill out
so kind of like having a sense of just wishing benevolence
doing well wishing out and then the second way which is maybe
more familiar is a little bit more structured and specific and
we would cultivate loving-kindness to a particular person a benefactor ourself
a friend a neutral person a difficult person and kind of like progressively in a
systematic way sending loving kindness using phrases often
to different uh individuals or categories of individuals so two ways to practice one where you
just kind of radiate loving-kindness in all directions and one in which it's kind of like a little
bit more specific to individuals whichever way it's all good it's all good this way in
which we can cultivate and develop meta as a way to support
greater freedom and greater ease so we can have the perfection of meta
and which allows it to wish well being for all beings
everywhere thank you