so
warm greetings i'm very happy to be back here at the
here in california the 7am sitting with you all it was very nice to have my friends uh
paul and phu uh uh uh lead these sittings and the
talks and i i was i participated i was here with you all participating and listening to them as
well and enjoyed them quite a bit and i'm also very happy to be back in
this way with you all they somehow trying to think of a theme
for this week i felt that i didn't want to jump right back
in with kind of a similar dharma kind of orientation way of
teaching that i've done much of this last year because of the way that my friends were teaching you know kind of had
felt like a both maybe to respect them and and um and not to have too abrupt kind
of a change so what i thought of doing is to tell you stories uh during the 7th
and 30th time so i'll say this again afterwards but um this mark's a little different for this
week and in doing the guided meditation today
brief words i'll say i want to say something maybe that's a little bit provocative that maybe points to
something and maybe will support you to take maybe a leap of faith into
uh giving yourself over to the simplicity of the meditation
so i like the word sacrifice not for some of its connotations it has
in english but rather because of its latin root that it comes from the latin
root to make sacred and and so with that in mind and the common
english definition of giving something up um one of the things we're doing in
meditation is sacrificing ourselves for ourselves and
uh or sacrificing one part of ourselves for another part
and we're sacrificing making something sacred by at least temporarily letting go of the
constructed self letting go of the self that's built up from stories and ideas and
desires and aversions and a self that's been created or built up from its hurts and its joys and
and its fears and its conceits not to dismiss that or deny it
but rather for now for the next you know 30 minutes just to sacrifice it
for yourself for that part of yourself that is unlimited that's not defined by stories not but
not preoccupied with what's in the future or what's in the past or with fantasy or
with uh defending oneself building oneself up uh even preoccupied with healing oneself
or fixing oneself or all this stuff but the self that is free the self that breathes easily
the self that just can be here in a very contented deep full
peaceful way we're sacrificing ourselves for that self
for these minutes so
to enter into and
enter into a meditation posture that's suitable for
you and to gently close your eyes
and to make a transition from the usual way that you are involved in
yourself to a different way you might take a few
long slow deep breaths breathing in deeply
and as you exhale imagine that you're letting go of everything everything but
sitting here in your body breathing in deeply and as you exhale
letting go into your body
exhaling and relaxing your body
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and this process of making sacred sacrificing is represented by
sacrificing the tension we hold in our body
sacrificing not so much as
having aversion to something pushing it away but making sacred
by relaxing the unnecessary tension we hold in our body
so you might begin by softening around the eyes and the
forehead
relaxing the muscles of the face
as you're exhaling softening the shoulders
and this relaxation this is a sacrifice that's worth making
to sacrifice the tense being the tense body for a body that's
more relaxed
softening relaxing in the chest
maybe at the end of the exhale the front ribcage can relax a bit more
and relaxing the belly
and also maybe there's a global relaxation you can do throughout your
body a global sacrifice
of tension contraction holding resistance
that you willingly offer out as a way of making sacred
sacrificing to feel the body
more at ease
to feel the living experience the lived body from the inside out
and then within this body this part of this body
to begin to feel and sense your breathing
and as you exhale to let go of your thoughts
your ideas your fantasies your plans
your past for these minutes let that be
sacrificed for the way that mindfulness of breathing
brings you into the non-constructed self
the self that is not limited by any of the ideas and stories
the simplicity of being here breathing in and breathing out
and perhaps lovingly maybe with a kind of a love for this
unconstructed self
you can let go of all the ideas and thoughts
willingly sacrifice it for something that's better
that which is not a story or conceit
a thought that which opens up
in the simplicity of breathing in and breathing out mindfully
perhaps it's worthwhile to let go what you gain is so much greater
than what you're holding on to
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
one of the great treasures of the sacrifice i'm talking about today
is that there is when we let go of the small self the constructed self the
preoccupations of the mind about the past and the future and fantasy
one treasure there is that there is a natural perhaps simple
care for other people a simple opening of our awareness
to include the humanity of others
a kind of awareness and way of thinking about people and feeling sensing people being aware
of them where a simplest form of care can arise
simplest form of appreciation of friendliness of kindness
one that doesn't have to be known by others or be put into action
necessarily but just a simple
simple kindness
and if such a thing or something seemingly related to that
that's your way that is available to you at the end of a
meditation session one way to continue
the sacred sacrifice of letting go of the small self
and giving room for something else is to spend a few moments with thoughts
and feelings and attitudes of well-wishing for others
may it be that others may be happy
may it be that others feel safe
may it be that others are peaceful
may it be that others are free
may it be that whatever whatever's well-being i experience that
you experience from meditation
may that well-being be shared with others
may our we live our life caring kindly
for all living beings may all beings be happy
so good morning and good day to all of you and i think i see now that
we're coming into that time of the year where we have a light show
and then buddha looks like he's disappearing in the shadows for a while and probably i will too and
maybe if i remember tomorrow i'll put up try to put up another light in here that maybe
helps you to see better but also i don't want to
to take away this wonderful light show that happens on the wall this
time of year
so i want to start by expressing my gratitude to
my friends paul heller and phu schrader for teaching this last two weeks and i was with you all during that time
i was also meditating and listening to them and delighted and really happy to listen to
their wonderful teachings and and uh and that their teachings and also these
uh their want their own wonderfulness they're these years of practice that's so palpable in them
that um that you got to they got to share themselves with you
and you got to meet them and
and partly because of the because of what happened the last two or three weeks i feel a little bit
hesitant to just kind of jump in and offer some new teachings that are um you know in the kind of mode that
i've usually been doing this last year and so i thought that um
um that may be a nice transition from that time is for me to tell some stories
and some buddhist stories and um number four in particular who was very
fond of stories and there is some theory uh in this field of religious studies
that um for most religions stories are more important than doctrine
that at least for most people the stories of the religion is what they kind of take in and evoke their imagination and
provide examples of how to live their lives and guidance for how to live so so you know i don't know how true it
is universally but it's an interesting theory and and certainly stories are important
so the first the story i want to tell today is um one that maybe is
a bit poignant for california these days where we have a lot of wildfires and already
we have more wildfires so early in the season than we did last year so we'll see what happens the rest
of the year but wildfires so in in the time in the ancient world in india this is a
jataka tale that the tales are kind of like aesop's fable
with having to do with animals usually and many of them and the animals uh
there's one main character in the in these stories that turns out to have been the buddha
in a previous life and so kind of he may be developing the virtue developing himself to be
to become the buddha and sometimes in the future so this story involves a parrot
and and a great forest fire that sweeps through the jungle and uh
as a bird the bird can relatively easily outfly the fire and come to safety
but as this little parrot is flying away he sees that underneath him all these animals are
running through the forest to get away from the um you know the approaching fire however
they're coming up against a great lake and it looks like they're going to be trapped against the lake and many of
these animals can't swim and so they're stuck between
the approaching fire and being burned or the lake where they would drown
so the little parrot said i have to do something i can't just let this continue the way it is so the
the um the parrot uh dives into the lake to make its little wings
wet and then flies over the hottest part of the fire and sprinkles its uh flaps its wings and
sprinkles a little water drops of water it has onto the fire and it does that over and over again
back and forth back and forth and it doesn't really make any difference on the fire there's a few
drops that are coming down they probably evaporate before they even hit the fire but the parrot keeps doing it
because of the paris great dedication and great sacrifice and virtue
they it has an impact in the unseen world of ancient india
and that is the great uh god brahma uh or the great kind of rule kind of
like the zeus of the pantheon of ancient indian gods the great god brahma or sakka
depending how it's named um
his throne heats up and apparently that's a phenomena in the unseen world that when someone on the
earth is being very virtuous he heats up the throne of the great god so he decides to come
down to see what's going on and do so he turns himself into a great eagle and he flies down and he sees this
little parrot that is uh what the parrot's trying to do and he flies next to the parrot and said you
know this is ridiculous it doesn't make any sense for you to be doing what you're doing
because no matter how many times you drop some drops of water onto the fire you're not going to
extinguish it you're not going to save your friends and this is not going gonna you can't this doesn't make any sense what you're doing
and the parrot flying next to the eagle says you know flying back to get more water
says um uh if not me then who
and uh and maybe if i keep doing it i don't know what the consequences are i don't know
where the what will happen but this is what i have to do and this moved to the great god
tremendously and to see this steadfastness this courage this this dedication
to be of help to others no matter how seemingly pointless it is inspired by
this uh the great god uh created a great rainstorm and a massive
rainstorm that very quickly uh put out the fire and saved all the
animals and then the parrot said yes you see you
never quite know i couldn't quite know what effect my efforts were going to make
but you see they worked so um so this idea of what i like this
story i like this story about a lot is that um for me the naturalness of which the the um
the naturalness of the parrots helping others that uh his whole being was dedicated to
doing this and i liken it to a parental care some parents would do the same for their
child they would do whatever it took they would sacrifice themselves for the life of their child
and and there's something kind of i kind of think almost natural
that parents care for their kids and you see that in the natural world as
well that so many mammals animals care for their young
and sometimes that a tremendous sacrifice dedication willingness to die for their little kids
if necessary and to protect them from predators or anything else and in this kind of parental dedication
care exactly what this nature of that care or that love or that
devotion is i don't know but it does feel
in when it occurs uh it doesn't have to always occur but when it occurs
that kind of a naturalness to it and so this parrot was just simply
acting on natural instincts acting on a natural good heart
that was not limited by the small sense of self that's constructed about me
myself and mine and what's in it for me and and will people like me if i do it will i be praised well
or maybe i have to do this because then i'll avoid avoid condemnation people won't think bad of me that i ran
off and abandoned my friends and all these kinds of uh calculations concerns of self that
are a contraction a constriction a limiting factor to how people live their lives
all the stories we live in and both imagine stories stories stories that predict the future
what this all means but when all those can fall away which is part of the function of meditation
then we tap into something very different a very different orientation a very
different set of values a very different way of being in the world that's not boxed in or limited
by conceit and stories and ideas or should and shouldn't even ideas of obligation and what we're
supposed to do so the parent the the parrot was not trying was not living under
uh some duty-bound rule that is supposed to save all these other beings but i think of it
as just natural movement of the good heart and uh and then we don't know what the
unseen world will do we don't know what the effects are going to be the impact we have and um
the and sometimes some people do a small act and it has a huge impact
and it changes the world the woman who filmed the teenager 17
year old who filmed george floyd's death a murder
she had no idea that she was doing anything but trying to record and have justice by
having a record of what she saw but she what her little action had a huge impact on
on the nation and the world and um and so we never know and maybe we
shouldn't know the impact we have and i'll end with one more little story that
um comes from the sufi tradition there was a a genie
who came to a sufi and said i will grant you um two wishes
and what would those wishes be and you can have anything you want and the sufi says wherever i go
i want to benefit people but i don't want to know that i'm doing it
and so the genie gave the the sufi a big bag to carry
and that's a special bag that had seeds of all kinds of wonderful beneficial plants
and had a little hole in the back so it was constantly but as the as a sufi was carrying it
and walking along the seeds would fall out of that backpack onto the ground and
sprout and create new plants but because it was always happening behind the sufi this
was always traveling on the sufi never got to know the way which was benefiting all the
people behind it through growing plants and food and forests and trees
and whatever it was so who knows what the unseen world
responds to our goodness in our care that comes not from obligation but comes
from the awakened goodness in our own hearts
may we all be parrots thank you