so hello everyone and welcome to our meditation together
and uh thank you for all the greetings on the chat
so
sometimes meditation is associated with having a quiet mind
and that can be certainly be one of the pleasures and
and wonderful aspects of meditation and sometimes a quiet mind is associated
with having no thoughts that also can happen but all in its own time
something that you might want to think about is that part of what medi
we do in meditation is to change our self-talk how we talk to ourselves
the nature of our thinking itself and sometimes it's more useful
to think about adjusting or thinking or self-talk than it is trying to fight it and trying
to stop it and partly that's to create the
conditions where it's easier for thinking to become quiet and calm but if thinking
is very active and assertive and afraid and a lot of strong drive in
it it can be almost kind of counterproductive to struggle against it
but kind of um kind of join it in a certain way in order to
adjust it and now just like you would adjust your speech
if you were at a i don't know if you were at
a loud party you were happy to see your friends again and for a long time and you were talking
loudly versus if you go into a nursery uh nursery school when the kids
are napping or you go to uh into uh some kind of sacred ceremony where
everyone is quiet and so you would quiet your voice maybe in these different settings
so um so to think of entering into meditation
as a time to also certainly quiet your thinking but shift
your thinking so that um you're thinking uh well of yourself that you're
bringing you're not dwelling and ruminating in in your challenges your negative
self-talk but there's a gentle movement towards
thinking in ways that are supportive that's generous to yourself that the generous to the world and it
involves an active shifting to thinking well and
asking yourself what would be beneficial right now and how could i address my pain my suffering
how can i uh think about it in ways that are supportive and compassionate
um how can i uh appreciate the good qualities and strengths that i have when
i sit to meditate and not get uh have the negative negativity bias and to look for the
problems all the time but to look at what's beneficial how you're
fortunate uh in this moment and and it's not to be
um sentimental or pollyannish about it but uh sometimes uh
the excessive criticalness which we live in and the drive-drivenness of thinking is not
really beneficial for anyone and uh and it's quite appropriate to
somehow shift the way we think so you don't have to make this a you
know a full-time practice during this meditation but you
might in the beginning and from time to time see if it can be helpful for you to shift how you're
oriented to your thinking and think in ways that are beneficial and positive supportive especially what's
supportive for the meditation practice itself so your thinking begins shifting
towards the present moment here and now and not about things that are other
places other times and plans and memories and things but having a positive kind of a positive regard to
what i hear and as you do that you might find that it becomes easier to begin also to let
go of thoughts and to begin settling down into the meditation
into the breathing and being here so taking a upright alert posture
or any posture that supports you in your meditation
and to gently close your eyes and before doing anything else
could you consider a few mo take a few moments to consider
what ways can you think about yourself and your circumstances right now
in a positive way in a generous way in a kind way
here now maybe with appreciation for yourself
a caring caring thoughts for your own well-being
and then to take a few long slow deep
breaths
aware of the body as you breathe deeply but may be aware slightly
conditioned by influenced by your good thoughts as you said here
as you exhale to relax and let go
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and perhaps i know with thoughts that are generous and caring let your attention
direct your attention to different parts of your body and as you exhale
generously relax or soften
and if you're able to relax some parts of your body don't rush on to the next thing
but have some thoughts of appreciation that you had this opportunity
especially relaxing the shoulders
the belly
sometimes the hands can be loosened up a bit
and as you exhale you might also relax any tension associated with
thinking any pressure to think
tightness contraction around thinking
relaxing the thinking muscle
and perhaps gently and calmly quietly
appreciate anything that's a you can appreciate about these first few minutes of meditation
thoughts of appreciation of being maybe a little bit more connected to yourself a little bit more
calm a little bit more relaxed
experimenting with thinking where the self-talk
has a tone of of support and warmth and
good will for yourself putting aside any harshness
criticalness that might be there
and then have a few thoughts gentle quiet thoughts about turning your
attention more fully into the breathing
thoughts about
how is the inhale different than the exhale
simple thoughts about how might you rest in the experience of
breathing more fully
maybe you can have a few simple thoughts about how there's so little you need to
think about right now it's enough just to be here breathing
if you do find yourself thinking notice whether the thinking is
supportive or kind or wholesome
and if it isn't switch your thinking to something that's wholesome
in relationship to being here meditating
and then maybe let go of your thoughts or quiet your thinking
maybe you can gently quiet your thinking
relaxing the energy the pressure to think
the forcefulness of thinking let it become quieter and quieter
softer and softer making more room in awareness
for saying for resting on the breathing
for experiencing breathing more fully
uh
and then as we come to the end of this meditation
maybe you could have a few wholesome thoughts
as you consider the world around you
the people who you are liable to think about or encounter
today or in the next period
to have wholesome thoughts about them maybe of appreciation
may be of good will well wishing for them
and to have a few wholesome thoughts about yourself
appreciating yourself and appreciating anything about how you are at this
moment
and maybe think about how you are at this moment
might support you in supporting others in being friendly
to the people you will encounter or think about
and may it be that any med benefits that have come from this meditation
that you consider how you might quietly and and
wholesomely use them to benefit others
contribute to the welfare and happiness of the world and may it be that meditation practice
for us is a means by which we can live a better
life contributing to the welfare and happiness of all
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere be free
uh
so the topic for this week is how to replicate at home in your
daily life some of the benefits that come from
living a kind of a religious life in in the dharma so for example living on a
retreat at a retreat or living in a monastery
some people will have a strong desire to really plunge more deeply into the
practice and and sometimes because of family and
work and stuff they can't go off and maybe spend some serious amount of time kind of devoting
themselves to the dharma and uh well that's a quite a you know a
wonderful desire to deepen that way and i support it wholeheartedly
you can get a lot of the benefits in your daily life by practicing in ordinary life and
and sometimes they're practicing in everyday life and not leaving to go someplace special the practice has a kind of honesty to it
or in a richness and a in a
you know it uh it's really addressing some of the issues of our life rather than avoiding them and thinking
that by avoiding them often a monastery we can somehow make progress and
so there are some simple ways that in principle are not very complicated i
think but uh in practice uh you know it can be quite significant profound and
the um and uh so yesterday i talked about you know
just bringing more attention to the body uh living a more embodied life coming back to your body over and over again
throughout the day whatever you're doing and seeing and understanding what's happening in the body and
the experience of the body learn from it today i want to emphasize speech how we
talk and that can be uh talking with our
voice it can be the communication we do electronically it can be
how we talk to ourselves how we talk you know self-talk and um and there's many things to say
about right speech and speaking well there's a tendency in buddhism when we speak about
speech and right speech to look a little bit more on the ethical sides of it than like i did in this last sunday where we
evaluate it in particular by the impact or how it is we're doing it
but the other way is to practice mindfulness of speaking so
not so much looking at whether is it beneficial what we're saying is it true
what we're saying is it kind what we're saying is it timely what we're saying all good
criteria for knowing how we speak but uh but just to simply bring a
non-judgmental awareness mindfulness to speech itself and to our communication
itself and and then as we do so to become more aware
of what's uh how we are as we speak what's what's uh prompting us to speak what are the
emotions what are the body sensations what how's the body activated as we
speak are we settled in our body are we outside our body are we leaning in our body pulling back
with our body what's happening with our body as we speak uh what emotions are there with this
speaking we have to what degree is there impatience when we speak to what degree is there kind of a
forcefulness like you have to get your word out and can't the person stop speaking so i
could speak there's all this there's a whole slew of things to become aware of
if we simply stop or may not to stop literally but if you start becoming attuned to
what's happening with you as you speak so just practice mindfulness of speaking
and one of the reasons why this is so powerful is that speaking is a tip of the iceberg
it represents so much of our beliefs or assumptions or desires or aversions or orientation
about life or belief about what purpose of life is and um our the sense of self that's been
reconstructed and lived with there's so many things that are kind of like underneath that tip of that iceberg
that if we just stop and take a good look at it we start seeing some these underlying
things and we learn so much about ourselves and and if you want to like for example
if you want to do one thing that can reveal so much is
before you speak ask yourself why are you speaking now why do you want to
speak and maybe don't settle for the first answer if i want to speak because they
asked me directions so i want to give them directions maybe that's true
but that's maybe a little bit this you know might overlook the benefits of this exercise
and instead you ask yes they asked me directions and so i wanted to give it to them but more deeply why am i speaking oh i'm
trying to prove them i'm a good direction giver or i want them to like me or or i don't
want to be seen as being unfriendly and so i want to try to make up for it or
i mean there's all kinds of things that can be there and there often isn't just one reason why we
speak but there's multiple reasons why we're going to say what we're going to say and it can be quite humbling to see all
the motivations we have as part of it and so it's a window into
what's under the water of the iceberg you can see so much more of who we are
one of the interesting areas to look at with speech is through the the
idea that sometimes given that leaders sometimes lead in front
and sometimes lead from behind leading in front it's like they're leading the charge and
pushing ahead and and bringing everyone along or encouraging everyone to follow
leading from behind is more encouraging it's more like letting other people take the lead and
giving them kind of you know enough space to be who they are and go forward and then to kind of offer like a
shepherd offered support guidance from behind encouragement from behind
um that other people don't feel like they're in the wake of a leader they don't feel like they're
becoming you know that they're only doing someone else's bidding kind of
thing so in the same way uh and when you when you have self-talk
when you talk to yourself are you asserting yourself when you are speaking
are you to others are you asserting yourself are you pushing ahead you have some agenda that you want to do
are you kind of leading in the front are you kind of pushing yourself into the forefront
or is there some appropriate way to lead from behind
with your self-talk or with your how you talk to other people um where leading from behind means that
we're not asserting ourselves we're not uh trying to manipulate or change situations so much
as that in a driven kind of way but rather we certainly can still be
involved in changing what needs to be changed but uh maybe there's more of a sense of
cooperation more sense of receptivity more sense that we're coming from a place of uh
really more in touch with ourselves more connected to ourselves than sometimes if we are if we're uh
you know advancing in the front and leading the whole show sometimes by being ahead of ourselves
and trying to focus on what we want and what we want to accomplish in our speak we often kind of lose touch with
ourselves we're not so much in touch with the feelings the emotions the center-ness
we're not resting on ourselves and i've certainly talked sometimes where i felt like i was in front of myself i was not
really inhabiting my body and so when we lead from behind
then um you know then we're at rest here we're connected to ourselves we know what's happening we can track our
feelings and emotions we can recognize when we're speaking in unwholesome ways much more easily
than if we're leading in the front we're not really following and tracking ourselves as carefully because we're trying focusing on the
what we're trying to accomplish what we're trying to get across so so to become aware of what are we
doing and we speak why do we speak why are we saying what we want to say
um and go through the layers of that be aware of the mindfulness of the body
as you speak be aware of what's really happening in the bigger picture of yourself
around what you're speaking or wanting to speak and say and um and then where do you where does
this are you being uh are you being driven by your speech is the speech kind of in is your speech
and your thoughts your ideas ahead of you pulling everything else about you with it so leading from you know leading from
the front or is your thinking uh coming along
with something deeper motivation deeper way of being in the world and is supporting and guiding and and um
and offering some leadership but from behind rather so where you're connected and
supportive for everything it's who you are so mindfulness of speaking
and that leads us to have the wherewithal to have more choice about what we say
to track what we're about to say to notice what's wholesome and what's unwholesome what might have
negative kind of consequences what might be hurtful what we want to say versus
saying things which are supportive and kind positive and
and then being better able to choose not to say this but wait and say wait
don't speak until i have something better to say something more useful to say or or more useful way of saying it
and so there's a saying that i think it's an ancient saying that
a speech is more like arrows than a sword you shoot an arrow
you can't go pull it back but you pull a sword out of a sheath you can always put it
back in the sheath so um be careful with our words
what comes out of our mouth and uh and by practicing mindfulness of speaking uh we might have the
and kind of leading from behind in a sense so we're seeing what's coming we're seeing what words wants to be said
then um we have much more wisdom and if our words are going to be a sword that
we're going to stab someone with and we can see it then you can put it back
put it back in a teeth and and see if you can say something more
supportive or helpful or beneficial in a situation
so my influence of speaking so of course you don't have to do this
but if what you want is to live a dharmic life and have the dharma much more fully in
your life in a way that is as beneficial as going on retreats or going in a monastery
um this is a way to do it it's it's a tremendous benefit tremendous good to
come out of this do it and start slowly
don't feel like you have to do all or nothing you know don't go from zero to 60 with mindfulness speech speaking in
three seconds maybe you do it over days where you slowly begin to
stretch yourself into this world of speaking so that you're leading from behind so you're
tracking and watching and and attentive to what's the whole world that's happening in yourself as you speak
and one of the great benefits of this is certainly you
can speak into the world in a way that's more beneficial for others
but also you begin kind of shifting how we talk to ourselves and maybe you'll find yourself with more
often with uh wholesome self-talk instead of unwholesome self-talk
so in these next 24 hours certainly
you might want to take time to practice with this and look at it and one way to do this that supports
this is to talk with friends about this thing i'm mindful of speaking and ask them what they've learned or tell
them what you're learning or what you're experimenting with and then do the experiments do the
exercise and see what you can learn today by pausing more and
and pausing more and thereby be more mindful
thank you