so hello hello and welcome everyone to this
rendition of happy hour so we've been practicing
um meta cultivating kindness love and kindness and
and systematically going through the categories uh one by one lingering in each one
spending a little more time and um
we spend some time with the category of uh the being we're having challenges
with there are small challenges big challenges ourselves as our
beloved challenging being we spend time doing that on monday so i like
us i like to invite us to to gently move to the next category
which by the way includes all the previous categories surprise
the next category being all beings everywhere all beings all human beings all
animals all everything all senti it's all sentient beings actually in
buddhist practice uh maybe later we'll practice with being all beings plants and earth and all that
too but for now maybe we'll just deal with sentient beings for for for this uh session so
so this category yes of course it includes all includes our
dear being our benefactor our good friend includes us includes the neutral being
that we practice with who is the stand-in for all of humanity it includes our challenging beings
it just includes everyone includes everyone so it's um yeah
it's it practicing with this category which is all beings allows our heart to really
shine to really shine its good will
its kindness unto the entire world
and again there's so many different ways to do these practices doing them without metaphrases with
metaphases and the next few days we'll explore the different different ways
so for for today what i wanted to invite us as always we'll start with
just settling with the breath with the body and i'll include a lot more silence at
the beginning just so that we settle uh and and get in touch with them
with our bodies and breath and then as we turn to all beings um
i wanted to share i wanted to bring in uh the karaniya meta sutta
um that has um oops i had it open
where was yes here excuse me that has a some different categories in
here and i like these different different categories here i wanted to name them
um wishing and gladness and in safety may all beings be at ease whatever
living beings there may be whether they are weak or strong omitting none the great or the mighty
medium short or small the scene and the unseen those living
near and far away those born and to be born may all beings be at ease
i love the poetry of the carnea metacitta those seen in the unseen born
and yet to be born oh how sweet so i'll evoke some of these categories
along with a whole bunch of other categories and i'll invite you to be as creative as you wish
in the way that you would divide beings into different categories
i've shared before at some point that there is there is some prayer in my culture i was
born in iran in the persian culture and the azeri azerbaijan
which my grandma and mom were from anyway there was this um my grandma used to say all those who
were born on a saturday on a sun on a monday tuesday so
that's another way to divide because if you go through the whole week all beings who are born on these
different days of course you'll catch everyone so in the same with the carnival mentos a medium
short small big all sizes you'll include everyone so there's so many different ways to cut the pie that's
that's what i'm trying to communicate and it's it's totally fun to be creative with this particular
practice and have fun with all the beings who who um are two-legged or who slither
who hop who this who's that so anyway let's just have some fun with expanding
our heart wishing good will for all beings it's supposed to be fun
yes and and of course yeah it's it's important it's our hearts
dedication it's heart our hearts growing and growing in love and care and it's not supposed to be
grim duty so whatever you love you have fun with you want to do more of so let's have fun
with this practice this beautiful practice of cultivated goodwill so
so with all that let's start
so i invite you to get into your meditation posture you need to shift and move to be more
comfortable landing landing in this body
landing
ah this body as the earth element
like earth it's heavy
there's a sense of solidity that we feel we experience with the body
letting the earthiness of this body be supported by gravity by mother earth
ah letting go relaxing
appreciating each part of the body in our own time doing a little body scan in our own time
connecting with the earthiness relaxing letting go each part of the body
unto mother earth
so
and whenever you are done in your own
time the body scan supporting letting go relaxing each part
of the body connecting with the breath
letting the air element of the breath
intermingle with the earth element
bringing more vitality life
awakens
to be received and perceived
hmm
okay
me okay
me
now i'd like to invite you
to bring to mind your dear being your lovable being your
could be your benefactor and a dear friend
as well as yourself
and the neutral being perhaps you're working with earlier
and the person you're having a mild challenge with
all these people to mind
may we all may you all be safe
to remain or an outer arm realizing that all of these beings
you've brought to mind
that you've been working with the past few days and weeks
maybe you've missed some sessions no problem just bring whoever is helpful in this
moment no problem realizing that these beings
they all share a wish for safety just as you want to be safe they all
want to be safe from inner and outer arm
your benefactor your dear friend
a neutral person you don't have much of a history with
person you have challenges with we all want to be safe
may you all be safe including yourself may we all be safe from inner and outer
arms
just as i want to be happy i wish all of us happiness
just as i want to be healthy
ah i wish all of us good health and strength
and just as i want to have ease in my life
wishing us all ease in our lives
spending another moment or two with
with this group or maybe a subset of them if that works
better for you that's fine
priming your heart in good will and in kindness
priming the heart and extending care
good well
hmm
it helps to bring them up close one by one
connecting with each especially with the benefactor and your good friend
hmm
so
now extending extending the circle
to all persons let's start there all
persons then i'm directly connected to
may you all be well
one degree of separation may you all be well
safe happy healthy and have ease
hmm
all the people who are two degrees
of separation from me i don't know them directly but they're connected to those whom i'm connected to
wishing them all well may you all be well
and it's okay to use your imagination for this
imagining being beings indirectly connected to you
extending now tall beings
any degree of connection
all around the world may you all be well
extending our heart it's good will
and kindness friendliness to all beings all beings who
are too liked
all beings that are four-legged
all beings that hope
all beings that slither
who crawl
to swim
who fly
remove or not move at all may all beings
be safe happy healthy and have ease
may all beings be well
all beings who are tiny
small medium large or extra-large
all creatures all sentient beings let
yourself have fun wishing well for all these creatures
these beings may they all be well
as much as possible
remember the purpose is to train our heart in wishing well without attachment to
outcome in the world sharing our good will
expanding our heart
it's care for all beings it's good oil friendliness for all
beings
all beings who have been born
wishing them well all creatures
and all beings yet to be born
all beings who are weak
all beings who are strong
all beings who are near
either physically near or near to your heart
may they be well may they be safe
may they be happy healthy and happiest
all beings who are far away
may they be well expanding our heart and kindness and
good will towards all beings anywhere on this planet
and beyond
whatever category spoke to you spending more time with them or coming up with your own
having fun with expanding your heart and goodwill and kindness
may all being be well
may all beings be happy
me
so
and for the last moment of this practice
making sure that you are included yourself in the category of all beings
may all beings including this being sitting on this cushion or chair
be well
may all beings everywhere be safe happy
healthy ah and have ease may all beings be free
thank you all for your practice
yes so [Music]
we have some time if you wish to share reflections you can
raise your hand or type them in chat especially if you haven't shared
recently i especially invite you to um
to share what came up for you questions comments reflections
for the benefit of the whole community
yeah reflection is coming from dawn it is a practice
yes you want to say more about what you mean by that uh don where
where are you i'm going to ask you tommy if you want to say more you're welcome to if not it's okay
good morning hi hi i just mean it's uh something to keep
doing and um it's sometimes hard and but um
yeah i i guess i'm just sort of like going to the gym um mental spiritual gymnastics for me
yeah yeah yeah thank you for naming that it's not always easy sometimes it is
sometimes it isn't and some categories some practices might be easier than others and some days
the same thing might come more easily than another day and it's all okay that's why it is a practice right it is
a practice if if you're all good at it then we wouldn't be engaging in this way so
so yes it is a practice thank you for highlighting what you meant by that yeah
other reflections how did you find it
yeah reflection coming rather than struggling with the flowing mind having
fun in the way the river of our mind drifts playing and resting in the water creates
a harmony of feeling into where it is yeah yeah i appreciate that
reflection and by the way i've started this thing of if you send it to me directly i won't
say your name out loud and if you say to send it to everyone i'll say your name just
in case you want to have privacy with share reflection but you know your name so i appreciate this reflection that
that came came okay either way works thank you now for the reflection
uh yeah it's and part of this part of this practice really is
um not struggling exactly not struggling with with with the mind it's a practice of
meta we are trying to cultivate kindness and good will towards ourselves so um having fun
exactly having fun and and this this practice in particular when we're imagining all these categories
slithering and flying and swimming and born and yet to be born it just feels like a party we're inviting
everyone we we know we're inviting everyone to to wish them
well so so i invite you with this practice really um treated with that sense of fun
and i appreciate enough talking about you know not struggling having fun with the mind drift to these categories and
have have a party and like oh you may you be well oh yeah you're inviting more you know no no kangaroos that are
hopping are now in your party oh yeah you may you be well too right you just keep wishing well extending your heart
um yeah turn says all beings in the six realms absolutely
all the uh realms and and buddhism there there the heavenly realms all the the the
happy realms that the gods were having a great time um joyfully in all
the pizza realms all the realms that are those who are suffering and the animals and we're kind of in the middle all the
human realm so yes there's so many different ways to to cut the pie so i appreciate that bill
asks how do you know if you're doing it right um you um
you know doing it right that's a good that's a doubt question that can come up as long as your uh wishing well you know
categories come up and you're wishing them well may you be well you're doing it right that's it it's not
that complicated don't make it complicated it's just wishing well cultivating kindness and
after we keep doing this at some point it becomes both easier and and our heart starts to kind of
glow and shine and feel like oh yeah you two you be well oh yeah you youtube you will too i
wish you well also it just comes it becomes the the wheels get more more oiled
so yeah as long as there's a sense of good will coming up you're doing it right and if the opposite comes up and as long
as you have good will for that you're doing it right it's all about
cultivating kindness so wherever you bring kindness in you're gentle with yourself for
example as as nav was saying earlier not struggling not struggling and just just having the
sense of harmony oh yeah the mind is drifting it's okay do your mind it's okay with kindness
with kindness meeting the mind then yeah you're doing the practice right even if you're not thinking about
slithering and flying you know as long as you're bringing in kindness at any point
you're doing it right so yeah so dear ones let's uh let's
practice in in community so the invitation for small groups
is you know you're all in some ways all beings to each other
right you're both connected and disconnected one one one uh
you know one degree of separation many degrees of separation so um first of all
actually here's the invitation when you come to practice meetings today in small groups my invitation is
first don't start talking just yet actually take 10
15 seconds 30 seconds in silence and just do meta for each other
for the other person or two in your small group then just do meta just good will for
this other human being and then after that then you can see
you know there's a timer so you can see whenever say 50 let's say 20 seconds do 20 seconds of
silent meta for each other and then whoever is moved can start sharing and holding each other
yeah let's try that so and if you need to leave understandable but don't hop off out of fear this is a
really nice community so okay so i'm going to create the breakout
rooms here we go [Music] let's see okay having
trouble again okay here we go all right created opening the robes here we go
hello everyone welcome back so um we have
about a few minutes left for reflections about your practice
and again especially if you haven't been uh sharing recently i'd like to invite you
how uh the practice was for you both individually and or in in groups and
also the invitation really is to offer each other safety so so just reflect on your own practice not
on anything anyone else said speaking from your own experience so so yeah
[Music] yeah jerry says you're right the small groups are very kind and safe
lovely yay thanks for sharing that jerry it makes me happy that's my sense about this community
just you're really kind we're here to cultivate kindness yay so that's what we try to do in small
groups too uh it's it is practice it's not hey just
go talk amongst yourself it's like hey you've just been practicing in your mind now come on let the rubber meet the road
can you practice it with other people can you hold them with kindness wish them well it's lovely thank you
jerry it delights me this is a special community very very dear to my heart
what else what else is coming up for you please i'd love to hear your reflections
especially you if you're new would love to hear your wisdom what came up for you
questions complaints it's all good
and you can raise your uh hand by going to reactions raise hand great
emily here you go hi um one question that comes up for me
this practice tends to be pretty difficult for me and i've heard some people say you know
just keep doing it and then something shifts and i i feel like i've heard other people say try to do it in a way
like shift what you're practicing so you're actually feeling the feeling maybe get a little more creative with it
do you have any thoughts on kind of like i don't want to feel like i'm banging my head against the wall like
torturing myself but i also want to kind of have faith in the process that it could change
yeah yeah yeah i appreciate that so both are true both are true one is that
you know it's okay to try please be creative and start to do what it's easy what what what you
connect with please do that and yet do don't don't necessarily think that
that's the only way because even if it feels like it's not working right you're just
saying may you be well but there's not a sense of cosmic love you just say oh may you
be well trust trusted you're planting seeds of kindness it's working in ways that
you can't quite understand in your conscious minds i i've seen this with so many
practitioners i've seen it over and over so please please take this
as a borrowed trust borrowed faith from what i'm saying that even it feels like nothing is happening
it is happening you get you you change you shift in ways that you'll surprise yourself
so um so don't think that that's banging your head against the wall you're just doing the practice
you're just planting seeds and it's also wise too now you know to be creative it's like oh
yeah i like fish so i'm just gonna wish fish well right or whatever or for they get all all the doggies and
cats come to my mind and that's okay too it's it's uh skillful means cultivation great thank
you for that emily uh michael says sweet and full of joy oh
that's sweet yay lovely that's lovely to whatever happens yeah and having
um and and i invite the community to also have have mudita vicarious jor for michael
because that's another way we can practice by by by celebrating other people's practice
uh as a way to actually practice for ourselves and jaime says each of us in my group
agreed it was easy to open and really receive metta from each other oh that's lovely brought
us a lot of gratitude for this sangha thank you oh that makes me so happy oh
to receive men from each other uh what a lovely note to end on
ah so thank you all for your practice thank you for practicing
both for your own benefit and for the benefit of all beings and supporting each other in this sangha what a beautiful sangha
to practice and support each other in this cultivation it's harder to do it alone it's it's
much easier to to do it in community so let's dedicate the merit of our practice may all beings
everywhere be safe happy healthy and have ease
us included may all beings be free and know their own goodness
thank you all