greetings to all of you and happy to be here
and one of the things that i love about sitting down to meditate
is i kind of return to a simplicity of being
a kind of um returning to the
elemental qualities of just being alive and the immediacy of the of it the
directness of it and
maybe it's uh the difference between spending a whole life eating processed
food versus uh going out into the garden and
picking vegetables and produce and coming in and
maybe if it's a salad just all raw ingredients that are gathered together and made into a nice
salad or zucchinis and onions that are chopped up and
and cooked directly and so in the same way we can live our lives
lost in thought preoccupied in abstractions involved in the complexity of political
philosophy family dramas
sensual fantasies and the world of regrets and
resentments all this kind of abstract world that we keep processing and processing and
processing and and it's not just a simple processed food it's over processed and
reprocessed and deprocessed and all kinds of things
but then we come to sit and meditate and we return to the garden
we return to where the elemental aspects of just being alive and
breathing and sensing and feeling exist and it's such a it can be such a
delight it can be a challenge too because the momentum of the
processing machine can be strong there's not a simple switch to turn off
the processor and but to appreciate
that underneath all the thoughts ideas experiencings we're
processing there is something very fundamental
and elemental and basic about just breathing and
blood coursing through our veins and the nerve ends in our skins and
throughout our bodies picking up whatever sensations that are
being whatever things are triggering the sensations
the elemental qualities of our temperature and warmth and coolness
hardness and softness movements of the body
so we'll sit here
and feeling the solidity of your body maybe against the
whatever object is supporting the weight of your pro of your body
so you're the bottom of your chair your cushion the floor the bed
whatever supporting the weight of your body to feel the elemental solidity of that
or hardness firmness of that the support of it
much of our life maybe all of our lives unless we're
flying fundamental is the foundational support
that holds our weight so we don't fall through space
and then there the solidity of our bones that
maintains the muscles in the flesh from just completely collapsing like a empty pillowcase
and to feel the sense the uprightness if you're sitting upright of the bones
the spine and the solidity perhaps all the way up the spine to the neck
to the skull
and then accompanying us through this life is basic movements of breathing
that can operate
without any concern or thought from ourselves or we can be actively involved in
breathing and to appreciate this play
by taking a few long slow deep breaths
this fundamental rhythm of breathing that's like the rhythm of the tides the rhythm of the days and nights
the natural rhythm that we have inherited
from the whole process of evolution
and relaxing softening
releasing the ways that muscles are sticky
close contracted
releasing softening
moving in the direction of the muscles of the shoulders the belly
arms and legs maybe becoming a little bit water-like
flowing and soft and not resisting anything not holding back
letting your breathing be normal
and settling down into the body's experience of itself
sensations there are in the body you might think of them as the
raw ingredients that takes in the data the information
that gathers together experiences which the mind can
process and abstract on and get involved in its thoughts and
concerns and for these minutes here
you do not need to think about anything or process anything
maybe you can give yourself a break a pause
to trust that there is something else to do here besides think and consider and remember
and plan to be in the garden of the body
the elemental qualities of sensations
where the mind's involvement is to receive
receive the elemental basic experience physical experience
of body shifting buzzing kaleidoscope
of changing sensations in the body
when you need to let the thinking mind become quieter
no need to do keep thinking
quieting the mind so the mind can spend more time
sensing feeling receiving
savoring the experience of body
and how those sensations of body are shifting and changing and moving and pulsing
in a flow just body for these minutes
you might relate to the sensations of your body
as you would to the weather
both impersonal and intimate if we're in the weather
if you have uncomfortable sensations in your body
it's a particular kind of weather
allow yourself to rest settle trust ex elemental experience
of the sensations of the body
one of the values of attention to the elemental qualities of
sensations is in fact a notice how much we will drift away from that in our
mental processing into a world that can be much more
complex convoluted stressful
than the raw simplicity of the body just breathing and heartbeating
and perhaps you have a small taste today or other times
of the thinking processing mind coming more and more to rest
and just sitting breathing peacefully quietly
just being
and maybe it helps us to realize appreciate how many people's minds are
spinning in this convoluted processing of
thoughts and ideas memories plans fantasies
spitting webs that they get caught in spinning webs of thoughts and ideas that
with which they suffer and may we have compassion
care good will
to all the people suffering because of their thoughts and way of thinking
and may we wish others that they can have a peaceful mind
an an anxious mind
a settled mind that's able to be here breathing and appreciating the simplicity of life
in this beautiful garden of the body the present moment
may all beings have peace of mind
may all beings can it break from their stresses of
their thinking mind
may all beings hold with care and compassion their struggles
may all beings experience a freedom from struggles and
stresses in their mind and in doing so
may they feel the richness and the peacefulness
of just being as they are
may all beings be happy and free
so before i offer my words this morning
when i say that announce that for tomorrow a nicki minaj will give the 7a and lead
to 7 am sitting in that talk i'm gonna go i'm going to go and see my
90 year old father and we'll start then we need to start this driving down to southern california
i'd like to start early before it's too hot or it's too late and
uh it's very fortuitous that the nikki will come because the schedule was to talk about
the final exercise and mindfulness of the body is an exercise that might sound gruesome
but i'm sure that nikki will present it in other ways
which is um a imaginary practice a visualizing practice or a
cons or an or reviewing practice of of uh of of how this body of ours
sooner or later will become a corpse and rather than being a
gruesome and and frightening depressing uh exercise i think it's really part and
parcel of this movement towards freedom and and so um nikki has done a lot of
contemplation of that a lot of consideration of this i think maybe last year she even talked about it a bit during when she was
leading this 7 a.m so it was very fortuitous that the topic should be one that's so close to the
to nikki's heart and i think you'll be in much better hands with her than me on this topic so i'm very happy for this
so so but the topic for today is i'll
introduce this way and that is that many years ago i saw a poem and
i remember all the pieces of the poem but it was a very simple poem that said something that if you're running
walk if you're walking stand if you're standing sit down
if you're sitting lay down and i think it went on and it was but there was a progressive movement
to be getting quieter and quieter stiller and stiller to less activity less energy involved in doing
and doing and doing and um and this is could be described a little bit the movement of meditation
that we're we're moving from a mind which is very much more active busy abstract
thinking a lot and letting the thinking mind the abstraction mind become quieter but not just become quiet and
calm but become clearer and clearer so there's a clarity of attention
that goes completely together with no longer being so involved in caught up
in the thinking world and so much of the stress that human beings experience
you might attribute it to the world around you which has some truth to it but it's all processed through the world
much of it process through the world of our thoughts and our thoughts themselves get
transformed into emotions and emotions come back and feed the thoughts and there can be
this complicated loop that mobius loop that we can never get out of
thoughts and feelings and spinning and and but
as we sit down to meditate some of this stuff quiets down and thinking about the future quiets
down and we're just thinking about the present thinking about the present in terms of me myself and mine
and how i feel all my resentments or dreams quiets down and we just get
quieter and quieter in there in that mind as we realize we give our mind a vacation a rest from the
incessant ways in which we can be think and think and think and think
and i can remember being laying on grass someplace looking at the
clouds drifting by and feeling so content and happy and peaceful and just watching the
patterns of the moving clouds as they move through the blue sky above me and
after a while not only you know so much of my my daily life and concerns fell away it was just
i was just there with kind of absorbed or involved and just watching the changing
patterns of clouds and the movement of it until i i would say that i wasn't even
thinking there are clouds uh there was just awareness of movement and color and shapes that were shifting
into and it's much more elemental basic and and the relief the peace the
simplicity the quiet of the mind that can do that with the clarity of seeing to them not
numbed out but with clarity it just gets so peaceful and it was a wonderful break it's a
wonderful pause it was a little vacation from uh being so caught up in things
so and then if we have that experience then we have a can have a new
appreciation of how the mind gets caught how the mind gets preoccupied and spins out and
busy and all that if all we ever know is a busy mind it feels normal and the stresses of it
just are taken for granted or not even known they're just it's so so um normalized we don't even
know it's there but if we have this experience this very strong radical experience of really
things getting quiet in the mind then we can start taking more uh
consideration and care and uh and of this of what the mind is
doing and we begin getting us a feeling for what freedom is and peace is
that's not in chasing more thoughts not by thinking better but by quieting
the thoughts but not to numb out or to be disconnected to the world
but to have a kind of a different kind of intelligence operating that is the intel that it's not so much
uh centered in thinking
so it's in this context i'd like to talk about this next exercise of the
mindfulness of the four elements and this is the simple very simple maybe appropriately simple
instructions some of the simplest ones for mindfulness practice
um one considers one one um
contemplates the same body um however it is placed
however disposed to whatever way the body's sitting standing walking whatever way we are
as consisting of elements thus in this body there are the earth element
the water element the fire element and the air element and
and this is supposed to be an ancient indian idea that all physical matter is made up of four different
elements or qualities or characteristics or processes uh
earth i think that that
yeah earth water fire and air and um kind of like you know the
earth is the foundation for the oceans and the rivers and so then um fire is a little bit more
the fires of kitchen fires of the ancient world campfires of the ancient world that
um and then higher than that is there so it kind of goes from the most solid to the most ethereal or most
light and but how it applies to our body is uh that it's aware of the raw basic
sensations of the body the physical sensations that make up our experience of the body
not necessarily what the body is but how from the inside out we experience the
body and it simplifies all the possible experience we have into four categories those of solidity
those of liquidity those of motion and those of movement so solidity is the
earth element liquidity is water element and the
temperature is the fire element and movement the wind associated is the
the air element and so there it isn't so much you have to
remember and fit everything into these four elements ideas but to really under
the sensations that those uh point to so to feel the solidity the
hardness the softness of the body the weight of the body the lightness of the body perhaps
to feel the temperature of the body the cold and the heat to feel
the movements of the body the movements of the chest and the diaphragms as we breathe the
sometimes you can feel it that feels like the blood coursing through us or the movements of the heart and
whatever it might be and then the water element is all the things that are kind of fluid
and a little bit sticky it says that uh it's what creates stickiness and so i
associate it with uh with the muscles or tents and other people might have different associations to the elements
but as they they get kind of tight sometimes sticky and we can unstick them and sometimes you have to
massage your muscles a lot to get them kind of to unstick but
saliva when we swallow is definitely fluid and and and so here the idea is to drop in
to the raw fundamental simplicity of the body kind of like you're looking at the
clouds and just letting everything else go trusting sensing this very basic
aspect of human life the sensing of the body to get concentrated to be quiet to begin
letting go of the complicated world of thoughts and ideas and and to really kind of become more and
more attuned to um to get concentrated into the world of
our sensations and as we do that the mind gets quieter and quieter still learns stiller
and there's two great benefits of this many benefits but one is that the mind gets quieter
and we have a whole different vantage point to be wise about the thinking mind
and not be lost in it and the other advantage is that as we get
deeper and deeper kind of absorbed in a concentrated way into this world of just basic flow of
sensations the kaleidoscope the the river of sensations that move through us all the
different sensations that come and go to we less and less hold them together relax
relate to them as abstractions the idea that there's a hand is it's true enough but it is a little
bit of abstraction compared to just the sensations of the hand
close your eyes and just the sensations as they buzzing glowing pulsing tingling sensations of the hand
and the kind of handness the idea of the hand falls away because that's a little bit
of a concept we overlay on the hand and but just the sensations
of it we find that it lends lends itself to
more and more of the mind letting go letting go letting go and even holding even there's a subtle way in which
the idea of hand is a little attachment a little holding on to something
that's not needed to hold on to in deep meditation and so this idea of dropping into the
elemental sensations the raw foundation from which we build so much of our lives
and and get concentrated there just the simplicity of the elemental qualities of our physical
body is um as a very
key aspect of mipasana practice and because it allows us to see
the changing nature of phenomena the impermanent inconstant nature of this and that
itself leads to freedom so may you spend time in the garden of
your body with the basic foundational ingredients
of the from which we build so much of our complicated life and maybe uh stop maybe for a while from
eating processed food but rather start with the elemental ingredients and
just feel and sense and let them the rawness of them like eating raw
vegetables raw food that might be full of nutrients
may the raw elemental sensations of your body nourish you with some of the best
nutrients that we can have so thank you very much and
i'll be with you indirectly with nikki's teaching and tomorrow and i'll be back on monday
thank you oh i can also say that maybe i said this already
that on sunday at 10 30 california time sunday morning
i will have a imc will have a community meeting to talk about the opening of imc
perhaps in august and um everyone's welcome to come to the meeting and i mean some of you also are
local so you might be coming and so if you want to talk a little bit about it here are some of the plans and
ideas of that opening that will be um
you know there'll be a zoom zoom meeting so the zoom information is already on the
what's new and the imc calendar and and i'll probably post it on the chat for the sunday morning talk
so thank you