so so then good morning everyone or good
day welcome and um
one of the things that uh i delight in and and somehow find myself
re-delighted maybe surprised almost when i sit down to meditate
is the regularity of meditation the continuity of it
the way that meditating regularly creates a kind of both the rhythm of meditation but also a
sense of continuity sometimes felt like a momentum some
sometimes felt like a homecoming sometimes feeling like
a a ongoing inspiration this ongoingness
so it's not just that this particular meditation but uh it's the stream of meditation
just being in a stream or a river of something flowing that
continuous day after day or month after month year of the year decade after decades for some of us
so i'm delighted to be here and be in this meditation posture of mine and
maybe some of you uh if you're able or you have been meditating on a regular basis maybe you
too will feel that the delight or the
inspiration or the of that momentum
to go along with the talk i'm going to give today
i'd like to suggest an exercise mindfulness exercise and if it's too
busy and goes against the makes you more agitated then peaceful
you're welcome to put it aside but the exercise is um when you um
find yourself when you're mindful of anything very lightly with a kind of light open
general touch without making it a lot of work or um anything
uh kind of ask yourself if i keep doing this
what is the consequence is this consequence beneficial for me or not
is it a healthy consequence or not um
maybe not so much in their final results but just like on the ongoing doing of it
does it feel like it's um you know a good thing to do and um
and whatever answer you have you get you know you don't don't think about it or to analyze it and if it's not obvious
just continue what you're doing but ask periodically it's particularly relevant if you get
pulled into the world of thoughts is if i continue in this realm of thinking
is this going to lead to a good result or in and of itself is this does it feel like it's a useful thing or healthy to
be involved this way or is it more beneficial for now more healthy
to come back into the meditation to shift the attention out of the world of thinking and
thoughts and concerns to hear to let something here
be known be settled be connected
and i know in my meditation often there's a after sitting for a few
minutes uh it's quite common to to kind of see and recognize a shift
where i've been thinking somewhat and then i say you know that's not sometimes my system
feels that's not the place to be and i'll settle back
and um settle in to be connected to something that's deeper or fuller or much more beneficial
even even i'm thinking about good things it's so much better to um
to come to this healing place settling place calming place of meditation for these minutes
so taking a assuming a
meditative posture and
lowering your gaze relaxing your gaze letting your eyeballs kind of rest in
their eyes and if it's comfortable you can close
your eyes and in a way that is calming
a calm way of doing it take a few long slow deep breaths
long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale calmly relax soften
gentle your body
and then calmly return to a ordinary
way of breathing breathing in and breathing out
and as you exhale relaxing parts of your body
may be a global relaxation the whole body
relaxing with the weight of the body into the surface that's holding your
body up from
your seat your cushion your bed whatever it might be
and maybe as you exhale relax in your belly
thereto may be allowing the weight of the belly as you relax the belly the weight can
gently settle down to a good foundation
for the rest of the torso
on the exhale relaxing the chest the heart center
and if there's tension or ache in that area
soften around it it's okay for it to be there for now just hold it gently softly
see if you can be relaxed about it being there
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
releasing them to the pull of gravity
and on the exhale to soften the muscles of the face maybe letting the lips be slightly apart
the teeth may be slightly apart so that the jaw relaxes
and softening the forehead and around the eyes
and on the exhale relaxing
the mind whatever tension pressure heaviness there might
be associated with thinking
tension in the forehead in the brain
temple area maybe the jaw
whatever physical tension there's associated with thinking
as you exhale
relax releasing the mind from tension
and then settling yourself into your breathing
shifting away from thoughts and concerns
into an embodiment where you are
you're present attending
accompanying the body breathing
in whatever way you're using your attention whatever gets the focus of attention
does it feel healthy for you to do so the way you're doing it
is it in some way that feels
beneficial if it doesn't feel healthy or beneficial
how you're being it how you're being attentive or what your attention is going towards
see if you can shift it to something healthy to a useful way of
paying attention to a useful thing to focus on
and hopefully something like the body the body breathing
is a useful place to attend and if not then maybe sounds
here now
foreign
yes we come to the end of this sitting you might with your mind's eye
turn your gaze outward into your world of
communities you know communities you're part of
out cross the lands and as you bring these to mind and
in a sense gazing out upon the world
in that gaze in that awareness is there any
anxiety or fear
that feels not healthy or beneficial
and can you shift that to gazing from a place of
feeling secure confident
as you gaze out upon the world is there any sense that the gaze is
influenced by aversion
irritation frustration
and if there is can you shift it to something that's healthier
shift it to a gaze that's informed by kindness compassion
care for others
and if they gaze out upon the world seems to be
filtered through desires ambitions
wanting something for oneself
can you shift it to something that maybe feels more healthy or wholesome
perhaps a gaze of generosity goodwill
and perhaps at the end of obsession of meditation you're a little bit better able to
notice the ways in which we are aware of
and to shift it from something that feels beneficial not beneficial to beneficial
not healthy to healthy unwholesome to wholesome
and in this way maybe we can dedicate the benefit of the
meditation out into the world for the welfare and happiness of all
beings anyway that we've benefited from today
from sitting and meditating together may it spread out from this meditation community out into the wider world
for the happiness the welfare of all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
you
thank you um sorry for forgetting to turn off the
microlight drink um
so after this talk uh when i will have a community meeting i'll open up the meeting and
when i have time after we finish but to talk about the opening of imc we'll
do a gradual opening and it'll start in a few weeks and the details of how that happens and
the kind of the process by which people can register to come and be here in person i'll talk about that meeting
and uh the link to the meeting is found at the very top of this chat
you might be able to either click on it or maybe you have to cut and paste it's also found on imc's website under
the section called what's new in the bottom right hand corner there's an announcement about this meeting
and there too you probably have to cut and paste the link i don't think it turns out to be clickable
and and then also on the imc calendar there's a listed the community meetings
listed there they're also the it's been posted but maybe not clickable so
you have to cut and paste and it's the password is meta
to get in so m-e-t-t-a the poly word for loving-kindness
and i see that people are putting the link there in the chat now so that's nice thank you
so
so um today i'm going to talk a little bit
about a discourse of the buddha that um
i find kind of inspiring in its simplicity it's very repetitive so in years past i
would have i just kind of glossed over it and didn't really read it carefully but and now lately i find it very
meaningful in its repetition and its simplicity and um and the context we're giving it
is uh kind of how how i'm feeling after a very full week of all kinds of
input from this world around me i did a retreat i taught a two-week
retweet that ended last sunday a wonderful experience of being absorbed
kind of in the world with dharma and in a sense kind of came out of it
into the wider world again to experience many things that are difficult and
wonderful in this world of ours and uh i mean the big one that uh had a big
impact on me was reading about and the
the covet 19 situation in the united states and in the wider world
and and also talking to people who work in hospitals and their experience there what's happening
there and around the hospital and reading you know reading about these things and
it's so tragic how many people are dying and sick and impacted from the illness
but the tremendous strain on the hospital systems and hospitals in various states overflowing and
people not being able to find hospitals they'll take them because they're all full
and and but i'm also struck by the
tremendous uh um fault lines of tension that exists in
this country are exacerbated through this uh the whole covet 19
crisis and the level of uh animosity and hate in all directions
um that is being spread and been
and acted on is uh kind of astounding for what is an illness
that illness in which many people are dying and
you know the beginning of the pandemic there was uh you know fair amount of last year a fair
amount of discussion about superheroes the medical
first responders and hospitals and nurses and doctors and staff
and who were not vaccinated and were kind of showing up to support and to help and try to
offer medical care to people who were sick and dying of coping so doing it at
their own risk of their own life and um and there's that still happening
and it's kind of frustrating for them that with the vaccine available that they still
you know they're probably vaccinated most of them but still it's dangerous for them and that they have to
experience so much death and you know some of these people in the
hospital doctors nurses chaplains staff are witnessing multiple deaths a
day and day after day day after day when they go to work but also that
there are some hospitals there are demonstrations outside the hospitals where people are angry at the medical staff
for treating kovid for the whole divide between the
the antibacts and the provacs people and antibacks people coming and
denying there's even covet and i've read about the nurses who will take off their
uniform and have no medical in you know badges or uniforms at all if they go into stores
and local stores because if they do people hate them they get get attacked
at least verbally and now it's like they don't feel safe i heard a story of people who are going
to work to try to help people from dying from covid
who had to go through a gauntlet of protesters who were yelling and hating at them
to do their medical care so it felt so painful to read and know and learn about these experiences
that are going on and so on so many fronts and i wanted to what do i say
how do i talk i felt like i had to talk say something about it in a dharma talk and
what do you what what do i say and then other experiences during the week that are very much on my heart that
also led me to what do i say here so i decided to talk about this
particular discourse discourse which i think many people would read and not
find it inspiring find it dead you know
soporifically repetitive and dull somehow but uh i don't think that was the case
when it was originally composed was composed in oral culture and the repetition was part of the song
the rhythm the there was a rhythm there was a tune there was a lyricism to it
and the chanting it in unison in the monastic communities and it was kind of like a
a song which repeats its lines over and over again and and it has a kind of rhythm of where it affects the heart and
washes through us and and makes it you know these really great dharma points are just washing through
and and they didn't have couldn't write back then either so if you wanted to have um
you know remember something you you didn't write it down and then check it later you had to really memorize it and
so to memorizing this rhythmic kind of way of repeating the same kind of thing with slight switches changes was
probably very effective in an oral culture maybe not effective in a written one
and and so this text is number 114 in the middle link
discourses and it's uh uh it's it's uh it's uh
the discourse on the word sevi taba means
there was a seva some of you know seva is a kind of a indic word
that uh it means to serve or to help someone there's an organization that
ramada started called seva that is doing humanitarian work in
in india and other places and and so it's just this word and the word
means to serve it also means or to attend to
it also means to practice and so i love this idea that the word means both that somehow we practice
in order to serve it's a way of serving um uh one translation the most common
translation uh translates what should be cultivated and but with cultivated that misses the
idea that um that there's a kind of little little bit of a devotional quality to it
of serving of helping what should we serve you know what do we give ourselves to in a nice way
and it is practices it's talking about so and this teaching is uh
is uh the buddha gives a very simple teaching and then um
without any explanation and then the buddhist disciple sorry puta follows up with an explanation
explanation what it means the buddha then approves of that and does it more simple teaching
sorry buddha explains and then the third round the same thing at the end of which the buddha says if
to summarize it if lay people
listen to this and apply this in their lives it'll be for their long-term
happiness and welfare and um and uh
it's interesting he specifies laypeople and uh in a sense it's a little bit like
secular buddhism there's nothing about rebirth there's nothing about
all kinds of liberation anything that makes it more complicated or more kind
of religious for some people it's uh here are some things you can do that
that is beneficial for you how you can live your ordinary life if you pay attention to this
and um and nothing religiously really is asked of people it's kind of uh secular practices that
way uh however it also points to the heart of what of the buddha's message and something very central to how he orients
himself and how it buddha starts he's talks about what should be done and what
should not be done or what's what one should serve and what one
should not serve what what's your practice and what one should not practice
and uh and then he goes through a list of things so it's you know there's this dichotomy that's put up there
and in that you know we're always doing something whether we're thinking or
using our body for something or speaking in some way what criteria do we use
for what we do with our body what we do with our speech and also what we do with our mind and how we think
and don't just leave it a chance don't let it kind of go amok by itself
but have some presence of mind to notice what we're doing and then to make a choice between
different things what do we serve and
the um and so the buddha goes through makes this list he says
there is conduct of body that one should serve
and contact of the conduct of the body that one should not serve there is conduct of voice of speech that
one should serve and conduct that one should not serve there's conduct of mind
that one should serve and conduct of mine which should not serve then he goes on says there are
dispositions of mind that one should serve dispositions of mind that one should not serve
there are um perceptions here we are kind of the
conceptions of the world conceptions of things that we should serve and conceptions that we should not serve
there are views opinions stories of the world and ourselves that we should serve and ones
we should not serve and then there are this is an interesting one for many
people people struggle with buddhist ideas there are identities that we should
serve and identities we should not serve and um this kind of way of thinking is
kind of central to the buddhist teaching which means that
it's avoiding of categorical teachings about what one should do
categorical teachings about what kind of views perceptions conceptions
dispositions and even identi identities that one should have or
shouldn't have and some buddhists have this categorical idea that you should have no identities
you should let go of all identities when you're practicing but here the buddha doesn't want to reject everything in some category or
accept everything in some category and he's always asking the question
looking at well there's some that you should some way you should do it in some way you shouldn't do it
and and uh and uh so that's all the buddha says
and then his disciple sartuta says well let me explain further buddha says sure
and sariputta says what when if what you're doing is unwholesome
uh don't do it if what you're serving is wholesome keep doing it
if what your uh your disposition is unwholesome
then um don't do it if it's wholesome do it if the identity
you're holding on to your living with is unwholesome and he explains it as
unwholesome leading to affliction it's unwholesome and it's harming you
don't do it but if it's wholesome leading to non-affliction then it's fine
to do it so there's always for the so sorry put this evaluation for what to do and not to do
is based on this idea of wholesomeness and unwholesomeness which
sometimes is translated as skillfulness and not skillfulness and which is it points to the it's consequential it's
considering in doing this what are the consequences um
and uh if it's skillful consequence beneficial consequences that are
useful for you then do it and and that if not then don't do it
and so here there's an evaluation process that each person can do for themselves these are not categorical
teachings of anything about how to behave about
ethics necessarily a little more nuanced than that but
or about views you know and some people will not like this text because it's so
dualistic they'll say what should be done and what shouldn't be done there's two things that are standing in opposition it's a
binary and like there's doesn't leave any other room for something and
and but that's a view and so the you know what about non-dualism
and the buddha would say there is a a way
to serve non-dualism that's one should do and a way of serving non-dualism one
wants you not to and how if it's wholesome to do it do it if it's
not wholesome don't do it and so having this kind of uh guide this
perspective each person becomes their own teacher their own guide their own
person finding our way forward and because the word for skillful also can mean
very close to the english word for ethical it's how we become our own ethical
guide and it's being what's wholesome and unwholesome
and this is so crucial to the buddhist teachings that we would be have our own ability
to recognize this quality of all the things that
we're going to do in body speech and mind and to track it and so when it's unwholesome
uh it feels painful it has an ouch in it there's an ache there's a contraction there's
tension there's stress there's a closing down there's the unwholesome uh
uh undermines the person who has it so things like anger
hostility delusion um greed are the primary representations
of what's unwholesome that undermine the person who does it the
ancient language they talk about these things greed hatred and delusion burn the person who has them
so they might be outwardly directed wanting something or being hostile to someone else
but we're harming ourselves when we do it so
it isn't always so like major like the harm but there's a feeling of of tension stress even sometimes
something gets lost some a self-alienation when things are done wholesomely there's
a whole other way of feeling it it feels um it doesn't feel uh
deflating or diminishing or or doesn't have an ouch it has more of an ah
it has more of a feeling of of uh yes to it there's a feeling of opening of
relaxing of a delight or warmth
a feeling of wholesomeness not everyone associates in english the word wholesomeness is something that
feels so good but the when i was a kid the advertisements for
bread talked about wholesome bread that's my big association with the word and um these adverti commercials on tv
and and i think the idea was that it was nutritious but when more than nutritious
is kind of felt you know comfortable like maybe some
food that we grew up with at home that uh a parent made that just felt like more than just tasty it was felt like
the parent's love came with it was so nourishing in a psychological way it's kind of what i associate wholesome
with so we do things that have this beneficial effect
and for some people this is a new idea that we could be tracking ourselves
carefully with mindfulness and make simple choices
away from what is unwholesome to what is wholesome um away from what has kind of
uh not has an ouch and towards what has an ah nourishing for us
away from what is de-nourishing unnourishing us and that and to be sensitive to one of the
purposes of mindfulness is develop a high intensity to that very difference
so that we can choose to be nourished and so it isn't just simply being mindful in the present moment and just
that's enough of it but it's doing being mindful in the present moment so we can make these simple choices as they're obvious
of how to do something and it could be as simple as how we make a meal
if we do it uh tense in a hurry resentful if we do it um afraid about you know
will they like my food or not that's a very that's kind of not that's has a little bit of an ouch to it
but if we do it with an inspiration and joy and love and generosity as part of
it just delighted that we have people we can feed that has a very different
feeling for it done from love and um
the um the um
uh so to kind of track this to know it and then to kind of begin to know
kind of smell the direction almost second nature that's the way to go
to what's wholesome and and this is the way
that hopefully we can find our way in a fractured society of society that
has a lot of tension in it and a lot of hatred in it and a lot of greed in it
that we don't want to contribute to that we want to contribute not the not to the
unwholesome but to the wholesome unwholesomeness produces more
unwholesomeness is a teaching of the buddha wholesomeness produces more wholesomeness
for oneself and also into the world so unfailingly dedicatingly committedly
living a life that's committed to the wholesome the ah the beneficial that which is
nourishing that's which is inspiring that which is for the greater welfare and happiness of all
beings we don't always know what that means like in terms of actual things in the
world should we vote for different kind of taxes or not what kind of tax system should we have
what kind of electoral system should we have and so all these big questions that are difficult to you know agree on let alone
really have answers for but be very careful not to lose sight of the
wholesome in discussing these don't sacrifice the wholesome
because of views and stories and opinions remember what the buddha said there are
some views that one should serve and some views one should not
serve and uh and um those views that
are wholesome and have wholesome consequences those should be served
but those which are unwholesome not to be served
and it isn't just the views but it's how we hold views how we use views how we speak of our
views there's a way of speaking about them and the way of not speaking about them
i what i felt most since felt inspired to talk about
in the wake of so many challenges that exist in our society and may it be that we are
a wholesome contribute to the wholesomeness of our society
the nourishment of our society so that what is really good and beneficial for the welfare and happiness
of every single person in our society including the people who are so often forgotten and marginalized
or that we don't include in our hearts let us include everyone in our hearts even the people we disagree with
so that our attitude towards them is wholesome even if we disagree with them