so related to the
topic of absorption that what we talked
about what i talked about in the guided
meditation just now
a a concept that the buddha refers to
often in terms of meditation practice
and this
path of liberation
is the idea of
often translated into english is
seclusion
and the word for seclusion viveka
v-i-v-e-k-a
more literally means to separate
something apart becomes separate
but in the context seclusion is probably
one of the better english words no
english words really work well but the
probably a better english
word if we associate seclusion
with being sheltered being protected
kind of cozy and nice and
secluded in the best possible kind of
associations of that word
cozy and warm and contented
deep feeling of satisfaction just being
here
secluded or somehow maybe after
a you know a long
walk and big invigorating nice walk in
the cold
maybe even stormy weather and coming
inside
and wrapping in a nice blanket and
having
a warm drink and just being all cozy and
alone and feel secluded from all the
difficulties of life around us maybe
something like that
so the word seclusion and
it's used in the buddhist teachings for
a variety of different
forms of seclusion and
the the first kind of gives us begins
giving us a sense of
what it's what's to come and it means
it's used to defer to going on retreat
they don't have the word retreat in in
ancient language but they say uh going
to be secluded
to be secluded is to go someplace where
you're separate from the
some people might say that it's a
process of escaping the world and
and the real world we have to face the
real world
but the what's more real
in terms of our mind and hearts is
becoming integrated not being fragmented
and
being pulled in all kinds of directions
and thoughts and feelings and everything
and so the process of meditation going
in physically
becoming secluded from many of the
aspects of the world
so we can find this inner health inner
wholesomeness and integration
process so we bring back that back into
the world
and it isn't pushing the world the world
away or abandoning it
any more than going alone and being
secluded in your bathroom to take a
shower
is pushing away the world and rejecting
the world
and take a shower and become clean and
we become you know
more it's more we're more of a
pleasant person to be with in the world
if we're clean and
and taken care of that way and
uh so uh so this is meditative seclusion
going off on retreat
and in the old days it was going into
the forest perhaps in some place where
the
people could be alone some people might
just be in your own room by yourself
in the early morning and maybe you get
up before everyone else and you feel
have this wonderful benefit of seclusion
just
nothing else to think about and be
involved in just here
practicing and um and then it's easier
to get absorbed it's easier easier to an
integration that wholeness and just the
satisfaction the contentment of being
this way of real and then settling in
and being
and then we become more and more
secluded and
and the meditative seclusion happens
when
we stop being so concerned
with the past and the future and the
thoughts don't take us spinning
out in other places and other times and
and we're secluded from those
um uh external thoughts thoughts that
kind of spin us away
and if we are thinking it's thoughts
that keep us here and connected and
involved as we get more absorbed in
meditation more connected and involved
in it and
you know really sink into it and then
um there's sensory seclusion that
happens
that uh sometimes we don't really
involved in hearing so much
or smelling or seeing or
even even some of the sensing of the
body
precedes and disappears sometimes people
the body becomes very
transparent or light or seems to have no
edges to the body or even the whole body
seems to disappear
because we're not we're not really
giving attention
to um the senses you know the six the
five
senses of of uh hearing seeing touching
um smelling tasting
and um and so those all we see
we still have the capacity to hear and
taste and do all these things
but they recede from where our attention
is we're
absorbed in what we're involved in and
just like we would perhaps reading a
really good book
and you don't hear people talking
anymore you don't notice the sounds
outside the house because you're so
absorbed in the in the book
there's a sensory seclusion and that
sensory seclusion
because there's absorption going on it's
uh it you know it feels really good it's
like
we're being pulled in we're being
absorbed we're being delighted we're
being enjoying we're really
the attention really is getting centered
in here
um because it's starting to get
concentrated and very present
as it does so and the mind becomes
quieter and stiller
one of the functions of this is for us
to become more sensitive to clinging
to grasping to how the mind gets
attached how the mind contracts
and um and uh and the more
still more absorbed more peaceful we can
become
the more sensitive we become to the
slightest movements of
contraction of clinging of resistance
that goes on
in the mind in the heart and so then we
have the opportunity then to let go of
that
or bring our attention to that and have
it let go of itself
and and uh and then over time
there becomes a seclusion from the
things we cling to
one of the important steps for this
process of seclusion
is to be secluded from to be separated
from not involved in anymore
with the five hindrances of of sensual
desire
ill will sloth interpret restlessness
and regrets and doubt because we're so
absorbed so connected so involved with
what we're doing with meditation like
really absorb
kind of dipping deep into the into the
world the ocean of breathing that um
that we're not you know we're not get
pulled into those it can be part of this
contentment and satisfaction of
meditation
is not to be involved anymore with the
hindrances
so we're secluded from them we're
separated from them as the ancient
language
and and that's temporary so
in deep meditation that that can those
fall away
but then they come back when we come out
of meditation their mind is no longer
concentrated
and maybe they come back a little bit
weaker than they were before
but sooner or later they'll come back
and then the ultimate seclusion
is their separation is when we become
more
permanently separated from some of our
clinging and attachment
and that more permanent separation from
attachment
is um is you know called liberation
and so um
so this somali practice is meant to
support that process of liberation
um and so it's not just getting absorbed
and feeling the healthiness
the goodness the wholesomeness the
satisfaction the deep contentment of
just being absorbed in the breathing
flowing with the breath but it's
preparing the mind
so the mind is softer more
workable more able to let go more
more
malleable in a sense so that the ways
it's contracted
has a room to breathe it's a room to let
go and open up
and we start feeling some of the
seclusions
some of these seclusions which partake
of or
or have qualities of liberation in them
for example being temporarily liberated
from the hindrances
and so that brings us to the 12th step
of these 16 steps of breathing
so the 11th one is breathing in
one concentrates the mind one unifies
the mind one
steady is the mind breathing out one
unifies the mind
steadies the mind composes the mind
concentrates the mind whatever that word
is translated as
the samadhi word and then
the 12th step is one liberates the mind
breathing in one liberates the mind
breathing out when liberates the mind
and and now we're starting to get into
the territory of the real purpose of
buddhist meditation
this area of liberation and we'll pick
up that
continue with that tomorrow and in the
meantime
you might look for how you can lovingly
delightfully be absorbed in what you do
during the day
wash dishes be absorbed and just do that
in a way just turn yourself over fully
to the enjoyment of that without
letting the mind take you away and maybe
there's a lot of activities
throughout the day that you can do if
you eat alone for example
absorbed in just the eating and
learning to kind of appreciate or
develop that capacity
to give ourselves over fully to what
we're doing when we're doing it
so that there's qualities of absorption
like a good
you know involved in playing music in a
nice way
they supports us to learn how to do that
meditation
so you might want to play around with
that during the day
today next 24 hours
so thank you very much and
and i look forward to our time tomorrow
thank you