hello again hello dear sangha makes me happy to see you all
and uh to practice together and for the sangha to be assembled
here on zoom on youtube and [Music]
actually if you wanted to to see to put zoom for those who are on zoom to
use gallery view to see each other to get a sense of the sangha here assembled it's quite sweet the sangha from all
over the world all over the country and the world so it's just heartwarming to sit and
practice with with friends so
so so for the practice today
um i'd like to invite us
i'd like to invite us um
to practice so in the past few sessions i think maybe
last week one of the sessions that one theme that i invited us to work
with was listening listening with our hearts listening with our hearts
and the sense of opening and some of you shared that that was like open awareness practice but with
the sense of warmth of the sense of care settling into our bodies
settling into our awareness the sense of warmth and care
and and also i remember at the end with the
reflections some sangha members who have tinnitus for some it became better easier to work
with the tendons since it was all about listening but not listening with the ears listening with the heart but their
tinnitus for some it got better and some for some it became more prominent
so i wanted to lean into that a little more actually and lean into that and
whether you have tinnitus tinnitus also pronounced and those who don't know
what that is that's a it's ringing in the ears that can happen for a period of time or
for a long time and the sense of hearing
a sound that is not there and yet and yet what i want to also invite us to
consider is something else that many practitioners or some practitioners
work with which is called the nada sound the nada sound so the
nada sound i think it's arjun suchita if i remember correctly yes ajahn suchita who is a
well practiced uh well-respected monk in the
uh ajahn chah forest tradition and
for an object of awareness you know we can use the breath the breath in breath
out breath in breath out breath as as a stabilizer as an anchor as a
support or we can use the sensations in the body
we can there's also so many different objects the visude maga
which is this book called the path of purification it's about a thousand page
meditation instruction from um from 500 years after the buddha's death
um so it's an ancient two thousand year old roughly i think two thousand roughly
maybe i'm getting their years old mixed up it's a 1500 2 000 year old
[Music] manual lists a lot of different
ways for our mind to get still for objects for objects to uh of them
various objects to bring our awareness to so
not a sound what is not a sound not a sound is the sound of silence
it's listening to silence it's the sound of silence so listening to the sound of silence and
when you listen to the sound of silence actually after a while you can hear it's almost
like you can hear a buzzing it's like an echo that is easily available to those who have tinnitus
tinnitus and for those who don't have that stimulus that sound readily available if
you really listen to silence you start to hear a sound you start to hear the
sound that's always present and actually that sound can be a very
comforting depending on how we see it how we relate to it it can seem like oh
this sound that helps that's pervasive that's everywhere and can support the mind to get very
still very open very quiet this this 360 degree soundscape is not a
sound this sound of silence which again recall it's we're saying
calling it the sound of silence but after a while you can hear it so in some ways it's actually it's tinnitus it's
tinnitus but when you really lower the threshold of hearing of listening and you listen very
very intently so
so why may this be helpful why am i bringing
bringing this in both to support those members in the sangha who
do have tinnitus and work with tinnitus and also for those who don't
it to open our hearts our minds to this other object of
um of concentration of the mind settling with appreciation
and it can shift one's perspective if one has tinnitus in this way perhaps for
some to open up to it as as a pervasive object
of sound that's present and non-threatening the same way that the sound of silence
is actually always present to share with you that for a period of
my practice i actually worked with sound of silence as my object of concentration
and it was lovely it was just lovely i could just relax it was like surround sound i
could relax into this sound this ambient sound that was
always present was always present and felt calming felt soothing felt as
if i was tuning into this ever-present sound
that's always there that i didn't notice before which again i can only imagine
not having had tinnitus again inviting inviting a shift in perspective that
might be helpful for working with tinnitus for those who have it and again if there is resistance
here it's okay to notice if there is resistance well not a sound is different well
is it maybe not so so inviting if we can inviting some
exploration for all of us with this with not a sound
with the sound of silence hearing this reverberation the sound that is ever
present ever-present and can help us relax settle
open our hearts to all the sounds in the universe in all the sounds in our
life present and unpresent that we don't always hear it's all like listening to
the cries of the world and compassion we open our heart to the
cries of the world so listening to not a sound is a symbolism
is a symbolic way to listen to to open up to the cries of
the world the ten thousand joys and ten thousand sorrows of the world
to open up to listen with our hearts to the sounds we usually do not hear
to this to make our hearing with our hearts again when i say hearing the
hearing with our of our hearts so attuned
so sensitive that we can hear
the sounds we usually don't hear the cries of the world but both internally
and externally so that's how i would like to relate the nada sound to our
practice of meta and compassion okay that is the invitation tonight and again
working with however it works for you you're always welcome to be your inner
dharma coach your own inner dharma coach and changing the invitations so that
they work for you so that they work for you okay
all right i've spoken a lot tonight to set up the frame it's a bit of a
different frame than usual so let us begin let us begin our
practice together so let's land
let's land in our bodies first and foremost become embodied
ah letting go of all the words letting go
of everything that has come before and tuning in
tuning inward to this body
what does this body need in this moment how can i take care of this body in this
moment do i need to sit up straighter
to give myself more energy to perk up
i need to relax and soften
the muscles
landing landing in the body
let us start as always with the breath and the body first to get embodied
feeling our bottom on the cushion [Music]
our feet on the floor contact points
our hands on our lap are touching each other
the weight of our body the whole weight of our body
ah the out breath relaxing
ah letting go of the weight of our forehead
our head our eyes our jaw
the chin the neck hands the arms
the torso our bottom [Music]
ah with the next out breath letting go of the weight of the legs
the entire body
bringing the awareness internally letting the awareness be in the belly
now receiving the movement of the breath
and the abdomen
if thoughts arise
you notice you're resting now in a thought awareness it's no longer with the breath it's okay
this is what minds do smilingly smile
at this thought memory plan
thank you thank you but not now please come back later
whining inviting awareness to rest to receive the breath of the abdomen
calming soothing
one breath at a time
so calming and soothing just to be with the breath opening opening the awareness
with ease with receptivity just this in-breath
the entirety of the in-breath and the entirety of the opera
now let yourself receive the breath
with the heart center and the heart center middle of the chest
as if the breath is coming in coming out from the proverbial heart center center
of emotions in the chest hello breath hello dear breath
life-giving breath and see if there can be a sense of
appreciation of the sense of awareness of each breath
and now imagine that the breath
is filling your heart
as if your heart is the area that the breath is filling
coming into and exiting is larger
within you and all around you
circular orb
don't try too hard don't push it let it just be kind of oh
easy it's just here
surrounding air surrounding me inside me outside me entering the heart
let it be a light imagination not too hard don't push it
one that doesn't bring strain but makes your
heart relax your mind relax soften feel supported
safety all around
breath coming in on its own exiting on its own
it's not much for us to do
and to just hold witness with our hearts
easeful peaceful easy
as you land relax more fully into your body into your sit bones
open up your heart not your ears in your head no
open your heart to all the sounds
again it's not effortful listening and if you're listening with your ears straining let it go
you're landing relaxedly as if loving all the sounds
the soundscape of being human in this moment
listening with your heart maybe even if you notice you're listening with your ears put your hand your heart center in the
middle of your chest listening with your heart
listening with your body resonating with your whole body
sounds internally externally it's all okay
all the sounds inviting your heart also to open
up to lovingly listen to
the not a sound the sound of silence
which at some point might present itself as a buzzing or hissing
or not each person's experience is different
don't try too hard just be open to all the sounds with your heart
no sound is a problem
no noise is a problem just what is in this moment
and this being human
no sound is a problem
sounds arising staying for a while maybe passing
silence between the sounds around
the sounds
notice if there is joy arising
listening sounds
mind is settling for ambient sounds the sound of the breath
the sound of silence vibrations
within and without
treat each new sound that arises as a mindfulness bell to bring you back
to the present in case you were lost in thought
every sound every noise and mindfulness spell
i'd like to invite you to lean in more
to heartful listening as if you're listening to the most beautiful
music your favorite music
the heart can soar
with the amazing with fascinating
notes sound silence
reverberations
delightfully delicious joyful
notes and silence
leaning more into the heart listening to all the sounds
as if ten thousand joys and ten thousand sorrows
ours that of the world
listening with our heart
one last invitation what if every sound you hear
every noise which we take for granted
is really an expression
of the divine
of beauty and grace
the music the mysterious music of life
may we all hear with our hearts
thank you for your practice everyone
listening with our hearts a different way of approaching this practice
sounds sounds sound of silence
sounds internally externally but not a sound
sounds is an expression of grace beauty divinity of being human
all that we take for granted
so i'd love to hear anything you'd like to share
but you noticed what came up for you what insights might have arisen
like to share oh mark says angel singing
thank you mark beautiful
that's lovely actually i have to say that's a feeling that came up for me also as i
was leading this yeah friend and see your hand please
well i can't say there were angels singing uh that's that's something i'll
like to aspire to but certainly um to the degree to which i understood the
direction and i'm not really sure i do i'm not i'm not quite sure
i could find the register right where my heart is to open up
but in any case whatever was listening um
certainly neutralize the the irritating quality of my tinnitus
uh and then as a comparison outside the door somebody had their
the horn to their car was was blaring rhythmically yeah which was actually
much more annoying than what was in my head
so thank you and i really i really appreciate again you you bringing our direction to this
again i really i really feel your generosity and do that i think
thank you fred thank you so much for sharing your practice and and uh i and i'm touched i'm delighted
i'm absolutely delighted to hear your practice report um
that is the direction that that is my hope that with a shift in perspective as you were
experiencing that it didn't seem that annoying quote-unquote this
tinnitus that's always present that you shared a few weeks ago it's really a lot of suffering and pain and it is
difficult and it just tends to be very hard so thank you for that gift of your
practice that you're sharing with others because also many others both in this sangha and
listening to this audio later your practice can be inspiring for them with the way you're working with your
tinnitus thank you
deborah says i noticed it felt very intimate and i felt safe with your guidance ah this feeling of intimacy
lovely marie christine says felt it deep into my concentration beautiful yes it does
that this practice doesn't it a sense of settling jerry says calmness and peace arose in
the context of lethal fear ah
wow beautiful sense of fear lethal fear being
met with calmness and peace that's profound jerry thank you
thanks for bringing that in thank you while it says
i like the invitation there is nothing wrong with what i'm hearing
it helped me notice my aversion to many sounds and showed how my aversion
closes my heart over and over again thank you violet beautiful
realization inside reflection
profound i'll share something from my own practice tonight besides what
the sound of angels that set seemed to be coming up as mark said
another one was um the ambient sounds the sound of a
motorcycle speeding outside and horns and
washing machine or whatever the sounds the sounds are they all actually they start to sound
delightful as i was inviting you to perhaps see if
it's possible to see them for them to to arise as a
sound of divinity i'm alive isn't it amazing there is this there's sound
there's these way sounds there's these waves and my ear can hear them and make
sense of it which is all this amazement this sense of wow
the sense of amazement [Music] in the midst of the settling in the
concentration which also mark christine talked about so
jia says i hope i'm saying your name right when i learned when i leaned into my heart
in listening when i leaned into my heart in listening i noticed
uh i had a smile at the corners of my mouth oh that is so lovely that is so
happy making it's so sweet when i lean into my heart and listening i noticed i had a smile
at the corners of my mouth that is so lovely oh that is so lovely yeah
a sense of joy beautiful so dear ones with this practice with
this practice like to invite us now especially as
for those of you who have some trepidation sometimes with
with being in small groups um what if tonight you stretched
yourself again if you have to go if you um have a meeting etc or something you have
to go it's perfectly fine no judgment and yet if it's just that trepidation of other human beings what if
what if you listen to them with your heart with your heart open as if it's the sound of angels and if you listen to
yourself as if it's a an angel singing and say as little or as much as you want
or just listen to sit together in silence sit together in silence that's
okay too so the invitation is we start with 15 seconds of silence
in um the breakout group the breakout room and then sharing as little or as much as
you like with each other about your practice so um
i'm making the rooms now here we go
they are open take care of yourselves take care of each other
okay welcome back everyone so we have a couple of minutes left
anybody likes to share any reflections that came up from uh the group or before your
practice please don't be shy especially if you haven't shared
reflections for a while for the benefit of the sangha questions comments
complaints it's all welcome uh hugh are you trying to raise your
hand is that what that is it was a thumbs up
i was trying to raise my hand i said all right that worked well i kind of saw
you but anyway so please oops
lost you again here okay wait here you can unmute yourself
you want to share there you go well thank you nikki for i had a lovely
uh meditation i uh
i missed you know i was a little bit late getting here and i missed the first three or four minutes
so but uh um jamie told me that you had
asked us to imagine ourselves in a place that's
perfectly silenced with absolutely quiet and to tune in to what sound we could
hear there there and [Music] um when jamie said that i remember that
like years ago i i wondered about that so i i rented a sensory deprivation chamber
to find a space that was perfectly silent to see you know
what i could hear and in there in the dark floating in warm water
i could only hear i could hear two sounds i could hear the sound of my heart beating
and i could hear a kind of very faint high humming sound
that i interpreted or i imagined it to be the
sound of my central nervous system working yeah yeah so
since then i have developed tinnitus like other members of the same yeah and the tinnitus sound is not at all like
the sound i'm talking about it's it's a different thing yeah right
right yeah yeah i appreciate you sharing that yeah so so i um
might be you might find it of interest later when this becomes available i mean in a
little bit i'll upload it into audiodharma to go back and listen to the first few minutes and
uh and it's in some ways the the it's not a
sound the sound of silence could be the one that you hear when there's absolutely no other sound and
it's completely quiet but not necessarily not necessarily so that wasn't
it it's one version of the invitation perhaps one could hear that i said but not that's not exactly the invitation
it's a little different so yes what you hear in the sensory deprivation could be one version of that but not a sound
actually after you start to hear it it's it's kind of a vibration it's everywhere
it's it's not just what you hear in the sensory deprivation tank or when there's absolutely no other sound so it's it's a
little different so i just want to invite that curiosity into the another
layer of nuance i'm trying to invite here thank you thank you great thank you hugh thank you so much
and also thank you to jamie to give you a version of that to tune into
[Laughter] that's great so thank you all thank you so much for
your practice for your heart for listening with your heart
to yourselves to each other to the world may all beings be well may all beings be
free including ourselves [Music]
thank you