so a warm welcome to you or a cool welcome if
if that would be welcome if it's summer and something something cool would be refreshing so a
refreshing welcome to you warm cool whatever your heart needs in this moment your body needs in this
moment um lovely to be with you from around the world
in this moment in time and to practice together so uh we've been going through the
brahmaviharas one by one we went through metta and now we're going through karuna compassion
and we're lingering with self-compassion for a few sessions so tonight we
all do self-compassion uh in a different way than we've done the past couple sessions
because you can never have enough self-compassion it's it's really the salve it's the
um support in in many ways it's the support for
many of the other practices because when we fill our own cups with
care with meta with compassion self-compassion self-meta then we can be more available for the
world and there is less neediness love me love me take care of me take care of me we can take care of
our own heart and the sense of resilience can also build so
so self-compassion
um so one thing that sometimes comes up when we try to practice self-compassion
is this voice that says oh if you're too
compassionate if you're compassionate to yourself then you won't get anything done
you just become a couch potato so you have to be hard on yourself
to get yourself accomplishing things that you need to accomplish in life
and that's unfortunately not the voice of wisdom
it's more the voice of fear and it's very common it's very common
plenty of work and research has been done on this and it's very common having
taught having practiced it myself self-compassion practices and also having taught it to many people
it often comes up there's a sense of suspicion of self-compassion as weakening it will
make me too weak in so many ways and this is one story um so
i invite you to distinguish between
when something is challenging and there is suffering for
us to hold ourselves with care for the suffering that is happening for for the suffering
that's arising for us in our heart emotionally in our bodies etc
as a way to support and empower us to be in our power
to really be ah a sense of when i actually say it i want to sit up
straighter because i'm holding myself in compassion in my own care there's a sense of
empowerment of care and love and this feeling that oh sweetie this
hurts and it's okay it's okay and an empowerment to actually
take on things that are more challenging instead of if i was beating myself
up say i'm hurting say um something has been challenging let's say
um i didn't get what i wanted to get done done today and now i'm beating myself up oh you're no good you're you're a loser
you never um complete your deadlines ouch ouch ouch
that's that feels very belittling it feels i i'm feeling even more hurt now i want
to go and crawl under the covers and not talk to anyone and so it's it it diminishes me it it
makes me even more powerless whereas a sense of oh okay i messed up
oh that feels really bad okay sweetie i realize various things that were going on and
also yeah maybe you didn't do your best i still love you i still love you i still care for you
and yes maybe you didn't have to watch netflix for two
hours maybe that was not a good maybe we should just not do that yeah you're right
okay but it's okay i still care for you and okay let's try to do better so
there's a different kind of a narrative there's a different kind of an attitude that self-compassion can bring in
and i bring this up because it it has come up before
um both here and and whenever i teach it of course it this this comes up
as um does this um self-compassion make me
a couch potato so i invite you to experiment with the with these different narratives and
see how actually it's not about um self-compassion is not about lying on
the sofa and eating bonbons it's not about cutting yourself complete slack
in every matter it's about caring for yourself and taking more responsibility
in many ways so all right so let's get started without
further ado let's practice self-compassion in a different way tonight
so i'd like to invite you to get into your meditation posture as always we start by the breath with
the breath and the body landing and settling
landing in the body
with the breath
receiving the breath
tethering tethering the attention
tethering the awareness
with the breath with the movement of the in-breath and the out-breath in the body
the entire breath the entire body of the breath in breath
and out breath and the pauses tethering awareness
to the breath in the body
letting go of thoughts memories
conversations realizing you don't need to have them
right now giving yourself to this practice
giving your heart to this moment
inviting your attention
to be tethered to accompany the breath intimately
not leaving the breath as if your life depended on it
as if your liberation depended on it
now i'd like to invite you to bring to mind
a being that represents unconditional love for you
it could be a living being in your life someone who's passed away
a human a pet or an archetype
it could be kuan yen representation of compassion
or the buddha or jesus the being of light whatever works for
you and represents complete acceptance
and unconditional love
it could even be the sun the ocean a well-rooted tree
bring to mind this being
let yourself feel being in their presence
how their love acceptance compassion
care is boundless not conditional
in their presence you feel completely loved and accepted
there's nothing you have to do
or accomplish
or be in any particular way
their love acceptance is on
and if you start doubting yourself
don't get in your own way trust that they see
they see your goodness
they see you
they see aspects of you the beauty
the unfathomability of you the ways perhaps you can't quite grasp yourself
and who are you to get in your own way
get in the way of this being that is you and greater than you
allowing yourself to receive be held
feeling safe loved completely appreciated
and this being this compassionate loving being
imagine they know the complete story of your life
your strengths your beauty your values and your foibles
they know your struggles
and they love you
with each breath receiving this unconditional love
as you are in the presence of this compassionate being
continuing to soak up soak in unconditional love and care
i invite you to bring up something in your heart that's challenging for you
right now and if you're new to the practice maybe
not the most challenging aspect of your life right now
up
something that's challenging
it's been hard for you
as you bring it up as if you are putting it on the lap of this being
letting it be held by them with care compassion
they see you they know this hurts they know this is hard for you this is challenging
they hold the pain with you acknowledging that this is hard
and hold it with so much gentleness love and care hold you
tenderly
the steadiness the strength of their love their compassion
let it awaken your own care and compassion for yourself
the strength of your own affection warmth care
so that you are holding this challenge this pain the sorrow this difficulty
with the strength of love and care compassion for yourself
feeling the empowerment of not just a compassionate being
but your own
love and care for yourself
okay
you can lean into what aspect whichever aspect supports you most in
this practice right now
leaning into compassionate image
being held in their love and care or challenge being held by them
compassionately or leaning more into
your own compassion awakened lovingly powerfully for yourself
or divided 50 50.
feel free to experiment
for the last moments of this practice
period holding yourself with care and affection
with compassion for whatever arose or did not arise during this practice period
if the mind was busy wandering or sleepy
or if challenges came up during the practice it's okay
see if it can be held with
love instead of judgment
you've done your best
given all the causes and conditions dear you've done your best
noticing how empowering
compassion love can be
for yourself
and opening up your circle of affection and care and compassion
for all those who are practicing with you in this moment
all of us human beings with our challenges pains and sorrows
this human condition doing our best
extending further to all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere
feel safe may they be free from harm
may they be free from sorrow challenges and difficulties may they all have peace
and these with any challenges difficulties
they are facing
[Music]
thank you thank you all for your practice
so i'd love to invite you if you like to
share any reflections or questions comments complaints it's
all okay you can type it in chat if you wish or raise your hand and you can raise
your hand by going to reactions or going to participants depending on
the version that you have and especially if you
haven't shared for a while genie i see your physical hand up
and if you could raise your zoom hand then i could actually let's see here okay you can unmute
yourself there you go ginny okay thank you very much nikki sure alex
lovely i found that um to my kind of delighted surprise that i
myself could give me the compassion that you know i was at the beginning i
searched you know for different beings faces people i've known and
but then it came down to me and that was strong that was very strong
and i was delightfully surprised so thank you for helping me find that
yay yay i'm cheering for you genie yay
what a delight what did they like to find that within oh that delight beautiful
what you just shared and why is we have a line of of poem
by hafez in farsi it's roughly translated to the
um do we we often beg strangers whereas we actually
we we often beg strangers whereas we have this um this gem the the gem
this this whole all these gems within our own hearts
so instead so looking outside looking inside it's
already here that gem of compassion and love it's already here
beautiful thank you for sharing genie lovely yeah um
reflection from one person who says nikki this was transformational for me i
felt i was relaxing in a healing way that i have not experienced before
thank you you are very welcome i'm cheering you on also dear one dear practitioner
and by the way if you send um reflections to me directly i won't say your name but if you
send in to everyone then i'll say in your name out loud this is what i'm starting to do emily says i found saying this is hard
to myself instead of the usual critical and self-judging thoughts has been
really helpful i've taken on mickey's challenge from last week yay emily that's great that makes me very
happy yay that's awesome i'm i'm so glad you're finding it supportive
um and and really helpful it's fantastic it brings me so much joy and delight thank you
and violet says i tried to give compassion to myself for a small problem being behind and
grading but i found it extremely challenging almost like the
smaller the challenge the easier it is to invalidate myself oh interesting that's a very interesting
observation um so is it okay if i ask you what what was the challenging aspect of it
and you're welcome to unmute yourself if you wish what yeah
um it's like oh it would have been so easy for you to
grade this morning instead of going on facebook it's just like so easy for me to like try and
correct what i did instead of like accept what i did [Music]
i see i see interesting so okay so so um
yeah so here's here's what i suggest working with it in this way because in
some ways small big you know um this is a standard maybe for
something else too so so here's what i would suggest there is pain right now right there is a pain of oh i'm behind
in grading this this hurts right so for a moment i'm going to suggest
separating it from judging yourself in the morning
and just feel like oh this is this this is painful being behind is painful so can you for a
moment in your mind to separate these two for a moment
yes i see you're nodding yes okay so and can there and we'll get to the taking
responsibility in a moment but is it okay to say oh this is really painful right now ouch
sweetie ouch this this hurts this is and for a moment yeah to keep it
separated for a moment like oh this ah sweetie this is hard this is oh
this is painful i don't like this situation this is ouch it's interesting
i have so much aversion to feeling that i would rather beat myself up over not grading than actually feel that hurt
oh interesting okay so there's something there i invite
you to to feel into have a question mark
why is that because feeling that hurt and having compassion to that for that then the next step would be to
actually take responsibility okay well that wasn't very wise and instead of beating yourself up so
so i'm going to leave this as a an inquiry to see why is it so difficult to let
yourself feel and and be and and hold that with care with kindness
is that okay thank you thank you for bringing this up powerful
yeah so okay dear ones let's see anything else here
um okay so let's wait um more reflections
well after we come back from groups attend to more but so here's the invitation before you sign off if you
have to to go it's perfectly fine but if you're signing off out of fear of not interacting with
other human beings believe me they're really really nice this sangha is really really nice
so and challenge yourself extend extend your um limits a little bit
if it scares you stay and see it's not that it's it's what scares us what's
difficult to be with sometimes that can actually be a gift of grace if
we stay with it if we touch into it so the invitation for the small groups
is start again with 30 seconds of silent
meta silent compassion for each other just silently as if you are each other's
compassionate being giving and knowing that you're also receiving others or giving it to you
giving and receiving then you're welcome to share if you wish as much or as
little as you want supporting each other which i know naturally comes up in these groups so
so with that i'm going to create the breakout rooms and
hope that you can stay and practice together um okay here we go opening the rooms now
welcome back welcome back and we have a couple of minutes
left [Music] for any reflections you may like to
share from the group so the or the practice and um and one
reflection also i wanted to share before we went in to groups uh
then typed the uh let's see where is it the um which yeah the part of self will
be rates the part of self who comforts which one of them actually wants you to
succeed rhetorical inspired by the book there is nothing wrong with you by jerry huber i
i love that question uh which part of you um actually which one of them wants you
to succeed the part this is the part of you that berates or the part of you that comforts
and what brings up for me is you know if you have this boss who berates you this manager will just be
raped every time you make the smallest mistake berates you another boss that
understands but really expects is kind but expects the best of you
you'll probably be um you'll you'll be burnt out by the sec by the
first boss you'll be in living in fear of being let go of being fired any moment and
you'll have a nervous breakdown probably but the second boss you might do you might you may want to
actually work for them and do your best anyway some reflections on that thanks for
sharing that ben so your turn please
what's up
thank you for the reflections that are coming the gratitudes and blessings coming in chat you will take one
verbal reflection if you haven't talk if you haven't shared for a while
yes mary please so this is my second time with you on on
happy hour and in the small group which i always find so powerful to be in small
groups with strangers um i came to this question of
the grief that i'm encountering and and
is it okay to be with the is it is it okay for the grief to be okay i don't know if i'm making any
sense but that there's so much grief how can it be okay for there to be so
much grief you know how can i be okay when there is so much grief
not just my grief but all of the grief and i i feel like that's a place where
i'm stuck yeah that it's not okay for me to be okay
yeah yeah yeah yeah thank you for bringing that in so
here's the invitation for maybe
a different way to see it is you know what one view as you were
saying is that the grief is there's so much grief not
just my grief not just your grief but so much grief in the world is it okay is is it okay to
be okay with so much grief oh it feels so overwhelming it it's just
oh you one with one wants to hang one's head and just like enough
this is just so much is it okay to even be okay with with it all is it that's what i'm hearing you say yeah so
the perspective i want so that's one perspective that
it's sorrow and suffering that's just senseless and it's not okay to be with
any sorrow and suffering because it's unjustified as unjustifiable
there's no point it's extra it's there's no point it's suffering and more
suffering and more sorrow so so i would say there
are two types of suffering and i'll come back to the word grief for a moment i'm going to use suffering there is
suffering that is just causes more suffering and sorrow and
then there is suffering that leads to the end of suffering
as aj i think beautifully said this forest master
i hope i'm attributing this correctly but so there are two different kinds of
suffering there are two different kinds of grief and what makes the difference between
the two is how we hold it it's how we see it it's how we relate to it
[Music] and i'm going to say something that's going to sound radical
and strange but i will say it nevertheless drop it in and that there is grace
and beauty and meaning
in grief
and so much more and so much more so opening up to the possibility of its
transformational power to serve one and to serve to serve everyone to
serve the world thank you mary
thank you so
so thank you all thank you for your practice thank you for being part of happy hour
sharing yourself supporting each other
may all beings everywhere be free
may all beings everywhere be happy including ourselves
thank you all