so hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour wherever in the world you are
in this moment and today being
thanksgiving day in canada as um kim just shared with us and also being
indigenous people today uh in the united states
the theme i'd like to invite us to to engage with
is um as as of course i'll introduce it in the guided meditation so
those who are new [Music] whatever you need to know will be shared with you in the guided meditation just
relax and and let let arise whatever needs to
arise so so the theme
is one of um gratitude and metta for
for ancestors for those who have come before us
you know we might have known some of our ancestors who might have known our
parents um maybe we knew our grandparents
maybe we heard of our great grandparents maybe not but these are people just like
us who walked the earth and had challenges
had hopes had dreams
and we are
this being who is us in this moment this being who is us
represents their hopes and dreams for the future
they may not have envisioned us or known us but maybe they thought
you know if we go so many generations back sense of
sending to the future the best of them the best they were able to give the best
they were able to offer um [Music] so
a theme of meta gratitude um
and with i don't want to get too heady about it because i don't want to talk too much about it
it's talking too much because might feel a little overwhelming but for us to just settle in as always into our bodies
with our breath in this moment and then i'll have some invitations and see what
comes up see what what you might get in touch with which may not have been
present before may not have been aware of before and what might bring up
a sense of connection and aliveness and brightness
spark in your heart and heart and mind so so let's explore
together let's be curious see what comes up we let's have humility
so so with that let's get started
landing landing in our bodies
hmm
arriving in this moment this being
this being who is me this being
breathes sits
walks the earth
this amazing incredible
beautiful [Music] sometimes confusing being
who am i privileged
to get to know more and more as i live and get to support the cultivation of
this being who does the best they can
continues to want to grow which is why
they're showing up here
connecting with this with this person with this being who is me
as if you're greeting yourself at your own door greeting yourself at your own door
opening the door of your heart
who's there it's me hi welcome
come in come in sit rest relax
ah you don't have to be anyone do anything
you're accepted just as the way you just the way you are in this moment
friend i don't judge you i don't expect
anything of you just come and sit rest
just rest and be friends
allowing the breath to move in the lower abdomen
to be received an awareness greeting awareness receiving the breath
spaciously
the entirety of the in-breath and the out-breath
simply aware
and if thoughts are arising if the mind is going on trips and thinking it's okay
minds do that like little puppies they get excited
it's okay come back sweet puppy come back to your mind dear awareness let's rest
ah fighting awareness to rest
the belly and the lower abdomen and greet the breath receive each breath
and you might find you will find the puppy will set off again and it's okay
don't yank the leash back lovingly lovingly
hug caress pat
pet awareness back gently
slowly
for it to rest rest with the breath
to rest and be nourished with the breath
aware of the breath in the abdomen simple
the breath also receiving
or being received by awareness and awareness also receiving not just the breath
in the abdomen but in the sit bones where
your bottom connects with the cushion
your feet connected to the earth your legs
all the contact points feet legs
bottom on the cushion your hands receiving receiving
sensations of breath and contact points
can help the mind settle just arrive
here now
awareness awareness intertwined with care with kindness
non-judgment saving the breath and the sensations of
the body to help our heart arrive
and settle before we turn our awareness to menta
just arriving and settling another couple minutes
and now i'd like to invite you if you want to continue to stay
connected to the body going to the head but let the
center of gravity be low your abdomen
your sit bones resting the body relaxing
settled if you would open your heart
someone you're descended from
a parent grandparent someone earlier
with whom you have a connection to you appreciate
you're grateful for you feel their care their love
something about them it may not be that their entirety
was loving or lovable but just one aspect might be their entirety of their being was loving and lovable
and maybe just one aspect that you really appreciate
you connect to bring this being this person to your mind's eye to your heart
inviting them hello
if other people want to come in bow to them and say a little while
one person at a time just inviting this one person first
letting yourself open to sensing them feeling them
they might be alive or passed away the arc of their life
they felt sense of this being
their felt sense may be an image of them how they talk to their mannerisms
how they made you feel just a sense using whatever senses are most available
to you
for some maybe imagining
and embrace a hug or maybe if you're very little sitting on their lap
whatever really conjures up for you felt sense of this being this person
and if other person's relatives ancestors want to come in
invite them have them sit by the side for now when you really
focus on your relationship with this one person first
opening to a sense of appreciation gratitude
for their care their love their whatever gifts
gifts of time affection attention
or maybe they are passionate about something that they passed on to you
they nurtured something in you
maybe they saw you they really saw you
whatever works for you makes it how it works for you these invitations
some may work some may not make it make it yours
the heart that is open to appreciation
gratitude
giving thanks
is naturally brightened
with gladness with happiness
the mind could veer to
guilt or not having done enough etc but bring the mind back it's okay dear mind it's okay
dear puppy come back let's stay with seeing the goodness and gratitude appreciation let's intend
our mind intend our mind
to stay puppy sweet puppy stay
with seeing the good with seeing the gifts with appreciation
and notice if your heart feels open [Music] naturally open to the generosity of meta
and love and if so receiving love
and giving love loving and being loved
whether this person is alive or past
loving them through the beyonds
and notice now if other
parents ancestors want to join the circle
join this first person joint being appreciated
you feel their love
and sharing your appreciation love for them
acknowledging that sometimes our ancestors might have been complex characters just as we are
they've had their own causes and conditions they did the best they could
given their background their upbringing their circumstances
their cultural conditioning family appreciating the good
you might have been you might have acted the same way
being born into there body life and genes
appreciating the good
giving and receiving
your own time allowing more ancestors to join
maybe people you've only seen photographs of or just heard names of or maybe not even
bad
their bloods run through your veins these human beings
you are their child
thank you for having existed thank you for doing the best you could
having the offspring who became my parent my grandparent my great great
great great grandparent
we are connected in this web of humanity
the ancestors honoring appreciating
the challenges the goodness the beauty
and if it gets too much at any point just come back to the easiest
maybe just parent or parents your grandparents keep it limited it's
okay see what works for you
and experiment if you would if you would by putting a palm your heart center connecting with
yourself this being who's me this being knows me
connecting your hand to your heart
being touched with sincerity
appreciating loving especially the complicated lives that may not have been so easy
lives that may not have been so easy
calling forth the parents the ancestors
and bringing to heart bringing to mind
inviting [Music] your friends
your sangha and their ancestors
this web of humanity they're connected to you're connected to
so many cultures from around the world
western eastern indigenous
northern southern this planet earth all who have walked
this earth and walk this earth today
this earth as a living organism all its people
appreciating the complexity the beauty the challenges of being human
wishing well may all beings be well may all beings be happy may all beings
be free all beings everywhere
thank you all thank you for your practice
so
so bringing in a sense of appreciation
gratitude thanksgiving thanks
for our ancestors
allowing meta to arise from that and sense of interconnection
so many beings so many cultures just this web of humanity we're not
alone even though we might feel like an island especially during cold times we are
we're not we are not some ways they're all present with us in
us
there we are the being whom they have sent into the future here we are
so i'd love to open up for questions for comments for reflections the chat
is open if you at this point if you chat send reflections directly to me
i will only read your um reflection not your name if it's to everyone i'll read your reflection then
name you can also raise your hand when reflection comes
compassion for black americans cut off from their family histories by slavery yes thank you
for bringing that in yeah yes so much can open up in this practice
and seeing the the pain the challenge of
histories and also historical trauma and pains
of ancestors that many people carry many of us carry
thank you for bringing that in compassion
awareness love to hear more what came up for you
what what happened what was challenging what did you discover
kim says that was beautiful thank you you are so welcome [Music]
he says the complexities of my ancestors what a rich stew
yes yeah anybody wants to raise their hand and
share anything your voice bringing your voice into the container i like the connections to all of us even if we may
seem alone yes yeah so i wait a week more reflections or
maybe a hand to come up if you like to say what this was like for you so i see
one person is um clapping that's a clap so it's
uh it's not a raised hand but i think i know who that is is that you hear you want to say something
debra says i'm still processing a lot of grief over the loss of both my parents in the past five years
this brought up gratitude and tears thank you deborah yes you
just to add to the complexities of my ancestors what a rich stew and now
the complexities of this worldwide saga what do rich do
yeah yeah yeah indeed thank you
thank you and yerba says on youtube this theme was beautiful and profound for me thank you
this opened up a lot from me david says thank you nikki thank you
sangha from dave in oak harbor washington grateful for our ancestors
intending atonement and i see mark's hand is up
and dia and let's see uh mark please
before i speak diana wants to say something diana if your hand is physical
i haven't seen it my dear unless it's your your zoom hand
see i don't see too many of you because of the privacy and so
there you are i see you diana there you go i'm sorry um i i was really stuck
because i am feeling sad i don't have a whole train of ancestors i know about
my parents put them down we only saw them in distant pictures it was kind of grim and yet i remembered my mother used
to talk about an ancestor who came across the country to california in a conestoga covered wagon and she always
talked about this person didn't norris i thought what the heck that's going to be an ancestor i know
nothing about her what you're talking about their life must have been what kind of cultural conditions it must have
been so now i have an ancestor to appreciate that's great
thanks dave yeah thank you for that and i have to say also for me as i was practicing you
know there are so many of my ancestors i don't know and i just imagine oh yeah that person must have had a father and
mother i'm like hey what come in i don't even know your names welcome welcome
because of course we have lots of ancestors even if we don't know them so it's the beauty of us being here as
human beings of course we have ancestors mark please well
i used to my mother
uh i moved to the west coast and she was still on the east coast where
where i grew up and i tried to visit uh four times a year i
made it at least three anyway and and would stay for a week to visit and
about 13 years ago i went for one of these visits and you know flew in
and got there pretty late at night and rang the bell and and she met me and uh
we went into the living room man and hugged and
she just it was one of those hugs where it was she was just
pulling me inside of her and she said oh i i just love you so much
and it wasn't that she'd have never said that before but not often it was just
one of those rare rare moments of just pulling you inside
and and so we had to visit which which was fine and great and i went back
to the west coast and and two weeks later i got a call
and she had a stroking and she died and i was just so
grateful for that moment just at the end from her
and this meditation brought that all back again and i was just
just loving thank you what a gift mark and thank you for sharing that beautiful moment of love
with all of us i feel graced i feel the grace of of her love gracing all of us pulling
you in and pulling all of us in into that that love that's just so lovely yeah
beautiful thank you mark yeah and nick i see your your hand and 6 50
at this time is when we transition into small groups so keep here so we're going to come back to you after the groups is
that okay yeah great so beautiful so let us turn
and and come into bring invite each other
into a small group practice period of just six minutes with one another
and um and to um
um bring our ancestors in to into the room with us so it's going to be a very
crowded room all of us bringing our ancestors and each other's ancestors too
and just acknowledging that we all were all descended we're all descendants from
all these human beings who as one of you wrote in your note is is um
recognizing that they probably did the best they could recognizing they did the best they could so so with this i'm
opening the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other here we go
and the rooms are getting close in about 10 seconds
okay rooms are closed everyone is back welcome back everyone
so uh nick you had your hand up is it or are you is it still relevant
yes no give me thumbs up yes okay here you go
i'll do it thanks nikki i appreciate it being part of the group and and uh it was very uh sticky a little bit
uncomfortable i i knew this day would come we would talk i'd be in a meditation group and that it
would be talking about ancestors and uh my ancestors are you know i have ancestors through um you know in america
for like eight generations and they were involved in everything epic battles you
know and you know uh building fortunes and and unfortunately all the bad things
they were involved into that so my point was that i'm gonna try not to romanticize
their actions and just kind of focus on well they had a lot of strength they certainly had strength and determination
and i i'm sure i got some of that you know i could i've had my own successes but
you know um anyhow that was that was the point that i wanted to make yeah thank you so much nick thank you for bringing
that in yes absolutely not to romanticize our ancestors
we're wonderful beautiful and flawed people just like us they're a mixed bag
just like we are and they had good intentions
in in the way they saw their intentions and complicated especially with the history
and who knows maybe history will look back at and say well yep they had good intentions and they really messed up in
these ways they messed up the environment and so
so to appreciate both it's a both end it's a both and to appreciate their goodness and given what they knew they
did the best they could and yeah they were flawed in many ways and so are we so
yes and all of that all of that appreciating all of that yeah so thank you nick so important to
bring that and really appreciate you bringing that in yeah so dear ones the time has come it's
already seven or minute past seven so thank you for engaging with this interesting challenging opening practice
to see our interconnectedness and all in all these ways thank you for showing up
and cultivating your heart and and awareness and in
unfathomable way may you be well me all beings everywhere
be well safe and happy
thank you