so
we've taken a little bit of a pause of
moving through the next steps of the
16 steps of mindfulness or breathing to
really look a little bit more deeply at
this particular way in which the mind
works
the use of imagination in the mind
and i'll talk a little bit more about
specifically the buddha's use of this
word imagination
and i've read sometimes people say that
there's no poly word for imagination
but there actually is it's a little bit
of translator's choice but i think
there's a good argument i'll talk about
it tomorrow
the words that have to do with it and
they have a lot to do with um
they also relate to this idea of
self and not self which is so important
in buddhism
for today i want to uh so this is kind
of pausing to look imagination is a
is a preparation for next week when we
start looking at
um uh the mind more carefully and
what goes on in the mind the mental
activity
but to create the right conditions for
supporting
investigation and a deeper letting go in
the mind
is part of the function of these earlier
parts of anapanasati mindfulness of
breathing
and to to the more sense of well-being
that can come in meditation
the easier it's going to be to really
work with the mind
there's a i've told the story many times
but i love the story
of when my son was in kindergarten
once a week they would play with
beeswax with a little wax and um
and uh when it was time for them to play
they would actually been sitting up on
the
shelf and it would be um usually when
the form or whatever animal they made
the week before
and they would it would be hard and
being hard
it would be brittle and the only thing
you can do with any of it would be to
break it
and a little animal legs can be broken
off easy enough for something
but what they would be instructed to do
every week would be
to put the little the piece of wax they
had
in the palm between the palms of their
two hands and just hold it there
while the teacher told the story and by
the time the story was over
the warmth of their hands had softened
the beeswax
so that the or whatever kind of wax it
was
and so that they um then they would then
they could make these beautiful little
figures animal figures or whatever it
was they made
but you had to have the warmth to soften
it so the same thing with the mind and
the heart
to in order to make it into something
beautiful to move it towards freedom
it helps to soften it and warm it up
and the the the the good feelings the
calmness the joy the happiness the
well-being
the contentment the calmness that we sit
in
um are all kind of creating the right
conditions
to begin softening the mind
so the mind can be more pliable
more flexible more malleable in the best
possible way
so that the healthy mind the healthy
functioning of the mind
can operate smoothly and easily
so on the way to do that the cultivation
of
these deeper states of well-being that
come in meditation
the the mind is actually used to do that
the mind is always being used the mind
is being used to apply the attention
uh to sustain the attention
but it's also used to um it can be used
supported by the imagination and the
buddha uses a lot of similes
and and rather than thinking about them
as being
active and intentional uses of
imagination when we sit down to meditate
it's more like we learn those similes
internalize them well enough so that
they're kind of in the background of the
mind
so the mind associates meditation with
those similes
in a kind of a natural way the similes
create kind of a positive kind of view
orientation that supports us
to be present now it's very easy
to have lots of
uh imagination which is um
not so helpful we can carry a lot of
unconscious and conscious associations
bias fears
projections onto our experience so that
it's kind of creating kind of an uh
unhealthy or unsupportive environment
for our practice
the simple imagination that i'm a lousy
meditator
i can never do this that's also kind of
an imagination it's kind of an
idea a thought that creates a certain
atmosphere
which is a little bit it's something in
extreme forms is a self-fulfilling
prophecy if we're completely preoccupied
by the idea that i cannot meditate
then you probably can't because of
because of that preoccupation
and and so there's you know there's also
fear
like there's people who uh there's fear
what's going to happen if i open my
heart in meditation if i relax and
really feel what's here
and there might be some good reasons to
have some caution
but to have chronic anxiety and then
kind of vague imaginary ideas of
why or what's going to happen um it
doesn't it's not really supportive for
the process of deepening and meditation
we have to be wise about that anxiety
and caution not not feel
not not feel bad about having it it's
there for reasons
but we want to try to work with it and
find another way of being
so when the buddha offers all these
similes
he's uh providing he's kind of seeding
in the mind uh associations and
imaginary associations which then begin
to create a different atmosphere
for what we're doing and what meditation
is about
so whether we bring up these these
imaginations
actively or we just let them sit there
in the background
both of those are supported by really
knowing these similes knowing these
imaginary
kind of scenarios
so this comes into particular play with
the deepening of concentration what's
called
genres deepening states of absorption
that really kind of really kind of
settling in and really being present
in a clear continuous way almost like
there's a state shift
so that oh now i'm here i'm present it's
clear i'm here
and the buddha doesn't give a lot of in
descriptions
kind of prose descriptions of these
states
he describes a little bit but
but to really get a feel for what the
buddha is talking about
he provides similes almost ever many of
times he talks about describes what they
are
he then follows up with a simile for
each of the four of these absorptions
and these similes if you kind of feel
your way into it and
and kind of let it kind of live
in the feeling of it or the sense of it
or almost imagine that you are the
simile in some way
then something begins to be kind of an
atmosphere
the context is being formed an
association that awakens something
inside of us
that's not the imagination but rather
the felt sense of what
the buddha is pointing to so the
imaginations for
uh these similes for deep states of
concentration where there's a lot of
well-being
um use
three of them use water as part of the
simile
and often in the kind of symbolism of
the buddha
water represents the mind and
perhaps the clarity of the mind or the
awareness itself of the mind i think
maybe awareness maybe more than the mind
and um and so we're getting a sense of
how to work with awareness or how to
relate to the awareness or how to
notice uh qualities or aspects of
awareness as we settle in into the
practice
and um so um
so there are four of these and i want to
read
the the similes for you and
maybe you could kind of let it sink in
for you and kind of
imagine that you're somehow this you can
feel this with your body or
feel it with inside
the first one begins with an assembly
that's very much with
in modern world maybe we would associate
it with making dough with flour
where you sprinkle water onto the dough
until and
and and knead the the water in until
it's the all the whole all the flour is
moist
and in the ancient world it has to do
with making a certain kind of powder
soap
powder that they had and making that
into a kind of a bald
so just as a skilled
bath person or a bath person's
apprentice
heaps bath powder in a metal basin
and sprinkling it sprinkling it
gradually with water
kneads it until the moisture wets one's
ball
of bath powder soaks its and pervades it
inside and out yet the ball itself does
not ooze
so too a practitioner makes the joy
and happiness born of seclusion
drench steep fill and pervade this very
body
so that there's no part of one's whole
body unpervaded with a joy and happiness
born of seclusion
so here there's awareness in in kind of
my kind of
description that's that's that comes
along with joy and happiness
so we're sitting in meditation there's
feelings of well-being
and then one big gently kind of needs it
massages it or or spreads it or expands
it
through the whole body so no part of the
body is not
moist with this goodness of joy
and happiness so so it
implies that there's a kind of
engagement with the process
so not just opening and allowing
well-being there but in a certain kind
of way gently lovingly
kind of maybe each time we breathe kind
of opening and
filling opening stretching letting it
kind of ooze or letting it like
spread through the body so there's a
little more active involvement
and and and this is where the mind is a
little bit more
involved in staying there stay present
be with it
work on work on the breath the
in-breaths and the out-breaths
as the mind gets stiller and quieter
there's no more needing no more work is
needed to stay present no more work
to spread anything or cultivating it
and so the next uh
level of absorption
so just as though there were a lake
whose waters welled up from below
and it has no inflow from east west
north or south and would not be
replenished from time to time by showers
of rain
so there's no streams flowing in from
any direction
into the lake from the top it's only an
upwelling of a spring from below
then that cool fount of underwater water
flowing
up in the lake would make the cool water
suffuse
fill completely fill and pervade the
lake
so there's no part of the whole lake
unpervaded
by the cool water um in this way
one suffuses and fills and completely
fills and pervades
this very body with the joy and
happiness
born of samadhi no part of the body is
unpervaded with joy and happiness born
of samadhi
the third absorption just
as in a pond of blue
or red or white lotuses some lotuses
that are born and grow in the water
thrive
immersed in the water without rising
out of it and cool water suffuses
feels completely fills and pervades
these lotuses to their tips and their
roots
so that there is no part of all these
lotuses unpervaded
by cool water
so one experiences happiness in the same
way one experiences happiness with the
body
that the noble ones describe when abides
abides with happiness
of one who is equanimous and mindful
when suffuses feels completely fills and
pervades this very body
with happiness no part of the body is
unpervaded with happiness
so the joy has stopped which is more
active and energetic and now it's just
happiness
and then the final one um
is um
just as though a person were sitting
covered from the head down with white
cloth
so that there's no part of one's whole
body enclosed
um not
enclosed by the white cloth
so once it fuses
and fills it completely fills and
pervades this very body
with mental purity mental clarity
no part of the body is unpervaded with
mental clarity
just as a so
the the idea of surrounded by a white
cloth so no part of the body is not
touched by this white cloth is the idea
that
there's no outside stimulus anymore and
there's no
clear defined body anymore it's kind of
you can't quite see it but it's there
it's it's covered and and
it's a softness to it the soft clean
cloth
that touches it everywhere so we go from
working the
working the joy through the body to
feeling the joy
uh so being a very peaceful quiet lake
with
whatever we've experienced kind of
floating in this stillness of awareness
happy awareness to um
to becoming so quiet and still
that the body begins to recede and very
peaceful safe
quiet equanimous and characterized by a
kind of mental purity mental clarity or
cleanliness that's there
so this is the closest we get to the
buddha really describing
or these met these states of
concentration
and i don't know if they mean something
for you or whether you kind of
evoke some imagination for you but if
they evoke your imagination
then these are things to kind of take in
and and
internalize a certain way some people
memorize these
descriptions and and then they're there
in the background
for the mind to kind of
perfume itself or perfume meditation
with
dissociation and associations which
might be a lot better
than some of the other ways in which
your imagination is
influencing your experience
so thank you and and
may you enjoy and may your joy and
happiness
have a chance have the opportunity
to spread and pervade and soak your
whole
body don't get so distracted
that you don't allow your well-being
happiness and joy
a real chance to really be felt and be
experienced in this body that we have
so until tomorrow thank you