hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour
hi i've missed you
and if the audios are right give me thumbs up yes fantastic you can hear me
so hi welcome so let's start as we always start by
the space warming the space with just greeting each other with friendliness
and i'll start by saying hi i'm nikki in mountain view california unseated oh
lonely land who wants to say hi hello kenneth from albuquerque miss you too oh that's nice
hello neil in new hampshire he says welcome back thank you it's nice to be
back oh who else wants to say hi you can either i'm wayne in richmond and that's very
nice to see you nikki hi wayne thank you good to see you also
hi marie christine who roo in sydney australia it's lovely to see your face
all so high oh hi dawn
from dc thank you for welcoming welcoming me back i was so sweet to be back to the
sangha after being away hi mark and swim thank you hi larry from seattle
welcomes me back as well thank you along with morgan hi marianne
from burlingame hi lydia in baltimore hello and david
says hi on youtube and ricky from new hampshire and diane
from santa cruz and johnny from san francisco first time
here oh that's great welcome johnny wonderful yay welcome to the sangha
lovely to have you beautiful and megan hi megan from south bay
hi deborah in san francisco oh i feel like the space is warmed up with
all these kind warm hellos
from different places in the country and the world
being afternoon where marie christine is in australia
so so let's let's begin let's begin
formally and uh thank you neil for sharing information about happy hour google
groups in the chat where folks can join share information with one another
resources are shared there and at this point i change the settings
so that accidental unmuting won't be possible so that we can have
some pride in the space silence of the space and and also chat will be
quiet for this period and i'll open it up again
later so oh yes and remember the preliminaries turning on recording
for audio dharma here we go okay
so hello and welcome to happier everyone
lovely to be with you so for today's practice
i've been wanting to um to touch in and reconnect with the
question that came up last time uh
about last friday last thursday last last wednesday anyway
um and fred asked a question about uh tinnitus or tinnitus
ringing in the ear and other people expressed appreciation for
that question and follow-up and also there was follow-up on in
the google groups about that question so we wanted to actually dedicate um
this this sitting this practice to um
this to the idea of something challenging arising something challenging arising
and and perhaps expand on the answer for the on the invitations i was giving that
night and to actually invite all of us to practice because whether or not
we have something physical let's say very specifically was brought up as tinnitus
ringing in the ear that can show up as very unpleasant and and as a distraction etc
but it can also be pain in the body discomfort in the body
any pain any discomfort any headache any back ache anything
but even more generally this can be anything that
we don't want to be present in our bodies uh in our mind
or in our heart in our emotional space or in our lives
anything that's that's unpleasant so so
if you don't have tinnitus or or pain in the body please consider these invitations i'm about to give
and the way to work with them specifically as we'll enter in a moment
for anything that is happening in your body in your life
that is unpleasant that you consider to be unpleasant you consider
a sense of you don't want it to be here you don't want it to be here it's unpleasant you don't want it to be here
so so all of us i trust being human beings
we have something we can relate to um in this way in our life so that can be a
general practice for everyone so so i'll say a couple of words and then
we'll practice with it more more more extendedly
but something to consider is that um when there is
pain discomfort something unpleasant there is the thing itself there is the
thing itself whatever it is the event the happening the pain the
sound etc there's the thing itself and then separate and then as we
quiet our minds as we settle as we will do in our meditation in the moment will
take time to settle you'll notice that yes there is the thing itself
and separate from the thing itself is
aversion to it actually separate from the thing itself first i want to say is the unpleasant
feeling tone there's the unpleasant feeling tone that this is unpleasant this is
unpleasant and we can recognize that to be separate when we quiet our minds but
it is separate and again separate from the thing itself
from the feeling tone number two separate from these two the
third is in is a reaction that comes up it's a
reaction that comes up which is pushing away there is i don't like this
i don't want this make it go away there's a resistance there's a pushing
away there's aversion there's this pressing of the aversion okay
so three different things the thing itself the vedana or feeling tone in politics
veda the feeling tone which in this case happens to be unpleasant but please know
that the feeling tone is separate so the same sound the same
feeling sensation actually seen from a different light at times
could have a neutral or even a pleasant feeling tone so
this is not a function of the object itself of the thing itself it's an
object it's it's a function of the way we see of the mind which is more subtle so
it's okay if you're like oh i don't get that it's okay but i do want to bring it in you don't have to force believe this
just know that the feeling tone is very flexible it's really flexible
it really amazes us when we see that and then the third that aversion the
pushing away the make it go away i don't like this which really comes up not from
the thing itself but really from the impact that the way
we perceive unpleasant habitually we're human beings we all do that but the reaction to unpleasant tends to
be make it go away aversion and it's really that aversion the
pushing away that both keeps all of this in place and also
causes the pain the suffering now as as you've all heard by now
pain is inevitable suffering is optional so if you think of the thing and the
as as the pain as the you know physical pain for example as the first object the
suffering is that pressing it's that rejection which really holds it in place okay
so so so in tonight's in practice as a part of
happier i like to invite you and i could again could be a sensation pain it could be
something in your life which is like this is unpleasant i don't like this make it go away
will notice all these parts and then the invitation is
what if there is an acceptance of the rejection because sometimes the rejection it it
gets fixed in the whole the whole nine yards this whole
uh you know all these pieces becomes a vicious cycle it gets hooked as it
becomes a dam as if you have a dam that that you know the flow of water gets
kind of gets um stopped the dam that's built up is from that
aversion from that pushing back so if we ah accept open up open up viscerally
feeling and again i'll give specific invitations but just opening yourself up to that feeling into opening into
relaxing into giving space
for this aversion
that relaxing can actually open up the latch of the dam and the water can flow
water can flow in the way that the object may still be there the
sensation the pain the whatever it is in your life the unpleasantness may or may not be
there it might still feel unpresent it may not feel as unpleasant as it once did
but this sense of suffering pain distraction that it's providing
that goes away so this thing whatever it is it can still be here it can still be
present but without taking so much energy without taking so much
ah energy to push it away it just is it's just the part of so many
other stimuli or so many other things that are happening in life so
um [Music] and as to how it relates to mental and warmth and friendliness
really the it is a way of cultivating friendliness and kindness towards ourselves to see
all these relationships and open to what arises with just a little more
receptivity kindness patience
so i have spoken plenty tonight to set up this structure
hope it's been helpful let's meditate together let's let's land
ah let's land
let's arrive let's land in our bodies
and let's just arrive take time
letting go of all the words whatever has come before this
letting go letting go letting go letting go
oh letting go some more just here
just simple
feeling this body connected to the earth
through our feet our legs our bottom on the cushion
landing relaxing into this body
to the chair
the cushion
taking refuge with each breath
and if you find thoughts and memories arise it's
okay smiling smiling at them
ah and releasing thank you come back later
i'm just giving myself wholeheartedly right now
this is practice of here being here now settling
with the simplicity of the breath
in the body in this moment
do
listen breath this out breath settling arriving
more and more receiving age
breath the sensations of it in the abdomen
sensations of the breath soothing
calming like a lullaby
tilling the soil tilling the soil calm awareness
abiding with each breath
enjoying the entirety of each breath
letting there be a kind awareness
receiving meeting each breath in the abdomen
receiving receiving each breath
in the abdomen
instead of breathing in kindness breathing out kindness and gentleness
into this body into this heart and mind
not letting the breath be work
in fact breathing has been happening all this time
so let breathing happen naturally
just as it has been
just simply bring awareness as if a smiling awareness
the belly area i know it's happening
breathing is happening on its own how nice
as if awareness was receiving a gift didn't have to work for it
you could relax relax just receive the gift of each in-breath and out-breath
smilingly
with the same appreciation we have when you receive
a gift
a cherished gift
each breath received with kind awareness
this is your whole body your whole being energetically you're sitting
in a space of kind awareness through your body
around your body you can relax into it
you're welcome to continue to sit with
kind awareness the space inside and outside
if this is what your heart needs right now
i mean if you like to try on the invitations
that will follow you are welcome also
you decide
so as you feel as you feel connected to your body
your bottom on the cushion your feet on the floor
your breath and the abdomen
through your body so you feel connected embodied this is
important as you feel embodied
staying embodied bring to your heart mind
not to your head but bring to your awareness
as you continue to breathe with
whatever is happening the sense of something
in your life in your body as discussed earlier where there is
some rejection there's pushing away there's aversion
maybe it's a pain in your body ringing in your ear
or something in your life
and let yourself feel into the contraction to this energy of pushing away not
wanting resisting hating
let yourself really know it
as if you're a scientist of your own mind heart
scientists are curious they don't judge they're just curious about phenomena
so too be curious about this not liking
i wish it weren't here make it go away feeling
where do you feel it in the body this aversion is it the tightness in
your chest and your belly somewhere else
your shoulders be curious about it and see
if there is aversion to this aversion if you don't like
this tightening this not wanting it to be here see if there are extra layers
of aversion not wanting it to be here and if so
bring gentle loving curiosity to that
and see if that's the case and if you bring curiosity
a sense of spacious open open inquiry non-judgmental
well whether that extra layer of aversion on top of what you're feeling
if if that opens up ah it feels a little more spacious
as if it says okay all right i'm just gonna release let you study
this tightness in your chest or your belly okay it's fine it can be here
it's here already okay
i'll let you study it maybe it says
this extra aversion layer of it letting go
if so smilingly bow to it ah
relax and study
feel feel is pushing away if it's still here
what if you allowed it to be here this tightness
this aversion completely this tightness
maybe it shows up in your belly your chest however it shows up physically this
aversion the sound to the pain to
something in your life you don't want it to be here what if you let it the aversion be here it's okay
give it space breathe around it
okay all right you can be here
plenty of other things that can be here it can be joy there can be ease it can be sensations on my feet
and you too you can be here too
dear not or whatever it is
there's plenty of space here in the sphere of awareness
for everything to be here
without the aversion sucking the air out of everything
doesn't have to if we don't give it primacy if we don't make it the focus just
acknowledging it's here yeah it can be here we don't try to push it away give it all
our energy
it's as if the giant what was once this scary giant
oh it becomes tiny small it's still here
but it's not so threatening anymore
just space around it breathe around it
hold it take your time
give it a lot of space not trying to push it to go away
not at all relax your body
relax your body
there's plenty of space for comfort for ease
sensations that are pleasant
awareness being so spacious like the sky
holding the body the breath and this too this can be here
this next step might take some time you can try it on tonight if you like
but maybe later in your own time and maybe you are ready to check in and see if
the original pain ringing in the ears or issue in your life if there is more ease
around that now that the aversion to it
there's more ease around
there's more ease that too this too can be here more
more easily it's not central stage anymore
and if bringing awareness directly to it brings up the unpleasantness and brings
up the aversion it's okay go back to the inversion
make a lot of space for the origin it's okay it's okay
breathe with it breathe around it relax relax your heart
relax your heart dear heart dear heart
dear heart you can hold so much to your heart
dear courageous compassionate heart
they need to go back and forth a few times or bring awareness more spaciously to
your feet to your hands ah
the space of kindness you're sitting in that can hold this all hold it up
hold all that arises and passes away
stimulus in our life and our body
whatever phenomenon it is unpleasantness that the mind
labels it as and any aversion which may come and go
this heart this body this mind is so spacious
and for the last moments of this practice holding yourself spaciously lovingly
for whatever arose or did not arrive during this practice period it's all okay
it's all okay
give it all the causes and conditions it had to be exactly as it was
or it would have been different appreciating yourself thanking yourself
offering the goodness of your practice to yourself and to all beings everywhere
may all beings be free including myself
thank you thank you for your practice
ah so
there's a lot that can come up with this practice so what we did is we started by
settling arriving feeling embodied with kind awareness
and we brought into our awareness something some phenomena in our body in our life
that's challenging and then i invited you
to notice the aversion to the unpleasantness that's associated with
this phenomena and we worked mainly with making space with for the
aversion which is this pushing is making it go away that this this dam that keeps it in
place noticing if there's a vern version on top of the version oh i don't like this
it's like i don't like this tightness in my chest that i don't like the fact that i have this thing like okay all right
can we can we bring acceptance spaciousness to that
and noticing if that allows some softening in the mind and the heart
and noticing if the phenomena itself there's more space for it to be
at times and if you notice okay if that for some
brings more um more aversion again okay going back to the vision so going back and forth and
over time really working with giving space giving a lot of space because when we just
narrow our mind to what is not working what is challenging what is difficult it feels like we bring it into our face
and that's the only thing we see there is no space to breathe at all it just sucks the air out of the room whereas oh
there's so much space oh my feet feel pleasant and this it's all okay and we realize there's so much more space for
this thing to be just as it is just as it is it becomes a practice
and over time there can be a sense of working through
layers of acceptance more and more and more and more so if radical acceptance
doesn't happen with this short meditation it's okay don't expect it it might have hallelujah great i'd love to
hear about it and and yet be patient be patient with yourself
more and more layers of acceptance will happen more and more and more and more
and more and the time at time the time might come where there's a subtle
um aversion still pushing away is there and when the question comes you can ask
yourself well am i gonna be okay if this thing this pain this situation never goes away
and at that point if the answer is yeah there's enough space that i will be okay there's okayness there is
okayness and this thing can be there that's the feels like the final layer of
acceptance and then it'll stop bothering us you can still be there i had this
experience years and years ago i'll share with you with as you know i have a chronic illness and a lot of body pain
and which i've had for years and years and i was i've been practicing
with it for a long time years ago i was practicing i felt like i had accepted yes pain i can be with pain yes
unpleasantness i see the unpleasantness and actually stopped being unpleasant after a while it can the unpleasantness
can shift to actually be neutral or even be pleasant at times which is wild that's another
uh i'll leave that to decide for a moment on a post-it note proverbial person note
but uh but the time came where i noticed that i was still practicing with the discomfort with the pain there was a
tiny tiny subtle subtle oh i wanted not to be here i wanted to
go away when i saw that there was just this complete acceptance like no we can be
here it's fine then there was complete freedom that yeah the pain can really be
here and i can be free i can have ease i can be i can have there can be
well-being even if in the conventional sense there is no
well-being so so lots and lots of layers of practice
over time be patient be patient be patient and i'd love to hear if there
any questions reflections you'd like to share yes please fred
um i just want to thank you for your kindness in in bringing this forward to the group
i understand it's something we all experience but you did it very specifically
with me reaching out to you last week and it's very generous and i very very
much appreciate it [Music]
thank you fred thank you for sharing your practice your
experience for the benefit of all beings for the benefit of sangha
thank you and thank you for letting us all support you as you are supporting others
with sharing your practice thank you
murray christine please um for me was a little bit complicated i
found in terms of the um wanting to push away the aversion that there was room that i was bringing openness
yeah and but even though i was bringing up openness to it the actual the density
or the intensity of the pain actually heightened but it wasn't i wasn't feeling aversion i was just aware that
the pain had kind of increased and i wasn't quite sure if it's because i was focusing too hard on it or
yeah thank you yeah yeah thank you mary christine so so what i'm hearing is that
by bringing your attention by bringing a aversion more into the sphere of experience it
seemed like the the pain intensified pain itself intensified and you wonder
whether it's because you're focusing on it too much because it wasn't my version that was intensifying i was quite aware of
letting go yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah interesting right um it it may
be so it's beautiful that you're aware you're aware of the letting go which is beautiful so what i would invite you to
to explore a little bit is is is your attention your awareness is it
laser sharp bring attention to the to the quality of your attention
bring awareness to the quality of your awareness is your awareness laser sharp
like okay like really paying attention to this right here now like what or is
it more diffuse and and so
which could be more spacious and helpful great thank you very christian great yeah megan please
i have a question with like a little bit of a reflection but i was curious
if you have advice on um times when the thing feels like a
threat to personal safety sort over the safety of others um
i had this experience today that was like a bit frightening and sort of left me
feeling uneasy and i just used that since it was there um and i noticed
unlike physical pain or even like other emotional pain where that spaciousness
just kind of works and um i can see it i just felt this like
vulnerability the whole time and so i actually switched over to tonglen because i couldn't
do anything else and i didn't know if that was a version coming up kind of
but when i did do the tongue one it it felt like it was the only thing that would help it to move
um so yeah yeah thank you megan and i'm gonna
as you if you need to be con stay unmuted because that what you're describing actually something that felt
threatening and unsafe for you and others it's slightly of a different
uh category than i think um the the invitation for for what a you
know in this particular practice i think what you were exploring so it sounds appropriate to more have tongue length
for that in a way so um let me feel interest you know is is this
would this tool still be appropriate for that um
i'm not yeah i think tonglen would be there right because it's here it's
yeah i'm i'm appreciating your inner wisdom to have i've decided that yeah actually
tangling feels more approved for this particular thing that feels unsafe from me and others uh
to work with and it's not just aversion to something that is
unpleasant it feels of a different category megan so yeah and you're welcome to unmute
yourself if you if you uh yeah you can do that if you want to make another comment yeah
yeah i guess i kind of i i like that you brought up the possibility that it would be in a
different category because i think it might be um yeah i'll have to keep
exploring the the thing that happened with the tongue line was i felt like there was almost like some
agency yeah in terms of it's like that fierce compassion sort of
exactly energy that i felt like needed to be there and and here's the
thing here's another clue i'm having right now it seems like this thing that happened was regarding
and some being some person yeah so tonglen the practice of
compassion especially and first compassion have to do with people whereas what i was describing is
has to do with phenomena right like something right phenomenal like pain ringing the ear something
that's happening or something in your life which is like something happening but not a person whereas what you're
working with was something happening with a person who did something that made you and feel unsafe and unsafe or
other so definitely tonglen and other practices people related practices so
yeah that's more appropriate thank you yeah thanks megan it's great
okay wow all right so um we've had so many wonderful reflections
and questions and i've talked a lot so let's quickly go into having some time
together in community and i realized i'm i'm running late tonight
for for our breakout group so let's let's turn our our attention to the
breakout group so that um can have some time to connect with one another it's so sacred so so beautiful to have time to
to share so here we go i'm going to open the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other with kindness
and here we go
so the rooms will close in about 20 seconds we'll wait for everyone to come back
before we conclude together
okay welcome back everyone everybody's back so given that we had
more reflections and questions earlier uh and it's already time so
let us formally close and dedicate the merit and i will stay a few minutes
extra tonight if anybody has questions or comments and would like to stay i can stay an extra 10 minutes so
thank you all for your practice for showing up and cultivating your heart and mind for yourself and all beings
everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music] thanks everyone take care
thank you