so welcome everyone um it's good to be with you my name is uh
matthew bransilver and um yeah happy to be back back with the
morning uh imc gill skills crew here and
uh this week will um be the same form in the morning of of sitting for
about half an hour and then some reflections for for 10 or 15 minutes
uh additionally uh there will be a couple evening sessions
that uh you're welcome to to join those will be on zoom and a day long
on uh on saturday uh two and i've i've organized the the week
around um the theme of uh sort of dharma in our interpersonal
life and so um yeah that
is really a kind of invitation to to make this this one
this one week a kind of laboratory where we explore
our um yeah the place of of these like core teachings of of the of of buddhism
silas ahmadi panya ethics mind training and wisdom
in our interpersonal life so that's the the uh the invitation
to consider this a little bit of a kind of immersive practice ground
for this week so uh
that's um that's uh that's it i'll say more about all of this
so settling into this familiarity and this freshness
the buzzing blooming aliveness of your body
we establish some sense of of groundedness
the downward pull of gravity
the settling effects of
the exhalation
the million consolations of the dhamma
we ground ourselves
and then open
the whole body as if bathed in awareness
no matter what is known
knowing is happening something in us
let's down relax us
[Music]
just giving a radical permission for the winds of feeling to blow as they blow
knowing
they won't blow anything over inside of us
and so imperfection
becomes our vehicle for peace
each moment in its own weird little way
beckons us towards peace
so we find our ground
and we renounce all our agendas around
fixing acquiring becoming
improving tweaking optimizing
we find our ground
we renounce the agenda
we let the logic of the dharma
unfold through our heart
do
so thank you it's good to uh
get to practice together
so tony kushner said
the smallest indivisible human unit is two people not
one one is a fiction from such nets of souls societies the
social world human life springs
so
sometimes when i give a talk about self-clinging the topic for today but
i give a talk on on that theme i tell a story of um visiting a local sangha
here in the bay area and um being sort of introduced in this grand
very generous way um
of uh maybe even in inflating or sort of like really celebratory bio kind of uh
introduction but on that particular night i had managed to show up this is pre-coveted i
had managed to show up to teach a meditation class with my zipper down
which i think we can all agree is the cardinal sin of mindfulness yeah
to uh not be properly dressed you know leaving the
house right this is uh this is not a sign of uh profound mindfulness right
so the juxtaposition of this kind of lovely intro and like the cardinal sin
of mindfulness something about that yeah
nobody is their bio and
we can only ever look good on paper
and i thought to share that as the framing for this week actually because
the relational world is a bit like that
our habits will not be concealed and
it's incredibly beautiful and incredibly rich the interpersonal realm
the learning and the healing it's um uh
just so much beauty is on offer and of course no one
no one escapes with their dignity fully intact right we should just give
up hope for that yeah this is a realm of of humility and
longing and ecstasy and loss and courage and
vulnerability and shame and grace and healing
yeah this is the realm we're entering into to consider
and so other people other people are are like steroids for the paramis and the
khaleesas yeah the the wholesome beautiful qualities of our
heart and our habits of suffering so the uh
emotion scientist um lisa feldman barrett says the best thing for a human nervous
system is another human and the worst thing for a human nervous system is another human
our life is is relational
sending and receiving sending pain receiving pain sending love
receiving love and of course in the beginning our our
very life depends on the care of others and that you know we we don't survive without
that care and so that that forges a deeply relational being
and the sense of belonging of relatedness that is fundamental
and if it's fundamental in the sense that if it is frustrated we suffer
yeah now as we begin this exploration i'm aware
that some of you may be feeling like you have too much contact others feeling like you have too little
and i hope this week is is relevant across the whole spectrum from those
feeling too much to those feeling lonely
um we try to get the amount the amount of contact just right but we
can never exactly dial that perfectly either
so some of meditation we do i would say only
only for itself it doesn't need to translate whatsoever it doesn't need to translate
into the next moment into the rest of our life it doesn't need to translate into the interpersonal realm
we sit and we experience the blessings of that
and that is enough yeah if it doesn't
if it doesn't function as the seed for something else that would be enough
and and some of what's developed on the cushion
uh needs to translate to we want it to translate to the rest of
our life especially our interpersonal life where
which is such a deep realm of practice yeah where where as i was saying the
what is evoked in us is so profound
and so other people other people we take this as a kind of formal realm of
practice um other people help us see how we're not
free where we have maybe overestimated our freedom
and other people help us through their love become more
free and this is the zone i feel where we investigate
where our insight has stabilized and where it has not stabilized
right we have an insight and we grow in our ease our freedom our care
uh we grow in the paramis but
then sometimes we recognize oh that's not actually stable maybe we know maybe
we've seen a thousand times a million times that greed and hatred are dead
ends but then [Music] all the sudden
they seem kind of appetizing yeah where has our insights stabilized and
where hasn't it you know sometimes
i entertain this um delusion about how
buttoned up my whole inner life is yeah
and then disrupting that is
a moment of seeing you know seeing just how glued together that delusion is
or a dream that seems too potent to be meaningless
or a reaction that takes me by surprise
and i want to have and i want to encourage all of us to have a measure of
fidelity to those realizations to the the ways in which the
the autobiography is punctured by moments
many of which are inter personal and when i teach you know i try
never to forget my freedom nor to forget my suffering
to have fidelity to all of that
so the interpersonal realm is uh is a realm of seeing what has stabilized
in us and what hasn't what has been realized
this is eve uh eucedric
i i still hadn't realized it that it hadn't succeeded in becoming
real to me real in the same register as a living room is real
that's the sense in which i want to discuss reality today she writes
reality not as what's true but as what's realized what is or has become
real where is the gap between knowing
something and realizing it taking it as real to practice buddhism after all is to
spend all the time you can in the attempt to realize a set of understandings most of whose
propositional contents are familiar to you from the beginning of your practice
the intensiveness of different buddhist traditions testifies to the centrality
of the project of realization to the sense of how normal it is
for realization to lag behind knowledge by months
or eons
dharma is not about knowledge but uh realization
to make these teachings real real to your heart
real such that you feel the freedom of it real such that they are
they are realized they are stabilized and the interpersonal realm is a
very potent field for the exploration
of what has been realized and so we take this you know
and the gimmick of just a week intensive right on the interpersonal life but we take
this i invite you in to take this like as a
um a serious uh inquiry yeah a loving inquiry
where okay i make this a realm of practice for this week
i really want to actually investigate
and so we approach the the whole question of
our interpersonal life the the maybe the the deep strong relationships
that we have the you know the casual encounters that we have we approach all
of it with respect and wonder and freshness
a respect for what um gets evoked in us
and respect for what is evoked in others
a forgiveness yeah a forgiveness for
all the ways this [Music] can
impact the heart mind yeah for our needs and our strength and
our confusion and all of it you know may be blessed with a quality
of understanding and forgiveness and
that sense of not being moralistic about our inner life not being moralistic
about our interpersonal life that frees us up to investigate yeah to
look more deeply with more fidelity
and so what happens to your mind in the interpersonal realm
what gets soothed what gets activated
notice all of that with care how do you how do you feel about
yourself when you're with others what ideas become more dominant what begins
to recede in your mind yeah what who do you take yourself to be
in the interpersonal realm does the dharma feel more
or less alive when you're with others versus when alone
please consider all of this in the next 23
hours and 15 minutes and we'll
come on back tomorrow morning yeah
so uh yeah may you have a lovely day and uh full of of exploration
if that um is uh intriguing to you and uh we'll gather back tomorrow and
then tomorrow night i'll you know give post information on an evening session tomorrow night
at seven o'clock pacific we'll sit and have some see how the day went yeah
um so uh thank you uh thank you all yeah
and i wish you uh wish you well i'll check