good morning
again
and for those of you on youtube who
weren't there at 6 45 this morning i'm
diana clark
and gil will be back tomorrow at seven
california time he's spending some time
with his family this morning
so to say a few words about
anapanasati practice mindfulness of
breathing
that gil has been doing on these
mornings
and as many of you know there are 16
steps and gil has been through the first
half the first eight and there's a
number of ways in which we might
understand all these
steps and the organization of them
one way is that this is a progression of
getting to know one aspect of our
experience
the body the mind
and then after becoming familiar with
it and being with it then there's some
letting go some releasing of that aspect
of experience
when the time is right it doesn't have
to be
in a hurry we just take our time
allowing the experience perhaps to
melt or soften
as best we can
so we started with noticing the physical
aspect of our experience
breathing and this breathing accompanies
us
through all the other explorations
just in the same way that when we're on
a pilgrimage we just keep walking
one step after another one breath
after another
and after breathing then there's
expanding to include the whole body
the bodily sensations of course
breath is occurring within a body
so to expand the awareness to include
the body
and in this we also include any sense of
contentment
any sense of okayness any pleasure
pleasant sensations
associated with this bodily experience
and allowing those to be a support
as we continue on our pilgrimage so to
speak
i mean then we turn towards the mental
aspect of our experience
including the physical sensations that
are associated with
thinking or whatever mental activity we
might be having
sometimes that's really subtle the
physical aspect of the
mental experience so without getting
tangled up and trying to
figure it out maybe just kind of being
with the experience without being
identified or
lost in the experience in some ways it's
a little bit of a pulling back
from our thinking and of course
noticing how our judging our evaluation
of our experiences yet one more mental
activity
we might feel feel how that feels
the judging the pushing the pulling
wanting not wanting this is desirable
not desirable
so this to help support this
experiencing mental activities it can be
a stepping
back of some sort so kind of a pulling
back a little bit
and knowing what is taking place rather
than being fully
immersed into it and
mental activity deserves our attention
sometimes we might have the idea that we
just have to get rid of it
but it deserves our attention because
when
unattended it often is running our lives
without
our even knowing it
so then there can be after becoming
familiar
with mental activity there can be a
calming a
softening or relaxing
of that mental activity
and notice that i'm not saying we have
to eliminate eradicate
exterminate something like this
the mental activity we're just allowing
it to
quiet
maybe i'll say a few words about what
can be some supports for this
one is that the earlier steps in
anapanasati
the breath being with the bodily
sensations allowing some
ease or relaxation of the bodily
sensations
can be a tremendous support for
calming the mental activity
so if we find ourselves really caught up
and busy
with thinking we can just
incline the mind towards the physical
experience
including the physical experience of
thinking
so that's one way is to ground
our awareness in the present moment in
the
embodied presence that we have right now
and this also includes being aware
of some of the pleasant sensations
we might be having there might be
some ease with the breath some
smoothness of the breath
there also might be some vague diffuse
experiences of just some contentment or
okayness
maybe we can incline the mind that
direction
that also can be a support for the
calming of the mental activities
is to if there's some aspect of ease
to tune into that aspect of ease
and maybe we can
rather than feeling like we have to get
rid of our thoughts or make them slow
down or go away or
whatever ideas we might have
maybe we can have this emphasis on
a gentle inquiry is this
helpful or is it unhelpful
is it helpful in promoting a sense of
ease
and freedom peace and
or am i learning something here
is this valuable or
or is there a feeling i'm just stuck and
i'm just going around and around and
around
there's no sense of potential potential
learning
or potential
freedom or ease
so that might be one another way to kind
of work with mental activity is
to shift away from it has to be
different
to shift towards well is this helpful
and sometimes the answer to that can
bring a different
reaction response to our mental activity
which
might allow that mental activity to
unfold in a way
that is helpful
another thing that we might do is to
just do a gentle
inquiry of what's fueling this thinking
there might be an emotion
and just like at the beginning of this
um
before the guided meditation i talked
about when we're on a pilgrimage there
might be some parking dogs
and one way to be with them is just to
like show them our open hands and show
them
that we're safe for them so
is there a way in which we can be safe
for our emotions to be expressed
to show up can we
maybe in some way listen deeply
to ourselves and allow the emotion to
arise
without getting tangled up and thinking
that it has to be otherwise or it has to
be different
can we just create the space for our
emotional
experience
and that might also kind of soften some
of the mental activity
as we soften the fuel what's supporting
that mental activity
and then maybe
one other thing that i will say is
sometimes it can be skillful
to replace unhelpful thoughts
with other mental activities that are
more helpful
so to intentionally do something
an example might be to do some loving
kindness practice if we
feel that we're filled with rage
and ill will and thoughts of harming
hostility
in a way that is not helpful or healthy
or
we just feel like we're lost in it
so we can do some loving-kindness
practice
in whichever way it's easiest
we're not necessarily towards the object
through which we have hostility but just
incline the mind
towards where it's easy with a lovable
being
allowing the mind to kind of like calm
down and settle with this loving
kindness
so it might bring in to like replace
thoughts and comfortable thoughts with
some
or unhelpful thoughts with some other
thoughts
another way might be to use our
imagination
sometimes we do this in guided
meditations maybe you do it yourself
the wings of a bird flapping
or maybe ice skaters that they skate
skate skate and then
glide and feeling into the glide
or maybe the imagination of
taking off this itchy scratchy sweater
and instead putting on your favorite
t-shirt
so there might be some skillful ways in
which we can
replace some of our thinking
and can we do this while being aware of
the breath
all the while allowing the breath to
accompany us
and maybe the last thing i'll say
is there might be also opportunity to
say for some thoughts
some mental activity no
i'll work with this later after
meditation
right now i'm going to be with the
sensations of breathing
so i offer these as some tools that
might be helpful as we're practicing
meditation
and as tools if they're not helpful
we don't use them
so with a
sincere wish
that you are being with the sensations
of breathing with your practice your
meditations
maybe they be a source of support of
ease
and peace and freedom
in your life and in the lives of others
thank you