so good morning good day everyone and
welcome to the meditation and
this is uh the week we're going to be looking at greed and one of the aspects of greed is the
way in which it takes us away from ourselves
now some people are so identified with intense desires and wants and cravings
that they feel that's this is who they are and they don't recognize how there's a kind of alienation or pulling away
from a deeper connection to our hearts our body our inner life a deeper place where
there's a settling at at-homeness a
and the buddha calls us doesn't talk about at-homeness but he talks about one's ancestral home
that the practice of mindfulness is to stay based on or grounded in
one's ancestral home and so it's not just one's immediate home which can be cozy and
nice for some people but a place where uh you know one has been
i don't know you know rooted for centuries and
and uh so that metaphor here is that we're here to meditate to really stay
closely connected from the inside out kind of and one of the interesting
things to notice is how when we get involved in thoughts especially if we get lost in thoughts
there is a pulling away getting lost from this groundedness and connectedness to something that's
more solid more connected more at home here and of course sometimes
uh there's good reason to go spinning out in thoughts and sometimes it's uncomfortable to be here
in our ancestral home there's conflict going on here and
difficulties and feelings but it turns out that uh for mindfulness
practice that there is a healing quality that comes from settling in and being present in the
body here so in this meditation you might want to just notice the difference between
when you kind of get pulled into the world of thoughts and if thoughts are about the external
world and past future and people how we're kind of leaving the present moment in a certain way
and that as we begin again with breathing with mindfulness see if
that can be a quality of coming home coming centered grounding here where there's a
a connectedness where we don't lose the some deeper fuller connection to
ourselves and then we notice that we lose that we get involved in thoughts or if we get involved in strong wants
or strong aversions there is a way in which that pulls us away from this deeper
place of groundedness and if get involved in strong ideas of self
and what's in it for me oh yeah there's a loss of something there
and and see experiment with and explore get to know this movement of a way
and coming back being disconnected and being connected
wandering off into distant lands and being at home
in your ancestral homeland here so assuming a meditation posture
and there is a way in which a long tradition of assuming a posture
that's dignified that is we're kind of expressing
our worthiness our value
we are not diminishing ourselves cowering or
or somehow discounting ourselves
and we're not puffed up by not asserting ourselves but a simple dignity simple
nobility so a posture that expresses that
and people who are sitting upright it might mean sitting a little bit straighter
maybe there's a way of pulling in the spine a little bit between the shoulder blades
so the chest is a little bit more open
feeling the weight on the sitting bones so your weight of your body seems
balanced on top of it not leaning forward too much or backwards
gently closing your eyes
and with a feeling that you have all the time in the world
in a loving way
take some slow deep breaths
maybe three quarters full the inhale
and as you inhale more fully to feel all the sensations that get
activated with the deeper breaths in the rib cage and the chest
and the shoulders belly
and as you exhale long relaxed exhale
just long enough to remain comfortable with it
relax settle in on the exhale
and letting your breaths return to normal
and with a kind of intimacy with your breathing
the physical sensations that come into play as you breathe
as you exhale soften in the face
and if the face doesn't soften be content just to feel and sense
the physicality of the muscles of the face
the sensations from the inside out
meaning not your thoughts and images of your face
but how the skin the muscles of your face feel for themselves
and then to
soften and relax the shoulders
and to soften the belly
and then to tenderly lovingly
experience how the feel how the body experiences breathing
a certain receptivity to feel how the body experiences the
rhythm of breathing
and then notice if and when you get pulled into the
world of thoughts or pulled into the worlds of world of wanting or not wanting how there might be a
loss of this deeper connection to the body
to the inner life here and now
maybe even a kind of alienation from oneself
and that mindfulness is to return to this ancestral home
to this place here in ourselves
grounded connected and noticing the move the rhythm the
contrast between being pulled away
and returning connecting here to the body breathing
see what you can notice and learn about yourself in that contrast between being connected
and disconnected with our embodied existence
from the inside out
if you are involved in thinking can you feel how that pulls you away
from a deeper connection to breathing
and even if you feel connected to breathing perhaps there's a some thinking
that limits the fullness of the connection to breathing
see if the thinking mind can become quieter
and the connection to your body breathing
fuller
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to be connected deeply to ourselves
to our hearts to our inner sensitivity to being at ease and calm and settled
might provide us with a heightened sensitivity
to others perhaps one that is
tender relaxed one that is not governed
by desire or craving or clinging or greed
or aversion hatred something simple
relaxed and to have that simple capacity
for gazing out upon the world
to gaze upon the world with kind eyes
and to wish well for this world
to have our well-wishing and care and our love
not confused or mixed up with distress or fear or desires or wanting
aversions resentments his simplicity
of looking upon the world kindly well wishing
and how wonderful it would be how meaningful it would be
how preferable it would be if
others could be happy safe
healthy peaceful and
free of all the forces within them that afflict them
all the forces around them in our societies that oppress them
it may it be that this practice that we do and how we live our lives
from this practice may it be for the welfare and happiness
of others may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings find peace
and may all beings share mutually in a life
that's free
[Music]
so this is the going to be the second talk on greed and um
in this one i'll just try to talk a little bit about what this word greed is it's very important concept in
buddhism in buddhist practice least because freedom from greed is one of the
definitions of one of the aspects of the spiritual liberation that buddhism
points to it's a possibility for us and so to understand what this is so we
can work through it and get to the other side is important
but it's a little difficult maybe for me to talk about greed
maybe because associations i have with the word and maybe other people have it
or that it or say it more specifically that
in my history with terevan buddhism i sometimes felt that greed was disrespected
that greed was somehow just considered to be all bad and therefore kind of the goal was just
to get rid of it or or if it was there it was kind of a it was it was kind of a negative it was
something wrong with us it was like we were somehow there's almost like the closest thing maybe to
sin or something that was really where so there's an impurity that we have if we have greed in fact
the tradition talks about greed as being impure and
the way i think we have to be very careful to um to consider that this thing that we
translating as greed uh is multifaceted and it is
is kind of integrated or connected to so many different aspects of our lives some of them are very healthy and
important and some of them which are because of suffering and that
we don't want to throw away the baby with the bathwater we don't want to kind of just kind of have a simple idea
of greed as being bad therefore let's get rid of it it's important to kind of take a deeper
look and really get to understand whatever it is we under whatever we associate with the word
greed we don't want to judge it negatively
or disrespect it or condemn it or condemn ourselves because of it in
mindfulness practice we want to take a deep good look at it and really find out what
is it for us and how does this work and what is it connected to and what is it trying to do and and
and is there anything valuable underneath or is part of what we call
greed so um um
there's two words uh and then that are uh sometimes translated as greed uh
that belong in this uh triad of greed hatred and delusion and uh
and so with those three those three words others the set sometimes there's the word raga
that's used for greed and sometimes the word loba so r-a-g-a or loba-l-o-b-h-a
and raga means has more to do with sensual desires
and so the desire for uh sensual pleasures and
um and but it's a desire that's not just like you know dime a dozen like oh it'd be nice to have uh
you know uh pleasant food it would be nice to have a you know a soft bed to sleep in or it's
nice though all kinds of things would be nice to have something but there's a a compulsion a
compellingness to it so some people will translate this word raga as lust
some people will translate it as passion and maybe different people have
different associations with these two words that some of them don't work very well
for a translation uh be kind of a synonym of greed um and don't really work as something that
uh is generally seen as being negative so you know there's some variability and
choice you have about what words you use but this word raga has to do with sensual pleasures and we know that some
people have a tremendous intensity of desire around sensual pleasure there's addictions
there's cravings there's a strong compulsion to be involved in that world
and and some people lose themselves and make huge cause tremendous amount of suffering in
life because of it and and very quickly regret what they've done and um
because uh there was pleasure in the moment but uh it was pleasure that hurt other people
uh or hurt themselves in some deep way so for uh drinking alcohol and drugs
sometimes it can be sometimes a drive for pleasure and um and but it doesn't really provide
happiness it provides a little bit of alienation and um
and so this is strong so he for human beings sensual pleasure plays a huge role in
their lives and so how to be involved with that in a wise way in a liberating so we're free in
relationship to them but not to dismiss sensual pleasures not to feel like we're not allowed to experience them but how
do we experience them without the suffering and pain that comes with
being compelled to search for sensual pleasure to really kind of hold on or cling
and then the other end the other word is loba and loba has more to do with acquiring things getting
things obtaining things and um and so there's a whole slew of things which are
not necessarily involve central pleasure but uh you know directly but
you know just wanting money wanting material things wanting fame wanting praise
and the and so this loba is a strong desire for things
and and when these uh intense desires are strong we can get
caught in the realm in the web of them and and this idea of getting
caught is one that the buddha usually the buddha kind of emphasized
that he talked about the metaphor of catching monkeys that apparently hunters
in his time had a kind of pitch a kind of maybe a pine tar or something
sap or something that they used it was very very sticky and they'd put someone on a piece of
wood maybe a stick maybe with food attached to the stick so
the monkey would come along and maybe grab onto the stick maybe it's on
a pole and so it has to kind of get up to the top of the pole to get the food and it would put his hand on the pitch
and then it couldn't pull its hand really free so it would take the other hand and and to push itself off the pole
but the other hand would get stuck in the pitch so then we take a foot to try to get the two hands free and
that foot would get stuck on the pole then take the second foot to the same thing and get stuck again
and then that's the metaphor the buddha said the monkey then takes its nose and pushes against the
stick to push away but then the nose gets stuck and with all five uh kind of
body parts stuck to the pitch the hunter can just walk right up and pick up the monkey and the poor
monkey has now been caught and um and so
with uh so this greed this loba or this raga
when it's strong we get caught in the web in the pitch of what we want and sometimes you know
we're inflamed and desires and and we can't think of anything else but getting what we want
but the reason one of the reasons to respect greed is that greed sometimes has deeper roots
inside of us that if there's a reason for it sometimes the pursuit of
very strong desire comes from deep conditionality deep
sometimes hurt or suffering or fear or distress that is trying trying to find some way
to be healed or cared for or be distracted from or
compensated for and if we simply let go or throw away greed too
quickly and dismiss it we don't understand that it's a symptom of some deeper desire
and not all desires are wrong some desires are attempts to move towards health and
to care for ourselves but sometimes they get misdirected and
they get directed in ways that can be harmful or disconnecting or
alienating and so if we stop and take a look at greed this intense desire to see what is what
more is going on here let's stop and not dismiss it not disrespect it
but think of it as something that really needs us to uh needs to be seen to be heard
to be connected to and so rather than having greed be a source of disconnection
we're disconnected from ourselves but network we're trapped or connected to the pitch
to the spider's web and it can't get away but rather to find a connection to the
greed that allows us to have a deepening experience of ourselves
so and partly what that involves is turning the attention around 180 degrees
from the object of the greed to what it's like to to be greedy
to what it feels like here in the body so this movement from alienation that
greed can cause when we're so focused on the object can be turned around and
to create the opposite of alienation the connection connectedness here
so so one of the things to study in greed so we really know for
ourselves is the way that greed when we're involved in incontinent
it doesn't really feel like it's for our own welfare the way that it leads to alienation the
way it maybe causes suffering at least in the teachings of the buddha
greed always involves
suffering some kind of distress stress
some kind of uh ouch for ourselves in having the green
and part of the reason to discover how greed is stressful to have or
or the underlying suffering or problems with the experience of greed
is so that we can discover a different kind of desire a healthy desire that has no suffering
involved in it that has no distress that doesn't diminish us limit us doesn't trap us
but it does the opposite it nourishes us frees us opens us there are such desires
so um so the fact that we're looking here at
greed and we see that greed is problematic doesn't mean that we should just dismiss it we should respect it look at
it deeply discover what's really happening under the surface of it and and and
search for other forms of desires that can animate our life that are freeing that
are healthy to have that are appropriate to have this is the task with mindfulness
practice in relationship to greed so then tomorrow i'll talk more about
this turning the attention around 180 degrees and really practicing with great looking at it in a deeper way
and but for today you might uh for the next 24 hours um you might look and see uh
maybe not use the word greed if that doesn't really resonate or if that's you think of that
as only as you know intense desires but see if in small ways
in the small compulsions the small ways you're compelled by desire
study what are you compelled by where do you lose your freedom around desire it could be as simple as
going for seconds or going for a cookie or you know all kinds of things that you
do where you can't help yourself but to go and and be pushed by a desire
and in that losing your freedom so i hope you enjoy the exploration of
greed and and i hope that you're a better person
because of it thank you