so welcome and let's begin meditating together today
so coming into the sense of your body sitting or lying down
standing whatever posture you're in
just letting go of any energy of arriving and settling in
and connecting with others and just now feeling that sense of being here
in the group and also in your body
if it's comfortable doing so you can close your eyes
just bring the attention inward
and it's often good at the beginning of a sit to just connect briefly with your
posture how it is that you're sitting
because in a sense the way that we have our body and our posture has an effect on the
mind during the sit so we connect in with where we're
sitting [Music] the body resting against some surface
cushion or a chair or bed with a floor
i'm just sensing those contact points where you're being supported
allowing yourself to relax into those
feeling the stability of where you're sitting
having a stable base or groundedness
and then you can sense the uprightness or the straightness of the body when
it's supported in that way so if you're sitting you may feel the way the spine rises up from the seat
almost as if suspended from above or the way a sea plant
rises off the sea floor floating in the water
just gently buoyed upward
even if you're lying down you can sense into the straightness of the spine that is easy when the body is well supported
and then allowing some softness in the rest of the body
liking the plant the fronds of the plant float in the water
the arms float the head floats on the spine
we can soften any tenseness in the shoulders
in the belly
softening any bracing in the legs
even relaxing the thinking muscle in the mind
not so much to stop any thinking but simply to reduce its intensity
letting some of the softness and spaciousness of the body
absorb some of that intensity of thinking
and then connecting in with the sensations of breathing
the gentle coming in and going out of the breath
just naturally however it is right now is fine
being receptive to the sensations of the breath
as if opening the door to them when they arrive as a guest
welcoming them in and out receptively
we may sense that the breath is a whole body experience
it doesn't only touch us in the nasal passages and the ones
kind of anatomical breath but it affects
many things throughout the body as we feel the gentle expansion of the
body as the breath comes in and then the softening
and release as it goes out
as the breath energy distributes itself throughout the body
just seeing if you can sense the breath as a whole body experience
in whatever way it is for you right now
and now i will offer an image
so imagine that you are sitting under a tree
on a warm and mild summer day
it's cool in the shade of the tree
and the grass where you're sitting is soft
and you're a little bit secluded like maybe up on a small hill
and your eyes are a little open and you're watching people
working or playing harmoniously down below
maybe they're working in the garden or perhaps it's a group of children
laughing as they play
and just in this simple scene you you feel a sense of well-being
there's kind of a completeness or a wholeness
to this moment on this day
you can simultaneously feel your body resting under the tree
the warmth of your skin the relaxation in your muscles
and you can see the harmonious activity going on below
which gives you a warm emotional feeling
now you can gently let this image fade
can let go of the effort of bringing it to mind but just keep that feeling of well-being
letting it pervade the body and mind
and just keep resting with the with the breath
and if the mind gets busy or begins to drift away
to something else when you notice that
you might just call up again this sense of well-being
just inviting that back in in a gentle way
if the emotions or sensations are very strong we might just have the well-being
as a partner with them along the side
or maybe it's possible to gradually return again to that sense of unity and
alignment
one teacher has called this experience of well-being
an experience of being coherent between the mind and the body
our system has somehow become coherent together when it's aligned like this
it can be very helpful in practice to find places within our system that do
feel coherent aligned and be able to
connect with those or even rest in those even if there are other parts that are
not so coherent
so we're aware of all of it but we particularly know where there is
this sense of well-being and we can connect in with that
seeing if you can stay with that even in the face of other experiences
happening too
um
when there's been a period in meditation when
the mind is somewhat coherent mind and body it can be helpful
to open and notice the experience of knowing
what is it like to be aware in this
state of mind what's it like to be aware of a
state of well-being
can you sense the quality of attention or knowing
in this state
there may be a kind of brightness or warmth
or openness and receptivity
somehow in the mind nothing needs to be done with it
just to know the quality of that awakeness
scented
and as we gently begin turning toward
the rest of our day or evening
we may consider how we can bring this
inner harmony to whatever degree it was experienced
out into the world
this sense of well-being or
unity or alignment
more coherence
this quality that we've touched in ourselves to whatever degree
how might it manifest out in the world
surely we will encounter what is not harmonious what is not coherent
but is there a way that we can still touch that with a
harmonious mind to be in harmony with what is not
harmonious
to have coherent understanding of what is not coherent
we may not immediately see how
that affects the world now in the moment we may not
have a change in the situation but there is an effect
from the larger picture all of our minds are interacting and
when there are some that are somewhat harmonious and
caring connected it contributes to the whole
often in unseen ways
and all we need to do is make to make a contribution is to remember
to stay connected to that part in us that has the well-being
and the coherence to whatever degree we can
it all helps
so we wish well for ourselves and for those around us
for the whole world
and we wish also that others may discover this part of themselves that is
in a state of well-being that is collected that is unified
may they too know such experiences may they too contribute to the whole
whenever possible for them
in this world so in need of peace and harmony and wholeness
may we do all we can to contribute to that
okay so as we learn to
be with our body this series is called the depth of the
body we'll begin to experience tranquility of the body
and we can discover ways in which the body and the mind
can find harmony at least in some areas and then maybe
spread that out and that degree of harmony that we can find supports our well-being
so the body is a tremendous support for well-being in the mind and the heart
so we'll unpack this a bit today so there is a suta that is devoted
entirely to mindfulness of the body for those of you who like references
it's mn 119 the kayak
and i find this to be a very interesting suta because the buddha
communicates many of the teachings about body practice
through images it seems to be you know somehow that was what he was inspired to talk about when
he talked about how to be mindful of the body and how to use mindfulness of the body to develop the
the path to awakening so i want to convey some of these images
today and you know you can maybe
just rest in the the images that are offered they're not really meant as visualizations you know
we don't need to put them up into our cognitive mind in a certain way
but they're you can imagine the image but i think it's meant more as a visceral
experience to try to touch in what into what that would feel like
to be conveyed by the image so there are a series of
meditative states where the mind and the body become deeply unified
these are actually known about in many traditions but they're described in a particular
way in this tradition so perhaps you've heard the word samadhi
this literally means collected together or composed or gathered
and there are many different forms of it there isn't just one one correct way to
do it or one experience of it and there are many different levels of it also you know we
can have some degree of genuine samadhi actually in daily life
if our mind is sufficiently unified around what we're doing
and then there are also you know many meditative states that have this quality of being gathered together
so i um i brought the text with me today
and i thought i would actually just read some of these images
some of you may have heard them but nonetheless it's really nice to just listen to
so here's one just as a skilled bath man or a bath
man's apprentice heaps bath powder in a metal basin
and sprinkling it gradually with water needs it until the moisture wets the
ball of bath powder soaks it and pervades it inside and out
and yet the ball itself does not ooze so too
a practitioner or meditator makes the rapture and pleasure born of
seclusion drench steep fill and pervade this body so that there
is no part of their whole body unpervaded by the rapture and pleasure
born of seclusion it's a really nice image so
we have this rapture and pleasure pervading and filling the body
and in this particular image we kind of work them into the body like working water into
bath powder according to this image we don't really use bath powder but we could imagine a flower say working
the water into it to make a nice dough something like that
and so there's a sense and this is at the beginning of when one starts to practice this on the
cushion so maybe there's a sense that we need to kind of connect the body and the
mind together there's two different things being unified through our effort
of filling the body with rapture and pleasure in some way
so that's kind of nice and then after that it goes on to images that are much more
about water there's a sense of um of water the purity
clearness of water so here we have this image just as though there were a lake whose
waters welled up from below and it had no inflow from east west
north or south and would not be replenished from time to time by showers of rain
then the cool fount of water welling up in the lake would make the cool water drench steep
fill and pervade the lake so that there would be no part of the whole lake
unpervaded by cool water so too a meditator makes the rapture and
pleasure born of concentration drench steep fill and pervade this body
so that there is no part of their whole body unpervaded by the rapture and pleasure
worn of concentration so as we get a little bit more settled there's this lake image
where the lake doesn't have any rain coming in it doesn't have any streams coming in
maybe it's a mountain lake and it's fed by an underwater spring
and the waters from that come up and fill the entire lake and we're to imagine the
body as being like a lake and there's a way in which this well-being that we're experiencing
begins to well up from within you know maybe before we were thinking about
external reasons why we could have well-being the body is feeling calm i've managed to
get it quiet in my house you know i'm at ease because i just had that good cup
of tea you know we're kind of settling in um but these are a little bit external
and then there's a point where something internal kicks in and the body has a sense somebody in
mind have a sense of well-being that comes entirely from inside
and then it goes on [Music] we'll just look a little bit farther
and then we have an image of lotuses in the water
it says there's a pond with blue red and white lotuses
some lotuses are born and grow in the water and they thrive immersed in the water without rising out of it
and the cool water drenches steeps fills and pervades these lotuses
to their tips and their roots so that there is no part of the lotuses unprovated by cool water
and so too the meditator [Music] feels this sense of
rapture and ease actually at that point there's only pleasure and ease of filling the body
so it's the same kind of image but it's actually a little bit more settled instead of having a
bubbling spring coming up and filling the lake we can imagine some dynamic
motion from that there's instead a sense of just a lotus standing still
with the water all around it it's a calmer image if you will
you know and then it goes on in certain ways they're quite amazing images um
and now they're not as i said they're not meant as visualizations we don't sit and imagine ourselves as a lotus but
they're meant to describe experiences that we can have when the mind begins to
rest with a single object for with a fairly good continuity of attention and these are
natural occurrences there's nothing that we need to force into existence for these things to
come about so i think what i want to convey with these is that this is a state that's
very healing you know the mind and the body become healed
through this strong presence of the body in these visceral bodily type images
if we just stay in the mind during our meditation it doesn't penetrate perhaps as deeply
into these more [Music] sensory based images so there's a way
that they bring healing and wholeness to our system so many of us are looking for healing in certain ways from meditation
my sense is that samadhi is really a good
possibility for that it may be how the buddha encouraged that among his followers
so the buddha isn't done with images yet in this suta he describes all these meditative images but he then goes on to
talk about the kind of wholesome strength that comes when we are connected deeply with the
body and he says that a person who has very well developed mindfulness of the body for
such a person mara who is the force that represents distraction as
well as on wholesomeness and buddhist teachings what it says is mara cannot find an
opportunity or a support in that person and so then there's a bunch of images about that
and maybe i'll just read one of those too so when the mind
is not well developed when mindfulness of the body is not well developed it says
suppose a person were to throw a heavy stone ball upon a mound of wet clay what
do you think would that heavy ball find entry into that mound of wet clay
and of course the monks say yes yes it would and then the buddha goes on and says
well for somebody who has well developed mindfulness of the body
suppose a person were to throw a light ball of string at a door panel made
entirely of heartwood what do you think would that light ball of string find entry through that door
panel made entirely of heartwood and of course the monks say no
so the buddha says well in the same way someone without well-developed mindfulness of the body mara
can find an opportunity just like a ball entering wet clay whereas
for someone with well-developed mindfulness of the body mara cannot find any entry or
opportunity just as if throwing a light wall of string at a wooden door panel
and there are other images given also so there's a sense then that mindfulness of the body creates a
lot of inner strength in a person you know the mind and the body become
unified and even if we don't go into you know very deep
states of of meditation there's a way that i think even just over time having a lot of mindfulness of
the body gradually imparts more and more strength to the system and i see that as
being related to the what i was calling alignment and coherence you know a
system that is coherent is stronger than one that's kind of scattered and going in lots of different directions
and this strength has very practical effects according to the suta
there are a whole bunch of then advanced benefits listed of mindfulness of the body i won't go through all of them
but here are a few one becomes a conqueror of discontent
and delight discontent does not conquer oneself and one abides overcoming discontent
whenever it arises one becomes a conqueror of fear and
dread and abides overcoming them whenever they arise
one bears heat and cold hunger and thirst contact with gadflies mosquitoes wind
the sun and creeping things one endures ill-spoken unwelcome words
and arisen bodily feelings that are painful and even life-threatening
so there's a lot of endurance and strength that comes through mindfulness of the body
practicing this will help us become more resilient in the face of
life maybe we don't have gadflies but maybe we too mosquitoes wind the sun and creeping
things so the inconveniences and difficulties of the natural world
heat and cold hunger and thirst how about ill-spoken unwelcome words
mindfulness of the body can help us become strong in the face of those
as well as other mental and physical difficulties discontent or risen bodily feelings that
are painful and i notice that it even includes delight we become a conqueror of delight
so of course we you know it's not that we don't want to have pleasure and delight in our life
that's fine but we we become conquered by them if we can be
drawn in and knocked off balance made giddy if you will by
pleasure and excitement so also mindfulness of the body will help us to
remain grounded during pleasant experiences so this is quite a lot of good things
that come from mindfulness of the body and then later down in the list it goes on even to say that
we can reach awakening through liberation through mindfulness of the body
and the buddha knew what he was talking about from his own experience it said in another part of the teachings
that when the buddha before his awakening was contemplating how he might reach
awakening he remembered a time when he was sitting peacefully
under a rose apple tree watching his father blow conduct a plowing ceremony
in the field and he was a boy at the time so he was not participating he was just watching
from under the tree and his mind spontaneously became unified and peaceful
you know there in the in the world sitting under the tree and he thought to himself as he remembered this
just before his awakening he remembered back to this and he thought is this the way to awakening
it is he had the insight oh that's the way and that was his inspiration to sit down
under the bodhi tree and have the insights that led to his waking up
so this gently unified mind that we're cultivating is quite important for
setting us up to be able to see clearly and deeply and tomorrow's topic will be the body
as a vehicle of insight so if you can join then i will see you then
be well