so hello from redwood city in
california and welcome to our meditation session together
one of the important supports for meditation
is no longer being fascinated by our own
thinking or no longer so actively involved in our
thinking no longer simply allowing thinking to go
along go go on and on and on without being clearly mindful of that and so
there is a kind of little little heightened attention to thinking that's useful for meditation
um so to protect us from being swept away in our thoughts
so one way to do this and and at the same time it's very important not to be
in conflict with thinking or struggling against it
it's better just to lend if i think it's almost better just to keep thinking and struggle but a few things that you
might try doing today one is every exhale
let go of what you're thinking thinking might begin again very quickly
that's okay but every exhale let go of your thinking and be there for the inhale
and then let go again and be there for the inhale kind of get into the rhythm of that
and so that whatever thought arises you're not swept away in it you're not caught in
it you're not fueling it or involved in it if letting go of it seems a bit too much
an alternative is to every exhale
if you're thinking recognize your thinking acknowledge that's the case and it can
be with a simple word thinking that you say to yourself
and saying the word thinking for many people help them step away from their involvement with
thinking and uh and then that's stepping away we're not fueling it and feeding it anymore the stories and
whatever we're involved in so both letting go of your thinking and
in just just recognizing that you are thinking
not have to be done with any opposition to thinking
but there are better things to do than to think and if what you want to do is to
meditate uh and so this kind of beginning to kind of create a little bit of freedom from
thinking then make space and room for a greater
settling a greater calm or clarity of mindfulness so
assuming a meditation posture
taking some time to move around twist and sway the body a
bit both to kind of wake up the body and connect to your body
but also to help the body kind of come into an aligned posture or just kind of
adjust to the best posture that's suitable for you
and then gently closing the eyes
and taking a few long deep slow breaths
three quarters full some people find it helpful to open the
mouth a little bit and breathe in through the mouth the steep inhales
so they'll look more conscious and engaged
breathing in deeply and then long slow relaxing exhale
perhaps as you exhale settling in to this body posture
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and continue the process of relaxing the body softening
some people like to do it systematically some people like to just do it randomly wherever the tension is in the body if
you do it systematically you can start at the forehead and the eyes
relaxing with the exhale
softening the cheeks in the jaws
there might be some relaxing of the neck softening of the neck
release the holding in the neck
on the exhale releasing the shoulders
or softening we're easing up with the shoulders
softening in the chest
softening the belly
perhaps there can be a softening relaxing of the hands the fingers
and relaxing of the legs
and if uh you have a location in your body in your head where thinking is most predominant
there's a physical engagement of energy or agitation contraction pressure associated with
thinking as you exhale
can you relax that thinking muscle that thinking the
the tightness associated with thinking
and then to settle into your breathing the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out maybe with your central vision in a
sense central attention going on breathing in your peripheral attention as you
exhale let go of your thinking every exhale
lighten up quiet you're thinking
or if that is difficult every exhale acknowledge
that you're thinking stepping back stepping away and seeing
thinking for what it is this is thinking this
is the mind thinking and that stepping away and seeing it
this way begins a process of not being so
identified or involved with thinking
uh
recognizing that you're thinking
and keep recognizing it letting go of your thinking
letting go into your breathing and keep letting go of thinking gently
kindly without struggle or aversion
just letting go
foreign
letting go of thoughts perhaps there can be a fresh
awareness of the inhale
a fresh involvement settling in to the experience of breathing in and
breathing out
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to again take a few long slow deep
breaths and this time perhaps breathing in
deeply into your heart almost as if you can expand your good
heart as you inhale
and spread that goodness out with the
exhale if we value
goodness kindness friendliness
generosity love if we value some of these heart
qualities the end of a meditation is a time to
remember them to touch into them
and on whatever benefit that's come from the meditation practice
let these good qualities of the heart
float on the benefits of meditation and the ways you're calm more settled
more open
and consider how whatever benefit known or unknown that comes from the
practice consider bringing those benefits into the world
that you yourself are an agent of make doing good in the
world benefiting others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe
may all beings be free
and may each of us contribute to that
possibility [Music]
okay uh
so i have a little bit of a tickle in my throat today so we'll see how this goes
so
so one of the things well known about mindfulness practice buddhist
meditation practice in general is that it's very much based on being
present in the present moment it's a practice that aims to bring us
into the present moment more fully and then to
uh but not just to be present for its own sake which sometimes is quite lovely and
profound but to begin
utilizing or engaging some of the potential that comes when we
can be present for our experience and some of the potential of mindfulness
practice that can be actualized when we're present
when they're in when when we're in the now is really something that is
belongs to the world of time that the benefits come in the future
that the benefits we're putting in place we're doing activities we're doing the
meditation practice in such a way that benefits will come
sometimes in in you know well into the future
and um so what are those benefits what is what is
it what's the what's what's part of the long game of meditation that um
that we're engaged in here now so i'll start with an analogy of
raising children and so i had the experience so i think probably plenty of parents have of
uh when the kids are quite young two three sometimes even four five
maybe even older sometimes that we might do
a lot of effort to do something wonderful with the children and take them to some wonderful place
do some kind of wonderful activity at home spend a lot of time to really do
something quite marvelous
and as the kids grow older they don't remember
so many of the things and what parents can remember were special moments the kids weren't particularly special
for the kids they don't remember and um and
uh but what so the event the activity that uh
the experience the conscious experience of something doesn't remain for the children and the
way sometimes for parents they do but what remains is the
is a few things one is early childhood things that the kids don't remember
is that they're receiving the conditions they're being conditioned they're being
influenced or nourished supported impacted by the environment that they're
in so if the parents are or the family
or the environment is creating an environment where the kids feel safe nurtured loved cared for
that creates a very different conditioning for the child then if the child grows up with violence
and anger and being ignored and being dismissed and all kinds of things and very different
conditioning if they feel safe and cared for
something has to relax and they feel at home in the world they feel comfortable but if there's
war and violence and anger and and um drunkenness and
you know chaos and dismissing and ignoring then they don't feel like they belong
they feel like something's wrong they feel they have to protect themselves they feel tense they feel afraid and that each of those
two scenarios creates a very different different conditioning and that conditioning can last
well into a person's whole life they don't remember all the details but the conditioning has
remained and some people feel like even before kids learn language and have the words
to remember what happened they're already being conditioned by the environment in that first year of their life in a very deep way
so one of the ways that meditation or buddhist practice works a very important part of it
is that we are putting in place uh conditions that um
that condition us in a good way that influence us on this maybe even the
subliminal or a deeper kind of physical heartfelt emotional level
that that words and understanding don't do
and so we are beginning to um understand what are the conditions
that are supportive um now being
so that's one thing this can the conditioning the second thing i want to talk about and then i'll bring these two
together is that you also see in young children that a lot of what
childhood is about is learning new skills that they don't know how to crawl and
then they develop the skills for crawling they don't know how to walk then they develop the skills for walking
maybe with a lot of falling as part of it they don't know how the skills of eating and then they develop the skills for how
to eat and those skills sometimes develop you know greater greater detail as they get older and
people who grow up when with spoons eventually get forks eventually gets forks and knives
maybe even they're introduced to chopsticks and they develop all this physical dexterity of how to eat
and it's a skill that gets developed and by time we're an adult we're not thinking about that as a skill
it's just kind of an obvious thing that we'd know how to do but you watch the little kids and you see they're learning how to do this
we learn language we learn to ride a bicycle we learn oh learn to put on our clothes for
ourselves and we learn all these different things we're learning these skills and these um
and these skills that we learn uh we continue right up until we die we're still learning skills and how to be in
in this world it's a very ordinary human thing to through repetition through engagement
that we learn mental skills physical skills maybe
emotional skills of how to do things and so part of buddhist meditation
practice that has to do with time is that we are developing skills and
we get developing the skills of concentration the skills of mindfulness developing a whole a whole bunch of
skills about knowing what to bring mindfulness to and what to include
we'll learn after a while that we should be mindful of the fact that we're drifting off in thought a lot
or we need to be mindful of our attitude as we meditate i know people can meditate without
realizing that there's a anger or a
best part of their mindfulness they're upset with something and or there's a a expectation
that you know that some wonderful things going to happen or there's some subtle thought that uh you know this i
can't really do this this is too difficult or there's a greed or a desire that's pushing
wanting some wonderful experience so all these attitudes there to learning the skill of recognizing
those subtle attitudes that are somehow sometimes even tripping us up as we meditate or
which are having an undue influence on how we meditate
and and part of the skill is then to learn about conditions to
learn that we we it's our job to put in place the proper conditions
that nourish us that support us that allow for the growth and well-being of who we are
meditation is one of those if you spent your time just watching movies on netflix or
something or and if you only spent your time
chasing after making lots of money or only spend time
chasing after anything at all you can name it and you're preoccupied busy involved
then that's a conditioning factor but if you spend time
having a sabbath having time just to be quiet and still and and content with your life as it is
creates a very different conditioning if you feel like you always want more
then you're conditioning you're influencing the predisposing yourself that you're always not enough
there's always more to be had and no matter then what you get there's always more
if you're conditioning yourself to be content then you're more likely to be content
you know or to recognize that things are content you don't need more and more and more and this
conditioning is not brainwashing it's just taking the good qualities
that we have and and developing this skill to connect with them more often
and remind ourselves more often and to cultivate the things that um bring those about and bring them
forth because we have we have the potential
of feeding ourselves good influences so classically the buddha said it's
useful to spend time with good spiritual friends to spend time with people that
represent values or present qualities of being that you want to be influenced by that
you want to you want those to be conditioning factors for yourself
if you spend time only with angry people only with hostile people then maybe
that's what gets kind of encouraged and returned back so
so to take care of what comes in
it influences us and the more we're in the present moment the more we can be custodian the
caretaker of that and we can make the choices both the choices about
you know uh to do something that's as simple as you know there's two freeways here
on the peninsula there's 101 and there's 280 and sometimes it's been more or less the
same which one i take maybe a little bit longer on 280. and i see that driving down 280 which goes
through sometimes beautiful hillsides and sometime a year these you know forests
and the mountains on the side and 101 goes through down through the airport and
city urban areas in a way that's not so inspiring parts of it and so just to go down 280 i just feel
better i just feel more refreshed and relaxed at the end um um but even if i go down 101 where
it's maybe a lot of more traffic and business and smog and and stuff then what conditions do i want
to support to develop inside of me it isn't just a moral obligation to be patient or
be a driver that's generous to the other drivers um but what do i want to
develop in myself maybe i want to develop i don't want to develop being in a hurry
and being impatient and zigzagging out of the traffic to get
someplace where i need to go as quickly as i can maybe one of what i develop is driving
in a way where i'm driving safe and content as if i have lots of time and this idea that
giving ourselves time and driving in a content way rather than a discontented way or
and pressure in the long game of life
those who begin creating conditions that allow something deeper to unfold and develop within
us so these two things are a very important
part of buddhist practice in general that buddhist practice has a lot to do
with putting conditions in place and there's a lot to do developing the skills to do so
um some of this these uh skills
some of these conditioning factors are things like kindness so we develop we develop the
skill of being kind some of it has to do with letting go we developed a skill of letting go
some of it has to do with you know being generous and so we cultivate the
capacity for generous become skillful at learning the art of generosity and how to give wisely
there's all these this variety of different things we're kind of developing
the skill that being ethical conduct the skill of wise speech
speech which we feel nourished by it when we finish speaking it we feel like we've benefited from it
rather than later we feel i'm so sorry i spoke that way i was so just mostly complaining the whole time
we were together and i feel a bit drained and maybe you do too or and so these are all called skills that
we develop we develop beneficial skills so it's not only a matter of showing up and being
mindful in the present moment and developing present moment awareness and then trusting
that all the goodness we have will come and take care of things it's a little bit magical thinking
we develop mindfulness of the present moment and then we see more choice we live in more considered
life we're more wise wise about things some people put a tremendous emphasis on
religious experiences they're looking to have a great aha moment they've heard in buddhism
there's enlightenment and i want to get that experience of enlightenment and then everything will be okay forever
after or you know i want to have this wonderful religious experience
that then i can go around and tell my friends you know aha you know it's so great what happened to me and
when it wasn't retreat and this great experience happened and it was so profound and
so glad i had this profound experience it's a wonderful experiences that can
have and can can arise in practice and i don't want to diminish their importance but to
over emphasize them at the expense of the ordinary day-to-day cultivating
skills cultivating the right conditions the long game and some of this
conditioning bears fruit in far into the future
it's possible that as we develop generosity or contentment or
capacity to be equanimous a capacity to be with pain and not to be reactive and afraid or
or hostile or contracted it's a skill when a skillfulness of being with pain
it's one of the things i started learning in my early years of buddhist practice when i was living at zen center
in a variety of different ways i got the message you know gil it'd be good if i understood how to
be present for pain without the self-pity the activity reactivity the anger
and i would look for situations where uh i was feeling a lot of pain
but it was safe to do so and then i would explore it and be with it and develop and develop a
skill of being present in an equanimous way open way without being troubled by the pain but
being wise by it i mean with simple things like sometimes we were carrying really heavy objects i was working on
the zen center farm and we had to carry farm implements and so uh you know allowing myself to
feel feel the pain and doing the work without up to a limit
hopefully the healthy limit but working with that edge learning about myself developing that skill and then later in
life i had accidents or had things happen to me where i was in a lot of pain not because
i wanted to be because it was an accident and then i had the skill of knowing how
to practice with pain and that was really useful to learn how to let go
and not because letting go is you know you know moral obligation it just you
can live a much better happier life when you let go that becomes obvious as
people get older i've now come seems like i've come into that stage of
age maybe old age maybe where um with my friends sometimes we
we go through we have a litany and i think of a litany as uh you know kind of a sacred
repetition of a chant or something or a piece of of um something anyway the um
the litany of different different physical ailments how our bodies are changing and shifting as we get older
and um and uh and to learn how to let go of all the physical changes that you
know let go of how things were and then embrace what's happening now uh
and finding some joy in it okay well that goes now too this that this too this too that's a
skill we develop if you've never never let go of anything your whole life
and then something happens in the old age where you can no longer have an ability you can get bitter
at the absence of that ability but if you learn to let go and learn that not only letting go but
letting go into something great you develop you develop can you've conditioned yourself you've
cultivated and developed a sense of peace and tranquility and
love and goodness here that letting go is not just letting go into
absence or deprived state but letting go is letting go into
this goodness that's been developed this goodness that's been allowed to grow and and and all that
so then um so we the skill of letting go comes together with how we've been
conditioned how we've allowed ourselves to be conditioned and uh and grow is um
is um you know is part of part of the long game of meditation practice
so the long game um and
so conditioning what are the conditions you want to have
in place one of the interesting things about buddhist practice and
the teachings of the buddha he didn't put a lot of emphasis on causality like we are we
are responsible to cause things cause our meditation practice to develop a certain way but rather we're
responsible putting the conditions in that allows these uh for growth
so there's kind of both a a removal responsibility and an addition of
responsibility we're not responsible for what actually happens but we are responsible for putting the
conditions the best conditions in place so that something good can happen
so there's a kind of releasing of obligation or releasing of a certain
kind of self-centered effort to make something happen it's more like grace it's more
like we receive all this goodness we make room for it and allow it to grow and
happen and that's one part of the conditions we offer is getting out of the way and allow
the goodness to evolve and develop but we put in the conditions that allow
the best conditions for that to to sow that the best can grow out of us
and so what are those conditions so part of a buddhist spiritual life
is reflecting and thinking about what conditions can you put
realistically put into place that supports that long game that supports that influence you want to have
and the conditioning you want to develop and what skills do you want to develop
meditation is a skill and it's done by repetition over and over and over again
um the other you know when i went her first raider who taught her recently
taught recently listened to her recently when she was abbess of the san francisco zen center she
sometimes would watch new students come in to meditate to be new students there
and how awkward they were in their physical body sitting in meditation posture and how they had to move and fidget
throughout the meditation session and then she'd watch slowly over the weeks and the months
their bodies would adjust and they would find a way to sit and and eventually they would sit in a
very good balanced settled zen posture
they develop a skill slowly over time to cultivate that you know subtle place
so there's so many ways some of these skills we developed are done by repetition over and over and over again
so i'll give you an analogy i've done before i love it has to do with the old-fashioned
people don't have them anymore i think telephone books that some of them are really fat
and they have very very thin paper and you take a bunch of them and stack
them up on the floor and then if you use them as a prop for a yoga posture yoga asana
and and one was at the triangle post and if you give you a triangle pose and
one arm is supposed to reach all the way down to the floor but it can't get there you have your heart your arm reached
down to the top of the telephone books and then every day
you tear off one page of the book of the books so each day it's almost inconsequential
the difference but slowly in a way it's imperceptible to you slowly slowly you're able to bring your
hand closer and closer and closer to the floor until finally you can do the triangle pose touching the floor
so um so the gradual growth the patient growth the patient
developing of skills the cra patient development of these inner qualities
and that support us and influence us that are mutually supportive for us and the world around us kindness love
generosity truthfulness wise speech
equanimity compassion letting go relinquishment
seeing clearly stopping and looking mindfulness itself um
so um so all this can get lend itself
to the idea that you have to be busy there's a lot of doing but the idea of being busy and a lot of
and doing doing doing that is not really a good condition to have that's not a really good influence in this process
and it's not necessarily one of the better skills we want to develop skills of being busy so there's a as we
pay attention to all this there's a self-correcting movement we start recognizing
uh what is it how do we do things how do we engage in buddhist practice and all the elements of it
so that it has a good influence on us so that we're developing good skills in
the process and so this is where we come closer and closer to the present moment also
rather than thinking of the long game that we want to discover the goodness of what
we do in the moment that we do it as well there has to be a good feeling
that oh this is this is nourishing this is supportive this is not stressful and so being
really busy doing too much if you really feel and are present for that experience you can feel oh this doesn't work
so so developing skills
and putting together conditions and to doing those things skillfully
and in a way that uh it provides conditions of ease and relaxation and
and um enjoyment of this life that we're we here this precious life that we have
appreciating this of these your our our role in putting the conditions in
place and developing skills uh it can give a life a tremendous sense of purpose
and value and and um and then it's not such a mystery how spiritual change happens
in fact one of the signs of maturity in buddhist practice is um is a real understanding of how to
work with the world of conditioning and the world of skill building and to have engaged in that for
you know for a long time and slowly slowly something develops and
evolves over time so the benefits that are immediate
and the benefits that come through time and i encourage you from time to time to
really consider the long game and if you do so
then you'll be ready for old age sickness and death and these won't be so frightening or
difficult because you've put the conditions in place and you develop
skills that will support you even through sickness old age and death itself so um
thank you and um so one announcement or uh
so i'm starting a retreat this afternoon a two-week retreat so the next two sundays i won't be here
but i've invited two wonderful uh teachers to come teach and these are both teachers who
have just graduated from their teacher training so they're relatively new teachers
though they've had a fair amount of experience already teaching and they're quite marvelous i just delight
in both of them and and so next week it's devon berry and the week after that is tara molay
who's been here for us teaching before and so i think you'll enjoy them quite a
bit and hearing a different voice and a different little slightly different mindfulness teaching will be i think
will be um you know you'll you'll you'll appreciate it a lot
and then i'll be back in a few weeks and and or i'll see some of you
in the weekday morning meditations we do thank you