good morning
so one of the interesting or very important areas for
meditation and the deepening of meditation or as i like sometimes i think the filling out
of meditation i like the word filling out because the
idea of including all of ourselves going deep sometimes is kind of
bypassing can be bypassing or putting aside things but
filling out that some of the language of
meditation is things language are like being settled and settling all of who we
are or becoming composed or unified
so compose composing ourselves so all of who we are is here in a certain kind of
balance or harmony or uni unit unity unification
and that's difficult to do if we prioritize certain parts of our life
over other parts sometimes we prioritize our thinking
and then we get focused on on
you know focus on the thoughts and ideas and we lose touch with our body and the present the present moment
sometimes we uh prioritize our emotions and uh and everything is seen through
our emotions or by our emotions or felt in the emotional realm
and um and sometimes we can prioritize the body
and in buddhism buddhist ancient buddhist practice the body seems to have been a huge
priority but not as the expense of these other areas of our life
but it's the beginning place of of filling out
of being inclusive of of not getting stuck
in the places we usually get stuck in uh prior where we get stuck prioritizing
and one way to prioritize is we identify with it it becomes the kind of the location in which we live
we live in our thoughts we live in our emotions and as soon as we do that we're living in a partial way
through mindfulness of the body there's a way in which we we learn how to be inclusive of it all
where in a sense the body can hold the emotions the body can hold the the thoughts
but even more than the body it's the fluidity
of experience it's the softness of experience of awareness
in a sense we begin living in awareness where things are soft and open and
inclusive composed unified and one of the ways of doing that is to
be centered in the body so we'll start that way and i'll
try to guide you through a little bit experience or sense of this being composed settled
unified as a means for being calm
so to gently close your eyes
and without much else become aware of your body whatever way your body is now
maybe without even fixing it or relaxing just take a few moments to feel
how it actually is now as if you're doing so for the first time
like meeting a new person and you're just present and taking them in
and then gently there's a way of including your
body more of your body take a few a deep breath
where you feel the expansion of the torso widely globally
and doing that a few times and then with the exhale also
globally settling into this body
gathering the body together as you exhale
deep breath in and then on the exhale relaxing the body
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and then continuing to experience your body globally as you
breathe
as you inhale feel the body globally
as you exhale let your body settle relax
wherever there's tightness and wholeness holding
so
and then settling into just the experience of the body breathing
but for now as your body is breathing imagine the body is like a
like a balloon filled with water a water bed perhaps it
when you it's just this fluid and the whole
balloon moves with the water jostling around some someone touches it and the whole thing
kind of moves and this flu is fluid
so as you experience your body breathing the movements of the body
feel the fluidity of them as if they're water moving
moving water nope in a bag or water bed
and feel how that movement and fluidity
it's kind of a global experience in your body in whatever way that's easy for you
with a settling as you exhale a settling of the water
and the body has a rhythm of expanding and settling
and then rather than prioritizing your body or your thoughts or your
feelings prioritize the fluidity of the movements
in your body and letting the awareness surf on them
or float on them
whatever feelings you have in your body pleasant or unpleasant whatever emotions
you have let them all be included within
the rhythm of the body's fluidity movement
changing
relax into the movement
it could be very very subtle pulsing and vibrating
whatever distracted mind there is as you exhale
let it relax into the gentle movements of the body
so
and as if awareness is floating on the sensations that arise and pass
sensations which may be the fluidity of the sensations in the body that come and go
an awareness that holds it all floats on it all
and what are you prioritizing where are you living at the awareness
your thinking your emotions a particular concern of the body
can you relax the prioritization to open awareness up
to open the body up everything is
included in a kind of openness
that's fluid
and with a global awareness
let it all be present
but let all of it be centered on the experience of breathing
as if the movement begins and ends
with breathing
as if breathing is the heartbeat
of the global experience
that doesn't prioritize anything
includes everything
while being centered on breathing
on the exhale relaxing back into the place where breathing
begins
and if you feel any calm or tranquility
perhaps you can feel it perhaps you can feel the movements of
breathing moving out through that calmness
coming and going through it with a kind of like your
forest bathing in your own calmness
as if you're being nourished nurtured
in a broad inclusive
calmness
that everything occurs within
being settled on oneself
can be calming calmness can be a way to settle on
oneself to be subtle here
in the present moment
and it can be this can be a gift that we bring with us into the world
the ability to be calm and settled with what we're doing
calm and settled in our conversations with others
not rushing on multitasking
but offering the gift of presence to another person
we can do this with our work and our activities and our driving whatever we're doing
we provide the gift with our settled calm attention
so we're really here for this life here for our experience
here for what's around us
and it has an impact others will feel it
the world will feel it in the ways
as we meditate as we come to appreciate the treasure of calmed settled attention
may we learn how to bring that into the world
to bring some of the best qualities of human beings with it
generosity and love and care [Music] wisdom
that thrive in settled calm attention
may this practice be for the welfare and happiness of everyone
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
so continuing with this theme of the week which is calmness
one of the words for calmness or tranquility is some mata
and uh it's s-a-m-a-t-h-a and it's um
often enough in english translated as serenity and it's seen as the partner of
vipassana and vipassana is insight so the inside practice
is partnered with a certain kind of serenity or calmness
that gives power or strength or clarity to the insight
and this samatha this kind of serenity is
associated with concentration and concentration is considered to be one of
the means of getting becoming calm and so concentration is
samadhi is is a process of becoming composed
or unified on our experience and i like to think of it as
begin with learning how to be centered in our experience but with the awareness not narrow and
tight but globally soft and expensive
so that everything is in a certain way included not that we're paying attention to everything and understanding
everything's going on but there's more like the there's a there's a feeling of openness in the body
uh a feeling of openness in the awareness that's not
stuck any one place or is not fixated any one place sometimes
concentration practice is associated with one pointedness which
can be you know just putting the attention on one place but that can be translated into a
stuckness into a fixation on one place which tends to be detrimental to the
person who's getting concentrated the idea is that awareness can be very soft
open even kind of an expansive feeling to it the attention the sense of presence that
we bring and that is so there's a kind of a a
it's kind of like if you
if you have a a big container like a
big jar full of sand and but you at the bottom there's a cone
and the bottom of the cone there's a little a valve and you can turn the valve and the sand pours through
then the sand will go pour in through the middle look from the top the middle falls in first and everything else
follows and so um and so it's kind of like we're we focus maybe
on the breathing but in the breathing we're kind of opening the faucet and everything begins
kind of flowing down through the force of gravity everything's included everything kind of
orients itself towards being here in this experience that can't happen
if we're prioritizing one part of our experience over other parts of the experience
if we're prioritizing our our emotions or prioritizing our
thinking and even prioritizing certain parts of our body or ideas about the body
or for prioritizing what should be happening too much and i like to think of this as kind of
living in emotions living through uh our thinking that where do we how do
we know some people live through certain parts of certain component parts of who
they are rather than living through the totality of who we are
and we do that we're limited and buddhism is the idea of freeing ourselves from those limitations of
being partial sometimes we use language of identification we identify with our
emotions we identify with our thoughts our ideas meaning that we define ourselves by them
i i emote therefore i am i think therefore i am
and i'm in pain therefore i am i suffer therefore i am
so we live in those things we take up a stance on those things we prioritize them in some way
and it's not to dismiss the importance of any of this and sometimes we need to give
caring attention to all these different parts of ourselves but to do it in a way where we don't live in it
we don't we don't uh give over importance to it so we limit
ourselves and so this idea of composing ourselves or unifying ourselves with awareness
so that the sense of presence with the body sense of being here is much more expansive and open to the
fluidity of of change the movements the the aliveness the an animated fluidity
of life from moment to moment that includes all of the above all these things
um so that because we're not compartmentalizing or fixating or in conflict or pushing
some things away and things become settled then the serenity begins settling in
we have an easier time to get um settled on something and we can settle on the breathing like
the sand all gets settled through this faucet maybe
and um that we open this valve we open things just flowing in so we're centered and
everything kind of comes along and is around it and gathers and is part of it but it's not an intentional thing of
gathering in it's more like we're open and relaxed that's why relaxation is so
important in meditation when we relax things have a chance to flow into
the center if the center is breathing it flows into the there and things have a chance to then settle
so there can be a calmness a tranquility a serenity that begins to occur
and i find it interesting that as the greater the calmness the more the calmness has no boundaries
the calmness almost feels like it's uh it extends out into the air the space
around me and with my eyes closed sitting i can't really feel the difference between the
inside and my outside of my body in relationship to the calmness and this idea that calmness begins
feelings like spreads and opens and has space for it all the calmness can hold our sorrow it can
hold our anger it could hold our pains it can hold our joys
it can hold the thinking mind all this has a place
but we're not prioritizing it we're not living in it it can just be there in the fluidity the movement the
the softness of life as it unfolds
so um so samata in that sometimes is to cultivate it
through concentration it might be with some you know
some centering one cell phones one's breathing but it's a centering where um there's an
opening going on so so we you know so on the exhale to
center ourselves on the breathing and maybe with the exhale also feeling that there's also an opening up into the
experience of breathing and then the inhale there's also an opening and receiving the experience of
breathing and and so there's we're centered on the experience of breathing but that
openness that open experience open feeling is one that is kind of like things open up so
everything can pour in the sand of our life so everything can pour in and and um and it isn't so much that it
pours in and fills it as it just pours through just everything has a fluid and
moving and flowing nothing is stuck
the deeper experiences of tranquility are ones where everything is flowing
everything is included everything is kind of allowed it's uh it's um
it's it's process nature it's a dynamic
nature everything is dynamic everything is process unless we fixate it on it or we think
too much about it then we can imagine it's kind of stuck or something
so samatha is very much an embodied experience
and so the ability to begin feeling and sensing calmness in the body
is a important foundation for this deeper
calmness that comes with a concentrated mind a unified mind a mind that knows how to be present
in a steady rooted way here for our experience i think of this calmness little bit as
as the ballast of a boat that the boat might have a keel with it's
quite heavy and um and so no matter how strong the winds goes the boat might tip a little
bit but it comes back to upright so the calmness is the balancer is that
gives us uh lets us kind of move relaxedly with
things and then come back to upright to presence we don't get knocked over
um calmness also sometimes associated with uh just letting being trans uh
being um porous and things because things are so calm
it's almost like the body the mind the heart is just so open everything just passes
right through when there's no calmness and we're fixated on something when we over prioritize or identify with
some part of ourselves it's kind of like putting up um you know a wall almost and life hits it life kind
of reacts to it and bumps into it and you know we have to deal with it but when we're relaxed
enough and don't prioritize or fixate on any one thing then the experiences of life kind of
move right through and now just to move you know just we're poorest to it
this is not to be aloof aloof and distant and disconnected from life
it actually lets us feel a deeper connection a deeper presence a deeper
intimacy that is both an intimacy to ourselves while there's a kind of intimacy with
the world so some of this is some of the deeper
benefits of cultivating calm and tranquility and um and the one that comes
specifically from uh the kind of uh
from meditation the concentration or the unification practices or
parts of what meditation does so um
maybe you can try it maybe you could today you can see how you can
relax any kind of way the mind is fixated or prioritizes anything or identifies with something as me myself
and mine see if you can open up the space open up the space of the body
the heart the mind to be more inclusive in is that creates space within which
things can relax it a little key little
tool for doing this is that giving yourself time
do things with lots of time opening up and making space for
just being open let it be open in time as well give give time
lots of time to your experience to what's happening so that uh this
samatha serenity can
can uh hold you can contain everything
so thank you very much and i look forward to the next talk on
calmness tomorrow