so hello and formally welcome to happy hour to all of you
so for today's practice um practicing menta together
meta for for all beings for ourselves for all beings i wanted to
take inspiration from
what is called the fire sermon
the fire sermon and the buddha and the fire sermon says
practitioners all is burning and what is
the all that is burning and then he goes through and lists
all the ways we experience life in the world
the eye is burning forms of the eye eye consciousness eye contact whatever's
felt etc etc ear nose tongue body and then mind the mind door the mind is
burning ideas are burning mind consciousness is burning mind contact is burning
whatever is felt is pleasant or painful or neutral that arises and contact is
burning burning with what burning with greed hatred and
confusion so i love
that suta and the the teaching that all is burning feels like sometimes our
world is burning burning externally sometimes burning internally
and speaking from california where there are fires literally burning and there's
smoke here today with windows closed with air unhealthy and again situation
in the world situation in the world feels like there is burning there is burning in the world
and of course internally with with what is arising
we're all living through a pandemic all of us together none of us are immune to
the burning of the challenges internally in our lives in the lives of people we
care about so meta meta is considered to be cooling
healing healing waters of metta for a world that is burning internally
externally all that is burning so we offer meta to cool our hearts to
cool our minds and to offer our goodness our cooling
healing [Music] comforting intentions
gifts in any way we can by cultivating our heart
offering this cooling healing loving-kindness menta to a world that is
burning so setting our intention
for offering this healing cooling meta
for ourselves and all beings today and with that let's start our practice
together settling in to our seat
you need to move if you need to lie down
or sit up straighter whatever is appropriate this always will
start with settling in the mind
the body with the breath
riding inviting a settling of the mind
as if it were a snow globe that had been
shaken all the thoughts twirling around
setting it down
letting it all settle
just being breathed just being simply breathed
in this moment not pushing not trying so hard
putting it all down putting down trying so hard not needed
not eat it
just resting moment of refuge nowhere to go nothing to do
taking refuge in the simplicity of this moment with the breath
and if thoughts arise it's okay no need for judgment
seeing them clearly and inviting them to settle
putting down the snow globe again and again letting it settle
with the body with the breath
here just here
putting down what's not needed
putting down whatever is not needed
just here with the breath with the body settling arriving
landing soothing
[Music] calming
connecting with the entirety of the breath
as if you are surfer surfing the breath in this body
just here
now if you like just as we're staying embodied feeling
the sensations of the breath
throughout the body breathing
what if we imagined ourselves being soaked
to cooling waters in the cooling lake
cooling pool inviting pool of water whatever is inviting
cooling calming healing
soothing any fires within
cooling healing meta
this well-wishing body of water this
body of water presenting meta kindness good will care
love
as if our body was inflamed from within as if there was inflammation
soothing cooling waters of meta may i be well
offering us healing
holding us
with care with good will is immersion
see what works best for you
soaking in these magical waters of meta
magical cooling waters of meta
bringing healing to your heart to your mind to your body
soothing calming the flames within
the heart and mind
it's okay it's okay dear it's okay
cooling healing
it's okay
as if the magical waters of metta are
whispering may you be safe to you
may you be healthy
may you be happy may you have ease
and you're receiving receiving
the good will the meta good wishes these magical healing waters
safe
healthy peas
now at any point where you feel
the meta has supported soothed
you sufficiently and the desire comes to share it with others
don't rush this next step and if you need much longer
for meta for yourself in these magical
meta waters stay stay soaking receiving
the good wish the good will the good wishes
whenever you're ready i'll share this with you can always come back you can try sharing it with others
and then come back to yourself and go back to others come back to
yourself why not let's try that
so bringing to mind someone who's dear to you
as if you were holding this gentle gentle garden hose
magical garden hose that has a sprinkle or a magical
sprinkler ever so gentle
the person you have in mind may not even know it
but you share you pour these soothing
healing magical waters of menta your wishes
onto them soaking them with goodness
whatever is burning them whatever is burning
their heart their mind and their body
you wish them well may you be well may you be safe
happy healthy have ease
may these healing soothing magical waters of my good will
or this good will this this meta this water isn't so much yours
you're just sharing it sharing it generously
this inexhaustible supply
of mitten as it soaks them it brings them ease
frees them from the burning of suffering may you be free
from what burns you dear one i wish you well
keep soaking watering them at any point you can go back to
soaking yourself either in the pool of water or turning
the direction of the water maybe covers both of you maybe both of you this
magical hose imagery gets soaked
by the good will the healing soothing goodwill
of matter
in your own time sharing
the healing waters of mental with others
we're near and dear to you and yourself going back and forth as you wish
may you be well may you be free from whatever is burning
burning you may i be well
may i be free from whatever is burning
my heart mind and body
you
now directing directing
the meta wishes healing meta-wishes is
portrayed in the this metaphor
the magical healing waters of meta
to all of those who are dear to you and yourself
sprinkling upon all of you
receiving receiving
then considering
all beings in a particular area maybe a country
or region that are particularly suffering right now
burning an offering offering your mentor
wishes for well-being freedom from suffering
as if your meta was rain in the dry hot air land cooling
moistening may you be well
may you be safe
may you be happy may you be healthy
may you have ease
may you be healed
from the fire burning may you be free from the sorrow the
suffering
offering the rain of meta cooling healing
and offering this mentor and the healing soothing cooling rain to
the entire earth all beings everywhere
yourself included
soothing what's burning
may all beings everywhere
be safe i know things everywhere
be well may all beings everywhere
including ourselves be free
thank you everyone for your practice
so
the world is burning internally externally
an offering offering the wishes of metta offering the wishes of meta the cooling
healing wash wishes of meta internally externally
so the floor is open for any reflections
for any thoughts any questions anything you've noticed anything that came up for you
and again if you raise your hand your zoom hand especially if you haven't shared in a
while that'd be lovely consider it a gift to the sangha to
share your practice what you discovered or your question something that didn't
work and you can also type it in chat if it's typed to everyone i would read your name
if it's just typed to me it will be private and i'll just read the reflection not your name
what was this like for you
did you have fun soaking your loved ones
did was it an image that worked for you as i wait for you to come forth with
what worked what didn't don't say that that actually worked for me was surprisingly fun and
and uh especially one deer being in my life was really suffering
and just feeling that this water was soothing calming and just the burning
they have right now in their heart in their life that ah may this bring you ease dear one may this bring you
um freedom from from this burning
it was another way to connect with the good wishes of meta and compassion for them
patricia says the healing waters were delightful that's lovely
would you like to say more patricia you don't have to but if you do
let's see after oh no i need to change something here
you're welcome to unmute yourself if you wish and if not it's all good
don't feel like you're on the spot bill says i found myself feeling
frustrated that this exercise doesn't directly help other people then i
realize that by transforming ourselves we might be able to help others
yes well said bill well said
right on i especially like how there was a sense of frustration and then oh yes and then
the inside realization coming through beautiful stephanie says yes i loved soaking my
loved ones i appreciate the flexibility of my mindset and heart during this
meditation moving from aversion towards compassion oh beautiful thanks for sharing that stephanie that's
lovely and any of you who've shared you're also welcome to to unmute yourself if you
wish to share more if you like
please melanie says i liked when the sprinkler hose was able to cover both me and my loved one yeah
yeah sweet i like that too
and it's an inexhaustible it doesn't run out that's another that's
another idea here with this metaphor because sometimes we feel like we have to pump it out it's our meta we have to
give it to others and oh i'm already running dry i'm already suffering how can i wish others well it's like hey
it's an inexhaustible supply can cover you cover
the others cover both you and others cover whole continents countries so
just the idea there again the metaphor here i'm trying to bring in which
isn't for us not to feel that it's ours and we're pushing it out which can become hard whereas it's just
good well good well offered good well offered that's one way that this metaphor can
help us not get caught in the sense of scarcity
of goodwill and just share it it's not ours here take it be well may you be well may you
be healed me too any other reflections before we turn to
practice in small groups together
one more reflection a good old friend of mine is in her last days oh and i get emotional and teary
really easily thanks for sharing that one of my best memories together was a day she
brought me to some old baths in london threw me in the cold pool after the
sauna the water images tonight were so wonderful thank you nikki oh thank you
so much for sharing that thank you thanks for sharing that memory
the cool after the sauna being hot and burning the cool refreshing pool and
this dear friend of yours who's in the last days thanks for sharing that with all of us
and marianne says it was like finding a precious gift that i could give to my loved ones yay
lovely beautiful and that's always available and especially this practice is
available if you feel dry if you feel dry and like i don't have anything for myself or to give guess what it's
available turn the faucet the hose any which way you want so it's
always available so dear ones let's turn to practice
in small groups of roughly size three or so
and the invitation is as always we start
with 15 seconds of silent meta for ourselves for each other and then
imagine actually in this case tonight that you have this meta hose
that is you turn into yourself may i be well and then you're soaking the people who are with you in the small groups
just have fun with it tonight don't be so serious just you know you're soaking each other with
with with waters of meta it's it's summer you're having a
what is it a um it's it's a meta pool party um soaking
each other with metal but also tuned into not just the fun of this image but also the good will you're
wishing you're sharing cooling good will with them may you be well dear beings who are in this
small zoom room with me so so with that both with a playful and
with a heart full of meta let's let's engage with each other take care
of yourselves take care of each other here we go
welcome back everyone so we have a few minutes for any
reflections that might have come up i see some smiling faces so
please don't be shy be lovely to hear your voice if you're willing to put it
in the space especially if you haven't shared in a while so yeah let's let's
pull friend to those whom you haven't shared in a long time and pull back those who have
your reflections are important
what did you discover discussing with others with sangha
with fellow practitioners about this practice
kim i enjoyed um hearing all the
the metaphors and the different kinds of dryness and moisture
and [Music] susan was one of her and was in the group she was
she had ridden her bike to a location was leaning against a tree and talked about so you could see the
tree that was quite dry and and talked about moisture coming out of the earth
and terence was talking about feeling feeling dry when he came into it and that what a healing
meta it was what a practice it was and so i really like that dryness and moisture and for myself i
had all kinds of different sorts of moisture ocean and
hose and heavy mist now so it was very enjoyable the
meditation and the group um sweet thanks so much for sharing thank
you as i hear you talk about it actually i feel um then the moisture seeping through
my body and then the heart is like oh so soothing so healing to hear it reflected back
in these different ways thank you for that yeah
lovely lovely yeah
you also named this feeling dry coming in tonight i think you said uh
uh someone came in tonight feeling dry like oh yes yes
it's feeling moistened our hearts feeling moist and it's lovely
other reflections please
oh i see it's seven o'clock maybe not moving thank you maybe that's a lovely
lovely note to end with so oh thank you all thank you for showing
up moisting your hearts softening
and sharing with others sharing with others thank you for your practice may all beings be well may all beings be
free from what's burning inside and outside
[Music]
thank you