oh good morning everyone and welcome to imc and
especially those of you who maybe this is one of the first times you've come together and
with maybe even so many people in a room like this for some maybe but maybe particularly to
come to meditate and to be in community this way so welcome so welcome to everyone who's here on
youtube watching and i i want to reassure you that um even
though there are people here and i'm looking at them a little bit and paying attention to them a little bit more unnatural to do that when you have
a room people i haven't forgotten about you all on youtube
and i have that i have my laptop open here so that a little bit trying to track the chats
and certainly appreciate the uh the greetings that come in
so
many years ago uh i read when
one of the great american saints died mr rogers
um i read an article about him and and said that he was uh invited to the emmys i guess that's
where the rights were when they get awards for tv shows a little bit
so emmys and um and so you know it's a big gala event in los angeles i think
and all these you know big celebrities show up and
and uh he asked um so he got up to give his little speech
and he said you know everybody he everybody here
probably is here because someone cared for you believed in you at some point in your
life let's take a minute to be silent and remember the people who believed in us
and cared for supported us that's kind of partly responsible for us being here
and the article said that the tv producers panicked because what do you do with a minute of
silence on tv and so they just
use the time to scan the audience and uh people were crying
and uh just that simple question and to be cared for
and uh so i bring it i bring it up here this morning because it's possible to care
for oneself and to meditate this assignment of self-care
and rather than saying self-compassion or self-love which is certainly wonderful and
important care is kind of a little more basic and maybe a little bit more accessible
for us we can care for ourselves and it's possible to care for someone you we don't like
if and for the neighbor down the street who we've always had difficulty with because they're they represent
everything that's challenging for your life and you find them on the sidewalk with a broken leg
you know suddenly all your the care you care then and
then you take care of things and maybe you get into the hospital or something but then you come back and you
care for their cat because a person's not there someone has to care for the cat and it isn't exactly compassion it's just
you know you maybe take in their mail or different things and there's a basic care that goes in
to just caring for people so maybe as we said today
maybe we can sit with if you're inclined or if it's easy enough
to sit with care for yourself what would that look like what would it look like to
take a posture and be with your breathing and and uh no matter what arises for you as
you meditate uh even if uh this little exercise evokes the opposite
or some challenge even then what would what it mean what would it be like to sit
quietly peacefully caring in a way that's not complicated some way
that perhaps is settling and quieting and intimate and kind of supports a kind of cozy
way of being here so with that we'll
sit quietly for these next 30 minutes and then go from there
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to take a few moments to consider what care we have
for others in the world around us
our communities friends family
and maybe consider how this path of meditation
that releases us from our attachments
our preoccupations is a way that
allows our care to flow more freely
and may it be that this meditation today
leads to a greater caring
care kindness
loving concern for the world may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free [Music]
[Music]
so so anyway so i'll tell you what
my main purpose or hope through this talk up front
and then then i'll kind of give the talk kind of to support that
and that is for you to reflect on your life
review your life like kind of your autobiography
through the lens of uh caregiving
emotions feelings like so you know emote kindness compassion love
care itself that's a whole thing i'll talk about
and uh you know it's interesting to look at a person's your own life and uh understand it in new ways and see
under proof and new perspectives and it can be quite freeing or opening or sometimes understanding one's life uh
story even from a new perspective sets the foundation for further growth growth in the dharma even
and um and uh it's so you know it's
not that it's maybe that interesting for everyone else but you could for example probably tell your uh your life story
from the perspective of your of your hair and over if you're old enough you know there's been a lot of
a lot of history about how you've been with your hair and maybe and so
so that would make a story you know so different different things so your life your life story from the
perspective of care so in that
regard and then i'd like to talk a little bit about my own maybe as an example of this kind of way of thinking
and orientation and it brings together some of the different things i've been thinking about lately so it's kind of topical for
me to give a talk on this and
they [Music] i don't think i gave a lot of thought to
caregiving feelings emotions motivations until i had been a zen student for a
while and then i uh reviewed little in my life at that point and then i saw oh there
were probably some influences on me and the big one that i associated with uh
kind of being compassionate or the value of compassion was
my mother and uh and i i think one of them made a big impact on me i grew up a little bit in
italy and and it seemed like in italy she was regularly stopping
for strangers who had were in car crashes and that seemed to be a regular thing to
encounter and she even bought a big first aid kit so she'd be ready to help people and
support people who were in car accidents and and she would pull over and stop if you
saw something like that and uh and that was i think that had a big impact on me that's you know she
would have this caregiving instinct for strangers and and help them out
and i didn't realize at the time that it had influence on me but i think it kind of went in by osmosis somehow and had an
impact and and then i remember
both my father and also a little later when i was working for the zen center my
brand new student there and i was working at the bakery both as two circumstances where uh my
father made a donation to some non-profit i think i think it was to save the children or something
and i thought wow people do this thing you know why would you do that and then um and then when i was at the
working present center they used to have a bakery called tosahara bakery and
so over in cole street in san francisco so i used to work there and one day i was up in the office
and the person who ran the bakery as a zen priest was sitting at his table some reason i
was sitting next to him and he got a letter from a local um
association for the coal street association or something asking for a donation and he asked me you know how much should
we give and i don't know i kind of i probably didn't say anything i didn't like what you give money
and uh and he said well so he could well i think we'll do fifty dollars and i
said well you know in 1979 that was
and uh and so this idea that you would do such things was kind of novel for me even though i saw a little bit growing
up as well but it had a big impact it went in kind of deeply and oh this is an interesting way of living
and then as i practice then my first buddhist practice i suffered a lot and
uh and at least the way i understand myself was that at the zen
center there was very little instructions on mindfulness or none and uh and so there wasn't no
instructions for mindfulness of emotions and mindfulness of your suffering the instruction was just to sit there
upright unmoving and just keep showing up for the present moment in a kind of
uh uncomplicated way just be there be there be there and so i didn't you know had any thought
i should do anything different so that's what i was told so that's what i did and so what it meant was i sat with a
lot of suffering and uh and uh
and so that had an impact on me to sit with a lot of suffering and just sit and breathe and not react and not get caught
up in stories and reactivity to it and just feel it and be with it and i felt quite lucky lucky that i
didn't have a lot of instructions of what to do with it because then the suffering could kind of the simplicity of suffering could it
somehow became like a tenderizer for the heart and as something shifted and changed and
i don't know if they're suffering so much but it it they definitely decreased but i it started to work on me and this
idea that suffering can work on you or you know that it has a chance to work on you if you're not trying to solve it and
fix it and you know and get away from it or something but just be with it
and uh but i didn't have a lot of psychological understanding no any either about all this and it was pretty
naive in many ways about my own suffering and uh
and then i started remember i started recognizing suffering and compassion in other people
and uh they just and then i started recognizing compassionate objects there was a
a statue at the san francisco zen center still there that it was positioned before where you
like you'd come out of meditation in the morning and you'd go walk right up against it before you have to make a
right turn it's like like it's right there it's about was five feet tall or so so it's
and um and it's kind of a sinewing kind of narrow kind of thing that
kind of spirals up a little bit and i would see this at the as the embodiment of compassion as like kuan
yin the body of compassion i'll go over there and see this and uh many years later i discovered
that the hardest thought that was of a flame going up and
it probably looks more like a flame than what most people think of as compassion but um what i and then also i started
feeling compassion in the wind when it breathed against my cheek and i would look for find photographs i started
collecting photographs of kuan yin of logitech and just just that's what i did and i
started drawing them and then different things and what i think what was happening was
that i needed more compassion and i was also beginning to feel something like compassion arising in me
from all this sitting with suffering and so i was kind of like tuned into it around me to receive it
but some of the tuning in around me i was projecting it on the situation i remember telling someone that that person is so compassionate
and they look at me you've got to be kidding and so i don't know what i was picking up but you know
the fact that i was seeing it in the statue you know i i i really needed it so i was finding it and getting it
and so i don't know how how enlightened i got in zen but i became compassioned and then and that made a big huge
difference for me that made you huge i'm so grateful for it and at some point
i decided to become a zen priest and it was kind of a culmination of that back then it was called i was it was called a
monk i got ordained as a zen monk and then three days three months later they changed the name to a priest and i said
what what did i just sign up for
i got a whole different feeling of what it was about and i'm happy with the word priest i don't mind it but
you know technically still am and and so
but the reason to become a monk was in fact to respond to the suffering of the world and
slowly over time especially the monastic zen life that um something began to settle and open up
and that it seemed like it was just inherent in me to be not even you can't even say me almost
like inherent within me this responsivity to suffering around me and and that
that's kind of what was wasn't like i chose to respond to it but it's kind of like
this you know that's what you do that's what happens sir and
but they did take this form that i became a zed monk really the purpose of it was
uh i thought that uh the deepest way fullest way i knew to address human
suffering was through buddhism i didn't know anything else and i i wanted to have a i'd feel like
i'd be dissatisfied if i did any other kind of care for the world and i had other ideas in mind i was supposed to go
to graduate school and was going to do a kind of thing that was and um but i felt like i needed to be
able to i felt like i had to for who i am i didn't want that dissatisfaction or that
sense of incompleteness i felt if i didn't try to meet the suffering of
the world address it and the deepest thing i knew how which was through buddhism and it wasn't like i was thinking of
becoming a teacher i just thought i'd you know i would
i thought one image i had was that i would have a little city like a city storefront or something
where i had meditation as a zendo meditation hall and i just had a key and i'd open up i keep it clean i'd open it
up and people come in they'd leave so who knew who knew that i spent a year and a half just
opening it up in the old game and um so um
so then so that so then being ordained the idea was that compassion was my motivating force in my life and that's
how i saw it for myself that that's what i was all about
and then um and for years i kind of still felt that was the case but slowly something began
shifting and i was always kind of late to understand the shift it's only retrospectively
so at some point i i left zen center from practicing there to practice
vipassana first in asia and then here in this country
and and clearly something shifted in the meditation
because meditation no longer became about suffering and about compassion
and um and and as something began shifting and i couldn't tell you what it was
but uh i while things were shifting i became and all along in this process i
became more and more acutely aware of how much suffering there is in the world but what was i think really
meaningful important to recognize is that because i was practicing so much
um there became more and more room in me to recognize the suffering more space for
it for me not to take it personally or for it to touch my own suffering and irritate like but salt in the wound or
something that there was just i was more a greater capacity to be be with
people suffering and pain and not can somehow wilt because of it or be burdened by it
and this openness is gonna and so that i think was a lovely thing to have that and and um
but then i went to practice in asia and and uh and it was kind of there was a dramatic shift that happened there
and uh and where my own suffering was no longer the salient issue
and uh and then the practice opened up in a new way and then something different happened to
me and again this was kind of also a surprise and it had this kind of funny kind of
story maybe funny sad i don't know what was uh i came to practice the united
states and um and practiced it at the retreat center
in massachusetts ims for three i did a three month retreat and that was like kind of the first time
to practice in the with western teachers and to my surprise they started doing
some of them beginning back in some of the meditations with doing loving-kindness meditation
a little guided loving kindness and the first time i did it i thought oh this is great i look like oh this is nice this
kind of surprise but they kept doing it and for the kind of zen student i was
you don't talk to people when they're meditating and and also and also zen is kind of
like a pla you know zen is more stoic and stern and like you you get to the
truth directly and nothing sentimental to kind of make it you know whatever something like that
it's uh that's the way i took it in i'm not saying that's what zen is about but that's how i took it in
and uh kind of silly but i did and uh and so i just
did what a reasonable person would do maybe i was they would teachers or show up and do this guide to loving kind of
meditation i would just tune them out and then um
and so then uh and so that but at some point during that three-month retreat
um this uh wonderful feeling of of clarity and kindness and goodness and
started to well up inside of me and then one day they came to do the guided living kindness meditation and i said oh
that's what they're talking about oh and then i had my own reference for it
it wasn't insincere it wasn't trying to make something happen it was just and then when they did it's like i just
tapped into that and built on what was already there and so then what happened in my practice
in my life was that um and i still kind of called it compassion i didn't know any better
but i think i was slowly was realized i was more motivated by a day-to-day kind of overall with a
mood of kindness and earlier it was kind of like there was a deep underlying mood that i
recognized always there of compassion but as it shifted to kindness as the
underlying mood i realized that that compassion as wonderful and profound as it is
involved a certain kind of a little bit more activated internal state
for me and uh and the kindness turned out to be a simpler uh less complicated or less involved
state i mean the difference here is very little and so i want to be very careful not to
there's no disrespect or devaluing the importance of compassion but i noticed this it was a shift happened and now
that shift happened i still thought it was i was motivated by compassion but in fact over time i realized it was a whole
different sentiment it had to be and it was simpler and sometimes it
would morph into compassion for sure but it was kindness became or friendliness or good will
became the silly and kind of interesting kind of expression of what was happening to me in practice and that kind of felt
like the mood or where i was coming from so that went along fine
for a while and then at some point in the last 15 years or so
i have all these decades you know i could review you know so it's a slow process you know this is not like you know sit
down and you know three day process and get to what i'm saying talking about for me it was like a decades-long process of
really simmering in the dharma and letting it unfold
and then i started noticing that one of the salient features that was happening to me
was that there was a kind of a peacefulness associated with whatever
caregiving compassion kindness goodwill whatever way i was involved in there was a
peacefulness in it where there was no very little inclination
to give into clinging to anything or reacting to anything or being caught in anything or
to define myself with it or try to prove myself like when i was a new teacher i felt like
when people came to see me this is like 30 years ago right so before we like meet with people one-on-one i thought i
had to give them something i can't just have them show up and and uh and not you know have done something
useful for them and you have to show something for myself as a teacher so that's a little bit crazy to have
that attitude but anything's natural enough maybe in the beginning of a new job like that
and there's all this peacefulness settled in and you know i i certainly wanted to support people and meet them
and respond to them best i could but uh and that extra attachment the need to do something
started to go away and there was peacefulness to it all and i thought this was kind of
interesting sometimes i felt that was a little bit uh people didn't like it because people are some people are
really aroused around all kinds of issues of justice and politics and all kind you know even
even sometimes one-on-one suffering someone's suffering and you know they want you to worry for them they want you to kind of
be alarmed or you know that's kind of the language of how we know we care for each other if we're
you know angry or something or upset or something and uh so sometimes i could feel the
tension of being in these situations where a certain expectation of how i was supposed to be
didn't match this peacefulness i had and some people might have thought i was
aloof or i was worried i'd be seen that way but in fact i wasn't i mean i was
certainly given my life over to try to support people in all kinds of ways and do things and that's what my life is
about and um so it was kind of like interesting to discover this
peacefulness or non-attachment as a reference point for it all and and then the challenge of and sometimes
the inner debates so the inner lawyers would come up and even tell me you know gail you're supposed to be a little more
you know upset here or a little bit more attached or something and uh and so i had to navigate that and
wonder about that and uh and so i still felt uh you know i
wanted to care for people and all that and then i started i was started at some point studying the pali canon the
teachings of the buddha much more and in some ways my real deeper study of this early teaching started about
12 13 years ago really kind of spending a lot of time in it
and uh and then a few years ago i was interested in what the buddha had to
say about compassion partly it was so important for me and
and i knew that the word for compassion is karuna many people know the word karuna
k-a-r-u-n-a and uh the um
and it turns out the buddha and these early texts have there's very little to say about it
in fact the only thing he says about it has to do with um
how you how some about how it's related to meditation practice how in meditation you would have
boundless karuna it doesn't even define what it is so we don't even know for sure that it's
supposed to be translated into english as compassion because the if if what we're doing
building on is the evidence from the ancient teachings so maybe compassion is fine to translate
as a translation but but the fact that i was so surprised to see
and but it's not so obvious because some of the translators translate
another word as compassion so when i read that in the old days i used to think oh that's karuna that's karuna
but it turns out that it's a karuna is not the word or the concept that involves everyday
caregiving and the word for that is anu kampa
so the a-a-a-n-u-k-a-m-p-a anu kampa
and in all the circumstances where the buddha is
offering some kind of care to someone else uh it's using this word ano kampa care
and i translate it as care as i said some people translate as compassion
and occasionally you see it translated as sympathy but if the buddha taught he spent you know
40 45 years teaching out of anu kampa so it seems like a very important emotion
because it's kind of the basis of why buddha taught if someone asked the buddha to come and teach for
them or even come to their house to have a meal they would ask can you do it please do
so out of anucampa for me and so the reason why this word is
something different than compassion is that the way that it's talked about in the suttas in the ancient language
is uh it's always in relationship to caring for the welfare and happiness of
others it's never talked about explicitly about suffering
uh you know the people you want people to be alleviated and freed from their suffering
it can include that for sure but it's it doesn't not limited to suffering it's a
broad-wide caregiving uh kind of emotion feeling it's also used in the ancient literature
for a much more ordinary simple kinds of care that people provide
child care providers have care for their children teachers you know outside of buddhism
you know have have an accompanist care for their students
parents have care for their children and
and so you know so what is it now
it was yesterday i think i talked to a friend of mine who has stage four cancer
and then starting treatment now and so i asked him
spend a lot of time in hospitals and stuff and and uh and i asked him
what would you prefer that all these people who are caring for you the nurses the doctors and all that
that they have compassion for you or they have care for you and he said right away oh i prefer they
have care so exactly well i didn't ask him why but um there's something very different
with compassion which is you know based my life on so i don't want to dismiss the disrespect or just diminish it's a
value but it's a particular kind of caregiving and i'm thinking about this as i was
studying this word on ocampa i realized that if a friend of mine went along we'd spend the day together
hanging out and every moment that we were together every conversation
they were expressing their compassion for me like i would start kind of stepping further and further away like you know
you know give me a break but if if they were constantly if there it was a continual feeling oh this
person cares for me there's care i i wouldn't feel troubled by it i wouldn't feel like it's getting too much
or a burden there's a very different feeling to care and to compassion
and so to to over emphasize compassion is the primary way to be with people
maybe misses something and and so this care
that involves care for people's welfare and happiness so you can then you can have that kind
of care for someone who's not suffering you know someone who's suffering
like the buddha met people or practitioners who were
not suffering they were deep in meditation they were filled with joy and happiness
and he would then care for them by offering them further teachings they go further into a greater kind of happiness
than what they're already feeling and so i like this word care so much as
a translation for anacampa because it's a kind of humble
word uh it also has a double meaning in english that uh
it's uh to care for something is to value it and so to offer value have value for the
people you're with or to appreciate them and to and to care
and then the care also means to offer like there's medical care we say or spiritual
care or child care or elder care it's a very common word
and um and uh oh so my friend who was in the hospital he said oh i'd prefer to have care right
to compassion and he said these nurses who are taking care of me they're just like
inspiring by how much care they have they care for everyone you watch them and there's so much care
of what they're doing but i don't think they have come to i don't think they're having compassion for all of us
but they're just going around their job and doing fantastic job caring for people
so i think it's possible to care for people who you don't love
it's possible to care for people because love and compassion are kind of high kind of a high bar sometimes
and so this care thing is a lower bar you can do it for someone who
you know it's just a basic ordinary human activity to care if you allow yourself to be a basic
ordinary human being without preoccupations attachments and being caught up
and then finally this uh in the sutas
the motivation for anukampa they don't they don't talk
much about why what motivates it what's the rationale you would have it it's kind of just assumed that people have it
when people were when some of the buddha's disciples were were fully enlightened he told them to go forth out into the
world for the welfare and benefit for others out of out of care for the world so that was
the motivating force but he just told them to do that or expect it it just kind of assumed
but but there is a few places in the sutras where this word for care
is or is closely connected to um the human capacity
for to have respect
to respect to honor to esteem or to venerate other people
or benefit each other this idea of respect and better veneration is are kind of strong word
but some people in the west talk about appreciating the sacredness of other people and they inherently they say sacredness
or some people use the word in the west of divinity divine in everyone but this anakampa coming not from
suffering uh it's not quite friendliness but it comes from a kind of place of
deep respect veneration so there's something very very uh
honor honor worthy of of each person we meet to have honor and
respect and care and you can do that for people you don't like there are people who are
challenging you know who behave in ways that are you know maybe even
you know distasteful or something and so that's not to
say that that's not you know that was distasteful what the person did but even so there can be this basic care
can still exist so go back to my story when i started reading about this
anu then i recognized it's that oh this is the good i think this concept least how
i'm understanding it that speaks to this more recent change i've had this
peacefulness around caregiving i think that i'm finding it what i'm living from now is this very simple
care that is for me is defined by non-attachment but not clinging
it's just a simple ordinary thing and it can morph into compassion it can
morph into friendliness and all these other all these things but
it has a simplicity to it an ordinariness to it and and uh sweetness to it
that um that just seems like that's what has evolved in it now if i look back
to kindness you know loving kindness or something that seems like a more activated state
and uh and there's nothing wrong to be a little bit activated so if compassion is more activating than
kindness then anakampa then kindness is more activated than anu kampa than care
and and to be able to go about the life without always being activated or
by something or or having to evoke or to make something happen
you know if your requirement is to always be kind you kind of have to kind of gear yourself up a little bit sometimes and
then if the requirement is to be compassionate you also have to kind of like oh how do i do that now and you know what do i have to do and i'm
supposed to be compassionate um maybe um but for me uh you know i am you
know pleased to hear listen to me a little bit this is a personal story so i'm not to want to say that it should be
your way but uh uh but anyway finding this piece this
non-attachment in relationship to caregiving and finding it kind of resonating with this word anu
with with care has been really kind of one inspiring for me and and feeling yeah this is good it kind of
like kind of you know if the lawyers in my mind were
arguing about is it okay to care for people without being attached it's like i got the star witness the
expert witness to come on the stand and then you know made us made the case
that it's okay yes so um
so i knew kampa just so there's movement towards at the care
so that was my story and uh and i told the story for the purpose of hopefully
inspiring you to think of your story and maybe you can even find someone you tell it to
say maybe even the telling of it is not is your discovery process so you maybe
find a good friend who you're willing to kind of stumble along and um but
so what's what's been your relationship to care is it did you have no examples of it growing up and no and cared for
you and which happens to some people it's like the primary background for some people is the absence of it and or
worse and uh and then has anything shifted and
opened and changed and what were the influences on you the impacts on you and
as you as you went through your life and and uh you know what have you learned
over your lifetime about your care your kindness your friendliness
or where have you received it how you've been nourished by it from others and or influenced by others by it
what is your story and whatever your story is
let's respect it let's honor it let's venerate it because your story
and uh and see it as a stepping stone for further growth the more clarity you
have about it then maybe you're ready to kind of
find something more or let it grow or evolve into new ways that maybe wouldn't
have evolved if you hadn't really kind of seen it clearly what what it is
so [Music] those are my thoughts for today
and we have a couple of minutes if any of you would like to
ask a question or a comment you're welcome to do so
another question here is peacefulness similar to equanimity from the youtube
um it's maybe it overlaps a little bit i think
of them as different i think of peacefulness is less complicated than
equanimity yeah i was thinking about empathy
as a way of it's not quite as intense as compassion and it's a way of feeling into
a person another person's state yeah and that that might be closer to caring
for someone yeah yeah it could well be there's a word uh another word that's sometimes translated
as sympathy um in the policy that
often goes together with the care they're they're they're a pair so empathy and care maybe are closely
related
maybe one more and then
so i think something that i've been struggling with particularly you know in the events of the last two
years or so is um exercising compassion for people where
the the root of their sufferings seem is something that i fundamentally disagree with like that
their suffering is due to not being able to engage in their own selfishness for example and it's to a
point that you know especially with so much like polarization and discourse around that that it's extremely fatiguing for for me to
and i feel that the the answer to it seems to be having compassion for those people
instead of yeah responding with more anger but i'm not sure how to go about that i think
it's completely reasonable to not have compassion for some of the reasons people suffer
but the reasons they suffer under the underneath under that there is some kind of suffering
and uh and that it's this it's the it's what's under what underlies it that's uh maybe you can connect to
others like so for example if i'm really upset and sad and i'm here crying and you know
and i've had a really difficult day today and you know gil what's wrong what's happened well
i just didn't win the california lottery today uh so probably you just shrug your
shoulders then it's like what's going on here and that wouldn't elicit a lot of compassion but if you listen to me more
deeply you might say you know what why why is gil interested in the california lottery
and um and maybe he's really kind of insecure or something and i i can maybe feel for his
insecurity is this a idea relevant for you yeah i i do think so yeah yeah so kind
of go listen deeper than the surface
so my friends thank you for being here and for those of you online
uh that uh helen and peter are the hosts for the
uh the host for um the discussion group that happens after
the dharma talks so if you go on imc's website and i don't know if they're going to put it posted there on the chat but on the
imc website uh it's under what's new or it's on the calendar too it's on the calendar where you can see the the zoom link and to
discuss a little bit the talk and just hang out the libido community and
so thank you all very much