i'll continue with what uh i'll give the talk i was thinking about giving and that's been on my mind for a
few days and the topic is the five faculties
but as but for introducing the five faculties i want to read a
story from my little book the monastery within
it says the title is noise and silence
the monastery work leader always appeared peaceful
this was not so unusual among the monks and nuns of the monastery he was unique however
in that he remained peaceful and calm even when the monastery was at its busiest
for example when large crowds of people visited to celebrate the buddha's birthday
if a person was needed to visit the hustle and bustle of the local market town
this was the monk the monastery usually sent when asked how he managed to remain
peaceful he said i entered the monastery for peace and quiet
i spent years in the harried world of commerce and people
i longed for the silence of the monastery it was rumored to have
i was delighted with my first weeks in the monastery the silence was exquisite
however as i settled into the silence of the place i was shocked to learn
how noisy my own mind was the real noise was within
it was the busyness of my own mind that oppressed me not the noise and activity of the world
now it doesn't matter where i go i carry the silence with me
so the part of the noise of the mind
is all the thinking that goes on the swirl of thoughts and images that
goes on in the mind and when those are strong and we are somehow obsessed with it or swept away
in those thoughts and concerns it's almost like losing our life
and when we stop being obsessed and swept along by the current of thinking
it's kind of like getting the life back and for some people meditation is maybe
one of the primary places where they get their life back because in meditation the mind quiets
and there we're not so we learn to let go of our preoccupation with thoughts
are being pulled away in them and the mind begins starts to become quieter
and stiller and it doesn't necessarily mean that thoughts have to go away
but that but that
it feels like there's silence it feels like there is a
piece a piece there as well so the day of silence in meditation
the idea of is the reference point for how i want to
teach today about the five faculties
and um so um the background for this talk
is the idea that when the buddha before the buddha was awakened
he went and studied with two spiritual teachers of his time and they
were kind of meditation teachers or they they had their access to the
truth that they were teaching their teeth there was through meditation but first he learned
um the teachings of these teachers and he learned them well and he became
together with others who had learned those teachings he kind of mastered the teachings
and and he assumed and this is an amazing story
he assumed that he now knew and saw what was true
but he actually he didn't he just learned the teachings but sometimes teachings can be so
compelling and so uh kind of enlightening the teachings that people sometimes confuse
a cognitive understanding of this life with this deeper deeper life that this has to do with a kind of
a more silent knowing a silent uh seeing of what's happening here
so then uh he went to those teachers and he said you know is how do i have access to
really know and see oh really to know and see what uh what you're teaching
and so they explained to him they taught him the kind of meditation practice they were teaching
both of them were kind of meditation practices where you really kind of disappear from this world a
world of senses and experience and one of them is it a meditation state of nothingness where you dip into a place
of tremendous oh nothing nothing is there just absence and the second one talked a little bit
further along that that even the perception of absence kind of disappears
and there's a bit is so rarified so simple so a lack of input on the mind
the mind is very very still and peaceful but the buddha thought this is not
uh this is not freedom and then he had a realization or had a
self-reflection that he had five qualities
that he could rely on to find his way he had faith
usually called faith he had confidence he had courage
he had the capacity to bring attention to his experience and he had ability to be
centered in his experience and he had the ability to be discerning to see clearly what's going on here and
differentiate between what's happening and these are my translation for today for the five faculties usually
translated as faith energy mindfulness concentration and wisdom
and now faith because sometimes it assumes to be kind of a faith in something
like in teachings in a teacher or something um this is not what the buddha had faith
in at this point but rather he had confidence in his himself
and so he was able then to go to meditate and call on this confidence
and he didn't know what the truth was he didn't know what liberation was yet he just knew that
that's what he was going uh pursuing and so the not knowing where this is
going not having a teacher to to accompany him on the path or point
him out the pitfalls of the path and keep him on track he was on his own
so it took courage not just energy but real courage
and then certainly took mindfulness but probably it took you know a real sense of presence with
all the attentional faculties that he had to engage attentively with what's
happening and then the concentration part was to be centered to be one
pointed or one centered really here centered
and then to be discerning now each of these five
could be seen in what i why i started with this this little teaching about silence one reference point for understanding
how to evoke these and support have they support meditation practice
is to evoke them in such a way that they help the mind become silent
to quiet the mind so this confidence is not
to stare us uh stir us up or faith is not to stir us up with beliefs ideas and thoughts about what we
have confidence and faith in but rather a kind of embodied confidence
which allows the anxious mind the planning mind the the confused mind
and the obsessed mind to quiet down almost as if the thinking is not really
needed much what's needed is is the mind to become
still and silent silent from his chatter silence from its inner noise that spins
around so to call on a
confidence to sit here and become still
quiet and to have the courage to do so
the pull and the authority of our concerns the things we're anxious about the things that we're resentful
for the things that we want the thoughts about me myself and mine
these have a lot of authority and people are often quite ready to defend them how important they are and
and how can i be safe how can i find my way in my life unless i engage in these
kinds of authoritative kind of thoughts which just if we engage with them are just more noise
and so to have the courage for in at least in meditation
to not pursue a career not pursue and fix a
relationship not to be worried about the future not to be caught up in what's happened
in the past all those things are appropriate at times there's a time and season for all
those kinds of thinking about the future the past our desires the problems we have in our life
but it takes a kind of courage to not succumb to them to not get sucked
into them but to have the courage to really sit okay now is a time
to be here silent and still and then uh attention
to do so with attention attentiveness an attentiveness that kind of partakes
to the silence so it's not attentiveness that uh is thinking about what's
happening some people confuse mindfulness with with thoughtfulness
and there's a kind of thinking of what's happening in the present moment but an attempt to a silent attentiveness
to enter into that the silence that is not the lack of sounds
but rather its a ability to be more attuned more sensitive to take in
all the data that's happening and then
and then the the support that's being
centered in our experience gives to being silent the ability to
uh to be within our middle of our experience
and find a place of center it could be the object of concentration it could be
the belly as it moves the sensations of the breathing someplace in the body tip of the nose but it isn't so much
that we're focusing like from the control tower onto this singular
place of attention it's kind of more likely of course we're composing ourselves on it
a composure a centeredness some people like the word become
grounded in this and so like all and that from this composure grounded centeredness
is an embodied experience where all of us is here present
and then this discernment and wisdom faculty in the service of silence
in the service of differentiating and seeing oh now i'm getting obsessed with thoughts
now i'm involved with the noise and contributing to the agitation of the mind what is it if i
turn my attention and keep it in the realm of what's quieting and
stilling and the silence what a part of the function of wisdom is
to see and discern and work with the other four faculties
so one way understanding these five faculties is that they are not separate from each
other it isn't like five separate capacities but rather there's a way in which when
the um when what we're doing is uh attentive
a silent attentiveness they actually are five facets of the
same jewel the jewel of stillness the jewel of silence the jewel of kind of peace
and so it's possible in meditation to go through uh kind of like a checklist
and check in with oneself where is my confidence
and to you know evoke it if necessary but don't
evoke it with thoughts and ideas but where is there an embodied feeling of
confidence that allows something to be still and quiet
and you know embodied feelings are not thoughts
and so they don't partake of the world of chatter of noise
but to feel the silent quality of embodiment an embodied sense of
confidence maybe a strength that's there
and then uh the embodied quality of courage
so not talking yourself into being courageous
being strong in your dedication but but a courage
to allow yourself to be still allow yourself to be silent
and this is probably takes a lot of courage because sometimes the forces of
concerns that we have are important sometimes they're
they have tremendous power and strength themselves so much so that if we try to sit still
and sit quiet we might get very restless anxious angry all kinds of things can happen
that because we're up meeting and confronting these deep kind of operating
systems or conditioning that that sometimes have been formed over a difficult lifetime
but what is the courage that allows us to sit still and quiet
and i love the fact that courage comes from the french word heart curl and that it not only is it courage but
maybe courage comes with or with compassion with heartfeltness
with care and then attentiveness what's the attention
that is left or that which has a chance to shine when
um we're still in quiet if we're not distracted by thoughts
if we're not busy talking to ourselves how would attention appears
it's kind of like if the curtains have been pulled we don't see outside and then if we pulled the curtains what
do we see outside how's the weather changed and what do we notice
so uh this silent attentiveness
is the attention that is left when the mind is silent
and rather being so much something that we have to apply and do do the mindfulness
it's more of a allowing of that attentiveness the natural attention
whatever the attentiveness is for you at any given time when the mind is allowed to be quiet
enough still enough receptive enough to just for the attentiveness to surface and be there
it's very hard not to be attentive not to be aware not to know what's happening
if the mind is quiet and still and alert and that's why the courage and the
strength the confidence brings that alertness
and then the centeredness that provides stability that provides steadiness
and and what is the steadiness stability centeredness groundedness
that you can feel your way to when the mind starts becoming quiet and
still and um and then the discernment again they're
recognizing they're keeping the attention noticing these things so going through the checklist and saying oh
here's my confidence here's my courage or my strength
here's my attention this is attentiveness here is
stability steadiness centeredness and here is the discernment the
understanding the seeing clearly and perhaps in going through that
rather than thinking of each of them as being separate they're each part and parcel of this quality
of attentiveness a quality of it's all kind of one big package there's one thing
so a jewel that has you know five sides and depending on what
side you're looking at you see a different quality so they're not these the qualities are
not distinct practices but they're
things that are there when we are stably attentive
here it's kind of like if you um
maybe you know uh if you've been on a train for a long long time and shaking on the train shaking on the train and
you know you have to kind of get your balance all the time and then you come out of the train and you're no longer cooped up and you're no
longer on this moving vehicle and you open up onto the you know maybe it's a
a train stop in some rural place where open skies and vast fields
and you come down on the and you're and you just it's so good to be now on solid
ground and and maybe that sense of stability and solidness
and space and aliveness and attentiveness is all one thing
it's being it's we're experiencing it all at once it isn't like we're uh
developing each one of them by itself so the buddha before he
when after he left his teachers he called on these five qualities that
he had to support him in sitting still and quiet
and and delving deeply into um his you know the realms of freedom of
letting go of being here and and seeing clearly and knowing clearly
what this lived life is and i think of the buddha's liberation as as giving him
life and and if we get caught up in too many thoughts and preoccupation we kind of
lose a life in the dhammapada it says this kind of to paraphrase it wildly
that um to spend too much time distracted and obsessing in thoughts
for it can be as if we're already dead but to really
show up and be attentive is to never die
something like that so in these last minutes of the sitting of this talk what i'd like to do
is to suggest we do a short maybe five minute meditation
and and i will name each of these five faculties
and see if you have any reference point for how each of these faculties
each of these sides of the jewel can support you
to become quiet a kind of inner silence
it doesn't have to be 100 quiet of thoughts but a kind of silence that allows the
thoughts to be there without you being obsessed it might not be that you have
direct access today but to kind of feel in and imagine and
maybe something some point in your life you something happened or some contact to these things that can be a reference
point for you about how these five faculties support you in becoming still and quiet
so if you're comfortable with with it you can close your eyes
and if you are sitting you might sit up a teeny bit a little bit straighter than you
are especially if you're you know
listening casually on the couch or something sit up straighter because
you want to find a way some this is an embodied practice we're doing here
where the embodiment of these qualities is what supports the silence
if we have to think about them then maybe we get more noise
and as you exhale for next three exhales allow yourself
to relax alert and relax they're going to settle
in quiet down
and then to
hear these words the the names for each of the faculties
and maybe not think about it so much but feel your way
is there some embodied quality that someplace in your body where these qualities live
or some way you associate with bodily feelings
that if you center yourself on them they support more silence
quiet
so the first is confidence
is there any confidence already in you
confidence in the in your capacity
for a few minutes to just sit to be still
to be quiet
the second is
courage
is there a courage to show up for what's here
to be present for this experience now your embodied experience
a courage which is calming
steadying
a courage that helps you become more embodied
here and now
and as you enter into the world of inner silence
stillness is there quality or
form of attentiveness
which is part of that silence
that is part of the stillness
that's not something you do but something you become
attuned to attuned to
quiet still attentiveness
and then there's a quality of being centered
steadiness stability
where attention is centered in the midst of your life midst of your
body
is there kind of a centering
that is part of the stillness part of the silence
that enhances the silence of now
and then your ability to notice confidence
courage attentiveness
centeredness that is discernment
maybe a silent recognition silent
attunement
and maybe these five qualities
make a part of the whole make part up of the whole experience
of sitting here with an inner silence stillness
and peace
and then to end this meditation
you can take a few long slow deep breaths
feel your body more fully
and when you're ready
you can open your eyes
[Music]
so thank you
and if you found this interesting the five
faculties it's one of the kind of foundational
teachings about these inner inner capacities we have that can
support meditation you might find it interesting to time to time to go through
them systematically and i've done it sometimes by on each breath i do a different one
first breath confidence strength or car
courage attentiveness centeredness and then discernment
and just kind of go through and there's something about having a little task that is self-esteem and focusing
and instance quieting and maybe you'll come to appreciate
your capacity for inner stillness and it's a stillness you can carry with you wherever you go
it doesn't matter how noisy it is around you because you you carry the stillness inside
so thank you very much for this time and then one announcement
and that is that um
you know i think that probably many of us have been moved by many of the
serious difficulties existing in the world right now and i thought it'd be very nice for this
youtube community and people are watching sharing and with these teachings for so long and
joining together and practicing together and you know i often end every meditation except today
every meditation with a dedication of merit or expression about the value of
of uh allowing the momentum of the meditation to go into
living a life that benefits the world around us so one way that we can do that if you're interested in is i thought
collectively to make donations to help the people of haiti a country that has been having
challenges for years and years and the donations will go to partners in health
a wonderful non-profit that does health care in in haiti and they do it at grassroots level
and so they really go out there and into the towns the villages work with the grassroots medical care
teams and nurses and people to make sure that it goes to the people who need it and um it's a they have a quite an
extensive network in in haiti so it's a great organization to support and you can certainly go there directly
to do it yourself to the um i think it's um
pih.org is the website or it's also be nice if you want to do
it through imc and so what we're doing is uh friday saturday and today
is that any donation that goes to imc whether it's to me sometimes people make
teacher donation or it goes to imc general fund that
that can will will turn right around and donate it to partners in health and all
of it will go that way and um and the way to make that donation we don't have a special haiti button
you just you just have to go into the donate button and and uh and then they'll see a win there would be
different options on the donate page and one of them will say imc slash audiodharma
and there's a window you type in how much you want to donate so that's the place to put it and as i said that
that'll go if it comes in today it will go to haiti to partners in health and i just got
delighted by this idea that maybe our community has been together for some some of us
for so many you know for so long of the pandemic might have a little project like this
so um if you'd like that's available and um and hopefully now we're on track with
the with
you know our internet service here at mc and i apologize for those of you who you know found it confusing or difficult
to not connect today because of the the internet service provider was down
so thank you very much