so good day everyone
and welcome to our meditation time together and beginning of the week
and as a very brief overview of this practice of mindfulness of breathing
it begins with a training in attention and in a sense attention or
awareness sits at the middle of this practice
and that establishing this attention this mindfulness then uh and helping establish it more
consistently more thoroughly more fully
that awareness is centered on breathing and breathing stays at the center of
tension and breathing attention on breathing stays at the center and as the capacity to stay more in the
present moment more continuously with the breathing then either
intentionally or as a byproduct of that settling of attention
the attention begins to expand and open up to include more and it includes then the body
and the feelings of the body and eventually the mind and there's a kind of a natural order to
it that kind of moves outwards all along we're staying with the breathing we're
keeping breathing at the center it's like having a a home base or having a
secure place from which to be free to not get wrapped up in things cotton things and to stay with the
natural rhythm of breathing where we have to let go constantly and and accept the new in-breath and let go
of the old breath we're learning to kind of keep the mind the heart relax soft
free as we begin to open up into areas of our life that might be more difficult
and we're more likely to get caught in and entangled in so the continuity of saying with the
breath is a way of having an effective attention to the rest of our minds and the rest of our
being attention to the body being centered in the body makes it easier to be attenti
attentive to the mind and so forth and so with this week we'll begin with
uh moving into more more closely into
aspects of the mind and so to begin
to uh establish oneself in your place of meditation
really take a few moments to really feel maybe sway back and forth rock a little bit
to really feel the contact where your body is supported
from the pull of gravity and to be in that contact in a way that feels
supportive and solid
and then to gently close the eyes
and because attention and intention can be closely related
it's helpful at the very beginning to do some intentional breathing just for a little bit not the whole time
not really loud or anything but just a way of beginning to orient oneself to the breathing
and beginning to let go of other things so very gently maybe
let yourself breathe more deeply maybe three quarters full
don't you have to fill your lungs entirely two-thirds full three-quarters full
whatever feels kind of easy for you to do but to take a fuller breath than usual
but not too much and then as you exhale
exhale slowly not too slowly but just exhale slowly
so the exhale is longer than the inhale
and as you inhale a little more deeply fully let the attention let that filling of
the lungs and also be kind of a feeling of attention
in different places of your body where there is tension
in the long slower exhale let that be a draining of that tension
so letting your attention roam around your body as you breathe in
filling awareness into places of tension or holding
and relaxing as long exhale
especially it can be useful to soften the shoulders
and the belly so the belly hangs out tanks forward a
little bit forward and maybe down
and also as you exhale
maybe there could be a global relaxation of the whole body
and then continuing with taking an in-breath which is maybe a little bit
more full than usual it doesn't have to be two-thirds full or
three-quarters full just a little bit more and with an exhale that's a little bit
more intentionally slow and long just a little bit
and then begin to count your exhales up to ten
and as you count one two the different for each one number for
each exhale
maybe you can say that number in the way that you would delightfully
and happily say the word yes to something
that tone of voice softly quietly but kind of an uplifting
happy intonation of one one
two and if you lose count no worry just
start over again at one and doing this counting is a way of
beginning to settle the attention down into the experience of breathing
and the counting is a way of giving the thinking mind something to think
so the rest of your thinking can become quieter
can fall away
uh and then if you'd like you continue with the counting
but let the breathing be now really natural
or you can let go of the counting and as you breathe
feel the whole body as you breathe in whatever way the global experience of
body is easy to experience it doesn't literally have to be all of
it just as globally as is available
maybe as if breathing is a massage that moves through this global body
and as you experience the global body become aware also of any
thing that's pleasant or enjoyable
that comes from doing the meditation and it could be very mild
sometimes in meditation there's nothing but if there is
breathe with that include that in the breathing
the breathing that moves through the global body
breathe with the pleasure the enjoyment
feeling a present moment well-being that encourages the mind to become
quieter thinking less
and more able to experience what's happening here and now in the
body breathing
breathing with the contentment of the body
the calmness
and then as you're breathing now on this basis of being rooted in your
body maybe feeling some well-being
also now become aware of the sensations associated with
the mind with the activities of the mind
in particular with thinking so there might be some sensations of
tension or pressure contraction
maybe an ache or maybe it's agitation or excitement
or maybe the mental activities is characterized by some emotion or mood
whatever sensations characterizes the mind
how the mind is active and involved let it completely be that way
no need to make it any different but let that be known
as you breathe with it stay rooted in your breathing
and in a simple easy way know the sensations connected to the
thinking mind
breathing through those sensations
staying rooted in your breathing breathing with the sensations
of body and mind being unconcerned with the details of
what you're thinking or what you're feeling any concern with the
why just for these simple minutes
breathe with the sensations the physical sensations of thinking and
feeling and emoting as if those sensations have complete
permission to be there and you just breathe with it
instead of thinking about or fixing anything with
mindfulness of breathing is just to breathe with what's here with a kind of intimacy or closeness
a calm careful willingness to just breathe with what is
here trusting that that's enough
for these few minutes just breathing with the sensations of bodies sensations of
mind
and then as we come to the end of the sitting and turn our attention
to the world outside of us ourselves
one of the profound things we can do for others
is to accompany them and if we learn to accompany ourselves
just breathing with our experience allowing our experience so whatever it
might be to be there
to unfold itself the way it wants to unfold but just accompany it
maybe it also teaches us how to accompany others without getting tense
or activated
to be able to offer a kind supportive presence
that allows others to relax cause others to be themselves
it allows others to be more attuned to themselves
so that they can move to greater health
and may it be that as we end this meditation that we dedicate the benefit and merit
of this practice to accompanying others
our goodness our calmness
our friendship
without being too complicated or
too ambitious about what we can do for others company it can be one of the great gifts
and as we learn to accompany ourselves may we better accompany others
with the wish the aspiration that all beings may be happy
all beings may be safe
all beings may feel respected
beings may be peaceful
and that all beings everywhere may be free
you