okay well I'm thinking that we should go ahead and get started according to my clock it's on
the hour so why don't we just start right away with the meditation and we'll
continue on um after that with our list of one so settling in finding a spot to
sit allowing yourself to ease into the Mind state of
meditation maybe taking a couple of long slow deep breaths and on the exhale just
allowing the body to settle more deeply into
itself so finding a natural feeling sitting posture or maybe lying down or
standing if you're comfortable doing so you can close the
eyes maybe softening a bit softening the face the
head shoulders letting them drop
down through the belly and the arms and legs just inviting a posture that's
upright and also
relaxed inclining the mind and the body toward each
perhaps allowing the attention to just naturally rest onto the sensations of
breathing in and out just to give the mind a simple
experience to connect with that's in the present
moment even if the mind mind is busy or if there are some emotions present
that's all fine we can just allow those and also sense the breath in order to
give the Mind something to rest with
and then inviting into your awareness a sense
of confidence in the process of
meditation so it doesn't have to be a large movement of mind maybe just
remembering that you do this because you know it has some good effects
letting this simple confidence or trust or faith be the foundation
and today we'll primarily be looking at our mind in this
meditation so in the realm of the mind there's kind of two things going on
there's how the mind is or what the content of the mind
is and then there's also how we are paying attention to that you know how is
the quality of the awareness that's observing that or being with
that and we'll actually start with how it is that we are attending to
our mind
so you might just notice if there is certain flavor to the way we're paying
attention is it tight is there wanting or not wanting sense of striving or a sense of
criticism
so I'm going to just offer three common flavors that we might
have that can color the mind and a
possible way to balance that out just so that we can kind of hone the
way that we're paying attention so it may be that we have some
degree of ill will in the mind you may be irritated about
something in the in our household this morning
or dreading something that we have to do later
some way the mind is in a little bit negative
State and sometimes we meet that by wishing it weren't that way so we add
kind of more ill will onto the ill will so the invitation is
to explicitly include a sense of warm
Acceptance in the mind maybe at first what we're accepting
is that the mind is in a state of ill will at least we can start with
accepting that and that's okay because it was
conditioned there were the conditions for it that's why it's
there and then maybe we can even accept what it is that we're a little
irritated about okay yeah we have a certain thing going on in our
relationship or something that needs to be done at least for now for this
meditation we can just include that except that part of the mind that part of our
life maybe the heating isn't working okay
another very common flavor in our mind that can color how we pay
attention is a sense of self-criticism or
self-doubt am I doing it
right am I
okay are we everyone else is more mindful than
me so this is also very common normal in a
sense and I would invite sense of respect as a natural
counterbalance you are sitting at this
moment that's pretty big deal you can respect that you made it to
the cushion or the chair you made it onto this live stream or this
recording right there is something worthy of respect
so just a little smile or
even wanting to
meditate you're engaging in a very beautiful and Noble
practice and all the other stuff about how we are in life how we made that
mistake we could think about that later maybe for now it's just really good to
be sitting here
maybe feeling the breath in and out again inviting KN through the
body and then a third flavor that we often carry in the
mind is a a kind of
striving so wanting to be more peaceful we wanting
to be really present wanting to get
concentrated so in a gentle form of course it's good to to wish these things
for ourselves but there's a way in which the
very wanting of them can bring a certain tightness into the mind we can feel that actually when
we're attuned to the mind so the natural counterbalance is to
invite continue to invite ease into the mind
a little bit like those um toys where you put your finger into it it's kind of
a woven woven toy and when you put your finger in if you try to pull it
out it just tightens around the finger and to get it out you actually have to
push Inward and then gently remove the finger
so there's a way in which pushing just binds us up even more and it's actually through ease that
the mind can settle so there's really nowhere to go
nothing that needs to be done right now
so this is something that can be done at the beginning of a Sit is to notice the
attention the way we're being attentive and invite acceptance to
counter ill will respect to counter self-criticism
or self-doubt and ease to counter striving
I may not need to do all of them but I wanted to offer a whole
spread I actually consider these three acceptance respect and ease to be
different facets of meta different aspects of how we can
love
so just resting for a moment perhaps returning the attention to the breath
so now that the the way that we're paying attention is fairly
balanced we can look a little bit more carefully at the natural flow of what's
in the
mind so we might check if even now there's a sense of sensual
desire in the mind
or there may not be and then we feel what it's like to
have a mind that's not particularly influenced by sensual desire
there's no need to change how the mind is since we have our clear balanced
attention we just notice what it's like to have or not have desire in the mind
and we can do the same with any sense of anger or irritation or ill
will just looking with a balanced
attention what it's like when that flickers through the mind oh this is a
mind that's influenced by a Moment of
irritation or if that's not there oh this is what a mind is like when it
doesn't have any irritation in it interesting
interestingly this can also be done with
delusion we might think oh there's no way to see
delusion by its very nature but actually we
can we could see if the mind is busy with some kind of story that we
know isn't really true we just say oh
okay there's some delusion present in the mind
or if the mind's a little fuzzy or maybe it's not maybe it's quite
clear feels balanced and then we say okay this is a mind that is not strongly
influenced by delusion right now
and we can also notice the degree of concentration in the
mind is the Mind fairly well
gathered steady in the present
moment does it feel like an unstable molecule ready to fly apart at any
moment scattering off into its own thoughts as soon as my voice isn't
present and that's just one more thing to notice
oh this is what a scattered mind is like or this is what a fairly gathered mind
is like
it can be quite empowering to realize that we can simply observe how the mind
is and that's perfectly good
meditation in the words of aan sumo WR now it's like
this
e
e e
and there may be times when we observe our mind and we notice
that it's not particularly influenced by sensual desire or greed at this
moment and it's also not particularly influenced by hatred or ill will at this
moment nor does it seem to be strongly diluted
at this moment it's possible after a period of
meditation the mind is in in a state like
that given that liberation of mind is
said to be the absence of greed hatred and delusion
such a mind is somewhat close to
liberation of course we may have those Tendencies still working in the
mind but it may be that at this moment your mind is relatively
free we can appreciate that
realizing that can deepen our
confidence so it may be that freedom is a relatively simple thing
something we could carry in our heart throughout the
day a place we could return to rest throughout the day
[Music]
okay so first today I'd like to share a list that I
received this week because it relates uh to our our countdown theme if you
will so this is um The 12 Days of Christmas Buddhist
version on the 12th day of Christmas my true love gave to me 12 links
arising 11 arahant laughing 10 Perfections growing nine deavas
dancing Eightfold Path a leading Seven Seas
seeing six doors as sensing five Training
precepts Four Noble Truths three precious gems two wings of
Awakening and a Buddha Neath a bow tree I thought it was pretty
good so um that takes us then today to our list of
one um I don't know how unusual this one item is but I can say that it's not
clearly defined uh anywhere in the sutas in kind of an analytical way and yet it
is incredibly important and so that is the word that is often translated as
mind or sometimes as heart or sometimes as heart mind and the word is
cheetah cheetah and it is to the degree that the terada teachings say it this
way um it is what gets liberated so it's not that you are going
to get liberated uh but your cheetah might your heart might get
liberated so this language of what I like to call all the Primacy of the mind
is very clear in the sutas so I'll read from quote from the
Buddha I do not see any other single thing that brings such woe as the Mind
cheetah that is Untamed uncontrolled unguarded and unrestrained such a mind
indeed brings great woe I do not see any other single thing that
brings such happiness as the mind that is tamed controlled guarded and
restrained such a mind indeed brings great
happiness so I don't think we need to see this in a restrictive way but more in a sense of not letting the mind run
rampant over our own heart and others so we see that it is about the
mind um the Buddhist teachings emphasize that the key is right here in
the mind or the heart and how the cheetah is strongly influences the
amount of happiness or suffering that we have in a given moment this is also stated up front in
the right in the first two stanzas of the dapada so all experiences preceded by
mind led by mind made by mind speak or act with a corrupt mind and suffering
follows as the Wagon Wheel follows the hoof of the ox all experiences proceeded
by mind led by mind made by mind speak or act with a peaceful mind and
happiness follows like a never departing Shadow so it's relatively simple um not
easy to do but relatively simple that if we have peace in the heart then What
comes forth from that is somehow related to
happiness for ourselves and others so where can we learn more about
the chetah and how it fits into the path it's effectively threaded everywhere
throughout the teachings the word chetah if you search for that there's you know many many instances of it um but maybe
the most prominent place where it's stated directly is right in the foundational text on the cultivation of
mindfulness the Sati patana suta so there the Buddha identified the chitta
as one of four areas of experience where we can establish
mindfulness so it's um worthwhile to look at our mind as we did in the
sitting so I think it's it's noteworthy that we can observe our mind through the
instructions of this which I'll talk a little bit more about in a moment we can
observe our mind as a set of Shifting changing mental qualities now that's
what we're that's what we see when we're mindful of the cheetah rather than say an individual
experience of I you know there isn't just one thing going on in the mind
there isn't just one one Experience One self that we could point to and this is
actually quite profound although it may not sound that way but the the instructions in this
establishment of su and the establishment of mindfulness are simply to observe a series of qualities in the
mind and notice whether they're there or whether they're not um and they are some of the ones
that we looked at in the in the sitting so for example uh sensual desire or
sometimes it's translated as lust we just notice is that present in the mind right now or not is the Mind
actually says something like is the Mind influenced by it at this moment or not
and the same for hatred and the same for delusion those are the three kind of
overarching difficulties that we have in the mind but we're also then supposed to
notice if the mind is uh contracted it's kind of small and contracted or if it's
uh scattered and Broad uh the Mind feels different at different times doesn't it
sometimes it feels very narrow uh focused um sometimes it feels uh
scattered or broad sometimes it feels um elevated kind of lofty in a sense and sometimes
not so much um we're also supposed to notice if the mind is uh concentrated
you know in the sense of whether it is gathered and um
yeah kind of organized or is it uh unconcentrated scattered flipping around
to different things and interestingly we're also supposed to notice if the mind is liberated or not liberated at a
given moment so that's something that we can detect also I don't see a difference between
noticing these things on or off the cushion you know we can sit and you know
when we're sitting peacefully quietly we have maybe a little bit more um Clarity
in how we can Precision in how we can observe the Mind from moment to moment
but we can definitely observe it also in daily life while you're cooking or
cleaning or even with enough practice while we're talking we can observe how
the mind is whether it's leaning towards something whether it's leaning away what what emotions are coming up um and the
instruction in this suta at least on my fulness is just to know just to know how
it is with no judgment see how the mind is there's a
certain importance to you using modern language to taking data about our mind
you know noticing how does the Mind get upset when it is angry what does it feel like instead of immediately saying oh
the mind has anger I'm not supposed to be angry I'm a spiritual person I'd better quickly do some meta practice to
eliminate at that anger U there's a little more leeway in this suta where
you know as long as we're not acting on the anger like it says in the DAP versus
we act on anger then then yes there will be some suffering but if we simply are knowing that the mind is in an angry
State that's important we can learn what it's like what does it feel like U
what's the what are the consequences internally of having that so it's important this is kind of a data taking
EX exercise uh to know about the moods of the Mind the flavor how things come and go it includes the emotional tone of
the mind it includes the cognitive tone of the mind and then also once we see these
qualities the suta ask asks us to observe them arising and passing away
and now on on the one hand we see how the conditioning of the mind works we see what conditions lead toward certain
states of mind and what conditions lead toward more peace states of mind and also at a just a fundamental level we're
learning that mind states are impermanent you know there's there's no mind state that has persisted since the
beginning of your life and probably so not since the beginning of today so we see that all these things
are coming and going and it's it's um important to uh have the process of
beginning to disidentify with the Mind beginning to see it as ah conditioned influenced by different things this is
from anali's book on Sati patana sustained contemplation of the
mind will expose the degree to which what one takes to be one's own mind is
in fact influenced by external conditions realizing the impermanent and
conditioned nature of the Mind leads toward nonattachment and nonidentification so
it's interesting right it is in a sense our own mind it's not somebody else's mind and it's a huge influence on our
experience but we see that actually um we have a lot of conditions that have
come into it from the culture from our family from our experience from our upbringing is it really ours
really um some of us are with uh family at a time of year like this and don't
you see where your habits come from If You observe your relatives so you know
um it's something that we can uh See Clearly as having a lot of different influences coming in so interestingly we
we do observe the mind but we also cultivate the mind the is to be cultivated along the Buddhist path it's
important to it does change over time and we can refine it we can hone it we can elevate it we can um yeah we can
refine it and interestingly these two tasks of observing the mind and
cultivating the mind are similar um simply because mindfulness has a way of
enhancing what is wholesome and diminishing what is UNH wholesome it's kind of the magic of mindfulness so
interestingly the cheetah develops or refines by seeing its qualities and by
also seeing what is not present so it's interesting that we're supposed to see what's there and what's not there
and once we've seen this clearly um the only maybe the only clear instructions on what to actually do with the mind uh
we can see in in the ananti Su on mindfulness of breathing we are said
that it said that we should Gladden our mind so to the degree that we can we should influence it positively and then
we should also um work on concentrating the mind I'm having some degree of some
some presence in the mind and then eventually this will lead to liberating the mind I don't think we have to do
that exactly so we observe the mind we try to have some kind of positive
influence on it so for example during the sit I asked us to bring in our confidence in the practice our
confidence in the process of the path and then we gather the Mind somehow and
you know try to kind of keep it in the roughly in the present moment but that's kind of it with the mind of course
there's infinite detail detail on that in suas so many practices we can do but I think at a broad level that's it we
strengthen the Mind through all of this and a strong cheetah is linked with the ability to stay with uncomfortable
experience and hence be able to penetrate through various habit patterns
essentially what we're doing is becoming free of the mind's conditioning so that the mind is able to be present even
though it has all these influences from our family from our culture Etc
so this all of this maybe could be called maturing the mind a few days ago I talked about a list of four uh
qualities of mind that we cultivate and that we emulate in others and the kind of collective term for those four was
mature conduct you might remember so we're maturing Mind through all this
observation and this has an impact on us of course but also on our
relationships um you know the more free we are of all the habits and patterns and reactivities that have been put into
our mind the more present we can be for others the more likely that our response
is going to be Compassion or wisdom or love something that's in the realm of
Freedom rather than anger reactivity control manipulation Envy greed the
other things that we do so when we're less stuck on our stuff we can meet others where they are unruffled on um
and be helpful to them so the free mind is highly available highly responsible
highly responsive responsible also and so it's compassionate it's
attuned and so then you know what is the fruit of all this cultivation there's a
wonderful term in the teachings chto vuti liberation of mind which is one of
the qualities of an nun but we can we can feel it too anytime the mind is relatively free of greed hatred and
delusion there's a nice image from the teachings let me just read
it just as if there were a lake in a mountain recess clear limpid and
undisturbed so that a person with good eyesight standing on the bank could see
shells gravel and Pebbles and also shs of fish swimming about and resting so
too a meditator understands this is suffering this is the arising of suffering this is the cessation of
suffering and this is the path of practice leading to the cessation of suffering so just as if we're looking
into clear water and seeing everything that's there the shells the fish swimming around uh when the mind and the
heart are clear aware present we can just look at the contents of life and
see okay that one's Dua there's the reason it's happening there's some clinging this is freedom these are and
these are some of the qualities of the path we see clearly in experience the four noble truths and that allows us to
navigate quite easily away from the suffering and toward the end of suffering
so as we go throughout our day see the Mind clearly know its qualities know
that there's suffering know that there's the end of suffering be with whichever of those we can hopefully leaning toward
the end of suffering we can do it in the kitchen with our relatives we can do it while taking a walk while
sitting so remembering what the Buddha said at the very beginning I do not see
any other single thing that brings such happiness as the mind that is tamed
controlled guarded and restrained maybe we would just say simply the mind that is well observed clearly seen such a
mind indeed brings great happiness so thank you all for this week
of countdown and I wish you much happiness thank you