so good day everyone and welcome
and it said that vipassana practice is simple
it's easy what's difficult is remembering to do it
and so here at uh during a meditation period
we are remembering to do it over and over again and to help this
idea it might be significant to
separate out remember and to remember
to bring the members back together into the field of awareness so that all
of us is included all of us as here and i know of no other way that all of
us can be in some way complete or have a feeling
of wholeness or complete completeness that all things are kind of feel like they're included and they're
all that we are and or at least we know that we are the wholeness of us without this
remembering without being aware so we we remember to be aware we remember to
be present and we train that remembering
with the breathing there could be other focuses for mindfulness practice but a classic one is to not just simply
stay with the breath and be with the breath but rather the breath is the vehicle for
this remembering this awakening awakening of an awareness
that brings us into the present moment that a practice that keeps us in the present
in a full and way and what's uh remarkable about
this is we're not asked to do things that are very complicated we're asked to to really kind of stay
and do just one thing at a time or just be with what's predominant here and now and so
we choose if the breathing works for you as a meditation objects this is the one thing that we give
ourselves over to the one place where we keep remembering
remembering to come back to be here to be present
and uh and you don't have to doesn't have to be sophisticated there's not a lot you have to figure out or
analyze or uh if you're able to just kind of follow through see it through just breathing trust your
breathing more than anything else if a simple way of developing
meditation i think would be to really trust your breathing more than
anything else or almost anything else keep it really simple
let all everything else kind of fall away for these minutes and remember yourself remember
your experience and awareness here over and over again
so stepping into a meditation posture
and and if it's comfortable for you to close
your eyes
and as a way of remembering that the breathing is the center of
focus take a few long slow deep breaths
really to feel those breaths to feel the body move and expand and contract as you breathe
deeply and to feel all the different places in your
body that move as you breathe in deeply as you exhale fully
all the places that move and when you breathe these are the places
to remember these are the places where we wake up the place of awareness
places for awareness to be aware and
then letting your breathing return to
normal and
and perhaps as you relax your body further there's a way of relaxing into the body
breathing maybe relaxing the belly
so there's more room and space to feel and sense the breathing body
so there's less restrictions
holding of the breathing
relaxing the belly
and perhaps there can be a relaxing of the chest
relaxing around the diaphragms
maybe as you
exhale maybe as you inhale at the top of the inhale
relaxing softening so the inhale can be fuller
not forcefully but naturally
at the end of the exhale let there be a relaxation so the exhale continues a bit
here and now breathing
and allowing yourself to be simple
simply with the breathing
for these minutes trusting
attention to your breathing as the one thing that you give yourself
over to relaxed in full
attention on breathing in and breathing out
remembering to be mindful of your breathing
and remembering that it's not just about breathing it's also about the awareness of
breathing the awareness that receives and all
contains breathing
the awareness that arises out of
breathing
so
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to let go of focusing on the breathing and remember the world
remember others in your life in your communities
even those in the news and those you read about
and people you don't know far flung around the globe
remember that we share this planet with others who also want to be happy
and safe and peaceful others who have beating hearts and
minds with dreams and wishes and
memories of life
and may we open our hearts to them
may we remember them as part of our human family
with all its diversity and may we wish
that our practice and our dedication to a mindful life a liberated life
maybe wish that it supports them in some way or other so that they can be happy
so that they can be safe and peaceful so they can be free
may through the strength and the goodness of this practice we've done
help us to contribute to creating a better world
contribute to supporting others to feel happy and
and well may all beings
be happy
and then i don't have my bell here so we can my bow can be the end of the
the sitting thank you
so here
maybe the last talk in this five-part series on the dharma life though perhaps
all um talks are about the dharma life
i like the idea that a spiritual life
is also a life a spiritual life is a lived life
but a live life that's infused with dharma terms infused with
mindfulness awareness intentionality a certain kind of sense of purpose um
an orientation towards in radical non-harming of oneself and
others but it's something we bring to all our life and to
have the opportunity to live a dharmic life a contemplative life where we infuse our life with our
spiritual life or a spiritual practice it's such a wonderful privilege it's a wonderful honor
to be able to do this in this human life that we have and it's easy to want maybe to want to
do this but that um it's remembering to do it which is hard
and rather than having some high standard like now you're supposed to be mindful aware throughout the whole day non-stop
i think for most of us if we just increase the percentage of our presence our attention to life
and we'll get tremendous amount of benefit i suspect that if ten percent of the day
you were really mindful of what you're doing that they would transform your life in big ways
and so
um the
so i want to offer another practice today that you could do or another approach
you can do it to infuse your life your daily life with a sense of practice living a dharmic life and that is
uh when you do something just do that one thing to practice doing one thing at a time
and in a world where now a common expression is multitasking
single tasking is not maybe even it as much but to really be present for one when
you're doing something really be there for it and why is this useful
this is what we're trying to do when we meditate we're trying to really be present for what's happening in the moment
and just one thing at a time just really there for it it might switch and be aware of something else a moment later but
whatever is happening that he has to be there for it in the process of doing that we learn
how easily we're distracted and we learn how easily we're bored or cotton desires or caught in aversions to
what's happening and cotton preferences and fantasies and we have to learn to
work with this mind that gets all entangled in these things and begin to uh learn to shed them not to
have them get in the way and uh to somehow the meditation to learn to be simpler and in that
simplicity to relax deeply and get in touch with ourselves in a much deeper way than we can
when we're spinning around in preferences desires aversions distractions and so this remembering
is to come home to ourselves to really be here in a deep intimate connected way that comes from
having a somewhat simple mind not a simplistic mind but a mind that is
not caught up in many many things and so to the benefits of in meditation
of feeling that simplicity of mind and non-destructibility of the mind just being here for this moment
we learn so much about ourselves in that process we learn to let we learn what makes us tick we learn to
let go of we learn what it's like to connect to ourselves in a peaceful way in a wonderful way so we can do the same
thing in daily life no matter in most things if that are simple enough that allows us to do that
one thing and and have it be the same way as with meditation
if you're washing the dishes just wash the dishes don't have the news on at the same time
because you know you want to be efficient and and do more than one thing at the same time and hear the news might as well
hear them while you're washing dishes dishes are kind of mindless and have no important
great value so might as well listen to the news or the soap opera or whatever but
if you infuse washing dishes dishes with the same kind of attention and
purpose and practice as you do in meditation just do the dishes and you get bored
learn to content work with that and let go of it or sometimes boredom just means that you're holding yourself apart from the
experience and so can you give yourself more to the experience just the washing the dishes
just you and the dishes and then wash with both hands while wash their
whole body present there and then that kind of focus and attention will certainly reveal
all the ways the mind wants to escape and do something else but in the process you also learned how
to quiet the mind or let go of these preoccupations and you learn how to simplify the mind
and to experience the benefits and the intimacy and the coming at home this with ourselves
of just being there for that one thing and that can be for all kinds of things
we do it can be cooking cleaning driving
just drive you know driving maybe involves many different senses and many different considerations you know your mind's
moving around rear view mirror side view mirror front looking just do what driving requires of you
don't have the radio on don't be talking on the phone just do this if you want to get the benefits of this
really being having the practice grow in your daily life
and some people will say complain and say well i have a lot to do and i need to multitask maybe that's so
so maybe please do it if that's necessary but sometimes things are done more
efficiently if you just do one thing at a time you do it properly the first time it
doesn't have to be done again you do it fully and so you don't have to come back to it later
and you understand it fully just this just this and
so what's one of the advantages of monastic life the monastic life that i led lived is that
you're given different tasks through the day where really what's called on is just do one thing at a time
um uh raking the uh temple grounds just rake uh you know washing dishes
i was a dishwasher in the monastery my first summer there and and uh so i spent this it was just me in
the dishwashing machine and so rather than washing of the sink i had this wonderful dance
of um completely being in the dishwashing shack and and um it was it was vigorous and active
work it wasn't like calm and relaxed but it was just beautiful and for me it was kind of dance of
putting dishes in and away and washing and and just gave myself over to what was
needed then doing one thing at a time does not mean that we do everything slowly
though sometimes it's delicious to do with that and very helpful we do it at a pace that's useful
sometimes doing one thing fully means we give ourselves over fully in a very full and active way
i worked at a after i was in the monastery i worked at a as a at a restaurant kind of as a little bit
of a fest you know as well as a line cook on a restaurant very busy restaurant
and and i was doing a lot of different things in a sense i was multitasking different
cooking different dishes at the same time tracking them but that's all i did i was completely absorbed in this
activity and this concentration absorption and what i was doing was you know i
would leave that leave work feeling more relaxed than when i came in because of giving myself over to really do this one
activity and so if you're if you're protesting a little bit that you can't do one thing
at a time you might experiment with it and find out if it doesn't actually
give you more ease in your life give you more relaxation maybe you don't have to spend time
afterwards relaxing as much relaxing is a wonderful thing but if you don't need to relax
and you can continue living your life in a nice nice way and there's a doing one thing
at a time and then sustaining it and really
following through on it to the end many years ago i discovered that when um
when i was i left the monastery i was living in a in a house that um how easy it was to go
one end of the house to the other to get the laundry out of the washing machine to the dryer and get
distracted by things little tasks that we do here and there and stop and it took a while to get to the laundry
area and and so sometimes i felt just nice to if i
the purpose is to go to the laundry area just go there so they get the the body and the mind
gets the sense of what it's like to kind of just do one thing and
not bounce around and not be busy or grabbing at everything that
comes up and um and uh so sustain follow through if you really
set yourself to do something with that you know unless something important comes up of course follow through as long as it's kind of
so you can just give yourself the pleasure the joy just doing one thing and for practitioners it's more than the
pleasure and the joy it's so that we're doing the same exploration of our inner life as we do in meditation
we're learning to let go of what doesn't serve us what's unhealthy we're learning to wake up
to the what's the present moment and we're learning to have some continuity with doing that
and that continuity is so beneficial continuity is what allows something to
dharma life to unfold and deepen so i end this five part series with
something which i think is quite simple in principle yesterday was more complicated
with the idea of intention and commitment and sense of purpose why we do things
and now today i'm bringing it back to the value of just something that's
ordinary simple i i hope almost anyone can do it doesn't take a lot of intelligence it doesn't
take a lot of sophistication and that is when you're doing something
just do it do it fully so i'll end the story with a story of two zen students
that's how that's how the story was told to me two zen students were
praising their own teachers and one of them says oh my teacher is so wonderful
has all these psychic powers can fly through the air and walk on water and and such so forth
and the other student said oh my teacher is really great too because my teacher
when she walks she just walks when she sits she just sits when she works it
just works and the first student said oh your teacher is really great
now that is wonderful so walk when you walk sit when you sit
clean when you're clean talk with friends as you when you talk um this is a great power
and uh and it's a gift to the world that we give ourselves to each thing
that we do carefully so thank you