okay so why don't we go ahead and get started this evening
it's nice to see at least uh on the screen a couple of comments there
know that you're out there and welcome to our monday evening sit
uh diana is away so i'm very happy to be here some of you uh know me
i've taught a number of times at imc for a while and it's a delight to share this time
with you so let's go ahead and get started with our meditation
so finding a posture that's upright also relaxed
something where you'll be able to sit for a little while
just feeling a sense of settling in so knowing that you've arrived
for the sitting and if you're comfortable doing so you
can close your eyes just let your eyes gently close if you're more comfortable with
them open that's okay but usually in our practice we would keep them closed
maybe taking a couple of long slow deep breaths to really
bring the air into the body and then on the exhale
encouraging the shoulders to drop the body to soften up the
spine to still remain upright so we're settling into
a posture that is at ease and also alert
and then you may begin to bring the attention inward
and just encourage some ease in parts of the body that we often
hold tense so softening the muscles of the face
the forehead around the eyes jaw
softening the eyes and the eye sockets especially if we've been looking at the
screen often the eyes get a little tense
and down through the shoulder area letting the shoulders drop
maybe thinking of the shoulder blades sliding down the back
so we don't slump as we soften the shoulders
down the arms into the hands releasing any tension in fingers
from typing [Music]
and down into the torso area softening the chest
maybe deliberately feeling the front back and sides of the
ribcage also when we look at the screen a lot of our energy tends to go forward
in the body so it's so helpful to bring the attention to the back
the back of the rib cage
down through the belly letting the belly be soft
all the way down into the hip joints feeling the seat against the chair or
the cushion or the bench wherever you're sitting
letting that support you
and softening down through the legs [Music] releasing any bracing or
tension in the knees or the ankles
and if you can feeling all the way into the feet
so then having invited ease through the body just returning attention to the full
sense of the body sitting general overall sense
and just being at ease mentally with how the body is right now
it's fine just as it is
gently allowing the attention to settle onto the sensations of breathing
these sensations are very simple almost elemental
touch of the air on the nostrils or the upper lip
sense of coolness in the nasal passages
some sense of expansion maybe the shift of clothing against the
skin
maybe even a sense of tension near the top of the in-breath and then that stops and
we begin the out breath there's a different kind of movement
maybe warmth there's the air exits it's a whole kaleidoscope of
simple sensations in sequence and we can just flow along with that
just as we invited ease through the body we can begin to encourage ease of the
mind perhaps using the body is a simple way
to stabilize the mind body is sitting still
relatively so we encourage the mind to become simpler stiller
certainly the goal is not to end our thinking or eliminate any emotions
present but more to have a simple presence with whatever is here
just as we can be simple with the movement of the breath in the body we can be simple with
the movement of thoughts emotions
the normal activity of the mind
let me just try not to get so caught up in it but instead just to hold it in simple
awareness
and if the mind has gotten caught up in thought some concern
it's no problem as soon as you notice just returning to the simple
presence of the body simple awareness
can anchor in the breath or the body
in fact we may even notice that the moment that we come back when
there's presence again there's a little bit of
joy it's actually slightly pleasant to be
present so i encourage you in this sitting to
notice the simple joy that accompanies mindfulness
even if what we're mindful of is some discomfort in the body
or in the mind the mindfulness itself has a certain
quality of joy to it i'm just seeing if you can notice that
from time to time as you continue with regular practice
oh
okay
in this meditation continuing on
if you begin to feel some degree of ease in the body
or the mind just from having settled even a little bit
you're encouraged to tune into that feeling that pleasant feeling of
well-being or a little bit of peace or
softness in the body or a mild kind of joy in the mind
we don't need to only be neutrally mindful about our experience
it's actually fine if we're feeling meditative feelings of well-being
to open to those include them explicitly
bring our mindfulness to those also so that they are supported and
nourished in a natural way and if you don't feel
so much of that that's okay too but just to be aware when such
sense of ease arises and allow it to to be nourished
you
the monk tanissero bagu says that sometimes as he practices with
the breath he just has the simple idea
of not adding any new tension on the in-breath and releasing
a little bit more tension on each out breath
that could be physical or mental tension
and practicing in that way it's very easy to tune into the ease that's present
so that we're not adding anything on the in-breath and we're deepening into the ease on the
out breath whatever use is available
and in the last few minutes of this meditation i'm going to invite
just a brief reflection if it's of interest
as you continue to sit in meditation with the breath with body
bringing the mind into the present moment
just reflect on any sense of delight
or joy or gratitude for the dharma for
your practice for having a path to walk however it is that
you think about this role of dharma in your life
consider the appreciation or positive feelings from that
just keeping the mind simple maybe even feeling in the body that feeling
simple sense of joy and the dharma however that is for you
i'm just resting and breathing with that
that feeling
[Music]
so good evening tonight's topic is joy
and you might first consider what you feel when you hear that word
for some people joy is almost the aim of the path there's a sense of
maybe seeking bliss or something like that for other people
they're might even be a slight negative connotation joy really i don't know it feels a
little bit fluffy maybe denial there's so much so many problems in the world surely joy
is a little bit surface level lightweight something like that
so whatever whatever your response is to that idea i encourage you
to consider for tonight the possibility that joy has some significant depth to
it it's it's not lightweight actually and neither is it solely
concerned with bliss and ease it actually it's it has some substance
it's not an escape from meeting suffering and i'm gonna talk a bit about
how it plays an essential role on the path to liberation we need joy actually it's important on
our path so joy is a very beautiful quality of
heart it points toward in an essential way it points toward abundance
and so we're going to talk about several different kinds of joy tonight
i'm going to offer kind of an abundance or a bouquet of different experiences of joy that
come on the path so just as an overview there's appreciative joy or
empathetic joy that we can feel for the success of others
there's meditative joy that comes when the mind becomes stiller and more
free of the hindrances and there can be joy in the path
in the practice in the dharma itself there's even other kinds of joy than
that perhaps but that's what we'll try to cover tonight as a as i said kind of a bouquet
of different types so let's start with this experience of
uh joy at the success or happiness of others this is a kind of joy that's
um also called mudita it's one of the four
brahmaviharas or heart qualities that we cultivate on the path
the others you might be more familiar with meta loving kindness karuna compassion
and upekka equanimity those three along with mudita appreciative joy
are the four brahmaviharas or divine abodes so these are relational qualities and
they acknowledge that we live in a world that does include happiness
we see people getting what they like we see them
succeeding we see them achieving goals and gaining
praise and one quality of having a mature heart is the ability
to celebrate the joy of others in a simple happy natural way the dalai lama said
if i am happy when good things happen to other people billions more chances to be happy
so really this is a wonderful thing all the time in the world there's actually a lot of good things going on
there are acts of generosity and kindness being done at every moment somewhere in the world
and we can tap into that now if this is sounding a little bit difficult often one way that we can touch into
appreciative joy immediately is through animals
like a dog dogs are excited about so many things and you can you can catch the excitement
of the dog or watching a a kitten um playing with a leaf
in the wind that it's gotten attracted to something you know we don't want to project too many things onto
animals but i think it's pretty easy to tell when there's a sense of of joy or
excitement in an animal and we can catch that [Music] we can catch that feeling i read a study
by the way that cute cat videos have been shown to reduce stress
so there you go one good thing as we're connecting with
joy in this simple way is to start to feel what joy feels like in our body you know
what is it like to have that sense of uplift into simple uplift at someone
else's joy start to feel where that is in the body how the energy moves
so that we can be um familiar with it and so we can experience it more often
it has a feeling in the mind too a lightness of openness of warmth in a
certain way so we can get familiar with that and then we can cultivate it for people
also of course and you know one way that we do this is to say phrases the common
phrase for mutita is may your happiness and good fortune continue
your happiness and good fortune continue so we wish well for the success and happiness of others
when we do that we can also feel the joy in our body and maybe imagine an image of the person being happy or joyful
and allow that feeling to mature in us to cook in us if you will
another form of joy practice is to evoke somehow that feeling of mudita
through an image or a phrase and then kind of drop the object that we
were thinking of and actually just radiate that feeling from our heart concentrate
it into the heart center and just feel it like a light shining from inside
it's a wonderful way to cultivate meditation so it's natural of course that as we try
to cultivate appreciative or empathetic joy we will
run into what gets in the way of that and that's this is normal it doesn't
mean the practice isn't working and you can imagine that the what's called the far enemy or the thing that
really opposes our ability to feel mudita is envy so somebody else gets some
success or gains something and we think well why did they get that they didn't
deserve that or or we think i should have gotten that how come i didn't get that instead or
also and so there's a you know a turning toward the cell for somehow some envy and so um
it's helpful just to notice that this blocks our appreciative joy
one thing that fuels envy and that the reason that we might have such
feelings is there can be an idea that in order to be happy we have to get something
and so seeing somebody else get something we would feel like i didn't get something and so but if we
can learn to feel this joy for others receiving uh we feel a great amount of relief we
can realize oh actually i can be happy without getting something there is a
kind of happiness that doesn't come from that and so this is actually quite a wonderful discovery
for us like the dalai lama says it greatly increases our chances of happiness in the world
now we don't of course have to feel joy at somebody else's joy it may be that they're feeling joy about
something that's a little bit unwholesome or that we suspect is not going to be good for them in the long run so it's not like you
have to have to experience joy if someone else is feeling joyful
you know maybe if we see that it's not leading in a good direction compassion would be a better response
so just so you're aware of that there is also what's called a near enemy
of mutita of appreciative joy and that is sometimes called giddiness it's not a
word we use very often but the you can get the sense of it it's like a sort of over-the-top uh excitement about
something and getting caught up in somebody else's uh pleasure and joy such that we
lose our own balance you know we fall into it and we're no longer aware present centered in in ourselves
um so our own heart so you can feel you can feel when that's
happening we've probably all experienced that tumbling feeling of of giddiness and so that's
just be aware that's not really that's not really medita um
so overall detail is of course a great way to reduce our self-focus like all the brahmaviharas are all of the
heart qualities are so we undermine you know this belief that we
have sometimes subtly that we need to be receiving and getting and you know being praised and bolstered all
the time in order to feel happy we don't actually there are many other forms of of happiness available and it's
it is an expansive feeling of heart to be able to tap into mudita
so much recommended as a cultivation
now in addition there's a whole other flavor of joy that comes from meditation and this is
something that the mind starts to feel when it has less of the
hindrances and less caught up in sense pleasures and sort of our usual pursuits
so this comes again through sitting practice it's called uh pt p-i-t-i and i'll
get to to it in a moment um often when people start sitting there's
not a lot of joy in the sitting and that can be because we're busy dealing with body pain or
we've somehow taken on sitting as an obligation or a chore and we're just trying to be with the
breath or bring the mind back all the time it's a sort of work where's the joy where's the joy in
that but there is an accessible way into
meditative joy we practiced it during the meditation which is that
even being mindful has a slight amount of pleasure to it
you know it's not our usual kind of sense pleasure like eating chocolate or something but being
present as opposed to being lost or caught up in something is actually slightly pleasant it's a
very subtle kind of joy being there being present and we can tap into that
as i said in the meditation even when what we're mindful of is something unpleasant or a little
painful or something the fact that we're present for it we can start to appreciate that
that's better than being lost and so that's an easy accessible way to
to start and so every time you get lost which we do all the time in meditation
when the mind comes back we wake up oh right meditation mindful we notice at that
moment ah it feels better there's a clarity it isn't there when we were lost
and that clarity is slightly pleasant then we tune into that that the mind wants to be present a
little bit more often so that's our first little taste of meditative joy actually
just being present and then it's also um just fine as we did in the
sitting to as we start to feel some degree of ease or peace or
softening in the body slowing down of the mind anything that's that's some direction
toward well-being it's totally fine to notice that and appreciate it we don't need to grab
on to it and try to make it bigger and try to hold on to it that will only cause more difficulty but
you can appreciate those um good feelings that start to come in meditation and just let them be
nourished by our attention to them let them be naturally present
that's also a nice way to slowly cultivate meditative joy
and then we will eventually at some point um start to feel some genuine sense of
well-being emerging from meditation you know we know that it's coming because we're
sitting there with some seclusion of the body some
seclusion of the mind we start to feel an internal sense of well-being
and it's often felt most strongly in the body we may even feel some kinds of pt meditative joy
feel almost like tingling or energy in the body sometimes the hair stands on end it's
kind of delightful these little feelings that we have and then it can also settle a
little bit more and be more pervasive but this is um this is a wonderful
development when it starts to come in meditation and maybe you'll have it once and then not for a while it's not like it comes
and then stays forever but just start to notice when this these feelings come
of one way that we can know that what we're having is meditative joy is that full balanced
pt leads to tranquility now this is not our usual mode with joy
right it's not your usual kind of excitement which tends to agitate the mind meditative joy is pleasant in and of
itself and it leads to tranquility it's almost like there's a little core of tranquility with this joy
wrapped around it and we touch the joy first and as we settle into it and deepen into it
we then touch the tranquility that's at its heart so that's um you might reflect for a
moment do you know anything of this kind of joy even a little bit
a sense of settledness and well-being that can come through the meditation so mostly
meditative joy comes as the mind softens and becomes more continuously mindful
we don't have to try to cultivate it in fact that's sometimes counterproductive it emerges
from a mind that is soft and more or less continually mindful so
here's a nice simile from the sutas that i wanted to read about this
just like a lake with spring water welling up from within having no inflow
from the east west north or south and with the skies not supplying rain
so that the cool fountain water welling up from the lake would permeate and pervade suffuse
and fill it with cool waters there being no part of the lake unpervaded by the cool waters even so
the meditator permeates this very body with the rapture and pleasure born of
concentration or of composure so there's a sense like okay lost in all
the words a sense of a lake with a a well within it
that is bringing something up it's coming from meditation itself
so what is the value of this joy there are a number of benefits of course but the the main one is
this deep sense of well-being that starts to train the mind that something besides sense pleasures
and thinking and our usual ways of trying to get pleasure there's something deeper than that
that's actually more satisfying this is from the dhammapada tasting the
flavor of solitude and peace one becomes free of distress and evil drinking the
flavor of dharma joy so it starts out as talking about
a concentration the settling of mind that leads to this joy the solitude and peace it gives the clue
to that but then this last line drinking the flavor of dharma joy
that's going to lead us into the next section i want to talk now turn now to the kind of joy
that can come from the practice itself of joy in the practice and the path in the
dharma and there isn't just one word for this like mudita or pt it comes from a whole
bunch of different places so now we really get to expand our bouquet of different kinds of joy
i'll go through some ways that the practice itself generates joy so it's great i love this
third kind of joy that we're talking about so one one way that it can come is through ethical
conduct um this isn't anything complicated or heavy
or rigid it's that when we've generally behaved well you know we've said and done things that
were wholesome enough uh we've get to the end of the day and we feel good
about how that went as sort of a sense of joy it's actually called the bliss of blamelessness
we don't need to absolutize that or make it you know blamelessness sounds a little bit too
idealistic to me but essentially we can get to the end of the day and feel like it went okay
that's actually very precious feeling it nourishes us to realize that we've
generally said and done and even thought things that were good throughout the day
it also comes from having confidence or faith if you will in the past so when we
have a moment where we realize that we're confident that what we're
doing is the right thing you know i have times when i realize
i'm just grateful that i have a path you know i'm grateful that i have some way of
managing the things that come up during the day in my mind and my body that's right i have a path and when i
reflect on that i feel a certain kind of joy just emerges naturally kind of a delight
oh yeah good there's there's um support there's a way to deal with life interestingly
joy can also come from renunciation now renunciation is not usually our
favorite word but it really just means letting go and in this case
it might it could mean uh we don't have so much conventional focus on stuff and
wealth and prestige and identity it's like we're not so wrapped up in
those usual kinds of pursuits that the advertisements and marketers tell us will make us happy
when we realize not really that's not really the path to happiness we can start to feel a subtle kind of
joy just in simplicity of living a more balanced
way the mind gets clearer so the buddha describes a certain kind of
joy that arises from if you will the wisdom of renunciation i'll read a little bit about that so
seeing things as they are so he says when by knowing the
impermanence change fading away and cessation of say forms could be any of the five
sense objects but material things and one sees as it actually is with
proper wisdom that forms are all impermanent and subject to change
joy arises such joy as this is called the joy based on
renunciation that's interesting so it's a little
subtle but it means that you know if i if i'm using this cup and you know it's a nice cup
holds water but i know at the same time that i'm looking at it that it's subject
to breakage it will not it's not a permanent source of happiness for me
i like it right now but this wouldn't be wise to place all of my
happiness in this cup there's certain subtle joy that comes from knowing that
you know there's some wisdom there and maybe a cup is somewhat trivial example but
we can think about how the path and the practice allow us to realize not take the bait of things in the world
quite so easily of course we still do sometimes but there can be a certain joy
in having that strength knowing okay i know that all things change they're going to pass
i shouldn't rely on this completely so if you do feel that if you have some
sense of that in some areas of your life take joy in that not everyone knows that
it's a kind of wisdom and kind of joy so
we should get also to a question that people sometimes ask at this point which is why
or how can we be joyful in a world with pain you know in the face of pain why be
joyful so first off let me ask why not seriously why not
so i do encounter people who think it's some kind of a betrayal to be happy or joyful or peaceful or
light when there is so much suffering in the world
or in a difficult situation why why wouldn't you just fall into that and
get agitated and worried like everybody else to show that you care but i would again ask a little question
betrayal of what trail of what so the buddhist teachings
point us toward a happiness that is unconditioned
what does that mean that's a word we don't use very often either but it means a kind of happiness that is
not subject to the conditions of the world so not
dependent on things being a certain way you can be happy if they're this way or that way or this other way
and it doesn't mean that at every moment we're skipping down the aisles and laughing that wouldn't be appropriate in
every situation but there's a way in which we have a certain happiness of heart
that can be present with anything in various ways appropriate to that
situation so we can look for that in our heart we can look for ways that we can find joy at the very least we
have the joy of presence if we're present for suffering yeah we may feel compassion for the suffering
concern wishing to help and in that in that deep presence or
that wisdom of being there for something there is actually a little bit of joy there's still that
that joy of presence subtle but it's there so jack cornfield says it this way
in joy we are not afraid of pleasure we do not mistakenly believe it is
disloyal to the suffering of the world to honor the happiness we have been given
so if we have some happiness in our life we're not being disloyal to appreciate and enjoy that
or this from archbishop desmond tutu wonderful minister
from south africa it helps no one if you sacrifice your joy
because others are suffering we people who care must be filled with joy
so that others recognize that caring helping and being generous are not a
burden they are a joy so how about that
we people who care we people who care must be filled with joy so that others
recognize caring is a joy it's so valuable
to see radiant joyful helpers of the world and
so inspiring and necessary you know uplifting offer some hope some vision
even in the face of suffering my friend spent some time in south
africa and she was fortunate enough to be working at an art museum
where archbishop tutu came for some event that was being held there
and somehow she managed to be standing just about six feet with from him um and she said he lit up the room
he was made of pure joy so there's just um something so valuable
in this quality and so many ways that we can touch into it in our practice
the medita the appreciative joy for others there's the meditative joy that can come
from settling the mind there's the joy in the path practice the dharma itself that
can fuel us through times in our practice that are difficult or through meeting the world and its
difficulties and in the end
joy is one of the factors of awakening there are seven factors of awakening
one of them is right in the middle is joy and it
is a necessary component for awakening so that we have a mind with some degree
of lightness some happiness that is coming from the heart from the path itself and when the mind
is in a state like that as well as possessing a number of other wholesome factors
that's when it can awaken so i encourage you to touch into this very beautiful quality
that's accessible in a number of ways through seeing other people through
the presence of mindfulness through reflection through the settling of the mind and
through wisdom through ethics almost everything can be a door to joy
if we are looking for it and are open to that so to whatever degree
you're able to touch into that whether it's just a little bit or whether you feel the opening of the heart happens to be
tonight i encourage you to really appreciate that and let it fill your being
so that we can help others with that so may your practice and your path
and your heart joyful
be well