okay great so now a formal hello formal opening of our time
together and happy hour so
so for the theme for today's practice um i'd like to invite us
to explore love and silence
love and solitude as a theme for our exploration today
so
a lot of times we might think that this idea of love is only relational it's
only when we're in relationship with others whereas actually
when we come together or say or on our own when we practice cultivating
meta loving kindness friendliness we take refuge in seclusion
we take refuge in silence we take refuge in our hearts
away from the busyness of our lives interacting with other people in order
to really tap into the sense of goodness kindness both for ourselves and for others so
this seclusion this silence is not a negative it's not
a um uh
a challenging it's it's not a dearth but it's actually rich with possibility
the seclusion the silence this this taking refuge
in the simplicity so for us to really bring that into the forefront because
yes of course we know that and yet to really honor this taking time
away in seclusion of our minds um in solitude giving our heart to
it with loving it not just because oh i have to be in solitude and i have to
be alone but actually relishing it what a beautiful what a beautiful
amazing opportunity it is to do this
and i'll share with you that this theme is quite relevant for me and and
maybe i'll make the announcement here at this point because for the next couple of weeks i'm going into personal retreat
um embracing solitude embracing um silent so there will be a host of
wonderful uh teachers for my wednesdays and fridays
and um so i'll be embracing a sense of solitude and to cultivate to
cultivate as out of love really cultivating love and and wisdom in
this beautiful container of of solitude
and i also want to bring this in because after a year of isolation more than a year of isolation
many of us might not have a very friendly relationship to solitude um anymore thinking oh
isolate we might equate it to loneliness or isolation or as it's a
beautiful thing solitude silence and again i might be
preaching to the choir you may already know this and yet to embrace that
and really embrace the juiciness the juiciness of taking refuge in silence and solitude
even if it may not be a couple of weeks but it might be just for 30 minutes together
taking refuge and before we start i wanted to share a quote by let me pull it up here we go
um a quote uh by thomas merton the well
known um priest and um and mystic
maybe one could call him so this is the quote
from vocation to solitude a vocation to solitude
so he says to deliver oneself up to hand oneself over to trust oneself
completely to the silence of a wide landscape of woods and hills
or sea or desert to sit still while the sun comes up over that land
and fills its silence with light to pray and work in the morning and to labor and rest in the afternoon
and to sit still again in meditation in the evening when night falls upon that land and when
silence fills itself with darkness and with stars this is a true and special vocation
there are a few who are willing to become complete who who belong completely to such silence to
let it soak into their bones to breathe nothing but silence to feed on silence and to turn
the very substance of their life into a living and vigilant silence
so in praise of silence again even it may not be complete the whole day but even in 30
minutes of silence of bringing ourselves this vocation this giving our hearts to
solitude to silence as a cultivation as a beautiful thing as an honoring
so plenty of words let's embrace more silence so i like to invite
us to get into our meditation posture
landing
landing in silence
embracing precious solitude
of solitude
calming comforting like a whisper revealing secrets
taking refuge in silence in our hearts
as much silence as available in our minds
letting the breath be the lullaby
of nature calming
soothing
relishing the deliciousness of solitude
of silence
noticing if your mind rushes to fill
the spaciousness of silence internally
notice if that's the case
as if teaching a beloved pupil
a beloved youngster that is your mind
instructing teaching pointing out
expansiveness the ease the nourishment
of silence
uh
notice how within [Music] the silence solitude
inherent in it can be a sense of ease
acceptance being accepted just as you are
you don't have to do anything or be anything or anybody
ah the heart can relax
be accepted be loved
put down the burdens of doing [Music]
and be nourished
the spaciousness of silence of solitude
how healing it can be
notice that your mind has a choice
you have a choice in the way you see
solitude and silence
your mind can choose to see it as unwelcome
as lonely as empty
unwelcome your mind can choose to see the beauty
the grace the spaciousness
the ease the healing nourishing loving
dimensions of silence precious
precious solitude
you have choice more choice than you realize
than you give yourself credit for
the beauty the grace
letting yourself be held the safety nourishment of silence
in the meta friendliness of silence
now if you wish within your solitude
silence if you wish you can invite
someone who's dear to you their image their sense felt sense
if you wish or you could invite yourself as you have in here the only one
as a beloved other or you could invite the whole world if
you wanted to within this silence the solitude of your
heart
it's a safe nourishing place
to offer generosity of love and care good will
maybe just inviting if you're relatively new to the practice
or if it not just inviting one being who's easy
maybe a pet a child
someone for whom your good will and care flows with ease
dividing them into your solitude
to this expansive safe castle of silence in your heart
and hold them dearly offer good will care
in silence or if you wish with words of meta or maybe just silently today
with a smile with a gesture of generosity and care
maybe a hug
maybe your silent expression of love and care for this being
is serving something for them to drink or eat
thanking this dear being who has joined you
in your silence your solitude bowing to them
allowing them to take leave
and in your heart the spaciousness of silence
showering yourself
with good will
with friendliness
holding yourself with kindness
and if judgments arise or busyness of thoughts
or non-deserving thoughts
let them fade into silence they don't have to be believed
let them drop into the silence lovingly engulfed in the silence
for the last couple of minutes see if there is a
sense of gratitude appreciation for this expansiveness
of solitude silence quiet
reigning in your heart and mind
and as i ring the bell i invite you to listen
to the silence the expanse of silence
between the notes and then maybe your mind will open up to
the silence expansiveness of silence within the
notes within the sound
[Music]
thank you for your practice
so this practice of embracing solitude embracing silence
the healing the nourishing the loving aspects of it tuning into those
like tuning into this expanse of silence
and seeing how solitude silence
is this beautiful castle where we can expand where we can cultivate
nourish our hearts in kindness for ourselves and others
so many different things might have come up and i would love to hear your reflections what you noticed
what was surprising what was interesting
you're welcome to raise your zoom hand you're welcome to type in chat if you
type to everyone i will say your name if otherwise if it's private
it'll just be to me i won't read your name
mark please
the breath was different and i realized that
it's always different because every day there's a different being experience in
it that's it
thank you indeed indeed every moment a different being
every day different being beautiful thank you for that astute
observation of how the breath felt different today and every day
yeah lovely thank you mark
bill shares thank you for this i noticed how easy and natural
my breathing was during this when i meditate on my own my breath is sometimes on is
sometimes uncomfortable thank you bill for sharing that and for noticing that
this tapping into the silent solitude relishing that ah i'm delighted to hear
how that brought in more ease for you so know that that's always available to
you when you practice on your own also tuning into
tuning into these dimensions that are available yeah and lovely i'm delighted bill
yay
other reflections what was surprising what was challenging
i also wonder uh austin says not sure how to raise my hand ah okay
i will find you austin and i'll ask you to unmute yourself and taryn says i love the phrase
expansive silence thank you you're welcome terence thank you austin please
hi yeah oh everybody um
so yeah this really spoke to me um i think i'm on my eighth day of 10 days
off right now from work which always sounds really nice and then
there's a lot of free time and then and i run out of things to do and um
people aren't as available as i am so i have a lot of time to myself and
and i've known like i'm i would i usually tell people i'm like 100 extrovert i love being around people i
feel the happiest i'm around people and i know that i need this solitude
to kind of reflect also be to be productive and get things
done and be creative i i need that time to myself
but i feel like just this last week i've had a lot of time to myself
and i've just noticed that i get less clear there's less clarity
when i have so much time with myself then it's like more thoughts come and almost a little
bit of rumination and i feel like i have the most clarity
and i'm the most happiest when i have like a few hours of solitude per
day where i can kind of reflect and be productive and get things done and create
and then i can kind of be social and
have that dialogue with people and get feedback from them and yeah
yeah yeah thank you for sharing that lovely thank you austin so appreciate the
wisdom of knowing that your heart needs solitude and silence in
order to nourish itself and be creative and and you've observed that a few hours
of solitude in silence and some interaction and feedback is is helpful
so one one invitation you can explore this and i know you've done silent
retreats right i i tried i i remember you have where there's a lot of silence and and
you know one is with other people but there's still a sense of solitude so um yes to honor
what you know about yourself what you're discovering about yourself this balance and not to completely believe it have
a little bit of question mark also about it too might be interesting to explore like oh
is it actually is it really really true that after some um solitude and silence then my mind
guess gets restless and gets um
rumination happens do you just take that for granted you see what i'm saying so taking that
like oh this is just what happens this is who i am might actually be limiting more
more wisdom more silence more even deeper nourishment to happen i don't know maybe be curious about that
who knows maybe might be true may not be but who knows
and again you can just let this go if this doesn't land for you at all austin
yeah thank you a few other reflections before we go into groups america says
was empowering how we can bring love and ease to our inner world by connecting to
silence yes thank you and another reflection
i also feel benefit from just the quiet rest of it beautiful thanks for that
reflection nicholas says exploring how silence can hold the thinking mind i tend to assume that
silence is threatened by thinking but it seems silence has plenty of space for a busy mind oh
beautiful nicholas i love what you said and i i especially
um what austin said about the ruminating mind i wonder if silence this is another
way to explore silences holding that instead of oh now i need to attend to the ruminations beautiful
one more reflection um just to me i noticed how i got attacked got
attached excuse me how i got attached to the silence i didn't want you to talk
yes exactly sarah isn't that interesting our heart gets touched like no i want any more talking
now let it continue that's sweet oh jamie says the contrast
this uh the contrast this practice provided with the incessant mental
chatter that fills most of my waking moments was breathtaking thank you thank you jamie really
appreciate your astute observation and and your your comment your
observation is breathtaking so so thank you dear ones
for taking this journey into silence one last comment i was noticing how
solitude is relational when listening to the rain falling outside there was no solitude there was
just experience ah nice interesting thank you david
so dear ones now let's take the sense of solitude invite a couple of other people into our
solitude wholeheartedly with meta with care for ourselves and
for others and see how this can work after some solitude opening up opening up to this relational
field and practicing with others so creating the breakout rooms and again
we'll always start we'll start with um 15 seconds of meta silent meta
for each other and then um you can share as little or as much as
you wish so here we go i'm opening the rooms
hello everyone welcome back so we have a couple of minutes
for final reflection or comment what you noticed they're about to practice or after
connecting with others
is please of silence connecting to others through silence
solitude
you're all silent you've taken the instructions well i see people nodding
and smiling [Laughter] oh that's sweet and heart that's great i
love it yes silence is delicious so
so dear ones um oh neil has something to say here we go
neil so so it
you know it doesn't directly relate to tonight's um small group but you know i find that
sometimes i'm in a group with you know people who tend to be quieter you know
and there's like you know awkward silences or potentially awkward silences
um you know and other times you know there are people who are very chatty and you know ask about the weather and you know about
the what's behind me you know and things of that sort you know and you know i
almost always find you know that you know the people who like lean to the silence you know i i feel a
deeper connection with them um you know yeah
thank you neil what you said in your experience is profound is profound i mean sometimes
there could be genuine curiosity about what's in the background where you're sitting and yet if if it feels like it's just a
rush to fill the uncomfortable silence it doesn't it doesn't feel
very connecting whereas just sitting in silence with another being and by the way in in
meditation circles we don't have such a thing as an awkward silence it's just silence it's delicious silence it's
beautiful silence so that's maybe that's one thing i'll invite from now on as we go into groups
for us to consider the silence is just precious as a time to be so really appreciate the awkward chatter
oh there you go that's it it's delicious silence awkward chatter i love it neil i
love it i love it maybe we'll add that to the like um we should come up with the
uh google groups here like things to consider when you go into to break out groups so
maybe this will be one of them neil so dear ones thank you all
for your practice for joining with the words and with silence and and the solitude
that we have shared together i wish you a wonderful couple of weeks as i said at the beginning i'll be
on retreat embracing solitude and silence myself relishing it for the next couple
of weeks and i look forward to being with you practicing with you
on the other side so thank you all may all beings be well may all beings
be happy and free
thanks everyone thank you for your practice be well