so good morning um
yeah who knew a chat stream could be a
source of uh quite a bit of joy anyway it's sweet too i like the
the um customs the customs around these uh
these parts you know of uh checking in and i've got the i've got
i'm on zoom but then there's the the youtube window and the chat scrolling on the side of my
screen and uh anyway very sweet to uh see uh see you all
so um yeah welcome welcome
um so uh
after the set i'll uh i'll reflect uh on uh
sort of the connections between equanimity and love
uh or equanimity as a kind of indirect route into to a kind of deep love
and we can can look in our uh
in our practice yeah like what what happens when
the openness of our heart and the balance of the mind
meets with the first noble truth meets with dukkha meets with
the the difficulties inherent in being human
and um my experience is that um
that in that that cauldron that meeting of equanimity
and dukkha the the byproduct
of that meeting is something like love
so yeah we gather in this spirit and uh
that's that's it
sometimes we sit and it it feels like uh
coming home and sometimes it feels like getting into
a body of water that's too cold
we just softened
just give the heart some moments to adjust
just still mass
even as the the spine ever so gently reaches towards the sky
also surrender the rest of the body to gravity that's subtle
soothing downward pull of the earth
receiving all of our concerns and worries
just another animal walking on the surface of the planet
and in any given moment
there are a million things right and a million things are wrong
and equanimity affords us the luxury
of not needing to sort all of that out
freedom beckons us from within each
experience
in the face of the flood of experience
can our heart be softened
can we bow to the truth of dukkha the intensity
of the human condition the intensity of being sentient
can we bow knowing that in that bow our
heart is softened
foreign
so thank you um
yes i just sense a certain kind of um
uh closeness to you to the sangha
sort of recognition that um whether we're in the same room or
on youtube spread across the globe um
it's only ever sight and sound and thought and feeling
and there's a kind of fundamental equivalence
to all of our situations yeah and
and so this this feeling of closeness is um
is not secondary you know
so equanimity
um the buddha the buddha is said to have found uh the
middle path the middle path between self-mortification
and self-indulgence and
and it should be noted that the the middle path
sounds middle but it's kind of hardcore yeah
it's um one meal a day and
no tick tock yeah it's kind of hardcore
and but it is not an aesthetic path yeah it's not
it is not a path of asceticism in other words it's not trying to
make ourselves suffer make the body suffer so that the mind
gains strength that was a model a reason to pursue a kind of path of of
pain this is not the buddhist conception
desire does not cause suffering the cause of suffering is grasping of desire
you really have to investigate desire and know it for what it is
we can be very idealistic and thinking that even the need for food is some kind
of desire we should not have one can be quite ridiculous about it
but the buddha was not an idealist and he was not a moralist
he was not trying to condemn anything he was trying to awaken us to truth so that we could
see things clearly
so pain pain on its own has no liberatory
potential in fact it usually has the opposite effect
self-denial is not a path
i i think it's a story from from the the suttas but maybe i'm misremembering but
it's something like the buddha meets a spiritual seeker who's standing on one
leg and asks like what are you doing and this the seeker says i'm burning up my
karma and uh and the buddha is like well how much is burn
i i don't know how much is left i don't know how will you know when you're done i
don't know and then buddha says like ah this is foolishness yeah
but here's the catch pain
minor dramatic met with equanimity has a profound liberatory
potential and in a way
uh the the buddhist path is about not squandering dukkha
not squandering dukkha not squandering the opportunities
of of dukkha of suffering of unsatisfactoriness and so
famously tiknot han just says no no mud no lotus
it's mud not problems and
we recognize that dukkha is usually it's usually squandered
it usually doesn't become wisdom it doesn't become love
and this this path is about this kind of this turn of the heart
how do we transform difficulty into something
uh nourishing and it is almost a kind of
i don't use the word often but alchemical sort of process where we
are transmuting difficulty into
love and a longing for liberation
that that that my experience like that is what what
dukkha is transformed into in the the cauldron of the heart in the
trenches of practice dukkha is transformed into something like love
and a longing for liberation and so sometimes people say you know i'm
doing meta practice i'm doing loving-kindness practice and i cannot feel the love
well sometimes the path into a deep steady radical love
it's more circuitous yeah it's not straight into meta
it's the circuitous path through dukkha meeting met by equanimity
and in a way it can be even more potent yeah than the direct path of love
it's a it's a love that that fully understands
that fully understands dukkha
uh one of my teaching teaching colleagues uh twari
sala said said described ecuador as kind of softening to the
uncontrollability of conditions yeah and she emphasized that word softening
softening the heart is softened by this we sit and here we are
who knows what comes up yeah knows what comes up and we're where we
just actually give up the kind of the rains we have on experience and
surrender surrender soften
and i feel like one of the primary roles of a dharma teachers being
something like a trustworthy cheerleader you know
because there is a part of our selves that just cannot believe this is
the practice yeah
everyone everyone wants peace but who wants purification
so experiencing
pain experiencing pain experiencing duca without equanimity
often often leads to hate
and we can perceive this at a kind of
different scales at the national level like pain not met with wisdom not
met with equanimity it can wreck the mind
can contort the mind into uh
just incredible destructiveness ugliness
but pain met with equanimity this
is a cause for love yeah in that the cauldron of the heart yeah
in the basement level of practice like the capacity to actually bring
difficulty into a attention to bring pain physical emotional into
attention this is profound and it's the basis for
not spilling or suffering on others right like when do we harm others when
do we do things we regret when do we
when does our own self-regulation fail yeah
um so we stay we stay
with the dissatisfaction and it does feel almost like magic what
happens that
so much of the time of practice has just been this kind of like
honest simple labor you know uh labor of
the heart this process of purification which is
transforming energy that ordinarily
causes suffering into the seeds of our growing freedom
king described non-violence as the sword that heals
yeah the sword that heals how can that be how can that work well
it's kind of wild
shinzon young said that equanimity is the
primary cathartic factor of dharma practice
i've always loved that that description the primary cathartic factor of practice
now not all of dharma practice is cathartic yeah this building of
intensity the pits of despair intense negative affect
so the wave crests and breaks and there's relief
there's ease there's bliss there's peace there's something yes uh not all of
practice is like that some of practice is just this very uh
invisible accumulation of the parameters yeah of goodness we don't even see it
but some of it is dramatic and cathartic the wave breaks
and equanimity is is uh very deeply
involved in that wave breaking in the catharsis in the
being reborn into some new open space new pasture
and so we start to get a taste a taste of this process of purification
an acquired taste for sure but a taste for it nonetheless
and that begins to bring a certain kind of
equivalence to experience to pleasure and pain
and after
we we work with this we work with this maybe it's just this sit just this set
we've worked patiently with tolerance with equanimity with difficulty
it's it's so
hard to hate it's hard to rush it's hard to despair
it's hard to do the subtle kinds of
violence to our own hearts
so something is softened love is the byproduct yeah of this meeting of equanimity
and dukkha and uh that is uh profound
and that is something we share with others
so thank you uh yeah thank you for your your attention
it's good too to be with you these days
uh yeah i wish you and wish you all a good good day
uh good morning if that's what it is but i i'm aware
that uh we don't live in a geocentric world nor is california the center of the universe
the the standard time zone or something so uh for those in the evening
uh you'll be well too and uh yeah it's sweet
to think of you everywhere so
thank you