so hello to everyone and i'm happy for all of you who are here
today and participating it's um a wonderful feeling of a
network or of a wonderful
network of connections between people within similar interests doing
something quite wholesome and something that i believe is very beneficial for
our world so thank you and because this meditation practice
is so beneficial beneficial for oneself beneficial for one's communities
beneficial for the world that is why i teach it and i'm quite
confident in its tremendous value and uh just uh
and because of that it's a great value it is set down to meditate it's useful to sit down with a sense of
commitment commitment is a big word there are people who
it said that their commitment shy i like the word
commitment because from latin it met the word uh mit part of the
mat of the latin means the same root as the word mitten it has to do with hand and with the hand
kind of what we can touch and um something like that and at least whether
it's quite accurate or not the point being that commitment with what we touch commitment with what we're in touch with
and to be in touch with oneself and then what's the commitment what's the way in which we touch
our experience right here once we take it in and really recognize and know what's
happening here for us in an in touch way then can we offer something to
that can we offer a commitment a dedication
and a word that i love that's connected to this is the word devotion
not that it's devoted to something outside of our experience but being
devoted committed to our experience and to have a commitment to meet it to
be with it in a wholesome way and and it said that mindfulness is
always wholesome and mindfulness is that attention
that we bring to our experience the way we touch our experience that is absent of any greed or hatred or
delusion and all the kind of associated states that are unwholesome and
this amazing thing that we can kind of find our way from the unwholesome to the wholesome
and it's actually can be theoretically so simple that it's just to be mindful we don't
have to drum up kindness or to drum up generosity or love just to see
clearly this is here and to have a commitment to that to be present to be aware to this moment
stay in touch with our experience and commitment
has shares with one quality at least one quality
that greed has both greed and commitment involve holding on to something
and however in terms of commitment in doing practice it's to be committed to
something wholesome something which leads to our benefit leads to freedom
whereas greed leads to bondage the commitment to the practice leads to
freedom but it's worth holding on to not and we have to hold on to it
wholesomely we have to hold on to it in a way that leads to freedom not further getting entangled and caught
so i take a word of commitment to be in touch with the purpose of why
we're sitting to be in touch with the purpose the tremendous value of staying present staying here staying
with our experience and um so for this sitting today
maybe you can see if you can be supported in the practice with a sense of
commitment or dedication devotion sense of purpose that you hold on to
gently lovingly or caringly um not tightly but you hold on stay
here and maybe that's even the mantra i'm gonna stay here stay in touch stay in touch
and um and uh but don't do it so tight that uh
you know that you're bringing tension to yourself but don't hold it so loosely that you
drift away too easily stay present stay committed
so assuming a
posture of commitment a posture of purpose
a posture that he expresses now here i am my whole being will be dedicated to
this period of staying in touch
and closing your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
and on the long exhale see if you can slowly
settle in not to be so not so much to be relaxed here and
settled here but settled into a sense of yes
this is what i'm going to do i'm going to be here staying in touch with my direct
experience
in touch with my embodied experience
in touch with a sense of purpose and commitment
to the simplicity of the body breathing to be awake and present
and then letting your
breathing return to normal
and as you relax different parts of your body maybe what you do is you're relaxing
into a sense of purpose or a sense of commitment
to being here to practice to stay present
maybe beginning by relaxing the muscles of the face
many of the micro muscles that tighten up in the face can represent other intentions other
purposes that we're trying to do and over the course of the day
but to relax the face
on the exhale to soften relax the shoulders
so more of you can settle down into a commitment here now
and more of and then relaxing the belly
softening the belly and maybe even settling your way to further down your torso
as a grounding to this commitment to be here and
present
and then to also relax the brain
soften the thinking mind
and relax any way that the sense of commitment may have tension in it or pressure in it
a dedication to keeping the commitment relaxed and easy
but still committed staying in touch with the practice
having a commitment to being present staying with your breathing
but to have a commitment where there's you don't have to be successful
you don't have to be managed to stay present or stay on the breathing
that's just a maybe a burden to have a need and requirement
for the commitment but rather to do your best and whenever
you wander off to remember the commitment so you come back right away
stay and relax into your present moment
experience with a commitment with a dedication
moment by moment
gently holding on to the present moment holding on to
staying in touch holding on to mindfulness
in such a way that it keeps opening you
to awareness that is free of attachment
um
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
i evoke the idea of the practice of dedication
some people will take dedication to a little higher level of making it a vow
but dedication to practice to live for the benefit and welfare of
the whole world and for others and not as a duty not as an obligation
not as something heavy burdened to carry but rather because it seems to express
a natural feeling intention desire that arises out of the heart
sometimes when practice gets very peaceful and settled
where there is very little anxiety or attachments
it can feel very natural to respond to the suffering of the world
as natural as if your pillow at night is a little uncomfortable under your head
half asleep you might bunch up the pillow in a different way
that kind of ordinariness and simplicity
the heart's dedication to care for the world can arise
and the end of the sitting it can be expressed
in words or in thoughts so that it moves through us it's
expressed and not just a feeling
may it be that this practice that we have done this morning
may it somehow see insane and unseen ways in intentional and unintentional ways
may it spread from us out into the world contributing to the greater welfare and
happiness and freedom of all beings
so that those who are unhappy may we contribute to their happiness
those who don't feel safe that we contribute to greater safety
to those who don't know peace they can taste and experience more peace
and those who are not free those who are oppressed
subjugated limited in bondage
that it brings them freedom
may we contribute this practice of ours contribute to the welfare and happiness
of all beings everywhere may all beings be free
[Music]
so before i start this talk
i want to mention that tomorrow morning i thought we could have a zoom meeting after our
7am sit and talk we haven't done that for a long time and i've certainly missed doing it and um
and maybe doing it for 45 minutes i have other things tomorrow to go to but
so i will post the zoom link on the imc calendar for our for tomorrow i'll also post it
in the what's new section of imc's website and also i'll post it here on the chat
and and there'll be a password to get in
and that password will be meta so paulie word for loving kindness
m-e-t-t-a so um so i'll i'll explain to that again
tomorrow how that all works but we'll just go over to zoom
and we can we can do a little bit of a q a if you want to have any questions about this week's topics or anything and maybe
a little short period for uh breakout groups you could meet each other a little bit and
it'll be kind of short and sweet with 45 minutes or so
um
so so the topic this week is living a
dharmic life with the emphasis that
there are these things we can bring into our daily life that will enhance or our sense of
practice dedication in our daily life that brings us the benefits of a full-time
religious life you know that uh being in a monastery being in a
retreat center the difference in uh being in a monastery being a monastic
or being in a retreat center living there is not it's more of a matter of degree
that when a person is living a monastic life they get all these reminders to practice all these
associations and and schedules and things that kind of puts them back in
thinking about the practice or remembering to do it
and people who are not living a monastic life or living in a crete center or it's harder to remember and sometimes
it's there's a lot of family responsibilities or work responsibilities that
pull us into their orbit so strongly that we don't think about practice or don't think about mindfulness being present or
the values of the dharma but the difference is not a matter of
all or nothing it's a matter of degree and i think overall for most
people who practice in monasteries for example
they're not necessarily stellar monastics and that they're you know every waking moment they're doing the practice they're
doing all kinds of things and some of them are maybe not even as dedicated to the practice as some
people i know who are lay people living in the world so it's a matter of degree
and and so all of you if you're living kind of an ordinary lay life or something like that
that it's possible to increase the degree to which you're dedicated to get a lot of the benefits of more of
a full time or more of a dedicated dharma life and if you like to do that that's what the teaching this weeks are about so
so the monday it was about being embodied being present mindfulness to the bodies
just practicing that through the day is tremendously beneficial and letting the body be your temple your
monastery the mindfulness of speech was second day
and um and to care for your speech and notice why you're going to say what
you're doing and the tone of voice in which you say it and and there's a whole world
of our inner life that gets revealed by if we really pay attention to our speaking and and so you know rather than
listening to the abbot to the monastery give a dharma talk listen to yourself speak and maybe it's
not a dharma talk but maybe then you start becoming conscious of what you are doing
that it starts moving naturally you'd want it to be more dharmic if you're really listening to yourself
and then there was the dedication to being harmless
that the singular kind of essential essence of the whole buddhadharma living a life
which is harmless to self and others and then today the topic
is commitment or living with a sense of purpose and really being dedicated to that sense
of purpose sometimes when mindfulness is taught we emphasize that side of mindfulness that
has to do with not wanting not reacting just being
in experience and just coming back to being still being and and and that's
you know all well and good but we have different layers of our psyche of our mind different
areas of how we engage in the world and so for example when we sit down to
meditate we might be really dedicated just being present just being and not trying to do so much perhaps and just
let go of the doing mind and just being in and feeling still and quiet and peaceful and
uh it can be so nourishing to do that but there was something that brought us to the meditation cushion
there was a dedication there was a commitment there was a sense of purpose that brought us there
to do that practice so at one point in life you know before we meditate
getting to meditations there's a sense of purpose and then we can put away that purpose just to sit and
meditate so i'm trying to say that in different areas of life it's appropriate to look at these
different qualities and the quality i'm encouraging today is to look at your intentions
and and why do you do things what's really the intention the sense of
purpose underneath it and not the surface purpose or surface intention but what's really
really the heart's intention in doing whatever we're doing what's the inner life's real
deeper deeper intentions and sense of purpose and what we're trying to do and just to look
at that to be mindful of that is a whole valuable practice in itself
to take it to a step further is to spend some time reflecting on your deepest intention what's your heart's
deepest wish if all things could be um you know provided for you if genie came
along and said you can i can i'll provide you with anything at all
and what would you what's your heart's deepest wish
not what your desires are or your ego is but what if you really get quiet and listen
what does your heart most want what's the deepest intention i think this is so valuable that i sometimes
encourage people to [Music] that it's more important to spend time every day reflecting on your deepest
intention than it is to meditate every day and clearly i value
meditation a lot so for me to say that's even more important as your reflect on your deepest intention it
says something about how important i think this is and and and do it over time not just do
it one day and to decide what it is but keep coming back and looking at it and looking at it every day
because it morphs and changes and you see different angles of it or you see layers and go deeper and deeper over
time if you find that you answer the question what is your deepest intention
with a negative statement my deepest intention is not to be afraid
that's fine but you might want to see that if that negative thing was accomplished
what then would be your deepest intention if you could feel safe then what would be available for
you and um and so then and then
with this reflection a reflection of a purposeful life an intentional life uh what are you living for um and not so
much from the ideas of shoulds and shouldn'ts and and but really what's the heart's wish
what's the heart's deepest intention and i i emphasize the heart because it's
it's a kind of a metaphor for what's some inner depth where it seems to arise out of us
in the most natural way we can imagine it's like not an effort for it to come but it really feels like it's integral to
who we are in some deep intimate way
and then there's a a commitment to that and um a living a committed life is
something if you have a if you have something that's wholesome and valuable that's your purpose or your intention
then uh it's a wholesome thing and a valuable thing to have a commitment to it and um
there are so many things wise things a person can do in one's life and some per some people they just have
too many choices just tremendous amounts like going into a supermarket these days and all these choices
that to make whereas in the old days you went to a little market and there wasn't so many brands and
choices you kind of just were took what was there and um so for some people in the modern
world there's so many uh choices and ideas what we should be doing and people
can get just so busy doing it all the different things that are called on to do
a wise life is one that is able to
let go of even wholesome things to do good things to do so that we could
really focus on a few things really well sometimes if we do a lot of different
things we don't go very deep in any of them and some things are really so valuable and so useful
to give ourselves over to in a fuller deeper way and really see it all the way through um
to the other side all the way through to the depth of it or the heart of it and this dharma life if that's what
you're interested in doing it's a topic of this week the dharmic life if this interests you if this is what
you would like to do there's no obligation to do it but if this
it's it's worth really spending time on your sense of purpose with it your intentions with it
and and also your sense of commitment and maybe there's a way of being more
committed so that you are this is what you're doing you have clarity and its purpose
and and um and you may be put aside just some of the things you do which
don't really fit that purpose that dilute your possibility of engagement and
involvement and really let it grow and develop if you are watching more movies on the
computer every day by a factor of you know twice three four times longer
than you ever meditate you know that says something about what you're committed to what's important for
you and maybe it's okay maybe there's a higher purpose that comes from watching tv or
tv programs but but uh what um
you know what what do you want your life most to be about by the time you get to be old or gonna
die do you want to look back and list all the tv programs and movies you've seen
it's ah that was a life well spent or do you look back at your practice life your dharmic life and
realize how much you've changed and grown and say oh that was a life well spent
or your life of supporting other people so a committed life and
and having a commitment there is a plenty of times in buddhism buddhist history buddhism and buddhist traditions
where the sense of commitment even takes a form of a vow
and it's almost that which goes on when we take refuge as to hold on to the refuge we have deep
faith and commitment conviction and we hold on in a wholesome way we dedicate
ourselves we limit ourselves to some degree this is what i want to do
so as you go through your daily life maybe your daily life doesn't change any
but the sense of commitment is is to bring practice to everything you do
and um and bring it into the embodiment with speech with all these things
but whatever you're doing you're going to do it in a committed way committed to the practice as you do it
as if that's more important than what you're doing so at work
practicing as you work is more important than getting a raise for example or or
you know all kinds of things so intention commitment dedication
devotion can be one of the great supports and nourishments and for a
dharmic life and you might want to consider at least for the next 24 hours
what is it that you are committed to and what are they if you really reflect deeply what intentions do you want to
have for your life and when you look back over your life at the end of it what would you like to
look back and see how you live that life and um
and does that reflection give you something to be committed to in a devoted and relaxed way
but still committed so thank you very much and
we'll continue one more time tomorrow from this topic