okay so why don't we go ahead and get started welcome
to the monday evening sid and dharma talk with the insight meditation center i'm
kim allen and i'm delighted to be here with you this evening
so why don't we go ahead and get started with the sit so finding a posture that's
upright also relaxed
sitting in position sitting posture so you can feel your seat against the
chair or the cushion or the bench and your legs or your feet against the
floor so there's a sense of the stable foundation
on which you're resting really feeling the stability of where
you're sitting and if you're comfortable doing so you
can close your eyes just gently allowing the eyes to close
so that the attention comes inward you're feeling the body from the inside
perhaps on the next out breath softening any
obvious areas of tension you can also shift your body
back and forth a little bit or forward and back to find
a central point where you feel like you're balanced
on the place where you're sitting so there's not very much effort to hold
yourself vertical if you're sitting vertically
and then it can be helpful at the beginning of a sit to just consciously
go through the body and inviting ease and softening
what can be softened especially at the end of the day when we may be carrying some tensions
from our activities of the day from what we needed to do to to get here
to the sit so softening the muscles of the face
the forehead around the eyes the jaw
just letting the expression on the face be soft and easeful
softening the eyes and the eye sockets they tend to get a little tight when
we've been looking at the computer screen [Music]
even releasing any tension from inside the head
maybe right behind the eyes from focusing the mind thinking
just allowing that to release if it will just inviting that
down the neck into the shoulder area
softening the shoulder joints letting the shoulders naturally drop
so the shoulder blades slide down the
back
relaxing down the arms and hands
and down into the chest area the heart lungs front back
sides of the ribcage
releasing the diaphragm [Music]
and then all down through the belly area just letting go of any obvious tension
[Music]
there and i like to simultaneously invite some ease in the muscles of the low back
so it's if what's on both sides of the spine is falling away to the front and to the
back
down into the hip joints softening a little further into the seat
and down into the legs releasing any bracing
softening the knee joints ankle joints all the way to the feet
so we've invited ease throughout the whole body i'm just returning attention to the
sense of sitting the whole body sitting
and orienting our mind toward meditation [Music]
intending to stay present
not with the idea that it will be 100 mindfulness
or just carrying the interest the intention of being with our experience
allowing the mind to gently rest on the sensations of breathing
it may be that we've done breath meditation a lot or
feel like we must by now know everything about our breath
but i'd like to encourage a sense of freshness newness
every breath is unique what would it be like to sit with the
breath and not know already what the breath is like
bringing some curiosity and openness
as we settle in further it can be helpful to notice
something about how the mind is now
is it generally a little dull tired
the end of the day is a bit restless and agitated
is there a dominant mood or emotion [Music] going on in the mind or the heart right
now just to know what that is
i'm bringing that same sense of freshness
to our mind and heart we may have felt tired many times or we
may have felt sadness
or even joy many times but what about this time
i'm going to sing again [Music] noticing afresh how the mind is
curious if it might be slightly different than we felt before
now
as you keep sitting if you begin to feel any sense of
ease or peace stillness even just a little bit
it's fine to turn toward that with even some curiosity
what is this stillness like this ease
opening to it gently so as not to disturb it
but that too can be seen [Music] with fresh eyes as if we haven't felt it
before
when we sit with the body and mind in this way with a sense of
seeing what is new or treating it as something open and fresh
there's a remarkable feeling of friendliness that can come a sense that we are
making friends with the body and the mind
more so than if we just treated it as the same old thing
that we've sat and meditated with for a long time
somehow that freshness and openness
creates a kind of intimacy it feels like having a good friend
in the zen tradition it said not knowing is most intimate
so if it feels right you can smile a bit at your friend body and mind as they are
at this moment i'm just resting for a few more minutes
and as we come into the last minutes of this sit
perhaps reflecting if there's anything new that you saw in your
experience that you hadn't really been aware of before
just by having this idea of freshness or newness did you see anything that
you hadn't seen before doesn't have to be major just any little
thing
you
so good evening or night or morning
i think many of us know that the essence of mindfulness practice
is to notice things in our experience
and when we first start paying attention to our body and our emotions and our
thoughts we discover all kinds of things that were there anyway about that we weren't
noticing before sometimes people tell me
that they wish they hadn't started mindfulness practice because as soon as they started looking
they saw some things that they didn't want to see or you know weren't so excited about seeing
various speech or actions going on that maybe they didn't want to know that they
were doing but i tend to take this with a a bit of a grain of salt a bit lightly
because i think people really really do want to see these things about themselves
and as we as we practice further we may start to notice that we have
a favorite set of storylines and ways of thinking
and habits of speech that we use in our life for
example we could call all of these things patterns you know we have various patterns that
come frequently in our experience it's quite common that we see that and
often there's a sense that these kind of are going on their own
you know because they were there before we were noticing them so they have they run on their own under
certain conditions okay and often what they're about is rehearsing
and refining and reinforcing the story of our life or the story of me
if you will so this aspect of our experience
is what could be called samsara in buddhism there's this term samsara
that means these habitual karmic kinds of patterns that are going on in the
background pretty much by themselves many of them are a form of dukkha
because effectively they're just reactive they
they're just going on in the background they tend to deviate from what's actually unfolding in experience and and
kind of take on a life of their own like when something happens and we start
it reminds us of a challenge that we're having and suddenly we're no longer paying attention to what's happening
we've moved into our thoughts about oh that's like that difficulty and then we go off on that and we've deviated from
the present moment that's how we often discover these things in meditation is there the ways that we
fall away from present moment mindfulness so that's essentially a kind of dukkha of being
disconnected from the ongoing flow of experience and these have um
they're said to have a deadening effect on the mind tamapada verse 21 says
the heedless or those who are not paying attention the heblets are as if already dead
wow so we're starting out on kind of a you know
the part of mindfulness that isn't as attractive but i want to then say oh the other thing that we'll notice as
we start practicing and we'll notice it more and more because it's enabled through mindfulness
practice is that we aren't only reacting there are actions that are more in the
realm of freedom they're unique in-the-moment responses
to what's happening that come from paying attention so we start to see more and more also as
we practice mindfulness that there is a freshness and an aliveness to the way we
meet the moment the mind can be vibrant alive connected to what's going
on sometimes we surprise ourselves that we say something quite wise simply because we were paying
attention more carefully than we had been up till now
so it's quite um kind of exciting to see those things to know that the mind has
this capacity to really meet experience some of the time so it's important in our practice to
start being able to discern the difference between what we could call pattern behavior and free
behavior so we start to learn what it feels like when the mind is just doing its habitual
thing and what it feels like when it's attentive and responsive and doing things that are appropriate to
the to the situation so then we start seeing that there's that contrast
those are the sort of two main ways that we could operate then we might start to get curious what
am i not seeing so you know what what i'm not seeing could hold me back
you know what i'm not paying attention to these patterns that run and i don't notice when they slip
in so i can start to wonder what am i missing here or how can i see what i don't see that's
the question i want to address tonight how can we learn to see what it is that we're not seeing about
our speech actions thoughts the very things that mindfulness tended to see we weren't seeing certain
things before we started what else might we not be seeing at this point so it's an interesting question
in spiritual practice how could we see what we're not seeing so this is the realm of ignorance
ignorance isn't some kind of stupidity or something or we didn't read enough or learn enough about it uh
ignorance is what we're ignoring it's what we're habitually not seeing
and so um it's difficult to let go of things that we don't even know are there
we can sometimes but often it's helpful if we're able to have some way
of directing our mind toward being able to see the things that we're not seeing of
course there are plenty of times when what we're not seeing will come and find us you don't have to worry it will that
will happen but it can be interesting to have some techniques for looking into what it is
that we may not be seeing so i want to offer three places tonight that we can look for
what we're not seeing to see what we don't see
okay so the first one is to take the direct approach and
literally try to notice things that we have not been noticing so
we can try to identify areas that we're not paying attention to
sometimes it's possible to literally ask about this to spiritual friends there's there's a
wonderful story in the sutures that's a conversation between two monks
between aniruddha and sorry puta who were friends they've been practicing
together for a long time and anuruddha comments to sarikuta
that he knows that he has attained clairvoyant and he has excellent energy and
concentration and yet he is not awakened so this may not be the realm that we're
practicing in but this is where anuruda was so even when you're close to awakening you may
still know that you don't know things and so he's kind of puzzled you know he comes to sariputta and he says i know
i'm not seeing something i've got all this good stuff happening in my practice
and yet i'm not awakened you know what is it that's going on and so sorry puta is a good
spiritual friend and he deftly points out that anuruda's
attitude toward his accomplishments is revealing certain things about his mind
so for example he's revealing that his mind still contains some conceit and some restlessness and
some remorse and so it would be good if he would abandon these things
and so anuruda is grateful that his friend pointed out what he was not seeing and he
practices in line with that and becomes an arahant becomes awakened as these stories go but it's it's it's
kind of a sweet suit up because it demonstrates that one of the things that our spiritual friends can do
for us is that they might be able to see what we haven't yet let go of and find
the right way to encourage us so it can be useful at the right time of
course to reveal to our spiritual friends where we think we're stuck
and actually ask for some advice about that you can do this with teachers also so
that's kind of the direct approach it may also be that we sometimes have to
try to discern what we're not noticing in a more indirect way and we can do
that by just observing what other people are noticing like our teacher our
friends our partner our colleagues i'll give an example there was a time very early in my
practice when i was at a buddhist gathering and there was a cart being passed around the group
for a sangha member who was ill and the group wanted to support her by
sending her a card so i didn't i was pretty new to the group i didn't really know all the people but i remember thinking
that uh noticing that this was nice you know and thinking oh this is the
kind of group that sends cards to people and i thought about the person a little bit that i knew her
and so i was kind of on a pragmatic practical level like that that was what i noticed about the
situation and then as the card was passed around one of the people in the group um
looked at the card and exclaimed with um put her her hand to her heart and said
this is such a beautiful buddha on this card it was like she was really touched by the beautiful
buddha image that was on the card and i realized at that moment card had already gone by me that i
hadn't even really noticed the picture on the card now i just i didn't even look at that
aspect of it and so i was intrigued that she had seen this and maybe at that time i was pretty new
to practice i don't know that i would have called a buddha image beautiful you know it was a buddha but i would
recognize it but but to sort of put my hand to my heart and say it was beautiful
i don't know that i would have done that and so that kind of that little incident was one of
the triggers for an investigation in my own practice into the quality of faith
which is something that i had not been paying really any attention to it sort of wasn't my style but because of
that i wondered you know what am i missing here and so i looked into that and i
i learned quite a bit about faith by trying to open to it and now i have this buddha which i think
is very beautiful so things change over time when we notice new things
so this is um important to be intrigued by what other people notice that we don't notice
so that's one area where we can look is you know what is it that i'm not
noticing so then the second area that we might
look at is what we don't question okay well we don't question so this has
two different aspects to it the first is there might be areas
where we simply don't think to question more deeply you know it's like we just don't think
to ask any questions and again there's a story in the suttas
there's a story about an elderly man whose name was nakula pita
and he comes to see the buddha and he points out to the buddha when he
arrives that it's quite a rare event for him to be able to come and see the
buddha so he says i am old venerable sir
aged burdened with years advanced in life come to the last stage afflicted in body
often ill i rarely get to see the blessed one and the big goose worthy
of esteem the monks worthy of esteem let the blessed one exhort me
venerable sir let him instruct me since that would lead to my welfare and happiness for a long time
so it's special for him to get to see the buddha and because he's kind of old and often
sick and it's probably hard for him to get there so the buddha first of all agrees with
him that this is indeed a rare event and he gives him a teaching so the buddha says
so it is householder so it is this body of yours is afflicted weighed
down encumbered if anyone carrying around this body were to claim to be healthy even for a
moment what is that due to other than foolishness oh it's quite straightforward so then he
says therefore householder you should train yourself thus even though i am afflicted in body my
mind will be unafflicted thus you should train yourself so he
gives a pretty concise teaching even though i'm afflicted in body my mind will be unafflicted
it's a great teaching by the way one that can be unfolded for a long time and so nakula pita it is said delighted
in the teaching of the buddha he was very happy and he departs and then later as he's
leaving he comes across sorry putta the same monk who was
giving anuruda advice in the last example he comes upon sorry putta
who comments how he looks very serene and you know wow householder your
faculties are serene he says and says oh yes and he repeats his whole
conversation with the buddha and sorry puta admonishes him
actually and he says didn't it occur to you householder to question the blessed one further as
to how one is afflicted in body and mind and how one is afflicted in body but not
afflicted in mind didn't you think to ask what it means to be
afflicted or unafflicted in mind when your body is afflicted and nakula peter says well um
no i didn't think to ask that actually and so then he asks for further
instruction from sorry putta so in which sorry putta then
gives a whole discourse on unfolding the the meaning of this very concise teaching that the buddha gave so
it may be that there are areas of the teachings where we're just sort of
passively taking them in but we are actually meant to engage with the teachings and
either by literally asking questions or by at least investigating in our practice and trying
them out and hoping and prodding and seeing if they work and how they work for us
so we're not really meant to let's say swallow things whole
and that doesn't mean that we need to be asking questions all the time you know things do unfold at their own pace
but it's you know there might be areas where we have some some question you know we never really
understood that teaching about dependent origination or not really sure
what not-self is about you know instead of continuing to just
hear these teachings we could uh ask some questions about them dig a little deeper sometimes
so sometimes what we don't question can reveal areas that we uh have not been paying
very much attention to in our practice then there's a deeper
or a second aspect of what we don't question and that points toward the assumptions
that we're living by which can be serious blocks in our practice and
they're very hard to see it's actually quite hard to see the assumptions that we're living by
you know the kind of the lenses that we have over our eyes over our practice over our way of being in the world there
are certain things that we're just not questioning about that so
assumptions lurk in generally in our thinking and in our interpretation
of events and one way that we can reveal them is to ask questions so i'm going to give
i'll give a specific example suppose that we are angry about
something and we could you know it's fairly common that we get
irritated at least or sometimes we actually get angry about something and we know that you know that's something that's really
bothering us and so we could just say mindfulness of anger anger
feel it in the body anger and then wait for it to go away eventually
but we could also do some some investigation of that and we might you know we might look a little bit more
carefully or of course what we might do is just justify the anger and say well i don't have to look into that anger
that's obviously justified that person is clearly in the wrong that social situation is clearly unjust
no need to question further however if you're interested here's a
a train of thinking and asking that can be quite revealing so if we're angry we are typically in
opposition to something that's kind of what the state of anger is about it's an opposition so we may not even
know what or we may or why we assume that that's useful
so when we're feeling angry or oppositional it can be interesting to ask
a set of three questions so the first one is what am i opposing
and it might be that we think sort of casually think that we know what we're opposing i'm opposing my sister
or something but it's not exactly your whole sister that you're opposing what precisely is it that you're
opposing and look a little bit more carefully and then
you know check into that and then the second question is do i need to oppose it
so i need to oppose that so then that calls into a question this
stance of opposition it doesn't say that you're not going to do anything or that you should approve
of it instead it only says do i need to oppose it which then just automatically opens up
oh might there be other responses or might there be other avenues to bring about
what i would like to see changed as opposed to as opposed to opposition
um so you know might there be other possibilities for this situation we hadn't ever
questioned that we might not have ever thought there was any option besides simply opposing this thing that i don't like or
that is unpleasant so then the third question
is opposing even called for here you might still think that you need to
oppose it is opposing even called for here so then we're sort of calling into
question whether opposing could have positive results
usually opposing creates more conflict actually that tends to be its nature
so these questions can help to you know they're not meant to say that you're wrong or that the other
person is actually good or that you know the whole there doesn't need to be anything done
it's just a way of teasing into what we might not be questioning about our way of being in the world we
could do this in all kinds of i picked out anger but all kinds of dukkha so cases of desire
what am i desiring do i need to desire it is desiring even called for here
or cases of confusion or other such things any kind of dukkha really so
don't be satisfied with surface answers to these questions and kind of see if you can go deeper
so another approach that people have to discovering about their thinking
is a set of repeating questions so you can ask why is that important
if you think something is important it's up you're obsessing about it thinking about it i can ask why is that important and you
get an answer and it's probably true but then you ask and why is that important
and you'll get another answer and you ask and why is that important and it draws the mind down
toward the values that we have and what it is that is really important
to us in that situation and that can help a lot in understanding first of all how we're thinking about
situation and what it is that's really um driving that obsessive thinking we can
learn a lot about our practice and our mind some things that we weren't noticing before
so we have what we don't notice but we don't question
and then the third way of approaching seeing what we don't see is what we
don't laugh about so what we don't find funny tends to
reveal where our identity is invested it is not that everything should be humorous
but if we can't find any lightness in some area it's worth investigating
to see if there's some kind of sticking point there for us it's likely a place where we're
identified the buddha points out in um similarly the snake suta majima 22
that any form of identification is dukkha it will eventually
bring dukkha that may or may not be clear to us but it's worth investigating these areas
that we can't find anything light or humorous in so it's very worthwhile to develop a
sense of humor in our practice many things in the mind are actually kind of funny including many of our patterns we can
have a little lightness and say uh there's that one again yes
that can be very helpful sylvia borstein says that we need three things in practice
gentleness precision and humor and i think she's on
to something you know we need to be so gentle with this habituated stressed mind but also precise
about questioning its assumptions and in the end we have to find it
somewhat humorous about how recalcitrant it is to be changed and
how tricky it is about reasserting its graspings and identity we don't have a
sense of humor we may not have the patience to uh continue to work with the mind
there's a wonderful there was a wonderful 20th century thai forest teacher named ajahn buratasa
was a boxer before he became a monk so that was his first profession is that
he was a professional boxer and then he ordained and he practiced
for a while and eventually he became a well-known teacher and had his own monastery and trained a lot of people including some
of the western teachers that we now have in our tradition here
and but because he was a boxer earlier he retained a somewhat belliger
belligerent heir let's say about him so he could sometimes come across as
rough or blunt he didn't really oppose in the way that i was just talking about in the previous example
but still he had that kind of gruffness about him and sometimes um sometimes people would
take offense at it in certain ways and think that a spiritual teacher should only be kind and gentle and warm
and so forth and if somebody challenged his demeanor sometimes autumn budadasa would just
roar with laughter and he would say oh that's just my personality
so he had learned in his own heart to make peace with just the way
his mind was still kind of a boxer in certain ways now he was of course quite free inside and
wasn't caught up in that identity but he recognized that his personality still had that and he had a certain
amount of lightness about just how he was that that air and that helped other people to lighten up then
you know if they were concerned about that and he just laughed and was was gentle about it then they would
say oh okay it's just his personality so i teach from the suttas fairly
frequently and one thing that i look for in people as they develop in their practice and
in their study is sometimes or often there will be a point where people
realize that the sutas are hilarious some of them some of the suitors are hilarious
you get to the point where you can imagine the scene going on and there's somebody asking
this question or questioning the buddha in a certain way or misunderstanding what he's saying in a certain way
you just you can just imagine the scene you think ah wow you know it must have been funny to
be there so i thought about trying to give an example of this but then i decided that it's something that we really have to
come to on our own but if you've never thought of the polycanon as funny
i recommend trying it and and just seeing some of the lightness in the exchanges that the buddha has
with people so it's clear to me at least that the people who compiled the discourses
had some sense of humor and how it got presented so we've talked tonight about
trying to have some way of seeing what we don't see of opening up our practice so that we
can notice more which is what mindfulness is about it's about noticing more things noticing
different things seeing the mind in different ways so that we can continue to
untangle the knots that com that bind our heart in various ways so
looking into what we don't notice looking into what we don't question and looking into what we don't
laugh about can be wonderful ways of broadening and also deepening
our practice and also keeping it fresh and alive so this is talk is especially if you're
feeling a little stale in your practice or like it's always the same or you're a little stuck or dry
we go through periods like that it's normal but it's good to have some ways of finding
new areas of the mind to uh to look into so i hope this is giving you some some
sense of that i wish you a very good evening and
ongoing practice well everyone