it feels wonderful to be here with you all of you even though it's this uh unusual world
of not being in person but still i have
strong sense in my heart of
all of you many of you who are participating here in our zoom practice thank you for being
here for this meditation today
uh i'd like to evoke the concept the practice
the virtue of truth of truth-telling it said that
there's all kinds of reasons why people think it's okay to do small lies white lies lies to save people's face
or you know little little ones uh as a way of taking care of people so
maybe that's true i don't want to engage in that now but what um
is never true is that it's okay to lie to oneself
that if you want to grow in the dharma if you want to grow in this mindfulness practice then never be and
never lie to yourself always be truthful to yourself and so we sit in meditation to support
that ability to develop the capacity to sit
in truth sit truthfully to recognize it to recognize when we're veering from it
and to sit in the truth of the moment
and maybe that expression sitting in the truth of the moment has two wonderful meanings it means
um and it means to sit in the middle of it not
reacting to it not turning away from it uh the truth and um
and to really be there in the middle just there sit in the middle of truth
so here we are to sit or whatever posture that works for you
to meditate and um assume your posture
give some initial care to the posture you're in and maybe some
wiggling around twisting and swaying supports you to be here in this body of yours
and then to gently close your eyes
and with the truth of this moment the truth of here and now
in the immediacy of what you're experiencing now in your
body what's immediately around you within you know a foot from the edges of your
body maybe or less to take a few long slow deep breaths
to encourage the mind to remember
that in meditation this is the meditation center your body here and now
to make of physical contact with the truth of this body of yours
and as you exhale to release and relax the concerns you have the
tensions you hold
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and with a normal enough breathing as you exhale relax into the truth of
this moment the truth of your physical embodied experience
relaxing the muscles of your face
relaxing the shoulders
and relaxing the belly
and then centering yourself from the body's experience of breathing
not to avoid anything but to sit in the middle of it to be in
the middle of it in the middle of the truth of this
moment let the breathing be at the center
and when your mind wanders off in thought and you found yourself distracted
ask yourself what's really true
what's the truth of this moment that's deeper than your thoughts your distractions
or it's a deeper truth that's underneath them or behind them that if you recognize that truth
you might find it easier to settle in to being here and now
breathing in the middle of all things allowing yourself to be simple just
breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to consider that when we're truthful when we're true to
ourselves we actually have more to offer others
that it's a position a place a resting place
with which to gaze upon the world
kindly and supportingly
compassionately feel and sense the challenges of other people
and to perhaps live with the wish that all beings could be well
that all beings could find joy and peace in their
own truth being truthful to themselves being honest
may it be that all beings be happy
all beings be safe
all beings be peaceful and all beings be free
and may we contribute to that
supported by our capacity to be truthful
[Music]
so so for this dharma talk i'd like to
begin with a story and it seemed that there was a
young woman who very much wanted to meditate she'd been introduced to meditation in college
and but college was a busy time especially the last couple of years and
coursework and all the other things of college and uh
but she looked forward to a time when she could finish college and she really wanted to live a
dharma life she was hoping to go live perhaps in a monastery or live at a retreat center someplace we
should really devote herself kind of full time to the dharma and
integrate all of the practice into her life not just meditation but
an integrated a life integrated with
with the path of liberation path of freedom path of love
and um so but then soon after she graduated uh her older sister
and her older sister's husband uh were in an accident and died
and her own parents were quite elderly and needed a lot of care
so she was left as a sole caretaker for her her sister's two
children and her plans to be able to go off and live this integrated dharma life that
didn't work out so well and she found herself caring for two kids needing to care for
her parents needing to work uh long hours in order just to have the
the finances to do all this and there was no time for even for meditation letting alone
thinking about or engaging in integrated dharma life but she went to
and found a meditation teacher and and asked the teacher um told her about
told the teacher about her problems and her challenges and and what could she do and
the teacher said to her uh well
if you don't have time for meditation and you want to live an integrated dharma life
and your life integrated with practice then what you can do is
[Music] have the practice of making sure that your words when you
speak are gifts practice generosity in your speech
whatever you say think about how it can be a gift to the person you're speaking to
so that's what she did and she learned a lot about herself in that process she learned
how often she was speaking not as a form of generosity but as expressions of
anger or spite or fear anxiety or desire and wanting something
and trying to get someone to behave just right so that she could get what she wanted
and she got to see so much about what she what was operating was driving her
and um but she was told not just to look not she wasn't told to look at that but that's what came up and
and then she had to work through that and adjust for that and find another way to come from a different place
and and to have her words be gifts
arising out of generosity generosity can't be an obligation it can't be
forced it's a it's a kind of upwelling of
goodness in the heart and she found that in practicing letting
her words be a gift she slowly learned how to do that and and over time it really transformed her
she grew in amazing ways and uh she grew in freedom she grew
in love she grew and understanding and wisdom in a way that made her life integrated
with the dharma so
are your words gifts could they be gifts for others could there be generosity
practiced in what you say and this begins maybe by for you to understand
what motivates you for what you're saying uh what do they
underline what drives you to say what you say is it generosity or is it something else
is it kindness and care and respect for others or something else
is it what is what's being expressed through
those words and what would it take for your words to be gifts
what are the gifts that people would like to receive through words could you say all the things that you
need to say but do it in a way that seems pleasant for other people to hear that
feels right for other people to hear that maybe helps people relax or open
or or trust you in some deep way how do you take care of yourself
socially and interactively with others if your speech is always going to have this
quality of generosity in it this goodness this gift-ness
in the words themselves so that's maybe not an
easy task but it's a phenomenal task and if what if some of you would like to
really take your meditation practice and really
learn how to integrate it or expand what's happening meditation into the rest of your life
so meditation just not just a refuge relief from your life but rather it's the
source from how you live your life and if you that and you want to kind of
grow into your life with a sense of freedom integrity openness truthfulness of
um love and sensitivity that comes from meditation
if you want to spread that into your life so that your life is integrated with this
then practice generosity and speaking
do it as an exercise do it as a way of learning about yourself do it as a way of of stretching yourself
do it as a way of understanding other people better be attuned to them rather than just
attune to yourself you better better attune to other people and attune to care for them and but not
at your own expense because you want to stay rooted in generosity and then you can't
sacrifice yourself because you have to really be available for yourself for this
upwelling of this beautiful quality to be there if we diminish yourself or forget yourself or sacrifice yourself too much
for others maybe that generosity is not really there available
so to practice generosity as a practice to learn about yourself to
learn but others to learn about how to relate to other people and i'm confident that
if your gen if your speech is generous to others you might actually be benefiting more than the other people
because uh we all benefit from the the uh the um
from our own generosity when that generosity comes with this upwelling of the heart this
freedom of the heart this loosening up of the constrictions the
fear the defensiveness the resentments the the
ambitions that get in the way of simple ordinary generosity
and you might argue with me that that this is maybe not such a profound
spiritual thing to do or maybe a little bit of a of a sentimental way of practicing or
something artificial way of practicing and that's far from what i intend to get
across but rather it's a vehicle it's a means by which
to really get deep into our hearts and minds to understand it to find out what really makes us tick
and to question it and maybe even debate it and with yourself and really find out uh is
are you really coming from the best place the most nourishing the most healthy place for you
when you speak and if you learn to speak with generosity you'll come from the best place i'm
confident in that you'll come from place that will help you to grow into phenomenal health freedom
and wisdom and understanding so to speak with generosity
so when the buddha taught about speech he talked about five
he said different things at different times but there's a point one uh one list of five criteria for speaking
and um and generosity is not one of them but but maybe all five of these are the
means or the support to help us understand how to speak generously and as a gift
and what they point to is that uh for the buddha buddhist life practice life is also a
reflective life it's a life that reflects and considers what it's doing it doesn't just act
impulsively or intuitively but there's a consideration and that consideration can be
second nature it doesn't be a lot of work but sometimes it's completely appropriate to actually step back and
think go through these like five criteria for speaking so the first one is the question
is what i'm going to say now what i want to say is it timely is it the right time for me
is the right time for the other person is the right time to have the conversation it might be something very
important that needs to be talked about but it's not that time for it someone is stressed out they're busy they're doing
something else they can't focus their mood is not really available for a real
you know conversation about what needs to be talked about um at different time the more receptive
the most different time they're more ready and available so is it timely and and uh
and when it's we ask the question is it timely uh you take into account the circumstance of the other person
is it timely for them and would be better to wait until it's the right time
the second is is it true what i'm gonna say is it truthful and um and here's where
it's so useful to be true to oneself to be honest about to oneself
and to grow in this self-honesty self truth in truthfulness in itself but
self-truth self-honesty in particular is a
is a guaranteed way to grow spiritually guaranteed way to grow on this path of
liberation and freedom keeping back and be really honest this is what's happening this was
and not just with the first thing you see but that to keep looking what's really going on here what's happening
here with me what's really true here it's a way of healing to do so it's a
way of creating healthy relationships to really stay close to what's true and
sometimes what's true is not the right time to speak it to other people but it's always the right time to know
it for yourself so to consider is what i'm saying true is it a is it a lot
you know probably most people don't lie automatically but is it a lie is it a falsehood am i twisting a little bit
am i adjusting what i'm saying so it's mostly true but i'm putting a little spin on it
in order to make it look better or something is it true the third is
um is how i'm going to speak is it gentle and a gentle might mean
is it harmonious is it is it uh with a tone of voice that is friendly
that is uh that people want to hear that feels you know a voice that's supportive for
others as opposed to a voice which is harsh that comes across a kind of critical or
angry or or demanding or something so um so it is is what i'm going to say
can i am i going to say is it gentle or is it harsh the fourth is is it beneficial
is what i'm going to say going to be beneficial does it have a good purpose and and part of that also is that maybe
you'll say yes it's beneficial because of what my purposes i have for it however
i don't think the person is going to be receptive so yes i hope it could be beneficial but in
fact when i realize a person is not perceptive i'm just going to waste my energy to
keep saying this to the person over and over again and so to maybe if it's not going to be beneficial
to say it even though in theory it should be maybe there's no
point of saying it and actually maybe maybe it makes it worse if the person is closed to hearing what i
need to what what i want to talk about is it beneficial um has other
connotation other associations as well is it going to have a good impact on
people it's going to have a good consequence if i say this um maybe i feel it's the
truth maybe i feel like i need to you know i can say it gently
but maybe the person will get angry maybe the person will not want to see with talk with me
anymore and so the doors are closed and that's maybe not beneficial to have
that kind of reaction so is it beneficial that people learn from it do people
change beneficial way because of how we speak what we're saying is it beneficial and there's a lot of
speech which is not particularly beneficial um the uh
yesterday i was at a talk and uh public talk and and uh i kind of thought
that the talk wasn't so you know very good talk um to say it
simply and um and i could i found it so strange that i had this inside i could feel this compulsion
to want to tell my companions you know that wasn't a good talk was it and i look at myself and say why would i
want to say that why bother is it beneficial to say that maybe it's
true that it was a talk wasn't particularly good um but why would i
say that out loud what's uh maybe some another uh approach i can have to talk
about what the person talked about and maybe i can highlight what was beneficial maybe
there was something beneficial in what the person talked about and then we can all benefit from the conversation
if we spend time talking about how it was not a good talk do we benefit from that
so is it timely is it true is what i'm going to say
gentle is it beneficial and the last one is is do i speak with a mind of loving
kindness a line a mind of care a mind of friendliness and um and sometimes
there's difficult conversations being made but can i do that with a mind of kindness
of kind regard or friendly regard for self and others and uh this is the in
the teachings of the buddha this has a very high value very he puts tremendous importance
on this idea of coming from a kind loving space
coming from metta and uh kind of my my assumption and my
understanding of why the buddha puts such a high level of importance on
coming from loving-kindness is that the alternative the more of so often is to come from a
place that's not beneficial to come from a place maybe of ill will
uh it's to come from a place where there's not much freedom that uh good will metta
is when is really genuine when it really is sometimes again this upwelling of the heart when
it's healthy and nourishing it is an expression of freedom it comes from the
kind of letting go of attachments and clinging we're no longer contracted around something or
tight around something and so this idea of opening to the world and so
uh anything less than that it goes in the opposite direction to this uh wonderful dharma path the
dharma path of freedom so if and that's the big big word
if what a person wants what you want is to really take what you're maybe
learning in meditation about yourself and the capacity for freedom for peace
for ease for love finding it here in meditation and and want to kind of not leave it as
something you do only in meditation but to learn how to bring that into the life so that
you live that because maybe that's where real honesty real integrity real being
true to yourself really resides in this place of of
being being free and to bring it into life this is one of the great satisfying tasks
and certainly for me as a teacher this is kind of what i love to hear this is what people want to do is to
is to integrate or bring it into the whole of their life
and so today i'm suggesting that one way to do that is to practice generosity with your
speech have your words be gifts to the people you speak them to
and and learn how to do it in a timely way
and speak what's true speak in a gentle or caring way
speak with what's beneficial and speak with a mind of loving kindness
a heart of loving kindness and in doing that especially the beneficial one
there's a feedback loop that we'll constantly want to kind of reassess and see how was that gift
received was that a useful way to do it because perhaps it takes a while to learn
how to be generous in speech so that it feels authentic for ourselves and and is not too
maybe contrived so that it makes other people actually uncomfortable because there's just too much trying to
be generous how to make it natural and simple and and so that when we speak
maybe we help people smile we help people readjust their direction in which their
mind and heart is going from talking about how a public talk was not such a good thing it wasn't a good
talk and and kind of commiserate with each other oh that wasn't so good
versus talk about something that was beneficial that kind of is a spark of joy and delight and and and
and we benefit from talking about it and so how can we
spread joy and delight and benefit and growth to grow in the dharma
one of the great ways to grow in the dharma is to be truthful
maybe there's very little growth in the dharma without truth that being true true honest to oneself
so those are my thoughts this this day and i hope that it gives you some
suggestions of how to practice in your life and i hope that you benefit from it and
and maybe run it as an experiment for a week and see what you learn in the process of
practicing generosity and speech so um thank you very very much