so i'd like to make a couple of
announcements before giving the talk
i mentioned some time ago that uh i'd
like to offer you
a chance to have some longer meditations
in the morning like we're doing here
we've been doing this for a long time
and
some of us together and some of you are
ready for sitting for more than 30
minutes
some of you are yeah you're ready and
it'll be actually
helpful to have a little longer sit and
also for this topic of vanapanasati
i think that mindfulness of breathing
having a little more
more practice with it and a little
longer sitting would be good as well
and so what i like to do is in two weeks
i think i believe it's the 15th
of february on the 14th i begin a
retreat
and and so i'd like to
integrate the morning sitting with the
retreat and the retreat with the morning
sitting and have our sitting start at
6 45 california time so 15 minutes
earlier than
we usually do so we can have 45 minutes
together and
and and i still still do the guided part
but
there'll be more time for silence we're
settling in
and i think this will also be very good
because of the topics we're coming to
um the uh by then i think we'll be
uh maybe at steps um
nine and ten which has to do with um
uh aspects of really really experiencing
the mind
the cheetah and um
so anyway so that's coming up and you
can certainly join us at seven there's
no problem with that i think
um but um if that's what your schedule
allows but
that's the plan we'll do that for one
week and
um and so i'll announce that a few times
or so make sure people
know about the change and the other is
that
the retreat that i'm doing at that time
and the following retreat at insight
retreat center
um the um we've kind of arranged to have
uh it's full the retreats but for but we
have arranging to have
spots for auditors and if some of you
would like to participate in a retreat
and happy especially if you've been on a
retreat before
and know the you know the basic routine
of how to practice that way
you're welcome to sign up to be an
auditor and
and uh in doing so you might um we have
auditor teachers we have a teacher
for it that is available to have uh
drop-in group discussions with it with
the um
the auditor so they feel a little bit
supported and um but that auditor
teacher won't give any teachings they'll
just be there to support the auditors
um
so anyway so some of you might want to
do that and participate and i think that
the
theme for that retweet starting on the
14th of february
is refuge and so we'll go through the
idea of refuge
as a as a wonderful topic itself but
also as a
support for the deepening practice of
meditation on retreat
so
so last week for anapanasati
talked about the steps
five and six five is
breathing in experiencing joy breathing
out
experiencing joy and then
six is breathing in breathing in
experiencing happiness
breathing out experiencing happiness
and the movement from joy to happiness
is a move towards tranquility
the mind the body becoming more tranquil
where the joy factor
is a little more energetic and the and
the happiness
quality is more subtle more peaceful
tranquil kind of sense of well-being
and that movement from something that's
a little more energetic
to this more tranquil is characterizes
the whole process of deepening
meditation and buddhism
that we're going from coarser states to
more refined subtler states of being
we're going for more active ways of
engaging and as the mind settles down
we're moving towards a clarity and an
alertness and a
peacefulness that where there's things
become
the mind becomes less active more
peaceful more softer
and so the quieting of the mind the
requiring the activity
settling and settling is kind of the
movement we're going here
and um and that's kind of like so the
principle of going from coarse to
refined or
more active to more tranquil states
and tranquil doesn't mean that we go
sleep or that we
become dull the movement is to a
tranquility that's quite
alert or has a lot of clarity to it
um but there's less activity and it's
fascinating process to
see this and one of the things we start
seeing is this relationship between the
mind and the body
and um and
so the first tetrad steps one to four
are kind of about the body and
and but it's not the physical body in
and of itself
it's more the body that um that we
experience
with experience is very much
influenced by what's going on in the
mind
and there's a reciprocal relationship
that as
the mind as the body settles down we get
more focus on the body and it relaxes
more
the fourth step is to relax the body
that also has a
relaxing effect on the mind and other
effects beneficial effects in the minds
it's reassuring for the mind it
brings a sense of safety to the mind
peacefulness to the mind
subtleness and focus to the mind it's
easier to be in the present moment
and and then we go into the second
tetrads now with
steps six seven eight uh five six seven
and eight
that um now we're beginning to enter
into the world of the mind
uh that is not separated from the body
these two are
inter interlinked but we're moving into
the area of the mind
and the qualities of joy and happiness
are a bridge between this
because the joy and happiness is felt in
an embodied way
and and but it's very much influenced by
the concentration level of the mind
the focus of the mind the peacefulness
of the mind
and um and then there's a reciprocal
relationship as there's more joy and
happiness that
courses through the body then that
reassures the mind more and allah and
and reassure a reassured mind will feel
like it doesn't need to think so much
and ruminate so much and can get quieter
so kind of this bridge with joy and
happiness between the
kind of the body and the mind is really
worth lingering with and developing
and and uh and i know it's a little hard
for
from oftentimes to feel joy and
happiness and short notice and just will
it up
like that but even if it you don't feel
this during this time when this section
of the
of the practice um is maybe just
imagine it or not imagine you're having
it but
but uh develop a kind of a intuitive
sense of it or learn these teachings and
sooner and later hopefully you'll
recognize a little bit this
meditative embodied joy happiness
well-being that can happen as we
as we practice and some people are
surprised
or delighted that they're given
permission to feel pleasure in
meditation
permission to feel joy and happiness
and and definitely this is really the
considered to be very important
foundation for moving forward
in many many places in sutas the buddha
actually describes a process
of steepening practice that is called
the
gladness the gladness sequence
or the gladness pentad because those are
five steps
and these are acquiring gladness
in meditation and then it the
description is
is very um kind of intransitive or
passive it's like
from we're not doing the next steps they
just flow
as one becomes mature it flows into the
next flows into the next
we do our practice and the practice
begins practicing
us something begins shifting and
changing and we don't have to be so
responsible except to be really present
for the experience
so with the gladness there arises joy
with the joy when it's mature there
arises a tranquility of the body
with the tranquility of the body there
arises happiness
and with the arising of happiness uh
they're they're with the maturity of
happiness
there rises uh concentration unification
being really unified and sitting and
feeling very whole
here in the present moment and this
wonderful kind of pattern the gladness
sequence
gladness joy tranquility happiness and
concentration
samadhi now what's interesting and what
i want to emphasize today is
the the first step is feeling a sense of
gladness
and the gladness comes from being
inspired by something
and this the buddha really understands
the value of becoming inspired being
gladdened being
delighted by some aspects of what's
happening in our practice or in our
lives
so that it kind of that certain kind of
gladness that we don't get lost in our
thoughts and stories and imagining over
and over again what happened
but we use our imagination just enough
to have that gladness begin settling us
into the present moment more and more
settling us into them into the body
and this use of the imagination to help
us to not make us go wandering away
but using the imagination to allow us to
be inspired
is one of the supports for meditation
practice
and uh and how that inspiration can be
not forced not imaginary not
an avoidance of the present moment but
really a support for really connecting
in a deeper and deeper way
in an honest way with what's really
happening in our lives what's really
present
is one of the great benefits of dharma
practice
to be able to be present even for
difficult things
with some form of well-being
some form of may sometimes joy delight
gladness
that holds it all not to be removed from
the challenges and suffering of the life
of life
but to really in some sense be receptive
to it in a really deep way
and not be a victim of it not be
oppressed by it
but to have compassion and love as a
possible response
so what i'd like to do for the next
maybe a couple of days and we'll see how
far we go
is talk a little bit more about the
buddha's emphasis or use of imagination
focus on teachings on imagination both
as what gets in our way
for meditation interferes with it but
also
in ways in which it supports meditation
and and and
this seems like a very nice bridge
between the mind and the body
this part we're talking about joy and
happiness but because this imagination
is very much to do with this happiness
and joy qualities and um
and to how to uh evoke
joy and happiness gladness with uh what
inspires us through
by thinking about it or something so
that's a topic and
and uh and hopefully you'll get a sense
as we go through these teachings
that how it's useful and connecting you
to uh this steps five and six joy and
happiness
and creates a very good foundation
for the continued settling
becoming more tranquil the mind becoming
more peaceful
it's a preparation for that so we can
look and start looking more deeply at
the mind itself
and the and the quieting settling
pacifying
of the mind so that it becomes an
instrument of awakening
so um that's the introduction for
this week and i look forward to our time
tomorrow and
and um delighted to um
to share this time with you thank you