so welcome to our monday night
drama talk
and so what i had in mind today is to
maybe unpack this poem um
a little bit together and just reflect
upon this poem that i just
uh read
and so i said that this poem sometimes
and the title is translated as a single
excellent night or an auspicious day
the first time when i read this poem and
i was
very touched
without knowing anything about this poem
the context of
it and the significance of it
i took this poem with me on
to various locations i read this poem
to the dharma cistern who's
in the in the hospital bed
and i took this poem and read it
at the memorial service
and i took this poem to my heart
i memorized it and reflected upon this
and so maybe i'll read the discipline
one more time
and then we'll kind of unpack this
together
and now unpack one stanza at a time
it's an auspicious day
the buddha said don't chase the past
or long for the future the past
is left behind the future is not
yet reached right where it is
have insight into whatever phenomenon
is present not watering
and not agitated by knowing
it one develops the mind
argently do what should be done today
who knows death may come tomorrow
there is no bargaining with mortality
and
his great army
whoever dwells thus ardent
active day and night is
says the peaceful sage one who has an
auspicious day
[Music]
so so what does this
mean to not chase the past
or long for the future
past is left behind the future is not
yet
reached
we all probably have experiences of this
and where we
might be chasing the past or lying for
you the for the future
right and for me
right away what becomes a vivid
is you know for
most of us when we are
getting older and older
we chase the youth that we used to have
and we really long for the use where we
had before
and name is pandemic it's probably not
hard to feel this kind of
lying for the past
or the future and the vacation
the vacations that you used to have
where you can travel to different places
and we can't be chasing the past
in this way you know whatever
accomplishments that we may have had
in our earlier careers and work and job
family or maybe even
you know you were the dance champion in
high school
and so in the suta and this is the maj
manika
yeah one one and let me see 131
where this poem shows up and the buddha
explained this
how does one chase after the past
and he said one gets carried away
with the delight of
in the past i had such a form or such a
body
in the past i had such a feeling
in the past i had such a perception in
the past i had such
a thought fabrication or mental
formation
in the past i had such a consciousness
this is called chasing after the past
i don't know if everyone is familiar
with this particular formula
and in that the buddha is
pointing at how one gets stuck
in the past and getting carried away by
it
endless ways that are related to
ourselves through this um this list
that's called the five aggregates
those are the things that we often
identify as
ourselves i mean
this is me
and i'm struck by the key word that's
being used
here um by the buddha and that is
and he defines how one chases the past
by that one would take delight
in the past
and this form of a taking delight could
be you know
and really getting um
consumed by the past in that
you know that may be pleasant
experiences we had
before and who we were before in the
past
and this taking delight
could also happen even when it's
unpleasant
it experiences unpleasant history
we could be defined by those
and when we're being defined by them
we get hooked by the past
even when we do not like them
you know sometimes um i can see
you know and then and sometimes i had a
certain recognition
that you know i used to be this way i
really didn't
didn't like it but somehow being really
annoyed by it
i actually get hooked by how
i and how i get myself identified with
those
and so this is taking delight in
the past this way or that way that
we how we are and how does one
not chase after the past and the buddha
continued by saying
well if one does not get get carried
away
with the delight in the past
in that and i in the past i had this
kind of a form
or the feelings and perception or the
mental formations or the consciousness
and then this is called
not chasing after the past
and so the formulae is quite simple you
know if we stop
being consumed to stop taking delight
in the past and we no longer
have that kind of um
[Music]
uh force
in us to begin to chase the past anymore
so so this recognition that
there is a possibility there is a choice
not to get swept away in the past
so how do we really do that
in our meditation practice in our
mindfulness practice
when i began to notice that
one is being hooked
by the memory and by the history by the
stories that were lived
in the past and that's when we began to
have
a choice well we see
wow you know here here i am
but i'm hooked by this story and i
recognize this is happening
when we begin to recognize that this is
happening
this is where um
detaching from
being taking delight in them
or detaching from being
attracted by the past the story of the
past
we can begin to loosen the hook with
it and often
what happens is when we're being mindful
we can for example rest our attention
in the body shifting from the stories of
the past
to what's happening in our body
then the memory and the images that came
from the past
can simply become kind of a
ripple that flow through in our
awareness
there's no need for the story of the
memory
and the the past to take a foot
in us so it's possible that
you know our mind may have a thoughts of
the past or the stories
but they don't have to be a problem
[Music]
it's when we begin to take delight in
them and really being
consumed by them that we get swept away
but when we're aware we can see
the memories as simply memories
they flow through like clouds in the
wide open sky
and similarly how does one
long for the future the buddha used a
similar language
no one one gets carried away with the
delight
in the future you know i might become
this way
i might become that way
and that this is becoming this is
what in the sutra it says this is called
placing expectations on the future
we all have this kind of experience in
our own
lived experience right
and maybe
there are lots of examples that we can
take
we're not comfortable with what is
happening here and now
sometimes we construct
a future in our head
and then we hook onto this
kind of constructed experience and we
really go after that
and to pull us out of what is happening
in the present experience
and so there's a form of expectations
in the future here's a construction
of um
it is a form of a mental construction
and we can believe in them so strongly
that they
become almost real for us
and similarly the buddha kind of
explained
you know how not to place expectations
in the future
and and and the the same formula was
prescribed by not
do not get carried away with the delight
in the future
and it's easy said and then dumb
you know we all know that and it's very
easy to fall
into this form of a taking delight
but what it takes is to become
recognized that this is happening
you know maybe expectation expectation
or projection is happening
and allow ourselves to then rest into
the field of awareness
to simply notice projection being
projection
and planning being planning our
expectations being expectations
sometimes they're really momentary maybe
they're just
one or two thoughts they come and go
just like a snap of the finger
but if a feed onto them you know
continue
to plan and
tell our stories and
and this can become something really big
take us away
but when we began to see
this expectations the simply being
expectations the thoughts as a thoughts
there is a real sense of lightness
in all of this experiences
and so the next stanza the buddha
brought us back
to where where it is here and now
why right where it is have insight
into whatever phenomena is present
not fattering and not agitated
by knowing it one develops mine
and it's disappointing that
this is this moment is where we live
the present moment the present
experience
the present phenomenon is
where we live and this is where
insight
can happen and this is where we practice
this is the field of our practice
but very interesting though in the sutta
it says that even in this
practicing with the present experience
there can be two ways
and one way is skillful and one way is
not very skillful
so when i first direct this i was kind
of puzzled wow
you know i thought being present was you
know it would be all
good and fine but there can be a way
that one will be
being present and we there can be still
unskillfulness in there
so how is that possible
and so let's let's take a look at this
so what happens is with respect to the
present experiences the present
qualities
an unskilled person can take
whatever is arising as i
me my
so what happened
so whatever is happening
[Music]
in one way an unskillful way
is that we take that this is me
for example right now
if there is a little moment of a sadness
that happened
in the field of emotion
one way to relate to this
sadness momentary sadness that
i'm a sad person i've always been
there sad so much sorrow in me
now what happens
we began to construct
myself in this simple moment of sadness
a moment of grief
oh my god
i am really miserable i've always
been very miserable i don't know how to
get out of this
and this is what the buddha is pointing
at
we can make self out of the momentary
experience that's happening and when we
do this
what happens is we get
hardened into this experiences
and this becomes more permanent than
what it
is
and most of the time our emotions flows
up and down this way and that way
throughout the day but we can oftentimes
pick onto hook onto
certain forms of emotion and make
it ourselves
i remember gil fransto sometimes would
teach
that it is more skillful to be
situational centric
rather than self-centric
or you know in another word in this
particular suta maybe we can say
it's a phenomenon centric rather than
self-centric
whatever phenomena or situation that
comes about
in our present lived experience
we simply see this as the situation
or the phenomenon
and this is the skillful way of
being with our experiences and the
self-centric approach
would be turning everything that is
happening into
something related to i me and mine
and for example you know if you drop a
plate on the floor
maybe the immediate the reaction would
be i am so sloppy
but is it is it really all about you
i use it to just well this is a
situation that just happened
and so i get identified with the
situation
what happens is there can be a lot
of dukkha a lot of stress that comes
along with it
our experiences become stuck
and no longer flows
like the clouds in the in the sky
and so the opposite and that if if we're
not
taking this phenomenon
and the situations as i mean mine
and there can be simple transient
changing
experiences arising in passing
and when this happens there can be a
quality of
not being wavered or shaken
by agitation by farthering
the agitation happens when there is a
center
like the center of the self
when there is no center of self
the agitation cannot shake anything
there's nothing to shake
so when one develops the mind in this
way
mind will no longer be shaky
or restless
and so the poem goes on
by encouraging this
and so the the next stanza says
ardently do what should be done today
who knows death may come tomorrow
there's no bargaining with mortality
and his great army
i don't know what more is to be said
about this particular line
because it is true
we don't know we don't know
when death may come
it may not even be tomorrow maybe next
moment
and i know this can be can sound
um untrue unreal
but we really don't know
and oftentimes you know our
intellectual mind understands that you
know
when everybody gets born and
death will be part of it i think
one of my teachers philip muffett
sometimes would like to quote his
teacher john sumato
and that birth
has a death as life sentence
and it's it's true and yet um
we often live our lives with the
complete denial
that this might happen to us it might
happen
anytime
and so the buddha knows this
and knows the preciousness of a
practicing
in this moment here and now
and so argently do what should be done
today
ardently do what should be done right
now
because we don't know
and the poem ended with this line
whoever dwells thus ardent
active day and night
yes says the peaceful sage
one who has an auspicious day
i love this definition because
oftentimes we associate
auspicious day with some i don't know
special days
like yesterday i know it's a full moon
day
and even in the buddhist tradition and
maybe many different spiritual
traditions full moon days
is considered to be auspicious day
but the buddha had a different
definition for this
whoever dwells thus ardent active day
and night
practicing ardently day and night
this
says the peaceful sage is the one who
has an auspicious day
i love it because this makes
the practice very accessible we don't
have to wait for
some special day in order to practice
this day if we practice here and now
it's an auspicious day
the other translation a single excellent
night
or an an excellent day
and so we just need to become become
fully present become aware
of what is happening cultivating our
mind
skillfully
seeing what's true
right in front of us
this is where the peace lies and this is
where the freedom
is found
i'm gonna close tonight by just reading
this poem
one more time maybe by now the few lines
even
sinked in in you in some way
the buddha said don't chase the past
or long for the future the past
is left behind the future
is not yet reached
right where it is have insight
into whatever phenomenon is present
not fartering and not agitated
by knowing it one develops the mind
ardently do what should be done today
who knows
death may come tomorrow there is no
bargaining with mortality
and his great army whoever
dwells thus ardent
active day and night is
says the peaceful sage one
who has an auspicious day
may you all have an excellent night
so take good care
[Music]
you