so warm greetings welcome to the meditation session and
welcome into this meditation community of ours
and if this is your first time special welcome and you get a sense of the
goodwill in this community through the chat that represents well many people
who come so um
many years ago a good number of years ago um
i went to with my young son who was maybe 13 maybe um
went for the only time in my life where i really went to play a round of golf
i don't know anything really about golf and i thought it'd be fun to go with him it was
fun and it turned out to be that that first tea
of phenomenally difficult to hit the ball i was so surprised how many times i
whiffed the ball on the tee and i remember finally hitting uh hitting a really good solid clunk
against the ball and i thought you know the immediate thought was wow this is great
and um and the ball rolled about four feet
as we went around the course there was maybe two maybe three times where i hit the ball off the tee
pretty nicely for me and you could hear in the in the smack
against the ball the club against the ball that something was right
and then the ball lifted up into the air and as it did so
my mind got really quiet it's kind of like time stopped and my mind just focused on the ball
going up up up out away sailing through the air and then sailing down quite
you know for me far away down the green and and i thought oh this is my thought at
the time was oh this is why people do golf the feeling of time stopping and the
feeling of just kind of fully almost like becoming the ball flying
through the air was uh was such a kind of wonderful
feeling of being standing there in harmony and with the natural world around me
so this idea of quieting the mind and
really being present for something in the wonder of this life that
is part of what can happen in meditation it's not easy of course for this to happen
but as we learn the art of release letting go quieting your thoughts
letting go of our thoughts one of the places that it's sometimes possible
to have the same kind of feeling as you would have i had watching the ball sail through the air
is is watching the breathing
kind of really but it's not so much the breathing that's so interesting as it is
when the mind becomes still and quiet and and the attention
is really just almost absorbed in the breathing or
becomes the breathing or there's no feeling of separation between awareness and breathing it's just like
in the in the breathing there's awareness in the breathing there's awareness in awareness there's breathing
and there's very little else going on or if there is it is receded far in the background
so to do that as i said
involves a quieting of the thinking mind and some people focus on the idea of
letting go of their thoughts or quieting their thoughts as a permanent thing to sit down and
you're able to quiet it but it might be more useful to think of it as happening in very small short
segments small little episodes that uh and to appreciate the small
maybe second half a second a moment when something about the thinking mind
has paused quietly there's a gap between thoughts and there what is that what is the
wondrous there what is it like to welcome or allow the breathing to
really sail through that awareness like the golf ball sailing through
the air so for this meditation
i'd like to suggest that the practice be a lot to do with letting go a lot of
these so you have a lot of these momentary episodes of letting go and being quiet
and so that more and more the awareness
is fully available for just the breathing so the awareness is not split between
thinking and trying to be with the breathing but that because when you're thinking
part of your awareness is dedicated to thinking and to let all that dedication of
awareness go into just breathing just breathing without any concern that
you're trying to do anything more than just um
allowing welcoming the experience of breathing into awareness
so i'll guide us through it a little bit here so taking in an upright posture
and lowering your gaze
and gently closing your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
and on the exhale relaxing
deep breath in and a releasing of
the shoulders the belly
maybe they also on the exhale that can be release of any holding in the small of the back
any tightening or holding in the thighs or the arms
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and with a normal breath not focusing so much on working at breathing
maybe there's more attention that can go to the subtlety of holding in your body
even the quiet subtle places where the body's tense or held
as you exhale relax let go
and also as you exhale to soften the mind
relax the thinking mind especially if you can identify any
tension pressure tightness
agitation physical agitation that's related connected to breathe to
thinking
maybe as you're breathing to relax let go of your thoughts
maybe you're thinking or like a piece of cloth that is
bunched up creased and as you exhale you're flattening it
out straightening it out quieting the thinking mind
and then become aware of the transition from the exhale to the inhale
and in that transition welcome allow
yourself to receive the inhale
and as you exhale let go of your thoughts
and as you exhale and let go let go into
the body's exhale
see if see if you can in letting go of thoughts quieting thoughts
for a few couple of moments give your full attention
to the experience of the body exhaling
maybe like you're watching a ball flying through the air bird
flying through the air marveling
at this natural process of breathing
every time you exhale let go of your thinking
as if you're opening up a door or window
to let the breeze of exhaling
move through you
and with every exhale that you let go of your thinking don't concern yourself with how well you
can do this that's just more thinking
be content to do it the best that is available
appreciating whatever degree there's more awareness available
to receive the experience of inhale exhale
as if for these minutes meditating the most important thing to do the most
important thing happening is the body breathing
and you letting go of everything else
so you can attend a company your body breathing
feeling your way into the deeper places that you can let go
letting go and letting go into that and then letting go into your breathing
so
so then as we come to the end of sitting
one of the significant consequence of
letting go release is that we become available
to experience the gifts of this life
when the mind is preoccupied in thoughts and anxiety
there's little room to be available for the wonder
of our moment-to-moment life
and if we turn that availability of attention available to
see available to listen available to perceive and be with other
people perhaps people will more often be seen
as a gift as a wonder
maybe there's more ability to care and love have good will
to listen deeply to hear deeply to see deeply
others and perhaps as we come to the end of the
sitting you can imagine
in the best of circumstances what it's like to be
to let go deeply of your concerns your thoughts judgments
and to be available to others available in the sense available to
perceive them to see them to know them
so that they are seen clearly known clearly
and they feel safe they feel known they feel cared for
loved may it be that this meditation we do
always has a role
in the social world that we live in always has a role to
help make this a better world for ourselves and for others
may our ability to be available with our attention
support the welfare and happiness of others may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free and may we
maybe in humble ways contribute to that
[Music]
hey
so on this fifth talk about mindfulness of breathing
the topic is release and now there is a saying in
english buddhist english maybe because it rhymes that release is peace
so there's something about the proper or appropriate way of letting go
that leads to peace it leads to
an availability when attention is hijacked
by our preoccupations excuse me here
i don't have the mute button for the time being so i have to hopefully take the mic away
from my mouth took off clear my throat so
to um to let go properly you were letting go of the things that
preoccupy our attention or awareness so awareness becomes more available
as awareness becomes more available we're available to what is happening
and some of those things are uncomfortable suffering or challenges
and there's something very special about being available to see it perceive it to know it
as opposed to not being available which kind of implies or leads to maybe feeling
like it's a problem or it's right to fix it or feeling oppressed by it
just available oh this is difficult it also helps us to be available for
love to be able to love or care or have good will to be friendly
and so this idea of letting go letting go gives lends us it gives us
all these wonderful gifts and the gifts of being available to the world
it's a wonderful feeling to really be present walking and be available rather than asserting ourselves into the world
and you know seeing the world through my our wants and our fears and our aversions
but being available to what's happening is um
also tends to lend itself to um much more perceived that this world is a
gift what happens rather than a right
or a should or something
so how does this relate to mindfulness of breathing as we
settle down in meditation and settle into something it doesn't have to be the breathing some primary focus
that's appropriate for us and so breathing is for many people works as we settle down into the breathing
that and more and more of our attention is able to stay with the breathing more we let go of our preoccupations our
thoughts um if they're easy enough to let go of just let go and come back to the
breathing let go and let go into the breathing let go and receive the experience of breathing
and root ourselves in the breathing the more that attention is available for breathing the more the
sense of availability the feeling of being available comes and the less we are caught up in the
world of thoughts of ideas of experiences memories few projections into the future
that tend to be agitating and and so we're more available
attention becomes more available for the breathing but as it becomes more available for the breathing the reciprocal aspect of that
is that we're less caught up and and so the more you're able to focus on
the breathing the more there is also kind of a natural letting go or letting things fall away or no longer being
involved in them so sometimes we let go of thoughts and sometimes we just hold the course
with the breathing staying with the breath and less energy than is given to the preoccupations
and as more attention goes to the breathing the more awareness gets gathered it gets available it's present
it's not kind of caught up in things which are not so healthy for us
now the opposite you know this the benefit of
breathing on meditation isn't just that we can do it but when we're the sense of availability
also means we're available to what makes it difficult to be with the breathing
and there are powerful forces in us that keep us distracted keep us caught up in
thoughts keep us swirling in our emotional life
those should be respected deeply and they're not should be dismissed or feel like they're you know unwanted
but to let go of what's easy enough to let go of or to stay focused on the breath in the way
that's relatively easy to stay focused and then being available
for for seeing more clearly what's going on in us and that's one of the values of
meditation and breathing is not being successful at the breathing staying with the breathing but how the
effort to be with the breathing highlights more what's really happening for us
if we're some people are so distracted by their distractions they don't know they're distracted
but if we have this reference point of of attempting to be with a breath
don't if even if you're not able to do it much just the effort to do it
is beneficial if it shows us much more clearly what it is is happening for us that
keeps us away from breathing the preoccupations we have and then this idea of being available
for that oh so this too should be cared for should be
should be you know loved in a certain kind of way and uh so in the next weeks i'll talk
about mindfulness of the body mindfulness of emotions mindfulness thinking that
is kind of how we practice with the things that are revealed
as we attempt to do mindfulness of breathing but these other things then get highlighted
and so sometimes it's a completely appropriate to not stay with the breath it's kind of
to fight against everything else and stay with the breath is counterproductive
and so the art of learning to let go of breathing sometimes to attend to these other things
is part of what you know i'll be teaching over the next few weeks but for now the topic is a
release with breathing and if you're able to kind of really settle in
get gather yourself on the breathing there's a natural process of things being let go of or
our concerns of the day the memories the the resentments we have that for the
time being kind of get forgotten and one of the values of meditation
something simple as breathing over and over coming back to the breathing is the way that um
the kind of a cleansing kind of emptying of the preoccupations of the day the
momentum of in the mind that goes on and so there's kind of a release that goes on
and sometimes it's appropriate to support that release by a little bit of active efforts at letting go
and uh and that i i see that the exhaled maybe other people would be the inhale
but for me it's the exhale that is a wonderful place to let go of my thoughts
it's amazing uh till to this day how thoughts kind of sneak in quietly
through the back door of the mind so that uh sometimes i don't really notice that i started to think again
and um but by every time i begin exhaling it's a time to kind of notice
in my thinking and if it's easy enough to let go and let go into the breathing
to let go into a receiving of the experience of breath and if i can let go with the exhale
then i'm more available more present to be able to receive the gift of the inhale the arising the
appearing of the inhalation as it occurs
and this rhythm of letting go with the exhale and receiving on the
inhale sometimes is a wonderful way of supporting this process of release
and um but in this way that i'm talking now about uh letting go on the exhale
it puts a lot of agency in the meditator like this is what that meditator is supposed to do
and that also kind of can keep us agitated and keep us kind of preoccupied
and so sometimes we want to kind of try to do this with a very light touch without expectation without need for
anything really to happen without using it to judge ourselves or to be in
a hurry as if we have lots of time in the world and uh and sometimes if there's too much
self going on and efforting then sometimes it's easier just to kind of
just simply very simplistically stay with the breath the best you can
hang in there gather yourself on the breathing and don't worry so much about letting go
the letting go will happen by itself the more we get gathered around the experience of breathing
and uh and then as we keep practicing that time will come it will feel obvious
that the right thing to do is to let go that it's such a healthy thing to let go
of what is unhealthy when it's not helpful what it diminishes us or brings that more
agitation into us and the quieter the mind becomes the more peaceful we are the more we can see
oh here i'm getting involved in that thought again i've done that a thousand times i don't
need to do that and let go and then let go back into
letting go into back into the breathing coming back just breathing in and breathing out
and uh the deeper we go in meditation the more that experience can be
characterized as a release either that something so released that's very
gradual over time or something that's very clear like a big shift that happens
suddenly there's a little like quantum shift boom and now we're here in a fuller way and embodied in a fuller way
or something um but release release is peace
release helps us become available for our experience in our life and the people in our life
that availability makes us available to know suffering
more intimately clearly but not as to suffer more
but to care more to meet it in a new way maybe with love
there's something about the availability to the challenging aspects of our life the
suffering that can give rise to real real love and compassion and care
good will and love supports letting go
letting go to be available to be available to feel
the fullness of this life all the aspects more fully and then perhaps to love some more
and so we go around and around and i hope that
you will trust mindfulness of breathing give yourself over to it if you continue
meditating through the weekend really kind of trust it and be intimate with it and
see if some of what i'm talking about can uh you can feel or sense
in the in the very very simplicity of mindfulness or breathing
and then on monday we'll talk about um
we'll talk about mindfulness of the body
and uh and have a week on that so thank you all very much