so here you are
you're all each of you is there and you're here here spot your spot for
being here and i think we should never
overlook the hereness of this moment the hereness of where we
are and where we're going to meditate to be here
not as a coincidence not as something to overlook not as something that is insignificant
but rather here is the most important place for this
moment for this meditation and so to assume a posture
for being here
to be rooted to this place and to this time
and to feel the connection of your body to this location
the way your the weight of your body is received by whatever
body that's that in a sense stops the pull of
gravity that keeps you in this location
and to adjust the body a bit especially it's nice to adjust it so the
breathing can be a freer more relaxed more open without
getting tense and without straining maybe it's something you can do with a
spine that frees up the front of the torso so
the breathing can be more easeful maybe sitting up a little
straighter in the spine
and then to
see if you can take some deeper breaths that are enjoyable for you to take
so maybe for you it's to do just a little bit deeper than
what you're already doing or maybe doing it slowly
maybe the feeling of depth or fullness of breathing is done more in the belly or more in the
top of the chest or middle of the chest
or maybe the sense of enjoyable fuller deeper breathing
is a more subtle expansion of the back ribcage
or maybe there's something pleasant about in a deep full breath the gentle
pressure downward as you breathe in
the diaphragm pushes down and pushes down the intestines and
innards there and perhaps
that pushing down a gentle pushing down is a grounding here to this spot
and as you exhale is there any place in your body that would be
kind of pleasant or enjoyable to relax or soften
instead of maybe pleasant or enjoyable any place in your body as you exhale
it would be nice to relax
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and take a few breaths to familiarize yourself with your breathing
noticing the places in your body that move the most as you breathe
and where there's movement in the breathing but the movement is just light
and then once again to take a few deeper breaths gently
quietly not too much
if if it happens to be that you feel some resistance or holding
back at the top of the in-breath
see if you can relax around that place of holding resistance not ambitiously
but more as a expression of kindness to yourself and
a willingness to relax there
and at the end of the exhale is there also some holding back
and if so can you relax and release the end of the exhale
maybe the exhale is a little bit longer
and then again letting the breathing return to normal
and feel your breathing now perhaps by letting the thinking mind
become quieter it allows you to have more attention
when feeling the body breathing
and then ever so gently maybe just very slightly
within the range of what could be considered normal breathing see if there's some simple
ways to adjust your breathing to make it more pleasant
a little bit slower a little bit faster
a little fuller
a little bit more shallow and a smaller breath
maybe you find it a little bit more pleasant to breathe more fully into the belly or more fully into the
chest
or to really focus on the sensations of air going in and out through the
nostrils and notice
if if there is any feelings of pleasure or pleasantness in the breathing
that it's pleasant to breathe maybe not so much your effort to breathe
but the sensations are in the body of breathing
is there anything about them that feels pleasant enjoyable or comforting
it can be very slight
any small ways you can adjust around your breathing
maybe by being aware of a smaller little spot in your body where it's most pleasant
or maybe it's a broad awareness of the body breathing over a larger spot or the whole
torso and then as you exhale
relax your body more and in order to settle into your breathing
settling in to be with your breathing
for these minutes we're together
and if your mind wanders off in thought when you begin again with your breathing
spend a few breaths re-establishing
an enjoyable breath the pleasant breathing
even if it's just one little piece of the cycle of breathing
or maybe just reestablish a breathing which is a
little bit feels a little bit better than what you were doing
every time the mind wanders off spend a little bit of time
reconnecting to whatever is good about breathing in and breathing out
let the thinking mind become quieter so you can be in your body more
feeling the embodied experience of
breathing
can you relax your belly as you breathe
maybe it's more present pleasant to breathe to breathe a little bit further behind
to feel the area just little bits in the back of where you feel breathing
not so much exactly in the center of your breathing area
but kind of like the little bit in the back of it
just behind it or in the back side of it so that maybe there's a little bit less sense of
control or there's a lighter [Music]
more delicate feeling of breathing
and while you're focusing on breathing so your central vision central awareness
is on breathing peripherally see if you can allow the
to have the body be allowing receptive
the body is open willing to experience
the influence of breathing
it's kind of like breathing
is a gentle wind
that spreads its influence across the
body or a light that's been turned on that
glows outwards
letting the body be receptive allowing for whatever
influence the focus on breathing might have
not looking for something particular just available
with breathing at the center
um quietly receiving the bodies breathing
and perhaps breathing within within whatever larger
context of pleasure or joy or contentment there might be
whatever larger feeling of wholeness
calmness so breathing is at the center of a wider field
of goodness wholeness settledness
pleasure joy happiness
the thinking mind becomes quieter so attention can better
feel and sense the fullness of the
the way breathing spreads its influence out into the
goodness around it
the wholeness around it
and there might be ways that you do not feel calm or do not feel pleasure
that you're uncomfortable it's okay but there might also be in
addition to that around it underneath it in the middle of
it somewhere the opposite feelings
a wholeness a calmness that holds it all
lorry can accept it all
an ability to stay gently aware of the breathing the rhythm of breathing so you're not
preoccupied by the discomfort it can be there but let it be just a
piece of the picture in the background you just breathing
and then sitting here quietly at the end of this meditation
is there anything that feels
more settled for you calmer for you having done this
meditation in some way or other do you feel
better than you were when you started the meditation
and if you do
if you if you would like you could offer
the goodness of your meditation how you're calmer more settled
maybe even a little happier peaceful offer that
for the welfare and happiness of others or dedicate it
let it be dedicated in some way or other that you use that
that it's the basis for benefiting the world out into the
world may it be a force may it be a avenue
support for bringing greater comfort and peace calm joy
love into the world and may we
do that a little bit actively not just as a wish
but as an inspiration for
being concerned for the welfare of others
may it be [Music]
that this meditation is dedicated to the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings
be free may all beings be peaceful
and may our love and our care support that possibility
[Music]
so i thought that before kind of going further with anapanasati with this
practice of mindfulness of breathing to kind of uh kind of start over again
in a little bit way if maybe a little different way and stay more with the basic
most basic aspect of the practice and over these weeks that i've been doing this i've offered
a variety of maybe subtly different ways of being with the breath and breathing and different ways
different little different little different each time it isn't that you have to remember all
those ways and and uh but rather maybe some of them
work for you inspire you in some way and it can be a basis of how you
practice and so the wider range that i give perhaps the more likely you'll find something
you'll piece together parts of it the subtle different ways of being with the breathing and work with
the breathing and the meditation and breath and um and i also wanted to kind of just
stay real basic today rather rather than moving further along the steps
as i said yesterday in some ways as we're going through slowly in some ways we're going through it very fast and
you know maybe it'd be ideal to spend a year going through the steps
and um and so uh it's on monday you know we'll start and
i'll go a little bit further and the next stages of the next steps of it are quite fascinating or very very
significant for this working with this meditation practice but before we
go on that way i wanted to um
maybe take some questions from you we've been doing this breath meditation now for a few weeks
and maybe it'll be nice if you had a chance a few of you had a chance to ask some questions and and if you can put them in the chat and
then i'll try to respond and maybe uh the questions that i pick out of the
chat uh hopefully they are relevant for many of you and be interesting to kind of have some at
least interesting for me to get some feedback or some hearing about learning a little bit about the kind of questions you have or
challenges you have with it or joys you have with it or something
and the um and the ways you know if there are a lot
of chat questions uh sometimes i can't really follow them in order and they're in place
because they passed by so quickly and i i try to do a little bit that way but
maybe we can think of it more as i'm pulling questions out of the hat than than uh and doing it in sequence
and um so someone said i experienced anxiety
um and um there's no question but it's interesting that anxiety um is a
i think it comes from a greek word to choke and like choke to not really be able to breathe fully in
so this kind of working the edge of where the breathing is held or resisted
or is sometimes can be helpful with anxiety
kind of expanding it relaxing that how can this help with the severe
chronic pain the um it might not help
i mean i can't promise you that this will help there are plenty of people who find that
breath meditation helps can help with severe pain certainly i've had lots of
severe pain in meditation but not chronic but certainly severe at times and
one of the surprises is to discover that it's possible to feel joy and pain at the same time it's
possible to have become and feel pain at the same time it's kind of like two different sides two different parts different aspects of
the of our being and often if we identify too much with a pain or we
too preoccupied with it or too caught up in it then that influences kind of the inner
state of how we are but if we don't identify two with it or aren't too preoccupied with it it's
there and we don't ignore it um but um then their inner interstate
inner state of our emotional state our mood and all that doesn't have to be tied to it and so the
interstate can be peaceful or calm and that doesn't necessarily make the pain go away
but it creates a different context for being with the pain so that the pain isn't the primary
influence on us but there's some other something inside which is an influence that might actually influence the pain
in some way i've also when i've had severe pain
in meditation or in life i sometimes have um i just breathe through it and around the
place of pain and it depends a little bit probably what kind of pain it is but uh sometimes uh just breathing
through it and and or with it i don't identify with it so much and there's a little
little sense of relaxation a little sense of something releases then and and if nothing what releases is that my
preoccupation with it there's much more to be said about pain but for now have you experienced all 16
sure and sometimes i've experienced them
sequentially one to the other usually but sometimes it's more random you know sit down to meditate
and i find myself some points different points of the of the steps or i'll jump ahead or seems
like go through it quickly and and one of the steps becomes more the predominant one for the day
and um so so you know but yeah um
oh what does it mean when the body disappears and there's no question mark so if that's already disappeared too
generally when the body disappears in meditation it means we're concentrated it means the the thinking mind has
become quiet quiet enough that um that we're not conceptualizing
about the body it turns out that it's a little hard to imagine you know if you have never experienced it
but it turns out that a lot of the ways in which we experience the body is mediated through our thoughts and
ideas through the activity of the mind that constructs the body and so uh
so for example with eyesight i'm seeing we all these little photon light
particles travel into the eye they get turned upside down in the eye and go against the retina and
and then there's these electrical signals the nerves that send these signals up into the brain and
then the brain reconstructs the signals into something which is a simile of the
world out there the world that was seen and sometimes that reconstruction is not accurate
as when you know you see a twig on the ground and you first you see it as a snake and um
or i've seen people in the distance in a crowd strangers but uh for a moment i thought it was a
friend of mine because there was enough similarity and then i filled in the blank to kind of see my friend and then i looked more
carefully no it's not my friend so the reconstruction process is is an
activity the mind does as the mind gets calmer it's not reconstructing so much
and as it doesn't reconstruct it doesn't it's not taking the signals or doesn't have the signals from the body
uh to reconstruct and it just um and it feels like the body is disappearing and um and sometimes it disappears
entirely and i've actually sometimes thought you know i had to open my eyes in meditation to
make sure that i was still here because it just felt so you know empty
sometimes there's an intermediate stage where we're still the mind is still
reconstructing uh sensations but it's not really doing it accurately anymore
and so sometimes people's uh in meditation they'll feel really like they get elongated like they're about to
touch the ceiling or they feel really squat their hands feel like they're getting really big usually it's not particularly
you know you know you know unusual it's just kind of little
perceptual distortion and it's usually a particular stage and then when people go deep just it also
doesn't last for too long and then after a while the capacity to settle and get more concentrated settles in and
and that perceptual distortion stops um
is it important to follow the steps uh in order um like i just said no sometimes it's
helpful to do so because it it can't help the concentration just you're on task
and you're just going to do it and sometimes it's not to do it on tasks and do a technique and kind of follow
something makes the mind too busy and and sometimes what happens is we
start with the first one we just start with breath meditation and getting settled in and then rather
than following this you know implying and following the steps exactly we are
we're recognizing as we deepen the practice we recognize the steps we recognize where we are
and because we can recognize it maybe it becomes a little fuller and we can let it become fuller and more
complete and then it just on its own it moves into the next step into the next step and i prefer
that way rather than kind of intentionally moving ahead when you know it's a time to move ahead now
it's more like you do your practice and you just kind of allow it to unfold in its own way and
sometimes it jumps around it doesn't have to be the same linear steps
how to work with controlling breath this is really common the i think the
the most useful thing to do is um not worry about it and
don't be bothered by it allow yourself to have a controlled breath and and you can cultivate just a strong
mindfulness and concentration with a controlled breath with the breath that's not controlled
it's not the breath that is the main issue it's really the main issues the quality of the attention you bring
also if you're not bothered with it you're more likely to get out of its way when we're bothered by a controlled
breath we actually in some subtle way reinforce it and it makes it more difficult to let go
also it can be very interesting to become a connoisseur of the controlled breath just be content to have a
controlled breath and then get to know it really well like where exactly is the sense of control where's the tightness the resistance
the pushing what are the emotions that are connected to it are there anything anything emotional
any beliefs connected to it just really get to know it inside and out and sometimes that
really getting to know it sometimes is a little trick because after a while focusing on that way directly kind of uh
disarms the control and sometimes you discover something interesting that needs to be relaxed and released then then it
becomes easier to to to do it so that's one of the things i would do
another thing that i've done you know i've done so much of this over the years that i've depending on times i've done different
things sometimes with that when i had a controlled breath uh i imagine that uh i was bringing my
attention uh from the back forward like going in through the back door my back rib cage and just feeling it in
the back rib cage where there's very little sense of control in the back ribcage and i felt the breath there for a while
and then that kind of relaxed the control in the front and then i slowly moved my attention forward gingerly
without kind of triggering the control
um
i have a challenge in the out breath smaller and belly tight your suggestion
observing the end of the in-breath at the end of the out breath is helpful since i
do get anxious there so any thoughts about that
i think a little bit same as with the control you know it's it's very very significant just simply to
recognize and observe what we're actually doing and um and there's a tendency when we
see something about ourselves to have judgments or reactions or think it should be different
but don't underestimate how very significant it is that you're just observing it and seeing it
and it might be all you need to do and i've had all kinds of ways in which you know i've been anxious
or tight in my breathing controlling my breathing all kinds of things about it
that i just allowed myself to feel it know it and there's continued with the breathing
kind of like the breathing is just a massage for it and i find it interesting that as a
massage some point in the in-breath is more like the
the heart of the massage and then like pushing it and then relaxing sometimes the top of the in-breath
sometimes the end of the out breath depends what's going on and just kind of like be with the rhythm be and and find a way
to be really content like you're in it for the long term like you're not trying to fix it you're not
you know pretty concerned about it not just okay just recognize oh
i'm you know it's uh it's unpleasant it's tight it's controlled there's anxiety and i just
breathe with it you know and we're going to be friends and just breathe and breathe and that kind of attitude sometimes is a
very effective way to over time the things just settle without us being involved in all kinds of mental
uh preoccupations and that often just kind of stir it up even more sometimes
um yes let's do another zoom soon to chat
with sangha yeah we'll do it maybe we can do it next week it depends a little bit about you know it depends
whether i have time and right now i have a number of
uh it thinks i'm having to take care of my
life that makes it a little harder
any idea for trauma survivors and disassociation sometimes i may think i'm concentrated maybe i'm
disassociated yeah i mean certainly
uh trauma survivors have their own path and and the care that's needed for
breath meditation and for meditation in general and it's a it's a noble path it's a
dignified path for people who've had trauma to work through and work with
their trauma in meditation and and all that but it often needs a little different
kind of attention than the kind of the basic usual you know instructions that i would give
the um the you know it usually what's really
good is a lot of compassion and a lot of care a lot of generosity to oneself
and a lot of patience with it all and and permission to not have to go
headlong into the trauma or the fear or something it's fine to be at the edges of it and
and and it's fine to avoid it if uh or it's fine to breathe with it without
fixing it or doing anything with it um so you can find exactly or to pull out
when trauma responses arises in meditation a very helpful skill to develop
is to kind of end the meditation or kind of come out of that state and revive
oneself or come back to normal a little bit and develop that skill so there's
confidence that as you go into it that you if you ever if you really wanted to you could come
out so at some point if you want to explore and go further with the sensations
of trauma that you do so with a lot of confidence that at a moment's notice you can pull
yourself out and um and maybe there is this
association and sometimes you know it's not there's not a you know it's not a it's not nothing you know not
a crime to be disassociated so it's okay to within reason and
and so if it just happens in meditation maybe it also has an uh helpful function sometimes there's a break or
there is a kind of relaxation that can happen with some disassociation so not to be in a hurry to make it wrong to
do that and then um but if it starts being a problem or you suspect that
it is a problem then um you know the the really the focus focus
on the body i find is one way to kind of work through disassociation because dissociation is very
more often than not i associate it with not being connected to the body
and um so um
and then getting professional help i think is good if you really think it's a big issue it's really good to find a professional
help nah there are now in some areas you know therapists who know about
mindfulness and buddhism and meditation and you know that can be particularly helpful
for people meditating um
after the 16th step this would be the last one after the 16 steps would you make letting go the next theme yeah that that
certainly can be uh the but we'll see it letting go is built into the anapanasati
and so next week we'll get to the end of each tetrad there is some quality of letting go in
the family of letting go and so we'll see next week when we get to the eighth step that has letting go and the first step
uh the end the first tetrad is relaxing or tranquilizing the bodily formations and that's that's
in the family of letting go and so at the end of each tetrad there's a letting go kind of uh
quality so we'll do some of that here well thank you for your questions and
i'll read the rest of the questions and so i get some sense of your concerns and
and i appreciate this chance to be this way with you and i look forward
to next week and continuing on this process
thank you very much