so hello
and welcome and
it occurred to me that i'm for teaching i'm teaching about thinking
this week and coming to the end and somehow i happily
don't have many thoughts about this topic at the moment
the i feel pretty content
so to
not need anything
to sit upright meditate and let go of needs
expectations let go of
it needing to be any particular way
to be here with the simplicity of being
with whatever is here including the complications
so lowering the gaze 45 degrees to the floor perhaps
relaxing the gaze lose focus not really looking at anything in
particular and then closing the eyes
and to be here with this body
this body that we have that we are that we're in
this body that just is
can be like the temple that we enter
and we can enter it with our deeper breathing
breathing in fully allowing the rib cage to expand
if you deep breathe deep enough it lifts the shoulders a bit
with a full deep in-breath even the belly might expand outward
and then on the exhale to relax all that
to release
maybe at the end of the exhale to let your elbows kind of flap a little bit
swing a little bit so that there's a looseness in the arms
letting the breathing return to normal
and continuing to relax
softening the muscles of the face
releasing the shoulders as you exhale
softening the belly as you exhale and maybe also softening it on the
inhale
feeling the touch of your clothes against your skin your skin against the clothes
and relaxing all along that meeting place of
skin and clothes relax soften
and gently on the exhale relax the core of your being
the most deepest tender place within allow it to trust
enough to relax to soften
and then there's the thinking muscle whatever tension or pressure
contraction that you might feel associated with thinking
it might be physical it might be
a mental tension whatever it might be
as you exhale soften it
let it become calmer
maybe letting go of any need to think
the pressure to think
the interest in thinking put it aside for now
so your thoughts can float away like thought bubbles
blowing away in the wind
one of the thoughts to let go of is any thoughts connected to time
even thinking about the end of the next breath is to be involved in time
do not have thoughts about time
it allows each passing thing to exist while it's present
as if it's there forever
in the quiet stillness of the of the mind
each in breath moments in forever
no time each part of the exhale
fully there itself no time forever
breathing in breathing out
no in no out just sensations
appearing and disappearing
and when there is no time no appearing and disappearing
just is each moment
loosening up on your thinking
let it become calmer and quieter
let yourself very gently think about
here just here
letting go into here let that be the content of your thinking
and now [Music] letting your thoughts be quiet and
soft calm thinking
have your thinking remember a time that
you received someone's care good will
kindness that was touching for you
heart softening
where something inside of you resonated with that care that kindness
or think of a time that you were caring and kind that was meaningful for you the feeling
the way it arose lived in you
quiet thoughts simple relax think they're thinking to remember
how it felt in the body the mind the heart
what was inspiring about that for you
and then quietly calmly
see if you can have thoughts in your own way of thinking
of good will kindness
for others people you know in your life people you
run into strangers
very simple ordinary
attitude of kindness and goodwill and what kind of thoughts would accompany that
what place in the heart or with what place inside
might be awakened with such
thoughts of good will of kindness
when the mind is quiet
it can be a meaningful time to think
wholesome thoughts beneficial thoughts
especially at the end of the meditation
to prepare yourself to go into the world
with a caring heart may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may you share in that happiness
and peace and freedom
may all beings be happy
[Music]
so we come now to the last talk on mindfulness of thinking
and as i've said mindfulness of thinking thinking is just as much of a
valid subject for mindfulness as anything else including the breathing
the art of it however is that to think to be mindful without thinking
more not be think fullness because you're mindful of thinking
and uh the um
and so usually uh the breathing is often a very good focus for meditation
because it tends to be calming and settling and it's not it's a physical sensation
so it tends to kind of help us kind of step out of the world of thinking so that can quiet down
the so thinking maybe isn't always a good
object for beginners because it pulls us into itself we start thinking more and more
but on principle thinking is just as valid as a subject of mindfulness as anything else
we turn our attention towards it and sooner or later it's really wise to do it
to especially if you've been meditating for a long time and you have some ability to just really
look at thinking and see it and look it right in the eye and and study what goes on in it
it's a whole systems a whole complex of things that are involved with the thinking that come
into play and one of those things is our clinging
our grasping or holding on our stickiness our compulsive
compulsivity we're thinking and
and in the end we're not looking to stop having thoughts
freedom is manifested in not having that stickiness with
thoughts not clinging to thoughts and having a state of mind a consciousness and
awareness which is has released itself from thinking
even if thinking still goes on and for this purpose i distinguish between thinking
and thoughting thoughting is just what the mind does the mind is a thoughting machine just
middle just produce thoughts they float up and float away thinking
is when we're involved in those thoughts when there's little bit and sometimes it's appropriate to be involved
but more often than not when we're involved there is a some compulsivity some clinging some grasping to it
and so to study thinking to as a way of discovering where
grasping and thing is where clinging is and as a kind of
a fascinating
window into the clinging into thoughts whenever you're in a hurry
chances are pretty high that
um your thinking is compulsive your thinking has scrapped onto something holding on
the the the syndrome of hurry hurriedness usually comes along with hurried
thoughts pushing thoughts wanting thoughts crowded thoughts one after the other
and uh and as and not only is the mind kind of crowded with a lot of thoughts when we
hurry but sometimes they're they're you can feel the push the compulsivity
if you allow yourself to feel it there's a kind of command from hurry
like don't pay attention to itself just get the job done do what has to be done so to turn around
180 degrees and look at thinking itself is a real task
the um and so in terms of hurrying it's possible to do things quickly
without hurrying so hurry is this extra kind of
compulsivity this being caught in something that has to be done quickly
it's possible to do things quickly without being caught so one of the things we're looking for
in in the dharma is not to be without thinking
or without thoughts but to be with them without clinging to them
and now this is a very profound thing because
that's all we ever cling to when there's clinging unless you're you know at the edge of a cliff holding on
clinging to the railing um you know then it's you clinging to the railing but generally the the clinging
that we're addressing in buddhism is the uh the the predominant clinging
that human beings are involved in all the time and that is we're clinging to ideas and
thoughts that's really what we cling to
we don't see it that way because if i'm clinging to
a person i think i'm clinging to that person
but if you're really quiet and study your mind you see you're not clinging to the person unless you're holding their
hand tight you're clinging to the idea that person is in your mind
the associations you have the meanings you have the value you have around that person the desires you have around that
person it's it's the clinging to ideas to thoughts and to start seeing that is fascinating
so you know the recipe is not the same thing as a meal
to cling to the recipe and never cook you never have a meal
to a map is not the territory
i had a when i was a new relatively young zen student i had some challenge with my when my father
enough so i talked to my zen teacher about it and and he made this comment to me which
really struck me he said before your father was a father
there was before he was a father he was a person without any fatherhood any being a
father and when he said that i said wow i'm only seeing him through the lens of
being my father he has a whole other side of him of how he lives his life without
being a father i wonder who he is i wonder how he is there in those situations
and um so um the
you know we hold on to these ideas of how it is so there's a kind of a cliche kind of a little saying that came from i
think manindraji this uh indian vipasta teacher who was a teacher for many of us i i just knew him briefly
and he said um the thoughts of your mother are not your mother
so we have these thoughts these ideas and we to release our thoughts
from our grasping and clinging and here's a very interesting idea
that you know in buddhism the goal is consensus liberation is freedom
and often the idea we're holding on to is that
i will be free when i'm liberated but maybe it doesn't work that way
maybe you will never be free those are just ideas and thoughts
if anything what's happening is you're giving freedom
to the world you give freedom to your thoughts not to think wildly and recklessly and
unwholesomely the the reckless the thoughts the unwholesome thoughts the harmful
thoughts that we think are a form of clinging we're holding on
to idea to something without clinging to anything
the thoughts will gravitate will flow towards what is wholesome
what's immediate because it's not driven by desires by hatreds and all this stuff
so rather than you becoming free you're giving freedom to your thoughts
and to have thoughts be free it's one of the great delights to have thoughts just kind of
relaxingly just appear it's kind of like a miracle that thoughts appear
where do they come from they just kind of you know to be quiet and still and watch a new thought be
born where did that come from it just arises and floats by and goes
away and and it's not any different than a flower blooming and fading
it's not any different than the clouds forming in the skies and passing by
it's not any different than a leaf floating in the wind hovering and finally landing someplace
they um if we don't identify with the thoughts
to identify with a thought is to be attached to little kind of identification thoughts this is me this
is mine to not make thoughts me myself and mine
is so wonderful to not have to take them personally
to not have to do anything with them to not have to measure oneself by it when i was
about 14 or so 13 or 14 my father took me aside to have a little father-son
talk and he said to me i don't know if it was that intentional but he said to me
as you grow up from time to time you'll have bizarre thoughts and i kind of
okay i thought okay i mean i didn't know what to do with that information and
and lo and behold some point or other i had bizarre thoughts
and i said oh my father told me about this that this might happen and because of that i had no indic no
inclination to do anything about them or to judge them or to be horrified by them or whatever i don't
you know whatever they were i don't even remember but they were just oh it just bizarre thoughts
just they come and they go thoughts are kind of like a dime a dozen they come and they go
and the ability to step back from them and not automatically latch onto them
is a kind of a power because it allows us to choose which thoughts we getting involved in
and which we don't and that is where maybe a certain kind of freedom resides
the freedom to choose what we think and the primary choice that i think that
we learned in this practice is mostly what not to do what not to think oh and i don't need to do that i
don't need to do that sometimes it's very very appropriate to actually choose what we think about like
at the end of the meditation spend a little time choosing to think about goodwill and kindness
it's so it has a double purpose it has a purpose of helping us stay free
to open the heart and not cling and just open ourselves and be available to the world in a kind way
kind of you know hopefully clears the decks of our hearts so that we can kind of
just be available for the world and we're not clinging and holding on to me myself and mine
and it nourishes something very important in us and
it supports and helps other people all those can happen that dedication of
our thinking that way but the thinking needs to be done in a free way
in a relaxed way easy way calmly and to learn how to think
some of us need to relearn our thinking but first to learn how to be free of
thoughts to release them so may you explore study
ride the edge of where you can find ways to not cling to your thinking
and you don't necessarily have to let go of your thoughts just let go of the clinging and see what happens
and um so releasing thoughts
so then um next week i'll continue this series on kind of the basic mindfulness practice
and i'm going to talk about now something that what called mindfulness of mind
and um and so that's uh we'll continue with
with this momentum that we have over the last four weeks so thank you very very much and i
look forward to monday