so warm greetings everyone
and we're continuing this process of
this exploration of samadhi and often in buddhism in
english buddhist buddhisms often enough the deepening levels of samadhi are
sometimes called absorptions to be absorbed
and in some ways it's an apt uh description of them the
if we liken it to the idea of uh being absorbed in a good book or absorbed and listening to music or
absorbed in some hot craft that we're doing that absorbed in a movie that uh
to absorb just to be fully uh attentive to it where kind of all our
senses are either focused on what we're doing or the senses kind of have receded
from receded from getting much attention from us
so if you're absorbed in a book you might not be listening so much to what's going around you someone might even talk
to you and you don't hear them because you're really absorbed
and but no in meditation it's not a it's an absorb that kind of absorption
is one of great interest or usually there's a kind of sense of
goodness or wholesomeness and people usually part of the joy of being absorbed in a book or something is the
absorption itself and so same thing with samadhi it's a
very nice state of absorption it's not a turning off of the world but rather it's letting the
world around us fall away as we enter into a very wholesome
healthy state a healthy kind of and all the you know steps of
anapanasati these steps of deepening meditation are steps that are opening up and
evoking healthier and healthier states of being inside and of course it's not always going to
be that way and it's a process to get there but to know that we're looking for the inner health
we're looking to recognize where nourishment is what's wholesome is here and so we do that in the very beginning
trying to can we approach meditation in a healthy
wholesome way without greed or contraction or conceit or pouncing on things or
strong aversion trying to escape and push things away can we have a spirit of generosity
of kindness a warmth of good will and ease as we start engaging our
attentional capacities our ability to bring attention and then we begin
finding where as we pay attention how to evoke and spread and develop
good feelings in the body partly because we're starting to relax this process of relaxation is such a
healthy thing to do and and so as a meditation deepens at
some point the inner health the inner goodness the nourishment the wholesomeness
feels so great that it becomes easier and easier to be absorbed in that to feel connected to it to be
really there and so to be absorbed and i also delight in
the idea that that of using the metaphor of a sponge
a sponge absorbs water and the same way
there's a we absorb the sensations we absorb this experience of breathing
we allow it to just kind of like the whole body is the sponge and um and we just kind of like are
there to receive and we take in the whole experience of the present moment
in a receptive way in a open way and and the sponges i don't think force the
world to force the itself to absorb water just that's what it is
uh sponges do they just absorb so this absorption that absorbs the
absorption that really let's allows there to be a kind of a intimacy
and a receptivity in a to our experience to our breathing to be
absorbed in the breathing so assuming a meditation posture
and perhaps sitting in such a way meditating such a posture where the chest is a little bit
more open open to be receptive
and sometimes when the chest is a little more open it's a little bit more useful than
or capable to relax the belly so softness throughout the front of our
body soft front and sometimes it said that meditation
we have a soft front and a strong back
and so to feel this especially if you're sitting upright to feel a little bit of strength
in the back stability
maybe adjusting the vertebrae a little bit so the spine is a little bit more aligned
centered instead of strength maybe some of you
prefer the word stability stability strength of the back and the
softness and openness in the front
and to gently close your eyes and to take a few long slow deep breaths
kind of a ritual procedure for adjusting your state of mind your
state of body your attitude
into one that can begin to be absorbed in this practice of meditation
that is put aside temporarily its concerns of the past and the future or other
places other times it is prepared preparing itself
to settle in here and now
and then letting your breathing return to normal
to continue this process of softening the front of our body by as you exhale softening the face
face is where we present to the world so much but in meditation we don't need to
activate the face we can let it rest
on the exhale softening the shoulders
releasing to the pull of gravity the weight of the shoulders
adjusting your arms so that they can be loose and relaxed
softening in the chest
and relaxing the belly
and wherever you feel your breathing the predominant place the common place
for experiencing the body breathing imagine that location
is a sponge for the sensations
of breathing so it's not so much that you're in the control tower
thinking looking down at breathing it's more like you are that
sponge in the body especially the inhale absorbing
the sensations of the inhale
and if those sensations are like water then in the exhale spreading
the goodness of that water throughout the body
absorbing the inhale and releasing it all on the exhale
throughout the body
and can you adjust your mind a little bit
so your mind is more like doing tai chi mental tai chi of receiving and flowing
moving along with the breathing
maybe as if the mind becomes more and more like water flowing
with and over and through the breathing
or as if the mind also gets absorbed into the body the body sponge
and abiding in the body breathing
abiding in intimacy will you turn yourself over to your
breathing entrusting yourself to your breathing
absorbed in the goodness of breathing
and whenever you exhale and you need to remember to let go of whatever takes you
away from your breathing let the breathing be the center of it
all the foundation of everything
the beginning of it all the end of it all just breathing
being absorbed in breathing not as a rejection of anything else
but in a way let everything else recede to the background
where your interest your involvement
your life energy
is intimately involved connected to
breathing
perhaps it's easier to be absorbed in the breathing if you make a small half smile with your
lips just turn up the corners of your lips just a little bit
maybe shifts the mood just enough then it's easier to flow with the
breathing
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to bring forth whatever
goodwill tenderness love that might live in your heart
that lives within you in whatever way that that caring loving
part of you can come forth as we sit here
and breathe with that
let that be absorbed into the bodies the sponge as you breathe in
and may that spread through your body as you exhale
like water being absorbed and then dispersed
the water of love and kindness compassion good will
and without any responsibility to act on your love your goodwill
to simply sit here open to it
feel it and see if you can sit
quietly for a few moments more gazing kindly with kind eyes
on the people of your life those you know well those you barely
know
strangers and perhaps and thinking about
maybe some of the people you will encounter today without needing to do anything with them
at all this while you're sitting here see can you gaze upon them kindly
can you hold them in the warmth of your heart
and taking a few moments to do this expresses our a wish
that our meditation practice supports us
in bringing helpful healthy attitudes to this world
around us that meditation is not just for ourselves
but it's also for how we see and relate to others
and maybe we unders discover more and more how that's the case
may it be that we meditate for the welfare and happiness of all
beings ourself included
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
so related to the topic of absorption that what we talked about what i talked
about in the guided meditation just now a a concept that the buddha refers to
often in terms of meditation practice and this path of liberation
is the idea of often translated into english is
seclusion and the word for seclusion viveka
v-i-v-e-k-a more literally means to separate
something apart becomes separate but in the context seclusion is probably
one of the better english words no english words really work well but the probably better english word if
we associate seclusion with being sheltered being protected
kind of cozy and nice and secluded in the best possible kind of
associations of that word cozy and warm and contented
deep feeling of satisfaction just being here secluded or somehow maybe after a
you know a long walk and big invigorating nice walk in the cold
maybe even stormy weather and coming inside and wrapping in a nice blanket and having a
warm drink and just being all cozy and alone and feel secluded from all the
difficulties of life around us maybe something like that so the word seclusion and
it's used in the buddhist teachings for a variety of different forms of seclusion and
the the first kind of gives us begins giving us a sense of what it's what's to come and it means
it's used to defer to uh going on retreat they don't have the word retreat in in
ancient language but they say uh going to be secluded um to be secluded is to go someplace
where you're separate from the some people might say that it's a process of escaping the world and
and the real world we have to face the real world but the what's more real
in terms of our mind and hearts is becoming integrated not being fragmented and
being pulled in all kinds of directions and where thoughts and feelings and everything and so the process of
meditation going in physically becoming secluded from many of the aspects of the world so we can find this
inner health inner wholesomeness and integration process so we can bring back that back into the
world and it isn't pushing the world the world away or abandoning it any more
than going alone and being secluded in your bathroom to take a shower is pushing away the world and rejecting
the world and take a shower and become clean and we become you know more it's more we're more of a
pleasant person to be with in the world if we're clean and and taken care of that way and uh
so uh so this is meditative seclusion going off on retreat and in the old days it was going into
the forest perhaps in some place where the people could be alone some people it might be to be in your own room by
yourself in the early morning and maybe you get up before everyone else and you feel have this wonderful benefit of seclusion
just nothing else to think about and be involved in just here practicing and um and then it's easier
to get absorbed it's even easier to an integration that wholeness and just the satisfaction the contentment of being this way
of real and then settling in and being and then we become more and more secluded
and and meditative seclusion happens when um we stop
being so concerned with the past and the future and the thoughts don't take us spinning
out in other places and other times and and we're secluded from those um uh
external thoughts thoughts that kind of spin us away and if we are thinking it's thoughts that keep us here and connected and
involved as we get more absorbed in meditation more connected and involved in it
and you know really sink into it and then um there's sensory
seclusion that happens that uh sometimes we don't really involved in
hearing so much or smelling or seeing or even even some of the sensing of the
body recedes and disappears sometimes people the body becomes very transparent or
light or seems to have no edges to the body or even the whole body seems to disappear
because we're we're not we're not really giving attention to um the senses you know the six the
five senses of of uh hearing seeing touching um smelling tasting
and um and so those all we seed we still have the capacity to hear and
taste and do all these things but they recede from where our attention is we're
absorbed in what we're involved in and just like we would perhaps if you're reading a really good book
and you don't hear people talking anymore you don't notice the sounds outside the house because you're so absorbed in the
in the book there's a sensory seclusion and that sensory seclusion because there's absorption going on it's
uh it you know it feels really good it's like we're being pulled in we're being absorbed we're being
delighted we're being enjoying we're really the attention really is getting centered in here
um because it's starting to get concentrated and very present as it does so and the mind becomes
quieter and stiller one of the functions of this is for us to become more sensitive to clinging
to grasping to how the mind gets attached to how the mind contracts and and uh and the more still
more absorbed more peaceful we can become the more sensitive we become to the slightest movements of
contraction of clinging of resistance that goes on in the mind in the heart and so then we
have the opportunity then to let go of that or bring our attention to that and have it let go of itself
and and and then over time there becomes a seclusion from the
things we cling to one of the important steps for this process of seclusion
is to be secluded from to be separated from not involved in any more with the five
hindrances of sensual desire ill will sloth intorper restlessness and regrets and doubt
because we're so absorbed so connected so involved with what we're doing with meditation like really
kind of dipping deep into the into the world the ocean of
breathing that um that we're not you know we're not get pulled into those
it can be part of this contentment and satisfaction of meditation is not to be involved anymore with the
hindrances so we're secluded from them we're separated from them as the ancient language
and and that's temporary so in deep meditation that that can
those fall away but then they come back when we come out of meditation their mind is no longer concentrated
and maybe they come back a little bit weaker than they were before but sooner or later they'll come back
and then the ultimate seclusion is their separation is when we become more permanently separated from some of
our clinging and attachment and that more permanent separation from attachment
is um is you know called liberation
and so um um so this somali practice is meant to
support that process of liberation um and so it's not just getting absorbed
and feeling the healthiness the goodness the wholesomeness the satisfaction the deep contentment of
just being absorbed in the breathing flowing with the breath but it's preparing the mind
so the mind is softer more workable more able to let go more
more malleable in a sense so that the ways
it's contracted has room to breathe it's a room to let go and open up
and we start feeling some of the seclusions some of these seclusions which partake
of or or have qualities of liberation in them for example being temporarily liberated
from the hindrances and so that brings us to the 12th step
of these 16 steps of breathing so the 11th one is breathing in
one concentrates the mind one unifies the mind one steadies the mind breathing out one
unifies the mind steadies the mind composes the mind
concentrates the mind whatever that word is translated as uh the samadhi word and then
the twelfth step is one liberates the mind
breathing in one liberates the mind breathing out when liberates the mind and and now we're starting to get into
uh the territory of the real purpose of buddhist meditation this area of liberation and we'll pick
up that uh continue with that tomorrow and in the meantime you might look for
how you can lovingly delightfully be absorbed in what you do during the day
wash dishes be absorbed and just do that in a way just turn yourself over fully to the enjoyment of that without
letting the mind take you away and maybe there's a lot of activities throughout the day that you can do if
you eat alone for example absorbed and just the eating and
learning to kind of appreciate or develop that capacity to give ourselves over fully to what
we're doing when we're doing it so that there's qualities of absorption like a good you know involved in playing music in a
nice way they supports us to learn how to do that
meditation so you might want to play around with that during the day today next 24 hours
so thank you very much and and i look forward to our time tomorrow
thank you