so we're still
lingering in the 13th step
of mindfulness of breathing that of
observing in constancy
and that there's something about
inconstancy and observing it that leads
to the 14 step
which is usually translated
into english as dispassion
uh when we'll get to the meanings of it
maybe tomorrow but or soon
but there's something about seeing
impermanence
that is onward leading seeing in
constancy which
opens something up that allows something
to unfold and deepen or
move along and the very common
uh term in the buddhist scriptures is
the idea of
the dharma is onward leading and it's
armored onward leading to greater and
greater freedom
and one of the things that's very much
so a part of this onward leading nature
is this settling back resting in
awareness in a sense
and becoming more and more aware of the
transiency of experience the inconstancy
of experience
sometimes it's called impermanence but
as i've said
that's going to imply for some people
only means
that sooner or later something will no
longer exist it'll
die or be gone forever and well
there's wisdom to that understanding for
sure
and it could be freeing in itself in a
certain way the core insight of the
buddha has more to do
with the momentary and constancy of
things
that everything is kind of part of or
like it's
he didn't say this but it's like the
inconstant waves or ripples
on um on a river that flows by and the
little wave let's come in they go they
exist and don't exist
and and they're in constant they're
constantly being reborn
constantly passing away and
so many of our sensations are coming and
going
coming and going sometimes they stay
longer than we wish
but uh sooner or later they pass and
they maybe come back again
but to really settle in and really start
seeing more and more precisely or
intimately uh closely
how much of our experience is it's a
flowing experience
the changing sensations is a
things are peering and disappearing
sometimes in rapid succession or
sometimes it can just feel like um
everything is just flowing sand
and the reason for flowing sand rather
than water as some people say is that
sand is a little bit more like
particular so it's a little bit more the
particular sensations that have
some kind of clarity to them whereas
water flows
but there's no sense of a particularity
to each molecule of water
whereas then there's a particularity or
some people it feels like snow
just everything is just like snow you
know or raindrops
but the flowing sand and
everything and just really settling back
and getting very still
and then appreciating how everything is
arising and
passing this was a very significant
insight for the buddha it was like his
in the ways described in some texts is
like this was his big aha moment
this is what he in seeing this he
realized this is the path to liberation
with seeing this arising and passing the
inconstancy
um there was light there was wisdom
there was clarity there was um
the path opened for the buddha but in
particular
what was particularly both seeing
arising was very important for him
but seeing the passing was very
important as well
and it seems like the passing and the
ceasing of things was even more
important than seeing their arising
i know exactly you know i'm not sure but
one reason
is that when we know that things pass
even if they're in constantly come back
we know that they're not
permanent we know that it's not always
that way
and uh and uh and that frees us from the
mind that it's
that kind of unconsciously or
subconsciously we relate to things
as if they're always going to be there
and
as opposed to relating to them as being
oh this is just part of the flavor of
the moment this is what's coming here
now
and in due time it'll pass and in fact
if i replay
really careful attention to the
particularity of the moment it's already
passing and then arising passing and
arising
and so knowing that it's not constant so
that's very helpful
with things like suffering if we think
that suffering is
durable stuck solid
unchanging then it's very hard to get in
this like concrete it's very hard to get
in
there and try to do anything with it but
we see it as more as
flowing sand or flowing water
then you know you try to reach into
water and hold on to it
grab a fistful of it it just disappears
through your fingers very quickly
and and so we realized suffering doesn't
have that solidity we thought before
self all the things we think of as this
myself or we identify strongly as being
this is who i am
to to really see that it also has a
certain way
a certain way of inconstancy that
it comes and goes the sensations the
experience the thing the role
the ideas the feelings the intuitions
the
whatever it might be that we think is it
this is myself
we start seeing that too as part of this
flow and current of
a river and we can't quite
hold on to it and so there's these gaps
in the arising and passing there's this
moments of freedom
and the passing begins to teach us not
to cling
not to grasp and we start seeing it's
simply not worth
grasping um it's um
and this is a powerful insight that
comes
many many times in life all kinds of
ways but in
deeper and deeper meditation there's a
sense of well-being or freedom and
openness a
lack of clinging that's so palpable
that we begin feeling that any movement
to contract
any movement to resist any movement to
hold on tight
or to linger and be involved with
something that's going on
is a loss of some of the peace we're
actually better off
in the freedom we're better off in this
deep subtle quiet peacefulness
and in that we can learn it's not worth
clinging we lose something
in the contracting we lose something in
the
resisting and it isn't that we are told
you know
it's a good buddhist you should let go
of clinging
it's more like there's no admonition
like that
it's more like pay careful attention
become
quiet and when you notice for yourself
that you're worse off clinging then
don't cling and one of the lessons for
this that helps this
is when we realize in certain deep
states of meditation
that clinging doesn't work at all
because
whatever it is we're clinging to is also
constantly passing away
constantly passing away and whether
you don't have to be in that constant
passing away place in meditation
to begin appreciating how much does pass
away
and how in the passing away
it is possible to tune into a kind of
peacefulness a freedom a spaciousness an
openness
that that kind of allows or makes room
for
permits if we don't cling to the next
thing that comes up
kind of allow it to pass and in the
space that it leaves behind in a sense
just be open there be relaxed there
take that in the next thing will
something else will
arise but rather than being you know
preoccupied by it or caught by it or
analyzing it or reflecting on or doing
things with it
allow the next thing to arise to rise in
that space
and that openness in that field of
awareness that just lets it comes and
goes
and um and in the process of doing that
we learn
more and more about letting go
we learn more and more we're not holding
on to anything
and and
i need to charge my battery
and so because batteries also pass away
and it's probably good
for the next couple of minutes to keep
it going
um so
the
and so uh this teaching on not self
that is often perplexing for people is a
teaching that makes more and more sense
when we understand that nothing
qualifies
as an enduring self there's nothing that
we can find
inside of ourselves or in direct
experience
then we're really intimate and close to
direct experience
nothing that qualifies as oh that's
myself
because it passes as well and the idea
being that anything that passes
cannot be an enduring self and
any theory any um for the buddha's point
of view
any doctrine of self any theory about
what the self is
lends itself to a kind of reification a
kind of solidification on what to self
that's not possible when it's things are
constantly changing
it's kind of like uh there's no place to
hang your hat
there's no place to tack
with thumbtack no place to attack
any philosophy idea concept theory
about what the self is you know it's
like taking a thumbtack and
trying to stick it into a river and have
it gets you know stuck it doesn't stick
anywhere
so any theory about self just doesn't
quite stick doesn't quite work when this
constantly flowing and constant nature
of experience
that begins to open up in deep vipassana
practice
so this the core deepest kind of
important insight of inside meditation
is this inconstancy of phenomena the
changing nature
the current of phenomena as it flows
through and arises and passes
here in the present moment so to settle
back and observe that
on this 13th step is what's talked about
and as we do that
we begin feeling that the things that we
cling to
have passionate lust for passionate
hatred for
that all that kind of um
the ways in which we're driven or about
things passionate around our
attachments um
just doesn't make any sense as well and
it stops losing its allure
it stops losing its enchantment we start
stop falling under its spell
and then we begin observing that we're
less and less interested in clinging
less and less interested in lust and
hatred and
you know this driven driven attached
kind of passion that can happen like the
passion for money or the passion for
power or
kind of the negative understandings of
passion
and so then the 14th step is observing
dispassion
so um
so then it will end and this will pass
as well
and will make room for the next thing to
happen
and um and chances are
it's simply inconstant and we'll meet
again here tomorrow
at the same time thank you