so
in these
16 stages 16 steps of mindfulness of
breathing
as i've said that they are organized in
groups of four called tetrads
and that the last step in each tetrad
the instructions are has to do with
something in the family of letting go
or of freedom or of release
whatever your language that you like to
think of that
is and in
step four it's calming
the bodily formations
sometimes it's translated as
tranquilizing
and i love the word tranquil but
tranquilizing i associate with
something you do with animals or
something
so it doesn't really evoke a positive
obviously positive response for me
and and but
you know bringing about tranquility of
the body
in the eighth step it's calming relaxing
tranquilizing the mental formations the
mind
we'll see in a while that in the
12th step it's
freedom release releasing the mind
freeing the mind and then in the
final step of the 16 steps number 16
it's something called relinquishment
which
maybe it's a big word that doesn't
really inspire so much
but it involves a real qualitative
transformative experience of freedom of
liberation
and so the movement towards greater and
greater freedom
begins with this simple thing of
relaxing the body
and uh it's kind of beginning to learn
the lesson
of freedom it's beginning to have a
reference point
for the goodness of what it's like to
not be tense
not be caught and i think for many
people
it's a little bit more accessible this
physical relaxation than it is
full-blown
liberation but we're beginning to get a
little taste of it
um and this embodied taste of it
and most people don't associate you know
just simple
physical relaxation with buddhist
liberation
but maybe there's um the liberation is
kind of such a
matter-of-fact thing it's uh it's not
once you the greater liberation we have
uh the more it just seems seen as
i don't know if ordinary is the right
word but uh
not such a uh
unusual thing or not such a
um
otherworldly thing in a sense it's uh
it's just a very profound
experience of what we're beginning to
experience
as we begin to relax the body as we
begin to relax as we begin to
experience a physical tranquility
so in so you know as you know those of
you following along
that i give a lot of emphasis on
relaxing at the beginning of the body
the beginning of the meditation
and now relaxing
you know it's maybe a little bit too s
limited in describing the sense of
tranquility that comes
that can come as we continue deeper and
deeper into this anapanasati
but looking for tranquility looking for
the calmness or the serenity that can
exist
in our practice is said to be the
support for
greater tranquility we're not making
calmness or tranquility
the beel and end-all but it's a
wonderful foundation that begins to
soften the hard hardness of the heart
the hardnesses of the mind
the word stuck and things don't move
tranquility begins to create a sense of
safety inner safety
where things begin to release more and
more
and we're not looking towards you know i
like the word tranquility more than
calmness
in my use of the words because calmness
can lend itself to the idea of becoming
too calm so calm that you fall asleep
and my vocabulary tranquility has an
alertness to it
and their tranquility is not just calm
but it's also kind of a harmonious
energy kind of
energetics and so this calm kind of
aliveness
a tranquil aliveness that can be here an
embodied way so i say all this as a way
to encourage you
to begin appreciating
the the influence that relaxation has
that in your daily life as you go about
if there are times when
you've noticed your shoulders relaxed
your belly relaxes
you sit down at the end of a long day
and you finally let let down
all your preoccupations and drive and
you know momentum that you have and you
feel more relaxed
see if you can appreciate the the
influence that has on you and
see if you can maybe begin feel some of
the initial feelings of
a certain kind of freedom if some kind
of release
a certain kind of no longer being
limited or bound or caught
in something feel feel what it's like
physically begin to appreciate the small
little movements
of freedom that can be here and as you
get a hang of it
you might find that there's actually a
lot more little movements of freedom
little movements of not being
caught that are happening all along
and and that may be often so easy to
overlook
because we're it's not valued
particularly
other things getting something done is
might be more valuable but there might
be a very a lot of little movements of
of just kind of oh that's great you
might step out of your house
after a rainstorm and the rain has
passed and the sun has come out
and something inside of you just kind of
releases
um in that feeling of just being in the
sun being outdoors in the fresh air
and so what does that influence what's
that effect on you
in the body to be there and
to appreciate it don't hang on to it
don't
you know get too complicated around it
but just kind of start
feeling the little movements of freedom
little movements of
release of relaxation of tranquility
of peacefulness that seems to emanate
from
the movements of relaxation of ease that
happen
and the more we start recognizing this
in daily life and
meditation different places
it reinforces that movement it
reinforces
the value of not being tense
it enforces the value of not being
caught up in preoccupations or
driven or or or
bracing ourselves since things or
closing down or trying to run away from
things
it it reinforces it kind of kind of
begins to question those movements of
mind those
ways in which we are which are the
opposite of freedom
and to do that in the small areas of
your life
ordinary things is a
wonderful stepping stone that supports
us finding it
deeper and further further along until
the deeper areas of letting go of
freedom that
anapanasathi is taking taking us to
become
more natural more accessible more
understandable because of what we've
kind of
really taken in earlier on in the
practice
so not just simply in meditation to
experience this
but in other times of the day as well
begin you know if you really want this
anapanasati to really
deepen deep deeper deeper deeper and
deeper in it
this movement towards freedom
can be called it can become a
a a
an ongoing sensitivity an ongoing
attention that we have
and it's not being self-preoccupied to
do this it's i hope you don't think it's
selfish
because the freedom is kind of beginning
to turn ourselves inside out
so that we're actually in the freedom we
are
i think kind of more easily naturally
going to be
more sensitive more caring for the world
around us
so tranquility
letting go release relaxation
calmness all kind of
all ways are connected to this the
family
of experiences of movements
that's connected to liberation and
and to become a connoisseur of this
become a
sensitive to it being informed by it to
be
inspired by it to be in touch with it
regularly
maybe even so it becomes a little bit of
a habit
so they can grow and develop in you
and so that may this practice that we do
lead you to greater and greater
experiences of freedom
and in doing so may it be for your
delight
so thank you so much for today and
we'll continue this tomorrow