so welcome welcome a really warm welcome for all of you
it's so nice to be practicing together i was smiling underneath my mask a little bit
there when i was just thinking how great opportunity it is to
come together so a deep bow to all of you for coming
and to our friends on youtube who are here with us
so tonight i'd like to talk a little bit about you know we often we have these good
intentions these good ideas of things that we're going to do and
maybe they don't always come to fruition
don't always happen and we all know this right it's so much easier to have ideas about things to do
and then it's something completely different to actually do them
we all have this experience i'm sure and so one thing that i'd like to talk
about today is this i'm just distracted here for a moment
while i'm trying to sorry keep track of uh what's happening
on the other side of that camera okay so
one of the things i'd like to talk about today is one of these uh pyramids
and so parame is a word that often gets translated as perfection
but that doesn't feel quite um inspiring perfection just feels like
some idealistic or either worldly or something quality but
this idea of pyramid these are these ten qualities that are associated with awakening that
really support awakening so they're associated with this movement towards freedom towards
greater ease and this movement towards
freedom and the tradition holds that there are
10 of them and these are practices that are in our daily life not just on the cushion you
know so much of the buddhist teachings are about what happens you know with our eyes
closed but these are about what's happening in daily life as well as you know in our
meditation practice and i don't know how long ago it was but
some time ago i started on this list of paramis and so now i'd like to add one
and this is the parame of aditana aritana
it rhymes with satypatana some of you may know the sati patana the
four foundations of mindfulness aditona has that same ending tonic had
like foundation something that be something we can stand on it's derived from what we can stand
on an audi has this idea of fullness or completeness or maybe the next
next step or something so aritana often gets
translated as determination like this foundation which allows things to come to completion
so determination resolve resoluteness
tenacity stick-to-itiveness you know something like this
and resolve is the eighth in this list of permis quickly i'll just say what the
other ones are generosity ethical behavior
generation renunciation wisdom energy
patience truth and resolve is number eight
number nine is loving kindness and number ten is equanimity
so you can see that
resolve is kind of you know down there in the list it's uh number eight uh out of ten
and part of the reason why it's there later in the list is because it requires a mind
that has already has a little bit of experience with some of the
the peace some of the ease that can happen with this uh renunciation was
letting go with generosity with ethical behavior
working with truth there's allows this mind to say yes okay
this is the direction i want to go so resolve is a is
is a commitment that's combined with a sense of okay i i i want to stick to this find my
way with us so one way to think about resolve is that
it's like a gentle and persistent wind
that keeps blowing and is like supporting us in this particular direction
so we could has this we can feel it at our backs
just encouraging us to take the next step just the next step
and so for some people this idea of resolve or steadfastness persistence is
not something that really needs to be cultivated there are some people who this is the way that they move through
the world is they set a goal they start and they complete and they finish and that's just what they do
there's they have their life is filled with this so maybe
just the sticktuaness and completeness isn't part of the parmy for them
but might be with the prior me is for those types of individuals
is to be able to stay connected to others to stay connected to
themselves while they're completing a task instead of kind of like slipping into
some sheer doggedness that kind of has this mood of get out of my way i have
something to do or maybe like a type of a tunnel vision
of not paying attention to the impact it's
having on others or not being aware of the impact it's having on ourselves and
maybe not taking care of ourselves because we feel like we have to finish this thing
so resolve aditana resoluteness is not stubbornness
even though it shares from the outside it might look a little bit like that but stubbornness also has this kind of like
ignoring the concerns and welfare for ourselves and for others
but it is a different way than
often when we're thinking about um where we want we have a direction we want to
go we often have a focusing on what's getting in the way
and often that comes with replaying and rehearsing and resentment
and blaming and we can find ourselves in this
loop of uh just thinking like well if only that hadn't happened or i should have done
this i should have said that or you know something along these lines that takes a tremendous amount of energy
so resolve isn't about just um
pushing through no matter what it's associated with wisdom
of course it is right if it's part of this path of practice towards greater freedom it's gonna have freedom
and wisdom as part of the practice itself
right the means is not completely different than the goal of course not
so what one of the ways that makes aditana
this resolve a pyramid rather than just another wholesome quality
is that it's associated with freedom awakening enlightenment
so it points us in that direction and it also
uh expresses as as best we can as what's available to
us at that time these qualities of going towards awakening going towards greater freedom
with some compassion and warm-heartedness
so aritana it serves to it kind of like strengthens all the other pyramids
helps us to be generous and to refrain from being harm and
to be truthful when it's difficult and certainly all these other good qualities
but just to recognize that we need
resolve for this practice simply because it is not always easy
sometimes it's difficult i'm having a regular meditation practice
is difficult going on retreats is difficult organizing one's life so that you can go
and retreat is difficult or once you're on retreat that's difficult too
right so sometimes we need resolve just to be with
the difficulties that arise when the mind starts to quiet and settle down
this can be the time when some of these difficulties from earlier in our life maybe even decades
ago start to arise
so the purpose of this of this practice is to help us to see what we haven't seen before
to realize what we haven't realized before in order for us to
do this to be stretched a little bit beyond what we've seen before we need to
be stretched allow ourselves to be stretched so resolve determination is a way to
maybe stretch us just a little bit out of our comfort zone but not to the point of breaking
this is where wisdom comes in right of course we need wisdom with this
there can be a way this sheer doggedness that ends up
just being harmful and painful i certainly have um done this too with
uh being on a long retreat and having this feeling like okay you know i don't know exactly what's
gonna happen but something better happened on this retreat and so just kind of like just the sense
of pushing and striving and not really noticing that at the same
time i was pushing and striving i was developing all this
um aversion and ill will towards everything else that i thought was like distracting
me and and including all this poor self-recrimination diana get it together
come on you have to go you know i was not noticing like how mean i was being to myself and
getting filled with irritation with everybody around me and week after week of this you know
it wasn't pretty and i after the end of that retreat i was a little bit of a mess
so there's so many different ways that this can show up this pushing and
striving in a way that's not helpful
so we need reserve resolve we need determination to stretch us
but not to break us and this is part of the art of practice
is to know what what is appropriate what is appropriate of stretching because this practice is about transformation
and of course for transformation to happen it requires a little bit of effort it requires
some sustained
effort some persistence
so what are some of the things that get in the way i'm not telling you something that you
anything that you don't already know we know that this takes some effort
sometimes we might have these underlying beliefs these ideas that okay my spiritual life is going to be about as
long as i i'm just nice and pleasant
and calm that should be enough
it's a it's certainly it is part of this practice but it's not enough
if we feel like we if there are times in our practice when that is perfectly sufficient and enough
and it's all we can do to get to the cushion it's all we can do to practice at all
but if we think the entire practice at all times under all situations
just have it's all about acceptance and i do teach a lot about this because
for me i this has been kind of a little bit of my edge just learning to accept and allow
but at the same time there are times when there needs to be a little bit of a warrior
spirit joseph goldstein
describes it as when you're noticing that there's some thoughts that are coming up that are just unhelpful and
you find yourself kind of ruminating or in this loop going around and around he describes it sometimes
it's helpful just to use his expression just chop off the head of the thoughts
you know kind of so maybe sometimes that's what's needed
like no this isn't helpful i'm not going to do it and so of course this is part of the art
of practice to know okay when is it's more about opening allowing and accepting and just watching things arise
and when is it time to a little bit more of that warrior spirit and to say nope i'm going to go a
different direction this isn't helpful my practice requires both
and for us to not think that it's only one way that could be a hindrance to our
practice to think that it's only one flavor only one way to meet all the different things
that arise during practice
so one thing i do want to say is so i'm talking about uh kind of like this tenacity stick to it
stick to it-ness but they don't want us to think that
when we don't follow through is a failure
instead this practice is about okay what can i learn here
what what what were the conditions that made it difficult for me to follow
through is there something that i can understand
here is there something that um can support me
for my other aspirations the other things that i want to do
so instead of you know completely giving up when we feel like oh okay i didn't follow through on
this resolve that i had made that i had intended okay
okay what can i learn here maybe to investigate
what what was what was happening maybe was the
resolution that i made was it maybe too vague
maybe too um made a resolve about something really
far in the future without also considering the steps that would get there it can be inspiring and beautiful to
have aspirations for our practice aspirations of greater freedom greater peace
but also an integral part of this is again so bring in some wisdom okay
so what what can i do today what can i do this moment that's moving in that direction
so maybe there wasn't follow-through because there wasn't a step it wasn't of thinking of okay what's the next step
instead of thinking i just want this or have this idea about some future state
without thinking about okay how can this moment right now contribute
and recently i've made this little
statement that i remind myself on occasion that
says physiology is paramount and
just to remind me that if i'm not feeling well haven't slept not eating well not
exercising you know all these types of things it has an impact that
sometimes just sitting on the cushion or whatever we're doing can't surmount that
we have to take care of ourselves as well as half of the human population
has hormones that are shifting on a regular basis and to just kind of honor
and respect that too and just kind of respect our physiology like okay this we can't pretend like
it's not there so maybe our resolutions our results have to be um
[Music] really honor and respect our physiology as well where
we are with that and maybe we learn like okay
if i haven't eaten i'm more likely to be grumpy and to say things that i wish i hadn't said
we all know this i'm not saying anything we don't know but sometimes it's just helpful to say it out loud or to
have this idea that or to be reminded of it in some kind of way
so what do we make resolves on what do we
make aspirations with on
what is the aspiration that comes forth after we've been practicing a little bit
once we've tasted some of the fruits of practice
probably in a generic idea or in a uh maybe broad brush is that we want to
move away from suffering we want to have more freedom
but is there a way that we can make it more specific for us is there a way that we can make it more
relevant for us and this is part of the art of practice too is to have a grand aspiration
which for me i think is a beautiful thing to think about it is possible to have greater freedom it is possible
the buddha points to this we know individuals and teachers and
people that have found greater ease and freedom so
why not for us
why not but then to
to join with this kind of aspiration
it's okay so what can i do now it's related to this
and just to recognize that you know we don't all have to have the same aspiration and of course
um different times of our life different seasons of our life different seasons of our practice
we'll have different ones
and so can we make an aspiration and a resolve
something that's inspiring but also to do it in a way in which the
the resolve itself was a beautiful thing
as not harsh not this sense of hard obligation but the resolve itself was a
beautiful thing what would that be like
so the buddha taught that there were four
supports for resolves we could also call them four
resolves so four things that could support us and
reaching and making results the way this works kind of is that these
are supports for all our resolves and so because they're supports we can also like resolve on them and they will help
us with anything else we want to do so the first of these four is wisdom
and this makes perfect sense right we need to bring some wisdom to the aspirations we have to the results we
have the ones that are appropriate for us and help bring in some of this
quality of what's helpful what's not helpful what's skillful what's not skillful
help us to set aspirations that aim at something worthwhile
for our life energy to put our life energy towards and one as i said that's a stretch for
us but not up to the point of breaking as well as wisdom is needed for clearly
understanding what are the different things that would be required what are the different steps
how can how can i create the conditions for this aspiration to arise
so wisdom and to be sure all of us have enough
wisdom to know what the next step is it's not like we have to wait to have enough wisdom
the second one is truth part of bringing truth in with our
aspirations could be just asking ourselves what's needed here what are the conditions what's the next step
but then the truth part comes in and being honest with ourselves
if i want to have more settledness maybe i need to
spend less time on the internet for example
maybe i need to spend less time ruminating about my favorite thing to
ruminate about and sometimes it's
hard difficult to see what we might have this idea what's required of us and we might feel like no no i don't want to do that
but this honesty about what's required
and then the third one is relinquishment
of course this can be something some letting go that's going to be required some letting
go that's going to be needed we know this from the dhamma part
of this famous verse right if by giving up a lesser happiness
one could experience a greater happiness a wise person would renounce the lesser
to behold the greater so just recognizing that
some there'll be some letting go that has to happen
of course that does if we want to exercise more then we have to find
we have to do less of something else in our life just to fit the time in
four resolves wisdom truth relinquishment then the last one is
peace is there a way that we can keep the mind
calm while working towards an aspiration
there will be difficulties it wouldn't be an aspiration it wouldn't
require determination if there were no difficulties there will be difficulties
is there a way that as best we can we can keep some composure some ease
about okay this is hard this is hard
and maybe i don't feel like i can take the next step right now but i'm not gonna abandon myself
maybe it's not gonna look pretty maybe it's not gonna be in a straight line but to just
not abandon ourselves maybe it doesn't look the way that we
were expecting hoping imagining but to hang in there with our
aspirations to hang in there with ourselves
just one step at a time just one step at a time
resolve determination resoluteness tenacity
just this ability to begin again
and again and again not only for ourselves but for our
communities and our loved ones
to hang in there with them to hang in there with ourselves when we
come across some difficulties in a way that
brings peace brings freedom and has that kind of that peace the freedom
the letting go the truth is integral parts of it
so that our practice is a benefit not only for ourselves but for those we come in contact with
and maybe they come in contact with others and this way
our practice can be for the benefit of all beings
everywhere thank you
so thank you all and
maybe we'll call it an evening with me having this
heart full of appreciation of our coming together practicing together
i'm trying to look and trying to see yes my microphone is still on so our people on youtube can still
hear me but it's finding our way right with this uh pandemic with uh coming practicing
together again and one step at a time and
you know i think um here at imc we're just finding our way and i'm appreciating that all of you are showing
up and like okay let's let's see what's happening how this is going and
what are we doing here so i appreciate that's very much i feel like together
you know as a community we'll find our way so with deep house