so hello hello and formerly welcome to happy hour
so we are um diana and i
have been systematically going through the different practices since the
beginning of the year just to create the context and now we are going through we just started to
to go through compassion practices in the past month we went through different aspects different concentric
circles of meta loving-kindness and now we're moving to
the next brahmavihara heavenly abode practice which is compassion karuna
and as we're going through the concentric circles of this cultivation um tonight we'll turn our attention to
cultivating compassion care for
a benefactor of ours someone who has been there for
us who supported us maybe a teacher maybe a coach maybe a parent
um or maybe even a friend who's been there for us in some way they you know the person
we're going to consider today doesn't need to be our primary benefactor they could be but
someone who's been who's been in that role in some way um in some way supported us
and you you all know what i mean by the by benefactor if you don't type it in chat and i'll explain but
basically someone who's had a supporting role of some kind for us and with compassion it
will bring to mind um something that's it is challenging for them right now or
maybe one aspect of their life maybe their health maybe their relationship work
finance something one aspect that's a little challenging and we work in
cultivating compassion wishing them ease from this challenge from the
suffering in this way so to say a couple more things before we
get into the practice so the practice of compassion as i've
said it before and it burst repeating is when metta which is love and kindness which is just
kindness good will it meets suffering so when suffering is held
by kindness and care this combination is called compassion
so there are near enemies and far enemies in this practice
called um you know there could be sense of pity oh poor you this would never happen to me that's
when there is a sense of oh there is an uh lack of equality in the
perception whereas with compassion for it to stay compassion and not become pity we have the sense of oh this could
be me this could be me this is a common human condition this could be me
this could be me in the future it could make me in the past i could have been born into this so so not to have a sense of oh poor you
you're suffering or you've been suffering but a sense of common humanity and i'll
talk about the other um maybe i'll talk about one more what's called near enemy which is
empathic distress and pathetic distress when we in this equation of suffering
plus good will two of them together make compassion if we lean too heavily into the
suffering then there could be a sense of empathic distress and grief
there's not enough kindness to support it that's actually what a lot of people
mistake compassion for when they say oh compassion is sad it's heavy it's not supposed to be they're
mistaking this empathic distress for compassion
which is like oh you're just feeling the sadness here there's not enough goodwill care love
shining holding it that can really balance so so again if you veer into empathic
distress it's not a sin it's okay just notice it and bring more kindness bring more good
will bring more care to yourself in that moment because you're the one who's suffering in that moment trying to cultivate compassion
so as long as you bring kindness and care you're doing this practice right so
without further ado let's practice together so let's get into our meditation posture
ah landing landing
landing in your seat landing in your body
landing in this moment
and we'll spend the first few moments as always cultivating
settling quieting landing arriving
simply receiving the breath in the body
receiving the breath in the abdomen and relaxing the whole body
um
hmm
putting aside all thoughts all concerns all the words that have come and taking
refuge so important to take refuge
right here right now in this moment this practice and your capacity of your
heart and mind for stability for love
for care taking refuge in this moment
me
hmm
okay
enjoying enjoying
the peace the gift the deliciousness of just
sitting and being breathed one breath at a time
here
hmm
okay
uh
hmm
letting your heart relax and rest in this moment letting your body
ah the next breath out breath relax let go
what you've been holding with your mind
and heart has been cold holding okay to set it down in this moment
okay
uh
hmm
and now if you wish to bring to mind
someone who served as a benefactor for you who supported you
in some way it could be a parent a relative
a teacher or maybe a good friend who's been there
for you in the role of a benefactor
and first to bring them to mind
as clearly as it's possible if your visual or their felt sense
or what they sound like
and first let yourself feel a sense of warmth and care and support they've had for you
and again it's okay if the relationship has had different aspects but just
bringing to mind this aspect of the relationship
them serving as a benefactor with care with concern with with warmth
with love for you let yourself receive that feel that
let your heart feel nourished by this
expression of care in the present or in the past it's okay
with each breath as if you're receiving
with each in-breath receiving the care the good will
and maybe it relaxes your body a little more
feeling more comfortable cared for safer
okay
me
your heart receiving feeling this warmth and care
now letting yourself feel the outflow feeling care and warmth
affection love whatever the nuance or the flavor might be for you
for this benefactor
holding them with each breath with age
out breath extending breathing out care
love warmth good will to them to this person
to this being may not be a person it could be a pet
me
okay and now with the feeling of meta this
warmth good will that you're extending to this benefactor
to this being now bringing to mind some aspect of this
being's life that's been challenging
maybe health maybe finances
relationships work whatever it might be
one aspect emotional challenges
and letting your good will this care
that you've been expecting extending to them let it hold let it meet
let it acknowledge
this challenge for them
acknowledging appreciating that this is hard this was hard
and holding it with an attitude of warmth and care and love
i appreciate that this is challenging for you
ouch this is hard for you and i care i care about your pain i care about your
suffering may you be free
from this sorrow may you have ease
with this pain
i wish you freedom from this challenge
choosing words that are right for you that acknowledge the difficulty
and and hold it with a lot of care affection
in your mind's eye maybe visualizing
you comforting them maybe wrapping a blanket of care of love
around them symbolically
or tapping their back caressing their shoulder whatever might
be appropriate or maybe with each breath you're beaming
soothing light it brings them comfort and ease from this challenge
be creative see what works for you
hmm
me
may you have ease in the midst of this challenge you have
freedom from the sorrow
i care about your pain
may you be soothed
may you be free
from this suffering
okay
me
um
hmm
me
okay
if the energy wanes bringing this benefactor's image
or felt sense or a voice up to your mind's eye as clearly as
possible with a felt sense of your connection
[Music]
letting there be a flow of good will kindness and care
and then connecting with the challenge they're facing
may you have ease you have peace with this challenge with
this difficulty i wish you well i care about you
me
with each breath with each out breath
shining sharing good will good wishes
healing wishes for them onto them
me
hmm
and for the last minutes of this practice period
visit
just as you were holding them with compassion [Music] this benefactor
let yourself be held in compassion for whatever might be challenging right
now holding both of you with care the
challenges
and maybe receive compassion from your benefactor add it to compassion
for yourself by yourself may i be free from this challenge
that i'm facing right now may i have ease
meeting acknowledging the difficulty with a lot of good will and care
may there be ease and goodness for me may i have ease
self-compassion and receiving it from your benefactor
also
and sharing your good will spreading your goodwill your kindness your compassion to all the
beings who are practicing with you right now
we all have challenges as part of this human condition
all of us that took suffering as a mark of existence
wishing all of us everyone ease freedom
with our challenges
and all our benefactors too
expanding the circle further and further to all beings everywhere
may all beings
have peace and well-being grace in the midst of their suffering
may they be free from sorrow and pain including ourselves
thank you so much for your practice everyone [Music]
hmm so i changed the settings and chat
so you're welcome to share your reflections what you discovered your questions in
chat or you can raise your hand if you like to share
and and jesse yes please unmute yourself
hi hi thank you i um you mentioned
uh the p the image of the person you're thinking of and the voice
and felt sense and i see all those things i feel those things
um but but intermittently and um and i i just find it sort of like
to hold a person in my consciousness is a bit trickier than an anchor like the breath
or something it kind of and i wonder if what you could um recommend as far as
trying to like i i know somebody suffering but but still they kind of
come and go it's hard for me to just i want to but it's hard to hold on to it yeah
excellent question i really appreciate you bringing this up because this is so common it is um
it is more complex than the breath absolutely the breast is right here it's a sensation whereas
the image of the person or their felt sense or they sound or how they feel all of that is a little it takes a
little more energy so yes it is more complicated and yet
there's something about conjuring that up that sometimes when we connect then ah
it's um it brings the rest of the practice alive so what i would recommend if you're noticing
that it comes and goes see what um what is easiest for you if you're
visual it could be um a visual sense for some people they're not visual so maybe
hearing the person's voice is easier maybe they felt sense of what they feel like when
you're in their presence maybe you feel kind of giddy or giggly or maybe or or so so that's why i name all of
these too for you to feel what works best for you and sometimes it helps to remember
particular interaction or in last session i suggested you know imagine them having a facetime
conversation with you or or on video chat because that's like oh maybe you it's like oh yeah
there it is you have them you have this image of them and this tiny little square on your phone or something
so so be creative play around with it and and and it's also okay if it's not
constant all the time don't flagellate don't self-flagellate
it might come and go and it's okay and when you notice it's kind of kind of
gone then bring it back really spends a few minutes to conjure them up as clearly as you can
and then it'll probably fade again and it's okay then spend a little more time
and through practice it'll become easier it'll become more steady and it will become more steady
it's it's like a muscle and having done this practice uh for a long time after a while it becomes
easier it just it just becomes steadier it it does so i hope that helps
yeah yeah thank you you're welcome thank you
and any other questions reflections
nancy hi um this is such a beautiful practice
i uh to wish well on a benefactor who you know is going through
a difficult time is um
not only a beautiful thing to do for somebody else but in a way is also a kindness to yourself
because there's a lot of feeling at least for me of powerlessness
in being able to help somebody going through a difficult time and this sort of addresses that for me
beautiful thank you nancy well said yeah there's so much that we can do
in cultivating our heart and being being there for them in our thoughts in our
hearts and it'll also translate for when if we have a chance to actually be for them
so yes an antidote to feeling powerless really reclaiming our power the power of our
heart recognizing how much goodness how much power here is to love this this is
this being here is so powerful so powerful yeah great thank you
so um so i'd like to invite us
and if at this time around this time you hop off like oh my god they're going to go into groups
wait just listen and and i invite you to actually see
if if you can if it's okay for you to stretch yourself just a little bit if you have to go if
you have obligations kids to take care of it's okay perfectly fine but if you're hopping off out of
fear of of being with others i invite you to stretch yourself just a tiny little bit
and see what it feels like and there are studies that people in this
situation they don't want to do a small group but then when they do it they're so
glad they did and their studies and i've done studies so many times with so many groups
believe me it's the case so if you kind of think if you're thinking ah i'm not so sure please stay and check it
out and and work with the sense of um [Music] fear anxiety unsureness i trust me this
is a really really nice sangha really kind sangha
so the invitation that i have is when you get into a small group with a couple of people
to spend again just 30 seconds or one minute um in silence but just
sharing meta just sharing good will for the other two people that you see on the screen
another two or three people you see on the screen just share good will for them and receive their
good will in silence this is such a powerful practice such a powerful practice with eyes open
with eyes open good will receiving good will knowing that they're doing the same for you may you be well dear friend dear
human being fellow human being and then after spending
30 seconds a minute with silence giving and receiving then imagine that
these two three people are your benefactors they're your benefits they're there to
support you they're there to support your practice and you can share as little or as much
as you like about your practice what happened or what didn't happen and it's all good and know that they're
seeing you as their benefactor so you're there to support other people
you have a role you're powerful you're there offering support to other human beings in this boat
in this boat of suffering and joy plenty of that so that's the invitation
for the practice for tonight so about a minute of silence and then imagine you're each other's uh
benefactors so so i will create the birth and so
please give it a try don't don't i really invite you not to hop off
and see how powerful it could be and i'm about to open the rooms so here you go dear ones great
the rooms are closed everyone is back and we have a couple of minutes to
um yeah to share what uh what that was like for you practicing
in in small groups so yeah especially if you haven't shared before
we'd love to hear from you oops i think i i also want to unmute i tried
so mistakenly but uh yeah so please raise your hand or you can type in chat
what what was that like for you what did you notice either about the first part of the practice or the second part
kim please i was uh in the middle of a thought
trying to beat the coming back to the group and i didn't quite make it so i wanted to finish my
i thought i was saying that um i would have found the practice um
difficult the last few sessions um because i find i'm isolating myself
quite a bit and it was uh um practice was with a dear friend
and uh so i have somebody that usually comes up for me that's a dear friend but
i i haven't heard from her for so long and i feel like i've lost her and so that wasn't working
um you know like having i don't have a best friend so that was the benefactor was it was very useful
because i had several benefactors thank you for letting me finish my thought
that's great thank you i'm delighted to hear that and yeah these first couple of categories
are supposed to be easy are supposed to be the easy category so just whatever is easiest
and um and starting tomorrow in the next couple of days we're gonna start moving into uh self
self compassion which is very important and can't have enough of and
um for some people it's challenge for many of us i have to say for many people is challenging to have compassion for
self it's easier to have compassion for others than for self so so
what you shared kim great i'm glad benefactor seemed easier yay hang out where it's easiest
because it's priming the heart it's priming the heart priming the heart where it's hanging out
where it's easy with compassion and then turning to the categories that are more challenging and difficult and
of course we'll later we'll get into neutral and then folks you're having challenges with and you know all of that so
uh yeah so so jamie types in chat how um
does the uh what we're offering here uh compared to kristen neff's mindful
self-compassion so so um christina it's a great program it's it's uh the book and the teachings uh
specifically about mindful self-compassion whereas what diana and i teach we teach
all the brahmaviharas we teach in and and it's in the buddhist
container it's we teach both meta which is loving-kindness as well as compassion as well as
vicarious joy we're going to get to that later equanimity and we share and we also teach
forgiveness practices and gratitude and all of this so the whole canon and
christine focuses on self compassion which we're going to get to
next here so so her program is fantastic i recommend her book to many people
so that's a difference we cover a lot more ground here jamie oh than than kristen neff's work does
and her work is fantastic thank you thank you i my question was specifically about
how you and diana are approaching self-compassion compared to her but it was kind of a silly question anyway i
just got hung up on her ideas and i i can just be open to yours
it um there's so many different ways to uh to practice um these things and and
she has a fantastic way to do it we have we have some boys they're similar some ways or different there's no right or
wrong it's it's all skillful means it's all skill for me whatever works
so it's all good it's all good whatever works whatever helps us cultivate compassion
so i didn't quite get the gist of your question but yeah this all sounds good so dear ones we've come
to the end of another happy hour together yay
i'm happier i don't know about you i hope you are so thank you all thank you for your
practice for doing this work for yourself and for all those whose
lives you touch so may all beings be free may all beings be happy including
[Music] ourselves
thank you