greetings sangha greetings lovely to be with you in this
moment in time and to practice together
so we will continue our explorations of tools
that are supportive and helpful in developing samadhi
concentration often translated some ideas settling
unifying collecting the mind calm abiding is another translation that
i favor over concentration
one supportive tool one supportive consideration
for collecting and settling the mind is collecting and settling and relaxing
the body
often one um invitation that i like people to drop
in if they're practicing if they're trying to cultivate the settling
mind is is um relax
and receive relax and receive
so in terms of wise engagement wise
engagement in which we'll talk about today and also partially tomorrow with respect to
to samadhi and i don't like to use the word effort wise effort i
like to translate in and use engagement another e-word because effort naturally brings up the sense of effort
tightening tightening of the brow i'm trying to get concentrated that's not really the idea
that's not how it works it's more i relax the body to be relaxed
and to receive to receive the breath to be with the breath yesterday we
talked about the joy of the present moment tuning into the simplicity of the joy of
the present moment while relinquishing what is not helpful we talked about that
the first day on monday so the relinquishing and tuning into the
joy especially of the present moment becomes possible when the body
is relaxed when the body is in a receptive mode hence the mind becomes more relaxed the
mind becomes in the more receptive mode
so let's begin let's practice together
let us arrive let us arrive
let us arrive in this moment in this posture
whether sitting lying down or standing
and inviting inviting the body
to let go to soften to relax
our body not separate from the mind
the embodied mind
inviting inviting our hands
bringing awareness to the hands
inviting them
to relax
and give their way to the earth
as we caress our hands with our attention our awareness
internally sensing feeling the sensations
and putting down the weight
moving up to the arms
to the shoulders
softening
relaxing
as if the hands the arms the shoulders
and the neck are being breathed they're receiving the breath
they're being breathed and with each out breath
these areas of the body settle on their own
relax on their own they know how to do this
effort is not needed
with each exhale
softening letting go
feeling sensing the face the forehead muscles of the
forehead
the jaw the eyes
must cells behind the eyes all the muscles in the face
as if they too are receiving the in-breath
exhaling with the out breath relaxing
on their own muscles of the face know how to do this trust
trust
moving down [Music] from the neck to the chest
the chest receives the breath this body receives
the breath and exhales with the exhale
it knows how to relax
to let go
to relinquish what is not helpful
the heart the heart center
softening relaxing emotions and feelings
exhaling
moving down to the abdomen
enlivened receiving the breath the abdomen the lower abdomen
it knows how to receive the in-breath
and how to exhale letting go relaxing
offering its weight to the earth with each exhale
and so to the sit bones making contact with the cushion with the chair with the
earth
receiving the breath
releasing their weight at the outbreath
and the upper legs lower legs and feet
feeling the contact points with the earth enlivened with the in-breath
and exhaling with the out breath this body exhaling with the out breath
every cell every nook and cranny of this body
the entire body
receiving man breath on its own relaxed relaxedly receiving
the in-breath sauce natural in breath not forced
and relaxing softening exhaling
the body receiving the exhale
relax and receive
relaxed and receiving
if you notice tightness contraction has arisen
anywhere in the body it's often the sawing
it often corresponds to contraction in the mind
relinquishing what's not helpful in the mind and in the body relaxing
letting go the contraction in the body the tightness
being aware of the joy
simplicity join the simplicity
of this moment
the gift of just sitting and being breathed
amazing amazing
relaxing and receiving
the breath the sensations of the breath
relax and receive
relaxing the mind the heart the body
receiving the breath
and for the last moment of this practice period
whatever arose or did not arise during this set
whether their mind was unsettled sleepy etc etc
relaxing releasing any thoughts any judgments
self-criticism letting go not needed
relaxing letting go [Music] or what's not helpful
and receiving receiving your own goodness
your own goodness that you showed up
as best as you possibly could given all the causes and conditions
and gave yourself as best as you could
as an offering an offering made an offering to cultivation
as if you put yourself your heart on the altar of humanity
here i am cultivating peace settledness
goodness for my own benefit benefit of others and the whole world
receiving the goodness of that trusting there is goodness there
generated and putting it on the altar sharing it
with all beings everywhere with generosity
sharing our goodness may be a cause and condition
for peace for ease for freedom of all beings everywhere
thank you for your practice
so continuing with the theme of samadhi
and just to say that the themes we are exploring this week
um there are not so much from a list as you know there are so
many lists in buddhism the buddha loved lists
love lists my mind thinks in lists it creates lists um
but what we're exploring these different supporting conditions what i like to
call supporting conditions aren't necessary earned from one set
list um of seven of these five of that these are more collected these tools
from from the different lists and from my own practice over the years um some of you may know
that the practice of samadhi samatha and and the jhanas have been a a primary
part of my practice over the years having practiced with uh
pa aksayada who's a burmese master of concentration
my primary teacher so these are many supporting conditions that i have
figured out in my own practice and also supporting many others in their practice
of developing samadhi concentration calm settling the mind
and i've collected them into a into a list for myself so so if you look there may not be a
canonical list that you'll find all of these numbered together so just as a footnote to bring
that in so exploring today
exploring today as a continuation of what we explored the last couple of days
the first day relinquishment renunciation of what is not helpful what's not
necessary one side of the coin the other one being turning to tuning to the joy of the present
moment the simplicity that it's lovely here no need to go out and and think and be distracted oh it can be
so softly cocooned in the in the delicious simplicity of the present
moment the joy of the present moment this other supportive condition today
that supports them all and they all interact with one another actually
is relaxing and receiving relaxing and
receiving this relaxed awareness
and i've found that to be very very important compared to
a an awareness that is is um it's like um
it's like a fork trying to to stab a piece of broccoli like okay where's
the broccoli okay where's where's the breath where's where is okay where's the thought okay okay okay
instead of that kind of an awareness which can which can tighten the body can tighten
the mind and the body cannot be in a receptive way to to relax and actually experience the
peace the settling of of calm of unification
instead to imagine awareness i guess continuing it with that simile
as a spoon as a spoon that is gathering collecting
soup oh it's receiving the soup it's kind of concave oh
yes it's not going out to stab okay bad breath this oh okay got it it's like i receiving
receiving receiving so this receptive quality
this receptive quality and the buddha talks about this receptive
quality of mindfulness of awareness of sati there are different modes to awareness
and satay in majima nikaya 19 um
the buddha talks about the cow herder the the uh when the cow
herders sitting on the top of the hill before the harvest and the cows are in
the field the cow herder needs to be really really vigilant and make sure the cows do not go and
trample uh what hasn't been harvested yet that's one mode that's one mode and then
there's another mode where the harvest has happened and
the cow herder on the top of the hill is is aware of the cows yeah they're there
that yup yup and yet that same sense of vigilance is not needed there is is a different
mode of sati of mindfulness
when the fields have already been plowed so the cows can can go into the
fields it's okay so as long as they don't go too far afield but there's a sense of
relaxing under the tree watching the the cows
there's a relaxed relaxing and receiving
uh mode to samadhi which can be to to to sati to awareness in this way which
can be very helpful for developing concentration developing
somebody and and i'll talk tomorrow
more about atapi about coming back about persistence which
together with this relaxed awareness can can support the cultivation of somebody
because if he's just relaxed and there is not no persistence then you know the cows can go and
trample anywhere and maybe the fields haven't been plowed so there needs to be a level of persistence
that we talk about tomorrow so these are kind of connected discourses um two
other points i wanted to bring in for your consideration
um another one actually is is from
the sutta from manchester nikaya 3631
where the buddha when he is sitting under the bodhi tree
and um he and there is this wanting to
to become free this desire is for desire to be free
and he remembers he has a memory of when he was
a child under a rose apple tree it's a beautiful memory and he realized and he remembers that
actually i'll read you the passage because it's so beautiful this paragraph he says i
thought i recall once when my father the sakyan
was working and i was sitting in the cool shade of a rose apple tree
then quite secluded from sensuality secluded from unskillful
mental qualities i entered and remained in the first jhana
rapture and pleasure born from seclusion accompanied by directed thought
and evaluation could this could that be the path to awakening and then
yes he realizes this is the path to awakening this delight this pleasure born from
seclusion not the oh the heart charging the
um well i mean there's a lot of intentionality too but not
the tightness there's a lot of relaxation of the body that can support here and i
want to bring your attention to sitting in the cool shade of a rose apple tree that's such a beautiful
image when we sit it's a hot day sitting under the cool shade of a rose
apple tree ah the body relaxes there is a sense of ease
peace um of of enjoyment and that's when the buddha
had fallen into the first jhana the the the pleasure
the the and with the seclusion of the mind with from unwholesome qualities that's when
uh the mind had settled was abiding in the first jhana so and he wonders is
this the path to awakening and yes and that's how it it opened up
so i offered that for your consideration um of noticing
is the body relaxed is the body relaxed is the bodiness a receptive motor is it
tight one last thing to mention for you to
notice is there is a strong connection when the mind is tight or when the
thoughts and entanglements come up it always shows up in the body
and in meditation we can see that especially when the mind is very very
settled and quiet and settled each and every thought even if it's not
an entangled thought any thought we can see the reverberation in the body it's quite
amazing to see that therefore it is skillful
as we cultivate especially at the beginning as it's a little the settling of the mind might be choppy
to check in with the body oh is there any tightness in the body is my forehead
tight is is my neck getting shoulder getting tired ah if so relaxing relaxing
softening letting go allowing the relaxed mind a relaxed body
to support a relaxed mind if the body is tight the mind will be tight if the body is
relaxed the mind can relax also
so experiment explore for yourself you don't have to take my word for it or the buddhist explore for
yourself be a scientist of your own mind of your own heart
of your own body so thank you for the gift of your practice
in this sangha and look forward to practicing together
tomorrow be well