welcome welcome a really warm welcome to everybody
wherever you are whatever time it is whomever you are really warm welcome
so as you know we'll start with a guided meditation
and just taking this opportunity to
maybe fully arrive at this moment
bringing a sense of presence a sense of aliveness
to the body
inhabiting the body and some kind of way
there might be portions of the body areas of the body
that feel neutral [Music]
and there might be some that feel a bit tight or tense or
otherwise calling for attention
and can we in a warm-hearted way just bring our attention
to those areas where there might be some tightness some contraction
this can be commonly in the face
around the eyes and the jaw
sometimes the shoulders get tight and raised up can we allow the
shoulder blades to slide down the back
and feeling grounded feeling connected
to whatever we're sitting on whatever the feet are touching
and whatever the hands are touching maybe they're
touching the top of the legs
maybe each other each hand is touching the other hand
and then can we rest our attention on the sensations of
breathing noticing this aspect of the
body feeling the expansion and contraction
associated with inhales and exhales
allowing ourselves to rest in the rhythm
of the breath can we soften
any ideas that things need to be different and instead
just rest here with the sensations of breathing
when the mind finds itself being busy with thought
just very simply gently begin again with the sensations of breathing
there might be a lot of momentum to our thinking
chances are you've been thinking all day
so can you have a warm-hearted attitude
towards the mind wanting to continue thinking
we don't have to make thinking a problem and we
just bring it back to the sensations of breathing
giving ourselves over to the sensations of breathing
right now there isn't anything else to do
while you're here meditating and where else to be
we're just here
meditating being aware of the sensations of
breathing
it can be helpful to make a quiet
mental note when we find ourselves thinking
there might be a way in which labeling it making a note
thinking like indicates a clear transition from
thinking back to the sensations of breathing
this is a tool you can use if it's helpful
if it is not helpful there's no need to do this practice
but it can be a support just a soft gentle note in the mind
thinking
we don't have to make thinking be a problem we can fold it into our meditation
practice not trying to make thoughts go away
we're just choosing to put our attention on the sensations of breathing
sometimes we might have this idea
that meditation is about having no thoughts
and having that kind of idea just creates the conditions for frustration
and disappointment
there's a lot of thinking that happens in our daily lives that of course continues into our
meditation
so is there a way that we can work with our thoughts
rather than insisting that they go away can we fold them into our practice
and maybe even they can be an ally they can be a
support for our practice
so in this way our warm-heartedness
our intention to quiet the mind settle the mind can be a
support not only for us but for those who are in
contact with us so that we are more aware of our
thoughts and aren't as pushed around by them
so that we may meet others with openness and ease
so that our practice is a benefit not only for ourselves but for others
i can spread out from there may our practice be for the benefit of
old beings everywhere
[Music] so [Music]
welcome welcome really warm welcome
so today i'd like to talk a little bit about thinking and meditation
within the meditation instructions or certainly mindfulness instructions are just to
notice our thoughts and that's a fantastic practice and it can be very effective and it's a great
way to go but it's not the only way to work with
thoughts and maybe sometimes something a little bit
different is needed so can we work with that thinking mind in a
way that goes beyond just being mindful of thoughts when the occasion arises
but to use the mind as an ally and use it as a support for our practice
it is a powerful tool are the mind of course it is
and there's this way that there are some analogies
or similes that are used in the suit does of um like a cloth being better able to
take up dye if it doesn't have stains
right so the dye just won't it'll either not be taken up where that stain is or
maybe it shows up darker or something like this
so when the cloth isn't filled with stains we might consider that the dye
represents some concentration or good will
some boundlessness some openness something like this
or the and the um in the same way that when there's a
cloth that isn't filled with stains is better able to like clean and polish
whatever needs to be cleaned and polished maybe even including itself
so is there some way in which we might consider that the mind is like a cloth
in these similes but for some of us this idea of like
actively using the mind during meditation um can be a big shift can be really
different than what we're accustomed to we we may have this habit of we just use
the mind in a certain way during meditation
or and so we have this idea that with our meditation practice it's just about
doing more of the same maybe longer or deeper whatever we've been doing with
the mind and to actively do something different might feel
different uncomfortable for example we may be attached to these ideas that there
should be a sense of not knowing like that's the most important thing and so for us
to meditation practice is associated with falling into a soft
cushiony cottony maybe foggy blurry space
that initially can have a certain amount of comfort because it's a
insulated from the outside world perhaps but then often you can find that the
energy um drops out of a practice like that and there can't be any wisdom that arises in
this kind of this dullness but there might be this idea that there
should be not knowing and we kind of try to shut down all of our
mental activity and instead fall into what sometimes it's called sinking mind
or alternatively we might have an idea that with meditation
we is finally an opportunity for us to figure things out figure out ourselves like why we do what
we do or what's underneath that um
trouble niggling mind or thoughts that we might have or something and so we're
doing some archaeological dig in our thought processes
lots of different ideas that we might have about the role of thinking in the mind during meditation
and there's a number of ways in which we might use the mind but that requires that we put down any notions about what
should be happening with the mind with thinking during meditation
and including putting aside the idea that there shouldn't be any thinking whatsoever
but instead to start wherever you are and
we use the mind in particular ways to be a support
so the practice doesn't require that our minds not be engaged
in order to move towards greater and greater freedom instead the practice is to find freedom
while the mind is engaged so
one way is i've been using just this word thoughts kind of in a generic way
you know just plumping them all together but in fact you know there's lots of different types of thoughts
and certainly it changes during the course of meditation
it might be with a longer meditation period at the beginning is we sit down and there's this thinking
mind is definitely present and there's kind of a strong momentum there's this
maybe a compulsive feeling to thinking that there's this can't be stopped and
there's one train of thought after another after another maybe the thoughts seem loud or solid or
authoritative and happening in a rapid succession so
maybe when we first sit down that's what we discover
but as the mind starts to settle as the body starts to
settle as the meditation period progresses
then thinking can becomes a little bit softer a little bit less compelling
and maybe with not a sense of rapidity like there was before
and with greater meditative clarity with greater stillness the thinking can then be a
little bit more light or thin or still
definitely less authoritative less solid
and there may be a way in which the thoughts like float into the mind and
the meditator doesn't really have that much interest in getting tangled up with
them isn't so identified with them they're not seen as a problem
necessarily and there might even be some gaps of
silence in between the thoughts
and then as meditation period progresses this might only be experienced on retreat
or with longer meditation sessions or maybe after some time of practice
it's really big beginners often don't have this experience but
there's this the thoughts seen arise and they're seen just as
phenomena oh there's just one more thought without any inclination to
be associate with them or to add any particular importance to them
there might even be kind of a feeling of the
creation of a thought and then the thought arises and then it passes away
like all things do so i'm using this word thought but we
can see that as meditation period progresses or meditation experience progresses whether that's in one sit one
retreat one's uh maybe years of meditation practice we
can see this progression we can see that
this one word thought actually refers to a whole range of things
and has different qualities it can be helpful to kind of notice the
quality maybe the how authoritative it seems or how solid
it seems another way another way to characterize
thoughts sometimes that i find useful is to think of them as
sometimes thoughts feel like they're just long novels you know just getting lost with
getting lost in thoughts getting lost in you know
just this papancha getting a proliferation of thoughts and then maybe as the mind settles maybe
instead of a whole novel maybe it's just a chapter and maybe just a paragraph and then we can get down to a sentence and then a
word so it can be helpful to notice that
there's these different qualities and that it can be a way in which we
interact with the thoughts is to be to notice the different qualities of them is one way
to be a little bit removed from them and not to be completely lost in them
and in the suit does we know that the buddha to be that is before he was awakened that he worked with thoughts in
this way too also to categorize them and uh here's a quote from one of the
sudas before my awakening when i was still
unawakened but intent on awakening i thought why don't i meditate by continually
dividing my thoughts into two classes
so i assigned thoughts of sensual desire thoughts of ill will and thoughts of harming
to one class and i assigned thoughts of renunciation good will and harmlessness to the second
class then as i meditated diligent keen and resolute
when essential thought arose i understood this sensual thought has arisen in me
it leads to affliction for myself it leads to affliction for others
it leads to affliction for both myself and others it destroys wisdom it brings irritation
and does not lead to nabana when i reflected in this way
the thought went away so i gave up got rid of and eliminated
sensual thoughts that arose then this continues with thoughts of ill
will and thoughts of harming so the buddha he categorized his
thoughts on whether are these wholesome are they helpful or are they on hopes of unhelpful and
even causing affliction and harm do they lead to awakening or do they lead to harm
so this can be a way in which we can interact with our thoughts also like a
third way in which we might categorize them to sense into is this the way that's leading to greater and greater freedom
and one thing that i appreciate is in this quote is that first the buddha noticed that he was having thoughts he
wasn't lost in them that's the first step the second step that he did a little bit
of noting practice oh this is a thought on sensual thoughts
sensual desires ill will harming
and then he subsided these thoughts subsided when he contemplated this actually isn't helpful
it doesn't lead to awakening and causes harm to myself or others or both
so he's actively using his mind here to help him with his thoughts
but sometimes that doesn't work right often once we hear what the buddha does it
sounds like so easy and so straightforward and it's true that often there's kind of these idealized
scenarios that are portrayed in the sudas but there's some more ideas about how to
work with thoughts in the sutas and these are some instructions that the
buddha is here's a quote he says when harmful and wholesome thoughts
connected with desire aversion and delusion arise due to paying attention
to a particular object of awareness then
shift one's attention from that object awareness to another
objective awareness that is connected with something wholesome
so this idea that if you notice that you're paying attention to something and there's um some sensual desire maybe
there's a individual that you're sexually attracted to and you're lost in sexual fantasies
or maybe there's an individual and which that you um have some it will some aversion and
you're lost and those thoughts whether they're lost thoughts of harming or if it's there's
thoughts of how you were harmed or kind of repeating things you know often how these types of thoughts kind of have a
real stickiness to them so the buddha's suggestion is to replace
them is to switch if you notice that you're thinking about this to think about something else
and it gives a simile it's as if there were a peg and some wood
then you want to replace it you have like maybe a coarse peg and you got one that's just a little bit smaller a
little bit more fine and you take a mallet and
kind of like pound it out and you just replace the
more coarse maybe one that's unwholesome unhelpful peg with one that's more
wholesome and helpful fortunately there's some gives a little
bit more details about this because maybe it's not that easy
to just reflect on to note the thoughts to reflect on these aren't helpful and then
to decide okay i'm going to try to replace them but maybe we find it's a little bit difficult to replace them
so there might be some ways which we can replace them with something that's
neutral and often this is the general instructions that are given that pay
attention to the body often i'm giving instructions to and i do this myself is to bring attention to
the sensations in the feet there's something about the feet that feel really grounded and connected to
the earth to whatever it is even if we're sitting our feet our chances are are touching
something so to replace thoughts
that are troubling and unwholesome and unhelpful with of the body it can be helpful to do with
what the feeders touching or what the hands are touching maybe if we're sitting to feel the
pressure of the chair or cushion against our bodies or another neutral one often is the
breath just put a little bit more effort into
bringing sensations to breathing for me sometimes i find it helpful to
set the intention to be with the beginning middle and end of an in-breath or the beginning middle
and end of an outer breath and setting that in tension brings just enough a little bit effort to stay with
the breath so that's one way to replace thoughts
but there's some other ways one is we can replace thoughts of
sensual desire sexual fantasies or something like this
by dismantling the attractiveness
and i appreciate the way that tennis robiku approaches this
by visualizing what the body of this other
desirable other would be like if we dissected it into its various parts not
necessarily dissecting with a scalpel but broke it up or considered all the different parts
so the purpose of doing this is just to help us if we feel like we're lost and
just these thoughts of sensual desire in it so to keep that in mind so in any time you
feel like doing this this practice leads into disgust or
something that feels unhelpful that's not the direction we're going right this
is just a replace the coarse peg with a finer peg just to
replace it with something that's has more wholesomeness to it so if you further feel like a sense of
disgust or depression or something like this then to just drop these practices i
haven't described them yet but kind of laying the found work
laying the groundwork here to drop them and just return your attention to the breath but maybe it's
easier to go to the breath after this little interlude
so this practice of thinking about body parts
instead of the body as a whole as a way to dismantle the attractiveness
in some ways we're kind of like dismantling the body
and part of the mind is sure to resist this practice
like there's a way in which we feel like we have a sense of vitality
or some i don't know there's some way in which we are loathed to give up
some of these what our minds get lost in
but until we kind of work with that resistance the mind will continually go this way
so this dismantling what we find attractive is a way in which we can help take some
of the power out of this the mind wanting to get lost in lust
full thoughts so one thing that tunis robigu tanjef
that he recommends which i appreciate very much is to bring an attitude of humor
to this contemplation so that it can shift the obsession that the mind is
currently lost and just right we don't want to get filled with disgust or depression or anything like this we're
just trying to help ourselves get out of our rut perhaps with our thinking
so uh ton jeff says to keep it lighthearted
this uh this uh exploration okay so how is this
first of all we need to use our imagination of course right there's no other way so here's a way in which our
mind can be our ally is to use our imagination and you can imagine that this person
that you're very attracted to and you might imagine that they have a beautiful hair let's say
luscious hair and maybe you have these ideas of running your fingers through their hair or something like this
then imagine that you're gonna have a meal with this desirable person and
you're gonna have some intimate time together and then you discover that their hair
is over everything it's in your food it's on the plate it's on the table
you look around the hair the place is covered with their hair like that just olson kind of shifts your
your perception or your relationship to it to their hair
or there's something that tonjes suggests as this idea of
you can think of maybe there's another part of their body that is attractive to you
and imagine what you would do if you opened a room you walked into a room you opened it in and there was
just that particular body part right there on the floor that body part completely removed from
everything else ugh right very different very different uh
experience this brings to mind
somebody a friend a child of a friend it was i think probably a preteen at
this time thought it would be really funny you know during halloween time you can get these
body parts like arms that look really real and i
saying this about walking into a room and seeing the um
just a part on the floor somebody i had this experience right where this preteen
put this uh arm that they had gotten from the halloween store and i remember just yelping and but then
we laughed and laughed and left we had such a good laugh about it so is there a way in which you can consider
there are different body parts of this individual in which you're having a sensual desire
or can you if you think about part of all human
bodies is liquids right we have the contents of our gut we have saliva we
have all these types of liquids contents of the bladder of course
what would you do if you saw a vat of that liquid
like wow right that's completely different so there's a way in which you might
use the imagination a little bit playful and
bringing up things that are a little bit outrageous as a way to
replace these thoughts that are unwholesome that are unhelpful just to get lost in
sensual thoughts and then maybe after this thinking of
parts being in unusual places and in unusual ways
then maybe it's easier to come back to the breath maybe it's easier to come back to something that can really calm
and settle the mind it's true that we might also have
thoughts of you know a will or some aversion and to replace those kinds of thoughts
the common teaching is to do some love and kindness to do some mata some good will
and i'm often instructing to just do goodwill wherever it's easy
so it doesn't have to be towards that person for whom you have ill will that's that's
a tall order to go from ill will to goodwill but instead just to shift over to
whomever it's the absolute easiest it could even be imaginary kittens
i saw some kitten videos the other day oh my goodness right there's something it's a little heart melting
so if that's true for you can you so your imagination for maybe it's imaginary kittens or maybe
there's somebody when you bring them to mind your heart really softens
but also tan jeff denis robiku he talks about one
way to do goodwill for those who have ill will which i think is uh
can be a really fruitful way and this that is this recognition
that we want to wish good will for those for
everybody that's in our own best interests we want the mind not to have ill will but have
good will so including those who we find difficult
and can we wish for those with whom that we find
difficult can we wish them to learn how to be skillful in their actions so that they may find happiness
so we may use that as a phrase
may you learn to be skillful in your actions
so that you might find happiness and this we kind wish for people
that they learn to be skillful so that they can be happy of course we don't want them to continue suffering we
all recognize that when people are happy they can take better care of others and take
better care of themselves so we can do some loving kindness some
meta some goodwill practice for those we find difficult by saying something along the lines of
you can find your own words that are meaningful for you but may you learn
to be skillful in your actions so that you might find happiness
i think all of us can do this we can wish this which is a different uh
it's a shift away from the ill will to wish them that they may learn
skillfulness in their actions and maybe with that with us we have this openness
this willingness that we could help show them if they wanted to but that's extra only think about that if that's helpful
so the way in which we can use the mind as an ally instead of just thinking that
thoughts are there should be no thinking or that we should
get ourselves sequestered into a cocoon where there's kind of a dullness or to
feel like we have to figure everything out there's a way in which we can
use our thoughts we can replace our thoughts for the unwholesome and replace them
with something wholesome so actively use our mind as part of our meditation practice as a way to help them it might
help the mind to settle and find more freedom help the heart settle and find more
freedom and so may our practice of finding more
freedom be for the benefit of all beings everywhere
thank you you