so good day and uh it's actually feel quite wonderful to be
here with you all and not only is there an opportunity to meditate and
talk about the dharma it's also remarkable to
feel the good will and the warmth and the gratitude that uh comes through the chat
and i'm sure represents many other people who don't participate in the chat and
for all of us to be sharing in this together quite remarkable and maybe it's
almost uh certainly adds to the richness of the meditation we do to feel like
we're doing it in such a friendly community so thank you very much
and um
when doing meditation it's really best not to try to be a perfectionist
any attempt at perfection probably goes in the opposite direction
it makes it harder we strain more and maybe it gets more brittle
and i think that the idea is to be at ease with how things are
not how we think they're supposed to be to be at ease with how things are not
with what we think they're supposed to be and to have that and then and to have
that ease not be perfect so that not looking for perfect ease and what
this means is that we're partly
learning to hold [Music]
ourselves be mindful of ourselves without it needing to be all one way but we have an ease with holding
things together that are maybe some good and some not so good some some pleasant
some not pleasant some uh you know what we think this what we is what's happening is what we think is
supposed to be happening what's happening is not what we think is happening all these things can co-exist so for
example um people associate meditation with a quiet mind not thinking so much or not
thinking at all and so people some people that are trying to have that no thinking state
i think it's better to be at ease with the mind that thinks and certainly it's nice to let go of thoughts and
quiet the mind and it's nice to come to a place where the mind is not thinking so much but even better is not to be disturbed
by your thoughts and to be at ease with them and in that way it's possible to let some
thinking just recede into the background and rather than being preoccupied by
with the idea of having no thoughts at all it's um it's uh we could just um
let some you know some thinking can just go on in the background and we can kind of know what we're thinking
or maybe not as long as in the foreground we're just staying with a breathing or
staying with our present moment experience and so those two can co-exist
and uh and so but when thinking comes into the foreground then we learn to practice with it but
even then the idea is to be at ease with it and the same with discomforts in the
body some people have like a homing instinct
maybe because of fear to just kind of really tune into uncomfortable painful sensations the
body be worried concerned but you know and expecting they're supposed to be completely comfortable
all the time but also comfort and uncomfortability can co-exist
and sometimes it's just fine to have a certain level of pain discomfort also be kind of
in the background or just be part of the overall environment and not needing to zero in on it and
focus on it and that allows us to kind of open up and focus on
all this allows us to then gently focus on what is onward leading what is really supportive
of us to develop the meditation further it's supportive to focus on that part of our
experience where we're not thinking a lot where we're feeling and quietly calmly
feeling the experience letting the thoughts be in the background at some point in meditation
it's onward leading to to become aware of the pleasant
sensations that um they're not there because of some we're getting you know some wonderful ex
sensual experience but rather as we settle as we settle and feel more
content here more then then we feel kind of the meditative contentment
meditative comfort and pleasant pleasantness of the experience
and that is a useful thing to open to and in the background there might be
discomfort but if it can just be in the background don't worry about it too much and gently open to the
pleasant to the meditative pleasure joy contentment that might be there
or the feeling of rightness the feeling of this is good to be here so there's a wide
range of kind of pleasant enjoyable or right feelings that might come as we meditate
and to open to those and let them spread or i like the notion of just opening the body to them and
so they they fill us more or they expand more
so taking a meditation posture and gently closing your eyes
and and kind of settling into your posture
and here also we don't want perfection with the posture i like the expression just good enough
just good enough for you to be here and settle settling in
and then you can set yourself at ease
set yourself at ease in your body
and that can mean to be easy be easy with what's happening in your
body ease up a bit around the body
and then as you exhale settle and relax the body further
and then set yourself at ease in your heart in your emotional life
let yourself be easy with whatever feelings and emotions you might have
ease up on them a bit not to make them go away or make them different
but ease up be easy with it all
an easy relationship
and then set yourself at ease in your mind with the things you're thinking about or
concerned with see if you can let yourself be easy
with the activities of your mind
easing up the pressure easing up the heaviness the contraction
around the concerns
and then as you exhale to relax your emotional
being relax and soften in your heart
as you exhale relax and soften in the thinking mind
maybe the notion that you're making lots of space for your thinking mind
so you start feeling the peacefulness or the calmness of the space around it
and then settling into your body and feeling your body
globally in whatever easy way there's
maybe a broad awareness maybe awareness that gently slowly
roams around the body to touch into things to be aware of the body
as you exhale softening the shoulders
as you exhale softening the belly
as you exhale settling in to your body your posture
your place here
and then to if it's possible if it's available
perhaps you can feel some modicum of contentment
or allow yourself yourself to feel some degree of contentment
to just be sitting here quietly peacefully
aware of whatever is here for you whether it's comfortable or
uncomfortable pleasant or unpleasant
it's very significant and valuable to be aware of how things are and to be
content with just this opportunity to be quiet enough
to be aware of it all pleasant and unpleasant
difficult and easy it's all okay just to be here aware
maybe letting go of perfection that things have to be just so
and then feeling your breathing more fully
being at ease with whatever way you're breathing
being easy with your breath even if it's labored or tight
be easy ease up
not needing the breathing to be perfect it's okay for it to be unpleasant
if you're feeling it
it's okay for it to be pleasant if you know it
and maybe there's a little bit of both with breathing
as you go through the cycles of in-breath and out-breath some of the experiences of breathing a
little bit more pleasant some are a little more
unpleasant
offering yourself the gift of knowing just knowing how it is and just knowing
is enough as you go through the cycle of in and out expanding and contracting
inhaling and exhaling
settling in to breathing
and in the breathing itself as you exhale relax
and let go soften go with the releasing
like you would let go of at the top of a slide just like to slide down
let go with the exhale sliding down the
length of the exhale
let go
and then as you inhale receive the full inhale
allow your body space to breathe in
and then as you're breathing breathe with whatever is pleasant
letting the unpleasant be there but not focusing on it so much
any feelings of contentment or comfort or pleasure
delight or joy happiness or well-being
maybe a subtle glow or a subtle warmth or a brightness
tingling or vibration
or maybe a pleasant energy that seems to come along with breathing through the
body
sliding down the exhale allowing for the inhale
sliding down what is pleasant
allowing for what is pleasant the joy the happiness well-being
letting the thinking mind become quieter so you can better feel the goodness of
just being here breathing
allowing that goodness the pleasure to fill you to spread throughout everywhere
even the places where that are uncomfortable let those be touched and filled
by whatever degree of well-being that might come meditating
so as we sit here to remember that things don't have to be
all one way or we don't have to focus on just one aspect of our experience
there's a way in which we can be at ease and inclusive of all of it
the pleasant and the unpleasant but then open more to the pleasant side
not at the exclusion of what's difficult but to better more balance in a more
balanced way to hold it and be with it
and if we turn our attention now to the suffering of the world suffering of people you know and
suffering of this covet time and
so many people challenged
there can be a strong tendency to focus on the suffering
exclusively to feel the suffering the pain of the world or of other people
and think that caring about it means you have to really focus on it exclusively
i believe that compassion is richer fuller
more compassionate if it doesn't exclusively focus on
the suffering but realize there's always more there's
always the pleasant the non-suffering that's happening at the same time
and to include what is good and what is
healthy and has sense of well-being to it or
goodness in it and to have a broader field of attention
so we the suffering can be held together with or inside of
a sense of well-being or sense of subtleness or ease
and so we can better recognize that the people we're thinking about or focused
on it they're more than just suffering people
and you are more than someone who just focuses on suffering there's a wider context
in that wider context of well-being and wellness and not wellness
allows compassion to be fuller and more penetrating and more pointing
to the end of suffering so as we end this meditation now
may it be that our ability to be inclusive of it all
allow us to meet the suffering of the world with greater care and kindness and
compassion may it be that the meditation we do
is a direct support for us to enter the world
with compassion for all may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so continuing the topic of anapanasati mindfulness of breathing in and
mindfulness of breathing out the we're kind of moving into the
territory now of the second tetrad where we train to experience joy
as we breathe in experience joy as we breathe out and then we train to as we breathe
in to experience happiness as we breathe out to experience happiness
and so all along here in all the 16 steps what
they have in common is mindfulness while breathing in and mindfulness breathing out and there's a connection
to this rhythm of breathing in and out that goes on and um
and as we move into this the joy part the the happiness part the
kind of the sense of wellness well-being that comes along uh i think it's important to remember
that we're that how important this rhythm of breathing in and breathing out is
so it's as i've said the the continuity of breathing
is keeps us can keep us in the present moment uh it's a breathing is always a present
moment experience and it keeps us going and moving along in the present and it's also but it's
also inconstant there's a discontinuity because the in-breath is only there
while you're breathing in and the out breath is only there when you're breathing out and one leads to the other and there's
this rhythm of one after the other the sensations at the beginning of the in-breath are different than the
end of the out-breath the sensations the beginning of the out-breath are different than the end of the out-breath
and so there's a constant change of sensations of movement experience in the body sometimes for focusing mostly on a
little spot of the chest or the belly we feel the changing texture of
sensations there if we're aware more broadly we might feel changing
ways and places where that are activated with sensations as we breathe so there's both this
constancy and this inconstancy with mindfulness of
breathing the constancy of the rhythm of breathing and the inconstancy of all the pieces of
it the subsets of it coming and going and
and so we can't hold on to any one part of the breathing without causing problems if you hold on to the
exhale you know you never inhale and so you know then you you know run out of
breath if you hold on same thing with the inhale some people kind of prioritize really don't want to
let go at the top it's very so it's going to be very very subtle some people come to the top
of the inhale and they don't really want to give up anything they kind of have a
policy of holding everything they don't want they want things for themselves so there's a little subtle
resistance there to let go some people don't start the
exhale because it's a kind of letting go especially the end of the exhale people get little
very very subtly people get a little bit anxious there or there's a very subtle attitude maybe
at the beginning of the in-breath no i don't want to breathe in it's just a bother just more work
and now just leave me alone there's enough input coming my way so there can be very subtle attitudes uh
in that cycles of breathing and that kind of little bit operate when you
when we get to that a little bit of holding perhaps a little bit resistance
or a little bit triggering of thoughts fear or resistance or or you know a
version or something and and you see if you're really attentive you can watch and see in that
cycle where it is that some little psychological thing is triggered occasionally don't don't try
too hard to look for it but it's a little bit there and or if we start thinking about something else
and it's really you know preoccupying really as major issue you can feel the breath gets
held and we're still breathing in and out but maybe it's all chest breathing and it's you know the belly's tight and and
and so there's this holding going on but if you just stay with the inconstancy in the
flow of breathing and remembering that this is constantly
letting go constantly opening up constantly releasing and softening and allowing the
flow to go that it's a protection from getting attached to anything getting hooked too
much on things getting caught in our thoughts caught in reactivity whatever
it's a way of keeping us limber keeping us relaxed or loose or not so caught
and that it's by degrees and so i don't think it's all or nothing again but we slowly the breathing begins
to massage us and begins to support the letting go and with time as the breathing becomes
more like a flow that goes smooth and easy that
the the watching the breath tuning into the breathing becomes a little bit like sitting at the
edge of a river and just watching the rippling occurrence so the water flowing down
the river and it's kind of like looking at a fire sometimes we can just spend a long time
just looking at the changing patterns of the water flow that you know that's
not that different from each other but it's changing and it can be just a watch that can be very relaxing and it we're not
necessarily trying to quiet our mind or stop thinking about anything but just letting that be the
you know the way the mind kind of the attention uh gets absorbed in and flowing with
something gets quite quieter and quieter and stiller so the same thing as with time
as the breathing becomes more relaxed more loose more open more flowing and we can kind
of be within constancy the and the constancy the inconsistency of
the little wavelets of breathing on top of the constancy of just the flow of the river of
breathing we get absorbed in it we get pulled into it
and there's a lot of it's not like we're looking at the surface of uh water we're actually what we're doing is
feeling sensing all the sensations that come alive as we breathe and and especially as we
kind of get settled in and really begin to settle into the present moment and stay with that rhythm and flow of
breathing that there gets born
pleasant sensations and that er that kind of can take the form
of contentment it can take the form of pleasure it can take the form of a joy
or delight or happiness a sense of goodness a glow a warmth and i know i'm repeating
my things i've said now but i think it's worth repeating i know so
and everyone will experience a little bit differently some people might feel something a glow in their chest as they settle
into breathing some people might feel it in their belly a warmth something good some people maybe it
feels intense um joyful tingling and kind of a delightful
uh in the nostrils that the air goes in and out it gets more and more intense the the the sharpness of the joy of the
the pleasure that's there and it's kind of a thrill almost it might be there's a kind of a sense of
uh locationless thrill throughout the body that comes as we really settle in and
get it get absorbed just like you get absorbed and watching the river get absorbed in this thing
my first experience of like this of being absorbed and feeling the goodness of it
was when i was about 10 years old and i would
take the public bus i was living in italy in a little town in italy and
i would go to school in town and we live in the outskirts of town and and my my bus stop that i got off on was
right near the very end of the line and i i learned at some point oh so
there was a driver and there was a conductor who sold the tickets to two people and the conductor would go
up and down and sell tickets as people got on board but the conductor at some point when we
kind of got outside the city enough that really not new people were gonna get on
the the conductor would sit on a particular seat and do the accounting of all the
different seat uh tickets uh he'd sold you know a round trip one way children
you know senior citizens whatever it might be um and he had his ledger he'd write on and
i learned that if i sat in a particular seat behind his seat and kind of looked over his shoulder and
watched him do his accounting in his ledger of the different kind of tickets he got
i would just start feeling so good i would just kind of feel so warm my chest would kind of glow and
delight and joy and i feel so content i felt safe and settled and
everything was right in the universe and just watching him and i have no idea why i didn't ever thought about it
i just knew that if i sat there i'd have this really good feeling and many years later when i started
meditating i realized that i was getting absorbed in this very simple
thing that he was doing maybe i was tapping into his concentration of working but just the movement of his
pencil on the paper and and his focus on it somehow i got kind of absorbed just
it wasn't like trying to get concentrated i wasn't i didn't know i was you know really getting absorbed
um it just like my my world kind of got so content and happy and settled and just him his pencil his
piece of paper watching him and um so this is the this maybe captures a
little bit the sense of what's possible in on breath meditation as we get into this
fifth and sixth step we're not trying too hard it's almost
like we're just sitting back and watching the you know on a nice quiet day and nothing to do nothing to be just
watching the river the conductor do his leg ledger in the on the bus and and and allowing ourselves to
include include the good feelings that come with that now remember they don't come
automatically and right away the first four steps of anapanasati are always the default
and and the basic default is the first two just becoming familiar with the breathing and and developing just kind
of developing capacity to stay a little bit in the present moment with things and we're always going back to the
beginning and you might go back to the beginning during some sittings it was one way in the beginning and then
we're kind of back near the beginning at the end because who knows all the ways that things change in our mind and body and
so uh don't have some idea of linear if it's linear don't have some idea that it has to be a certain way don't be in a
rush but when you're settled enough and present enough then at some point the fifth and sixth
steps might be relevant and this idea of kind of gently allowing yourself to be absorbed in that
and feeling the goodness of that and and kind of let the breathing in and bring out always going on that rhythm keep you
from getting attached and wanting keeping you loose and limber in the mind staying with that flow in and out and
then letting that rhythm of breathing and out move through or with the goodness that's there as well
and let that grow and be expansive and let it grow and be expensive so it includes
it can include all the challenges as well without us needing to be preoccupied
with the challenges or caught by them or needing to fix them they're just there in a relaxed way and
so um so i hope that um
you'll feel content contentment and perhaps the assignment for the next
24 hours is maybe you can look for more opportunities to be have contentment in your day
and i suspect that it you you can do it if uh even if it's a minute or so that
you'll have more opportunities if you look for them and and
and hang out with them a little bit and that contentment in your daily life will maybe support you to feel this
meditative goodness and contentment uh that supports a deepening of this practice
so thank you very much and i look forward to our time tomorrow