yes good day everyone and welcome
and
so one of the orientation that's uh i've been talking about these last two
weeks is that of wholesome and unwholesome skillful and
unskillful and to learn to recognize when in
meditation the mind is doing something unskillfully that's unhelpful not useful
and also to recognize the authority we give these unhealthy thoughts and ideas their
importance we grant them in doing so being involved with them
maybe even perpetuating them but also recognizing that there's an
alternative there is wholesome skillful useful helpful ways
of engaging the mind and part of the health healthy wholesome ways is not to be
angry or upset about the presence of unwholesome
but rather to meet everything with compassion with kindness but not with
a compassion or kindness that accepts it in a way that just
perpetuates it accepts our involvement with it or our entanglement with it accepts the way we
give it importance and authority but lovingly and openly
kindly stepping away from it and and either holding it
kindly or focusing on something which is more wholesome
so in both both circumstances one of the most wholesome things we can
do is to meet everything with friendliness
it's my translation today for metta sometimes translated as good will
sometimes as loving kindness and so when we have unwholesome states of mind that
we hold that we look we look upon that with kindness with friendliness but not to
you know condone it but just to but not to condemn it either but to end the ways in which we
perpetuate these things but to hold it kindly so it can relax perhaps or
so that we can relax around it and to uh view everything friend in a
friendly way to view ourselves be our own friend
be a friend for our breathing so to have good will friendliness to all things
and it doesn't have to be so complicated to do so maybe but uh some very simple
basic human capacity for for kind of a simple friendliness to our
experience and to begin this meditation
you might close your eyes and you might simply think about
some um some person or
animal or location anything at all which when you
are with this person or being or location that it's pretty simple and natural
for you to have a friendly disposition maybe appreciation of the person the
people the beings maybe a sense of friendliness
and um and maybe imagine being in the presence of the
person or imagine a time when you had this friendly feeling for the person
and feel it in your body feel it in your heart
maybe even noticing what happens in your mind when you have this friendliness
and then to
maybe let go of the memory or the being you're thinking about but
let's stay keep the sense the feeling of friendliness
the sense of it almost maybe as if it's an open door and
then you allow your experience to come into it
and then allow your breathing to come into your simple friendliness
maybe in a friendly way that's meant to support your body's breathing
taking a few longer slower deeper breaths
breathing in breathing out
to be with someone as a friend means to be present for them
not too much and not too little but to be present
in a friendly way
then letting your breathing return to normal
and continue to
be with your breathing in a friendly way or allow your breathing to breathe
through or with a feeling of friendliness and kindness
and if there's any mind states that arise that are difficult or diversive
or impatient or some ways are considered unwholesome
see what it's like to not condemn it be upset by it but rather
to be friendly towards it
as if you're friendly with a angry person and the friendliness
helps the angry person to relax
is simple friendliness to yourself including what's difficult
maybe allow something to relax and to support that
maybe you can relax parts of your body
a friendly relaxation of the shoulders
the belly
muscles of the face
and a friendly
softening relaxing of the mind
and maybe there are many ways to be
friendly see during this meditation whether you can find
your way to do it in a simple way
without a high standard but just good enough friendly
disposition of goodwill care kindness
as an orientation for how to sit in this
meditation
maybe during this meditation you don't have to bother being involved
in an unwholesome mind states this is a time you can take a vacation
or a break from your involvement with them
any involvement except a basic friendliness to all things including
what's unwholesome
one way to be friendly in meditation
friendly towards all experience
whatever you're mindful of while you meditate you might gently quietly
meet it with the word yes
the word yes might protect you from unwholesome states
and might evoke in you
a wholesome state in relationship to what's present
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to turn our good will outward into the world
to in a sense gaze upon the world with kind eyes
in a way that might be easier or clearer
when we're calm or settled
and one of the great questions is why not be friendly
and chances are there's not a lot of good reasons to avoid being friendly
friendly doesn't have to be dramatic or doesn't require much of us
we have to do something or agree with people or invite them into our homes
it just means that we have good will in our hearts that we
look upon them in friendly ways even if we keep walking
away but to always come back to being friendly
to learn the art of walking in the world in a friendly way
and it's with basic friendliness is a way of
enacting
the wish or supporting the wish or contributing to the possibility
that all beings be happy that all beings be safe
that all beings be peaceful
that all beings be free
may we
remember to be friendly so we can contribute to the welfare and
happiness of all beings
[Music]
so as we come to the end of these two weeks that i've been talking about kusala
wholesomeness and skillfulness
there was a man who came to the buddha to ask a question about the kusala dhamma
a question about skillful teachings spiritual teachings or or wholesome
spiritual teachings i love this kind of idea that the dhamma
and the teachings excuse me that the buddha teaches or that people
are oriented towards is something which is wholesome or skillful
beneficial and that's an alternative to someone coming and talking about what
is the true teaching as if there's some absolute truth ultimate truth that we have to discover
or see teaching which is ultimate you know ultimate teaching that the most
profound teaching ever and uh the buddha regularly
kind of avoided that kind of language but it was always pragmatic and he
emphasizes that which was wholesome and beneficial that which is beneficial for leading to the end of
suffering and brought happiness and welfare it's a very different orientation for
religious teachings where many times in philosophy and religion people are looking for what's ultimately true
in buddhism it's more looking at what leads to happiness and welfare and what leads to
the end of suffering so this man comes that's coming a little bit to challenge the buddha
and uh he says that um it seems to me that if someone discovers
a wholesome teaching a wholesome dharma that they shouldn't teach that to
anybody else because it's an impediment to them it's
a obstacle to them it's just causes them headaches to uh have to go and teach other people
and after all what can one person do for another person implying that you really can't really
can't do something for another much for other people so he asked what do you think about this
to the buddha and the buddha said well let me reply with a simile
and i think this is a very kind thing to do is rather than directly criticizing the man for his
teachings or or offering an alternative directly as almost like there's two different views
and i'm going to offer my view now and that's that clearly opposed to your view he says well i'm going to uh
offer you a simile and i'll ask you questions
so so this brought man who's talking to the buddha it's important to understand that he's a
large landholder and in a time in time of the buddha he owns a vast
estate where there are many sharecroppers who work his fields and
you know they share in the crop a little bit and that's their payment and um so
the buddha says well imagine a visitor comes to you and says
you know you should just keep all the produce that's produced on your estate for yourself so you can enjoy it
and have a good life and and don't share anything with your sharecroppers
if that person came to you and told you that would that be a challenge difficulty
for your sharecroppers and the man said yes that would be a difficulty for them and
be challenged for them not to receive any payment or any any of the produce for themselves
and uh would that person be uh that visitor who came would that visitor be would be would
that person be concerned with their welfare and the man said oh
no the person would have no concern for their welfare well then if that uh what do you think
with that person more have ill will for your sharecroppers
or goodwill or love and kindness kindness for them for your sharecroppers
and the person said oh even more ill will for them and the buddha said in the same way if a
person discovers a wholesome teaching a wholesome dharma
wholesome practice and it doesn't share it with people who could benefit from it
that's a challenge for them it's an obstacle for them it uh it's a you know
and it's an impediment for them in terms of moving towards greater welfare and um it would not support them and
benefit them and maybe it's more likely that kind of keeping the teachings to oneself is a
kind of ill will a little bit aversion that's there
so that so rather than directly countering the man the buddha said here is a simile how would you behave under a
similar circumstance and when the man understood how he'd behave in a similar circumstance
then i think the idea is the buddha didn't have to answer the question directly as asked a person could
figure out how the simile was applied to his own question and so here the idea being that um
there is a wholesome dharma skillful dharmas and that it's a good thing to share it
with people it's a good thing to teach if you have if you really discovered it and know it really for yourself
and so whether everyone should be teaching explicitly or be a teacher that's another question but the idea
that um that we're here we have something we discovered how to live in a way that
is beneficial and we share it with others we live it so that we can benefit other
people as well that we don't live uh hermetically sealed off from others but we live in a world uh to cooperate
into and to um and to live in mutual kind regard and mutual support for each other
and um and so we discover wholesome states of mind we discover wholesome
practices wholesome ways of being and you could just keep it to yourself
but rather than necessarily teaching your family and friends be sure to live it be sure to express it
in how you live your life share the goodness you discovered the freedom you discovered
and that's an art that's a skill to be learned gradually slowly by
continuing to do it just because it's difficult um the or it feels a little bit like a
you know tiring to kind of be kind to people or friendly
if we keep practicing it and doing it it becomes easier and easier it becomes second nature
and in some sense it eventually becomes easier than many of the alternatives
so the whole sum dharma and i want to end this series of talks with emphasizing what
i've said now repeatedly about the nature of the buddha's teachings that they're pragmatic
there are many people who came to the buddha to ask ultimate questions you know ultimate spiritual
religious philosophical existential questions and um some people even demanded the
buddha that he should answer these kinds of questions like uh does does the soul exist will the
soul exist after we die does a soul die when we die
is consciousness something eternal is conscious of something that is temporary only here when we're alive
is uh the world eternal is the world fine you know not going to last forever
is the world infinite it goes on forever or is it finite all these kinds of kind of ultimate
questions and we can add probably all kinds of ones that we've probably hurt ourselves over time um
and um and some people really want answers to these things because somehow that reassures them or
tells them they're on a good path or i don't know what the reasons but
but the the buddha always said oh those kinds of questions
they are not beneficial so he kind of mostly just stays silent he
doesn't answer those questions they don't not beneficial for helping people come to the end of suffering
to discover a real happiness and and what is what i teach
is the practice the orientation the view that supports people to discover what is
really beneficial what brings welfare what brings happiness the end of suffering
and and and so with this kind of pragmatic orientation
the buddha's concern is um is really with people suffering and
overcoming it that's the the topic and sometimes our
particular buddhist tradition is considered kind of a lesser lesser buddhist tradition and
and maybe that's a nice label we can embrace because yes it's lesser in the sense that it doesn't
uh pursue all the grand and wonderful cosmic existential questions that people
can think of but rather focus on something very fundamental and root
that is the suffering and the end of suffering um happiness and the discovery of a
lasting really profound happiness and well-being
and with that end of suffering and with this discovery of happiness then our relationship to these great
existential questions the meaning of life and what happens when we die
takes a they might still be interesting questions but then they have more they're a little bit more philosophical
in nature a little bit more abstract or a little bit more there's not a they're not as a weighty or as important for us
because we've discovered how to be at peace and very happy here there's no fear that's driving those
questions so so
wholesome and wholesomeness skillfulness uh this is a really
fundamental uh concept uh in the teachings of the buddha that i
find quite inspiring it's simple and it's meant to simplify
things uh to keep us close to what's most important if what we want to do is to become free
of suffering so um thank you very much
and uh i hope that you will live a wholesome skillful life for your own
sake and for the sake of others it's a great privilege great honor to be able to do even the
smallest thing to benefit the life of someone else so thank you very much