so
the mindfulness of mind or
breathing in experiencing the mind
breathing out experiencing the mind
and i'm in you know what the exactly
cheat mind is
i'm sorry arguing that we can't really
know
what the buddha had in mind
but i wanted to read you part of the
definition
in the polytech society dictionary so
them
more or less a standard poly english
dictionary
it was written over a hundred years ago
now
but it's still excellent resource for
understanding this
and and they have a wonderful little
entry for cheetah the word that we're
mostly translating as mind
it says the meaning of chitta is best
understood when explaining it
by expressions familiar to us as
for example with all my heart
and soul i have no heart
to do it blessed are the pure
in heart singleness of heart
all of which emphasize the emotional and
cognitive
connotative side more
than it's the mental and rational side
it may therefore be rendered mood
disposition state of mind
so some people prefer to translate this
word cheetah
as heart or as heart mind
it kind of touches into the emotional
side of all this more than
the word mind might even feel a little
bit this
emotional this you know and not so
connected to our emotional life
and uh and also when some people like me
treat mind and awareness almost as
synonymous sometimes as we get into
deeper meditation
that also might kind of lend itself to
the idea that
we're kind of being removed a little bit
from the embodied emotional life that we
have
and uh which may be a little unfortunate
maybe this whatever chitta is whatever
the mind is
uh whatever awareness is maybe it's a
rich world that includes our
emotionality to some you know to
important ways
and so uh in the step eight
seven and 8 of mindfulness of breathing
it's looking at the mental activities
recognizing the mental activities in the
mind and
then relaxing those mental activities
and there or tranquilizing or calming
them
which is that movement or opening having
the mind
become open not contracted
and as i said earlier the mind that's
preoccupied
gets in my mind gets hijacked attention
gets hijacked
by um our desires by our aversions by
our
doubts by our restlessness our anxiety
and um and it's almost like that the
times are like a black hole
that uh attention falls into and it
doesn't really come out there isn't like
we step back and get the bigger picture
we get swept away and our preoccupations
our thoughts our fantasies the stories
um our resentments all these kinds of
inner world of what goes on
and and uh and these are all mental
activities that hijack awareness
and there are other mental activities
that enable awareness or
open the mind that doesn't hijack but
rather enhances
the quality of the mind so
the buddha made the distinction between
mental factors that do
the closing the mind those that open is
the distinction between what's called
the five five hindrances and the seven
factors of awakening
the five hindrances are um strong
sensual desire
lust craving um aversion
ill will hostility when it's strong
sloth intorper lethargy resistance
and and then agitation restlessness
anxiety regrets kind of agitated states
of preoccupation
and then confusion uncertainty doubt
that can really we get lost in a rabbit
hole of doubt and confusion
and um and these can have very strong
gravitational pulls and
we you know we get pulled into them they
can come sometimes with a lot of
authority like this is really important
i have to be involved in this
and but the consequence is that
attention gets hijacked
and for the buddha when attention gets
hijacked like this
he calls that a loss of wisdom a
blindness
an obstruction to the mind a covering
over of the mind
a makes the mind fragile and brittle
and uh hard and and
whereas the other that opens seven
factors of awakening
those are awareness mindfulness itself
a clarity of mind that's sometimes
called investigation
a effort joy
tranquility samadhi
concentration and equanimity
and all those can work together as a
whole and each of those can operate
uh singularly to really kind of open the
mind up
and open the inner quality of the inner
life and this is where
the emotional side uh really comes to
play i mean some of the most
one of the most sublime beautiful
emotions that's hard for the
people who haven't experienced it to
appreciate is the quality of equanimity
um it's a you know it's uh just
it's it's a beautiful kind of feeling
uh tranquilities has a kind of almost an
emotional quality to it it's really
strong and embodied and
broad and has a warmth and
clarity to it stillness and peacefulness
joy of course seems emotional
samadhi is an integration of bringing
together of all aspects of our life
including the emotional
so um but the the um
the the the what what these seven
factors awakening are
they are characteristics or supports
for awareness itself for mindfulness
itself
and so the more they operate together
with awareness
they tend to open awareness strengthen
awareness
they create vision they support wisdom
they remove obstructions they remove the
coverings that
keeps us from seeing things clearly and
they make the mind
malleable soft workable
ready to do the work receptive maybe
to do do work and so here we're talking
about
mental activities kind of
that represent this divide between
becoming more closed
or more open and
and it's possible to cultivate each of
the seven factors awakening by itself
to be attuned to them and learn to
recognize them and support them
and it's also they they tend to grow in
the wake
of uh really emphasizing
mindfulness attention here but being
attentive
that the mindfulness whatever way we
practice it
in and of itself is not a closing
activity
that it hasn't uh there isn't some other
factors that come along with mindfulness
like striving or
or expectation or
pushing or contracting around the
mindfulness
that begins moving it in the direction
of the hindrances closing down
so this ability to track the mind state
allows us to be to protect the
mindfulness from
being hijacked that way and so we can
turn the mindfulness
now it's getting closed more as i try
hard and maybe i can find a way to be
more open
more relaxed and this simple movement
from
being more close to being more open but
yesterday i used the
for gail fransdel the technical terms
ouch and ah what involves more stress
or more suffering more discomfort
and what goes in the opposite direction
to be able to see
that simple divide is one of the primary
characteristics of the second factor of
awakening
as i said usually called investigation
but
is really a clarity of mind that sees
this
veil and sees this distinction between
the ouch and the ah
being closed and being open
becoming blind or lost in our
preoccupations
and opening up and having vision and and
clarity what's happening
so this is one of the great advantages
of beginning to tune into the mind state
and i as i said in the meditation it's
fascinating i
kind of said it's fascinating because
they're very valuable and even healing
because just being attentive to that
simple movement
can free us from having to get caught up
in
the details of what's happening uh
whether it's right or wrong or am i good
and bad person because of what i'm doing
this way
and you can have the worst thought that
any
preoccupation that anybody has ever
happened in the history of humanity
and in this mind state thing it doesn't
really matter that it's the worst
thought anybody's ever had
it just matters that you recognize that
you closed down you got tight
and that there's an opportunity then
just to allow yourself to open
and not and just let it go let it kind
of recede
and move towards the openness of mind
and so that simple movement that's the
direction to go
can make the practice some ways much
simpler
and very forgiving
so the mind state and
so that's
what we're doing today and um
and we will continue tomorrow and then
starting on monday the idea is to go
through these seven factors awakening
and hopefully as we kind of linger in
this area of the mind state
it's such an important one and and then
we'll
go on from there and
so thank you very much and
i look forward to our time together
tomorrow