well good morning welcome as some of you know my name is fu schrader and i'm a visiting teacher from
the san francisco zen center who for a few days anyway this week is sharing the dharma seat
with your teacher gail franz doll and also paul haller from last week also from the
zen center as part of a three-week intensive that we're calling the harmony
of zen and vipassana so this week of our intensive is focusing on the buddha's
teaching of right conduct so the previous two weeks we focused on
meditation samadhi and on wisdom prajna and
yesterday morning for those of us those of you who joined i talked about the precepts
which are the cornerstone of right conduct and precepts are given to us in order to
connect us to one another in order to bring harmony to humankind
through connecting practices ones that we all know like kindness and generosity
patience and wisdom so zen center's founding teacher shinryu
suzuki roshi taught that receiving the precepts is a way of understanding what it means to just sit
the integration of precepts and meditation is the foundation for all of the practices and activities
of our daily life so for this morning's meditation i'm going to remind you briefly about the
points of your posture that will help support just sitting and after that i'm going to
read you a small passage on silent illumination by a 12th century chinese zen master
named hong ju silent illumination practice is considered the hallmark
of this living branch of buddhism on which i happen to be sitting called sotozen so please first find a nice
comfortable position for your legs and your torso
and then bring your awareness slowly up from the base of your spine
toward the top of your head you know take all the time you like allowing each vertebra in your spine to
lengthen upward along the way the lower back is a nice deep curve
going into the abdomen which allows your chest to raise and open
there's another slight curve outward between the shoulder blades which themselves drop down as though
they're little pockets in your back you can slip them into the pockets there's another curve gentle curve at
the neck going in toward the throat and then let your head balance slightly
on the top of the spine the chin pulled slightly downward the ears
in alignment with your shoulders and the nose with the navel
excuse me keep your eyes slightly open with a soft resting gaze at about a 45
degree angle from your eyes to whatever surface is in front of you there the floor or table
let all the tension in your body begin to melt away from the top of the head i like to
imagine cracking an egg a raw egg on the top of my head and letting it run down the back
and the arms across the shoulders
and then softly across the belly and down to the floor carrying with it
all of that tension now gently inhale two or three full
breaths through your mouth and then out
again
now after which you can just return to normal breathing
the one traditional technique for quieting the mind is to count the breaths from one to ten
on the impulse to inhale one
i i like to notice that impulse in my abdomen where you low down and then fully exhale
on the impulse inhale
two three
and so on and once you reach 10 you start over with one if you forget
as we all do simply go back again to one it's like riding in your breath a little
bit like a small boat on the open ocean up and down with the waves
your arms can rest on your knees or be brought together into the cosmic mudra which is clearly visible on many statues
of the buddha in seated meditation the left hand is on top of the right
with the fingers overlapping your thumbs are lightly touching at the tips making a nice oval shape
with your hands like a little little cradle sometimes i imagine resting my mind in that cradle
as i sit when your mind is agitated it's it's
recommended that you bring it down bring your attention downwards so the hands are a nice place to hold
an agitated mind and if you're sleepy the instruction is to bring your
attention up to your forehead you know here third eye
so as we continue to settle ourselves into a comfortable upright posture i'm going to read you a teaching from the
zen and zen ancestor hong jour he was a master of the meditation that we call
silent illumination the model of practice that is enacted at a pivotal juncture
between meditative absorption and skillful activity of our life in the world
here master hunger
this short essay is called drop off your skin and accept your function
in daytime the sun at night the moon each in turn does not blind the other
this is how a patch-roped monk steadily practices naturally without edges or seams
to gain such steadiness you must completely withdraw from the invisible pounding and weaving
of your ingrained ideas if you want to be rid of this invisible turmoil you must just sit
through it and let go of everything attain fulfillment and illuminate thoroughly
light and shadow altogether forgotten drop off your own skin and the sense
dusts will be fully purified the eye readily discerning the brightness
accept your function and be wholly satisfied in the entire place you are not
restricted the whole time you still mutually respond
right in light there is darkness right in darkness there is light a solitary boat carries the moon
at night it lodges amid the reed flowers gently swaying in total brilliance
you
oh welcome back to the world of shared language and innumerable meanings
so for those of you who are just joining i am fuschrader from the san francisco zen center and i'm a guest of gil
fronsdale who along with paul haler and myself are offering a three-week intensive
called the harmony of zen and vipassana so this morning
is the second day of our week-long study of the teachings the buddha gave on right conduct sheila and to begin i'm going to
share with you a teaching story from the pali canon about the source of what is called the bodhisattva vow
or the vow to live for the benefit of all beings so this vow underlies not only the
tradition that we endeavor to practice here at greengauge farm where i'm sitting right now
but wherever humans are conducting their lives for the benefit of others as i know so many of you are doing right
now on the front lines of this pandemic for which all of us are deeply grateful
so here's a story about a yogi named sumera that illustrates the origins of the
bodhisattva vowel and please keep in mind that it's just a story
countless eons ago in a city called amaravati there lived a brahmana named sumeda
a son of good family when sumeda was still quite young his parents died
and the minister of the state showed sumaida the wealth accumulated for seven generations
that he now had inherited from his parents the family treasury was filled to
overflowing with gold silver gems pearls and other valuables
when sumaida saw the treasure he thought after amassing all this wealth none of
my ancestors were able to take even one penny with them when they passed away
can it be right that i should seek to take my wealth with me to the end of my days and then he told the minister of state
to give all of this wealth to the poor
when he saw how a life of transmigrating within samsara the cycle of birth sickness aging and
dying moment after moment was suffering he wanted to find the path of deliverance
that would lead to extinction to no more rebirth so he left home and entered a forest in
the himalayas to practice as a hermit because he was a person of great integrity over time he attained
superhuman knowledge and supernatural powers one day deepangara buddha appeared in
the world and began to teach to prepare for the buddha's arrival the people of the town began to fix the road
which had flooded and to decorate it with flowers sumaida who lived near heard of the buddha's visit
and flew to the town offering to help with preparations the people were so excited because they
knew that sumeda could fix the road with his supernatural powers just in time for deepankara buddha's arrival
but sumeda wanted to do so with his own hands and so he started to carry the soil by
hand unfortunately deepangara buddha and his assembly arrived before his work was done
sumaida did not want the buddha to walk through the mud so he loosened his matted hair lay down on the ground and with
outstretched hands asked the buddha to walk on him
lying there in the mud sumeda looked up at deepangara buddha and he thought to himself
if i wanted i could now enter the buddha sangha and free myself from deluded states of human desire
becoming an arhat and then at death i would at once attain nirvana and cease to be reborn but this would be
a benefit to myself alone i want to help all beings as deepangara
buddha is doing right now and i am determined and then he made a vow i vowed to attain
what deepangara buddha has attained anu tara samyaksambodi the complete
perfect enlightenment of a buddha for the benefit of all beings when
deepangara buddha saw sumeda lying in the mud he understood that the young man had vowed to become a buddha
so he told his assembly that in the distant future sumaida would indeed become a buddha
named shakyamuni hearing this prediction sumaida was overjoyed
believing that his vow would be realized and thus sumeda became a bodhisattva
meaning a buddha to be vowing to remain in the realms of suffering until all beings
had been saved so this is our inheritance as well you
know all of us as a gift from sumaida and our own buddha shakib who came here
to this earth looking for suffering beings it might be saved which in buddha's world means to be
awakened so this vow to live for others is the true heart of our human life whether we know it or
not say it or not believe it or not still some part of our mind turns
towards this thought of awakening the bodhichitta the thought of enlightenment and some part of our body
turns toward the image of an awakened being toward the possibility of becoming an awakened being ourselves
and so we sit like a buddha we study the buddhist teaching and we endeavor to
act like buddha over and over and over again and then
on the morning of his awakening what shakimani would have saw was his own miraculous face appearing as
the morning star as the branches of an overhanging tree the bodhi tree
as a lovely young woman carrying water in a jar on her head as bees and flowers as grass and flowing
water just as we're all seeing right now and for the first time in his many lives
he knew he wasn't separate from the world he knew he wasn't alone there was nothing
outside of himself so what the buddha then recommended to
his many disciples was an opposite world where each of us is devoted
ourselves to the welfare of someone else or maybe to everyone else
in his search for liberation from suffering the young prince said undermined his own self-concern
self-love self-conceit and ignorance a radical act that
diverted the flow of his ambition away from accumulating more cargo more wealth to preserving the
precious resources of this life-giving planet for everyone and everything that depends
on it so when we take this vow to live for others much like in a marriage it's done
before witnesses in our family our friends our community and for a brief moment moment or two we see into
the heart of creation itself herself himself into the great wholeness of
being our own true body and our own true life so basically the precepts are like a
trellis to hold ourselves up as we undertake this very same journey lifetime after lifetime moment after
moment need be that led to the awakening of a young prince turning toward the thought of awakening
is a natural thing for us to want something that sounds so wonderful you know like enlightenment
although wanting something for ourselves alone is perhaps the very thing that blocks our way fortunately we
really have no other choice but to start from where we are and most often if not always
we will find that we are starting from selfishness one of the four defiled ways of thinking
that block our view of buddhahood these four are called the klishtamanas
krishnamanas sounds defiled thinking the first is ignorance which along with
desire is the cause of human suffering the next is the belief in a self a
separate self the third is the conceit about that self and the fourth is the love for that self
above all else basic narcissism
and yet right there is our first opportunity for a taste of liberation by studying the self that we believe
that we are and then by telling the truth about what we see i see that i am selfish
already in that recognition and acknowledgement the precepts suddenly appear beginning with what from
my point of view is the most important precept of them all a disciple of buddha does not lie not to
oneself and not to others and that very truth will set us free
which reminds me of another amazing story also from the poly canon about the power of telling the truth
excuse me
a young boy is bitten by a poisonous snake the distraught parents stop a passing monk and ask him to use his medical
knowledge to save the child the monk replies that the situation is so grave that the only possible cure
would be emphatic statements of truth the father then says
i have never seen a monk that i did not think was a scoundrel may the boy live without the poison left
the boy's leg the mother then said i have never loved my husband
may the boy live the poison retreated to the boy's waist the monk then said i have never believed
a word of the dharma but found it utter nonsense may the boy live and with that the boy
rose completely cured such is the power of the truth
so telling the truth also called the practices of confession and repentance in the
buddhist tradition is intimately connected to the bodhisattva vowel there are two sides of one practice or
one coin and that's because our vow of saving all beings is endless
and therefore will never be complete you know we just can't do it our awareness of the incompleteness is
in itself a kind of repentance you know as in i am so sorry but i just cannot finish
this job even the buddha said this very thing when he could no longer stay in his
painful human body gotta go i think you've all seen the
enso the zen masters draw as a demonstration demonstration of both their unique
personalities but also of their understanding of this universal truth of incompleteness
the circle will never be closed this truth is the same for all who undertake
the bodhisattva vow and practice and at the same time that our task is unachievable
it's also important to reflect honestly on our personal shortcomings as part of entry into a life that's devoted to vow
such reflection sets up a resonance between the enormous task and ourselves as limited beings
endeavoring to undertake it you know it's harmonics shanti deva the 8th
century indian buddhist monk and scholar and an adherent of the middle way philosophy with its
primary focus on the emptiness teaching said one law serves to summarize the whole of
the great vehicle the protection of all beings is accomplished through the examination
of one's own mistakes this kind of honest self-reflection
helps to motivate us and to inspire us to continue finding our way oftentimes we back away from looking at
our mistakes and instead we lead with a string of justifications you know stories good
stories i've always appreciated the practice of the zen center when one of us misses a bell or relate or do some other
unskillful things we simply bow and apologize without bringing in a lot a lot of extra information you
know better known as excuses it's also part of the mahayana tradition
when entering into a relationship with dharma practice and in particular with the bodhisattva
val to acknowledge not only the impossibility of completing our mission
and our current mistakes but also our previous mistakes our previous way of life our selfish
life in which from which we are in recovery so which is exactly why we chant every
morning during service following our meditation all my ancient twisted karma from
beginningless greed hate and delusion born through body speech and mind i now fully avow
meaning i now fully accept i did it and i'm very sorry so being conscious of our errors and
being concerned about the effect our behavior has on others is essential to our life together in community both
locally and globally as we hippies used to say you know think globally act locally
in a citation to asuta thanissaro tells us throughout ancient cultures the
terminology of music was used to describe the moral qualities of people and of actions discordant intervals and
poorly tuned instruments were metaphors for doing harm harmonious intervals and well-tuned
instruments were metaphors were doing good in pali the term sama even
meaning even sama describes an instrument that is tuned on pitch
so this term samana meaning a monk or a contemplative also derives from this same word summa
evenness referring to the greatly admired characteristics of those human beings who have developed
in themselves the quality of being in tune with what is proper and good and most
importantly for everyone around them so tomorrow morning i will be talking about the verses
known as the three refuges that we recite also each morning following meditation
i take refuge in buna i take refuge in dharma i take refuge in sangha
the three refugees also known as the triple treasure are the first three of the sixteen
bodhisattva precepts without the buddha his teachings the dharma without the people who came to
study with him the sangha there would be no buddhism and which is kind of obvious
less obvious perhaps is that none of us would be here this morning to talk about it there would be no us no it no way of
life so taking refuge in the triple treasure as suzuki roshi said means that you
adore the buddha the dharma and the sangha and that for you taking refuge is an act
of adoration so before declaring our adoration to the triple treasure it might be a good idea
to consider just what each of those refuges means to you and that's what i'm going to talk
about tomorrow so thank you all for your kind attention please take care stay safe