hello everyone hi and welcome to happy hour
and if the audio's alright would you give me a thumbs up fantastic thank you so
let's get started informally by welcoming ourselves welcoming each
other to the space wonderful sangha of ours and i start by saying hi
i'm nikki i'm in mountain view california unseated oloneyland where the weather has been pretty warm
today we're going into another heatwave so who is here who wants to say hi
hi neil in new hampshire as to whether in new hampshire mia
it's been raining for about nine days but it it finally got sunny today oh wow nice
wish we had the rain hi bill in dallas texas how's the
weather in dallas
warm hi ricardo from brazil on youtube thanks for joining us ricardo
the youtube sangha anybody else please feel free to unmute i'm lish and i'm in
oakland and it was in the high 70s which i complained about which i shouldn't be complaining about
because it's really nice yeah it's about 10 degrees cooler than
down here in on the peninsula good to see you
and hi says girl girl from uh friendly greetings from cork city in
ireland welcome girl and hello elaine from toasty belmont california
yes and gabrielle from montreal hello glad to be here with you glad you're
joining gabrielle and hi kenneth from albuquerque ken
hi charles lee all saying albuquerque hi the albuquerque albuquerque crowd
yay my parisian accent is is coming in with interesting pronunciation of albuquerque
megan hi from palo alto which is also toasty i bet megan yes yes yes great anybody else wants to say
hi it's such a nice ritual of saying hello
to each other i just love this part it just warms my heart
hi mark and terence from squam washington and hi claire hot and humid in new york city okay
all right this is this is sweet to get a bit of a weather report from different parts of
our sangha or global santa so let's get started
formally thank you neil for sharing information about the happy hour google groups
where folks can share information with one another and also references quotes etc are sent
to that uh to the google groups they also had this time i changed the
settings um so that accidental unmuting will go away
the possibility of that and also the chat will become host only in case my sound
drops out or something dramatic otherwise let's keep all the chat pretty
quiet uh for the duration of the guided meditation and um the little dormant and last
but not the least i'm going to turn on recording and it's going to ask you whether you got it or leave meeting wait for it
wait for it it's gonna come okay hi welcome
so so for the theme of our practice
today um i'd like to invite us to to continue to explore
um the breath on the last time we practiced together on
wednesday i introduced um some ideas from this
book i've been listening to this audiobook called breath by james nestor
and and we did some experiments together as a
sangha and also i got some emails but people would listen to the audio and experimented so
we're gonna continue with the breath experimenting with meta and breath similarly and slightly
differently we're having learned from our experiments perhaps so here's here are the
the ways to to consider the practice for tonight so
so the practice of meta loving-kindness is both a cultivation practice
it's also considered a practice of concentration or samadhi
samata practice where the mind gets settled settled quiet peaceful
and perhaps absorptions states of jhana can arise
so practicing meta really has this dual effect both the cultivation of the
heart the good will for others for oneself as well as the settling of the mind
really subtly so bringing in bringing in
the slowing down of the breath and supposedly based on some studies the
optimal breath rate is about six seconds per in breath sex six seconds per out breath
and the exhale especially elongating exhale seems to be important so that
can really support the calming and settling of the mind
so so [Music] the invitation would be as
as we'll go through some of the categories tonight and i'll leave a lot more space silent
space for you to experiment with the pacing i'll i'll start with the phrases to set the
phrasing and then we'll also simplify the phrases instead of perhaps trying all the four
phrases as we did last time which might have been too much to juggle for
for some and became a little overwhelming okay okay there's the breath there's the feeling of meta
there's the elongating there's the exhale like oh what do i do so so we will simplify and it's
perfectly fine to work with simplified phrases
we sometimes work with the four phrases you be safe happy healthy and have ease and
it's also fine to work with a simplified phrase may you be well may i be well and really bring in more
emphasis to the feeling to the feeling of meta so maybe tonight we'll simplify the
the phrase if you wish if the simplified phrase after a while you want to bring
on all four phrases you're welcome to and also bringing
attention to the to the breath of the slow down breath they're roughly five
and a half uh in breath and out breaths per second so
and um let me see if there's anything else to set the
frame maybe i'll pause for a moment and ask if there are any questions
uh unusually so before i start if you actually tell you what if
you have questions i'll be saying a lot more during the guided meditation so i'll all become clear we'll all become clear
especially if it isn't so it's all good so let's just start together let's start practicing
together so landing
landing in the body
landing in this moment
inviting first and foremost inviting your body to rest
to let go
of anything that's not needed in this moment any tension
any extra thoughts plans from today
for the future memories of the past
as if you were putting down
as if you were putting down the heavy weight on your shoulders or plans and memories
ah feeling lighter feeling lighter just coming to this moment
taking refuge in this moment
feeling your feet and the floor if you're sitting on the
cushion your lower legs connecting to the earth
letting go of the weight of the weight of the lower body
onto the earth
feeling your sit bones your bottom contacting the cushion or
the chair ah letting go of the weight of the upper
body releasing releasing onto your sit bones
fighting your belly your lower abdomen to relax and soften
ah letting go internally
inviting the chest
to soften the heart center the proverbial heart
center in the center of the chest inviting your heart to relax
a quote-unquote center of emotions letting your heart rest in this moment
whatever has been arising is okay
can all rest and feel safe
softening the arms the hands
letting gravity pull down
relaxing the shoulders and the neck
the face
letting the eyes rest their socket the forehead to relax
to jaw to unwind
for your scalp
to settle
nowhere to be nothing to do but to greet
to embrace this moment intimately
with the in-breath and the out-breath
moving right now naturally letting them be natural throughout the body
the natural breath through the body
now keeping keeping the attention receptive attention
in the body maybe in the lower abdomen
the sensations of the body
ever so slowly
elongating slowing down the in-breath and the out-breath
both this time okay and
count to five one breathing five
breathing out five one two three four five
breathing in front
breathing out five one two three
breathing again
now breathing in six
breathing out six one two three
breathing in six
breathing out six
breathing out six one two three four five
six breathing and six
thank you
this
letting the breath be a count of six but increasing the out breath to a count
of seven even slower out breath
four five six in breath one two three four
five six seven out of breath
now letting the counting should drop
but maintaining letting the slower rhythm of breathing in
and the slower rhythm of breathing out
stay no counting needed you know the rhythm now
trust it
close enough is good enough
letting the exhale be long and full letting go at the end of the exhale
relaxing softening
the body the mind
now with this expansive rhythm of the breath
received in the body
inviting someone who is dear to you
a child a pet a friend a benefactor inviting
their image their fat sense
and just breathing with them with their sense the image of this person who is
dear to you this being who's dear to you
them slowly with each in-breath and outbreath
unhurry you have plenty of time
to just sit with them
sharing a felt sense of good will kindness
good wishes pour them with every breath
every slow gentle [Music] expansive in expansive outbreath
it can be silent this sharing of good will good wishes
friendliness if you wish you can share
bless them with a simple phrase
of your good wishes may you be well
dear one
may you be well
[Music] dear
dear you can say the phrases out loud if you wish
or silently repeating them feel free to experiment
or any phrase of mention you wish
or phrases
remember the expansive in-breath and even more expansive breath
exhale
offering your good wishes friendliness as a gift
as well as you're slowed in breath and out breath as a gift to the gift of patience
to this dear being
now including yourself
in the wishes of mittal
may both of us be well
may both of us be
well
unhurried patient relaxed
let the body soften with age
exhale
oh turning your mental for yourself
may this being who's me be well
or may this being or may i be well may simply
may i be well
for any of the wishes of menta
feel appropriate for yourself in this moment
safety happiness health
ease
no rash to go anywhere spending sweet time with yourself
slow down breath
drenched in metal
branching your own heart slowly slowly with each breath
in good will and care
bury yourself
and for the last moments of practice
shining a good will slowly
patiently unto all beings
may all beings be well
may your things be well
making sure you are included in all beings
meta touching you first as it leaves your heart shining
onto the whole world
may all beings be well
may all beings be free
thank you all for your practice
so i feel a deep calm
slowness sense of well-being
that wasn't here when we started
so calm that i don't want to talk i wonder if that is similar for you
i see some of you still have your eyes closed
so i think there is genuinely something to
this to this these various research studies about
a slowed breath roughly six seconds for in-breath and out-breath as i
mentioned last time roughly the same length of time that takes
to chant some of the well-known buddhist chant with his
chants as well as christian ones it turns out
so we'd love to hear your reflections what you've noticed what's coming up for you you can type in
chat if it's to everyone else read your name as well as the reflection
if it's just to me i'll only read the reflection not your name
you're welcome to raise your hand too reports from the field
questions comments and bill says yes this was very calming
yeah thank you bill for sharing that reflection
and this is the sense of samadhi stillness calming the mind settling the mind
which can both which can arise both from the practice of meta alone
as well as on the panasonic mindfulness of the breath so we're really bringing these practices
together here and it's almost like supercharging the calming effect
this the sense of well-being and self-well beings like a sense of mehta through the sense of meta and the
sense of well-being that i feel more of there's more available when i have a sense of well-being
i have more mental more good will to share with others not just with myself but i have more
capacity to share with others
lish says may both of us who was both oops
they in the guided meditation maybe i wasn't clear enough when i
invited us to bring the beer being and then i invited for the self to join them so both the
dear being and herself i wasn't as clear as i could have been
thank you next time i'll be career clear
yeah and um and guergel says beautiful
practice lovely voice intonations of the phrases towards the end thank you and lengthening the breath was
super helpful thank you great thank you griegel thank you for your reflections
glad to hear it was helpful yeah one reflection coming in there was
sending well-being to dear ones who have died ah nice did that feel a person who would
send me that reflection you're welcome to send more reflection or raise your hand if you
like did that feel calming soothing um in this case because if
i'm trusting that that was the case um
it wasn't so much that grief was arising but that there was a sense of oh sending joy oh beautiful oh
yeah lovely thank you for sharing that beautiful reflection
sending joy to dear ones who have died lovely touches my heart
any other reflections you like to share especially if you haven't had the chance to speak or ask a question
in recent times we have a couple of minutes
how was this for you if you like to share more questions
did you notice more calmness
oh comment coming in the singing was like a lullaby invited me to hold the
heart so caringly oh that is sweet i am so glad
ah thanks for that reflection not so much a singer but i was trying
even if i had a tune [Laughter]
one more reflection this was a wonderful way to move into
the weekend i feel like i have some perspective when i was so contracted when we started thank you oh
beautiful thank you i'm so happy that reflection makes me so happy it gives me so much
joy and another reflection i love the singing [Laughter]
well thank you that's multiple votes for for my my singing in quotes the lullaby
maybe i'll do more of that in the future and not be afraid of the out of tune
it's sweet you're very kind all of you oh
ah so dear ones how about we sing little lullabies and
take time slow down slow down your breath slow down yourself
and enter practice space with small sangha
tonight with a lot of spaciousness maybe not too many words
get exchanged but maybe the breath is slow maybe it's it's um
yeah spacious so i'm gonna create the breakout room on mark says yes i was really tense
thank you more singing okay all right more votes for more
singing i might have to take voice lessons you guys alright
so here making the breakout rooms and let's start with 15 seconds of
silent meta and here we go
you
hello
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed and we have
a few minutes for reflections what you discovered you're slowed
down ah time with yourself and with sangha
anyone has the desire to share to speak the floor is open
and so is chat terence are you raising your hand
yes you are okay let's see here there
oh there it's letting me unmute now i just wanted to say that i appreciate the slowing down
i i like it very very much and it's like uh it's
pretty dependable i come here and i sit with these people with this group and i slow down and i
i'm better for it i'm a nicer person [Laughter]
i love that can we quote you
here is the tagline here is advertisement for haptier i come here it's dependable i sit with
this crew with these people i what did you say i mean i feel better i'm a better person
i i feel better i'm a nicer person a better person yeah i love that okay
i love it that's sweet thank you parents i'm i'm joking and and
partly but and yet so so appreciate i mean i'm joking about the the
advertisement aspect but just so appreciate the the the sense the felt sense of of the the
dependability of yes there is something about coming and practicing together here with sangha
um goodness arises one feels better more well-being and also one is
kinder nicer just of course the two go together um yeah so
absolutely just love that and what a lovely note to end on tonight thank you terence
for the reflection so let's
close our practice together
i'd like to thank you all for coming to the sangha creating co-creating the
sangha the space together for the benefit of yourself and all
beings whose lives yours touches may all beings
including this being who's us may all beings be well may all beings be free
thank you