continuing on this series of the seven
factors of awakening
the factor for today is joy
and joy is the particular joy that's a
factor of awakening
is really a product of doing the
practice
of mindfulness so it's not a
joy that comes from reflection and that
wonderful things are happening to us in
the world
it's really a joy that rises out of the
practice
doing the practice really engaging in
the practice in a kind of sincere
wholehearted way
and i'd like to think of this joy as
being also
a expression or enactment or
manifestation of our freedom
that grows as we do the practice of
mindfulness
and that these seven factors of
awakening all can be seen as
enactments of freedom
and rather than waiting for freedom to
occur in a big bang of enlightenment
down the road if we just huff and puff
and get concentrated enough and still
enough and then eventually
maybe by magic there'll be a big aha
moment or a
big transformation moment
and now you live happily free for the
rest of your life
you have it made in enlightened
retirement
it's much more i think valuable to
appreciate
that we're beginning to move
we're taking a seed a a little
of freedom the potential for freedom
inside of us
and germinating it caring for it
carefully in the greenhouse
tending to it carefully transplanting it
out into the world
and letting it grow and develop and
mature
into something into freedom full freedom
because then we're beginning to take a
little bit more responsibility for this
freedom thing
ourselves rather than thinking that you
know something else is going to do it
for me
and so these lit beginning to to
recognize
little movements of freedom that we all
use
all day long in fact i would
venture to guess that
most of us have more moments of freedom
through the day
than non-freedom
but the reason we don't feel like we're
free is that we prioritize
our our attention we let our attention
prioritize or focus on
the ways that we're unhappy or the ways
of what we want
what we don't want we get swept
up into the world of thinking where in
the thinking there's not much freedom
more often than not for people we're
kind of
hijacked by our thoughts our concerns
our fears our desires
and so it might seem that in the
important ways
psychological ways that we're not free
but there are plenty of ways that we are
free
when you if you sit down in a chair
you have a fair amount of freedom about
how you adjust yourself into that chair
and you probably never really gave me
much thought to how you sat in the chair
and how you adjust your
yourself to be comfortable
but that movement of sitting down and
choosing how you sit in the chair
is an expression is a manifestation of
some freedom
reaching forward to open your front door
is an expression of freedom that you can
do that there are people who can't do
that
for all kinds of reasons
there's lots of little moments of where
you choose to do something and there's a
freedom in doing it
as we start doing mindfulness practice
to begin
recognizing how mindfulness itself
can be an enactment of freedom
and that's hard to do if mindfulness is
burdened
by shoulds and shouldn'ts and gotta do
better and supposed to get somewhere and
am i there yet then
i'm not a good meditator and someone
else is a better meditator or
i'm supposed to bear down and really
strain and
what's important they say is continuity
of mindfulness so i'm really gonna when
i'm mindful i'm just
just gonna be mindful i'm gonna you know
really push
and make strong effort you know and
really strain
so all this extra stuff comes along with
mindfulness
a moment of mindfulness is something is
phenomenally simple
and if just just to know in the moment
what's happening
and in fact you have many of these
moments throughout the day
where you know something without the
burden of anything
more thing more complicated than knowing
that it's doing there
chances that you open that door
half the time at least when you open the
door you just know you something inside
of you no it's a door
no it's a door handle and it's not
anything more complicated than that
you know comparing your door handle to
your neighbor's door handle and who has
the better door handle and
i should have a better door handle it's
just a door handle
but the practice of mindfulness is also
the practice of appreciating
that simplicity of awareness in the
moment
and seeing can feel an enactment of
freedom
there's freedom in that knowing before
all the extra stuff is added on top of
it
and then the ch the freedom to choose
to investigate as soon as you choose to
investigate to look more carefully
to recognize more carefully what's here
you're not being swept off in your
thoughts you're not being swept off in
your
agendas desires wishes there is
it's a little movement i'm choosing not
to be
the old way i'm choosing to take a
better look
give a second look to what's happening
and that's enactment enactment of
freedom
effort being having to do with choices
choosing the
endeavor which is more healthy for us
as soon as we make a choice towards
health towards skillfulness to
wholesomeness
we're enacting our freedom
as i keep saying we don't recognize it
so much
because many of us carry with us this
huge huge huge backpack
everywhere we go of shoulds and
desires and agendas and self-concepts
and
self-criticism and aversion and all this
stuff that we carry along
and so we don't because of that heavy
backpack we don't recognize
the ease and simplicity and freedom in
these choices
to move in the healthy direction
so part of this practice is begin
recognizing
something that's probably there in to
some degree all along
the enactment of freedom the expression
of it
and that brings us to joy
the word joy is pity p-i-t-i
and it means usually translates joy
sometimes as ecstasy sometimes as
rapture
but that's a particular theravada slant
on this or a
meditation slant on this word pity it
could also mean
pleasure it can mean delight
enjoyment in sanskrit
the pretty the sanskrit word can also
mean
friendliness and pleasure and affection
which i think begins showing that it's a
it's an emotional quality
sometimes pure you know it's it's in the
we're tapping into an emotional
connection to the practice
and to being free and what's being
present that comes from a kind of an
emotional contentment
a contentment i'm doing a practice i'm
practicing a path of freedom
this is worthwhile this is a
healthy thing to be doing
and we're enacting the freedom which
feels so good
to feel like we're not
entangled trapped caught in things
because the awareness the mind has
become free
in the enactment of these freedoms and
so
the continuity of this free act of
mindfulness the continuity of
mindfulness
of concentration tends to give birth to
a variety of different kinds of
contentment joys happinesses
and there's different all kinds of
different types
but some of it is simply like it's like
if you go to
you slide down a long long slide there
is a joy of that freedom of just letting
go and going
and it's just a delight
so the same way if you can have the
continuity of these moments of freedom
continuity of choosing and engaging and
being mindful
and aware there's a feeling that oh
we'll start to getting a more taste for
that freedom
and it feels like not necessarily a
slide but the same kind of
the continuity gives birth to a joy and
delight and
boy am i lucky this is a great thing
it's not so evil it's not so much we
evaluate that
we you know it's not like we think ours
think our way into that
but there is a delight a joy a gladness
just in the in the freshness and the
you know it used to be in the united
states this did
there was a reference point to the joy
of driving on
an empty open freeway open highway
you know we don't think we be forgotten
what that is like
but this you know this joy this open
you know free free highway of meditation
of practice
and the amazing thing about this is that
then it doesn't matter as much
whether what's happening to us is
pleasant and unpleasant
because we discover how to be free and
be mindful aware
investigate make healthy choices this
inner freedom is discovered even when
things are unpleasant
even when things are in the world around
us are not so
good and what an amazing
thing to have discovered that because we
know how to be mindful
because we know how to investigate and
make choices and
appreciate that we're doing this there
can even be
joy and delight when conventionally when
the world expects us or
even our people and our people want us
to be miserable
you're supposed to be miserable when i'm
miserable so you're supposed to be
miserable
we're supposed to commiserate in her
commune in her
miserableness isn't it terrible things
are awful
so what happens as we start moving
through these factors of awakening and
when i say what i'm about to say you
might decide to get off the
factor's awakening path because what
happens is when you get far enough along
it
you won't be inclined to complain
anymore
because you have something much much
better to do
much more wonderful to do the enactment
of your freedom through mindfulness
investigation
effort endeavoring and
and this wonderful joy of freedom
may you find that complain free zone of
freedom
and delight in it
thank you