good evening welcome welcome and even if it's not
evening when you're listening to this sometime in the future or
maybe you're on a different place on the planet where it's no longer evening a warm welcome
so we'll start with a little bit of a guided meditation
and just settling in
feeling what it feels like at this moment
feeling the pressure of the chair or cushion against the body
feeling with the hands or resting on
and feeling connected grounded we are here
at this moment
paying a little attention to the posture
a posture that has both some uprightness if not literally then
figuratively has a brightness with some dignity
but also some ease
also some relaxation
sometimes it can be helpful to just notice the chin sometimes we
raise them up a little bit or we find ourselves going down but to have it to be level with the shoulder
and to just tuck it just a tiny tiny bit
to open up a little space in the back of the neck
the placement of the chin and therefore the head
can really have a big impact on our
posture
perhaps taking a few full breaths
and just connecting to the sensations of
breathing
feeling the breath in the chest
and the abdomen or in the nose
and just allowing the attention to rest there on the
sensations of breathing
and what is it like to tune into the out breath to feel the out
breath from the beginning to the end
and what about the in-breath
all the phases of the in-breath
without straining more just opening up to
these experiences
and we can notice the transitions between the in-breaths and out-breaths
and it might be that at the end of the exhale
there's a little bit of a letting go a little bit of
a moment just a moment very subtle
moment of ease letting go of the exhale
and then the inhale naturally begins
it can be helpful to tune into that very slight
sense of letting go that's just naturally there at the end
of the exhale
there might be some other moments of letting go
letting go of thoughts
allowing the mind to come back to the sensations of breathing
there can be a time when the thought train
just runs out of steam and there's just a subtle moment there
a little bit of letting go and returning to mindfulness
it might be
but the mind this caught up in desire wanting
something fantasies of something you're going to
purchase or
sexual fantasies or thinking about what food you want to eat
you can be really supportive as best you can
on occasion to just hang out
with these desires
maintaining balance maintaining mindfulness as best you can
maybe making the note desire
maybe feeling the desire in the body
allowing it to be there
in a relaxed easy manner
for just noticing
this desire and sooner or later
it will subside
it's impermanent like everything else
and then as best we can to watch when the desire ends
not always easy and importantly to notice
what does it feel like after it has ended
when there's a certain letting go of that desire
feeling the absence of that desire the increased freedom of the mind not
being bound up in that
it's not our habit to notice the absence
but it can be really helpful oh yes it feels like this now
now that that desire has subsided
and feel the ease the freedom this spaciousness it might be subtle
there are lots of ways in which there's some letting go
that naturally happens with our meditation practice
i can support our practice to recognize
how does it feel after there's a letting go
before the next clinging
there are so many things we can let go of
this path of practice is not about acquiring getting more and more and more
it's really about letting go letting go
and discovering the freedom the peace the ease the openness spaciousness that
becomes available when letting go happens
and this spaciousness and openness can support our practice support our
lives and also helps to make room
so that we can see others really see them and meet them how they are
support them in a way that's appropriate for us
and in this way our practice is a support not only for us
but for those around us
so may our practice together be for the benefit of all beings
everywhere without exception
[Music]
good evening and welcome welcome welcome a really warm welcome
i'm happy to be practicing with you all even though we're not all together in
the same room just to know that there's other people
practicing i don't know it's heartfelt or meaningful in some kind of way
so tonight i'd like to talk about the notion the practice the teachings of
letting go and in some way we could say that all
the teachings and all the practices come down to this idea of letting go
in fact we might understand that nibbana is a really radical type of letting go
a very thorough letting go letting go just completely letting go so
thoroughly that there's not even anyone to let go of anything
just this complete letting go
and it's quite something that maybe to think that it could be summarized and so simply and yet
how many sutas are there how many dharma talks have there been how many times have we meditated
so somehow this um letting go is not so easy or
maybe it's simple the idea is simple but maybe not so easy
and part of it is to have the confidence and to have the trust that this is the
direction to go it's not to be grabbing on for more and more things or
not to be clinging tighter but to be softening and loosening
whatever it is we find ourselves holding to whether that's ideas or
people experiences wishes
and so this confidence this trust on why to let go or how to let go or
even to ask one question does one even do the letting go or does letting go
just arise just happen
and it can take years of practice to unlearn a lifetime of clinging and
acquiring of course it does when
certainly our society certainly promotes acquisition so kind of a renunciation or letting go
is the opposite movement of what we've probably been doing for most
of our lives and what other people around us are doing
and it takes years of practice to appreciate that more freedom and ease
arise with this letting go on the guided meditation i did before
this dharma talk i pointed to some they might be very subtle but some letting go
that just naturally happens with meditation practice
letting go of thought trains that happen and then we come back to the breath and
just to notice that slight moment maybe it's a split second
when that letting go happens and there's a little bit more ease and freedom
the letting go that happens at the end of the exhale just a natural physiological letting go
or we can hang out with a strong emotion and if we can stay steady and with a
certain degree of mindfulness we can notice that even that too there's a certain letting go
it subsides
and certainly not only in our meditation practice but we can notice letting go in our daily life
and we might even say that learning to let go skillfully is part of having a happy life
but we regularly let go of plans that go with preferences maybe let go of opinions when we get new
information when it just doesn't make sense anymore to be holding on
to the picnic outside when it starts to rain
it doesn't make sense to have one particular view when you get more information you
realize oh i didn't realize that i guess what i was thinking isn't quite right
i'm gonna adjust my thinking now
and if maybe i'll say also thinking about daily life that there
might be competing priorities that cause us to let go of you know we
want to do this but then when we realize it conflicts or gets in the way of
something that's more important to us and of course we just naturally let go of what is less
important through us and the same way letting go is part of
buddhist practice part of our spiritual practice this letting go of this
it's kind of this underlying compulsion that we have to want to hold on to
things and to go get things
but it's not only the things the objects or the views or ideas that we might have
but it's the clinging to them of course we need to hold on to things
literally to carry them but of course we have views opinions ideas
of course we have preferences but the practice here is not to cling to
them not to be strangling them and not to be holding on to them
so tightly that that the clinging is painful which again might be really
subtle but kind of like inhibits our life shrinks our life makes things smaller
and letting go of this idea that if i just have this one more
object this one more experience if i just leave this thing hard enough then that
will be a source of lasting happiness sometimes we're clinging to this ideas this has to make me happy
so can we let go of that type of clinging
as well as letting go of a strong sense of self so
not only like these outdated or no longer accurate ideas that we
might have about ourselves certainly we can let go of those and that often happens naturally
but also the idea that there's a a me at the center of it all me
right here i'm here and everything else is over there
me and you something like this
can there be a letting go of that strong sense of me in the center often this doesn't make sense to people
until they have some experience of it but we can point to it if we point to those ideas of flow
you've heard about this where when we're doing something enjoyable
and we kind of just get lost in what we're doing and there's the sense of me isn't really
prevalent there this could be with gardening finding ourselves with the plants singing
dancing sports our favorite hobbies often there are they are
our favorite hobbies because we can see the sense of self often
is often while we're crocheting or whatever it might be
i appreciate very much um what i've seen gil do about this idea of letting go of
clinging or just letting go in general and he often uh does this demonstration
with this striker and it talks about this can be a letting
go which then we're really holding on very tightly to this and there can be a letting go that's
like this so that we no longer have it let's just let go and the striker is no
longer there and that might be appropriate if what we're holding on to
is unwholesome and unhelpful
but often if we're really holding on to something we can't just simply let go especially if it's
unhelpful we might know it's unhelpful but we can't stop the clinging
so something that i appreciate very much that gill has shown is to let go this way
just to soften the clinging the striker is still here in my hand
i've just unclenched my fist around it so is there a way in which we can have
this movement of opening maybe we can just open a little bit maybe we open
a lot so this idea of clinging and letting go
letting go of clinging so it's not so much the actual objects because
or objects or views because some of them are really worth having in our life and are
appropriate to have so you might say okay well
sure klingon seems like it should be a good idea but how does one do this
how does one let go either by unclenching the fist this way but still holding the object or
letting go in a way which the object completely goes away
well one way is to notice the feeling
the experience or maybe even imagine what will be gained with the letting go
that is let go into something that feels more open more
spacious a little more ease something that's more satisfying and
pleasant and for those of you who are familiar with concentration practices
to get deeper and deeper with concentration in fact to even get concentrated at the beginning
is all about letting go whether we think about that explicitly or not
but uh concentration is described as like a shedding first of the hindrances
and then of different factors that arise the kind of like let go let go
so just to recognize that when you find yourself that there's a certain amount of settledness
you might just do a little bit of reflection oh yeah this feels a little more spacious or open
than the unsettled mind that was perhaps a few moments before or at the beginning
of the meditation session so to recognize that this movement of
letting go is associated with settledness ease pleasantness
i'm using this word openness spaciousness but it's usually um a pleasant a comfortable
feeling
and here's a poem from rosemary trummer so kind of about this about this idea of
letting go and letting go into and rosemary trauma she wrote this in
on december 9th 2020 still in the midst of the pandemic
and the title is a little pep talk i love this a little pep talk
and this poem goes like this the swirling ash doesn't try to become
log again the flying leaves don't attempt to
return to the tree the girl can't untwist her genome back
into separate strands the flower in the bed the flower in the
bread can't return to the sack can't undo the kneading of hands
in all things lives a memory of letting go and the chance to transform into what it
can't know what do you say to that heart good self
what do you say to that
so rosemary trauma and in my mind she's uh giving herself a little pep talk
reminding herself yeah you know good things happen nice cozy
fires bread the leaves just fall from the tree it's
natural senescence is a natural thing that happens it's you know part of the lifespan of trees
maybe it's pleasant to walk around in crunchy leaves
but just this recognition that letting go is natural and it's part of what happens
but it helps create the conditions for something else to arise and maybe we already know
what this something else is that arises something pleasant and open
so that's one way to support letting go is to let go into
maybe it's letting go of some of the hindrances letting go of insisting that our meditation go a particular way
and instead being able to just acknowledge and
appreciate how it is going
then the second way the buddha talks about a lot
is this idea of noticing the gratification the drawbacks and the escape
the gratification drawbacks and escape and the buddha talks about this in lots
of different contexts and i appreciate very much that it starts with gratification
so what is meant here is to start with acknowledging that our experience in the
world provides some degree of gratification and enjoyment there are pleasant
experiences to be had and to notice them
and and maybe to also to notice the pleasure or the happiness that
arises when our desires are fulfilled when we get to that thing that we
believe we want when we get it at that moment there can be a certain ah i don't know
maybe certain like i got it i achieved it whether that's just the satisfaction
comes out of the ending of the desire or the beginning of having that's
another dharma talk but just to notice that we there is a
there can be a pleasant sensation that's associated with achieving acquiring getting something
and holding on and whether that's just an experience or an object or an idea
but then when we look more closely and often this is what meditation practice can help us do
it can help um fine-tune the mind so we can look more closely when we look
more closely we notice that there is a little bit of a dark underbelly
of these pleasant experiences
i remember one time being on vacation and it's a wonderful place just really
enjoying it and my traveling partner kept on talking about oh next i want to
go here and next i want to have that and oh my gosh i can't believe we have to leave on this
date and so they were like kind of tuned in to like this fear that it's going to end
and what are we going to do next and i don't want it to end and maybe this other place will be
just as okay
so there's often this dark underbelly the unpleasant experiences there's this
little niggling oh i hope this doesn't end how can i
keep this can i turn up the volume on this just a little bit
i want more so often even with these pleasant
experiences there's a little bit of agitation associated with them
and this is what the buddha's talking about the drawbacks there's often some agitation because
we know that things are impermanent we know that it's not going to last forever
and we wish it were we wish it would last forever
and not only are things impermanent but they are they have this liability for
suffering this kind of the agitation of not wanting it to end and i have to find the next thing that's
going to be just as pleasant or how can i make sure that this doesn't go away
and this might be subtle but that doesn't mean that it's insignificant
this little bit of unease that happens when we're associated with
things and so that that the buddha often emphasized the drawbacks
in many experiences and he talked a lot about the drawbacks in
sensual pleasures not because that they're sinful
or something like that but just because he noticed that as humans we so much are just
can spend our lives chasing one sensual pleasure after another and not really paying attention
trying to deny that there are any drawbacks even though there's a part of us that knows that there
are so trying to have this sense that um
trying to ignore maybe that part of our experience so that the buddha was pointing there is
suffering and an encouragement not to indulge in
sensual pleasures and so when we see this in some
deep radical way when we see that ideas
people objects experiences can't be sources of lasting happiness
they just can't they're changing they're inconstant they end they
create the conditions in which we have this agitation where we're trying to want more or chase after them in some
kind of way but when there's a real a real deep understanding oh this
this can't be a source of lasting happiness perhaps there's a part i wish it were
but this deep understanding that it can't then letting go
naturally happens it just doesn't make sense anymore to be
holding on so there's a way in which some deep
insights maybe more than just an intellectual understanding but more an experiential
understanding maybe like deep inside to see that the agitation the suffering
that's associated with clinging to recognize that things are inconstant and
they end then letting go naturally happens
and that is the escape but the buddha talked about the gratification drawbacks and escape
that's the the release from the drawbacks the ending of them
when we see that our craving for pleasure in some way kind of like binds us to what is inherently
flawed maybe not perfect it won't be perfectly satisfying
then we just stop maybe i shouldn't say we just stop i should say maybe just clinging stops
so the buddha talked about this in his own practice
and maybe in some ways this gratification drawbacks sometimes also translated as
danger and escape these three elements in some ways we might say this is a
foundation onto the whole buddhist practice and the buddha describes in his own
practice this is a quote from asuta he says mendicants
talking to his followers before my awakening when i was still unawakened but intent
on awakening i thought what is the gratification in the world
what is the drawback and what is the escape
then it occurred to me the pleasure and happiness that arise from the world
this is the gratification that the world is impermanent suffering and perishable
that is its drawback and removing and giving up desire and greed
for the world this is its escape and as long as i didn't truly understand
the world's gratification drawback and escape in this way for what they are i didn't
announce my supreme perfect awakening but when i did truly understand the
world's gratification drawback and escape in this way i announced my supreme perfect awakening
in this world so his realization was a part of his
awakening that kind of allowed this uh radical letting go that's nibana this really radical
complete completely thorough letting go that is nibana
so this grad noticing the gratification drawback and escape is another way that can support the letting
go and it might be that with some
more obvious or [Music] less dearly held
experiences objects people things we can let go we can say you know
what this just doesn't make any sense anymore i'm going to let go and it might be that with some of the
more subtle ones it's with insight into impermanence
suffering not self that letting go naturally happens
so maybe in some way we can also as a support for letting go
or we can consider it as a giving up and up as in like we give
up and we put up onto the altar i kind of like this idea like we make an
offering like as an act of generosity to let go might be to give up
as to recognize that i'm going to offer this
to something bigger something other than me
makes it more kind of a sacred act if you will in a type of movement of
the heart and to be sure this letting go and
giving up should be done in the service of what is wholesome and
virtuous you know or and in service of beneficial states of mind
there's absolutely no obligation to do this it's just part of the path of finding
more and more ease and more and more freedom in our lives
so to let go if we feel like we're kicking and screaming and kind of you know um
really protesting wanting to letting go maybe maybe it's not quite right to let go of
that maybe there's something more to understand about why we're letting go and
what is it that we believe is the support that we're getting from whatever it is we might be holding on to
so that letting go is the service of creating a inner wealth this
inner treasure if you will of this spaciousness and ease
and so that we're able to let go of the unwholesome and make the which helps makes room and
brings in the wholesome so in this way we might understand that
letting go is an integral part of the practice and there's a number of movements
that we can do to support letting go and maybe some of those are intentional
and some of them are creating the conditions in which insights can arise and then letting go just arises
but whatever degree of letting go we do and whatever manner we do it
can it be for the benefit of ourselves and for those around us if we're no
longer clinging so tightly to things can there make space
for other people make space for our ability to be able to
hear them and see them and to be available for them and to be available for ourselves
so that letting go may be for the benefit of
ourselves others and all beings everywhere thank you