so hello everyone and
it's a special occasion whenever people
gather together to meditate and thank you for being part of this gathering and
and kind of a collective focus on meditation for these next 30 minutes
and
i would like to uh suggest that you imagine something for this next
meditation or perhaps if imagining isn't quite right for you that you assume
or perhaps if this is something you already know that you remember
and that is that your ability
to know things in a simple way to be aware
to be conscious of what's happening in its simplest possible ways before
interpretations and stories reactions just the simplest awareness
is able to be aware it has enough space is big enough
to be aware of things as
as part of being aware part of the field of consciousness
as opposed to the tendency for consciousness knowing awareness to be limited by what it knows
that we kind of lean into the thing that we're focusing on whether it's thoughts
ideas feelings things in the world that we see that some the consciousness gets
narrowed down contracted and almost as if it be lives inside of
whatever it's focusing on and it's limited by it is trapped by it caught by it
attached to it uh preoccupied with it and that um and so then awareness
becomes as small as what it knows
but in fact awareness it can be feel like much more spacious it has lots
of room or if you don't like the metaphor of space and size
then the awareness can always remain free of what is known
it doesn't have to lean into it it doesn't have to be defined by it we
don't have to be caught in what we know what we know can just be part of
consciousness part of what we know but it doesn't become everything
and that's closely related to the idea of identity because
part of what can create the sense of identity is when consciousness awareness knowing kind of
leans into holds on to narrows itself into a particular ideas
even if they're accurate ideas we inhabit those ideas
rather than ideas and thoughts and who are experiences and habits awareness
so the suggestion for this meditation is that whether it's
using a single word that kind of precedes every act of knowing
every act of being aware and that's the word with w-i-t-h
and uh and when you're saying this to yourself you're saying that
you're aware with the inhale you're aware with the exhale
you are aware with a thought you're aware with an emotion
you're aware with a desire you're aware with
some aversion or frustration you're aware with anxiety
and the word with is suggesting to the the mind the heart
that whatever you're aware of does not define you does not define consciousness or
awareness does not is not doesn't have to limit your freedom
and so the word with is meant to kind of open you up a bit or loosen you up or
it just it's just a part the word with implies well this is just part of the
big picture it's not it the mind doesn't have to make it the
thing that we're caught in for right now it's just part of awareness just part of this world
it's consciousness with these and see if the word just adding the word
with it doesn't uh if it creates maybe space in the mind
stillness in the mind openness in the mind spaciousness a little bit of freedom less
or it could be simply less locking into things getting glued to things
there's so much more here always than what awareness gets locked into
and by simply saying with maybe kind of opens the opens it up a little bit and unlocks
then the knowing and also keeps things very simple returning to a simplicity of knowing
just this just this without being defined by it leaning into it or even pulling away
from it which is also kind of over involvement in terms of awareness
in terms of getting collapsing into something so i hope what i say makes sense
so to start
giving some care to the posture for your meditation
finding a posture that works for you but also works for you to help you feel
a little more alert awake present
a posture that way you too comfortable and you kind of sink into
kind of too much relaxation it might be nice in the short term
but not in the long term
and relaxing your eyes relaxing your gaze
and perhaps closing your eyes
feeling the contact of your body and its weight against whatever surface it's resting against
and as you take a few long deep breaths maybe there's a subtle way in which the
pressure against that surface increases with the deeper breaths
and if it does imagine you're becoming rooted
to the present moment here and now
and letting your breathing return to normal
and spend a few moments here on the exhale relaxing
any place in your body where you feel tense tight muscles are
the muscles can relax and soften
and then becoming aware of your breathing
and for a few rounds of breath you might even say the word with
as shorthand for being aware with
the inhale being aware with the exhale
being aware
and being aware intimately
intimate awareness of breathing in and breathing out but it's not the full picture it's not
the totality of awareness awareness holds
doesn't lean into or limit itself with it
and similarly if there are thoughts that arise in the sitting or feelings emotions sounds
see if the word with can help you
have the experience of that the awareness is able to hold
contain whatever is happening because awareness is bigger or
more peaceful or less identified just awareness with
thoughts awareness with feeling one breath at a time
here now
whatever you're aware of recognize it that awareness
is aware with it so that your knowing doesn't become it
you don't become it it's just a piece of the bigger picture
whatever you're thinking or concerned with it's just one aspect of
life with it
and as we come to the end of the sitting
if you can appreciate your capacity to be aware
with things with experience
perhaps you can feel or know that knowing awareness being conscious
can hold things without being caught in them there's lots of room to know
without leaning into it or without reacting to things
without being defined by them in any way or
without implying anything about oneself it's just known
there's lots of space just to know and perhaps at the end of the
sitting you can imagine or allow
your awareness to become so large so open
that you can receive the suffering of the world
in whatever way whatever particular way that that comes to mind comes to heart
and to recognize that now you're aware with this suffering
you don't become the suffering you don't lean into it or be defined by
the suffering but maybe you can make your heart as wide as the world
and part of the wonderful benefit of
not clinging to anything not holding on to anything not resisting anything
is that we can become the witnesses we can become the eyes of the world witnesses to what's happening
so important to have people know the suffering of the world
aware with suffering with awareness as wide as the world
even bigger can hold it
and then from the heart maybe there can come the wish
to live for the welfare and happiness of this world
and that if all who suffer may their suffering end
all who suffer may they be safe and peaceful
that all who suffer may they know that there is compassion and care
that they're not alone in their suffering
and may it be that they are all they suffer become happy
and free
and may we each of us in our own way contribute to that
[Music]
thank you
so this will be the second talk on the third foundation of mindfulness and the third foundation of
mindfulness is that of becoming aware of
the general state of our mind or state of our heart the mood or disposition
that's in some ways more enduring than particular sensations we have in
the body that come and go or particular thoughts that we have that come and go
or particular sensations that come and go feeling tones pleasant and unpleasant
that come and go and certainly mind states also can come and go but they tend to be more enduring
tends to be a disposition through which we sometimes see the world experience the
world interpret the world and um and there's this the disposition the
state the quality of the mind that through which we're aware is um
has a huge bearing on how we live our lives huge influence
and it's also something that's intimate and closer in than the
changing details of the moment that might be here fleetingly
and uh it's more kind of close in to who we are in a sense
and um and so the general instructions around this mindfulness of the cheetah mind
state is in regard to it simply to know it as it is
to know the mind state in regard to the mind state
and what this means is that we don't have to add stories and ideas interpretations
we don't connect it to a lot of things just know it in the simplicity how it is in the moment right now
and then it begins by knowing mind states dispositions that are
characterized by greed or the absence of it
with ill will or the absence of it and delusion and the absence of it
and um in august if you know a month ago or so a few weeks ago we did
three weeks on each of these greed hatred and delusion and in part that was in preparation for
this teaching on this third foundation of mindfulness so those of you who are there perhaps
you now you know you're more sensitized they're ready to be mindful of greed hatred and delusion and the absence of
it and and so the idea is to become aware of it but not as a fleeting moment of greed or
fleeting moment you know of a moment a few moments of it but how it can appear sometimes as a
disposition as a general state or mood that we're in um we're just kind of the mood is that
of desire the mood is that of ill will or aversion
the mood is that of just being confused bewildered deluded
and so it's a little more more um persistent and more more
like more like you know the mood the veil through which we see
the filters through which we see the world and but what's very interesting and the
buddha says when he gives instructions here he says something he uses the word with
in paulie it's not a word it's a prefix but he says that uses this with he says
when the mind state is with greed
know that it is with greed when the mind state is without greed know that is without greed and the
same for ill will and delusion and so this word with is there
and and now the idea is to be mindful to know that it's there and the
the marvelous thing about when we're really clearly practicing mindfulness to be
really mindful really know what's happening really conscious of what's happening part of the mind is not
caught in what is known part of the mind is not defined by what is known
now if we get distract if we get preoccupied by our thoughts our fantasies that go on in the mind our concerns
we can be so involved in it that it become kind of becomes who we are there's no outside of it everything's
seen through that lens everything is related to it that becomes the be-all and end-all occasionally
so sometimes when there's desire desire takes over and we become the desire and you know
get out of the way sometimes occasionally
the um uh occasionally when uh i can get famished
and uh i come home and my wife says you had look in your eyes and i'm kind of looking around the kitchen for
for food maybe i'm like hunting or something and and it becomes kind of like the my disposition is like wanting
and so some people are saying it's frozen with no sound
but other people are not so i'll just continue so um
the um so the buddha uses this idea of width
and as i did in this guided meditation uh it's possible to be aware to know
uh when what we know doesn't make up the whole experience of what's happening it's only part of it
and because of that it's like we become make room for it we can allow it to be there because
we're not defined by it and we're not collapsed into not leaning into it
the knowing is free of what is known the knowing has space to feel and
experience what is knowing and um and this idea i kind of very much like the idea of space for things
we have a capacity to hold things we have a capacity to allow and to know
and part of what we're doing in mindfulness practice is increasing that capacity to know things
not not knowing you know not knowledge of things but rather the capacity to be present
for our experience be conscious of it without reactivity without
becoming it without resisting it without being defined by it
without making entering into it and becoming it and so we have capacity so we can really
hold in a feel and practice really becomes different if we
have things like desires greeds hatreds delusions fears
and we've learned how to open up how to relax how to make space
to know it in and of itself in relationship to our desires
greeds we simply know it's greed without a story without justification
without putting a value on it even without kind of saying well i'm a bad person now because of i have it this is
wrong it's embarrassing i should i should i should feel shame or or getting involved in justification i'm
supposed to have desire this is important this is time my life that desire it's just just desire just greed just
lust whatever it might be anger hostility
irritation frustration all the different flavors of kind of hostility or ill will that might be
there it's just known in its simplicity
and this is not necessarily easy to do but this is the direction the practice is going
the third foundation of mindfulness is the third foundation one
very wonderful way of practicing these is to build towards this
so the the the teachings and the four foundations of mindfulness begins with mindfulness
of breathing with anapanasati the first tetrad breathing in breathing out
breathing experiencing the whole body breathing and relaxing the body it be
such a great place to begin and to get settled to get stable to
relax to and then it continues with mindfulness of the body continues with mindfulness of feeling
tones how we react and respond to pleasure and and the pain and learning how to be with
that in a simple way and not be so reactive and as we learn the skills and the
stability and the steadiness and the and the clarity of knowing
then at some point we can become aware of great hatred and delusion that the mind
is with it not the mind is it and as i've said i think the
um if there's clear mindfulness there's more to the mind there's more to
the mind state than greed hatred and delusion uh we've we've created space we've
created a healthy kind of sense of distance or independence
from whatever it is we know and so this is something you can experiment with
next time you have a really good bout of greed hatred and delusion
just stand still or sit down and and see
if you could come back into mindfulness of it where there's space for it and room for you to be this way you're not trying to
stop it necessarily but you're not participating in it mindfulness is not participating it
not reacting to it and just you know it oh here's greed with
here's a mind state with greed and here is mindfulness
that is independent from it is free of it and it might take some experimentation
to see what is it like to have a knowing have an awareness be conscious of something where that consciousness
is not caught by it reactive to it and the same thing for the absence of
greed hate and delusion and here it gets a little bit more interesting because
the absence of greed is not quite the same thing as the
presence of greed if the absence of greed is generosity if the absence of
a hatred is love the absence of delusion is wisdom then yes
that can be without that can be a mind with generosity with
love with wisdom so and the same freedom can be there the same spaciousness the openness can be
discovered and however if the absence of greed is
simply the absence of greed if the absence of hatred is simply the absence of hatred
the absence delusion is simply the absence of delusion then um
then that absence kind of overlaps or
shades into or merges with the state of mind
the quality of awareness that's open and receptive and there
and and so to experience the goodness of the absence of great hate and delusion to
experience the spaciousness the freedom that's there kind of uh
allows us to kind of more and more develop or grow in this capacity
for the mind to hold experience including the ability to hold the suffering of the world
and i'd like to think this is one of the directions one of the tremendous potentials of this practice of
mindfulness is that is that it doesn't
keep us aloof or distant or unaware of the suffering of the world it actually
increases our capacity to experience it without having it weigh us down
so this is the beginning and now talking
about these instructions for mindfulness of the mind states and i'll continue tomorrow i'll continue for the
rest of the week and it develops and grows through here and and as it grows
we enter into kind of more wonderful qualities or states of mind
that are available when we the mind is no longer identified or caught in what
is known so thank you