so so hello and welcome everyone [Music]
so happy to be with you to see you and to practice together in this day
observing independence in the u.s
and the topic of independence
can have many different connotations many different connotations of course in
this context celebrated here as independents um having um autonomy
being able to have autonomy to make one's own choices etc so so one way we can
in the dharma in the practice in our practice [Music]
the theme of independence can show up in many ways one is to have independence to have autonomy through
practice from what's called the three poisonous roots from greed hatred and
confusion so that we have autonomy from them we're not um bound by them
something arises some thought arises in the mind all of a sudden greed arises we need to have it we want to have it or we
hate it make it go away so as if we're in bondage as if we are in bondage we don't have control
we don't when we don't have autonomy that's the word i want to use we don't have autonomy it seems like we
are on a leash like greed and hatred and delusion so that's one way i like to think of
independence in the dharma independent in the dharma and there's other senses of independence
in the dharma when one actually practices for a while the practice becomes the
path the path become life becomes um practice
practice becomes life interchangeably and there's a sense of trust there's a sense of trust in the
practice that arises there's a sense of autonomy that arises actually
one has this complete faith and trust that no these practices
actually work i'm freer i have more freedom again freedom in this sense in the sense of dharmic senses and
freedom to go and wreak havoc and do whatever but it's freedom from again
these um these bondages greed hatred delusion
these um bondages in the mind and heart that come
up and we are reactive we we act reactively so so there's a lot of and and also to
say kim allen who's one of the teachers at imc gave a lovely talk about
other nuances of independence in the dharma independent in the dharma on sunday yesterday and so
that's an audio dharma for any of you would like to listen to that
but for tonight for so having acknowledged this idea of independence in the dharma it depends on great hatred
and delusion one way one way of practicing which is what we cultivate here
and happy hour are the practices of the heart which support which are liberating
practices which they attenuate greed hatred and delusion they also attenuate
especially hatred self-hatred hatred of others self-judgement type
judgment criticism all these bondages of the mind all these habitual patterns
um that can become a lot bring up a lot of sadness bring up a lot of
depression bring up anxiety bring up a sense that you're imprisoned you're imprisoned in your own mind you're
imprisoned in your own life because of these prisons that we create
in your in our own hearts and mind habitually
and sometimes we can step out and look at our way of thinking and go huh that wasn't very helpful what was i
thinking you can ah the sense of freedom sense of freedom when you step out of yourself
when you step out of some habitual ways of thinking that may not be supportive may not be helpful
so so with that another thing i want to bring in in our
practice which we'll start in just a few seconds is the theme of interdependence
independence always brings up a sense of interdependence the more we become
independent in the dharma the more we
feel the more we become fully aware of our
interdependence with other beings our interdependence with others
people we love people we don't like we see our independence interdependence
with all beings so independence in the dharma brings up the sense of interdependence
with all beings everywhere i am because you are you are because i am
our happiness our goodness our freedom is dependent on each other which
is also similar to the concept of ubuntu
in south african culture open to i am because you are so all right i've
said plenty so that's setting that is the setting for our practice tonight
and i'll weave some of these themes together and allow silence
silent space stretches for us to explore so without further ado dear ones
let's let's get into our practice together
ah landing landing
landing into our body
landing with a sense of
recognition of this moment the recognition of this body
turning our gaze inward
allowing the breath the entirety of the in-breath
especially the entirety of the out breath making space for the next in-breath
to be soothing calming to connect
to arrive and land in this body
with age and breath and abra on their own breathing
being breathed
noticing that your mind can have malleability in this moment
as you invite it invited to connect with the breath
being calm besettled soothed
to have a sense of independence
even if we're a moment from habitual thoughts patterns of mind
sense of freedom freed for a moment
ah releasing letting go
as if thoughts are the fireworks of the mind letting them go ah burst
and in between there's stillness silence
hmm freedom
independence from habitual patterns of the mind
even for just a moment
and then tying these little moments
together
letting go ah releasing releasing
not that there is anything wrong with thinking but in this moment
giving our heart giving ourselves completely to this practice
steadily inquiring the mind receiving
each breath celebrating independence
from habitual thoughts putting them down with respect
with kindness claiming our autonomy our independence
in this moment
noticing the freedom that arises
when you notice thoughts or habitual patterns
and kindly gently smilingly let go
ah the peace the ease
the freedom that shows up in the body the heart and mind
observing it's sitting or lying being where you are
in this moment
noticing that it's dependent dependent on gravity
[Music]
noticing the contact points between your bottom and the cushion your
feet and the floor your lower legs as you're sitting on the
floor contact contacting the earth
and how this body is dependent on the air
that we're all breathing in this moment
interdependence appreciation gratitude for this gift
of the air life-giving breath
the parts of the body are so many processes in this body
so many processes that work
even if there may not be full health at this moment or some pain but so many processes
work interdependently
with one another
appreciating appreciating
all the interdependence the processes of this body
they depend on each other hearts and lungs that the lungs bringing
oxygen the heart pumping blood etc etc so many systems
interdependently working
and this body interdependent on the food on the air
and the food we eat this body eats sustain itself
the earth the land the sun the water
that helps produce the food
the farmers
the drivers
the shippers all the infrastructure
the store
in a town the country
in the world
and all the people
to have something to do a part to play
the food that sustains us every bit touching every piece
of what supports us the clothes we wear
the technology we're using to connect right now to practice together
and all the people all the beings
we have dependent we have depended on
all the people who have nurtured us cared for us who've challenged us pushed our buttons
so we grow we've come to this world a helpless
baby helpless no born
so much interdependence so much to be grateful for that has
sustained us that we have contributed to we continue
to people whose lives we touch directly
or indirectly
gratitude aw sense of awe stepping outside of ourselves for a
moment as if we're looking at this planet
this universe with all these beings interconnected all these systems
interconnected sense of awe
amazing stepping out of ourselves this being
that is us deeply connected not an
island deeply deeply connected
even if we feel disconnected
uh
as a physicist once said in order to make apple pie
you need to create the whole universe first
allowing sense of gratitude appreciation arise from a sense of
[Applause] awe
and all in appreciation turned around
and radiated through the whole world with good will
wishes of well-being for all beings this interconnected web of life
all the critters
including ourselves
may all beings be well
may all beings be well including this being and as myself
in this in dirt interdependent web of
life
you're welcome to do meta with phrases if you wish or just radiating good will
and friendliness all around touching yourself first
wishing well for all the beings all these interdependent ecosystems
all the plankton and the sea [Music]
serves as food sustenance
for other organism all the fish
all the little critters that crawl and hop and slither
all the mammals
all four-legged creatures all
two-legged creatures
all creatures that fly
you can choose particular creatures if you wish
to wish well for
may you be safe happy healthy and have ease
your interdependence with your family of origin
your interdependence with so many chosen families
communities sanghas
may all be well
for the last moment of this practice let's step out of outside of ourselves
for a moment again as if we're looking at ourselves
our life is at our interconnection interdependence
we're not an island letting that interdependence fill our
heart with all appreciation
for all the ways we receive and all the ways we give
acknowledging the giving too
the way this person you're watching was yourself is a good friend to someone
perhaps a sibling of someone
a colleague of someone so many other functions
bowing to the inner goodness of this sharing giving and receiving
and stepping back into yourself may all beings everywhere may all beings
everywhere be well may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so explored a couple of themes today well thoughts and themes but in
the guided meditation we started with the theme of independence independence
independence freedom from habitual tendencies of thoughts
reactivities putting them down releasing them ah landing in the sense of freedom
independence from those thoughts habitual patterns
even for a split second feeling that sense of freedom and peace
and then we turned to feeling interdependence the interdependence of this body
on gravity and breath all the interdependence says inside this body all these
intricate processes and the interdependence of this being on
so many processes externally so many beings inter externally
and from that place of awe
allowing meta loving-kindness good will to shine for all these beings who are
just like us they want to be well acknowledging our interdependence
so so many things and i'd love to hear i'd love to invite
your reflections what you've noticed in this practice today
for both your own benefit to be witnessed and for the benefit of the sangha when
you share your practice whether it's something that you discovered
it's a gift to others or it could be a question a challenge this didn't quite work how this was hard
that is also a gift definitely a gift because you can trust that other people other practitioners
will either have a similar question or have had it etc
so you're welcome to raise your zoom hand especially if you haven't shared in a while
i'd like to encourage you to speak up you can also type in chat
and i share and i change the settings so that you can type to everyone if you wish in
which case i'll read it out loud i'll say your name if it's just typed to me privately the chat i will
not say your name but i will just read out the reflection for the benefit of the sangha so
what did you notice how was this practice for you
practice of independence in the dharma
as well as interdependence sense of all perhaps arising or overwhelming rising
that can come up too in this practice a sense of goodness
jerry says the interdependence seemed amazing jerry i'd love to invite you to say more
if you would what you mean by amazing um if you would hear uh if you could
unmute yourself now you should be able to please tell me what arose for you um
well it was uh the dependence part i got about the
independent interdependence when you started thinking to the plankton and everything else in the universe
it made it made me think of the earth as a sort
of organism and we're just part of that organism or maybe the whole universe and um so it really became
quite powerful to think uh you talked about you know all the biochemical reactions
that happened in the last second probably in the millions in her body and then thinking you know more that's at the
granular level and then you look interdependently and you think wow it's quite a uh uh and they were not an island
we're all and of course with things facing the world nowadays covet
into you know climate change it makes it seem so even more real so it seemed uh a whale a way
amazing in terms of its um
breath and and and and hand also in terms of its
um it almost seemed amazing in terms of its uh like
the patterns you know like in nature you see fractals here like all of these things that you just
go like how does this all happen just happens so i was in awe
thank you beautiful thank you jerry thank you and thanks for sharing your sense of awe
that arose yeah beautiful to witness thank you for sharing that
um a few more reflections in chat uh i appreciate it connected even
when we feel disconnected i have been feeling disconnected nice to not also feel like a failure for
it thank you for sharing that yeah it's okay to feel disconnected now
that it's part of being human it's part of being human
and not to feel like a failure and it's okay it's okay sweetie it's all right it's
okay casey says yes agree with jerry felt a lot of gratitude as you named
different examples of interdependence thanks casey and mark says thank you all
thank you to all beings in all countries of this world who sustain my life through our
interdependence i am grateful and thank you nikki and thank you mark for coming
and practicing in this sangha i wouldn't be here if it wasn't for
you guys all of you being here practicing this is part of our interdependence here
we co-create happy hour together don't forget that
claire says love thinking of letting go of negative thoughts as a path to freedom yes yes
absolutely beautiful so dear ones on this day of
observing independence interdependence now let us practice in small groups
of interdependent to create interdependence and let's show up just as you are
let's show up just as you are just for six minutes or so you will be in
these small groups interacting with each other co-creating a sense of connection with
each other it's so precious to just connect with fellow human beings from around the
world i'm so touched by this sangha for just a few minutes and sharing goodwill
sharing goodwill so i'll create the breakout rooms and let's
let's always start with 15 seconds of silent meta for one another
just in silence um and then you can share as little or as much as
you like with each other about your practice caring for yourselves for each other
just in kindness in kindness in interdependence the two other human beings in this room there
will be three of you uh three or four we'll see how it goes or two or three of her um they're just like you so caring for
each other in this way all right i'm opening the rooms here we go
okay everyone welcome back the room circle so we have a couple minutes
for any reflections uh what you discovered in groups especially if you haven't
shared before for a while we'd love to hear from you you can either type in chat or
raise your zoom hand so i can see you what did you discover please
questions comments
do you feel more connected interconnected yes anyone feel more interconnected
after happy hour yes i see a few thumbs up yeah that's great yeah richard please
you hear me yeah um my morning out of berry with bill
and sue morgan they've been discussing um the contrast between dukkha and
sukkah the last few days and this sid reminded me of the suka side of that
equation nice nice so what i'm hearing is that you've been exploring
so for those who don't know those words uh dukkha is suffering his challenges pain is is
is what's difficult and sukkah is the opposite of dukkha is is you can think of it as
sugar sukkah you know they have similar um
i think similar to etymological attempt same background verbally in any way in
words so sukkah is what's pleasant in the mind what's pleasant in the mind what's
pleasant in the body so sukkah and dukkha they play the opposite of each other and
richard you're saying that this sid reminded you or or was more filled with
sukkah for you of pleasantness in the mind and the body anything particularly that brought that
about that brought that up your presence always brings me
oh send you meta richard
yeah great so so violet says nice to connect with
the group on the theme of independence and loneliness
thank you violet thank you for sharing that yeah in of independence and loneliness
yeah very profound theme yeah and susan says i felt very
connected to my small group it was very it was lovely to know others
feel similar yeah i'm really touched by all of those
um comments and um i think in particular the theme of
independence and loneliness it's a really important one maybe we'll pick that up
later yeah thank you all so thank you all thank you so much
for your practice thank you for your devotion your dedication your kindness
for cultivating your goodness to benefit all beings everywhere may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
[Music] free [Music]
thank you now