so then we'll start and with more kind of official uh
good day to all of you and welcome and uh some idea that you might want to
incorporate into your your sitting
is the idea that we are in doing meditation not just trying to
become calm and peaceful not just to have insight and see clearly
what's going on we're also trying to grow grow inner qualities
wholesome qualities the skillful qualities and there is a movement towards this
there's some in this teachings of the buddha some powerful words that are used that could
be translated into english as growing in in a way that we thrive or into
abundance and and so this recognition of something can develop inside of me
that um that um inside of us that grows and develops and
unfolds over time and this can be in confidence it can be
growing in wisdom it can be growing in equanimity growing in generosity compassion
kindness a certain kind of strength of fortitude
all kinds of things can develop and the metaphor for this growth is that of a plant growing
and um and so the farmer provides the conditions this is
the soil and the i mean there's a price so the the fertilizer and the water and maybe
the light to allow something to grow and so meditation practice is also
providing these things so that we could grow and one of the things that
we try we try to do in meditation is to let go of thinking and preoccupations
so that our awareness our capacity for pr being present becomes open and available
for something to fill it to grow into it if awareness is preoccupied and
claustrophobic there's no room for something to grow and develop in almost like into that space so there's
no space for it to grow it's like a crowded um uh
garden bed was full of weeds and the plants we want to grow that our little seedlings don't have any
don't get to the light and so we clear the weeds so the plants that we want to grow can grow and
develop and so we have you know some of us have some weeds in our mind
that interfere with the growth of these beautiful plants we have
and so the idea of getting out of the way and allowing something to grow make
space for something just that very idea of okay let go of my thoughts
let go of my preoccupations and offer a kind of open awareness a kind of
uh clear attention to what's here in which there's almost like space
there's almost like silence or stillness or spaciousness in which there's space for something
that's new something healthy that can grow and
and sometimes what needs to grow first is the weeds so we can really see them and um and then can
work with them and find a way with them but really they do have something growing
so um so so taking a meditation posture
and
and it's a posture ideally that you have some sense an idea that allows for
space for something to grow so some people find that taking a
posture that has some confidence and
openness and presence real sense of presence it's in the presence that
something healthy can grow
softly close your eyes
and become aware of your breathing very simply calmly
become aware of breathing the body breathing
maybe even becoming aware sweetly
gently quietly aware of breathing
as if breathing is a
maybe a gentle being gentle place that you want to approach in a gentle
way with awareness
and maybe the idea is to approach yourself gently
sweetly and as you exhale
to gently relax parts of your body gently means not forcefully not with
high expectations just enough
relaxing the muscles of the face
relaxing the shoulders in the relaxation
there's more room in your body for something to grow
there's space tension limits the space for things to grow
and softening the belly
soft belly is like a field that's been well tilled and soft and rich with
a mess with compost
and then gently
quieting the mind the thinking mind gentling the thinking mind
to begin the process of making more mental space
for something to grow
if we are preoccupied in ill will or resentment or
strong desires it's sometimes likened to an
infertile field in which nothing can
grow
letting go of your thoughts with the idea that you are getting out
of the way or making space for something to unfold and show itself
and grow maybe something you can't know ahead of time
without expectations of what will grow
letting go of thoughts preoccupations opening to your body breathing
as if you're giving open clear space
for the wholesome within you to grow
letting go of thoughts
centering yourself in your body in the body that's breathing
the more aware you are of your body
the more the wholesome has a chance to
grow
as we come to the end of this sitting
i'll point out that there are some
expressions of ways of living that open
us up in some that close us
when there is friendliness it tends to be an opening of the heart opening of
ourselves to someone else when there's animosity there's a closing
barrier when there's love tends to be opening
hate is closing as we come to the end of a sitting and
whenever a buddhist practice session is over
there's the practice of doing something which is opening partly to allow what's
within us to continue to grow and flourish to give expression to what is the good
in us and also to express our care for the
world and that is called the dedication of
merit and here on this morning this day of
meditation may we offer up
through generosity and love and kindness
whatever benefit that we received from this practice today may we share that benefit with others
may we share it in a way that continues to make room and space
for the wholesome to grow in us
may the benefits of this practice that we do be expressed in the wish and the actions
that promote the welfare and happiness of all beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
so continue our discussion about the wholesome and the skillful
and one of the definitions of what is kusala wholesaler wholesome or skillful is that
which um
results in happiness and is non-afflictive so the idea that it
doesn't cause harm doesn't hurt us in any kind of way that's one of the requirements what's
wholesome and it brings happiness and
the word is results in happiness and so meaning that there's a movement
towards greater well-being greater happiness that's that's part of what wholesome is
but wholesome is also considered to be beneficial or healthy
or good in and of itself so it's both good in itself and it has a further on
the onward leading towards happiness because sometimes we the wholesome's not automatically happy
we're practicing and making space and allowing for the growth of that over time and we want to create a stable strong
foundation for happiness so we're not so dependent on the
changing nature of our experience our life circumstances are also the changing
experience changing nature of our physiology and our and you know our
hormones and our tiredness and how much food we've eaten and all kinds of other things that can affect our mood to have some kind of
stability there because of the strength of these good qualities that have been developed in us
over time and uh when i first came to buddhism
the in zen practice there was very little discussion about
that we're actually maturing and developing and growing through the practice because there was a a
very strong tendency to point towards what was considered the absolute what's ultimately true
um so for example emptiness to really see into the nature of emptiness or or to see into the nature of
enlightenment here and now and and uh experience some kind of non-dual
state that and as soon as we talk about growth then we're into a duality do do list dualism or we're into uh gaining
ideas or we're into kind of missing the boat of really being here and discovering freedom right here
and now and there's some real wisdom to that kind of kind of direct
pointing to some kind of awakening or state of being but it also can really miss or
shortchange a hugely important natural part of the human being and that is human beings whether they
want to or not are constantly changing and growing and developing
sometimes what's growing and developing is not healthy so if someone has a habit of complaining
or being angry or irritated if they do that a lot that's what grows inside if
and so there's all this kind of unhealthy stuff that can grow by the repeated doing of it
and and if we keep making space for what's good then something will
different will happen and come up and so even if we do this non-dual to
directly pointing to reality the whole system that we're in the psychophysical system
will begin shifting and changing as a result of that and it's possible to track that and see
how people change and develop over time and
it's also possible to support that growth and development and
move it along when i was uh doing zen practice at some point in the
monastery i was made the gardener and and i would go around and
part of the job was to weed and uh that was the instructions it was to weed
and let plants grow and at some point i wondered whether wasn't it okay also to weed the weeds of the mind
weeding the mind did was that some kind of dualist dualism was some kind of
gaining idea was some kind of conceit or missing the boat that we would notice
there's weeds in the mind and i didn't see there was any reason to see that my mind is any different in the
garden in the garden i took care of weeds why not take care of the weeds of the mind as well when i was angry or greedy
or something and so um but as we kind of uh
make space and take the weeds out it makes room for something else to grow and develop
and this so you find the teachings of the buddha a great emphasis on this developing of growth and uh
and i can't under uh uh value it and i can't can't emphasize it
enough that it creates a really good strong strength or foundation
that carries a stable into all kinds of challenges of our life and
known people who've relied on having kind of shortcuts to kind of mystical
experiences or great states of consciousness or even it's kind of what felt like states of freedom
but they didn't really have this inner strength to hold that and to rest in that and to receive it
and be influenced by it and they would succumb back to the usual old habits which are
not so healthy and then they would swing between these great states and then
and then um you know go back to where they were so for the buddha the idea is to develop
and cultivate these inner capacities so that we can hold some of the higher
experiences of realization of freedom that come with practice
and if the idea of these higher states of attainment or freedom is not so interesting for you
the it's also that as we become stronger develop these healthy qualities
we also able to hold basic human experiences of love better and our love is so much
healthier and stable and and um non not so fragile when the all these
other wholesome qualities have developed and grown in us
um so the buddha said abandon what is unwholesome so that just means
you know weed the mind of the weeds the things that are not helpful and also what's unwholesome is what is
afflictive and which leads to the opposite of suffering opposite of of happiness it leads to
suffering so abandon what is unwholesome and devote yourself
to wholesome to wholesome conduct this particular quotation so
to actively behave in ways which are beneficial skillful wholesome for that is how you will grow
increase and come to fulfillment in this dharma that the buddha was
teaching so part of what we're doing is living behavioral changes so not just changing
the what we do you know quality of our inner attitudes and hearts but actually making choices for how to
behave differently and to choose those behaviors which are wholesome
beneficial and so yesterday i read the 10 skillful actions
which are 10 wholesome things to do that helps this inner growth and
development happen
so one of the meanings of translations of
kusula is as skillful and and that has a wonderful benefit to
translate a skillful because it um um
it doesn't it tends a lot less to have it tends not to have so much of a moral moralistic kind of weight to it that
even wholesome can seem moralistic and some people are a little oppressed or it's heavy kind of
uh to kind of even to get close to that kind of language but skillful is kind of free of that
and um and then you ask skillful for what skillful for cultivating the path of liberation
skillful for developing you know all kinds of wonderful things we can develop including
skillful in developing the practice and and skill developing a skill
is done by repeated engagement over and over and over again and a lot of small movements sometimes
to learn a skill and uh and so one of the skills that i've
learned in the last three months and i'm surprised you know how i'm still learning
the art of it it seems like it's very very simple and i thought it was much simpler than it is but
i'm learning these very subtle distinctions that makes me more and more skillful and
the actually the word skill in english comes from a germanic word
in norwegian at least it's the word schiller and it means to
distinguish or separate out and that's the original kind of germanic source of the word to make distinctions
to separate out and so i'm making this skill i'm learning finer and finer little skills to make it easier and easier
and that is my right eye now i wear a contact and for these last few
months and putting that contact in i'm getting better and better at and sometimes it
was a real challenge i could it would fall out it wouldn't get in right i didn't couldn't quite sometimes get it to work
and and then and then over these months doing a day after day after day and
paying attention to what i'm doing paying attention to exactly the position of the fingers where the contact fits in
my fingers all these little details and i'm getting better and better and and it was surprisingly now
it's just like so easy when it's when it's done right it's like it's just like so
it's like such a beautiful smooth easy kind of graceful kind of it just kind of just
slides right up on the eye just sits there with no effort on my part it's just like almost like
it wants to be there and sit there on the on the eyeball and um so you know i'm
still learning skills in my old age right so that's a wonderful skill i'm learning
but these subtle little distinctions same thing happens in doing buddhist practice we're learning these subtle subtle
distinctions in our posture and how to sit and we develop our meditation posture
it's more more skillful or wholesome or beneficial we're developing all these little skills
and how to be with a breath and how to pay attention to the breath um we're learning all the little
movements of the mind slowly slowly incrementally we learn what it's like to be mindful what it's
like to let go what it's like to where to focus and how to focus and and
uh how to concentrate and how to be equanimists and how to um you know what kind of effort to make
an energy to make just the right amount of effort not too much and too little and this is
partly learned not because you read a book and say this is the formula what you do but rather it's
um it's through engagement over and over and over again
like a swimmer whose athlete who's swimming training for competitive
racing they learn ever ever refined distinctions and how they move their arm
in the water to make the least resistance get the most uh push off the water so the same thing
in meditation we learn the body the system even unconsciously there's this growth and development of
skills and so when we talk about meditation practice rather than how we live in our
interpersonal lives uh the word kusala is sometimes better translated as
skill and we're doing what's skillful we're developing certain kinds of skills
and the the metaphor the buddha uses for uh uses metaphors that are clearly
having to do with skills that people develop so developing the five faculties
which was the theme for the first five weeks of these youtube 7 a.m teachings i did starting last
march the metaphor used for the five faculties was tuning and playing a loot
and a five string loot and you know you want to you get you you learn how to tune it better and
better you learn how to play it better and better and so we're learning these five strings inside of us
and slowly we learn to tune them and play them for mindfulness practice the metaphor
there is also developing a skill and that is learning to cook and
and cooking also is a skill that's learned over time and and the more we cook a dish the simpler
straightforward easier more creative we can get and we develop a skill that we were awkward when we first began with
the recipe and kind of trying to put it all together and figure out how it all worked
so a skilled meditator skilled mindfulness practitioner is like a skilled cook according to the buddha and
and so this idea of developing a skill and so a skill grows through time
and as certain skills develop they make room for other good qualities to develop and grow
as well and so the theme for today is idea of
growth of kind of inner growth of our good qualities our abilities
our mental capacities our mental attitudes a growth in what's beneficial
that is little bit different than making something happen but allowing for this natural process of
growing that is slow comes repetition over over and over again doing the same thing
over and over again doing kindness over and over again friendliness generosity over and over again
we're developing a skill and making finer finer distinction in all kinds of ways that benefit us and hopefully benefit
others and uh in such a way that over time something's growing and
thriving there's an abundance there's a there's a filling out of something really
marvelous within us um and um
and so to make room for that to recognize that that's part of what we're doing here so we have the
patience to continue and keep going
and also the ability to recognize that it's not just about experiencing
emptiness or strong states of concentration there's all these things we're cultivating and developing and become
skilled for that will support us so i'll talk more about some of the wholesome
skills that are developed in the next couple of days next few days so thank you very much may
may you study reflect on ways that you have grown in whole
wholesome qualities how over the last five years 10 years 20 years
have you changed and grown in wholesome beneficial ways with your inner life and how you live
your life and how did that steady slow growth happen for you
so thank you
you