so good morning everyone or good day and welcome to our meditation session
and as we begin this meditation i'd like to suggest
an idea maybe some of you will find it meaningful
and that is that there are two halves to meditation there's what you bring and there's what
you receive there is what you contribute
to your meditation and then what
you allow and the meeting of those two is where meditation is
and so on one hand what you contribute it has to do with your autonomy your ability to engage
autonomously independently from what is happening around you what's
happening within you and and then
what you receive is i like to call it the natural world
that uh kind of like you're a naturalist who is clearly autonomous in engaging observing
the natural world that's being studied but is also not interfering with it and
allowing the natural world to kind of unfold the way that it is so they can be
studied and so we ourselves are a natural system nature is found right here in our body
and our minds our hearts and our emotions the whole working of our psychophysical
system you know 99.9999 percent of it they're
at at the minimum is this uh phenomenal natural system
that's evolved over millennia and uh
you know we don't still don't even know the full extent to which this whole psychophysical system really works and
and um and but it works it keeps us alive keeps us going for a good number of years
and uh it's a probably more of
who we are is the product of our natural
of nature doing its thing through us than it is what we think or what we do what we feel
we're responsible for what we judge ourselves for what we criticize ourselves for what we
so in meditation we're sitting here to be autonomous to send up
metaphorically upright present attentive the attention is where the autonomy is
found so in order to get make some complicated idea of individualistic autonomy
but it's the autonomy that comes from showing up and being present for the experience for being aware of this is
what's happening and in that this is what's happening
then there's also what's what's happening isn't is nature and nature can be trusted nature
uh if if we stay autonomous if we don't interfere and don't participate
and that's the autonomy part don't participate don't get entangled or caught in anything almost like you're
making a room to wow this is nature this is a natural world unfolding here
and my proposal is you assume the natural world moves towards health
if there's tension it moves towards relaxation
if there's fear it moves towards relaxation
if there is anger it moves towards release
if there's sadness it moves to a freeing of certain kind of
healing of the sadness there's all this forces inside of us
that moves towards health if we allow it and so this meeting and this gesture of namaste bring our
hands together and anjali of putting our hands together like this it's our autonomy
and nature that meet in this practice and then we see what happens
so um to assume a
appropriate posture for meditation appropriate for you
and relax your gaze if you're looking at the screen for example you might
turn your head your gaze down at about 45 degrees
in a way with their eyes can relax
and if it's comfortable you might close your eyes
and then to
take a few long leisurely and deep breaths
maybe three quarters full so you don't doesn't tire you two breathe deep
then a long exhale slow relaxed long
but not so long that it becomes a strain
and then deep full inhales to feel your body
your torso your shoulders rib cage
many of the things that you feel as you deep breathe in deeply in your torso
you share with many other animals that breathe as well ribcage and shoulders and movement
filling of the lungs it's a natural process
and then as you exhale to relax the body
sometimes as the shoulders the belly different parts relax
it's appropriate to adjust the posture a little bit
maybe sit up little [Music] straighter open the chest a bit more
and then letting the breathing return to normal
and on the exhale softening the face
around the eyes
maybe the lips can in the middle of the lips maybe they can part a little bit
maybe just a millimeter that allows maybe the lip area the mouth
ear to be a little bit more relaxed
on the exhale to relax the shoulders
maybe feeling the weight of the shoulders allows for something to release
relaxing to the pull of gravity
on the exhale relaxing the area around the heart
maybe relaxing together with the phrase it's okay
for now it's okay however you're feeling however things are
and then the exhale relaxing the belly
sometimes relaxing the belly and letting it maybe sag forward
the weight of it to settle further down
can be a reminder to be grounded here
rooted here in the body in the lower torso here now
and the autonomy i'm talking about is very very simple
the autonomy of being aware
to be aware [Music] without entanglement
to be a naturalist of yourself
an awareness perhaps that's receptive allowing
you might have preferences you might have ideas and judgments about
what's happening but awareness does not
to disentangle yourself from your preferences and
agendas judgments let them be
and take refuge in the simplicity of awareness there is where we discover our autonomy
and freedom
and for now just assume that everything else is nature
and you're allowing there to be a meeting a recognition and knowing
contact between awareness and nature
and with the rhythm of breathing being relatively constant
it's a good place to stabilize steady yourself
in that meeting between awareness and nature
nature is a natural functioning
even if you you are controlling your breath
it's okay it's that's nature true too
just be aware of how things are in an autonomy
of awareness just aware and the meeting of awareness
and breathing
how simple can you be
with your awareness present moment awareness
just aware what is and everything else everything what is
is nature
be aware don't participate in it
just see it for what it is nature
and as you step away maybe the healing
forces of nature the harmonizing forces
have a chance to operate
you
as we come to the end of this meditation
it's a gift to yourself and to others
to have this open autonomous capacity for awareness
inclusive of the people in your lives people you'll encounter today
the people of your communities immediate communities
wider communities the communities of people on your continent where you live
and around the world
and in this autonomous autonomy of awareness
to let it be a channel through which your heart can sing
your heart can smile in appreciation
and valuing of others
they too are nature profound
important part of a whole
who knows what important parts they play
but they too can move towards harmony healing
wholeness when they're held in awareness
and care and may we with our capacity for
awareness hold all beings in our care
may all beings be appreciated
may all beings be valued
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we contribute to all that
[Music]
so good day everyone thank you for being here and part of this valued community of
meditators and interest people interested in the dharma and i certainly appreciate my opportunity
come and share something that's very important for me
and i'll have one announcement lest i forget later and today um
barry and jan rothman are going to
have to host a discussion group after the dharma talk
on zoom and i think that the zoom link is at the very top of the chat
and i'll i'll try to post it at the end when i finish here it's also on imc's website
on the bottom right it's in the what's new section
there's an announcement there for it and um in the calendar which is in the bottom
left uh it's listed there as an event and you click on the event and then the zoom
information is there so it's a nice time nice way of being in community and
talking about the dar mine
so for um the talk today i want to start with a story i'm fond of
as an introduction to what i'll be talking about
there was a person who was well learned in buddhism
many years studying with the great teachers of the era
studied all the great books and sutras and commentaries and
so but then at some point i went to a zen master
and now with the piece of beautiful paper calligraphy paper
and asked the zen master to do a calligraphy to write down the most important teaching of buddhism
in this calligraphy there's a tradition especially in japan of that zen masters will do calligraphy
and and sometimes they're on scrolls and their scrolls are hung in a respectful place
in a home and so in that custom the person went to the zen master and made that request
and so they uh then master thought about it for a while and then wrote
great focus and presence wrote something on the scroll
and the person was very excited that this great zen master was going to write the essential kind of nugget to what
buddhism is about and the zen master wrote on the but the character in japanese for
attention just that one word attention single character
and um and the zen master and the and the person said oh no no you seem to not
quite understood uh you know i want the most important the essential the key
teaching and so the zen master took another piece of paper and with great focus and
presence wrote another two characters now and the person was
very excited to see it now but certainly there'd be something profound and the zen master had written attention
attention so then the person explained you know they're well studied they've
read all the great philosophies of buddhism they they really have surveyed the whole
terrain lots of teachers they've studied with and and they're sophisticated and they know a lot already so you know can you really
kind of capture the the really the essence of the philosophy of the teachings of you know
and the zen masters oh now i understand okay
and um took another piece of paper and with great focus and presence looked at
the paper composed attention in the moment
grounded here and then wrote attention attention attention
so this idea of attention is so important for this tradition for
buddhism and everything you need to know and need to occur in buddhist practice
happens through the vehicle of paying attention being attentive to what's going on
and a beginning class in meditation would tell you to start being mindful
start engaging your attention in the present moment so in some ways it can be seen as
beginner's practice but it's the same practice for someone who has been practicing for years
someone who has matured in the practice reached full mutual maturity for it
it's still attention the core practice is the same and so the practice of a beginner and
the practice of someone's practice for a long time is in some ways the same
and people who practice for a long time it's always good to go back to the beginning to really start over again in a sense
but we start over again if we've done practice for a long time we don't quite start over the practice
is the same attention the basic instructions might be the same as for a beginner
but we bring something along something accompanies us from the maturity of our practice
that creates a little different context for doing the basic practice
so what i'd like this talk to be about is an introduction
to meditation practice and and
so it's meant for people who are maybe pretty new to all this maybe this is your first time coming to
talk at imc and also some of you i know i practiced for a long time and i hope it's going to
work for you too that you don't say you know you're ready to you know turn off the
youtube channel because oh it's just going to be an introduction to meditation i know all too well what meditation is about
i hope that you'll appreciate as i these minutes that i talk that it is
offer something a little different so the reason for this uh topic is that
my current plan which is subject to change by tomorrow morning but is to for the next few weeks on the
7 a.m teaching that i do to go through the basic instructions in
meditation practice that i teach here at imc and
and like i teach a five week intro to meditation class periodically and
and that follows a pattern and the pattern is the first day first evening we talk about breathing
the second evening we talk about a body mindfulness of the body the third time day is um
mindfulness of emotions the fourth one is mindfulness of thinking and then the fifth time is
everything else kind of um and um and so i thought we would go through
that one week at a time so a week on breathing a week on
body a week on emotions in a week on on thinking and then maybe a week or two
or some other things and and i feel it's really really useful to come back to the beginning to basics for
everyone and as i said i think that basics are not just basics for people who have a
lot of experience it's still the basic practice but hopefully something accompanies that
there's a understanding and insight a an approach to starting over again
that is both just starting over again sharing the practice of a beginner but somehow there's something else that's happening
there along with it and
so that's the plan and so this talk today is a little bit like an introduction to the series that
i'm planning to do so i wanted to take the opportunity to contextualize
a little step back a little bit more more objectively contextualize the instructions and meditation that i've
been doing here during this pandemic time and also at imc and how it fits into the
larger scene because all instructions
are probably not best choice of words but are contrived are artificial they're
something that are constructed and made and presented and as such they have history
and um the way that i teach this five-week intro class at imc
um i had it uh i'll tell you the origins of it
so when i went to practice vipassana insight meditation in thailand and burma
the instructions were very simple in fact in burma i showed up at kind of like the ground headquarters this ground
zero for the whole in some ways the vipassana movement that spread into the west
and um and they gave me a cassette and a cassette player
with the 15 minute instructions in the meditation and that was the extent of the
instructions that i was supposed to i used for them for eight months that i was on retreat there
every all the instructions were given in 15 minutes and the simplest way of understanding
repeating those 15 minutes is
focus on the sensations of your breathing and if something becomes more
predominant more compelling than your breathing let go of the breathing and bring your attention to
really see what it is that's pulling you away or what's more compelling and when that's subtle enough
somehow it doesn't have to stop but subtle enough and no longer so compelling go back to your breathing
and so it was a lovely practice for me to discover because in doing zen practice before
that the focus was so much on breathing and on posture
that there was no instructions for emotions for thinking for all the kind of wider range of our experience
and vipasse and i learned that this simple instructions included this wide all of our humanity everything was
included and i remember when i was after practicing in burma for a while
i got so happy when i realized at some point that distance practice taught me to be
mindful be present for all everything in my experience
and and uh and the reason i became so happy was that
i knew that if i was mindful there was a way of being free liberated from
experience and this idea that that no matter what the human experience
is because i knew now how to be mindful of it i could find some kind of freedom
some kind of peace some kind of independence some kind of autonomy disentanglement with it all
and i still couldn't do it so well but i now i knew the theory i could be free anywhere i go
if i keep practicing mindfulness so um so that was what these extra
instructions was very simple and there's certainly more that happened in those 15 minutes of instructions but it was all
done like that i came to practice a little bit here in the west and um and then at some point i
was invited to become a teacher in this vipassana tradition and um and only then did i really kind
of start attending western insight meditation retreats i hadn't done a lot of things here in the
west and and here i've discovered they taught the
instructions in a different way on retreats they would start on the
first day teaching about breathing meditation and they get grounded get settled
the second day they talk about mindfulness to the body partly because by this by the second day
people's bodies were aching and challenging the third day they would talk about instructions in mindfulness of emotion
and uh and by third day that was often kind of challenging for people so that was
useful and the fourth day they talk about mindfulness of thinking
and then there'd be some other things the next days of the retreat and that was a pattern
and so i was introduced to that pattern and i thought this was a nice pattern
as part of my teacher training starting in 1990 i was asked to
take over a group small meditation group in palo alto and i taught them for every week for
about a year or year and a half or so until it became clear it'd be useful to do in instructions in meditation for
people so then i offered the first time but i had never received any kind of
basic meditation class instructions and meditation class which i was about to teach
and so i you know i didn't i didn't have any reference points for how you do it and i wasn't certainly i wasn't going to
do the 15-minute instructions that i got in burma so i thought well these the way that they're taught on
retreat that's a very nice sequence and and it leads up to the way we're taught
in burma because after you get the full set of instructions then you know how to be present for
everything and that was the that was what they're building to on the retreats by the fifth sixth day then the
instructions were similar to what they are in burma so i thought why didn't i teach a
five-week course following the the instructions on the retreats
and one of the reasons i was motivated was that the the class was an hour and a half
actually initially i think there were maybe 45 minutes and um but it's longer than that 10 15
minute instructions on a retreat and so i then
i thought you know those instructions are so brief there's so much more to say about the instructions for each of these
things so i want more time so initially i had 45 minutes and then eventually became an hour and a half
in order to go into some real explanations real care around how to teach
mindfulness with each of these areas and and so i kind of made up this
course that way and that's what i've been doing and other people at imc have been doing now for almost 30 years
and i think it works very well but it's only one way of practicing one way of giving the instructions
in the pandemic last earlier this year i gave like 60 or so
talks there were basically instructions on mindfulness of breathing according to the anapanasati technique
and that's a whole other way of practicing which i find tremendously valuable but it is
different i've been asked now repeatedly to do a similar series on the sati
patana suta the four foundations of mindfulness which if you take that as your primary instructions is a little
bit different again it's a little different technique so these are all kinds of realizes all
these different ways of doing it and so and so my hope in offering the classic
now for 30 years away it's done here at imc on this you know sequentially
is that even if you don't take that as the as the as the
core technique in a sense it's laying a very good foundation
for how to include breathing body emotions uh thinking in
whatever technique you do become wiser you're more understanding i've also hoped in teaching this at imc
this way that is also relevant people who never meditate that people in their ordinary life
will also find it useful to understand some of the
principles ideas that i teach around breathing body emotions and thinking and
the rest of it and and so i'm and when i do interclass i'm trying to kind of
make it relevant in such a broad way so that's kind of like the background and so some of you i'm going to
hopefully prevent a little bit of confusion if some of you come to the 7 a.m teaching and say wait
a minute just early in the year we had this all 60 steps you know the 16 16 steps the 60 talks about it
on anapanasati now how does this fit in so i hope this helps a little bit
and the so
um um in terms of the sati patano suta i'm planning next year
to do a series on it and probably do a little gap before i do it after doing this current series on
the basic instructions here and hopefully the basic instructions here will be tremendously supportive
for understanding sati patana so um
so there are these basic instructions and and
and as a beginner the instructions are more prescriptive meaning these are the things that we do
for someone who as we mature there starts to be a shift in the practice where it becomes less and less something
we do and more and more something we allow so because more and more the so-called
instructions are no longer prescriptive they become descriptive so
it's more and more that we are discovering a capacity for being aware here
and then we're just receptive in a certain way and then we're aware
of breathing and so it isn't so much we're
following instructions to be with the breathing breathing has found us and that's where the practice is
at some point sometimes the the body speaks up and so then we're aware of the body it's
the loudest thing happening and so that's what fills this autonomous independent kind of capacity just to be
aware sometimes emotions sometimes thoughts sometimes other aspects of all
this and and so awareness becomes more
something we allow it develops certain independence it's not being directed necessarily but
it might be very specific if one thing is the loudest thing but it's not like we're doing it
it's more like we're allowing it and over time as practice matures and
there's some degree some experience some some um taste of what freedom is like
then the awareness shares with some of the qualities of that freedom that it's still the basic
practice but it's accompanied by a sense of what freedom is
or a feel for freedom and and disenchantment and uh
um uh and the equalities of that are come
from a sense of freedom and independence that i call it for autonomy
that there's a sense that awareness becomes more autonomous not that you become autonomous
because that's dangerous in terms of conceit like i look at me i'm autonomous and
capable independent the idea that you are independent that you are anything
is not really needed in the freedom and the ease and the peace of autonomous awareness
and so the autonomous awareness the awareness that can just be is has lent itself to like in the west
to the language of to have non-judgmental awareness to have an awareness that's accepting of
everything uh to have uh open awareness
to have um there was a time that was popular was something called choiceless awareness
and so over time there are different trends about how to talk about this and the current trend as of today here
with me is to talk about in terms of being autonomous autonomous awareness
and um and as practice deepens as i said rather than the mindfulness of
something we do mindfulness something we allow we allow that autonomy of awareness
that is not entangled or cut up or for and against any experience
and and then it becomes more and more kind of a marvel kind of a wondrous thing
that there is this free feeling of awareness that's free and independent and
not pushed around not attached to anything not for anything or against anything
and then everything else becomes nature even things which are unfortunate
say that you're angry with someone that they're in a hostile with someone in a very unfortunate way
um the autonomy means that you're not going to give in to it you're not going to
participate in it the forces of australian anger exists within you
but this precious core of who we kind of since are the awareness
allows us just to leave it alone and maybe seeing it it's and then not
identifying with it and this is one of the characteristics of a mature practitioner
is that there's less and less identification with whatever the experience is
identification here means that we define ourselves by it we limit ourselves and
this is who i am we hold on to it we grab onto it that now i know who i am that immediately
limits the range and the wholeness the fullness of the experience
and it's not a denial of certain appropriate identities that people have it's the movement of identity movements
of the identification that we have that is the issue
and uh and so as practice matures it's still the same practice but what we're doing is we are
no longer identifying with these things
and so we are um
and so the um and so everything we see then
becomes nature that it becomes just part of the process
and that kind of independence being having those two meet
to ho or to hold in awareness whatever the experience is breath body emotions thoughts
challenges pain suffering whatever it might be it's a remarkable process
because then the natural functioning of who we are begins to operate better and better and
this idea of being able to step feel the freedom and allowance of a natural functioning
that comes when we don't restrict nature we don't limit it when bottle it up we don't become attached to it
and uh the kind of understanding of buddhism is that all the
unhealthy ways that we live our lives all the ways that we cause harm to ourselves and others
comes from not not leaving things alone not letting things
equilibrate come to harmony it becomes entanglement wanting
contracting around something resisting something judging something
identifying with something in a heavy burdensome way so
so the instructions are very simple basic
and the more longer ones practices the more one has
practiced them then basic instructions become even more relevant than they were when you were a
beginner because of what accompanies it because now there's a sense and a feeling and
this possibility of having to be simpler and simpler and simpler is not simplistic
simpler is where where freedom is found
so um so that's the introduction and hopefully
um for those of you who are not gonna come to the 7am
hopefully that was nice for you and and um and uh
and for those of you who do i certainly look forward to seeing you tomorrow morning or seeing you being with you
and we will us
hopefully go through it in a way that all of us including me find valuable and meaningful
so thank you all and wish you all a good week