so hello and welcome everyone lovely to see you to be with you
so for today's practice um i'd like to invite us
to explore the practice of compassion
for others in a particular way so the practice of compassion compassion
is where meta love good will meets meets challenge meets
suffering either ours or others and holds it with kindness
and one way to practice um this beautiful practice of compassion
cultivating our hearts towards compassion is um called tonglen tonglen i've mentioned it
before we practice it before some of you might be familiar some of you may not be
it's all good so so the idea of tonglen and something
that some people find actually perhaps challenging with tanglin which is really the crux of what i'd
like to focus on is this connecting the
our breath breathing in breathing out breathing in breathing out that's one
part of tongue line breathing in suffering breathing out
good will love kindness compassion soothing but what really makes this possible what
really makes this tongle impossible and actually makes it a beautiful
practice not a heavy practice of oh my god i'm breathing in the suffering of others
which is where sometimes people go off and like i don't like tongue line because it's heavy i'm breathing in
suffering of others is the idea that actually when
breathing in happens the idea of this this um transformative capacity
in our heart that suffering gets transformed suffering that's breathed
and gets transformed without us doing anything it's not ours so we take the self out of it because if
you make it about me i'm breathing in the suffering of the world like it's too heavy it gets too much how does the
little me do that well it's not about the little me it's about the
this me that's unfathomable that's that's much
more dimensionally divine and and
the capacities of this heart this mind are much more expansive than the little me
has access to or the little me can even envision so so
it connects so this practice connects with the bodhisattva vow that i vow to
free up all human beings to support the freedom of all human beings which if you take it as face values like are you
kidding me the little me is going to do all that well it's not the little needs it's the sense of
tapping into something that's bigger than me i am part of something that is
so bigger than me um then i can't even envision but in imagine but i trust i trust this heart
this kindness goodness of my heart um as suffering is breathed in is
transformed as if there is this fire this holy fire this um
this this fire that transforms this the suffering into good will into
light into light of well-being that then shines out so i'm
just being a i'm being a be i'm supporting this
process that's happening on its own i'm not doing it i'm witnessing it so you
participate as a witness as something that you witness and you
you take um you're even maybe even amazed by and it
inspires you wow wow this is beautiful this is amazing
i also want to connect it to something else that thing was brought up
in the google groups that is practiced that yes my suffering there's a particular way to
see that my suffering is a part of is a part of this uh this transformation
it's a part of this transformation it's part of of this transformation of suffering into
goodness suffering into care into love and that's one way that we can see our
own suffering as a way to to support the the uh well-being the compassion um
that that it's an act of compassion it's an act of taking on it's an act of
taking on of course not in the way of making it heavy and and um
and like oh i have to take on this suffering of the world it's not about that it's a sense of aspiration
so without saying so much more about it and let's just engage with this practice see
what arises and not get too heady about it because the more i talk i'm afraid we'll get
more heady about it trying to analyze but see what comes up see what you might
explore or realize discover that may not have been [Music]
evident like discover something new wow this is beautiful this is amazing with each breath
this being is providing is shining more love is shining more compassion onto the
world wow what a capacity i didn't know my heart was capable of that so let
yourself be surprised and if at any point it gets too much then
step back take a step back turn the compassion to yourself to your
own heart to your own body to your own mind there are no shoulds in this
cultivation see what is nourishing see what is supportive so
so without further ado let's engage let's practice together and as always we
start by landing landing in our bodies landing with the
breath
in this moment in time
letting go of the words of the thoughts of the thinking
and just connecting with the breath with the body
feeling receiving the breath in the abdomen
and relaxing softening into the body
with each breath arriving taking refuge nowhere to go nothing to do
and if thoughts are arising and if awareness
is now resting on thoughts plans it's okay it's right
it's okay have compassion kindness humor
to your own mind it's okay come back to your mind
come back sweet little puppy of the mind running away
here and there it's okay come back come back rest rest rest on my lab
with the breath in the lower abdomen
each breath
helping us land dry more deeply here now
each out breath relaxing softening
can be so delicious just to sit and receive the breath
rest rest rest now
i'd like to invite you to mention as if the breath was entering through
center of your chest the breath entering through your heart center
as it would enter would enliven
it would set a light bring a life
a sense of kindness good will
shining
it awakens this light this brightness in your heart
good will care shines out
as it shines out it touches you first touches your body first
and this heart this center of your chest this heart center proverbial heart center
it's both yours it's personal
it's also not yours
it's connected with goodness with grace with beauty with
with love
that you are a part of but you don't own it's too big for anyone to own
but you are definitely a part of as if it's an ocean
it's an ocean and yours is a drop of the same taste
same quality this good will this care this
unconditional love
that you are a part of
whether or not you see it in this moment where it's
accessible it doesn't matter no problem
and each breath entering through the heart center
at the vacancy it awakens it's enlivens brightens
the spark this light
this fire
the light shining
let's imagine that your own suffering
your own challenges in this life whether it's physical pain
difficulty in the body and the mind and the heart and your life
let's imagine that it's like a fog or
some kind of a cloud maybe
and it gets breathed in the suffering this challenge
into the heart center and it gets transformed it gets transformed this suffering
and this bright light and this holy fire
whatever vision metaphor works for you
one thing that works for me is to imagine this bright burning
alchemical fire
our suffering gets transformed
and it becomes light becomes soothing calming
lovely loving light that just shines out
ah
and it brain brings comfort and ease
the transformation happens on its own the breathing even the breathing happens
on its own there's nothing for you to do the body knows how to breathe
you are just holding witness
nothing to do
too well
pain suffering your own is breathed in
as if a fog smoke
to the heart center transformed to bright soothing
light brings comfort and ease and healing
this heart
this heart center
transformative transforming
powerful [Music] energetically powerful beyond
our imagination
the power to transform
let yourself feel drenched in the light of your own healing
of your own heart that gets shona outward
now if you like to invite someone you care about whom you're close to
imagine their challenges their suffering something that's difficult for them
is this cloud it gets breathed in
the heart center naturally and transformed into healing light
compassion love care and breathed out
through the heart center and bring them ease care love
your soothing wishes for their ease from their challenge
and witnessing the process happening on its own
this being breathed in breathed out it's an offering it's an offering of
generosity of compassion that you make
you give knowing the other person's suffering
how challenging this situation is for them it's your offering to them your offering of love and care
for their suffering to be breathed in and transformed into love
into healing your offering to them
do
oh if this heart is this heart
if this heart could take away
suffering of loved ones offering this wish
offering our goodness
again this transformation happening on its own
the cloud
breathed into the heart center brought into the heart center transformed
into love care soothing
breathe out shining out
360 degrees touching
your left one
now you can if you wish you can include your own challenge your own suffering
[Music] this cloud
the cloud includes both your difficulty and your loved ones
entering the heart center transformed on its own
shining out ah bringing peace ease to yourself and
to your loved one
each breath
as we engage with each breath more peace and ease
born into our world
this practice helps us not turn away from suffering but recognize
the strength of our heart are courage curl
meaning heart courage of our heart
to open up the suffering
to trust in its own transformative power
oh goodness good will
care shining up
you're welcome to stay with this for the last couple minutes
or if you wish
hello this cloud let's breathe in represent
challenges suffering of so many beings
around this world our planet
transformed the oven
alchemical event of the heart shining out far and wide
as our goodwill as our care inclining our heart to care not shy away
from the challenges of other beings this planet
so much great hatred and delusion
so much suffering
the light breathed out with kindness with good will
wishing all beings everywhere including this being that is me
clarity ease
well-being freedom from suffering
peace and ease
healing
letting all of our lights shine
all of these lights
our lights
ours and also part of
a bigger light may all beings everywhere
be well and free including ourselves
thank you so much for your practice
tong blend
an intense practice and can bring so much up for so many of us so
ah i'd love to hear your questions reflections comments
claire please thanks nikki um i i i couldn't help but
get my hand up because what you worked on tonight is so closely integrated into my personal life
that i can't begin to tell you i'm an only child both my parents died when i was quite young
so i went about my life in pretty normal way until about
15 20 years ago i got very involved in spiritual work and
within about 10 years of that i started experiencing situations where people died
unexpectedly and i was asked to help the survivor and the most dramatic of it came and
will always be with me because it was so moving someone who knew my story uh asked the red cross to send me down
to ground zero to do grief counseling and it was just it was amazing
uh and you know sort of a testimonial to what she said because
for me it is so enriching to be able to make that gift to others
i can't i can't describe it it's just it's like i'm a channel and i'm just giving to them
what i was given um and it's just a very important part of who i am so i wanted
to share that with you thank you claire thank you so much for
your hands being shot up on its own to share this as a gift as a part of your practice which is this
i hope everybody has the chance yeah and it's and it's also it's a gift that i so
appreciate as you said at the beginning and gives me chills is from your own background your own
suffering right losing your parents at a young age and it's
it's it's owned our own suffering it was what was in me together yeah exactly it's turning
towards it not shying away but turning towards it and builds up the courage of our hearts and you going to ground zero
to offer that support as a gift as just and in strengthening your heart as a gift can
do it yeah i mean it just made me so
grateful that i could help others that way thank you thank you so much for sharing i'm
getting chills as you share this thank you claire and richard also says
touching sharing in tears thank you claire i really appreciate
ah
other reflections please questions comments
what worked what was challenging it's all welcome you know it's all welcome
if you haven't spoken for a while
were there particular images that worked for you as you were finding your own way
with this practice [Music] especially with the heart being this
transformative alchemical powerful
transformative oven or orb of light or whatever works for you
any any thing you like to share for the benefit of others
you can raise your hand if you like or type in chat
i'll take one more pause and if
uh jeanne is raising her hand which there i
don't see everybody's physical hand genie so but so thanks for pointing out to those who did okay
um thank you so much the thing that the idea that
brings me the most light is light when the idea of
focusing on the light you know the light that's all around us it's just um it's uplifting so much for
me and i really appreciate it it makes my heart
just kind of go out everywhere
nice thank you for sharing that jamie lovely and this light as you're saying
not just my light but part of the light light goody this yes yes wow and
realizing that hello this is not just not just this little light of mine it is
this light little light of mine but it's also part of this bigger light let it shine
let it shine it's great and richard says
it was well it was a welcome reminder for me that the suffering is not my suffering but our suffering can be
transformed when faced together yeah thank you
he says think globally act locally yeah
yeah and also um david asking claire
for thanking claire for the uh reflection and this
idea of this archetype of a wounded healer that jung brings up the more we suffer the more we're able to identify
and support other suffering yeah indeed so dear ones the time has come
for us to to open our hearts to each other in small groups such a
rich practice for us to sit just for six minutes seven minutes with each other
you can share your meta your compassion in silence or you can speak if you wish share your
practice or just breathe breathe in breathe out um practice together however use this
time in whichever way it's helpful for you in in your little
group you decide so so i'm creating the groups now and uh opening the rooms take care of
yourselves take care of each other here we go group so welcome back everyone we have a
couple minutes for um reflections what came up for you what did you notice observe
when practicing with each other in groups it makes me so happy
um group practice fred please
i wonder if you would say a little more about the in in the practice
how it happens without without our willing it without without effort that it's how it's like breathing
yeah yeah so the way to bring that in that sense
in and it takes a while you know there's with tong len there's so many pieces it's it's
like you know multi-multi-ring circus there's the breath there's this there's so it takes
a while to get it all together and then so so it may not be immediate what i'm saying
that becomes a print but at some point it just seems like the breath comes in
this suffering is breathed and it gets transformed and it it's it's it's shown outward the sense of kindness
love healing it just all happens instead of okay now i'm gonna make it better there's not a sense of
willing it it's just a sense of witnessing and it's connected what's beautiful about this practice of
compassion this way of doing compassion practice i mean there are lots of beautiful ways one way as we've done
before is you know may you be free from suffering you know bringing up the the
suffering of the person in mind meeting it with kindness saying the phrases so it's more active there's a sense of
phrases whereas here this there's this sense of the breath comes in birth comes out and
it's just so there's a sense of witnessing what's happening of course we are
part of this but it's it doesn't feel so willful um
so it's it's just witnessing this it's it's not so much willing it happens
does that does that help does that clarify a little bit yeah thumbs up great thanks fred
any other last minute questions or comments
it's a beautiful practice it can take a little while at first could be clunky
i'll tell you that i learned this practice years ago when i was going through the teacher training at
stanford seacare center for compassion and
what is secure center for compassion and altruism research and education that's what it stands for a mouthful it's going
through the teacher training it was nine months and this is when i really got to
practice this and and at first it was like okay all these pieces and then at some point
it really became a lie for me and i loved it i just loved it became my
primary practice for a while i just love the sense that wow with each breath
with each breath it's i'm holding witness there's a sense of
goodness i'm not turning away from suffering and it just became easy it was just compassion practice justice feel
like it happened on its own so when it when it gets going can be really really
lovely so so it's seven o'clock
and we have come to the end of the session then click i see your hand if
it's really quick it's yes no
you tell me i just wanted to add really quickly
because what you're saying my original buddhist practice preceded all of these events
and was i worked on the sutra of compassion for two years so there you go there you go exactly
yeah beautiful thank you for that so yes may compassion
be our way of being may it support us
to meet the challenges in our lives not to turn away and also the suffering in
other people's lives it's a heart that is is um
resting in compassion as curl this curl that has courage can
be with compassion and not cower all these c words so may you all be well
safe free from suffering and thank you for your practice
may you be well and all beings may all beings be well safe and happy
[Music]
thank you