good evening welcome
welcome yeah it's nice to
arrive this moment and to practice
together wherever you are
so we'll do a little bit of a guided
meditation just allowing the mind and the body to
arrive maybe some deep
breaths and noticing with that exhale there can
be a little bit of relaxation a little bit of Letting
Go little bit more ease with the exhale
and feeling the contact of the body with whatever is supporting the
body and our feet our
legs our seat
and then checking in with the head and
face just seeing if there are any obvious places where some Letting Go
might happen
without making it a project that we have to let go or get rid
of so more it's an invitation or an
opportunity than a instruction or
imperative checking in with the neck and the
shoulders the upper back back and lower
back the chest and
belly arms and hands
and then to allow the awareness to rest on the
sensations of breathing
feeling the movement associated with
breathing e
and when the mind wanders just very gently
simply begin again with the sensations of
breathing
e e
for
we might notice that thoughts come thoughts
go maybe there's some swirling around a
particular notion or maybe there's a family of
thoughts but they're coming and going
we're not asking to have particular thoughts we didn't order them from the
menu they just arise or maybe I should say arrive
and then they
go we can't grab on to them
we can't control them so
much they're
ephemeral and yet we are often give them so much Authority
to be sure thinking is very helpful we need it to navigate Our Lives
it's important healthy normal of
course and for the purpose of
meditation for this meditation
period can we let the thoughts be in the
background and in the foreground could be the experience of
breathing or perhaps some other bodily Sensations
as best we can we let the thoughts think
themselves without our getting tangled up in
them
e e
in a simple kind-hearted way can we just begin
again with the sensations of
breathing Begin
Again
e
e e
we don't have to make thinking the enemy we don't have to make it wrong we
don't have to struggle or wrestle with thinking and thoughts
we just begin again we recognize
that most likely there's a momentum to
thinking it's natural that there might be some lot of
thoughts so we just Begin Again the sensations of breathing or the
body
e
for
e e
if we recognize that thoughts come and go and
come and go sometimes we
invest so much Authority into
them even when it's not helpful we find ourselves caught up in
them so this practice of Simply beginning
again helps to recog ize and shift our relationship to our
thoughts so that we have more space more
freedom we're not being pushed around by our thoughts but we can use them to support
us so that we might be of Greater support for others
so that we might be available to help others to fully see
others to be with others and to see and be with
ourselves so in this way may our practice be for the benefit of all
beings
everywhere for [Music]
good evening welcome I I I always want to say it's
nice to be here but I guess even though I'm here by myself but it's I am
imagining that uh there are people out there that are
listening and whether it's in real time or at a later time I'm just appreciating that there are
other practitioners so I think it's probably
safe to say that it at least once in the history
of everybody's meditation practice there's been a time in which there's been difficult experiences or
uncomfortable experiences and there might be a time in
which the inner critic gets activated and then there's this little voice saying I can't do
this everybody else can do this it seems but I can't do
this or maybe there's this uh voice that
saids say why am I even meditating anyway like it probably doesn't
work or something along the lines of uh I'm not sure about this
practice that teacher they don't understand their life has been probably easy peasy and they
don't understand the difficulties that I have and these suggestions for practice
that it's for other people not not for me or the Buddha that was so long
ago do we even know that the Buddha existed so these kinds of thoughts these
thoughts that really aren't supportive aren't helpful but there's um a sense of
agitation with them kind of like a lack of settling down and there's also a
sense of whirling maybe that they aren't really Landing anywhere or going
anywhere they're just kind of I can't do this and I don't know why I think I can
do these things and here's just proof that I can't do it or you know something along these
lines of course we we don't have these kinds of thoughts when our meditation is
settled or when there's a certain amount of ease we're not questioning the validity
of the practice or or the the uh or our
capabilities but it's only when there's some difficulties and It's Perfectly Natural right when we have some
resistance some difficulties it's that there might be some thoughts that arise
around this but a consequence of this type of
thinking is that we stop being engaged with what's actually happening instead
we're lost in this thought pattern this thought train that's going and we like
is this practice work is it going to work for me and what is the best
practice maybe I should be doing meta like have some openhearted and then go
to the mindfulness but it's hard to do mat unless I'm settled maybe I should do some concentration practice don't even
really know how to do concentration practice okay so I'll just do mindfulness but mindfulness is hard
right we could spend our whole meditation period doing this kind of thing and if you find yourself doing
this I assure you you are not the first one to do this so instead of actually
being with our experience we're having a type of debate in our mind and we're lost in
these abstract ideas that don't really have
answers I mean the question about is this practice going to work the answer to that of course is try it and find out
right that's really the only way to to know for
oneself so the Buddha recognized this this tendency for humans to do this to
kind of get lost in abstract ideas and to kind of have questioning our
capabilities and having a this hesitation or this vacillation maybe I
should do this andbe I shouldn't do that is this really right this type of thing
and he called it vcha it's kind of a nice word it's often translated as doubt or
skeptical doubt and maybe I would like to say it's more like swirling
doubt this idea of like having reservations having hesitation having
vacillation being indecisive maybe even being suspicious so it's this way in which we
kind of go around and round in our thoughts but we're not really getting anywhere and we're not really Landing in
the present moment busy with these kinds of thoughts that
undermine our capabilities undermine our capacity to actually land here and be
mindful of what's happening and this hesitation this wavering this vacillation it gets in the
way it gets in the way of practice and we end up not really going
anywhere or it's not so much that the purpose of meditation is to get
somewhere in particular even though we do have this model of uh development but
instead there's a feeling of spinning one's wheels or just going into circles
cuz we're lost and endless speculation or endlessly trying to decide which way to
go and the Buddha he used a simile to uh describe this as um crossing a
desert and I in my imagination it's a desert that's with these giant sand
dunes like nothing but sand dunes and maybe it's windy so it's kind of like hard to walk
through right you know sand dunes are not so easy to walk and because it's
windy when you look behind there are no Footprints so your Footprints are getting washed away and because it say
sandunes there aren't any um landmarks so you feel lost like you
don't know which direction to go it's not clear where you've been and it's not
clear where you're going and it's this uncomfortable experience to everywhere we look is just
more sand more sand which is really
uncomfortable but if we pay a little bit closer attention we can see that this
doubt vcha is simply a loose collection of a
certain family of thoughts that aren't onward leading but are going round and round so this doubt
is just to maybe like um drive home this point because when we use this word
doubt we might think well of course does this mean that we have to believe everything we shouldn't have doubt and
that's not what we're saying we're talking to about the doubt where it's
this uh not clear where to go next maybe even unclear where you are now and no
sense of anything that's onward leading or um sense of something that might be
supportive because sometimes to be sure doubt is
healthy doubt is helpful in the same way that we might
have this idea H the price of this object seems too good to be true what's
the catch right that's a healthy type type of doubt that we have in our daily
life but it's this part what's the catch that we ask
ourselves and then we try to find it we read the footnotes we look at okay is it this
amount of money once or is it do I have to pay that monthly or what was there a
catch maybe I can never uh uh unsubscribe or I can never return it or
you know whatever it is this idea like what's the catch so we look more closely
to see okay what's What's Happening Here We engage with what uh seems to not be
quite right we investigate in the same way we don't
believe or disbelieve something simply because somebody told us but often we hold
things true provisionally like and we do maybe a quick mental check or maybe it's
not even mental it's just maybe it's somatic as well as mental like H is this
consistent with my experience
is do what do other wise people people that I have respect for and that I
believe um have some wisdom or some knowledge on this topic what do they say
about it so it's not that we have to believe or disbelieve but just to
investigate a little bit more and this is very healthy this is
very helpful to be sure Buddhist practice is is not about just adopting a certain
amount of beliefs and there you go that's all it is certainly in especially
there's a emphasis in this tradition of Buddhism of um practice practice
practice some meditation practice this being mindful some concentration
practice getting settled loving kindness practice softening the
heart and then with practice things unfold and we start to learn and understand things
differently and this healthy doubt asks the question does this
teaching and does this practice help lesson Dua does it help uh free the
mind with this recognition that really the answer how we can really know it for
ourself is to actually do the practice run the experiment and actually do it
we can also maybe read what other people have to say about it there is no shortage of Dharma books these
days we can talk to a teacher we can listen to a Dharma talk we can have a
what we call kalamita friends spiritual friends other people that have a practice that we can
talk with but sometimes this doubt is
unhealthy and unhelpful and that's what I'd like to talk a little bit more
about this when we're lost and stuck just going around and around teaching um
asking questions and it's maybe less asking specific questions and more just
wondering are these teachings from so long ago is it really relevant thousands
of years ago and and we can get stuck in this kind of
like endless conjecture or this endless speculation and it takes it takes us
away from the experience before it teaches us
anything and in some way having this kind of speculation also supports a
indecision which can um support a habit of undermining
ourselves so it's also just exhausting to always be wondering and
not to actually settle down and try the practice instead of trying to figure it out and wondering
things okay so how can we practice with this when we see that it's
arising maybe first I'll say as doubt is rarely recognized as doubt
initially so often we can say some of the instructions are
for other hindrances or for other experiences or just to recognize that hindrance or that experience but doubt
is a little bit difficult to recognize so instead we might
say we might recognize the hesitation recognize the vacillation recognize the
indecision recognize the confusion and recognize the way in which
we might be in a debate with ourselves of uh about this practice or which practice we should do or which Dharma
talk we should listen to or something like that so just notice that the
vacillation the hesitation the maybe some
confusion and as best we can can we just allow that experience to be
there without making it go away or without um allowing all our aversion to
rise up but can in the best as best we can can we allow it to be there and one
way to support allow it to be there is first I'll maybe I'll offer this that if
we have this sense of confusion like I'm
confused just to even say I'm confused is to recognize that you're confused and
then you're no longer confused you're not confused you know that confusion is present and then that can shift uh the
experience just being with what's obvious and maybe we might recognize
that with this vacillation hesitation confusion speculation endless speculation there's also some
restlessness right it's the opposite of being settled right it doesn't support being settled so maybe we just recognize
that oh the body feels like it wants to run up or jump up and run away and the mind is
running all around or something like this so we can maybe feel the
uncomfortableness like the uneasiness I'm like wiggling in my seat maybe that's has that kind of a
feeling or maybe there's this heaviness so in this way we could feel it in the
body heaviness wanting to get up and run away or this
uh maybe a yeah I I'll offer those we each have our own idea maybe there's a s
like buzzing in the head this kind of this electric feeling
or something like this maybe it'll just remind us that that's the first Foundation of mindfulness right just to
be with the sensations in the body so in this way just doing this recognizing
turning towards what's obvious if it's helpful using some labels buzziness tingling heaviness
whatever it might be and there we are we're back into practice it doesn't mean that the
thoughts won't arise again and maybe we'll get lost but then we can just
notice what it is again and be with that experience sometimes it can be helpful
if that isn't sufficient to remember thoughts are just
thoughts they're just thoughts and then we might actually have a just a gentle
inquiry what's the difference between a thought and a memory of a
thought are they the same is remembering the thought it's still a mental event
and and the reason why I'm asking this is just maybe to take some of the
substantiality that we might attribute to thoughts away to see like wait if a
memory of a thought is not different than a thought then you know then they somehow take some of their Authority
away and just to recognize okay we're having a lot of
thoughts and maybe to remind ourselves they're just thoughts they arise and
pass away just like everything else
and maybe we can also recognize that this is a mind when that's happening the
mind is experiencing vacillation restlessness hesitation
or and just recognize oh yeah the mind is
spinning in some kind of way that could be the third Foundation
of mindfulness you might recognize oh this is
doubt that would be the fourth Foundation of mindfulness recognizing a hindrance so in all these ways just kind
of like recognizing and being with the experience whether it's the bodily experience whether it's the quality of
the mind or it's just recognizing specific that thoughts arise can help bring us back to the practice and can
disrupt some of the momentum that we might have with all this thinking
but it might be that there is tremendous momentum maybe we have a this doubt is
showing up in our daily lives and with indecision and not being able to make
decisions for me I'll say that this um kind of doubt kind of shows up in when
I'm driving should I go this way well no maybe I should go that way oh but then the traffic but it might be shorter okay
well at this time okay maybe I'll go there and some how I feel like I can't decide whether I should go this way or
that way this route or another route so there can be uh a more that we
could take that literally or maybe figuratively should I go this way or this other
way and if just recognizing what's happening and being with what's happening isn't enough to kind of like
undermine and interrupt the momentum then we can apply some antidotes can be a little bit more
active about that and one is we could do this gentle
inquiry was there an uncomfortable experience that started
this whole Cascade of
thinking or is there a view that I'm holding that things should be a a
certain way that they have to be just right so this way it's a type of
investigation and investigation is the antidote to
doubt some religious Traditions have faith as antidote and this tradition
investigation is the antidote if you feel unsure do what you can to see what helps
you feel more sure talk to people read
or just investigate your experience so when we're on the cushion we could just do this gentle
inquiry like maybe unpack The Experience like okay I can see that I have this
underlying view that things need to be just right and or I can see that this whole
thing started because yeah I'm feeling a little Restless all day I've been a little bit
Restless or oh all day I've been really tired and have this sloth and torper
and now I'm then it just started the this uncomfortable experience met the
inner critic they got together and they kind of came up with these uh sayings like oh I can't do it or or this
practice I'm not sure this practice works so to do a little bit of Investigation to unpack like how did you
get here so that could be maybe a little bit more actively um getting being involved
with the experience we might also gently inquire is there fear underneath this
sometimes there's fear that's really fueling our
doubt without this turning into yet another like big giant project but a
gentle inquiry like dropping in the question opening up to the question and
then feeling into the answer so not so much like thinking our way to the answer
of course thinking is involved but feeling our way to the answer right we
don't want to just create the conditions in which we're just thinking thinking thinking wondering wondering wondering trying to figure it out but can we do an
inquiry in which we can feel our way we can drop in a
question and then open up and listen for an answer so that's one an antidote is to
investigate another antidote is to openly inquire to ask ourselves what do
I have confidence in what do I know about this practice
what do I know about what I'm capable of doing I have sat here during a
meditation period before this practice has brought some
subtleness some ease some insights I have heard things from a
teacher that really resonated with me and made a difference I do know people who are
Buddhist practitioners who seem to be moving in the world without causing harm to others
or not very much harm so we might just spend a little time reflecting what do I have
confidence in kind of like interrupt this vacillation and what do we know from our
experience what is uplifting what can support us maybe we know that meditation
sessions don't end necessarily the way they begin so if we find ourselves
caught in this vacillation or hesitation doesn't mean that we're going to have it for the whole rest of the period
meditation session
another way to work with doubt is to called apply what's called wise
attention yanis so Manas Sakara is the poly for this I say those words because
I just like the way that they sound and the Buddha talks about this this is what
the Buddha says as an antidote for doubt there's an excerpt from
auta and the Buddha says there are things that are the basis for
doubt frequently giving careless attention is the nutriment for the
arising of unrisen doubt and for the increase of
and expansion of doubt that has arisen so careless attention gives rise to doubt and if
Doubt's already there careless attention makes there be more doubt
and then continues and what is the den nourishment you know it's kind of a
clunky translation if we're going to say what is the nourishment of uh doubt in
poly it's just uh the opposite of nourishment so this translator is doing Den nourishment if we were say the word
starvation that just I don't know to my ear sounds cruel or something so we'll
use this word Den nourishment and what so the Buddha continues in the
suta and what is the den nourishment that prevents doubt from arising and
when doubt has already Arisen um prevents it from increasing and
expanding there are wholesome and UNH wholesome states there are blamable and blameless
states there are inferior and Superior states there are dark and bright St
States frequently giving careful attention to these is the den
nourishment that prevents doubt from arising and if doubt has already Arisen
to prevent doubt from increasing and expanding so recognizing oh wholesome
and UNH wholesome cusa and ausa helpful and unhelpful blamable and
blameless inferior and Superior dark and bright so to help so wise attention is
to bring in what we know from our practice from our lives like oh yeah this is helpful this isn't helpful to
use some discernment to pay attention to those things
that are a support for practice if we are having feeling greedy
or a lot of Desire or something that's um and that's getting in the way of our
practice in our life we don't spend all our time looking at photos of those
things that we want we don't uh spend
imagining all those things that we want we don't like fuel the desire by always
bringing the objects of desire to mind or in the visual field or hearing them or whatever so why is attention is to
pay attention to what's supportive for us and to bring in mind what do we know
from the teachings that we have confidence in about what's wise and what's not wise
what's helpful and what's not helpful and then if we still if we have
paid attention to the experience of this vacillation and hesitation we've brought
in antidotes and we still find oursel completely caught up and filled with
doubt one uh thing that we might do is to do something for somebody
else be generous with words [Music]
actions effort help somebody else do something for somebody else and in this
way it can help really soften and interrupt this kind of vacillation that we find ourselves El in and then it just
creates the conditions for something else to unfold if we were to do something for
somebody else so doubt is can be really pernicious it
can undermine our entire practice but there's a way in which we can be with it
and we can turn it instead of being an obstacle it can just be the object of
practice right instead of being a roadblock it can be a stepping stone to
just further practice it doesn't have to be a problem we can practice with
it in this way as we learn to practice with whatever
arising and this way can we be practice in such a way that it's a benefit for
ourselves and a benefit for others thank you