so good day everyone and welcome to this meditation session
and one of the functions of buddhist meditation
is to place ourselves
squarely fully into the vibrant
and dynamic pulsing [Music]
experience of life of being alive that um
all the sensations that you experience whatever they might be pleasant or
unpleasant they come and they go they're dynamic they vibrate they are
flashing in and out of existence moment by moment
that all the experiences sensations that you have you have because you're alive once
you're dead your body is no longer energized or
animated with the whatever the life force is within us
there are no sensations whatsoever and um and the sensations we experience
are proof of the living livingness in us the dynamic and
active quality of the natural world the energies of the natural world that
how they flow through us and manifest in us and so to sit in
the middle of our body and with anapanasati and to be able to be
centered unified collected
liberated from distractions and really he be here to feel and sense and
be intimate with the dynamism of change dynamism of the
the coming and going appearing and disappearing of phenomena everything to be called
experience in a certain way what it doesn't change
are concepts platonic concepts of things which their ideas of
them which stay constant ideas of self ideas of others ideas of what has
happened to us and even some kind of funny way what will happen to us these ideas give the semblance that
things are continuous maybe in some things are in certain kind of way
but to drop into the flow of experience
to the direct direct immediate perception knowing experiencing
of life as it flows in that little window little kind of
where they vast past and vast future of you know coming and going
we have this idea i think in in english sometimes that we're moving into the future and i think
in ancient india they had the idea more the idea that the future was coming towards us
in this river of you know just time just flows and when and we know the future
only in the experience as it becomes the present and as we know it it already vanishes
there's something about the immediacy it already vanishes here
so assuming a meditation posture a posture to
embody inhabit the lived experience of the moment
and perhaps to close your eyes in order to
be inside to sense and feel inside your life
your body sometimes with the eyes open we're looking at things externally and pulled into the external
world the eyes closed the idea is to
come into this intimate world of our physical embodied experience
in the immediacy of here
and to gently maybe lovingly kindly slowly take some deeper breaths
maybe three quarters full
taking deeper breaths so slow and careful enough that you almost like you're savoring and enjoying
this the feelings in your body of the chest expanding the belly expanding
and then a longer exhale than usual not so much maybe that you're forcing
the air out but you let go you release
the muscles around your diaphragm your chest so that the exhale extends itself
as you have these long exhales also relax other parts of your body
relaxing into your body
and then again lovingly gently
allow your breathing to return to normal without the need for any
clear idea of what normal is just allow your breathing to breathe
itself
and also continue this relaxing softening the face
softening the shoulders
releasing the belly
and somehow maybe even releasing all the holding the global holding of the body
holding it all together no need to in meditation
to relax release
releasing into this body to feel and sense
the immediacy of our lived life
the experience of sensations
and then kindly gently maybe even tenderly
and determinedly center yourself on the experience of
breathing
breathing is often taken as a sign of being alive
and the inconstant shifting changing sensations of breathing
sensations of breathing in are different than breathing out
sensations of breathing in disappear so that sensations of exhale can begin
and vice versa
regardless of how pleasant or unpleasant your breathing is
to feel it and experience it to center yourself in it
is to enter into the intimacy and of being really here with our lived life
and then as you're with your breathing and maybe that's mostly what you do
to feel the inconstancy of all the sensations that flow through that appear and disappear
and perhaps as you do so you relax and open all everything around
the breathing perhaps as they just get more and more
intimate there will be some experience that everything
is shifting changing arising disappearing
in the immediacy of how they are felt and experienced
if we recede into thoughts and ideas of things
we begin projecting ideas of constancy and
permanence but as a thinking mind gets quieter
we just feel and sense experience
breathing in and breathing out
with all the inconstancy of things coming and going
the experience of thinking if we intimate with the actual
experience thoughts are also inconstant they come
and they go rather than being involved in thoughts
to settle further in and just see thoughts as
arising and passing coming and going
individual words or images that appear come and they go
in the intimacy of the moment everything
is part of a field of appearing and disappearing phenomenon
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
there's something about being at rest
in the middle of change settling back as if we're sitting in an
easy chair allowing everything to
move and change and peer and disappear
freely without us interfering with them
feeling safe and comfortable just letting the things everything come
and go everything
it can be uncomfortable to do this but it also can open up
the barriers to feeling tender love and kindness
to feel compassion care
for this changing buzzing flowing world
because what that gets in the way of our love is something we're holding on to
something that we are that blocks or covers over
but when everything is buzzing and changing and but we're at rest with awareness
there can be a greater capacity for compassion for all this
to be still and gaze upon everything kindly
to be still in the middle of all the
change and to feel compassion for
the challenges that everyone has in this changing world
to feel the joy budita that because things change things also
get better for people
and because we're not holding on to anything there can be kindness
may all beings be free of suffering
may all beings celebrate
their capacity for freedom
may all beings live in a world of kindness and friendliness
may all beings be the kind and friendly ones
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings contribute to the peacefulness of this world
may all beings be free and may all beings
support the freedom of others
may we all share in love and kindness and friendliness
in living this buzzing changing
impermanent life that we find ourselves in
so in this process of anapanasati
mindfulness of breathing in mindfulness of breathing out we've come to the core
heart of it the insight aspect of it
and and the purpose of insight is to liberate us to free us
and it involves a very clear centering ourselves in the core
dynamism core aspect of how this life is
and all the steps before in a sense are preparing us
and preparing us and i don't want to
i want to emphasize how important this preparation is
certainly preparation for what we're doing in the last steps but
what we're doing the last steps is also preparing ourselves or our willingness to meet this world as it
is the ability to really be in this suffering world
and to be prepared for that to have really developed the qualities of
attention and concentration and persistence and and and well-being and
purified ourselves got to work through some of the hindrances all the hindrances work through our
are the attitudes and the
places where where we kind of can you need to be healed
and and settled and this is a beautiful and
profound process and we need this for it to be available to be available to care for the suffering world
and so then we come to this 13th step where we're experiencing
um observing impermanence or in constancy
and this has um three different aspects that things are changing and inconstant one is there
is loss things disappear but also the very fact
that things change allows for new beginnings
the fall gives birth to the winter the winter bring gives birth to the spring things pass away in the fall die
away and then get reborn in the spring and now we need this cycle is what we need
and so we live in a world of tremendous suffering and uh so much that we've experienced in
the news now for so long and you know the amount of hate that
gets expressed in violence and killing is astounding
and and it's been going on since the time of the buddha
and so how do we address this how do we meet this and so anapanasati is this beautiful
practice of profound practice maybe i shouldn't use beautiful in this context but
profound helpful and healing practice that just to stay the stay constant within
constancy of breathing the rhythm of breathing frees us from this the
contractions the resistance the fears the preoccupations the distractions of
the mind it allows something to uh be settled and and to be
come into kind of harmony and ease that allows for the self-healing
qualities of this human body and heart to operate it makes room for some of the
most beautiful qualities of who we are to surface and come forward
and so to really be able to dip into the inconstancy and the changing nature of it is to have a
direct confrontation with what's most difficult with human life but also with what's most
wonderful and healing in this human life as well and and because things have changed not
only is it filters loss and there's also the disappearing of things which are
not useful or that are that are painful and difficult suffering disappears as well and so part
of the inconstancy and the changing and permanent nature of all this is a rich rich world of so many things
that we enter into sometimes simultaneously where there is loss but with loss
there's also gain we or in the sense that we also lose our suffering at times
um and uh with the new arising of things appearing of things some things that
appear are not good but also there's possibility of good things and then the teachings of the
buddha to really see and feel and be in this current of change gives us some agency
to shape how we experience and how we are in this world and we certainly can't
change the world dramatically most of us but we can't change our immediate world we can't
change ourselves and the practice has a lot to do with
with understanding change and finding a way to harmonize
with it and work with it so that we cultivate ourselves we develop ourselves
to become better people so to prepare ourselves for this world so that we have resiliency we
have openheartedness we have non-clinging we have non-hostility
it's a it's a powerful thing to uh you know to work with
the changing nature of this world in the in vipassana practice we're working with that changing nature
of the world all the time but it's not all often emphasized but now on this thirteenth step of
anapanasati this is the part of the world that we're really working with this is the
we're entering into this flow and the change and um it's easy it may be easy to at
least for a teacher to say what i'm about to say but maybe much more difficult to do it and that is
that to really enter into this this part of what the buddha was emphasizing to really
to really observe in constancy means that we're no longer in the sway
or caught in or seeing the reality through the lens of our concepts and
ideas our stories uh and all the
those also are part of the inconstant world the changing world and and stories come and go they arise
and they pass there's all this change and flow and movement in the story making mind and the concept
concept making mind everything is flowing and changing and so
how do we really get to really get into that and really rest in it the buddha taught
that because it's liberating that's where freedom is found and it's a
the core insight of the buddhist teachings uh over and over again is to see in
constancy is to see change is to see
maybe we can say the word impermanence and um and uh it represented by
a number of things kind of the first person who was enlightened
after the buddha was hearing the buddhist teachings exclaimed kind of proclaimed his awakening with the
statement everything that has the nature to arise has the nature to pass away
everything that arises passes away the buddha explained that everything is
inconstant everything that is an experience
concepts might not be and the ancient greeks you know had a lot of
controversy debates about the nature of impermanence and change and constancy in this world it's a common topic for
philosophers and the famous philosopher plato wasn't that comfortable with that everything was changing and he
wanted to have something that was permanent and i believe a little bit i know about him that he settled on the said he has
platonic concepts there's ideas that are unchanging
but the ideas are not direct experience and the buddha over and over again was placing ourselves in direct experience
breathing with it being mindful of it feeling it and really entering into this
inconstant world to know it because that is the way to freedom so i
said the first person was enlightened said that everything has everything that has a nature to arise is
a nature of passing away there's something about that insight that was liberating
the when the buddha died the the final statement that
the first statement i believe one of the first statements someone said when he died it became kind of the funeral chant for buddhists
it also became it's said to be the the um the sayings or the afrom the saying
the the saying of the our heart saying of the fully enlightened one
and it goes to chant in pali it's anitcha what the song
all things are inconstant they have the nature of arising and passing away
those who see deeply into this truth experience happiness
so but the happiness not of you know being totally delighted and
happy all the time but a deeper happiness or contentment or satisfaction or
intimacy or something that we are in touch with what is real
in this real world of ours so even if we this world is full of suffering which it
is and the violence against the asian americans likely and
the shootings and so many places in this country but most recently
in boulder is um
you can't say we're happy in the relationship to that but there can be a feeling of rightness
that yes if this happens in the world we want to be present for it we want to
know it we want to it's right to be aware of it even if it's painful
even if it's what touches some of the deepest strings in our hearts but to have the capacity that's if this
is what's happening yes let's be present for it let's breathe with it
and all the steps of anapanasati can be relevant for this feeling that pain but to feel the pain
is not the same as i feel suffering and this freedom of this practice the
rightness of this practice to feel this world be present to this world without suffering but willingly feeling
the pain of this world so that we can also have compassion for
it and care so we prepare ourselves for all that what this world has to offer
so that we can offer ourselves as someone who is loving compassionate caring
and that we live in this world in a way that supports the betterment of all beings
out everywhere may all beings everywhere
be free thank you