okay so hello and welcome everyone
ah it's nice to be with you in the hellos and greetings that we do
[Music] before i turn on the recording is are always are always heartwarming really
heartwarming to me and really a nice way to just start landing with meta for
ourselves and each other i see many of you also nodding and smiling yep it's supportive coming we come together in
community in this practice in this international
community different time zones countries
so so for today's practice i'd like to invite us
to to consider the importance of mindfulness of the
body with meta so mindfulness of the body
is a primary practice it's actually a foundational practice
in in this practice of ours and if you have noticed if you've been coming to happier for a while
we always start the first you know third of the time usually quarter of the time third of the time of
the guided meditation is usually grounding in the body with the breath so we always start there and
then we open up to [Music] the practice that we're practicing for
the day if it's meta compassion gratitude whatever it might be so so if you've noticed
very happy are already this practice of the body is foundational it's really foundational
so today i want to bring it even more to the forefront in the way of how important it is
for establishing meta but we'll actually approach it a little differently today
the body as the basis the body being infused with meta permeating meta the
sense of whole bodiness whole bodiness you know we're familiar with the term wholeheartedness
so whole bodiness sort of mindful body fall so really
bringing our awareness infusing the body with meta this body this being who is me
being infused with care with affection with friendliness
and also it it permeating it's shining out
again many times i've talked about the statue of one mudra of the buddha is the mudra
of touching the earth the buddha touching the earth as earth be my witness i belong here
sense of embodiment embodiment connecting with the body
connecting with the body important all practices especially in meta
to connect with the body as much as possible as much as available as much as it feels safe
and having said this for some people if there is a history of trauma it might
be more appropriate to connect with the hands and feet that is the connection with the body
so if connecting with the whole body is not available that's perfectly okay
don't push it please no pushing no struggling no shoulding
the practice of meta these are just invitation it's just
invitations to consider as we come together in community
so that's the frame for our practice today
so with that frame i invite us ah to land in our bodies and notice what
your body needs if you need to move to shift as we start our form or meditation
if you need to move to a lying position that's okay if that's your body needs
see how your body can be particularly comfortable for meta it's really important for the body to be comfortable
so be kind be kind to this body especially today
given that that is the theme kind to this body
so
creating this body this breath
reading this amazing body this amazing body
that breathes that knows how to
take care of itself internally digest
the heart knows how to be [Music] cuts know how to heal
it's amazing that's amazing
nature that is this body connecting with
appreciation
devoting as if you were giving a gift of your awareness gifting your awareness
to your body the sensations
for this period of practice devoting as if you're honoring this
precious sacred by giving your entire attention to it
with all with interest movement the sensations of breathing
and notice if there is any forcing or trying too hard if you notice any of
that ah shake it off let it go
not knead it relax
when we give a gift to someone we don't force or push the gift upon them
it's an offering so offering your awareness gently lovingly
relaxedly
as if your awareness is hanging out chilling
spending time with a good friend the body hey potty have you been
how are ya oh how are your toes feeling the bottom
of your feet dear friend
awareness awareness greeting the body
sit bones
your bottom on the cushion
all the areas of contact
let this greeting awareness greeting the body internally
the sensations of the breath different parts let it be joyful
too old good friends meeting
delighting in each other
even if there is pain discomfort in the body that's okay awareness
is not phased awareness can be spacious
knowing the discomfort and all the space around it too
a patient patient friend holding space and presence
an awareness awareness
that is patient
with the body and patience
is an expression of meta of love of care
awareness that doesn't want to rush away
spaciously greets whatever is arising
the breath sensations in the body
pleasant unpleasant
or neutral
an awareness that infuses infuses the whole body
permeates the whole body
with kindness kind awareness that infuses the whole
body the body can relax
and be held in it also
awareness holding the body
gently cradling it
the body can release itself into this kind awareness
release any holding any tightness
any pain sorrow for this kind awareness
holding simply knowing
caringly knowing
the body infused with this kind non-judgmental
[Music] caring [Music] warm-hearted
knowing as if a golden light
or whatever imagery or felt sense
works for you
sitting in kindness breathing kindness
kindness knowing itself
awareness knowing itself through the body
sensations of the body
kind awareness infusing the body
with care the body can relax
ah
feeling held
you feel like you can continue with menta for the body
for the self if you wish
you can also
allow this sense of good will
this kindness kind awareness that's infusing the body
to permeate to shine out
this bright golden light pushing
not trying to let it shine not trying to make it shine
but allowing this kindness to just gently permeate out
embracing this slight embracing those who are near and dear to you first
your dear beings
this light shining upon their bodies with good will
with care
and if phrases help you're welcome to use the phrases
neither may i be well or may you be well or any variations thereof
i be infused with well-being
may i feel infused held in well-being
may you be held may you be infused
with well-being
may we both be infused
holding being held and well-being
if your visual may be the golden light is permeating
you and your dear being or beings
with care and good will
and for the last moments of this practice period
letting your goodness of meta
bright light shine brightly
trusting there is goodness and goodness cultivated generated from
our practice together
may this goodness or attempt our effort towards cultivation even if
mindful or meta-filled for a split second
and the rest was distracted or sleepy doesn't matter doesn't matter you showed up
you tried letting go of self-judgment if any appreciating that you've showed up
you've tried you've practiced you've planted seeds
and sharing offering this goodness
to all beings everywhere generously
may the efforts of my life
may my life my work my efforts
serve others be of service in ways i may not be able to imagine
serve others in goodness may all beings
be well may all beings be free
thank you for your practice everyone
ah so
we have some time for reflections for thoughts for questions
and i changed the settings in chat you're welcome to uh type
your questions or reflections in chat if it's typed to everyone i'll read your name
if it's just to me i'll only read the reflection not your name i'll be private can also raise your
hand to share your questions reflections and please know
that when you share what you discovered whether something was challenging or or
a new insight showed up or something opened up you're offering
this gift to serve other practitioners it's of service to others so
so you're welcome i'll pause for a moment
maybe as i'm pausing
and one reflection there wasn't much warmth but space for me
great great um and sometimes there may not but warmth
may not be sense it's okay but if there is space for things to be held
a patient space for things to be held that is as good as
meta you know when we're patient like it can be it's okay this pain doesn't need to go away be pushed away there's space
for it to be held monica says there came a point where
sensations of the body arose seem to be manifestations of kindness
inseparable from kind awareness just another form lovely thank you for sharing that
reflection that's beautiful yeah and any of you are welcome to raise your hands
claire says thanks for a very healing experience thank you claire i see abrahams hand us up please abraham
thanks um uh it was so nice to offer my body
loving kindness my body has been the basis for me having so many rich
experiences of meditation and just to turn it around and say thank you buddy
the body is such a refuge so i appreciate it thank you abraham i so appreciate
your rich and beautiful reflection indeed
body such a refuge and to turn it around beautiful thank you
deborah says it was nice to just be kindly with my body this way
beautiful beautiful larry says i saw clearly the part of me
that is frightened to speak in a setting like this and give it some love ah
not quite ready to talk but it felt like a movement beautiful beautiful thank you
so much for sharing that yeah and so wonderful to see those part
of ourselves that are frightened and hold them with love and i see others are
are choosing the light the the love
emoticon here larry really appreciating what you shared really appreciating
giving love to those parts of ourselves that are afraid which we up often take a little whip and whip them up right like
oh you shouldn't be here so thank you so much that's beautiful thank you so much for sharing that
to be with you mark yeah
any other reflections before we turn to
practice small groups i'll share one thing and and
i'll say that for me um this was quite a lovely practice too because as i
guide the guided meditation probably you know by now that i'm doing it myself i'm
not just a talking head i'm actually guiding from where i am from my own
experience and
and again this also to say that you know we co-create this space together this
practice together i am here because of you well you may think you're here because of me but i'm
here because of you so thank you for showing up and practicing and to say that for me as today i
i was experiencing a lot of pain oh it was just so lovely to hold all of
the discomfort with just kind kind easy
uh there's a sense of well-being well-being for me that really bubbled up
the pain this discomfort can be here the well-being can be here too the
kindness holding both kindness really holding both doesn't have to push
the discomfort away so
yeah thank you patricia deeply grateful for sharing this beautiful practice with you
all thank you yeah it's sweet and hugh says this little
light of mine i'm gonna let it shine yes please you by all means
that's great so he is joining on youtube tonight so
so dear ones yeah i love that it's the sense of this light of meta this light
of meta letting it shine both for ourselves touching hitting this body first as it's
shining out and then others so with that with this letting our light
shine the invitation now is to hold each other's light and shining
it with small groups holding ourselves with kindness holding each other with kindness we all have bodies we all have
discomfort we all have joys as abraham said our bodies are nourishing sources of refuge for many
meditative experiences that the body supports not only physical experiences walking outside and feeding ourselves
and all of that so so we turn to small groups of size roughly three
and the first 15 seconds so let's start with
the silent meta for our bodies and other people's bodies which may be hurting or not who
knows we all have bodies and then you can share as little or as much as
you like about your practice supporting each other it's really about listening and
sharing and supporting so here we go take care of yourselves take
care of each other in the small groups here we go
and everyone's back welcome back everyone so
we have a couple of minutes for any reflections that might have arisen from
your group practice small sangha practice and you can raise your hand your zoom
hand if it's a physical hand i won't see you but the zoom hand i will see or you can
type in chat please any reflections anything you noticed about
this particular way of practicing for you
the violet says someone in our group reflected at the end how easy it is now during practice to
call to mind the faces and names of people in the sangha we've been with for
a while yeah that is so sweet
thanks for sharing that violet yeah this sangha has been going
strong for over a year now we started when
uh we started last year was it march i think march or april we went online when
everything closed down in california so oh yeah so sweet so sweet thanks for
sharing that violet as i've said once sometimes i think of
you know there's some of you might be familiar with this old uh
american um series it's called cheers and uh
the their their tagline was you know there was it was about a bar we were where everybody knows your name you go
there because everybody knows your name and that's that's really why you go and you so anyway so but here we practice
cultivating our hearts what a beautiful thing to do together what a beautiful thing to do together dear sangha
mary please hi
um i've been away for a month and um hoped that i would
you know join in from the distances where i was but that just wasn't possible it just
didn't seem possible and here i am back and it's just so wonderful thank you
and kept it going in my while i was away but it's so wonderful to
to see faces familiar and new thank you yeah thank you mary
thanks welcome back and and welcome to everyone new old old
new it's we'd love new folks coming and joining our sangha this
is absolutely lovely deborah says this is my first visit to the happy hour live and i look forward
to more i attend gil's morning sessions and we connect on the youtube but it's a
much lighter connection oh yes absolutely welcome deborah lovely to have you here
yeah beautiful wonderful to to have you here so
so dear ones we have come to the end of another happy hour together
thank you for your practice may ah our cultivation together be a cause and
condition for goodness in the world may all beings be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves [Music]
thank you