so welcome to this meditation session
and a valuable perspective on mindfulness meditation
is that it is the enactment of freedom
where expressing in in mental action our capacity to be free
so when we decide to be mindful of something something as simple as mindful of the breathing we are making a choice
when the mind wanders off in thought and you're mindful enough to and
choose to be mindful rather than wandering off in thought when you're mindful enough to choose
beginning again with your breathing that's an expression of freedom to
choose what often happens is that
we will what comes along with that choice and which obscures the freedom is ideas
that i didn't do it well enough i need to do it better i should try harder i should
strain push make more effort all these uh you know that i'm a lousy
meditator or someone else is doing it better than me or the real thing is something different
and all these ideas and all these get carried along and all these shoulds
get carried along and obscures the fact that for one little moment
there was an ex an enactment of freedom the freedom to of where our attention
can be focused and uh and we and so to appreciate that
moment that initial moment that moment that's independent and free of all the thoughts
agendas fears that we might have all the ideas of self
that kind of come along with it obscures the fact that we have just
enacted a small little moment of freedom
and if then we choose to investigate to explore to look
more closely at the experience they're also
it's an enactment of freedom it's a freedom from our preoccupations
from all our judgments and reactivity
so to be first to be mindful is a little freedom from preoccupation from being
pulled into a world where we're trapped or not free
of thoughts ideas fantasies judgments just simple be mindful of this
that freedom is enacted a little bit more strongly in the initial moment we decide to look
more carefully and that's often obscured the freedom because
we think that we have to be successful there's it's an exam and we're gonna get it tested if we you
know how well we discover what we're gonna what's there and there's some magic key that we have to see and
and i have to really strain now and look and analyze and all these other ideas that obscure
the simplicity of the moment of looking more carefully looking what is this that's an enactment of
freedom and as we see more clearly the choices we make become
an enactment of freedom the choice not to strain as we look at our
breathing as we meditate on breathing the choice to
turn our attention from the breath to look at how we're being critical of ourselves
in the criticalness lost in that there's no freedom but in the moment of turning around to
look at it a choice to look at it rather than just going along with it is also
an enactment of freedom to see what is helpful and not helpful healthy and not healthy
and to choose the healthy is an enactment of freedom
and so to begin appreciating no the little hints the little hints of freedom in
mindfulness investigation in effort
and as we appreciate it we can that appreciation
is a pleasure that appreciation can be
can give rise to a contentment oh this is the path to freedom
i'm on a good i'm discovering something helpful here
they can give rise to joy the joy of freely
being aware of our experience
and then there can be even affection for the difficult things because we're
aware of them with our freedom
so as these seven factors awakening develop first they develop as little hints
little as little intuitions of how they're there but as we do this meditation perhaps you
can sit here now with an intuition the hints a recognition
of how you enact freedom in choosing to be mindful investigate
make effort and the freedom that's found before all
the complexities we bring to those things in their simplicity
so to sit to assume your meditation posture
and some of you probably didn't recognize that in assuming your posture you were expressing your freedom
there is a choice free will choice to now adjust your posture
take a posture
and then to gently close your eyes
and as you're sitting here with the eyes closed
what is the simplest freest way that you can allow yourself to be aware
of your body
a choice a free will choice if you want to take it
to become aware of how your body is right now
before preferences before likes and dislikes
just aware
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
as you exhale relax into the posture
deep breath in exhale relax the whole body as if the posture
relaxing is a homecoming to this posture
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale softening the muscles of your forehead
and temple and if they don't soften or relax
maybe you can the awareness of it can be spacious and open
as you exhale softening around the eyes
the cheeks
the jaws
as you exhale maybe there can be a relaxation and opening
in this the back of your neck the vertebrae just below the skull
can they soften and relax
softening as you exhale around the
collarbones
and then releasing the shoulders
as you exhale relaxing the chest
the heart center
and then softening the belly
in the lower half of your torso
lower back the hip area hip joints
and down your legs
and then gently calmly
become mindful of your breathing
and can you as you're mindful of breathing
feel or perceive how the choice to do so
if it's your own is it small little enactment of freedom
freedom from the tyranny of thinking just mindful for a moment
receptive to the inhalation receptive to the movements of the body
as you breathe in
and is there some way that that simple receptive awareness
have qualities of freedom independence
for a few moments maybe awareness free of being hijacked by thoughts and
ideas and judgments
simple awareness receptive to breathing
as you exhale allowing the exhale and allowing awareness
is there some freedom and awareness that is so simple it just allows the
experience to be there
even if you are thinking and judging
maybe part of the awareness of breathing can feel like there's freedom there
a silent freedom spacious open
and very gently exploring the experience of breathing
feeling it more fully more clearly not dramatically so just a little more
and in that choice to explore and feel it more fully
there's also an enactment of freedom
enactment to be aware rather than being pulled into thinking
and if you find yourself thinking and you choose to begin again with your
breathing
that's an enactment of effort which might also contain
some freedom freedom of choice freedom of where your effort is placed
if while you're inhaling you choose to be with the inhale
but then when you exhale the choice becomes to be with the exhale
it's a simple enactment of liberated
effort
into whatever degree however small
you can feel that your practice enacts
freedom even if you keep getting caught and
thought and preoccupied in it
even so is there some little corner of awareness of effort
will you feel your freedom
and to appreciate that to feel the pleasure of that
maybe even the joy of that
appreciating our freedom is also an enactment of freedom
feeling the joy
of liberated mindfulness
and then it doesn't matter so much what we're mindful of
because we delight in mindfulness itself
we delight in investigation there's a delight in this effort or
choice that has qualities of freedom in it
and there's freedom in enjoying
the joy of freedom as we practice mindfulness
no matter what we're mindful of there can be a delight
in that freedom
if you find yourself caught up in thought or caught up in anything
if you allow yourself to clearly know that that's the case
there is some quality of freedom in that clear knowing
see if you can build on that freedom expand that freedom
by doing it again and again
in the last 10 minutes of this sitting perhaps you can feel your way
to stay close to where you're free
the freedom which is closely related to simplicity of being
nothing complicated
recognizing the simple freedom in choosing to be
aware the simple freedom in seeing what's
happening the freedom to en to appreciate to enjoy
the simplicity of being that's related
to our freedom
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
imagine what it's like for what would be like for you
to be resting in the simplicity of being
resting in a freedom of being
where you're not caught up in your reactions your judgments your criticalness
not cut up in the shoulds and shouldn'ts sense of obligations and
just resting in simple freedom where you're allowed to be free you're
allowed to be simple and present
and in this way imagine that you encounter another person
who's also free a person who has no agendas and has no
needs at the moment is not living in their judgments or
preferences likes and dislikes
this person is also at rest at ease in their own simplicity of being
at ease in their freedom
and to sit with this person you and your freedom and they and their
freedom
a freedom where it makes it safe to have good will love care
friendliness for the other
and perhaps you can open your heart safely fully
a meeting of hearts each of you independent and free
without any need from the other content to sit with each other
appreciating each other
and how much can you open your heart your good will your friendliness in this
circumstance and now imagine that you can do that
with others who are not so free people who come with agendas and
preferences and needs imagine that you can rest in your
simplicity of being even then
and without them necessarily knowing
to continue with your good will your friendliness
choosing freely choosing
goodwill and may it be that we learn
through this practice to open our good will to all beings
equally while being rooted in our capacity for
freedom freedom that allows us to return to a
simplicity of being
so that we might genuinely feel and think may it be that all beings be happy
may it be that all beings be safe
may it be that all beings be peaceful
may it be that all beings be free
and may i in my capacity for freedom
help make this possible at least radiating for me
comes good will and safety for others
may all beings be happy
continuing on this series of the seven factors of awakening
the factor for today is joy
and joy is the particular joy that's a factor of awakening
is really a product of doing the practice of mindfulness so it's not a
joy that comes from reflection and that wonderful things are happening to us in the world
it's really a joy that rises out of the practice doing the practice really engaging in
the practice in a kind of sincere wholehearted way
and i'd like to think of this joy as being also a expression or enactment or
manifestation of our freedom that grows as we do the practice of
mindfulness and that these seven factors of awakening all can be seen as
enactments of freedom and rather than waiting for freedom to
occur in a big bang of enlightenment down the road if we just huff and puff
and get concentrated enough and still enough and then eventually maybe by magic there'll be a big aha
moment or a big transformation moment boom and now you live happily free
for the rest of your life you have it made in enlightened retirement
it's much more i think valuable to appreciate that we're beginning to move
we're taking a seed a a little of freedom the potential for freedom
inside of us and germinating it caring for it carefully in the greenhouse
tending to it carefully transplanting it out into the world
and letting it grow and develop and and mature into something into freedom full freedom
because then we're beginning to take a little bit more responsibility for this freedom thing ourselves rather than thinking that you
know something else is going to do it for me and so these lit beginning to tune
recognize little movements of freedom that we all use all day long in fact i would
venture to guess that most of us have more moments of freedom through the
day than non-freedom but the reason we don't
feel like we're free is that we prioritize our our attention we let our attention prioritize or focus
on the ways that we're unhappy or the ways of what we want
what we don't want we get swept up into the world of thinking
where in the thinking there's not much freedom more often than not for people we're
kind of hijacked by our thoughts our concerns our fears our desires
and so it might seem that in the important ways psychological ways that we're not free
but there are plenty of ways that we are free
when you if you sit down in a chair you have a fair amount of freedom about
how you adjust yourself into that chair and you probably never really gave me
much thought to how you sat in the chair and how you adjust your yourself to be comfortable
but that movement of sitting down and choosing how you sit in the chair
is an expression is a manifestation of some freedom
reaching forward to open your front door is an expression of freedom that you can
do that there are people who can't do that for all kinds of reasons
there's lots of little moments of where you choose to do something and there's a freedom in doing it
as we start doing mindfulness practice to begin recognizing how mindfulness itself
can be an enactment of freedom and that's hard to do if mindfulness is
burdened by shoulds and shouldn'ts and gotta do better and supposed to get somewhere and
am i there yet then i'm not a good meditator and someone else is a better meditator or
i'm supposed to bear down and really strain and what's important they say is continuity
of mindfulness so i'm really gonna when i'm mindful i'm just just gonna be mindful i'm gonna you know really push and make strong
effort you know and really strain so all this extra stuff comes along with mindfulness
a moment of mindfulness is something is phenomenally simple
and if just just to know in the moment what's happening and in fact you have many of these
moments throughout the day where you know something without the burden of anything more thing more
complicated than knowing that it's doing there chances that you open that door
half the time at least when you open the door you just know you something inside of you no it's a door
no it's a door handle and it's not anything more complicated than that
you're not comparing your door handle to your neighbor's door handle and who has the better door handle and
i should have a better door handle it's just a door handle
but the practice of mindfulness is also the practice of appreciating
that simplicity of awareness in the moment
and seeing can feel an enactment of freedom there's freedom in that knowing before
all the extra stuff is added on top of it and then the ch the freedom to choose
to investigate as soon as you choose to investigate to look more carefully to recognize more carefully what's here
you're not being swept off in your thoughts you know it's being swept off in your
agendas desires wishes there is it's a little movement i'm choosing not
to be the old way i'm choosing to take a better look to give a second look to what's
happening and that's enactment enactment of freedom
effort being having to do with choices choosing the endeavor which is more healthy for us
as soon as we make a choice towards health towards skillfulness to wholesomeness we're enacting our freedom
as i keep saying we don't recognize it so much because many of us carry with us this
huge huge huge backpack everywhere we go of shoulds and
desires and agendas and self-concepts and self-criticism and aversion and all this
stuff that we carry along and so we don't because of that heavy backpack we don't recognize
the ease and simplicity and freedom in these choices to move in the healthy direction
so part of this practice is begin recognizing something that's probably there in to
some degree all along the enactment of freedom the expression
of it and that brings us to joy
the word joy is pity p-i-t-i and it means uh usually translates joy
sometimes as ecstasy sometimes as rapture but that's a particular theravada slant
on this or a meditation slant on this word pity it could also mean pleasure it can mean delight
enjoyment in sanskrit the pretty the sanskrit word can also
mean friendliness and pleasure and affection
which i think begins showing that it's a it's an emotional quality sometimes pure you know it's in
we're tapping into an emotional connection to the practice and to being free and what's being present
that comes from a kind of an emotional contentment i contentment i'm doing a practice i'm
practicing a path of freedom this is worthwhile this is a
healthy thing to be doing and we're enacting the freedom which
feels so good to feel like we're not
entangled trapped caught in things because the awareness the mind has
become free in the enactment of these freedoms and so the continuity of this free act of
mindfulness the continuity of mindfulness of concentration tends to give birth to
a variety of different kinds of contentment joys happinesses
and there's different all kinds of different types but some of it is simply like it's like
if you go to if you slide down a long long slide there is a joy of that freedom of just
letting go and going and it's just a delight
so the same way if you can have the continuity of these moments of freedom
continuity of choosing and engaging and being mindful and aware there's a feeling that oh
we'll start getting a more taste for that freedom and it feels like not necessarily a slide but
the same kind of the continuity gives birth to a joy and delight and boy am i lucky this is a great thing
it's not so evil it's not so much we evaluate that we you know it's not like we thinkers think our way into that
but there's a delight a joy a gladness just in the in the freshness in the
you know it used to be in the united states there was a reference point to the joy
of driving on an empty open freeway open highway
you know we don't think we'd be forgotten what that is like but this you know this joy this open
you know free free highway of meditation of practice and the the amazing thing about this is
that then it doesn't matter as much whether what's happening to us is
pleasant and unpleasant because we discover how to be free and then be mindful aware
investigate make healthy choices this inner freedom is discovered even when
things are unpleasant even when things are in the world around us are not so
good and what an amazing thing to have discovered
that because we know how to be mindful because we know how to investigate and make choices and appreciate that we're
doing this there can even be joy and delight when conventionally when the world expects us
or even our people in our people want us to be miserable you're supposed to be miserable when i'm
miserable so you're supposed to be miserable we're supposed to commiserate in our commune in our
miserableness isn't it terrible things are awful
so what happens as we start moving through these factors of awakening and when i say what i'm about to say you
might decide to get off the factors awakening path because what happens is when you get far enough along
it you won't be inclined to complain anymore
because you have something much much better to do much more wonderful to do the enactment
of your freedom through mindfulness investigation effort endeavoring and
and this wonderful joy of freedom may you find that complain free zone of
freedom and delight in it thank you