so in doing breath meditation and doing this
over these weeks from one perspective we're going through it slowly from another perspective we're going
through it quickly and i'm sure there's people who feel it
both way one way or the other and from the slow perspective
we're putting together slowly piece by piece the el the alphabet for breath
meditation all the little basic elements and and
learning you know once you learn the alphabet that gives you access to
a tremendous wealth of knowledge potential for communication writing
reading understanding all kinds of things that uh come alive with uh reading and writing
and so in the same way we're learning kind of the basic elements the alphabet in the sense of all the little things to notice and be
aware of as we're breathing and and then slowly over time these begin to be put together and
after a while it's you know you can read the book pretty quickly or easily maybe
and so after a while we get a sense of the all the little elements how they come together and
create the grammar of meditation and create the sentences of spirituality and freedom
so we're going to continue and uh with this um
with this uh our education and
the elements of breathing in meditation so
to assume a meditation posture and taking a few moments to settle into
your posture to
maybe sway a little bit front and back forward sideways
maybe twisting a little bit maybe making small adjustments
so that the the weight and the way your body is organized
can be one that is settling for you
that allows certain things to settle and so that taking your meditation
posture is a little bit of a homecoming or a little coming to a place
where you have some modicum of contentment
and so taking the time to feel that not to be in a hurry in meditation
and overlook the basic establishing your posture and in doing so
establish a mindfulness of the body establish a degree of embodiment in this
posture and then to close your eyes and
take a few moments to feel this body
okay sense how the what's happening in the body
all the different kinds of sensations that come alive in the body
and don't don't focus on any particular one just let your attention roam around
taking it all in
and if in doing so there are still some small adjustments in the posture it can still be a good thing to do
and then ever so gently ever so lightly
bring your awareness close to your breathing
not head long into it just kind of on the edges of it maybe
and begin feeling the experience of the body breathing
maybe coming to the breathing through your back and from there towards
the front lightly slowly
and taking a few moments to familiarize yourself
with how the body's breathing
and letting your attention quietly roam around the various places in the
body where the movements and the pressures and the
release of pressures appear that are associated with
breathing
and perhaps as you exhale there's some places in your body that
the breathing can relax more
release as you exhale
perhaps as you exhale there can be a softening
in the breathing body
and feeling more fully the experience of inhaling
and ever so gently as you inhale inhale
more fully longer inhale
so in the as you inhale the chest expands or fully
maybe there's a lifting of the shoulders
and not breathing in so fully or deeply that you get winded
in a relaxed way
and as you inhale see if you can notice if there's any
upwelling feelings the way in which energy in your body or a lightning feel
feeling that of lightness feeling of movement that's
lifts upward through your torso and up towards the head
a little movement that is energizing
perhaps as you breathe in a little deeper than usual
there's a movement towards greater clarity especially if you let
the thinking mind get quiet as you feel it more fully
and energetics that is that moves in the direction of waking you up
awakening a clarity and a lightness
and if you do this breathe deeper breathing just very slightly
is there anything that feels pleasant in doing so in the upwelling is there an upwelling
that brings pleasure or pleasantness
maybe even delight
some people might feel there's things get brighter a little bit more
light in the mind and letting your
breathing return to normal but still on the inhale
is there any upwelling feelings that occur in your body
ever so ever so slightly movement which lifts and straightens
the spine
and then as you exhale ride the exhale
with a very simple quiet ah
to feel the releasing the relaxing
and then on the inhale to receive and allow the upwelling
of energy of brightness lightness
receive it with the receiving of the
in-breath
a releasing as you exhale that releases the edges of your body
releases tension in your body
will you release into a tingling vibration
warmth softness in the body perhaps
and then receiving allowing the upwelling of in-breath of the inhale
the exhale tends to be more for relaxation
the inhale more for energizing or brightening
and as you're breathing is there any feelings of pleasure
pleasantness the joy
that comes along with the body breathing in
the body exhaling
low that pleasure
to flow through your body as you inhale
maybe flowing in an upward direction or outwards
maybe it flows downwards as you exhale
receive and let it spread through the inhale and ride on it as it in the exhale
let it flow it could be very subtle tingling and
warmth feeling of goodness
pleasure and as you breathe with a quiet mind
letting your thinking become very quiet and sensitive
so you're sensitive to feeling the pleasure that might be here
with your in-breaths and out-breaths breathing in and breathing out
there may also be unpleasant sensations as you're sitting here
don't don't don't ignore that they're there but don't give them any real attention
let your attention go with the pleasant sensations of breathing the
pleasant sensations of just sitting here in your body
as if they are big enough to hold what's unpleasant
as if they are a tender caring for what's difficult
and if the mind wanders off in thought
let yourself have a homecoming
into what's pleasant enjoyable contentful
in your body as you breathe
and as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps with this light touch a light touch with the breathing
and the breathing as it moves through your body letting it have a light touch
on whatever is tender or difficult in your body
very tenderly touch it with your breathing
touch it with your light awareness
just a light touch of recognition of accompaniment
so that whatever pleasantness and joy there is contentment
it shares itself tenderly with what is difficult
what is not so pleasant
and in our capacity to sit here
quietly contentedly
openly maybe softly
many different ways of you might feel at the end of a
meditation can you now lightly tenderly
just lightly touching opening to the suffering of the world
just touch the edge of the edges of it
no need to go into the middle of it challenges of our people you know and
don't know around the world a gentle soft
touch on the edges of their suffering arising out of your soft
light awareness soft light breathing
so their suffering doesn't disturb you and you don't disturb them
but you're there to accompany to recognize to clearly see
the world suffers
and then perhaps from whatever tenderness you have
towards the suffering world a tenderness that maybe comes from a
that's seeded in a place of meditative contentment
meditative ease or subtleness
and allow your compassion and care and good will
maybe to take the form of wishing well for others
wishing them happiness freedom from suffering
wishing them hell then well-being
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be healthy
may all beings be free
and may all beings live together
in good will
you