greetings friends greetings whatever time zone in the world you are
joining from dear sangha greetings and welcome to you
so today we continue our exploration
with the theme letting our hearts and minds swim
and relish the theme of generosity exploring generosity the
inner not just the outer dimensions but the inner dimensions of it
which are said to be liberative part of the path of liberation and
actually part of the practice of liberation itself
so so with an attitude of generosity
towards ourselves given that we are giving ourselves
this gift giving ourselves this gift of time
this gift to sit together in sangha
let us begin let us begin our meditation together so
i invite you to to find
how you can sit comfortably
and if this body this moment needs to lie down or stand that's okay too
those are fine positions of practice as long as the spine can be straight
there can be a sense of wakefulness
allowing
allowing your bottom to really land in the chair in the cushion
to feel the contact to feel how you are supported how this
body is supported
being held
if you're sitting in a chair on a cushion let your spine rise up
on its own rise up with integrity
sitting tall
as if there is an invisible string connected to the top of your head
supporting you
kind generously supporting you don't have to push up the spine
supported by the chair the cushion on one end
ah and you invisibly
invite it upward as if to the heavens
and your muscles your muscles can relax your muscles can relax
the soft tissue of your hands
your wrists your arms
can give their way to the earth
supported
your feet touching the earth
your legs you're sitting on the cushion
giving your weight offering your weight to the earth
i am here dear earth i am here
as if your weight as if this body is kissing the ground
kissing the earth
as if it were the prostration
[Music] is sitting in meditation the sitting tall
in meditation let your body your feet your legs
your bottom kiss the earth
offering your presence
as we kiss the earth with our bodies the earth may i be of service today
i offer you myself this practice in this moment
ah am i sitting
i offer my practice
so letting the breath find you letting the breath
find your body settle in the lower abdomen the center of gravity to be low
[Music] not in the head
and not in the nostrils today or the chest but lower
lower
greeting creating the breath the air
does it find this body nourishes this body
with oxygen
appreciatively generously graciously
receiving
the breath the air support from the earth
and offering generously offering your wholehearted intention in this moment
a presence for cultivating goodness
offering our hearts our hearts our minds our heart minds
in goodness to the world
to this interconnected web of humanity
to the earth
as a descendant so many ancestors
who have passed down have offered their lives so much
here we are
this being who is me
our presence our intentions our goodness the best gift we have to offer
ourselves
and to be of service to others
each breath both are receiving
and a generous offering of this life force
offering our practice
our goodness as our practices goodness
the goodness of our practice offering it generously
a service
if and when we find our mind
thinking entangled may be lost in thought it's okay it's okay
can we have generosity for our minds or our poor minds
are distracted thinking minds it's okay dear it's okay
generosity of spirit
towards ourselves
and knowing that simply showing up and doing our best even if we
deem it to be distracted
or whatever is an offering is a gift showing up
is a gift to ourselves and others
so showing up each and every second
again and again with ease
our practice our practices generosity
ourselves and others
and for the last moment of the sit together
relinquishing letting go of any judgments that might have come up
oh i was sleepy i was distracted whatever no need no need not helpful
letting go and appreciating graciously appreciating
that i showed up yay appreciating with gratitude
the gift of aligning our actions as best as we can interactions out outer actions
actions of the mind speech and body with our intentions with
our wholesome intentions as much as you are able to
you showed up yay not attaching not clinging to the
outcome letting go
trusting trusting
that goodness has been generated in our practice
our practice is an act of generosity
giving this time to ourselves cultivating our hearts and minds for
others may our goodness generated here collectively
may be of benefit of service in ways we cannot fathom
to ourselves and to all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy may all beings
be free
[Music]
thank you for your practice
greetings greetings sangha
so today is the second day of our exploration with the theme of generosity
donna in pali
and to follow up from yesterday the um
the word donna d-a-n-a many of you are already familiar with this word
refers both to the act of giving don giving and also
refers to what is given and
there is a similar word that i briefly mentioned yesterday which is one of my
favorite words actually in pali and the word is chaga chaga and it's
spelled c-a-g-a
which refers to a quality of mind heart mind heart being the chitta
the quality of mind heart so it's the quality of feeling generous
um there's a sense of generosity of spirit chaga is also
um translated as as relinquishing as
letting go because it is the same movement of the heart when the hand opens up to
to give something to someone else it is letting go of it it is letting go
of it for the benefit of someone else so that
that motion of the heart that motion of the the the body
is the same is the same as the movement of liberation it's the same
movement of awakening of letting go of of liberation
which is why donna generosity is such an important practice
such an important practice as i mentioned the buddha taught
donna as a primary practice especially for for lay practitioners and it shows up
in the triad an important triad of dhana sila
ethical conduct bhavana meditation practice cultivation of the
mind and heart so dana comes first and then ethical conduct and then meditation
so that's one important triad and it's it's you might have been
familiar with another triad of practice which is sila samadi panya
again ethical conduct samadhi concentration or calming the mind and pioneer wisdom so that's a
related triad here a different way to enter
and hold practice just as an important one just they're both as important
so so donna this this inner and outer
um dimension of of generosity
being paralleled with the same movement of the heart
for the same movement of the heart that we cultivate
towards liberation freedom letting go
so let's consider some of the similarities
so with liberation with letting go with non-attachment
which actually sometimes we think of letting go like oh i have to let go i have to let go this
buddhist path thing tells me not to be attached i'm supposed to be unattached
and it sounds so um dire sounds so heavy like oh be
unattached don't sound so grim be unattached let go of everything
right however if you think of that the way to think of that is the same way we think
of generosity it's the same spirit it's the same idea that's why
letting go liberation and and donna generosity are so related and one really
supports the other donna supports liberation because it's the same movement of the heart
donna generosity is not a dire well it's not supposed to be a heavy thing like oh
i have to be generous i have to give if that's not the spirit
for um generosity and you know from your own generosity which it's it's really a
movement of the heart when you feel moved when your heart feels bright it wants to offer it wants to offer
something that that you have your time
your skills your resources maybe a smile maybe a compliment
letting go of something that some some resource for the benefit of someone else
and there's a joy there is a delight there is a happiness in that giving
and the receiver in this case in the case of donna often there's a receiver
um the heart is uplifted and joyous and we'll talk more about the joy of
generosity tomorrow and i'll share some research studies also
so with donna there is this sense of ah this delight of yes i want you to have
this i want you to have this please have this yay there's there's the sense of
celebration of letting go there is this brightness of letting go it's okay that i don't
have this thing anymore yay it's giving me more joy my heart is freer that
this thing somebody else has it now so consider this this practice or this
sense this feeling of generosity now for liberation it's the same
movement of the heart yes i'm going to give give away this this tightening
attachment this wanting this thing because it's yay for the benefit of all beings for
the benefit of myself for the benefit of ah in ways i can't even fathom
for the ben for for liberation for nibana i
grant this i i give it away i release it so you see the two movements
of the heart of donna and liberation letting go for the
benefit of of liberation are the same they both have or should have well i don't want to
use the worship but they need to have they they're inspired from the same
movement of the heart the same brightness the same letting go that's
and it's it's not a tight letting go otherwise it doesn't quite work that well
but it's a bright it's a bright yay for the benefit of myself for the
benefit of in the case of liberation for the benefit of myself for the benefit of all beings
um for these other dimensions of freedom ease i let go i let go of greed hatred
delusion i let go i let go and i offer myself i offer my heart
my purity my goodness trusting there is goodness and purity
to to the world and here again donna as a practice that supports liberation
i offer this i offer something that i have i offer some um thing that
i quote unquote possess and again we are only custodians of of everything we
don't own stuff in this world we're just passing
through so this thing that i'm a custodian of for a limited time
i i give it away i give it away it just generates a practice
so so it is said that the practice of uh
generosity so practicing generosity practicing on
practicing practicing actually giving making it a habit to give things away to offer to make offerings
can help this inner dimension of generosity to be cultivated this inner
dimension of not a non-attachment to be cultivated
and of course it's a virtual cycle when you have when we have this inner dimension of
cultivation when we have the inner dimension of generosity when our hearts um don't hold tightly and are aware of
opportunities to help and support oh yes then the outer act of
donna generosity comes a lot easier
another um the way that it is said and bhikkhupuri
puts it this way generosity
donna um connects with the path connects with
the goal of the path which is liberation as i briefly mentioned with the destruction
of greed hatred and delusion because when we're cultivating
generosity of our generosity of spirit um
of course generosity is the the anti-thesis
of greed greed is holding on is grabbing grasping and ah the opposite
movement of the heart movement of the mind is is releasing letting go so
the practice of generosity is the antonym
to to greed so okay so that's one of the poisonous roots okay how about hate
hate is is this sense of ill will not liking people
again generosity it it brings up this sense of um
it's synonymous it's it also brings up a sense of meta in fact this is an amazing
practice i learned years ago studying visudi maga
the path of purification book where there are 10 practices listed
if you're angry at someone where there is ill will with someone how to work with the ill will there are ten things
mentioned the last one the last one if nothing else was the last one was to give them a gift
and when i saw that i was astounded what give someone a gift and it makes sense
it actually makes sense try it and it's for the liberation of your own heart if you're angry at someone give
them a gift because it opens it shifts something in your heart
when you give someone a gift i've tried that actually and yes
it's for the liberation of my own heart not to have ill will towards anyone
giving a gift open shifts something this act of generosity donna it dispels
hatred so greed hatred and confusion and again
there are outer there are other dimensions of generosity
there are visible dimensions of yes transferring this item from one person to another
but there are other dimensions that it dispels delusion thinking that it is
ours that it that there are boundaries that we're not all connected
so in in many ways it dispels delusion in ways we cannot even fathom so the
practice of generosity the practice of dhana
is synonymous is it supports liberation in ways we cannot imagine which is why
the buddha espoused it so much so my invitation for
today if you if you would like to take it on you don't have to this is again generous
it needs to come from the heart it's not an act of should if you're inspired
find an opportunity today to be generous with someone
um it could be your time could be maybe pick up the phone and call a friend see how they're doing
maybe it's with some your resources maybe it's something you have or your
whatever you decide but see if you can find one opportunity to be generous
today and see and observe observe and we'll discuss more about these
observations and and um uh yeah the inner works and workings of
donna so thank you for the generosity of your practice and your presence
may you all be well safe and free