so good morning everyone and good day and
i'm quite happy to be back here and sitting here and continuing where we left off from a week ago on monday
and the topic still is patience and hopefully
you've been patient to wait for the continuation of this
so in a certain way
when we meditate we don't
accept the status quo in a certain way we don't just
sit and just allow things to be as they are
and there's a certain way in which we don't do that there's many ways depending on the meditation technique
and all kinds of things but the certain way with mindfulness is that
we always continue with the mindfulness practice
we always keep a steadiness coming back to it coming back to it being mindful again being mindful again
and and that makes a world of difference to accept the status quo is to not be
mindful and one way that
but some for some of you a simple way to
maintain the continuity to keep coming back to mindfulness not drift off in thought
is on every exhale it could be inhaled that people prefer
that every exhale you recognize whether or not you've started to think
again and just that mindfulness of thinking
it might be enough not for you not to be caught in it or drift off in it if you want you could also let go of it
at that point recognize your thinking and let go of it every time in the cycle so you only goes
a couple of seconds between a recognition of thinking and letting go
there is um it can be quite uh thinking can be in some ways quite clever and camouflaging
itself or that uh or pulling us into its world so we don't
know or recognize that we're thinking and but the clear
recognition oh this i'm thinking again thinking and to do it on such a regular basis
patiently steadily practice coming back to mindfulness
every exhale every exhale and that every exhale
of the moment of mindfulness that kind of clarity um is where the steady slow patient
approach to mindfulness occurs not looking for you know some big experience
but just looking being content and patient with showing up and waking up to this
here they're thinking so taking a
assuming a comfortable alert posture
and
relaxing your gaze if you're looking at the screen maybe
looking down and maybe a 45 degree angle and
see if the eyes can be a little bit more at rest
and then to gently if it's comfortable for you nice you can gently close your eyes
and then to establish a stronger connection to the present moment through your body
taking a few long slow deep breaths
deep enough so you feel your rib cages stretch as they expand
or you feel the ballooning out of your belly in that deep exhale
and with a long long inhale and a long exhale
sort of ballooning out ballooning out of the belly as you inhale
and then with the exhale releasing relaxing
softening
letting the breathing return to normal and taking a few moments
in the silence to relax your body
maybe each time you exhale relax some part of your body release the holding
and then from within your body as part of your bodily experience
become aware of the body breathing wherever the breathing is
most comfortable for you to experience
or where it's clearest to easiest to connect to
it could be the movements of the belly the movements of the chest the sensations of the air going in and
out through the nostrils or some broad
whole body experience of breathing
and as you exhale at the end of the exhale
perhaps you can relax a bit or release a teeny bit more
so there's a slight continuation of the exhale
or perhaps of ever so slight pause before you inhale
and whenever it's time to inhale quietly
attentively receive the inhale
receive the movement sensations of the body as you inhale
and as you exhale allow the exhale allow the release
and every time you exhale notice if you've been thinking
if you have you might very gently whisper to yourself
thinking as a clear recognition
and if it's easy enough to let go of your thoughts during the exhale let them go
so there's a letting go into the quiet and stillness
at the end of the exhale
so you can better receive the inhale
and remembering to every exhale recognizing if thinking has returned
and if it's easy enough let go of it if it's not easy enough
be ready to recognize that you're thinking again when you exhale next time
perhaps being a little bit more attentive
so that you can notice if you've begun thinking on the exhale
and if you're able to let go of your thoughts by the end of the exhale
to be attentive to how thoughts begin how they creep in on the inhale
and watching this phenomena from a quiet place within
unperturbed undisturbed by it but clearly recognizing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to appreciate
that if you can recognize that you're thinking
you might recognize the ways you're thinking that are not so
accurate the projections you have on people and
events the interpretations perhaps even the bias
and if you're also able to let go of your thoughts or to put them aside enough to see
clearly without the filter of your thinking
then it's possible to be present for people
to be companions for people be friends with people more fully more
clearly
and this is a gift and may it be that our ability to be
mindful supports our ability to be friends with
others to see them clearly do they have the ability to be present
without the pull and the tug of our desires and aversions and
interpretations
may it be that this practice that we do
helps us to engage in the world in a kinder friendlier
supportive way and in that way when we dedicate the
merit maybe we're more likely
to be the conduit in which the merit travels
out into the world so whatever benefit and merit we've had
from this practice this together may we dedicate it to the welfare and
happiness of all beings everywhere may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
uh so
hello and welcome to the continuation of our
little series on patients and
today's topic is another form of patients called patients
patience or i call it gentle perseverance
perseverance is just the small little ongoing step by step by step
of engagement involvement doing the gentle is to do it without strain
without strife without resistance just kind of the simple steps
go keep going and now in this way it's uh it's sometimes helpful to
appreciate that in the buddha's teaching that action
was extremely important that he's even his teaching sometimes call is called a teaching of action
that means a variety of different things but one of the things that i like to think of it is that it is not a passive
practice even though for a lot of uh modern western practitioners
who are over striving overdoing over analyzing over critical of themselves
that the lesson of kind of just letting things be and not doing is such a
powerful and useful medicine but it's the medicine
for the buddha i think that for him that there's an element in which the practice is always
an activity of a little bit of a kind of doing but a doing which is an undoing of
stress and strain and tension and criticism and you know
striving but it is a kind of doing and uh in sitting in meditation
mindfulness can be experienced as a non-doing just allowing awareness to be there
but even that is a very subtle doing because chances are we have to keep coming back to allowing to receiving to
being and that's the doing that's the action and
and so whatever the action there's is a very simple action in practice so today in the meditation i suggested
the action of every time you exhale noticing if you're thinking
and if it's easy enough to let go of those thoughts and and so there's always a little bit
something waking up being present being here for the next thing for the next thing
and so there's a little engagement little effort and work that's involved
as we get familiar with mindfulness that work is better often better than the alternative
uh what the mind does and you know the what the spinning often
and so this uh amazing capacity we have for gentle perseverance just keep doing the
practice in other walks of life other situations in life sometimes you know perseverance doing it
over and over again being willing to fail and coming back and starting over again can be a huge
strength a huge support for a wise life a good life
but so this gentle perseverance is useful in so many areas in life
but in practice gentle perseverance not to be looking for the big dramatic
experiences in meditation but being very content and patient with
a simple ongoing practice moment by moment just wake showing up
and being mindful of this being present for this here now
and um or in a little bit larger scale i'm meditating every day
gentle perseverance of every day no matter what sitting down to meditate
and even if there's nothing more than getting into your meditation posture for a minute
every day this gentle perseverance of touching into this wonderful
kind of repository or or
special place where a certain kind of special attention and calm and subtleness
can be so this so we keep doing keep doing keep doing
and um and it's uh this gentle perseverance and practice
in the day-to-day ordinary way it's
represented or enacted in small little steps as small little things we do
just being a little bit more attentive more present coming back more often
and um but small little steps can make huge difference into the future
one of the you know if you take two parallel lines that would they would go parallel on
forever but if you take and nudge one of them little bit to the side
then initially you know just infinitesimal you might not see that they're
separating from each other but as you over time the distance between them
becomes greater and greater and greater so if you make sometimes a small change
those ends keep up the small change that can over time can make a huge difference for our life and can
transform it in beneficial ways and so this gentle perseverance not giving up
not being discouraged or maybe being discouraged but have the patience to do it anyway just keep
showing up to sit to meditate keep showing up to be present for the next moment
and and this very much applies to meditation practice maybe that's the place where
it's most um you know it's easiest or the the most
kind of the pro the ideal place to practice this gentle perseverance
just keep coming back for the next breath this breath this breath
this breath sometimes we have all these issues and problems and difficult things that
happen in our lives and there's something about the continuity the ballast
of the grounding the sense of of stability that just being with the
breath through it all through it all that allows so many things to settle it allows us not to get
wrapped up in other things or be reactive to other things and so not to deny anything
but the gentle perseverance with the breathing with the breathing with the breathing
or the gentle perseverance of being mindful attentive recognizing oh
this is happening this is happening my mind is afraid my mind is afraid
there's fear there's fear and in that little recognition it might be
actively even those words in your mind where you follow up the words with just
feeling and sensing what's happening more fully perhaps that in this
simple mindfulness you begin finding that you're not wrapped up in it or
or caught by it or impacted as fully by the fear or the anxiety or
the desire you know whatever it might be just to keep steady recognizing
recognizing that this is what happened this is what's happening and um
and so this gentle perseverance in buddhist practice takes can take many forms
it could be a gentle perseverance of not giving into anger just one one
one act of speech after another just okay i'm not going to say it now i'm not going to say this now not now
not now and to say i'm not no longer no longer going to be angry no longer say some kind of
um mean things to anyone
ever again when we make these big commitments or big
ideas sometimes it's much harder for the mind to cooperate and participate
but sometimes it's the moment and moment steps where we can really it really counts the
most and so um that's not saying that not this not
saying that mean word nope nope nope gentle perseverance
or a strong desire arises and nope nope i'm not giving into that i know what happens this is not healthy for me
or good for others nope nope and a gentle perseverance
uh is just is uh repeating it over and over again until something settles
the whole thing shifts and so it's not a big struggle it's not meant to be a big
a wrestling match it's just like because it's so it's just these little steps moment by moment
now now now so um
to be patient with the if we're doing things which are useful and healthy and appropriate and
and necessary to persevere
to not resist not procrastinate not
give up but just get steady gentle steadiness just showing up showing up and for me i
don't know how it is for some of you but this word uh [Music] idea of gentleness
it implies that it doesn't require
heroic effort that will always or strong effort or um it just
just move in that direction don't hesitate don't give up
just take a little move in that direction keep doing it keep doing it and
and certainly in buddhist practice and meditation practice
probably gentle perseverance carries the day because any other effort that you make
probably is agitating probably will not really be sustainable in the
long term but the gentle perseverance it may be a sustainable engaging maybe
becomes self-rewarding and maybe begins to shift that line just
a little bit so that over time it makes a huge difference in your life
maybe you don't see it in one day or one week or one month but the gentle perseverance gentle
continuity can just doing and doing and doing that can be revolutionary in one's
in one's life so um
so gentle perseverance gentle
and the person what we persevere in depends on the context we're in gentle forgiveness gentle kindness
compassion just whatever is needed gentle keep doing it so we don't succumb don't
collapse into states of mind and thoughts and ideas which are not really helpful for
us and finally i'll say that the alternative sometimes
the continuity the perseverance of distracted thought of
of uh aversive thoughts of desirous thoughts of selfish thoughts of
thoughts you know victim thoughts the perseverance of those
you know they also have an effect over time and slowly and perceptibly the line the
parallel lines move within a different direction that may be not so useful so it's very helpful to be careful
with what is what what the mind does regularly and continuously because it really has a big effect over
time and so once you have a sense of what practice is and what a wise and wholesome way of living
is the gentle perseverance gentle step-by-step ordinary step
ordinary movement in the direction of what's wholesome and good and
and it can be done and it can make a huge difference so thank you
very much and and tomorrow we'll do um
patience under insult which is a much more difficult one but
it has its uh tremendous benefit so thank you
you