okay
so hello and welcome everyone welcome to happy hour
so for today's practice
i'd like to talk about the secret to happiness this is happy hour so i figured we'd
talk about the secret to happiness what the subtitle of this this practice will do might be the
secret to happiness on zoo
so so the practice of meta the practice of
meta wishing well having kindness good goodwill friendliness
for ourselves others people we know people we don't know people we like people we don't like
equal opportunity friendliness and goodwill as part of this cultivation
and it does make our heart happier it's it makes us happier so what i'd like to talk about
specifically the the nuance that i like to bring in today is you know with the pandemic
[Music] many of us are still experiencing zoom calls
oh they're not going to go away anytime soon it is a part of or the way we're going
to be working uh remotely or or perhaps also even if
you would go back to work with people who are not local with us so so teleconferencing video
chat etc video work will continue to be a part of the way both we work and maybe we
socialize in groups so
so so this practice um is
you know how we wish well for example you know before before the pandemic the variation of
this practice was stealth meta if you got if you were driving
you would wish meta for people on the road and you would be calmer happier you
wouldn't be upset as much especially if people cut cut in front of you especially wish them
well ah really in order to to bring soothing and calm
and ease to yourself and you would arrive at your destination feeling uh much better similarly if you rode
the subway or buses oh you would be you would be wishing well for everyone
around now with with what i'd like to bring in
and this is a zoom practice meeting well some people are on youtube
but many of us are here on zoom you can see me you can see each other so this will serve as a perfect practice
ground for for many of the work meetings so
um wishing well so the idea the invitation is that we will practice the wishing wishing well
for people who are on a meeting with us and we'll bring that bring them to mind or you can
start maybe if you wanted to um you're able to put
in gallery view so you can choose someone to wish well for kind of warm up your your your meta
right now but really what i'd like to focus on is a practice that we can take to our
other zoom meetings other other work meetings in this way so so why
well some meetings actually many meetings
might you might feel tired bored it might be something like i don't disa i don't agree with this person ah
they're going on and on you know these little quirks we develop with people we know and and work with and and actually
choosing choosing to find something that either you appreciate about them
you like about them or some way in which you are similar the common humanity oh
yes you you're both dedicated to this work you were doing you both appreciate
whatever project you're working on
and finding a way finding a way to find common humanity and for those of you who are retired perhaps
i invite you to engage in this practice creatively creatively
cultivating meta is all about creativity so find other ways maybe you are going for walks
and seeing people in your neighborhood or going to the grocery store and and feeling annoyed by someone's like
okay they're taking forever during the whatever 10 or less items and they have 30 items
check out lane you know there are all these ways that that we find that that would get
irritated so stealth meta this is stealth meta and
one one thing i want to bring in before we get into it into the practice is um that
some people say well when i'm in a meeting or doing something or other it takes too much um it's too
distracting to perhaps do meta for someone well yes and no so one idea could be
before you go into the meeting you know spend a couple of minutes imagining people you'll be
seeing you'll be either in a meeting with or even visiting in person again be creative you don't have to take
it exactly the script that i will be talking about be creative see what works for your life situation
um be your inner own inner dharma guide
so can prime the heart either before and also what i have found is that if i don't do
this practice actually i get more tired and more waned my energy gets kind of waned in the
meeting and my attention starts to not be here completely whereas actually when i
engage by you know different people in the meeting perhaps are talking i i wish them well i
even if i deci especially if i disagree with them or there's something i'm like i wish you well may you people and then
i all of a sudden i realized oh wow i'm more attentive i have more energy i have more good will i'm
more present in this meeting i don't feel like oh when is this going to be or i just i want to be done with this me
so he changes the way i perce i i show up i i'm present at the meeting instead of
actually being distracting it's actually the opposite so i challenge you
gently to see that for yourself to see that for yourself how you could
actually become even more present and available your energy will
be arisen aroused or risen
anyway uh there'll be more energy present with this practice instead of it being a
distraction stuff so i have said plenty to frame the practice let's practice to
be together ah i'd like to invite you
to land to land in your body
to arrive to come here
right here right now
feeling your feet on the ground or if you're sitting on the floor feeling your whole underside
of your legs
on the cushion feeling your bottom on the chair or the
contact points relaxing
letting go of your body weight into the contact points
feeling the connection to the earth let's just hang out here
feeling connected to the earth sensing feeling
appreciating the contact points
inviting your breath
to move through the body the lower part of the body
the abdomen
the contact points enlivening
bringing more awareness
to these sensations
deeply rooted and connected to all the sensations
inviting the awareness to rest the lower abdomen sensing
the movement the sensations of the breath
fighting your awareness to move through the body with the breath
calming relaxing letting go [Music]
of any tightness or holding anywhere
okay
now i would like to invite you
as you continue to feel embodied feeling your bottom on the cushion
contact point your feet your legs the breath moving through your body
here here
imagine you're in a meeting
it could be a zoom meeting an in-person meeting
or perhaps somewhere where there are others present that
you're interacting with in some capacity could even be a grocery store or a walk
in the neighborhood see what situation works for you best
for the narrative i will use i will refer
to meetings but again see what works best for you
as you are embodied feeling your body sitting
lying down standing
perhaps bring to mind a recent scenario
a recent scenario
where you were with others
in a meeting perhaps on soon
again feel free to adapt to what comes up for you
feeling yourself rooted in your body with your breath and just take some time imagining
yourself present this meeting fully present in your body
not leaving the body in order to be with others
staying with the body staying with the breath
feeling your presence why you are imagining being in this meeting
starting with appreciation meta for yourself
for your work your work as service
appreciating your own goodness
your own intentions for service from
offering your offering to the world
may i be safe
happy healthy
and have ease
staying connected to your body
may i be safe may i be happy
may i be healthy may i have ease
and now feeling a body to continue to feel embodied
the sensations of your feet your sit bones your breath
whatever calls to you in your body feeling your presence with others in
this meeting or in this situation you've conjured up something that has happened maybe
earlier today or recently
and imagining yourself in relationship
with these other beings and as they speak or as they relate to
you as they're going about doing what they do in this interaction wishing them well
one by one perhaps starting with the person who was easiest for you
person who's easiest have most
warmth ease care appreciation perhaps for them
may you be safe may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you have ease
either sharing these metaphases or whatever metaphases you like or perhaps without
words just wishing them well wishing them goodness
and happiness in your mind's eye
staying connected to your body
staying with this first person for a while
a few minutes
you're welcome to move to another person in this meeting
in this group saving the person who perhaps is most
challenging for last i'll tell you when we have a few minutes left
or if you want to move to them earlier you're welcome too
at any point if you feel that you need some of this goodness and care feel free
to direct better to yourself
maybe it was a challenging meeting it's okay to hold yourself with care
and mental
if you haven't yet moved the person who may be more challenging for you the meeting this is
a good time
perhaps considering something the two of you have in common
seeing their humanity something you appreciate about them
or you have appreciated in the past that that be the basis for the meta
for your connection with them
or maybe simply that you're both human you're both aging you're subject to aging
you have a body subject to pain and illness you're not so different
for the last couple of minutes let's practice
sharing your mental your good will your friendliness
with all the beings in this meeting and this circumstance and this situation all of
you may all of us meeting
talking working together being together
and this cause in the service in this way may all of us
be well
seeing your connection through your common cause
even if you're imagining being in the grocery store for this common cause of feeding yourself
may all of us and may all beings everywhere
be safe be happy be healthy
and have ease as much as possible may all beings be free
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so changing the settings on chat so you can
chat publicly with your reflections if it's sent to everyone i'll read your name if it's just to me it'll be private
i won't read your name and you can also raise your hand your zoom
hand especially if you haven't spoken for a while if you're new love to hear your reflections what you
discovered and um yeah
i see forest please nikki hi for this topic it's actually
perfect timing for me because i recently returned to work and
meetings that i feel like are a waste of time have been one of the things i was just trying to figure out how i work with and
during the meditation it really shifted my attitude because i realized that the meeting was not just about the work
it was also this kind of human um about the humanity somehow not just
the work so i'll definitely be bringing that with me
i am touched that i am so touched forest thank you for your words and your reflections i am
delighted i'm yeah i got your missive your mental missive
[Laughter] thank you so much you may this be of support to you and
what you say is super fun i do want to highlight it that meetings aren't just about the work
being done there's so much about the relationship but the human relationships these are the people
we are serving with we haven't chosen them they're kind of like our family we don't
choose our family and yet they can serve as our teachers and there's so much so um
and as you were saying that in the meetings where it could in the previously it was a
waste of time now it's no longer a waste of time it's practice time it's practice time meta practice
it's lovely thank you first other reflections please
and one thing that i'll share as i'll wait for you to raise your hand or type is um i've i've done this practice
especially in meetings where i felt it's long or there's as i mentioned at the beginning
um just yeah you know some meetings they have spark and some meetings are heavier
and i've noticed that my energy gets completely transformed and shifted
in the meeting okay it's time to do that i start smiling i start smiling at my to myself i start
smiling at others when i'm looking at them wishing them well it just and and it shifts my energy and also
i've noticed it shifts other people's energy in the meeting when that happens
um so this is your secret happiness happiness secret
happiness secret and zoom meetings not such a secret please spread it
any other reflections or thoughts you'll notice anything that maybe was
challenging too is welcome
again hi this is megan um i was thinking of a
zoom meeting that i had by phone last week with people i have yet to meet
um i have a lot of people to meet i just moved here to california so welcome
welcome to california megan yeah but uh it's also kind of scary and um there's a lot of nerves and
just a lot of like self thing when it comes to starting over and being in all of these
groups and so it was really helpful to like to bring meta
to that um with all these people i haven't actually met in person yet and think about like little things i've heard that i just really appreciated
about them um so i'm gonna try it in real life we'll see how it goes
oh that's awesome that's great i love that and also the actionability of of you know things that
you've heard you appreciate the bottom oh yeah yeah here it is um letting that be the
basis and also you know as we know meta is is a um antidote for
fear anxiety and various flavors of it so especially in the new situation may may
it support you may it profoundly support you make it that's great thanks for your reflection
marie christine says in chat i would like your life's subscription to the happiness club
that's great you already have one [Laughter] i love it i love it mine christine was
great very sweet
another thing also again feel free to raise your hand um another thing i've i've also done in
the past is sometimes um you know if people have a virtual background that's one thing but if they
if in their environment sometimes in the background you can see something that oh yes they like art
or oh they have a child's painting you know drawing in the back oh maybe they're a parent maybe they're a
grandparent there's something there's a way that you can really connect
um with with them there's so many ways to be creative and create the connection so
so speaking of that we are in the zoo meeting dear ones let's take this as an opportunity
for meta for one another so in a moment we will be in small
groups small practice groups and let's start
um by let's start by 15 seconds of
meta silent meta for each other and um then you can share as little or
as as much as you like but maybe in the background have a sense of meta for yourself
in the small breakout groups with others really actively and see how it goes
so so i'll create the breakout room rooms now and they are
open and enjoy
welcome back everyone so we have a few minutes
for any reflections questions what you notice what you observed
especially doing this practicing this in real time especially if you're new if
you haven't spoken before we'd love to hear from you
your observations are important
yes parents i just want to say how important this this group practices
i was you know before the small group thing i was this feeling kind of turned inward and
um not very happy uh you know we're we're doing happy hour right i've been a
little group just talking with three other people i felt the shift now and i thank you for
this group yay nice thank you thank you terence yay
thank heavens for our community yeah and for happy our community yay yeah thank you for that
yeah i see hearts showing up on zoom yeah and the human connection yeah the
connection in this way and the safe supportive um as safe as supportive as we can make
it and taking care of each other really yeah glad to hear it thank you terence
other reflections please
yes melanie hi hi yeah i was
feeling the same level of gratitude for their breakout rooms and um there's one person in particular that
i've happened to be in a breakout room with a number of times just like seems a bit coincidental but like
there were like a few maybe like three or four times like we've been in the same breakout room together and he isn't here right now but
um we did the exercise together once of um uh like what brings you joy i think or
there was something where we repeatedly asked each other the same question i think it was like what makes your heart sore i think that was
the actual question and he was talking about how he like loves going to st farts and like running and like swimming
naked in the beach he's actually like not on the call right now um but i was like oh like
you know like now i just think of such joy i'm like you know he's not here but like you know i feel like this image
of feeling so happy for him like maybe he made it to saint parts and that's why he's not dialing in
um and so i i think that was key to what you were saying of like just like getting to know little parts
of someone especially like what makes them really happy and then being able to think of those it makes it much easier for the meta to
flow for them beautiful thank you melody i love it
it just makes my heart sing also as you talk about this makes me so happy
it's lovely that's a lovely lovely note to end on thank you both for those reflections at
the end of both terence and melanie and everyone else we shared
earlier so thank you all for your practice thank you for showing up to happier
supporting yourself and others in the world this cultivation of good will
friendliness metta may all beings be happy may all beings
be free including ourselves
thank you