so everyone [Music] hello and welcome to happy hour
so for today's practice
the theme i'd like to invite us to explore and consider
is is one that can come [Music] quite handy and can be supportive
especially when our minds are really really busy when our minds and hearts are really
busy and say we sit down to meditate and the
idea of oh my goodness i'm gonna meditate what for the next 20 minutes 30 minutes are
you kidding me says the mind just going all over the place so it can
be particularly handy for those times when there is the busy buddha when there is the thinking buddha
of showing up on your cushion at home wherever you're practicing
especially for those moments but it can actually this this thing for
tonight which i haven't introduced yet i'm setting it up on the edge of your seats um
can also be helpful anytime for for deepening for really giving our
hearts in any moment of meditation any moment of exploration any moment not just meditation but in
life any endeavor that we are doing especially one that seems
um weighty perhaps
so what what this exploration is tonight is to just
give our hearts our complete heart to it whatever it is
just in this moment just just this just this justice
justice just landing in the body it's a very
embodied invitation justice justice just aware for just this
moment just loving cultivating goodwill towards myself for others
just just this moment just here it's okay not reaching towards the
future and not blaming ourselves for the past
so landing landing their whole body our whole heart and
just just this just this justice letting go
of the future clinging wanting responsibility i'll do this i dread this
or oh i didn't do it it was terrible my mind wandered last you know for the
past 29 minutes of this sit just justice just this is perfect
just this right here is enough so that's the theme i'd like to invite us to
explore together tonight as a tool in your
in your um toolbag humanities tool bag not just meditative but
so let's let's embark together let's embark together so
i'd like to invite us invite you to land
ah to land this body in this moment
arriving
starting with the theme of our exploration from the very beginning
this is all that i'm sure of right here this magical presence of this present
moment ever so fleeting [Music] fleeting every moment
blending landing and giving my heart my whole body landing
giving it my full presence
as the expression in english goes like there is no tomorrow like there is no next moment just
this
and if you notice if you notice the mind wanders
it's okay the last moment is gone no need
for judgment self-flagellation just give your heart giving your heart
our attention our wholeheartedness
relaxing into just this moment
and i like to suggest to drop in an idea too
explore sit with as you're practicing in this way as if you were taking a dropper
of a color and dropping one drop
of color into the waters of exploration
this invitation this drop of color is as you sit here as we sit here in
practice not so much consider this a performance
i am doing this the performative aspect of meditation that we often
sometimes inadvertently have
but what if this dropper this idea introduced to our hearts
squeezed into the heart and mind is this idea of devotion
wholeheartedly devoting ourselves showing up for ourselves
for ourselves for all beings
showing up out of love devotion in this moment fully just this
moment not the next not the last
if our presents are wholehearted
our wholeheartedness is the gift
that we put on all on the altar in this moment just this moment
what if simply collecting
our attention our awareness
our wholehearted presence in this moment
what if this is an utmost act of care
especially in today's world
an utmost act of care and love
to show up fully wholeheartedly in this moment
for ourselves for whatever is arising
in the sphere of awareness
just this moment meeting it fully
kindly not the last moment it's gone it's okay letting go
not judging planning for the next moments
but a radical dedication to this mystery
of time that just shows up right here right now
it's always now can we meet it can we be in it inhabit it fully
in our body relaxing into it
the fullness of our humanity in this fleeting
mysterious amazing moment with fullness
wholeheartedness
and love
if there's any discomfort or pain in the body
can i just be with it for this moment just this moment
relaxing around it into it with it
just this much just here
can i meet this too
or if any emotional pain or sorrow
is coming up physical or emotional can i just be with it this morning
this moment meet i need it right here right now not worrying about
how i've met it in the past or how long it might last in the future
just made it fully
open-heartedly
this moment is it possible can i be with it
just this moment
and if there is peace and calm
just greeting at this morning moment not attaching wanting more
just landing relinquishing ourselves
our hearts in just this moment
how does your body feel your entire body
feel in this moment
not leaving the body behind this is an embodied practice
the whole body the breath embracing this moment
for this moment embracing the whole body and the breath
which is embracing which just here fully present
embodied
tending this way in this moment present moment
does time feel expensive
and for the last wholehearted moment of this practice
bowing to yourself with appreciation for having practiced
even for one split second having given your heart
with presence without expectation of presence in every moment
just appreciating that you tried without judging without judging
may my heart be free may my heart know its own goodness may
all beings be free
thank you all for your practice
so we have time for reflections questions
you can type them in chat it's just type to me
privately i won't read your name if it's to everyone i'll say your name you can raise your zoom hand
and appreciation is coming in through youtube you are welcome thanks for joining dear youtube sangha
and practicing so so many different
aspects or dimensions as we explored here can come up we wanted to reflect on one
thing that happened for me which is very interesting and actually quite lovely
exploring this way of just this moment showing up and embracing giving my heart
the sense of time it actually shifted time became very spacious as if time
dropped away and well everything is a concept everything is empty
including time and perception of time shifted through this
practice it's just an expansiveness which was very interesting
um just noticing that playing around with that anyway um
so and it could have been also challenging in different ways this practice it's more open our way of showing up
is a way of expressing care and love so would love to hear questions complaints
reflections how was it for you let us learn from
from what happened for you parents
okay um you mentioned a couple of times
returning to the body um something around the discomfort
that may be associated with the body and i've been having a lot of bodily discomfort
it doesn't affect the stability of my setting but it's uncomfortable and
and feeling the what that way that that they waft and wane and coming and going with
attention and then remembering that this is the this is for mental practice or
the compassion practice of course for for myself is the most obvious but i began to sense this pain as
somehow being kind of a symptom of the world or the
pain of pain except share this is something that we're very common we share and that shifted the pain
that shifted uh really opened you know in a sense awareness to a
different view a different association to the pain may this pain be the uh
cause for less pain in the world may this this pain served to
relieve the suffering of the world very big change
beautiful turns thank you so much for sharing that shift in
perception in this different way of relating holding being that is profound instead of
habitually you know our mind see it as oh my pain my shoulder my back my to whoa
common humanity pain of both common humanity other people and
also the pain of the world this is the suffering it's the shared suffering oh and i'm holding this peace there's a
sense of nobility i'm holding this peace
for for us fellow beings it's beautiful conceptions it just yes
so it's a dimension of beauty and really this wholehearted offering
of your suffering putting it on the altar and here it is i'm holding it for all of us
it's lovely thanks for sharing that hair it's beautiful how that opened up for you
lovely thank you [Music]
yeah any other reflections
anything you've noticed or any challenges questions it's all welcome
a phrase that has helped me a lot and in reference to the
previous comment um is i am feeling this now
so others don't have to uh that's from pema children
yeah i am feeling this now so others don't have to yeah yeah one way of burning off our
karma yeah thank you thanks for reading that in yeah and as you mentioned as you give
credit to pemo children this is very common this way of conceptualizing and seeing
suffering as as offering our suffering as as an offering um is
uh is very is is common especially in vajrayana uh buddhism in tibetan
buddhism not so much in terra vada but yes very common it's it can be a beautiful way
that the heart can find a lot of meaning in in suffering in that instead of it
being senseless and there's no point it's just there's a beauty there's a sacredness
that can show up in this way yeah thank you so let's let's um
join jump into our sangha practice where the practice meets the road or
comes into contact and relationally holding ourselves just in this moment
with care holding others in just this moment with care showing up fully can we show up fully
for ourselves can we show up fully for everyone else just showing up fully this could be
great practice in small groups today for how we show up for ourselves and
others in relationships instead of thinking about what we're gonna say or what we're gonna have for lunch or
dinner can we show up for others ourselves for just the six
minutes uh practicing wholeheartedly and see how what that might feel like in the
body and in the mind and as always let's start with 15
seconds of um of silent meta for ourselves and for
each other and um let's see i'm going to create the rooms they will
take a second so okay all right
so let's let's see here problem here
let me fix this okay here we go all right i'm going to open the rooms
here we go the rooms are closed everyone is back
and um we have a couple of minutes for any reflections but any questions anything that has come
up while you were practicing together in groups why don't you notice
especially if you haven't spoken for a while would love to hear your what's come up for you your practice is
important your insight can support others even your
the confusion or if it didn't work trusting that somebody else had the same
[Music] question question yeah
rebecca hi yeah it's really helpful to be in the grid
because of gaining perspectives that i don't have yeah even after years uh all of a sudden
there's a fresh perspective so someone in my group said that the important thing is effort it's like what
and and then and then i questioned it because that didn't that i didn't understand that the
important thing is effort i've never i don't remember ever hearing that and he explained
the effort to be here it's like yeah just that the effort to be here yeah
i just got it yeah that's that yeah yeah great thanks for sharing that
i appreciate how um through the groups you know they're
different perspectives different way of practicing which could be different from you from the way you conceptualize and it's
important for you it's like oh how can that be important effort like oh yes it lights up something completely new
lit up for you through that yeah yeah beautiful thank you and jennifer says
often in speech just is used to take attention away from
just one more just a little tonight just was used to draw simple attention to yes very observant
jennifer thank you for that linguistic uh um attunement of yours yes
exactly yeah just as emphasizes just as important right here
right now beautiful thank you for that yeah great
any last minute reflections questions before we wrap up
our time together
yeah nikki yes i see anthony's yeah yes i just wanted to mention you
know sometimes when you said about the timeless you know yeah uh really hit a note with me uh
when you when we're uh connected with that that peacefulness that you know the inner peace and the
the joy of the of that uh just being uh connected with the body
the breath yeah sometimes i feel like like it feels so good that it feels like like if it's
an escape you know like if i'm using it as an escape but then i remember uh someone mentioned in a dharma talk
that the buddha said that uh that he he he had the same uh state of mind or
something but he he said that if it's wholesome how could it be you know how could it be
uh what is it called like uh bad for you you know how could it be bad for you if
it's wholesome you know yeah for something that you you know uh that you could get uh cling
on you know something that you can attach to yeah i'm so glad you bring that in uh anthony that's fantastic
first of all delighted that that sense of spaciousness and timelessness and that peace that arises for you
in meditation because it's very nourishing it is very nourishing and and this fear that
comes up for you oh is this bad for me am i checking out is this just like kind of like am i taking drugs happy drugs
and just checking out in this happy space is that what that is um if it is
if it becomes that really people do it just to check out just then yes it can become but but that's
not what i'm hearing is happening for you and that's not how the buddha utilized it etc
the way actually we practice it with its spaciousness supports us it gives us calm and peace to then
bring love compassion stability care to the world instead of just checking
out it's like okay i'm going to take care of myself rest it
and and i'll be more nourished to be in the world to serve in the world instead of just check out
in this fun land does that make sense in the context
yeah definitely thank you and these states are very supportive very supportive so
please please don't shy away from them feel nourished and then serve the world more from this place of calm
and stillness and love yeah beautiful so thank you all for your practice thank you thank
you thank you for your practice showing up supporting yourself supporting each other may all beings be well may all
wings beings be happy including ourselves
thank you