so
the 16 stages of anapanasati
each stage each step along the way
i think it's nice to think of it as
being complete in itself
to not be so concerned about making
one's way through these steps
but to be fully with present for
practicing with what is
and content with whatever the practice
is whatever the focus is for the time
but then as it develops practice sooner
or later
the body starts feeling settled and
unified the whole body we're breathing
with and relaxing
the whole as we develop kind of
ability to be a little more content and
happy to be here
then we have a kind of a
a feeling of well-being
that makes it easier to both notice
what's going on in our mind the mental
activity and to relax it
to tranquilize it and it's nice to have
a sense of well-being
so we can look at some of the craziness
that goes on in some of our minds
and not so we're not disturbed by it or
troubled by it or
reactive to you know the unusual things
that we can think
and do and feel but see it as just a
um you know mental activity as opposed
to making it personal or
material which should judge ourselves
and so to experience the mental activity
and to relax it and calm it down
and kind of in a little summary that's
the first eight steps of anapanasati
and then the whole practice of these 16
stages
takes a dramatic shift with step nine
experiencing the mind
and it's kind of like this is a pivot uh
into a deeper dive
into our you know maybe we could say our
spiritual life
and the word mind cheetah is a
um you know it's usually translated as
mind or mind heart or even heart
sometimes
and uh it probably is to use to kind of
be a little bit of
heretic buddhist heretic
uh border on it is that the word mind is
the cheetah is so
important in the teachings of the buddha
and so generally respected and
that it's the closest thing we get from
the buddha
to something that we would maybe in
english called the self
and but the self this idea of self is
in put in buddhist kind of orientation
is all seen as represents some activity
of the mind some idea
interpretation some thing we're holding
on to
and so there's a kind of a desire not to
get
involved in this whole idea of self and
what is the self and who am i
that that investigation is considered
more complicated and more stressful
than is useful for deepening our
meditation so we get to put the self
idea aside
but the cheetah the mind is kind of what
takes its place but the mind is not a
thing
the mind is a the gestalt
of all the mental activities in the way
that we experience that
and so it's a fluid thing it's not
nothing not a thing to get attached to
or to
reify into like a solid thing it's
dynamic and fluid and
it gets very clear as we go deeper and
deeper in meditation
how fluid and changeable the mind is and
how the experience of mind
changes in different levels of
concentration different levels of
clarity
and and it's fascinating to watch this
how we sense and feel the mind
kind of oscillates between sometimes
being contracted and small and sometimes
being expansive
sometimes being you know all kinds of
ways
but when the when the
body gets relaxed the mental activity is
relaxed
generally the cheetah the mind state
tends to become
very welcoming very wholesome very
wholesome nourishing feeling
it's like we've discovered a treasure
inside as treasure of well-being of
goodness of
wholeness of intimacy that
that is a kind of a state rather than a
thing
and it's a dynamic state it's not
something that's easy to hold on to or
cling to
i mean we can have desires for it and
all that but if we get close to it
we realize there's nothing here to cling
to or it doesn't make sense to cling
because if we cling to this
this this mind we're actually getting
involved in a mental activity
which is a subset of the mind and any
kind of
to too involved with these activities of
mind the thoughts of the mind
interpretations of the mind
certain arrows and collapses the freedom
the openness the
fullness that is the sense of the mind
and that's why in step 10 uh we we're
allowed we can satisfy the mind we
nourish the mind we gladden the mind
with this sense of wholeness the sense
of being complete or centered or
that can happen so there's a sense of
well-being a certain kind of well-being
and this is the foundation this is the
for when
the practice of anapanasati switches to
something we can call an english
concentration practice
or that concentration practice is
separate practice
but where uh the that we can develop
concentration in doing mindfulness of
breathing in mindfulness are breathing
out
because we center ourselves we have this
this
mind state that we're intimate with and
feel
and we take the whole mind state with us
as we center ourselves on the breathing
or the breathing becomes the very wind
that moves through the mind state kind
of the massage that moves through it
and it becomes the breathing becomes
more and more the place in which we
gather
ourselves the place in which we the
concentric circles of our life
hold counsel hold gather together
and be present for and supported for
it's not like you're sitting at the
center
of a room and there's concentric circles
around you
and all your best friends and family
and supporters just come there because
just to be with you and hold you and
and love you and you know show that
you're you know that you
you're you know you know you can you can
you're good you can rest in yourself you
can be at ease
and so we gather together all of
ourselves
and um and the word for uh
that's usually translated as
concentration for step
um 11 of anupanasati
is uh is not actually samadhi it's a
different word that looks like
samadhi i think i didn't look and get
exactly right but sama
sama hiti or samahati and
it more literally means a gathering
together
a gathering together or a settling
a settling in here and
so breathing in one settles in
breathing out one settles in breathing
in
one gathers oneself here breathing out
one gathers
oneself here and this gathering
centering settling is difficult to do
if we're preoccupied with thoughts and
ideas and
feelings emotions it works best when
those are uh we're relaxed enough about
that we're not
tight or contracted around that or
nervous about those things
that those things can still happen but
we don't want we don't have to be
involved in them they can be
in the background or on the side or they
can be in the outer chairs in that
circle of all our supporters there
or as we get more and more gathered in
the thoughts and feelings and emotions
all kind of get started getting oriented
as supporters for this process of the
mind
being centered in on the breathing so if
we are thinking
they're very simple and innocent
thoughts about staying with the breath
feeling the breath
if there are emotions happening or
feelings
they really feel connected to the
process of being settled it's like
almost part of settling
the goodness the wholeness the
wholesomeness and nourishment
seems to flow with or out of being
settled on the breathing and being with
the breath
so this process of settling of gathering
together
gathering in every all of who we are it
continues this process
of becoming whole in the first tetrad
experiencing the whole body and then
relaxing the bodily
activity in the in the second tetrad
experiencing the mental activity
all the activity and relaxing it
contributes to that sense of
the mind as a whole the gestalt of the
mind
and then go further settling everything
begins to
come in and when it gets really sweet
the sense of being settled and
deeply connected and not distracted by
things
then when there's a sound or something
else happens in the body a sensation
it just seems to be soft and tenderly
held and included
it's not a problem it's just kind of
part of this wonderful
landscape of of subtleness of softness
of intimacy of
care of of attention
so samadhi is a
sometimes called the unification
unification of that mind
making it whole so i'm very aware that
this is not easy to experience and
describing it this way can set up
expectation or striving for it or
comparative thinking like
i'm not any ever going to be in that
kind of state
so if those kinds of things happen
that's why the earlier steps of
anapanasati is so important
because we're always staying attentive
to the stresses and the strains that
happen in the body around our reactions
and then relaxing those we're always
attentive and sensitive
to how we get trapped and caught in our
mental activity our thoughts our
judgments our
our interpretations are expected you
know
and our comparative thinking and we're
always ready to relax those
and this is so important these early
steps of anapanasati
to always keep them close by always
being content
to do those and that's the massage
that we do to always go back catch
ourselves
do the earlier steps again and massaging
yourselves and
and then we come back into a nice mind
state a nice way of being and then we
get caught again
and there's a massage back and forth and
rather than thinking of this as a
mistake
or a problem and we're supposed to be
always at the growing edge of the
practice
it's actually this massaging and going
back and forth and discovering ourselves
and
works our slowly is working out the
kinks slowly working out the
wrinkles that need to be ironed out
so we get more and more whole and
holistic and settled in this practice
so uh don't um
don't be concerned too much if these
teachings we do now for
these deeper and deeper teachings don't
quite work for you
they'll work in some way don't you can
trust that
you might not be aware of it consciously
and
always be content to do whatever step
that you're on
and we'll continue so um
thank you for today and we'll probably
continue for a while now
if at least a few days into the week
with
the samadhi and concentration thank you