so warm greetings everyone and welcome to our meditation time
and uh one of the principles of mindfulness meditation
is or one of the potentials is to be equanimously mindful
of everything that no matter what the experience we're having it's possible to have a relaxed calm
clear recognition that this is happening and in relationship to mental activity
the topic of this week thinking uh mindfulness meditation
is not making an enemy of our thinking it's not uh condemning it to some
place where it's not supposed to exist at all and we're supposed to get rid of it
it certainly can calm down thinking and it's quite nice to have it become quieter and
still there sometimes there seems to be thinking stops entirely and it can be very peaceful but that's not
necessarily the point the point of mindfulness meditation is to see clearly without being for or
against the experience being forward against that's uh
you know that that is a different capacity of the mind it's a different function of the mind
that sometimes has a role and sometimes doesn't but for mindfulness itself it's just a
simple being present for our experience so with that as an introduction
just to maybe just close your eyes as you are and think that the principle for
mindfulness meditation is that you're allowed to come as you
are to come as you are meditation and and so when you sit and close your
eyes one of the possibilities is begin first by just noticing how you are
without any effort to meditate just notice how you are right now
what's happening for you and your body what's happening for you
in your heart and what's happening for you in your mind
and to
in particular for the purposes of today
without any idea to be any different notice your thinking
allow yourself to think whatever you have to be thinking but just become aware of it be curious
a simple recognition of what you're thinking
maybe a little bit as if you could step away step backward a few steps
and then turn around to look at yourself look at your mind
as if it's thinking
thinking in words thinking in images sometimes just that clear recognition
and allowance to think
the thinking quiets down or even stop sometimes it'll come back so just take your time
and notice how it is
and notice the energy of thinking the pull of it
is it strong is it weak
do you have an attitude about your thinking
are you do you relate to your thoughts as if they're
you know you relate to them in a friendly way in a hostile way
in different ways
and what it would be like to neither be friendly nor hostile
and certainly not indifferent just present and seeing
in the way that you would maybe look at walking down the street
you might look at a tree here look up in the sky and watch clouds
sail by
and is there any physical sensations connected to thinking
is there pressure or attention
contraction
is it the experience not what you're thinking about but the
experience of thinking in and of itself as an experience as something that
this has sensations or you can feel it in some way
is it pleasant or unpleasant
and now thinking of thinking of thoughts you're thinking imagine your
thinking are like bubbles thought bubbles
take a deep full breath as you exhale let those bubbles float
away
deep breath in relaxing the mental activity
relaxing the pressure and tension
and now continue thinking
as the mind wants to think but can you think in quieter ways
can you think with a quieter voice or calmer images
maybe you let the images recede a little bit further away from you
or they slow down the quieter thoughts
slower thoughts adjusting the volume and the speed of
your thinking
and then instead of letting yourself think whatever you wish to think about
choose what you think about and what i'd suggest is you choose to
think instructions for meditation
maybe i'll give you some now you can repeat them to yourself
in a quiet calm thinking or you might have variations
gently softly
take a few fuller breaths and as you exhale
relax your body
as you exhale softening the shoulders
releasing the shoulders
as you exhale softening the belly
letting your breathing return to normal
as you exhale soften the muscles of your face
around the eyes and the forehead
and soften what can be softened in the area of your brain
even if it's softening around the brain
and then to settle into the experience of the body breathing
and for these minutes you'll accompany your breathing
maybe imagining that your you and your breathing are walking along
holding hands so there's continuous contact between
awareness and the breathing breathing and the
awareness
and without leaving the attention to breathing if
while you're breathing mindfully you notice that it's easy to relax the
body more you might do so
if you notice that there's a feelings of well-being or contentment
or joy
allow it to grow mix allow it give it space in your body
and if you notice it's possible to relax the mental activity the thinking muscle
without leaving your breathing maybe on the exhale relax the mental
activity but all along accompanying your
breathing awareness and breathing walking along
hand in hand
softening your thinking slowing your thinking down
quieting your thinking and with your thinking quieter
maybe it's easier to relax the mental activity
the drive the push the pressure
an image for relaxing the mental activity
is that of a flower bud that goes from being tightly closed
to opening up wide so the inside of the petals
are open to the wide open sky and space
so we relax the mind
and intuit or feel the vastness of quiet space
all around
and in that space we stay rooted in the breathing
relaxed and open receiving the experience of breathing
maybe you can assume that for these next minutes there's nothing that you need to think
about even though you might think there's no need to
no need to invest any importance in your thinking
and there might be a greater contentment available
by dropping into your body to feel what is more tender and soft
and open in your body
the quiet still place within
through which you could be breathing from which you can be breathing
thinking can be a powerful storm
howling wind and thinking can be a soft breeze
a soft refreshing breeze that lightly moves through us
and with the lightest softest
maybe almost insubstantial or imperceptible thoughts
have thoughts of good will for others
maybe thoughts of wishing them well wishing them happiness and peace
and see how softly is there from a still tender place
within that you can silently in your mind atone
evoke thoughts ideas wishes of goodwill
for others
maybe they're even just half thoughts
in a way that opens you up your heart opens you to a
care a tender care respect and valuing of others
and may a soft quiet tender
kind regard for others be something that you touch into
throughout the day today it doesn't have to be dramatic
it doesn't have to be obvious to others
but in a sense from the quiet place within
simple quiet thoughts of well-wishing for others
and may it be that
the benefits of this 30 minutes together meditating
may those benefits be shared with others either directly or indirectly knowingly or
unknowingly
and may it be that this meditation supports the possibility of others being
happy may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
so continuing these talks on anapanasati mindfulness of breathing
we've entered into the domain of mental activity and the
pali word is um chitta sankara so it's
usually translated as mind and sankara is formations or calling it to this week
activities of the mind and um so
activities of the mind it turns out that the mind is not the
container for activities or the organ for activities like
the brain that's maybe the organ for you know what many of us the modern
world think of as mental activities the cheetah is itself an activity
or it's the sum total of all the activities
of the of what we might call the mind
it's the um or the cheetah is all the activities of the mind as we
experience them as we can know them and so this idea that the mind itself is
an activity is an encouragement not to take the mind as a particular thing
not to kind of reify it or treat it as a almost like a foreign
object but rather uh all we have as human beings really in
buddhist point of view is uh the activities that are all operating together
to to make make us alive it's when the activities of life are no longer here
that we're no longer alive and one of those activities is the activities of the mind the mental
activities and to start becoming aware of the mind
appreciating it is the task now in the middle stages
of anapanasati and it's very important to appreciate it that it's
it's uh it's kind of in the middle here so that there's been a lot of emphasis
on breathing for sure embodied breathing and but also being rooted in the body
really feeling the whole body and then also starting feeling a real sense of
well-being a contentment in the body joy in the body and and spreading that contentment
throughout the body and so there's a movement towards becoming whole
or the classic language is becoming unified where everything is included and
and and so as we move through panasoti it's not so much that we're now starting
to emphasize more the mind but we're opening up wider and wider to more
and more inclusive of this whole but if we're very s
quiet and still centered and in the body the body begins to because it's taken
care of so well because it's no longer the challenging place to be
uh in deeper meditation that the body begins to recede from
the central focus of awareness the breathing tends to change its quality
and it's fascinating to watch as we go through meditation the different stages that breathing will
take and sometimes breathing will go very quiet and subtle and still
sometimes it's so quiet the breathing it seems like we've stopped breathing the first time that happened to me in
meditation i was very content and a lot of well-being and just
sitting there very still and and nope no trouble at all and then
i know i noticed i hadn't breathed for a while and i immediately gasped for breath with fear and i had
this thought i'm going to die and um but you know there was no danger of that to just that i'd never
you know you know you're supposed to be breathing all the time and uh so this idea that the breathing
had seemingly seemingly stopped was you know a little bit jarring for me and then eventually i learned that
it seems like there's plenty enough oxygen getting into the bloodstream some way or other even when seemingly
the experience of breathing has gotten so still that it's kind of stopped and so the body and the breathing
sometimes recede and so then this sense of wholeness and inclusion
begins to include the mental activity the mind itself
and and one of the things we begin appreciating in this path this journey
is at some point it's possible to understand that the body itself
not the physical body but the body that we experience how we experience the body
is a byproduct or contingent upon the mental activities we have so
uh if the mind is um really quiet and still
the construction of the body the the making of the body experiences and interpreting the body and focusing the
body begins to recede as well and the experienced body begins to become more porous
more transparent more translucent until it also sometimes kind of disappears
so this activity of the mind is part of this his incense all in
some forms of buddhism they say them it's all we have all there is um consciousness is all
there is they're saying but i don't think that the buddha would say that
but he would say that most of what we experience the experience of life is very much
conditioned and affected by the quality and the activity and the of the mind itself of this cheetah so
this cheetah activity the activity of the mind is actually a very important part of our
hugely important part of our life and it's how we construct ourselves
construct our world in the way that we live in it and experience it so to start becoming aware not of this
complicated idea that we're constructing our own experience in some way or influencing it greatly but to begin
appreciating that as the that we can it's actually possible to quiet the mind still the mind soften the mind
not so much by necessarily doing it too intentionally but it tends to happen as we start
getting more and more settled and unified less in conflict with things thus in conflict with the mind or the heart or
the world and there's kind of a lesbian for and against things
the mind tends to become quieter and the activity slows down and
and but slowing down doesn't mean it doesn't mean we could be we become slow-witted it it's like i
said the last few days um the mind actually operates so much better clear more creatively more intelligently
more wisely uh when they're less
active energy or less applied energy goes into our thinking into the mental
activity and the mental activity is kind of like it's begins coasting or it comes into a harmony where there's
no resistance to anything there's no and so it just kind of
begins to operate in a very harmonious deep way and almost effortlessly so this movement
of quieting the mental activity so part of this is then
to recognize what it feels like the mental activity the experience of it
and and that's how we can start becoming aware of how energetic it is how tense it is
how much pressure there's in it contraction um how much resistance there is how much
agitation there is in the mental activity and then to hold that in awareness
breathe with that just be aware of that and then when it's easy to uh relax
calm the mental activities not to do that too much not to make it a big project in
fact the bigger project than calming the mental activities is just to get to know it step seven
we can't under i can't underestimate how important it is for people who do be faster practice to really just learn the art of just
knowing the experience really well and knowing how to be with it
without being for and against it without being actively engaged trying to do something with it and when
that's learned well then it's a really good time to
actively quiet and soften the mind the mental activity to let go of our
thoughts to let go of our preoccupations too and but not to do it because we have to
but because it's wise to do it nothing and not do it because we're expecting to be successful
but just because you know we're so quiet and peaceful and calm
enough that why not why not let the mind become even stiller and quieter
and so appreciating the mind as an activity activities
and and relaxing and calming it and then also beginning to appreciate
and recognize the ways in which the mental activity has become calm
has become quieter and that's a relative degree if you're super agitated it's really
good to appreciate that you've now you're half agitated and before you're 100 agitated rather
than feeling upset about the 50 agitation celebrate it
any movement in the right direction in meditation just be celebrated rather than to be
give yourself more material for why you're not far enough along and not doing better
and but then to appreciate the calmness of the mind the tranquility of the mind
and for the buddha tranquility uh begets tranquility extreme
tranquility you actually use the word food tranquility is the food or the nourishment
for more tranquility so as we uh relax calm the mind as the mind
becomes calmer um nourish yourself with that calm
take it in enjoy it let it spread let it let it be more part
of who you are and appreciate it i've had situations where i got calm enough
but the authority of my thoughts and my things i my sense of responsibility were
strong enough that i felt like i had to think about things and not sit and appreciate the calm
but tranquility is the food for more tranquility so you're allowed
to take in that food you're allowed to be nourished by it when it's there when it comes
so step seven is breathing in one experiences mental activity
breathing out one experiences mental activity step eight is breathing in
one calms the mental activity breathing out one calms the mental
activity and so i hope that you enjoy that
and and also i hope that you don't set up
an excited mind in opposition to a calm mind because there are times in life where
it's quite wonderful to be excited and engaged in things and and um and to be able to be fluid
and relaxed and fluid in just going back and forth between happily excited minds and
happily combines is one of the joys of practice so enjoy your day thank you