so good day everyone hello
and we are gathering for this time of
meditation a time of mindfulness and a certain kind of intimacy or closeness to
our experience some people might say to ourselves
the so i'd like to begin with
these ideas that because
clinging and craving and grasping are all forms of desire
in buddhist circles sometimes desire has a bad reputation
because sometimes we have desires together with expectations or
a lot of ideas of success and failure
desires can be a connected to a lot of suffering
and therefore because of that connection it can have a bad reputation
and so sometimes because of this bad reputation buddhist practitioners will undervalue the importance and val
undervalue the importance of desire and maybe even haven't really learned
how to engage desire in a useful and even necessary way
and so desires can be present without clinging craving or grasping desires can be
present without the trap of expectations or the traps
that come along with ideas of success and failure
desires are are really essential on the buddhist path the buddhist path
of liberation and so if we keep kind of thinking we're not supposed to have any desires
then it's hard to engage in that path so how to have desires that are kind of
open-handed that are relaxed that are open that are
that set the direction in which we go but don't set an expectation of success
or failure or um it just
and how to have desires that in having the desires themselves it is a kind of liberation it's a kind
of freedom that's found there kind of ease and peacefulness that's found there
that's kind of the task is to discover how to hold desires
discover how to use them in ways that are freeing and beneficial for us and not harmful for us
so desires are wholesome skillful and
so the desi so when we meditate there's a desire to be present
the desire to be here and now a desire to to stay connected to the
breathing and have a continuity just breathing kind of like just staying with the breath
and let everything else kind of fall away to the side somewhat like a boat going through water
the water the boat doesn't stop because of the water by itself it is not blocked by the water
it moves through the water and the water gets washed to the side of the bow along the
hull and just again you leave the water behind in the wake of the boat
so the same thing we certain kinds of desires in meditation are meant not to
deny things or ignore things but there's a lot of things that the mind does
that we get caught in is simply not useful simply not beneficial or it's not for
our higher welfare and so it's nice just let those things fall off and so just staying the
desire to stay on the breath stay on the breath there's also the
desire to do so kindly to do so with friendliness
to be a kind meditator or a loving meditator or
one that's diligent one that maybe is resolved to do this desire strong desires resolve
but does so in a kind way in a loving way in a
friendly way too and it's of course it's hard to be kind or loving or
but even the desire to do so is a beautiful thing even if we can't do it the desire to do
it is can be that can be a beautiful desire it can be a wonderful oh i have this desire
and then to in a sense celebrate having the desire to be having loving kindness desire to be kind
and don't get too hung up the fact that you're not the desire can be nourishing and
supportive so desire so in this sitting
perhaps you can experiment explore how you can have a desire for meditation
or desires for meditation that help you to settle down get calmer quieter focused more
present here here so assuming a meditation posture
and closing your eyes if that's comfortable
for you
and then having a simple desire to relax
and to do so you can take a few long slow deep breaths
and on the exhale relax your body
if you're sitting upright don't lose the uprightness as you relax more like relax
around the uprightness
deep in breath and then a long exhale to settle in
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and to
also in a few exhales relaxing further
relaxing the muscles of the face
relaxing the shoulders
and relaxing the belly
and with as much gentleness as you can see if you can also relax your thinking
mind calming your thinking
quieting your thinking
and then to
settle your attention on the body breathing the body sensations
that come into play as you breathe
wherever it's easiest for you to do so
and gently but clearly to have desire
to be present here now the desire to
not wander often thought
a desire to be with your breathing
and a desire to do so with good will with kindness
maybe even with love and if you can't have goodness and
kindness and love i appreciate that is that if you have the sincere desire that that would be
good having that desire is enough
having that desire itself can be wholesome and supportive nourishing
as you stay breathing in and breathing
out
remembering the desire to be present
perhaps there's a way of having that desire which is simple
wholesome just feels good to have the desire
desire to be present not lost in thought
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
is there a way that from this whatever calm or subtleness
that you have or whatever connection you have with yourself at
this point that you can turn your attention outward
for the simple desire
to have good will for others and if that a good will can arise
wonderful and if not simply having the desire for
it makes a difference
it can be beneficial for you
to turn your attention outward to the world of your community friends
family people who you read about in the news
and see if you can come out of your meditation
with the desire for their welfare
so there's a bridge between meditation and the world in which you live and that
bridge is your goodwill
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
and may i have the kind of good will for others then i can look for how to contribute to
that as a possibility in whatever way that's appropriate for
me or for you or for all of us
may we contribute to the welfare and happiness of this world
so
so then continuing on uh this topic of the meta suita the
discourse on lovingkindness attributed to the buddha we don't know
if really the buddha wrote it or composed it but that's the attribution of the tradition
it's a beautiful little text a series of verses
that as i said yesterday is considered the foundational text for
loving-kindness practice or living but that the fundamental purpose of the
text is to reach the state of peace
liberation and freedom and that and that to do so it's important to
develop these different qualities and a lot of these can be seen as
expressions of the seven factor second factor of the eightfold path right intention
the right resolve and um which is said to be
renunciation
non-hostility or non-ill will
so renunciation non-ill will and non-cruelty non-violence
and um and this idea in the text where there is in the in the pali tradition where
there's a lot of these negative prefixes the not ill will then not cruelty
it's understood in the tradition that that encompasses not the opposite
it's not just the absence it involves the presence of the opposite and you could say why don't you say the opposite
and the reason is that the opposite of non-ill will could be a range of different attitudes
not just one and so by the when we let go of ill will then we are available
for the range and whatever is appropriate at the time sometimes it might be loving kindness sometimes compassion
sometimes generosity sometimes it might be patience or or it might be
equanimity or it might be you know
different things and and so we're not limited just to one
however uh so in this um opening of the text we talked about yesterday
all of those can be seen as expressions of renunciation non-ill will and um
and non-cruelty um especially the first two
and uh so they're um uh gentle and not proud contented easily
supported living likely with few duties all about renunciation of a certain kind of healthy letting go wise
with senses calmed not arrogant without greed for supporters they should not do the least thing that
the wise would criticize so then the next one
is uh this describes the in the um the intention the motivations the
aspiration of loving kindness it's the heart's wish that others be happy and here it's put
in the context of reaching the state of peace it's in the context of becoming liberated
oneself that one develops and cultivates this care and goodwill for others
that if the path of liberation is only about me myself and mine there's no liberation that
the way we close down and hold ourselves in check and gripped in our sense of self
when we're only focusing on our own practice and our own welfare uh actually limits the movement towards
freedom and so here we next next section of this
is now including a care for the others in the world a kind of relaxing of the barriers the
relaxing of the strong sense of separation and otherness and meanness and me against
you or it's all about me and what's good for me but now there's an
opening relaxing of that strong grip of self into
now in a relaxed open way having the good will go out and include
the welfare of others as well and and so the the goes on
and so it's those skilled and the good should be and then it all says all these
kind of ethical things and then it goes they should also reflect as follows they should
consider as follows may all be happy and secure may all beings be
happy at heart all living beings whether weak or strong
tall large medium or short tiny or big
seen or unseen near or distant born or to be born may they all
be happy so it's not just a simple good will to the people that you love
here it's a kind of a universal goodwill may all beings be happy and the
universality of it is not easy to come to but as we begin we begin with love
towards those that we care about those who is easy for and then the practice is to begin
expanding it what does it take to relax and open and and and be inclusive in our
good will so that we can genuinely have good will for the whole world
and part of the advantage of this in terms of the benefit of this in meditation practice is that this really frees up the
restrictions on the heart the constrictions of the heart the limitations we have by by keeping our
love bounded or in check there's something about opening up the windows of the heart
completely all the windows so that the radiance of the heart can be
in all directions not limited by anything an unlimited heart
this of course is a very large ideal and and so one of the things
that is very useful to consider is that we're talking here about
an intention and intentions don't necessarily mean that we feel loving
it means that we have the intention to do so we have the desire to be loving to have
good will and um and it would if the requirement is to feel that have an emotional
feeling of love that uh could limit uh and hinder a person from actually
practicing it or feeling you know feeling like they're doing the practice well
um it's enough to have the intention that's where it begins intention is considered a seed and you
plant that seed so something can begin to grow and over time something important will grow
within us exactly what that is for any one individual i don't want to say
for some it might be emotional for some it might be as has more cognitive quality to it and
comes with understanding and and ideas that
really are all encompassing and but it does involve a releasing
of clinging releasing of self preoccupation but it begins just by an
intention and so i think that it's very invaluable
to simply have the desire to have goodwill even if you don't have any goodwill you
might want to consider whether it's a good idea to have it yes i would like to have it i'd like to have it someday i wish i
could do it and rather than berating oneself or diminishing the value of that because
it's just a desire and we can't actually have the good will the idea is to
celebrate to appreciate the desire is actually quite phenomenal this member desires intentions are
so important part of human life when we have wholesome desires it's good
to appreciate that especially if the alternative is unwholesome desires
and um and so the desire to have goodwill is enough in itself it's a beginning
and then to appreciate that and and then maybe give it voice and one of the ways that loving-kindness
practice is practiced is uh by in one's own mind maybe quietly
uh giving voice to it saying saying words that express it and there's something about giving voice
that is good for the heart some of you if you're driving a car or if you're alone sometime
you might try speaking out loud expressions of good will maybe very
personal expressions of it that you have for others or for all beings or to do it
with the classic phrases and or you do it from the um these phrases that
from this metasuta may all be happy and secure may all be happy
and safe may all beings be happy at heart and then
all is really emphasized here the all-encompassing natures in all directions no limitations to your
goodwill all living beings whether weak or strong
tall large medium or short tiny or big seen or unseen
near or distant born or to be born may they all be happy
and um and this is not just human beings i think tiny and big and all that
means the smallest little creatures to the largest seen and unseen doesn't just means the
people you don't see but even the bacteria the insects that are so small you don't see them
so this all-encompassing nature of this good will and so what what does it take to do that
so it takes intentionality it takes having some desire which cut with for which we have to
appreciate that desire has important role in our life and um and to learn how to be wise with desires
our desires are wholesome and beneficial so we don't succumb to the limitations of expectation and demand
and success success and failure that we don't um
hijack the desire with clinging and craving and grasping in you know compulsive
desire but just an open-handed uh free kind of
uh generosity of heart where we wish we wish well for people we
wish for their welfare it doesn't have to be publicly known so
some people are afraid to kind of have develop goodwill or have this intention because
if they people know about it they'll be taken advantage of or it's embarrassing or something it's awkward but this good will we're
cultivating doesn't have to be publicly known it can be your secret that you're really sitting there just
wishing that the people are angry with you or annoyed with you wishing for their welfare wishing they
can be happy and it might be wholesome enough
to wish their welfare and happiness because if they're happy they probably wouldn't be so mean to you
they'd be a lot better shape so these beautiful words may all
be happy and secure may all beings be happy at heart how can those
words be intentions or desires or aspirations
that live in you in a way that has integrity a way that
is really comes out of you and flows out of you and is valuable for you
one of the ways that the many ways to answer that question but one of the ways that comes out of
meditation is to have a non-claustrophobic mind
to have a mind that's not so busy with thoughts and other desires and ill wills and annoyances and fantasies
there's no room for the quieter emotions the emotions of
goodwill of love and kindness so to live a calm life
can make room for frequent connection to the intention the desire for
good will so may you explore this this next day
maybe you may explore maybe by repeating to yourself and seeing what it uh what it brings up for you in your
heart and your mind and your body just repeat to you with yourself the phrase is may all
be happy and secure may all beings be happy at heart you don't have to even
feel any good will saying them but what happens to you if you make those a mantra for the day
just keep coming back to them and back to them and living with them what is it what do you learn about
yourself and what do you learn about your heart in doing so
so thank you and uh there's a copy of my translation of the metasuta
in um on the imc uh website on the home page and in the
bottom right hand corner there's a little section called what's new and in this section there's a little
line that says reflections from gil and there you'll find the discourse on loving kindness
um so thank you and then i look forward to continuing tomorrow