so just beginning to settle in for meditation
perhaps closing the eyes if that's comfortable for you
and sensing into the place where you're sitting
your seat your cushion your chair bench
bed couch and just having a sense of being
in the sitting posture
maybe connecting in with that contact point
where your seat is touching and also your feet or legs against the floor
so having a sense of stability sometimes we can even sense
three-pointed stability
it's a very stable way to be sitting
and just relaxing and allowing yourself to be supported by whatever you're sitting relying on
bringing a sense of straightness to the spine
perhaps trusting that the body itself can find a posture that is both upright
and relaxed one that is supported from the inside
but not tense
and as an extra support for our posture we can gently soften areas that tend to be tense
so the face particularly the eyes
the jaw
softening down through the throat and the shoulders
letting the shoulder blades slide down the back so that the heart
moves forward a bit in the posture
softening the arms
and then down into the belly area
letting the belly fall forward away from the spine
and also letting the low back muscles fall away from the spine
so we just have the support of the bones without a lot of tension around
them
down into the hips
the thighs
the calves and into the ankles and the feet
just inviting ease to whatever degree is possible today
and for any parts of the body that don't feel at ease or that you couldn't feel very well
we just have mental ease about that the body is fine as it is right now
we might open to the idea of the body as a friend
just like our friend is fine as they are when they come to our house
the body is fine right now you can just open to it mindfully with
kind attention [Music] feeling what it has to offer us right
now various sensations
we may wish to tune into the sensations of breathing coming in going out
just letting the breath be as it is
or we may sense into the energy level of the body
subtle sensations of having a body
and just resting for a moment and allowing the simplicity of the
bodily sensations to help calm the mind
bye
today we will focus on the experience
of the body
which is different often from our idea of the body
the concepts that we bring to our body the encouragement today will be to tune
into something more simple maybe more basic
than what our mind does with the body but i'll offer a series of four
perceptions that we may find in our body
four types of sensations that relate to how it's actually sensed
so first you may notice in your experience of the body that
there are experiences of hardness or solidity
the solid parts of the body
and the structure that's holding you up there's some some hardness there perhaps you feel it in
where you're touching against the cushion or the chair i'm just sensing that
part of the experience of the body is hardness or solidity
in the buddhist teachings these are related to elements so this would be the earth
element
and then the corresponding feeling of softness is also part of the earth element
there are feelings all throughout the body of this hardness or solidity
and we can tune into those
we can understand that this kind of solidity is really the same as
what we feel in external objects so
the table or the cup that we hold also feel
solid in a certain way that's the experience and it's the same it's the earth element
and then the second type of experience we have in the body
is that of liquidity or wetness
the water element we feel this easily in the mouth
sometimes we can sense it in the eyes or if there's any sweat
this is the water element of the body it's more subtle
but still there are these easy places to detect it
and the water element is also related to the cohesion of the body
in the same way that when we go to the beach when we're just out on the sand
it's very dry but then as we walk towards the water
there comes a place where it becomes more solid and actually easy to walk on and
that's where the sand gets wet has enough water to hold it together
so this is happening in the body also the water element is the cohesion of the
body
consents into that all throughout the body
and this water element is really the same as the water in rivers and lakes
the water in our home
it's all water element
and then the third experience in the body is
one of temperature of heat and coolness
we may notice that the hands
may be warm or sometimes they're cool often the torso area is warm
and as we tune into the quality of temperature we'll find it variable throughout the body
is the fire element
at different times different parts are warm or cool and we can just feel for now how it is
now
this quality of temperature
so
and we can understand that this heat is the same as the experience of temperature we have
externally the warmth of the sun the heat of the sun
or the coolness in the shade
it's all fire elements
oh
and then in addition to the solidity and the liquidity
in the heat we feel throughout the body
there is also a sense of motion the body is dynamic it's not static
so there's a sense of movement the air element
most easily discerned in the breath coming in going out
causes movement all through the body
but there are other movements going on [Music]
the gut is moving while it's digesting [Music] we may tune into that
other energetic sensations
literal movements of the muscles all of this is air element
so tuning into that sense throughout the body
and this is really the same as the blowing of the wind outside
the world of motion that we live in it's all related to the air element
so as we rest in these flowing sensations you just open your
perception and let it move between solidity liquidity
heat emotion [Music] feeling the body as the
union and the dance and the sum of all of these
and knowing that the body is part of nature it's one more process
like all of those we experience externally
we may sense a certain ease and lightness in perceiving the body this way
so natural so simple
not very personal
may even bring some happiness
can we just rest in these simple experiences of nature
so as we practice with seeing the body in terms of these
four elements which are really more the
experiential aspect of the body how it really feels
we free ourselves from various fixed ideas we might carry about our body
things that are more concepts or ideas
instead of the actual experience
and this movement of moving from what is conceptual and
idea based and abstract to what is actually real in our experience
is much of what we do in practice and so then
we discover that we have many fixed ideas about ourself
about the world about other people
if we can just open to more of what the actual experience is
the sensations the reality
we become freer we can have a freer response to these
things so as we go out into the world
how else might we have this light feeling
freed from our usual ways of seeing things
would there be some way even just a little bit
to see things more as just nature
how might this more useful way of seeing be supportive of other people
maybe this kind of ease and flexibility and willingness to meet the
experience maybe that could open a space for more kindness more compassion
more willingness to be a little flexible
sometimes even relaxing and opening a bit
brings a surprise that we couldn't have anticipated
when we look back we think ah of course
so may your openness to your body
seeing it in a different way be supportive to the people around you
be supportive to the whole world
as we go out into today or the afternoon or evening
just keeping in mind that there can be a difference between the actual experience
and our ideas and concepts i'm trying to tend toward
the actuality of the moment may this bring peace and whiteness
and kindness into the world
so today we come to the final talk in our series on
the depth of the body and we'll talk about how the body
can play a role in insight practice
i'm amazed at how fruitful it has been and continues to be
to work with the body both on and off the cushion
actually troubles with my body are what got me into meditation and
even after many years i can say that it just goes deeper and deeper
and the the buddhist teachings uh support this idea it is said that um practicing with the
body in the right way can lead all the way to liberation from suffering
so there's quite a lot of potential there but to to do that
we do need to take a dharma perspective in looking at the body
despite living in our body for many years we may actually know very little about it
from a dharma perspective because that's not necessarily the usual way we would see it
we could start to ask questions like what what is the body really i mean the sense of the body is so
different at different times imagine how different you feel when you're
hungry when you're sick when you're tired when you're sleeping
when you're meditating when you're doing a headstand
all of these are very different experiences right is it even correct to say this is
the body much less my body it seems like it's a different thing
from moment to moment so body practice is wonderful because it
can be approached at any level actually we've explored a number of them this
week the body is immediately accessible at a top level
and there are times when it's the most obvious part of our experience
but also with certain practices that we do often in meditation the body can open to deeper and deeper
layers it can become very subtle and it can eventually reveal new perspectives on experience
so through dharma practice we're learning to see the body in new ways
maybe this is our greatest teacher and it's very close at hand you know our greatest teacher might be
right here with us so the body
that we see in the mirror with its eyes and nose and
shoulders and skin and hair and that ground belly
or whatever it's just one way to perceive it we're strongly conditioned to see our
body in this very conceptual way because we've done that for so long and
that's the support that we get from other people and from society around us
but many of the classical body meditations and contemplations
are designed to undermine or break down these habitual concepts that we bring
into our experience of the body and they're actually designed to get us to see things in a different way
not because this top level way or conventional way is wrong but because it's only one possibility and we limit
ourselves if we just use one so when we do this we do start to see the body differently
and actually it is more accurate to begin to see the body more experientially
and that opens a path toward wise understanding the body can be a
vehicle through which we start to understand more deeply how things work
so just we as we we can take an example of what we just did in the meditation which is the four elements meditation
and if you're interested in where that's found it's in writing the key instructions that we have on mindfulness
it's in the sati patana suta which is mn10 so this practice
of the four elements asks us to touch into the experience of the body
which is actually a mixture of different experiences the ones highlighted are the solidity
liquidity heat and motion uh that are found throughout the body
and these are not fundamentally different from [Music] external experiences those four things
which we encounter all the time in the world around us here in this cup i have some water
it has a certain temperature it moves when i shake the glass
cup so right there we have the four elements
it's kind of interesting also to consider when i take this water in
at one point at what point does it become part of my body
as opposed to outside of my body maybe it's already there because it's
disappeared but on the other hand it's still kind of just in my belly
it's interesting where is that dividing line we don't need to get really philosophically into this but
when we start to look a little bit just a little bit more carefully we see immediately that there are
questions about where is the division between external and internal
it can get you know subtle and not as obvious as we think when we
divide things up conceptually into words like internal and external those are nice words
but what do they where do they really shift from one to the other where are the boundaries around those not so clear
when we look in experience we also see that these things are shifting and changing you know there's
uh continual change about what's internal and external and breathing every moment
so we can start to see the uh inconstancy and impermanence and
changingness of the body and experience and internal and external and all of this so
we we leave this leads to important insights even at this very
basic level of experience into a nietzsche impermanence or in
constancy and then also toward anata not self
i mean really what part of this is yours
so this is worth exploring because it's an area of a lot of suffering
so all of this is is beginning to take what i'm calling a dharma perspective
on the body so we meet the actual experience of the body rather than various concepts that we
have about it we start to ask questions around those edges just to play a little bit with
what are the ways that our concepts might be restricting us so we also have concepts like
knee or back usually when we're talking about pain my knee hurts
so um as joseph goldstein says he's one of our elder insight teachers
he says there's no sensation called me and it's true right if you look into
what is the knee that is hurting right now there isn't one experience called knee
it's a concept it's an idea of some part of the body but when we look at the actual
experience we will see that even that pain is you know it's tension it's heat it's
pulling its sharpness there are more there are words that are much more specific than pain which is a
concept so we can start to meet our experience more at that level
grounding ourselves in actual sensations and we'll find that our experience of
that pain differs you know then our response to it and our possibilities of how we can be with it
also open up when our mental image of it opens up a bit so what we're learning is some
flexibility around experience and this has a lot to do with freedom
you know with having a freer response than when we can only be locked into one
way of seeing things so as we then going on as we experience the body
is ever changing from moment to moment it's very natural to begin to understand
that the body is not going to last forever in this form it's quite finite
um certainly it's undergoing it's undergone a lot of change to get to the point
where you are now isn't your body very different than it was 10 years ago 20 years ago
if you're old enough 50 years ago 60 yeah of course very different and it
will continue to be different that's called aging and of course it's finite eventually
something will end there yes so um
it's interesting and and important to begin contemplating in these directions
we do it gently you know everybody's in a different place around how they want to approach
the finiteness of the body but one of the easiest ways that we can start turning our mind in this direction
is simply to notice endings of all types so we can you know actually everything
ends uh our normal way of perceiving not our dharma way of perceiving is that we like
beginnings and so we rush on to the next thing that's beginning we prefer what is new and young
to what is old and decaying and so we start to notice things that are decaying or ending in very simple
ways we can do it externally internal external you know so we can notice leaves dropping from
the trees for example fall is beginning isn't it so flowers wilt
we can also notice the gatherings of friends come to an end so you know pause
to recognize endings just begin to flavor the mind with this notion that
there are beginnings and there are endings and it's beginning to take a very simple dharma perspective on life realistic
seeing the reality of how things actually are coming and going
there are times when it will be challenging to stay with reflections like this and
if that's the case you don't have to but um it's fine to maybe touch into this from
time to time you know to consider that the the body is going
toward a certain end at some point we may need patience to really take in the reality of the body
its ever changingness and its finitude and of course its impersonality in the
end these can be a little bit challenging to see into sometimes we can have the sense whoa
is this what i signed up for yes it is that we have this body
so truly the body is our friend you know it's always in the present moment
it's always honest the mind can be very tricky but the body is pretty honest
and it gently but persistently serves as a very deep dharma teacher
our closest teacher is very close at hand and who could ask for a better friend
so just as we talked about in the first talk this week
venerable ananda the attendant of the buddha said there's no friend like mindfulness
of the body so i hope that you've maybe have gained some
deeper appreciation of the depth of the body and its potential its power in our
dharma practice we want to learn about how things work and gain the kind
of wisdom that will help us live well in the world and really serve the world well
the body is a great vehicle a great teacher for that so perhaps you will honor your body in
some way today what a gift it is that we have this teacher for the short time
that we do so much appreciation for your presence and
your dharma practice and i wish you all very well thank you