thank you all for your greetings in the chat those of you putting the greetings there
and i take it they take them as representative of many of you who
don't have access to the chat then so thank you all very much for being
here so um
the topic of this week is mindfulness of emotions
and one of the ways of thinking about mindfulness and emotions
is that mindfulness is giving breathing room to our emotions
it's making more space for them to be there and one of the remarkable things that
can happen with meditation practice is the mind becomes more
calm or steady or open is that it can feel like there's actually a lot of space in the mind
in the heart in the body for uh everything
for the inner processing that goes on so including for our emotions
and so rather than thinking that we have to solve an emotion or fix an emotion or do
something with an emotion the um
one of the options in mindfulness practice is uh to make more room for the emotions
increase the space in which it's held space of awareness space of the mind
and doing so allows us to more kind of clarity
to see what's there when we're crowded with the emotion or identified with it strongly it's hard to
see what's there and sometimes what's there is something deeper
some emotions are just uh you know something knocking on
on the door saying here come here take a deeper look
so relaxing
is part of this path to making more room learning the art of simple recognition
is part of this path so assuming a meditation posture
and kind of a little bit wiggling around a little bit in your
posture and maybe to loosen things up a little bit when i first was taught meditation in
zen they i got the instructions to flap the elbows around a little bit
uh to uh kind of maybe loosen up the ways in which holding happens in the arms and the
hands it's kind of like a chicken and uh
and then kind of find a aligned posture in whatever way your posture
you're in is it aligned is it somehow allow
the maximum feeling of of the body being
in position
so there could be a flow or deeper relaxation
lowering your gaze softening your gaze
cooling your eyes
and then gently closing your eyes
and with your eyes closed might there be a deeper sensitivity now
for your body and its posture
maybe gently having the attention travel up the spine from the base of the spine
are there any small adjustments that you would like to make
partly so that the spine itself feels more alert
more here
so
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
as if you have all the time in the world to savor the inhale
to ride the exhale
and on that exhale to relax the body more
maybe a global relaxation
and letting the breathing return to normal
and on the inhale let your attention roam around your body
going to pick up or to feel any place where there's holding in the body
and on the exhale relax that part of your body
so it's kind of a random whatever shows itself to you relax as you exhale
relaxing deep in your belly
softening the belly
and then for about three or four breaths
settle into your breathing give yourself over to the inhales and exhales for just
three or four breaths
and then now notice how you're feeling
it might feel like an emotional state it might be a mood
mental state you might not think of it particularly
as an emotion but more that you're calm or
agitated it might feel more like a physical state
whatever it might be recognize it
and as you exhale is there any relaxation you can do
around it in the middle of it
or any relaxation you do you can do in the mind's relationship to it
and as if you can have more space around how you feel
feel your way into that space surround how you feel
maybe you can feel or imagine a sense of openness spaciousness
expansiveness around whatever way you're feeling
relax into that spaciousness
and then as if there's lots of space for breathing let the breathing
come and go in the space of the mind
with breathing at the center not to push away how you're feeling or
deny it but not to be involved with how you feel
letting us be there in the spaciousness of the mind
and you gently settling in
on breathing in and breathing out
if you are involved in your thinking chances are there's no space for how you
feel
if you're reacting to what's happening chances are there's not much space
for how you feel not much so much space for breathing
release your thinking
release your reactivity
release any contraction or narrowness
and relax into the space of awareness space
so you can better breathe with what is with lots of breathing room
and then as we come to the end of the sitting as you exhale
breathe relax again
what are you able to relax release
at the end of the sitting in the face and the shoulders the belly
in the heart in the mind
and the ability to relax can be seen as a gift that we bring into
the world if you're with small children and you're
tense and anxious by osmosis you're teaching the children
that there are things to be afraid of things to be
tense about but if you know how to relax
and be with the small children in a relaxed open non-anxious way
you teach those children that the world is a
comfortable enough place to be happy and playful and at ease
if you go into the world and people around you are in
challenge challenged by their health or by work or by
the world around them perhaps it's a gift that you come into
the world in a calm way relaxed way
just relaxed inappropriate way so by osmosis
we are spreading non-anxiousness
non-agitation making room for others
to relax as well
may it be that as we do this practice that we support the world we
help the world around us to be less anxious less agitated and tense
not by making them or teaching them how to do it but by our own
relaxation ease calm non-agitation
may we not stay keep the benefits of meditation for ourselves
let us share it with others maybe without them knowing that we're
meditators just by our presence
may it be that this practice we do is for the welfare and happiness of all
beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so in discussing mindfulness of emotion the
theme for today is respect
we started with relaxation and recognition and now respect as we recognize as we relax it's easier
to recognize as we recognize it's either easier to recognize
how we are relating to our emotional life are we are we
relating do we have an attitude towards it which is um
making it more difficult than it needs to be do we identify with it strongly defining
ourselves by it do we have hostility towards it do we not like
it and push it away or we do we have shame or embarrassment about it
do we have ideas that should be different are we trying to get rid of things
are we trying to have certain emotions certain feelings certain attitudes to the world and
are we kind of forcing kind of maybe even sugar coating
experience by trying too hard or are we holding on to things
maybe we were happy yesterday and so we're holding on to that idea that we should be
and um the um so they as we as we started recognizing the
component parts of emotions we see the extra reactivity we might have to it
and seeing that reactivity is the beginning of respect
and i really like this word respect because from the latin it means to see again
to uh to like spectacle to look again and um
and so to to start taking a deeper look at what's here
and if we can see our reactivity maybe we can put it aside enough that we can bring a respectful attention
to the emotion itself and and uh as if
as if it's allowed to be there because the disrespectful ways are often
trying to change something or hold on to something and not allowing it to be itself
so the second look the vipassana look that really taking a deeper look making
space for it allowing it for it to be there i like the idea that we're giving
permission for our emotions to be present and uh it's a little different than
allowing it's a little more active it's like a choice it's a decision i'm going to give i'm going to offer it's like a
generosity i'm going to offer permission for myself to be the way i am sophia and
as i said yesterday i think um sitting in meditation is a wonderful
place to do this because um you're kind of committed to sitting still
and not acting on whatever the feelings might be so
you know there might be some anger that seems very undesirable very strong
but in meditation we give it permission to be there
and then um and then um or if there's sadness or grief
or if there's joy and happiness we give permission for it to be there as we give permission for it to be
there and just allow it to be there without our reactivity or judgments or with those put aside enough we can so we
can really respect it what's there then i i
find it useful to think of emotions as either a message
or a messenger as a message emotions are here are they're not random
they're not incidental accidental phenomena just to kind of come through
they have some kind of message in them and maybe the message is that
asking for respect maybe the message is to
to saying to you here's an opportunity for you to discover how to be non-attached
how to not cling or resist and be more make more space
but it might be a deeper message you know so um and then anger might be a message
that we feel hurt or we feel threatened um sadness might be a message message
that we might feel um the um
um you know that uh we feel really impacted we really care we love something
and that love now feels you know feels sad or but the love is
underneath it and so it's a message of love and so rather than to think of grief and
sadness as a problem it's a it's a manifestation it's a movement it's a process that that love
needs to go through to be whole again or to find its way again
but sometimes emotions are messengers and
especially i think of this way when the emotions are afflictive
when the emotions are bringing suffering along to us
that and then you don't want to kill the messenger you want to really see what is the message here
so so so the ability to respect and get
permission and make breathing room allow for emotions to be there that's such a big part of mindfulness
uh then we start kind of seeing more deeply into the cracks of it
what else shows itself so it's not digging it's not analyzing
but feeling our way deeply into the emotion what else is there and so if it's with anger perhaps
what's there with it is hurt what's there with it is is fear and that is what needs our attention
that's probably that's more primary and so the messenger is pointing to these
deeper underlying kind of feelings that are there if there is grief
sometimes the messenger is that there is love and it's like hey have you really taken
into account how much their love there's been about what you've lost
sometimes the message of of
of despair is a message of healing fear
or feeling inadequate in some way sometimes the message of the messenger
is that it's time to take a deep honest look at the self-identity issues the way we
define ourselves the way that we um insert ourselves me myself and mine
into our life and some emotions have to do with that either the self the self-identity
self-definition we have has been threatened and now so boredom for example sometimes
is a symptom of whatever is happening around has no bearing on my self-concept how i
like to define myself or assert myself in the world no one's praising me
i'm not getting any real kind of praise and no one's criticizing me both
of those which are very riveting for some people and without either one of those the situation has no bearing i don't i'm not
building up myself in it or it's not threatened with it and so it's boring situation so boredom sometimes the whole
you know has to do sometimes with the complex of self-identity sometimes hostility sometimes
fear sometimes all the emotions
are closely connected to how threatened or how supported
our idea of who we should be is and so by really respecting emotions
taking our time making room for it and allowing it then
we can start seeing the underlying kind of processes that are going on that are deeper
so sometimes you can ask you know what is the message here in this emotion
and um and that way also it's very respectful of emotions it's kind of like they they
all have something to say they all they're not accidental incidental they're all represent some
deeper thing that's going on it doesn't require analysis when you do vipassana practice but what it involves
is this kind of more sensitive looking this more sensitive being present breathing with
it taking making room for it allowing it to be there so that
we can hear the subtler messages that are going on with it we can see the subtler process that goes on
and part of this permission for emotions to be there part of this respect for emotions
is that the emotions themselves
have the wisdom to process themselves to find their way to
peace if we make room for it if we really make space for it if we don't interfere with
them or or grab a hold of them or repress them or um if we don't you know acting on
emotions especially when you're in meditation interferes with that deeper process
towards healing towards peace to resolution that it's kind of inherent in the
emotions themselves so to respect emotions
and uh if you are challenged with an emotion um
and you know it's really caught you in some powerful way
and you would like to try this respect thing you might
put your hands together in the anjali and bow to your emotions
and just bow and if you want to you know really do something powerful
you about you bow and say thank you thank you for what you're trying to
do for me or the message you're bringing or how this is the best i can do at the moment to try to work with this
difficult world but it's going to bow to the emotions and um
and as a way of of um
as an alternative to being entangled reactive judgmental for there
and uh you might try it it's possible that one of the greatest goods you can do for
your emotional life is to offer a deep respect to it and maybe even a kind of reverence for
it that gets you out of the way of it but in meditation
protects you from acting on it in ways that may or may not be healthy
so um thank you and
and then we'll continue tomorrow on this topic so for today for the next 24 hours
um you might if you this idea of bowing to your emotions is at all interesting for
you you might either do it or physically or you might actually do it in your imagination
try bowing to your emotions and see what happens but
but give room for your emotions that's the most important thing and if you have enough ability to take a
break if you're in the middle of something work or family life or something and you have a strong
emotional response and you don't usually do this see if you can go take a walk around the
block with it take the emotions with you yeah just like you could take them take the
emotions for a walk and and use that maybe as a time to make room for it to respect respect
it listen to it more deeply and see what happens if you if that's an alternative to how you
usually are with emotions um try this alternative try the respect
thing for and see what happens over the next time so thank you