so good day greetings and uh happy sitting here seeing the greetings
on the chat and the names and so thank you all and
so the topic is still samadhi and uh
i like to sometimes translate this word as to be composed and that's a wonderful i think concept
that brings together some of the qualities of somebody of
landing on some place being established being calm and
centered being steady with the experience that we're focusing
on if um we go i've gone into the wilderness like up in the mountains
where there was no trails but there were cairns there were these little piles of stones that people had
built that indicated where more or less where the direction was to walk
and so we would hike along and we would look for the cairns and and then we'd find our way
but if uh we hadn't looked you know if i hadn't known about karen's and also just was fascinated by
everything up there and and um and was looking at everything equally i
wouldn't have found uh you know the way forward if i was if i was really scared about running
into trolls up in the high sierras in california and was constantly looking out for
trolls i also wouldn't have found my way because i wouldn't have seen the cairns if not even if i knew there
to look for them but if we know to look for karen's then we know how to find the way so the same
thing with meditation we can be afraid of trolls and spend our time looking for trolls
we can be searching for long lost treasures in
the world lottery tickets and we don't really pay attention to what's really here
and but there are karen's there are these markers these uh signposts that for samadhi it's
helpful to recognize them and in recognizing them that's how we find our way
and um and there's many signposts but i would like to emphasize two of them
now one is um a uh to be steady a certain kind of steady
composure with the experience and if when we're steady when we hold ourselves steady when the the gaze
is steady when the when the our composure is steady when our attention is steady
or that part of our attention is steady so we're looking for that part of our attention that
is steady or can be steady and we're steadying ourselves in that the other is um a quietude
a tranquility maybe it's a a serenity and and
even if we're agitated we might be able to just pick out the corners of the mind
the heart the body where there is some tranquility uh some quietude
and uh and then to include that to kind of orient ourselves oh this is the place
this is the way forward here in this part and um and but if we don't recognize that
quietude that tranquility then we don't uh we know we don't see the signposts
and the third is um to um so composure quietude tranquilly
and third is non-destructibility a kind of a non-dispersal of the mind
non-distractedness of the mind and even if we're you know 99 distracted we might kind of pick up
uh the signpost of that way in which the mind is not distracted
is not dispersed not spinning out centrifugal force are kind of just scattered and all kinds of thoughts and
ideas and as the as samadhi begins becoming stronger there's a stronger and stronger feeling
of the mind not being dispersed not being scattered not jumping around not being
fragmented the mind starts feeling composed quiet
centered um and it is just a feeling like the mind is really here now it's
not just non-distracted or non-dispersed kind of feeling and
and and so
so these are three signposts that we can follow so to take an upright
meditation posture and if you're lying down then upright means
laying with a certain dignity and vitality or openness some way that
maybe expresses
an integrity or a wholeness or confidence in being here
and gently closing your eyes
and being a little bit delightfully serious at the beginning of the meditation
to prepare yourself to so that you can really be here and the sacredness of the present
moment so you're preparing yourself and so you take a few long slow deep
breaths and the deep inhale is a
for affirmation that indeed you are here that you've
showed up here i am i'm showing up for this deep breath filling the torso with
not just air but with sensations and expansion and maybe even
confidence here i am
and then to exhale long gentle exhale letting all of that go
letting go of it tension and holding and
and then letting your breathing return to normal and we prepare the mind and the heart by
relaxing the body all these are very closely connected
so relaxing the muscles of the face
around the eyes the jaw
and to soften and release the shoulders
the area around the shoulder blades perhaps
perhaps the outer edge of your shoulders as the shoulders turn around to go down the arm
the very top of the upper arms
perhaps relaxing the chest softening in the chest
and then relaxing the belly in such a way the belly the weight of the belly
gets lower
settles into a foundation the lower torso
and then with your attention your mind
gently placing it on your breathing wherever you're going
to be primarily focusing on breathing imagine that attention is gently
placed on that area
but clearly kind of settling into your breathing
again affirmation that here is where you're going to walk here's where you're going to be
present
if you can make some small adjustments in your breathing to make it more comfortable
relaxing some part of the musculature breathing
breathing a little slower a little faster a little deeper or shallower
whatever makes it comfortable for you
and adjusting how you are with your attention
is there some way that your attention can be less forceful or strained
less up in the control tower trying to stare at the breathing
and more that the attention the awareness is within the breathing itself
in the sensations of breathing
and then noticing whatever's quietude or tranquility there might be
here even if it's in the cracks between any agitation
or in the side or deeper inside
that's right letting them thinking mind become quieter
slower maybe the thinking mind can even be more
gentle so it's easier to notice the quietude
the tranquility
that
and let that tranquility be part of the atmosphere within which
you're mindful of your breathing
and notice whatever degree of
stability or steadiness
you can establish with your breathing
whatever steadiness on breathing that's here for you
and then also notice any way that you are non-distracted
the mind is not scattering out into all kinds of thoughts
and even if you are doing that look for the signposts look for that part of you which is not
that way that's capable of being undistracted
with your breathing
relaxed calm
steady undistracted
these are the signposts
that point you to samadhi to staying present
to being intimate with the experience of breathing
one breath at a time
when you notice yourself thinking a lot look for the quiet and tranquility here
let that tranquility of mind spread
open up further so it's easier to stay with your
breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
you could begin by remembering that we're still meditating
there's nothing you have to say to anyone or do for anyone for this few next two minutes
there's no responsibility and obligation to to do anything but sit here quietly
and in the privacy of just sitting here with nothing you have to do
can you somehow let the your heart open
your kindness open
to think of people around you and here on this youtube
sitting together or in your homes or communities places of
work think of them with
goodwill a very private goodwill
they don't have to know about it you don't have to do anything
just opening your kindness goodwill
in a sense
being aware of these people around you
within the quietude the tranquility that might be here
and without needing to bring them into your bring too close to you just there
in the privacy of your own heart perhaps you can feel or sense or extend
the sentiments of these words
may you be happy
may you be safe
may you be peaceful
may you be free
and if in the safety and privacy of meditation
in your own heart if it's possible easier than to have
good will for others
stay close to that maybe you don't have to confuse it with
what you actually do
or feel obligated to do stay close to that place where it's private
maybe even secret trusting
that having good will for others will some way or other spread from you
with benefits for the world
may whatever benefits that come from this practice this morning
spread from us like the scent of a rose spreads out
into the garden so may this benefits that we've had today
laughed out into the world for the welfare and happiness of all beings everywhere may all
beings be happy
um
so some people are fond of reading books
about buddhism and if they want to learn about meditation they might go find a book
or maybe nowadays some people go find audio recording
for the book people the book we're trying to read is
found within ourselves we're learning to read
ourselves read the signposts the symptoms the movements the
process of meditation that unfolds within us that's the book to read or that's the
audio recording to listen to really listen deeply into what's happening here
and sooner or later all that we are to discover in buddhism
is meant to be discovered here in our own body in our own experience
so to learn to read the signposts to read the to you know to leave to read what's
happening is part of the skill uh for samadhi for developing concentration
they uh the stability this composure this unification of mind
there are signposts and the pali word for signposts
usually translated into english as signs is nimita n-i-m-i-t-a
and it's um it's used in a very different way different ways down through the history
of buddhism it has different meanings what this is sometimes it's reduced in
meaning to being a visual image that some people will see when their
concentration gets strong maybe they're seeing a light maybe a white light or yellow light this this
it kind of lights up as they get concentrated and so the the image is called the nimita but in the
early buddhist tradition and nimitz any kind of sign or indicator of the presence of
something or that something is about to happen and and so the the buddha said that the
nourishment for samadhi what feeds and supports somebody
is is two of these two of these signposts that we can find and
we can read we can recognize in ourselves and one of them is this word samata
s-a-m-a-t-h-a and which means tranquility or calm or
quietude and the other is a word that means
something like non-dispersal or non-fragmentation or
non-um agitation of our thinking mind and so
as part of this unification process this gathering together being centered here we're not being
de-centered by spinning out and and
i think the pali word that's translated as non-dispersal could maybe uh be read as a
non-de-centered uh as a as a um
you know so and so so these these are nimitz so as as we start getting
concentrated as we start getting settled and start a steadiness of mind then um
to recognize these signposts to recognize that there is a quietude or a
tranquility or serenity however we want to translate this word samata and and to recognize we're
starting to be non-de-centered we're starting to be not scattered or dispersed in our minds and
the mind's not jumping around and chasing every thought that comes along and we're wandering off for minutes at a
time in our fantasies or our thoughts but there's a real feeling now of being
gathered in being non-dispersed being here and uh that doesn't have to neither one
of these have to be very strong at first and this is where learning to reckon
know that these are signposts they're kind of pointing the way so
there might be a lot of agitation there might be a lot of dispersal of the mind but if we keep focusing on those we
it's too easy to reinforce those and the nourishment for samadhi is to
take in to allow our son to experience to experience or to be supported by tranquility and
non-dispersal of the mind this centeredness of the mind and um
and so this um and so even if there's a lot of agitation uh to recognize maybe in the cracks of
it behind it in the back room of it in the attic and the basement somewhere inside to recognize oh there's
a little bit there yes i'm agitated but in fact a little bit in my sternum there's a
little feeling of tranquility there a little bit in my hands my hands feel
steady and confident and a little bit calm tranquil and so to find where it
might be don't manufacture it and don't worry too much if you can't find it
we're talking about now as meditation deepens and deepens
not just from you know just sitting down and boom there you have to be able to do this but as you begin feeling yourself
settling and feeling yourself getting more and more here and calmer than you were before
um that's when you start feeling that's where the to appreciate to affirm
to validate these signs these signposts this is good this is the path forward
this is the direction to go this is the now i'm now i've picked up the book
where the chapter where i left it this is where where you know now i'm picking up again where
you know the place where my practice is really deepening and and so to recognize these
um um uh you know these these signposts so i
see there's a for the other uh nimita there's two nibitas in pali what is samata and the other one is
a v y a g g a and aga could mean like center and
uh and the vui is divided or separated and a means not
not separated from the center so this idea being centered
so there are other signposts for samadhi there's a lot of them and so over time you might learn these
different ones that that can support us oh this is good now that
we're in the territory this is the direction forward because to recognize it not so much to
be a not at all to be attached to it or try to engineer and work too hard to get concentrated
but simply to uh not for the mind to begin recognizing that
this is the way forward this is the path in the forest as opposed to being distracted by every
little troll and bird and insect and butterfly off into the forest and we go chasing
after it and we lose the trail so to gather ourselves together
to start feeling and recognizing these signposts so some of the other ones are as
some people feel the physical sensations that shift and change that show they're getting concentrated there can be tingling feeling of
lightness a feeling of warmth the glow the feeling there might be
some people there's a strong feeling of physical pleasure uh sometimes a little bit of pressure uh
vibration that begins happening someplace some sometimes in the forehead the people feel it there sometimes in
the chest sometimes the belly and sometimes parts of our body like the
arms start feeling so light and maybe even they seem to disappear because
things are so tranquil so peaceful there or other parts of the body the um there might be a
visual uh signpost like i said there might be uh the field of vision starts it might
get completely white or some other color sometimes there are
some people when they get concentrated will see little shapes in their field of vision sometimes geometrical shapes
and it's important not to get distracted by these things by the by the visual uh
images especially if there's like geometrical signs or shapes or something um but they are supportive and so to
take them kind of like in the background of your experience oh i'm on track i'm getting this is this
this is a signpost that i'm getting concentrated that i'm deepening here and um
and uh is is and then there are um what could be
considered may be more mental uh signposts or emotional signposts
a common one is joy and feeling a joy welling up
a delight the kind of pleasure sometimes it's even a sense of rapture when the samadhi gets strong but there's
a feeling of delight of gladness of relief that might be there and sometimes it's a deep sense of
happiness something is more sublime more subtle more more of a sense of contentment a
deep contentment in the quietude here and sometimes a sign of getting
concentrated is that the mindfulness gets clearer and clearer the awareness gets clearer and clearer
and there becomes more equanimity in that clear awareness which is equanimous we're less likely to be reactive to things
and feeling that equanimity feels so good and um so don't expect all these things
to happen at once um and maybe don't even memorize don't even try to memorize and look for all
the things i've said i've talked about the two things that buddha emphasized as nimitz was this
tranquility or calm quietude samata
or this non-de-centeredness the non-dispersal non-scatterness of the
mind the mind being composed and both of those are supported by the two
actions verbs that buddha used when he instructed us for what in english we
might say become concentrated he didn't use the english word concentrated because he
didn't speak english he used two words one was the word to settle and the other is to steady
to settle on something and to steady oneself on something so the those four can be your signposts
settle settle the settling on the breathing or in your experience
a steadiness with your breathing a delightful warm
content quietude tranquility and and and in
non-de-centeredness a feeling ah this is good to really be
here not scattered anymore and perhaps you can read the read at the
inner book read yourself and see if you can find
the you know that supports you and guides you and gives you kind of more something to
in a good sense of the term hold on to as you're developing concentration and and or be cheerleaders or support
from the side just stay there be there this is good this is keep opening to this keep opening to
this and if you're not ready for that or if you're not uh you know if it didn't it doesn't work
because you're trying too hard or you're not you know it's too much work just put it aside
um but sooner or later hopefully you begin begin recognizing your signposts for what it means when
the goodness of samadhi goodness of being settled and unified begins to come into play
and then to appreciate that to validate that to affirm that so the mind knows this is
what's important this is what's valuable thinking about trolls and
butterflies and all the other things are useful sometimes but not for the purpose of meditation
so um thank you all very much and and we'll continue
tomorrow