b
this
hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour hi
and if you can hear me okay if you would give me a thumbs up audios are right fantastic great
let's start by saying some hellos and i'll start by saying hi i'm nikki
i'm in mountain view california on seated oloneyland who is here who wants to say hi
you can either unmute yourself or you can type it in chat
hi i'm jamie from redwood city california hi jeannie welcome oh thank you
hi neil from new hampshire hi ken from albuquerque hi bill from dallas texas hi violet from
chicago airport enroute to cape town wow you're good i'll add another continent
to our sangha she says so exciting violet this is very oh yeah look at you with your mask at
the airport huh it's so sweet it warms my heart to see that's great uh hi marianne from
burlingame it's great yes you add another continent i love it
uh harm i'm mark and terence from squim washington hi
great anybody else wants to say hi before we formally get started
hi i see people waving see jerry waving i don't see everyone just a few people
but that's great okay well let's get started let's get started so um let's
mute ourselves if you aren't already muted and i change the setting so that um i'm muting
accidental unmuting won't be possible for the guided meditation and thank you neil for sharing the
google groups information in the chat and i also am changing the chat capacity
uh so that it'll be quiet and if there's only something very urgent like if the sound drops out you can send me text
and mark says hello on youtube from colorado hello mark and other folks on youtube for joining us terrific
oh yes and recording for audio dharma let's do that
okay all right here we go so so hello hello warm hello everyone
ah good to be with you good to be together this friday or
or saturday or for folks who would be listening on audio dharma later whatever time or it
might be so so for our practice today um especially given that it's
you know conventionally it's the end of the week i like to have a lot of silence and space for us to settle
and be together in this space and the theme i'd like to invite us to explore
is um is uh inspired
from uh oh various inspirations but really the the words we'll be playing with
tonight is it's okay it's okay it's okay
it's okay and if if you want to translate that to your mother tongue the equivalent of that and so it's okay
and the the sense to bring that in is um the the sense to bring in and play
with tonight and explore is um one aspect of it i'll offer
different things but just to set the stages you know when say if there is a child
who's hurt themselves themselves and and fallen um on the playground and they get
up and they're crying say it's okay it's okay it's not a way of saying you know
shut up stop crying it's like it's okay sweetie you know it's hurting but it's okay it's really okay because as the adult
you have the bigger picture that yes this is this is just a scrape and yes you're
upset and in the big picture it's really okay so it's that wisdom perspective it's
that in the inner wisdom the wider perspective that you bring in in this
way and for the younger child like it's okay it's okay sweetie it's okay um
it's the sense of comforting there's a sense of also confidence that it is okay even though
it might be hurting right now or challenging but really it's okay it's okay and there's another
aspect of that with the it's okay which i like to invite you to explore is that
it's okay even when it's not okay it's okay and that
is a perspective of
awakening a perspective of wisdom that it's all okay even when it's not okay
it's okay and as i say this don't try to figure it out
um and if it doesn't work for you throw it away but there is some there
can be a sense of okayness when we really um
drop in or expand dropping into a sense of spaciousness expansiveness this
the knowing of the inner buddha within us that it really is okay it's
all okay even when it doesn't feel like it's okay so working with that um
and even even if you we might think oh i'm not there yet i don't i don't know and she's talking
about this and this awaken enlightenment perspective when it's all okay like it's not this is terrible
can can we for a moment just for a moment drop into that and allow in knowing that
we all have this capacity this inner awakened buddha that we all
share and and and have um allow that to shine for a moment with
the yeah it's okay it's really okay so
so we can take this practice of it's okay on many different levels on the relative level of oh i've had a
hard week or i've had a hard day or right now my body is hurting oh it's
okay it's okay it's okay sweetie it's okay so you can take it on the relative level
and that's perfectly fine please let's let's actually explore it on the
relative level and as we quiet invite our mind to be
quiet maybe the maybe what's called perhaps
the ultimate level might peak through might show itself
through a grace beyond our control we might just show up like oh yeah it really is okay it's all okay
it's great actually just as it is i can be happy just as things are
not needing anything to be different or perfect not waiting for life to be perfect for
me to be happy um it's it's okay it's all okay
so some invitations to play with so so if it's okay let's start our practice
together like to invite you
to land to land into your meditation posture
the weather sitting lying down it's all okay
landing in this body
inviting gently inviting
the body to relax to soften
landing in your seat in your sit bones
feeling your feet
on the floor your bottom on the cushion
taking a few minutes to just arrive it's okay to take my time
to arrive with my body
gaze turned inward feeling the sensations receiving
sensations
how is the abdomen
receiving the breath feeling the sensations in the chest
relaxing releasing
c
letting the breath greet neck and shoulders
arms and hands the sensations
throughout softening and relaxing
c checking in with your face
softening relaxing the forehead the jaw
moving down
relaxing softening the heart the heart center
it's okay it's okay to let our hearts relax in this moment whatever is happening
right now is okay there is joy contentment
or heaviness fatigue it's all okay
it doesn't have to be any other way
landing again in the sit bones
the breath as if it's expanding
the contact area as if we were a beach ball being inflated by the breath
our bottom breathy contacting [Music]
ah the legs lower legs and feet
not scrunched up but having a lot of surface area
to connect the cushion of the earth
and if thoughts arise
it's okay it's really okay
no it's the thinking buddha showing up in this moment the distracted buddha it's okay
seeing clearly smiling late
letting there be space
as you breathe throughout your body feeling spacious not tight
about thinking it's okay thoughts come they go
let's land again with ease in the body with the breath befriending the breath
taking a moment of refuge
together
and whatever arises sounds arise
if pain discomfort arises
or if the mind wanders onto something else
let there not be self-judgment
criticism it's okay it's okay
it's all okay and gently lovingly
releasing
without judgment smilingly
coming back to the breath and the body it's okay
it's okay it's okay just as it is
it's okay whatever it's is arising in this moment
not fighting
not resisting
is it possible to open up to whatever is arising
with joy it's okay it's okay
you're welcome to stay with the simplicity of the practice
without any images just offering radical okayness to whatever is
arising the mind and heart that's okay perfectly okay
and if you wish i'll offer some other invitations to
explore with this practice of it's okay
so you can tune them out or explore further here we go
if you wish can bring in bring in someone into your heart space
into this space this quiet space
maybe someone who's dear to you and maybe there's something challenging that they're dealing with
that's impermanent and if that feels too big or not easy to
access maybe having bringing inviting
an image of a child you know or when they were a child maybe
they're grown up now
maybe has a scrape or has just fallen
maybe not even a scrape but but they're upset they're crying and you're holding them
saying it's okay it's okay sweetie you're letting them cry it's okay
it's okay it's okay
and you know with your wisdom
the bigger picture you have access to the vision the perspective that you have that it's
okay this is impermanent it hurts now and in the big picture it's
okay
it's okay it's okay we all feel hurt sometimes
it's okay it's okay
and it's okay to cry it's okay to be hurt it's okay it's all okay
offering comfort offering meta friendliness care
love
might show up in the form of meta or compassion if there's a lot of hurt that's being
met it's okay it's okay
it could be a sense of equanimity
imbued with love imbued with care it's okay it's okay seeing the bigger picture
it's okay
see what nuance works best for you
and now letting ourselves be the recipient
of the care
can either have a sense of yourself sitting as you are maybe even putting the palm
of your hand in your heart center it's okay sweetie it's okay it's
all okay it's all okay sense of comfort peace reassurance
it's okay or you can imagine yourself a younger
version of yourself
having had a little fall playing or riding a bike
you're comforting a younger version of yourself it's okay sweetie it's okay
now now it's okay i love you it's okay
see what works best for you play around
and remember you're both the wise
loving compassionate being
who has equanimity as well as the one who is
receiving it and if holding both is difficult maybe you can
see yourself receiving it from [Music] a compassionate image maybe
the buddha or konya or the being of light is holding you and
saying it's okay it's okay it's okay it's okay
feel free to explore
and for the last few minutes of this practice i'd like to invite you to explore in
your own voice it's okay with empowerment
it's okay it's okay
it's okay it's all okay
see if there might be nuances not just of comfort and compassion
but have empowered equanimity
radiant it's okay
nuances of joy
do
may all beings everywhere
enjoy a deep okayness and be free
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so it's okay it's all okay so this
it's okay can have a sense of care love comfort and yet this perspective
this perspective equanimity of holding it all
having a bigger picture of you and interested to hear what nuances you
discovered and explore it and you're welcome to type in chat
questions comments and if you type to me privately i won't say your name
and if it's to everyone i'll read your name and you can also raise your zoom hand
especially if you haven't commented if you haven't spoken and shared in the group for a while
your practice is is precious your questions whatever you bring forth
know that it's an offering to the sangha and i like to make space again stepping
forward for those who haven't spoken in a while first so uh
what did you notice what what did you
discover and silence is okay too it's okay
jerry says it reminded me of the beatles song let it be yeah
since you talked about the song i'll also say i was going to talk about this a little later
but but i'll say it now the um one inspiration for the session
this evening was a friend forwarded to me a
um little youtube segment um and in that it's it's one of these
shows the um these talent shows where someone comes and
sings and in this one very touching a young woman 30 years old um
comes and sings this song and she's very thin not quite clear at first and she says
she's okay and turns out she has cancer active cancer and she has two percent chance of survival and she sings this
song beautifully with so much joy that it's okay it's an original song so i'll ask neil
to to forward that to um to the google groups
so that if you're interested you can all watch it but it's so touching that it's okay it's okay
there's such a sense of power and grace in in her offering it's okay it's okay
so i wanted to give her credit and unfortunately i don't know her name to give her proper credit uh whoops
if i find it i will share it when you come back from the groups but any other kenneth yes please
ah hi nikki thank you um near the end when you were when you
started talking about saying okay as an and empowerment
yeah it reminded me of kristen neff divides self-compassion
into tender and fierce yeah so it reminds me of fierce self-compassion yeah
yeah yeah thank you yeah it's um exactly there's so many nuances there
can be tender self-compassion that that's one aspect it's like it's okay sweetie it's
okay and then there's like okay i'm here for you i'm gonna protect you it's okay sweetie it's it's it can still be the
same words but different nuance itself of yep i'm i'm here for myself yeah
thank you kenneth charles lee please
okay there we go hi yes thank you this is a
concept that uh my understanding is certainly cheap and
changed by practice i always thought the phrase
it's okay was kind of patronizing kind of uh just
kind of one of those meaningless things that you know that that people say in uncomfortable
situations but uh leaning leaning into practice and
really you know leaning into that that that suchness just just you know it
you know being able to experience something just just as it is um i think i had a
an experience of this on on the playground with my daughter
she had apparently been yelled at or talked to not nicely by
another another five-year-old and she came crying to me
and um i could sense uh this immediate want to like go fix
something and go like you know who you know who treated you badly and who and i and then i
recognized that wait a minute you know um right now
she's upset and she needs you know she needs to be held and and uh and i was able to do that uh
and and what happened was that i i kind of just i forgot about the other kid i forgot about needing to kind of
get revenge or or figure out you know what went wrong um
and i thought that was uh you know that was something i wouldn't have done two years ago i would have been
you know already you know become a detective prosecutor you know judge and jury for this you
know five-year-old kid who who knows who they are so thanks
thank you charlie it was a beautiful story i loved both aspects of it and how leaning into
the practice you know it's okay it really has it's not this dismissive oh it's okay
it's it's more like oh it's tapping into the suchness of things oh it's okay there's a deeper okayness that
we're acknowledging when we say it's okay and and beautiful i love the the the story the
reactive catching yourself and especially given that i brought the story of the the image of the playground i love that
your story had this you know your child actually on the playground and being upset and oh yeah with the appropriate
response the appropriate response is what's needed here thank you it's beautiful i appreciate you sharing that
lovely and mark has a comment the impermanence is crucial
however awful the suffering it will end sometime even if it takes death to end it death can be the ultimate
in our being loved yeah yeah touching yeah
so dear ones let's turn our attention to practicing together in small groups and
it's okay if you have to go but it's okay if you're uncomfortable in the group so extend
your limit like oh i don't want to be with people see it's okay to be just a little uncomfortable
if you to stretch yourself a little bit and see what it's like to practice with sangha members it's it's actually
they're quite lovely they're more than okay so so um let's start with 15
when you get into groups uh when you get into groups of three
roughly that would be the size let's start with 15 seconds of silent
meta just warmth for yourself care for each other it's all okay to be in silence together and
then you can share as little or as much as you like with each other with this precious
sangha small sangha so here we go the rooms are open
enjoy
thank you thank you mark okay welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed welcome back great so
okay we've got a few minutes for any reflections anything you might have discovered
conversation with each other and especially like to again open it up if you haven't spoken for a while
oh and i found the youtube link and the name of the person who offered the song
was was nightbird to give her the inspiration i'll put the link but then watch it now
i'll also send we'll send it also in the youtube uh in in google groups anyway reflections what
what did you notice what came up in the groups
anything about your practice you like to share tonight
okay now everyone is clicking on the link i sent don't don't do that now
my mistake
oh anything you notice about your practice
the practice of it's okay did anything shift or change
did some things become more clear when you discuss them in group
yes please
sue chung yeah your name right yes thank you thank you i feel like i'm
the one who's always talking every day
so um again a different different style of just practice
and uh which is what i really needed today um it's like
one of my i mean in a chat room someone told me oh yeah i don't think that i really um treat
myself well but whenever i feel that way then you practice it's i mean
it's it's okay you don't have to be perfect it's okay but then
for me like i was just freaked out in the morning about just unexpected things happen
and then i was just trying to figure things out and then and i knew that oh yeah
happy sangha hours it's six o'clock i'm like okay and then all of a sudden you say
it's okay you know like so resonated about your situation
everything will be okay everything is okay yeah everything
is okay which is a little different i would say from everything will be okay is more like everything is okay it's
it's okay it's okay it's it's yeah so yeah so yeah we're all human we all
get frazzled it's okay it's okay it's all okay
thank you for bringing that in beautiful yeah the common humanity very sweet so thank you
all thank you for your practice for your beautiful practice
for doing this work not just for yourself but for all beings whose lives you touch may all
beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you thank you