okay great so welcome warm welcome to all of you
for this friday's edition of happy hour
so for today's theme of our practice um
[Music] i'd like to invite us to consider it's a
merging of different of a couple of different themes and ideas and one is
um an antidote an anti as an antidote you know meta has been
taught also can serve as an antidote to self-criticism
to self-judgment to the self-judgmental thought coming up you're terrible you're awful you're a
failure you haven't accomplished anything in your life you know you're not going anywhere just the most horrible terrible things
that we wouldn't tell anyone but oh it just comes up and just gets unleashed and it can be very
painful and not for everyone not all the time but it can come up now and then and and
it um tends to be more prevalent somehow in the west because we measure us ourselves so much
according to these external standards of that the media holds up power and money
and use and beauty and and can cause a lot of
suffering so so with that and again you may not identify with this
right now and so you are welcome to file this teaching on and um uh
for a later user there might be some other areas that this can actually be helpful as this can be
supportive so so a meta loving kindness and practices of
the heart in general there are many ways many ways to really shake us shake ourselves out of
the prison this make fabricated this made-up fabricated prison
of comparison and self-judgment because maybe you have a memory of you know a
moment or if you've had the storm of self-judgements of comparison
a moment one moment you're fine it's like you're going about your business and the next moment it just comes on
and then this fabrication gets created and then sadness and depression
self-recrimination so so how to one way one way to shake ourselves out of there
are many many practices one practice i'd like to offer for us to to explore
is is um in a way taking ourselves out of it
because the self criticism self recombination self self self it all has to do with the
self me me me me i'm terrible i'm great i'm awful i'm fantastic i'm i i are right
so what if we just take the self out of it in a very healthy way
really turn this whole paradigm on its head and one question
one come one question one way we can explore this is how may i be of service
how may this being be of service how can i serve so in a way with that question
it's intended to not see us as getting wanting i want this i'm not
getting that is oh how can this being that is me with all the connections in the world with
all the personal connections with all the relationships with all the skills
how can i show up in the way to serve to serve the world so it's not about me getting it's me about me ah
how can i offer how can i offer how can i how can i let my heart my body my
resources be a gift unto others and
this can be this can be a radical way to shift ourselves out of this
this me i'm not good enough i want this it just completely changes the frame it changes
the frame and along these lines of how may i serve
how can i be of service and it can be simple it can be very simple we're not talking
about grand um you know could be grand right you could you could change the
the direction of your life but it could also be in very subtle ways oh with you know this person i'm in a
relationship with i can smile i can say something kind to them i can serve them
i can call them up and call up a friend or someone say how are you doing you know
do you need anything do if they're alone can we hang out this weekend or something just could be
serviced could show up in very very small ways so how so basically instead of it being
about us to not make it about us not about me it's not about me it's not
about you it's not about me and this practice isn't about me me me me me make it not about
me and in the same way i'll share i'll share a quote
by marianne williamson um that has been attributed to so many
people but again within this perspective of service of shining of shining
our hearts shining our lights not from a place of ego like i'm great i'm fantastic but
shining our light from a place of service of a place of goodness
so i'll read this quote and then we'll start the practice together you might have heard
it before so here we go she says our deepest fear
is not that we are inadequate our deepest fear is that we are powerful beyond
measure it is our light not our darkness that most frightens us we ask ourselves
who am i to be brilliant gorgeous talented fabulous actually who are you
not to be you're a child of god you're playing small does not serve the
world there is nothing enlightened about shrinking so that other people won't feel insecure
around you we're all meant to shine as children do
we were born to make manifest the glory of god that is within us it's not just in some
of us it's in everyone and and as we let our light our own light shine
we unconsciously give other people permission to do the same as we are liberated from
our own fear our presence automatically liberates others so this way of shining
shining our light shining our goodness not in this self-centered way but as a
way of serving as a way of serving others letting this
light all the gifts that have been given to to be of service so
so with those as themes for our practice let's embrace
some silence let's practice together so i'd like to invite you
to get into your meditation posture whatever might be comfortable for you
sitting lying down
standing walking whatever it might be
before postures
since i'm sitting i'll give the instructions the touch points
with settings
translate for your own body posture
so sensing feeling your feet
your feet on the floor
connecting with the earth child of the earth child of the universe
all of us in our humanity not different
feeling your sit bones your lower legs
contacting the cushion or the chair
letting yourself land release release
releasing into the contact points with the earth
letting the breath breathe you soothe you
settle and calm every muscle of the body
fighting your lower body your feet your legs ah
your sit bones to relax let go of any tension
so too your abdomen
the chest
shoulders neck but the arms feel heavy the hands
dropping their weight
letting the muscles of the face unwind
no need to wear any mask no smile or anything right now
releasing completely releasing
muscles behind the eyes
behind the jaw the chin the forehead
letting the weight of every muscle entire body to drop internally
to be released to be freed
if thoughts arise it's not a problem
inviting the thoughts to settle with the next breath
there's nothing wrong with thinking but for now we are calming inviting the mind to settle
thinking thought let's settle come back later
giving my heart to this practice to cultivating kindness
goodness right now
letting each breath feel the heart
fill the body with ease
settling more and more into this moment to the gift of this moment
i like to invite you if you wish
if you're sitting let yourself sit just a little taller
you need to adjust sitting just a little taller
the sense of integrity in your posture
a sense of nobility in this being
showing up on this cushion in this chair
with a role to play in service to serve others
for this life to unfold
according to your highest values which from the outside may not be
visible but from the inside
you know [Music] that cultivating goodness cultivating
kindness cultivating integrity
cultivating service compassion
friendliness
a brightness honesty so many other beautiful values
whatever there might be for you
are important to you as as if there were as if there was a
vertical line
aligning upholding lifting you up
is consideration uplifts you
as if opening your chest your heart to shine shine its goodness into the
world how may i be of service
how may i be of service how may this be life be of service
to goodness and goodness
not so much about me and mine what i get what i don't get
but turning the frame turning the frame of selfishness on its head
it's not about me what if it's not about me just this moment trying it on for size
you can always take it all back and make it all about you later but experiment
try it on for size for a moment cultivating goodness
menta friendliness
in service
in service to what is me and beyond me larger than me
greater than me greater than conception this conceiving that i have
of who i am and my role in the world
wishing wishing goodness for all beings everywhere
cultivating friendliness friendliness and goodwill
no matter what their circumstances are whether they're friends
or whether you have challenges with them or whether they in their own way they're causing harm
their own confusion
letting therapy kindness goodwill
unconditionally
for the freedom of your own heart and letting your light shine
your goodness
shine in the world and be of service
and if you notice any judgments arising any self-judgments
as we discussed at the beginning i'm not doing this right i'm not good
enough my mind is distracted
what if this is not about me but how i am doing what if we can let go
of all of that taking the self out of the equation
this concern self concern me me my mind
how am i perceived how am i this just taking it all out how can this being be of service how can
i serve it's not about me it doesn't matter
we feel into that radical shift even for a split second
what if this isn't so much about me this self that i take myself to be
but beyond me this being is part of
the magnificent fabric of humanity
beyond my conception what if it's not just about me in this moment this cultivation of my
heart and goodness can i trust can i trust to let my
goodness shine without fear without fear
for the last moments of this practice
period and if there are any self-criticisms coming up
about oh i was distracted i'm sleepy
it's not about me this cultivation it's a gift how can i
serve this is a gift of service showing up as best as possible in this
moment and letting go of the rest
showing up as well as we can as a gift
the gift of goodness
and letting go of the rest
may all beings be happy
may all beings be free
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
i will change the settings now
and you are welcome to [Music]
erase your zoom hand if you like to share you can uh type in chat if it's
privately to me i won't say your name if it's publicly i'll read your name
and um yeah i would love to hear how this was
for you richard please
you could hear me yeah um i was recalling
the things i have been doing for other people today i did some
substantial good deeds but but i've also done things for myself i mean i listened
to a dharma talk i read a chapter in a very good book
i practice my my scales or whatever and and i really don't personally
see much difference there great beautiful that's it perfect
great because when you're talking about that i'm not hearing the self-criticism the
self-involvement it's more of a oh it's kind of it's it's the the things you're doing for your self
isn't so much it's just doing the scales it's just you know music is a gift or reading there's all
these beautiful it's as if you're cultivating yourself as this gift so of course i i don't see any
difference either it and it's really the attitude it's the way of seeing
that makes it makes it so so yeah beautiful we're on the same page
thank you yeah thanks richard that's lovely that's that's just lovely
bill please uh hello hi all right i just want to say
that i find this this theme very compelling um i'm not
sure if i can express this right but this is this is ties into my motives
for for doing meta in a really strong way and one hoping that we can do more of it
in the future so anyway that's all i want to say
oh that's beautiful thank you bill thank you so much for sharing this i'm so glad to hear that this is
compelling to you there's there's something compelling there's something that speaks to you
and um and i wonder if it's possible to say maybe just one or two more words
bill if it's possible if not it's okay but how do you find it compelling i would love
to hear more um it speaks to the better angels of my
nature how about that beautiful beautifully put yeah thanks for adding that that's
lovely just hearing that my heart is uplifted my heart
you know i resonate i completely resonate with what you're sharing like yes this this works for me so so
yes i'll try to remember to bring it more into the future thank you for that and knowing that this resonates with you
this really speaks to the better angel of just something wakes
up in you we just like yes it's not about me it is and it isn't you know
there's just um beautiful thank you for bringing that into the space
yeah lovely thanks bill yeah forrest says thank you for teaching
us this technique at some point the switch suddenly happened and it really worked oh lovely
that sounds fantastic thank you for sharing that um
and i see charles lee's hand up please and the first if you want to
raise your hand and say a little more we'd love to hear more about from you yes charles lee
yes okay hi uh uh hi thank you the uh what stood out for me
was the invitation to sit up taller or straighter or more dignified
it kind of kind of was a was a was a signpost for me
but then i started kind of getting interested in the position of my my shoulders and my neck
and my chin and uh just ver just a very interested in embodied
uh place where i was you know making small movements uh uh raising my chin
realizing that that does make breathing a little bit easier but put some tension
on the back of the neck dropping the chin a little bit um which tends to balance
you know i think balance my head um and then um you know one of my intentions has has
really been to uh work on releasing releasing my shoulders
um i feel like i have 40 years of like clenched or maybe i probably didn't do that as a
baby so maybe 35 years of clenched
uh clenched shoulders to kind of work with but thank you thank you for the uh i think the
invitation to adjust posture um which uh which was uh which i liked
yeah thank you charlie and i'm really appreciating how you really took that invitation and
worked with it with a lot of awareness and mindfulness
of oh how the impact how these different minor adjustments are
having impact in both my physiology and in in my
in my perception so yeah very interesting
so tamara says greetings from campbell that was nice to release the focus from myself
thinking of how i can bring goodness to others that is a nice idea i'll be practicing this going forward
lovely thank you and forrest says i'm doing a self retreat right now so a little shy no problem for us you can
continue to keep your silence that's great i'm delighted for you that you're doing
a self-retreat yay so great
so dear ones let's um practice in community how can we serve
each other in small groups is it possible for us to show up both for ourselves and for each other
for these beautiful beings who are practicing with us can we just show up in silence with them
maybe we don't even have to talk in the if our turn comes in the small triad and say you know i'm just
here supporting you and and offering my presence now what if we
just show up like that today if you don't feel like talking and that's okay people understand they'll support you uh you know
we don't have to say anything or you can share as little or as much as you like about your practice
let's show up with that spirit today in the small groups
maybe a little more silent it was just showing up and see what happens so and of course you can speak as you
wish we'll start with 15 seconds of silence uh in the breakout rooms 50 seconds of
sorry 15 seconds of silent meta for each other in the uh breakout rooms and
uh here we go i've created the rooms and i'm opening them now okay here you
go enjoy welcome back everyone
and uh we have a couple of minutes for any reflection especially if you haven't
spoken for a while uh would like to make space for those who usually pull back
first so what did you just discover
especially in group practice
making space for especially those who don't speak
often would love to hear what you discovered what worked what was
challenging what didn't work complaints oh welcome
okay all right so
given that it's 6 59 let's let's close we had a lot of lovely
reflections before we went into groups so we're close together thank you all thank
you so much thank you all for showing up
it's both about us and it's above and beyond us we should show up and cultivate and
do this practice as a gift as a gift
as a gift of us being alive and breathing in this form in this universe may all beings be happy may all beings
be free
thank you