okay great so hello everyone hello and welcome
warm welcome to happy hour so so for today's practice at happy hour
um i would like to invite us into a practice of
appreciative perception appreciative perception and
we'll explore that more appreciative perception there would be some meta in there some
some loving kindness some would detail vicarious joy and some gratitude practice and the
inspiration for this practice uh this this evening morning afternoon whatever
the time zone might be this moment in time the inspiration comes from a a quote
by rilke that i will share with you it's a quote by rilka so so rilker writes
if your daily life seems poor do not blame it blame yourself
tell yourself that you are not poet enough to call forth its riches
for the creator there is no poverty and no poor indifferent place
ah that's quite profound so i'll read it again and maybe i'll say
one thing before i read it again so the idea of mutation is sometimes we go through our lives like oh
ho ho hum ho-hum hum drum um and our life
seems poor our life seems poor and what the invitation is
as as he's inviting us that it's not so much that not
to blame our lives but maybe it's our way of seeing of seeing or actually our way of
not seeing it's our perception it's our lack of perception
to the riches that are in our life to the diversity to the beauty to the grace
to the opportunities to so much that there is in our lives so it's really the
the poverty of our perception so what he's inviting is what i like to call a poetry
of perception we can use the word gratitude meta all of that but let's make it
poetic tonight let's mix it up a little bit so the poetry of perception
now i'd like to read the the quote one more time with that appreciation so
he says if your daily life seems poor do not blame it
blame yourself tell yourself that you are not poet enough to call
forth its riches for to the creator there is no poverty
and no poor and different place so so
again you know the the uh buddhist language probably doesn't have
blame yourself so those parts will work you know kind of like we'll take out but
just the idea of if the life seems poor ah it's about our perception
how is our perception perceiving the good perceiving the beauty perceiving
all the poetry all the music all the color all the riches that are available
in life so that would be an invitation this meta practice in this happy hour
uh to invite us to open up to that perception if our life feels poor even if it
doesn't feel poor let's bring in the sense of appreciation
that the um poetry of perception perception to perceiving what is good
inclining the mind to what is beautiful what is wholesome inside
and outside so all right that's enough framing let's do it ah so
i'd like to invite you to get into your meditation posture shifting
moving
if you need to lie down that's fine see what your body needs in this moment
need to move to a cushion or a chair sit up straighter
as always we'll start by start by about 10 minutes of settling
with the breath in the body
landing
greeting
creating this body that's showing up as best as it is able to in this moment
and greeting the heart
the emotions our hearts showing up as well as it's
able to show up in this moment whether it's light or heavy
eating greeting
this moment like this you are welcome heart please feel safe
it's all okay however you're showing up
and welcoming our mind our mind heart however it's showing up in this moment
bright a little tired weary excited however
a little distracted previously with preoccupations
welcoming all of ourselves welcoming
so welcome warm welcome to ourselves to set the tone for this
practice no part left out
embracing and welcoming all
letting the body inviting the body to relax
it doesn't have to do anything
inviting it not to do anything the breath itself moves in and out by itself the
breath is breathed by itself
not needing to make it into a project just allow it to move as it has been
moving breathing you being breathed for all this time
without any extra effort from your part thank you very much let
it be let the breath be natural
and see if the breath may be received
in the abdomen not from the control tower of the head
but sensed felt intimately
being breathed in the abdomen inviting all the muscles
to soften to soften and let go with each out breath
and if thoughts are arising it's okay see them notice them
[Music] with friendliness see if you can release
them in this moment not throw them away
like a rock but release them like a helium balloon gently kindly
see them float and let let the awareness
cradle the breath in the belly
what if every breath was appreciated
every breath in breath and that breath
what if every breath was received with friendliness
what if every thought was received with
friendliness
and let go with friendliness
what if every judgment if any arising
it was received as if it was directed to your best friend
best friend your twin being yourself
shifting the perception from me mine
i am this i am bad i am unworthy i am great
just a little bit of space
seeing yourself from a friendly perspective
from the outside could be either your
your best friend's perspective or maybe your best friend is the buddha the buddha's perspective unconditionally
loving unconditionally kind
be your best friend the buddha hears the judgmental thoughts
the acrimony within and smiles and knowing loving smile
holding you with care
your best friend buddha and you can use any other archetype loving archetype
who stands for unconditional love next to you could be
kuan yin buddha jesus being of light
or even a loving family member next to you they feel your breath maybe
they know you so well this being this archetype i'm just gonna use the
buddha as you feel free to
invoke anyone they hear your thoughts
they hold you with care and compassion they see how you berate yourself
they chuckle with humor with love with care
it's just sitting next to them you feel their love you feel their care
not because you have to do anything to deserve it or earn it it's just available
it's just available because you're human being and life is hard enough as a human being
we each have our own challenges every single one of us
whatever my unique challenges are in
their particularities as i struggle
as i suffer
this buddha sitting next to me understands understands completely
appreciates respects loves
me regardless or because of with all
together with all the challenges
with compassion complete compassion acceptance and love
it's hard enough being human it's hard being human
it's not for the faint of heart
the buddha understands he understands the human condition
if he completely understands it
he has boundless compassion for all of humanity
every human
i am no exception just like everyone
else
maybe even putting the challenges on the lap of the buddha
ah letting the hand hold it with you
and he's patient he listens
you feel safe in his presence
unconditional love and acceptance
is available
my
and now this compassionate knee next to
you
now they invite you to see a gift in your life
and they look at it with you appreciating it with you this gift in your life
perceiving it with you they see it you see it you see through
their eyes they see through your eyes
what is one blessing
yet they see they see in your life they pointed out
in this moment
letting yourself cherish see the goodness
savor this blessing
and the compassion happiness for you
they're happy for you glad for you embrace you in joy
so happy you have this blessing in your life
if you find your mind going to the future i might lose this bring the mind back invite your
perception to this moment right here you can choose to be right here right
now choosing the poetry of your perception
to relish
with the support of the compassionate being next to you
right here right now sitting breathed
this moment of aliveness
the brightness the goodness right here
and now the compassionate being next to you
sees another blessing in your life they celebrate for you with you
you see how happy they are for you
letting yourself relax into it
both of you savoring this good fortune
and one last time now this time you
bring something up some goodness some gift blessing in your
life and put it on the lap of this compassionate being
and they feel so happy in your happiness and your good fortune
feel free to continue with this borrowed perception
the perception of the compassionate being next to you
whether there are challenges that you put on their lap they give you
unconditional love and compassion where they feel happy for your good
fortune and happiness
awakening your own appreciation and happiness
feeling receiving complete unconditional love and support
feel free to be creative maybe maybe seeing yourself
hugged by this compassionate being a completely loving embrace
you're doing your best
they think you're doing your best
it's okay
held in a loving
embrace
and for the last moments of this practice that whatever came up or didn't come up
during this practice period to also be held
in the loving gaze of the compassionate being
no judgment just appreciation that you showed up and
you did your best
thank you all for your practice
so so we have some time or reflections for questions
you're welcome to raise your zoom hand
or type in chat as to what you noticed what
came up for you what was easy what was challenging what was
what you discovered in your practice and the invitation to share with the
sangha as a gift as a gift the gift of practice we give supports everyone
questions comments reflections especially if you haven't spoken for a
while in sangha
and just to as i'm as i invite you to feel free to raise
your hand i'll say a couple more words with the theme of perception there's so
many different ways that we can play with our perception in this way the perception of the
compassionate being next to us the buddha
because it is available so we can have this playing with this perception for poetry
of perception to turn our attention with kindness with love both to
ourselves and also to see the good in our lives to see the good
as ryoka said if your life if your daily life seems poor do not
blame it so dawn please
hello everyone nikki welcome back great to have you with us thank you well
thank you and um i i had a hard time uh imagining this compassionate being
and [Music] and so i struggled with that and so i
didn't i just sort of let it go at some point and just sort of focused uh on the breath or
the sensations in the body sort of a body scan and the the compassion being
was very vague towards the end it may be a ghost-like thing maybe but
it was it was tough yeah yeah yeah thanks for sharing that i really appreciate it
and i also really appreciate don that you hung in there with you know with the body and and
and um with the body scan with the breath which is great it's always a
great anchor to go to to be in body to be with the body and the breath and
and also the at the end it seems like the compassion the image may be kind of hanging out with it became a
little perhaps or it was there so so let me ask you a question if it's okay um
what what felt what felt like the crux of the challenge of the
kind was it the conjuring up was it power of imaginations or was it like oh
they're not compassionate enough if you could put in your own words i wonder yeah trying to just trying to imagine
such a being it's it's it's a foreign concept in my life it's very icy just trying to imagine
that it's like wow what is that got it okay okay that's helpful that's very helpful
for me too okay so so um so
so is there so is there any um let's see so um yeah what would a compassionate
image be like so so are there uh and this is both for you and for everyone who might have had
challenge with this or will have challenge with this you know is there living being
you know anyone that you kind of identify or think of someone who's just a like a kind loving
being is is there one that is there someone you identify with again could be either living being
or or archetype for you that's like wow this person represents love and if is there one is it okay for
you to say it out loud if not that's okay too uh yeah there's somebody that helped me
when i was a teenager and um and so i often think of him fantastic yay so
so if you think of that person so is it easier to conjure that person up
as someone who's next to you yes i see you're you're not you can be unmuted yeah so
so instead of the compassion that they so that person can be your compassionate image so that that would be workable
don yes what's that yeah great tastic so
great thanks for bringing that up because he could be a living person someone from your past
an archetype someone from history it could be anyone so great i'm glad
yay so you can practice in that way on your own see great
thank you for bringing that up don you're and
just as i appreciate the reminder that we need not judge or practice no matter the outcome
even a good one yes yes i appreciate that exactly we're just planting seeds we're
planting seeds or planting seeds who are we to judge our practice it's it's more profound
than even we can understand it to be we don't want to limit our practice to our
limited mind and judge it good bad a star so great the other reflections we
have maybe time for one more reflection before we
transition hey nikki hey enough so
um i thought i'd share a story with the sangha that i think would support um the
theme that you introduced today a friend of mine used to volunteer with mother teresa and he told me a story of
a man who had donated a hospital to her and at the end of the tour
who who basically asked for a photo with mother teresa in front of the hospital
and this photo ended up being uh 15 minutes under the hot indian sun of him
trying to pose mother teresa for the perfect photo for him and and at the end of it my friend who
was observing all this went up to mother teresa as the man left and said hey you know i thought that was
a bit rude um why did you agree to take this photo with this man and she turned to him and said poverty
comes in many forms [Music]
beautiful thank you enough
thank you for sharing that yeah yeah poverty comes in many forms yes
great great story thank you now and yes yeah and do you
know this quote from rilka in our chat let's see if i can do that
doesn't can i grab here we go those of you here we go speaking of
poverty yes poverty comes in many different forms
so dear ones let's transition let's transition for those who are able
to stay uh if you have to go it's understandable
but if you're afraid to to be in small groups please stay if you if you have work to do family to
take care of it's okay but if you're afraid please stay it's really lovely this is a
very friendly sangha and there's just such beauty in the practice that can arise
from from sharing so so the invitation for tonight as we get
in small groups is again to start with 30 seconds of silent meta
for each other and receiving it from others
and then after the 30 seconds you are well you're invited to speak from
your practice from your personal experience how this practice was for you what
worked what didn't just sharing sharing with the sangha and the sangha holding with
with care with compassion and you can share as little
much as you wish so um so with that making the groups
now and you can start with your with your uh meta
with your silent meta for the community
and i'm opening the groups now here we go
okay everyone welcome back so we've got a couple minutes for
reflections nicholas please that that hand shot right up tell me what's up enough of others in my
group it's it's anonymous um they came up that the the person that came up for them
was brought grief because they had passed or they were in poor health and so i thought that might be something
for a lot of people that would be helpful to discuss it's like whether to bring that person in in this case or how to
cope with grief also to work with that that's a good point and um
yeah and you know this practice is is intended to support the perception
through a compassionate being and not to bring up grief so if if this particular being is bringing up grief
then it's skillful to bow to them love them thank them and invite another
compassionate being until a day when this being coming up
doesn't bring up um doesn't bring up uh grief from i'll
share with you for example a lot of times a person who comes up is my mom for me who passed away three years ago
and i love her dearly and i still miss her and there is no grief there is just a sense of love that complete love
engulfing so until that can happen it is skillful to to use a different compassionate
image yeah thanks nicholas thanks for bringing that up fred please
um well i i've i've been um
nest in grief the last few months as my wife has died a couple of months ago and um
and that's the that's has been the state of things for me for these last few months but i as i
uh the person who came up for me was and was my wife um
in a way that was not grief at all but just the
um seeing the person i i have loved so much for so
long um in a in a beautiful edition and
i wasn't trying to conjure her up but she's i mean she's on my mind all the time but
um she she stepped in in a way that i hadn't experienced in the last
couple of months and and i'll go back to grieving her you know since we're done but she's uh it was
it was uh it was nice just to have that the visit from her in that way
and surprising thank you fred thank you so much for sharing
i'm allowing myself to feel the grace and the beauty of that and the smile on your face that just
flashed for a moment at the end just just the brightness of of your love for
her and her love for you that the opening to that to just be held with
with love to love and be be loved for a moment going back to
grief yes hello grief i'm going to come back to you and and for that gift thank you so much for
sharing that fred thank you [Music]
so dear ones thank you so much for your wholehearted practice
and for sharing of yourself
may all of you me all of us may all beings be happy
and free may all beings be happy may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you for showing up and for your practice