so hello and welcome to happy hour a warm welcome wherever you are in the
world so as we've been working our way through
the different categories as well as a different brahma viharas
just to give sense of context and again if this is your first time at happy hour no problem
whatever you need to know will be shared with you explained to you um so
it's all good and i still want to give the context just for those who've been coming regularly
just kind of get the sense of where we are so with the four brahma viharas practices of the heart we start with metta
loving kindness we worked through the categories all the categories with that and then we moved to the second
brahmavir heavenly abode practice which is compassion then we went through all the concentric
circles through that starting with um our easy person ourselves etc that
are moving to all beings then we switch to mudita empathetic joy
and we've been pla playing around with different categories in empathetic joy and we
stayed with empathetic joy for for a good long while uh which was fun
awakening joy and um and um the the fourth brahma vihara is
equinemedi opeka and sometimes we think of upeka as oh
very cool detached
but that's actually the near enemy of equanimity that's not equanimity equanimity is in
the same family as loving kindness and vicarious joy and compassion so
that should give us a signal oh equanimity has warmth to it has care to it it's not
like oh i'm just equanimous i don't care [Music]
but it's a sense of equipoise holding holding whatever
is arising challenges goodness holding it all holding it all
with balance with care not diving into it not overwhelmed not into
it diving into and not pulling away not turning away from it
equipoise equanimity stays with whatever is arising
whether it's joy so that it doesn't become exuberance there's a sense of balance
or with compassion so that it doesn't become empathic distress pain on top of some
our own pain or someone else's pain equipoise stays balanced so it's a it's a practice
in and of itself as we will practice tonight and
it's also it's the platform it's the stability
you if you think if you consider for example a buddha image or with a statue or a
statue of kuan yin compassionate image they're always on a platform
of stability so if you think of yourself as this ah embodiment here let's start
feel yourself as an embodiment of goodness compassion care
you sit on a platform a stable platform one that's not wobbly
one that's stable and supports you and that platform of stability
that foundation however the image works for you is one of
equanimity it allows you to engage with all the other brahma-viharas from a place of
balance as well as relate to anything in the world from a place of balance
so i like to sing the praises of equanimity because we've been bringing equanimity
in without really advertising it so much into all of our practices
so far with all the other brahmavirus and another thing to say equanimity is the
crown jewel of buddhist practice it's really the crown jewel
so it's not detached at all it cares it's engaged with the world
it's it's a part of the family of the heavenly abodes together with as i mentioned with meta
and compassion and and vicarious joy and it supports them all and it supports
us to have a stable expanse of heart not to be um
washed over or or um or caught up and and if we do get caught
up or washed over oh being able to stand up again so praise of in praise of equanimity
practice so i hope you're excited by now to practice equanimity formally
together so so the place we start this equanimity practice
traditionally is where it's easiest and it is said the easiest
category is the neutral person makes sense right neutral person
there is kind of a balance you you it's not your difficult person so you don't have antipathy towards them
it's not your dear person so you don't love them it's like oh there's some neutrality right you can
both feel their pain and their happiness but their senses through neutrality so
traditionally it is said this is the easiest place to start it may not be the easiest place for us
to give but let's start there okay let's let's see canonical teachings work for us in terms of story starting
where it's easy so so
let's start i think that's all i want to say let's dive into it um
yeah oh i guess i'll say one last thing the near enemy of it as i mentioned is aloofness this detachment is kind of
like oh i don't care it's all okay um and of course the far enemy the opposite
is when you get really entangled like uh or either you get really jump into it
you get entangled you get attached or you completely turn away um so aloof
is still cool so anyway you'll you'll discover the far and near enemies for yourselves
because they'll they might come up they probably will it's part of learning uh this practice it's not that
we completely avoid these ends it's just that they will come up we recognize them and we learn how to
relate to them and ourselves all right now let's jump in
okay let's blend ah
in our bodies let's land
ah our bodies with our breath
feeling [Music] our stability on the earth
this body connected through our feet through our legs our
sit bones whether you're sitting on a chair or a cushion
feeling this body connected to the floor to the cushion to the earth
sense of stability landing
ah relaxing letting go of
any tension the muscles in the face are holding
let the forehead be soft the jaw
muscles of the face from the inside
relaxing the neck and the shoulders
letting them drop
letting your chest soften your heart
feel safe
lowering the center of gravity of your attention from your head where the thoughts reside often we
associate our heads with our thoughts bringing
down [Music] center of gravity of attention to chest
feeling the breath in center of the chest heart center
then moving further down attention down down down the belly
and into the sit bones
to the legs the feet letting your attention hover hover in
the lower part of your body
putting your whole trunk chest and abdomen relax
your groin area
your sit bones in your legs dropping dropping their weight onto the
earth drop
as if an elevator goes down down down down
the weight shifting down down down down
if ever you notice your top heavy in the head with thoughts
push the ground floor button on your elevator of attention
traveling down down down down
it's okay to push this button many times throughout
if you feel it's helpful and needed it's okay
you can even push this ground floor button on the elevator of tension in every out
breath to settle in more see what it feels like
experiment
now i would like to invite you
to bring to mind someone who
is somewhat of a neutral person for you
you don't have much history with them maybe a neighbor a delivery person
someone who works at a store where you shop someone you don't know very well
you've seen them they're a human being they've made an impression
but you don't know them much as a stand-in for all of humanity
bringing this person this person to mind
for the purpose of this practice as as clearly as possible
what they look like maybe what they sound like
be with what you've picked up from their mannerism from the little interaction you've had
with them
and consider that just like you
just like you just like me
this human being wants to be happy
just as i don't want to suffer
they don't want to suffer
just as i have a complex inner life with inner dialogue
concerns worries fears hopes dreams disappointments
people i care about challenges in life
they too just like me
they have a very complex inner life that's compelling to them
that's as compelling complicated as mine
and just like me they care about
others and they're also object of affection
of others they're a child of someone
or a parent someone a sibling a friend a partner
they have loves things they love to do things that bring them joy who knows
maybe even your favorite food favorite flavor of ice cream is the same
imagine them enjoying what you love to to eat
and now [Music] imagine that this being this person
is experiencing challenges in their life right now
you may not know what they are as you don't know them and it's okay to use your imagination
perhaps you want to relate to something you're experiencing right now
that's challenging for you something very common these days with
the pandemic could be a sense of isolation or loneliness perhaps
or could be something else that's more present your life can you imagine
they have the same challenge too as a way in is a way to relate it's okay to use our
imagination to relate
seeing them working with this
or feeling or feeling challenged in the same way
and now from a place of stability
of the body of the mind feeling your body feeling your feet on the ground
feeling your sit bones on the cushion [Music] your hands touching each other your lap
feeling your body stable breathing
as if this body is sitting on as if this body is
the stable foundation of stability that grounds you
so that you don't get knocked over it grounds you
from this place of stability and also holding in mind in your heart
this person this human being relating
feeling this challenge they feel this shared challenge
but focusing on theirs
how they're suffering through it
allowing your self to feel a sense of balance and equanimity
not turning away with coldness from their challenge but feeling present as if you were
holding present caring space for them
the feeling of equanimity is present not turning away caring
but not entangled and not turning away holding space
being present with care for them to be
exactly as they are
but holding caring presence i'll offer a
few phrases of equanimity that might support this practice
things are as they are right now
things are as they are right now each breath can silence through your
sight or
it is what it is it is what it is
or may you be with peace
with the comings of goings of things
may you have peace with the comings and goings of things
continuing to stay connected and attached to your care
as if you're giving a lot of space holding with a lot of space
i wish you well and i know that your happiness
or unhappiness
is dependent on your actions and not my wishes for you
or the classic equanimity phrase
all beings our air are heir to their own
factions
their happiness or unhappiness depend on them
and not my wishes
keep your connection with this person the sense of care the sense of spaciousness
see which of these phrases might connect for you better you don't have to use them all
experiment and see in this practice today which one works
best
whether i whether or not i like it
things unfold
lawfully
events unfold according
to universal laws
or all beings have their own journey according to their karma
or no matter how i might wish things to be different
things are as they are right now
checking in if there's a sense of stability connection and care for this person
allowing a lot of space for the unfolding
i care for you but i can't control your happiness and unhappiness
whether or not i understand it
things are unfolding according to a lawful nature
and for the last moment of this practice may i be at peace
and ease for whatever arose or did not arise during this practice
were there challenges arose distractions emotions that were difficult
joyous may i have peace and ease with the comings and goings that
happened during this practice period
may i accept with equanimity and peace
may all beings be at peace may all beings be free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so now we have started to dip our toes at happier to equanimity practice
and love to hear your questions reflections observations you're welcome
to raise your hand or type them in chat if you type them privately to me i won't
say your name if it's public i will say your name and of course you can raise your hand
and share and to say one thing that can happen with equanimity practice the sense of
calm stability the heart can feel really calm
with a sense of care there's a sense of warmth and care that's there but there's a sense of ah
as we if you were here last night and we did um
modita vicarious or empathetic joy or the past few nights you know there's a sense of joyous exuberance that can be
there and this can be ah connected and um and more stable anywhere lots of
different things can come up and uh we're finding our way together in
this practice so so love to hear from you
what did you notice bill says compared to metta equanimity
practice seems cold to me indifferent so i'm probably in one of
those near enemy things right
so maybe yes could be so here's so you said two different things so if
compared to mental equanimity practice seems cold i wouldn't say cold it's cooler
it's a little cooler it's not as warm and yet if it feels indifferent then you
probably are hanging out in a near enemy so notice where you are and it's okay we explore our
relationship here and see if there can be more connection and more care and maybe with the other
beings it could be it could be easier emily says i noticed
that it was a little hard for me to concentrate compared to mindfulness practice simply following the breath
switching between listening to different phrases and the guidance and choosing phrases to use in my own mind felt a
little complicated sometimes yes yeah i was offering this is the first night we're exploring there are a lot of
phrases because some phrases work some phrases don't and as we go through through the week you would have had you
choose the phrases that work for you and the ones that connect and also one thing that i will do i
think that will make it more helpful for the next sessions i will um have the the list of phrases shared in
the google groups so if you're not on google groups please join
because all the phrases will be shared with you there so you can read over them and see which ones work
for you and i might offer fewer options uh next week just one or
two and then i trust that you've already looked over and you're experimenting so that's one thus so thank you emily
thanks for that this can happen of course this is a little intellectual but i
realized today that i don't think of equanimity as being oriented towards specific people the other brahmavihara is yes but i
think of economy as just being a better relationship to experience not necessarily ben so there are
different kinds of equanimity practice and there are 10 different kinds of equanimity in buddhism
so this practice of equanimity specifically that we're practicing is related to a person
this is how it's practiced as part of the other brahma viharas there are other equanimities as part of the seven
factors of awakening etc etc that are related relate to experience in
general but not this one what else let's see jerry says it was
helpful to hear that in this neutral person that they have an inner life and this helps me
feel more connected to them great thank you and emily says plus one to what jerry wrote a cool new experience
great nice thank you both for that and a direct message to me really helped me
with a former spouse i of which there was tension this week this was
so needed to me letting go of being responsible for their happiness it felt freeing and compassionate and
released thank you oh thank you so much for that i'm so glad this connected for you
great this is a really powerful practice and we're going to continue to engage with it with
other categories and 10 different kinds wow okay i guess
i have some educating myself to do yes ben yes indeed
[Laughter] uh humility beginner's mind is
good in at every stage of practice and susan has their hand up so
susan please hey thanks um hi everybody um
i think this is kind of yeah this is totally part of it i am recalling when i used to go to a
lot of aaa meetings um and i have this experience like
somebody would come in with new who would have a lot of problems obviously and um
when they would be distressed i would have this wave of faith in them and that's what
i kind of form my feelings around equanimity i don't know if that makes sense so
it would be that they would be okay that everything was going to work out fine um that it of cour you know it was both
and that they were having really difficult times but that they were also
yeah covering and so yeah i see what you're saying i appreciate you bringing that in susan so
so i would say there is a similarity here and a slight difference and i want to point that out the new ones here
tease it out so the um the sense this beautiful sense
that you're bringing in is that you know they're having trouble right now but they're going to be okay there's a sense there's a trust
there so now if we shift that if we shift that to actually at the awakened mind
perspective that actually in the big picture they are okay
this is what this is what's happening this is what needs to be happening according to a lawful nature so that's
even a bigger a bigger okayness it's a bigger trust so i'm building on what you said
it's not so much trust that in the future they will be okay but it's like this is okay this is part of
being human there's a bigger picture whether or not i know it i'm aware of it whether or not i
understand it um it this is okay so there's a sense of
trust so thank you so much for bringing that up really really uh i appreciate that so
and a couple of quick comments uh on uh youtube had difficulty imagining
someone having difficult time because i think that everyone around me is doing so much better than i am
ah that is so interest in an interesting perspective because it
is so not true everybody has challenges in their lives every single person it's
it's a mark of existence dukkha is a mark of existence
and let's see it was difficult for me to follow some instructions because i don't speak
english but spanish but i was able to connect oh that's sweet thank you for for that reflection uh
gero and the previous one was robin thank you so much for both of those reflections so um i'm glad that you were able to
connect even if not with all the words and also rob and i i invite
feeling into this um misconception that everybody else is
okay know that suffering is the common bond
we may not know what people are experiencing but we can be sure they're having difficulty it's a part of
being human there's so much more i can say about that but time is running out and there are more
questions but we're going to be doing this practice all of next week so let's um i want to make
time for practice meeting in groups and hold your questions for uh
for later so i'm going to create the breakout group so the invitation is to start with um 30 seconds of meta
for each other just quiet 30 seconds of meta wishing each other well and then you can
share how this practice was what you discovered uh tonight with this new practice which is
different and there's no right or wrong you know that you're not trying to impress each other but just to support each other and
share each other's practice so here we go i'm opening the rooms now
okay enjoy welcome back everyone
so we have maybe a minute for for one reflection if you like to share what
did you discover both in your practice and sharing with others
yes jerry i see you um um
so uh i'm amazed at the comments that people make in the group that are so uh helpful in terms of
uh just trying to want to say things that actually hit the mark
about what you were trying to do so it's an amazing supportive group so that's what i want to say
great thank you yeah it buoys my heart to hear how supportive
sharing this practice this intensive practice that you do in the group is for for you so thanks
for reporting back in the other quick report back
see i don't see any other hands or anything typed
um lisa is very grateful for this offering thank you thank you emily for showing up
and for supporting yourself and everyone else this is beautiful and before we went into groups been
asked do you have a reference for the ten types yes in the path of purification there
are ten different types of equanimity listed and the teaching is is in there so dear ones
let's um let's close let's close our our evening our morning or
afternoon for those in asia together thank you all for showing up for practicing
for your own benefit and benefit of all those whose lives you touch
may all beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music] thank you