so hello everyone and welcome
and
one of the ways that the buddha talks about realization or about the depths of possibility in
this practice is that it's something to be known and experienced
through the body and the emphasis on embodiment or the body
is is uh quite strong in these early teachings of buddhism
and so we begin with our body and taking a assuming a
bodily posture that might support bodily awareness
the process of coming maybe home to your body or settling into your
physical experience here and now
i think of our physical experience as adding the full dimension that dimensionality
to our life that we live in our thoughts only it's like living in
two dimensions and with the body it becomes three dimensions maybe something like that
so assuming the meditation posture that you for this period of time
and gently closing your eyes
and attuning yourself to your body kind of like as
from the inside out not from your mind so much as thinking
about it but feeling and sensing and there can be an intimacy
in sensing and feeling our bodily
experience and maybe this allowing ourselves to feel and sense the body it's a little bit
like someone putting a gentle hand on your shoulder reassuring hand or a loving hand
that's something reassuring and of making that connection
with our body touching it and being touched
and then from the depths of your body whatever that means deep inside
gently arising from that depth
deep full inhale
arising from the depths stretching outwards into the ribcage the shoulders
kind of stretching and expanding of the torso
and as you exhale a settling
a calming a returning to the depths within
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and to relax your body on the exhale
relaxing the face
softening the shoulders
softening the belly
and then settling in now
to the body's experience of breathing
as if in this body of yours you will find the path of meditation
you will find the path for where to place your
attention where awareness can be awakened
in the body breathing mindfully
feeling the vitality
the aliveness of the physical body the hum of
the body's aliveness
and to relax and settle more deeply into
an embodiment of the body here body is always in the present
moment here in this body gently
quietly feeling the embodiment of the body
breathing
just here body breathing
letting go of your thoughts maybe sometimes letting go of
whatever you're thinking every time you exhale
letting go of thoughts and letting go into the body
breathing in and breathing out
letting go of your thoughts unless navigating from your mind
but more navigating meditation through your body
awakening capacity to be present with your body
you
again
and as we come to the end of the sitting
even more we are connected to our body the more likely we are to be close to
the source of love within
and what would it be like to let yourself become quiet and still so that
the place of tender care and love and kindness
is something that you can feel more connected to
allowing something to settle and let go and feel
the place within
where there can be a warm regard for others
where there can be a generosity of heart
a willingness and capacity to appreciate other beings
and from this place perhaps
to intentionally conclude your meditation
with a wish for the welfare and happiness of others
may it be that others can be happy
may it be that others can feel safe
may it be that others can experience peace
no a peaceful life
and may it be that others could wake up to freedom
to experience the heart free and unknown unfettered
and may the benefit and goodness of this meditation this day may those benefits
be shared widely to the welfare and happiness of all
beings may all beings be happy and free
you
so this uh sunday talk could be seen as a continuation of the
last three weeks of early morning talks on greed hatred and
delusion and now this is a theme that comes up repeatedly for the buddha
and in some ways it's important because it's the goal of practice is to wake up be
experience the peace wake up to the absence of greed hate delusion to wake up to the presence of
the peace that's possible without it so what i want to do today is uh maybe a
little different than just usually on sundays i want to tell you a little bit about a discourse
uh ancient text that purports to talk about the teachings and
conversations the buddha had and it's uh the talk that um
it's a suta which is maybe one of my favorite maybe the top 10 if i had a
list like that of ones that i value and it's called the chunky sutum
and it's in the middle length discourses number 95
and and why i like it is one of many reasons but one of the reasons is
how it talks about truth it talks about protecting truth and who doesn't want to
protect truth and then discovering truth or awakening to truth
and finally uh the talks about the final arrival to truth so what is a final arrival a
complete coming into truth and
so i'm not going to tell you the full story of the text but the basic idea is that
uh the young very well-educated uh brahmana comes to
the buddha and asks a simple question he says that
the brahmanas in my tradition they claim that their scriptures
contain the only truth and no one else has the truth and what does the buddha think about
this instead of answering it directly the buddha says well do any of the
brahmanas in the present generation do they themselves say
i know and i see this truth or is it the truth that they've just
taken from the texts and they could believe it because they have faith in it because in the texts and the young man says well
no one says that they have seen it for themselves or known it for themselves
and the buddha says well what about their teachers and the teachers before them and back seven generations has anyone
said that they themselves have seen the truth or they themselves
have known the truth directly and he says no and the buddha says well basically then
he would indicate he's kind of a little bit dismissive than ever or there's not much you know value
in a statement this is only the only truth if for many generations no one's actually known it for themselves
so it's little bit challenging i suppose to the brahmana because they're back then their religion is
based on the ancient texts and they are taken on faith i guess
and so the buddha says well if you want to so the man asks the buddha well how do we protect the
truth and probably he asked the question because they thought they were protecting the truth by
protecting those texts protecting and meant memor there's no writing back then so memorizing them and
passing them down to generation to generation and the buddha says well you
protect the truth if you when you talk about what you think is
true like religiously true you indicate
on with a reason for why you take it to be true the basis for that statement
so if you take it on faith preface your your your conversation with i have it on
faith that this is true if you believe it's true because the tradition tells you so then say
based on the tradition i take this to be true if it's a matter of um
because it's in in your in your sacred text say uh because of my sacred text
i take it to be true and uh if it's because of your reasoning and
your logic say that and if it's just because you have some intuitive sense that this is true
say that i have some intuitive sense of uh of this is true so
it's kind of a very helpful thing for other people to know that if you make a truth claim on what
basis do you make it it's on faith it's on whatever
so the young man says okay but can't you discover truth for yourself
and the buddha says yes you can and so the man says how do i do that how does one do that
and this is the oh another wonderful part of the text is the buddha then describes a process
by which someone can discover the truth but the young man is not he's just
replying to the man's question how how does one discover the truth the buddha provides a means a
process and the buddha doesn't directly proselytize he doesn't really
directly say what's important for him what he the buddha's truth is what he has realized
he just informs the man of a process but indirectly the the buddha's goal
of their spiritual life is emphasized and it's kind of a slight of hand perhaps
or maybe you have to be really attentive to see that he's what he's doing here so i'll try to uh explain this
um that i see you trying to spell the text the chunky it's uh usually um uh see
a n k i that's the poly spelling c a n k i but it's pronounced uh chunky
like with ch and um so he discovers
so the so the buddha says so the buddha is going to describe the process of discovering the truth and so and this
is important from the buddhist teachings because the buddha really wants everyone to discover it for themselves and don't rely on texts to know what's
true but to really know for yourself in some direct way but it's a process for doing that and
so you have to realize that in the ancient world there were no books so you couldn't say well go to the
library and read up on it at the teachings but you if you want to hear and learn
spiritual teachings learn about a process to become discover the truth you have to go
find someone who would teach it to you and so the first criteria for this
process has to do with a relationship we have to a teacher
the teacher teaches and so the next part of the process is the relationship we have to teachings
and the final step of this steps of this process has to do with the practices we do what we engage in
so that we can discover the truth but these three areas are important the teacher the teachings and then the
practice so the buddha says that
first you want to find yourself a teacher
and to do so uh go find find the teachers in your area a little bit paraphrasing here and um
and investigate them uh investigate the teacher
and then he gives goes to great detail how are you supposed to check them out
but they all have to it has to do with checking out whether the teacher in the teacher there's a presence of any
greed and any hatred and any delusion
because of which they will uh twist the teachings they will kind of
not quite give real teachings or somehow influence the flavor the texture
of the teachings they give because they're infused with the teachers greed hatred and delusion
and you want to have a teacher who they're they're not going to have any greed and hatred and delusion
which influences what they say and so there's this wonderful instruction is check out the teacher
and so to really check out a teacher it takes time uh you know
don't rush headlong into a teacher and but really kind of tune in and pay attention and see how they live their
lives maybe and um and to see you know this are they free of any great hate and delusion
that's going to that's going to skew the way that they teach the simplicity or the clarity of
what they have to teach and and so if if you decide that they
have don't have that kind of greed hate and delusion then um pl have some confidence in that
teacher offer some have some faith some trust in that teacher that's then the teacher is worthy of
some degree of trust and trust enough so
the next step is go visit the teacher so in the ancient world again you couldn't read the teacher's books
watch them on youtube you had to go and go find a teacher so go visit the teacher it's important
to be in the presence especially that back then in the oral tradition
and offer respect to the teacher there's a long ancient tradition that
some modicum of respect prepares the listener to listen well it kind of clears a
certain certain degree of clouds or agitation
that kind of genuine respect or care is a kind of willingness to be open and
and give a kind of a willingness to listen well to what a teacher has to say
but remember this is after having really checked out the teacher and decided okay this person is
worthy of some respect and then listen to the teacher so listen to what
they have to say in the modern world we might say read the teachings carefully
you know listen read well take your time back then there was only listening there
was no libraries no books so the so the process with the teacher
is to investigate to have faith trust some degree
to visit to offer respect and then to really listen to the teacher
listen to the teachings from the teacher um then as you listen listen and
hear the teachings fully take them in as you hear them memorize the teachings
so that make again a lot of sense back in the ancient world because you didn't have a book to refer back to
and people didn't know how to write so they didn't take notes when the teacher was teaching and so you can go to the
library or something and check out a book to find out if you wanted to review and and read
again and think about what was being taught you had to memorize what was being taught
and people back then almost certainly had a much higher ability to memorize than we have today because that
was the medium for knowledge in a way that is not the case today
and then having memorized them or have them in writing or some way examine them reflect on them
think about them and uh so here again just like with a teacher you don't accept teachings you don't
accept a teacher blindly quickly but you really check it out there's a process of
checking it out thinking about it looking at it not automatically believing
the teacher or believing the teachings but really reflect on them examining them when one has examined and
thought about them deeply and if they really from your best
understanding seem to be good teachings then accept those teachings
enough to be willing to begin the process of practice so hear the teachings memorize the
teachings and reflect deeply on the teachings and
then some modicum of accepting them as something that
is accepted well enough now you can practice with them it's kind of like you've gotten the ingredients for the experiment and now
you have to run the experiment if you want to discover something so
then comes the practice and the practice is first by understanding the teachings by
having faith in the teacher this whole process is to have their spring up
arise out of yourself the desire to practice without some inspiration
some enthusiasm some feeling of yes i'm going to practice you know then
the experiment is not going to really going to work so we want to listen to teachings take them in until we
really feel like yes and it might be part of that yes to practice is comes from having checked out the
teacher wow if it's possible to live without great hatred and delusion
this is a worthwhile path this is good this is inspiring and so that inspires us to want to do it
for ourselves to discover how to do it so um then there's preparing oneself the
text says being fit to practice so preparing ourselves to practice
whatever that means getting ready for practicing or
getting established in practice and then once again the word examine
when we have a practicing meditation for example and gets quiet and settled and
really able to be in the present moment there is a non-discursive non-analytical way
of looking examining more and more deeply what is our experience what's really going on
in our direct experience and so here we give again this exam examine the teacher
you reflect on the teachings and now we're examining and looking deeply at our own experience
because that's where the discovery of truth is going to be and then a person continues practicing
and endeavors and makes more effort and you kind of really uh as as practice moves along there
comes a time when this becomes kind of like we give ourselves over to it
um give ourselves over to really see the experiment all the way through
and then at some point one realizes one has a realization
of ultimate truth with the body one realizes with the body
ultimate truth and i believe the experience with the body is being said to emphasize the direct
personal way in which we see and perceive and experience the
truth this is not from a book it's not ideas it's not it doesn't exactly belong to the mind of
analysis and and cognitive beliefs or even maybe
a certain kind of not even cognitive understanding in a certain way but uh first and foremost it's coming
it's so obvious that oh this is this this so you know if you
um are really hot and hot day and you go stand in a shade of a tree
that's what's cool you know you experience the coolness the truth of that
coolness with your body it's a really a felt sense experience and this uh
this kind of realization of the truth with the body directly is called discovering the truth
this young brahmana asks the buddha then is this the final arrival at truth is this the final
complete experience of truth and the buddha says no in order to
really arrive at it fully be centered in the truth then you want to do that process that he
described before over and over and over again i imagine
you don't have to keep doing the checking out the teacher at some point you have to check out the teaching so
much but to do the practice part of it over and over and over again
and uh and it's the repetition of basic practice and repetition of coming back into the
discovery of the truth discovering this truth over and over and over again that begins to expand and fill out and
develop this capacity of so we become the truth we arrive in truth in a full way
and in this uh teaching the buddha does not say what the truth is so the
young brahmana does not ask the buddha what do you teach and what do you teach about the truth
he's really asked first and foremost asks about his own religion and then he asks maybe to understand it
better his own religion he says how do i protect the truth how do i discover the truth how do i
finally final arrival that truth and the buddha just then
answers in a kind of a generic way perhaps or a vague way without specifying any particular teaching of
his own almost and but uh this is where there's a slight of
hand maybe or a keto move because um
what the buddha says at the beginning the very first step is check out the teacher to make sure
the teacher doesn't have great hatred and delusion well this is the goal of the buddha the
goal of the buddha is for people to come to a place where they're free of greed hate and delusion
and so by having this young man first and foremost check out you know be told this is what
you have to check out first um it does a number of things it means
that he's only going to study with people who have realized the absence of great hatred and delusion
and and because they've realized that they know the value of that maybe they have other all kinds of
non-buddhist ideas maybe believe in all kinds of things but for the buddha that's maybe secondary
what's really important what's primary is this freedom from clinging freedom from grasping that
the freedom from greed hit and delusion represents and also by uh telling a young man
to pay attention to check out the teacher in these states of greek hate and delusion it's actually a beginning of attuning
him to this possibility of being free of great hate and delusion and to really study someone else and
investigate someone else and really see the way that they are free of great hate and delusion that they have this amazing freedom from
these kind of powerful forces that are so big in our society um
it i imagine it's really inspiring inspires a possibility
and also i can't imagine that the the young man if he did this would
begin uh becoming having spent time studying greed hating delusion or the absence of
another person would start becoming more self-aware of uh one's own great hatred and delusion
uh seeing it more likely and seeing maybe the uh the unfortunate nature of it being there
and and the teacher is without it but i have it there might be kind of an inspiration
to maybe that's important not to have it to work through it
and so i believe that the buddha is kind of like one of his primary messages he kind of kind of in a kind of side
door gets through to this young brahman who's talking with him and so that by the time you get to the
full discovery of truth the full attainment of truth the idea that it involves the absence of
greed hate and delusion is not very far away because if you want to become what the teacher has attained
that also has to be an absence of greed hector and delusion and that is what the buddha was teaching
and and the idea of religious truths doctrines beliefs that are
maybe are not that important for the buddha unless they interfere with the
possibility of this radical freedom but this radical freedom perhaps
can it can exist without too much concern about what people believe if it's not
harmful if they believe all kinds of religious beliefs and ideas that come from
their tradition from faith from their logic whatever um may it be so or let it be that way
um provided that we discover how to live together on this planet
uh free of greed hatred and delusion so protecting the truth i think is a
generous thing to do if we tell other people the basis upon
what we know what we believe to be religiously true by faith by tradition from the texts from my
teacher or whatever and then then engage in a process of discovering
the truth for ourselves this is a great thing to do and
and and not only maybe we can't discover what that is
while we are ourselves still involved in greed hate and delusion because just like a teacher maybe skews
their understanding by the influence of great hatred and delusion so we would skew
our discovery of the truth by those forces as well and so to cleanse ourselves to learn to
to empty ourselves of these forces is possible and it's worthwhile
and it's one of the great instructions from the buddha to do so so
the chunky suta so thank you very much and
i look forward to being here again with you next sunday no i won't be here next sunday it's i'll be here in two weeks uh this
coming sunday um andrea fella is coming to speak she's my co-teacher here at imc
a wonderful teacher and and i feel like you're very happy that she's coming to continue
with these teachings while i'm away and you'll be in good hands and
and i look forward to seeing you in a couple of weeks thank you