so good day everyone hello and i'm happy to be here
uh i might be a little bit um not quite myself today i had
the covet booster shot yesterday and been going through chills and feeling
very tired and the moment i feel great and so maybe it'll stay that way but if i
begin to sag then that is why probably
so
the topic for today is some people have said as the crown jewels of buddhism
it is a list called usually called the seven factors of awakening
the word for factors can also mean limb and some occasionally you see uh seven
limbs of uh awakening and i like the study of limbs factor just seems like a you know
list a list but lim seems like a part of a whole it's like a uh you know a body
and and uh and it a little bit more associates it to me to our own body
our lived experience and the seven factors awakening are not abstractions but they are lived experiences
that maybe you can understand them to be
what happens when you get in the groove of meditation groove of mindfulness of the practice
that you know you maybe you're just learning to ride a bike and it's awkward and difficult and
but at some point you can jump on your bike and maybe you're going for a long distance and you get in the groove it just feels like you're just like
moving along just in a really wonderful way and or many other things we do once
we master them in the groove it's just delight to be absorbed and doing the activity
so these seven limbs of awakening are things that begin to arise when the hindrances abate
and the distractions abate and the attachments abate and and we get into the groove of
mindfulness so what i'd like to do for this sitting is a little bit of a guided tour or
guided meditation on the seven factors of awakening and perhaps that's a nice way of being
introduced to them or to be connected to them is uh if i'm able to kind
of point to the point to them or evoke them or
give you a sense in your own experience how they work now they are
so first i'll tell you what the seven are they are mindfulness
investigation usually next one is energy i'd like to
today call it strength and then joy
tranquility and concentration samadhi
and equanimity and we'll go through these again so we don't have to memorize them right now
so assuming a meditation posture
that you can
gently close your eyes
and it's a way of establishing yourself here kind of definitively here
taking a few long slow deep breaths three quarters full
big enough breath so that it becomes a predominant thing you're focusing on it takes some intentionality
long exhale so that it takes some attention to this to do it
and begins this turning from the distracted mind to being present
and maybe deep breaths and as you exhale
also to relax the body
sometimes the deep in breath allows for kind of a deeper even internal relaxation on the exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and with the orientation to gather yourself here
in this present moment putting aside your distracted thoughts
as you exhale relaxing the muscles of your face as if you're settling in
with your face to be here
face doesn't have to work or figure things out or reach forward be outward directed
the face can settle back on itself be at ease
on the exhale to soften the shoulders
let go relax
release the holding contraction of the shoulders when
from busyness and fear and
and on the exhale softening the belly
and with the softening of the belly also kind of a settling of your weight into your lower torso
and then to settle in now
on the experience of the body breathing
accompanying the body as it breathes with your attention
the first factor of awakening is mindfulness awareness
and you might say use the word here h-e-r-e
awareness is here nowhere else
here with awareness here with a little bit of clarity
present attentive to your experience
here and now breathing
letting your awareness be here with breathing
awareness accompanies breath is a companion for the body breathing
perhaps as you exhale to let go of your thoughts
so that the quieting absence of thinking
makes more room for awareness
to be here to be open to be clear
the second factor of investigation is investigation second vector of
awakening is investigation
it's not analysis or probing or but rather very simple
attunement to your experience that can be expressed through the word
what whatever you're aware of just say what
what is this and not answering it with words but
i'd rather let it register more fully as if you get closer to it or feel it
more fully maybe even a sensory awareness
that you receive so there's more clarity distinction of
what's here with the question what says if you get closer to the experience
putting a hand on a piece of wood and then
you can feel it more carefully
the hand of awareness goes on the breathing and there's more
richness and variety of sensations that you experience in breathing
the next factor of awakening is strength can you call upon a gentle strength
to so you inhabit in a strong way
the simplicity of being here and present
maybe a kind of inner strength in your body
not the same as muscular strength but maybe a kind of strength of
gentle determination yes here
engaged strength that supports awareness
the fourth factor of awakening is joy
the delight of being engaged fully in the experience
coursing in mindfulness in the present moment
appreciating the opportunity to be here
i associate joy with the word yes
yes to be with this experience yes to feeling the breath in the body
and maybe even you can make a small half smile
that makes it easier to enjoy
being present here with breathing
that next factor is tranquility
perhaps there's a way of continuing to relax and let things be calmer
the calming of your thinking mind
a deeper relaxation of the body
and whatever reference point you have for present moment tranquility
maybe that can be a magnet for awareness in the present moment
the next factor is samadhi
i think of an associate i associate this with the word steady
to steady oneself here and now
to steady oneself in the middle of our whole being
so all of us is here supporting present moment awareness
awareness that flows or radiates from all of our life
now here
steadying oneself on the breathing
and the last factor of awakening is equanimity
maybe can be associated with the word okay
not being in conflict with anything or troubled by anything just it's okay
so the mind is less reactive more balanced
to be here with the breathing in your body
strong centered
awareness not pushed around or caught up in
what is happening but staying balanced
equanimous non-reactive
it's okay
and then i'll name each of the seven factors of awakening
as you listen to them can you find a reference inside of
yourself for each through a memory or a place in your body or
some feeling of each and within and see them as a kind of strength
that support you to be balanced and attentive
grounded in the middle of all the difficulties of life
mindfulness
investigation
strength
joy
tranquility
concentration
equanimity
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
perhaps consider that each of these seven limbs of awakening
are a support for gazing upon the world kindly
compassionately they're a way of
being available
in a helpful way for others
supported by the seven limbs of awakening you're less likely to get caught up in
your reactivity and more likely to be present and see
clearly
respond to the world with something with something from a place of
wholesomeness goodness
made through this practice we strengthen a wholesome
caring way of being with the world certainly this world needs more people
who bring kindness and compassion and care friendliness
it may be that this practice we do does that for us
so that we intentionally consciously
are attentive to making this world a better place for others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so the topic is the seven factors of awakening the seven limbs of awakening
and as i said earlier i like the expression limbs limbs of awakening because
it connects it to our lived body you know it's something that's embodied in these seven
seven factors the word seems to just imply a list and um
and these are seven qualities or seven states of being that get activated in a very nice way
as we get into the groove into the flow of meditation practice it's kind of like the reward
of meditation when you're really kind of able to put aside distractions and really get focused on just being here in
the present moment steady continuous kind of in the flow of the of the
present in the
ancient texts they uh contrast them or pair it up with
uh the five hindrances and the five as being opposites that have a very
opposite effect on us and the task is to put the five hindrances to sleep or let
go of them and awaken the seven factors of awakening the five hindrances what we talked about
monday are said to be forces of um of uh
uh we forces that obscure wisdom
that obscure a clear vision of what's happening it uh kind of is blinding to our clarity
and our wisdom and our good understanding whereas the seven factors awakening are the opposite
they bring forth clarity with the clarity of vision clarity of
wisdom and um and i kind of aliveness and
the hindrances are kind of deadening in a certain way and so uh where practice is going from the world
of the being caught up in the hindrances to the world of coursing in the seven
factors of awakening and so uh as the practice proceeds
then at some point they wake up and then it's good to recognize them and and the
recognition of them is meant to kind of support them to grow even more and they're a little bit like a cheerleader
that kind of cheering you on this is really good you're on track so the way i presented these uh this
fourth foundation of mindfulness the first three exercises are progressive
coming to terms with letting go of settling down coarser to more refined or deeper
forms of attachment and preoccupation and so the practice is a lot to do is to
see the preoccupations the hindrances the attachments the the entanglements we have so we're no
longer in tango no longer caught in them but we begin waking up and become free of them
as that freedom begins to unfold and we're no longer caught in these things then these seven factors awakening are
what uh begin to show that you show up and it's a beautiful thing to practice
present moment awareness and really get into the groove of it and then feel the birth the arising of these
very healthy wholesome wonderful states
that are in some ways feel impersonal attachments and entanglements and
identifications and the hindrances have a kind of very strong stickiness that kind of
where we get caught up in our egoistic ideas our our sense of self and agency in certain
way but the seven factor awakening even though our practice is what brings them about
it feels they're definitely arising from within ourselves but they have this beautiful quality of having this
naturalness to them and almost like this is what happens when i get out of my way
and not be so focused on me myself and mine and it's a quite encouraging to feel
these healthy states bubbling up coursing through us
it's very encouraging it's very encouraging for appreciating kind of a positive
disposition towards life and what's possible it's um it's just a feeling of health
in fact as in the ancient world sometimes it was really clear the seven factors awakening were considered a kind
of medicine and when the buddha was sick he asked for example a monk to recite these seven
factors awakening maybe like a guided meditation in order to kind of say help arouse him or help heal him
from his sickness and sometimes the buddha went to see a sick monastic and he would recite the
seven factors awakening this is for people who know who are familiar with them who are coursing in
them into regular part of their lives so that when they're named they kind of come alive and a good energy comes up
and it's kind of considered a healing energy i've had them coursing through me and
the best language i had was was i felt like there was healing
fluid kind of coursing through all my veins and throughout my nerves and just the sense of healingness that
comes with the seven factors awakening is remarkable and so these are mindfulness
investigation energy or strength
joy tranquility concentration and equanimity
and sometimes they are presented as being progression as mindfulness gets stronger
then at some point we get the clarity that the investigation is we see more clearly what's here
as we see more clearly it's just easier to have evoked a kind of good sense of strength and energy and enthusiasm for
the practice and so we we engage more fully and it's like second nature to like oh yes let's do this
and then as we do that then joy arises at some point joy is felt great but uh
just when we're settled in the joy sometimes something settles can settle and relax and tranquility sets in
and the joy becomes more of a happiness than than joy and then with that kind of well-being
and tranquility that's the ideal conditions in which to for concentration to arise
it's hard to get concentrated if you do it from just the ordinary street state that you're walking around and
preoccupied and and i have the idea that you're supposed to have a laser focus and really work hard
at getting concentrated it's a lot easier if you if one prepares the ground for
concentration and the first five
factors awakening are part of this preparation that allows us to kind of get unified and stable and
rooted here and then um the uh and then there's equanimity
and um and uh equanimity can seem kind of boring or just uninteresting but it's a it's a
really uh pristine kind of like an emotional state it feels
so clean and good and peaceful and and um it's like one of the most uh
pinnacle of of like fantastic emotional states that you can feel that's equanimity um and um
and uh and here the mind is so balanced so non-reactive but with this beautiful sense of
cleanliness and clarity and openness and and um it's kind of it's a you know so
so the mind is not going to react to anything anymore it's just there and a feeling of strength and
and um so these seven factors of awakening uh can appear
in little hints of it at first and it's helpful to recognize it all right this is it this is it
and probably some of you have them arising in everyday life as well maybe some of you really some of the
ordinary activities of life that you really get focused and enjoy doing um you can recognize that in fact some
of the seven factors are present like even cooking to really get into cooking and let the
world drop away and and really have the sense of presence and uh and this
attentiveness of investigation where you you know really attending to uh the food and you know this
you know tracking it carefully and knowing how much more seasoning to put in or how long it needs
to cook or turn down the flames or all kinds of things and um and there can be a delight and
there can be a sense of joy and there can be everything gets kind of tranquil our
cares of the world fall away and it's a piece it can be peaceful to just kind of go around
cooking and maybe some equanimity maybe the sense of well-being is good enough
that uh if uh you know you suddenly get a phone call that's a little bit difficult uh you're
in a state of mind where it's easier to take that in calmly because there's a calm state a quantum
state so to begin recognizing these seven factors in ordinary life they come up
and appreciating them and making room for them and not overlooking them not
dismissing them or thinking they're unimportant they're very important for this practice
and allow them avail yourself of them more often get familiar with them
and when there are times when they're there appreciate them riding a bicycle if you're a bicycle rider or going for a
hike or sometimes reading a great novel can bring up some of these feelings
whatever it might be and um and uh the
wonderful alchemy of this meditation practice or mindfulness practice is that
um mindfulness of the hindrances mindfulness of attachment
decreases the attachments mindfulness of what's wholesome increases what's wholesome
so it's a wonderful balance uh mindfulness of what's unwholesome and helpful in our psychological states
uh gives us a little freedom and distance from it and that freedom and distance uh takes
some of the juice and an investment we put into it as we
are to bring this kind of open awareness clarity to really see the seven factors awakening the seven factor
awakening they thrive in receptivity openness relaxation
and non-entanglement and so they grow it's a wonderful kind of
thing that works this way so may you
become familiar with the seven factors awakening may they be part of your life may you enjoy them
and i think in this pandemic at some point maybe last year i did a whole series on
the seven factors awakening on this you know early this early morning sitting so you could listen to those talks
and you know it's a good thing to learn about and uh in terms of the path to
liberation the seven factors awakening then set the stage for liberation itself that's why they're
limbs of awakening and so um and that's a little bit the topic this is a topic for tomorrow the
last exercise and the fourth foundation of mindfulness and um
then has the seven factors awakening as the
platform in which to realize it so thank you very much and i look forward to tomorrow