okay there we go so hello hello everyone the warm warm welcome
[Music] so for today's practice together
um [Music] wanted to invite us
to turn our our hearts our awareness
to to meta which is tinged with
joy with delight with this bright quality of happiness
which is so nourishing so supportive
for for us as human beings in every i mean
it's it whatever the conditions of our lives are whether we're going through a period of
ease yay joy can can support us in making it brighter and being of support
to us ourselves and others and also um if we're going through a tough time also
there can still be space for joy there can joy can still actually especially be
supportive if there are challenges and difficulties so that
sorrow pain dukkha doesn't become the entire measure of
all that we see it doesn't just take the suck the air out of the room it doesn't become all there is but we notice that
actually yes maybe challenges are here but yes joy can be present too
there can be different guests present at the same time there can be joy there can be
sorrow etc so so with that the invitation to turn towards joy
today and whatever you need i will share with you
um during the guided meditation so [Music]
as you know no experience no previous experience necessary ah
so let's begin let's begin our practice together so
arriving arriving in our body
arriving in this moment
as always we begin [Music]
with settling the mind
inviting ourselves to arrive gently with the breath with embodiment
nowhere to go nothing to do
but to just
sit or even lie down
if that's what the body needs
and connect become aligned unified
feeling our bottom and the cushion [Music]
the contact points really connecting
and letting our spine be aligned our vertebrae
the sense of integrity be uplifted from our sit bones
the more stable and wide our base feels more connected
we feel the easier we can sit upright
tall like a mountain that is well connected well rooted to
the earth
and as if there is an internal vertical
pull aligning us aligning our heart connecting our heart
to our head to our belly
feeling connected
the breath enlivening
this verticality this vertical pull
connecting us to the earth and the skies
well rooted to the earth
uplifted
to the skies
allowing each breath as it moves in to fill out to fill out
space of the heart sense of alignment energetic alignment
and see which part of this
verticality needs more energy if you're feeling a little too
flighty or unsettled scattered and bring more attention to the lower part of this
verticality to the earthiness
connected to the earth if you're feeling heavy tired sleepy
maybe more energy to the upper left
the chest the upper part connected to the sky
this
relating invite you now while you stay
while you stay embodied feeling
your bottom on the cushion your feet on the earth
your legs on the earth if you're sitting on a cushion
breath in the abdomen
while we feel continue to stay embodied connected
aligned in this body
to bring to mind
someone who's easy for us to feel happy for
something that is going well in their lives that we naturally feel happy for them
choosing someone easy
it doesn't bring a sense of envy could be a child could be
a pet you think of or a friend or a relative or anyone
where you genuinely celebrate you feel happy you feel glad you feel glad
for them you feel glad for them
there's something good in their lives anything
maybe they're healthy after not having been healthy or
any other areas of life there's a sense of well-being gladness
that they have appreciation they have for an area of
their life
or even if they don't feel it they're not so conscious in the case of pets but
you you're glad for them you're happy for their goodness their
good fortune they're enjoying
you're glad that they're glad you're happy that they're happy
it could even be someone you barely know as long as it doesn't bring up
envy maybe they went on a trip recently
maybe you saw the photos say on social media and you're just glad for them
even if you're not going on a trip right now you're glad yay somebody in the world
a lovely experience yay tapping into the generosity of the heart
generosity of your heart i'm happy for you i'm happy that you're
happy
i'm happy that you're happy
may you feel nourished by your happiness
may your happiness continue mating praise
may it never end
i had a friend today describe their hiking trip where
they so delighted in the fall foliage the colors of the leaves
the brightness the beautiful display of the leaves
of autumn their description their happiness made
me so happy vicarious delight by precarious joy
see what might come up for you
this shared happiness shared gladness
this interconnected web of humanity
bringing gladness in our heart as if it was our joy our joy
we experience it right here in this moment
flattening our heart
letting yourself relish delight in someone else's happiness
vicarious joy sympathetic joy
if we feel happy for other people's happiness
the sense of generosity of heart generosity of spirit
so much gladness our heart can swim it
can be light
imagining relishing this goodness this blessing [Music]
how happy they are ah
allowing yourself to rejoice with them for them
sharing [Music] sharing their joy
i'm happy for your happiness
joy is joy neurobiology biologically
our brains don't distinguish between vicarious joy
one the joy we experience for happiness of others and as if
we experience it ourselves it's the same nourishing
joy happy making see for yourself
we're tuning into a sense of generosity of heart
that feels happy with others happiness
breathing in their joy as if it's ours
lightening up our heart
lighting up our heart
if you wish you can stay with others if you like now you can turn
to yourself this being who is you
the aspects of your life this life something
what are the blessings in your life the gifts
that you can feel happy for your own good fortune your own happiness
let your heart relish and shine this is no time for feeling small or
ashamed of your well-being or good fortune let yourself relish what is good
and you'll discover there is more than you knew perhaps
are you acknowledged
focusing on the abundance
that is also present in your life
we can choose to focus on what's challenging and we can choose
to focus on [Music] what is good see what happens if you make this choice
does your heart feel more full with gladness
with ease with delight with gratitude
may i could may my good fortune continue
made increase may it never end
or simply i'm happy for my own happiness
you
this being who is me
i'm glad for the goodness in their life
whatever good fortune blessings this being who is me enjoys
is graced with may they continue may they increase may
they never cease
i delight i take joy in them
you
see if your hand the palm of your hand wants to be placed
on your chest your heart center middle of your chest connecting with yourself
the goodness the gratitude for these blessings
not to make darkness only darkness the measure of our existence but our
light our good fortune
our goodness
notice if this practice of joy for your own joy
transitions naturally into gratitude
for the last moments of this practice period
appreciating our good fortune
for practicing together before
having met the dharma
such good fortune to be able to practice
cultivate our hearts our minds in this way what a blessing
to get in touch with our own goodness in our goodness our inner buddha
the benefit to benefit from the dharma
the way things are the teachings
awakening teachings and
sangha the good fortune of sangha
may all beings everywhere have blessings in their lives
be happy and joyful may all beings be free
including ourselves
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
well
i don't know about you but i certainly feel lighter and more joyous than when we started there's the sense
of delight and joy both for others good fortunate and for
my own and as i was saying you know
nor physiologically or our brains doesn't don't distinguish between
gladness or somebody else's gladness and gladdens for our own gladness it's just joy it's
just the same stuff it's the same neurotransmitters so and we can feel
that we can feel into that actually when we experience just happiness
joy glad so we'd love to hear your reflections
what did you discover what came up for you
bill says that felt good thank you nikki you are so welcome bill i'm glad i'm
glad yeah so glad and um
yeah you're welcome to raise your hand or or type your reflections in chat
what did you discover
do you feel lighter you feel more joyful are you smiling yes i see
i see not yes yeah
yeah i have a reflection and reflection sent to me personally i
won't read the name i treat them as private but i'll read the reflection says it's great to
end the week on a joyous note yes i agree it's the perfect friday or for
those of you asia pacific timeline perfect saturday morning practice
deborah says i appreciated the opportunity to reflect on the simple joys i experienced today i don't think i
realized them until i looked back at the day oh that's lovely yay
that's wonderful oh and i missed this from bill bill says could you review what you said
earlier about focusing on the lower or upper body depending on whether you are
tired or scattered not sure i understood oh okay so
when i was inviting you there is this
one way we can envision our body or or is is a work with
what can be termed as the energy body energetically energy body and there's so many different ways to to work with the
energy body and and don't stop listening thinking wow energy body that's advanced no no
it's it's very simple let me explain it so what was what i was bringing forth inviting you to just have the sense of
verticality you know as if there was a in in your body there's this pull and if
you're feeling kind of scattered and everywhere then bring more attention to
the lower part of it just feel grounded like oh yes and if you're feeling heavy
and tired and sleepy oh then bring more attention awareness to the upper end of
this energy body the uplift so that's that thanks for asking bill
um aaron says i just feel more peaceful a deep quieter joy oh beautiful
beautiful deep quieter joy i love it vicky asks when darkness arises does one
replace heavier reminders with lighter sensibility
that's an ex excellent question so so it depends if darkness or say if
you're doing a mudita practice which is what we just did vicarious joy
and if darkness if heaviness if sadness arises you have two options one option is to
turn towards the darkness with with kindness so
then your practice will become compassion because you're holding
suffering darkness with mental with kindness and it becomes compassion and it's fine
mudita vicarious joy and compassion and meta they're all related they keep transitioning to one another so that's
one option you can you can if it feels appropriate you can do it
bad that way another option is you can say hello darkness my old friend i see you i
see you it's okay you can be here i'm not gonna push you away you don't have to go away but can you sit here and
and still be and hold witness as i acknowledge the light and if it says yeah okay i can hang out
for a few minutes let you acknowledge the light then you can continue with the modita practice with the
joy practice and if it says no take care of me then you can turn to
compassion so those are a couple ways you can go
oh it's so sweet and here's a reflection from yuka thank you
for reminding me i have everything i just need to to remember it more oh that is so sweet
it just makes me happy to no end the sense of reminding ourselves of the abundance oh
thank you for sharing that you can we've missed your poetry the poetry in your words and in your
practice yeah so
so dear ones it is time now uh to turn to practice in in small
groups to share our joy and actually this is how we're gonna do it we're going to
spend so we're going to do it this is the format we'll go it's going to be round robin so one person will say what
brings them joy what they're grateful for and the next person says what they're grateful for and the third
person says what what brings them joy so you just go around and round and listen to each other and feel mudita feel
vicarious joy for each other's goodness and this is such a happy making practice
oh it's as we've done this before in happier it can it can be so happy making
so so i invite you to practice um engaging sharing your joy sharing your
goodness as a gift of generosity allowing others to delight in your joy
and to for you to delight in theirs so
i've created the rooms and take care of yourselves take care of
each other here we go okay welcome back everyone
the uh the rooms are closed so so we have a few minutes for reflections
what was that like what happened especially if you haven't spoken shared for a while i would love
to hear from you and raise your hand
deborah says we all agree this happy hour and the sangha brings us joy oh
it's sweet that's sweet it's sweet you see many of you smiling
bill says agreed barbara gives a heart it's sweet
oh that's lovely yes anthony has erased and anthony let's see
uh physical hands i often don't see here there you go okay
anthony please thanks for pointing that out yeah that's exactly what i was gonna say
yeah oh yeah i agree you know i have much joy for the uh
dharma teachers at ims you know and for you nikki you know for uh just uh sharing your wisdom with us you
know you know giving your time and effort thank you thank you anthony thank you and thank
you for your practice it's it's giving and receiving joy yeah our
good fortune yeah beautiful thank you anyone else any other reflections we
have another minute oh melanie says thank you nikki your joy
gives me joy oh you're sweet and your joy gives me joy melanie
oh hand up let's see who has their uh does not have their hand ugly
haha let's see now i don't see your hand up where are you there you are okay there okay
uh hey nikki i i'd like to express gratitude to zoom um because i think you know this sangha is
not possible without this technology and and uh as as the amazing group that i was in pointed
out it'll be great if you're all physically together but feeling that you know i'm very grateful that we can meet
this way yes absolutely no and and given that you
and and right now you're in japan wow here we
have this international song from different places in the world and uh
different time zones yes gratitude to technology gratitude to zoom and actually i get
chills saying this it's amazing right 10 20 years ago who would well just say 10 years ago who
would have imagined having this kind of international sangha that we come together and practice and get into small
groups and share so much gratitude so much gratitude so
so thank you all that's beautiful beautiful uh point to oh i see deborah in your
hand if it's quick because we're running out of time we're out of time actually deborah
oh shall i just similarly i i mentioned that there are two i have two new friends that i've never met that i've
met through being in class with one's in singapore and one's in san diego and they're delightful loving people
it's just boggles my mind how this happened you know it's all happened it is a silver lining and i'll i'll mute myself so much
thank you thank you so much yes and eileen says i might have taken today's joys for granted if it weren't
for this session thank you and one more reflection oh yes you are so welcome
carmen thank you oh it's a note to me so so dear ones thank
you so much for your practice for showing up with your heart with your minds with
your full beings and and uh with your joys
and sorrows too all of it included may we all be happy may we all be free all
beings everywhere [Music]
thank you [Music]