so i'll wait another minute or so before the formal beginning of our time together
and i appreciate very much all the chats and
the good mornings and it's a very friendly and warm
way to begin our time together on meditation together
um and thank you for all for being here
so to begin i offer my warm greetings to all of you
and especially warm to the people who are new here on uh 7 a.m or this morning sitting who
are participating in the zen center's uh intensive on the harmony of zen
and vipassana and just a couple of words for those of you who might be here from there is that
the um the way this format works is i usually begin with a few minutes of introductory
comments that are setting the context for the meditation of the morning and then there's some guided meditation
that follows that and and then end with a what i call a
dedication of merit a variation of that and then a little at 7 30 what we call a dharmet
15 minute talk uh if you have problems with the youtube
that it's frozen or if uh i don't appear on the screen at the beginning at all
even though the chats are beginning to roll through the um no if the chats don't roll
through and if nothing's happening and problems like that are usually resolved by refreshing
and if you're not sure how to refresh just close the window and open it again in the way you got to it and the most
prominent most common problem with not hearing the sound is that there's actually some issue with
your computer and and so just check all the settings on your computer including the speaker
setting and see and and then like if there's no sound and
you look at the chat and there's lots of people who are saying no sound then the problem's here on my end and
hopefully i'll notice soon enough that there's a problem and that i'm talking just to myself
usually i don't push a button so the harmony of zen and vipassanam
in my mind and in my heart i begin
this idea of the harmony or the commonality even of these two wonderful buddhist
meditation traditions with a teaching from
one of our teachers our first generation of teachers here in the west study with a man named munindra
ji and indian who studied in burma and became a great vipassana
teacher and he had this wonderful teaching that if it is not simple it's not vipassana
and that in simplicity maybe is where commonality
harmony can be found that there's something powerful and profound about
simplicity a simple simplicity of being
a willingness and allowing valuing of just being alive my zen teacher mel
weitzman made this powerful statement to me once we were driving across the
bridge here in san francisco the bay bridge and i was driving him and he was asking about my life and i was
telling him about different things that were new for me and at some point listening to me he
said just calmly relaxedly it seemed like just the right time he said just to be alive is enough
and that was a powerful moment for me just to be alive is enough
just to be simple and breathing and hear and so we make it complicated and uh
understanding how we make things unnecessarily complicated can help us return to a very powerful
significant way of being which is to allow this life force allow this
breathing being to manifest to express itself in this
fullest possible way that it can be that sometimes is called liberated
but to keep it simple and one of the ways that we make it complicated
is by getting preoccupied or caught up in our thinking
and so one of the ways to return to simplicity return from the fixation the caught upness
in thinking is to rely on breathing
the rhythm of breathing the way the inhale appears and disappears the exhale
appears and disappears the rhythm of that if we stay close to it
the fluidity the change the cycles of that breathing is an alternative to getting the mind
caught in thoughts we come back to the breathing we stay with that rhythm that massage of
breathing and it helps us to notice when we wander off in thought and
have lost in preoccupation and fantasy it helps us to know there's an alternative and we come back to the
embodied physical simplicity of just being a human being that's breathing
and in the process of doing so our minds might protest have other ideas
and say that other things are more important and maybe so but maybe those can wait
for later maybe first to keep returning to the breathing being with the breathing
letting the thinking mind quiet down release itself thaw open
up and discover some deeper intimacy with this live life as
it's being lived so breathing the simplicity of just being staying
resting with the breathing is one way to discover the simplicity of being
no matter what your posture maybe there's some way you can gently um gently kind of
put your body a little bit more alert like if so there's a phys embodied
attentiveness
and then gently closing your eyes and to begin this
connection to breathing it can be helpful to take a few long
slow deep breaths
and the fuller breaths is it like a ritual reminder of here this is the meditation
hall the inner meditation hall the body body's experience of breathing
and with a deeper breaths long exhale
the long exhale if you can then relax
on the exhale
relax your body
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and then with a normal breath continue this process of
letting go
relaxing relaxing your body
breathing in and breathing out as you exhale relaxing and softening
your belly
as you exhale relaxing your shoulders
as you exhale softening the muscles of your face
and then when we're
attuning ourselves to the experience of breathing you might think of it as
becoming aware of the way of the body's experience of breathing
so it's not so much being in the control tower looking and focusing on the breathing
it is it is being inside feeling sensing how the body experiences
breathing
in feeling the rhythm of the body breathing
breathing in and breathing out
and feeling that rhythm where it's most pronounced sometimes in the belly sometimes in the
chest or perhaps in the nostrils of the air goes in and out
wherever it's easiest nicest
allowing the attention to rest there
and if you notice your mind wanders off in thought
as simply and non-conflictually as you
can begin again with your breathing
always ready to begin again
allowing yourself the simplicity
of riding the body's experience of
breathing
um
attention can be seen to be a food that wherever attention goes it's
feeding something if you allow your attention to go into thinking
and distracted thoughts we feed the thinking mind
but if we bring our attention and
bring it into awareness of breathing
not just focusing on the breath but attention is in the awareness of
breathing in the body's experience of breathing
then we're feeding awareness we're feeding our ability
to be present
so
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
we can dedicate the merit of our practice together for the welfare of others
and the way one way to do this is to do it consciously and explicitly
to think of merit as the ways that we have benefited
from this meditation today and to spend a few moments at the end of
his sitting considering what those benefits might be
maybe we're calmer or less agitated
maybe we know ourselves better we know something about our agitation or
even our craziness
and it's good to know it we can be wiser than him
or maybe we're more accepting
less angry or less afraid
more peaceful
more in touch with ourselves
more forgiving so the list could be quite long
it doesn't have to be a dramatic benefit but to consider the benefits
what you can know and recognize maybe there's many you don't know
and then to consider how those benefits how you can bring those
benefits into the world today
how can you extend those benefits or express them for the welfare and
happiness of others
if we live with a wall of separation between ourselves and others
then we're also separated from ourselves but as the wall comes down
we actually know ourselves more fully
and this dedication of merit is part of this crumbling of the walls
and allowing our good will
to begin spreading out into the world
and not let not just letting this be a wishful thinking
but to imagine how the benefits of this meditation
might support someone in your conversations
today and communications today and your way of being with someone
and may it be that the benefits of this meditation
somehow or other can be expressed in these well wishing
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
great okay
i'll wait for the stream of no sounds to stop and then uh i'll continue
so so let's see still no sound
yay sounds back okay great so
so those of you who are new got to see a little bit how this works
periodically i forget to push the buttons and so that's what happened
so to say start over again
it's you know my honor to begin this series of talks on
the harmony of zen and vipassana this week i'll give the morning 7 a.m talks like
today and next two weeks my good friends and wonderful teachers from san
francisco zen center uh fu schrader the abyss of green gulch zen center and
paul haller former abbot of san francisco zen center in the city
will give the talks and and so you know i've been involved in
both these wonderful traditions and traditions i have tremendous respect for and i
celebrate their great value and and um and i feel very fortunate to have
done both i think they in myself have mutually supported each other
in all kinds of ways and um and uh so to have a chance to talk about
the meeting of these two or the harmony of these two is a wonderful exercise for me
the sometimes i think of zen and vipassana as being
the kind of like uh with their meeting is kind of like a two like a venn diagram like two circles
that overlap some places and um in some teachings some teachers might
both be positioned in their mutual circle in the place where the two circles
overlap and so they seem very similar and very similar teachings and and some might be
sitting on opposite you know sides of the circle so that they don't overlap or share much and how big that then
those then circles are you know i don't you know how much bit big that overlap is i don't know
maybe it depends on who's defining it but there's certainly overlap
and but where there's not overlap there's uh there can be harmony there can be complementarity there can be ways in
which uh understanding one helps to understand the other there's a wonderful for me a wonderful
saying that i learned when i was in england that said that if you don't leave
england you don't really know england and i think if you if you lived that grew up there i
suppose if you leave and they come back you see it in different ways so sometimes having being outside of
particular religious tradition for a while that we've been immersed in helps us to see with clear eyes something
we've been missing before and one of those things can be to understand even better the value of the
tradition and so one of the
kind of wonderful maybe coincidences of language
is that the word zen comes from the chinese word chan which
comes from the sanskrit word gianna and it's just a different language
pronouncing the same word and in in pali jaanai is jhana
which is states of concentration the practice of concentration vipassana
comes from the ancient pali word for insight and this also especially here in the
modern west but little bit in india and in modern times the word vipassana no longer simply
meant the insights that come from practicing mindfulness but became the
name for a technique of meditation practice the mindfulness technique in a
sense and then became a word that began to encompass uh kind of the i don't know the full
teachings and culture and religion of people practicing vipassana and so we have this
very odd thing or new thing that happened here especially in the united states i think
starting i don't know how many decades ago but maybe three decades ago or so that
that we started seeing in the west um this expression the vipassana
tradition and then there were sometimes meetings or references to the three traditions
zen tibetan and vipassana um and as if these were and so a little
surprised to see vipassana was now a tradition when it's a relatively new
word to refer to a school of meditation but
uh the wonderfulness of it is that you know on one hand we have in the in the ancient world the pasta
the insights of meditation were supported by
jhana supported by deep concentration and in teachings of the buddha the
ancient teachings these two came in harmony they worked together they were partners and and then over
time as as buddhism developed in india china japan sri lanka burma thailand
kind of in different ways meditation remained a constant in
some way one way the others different countries where they practice buddhism and there were people in lineages and
schools that really emphasized meditation and and zen and vipassana are
[Music] are two of them and once you talk about
sitting in meditation practicing in meditation there's a lot of overlap to what human beings experience in meditation
most people when they sit down to meditate discover very quickly how out of control their mind is how
much they're thinking and all that and how many obstacles there are to being really present and so learning and developing capacity
to be present is very much the same no matter what meditation one's doing
we're developing our capacity not to be distracted not to be lost from our present moment
experience and and
as we do that then we become more settled more calm which is more the
concentration factor but as we become more subtle and more calm we start seeing more clearly what
our experience is which is the insight the vipassana side of it
and and these go back and forth as we become calmer maybe we see better as we see better we can become calmer
more settled or more present whatever the language we have
so uh coincidentally then these two big traditions so called vipassana
are named after these two ancient aspects of meditation that the ancient
world were harmonious were connected to each other quite closely
and um so the general way uh in the there's two ways of practicing
vipassana uh one is directed attention
and the other is undirected attention and and
be interesting to hear from the zen teachers if the same distinction can be made in in zen when i first started
practicing zen meditation i was told to direct my attention on the breathing
and to count the breaths and i did that for years and it was a wonderful practice for me
and the and when i went to burma uh they seemingly did the same thing and
they went to told me to now focus and then they often had an emphasis on feeling the movements
of the belly as you as the breathing happened the hara and in burma they put the attention
the same place uh where the hara area and to feel the movements there so this
was very familiar to me it's the same directed attention as i did in zen
and but what happens with vipassana practice is that the practice begins to be directed and
then as it goes along it becomes more undirected and so we'll
see that in the course of this five days that i'm be teaching here that the way that we've
come to teach vipassana many of us inside practice mindfulness in the west
we start with directed practice and then we begin to opening up the attention to include more
and more in the awareness so we begin with the breathing and the breathing is a wonderful place
to calm down to relax to step out of the thinking mind to see
how much we're caught in thought and then come back to come back come back
and then and then we'll go to body to emotions to thinking and then friday
i'll give you a little taste a real pointer to the undirected
attention of vipassana which maybe is similar to what nzen they call just sitting or shikhan taza
and and in vipassana there's often kind of a sequential or a step-by-step kind of
approach to settling in and arriving to this undirected attention
and so we begin with mindfulness of breathing and i'd like to do a little teaching
around this briefly and that is if we're practicing
attention to breathing a mindfulness of breathing and meditation
um it works when it doesn't work in this way that it works
if we're able to stay our attention stays stable and connected and continuous with the rhythm
and flow of breathing in and breathing out and as we do that sometimes because the attention is long going into thinking
that thinking mind gets quieter and stiller and and then things open up in a nice way
but plenty of times our ability to stay with the breathing doesn't work
and um and then it's like this when many years ago i was up in the mountains here in the santa cruz mountains
sitting in the edge of a creek and it seemed like the creek the water was not flowing at all it was
completely still and so then i took a stick from the shore
and put it into the into the river into the creek vertically and then i could see there
was little wake formed on the surface of the water where the stick went into the water
and then i could see that the water wasn't still it was there was a current that was flowing
so the same way mindfulness of breathing is like the stick we put into the current of our lives
and we get to see more clearly how strong that current is especially look at the current of thinking or the
currents of feelings that we might have and and so it isn't necessarily we're supposed to stay with the breath
and criticize ourselves we can't but they just keep showing up for their
breath then highlights what it is that is really flowing and moving oh look at
that my mind is really busy he was busier and more actively involved in thinking than i realized or i'm more
interested in food than i ever could have imagined that's all i think about and that's the
beginning of mindfulness to see clearly what's going on and the more clearly we can see the more
choice we have about where do we really want our attention to be
do we want our attention to be hijacked by our neurosis by our preoccupations
or do we want our attention to be something that really enlivens us embodies us really kind of
brings out a freedom of life that i would like to think of as
simplicity the simplicity of just being alive and letting life the lived life flow
through us so um so thank you
and um and i look forward to having this chance with you tomorrow
morning and for those of you in the intensive there'll be a
you know a more formal welcome and introduction to this intensive program at their 10 o'clock
program this morning later and i look forward to seeing the intensive
folks there then thank you