so warm welcome to all of you um wherever in the world you are
and um we've been practicing we've been going through since the beginning of the year we've
been going through the categories of meta
one by one the concentric circles and now we've moved to compassion we've
been going through the categories of practicing compassion for our friend for ourselves
for the neutral person which we hung out with for three sessions and now we've
come to a really important practice
which might seem challenging but it's actually really heart opening
and we'll approach it very very gently it's the practice of contemplating
compassion care for someone whom we have a challenge with
seeing their humanity because we're all human beings we all
have challenges so by seeing the humanity
by opening our hearts as much as possible we're not going to force it to open to compassion and care
but ever so gently as much as it's available seeing the common humanity of someone
who's a little challenging of course we're not going to choose the most challenging person in our lives that will just topple us over but
someone we have a little bit of challenge with as a start and surprisingly we'll find
that we will experience more peace more ease more joy more connection
ourselves so we don't do it as a service to them but we're doing it for
our own heart we're doing it for the opening of our own heart so that when we are interacting with
them or thinking of them there is not a sense of fear or contraction or or more pain
um either thinking about this person or interacting with them there can be a sense of ah
more peace more ease and even if it's appropriate some
forgiveness again not to condone the harm that has been done
this practice of compassion is not about condoning
any harm it's about seeing their common humanity
that they too are human being just like us yes we've been heard they've done things
that have been unskillful we can separate the intention the the
actions the impact from the humanity of the person and thereby offering ourselves more
safety and the way to actually work with
if reparations need to be made to have a more sense of empowerment
through practicing compassion to actually enable that
so it seems like a complex practice but it's not as complex as
perhaps conceptualized as we feel into it it will open up into the ways that we don't expect
so as i guide us into this practice tonight a
couple of things to keep in mind one day one is don't push it
and at any point if it becomes challenging for you their sense of lack of safety anger
upset comes up then turn the compassion to yourself
because you're the one who's hurting in that moment so turn the compassion to yourself
and see anything else i want to add um
[Music] i think that's it let's explore anything
you need to know will be shared with you and enjoy
enjoy take delight in this capacity of our heart to see the humanity of all human beings
even those we happen to be locked into some kind of something with right
now so so with that i'd like to invite you to get into your
meditation posture you need to lie down shift
move this is the perfect time to do that
landing arriving in your body arriving in this moment
letting go of all the words
and just landing with the breath
the sensations of the body the feet
on the floor your bottom
and the cushion the raw sensations grounding settling soothing
[Music] connecting
just connecting with the breath
and as thoughts arise
as they will gently telling them thank you not now
i'm giving myself to this practice right now come back later please putting them
aside gently
but confidently reconnecting with the breath
and the body
just this in-breath just this out breath
intimately connecting with the sensations of the breath
let your body relax soften let go arrive
just settling and arriving
tilling the soil
of awareness
now i'd like to invite you you would bring to mind someone
you have a small entangled entanglement
i'm with choosing the most entangled relationship
someone who maybe you have a sensitive been doing their best as you have but there's some kind
of entanglement
there's not an ease of flow but
something that needs to be put down
[Music] for the ease and freedom of your own
heart for their sake
bringing this person to mind as clearly as possible
and realizing perhaps at some point maybe you you weren't entangled with
this person maybe you were friends
maybe in the future you won't be entangled it's just that right now there's some entitlement
the beautiful practice
it opens our heart and offers us ease too
to let us to let ourselves invite ourselves to think about
something good something good about this person
might be something good they've done for us in the past
even if your mind doesn't want to go there no i don't want to think of their good
qualities it's okay mind it's okay let's just try
it for a second we can go back after this meditation and not think about their good qualities at
all but now let's just give it a try let it be an experiment
just these few minutes thinking about some good quality
or something they've done for you that you appreciate at some point
or maybe there's a value about them that you respect maybe you know that they're a good
parent or a good friend to someone
or a good sibling or a good child maybe they're caring
maybe they work hard they're a hard worker
maybe they show up on time something about them some value
that you appreciate you admire something good about them
or again something good they've done for you in the past
this way our minds our hearts can have a more well-rounded feeling
our perspective can shift to be more
balanced again not condoning the harm but having just a more balanced view that
this person is not one-dimensional there is complexity to them
they are a mixed bag just as we are just as everyone is
i'm seeing their goodness too
spending some time being creative in the ways you need to
okay
thinking about the aspects of this person's life where there is goodness
where there are wholesome actions
where their beauty and their values
and seeing allowing that to open you up to their humanity
again not condoning the harm that has been done but that they too are human being
complex with intentions for goodness
and ignorance that causes harm
but letting yourself open up to the goodness to have a more balanced view
feel free to be creative
appreciating that just like you this person as a complex
inner life with challenges sorrow
suffering just like you they want to be happy
they don't wake up in the morning wanting to cause harm in the world they're doing the best they can just as
you are of course they have ignorance they don't see clearly
but perhaps you can see that you have hurt other people too
we have all been harmed and have harmed others
knowingly or unknowingly
so saying that this person is not so different from you
there maybe things that you both love appreciate
are dedicated to and seeing
this place of common humanity
wishing them well from whatever sorrow challenge they're having
[Music] might be physical physical pain illness sickness
emotional psychological
relationship financial part of the human condition
they hurt just like you do and there is goodness in them
and again you don't have to be best friends you don't have to be a part of your life
at all but releasing your own heart
from enmity from ill will by wishing them well
fellow human beings may you be well and free from pain and sorrow
just as i don't want to suffer i know you don't want to suffer
just as i want to be free from suffering and pain
i wish you the same may both of us both of us entangled in in this way
due to causes and conditions
perhaps many of them beyond control above and beyond our control we're in try we're entangled
in this wave we've become entangled
i wish you ease i wish you well many ways our entanglement isn't
personal it's born of causes and conditions
may you be free may you be free from pain and sorrow
may you have ease and peace just as i want to have peace and ease i
wish you the same and release my heart from ill
seeing what works best for you repeating the phrases of compassion
connecting with a common humanity suffering they both experience
extending grace good will to them
as much as it's available right now as little as it's available right now
you be free from sorrow and pain
may you have ease you have peace
just as i want to have peace may you have peace
last couple of minutes of this practice period made both of us
entangled in this way may both of us be free
challenges sorrow pain disappointment whatever is difficult for us loneliness
may we both be happy and happiest
may we both be free from the pain and challenge of our entanglement
me all the beings all the people in this zoom room on youtube
practicing together listening later on dharma
may all of us and all the people we're entangled with all the pears may we all be free
from sorrow challenge pain difficulty may we all have peace and peace
offering the gift of goodness freely to all these beings
including yourself
thanks for your practice everyone
so this this can sometimes appear as a challenging
practice and yet it can be so heart opening
offering us so much ease and freedom safety in our own heart when the
entanglement is a little softened
i would love to hear some reflections from you how was this for you questions comments
complaints and if you haven't shared in a while you can raise your hand
[Music] or if you can type in chat i'll change the settings
you can chat publicly or just to me if you just send me chat i would say your name i'll read
your reflection or you can raise your hand by going to reactions
at the bottom or or open the participants button
so so what came up what arose how did you find this
insights challenges all welcome
as i'm waiting for your reflections to come i'll say that i think this practice of it's actually
in the visuri maga path of purification teachings that oh think about something positive about
the person you're having a challenge with um it's at first you think no nothing
positive i don't want to think about something pleasant or positive about them but then when you work with it it becomes uh
actually the heart really softens it's magical it's almost magical
kim says there was more ease after i imagined apologizing to them ah thanks for sharing that kim
yeah interesting would you like to say more or you're welcome to if you wish you
don't have to um you can unmute yourself if you like or pass
it's all good
not sure what more i can say uh i well i realized that
yeah the entanglement was there was a different cause from my side and her side
so i guess when i saw i was very judgmental of her
so when i imagined myself apologizing to her that loosened the tangles
nice nice nice thank you for sharing that it's
that is quite an insight that there was something about the that the entanglement was being kept in
place by this judgment and then when there was the ah softening of i'm sorry then
everything kind of softened so that's the transition so when i asked
you if you would like to see more that's exactly it's like the observation though oh step by step this is how this is how the
sausage is made this is how entanglement is made
brilliant yeah thanks for sharing that insight kim and one reflection coming through the
chat i was getting ready to say i forgive you at the end of the practice and didn't
expect the wish for both of us to breathe to be free of
pain make sure i got that i was getting ready to say
i forgive you at the end of the practice okay so you're getting ready and then
and didn't expect the wish for both of us to be free oh so you didn't expect that to be an instruction
at the end that's how i'm interpreting the the comment
if you want to say more you're welcome to chat type it in chat or you're also welcome to unmute yourself if you wish
um you don't have to raise your hand but thank you for that i'm also getting this sense of
oh yes you're unmuted go ahead please um yeah i think i was realizing that i was
also building expectation and um from the person and
um for the harm i was getting ready to you know forgive and and let go um
but just that wish of you know i don't want to be in pain and
i want to be free and i don't want you to be in pain and free was was enough it was it was liberating i
didn't need to forgive him or for him to forgive me
thank you for sharing that that's really powerful it's a very powerful insight actually
just as you said that i got i got chills the sense of oh just that wish of both
of us being free that's that that is a co-forgiveness it's
forgiveness it somehow isn't needed anymore it just becomes a part of this wish for both of
us to be it's not directional it's just for both of us beautiful thank you so much for sharing
that powerful [Music]
one more reflection in chat i'm just coming off of a meta retreat so
i'm riding the wave of mitta lots of concentration expansion and care it felt sweet overall to offer care to
someone i have a very mild entanglement with beautiful yeah great great to hear the wave of meta and
writing that way and overall the sweetness of of offering um this
this care yeah this practice can be so beautiful really so freeing any last comments
before one more don says wishing this person well makes it
easier for me to interact with them yay lovely when i talk with this person i
specifically keep in mind this practice oh fantastic that's great i appreciate how there is the uh really
thinking of how to take this to the to the world into the real world how to interact with them and
it is freeing it is so freeing thank you for sharing that don
such beautiful wise reflections i love this community and the
wholehearted practice and the wisdom you share so so as a part of our community
practice [Music] we transition to practicing connecting
with other people this is an important part of happy hour that we connect with others in the way
of holding them sharing with them and then holding us with care and
as i create the breakout rooms maybe spend 30 seconds without any words just wishing each other well
with eyes open just looking at each other sharing meta sharing care for these
fellow human beings who are just like you they're in they have entanglements just like you
we're not so different so there's humor in that right in the common humanity oh all this oh dear fellow human beings
um and then as you wish you can share as little or as much as you wish about your
practice and be held in care by others and hold them with affection and care
in your heart and see how beautiful it can be to connect with people in this way
um and i'll create the breakout rooms and it's usually
just for six minutes or so so it's pretty quick six plus one minute so i'm going to
create the breakout rooms and i hope you don't jump off and i hope you you
participate as uh yeah this is really beautiful practice
okay so rooms are created opening them here you go so welcome back
everyone welcome back and we've got a couple of minutes for any reflections
you might have about how the practice was um the practicing groups
um the first part of practice on your own the reflections in groups would love to
hear from you especially if you're new to happier would love love love to hear from you please
our new wish to happier
it was my first session thank you very much it was lovely to meet the group and i really enjoyed the six minutes of
kind of small group sharing it's nice to meet some people individually thank you great lovely fantastic
welcome to happy hour gym and hope you come back and practice with us in the community
lovely great thanks nikki for giving this opportunity
it was beautiful um i really liked the group interaction as well
because in these times you tend to get very isolated so practicing with everyone online and
then getting to know them individually that it was really beautiful thank you so much for that
great thank you lena thanks for showing up and being here and supporting yourself and supporting
others by showing up and sharing of yourself it's a big gift we can give each other at this
time of isolation yeah
maybe one last reflection anyone else please yes fred
whoops i'm sorry i have my there i am sorry um yeah i'm
newish and um i was just noticing how in
any exercise like this there's always for me a little threshold to be crossed to
[Music] talk with people i don't know in an intimate way and
you know it's always there's always reluctance to cross it and it's always worth doing my experience again tonight
thank you for sharing that fred and exactly as you put it that there is a threshold of discomfort to cross
and and the sense that ah it was crossed and a sense of delight and gratitude that
comes up afterwards that the threshold was crossed
the way you put it is exactly what actually studies put it but studies have been
done for this phenomena of of practicing in groups in this way
and it tends to come up for a lot of people that threshold and after they do it ah there's such a sense of gratitude and
gladness for having crosses so thank you for verbalizing as beautifully as you did
so we have come to the end of the sessions happy hour thank you so much for showing up for
practicing for your own sake for the sake of all those whose lives you touch
and for the sake of those with whom you have some entanglement may you all be safe happy healthy may
all beings everywhere be free
[Music] thank you all