so good morning good day everyone and
happy to have this time with you and to share the dharma and to meditate
together and um you know the topic this week is
the vedana the feeling tones of our experience
and there are layers of such within us or there's a kind of journey and practice to go in a
sense deeper and deeper to discover edina's feelings
of pleasant and unpleasant feelings which are reliable or supportive for us and to
not invest so much in feelings which are not reliable
and the idea is that this sensual feelings as valuable as it
sometimes can be can be are more unreliable they're not enduring
they need the senses need to be continually stimulated and there's something to be found deeper
inside and one way to access it is to or think about it is to
think of it as the
the quality of our inner being you know below the surface below our
concerns for what's happening with us in our daily life and our relationship to other people and the
comfort levels of our lives that as they occur in the moment uh
if we really kind of settle into the inner life what quality is that
what's what's the feeling tone of that and is it a place of comfort and warmth and
well-being or is it a place of anxiety and distress or anger
annoyance what is down there
and uh and then depending on how it is it's possible to see it as either being
pleasant or unpleasant and seeing it with that simplicity is meant to be a way of
kind of being a little bit free of it not not getting entangled in the complexity
of it just very simple that aspect of it that's pleasant or unpleasant or neither
to see that and what i'd like to propose for this sitting as you settle down and connect
to deeper and deeper within you that if what you find is unpleasant
is that uh you gotta tell yourself not that that's not that's not it that's not it
so you keep kind of stepping back or looking deeper because one of the places of
the wonderfulness is the awareness that knows what's happening
so we don't need to get entangled or caught in what is unpleasant
because we're we can keep kind of kind of going deeper or settling back more and recognizing that
simply being aware perceiving being mindful in there
there is some freedom from the unpleasant and that kind of freedom that kind of
clarity of mindfulness clear recognition has a kind of
pleasure to it kind of goodness to it that's where we begin tapping into something like well-being
within and if along the way before you discover
that kind of freedom of awareness there are if you do find that the inner life has some pleasantness
warmth to it or goodness to it um that too is you know not it
no not this not this but to do it with no aversion with no sense of pushing it away but rather more
like as a way of keep opening to opening and opening to um
so we're not not stuck with anything so assume taking a meditation posture
that's supportive for you
and to take a few long slow deep breaths
kind of deep breaths of initiation that you're stepping into
a sacred dimension and you initiate yourself into this inner world
of awareness of here and now
letting go of thoughts and concerns of the day
as you exhale settling into your body
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and perhaps if you relax your body further
with the relaxation being settling in deeper and deeper into your
body your being tension is a way of being at the surface
of our body there's a tense surface tension relaxes
we can maybe settle in on the exhale relaxing the face
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
on the exhale softening the belly
and then the exhale relaxing the mind
any tension associated with thinking let that soften quiet
relax any contraction associated with thinking
let that open up
and then settling into your breathing
and for a few breaths think of the breaths the breathing this
the rhythm of breathing as a guide inward
to your inner life your inner quality of your inner state
breathing with it letting go of thoughts enough so you can
sense and feel here and now how you are deep inside
and if you really feel yourself inside within
how are you how are you really
and notice if it's pleasant or unpleasant or neither keep it that simple and
rather than getting pulled into the complexity of it simply be aware
of how it's pleasant or unpleasant
maybe that can be a perspective that gives you some freedom
feeling yourself deep inside and
maybe tell yourself not this this is not the heart of the matter
no aversion no desire
just freedom in relationship to how you feel
as you search deeper and deeper within
to a place of freedom
a freedom that's not separate from flowing along with the rhythm of
breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to whatever degree you're aware of having a inner life
or not an inner life maybe seems too complicated
you have an inner place where you feel the depths of life
the depths of yourself the places that are most
intimate and tender
the places inside which maintain the more enduring
feelings about just being alive and being present
and this is a part of ourselves to care for
to respect to love
to nourish and support
and just as you have such an inner life a feeling tone a place of depth that
inside where your greatest capacity for peace and
happiness reside
so do others have this and we know that this inner world that
we have can be in turmoil and be challenging
and that life challenges it in all kinds of ways
but if we realize that others have this inner depth this inner capacity potential
and this is where the greatest well-being and happiness resides
perhaps we can look beyond the surface behavior and activities of people and have some care
for them as so as a being of depth some attention some respect
maybe even reverence for the potential everyone has in the
depths of their inner intimacy and tenderness
and if they're not peaceful there they're suffering
and to be attuned to this depth in others
and from that connection to them to wish them well
to relate to them with compassion and kindness
and to wish for them the best may their inner life
be happy and find real welfare and benefit
may all beings be happy
in their core may all beings be safe
and so feel safe at the very core of the being
may all beings be peaceful deep inside
the core of who they are may they know peace
may all beings be free may their good hearts be set free
so they too can live for the welfare and happiness of others
may we all live for each other's care may we all
have it as our concern the welfare and happiness of others
for this fourth talk on vedana
feeling tones the
we have a capacity to recognize the
when things are pleasant when things are unpleasant and when they're neither
pleasant or unpleasant if we don't recognize it sometimes if we
do then there can be these underlying tendencies these habits of mind or um
drives of the mind that can pick up kind of almost automatically maybe even take
over so when there's in the presence of something that's pleasant
there can be strong desire there can be desire wanting in the presence of something
which is unpleasant there can be aversion there can be pushing away there can be
not wanting it and in the presence of what is neither pleasant or unpleasant
there can be confusion there can be delusion partly because if we're very oriented to
looking for what's pleasant and unpleasant and that's kind of you know for some
people a fundamental orientation to find their way in their world always looking for pleasure
in fact i think from some people who practice mindfulness and really start seeing what is operating in their minds in the
hearts when they go through the world it can be quite an embarrassment or a shock to discover
how much we're motivated by pleasant and unpleasant and how much we react to that
and search for it and then we can appreciate when things are neither pleasant or unpleasant
there can be confusion not sure which way to go or what to do or there can be delusion where we kind
of make up fantasies to fill in the gap for the kind of the vacuum the fantasies of
you know pleasant fantasies unpleasant fantasies kind of to fill it in and make it understandable
so these fundamental drives these underlying tendencies can get triggered can be awakened
or kind of waiting in the wing ready to step up if uh in the presence of
what's pleasant unpleasant or neither if we can be aware
of things being pleasant and unpleasant or neither really be aware how this
clear recognition talked about recently the clear recognition the clear
comprehension now this is pleasant it makes things a lot simpler
not to be simplistic or reductionistic but it gives us a very realistic and
helpful kind of kind of perspective that helps us to uh to to leave pleasant and unpleasant
alone and not have the automatic underlying tendencies kick in and move along
and so you know situations can be quite complicated and if we try to react and respond and
figure out the complication of it we might actually get pulled in and the desires and the versions kind of get
have it have the in in a sense to start operating by making it very simple oh that's an
unpleasant situation that's uncomfortable sometimes we don't get pulled in or
sucked in in such a way that the desires and aversions kind of maybe sneak in through the back
door and so oh it's it's unpleasant if we can see it clearly
then there's a way in which that seek clear seeing doesn't make room for the underlying
tendencies to come and get involved or if they arise it's so clear that
they're there that you know we don't have to do anything with that leave it alone there's a desire for more of some
pleasant and so you see it's just a desire or there's aversion to something
unpleasant it's just an aversion for some of us desires are a dime a
dozen for others of us aversions are a dime or a dozen but if
we're an automatic pilot or give ourselves over or give ourselves up or you know
just yield constantly to desire an aversion it's an exhausting life and it's not a
free life so to begin kind of um clearly
recognizing this is pleasant this is unpleasant and not me having you know not
having a back door open for desire and aversion or confusion or delusion to operate
to come in and sweep us away is one of the very powerful things about this
and um the um um
and as we don't get swept away as desires and aversions don't desires
desires here is more like compulsive desires don't take over then there starts to be
space for non desire non aversion
non-clinging non-grasping non-pushing away non-hostility
and that space that opens up is a pleasant space that space
is uh is a feeling is a place where the there starts the breathing room for
our inner life breathing room for other energies or forces or
sentiments to begin appearing and bubbling up
you know it allows for equanimity to be there and equanimity is not a neutral thing
it comes with a very strong sense of well-being when it's strong when it's strong
there's room for generosity room for kindness and love there's room for delight and joy
and appreciation there's so much more room for these good qualities in the heart
when there's no clinging and there's no grasping on things
and so the buddha made a distinction between those feeling feeling tones which
come along with this compulsive desires and aversions and confusions and delusions we have
that there's part and parcel of it you know if i win the california lottery
and i have a lot of greed for that i could be very happy or joyful or delighted for a while
but it's a joy that comes with a strong perhaps attachment clinging to wealth and all
the fantastic things i can do with it and um and you know i've
i've read that uh they've done studies of people who won lotteries and a year after the law they won these big
pots of money they're actually less happy than they were before
so uh how much how much do we uh hope to be put into
uh goes along with compulsive desire and aversion that is going to fix us and
do something and it doesn't so the um the alternative is to let go
and to this non-clinging and there is a joy and delight and pleasantness
pleasant experiences that come with that and um and so the buddha makes a distinction between these two kinds of
pleasantness and two kinds of unpleasantness the unpleasantness of letting go
is that to know that there is more letting go to do and sometimes they feel longing or feel
kind of like something's not quite right here it's a little unpleasant to still feel that i'm contracted and tight
because i know something now about freedom and and so making that distinction
is between the feeling tones that arise from
that are associated with clinging and the feeling tones that are associated with non-clinging
the buddha refers to into a few different ways one way is literally he says the first
is of the flesh and the other is not of the flesh and i think how i interpret that is that
of the flesh means that places where all our ordinary sense
apparatus are operating touch and taste and seeing and hearing that our senses are stimulated
and not of the flesh means that there's something that wells up from within that happens independent of what's
happening in our environment and independent of what's happening with our um you know what's feeding or or impacting
or conceit or the mental attachments we have so if our mental attachments are
challenged or supported there can be a kind of inner well-being that's not of the senses
but it's the mental sense then it's operating something's being stimulated like that
there's a beautiful quality welling up inside it almost feels like that's not of the flesh
it almost feels like it's there for no reason it's just the natural kind of feels almost like the natural
wellspring of life or something it's there for causes and conditions but it has this feeling of being almost
um you know free of the ordinary cause and conditions of our life and so he would have called it of the
flesh and not of the flesh some translators will translate it as uh worldly and not worldly unworldly
which seems a lot some people do worldly and spiritual
but i like that they flesh the knot of the flesh another way the buddha's talked about it
is he talked about it as the vedana the feeling tones associated
with domestic life and that was associated with the renunciant life
and that usually doesn't work very well in english-speaking modern audience
but if we understand the domestic life is you know the surface of it perhaps is
often involved with um all kinds of sensual pursuits the most clear
association with sensual desire is sex with domestic life and um you know that there's a lot of
concerns of sexuality the renunciant life is not so concerned with sexuality and
um but then it's a pursuit of all kinds of pleasures and domestic life that keeps us busy sometimes keeps us
with so busy we don't have time to meditate whereas a renunciant life is not pursuing sensual pleasures
but pursuing something in deeper pleasure that's not of the senses not of the world
and the word renunciant has a kind of maybe negative connotations for some english speakers
but the pali word probably has a very different association in the minds of the ancient people and
and maybe uh we could call it a sacred life there's the domestic
life and the sacred life and maybe it's unfortunate to make a distinction between those two
there doesn't have to be a distinction to the kansas concepts the sacred life can be found in the
domestic life but the the real thing that buddha is pointing to
is the the pleasures that the pleasant unpleasant experiences we
have that are associated with clinging and those which are associated with
non-clinging non-grasping and those which are non-come out of
non-grasping are more reliable more enduring they're the ones that are more nourishing for
something deep inside they're deeply satisfying that
if you never tasted it it's hard to understand why they're so deeply satisfying
and it feels so good to have access to something inside that is um not dependent
on the world being just right everybody behaving in the way that you think they should treat you
and um and to know something about the deep sense of freedom that can come with
non-clinging and the pleasantness of that where pleasantness seems just too
trite or too many that seems minimalistic or reductionistic for how marvelous or
wonderful the experience experience of inner freedom can be
so um so this distinction and to be attuned to this distinction
between pleasures that involve clinging and pleasures that involve non-clinging helps us to find
our way it's meant to be inspiring to help us find more and more freedom
and not get caught in our clinging so thank you and maybe for the next 24
hours you might see if that distinction is something you can feel in your own experience
the pleasure of that comes with long with clinging and that which doesn't
so thank you