okay there we go so good morning and um welcome
to our meditation session okay there we go
and
when one of the important qualities or
approaches to meditation that can be very helpful
is to steady the mind on something and have a continuity of
attention where the mind doesn't jump off that very easily
and so it doesn't get distracted and i don't know if it's a good analogy but
uh if you're driving on a on a
on a road to go far to the east or something
and then you just stay on the big highway that goes east
there's a lot of exits you could take but if you jumped off every exit you
would never get to where you want to go so if every time the mind is thinking
about something or every time that something different happens in your experience and you jump off
the exit you don't really get you don't really go very far you don't settle in for the long haul
so this is called a continuity of attention on one thing and um
and one of the interesting things about a continuity of attention on one thing something like just the breathing it can
be seen very simple and simplistic you know not much life of our you know complicated rich life
not much is in the breathing we might think and so all this interesting stuff comes up in
our minds our thoughts our emotions and feelings but there's something about staying on
the continuity of something staying on the road without getting off
that allows a deepening allows us to connect to something that's uh deeper and deeper within us
that if we keep getting off at the all the different exits for all kinds of things that might be important enough in themselves
they it interrupts the process of of of windowing
out a lot of extra stuff is that keeps us from coming down to the kernel to
this to the source to the the kernel or to that kind of something that's really
much more deep and connected so it's not to hold on tight
to one thing but to have a love or a dedication or a real kind of okay let's let's
really do this and if i can i'll just stay with the breathing
and if i get pulled off into thoughts and other things it's okay
you practically practice with that but to not do it too casually have a
little strength or little gentle loving intentionality just just stay here let's
see it through let's stay on this road and see where it takes us
and let everything else kind of fall away like all the exits let them just go by go by thoughts are come emotions come
let them just kind of wash off to the side let them just pass them by for now unless
you come to a place where the you know where you really need to change roads
sometimes you know you have to take detours and sometimes you have to the road isn't straight and you have to
take a different road for a while that's okay but what i'm emphasizing here's a little
emphasis on just stay and stay and stay
so assuming a posture
and really spend a little bit of time settling into your posture
in such a way that um like you're settling in to really you know
be in the driver's seat really stay engaged stay present
alert maybe a certain intentness to stay
alert enough to not wander off easily
and to then gently close your eyes
and if you're going to use the breathing as your primary focus
to make a strong connection to the breathing by taking a few long slow deep breaths
you're breathing in deeply in a long exhale
long exhale relaxing as you exhale
relaxing the whole body
and then letting your breathing return to normal and continue
to relax your body the muscles of the face
the shoulders
relaxing the belly
and then settling yourself on the body's experience of breathing
wherever that experience
his most comforting or most pleasant or most compelling for your mind
the movements of the belly the chest sensations in the nostrils
or the whole breath body
and as you exhale
settle into your breathing
as if breathing is the main highway breathing is where you'll stay
just as you would stay attentive to the road as you drove on the freeway
and not let your mind wonder too much from the road or at all
so let your attention be with your
breathing not straying from the breath
not easily pulled aside by all the exits that come along
just with the breathing
okay continuity with breathing that's supported by relaxing with every
exhale relaxing into the breathing
and rather than straining to be with a breath relaxing into the breathing as you
exhale and receiving
the inhale
and for these minutes that we're meditating
trust that all you really need to do
you need to stay close to your breathing letting your thinking
recede behind you like the exits that you've
passed
keeping inside your breathing
staying connected to breathing
remain feeling the sensations of breathing one after another just breathing
in the last few minutes of the sitting gently persist
with a focus on your breathing for these minutes as if it's all you
have to do let everything else just recede
with breathing in the foreground
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to direct your steady gaze
onto the world of others beyond you
a steady and kind gaze
being still and looking upon all things kindly
and the steadiness of attention that can come from meditation
can be
been directed as a steady gaze steady presence
on which travels our kindness our care
compassion and it's invaluable
to persist in our kindness
in our non-harming
in the peacefulness that we provide for other people so they
can feel safe may it be that
what we learn in meditation
supports us to find new ways or fuller ways
to benefit the lives of others
to live with a wonderful happy concern for the welfare and
happiness of others
as if their happiness and welfare is our own
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be
free
[Music]
so
so i'll continue today with some stories from the suttas the ancient discourses
of the buddha and the buddha himself was a storyteller
in that he tells innumerable stories
as part of his teachings and some of them maybe or events that he
experienced some of them i think he just made up for the purposes of teaching
he also makes up many analogies and metaphors and he's kind of a wonderful uh
storyteller who has a rich kind of vocabulary of storytelling techniques and for helping
us understand better and and so here's a story the buddha
told it seems that there was a monk who
when he was criticized would easily get upset get angry when someone pointed out that
he wasn't behaving properly so he told this story
that once there was a lady
fedex who was known for being gentle
and kind and peaceful she had a reputation around town that that was how she was
but this lady also had a servant by the name of kali
and kali was
worked hard she was very clever and competent in her work was very neat in her work
cooked delicious food did everything for the household that made everything go smoothly and
easily and then one day kali the servant
thought to herself you know it seems that people have this idea that the lady
is kind and gentle and peaceful but i wonder if this is really the case
let me find out so the next morning uh when usually kali would wake up
before the lady and get everything ready for the day but on this day kali slept in
and the lady woke up and found that the servant was still sleeping so she
spoke harshly oh she said to us first she said to her what's the matter kali that you're
sleeping and kali said nothing's the matter i'm just sleeping in and
then the lady got upset and angry and said and it was harsh spoke harshly to her
you know don't do that again you shouldn't you can't you have to do your work
so then the next day kali slept in again and
the next day the the lady asked what's the matter and kali said
nothing's the matter i'm just sleeping in and so then the lady got even more upset
and spoke even more harshly the next day the same thing happened
but this time the lady got really upset and she got a rolling pin from the
kitchen and started hitting the the servant over the head terrible
you're wicked you're bad how could you do such a thing and with
blood running down her face the servant ran out in the street and said look everyone
you thought that the lady was kind and gentle and peaceful but it doesn't take much to provoke her
that she's actually underneath she had carries a lot of anger and that anger
given half a chance or even a mild chance will surface and look what she's capable of doing
and from then on the lady's reputation of being kind and gentle and peaceful was no longer
in that town so i imagine the buddha made the story up and maybe we don't like the story too
much but still it's an example of him using a story as an analogy
because then he goes on and he says that there are five ways that
people might speak to you he's talking to the monastics he says that either
someone might say something that's true or not true someone might speak in a timely fashion
or a not timely fashion someone might speak gently
or harshly someone might speak with loving-kindness uh or not
with loving-kindness someone might speak to benefit others
or to harm them so these are the five ways it's possible to speak
regardless of how they speak to you you should have loving kindness for them you should have
kind regard for them you should be concerned for care for their welfare and their happiness
in other words don't succumb to anger bitterness resentment if they speak to you in a way that's not
kind not beneficial way that's harmful that's untimely or
that is false that's not a reason to get angry to get upset to be
distressed or to be you should always maintain a heart of
kindness that doesn't mean that we're pushover doesn't mean that we
go along with what they want but it means that we find our way without getting angry
and then he goes on to make some analogies and he says what do you think if a person comes
along with a shovel maybe a wheelbarrow and starts digging up the dirt
on in on the earth to take it away could that man that person succeed at
hauling away all the dirt from the earth and i imagine those listening kind of
laughed and said no you can't take the dirt away from the earth where are you going to put it
and and so in the same way you should make your mind like the earth
that no matter what comes your way that uh you're undisturbed you you
you're balanced you're not disturbed you're not you're unchanged uh by the harshness or the trouble that
when people speak to you in unkind ways or in untruthful ways
rather you should continue to spread loving kindness
suppose he said next that a person comes along with paint all kinds of beautiful colored paints
and a paintbrush and dips the brush in the paint and starts painting
with a brush on in the air would that person make an any kind of
painting and they say no you can't paint that way you have to paint on something you can't
just kind of wave your brush in the air in the same way make your mind like empty space
and so that whatever words come your way um they don't paint a picture on your
mind they don't your mind doesn't react it doesn't take the colors that are thrown at you and people are
unkind or speak words of harmful but rather
maintain loving kindness and stay concerned care for the welfare of this person
and start with that person and then spread that care and good will through everyone in all directions
and then he goes on to say that
if you put a little bit of dye i think this is right
and i don't have the story 100 accurate so you have to be a little bit generous that i'm being a
storyteller myself and in some of the details
and um but anyway so he says then and then imagine that there's a ganges river
and someone puts a little bit of dye and a few drops of dye in that ganges river
would that change the river would it color the river and the person said no a few drops might
change the color in a small glass of water but it has no impact on the ganges river
and so in the same way make your mind like the ganges river broad and wide and
flowing and the words that other people say towards you let it be like those few drops so that
it has no impact on you it has no effect on you so that
you can maintain a heart of kindness good will loving kindness
for this other person you can maintain care you can stay caring for their welfare and their
happiness even if they want to harm you and with that person
cultivating your loving kindness to that person then spread it out to all beings everywhere
so the first story of the lady and kali is a story about how there's underlying
tendencies we have that we can behave one way but deeper down
in the mind there might be triggers for us to get angry upset even
hostile violent even and that the point of practice
buddhist practice is really to touch the deeper place and transform it and to change it
so that our kindness is not superficial or uh feigned or pretend or
you know or doesn't really come from who we are or we're not in danger of of really kind of causing harm
ourselves and this is one of the reasons why we want to develop concentration in meditation
there's something about concentration that can sometimes
bring us deeper under the surface concerns we have the surface mind and preoccupations and
concerns and stories we tell ourselves deeper down to really see what's there
and sometimes what we find is that there's underlying layers of resentment and anger or
upsetness or fear or greed that's there and that is something really good to
touch and to see so we know it's there and then we can practice with it
and resolve it dissolve it solve it all these words having to solve in them
have to do with releasing untying them and in the latin root
to untie it and to cultivate loving-kindness
not just to be neutral as we untie the knots of the heart but to cultivate loving-kindness
no matter what even if people are speaking words that are difficult for us
to hear it's a kind of a tall order it's a challenge with the lives that we live
but here the buddha is really pointing to the role of practice
we practice because this is a valuable way of living that this is a valuable way not as a
moral obligation to be kind or to uproot our anger but rather this is both
working for the welfare of ourselves and the welfare of others that to really uproot our underlying
tendencies to anger and to cultivate the ability not to
succumb to anger and hostility no matter what people say to us
this preserves our own peace and well-being and is for our own welfare and
as we do it we are also creating the conditions where that other people might
work for their own welfare that other people might relax making it possible for other people
to be at peace if they know how to use it if they know how
to allow for it
so thank you and we'll continue a few more stories this
week