my greetings my warmest greetings to all of you and here from redwood city
in california at the inside meditation center
and um the topic for most much of this week is
the uh important insight one of the probably the most
important insight for people doing vipassana practice and
for what we see in the teachings of the buddha is the insight into the inconstancy of
experience and in constancy means that the moment-to-moment experience that we have
there's a lot of arising and passing appearing and disappearing of our
experience that is hidden from us if we
dwell in the ideas of what is happening
ideas have a constancy to them in our imagination we have an image perhaps of something and and the image
is not really current with how things are changing always
and uh and this in constancy is a repetition of uh just new things appearing they disappear
or they get replaced they're superseded by other things that arise and so for this meditation today i would
like to emphasize the appearing of experience the arising
of phenomena that we are aware of we perceive and
many things appear in awareness without any choice in our part or wish on our
part they just appear if there's a building in the environment where you're
a sound in the environment where you're at chances are some of those sounds are
creaking of a building or traffic outside is not something you willed or planned
on having or but it just arises it appears in awareness and then there's a recognition
there's a sound and it happens on your cheek and it wasn't
there before and now it's appeared and it was not planned it was not engineered
it just appeared no choice or no choice on your part and but it's
there it is and the initial appearance of many of these things is effortless in that it's effortless on
our part we don't have to make any effort to make it appear and so as we sit and meditate there are
many things that will just appear in awareness and to settle back and just watch
and observe the appearance of things don't have to worry about how long it
stays and you don't have to worry about seeing it's passing away
but in the course of the meditation many of the things that appear will in fact disappear
they'll be there for a while and and then they will pass away there may be some things that dir endure
don't worry about that and um but for this meditation we'll stay with
the breathing it's the kind of that's the the beat or the the base that we kind of
keep staying at um being with the breathing in breathing out but as we do that in the
breathing itself we can be aware of just new sensations arise
um or maybe not new it might be similar to what's happened at the last in-breath or last out breath but still we can
we're there to not do not necessarily experience new things arising just that things arise
arise arise arise things appear without and there can be a cascade or a
rapid sequence of many little sensations that arise on the in-breath than the out-breath but that he has to rest and stay with
the breathing stay close and intimate to the breathing but then as you do so
gently in the peripheral attention as things arise a sound a sensation
your body a thought see it as something that's arising
if your thinking is incessant then notice how the the pixels of thinking
appear in the the structure of your thinking the thoughts that
if you think in words different words appear and disappear if you think more in
images different images images changes and new things appear just be sensitive
much as you can to appearing appearing and you might even gently use the label
appearing appearing as just a reminder stay here
don't strain don't be actively looking so much as settling back and allowing
like you're giving space for things to appear sensations experiences to show
themselves so taking a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes and sitting here just right away
what appears what shows up
what sensations what feelings what emotions what even
thoughts that didn't exist before or didn't weren't happening just before
but then appear
the sound of my voice appears
and if you drop into your body what appears what sensations feelings
and say are there that you weren't aware of
before
and if as you feel your body you feel the body's wish to relax
maybe the shoulders the arms the belly the face give into that pull of
relaxation allow it to happen
and as you do there may be new sensations arise
and if what arises as you're sitting here is unpleasant
maybe don't worry about it even if it's if it stays for a while
don't worry about it this is a meditation about being open
to the next thing that arises
the next thing that arises
and if it's a presence what arises
don't hang on to it because you want to be available for the next arising
if you find yourself straining or trying too hard to just be with the arising of phenomena
then relax and center yourself from the breathing again
simple breathing in and breathing out and then at some point gently
not trying too hard begin noticing again
the arising of experience and it might be mostly in the breathing
or in the body around the breathing or anywhere where arising new things
come into awareness and just know it's very simply know it
as an arising and appearing
without any other need to label it or understand it
just knowing it as something that's
arising
and knowing that it is good to be aware of
the appearing of experience in awareness
as it moves through as it appears and comes
in this small little sliver of time that we call the present
moment noticing what appears
and how it appears changes
in the way that awareness operates it tends to move around
now aware of this now that sometimes following the train of thought
or feelings or so part of things that arise in
awareness arise because our awareness has shifted
were shifts
even when something is relatively constant
in the subtle details of awareness
or attention goes somewhere else and then it might return
and it's a new er and what was before arises again in awareness
to be aware of change in the arising of phenomena of experience
as if your mind your awareness is wide and receptive and open
receiving whatever arises
like the surface of the lake receives the raindrops
or receiving the arising of sensations in your body
like the bubbles that appear in sparkling water
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
that new experiences new things arise all the time for us not so hard to
understand a new new person appears or calls or
emails the email arises
maybe we'd eaten and we're satiated and full and then at some point hunger arises
again we rest well rested and then sleepiness arises again
but to see phenomena first and foremost has something that's
a risen to be right there in the present moment see oh it just appeared
there it is and to do so in a receptive way open way
to receive it in a liberated way
not entangled or caught in it but with an attitude that you could
bow to it whatever arises you bow
yes and so as you go through the day
new people will somehow or other come into your awareness maybe you'll see them
maybe they'll talk to you on the phone or send you an email
maybe you can be go through the day ready and open in the present to receive the
next arising person in such a way that you could bow to them
bow to them as a in a certain reverence or certain
deep appreciation of their capacity to have emotions and
thoughts and feelings their capacity for
goodness they have a heart a sensitive heart as
well as you
to give some care and attention to the first appearance of others into
your life today and how you are how that's received in
your awareness in your heart and your mind
perhaps before the reactions and usual thoughts and
ideas and entanglements as if you could bow to everyone who
appears and the bowing expresses a wish
may you be happy
may you be safe
may you be peaceful
and may you be free
and then my receptive awareness of you
always ready to have those wishes may it be that i contribute to it being
so may i live this day
aware of the people who come into my awareness
living for their welfare and happiness and freedom may all beings everywhere
be happy may all beings everywhere be free
so you