so
we come then to the end of this week's
theme which is ourselves
and um
i'd like to
tell you of a somewhat famous
quote by a japanese zen master named
dogen
and
it has these i want to quote two
sentences that have this dual nature of
buddhist practice
dual processes
so he says
to study buddhism
is to study the self
to study the self
is to forget the self
so those are the two i want to emphasize
he continues to say
something like to forget the self
is to be awakened by all beings to be
confirmed by all beings
and now but this idea that we can still
study oneself and in the process forget
oneself one can
practice with oneself what can we
observe and be present for oneself
and at the same time the process is out
of forgetting ourselves
and this dual nature might sound
paradoxical or contradictory
but as i've been saying lately there are
a number of
things that humans do
that have that dual nature
and one of them is hospitality
that
we both
act we energetically and fully engage in
the process of being host while
simultaneously
putting some of our own desires for
ourselves aside so we can be the good
host for and care for someone else
that same movement is present with
respect with generosity and perhaps with
a healthy love
that when we love someone
that
you know if we want to express it and
act on it in some healthy appropriate
ways
there's also kind of a letting go of
self in the process hopefully it's not
about just my own
needs desires pleasures uh feelings but
it's also about the other person and
caring for that person so kind of little
bit putting oneself aside
and this dual nature of uh
engaging in practice
in a practice that is
uh to some degree
studying ourselves
and then in the process forgetting
ourselves
i think it's a beautiful kind of
expression of
of um
of the movement of practice
and there's a number of ways that this
can work
and um
one is that
uh first i want to say that sometimes
because
meditation practice mindfulness practice
has a kind of self-reference you know
like we're paying attention to our own
breathing or paying attention to our
body sensations our thoughts we're and
um
meditation we often close our eyes and
just with our own experience
it's very easy
for that to be confused with
self-consciousness and in extreme
situations even narcissism
that an excessive preoccupation with
oneself but
putting oneself as every little detail
of ourselves is so
impactful and meaningful and important
and says always says something about
ourselves so something about
defining ourselves or judging ourselves
or proving ourselves or we need to be
someone comparing ourselves to others
so it can so there's a little bit
dangerous this mindfulness practice if
we bring a lot of self along
but to turn the attention to do the
practice of mindfulness moment by moment
in a meditation maybe just being with
the inner experience the breathing the
body
the thoughts the it's all settling at
everything focusing on it
to do it well to really well means to
really give yourself over to it
so there's not much room for
distractions
if we kind of sit down laxadaisically
a lot of distractions a lot of our
concerns can come pouring in
but if we sit down to practice in a
really
in a relaxed way but in a dedicated way
like this is important this is and
clearly what i'm going to do
in the beginning of meditation to kind
of actually
affirm that oh this is what i'm doing
now
not don't sit down casually and just let
the mind continue to think
but this clarity of really giving
oneself over to
uh the meditation practice to the
present moment
what that does
is it takes some of the energy of
attention away from our
self-preoccupations self-concern
self-ruminations that we have
and it's amazing how much
self-preoccupation a human being can
have and
i think many meditators
will
um
will um be surprised how self-centered
many of the thinking is
distracted thoughts being caught up in
thoughts where we're the central
character in our thoughts in one way or
the other
we have some role it's a lot of thoughts
are in relationship to ourselves
and
but as we kind of give ourselves over to
some like mindfulness or breathing
there's less energy and attention going
into that self-concern
and if we really give ourselves over
well to it to get a
there's a forgetting of self forgetting
of uh everyday concerns just like what
we do if you're reading a really good
book or if you're involved in some
delightful craft or art project or music
playing or something that
you're really absorbed in it there's a
forgetting of yourself forgetting of
your daily concerns even though there
might be a lot of attention
to some parts aspects of yourself to do
the task well
the mental activity of
self-preoccupation concern is not there
so just simply kind of being able to
give ourselves over to the practice
there's a forgetting of self in it
hopefully in a healthy way
as a practice deepens
we start seeing a deeper
forms of attachment stress clinging
contractions that are there around self
and one of them can be just simply in
the nature of how we're doing the
practice
practice itself brings a long baggage of
self
of
association with what it means to be the
practitioner the doer
and there's a simplification process
that goes on in meditation practice
where
everything that's extra that's not
needed it would start seeing as extra as
actually not only extra but often a
little bit
stressful compared to the deeper and
deeper calm
that's being experienced
and so we start kind of uh relaxing the
grip of self relaxing the the
preoccupation with self that can be
quite deep
um even subconscious sometimes
and um and there's a deeper and deeper
forgetting of self and
and that goes deeper and deeper until
uh at some point whatever ex whatever
happens in
meditation in our experience
there's no orientation no inclination
to define ourselves by any of it
to appropriate any of it to
to
either
have us be against it or for it just to
kind of see it clearly in the freedom of
the mind
in the mind that in the heart that is
untroubled by it
but also it doesn't
attribute a self to it doesn't project
ideas of me myself and mine on it
and this uh kind of forgetting or
putting down or relaxing
me myself and mine thinking me and
myself and mine preoccupations me myself
and mine
tightness and contraction and
the fear that sometimes comes with that
or the push and the
the resistance the
the ambition that comes with it
are all kind of this forgetting of all
that
so there's a movement of studying the
self
in order to forget the self
where forgetting the self here is one of
the most it's like it's like taking a
delightful vacation
everyone should have a vacation
and uh it's nice to have a vacation for
himself
it doesn't mean that uh
you're not going to pick it up again or
you're not going to take care of
yourself or you don't it's not that
doesn't mean you have to have a big
debate about the philosophical nature of
what the self is and isn't
it just means that you've radically kind
of given yourself a vacation a break a
pause a sacred pause
where self-concern self-preoccupation is
no longer present
and
and and it has been discovered simply by
settling into the present moment
and practicing simple attention and
concentration just this just this just
this breath just as in breath just as
out breath
just this sound just this
just thought just a thought just a
simplicity more and more simple
to be with each moment as it arises as
it passes as it occurs
be in the flow of the present moment the
flow of the occurrence right now
with no
retrospective thinking even two seconds
before what was that that just happened
well that was great even that can fall
away and no anticipatory thinking
it just the flow of this moment absorbed
in it delighted it like you're playing
music and just absorbed in the music of
the moment or
doing a craft or an art or reading a
book or
or maybe playing with a child that's
just you know so delightful just to be
there and
in the moment with the child no before
and after
a forgetting of self
and this is one of the great
pleasures of life
and it's one of the great of sources of
wisdom and freedom as well
so
we started this week with respecting the
self
and uh
this whole movement that we're talking
about here
is a form of profound respect
of freeing ourselves from suffering
respecting ourselves enough not to
suffer
not to contribute to our suffering by a
healthy kind of forgetting
of self-preoccupation
so
thank you
very much