so in doing breath meditation and doing the sana panasati
over these weeks from one perspective we're going through it slowly from another perspective we're going
through it uh quickly and i'm sure there's people
who feel it both way one way or the other and uh from the slow perspective
we're putting together slowly piece by piece the el the alphabet for breath
meditation all the little basic elements and um and uh
learning you know once you learn the alphabet that gives you access to
a tremendous wealth of knowledge potential for communication writing
reading uh understanding all kinds of things that come alive with reading and writing
and so in the same way we're learning kind of the basic elements the alphabet in the sense of
all the little things to notice and be aware of as we're breathing and um and then slowly over time these
begin to be put together and after a while it's you know you can read
the book pretty quickly or easily maybe and so after a while we get a sense of
the all the little elements how they come together and create the grammar of meditation and
create the sentences of spirituality and freedom so um we're going to continue and uh
with this um with this uh
our education and elements of breathing
in meditation so to assume a meditation posture
and taking a few moments to settle into your posture
to maybe sway a little bit front and back
forward sideways
maybe twisting a little bit maybe making small adjustments
so that the the weight and the way your body is organized
can be one that is settling for you
that allows certain things to settle and so that taking your meditation
posture is a little bit of a homecoming or a little
coming to a place where you have some modicum of contentment
and so taking the time to feel that not to be in a hurry in meditation
and overlook the basic establishing your posture and in doing so
establish a mindfulness of the body establish a degree of embodiment in this
posture
and then to close your eyes and take a few moments to feel this body
okay sense how the what's happening in the body
all the different kinds of sensations that come alive in the body
and don't don't focus on any particular one just let your attention roam around
taking it all in
and if in doing so there are still some small adjustments in the posture it can still be a good thing to do
and then ever so gently ever so lightly
bring your awareness close to your breathing
not head long into it just kind of on the edges of it maybe and begin
feeling the experience of the body breathing
maybe coming to the breathing through your back and from there towards
the front lightly slowly
and taking a few moments to familiarize yourself
with how the body's breathing
and letting your attention quietly roam around the various places in the
body where the movements and the pressures and the
release of pressures appear that are associated with breathing
and perhaps as you exhale there's some places in your body that
the breathing can relax more
release as you exhale
perhaps as you exhale there can be a softening
in the breathing body
and feeling more fully the experience of inhaling
and ever so gently as you inhale inhale
more fully longer inhale
so in the as you inhale the chest expands or fully
maybe there's a lifting of the shoulders
and not breathing in so fully or deeply that you get winded
in a relaxed way
and as you inhale see if you can notice if there's any
upwelling feelings the way in which energy in your body or a lightning feel
feeling it of lightness a feeling of movement that's lifts
upward through your torso and up towards the head
a little movement that is energizing
perhaps as you breathe in a little deeper than usual
there's a movement towards greater clarity
especially if you let the thinking mind get quiet as you feel it more fully
and energetics that is that moves in the direction of waking you up
awakening a clarity and a lightness
and if you do this breathe deeper breathing just very slightly
is there anything that feels pleasant in doing so in the is there an upwelling that brings
pleasure or pleasantness maybe even delight
some people might feel there's things get brighter a little bit more
light in the mind
and letting your breathing return to normal but still on the inhale
is there any upwelling feelings that occur in your body
ever so ever so slightly a movement which lifts and straightens
the spine
and then as you exhale ride the exhale
with a very simple quiet ah
to feel the releasing the relaxing
and then on the inhale to receive and allow the upwelling
of energy of brightness
lightness receive it with the receiving of the in-breath
a releasing as you exhale that releases the edges of your body
releases tension in your body
will you release into a tingling vibration
warmth softness in the body perhaps
and then receiving allowing the upwelling of in-breath of the inhale
the exhale tends to be more for relaxation
the inhale more for energizing or brightening
and as you're breathing is there any feelings of pleasure
pleasantness the joy
that comes along with the body breathing in
the body exhaling
allow that pleasure
to flow through your body as you inhale
maybe flowing in an upward direction or outwards
maybe it flows downwards as you exhale
receive and let it spread through the inhale and ride on it as it in the exhale
let it flow it could be very subtle tingling and
warmth feeling of goodness
pleasure and as you breathe with a quiet mind
letting your thinking become very quiet and sensitive
so you're sensitive to feeling the pleasure that might be here
with your in-breaths and out-breaths breathing in and breathing out
there may also be unpleasant sensations as you're sitting here
don't don't don't ignore that they're there but don't give them any real attention
let your attention go with the pleasant sensations of breathing the
pleasant sensations of just sitting here in your body
as if they are big enough to hold what's unpleasant
as if they are a tender caring for what's difficult
and if the mind wanders off in thought okay let yourself have a homecoming
into what's pleasant enjoyable contentful
in your body as you breathe
and as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps with this light touch a light touch with the breathing
and the breathing as it moves through your body letting it have a light touch
on whatever is tender or difficult in your body
very tenderly touch it with your
breathing touch it with your light awareness
just a light touch of recognition of accompaniment
so that whatever pleasantness and joy there is contentment
it shares itself tenderly with what is difficult
what is not so pleasant
and in our capacity to sit here
quietly contentedly openly
maybe softly many different ways of
you might feel at the end of a meditation can you now lightly tenderly
just lightly touching opening to the suffering of the world
just touch the edge of the edges of it
no need to go into the middle of it challenges of our people you know and
don't know around the world a gentle soft
touch on the edges of their suffering arising out of your soft
light awareness soft light
breathing so their suffering doesn't disturb you
and you don't disturb them but you're there to accompany to
recognize to clearly see ah the world suffers
and then perhaps from whatever tenderness you have
towards a suffering world a tenderness that maybe comes from
it's seated in a place of meditative contentment
meditative ease or subtleness
and allow your compassion and care and good will
maybe to take the form of wishing well for others
wishing them happiness freedom from suffering
wishing them hell then well-being
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be healthy
may all beings be free
and may all beings live together
in goodwill
so a couple of words kind of to end this meditation before switching to the talk
because of the nature of these 16 steps of anapanasati
you know there's more to teach as we go along and so maybe i'll be talking more guiding
more in meditation than maybe than usual and um
and what you might want to do and consider is to um if it works for your life
is to meditate a second time during the day even if it's just 10 minutes 15 minutes
or another half an hour and perhaps having a little more
practice with what we're doing in this guided meditation
and or build with it or allow for more of it to kind of percolate and develop and and then it might uh you might find
that it supports you more when you come so you have back to the guided meditation and also
you might appreciate the time to have more silence to explore this on your own
so continuing on the 16 steps of breathing meditation that the buddha
taught that does come from a variety of places in the discourses of the buddha the most common
one place is a text called discourse on mindfulness of breathing
anapanasati suta and it's in the what's a collection called the middle length discourses
and there's been a variety of books that are you know ex explaining this or describing this the
descriptions are 16 steps are really just like cliff notes there's like brief sentences
and different meditation teachers will have a little different take or
explanation of how these work or what they are and which is appropriate there's many techniques and they're like
you know these are just kind of little placeholders for a whole universe of experience
so we're coming into the fifth and sixth step of anapanasati
and um it's um the fifth one says uh one trains in other words one
practices one like one practices the alphabet to really learn it one does it over and over again
one trains to trains that as one is breathing in
one experiences joy as one breathes one trains that as
one breathes out one experiences joy and then this the sixth the sixth one is as breathing in
one experiences happiness breathing out one experiences happiness
and the so these words for joy and happiness
some people will translate uh like the famous translator bhi kabody which has translated as a rapture
for joy and what i translate as happiness he translates as pleasure
and and the difference between these two is that uh whatever this uh the joy
factor is or um is it's a it's something that's a little bit energizing it's a little bit
it can be quite strong but it's something that's a little bit more like a thrill in the body
a delight it's a flow of energy or flow of pleasure in the body that is kind of uplifting
and delightful and and just has a lightning feeling
and and then the the next one that what i call happiness he calls pleasure is uh when the
energy energetics of joy quiet down that that the pleasure of the joy the
happiness of the joy remains something more subtle than something has more
sense of contentment some people get quite attached to the energetics of
joy and sometimes this feeling of ecstasy and rapture and very strong can course through our body the wave
cascading waves of joy and it's quite and can be quite intense
and but sooner or later people get a little tired of the energetics of it
and then the energy the energetics the upwelling energy of it begins to settle and quiet
and now there's kind of a state shift and and that uh and uh and in retrospect we see that the
joy has a kind of mental quality mental energetics of it that that settles and then we're more
subtle in the body and then a more feeling of contentment in the body
of well-being in the body tranquility in the body
that for me feels like a very sublime kind of
happiness but because it's more physical some translators like to translate it as
pleasure and because it doesn't have the mental energy of it of it as well
and um and so uh um and the operating word
verb is is one experiences uh you could just as well translate the
pali language word here as one feels when it allows when someone
really feels what it's there elsewhere the buddha says when this kind of pleasure or joy
begins to surface when it's allowed to feel it in such a way that it allows it to spread through the
body and as i said yesterday the buddha said this kind of pleasure or joy
is is not to be feared and as not to be kind of dismissed or
belittled it's actually quite a healthy thing to experience it some
people when they feel it finds very healing and it creates a context in the body and
the heart in order to better kind of be present for what is difficult
it's not a denial of what's difficult and painful in our lives or difficult
emotions and what's happening in the world around us but it's easier to
be present for it with uh without uh falling victim of it or being
oppressed by it or being you know suffering ourselves even more by it or feeling self-pity
but because we have this goodness we have this joy happiness well-being in which to hold um the challenges of
our lives so um so uh
there's something about so this joy this well-being that comes in this step
comes a lot from really being starting to be absorbed or really intimate and continuous with
the experience of breathing it also comes when there's more sense of
a wholeness everything is included nothing's being held at bay and so the earlier steps the steps of
the body has to do with um really feeling the body and relaxing the body when the body is
tense the body is in a certain way not whole so we're kind of cut off from parts of it in this kind of way
but as we feel the body and relax the body there's feeling of wholeness of gathering together
and that gathering together and becoming whole is what contributes to the joy arising it's kind of like
we're creating the channels we're creating the the openings for this well-being to be
there that can come when we start becoming really
intimate or connected or continuous in the attention and so the awareness
itself gets gathered together to really be in the present moment
with the breathing as opposed to the thoughts jumping around here and there and about what's for dinner and what i'm doing
tomorrow and what i did yesterday or something the the mind begins to the wholeness the
mind also begins to gather around just this experience here the mind itself now
centers itself on the experience of the body just breathing and this i this centering itself in the
body breathing has the joy or the delight of you know the the problems of our life the
preoccupations the agitations the anxieties that are um that are fed by thoughts and
perpetuate by thoughts begin to quiet down and so just that is
a relief to have and then we uh and then this the combination of the
the mind's intimacy the awareness is intimacy with the whole experience of breathing in
and the wholeness of the body then it tends to um start producing from the inside out a
sense of goodness which is my kind of generic name for a whole whole class of things family of things
we might feel joy delight satisfaction contentment
pleasure that thrill wonderful feelings that come
and and they don't they come back for no good reason for what's outside in the world nothing
has to be better in the world in our you know it just comes because of this
really this intimacy and gathering together this harmony harmonizing of our whole being that
can come when we're really present here so the first uh four steps of panasonic
which can take a long time to kind of really do and have a lot to do with really finding
ourselves really present here in a whole way in an embodied way in an
inclusive way so it's not a narrow tight little concentration
but rather a centering on everything's included and everything is centered so the image i have for it
is a big bowl that if you take a a a marble and drop
it into this big bowl it'll go up and down and around and if you
dip lean into the bowl and push the marble you can just keep it going it just keeps
spinning forever if you keep pushing it but if we stop pushing it slowly slowly
it'll come to center at the bottom of the bowl with um the whole bowl is there but
it's center it's resting at the center so the same thing with our attention our thoughts our
awareness that we keep spinning it pushing the marbles in our mind with our
thoughts with our involvement with our interest with our reactivity to things and the mind just the thinking mind just
spins and goes and gets distracted but as we leave it alone then
everything begins to settle gather together and we support it with our practice of intimacy and getting close
to breathing and and uh and then with time we find we get
centered at the bottom of the bowl centered on the breathing and this can starts becoming a very
pleasant experience and uh very enjoyable and if
this uh the the joy factors begin bubbling up within and the buddha's description of this is
i think i said it recently is that of an uh water spring
flowing up into a lake and it just flows up from the inside and
spreads out and so with a for example sometimes you can feel that with the inhale
it's almost like there's an underwater spring under deep in her torso
right down near the base of our body or base of our chest or something and as we
breathe in there's an upwelling feeling of this and then as we exhale perhaps there's a
feeling of it flowing all back down again and flowing out because flow and flow
happening of this pleasure this energetics this lightness
they can be quite subtle when it begins happening and it's good to recognize it and
realize oh this is actually a good thing to pay attention to don't look for it when it's not there
don't try to manufacture it and don't feel like you have to have it this fifth step and sixth step of
anapanasati um it's you know only only sometimes it begins to cut happening
the core practices the first four and this is so beneficial just to stay in the first four for a long time
in a sense the longer we stay with the four the stronger foundation we allow ourselves to have for what follows
but unless you learn about this potential for joy and pleasure as part of the
meditation practice then you might not appreciate it when it happens you might not recognize it when
it happens and then you won't kind of include that or become whole with that
let that spread and open and receive it through your body and all this requires some modicum of a
quiet mind it doesn't have to be completely quiet there can be some thoughts in the background or
light thoughts so don't be at war with your thoughts and think you have to not think at all that just produces tension but
there is a quieting that happens as we practice so
mindfulness of breathing and i hope that you'll have some
opportunities through the day and through meditation to appreciate and value and enjoy
yourself breathing thank you very much