so now let's see okay so
all the equipment i think is right now
so good morning a good day it's a nice day here in redwood city
because we've had a nice rainstorm overnight and we certainly
certainly needed it here so
i would like to try something different this week for the this seven o'clock time this guided
meditation time and uh and that is um not to do a guided
meditation but to allow you to have these minutes in silence
we've done doing for many of us guided meditations now for you know since the beginning of the pandemic
and there's also a great value in sitting silently and quietly in community in this way
i know some of you will be disappointed and but just for this one week and
and i hope that the teachings the instructions you've
received now over this time will um you know
come to fruit and as you sit for these minutes of quietly about 25 minutes
we'll have and then and then i'll give the teachings for this week starting at 7 30.
and so so without anything
more to say please
settle in and and then maybe in the silence of practice you'll be more
receptive or ready for the teachings that will come today
so then as we come to the end of the sitting
to
spend a few moments
reflecting on how whatever benefits have come or whatever
has we've learned from this meditation about ourselves about
presence attention silence stillness
how can it be beneficial as we go into the world how can we benefit it benefit others
through what we've had this morning
to be able to reflect on
benefiting this world is one of the great
benefits of treasures of spending quiet time meditating
to come out of that wishing for the welfare and happiness of all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
okay so um
so for this week the theme will be
oneself so the focus is on a relationship through oneself
and um i was a little surprised that this came up as a theme for this time of the year
i had thought perhaps this was a better time for something like loving kindness or
compassion or generosity so we get into the holiday season
but then i thought that no i think that a focus on oneself
to kind of come into a better space a
better way of being with oneself can prepare ourselves to be in the social world those of us who are going
to be more social perhaps or more interactive during the holiday season
so oneself it's a little bit of surprising theme for
buddhists sometimes because of sometimes an excessive emphasis on
not-self and it seems like we should not shouldn't talk about self at all
but if you find and then look in the teachings of the buddha he often talked about
that we use the word self the pali word is atta atta in positive sense
i believe without any [Music] fear a concern
that would be misunderstood as being a metaphysical cell self or being some kind of permanent self or
permanent existential self that somehow the ordinary idea of
oneself is a valuable and and useful uh reference point
for understanding ourselves and our lives and uh the um
and i think that to some degree there's this wonderful uh interactiveness and and balance and
ancient teachings of the buddha between a certain kind of individualism
and a certain kind of collectivism certain kind of emphasis on
personal agency and what we can do and an emphasis on
being open receptive connected with others in the world around us
and the combination of those is a fascinating way of living this life
and i'll say more about that in a couple of minutes but i wanted to read a passage from the dhammapada
where this word self is is utta is used
and here it's being translated as oneself
if one knew oneself to be precious one would guard oneself with care
the sage sages watch over themselves in any part of the night
so i think that sages often stay up and meditate through the night so they're caring for each other caring for
themselves this idea if one knew oneself to be precious one would guard oneself with care
and also goes on and says one self indeed is one's own protector
what other protector could there be with with self-control one gains a protector
hard to obtain so to having the agency of being one's own
protector and um what other protector could there be
many of us are hoping others will protect us others will make us safe if only other people would behave in a
certain way then we'll be safe and it's it's common these days to for plenty of people to
say that they're not safe and then insist that others change how they are to make them safe
and there's some value to that and we don't want to discredit its importance of doing that
at times but there's also something very important about learning how to be one's own protector
and learning how to find safety within and here it's i said it's
obtained through self-control when gains a protector hard to obtain
and so one of the uh one of those ways i i'd
like to present this idea that each of us for ourselves is precious each of us for ourselves is dear
is uh through the notion of self-respect respecting ourselves and
respect has this wonderful combination of having agency
with doing something and also a kind of openness a kind of
making space for kind of letting go of conceit and self-concern for something to that which we respect
to give some kind of care to it or deference to it generally we think that it's easier to
understand with other people or some other parts of reality if we have respect for it
so to respect someone is a powerful act that we generate from
inside of us when it's done wisely and then to
at the same time as this taking agency for this respect having this respect for someone
there's also a kind of putting oneself a little bit aside hopefully in a healthy way a little bit
of a difference here they're making space for the other person that we respect it's kind of like hospitality
is one of these things where these dual related dual activities is there then on one hand we are the agent of offering
hospitality to someone and in offering hospitality we there is
a kind of self-forgetting it's kind of putting oneself aside for the purpose of supporting helping
hosting someone else i think generosity also has this this
dual action of of agency that we do but also a giving away
and perhaps compassion is the same way that we can generate compassion care for
others and at the same time it is caring for others and a certain kind of healthy
way we're putting ourselves aside our preferences and things
so respect is that way and and um and that dual kind of relationship can be towards ourselves
we can have agency in deciding or having respect for ourselves
giving ourselves respect and at the same time as doing that
letting go of conceit letting go of certain kind of preferences for what we do and what we
should do so that we can really know ourselves better feel ourselves better be present
for us in a bigger way and um
so this idea of um we are important enough we're valuable
enough that we are appropriate object of our own respect
and and just like everyone we can respect
there's certain kind of way of valuing and seeing the worth of every human being and
not to leave ourselves out of that to have respect for ourselves to have
care for ourselves the the movement of love in buddhism
is not a movement where everyone is loved but oneself
but it's a movement of love that includes ourselves so i think of sometimes as the
as the heart the emotional heart being kind of like a light bulb and then you turn it on the light you
know maybe it's you know the room gets filled quickly with light but there the if it went the first light shines on
ourselves and and then it light it shines on what's
around us the the love the care the respect first goes through us
and then into the world around us and it's my hope that if we have self-respect we actually have uh uh
more substance in ourselves for respecting others that we show up more fully when we have
self-respect and the more fully we show up the more we're there
to care love be friendly supportive kind to other people
the self-respect that we are we are we're allowed to live we're allowed to
be we don't have to be apologetic for ourselves defend ourselves we don't have to be self-effacing we don't have to
kind of um not count we're allowed to account
so that we can let everyone else count better we're allowed to be worthy and full so that we can
offer the gift of attention and presence and space for other people as well
so this idea of refuge
oneself is the refuge of oneself what other refuge can there be
so again the idea of protector with our own protector our own refuge
and so how do we make ourselves a refuge for ourselves how do we make protect
ourselves and uh how do we so i would like to say that
it takes some agency it's not kind of just trusting that we're innately good
or everything is is wonderful about ourselves which some people are so eager to feel because there's maybe such
a low negative self image that's a bomb it's a kind of medicine to
hear that you're worthy and wonderful but the way to give substance to it is through
agency and the buddha gave a number of things one was through living ethically
that the more we can live ethically the more self-respect there can be
so we we kind of create the conditions to have self-respect and in that regard
one way to develop self-respect is not that we are automatically ethical
but rather where we have a commitment some people would say a vow to live as ethically as we can
and to learn from our ethical mistakes to try to do better in the future that kind of attitude i think is
warrants more self-respect and so the idea of making a commitment
making a vow is um is a very i think a powerful thing
to do the other thing that can uh for making ourselves a refuge or self-respect
is to develop mindfulness to have the self-awareness enough self-awareness to see how we
undermine ourselves how we criticize ourselves how we doubt ourselves
and then um and then not not believe it so much
be able to see it clearly enough and fully enough that we begin trusting the
seeing the knowing the perception uh well there it is again that habit of
mind to be self negating but i see it
and the word respect as you know many of you know um
comes from the word to see again the latin word respect
and so to this idea of mindfulness really being able to see
and see with care see with kindness see with a certain kind of openness
so that there's this we're not caught in the negative self-talk
and begin having respect that we can do this we can meet our negative negativity
with kindness with care with openness that's respect worthy
so to um
and then the last one i think the last one i want to read here
is um fascinating poem by the buddha verse
a person should not give oneself away should not give oneself up
beautiful speech should be released malevolent speech should not
um so this so this idea of one should not give
oneself away to have self-respect we never give ourselves away
though we might do that dual action where there's self-respect and we get out of the way
to supp we get rid of our we let go of our conceit we kind of
respect powerfully with agency put aside our own preferences sometimes
for the benefit of others but we're not giving ourselves away we're not giving
up on anything we're not giving up on ourselves so uh
so the theme for this week is oneself and
the topic for today is respect to self-respect and
i suspect that not many of you have thought about this in relationship to yourself some of you probably have
and maybe for today you can reflect on this idea of self-respect what does it mean for you
maybe talk to friends and family about you know what it might mean and how it this idea of self-respect can be
beneficial for you and and maybe significant maybe even powerful for you
to live with greater risk self-respect to um
to find how to have self-respect to tap into self-respect
and so reflect on this topic and uh look at it and live with it for the day and
then tomorrow we'll go on on in other aspects of focusing on oneself
so thank you