okay great so a warm welcome to all of
you wherever in the world you are joining this
moment so for today's practice we have been making our way
through the different categories um of the Brahma viharas and where we've made our way to the category
of compassion cultivating our heart in compassion in karuna for all beings for
all beings so I'll say a couple of words about this particular
category so this category actually similar to all categories they're
aspirational um because sometimes it can feel like wait all beings wishing all of
all beings to be free from suffering and be well that's impossible of course they
suffer so it's not the I idea that you are going to wish them
well and that they will be well um I see
a message someone can't hear is anybody else having trouble hearing me no everybody else is having not
having trouble so I think it's it might be on your end um so just continuing with that so
so this is similar to the um aspiration
to the aspiration to the bodh satva aspiration so the Bodhi satva vow um
which is something like beings are numberless I vow to save
them fully well knowing that you can't save every
single being it just it's inconceivable right so to even taking
that vow your our perception needs to shift it's it's aspirational we are
doing this in order to cultivate our own heart not that every single being will
be saved or every single being will be free from suffering but you're cultivating your heart in this case
in the wish for every being to be free from
suffering to be cared so it's it's training our own heart it's without
attachment to outcome that yes every being will be happy because the outcome
is beyond our control whereas what is within our
control is the cultivation of our heart so this practice of Wishing Well of
cultivating compassion for all beings everywhere is an aspiration of
cultivating our heart in kindness in
goodness okay does that make sense give me a nod if you're with
me yes okay all right I'm seeing lots of nods and I don't see every single one of
you but uh but okay so with that
aspiration with that aspiration of cultivating our hearts for
Wishing Well wishing well for all beings knowing fully well that yes there is
suffering in the world there is pain there is sadness and we are not empowered the
this one person to take it all away to make it all better but that's not the object it's about us cultivating us
turning our hearts into the Good Will may that be so may that be so fully well
knowing that it's not possible but may that be so that is our wish that is Our
intention all beings no one left out not just these beings but not those other
beings the ones that are this shape but not those other shape no all beings may
all all beings be well so that's the idea here so with
that let go of all the words too many words let's practice first of all with
settling with arriving in our
bodies in our breath
arriving Landing settling in the
body letting go of any tension any tightness
settling it with the breath and the body
relaxing relaxing softening intimate with each
breath
e
e e
just tilling the soil first settling
[Music] arriving with the breath The lure
abdomen greeting greeting this body and whatever is
present
e
e e
intimately connecting with age INB breath and out breath the entirety of the in breath and
the up breath in the lower abdomen
e
e e
just this Breath Right Here
not past not future right here right now
and now I would like to invite you
as you breathe as the breath is received in your lower
abdomen in your chest Your Heart Center proverbial Heart
Center as each breath is received
inhale and exhale
imagining that you're connecting with every
exhale and every exhale is bringing comfort and ease spreading
goodness and at first let's start with the circle of beings who are close to
you yourself people you care
about close to you your heart maybe close to you
physically if you wish
knowing fully well that everyone that you're considering In
This Moment yourself and the
beings who are close to your heart they all have you all have we all
have challenges in our lives
some stress some
difficulty some duka some dissatisfaction or suffering
and with each breath with each out breath wishing ease and comfort freedom
from this suffering it's an aspiration as a
cultivation of your
heart may all of us be free from Pain and
sorrow from difficulties may we have peace may we have
ease Circle could just be you and maybe a couple of people you care
about starting simple
or a couple of pets included it's all good
and then expanding in your own time little by
little as if your heart shining goodness
shining Good Will warmth good wishes well-being
with each breath spread further
out and you don't have to to breathe any
harder imagine it happens on its
own the light of your heart good willll gets
shared may all beings all beings all over the
world may they be free from sorrow pain difficulty challenges
All Humans whatever continent they live
[Music] on all continents of the
world whatever language they speak
whatever race nationality gender
identity size
age all people around the [Music]
world may they be free from
sorrow may they be
happy may all beings who
fly be from free from sor and challenges and
pain may they be
free may all beings
who are four-legged
may they be free from challenge
difficulty pain may they be free may they be happy
knowing full well that many four-legged beings in the
world are hunted and hunted etc
etc knowing that challenge is a part of life and cultivating our heart for
wishing them well Shing them freedom from challenge
pain difficulty
Fe all beings who Slither will crawl
all beings born and yet to be
born May they be free from sorrow
pain physical emotional
may they be free may they be
happy beaming beaming your good will for all
beings no beings left out
cultivating Breath by breath goodwi and kindness a heart of
goodwi and
kindness as if your heart was shining shining its beam
of Goodwill care light and would bring
sucker as if it were bringing sucker in is to all beings
who are in front of you the frontal the front
[Music]
Direction number less [Music]
beings all beings to the front may they be free from sorrow and pain and challenges
may they be free they have
ease all the beings to the right side
all beings in the back [Music] Direction all beings in the back
Direction the beam of light of goodness of your heart
shining as if a curtain is being
pulled a curtain that was obstructing this light of
goodness shining to the back this light of Goodwill
into the left Direction the curtain pulled back now
the light shining this light from your heart there's nothing you have to do
it's already there [Music] shining wishing
well may all beings in this direction may
all of them be free from sorrow and
suffering and to the upwards Direction
removing the curtain on top letting it Shine upward
all the beings seen and
unseen and then the bottom Direction lower Direction downwards to the
depths all the [Music] worms underground creatures into the
other side of the earth and
beyond your heart shining in all directions this
light of Goodwill noticing that this light
also Shines on yourself first before shining on all beings everywhere
letting your body relax you are included in this compassion may all beings
everywhere be free from sorrow and pain and
difficulty may they have ease may they have [Music]
goodness
e e
if at any point this practice becomes challenging or overwhelming you
can simply hold yourself in compassion CU you're the one who's
feeling challenged having difficulty and most deserving of
compassion if if it may feel challenging if not you can
continue shining shining your light of Goodwill or letting it Shine letting it
Shine not getting in the way there a friendliness goodwi but we
all have available in US
and noticing how bringing awareness to this good will light of goodness brings
more Comfort Care More
ease to your own heart more gladness
more
safety
e
e e
for the last moment of this ractice holding yourself in kindness
appreciation meta and karuna if this was
challenging also appreciating whatever arose or did not arise you're here you're planting
seeds cultivating your heart in goodness in Connection in
gladness without attachment to outcome
[Music]
thank you all for your
practice would love to invite you if you wish to share any
Reflections questions comments challenges complaints especially if you
haven't shared in a while you can raise your hand um um using the raise hand
function or type in chat if you
wish what did you notice and knowing that by sharing
your wisdom you're supporting supporting the whole SA
with your questions observations if you wish
and Clark please um like I've always
found uh meta or compassion for all beings difficult because I do well with
visualization and so it's sometimes hard to know what to visualize for all beings
my mind's just like I don't know what that is and I also s struggle with comp passion because I tend to want to like
fix the problem or it feels hard to be like here I'm just going to like shine
this light on you not really helping you sorry um but tonight I think what I
really noticed was I was like imagining myself as just this sort of like I don't
know Heart Light flying around and I would like imagine a scene and imagine the Heart Light flying around and like
Illuminating people and they didn't even necessarily know I was there but I felt like care and tenderness for them rather
than when I feel like I have to solve the problem I constrict because I'm like that's a lot of responsibility and I
don't think I can do it um I think I'm sure the framing that you did at the beginning really helped me get there uh
so it was subtle but it was pretty powerful so I was like oh that's the point right like
that's the point is to don't have to make them smile they might not want it at all but yeah so thank you that kind
of finally helped that land for me the compassion for all
beings beautiful Clark I'm yay I'm getting chills as you're describing your
experience and how this subtle shift in the framing really brought it a life for you
and I love you imagining yourself as the the Del light traveling and just with a
sense of concern and warmth for for people's challenges not a sense of it's my respon responsibility that's exactly
it beautiful oh beautiful that's it yay
yay I'm celebrating your the shift and the opening for this practice for you
yay lovely thanks so much for sharing that beautifully shared thank you and Susan
thanks um that made me happy what Clark was sharing and then I after being happy
I be I had sympathetic joy that was cool um but I wanted to
jump on here and say that I had the experience of being really distracted
and having a lot of thoughts and I'm so grateful for the reminders so often that
there's no bad meditation and it you know so I noticed there was a kind of a lack
of beating myself up and then I could just be with the disappointment of not
having had those moments of Liberation that I wanted that was cool great thank you
great thank you Susan I really appreciate what you said about oh not
beating yourself up yay yes distractions
happen and really that U the not beating ourselves up at the end of this period
of practice as a reminder that's the moment that's perhaps I mean all of the
moments of practicing MAA and compassion throughout the whatever 30 minute guid of meditation are just as important but
somehow for me that last moment is more important if you don't beat yourself up
because you were distracted yay now that that's that's really in action because
also what you can take to the all of this you can take so I don't
want to privilege anything or another one though it seems like I am but I really want to celebrate not beating yourself up that is so important like
yeah I did my best these are the causes and conditions that I tried to bring my mind back and I did my best and I was
present for half of it and not and I did my best I planted the seeds and it's
okay um beautiful so thank you for sharing I'm so happy to to hear that
shift which can happen over time oh great
lovely and bill says I was able to generate a loving feeling in short iterations great but it was too easy to
let my attention stray and for the feeling to dissipate fine see above as Susan talked about it bill yeah
so so dear ones Let's uh practicing Community because
now the others who will be in a small GR group with you holding you and you holding them they're part of all beings
they're part you're part of all beings and they're part of all beings so so just as beautifully as as uh Clark
described you're This little light shining and not taking responsibility
but expressing care expressing warmth for them and for yourself so let's let's
work with that image and maybe we'll start with 30 second of silent meta for
each other as you go into group just 30 seconds of Silence just looking at each other with eyes open with meta and
karuna knowing that everybody here has challenges of course we do um and
sharing as much or as little as you wish about your practice after the 30 seconds
so and if you have to go understandable but I hope you stay I hope you stay
because this this part of connecting with others is a really beautiful part
of creating creating connections creating community and heaven knows we
need connections and community at the time of covid so so here we go I'm going to open the
rooms enjoy okay welcome back
everyone and we have a few minutes left if you would like to
share any reflection ctions from your group practice or uh from the first part
of practice um yeah I would love to
hear love for you to share your wisdom your observations as they support others
especially if you usually don't share
Holly hi um just after that group chat it's making me think that life doesn't
stop for the meditation um you know like things have momentum or want to come up or want to
be heard or something and then we just sit and we just have a go at the meditation in the middle of what's
Happening yeah yeah do you want to say more they have something specific I I
find it helpful because it's like whatever is happening well the happy
hour in particular like helps bring an atmosphere of kindness around it and and
and then that like Love Can can seep
in and then I can hold the experiences more lightly and with more um compassion
and yeah and get a bit of distance from it maybe like it's not
so like coming from inside and um like dominating my whole experience but
it's my experience is like wider and it's one thing that's happening yeah it saves through yeah I I appreciate what
you're saying and and Emily is agreeing with you in chat and she say especially
being at home so yeah so there's something about you're you're doing you know you're at home you're doing your
thing oh happy hour okay you you you practice it infuses your heart your life
and your mind might kind of get uh think about that issue or problem during meditation which is fine you're like oh
maybe your P it the heart brings a perspective of kindness towards yourself
and towards the human beings in your life that perhaps you're entangled with whatever is happening then you know you
come back to the medit guided meditation and then when you leave um The Happy are
is like oh there might be a slightly different perspective it has se through your life yes that's what I'm hearing
yeah lovely what what a beautiful perspective to bring in and to acknowledge to see I
completely agree that's lovely that can be the advertisement for for happy
hours let the kindness see through your life that's love brilliant thank you
Holly my pleasure and Jerry says it was helpful in the group chat to hear how
active listening to others is in itself a way of reducing suffering thanks oh
beautiful yeah thank you for raising that anything else you want to add to that
cherry oh let me ask hold on I need to there now try
it okay so um I was uh I was thinking I
had commented in the group I'll speak to myself but how I was wondering how when people die I know you
had mentioned but when people die that acceptance of it is natural but still
people are suffering and I guess I was questioning how am I helping reducing
suffering when someone is dying and grieving profusely so I was relieved
when I heard the comment of the group about well that actually just by
listening active listening could be a form of reducing suffering and I yeah
because I was feeling some pain that I wasn't doing enough so yeah yeah I I
appreciate you raising that and and I want to highlight it some more as you've highlighted and your your group has
wisely highlighted that the act of just listening just listening can be so
healing um we underestimate how healing and supportive that can be um not
jumping in in fact trying to jump in to fix or give advice can be painful
earlier today I was with with someone dear to me who's going through a really
difficult time and I just sat and listened just touched her knee and just
listened and just listened you know I said M aha yes I agreed but just it
wasn't my role to give advice do this you know it just listened just listen
and that seemed I could feel the nervous system their nervous kind of relax and mind
relaxed it just kind of ah just listening so thanks for raising that
Jerry so dear ones we have come to the end of another happy hour together I
want to thank you all for your practice you do this practice not just for
yourself but for all beings whose lives you touch directly and indirectly may all beings
be happy may all beings be free including [Music]
ourselves thank you all