so
welcome everyone
i feel delighted sitting here and being able to be in this kind of way
with you all and seeing the greetings certainly is a
happiness producing uh beginning of our time together and um
and also delighted to be able to share a practice with you and teachings with you that have been so
meaningful for me and and bring me brought me much happiness and and satisfaction
so thank you
one of the one of the things that brings much
benefit and even a joy in this mindfulness practice is
beginning to value how much we have better things to do
with our life than just letting our mind wander off in its usual habits
now some of you might have very wholesome and beneficial and habits of mind and
you all you ever think about is how to do wonderfully virtuous and
activities and things and for the world and you just your uh
your whole very thought strain my thought streams and mind streams and
heart streams are simply a paradigm of
joy and happiness and benefit for the whole world or maybe even part of it is that
frequently but i think it's a little bit
embarrassing to say it mildly for some for many people when they begin meditating
to discover what their mind is up to and uh and how often the mind stream is
actually not that beneficial and even if it's just neutral it's not really
nourishing and enhancing our life and and to learn slowly through
mindfulness that maybe we in fact do have better things to do
than the usual habits of mind and what the directions were going
and now one of those things is to be present here for direct experience
to really be attuned to be aligned to what is actually happening in the
flow of present moment experience and um and to have that be clear
a clear recognition a clear up this is what's going on where the clarity of knowing the clarity
of mindfulness or the the the groundedness of the attention
is the alternative to just letting the mind stream flow and and do go along the regular
highways and byways of its habits and and um
and uh not in opposition to what the habits of the mind are
but rather um you know a uh just an alternative
resting place an alternative place to where we feel grounded this is where life our life flows from
doesn't flow from the habits and of the mind unwholesome tendencies of the mind but
it flows from a place that's deeper or fuller or an alternative
and one of those things is to clearly be aware to clearly be present to know what's
happening in the present moment as it's happening and it's not so much as a you know
a a full throttle doing like okay now i have to really get
busy but it's a kind of a knowing and clear comprehension that we learn that is um
alternative to the stressful ways in which the mind operates that it is kind of brings with it a kind
of clarity and a calmness and a and a spaciousness that becomes more and more
a place of in comparison to the usual flow of
mind for many of us a place of rest but as that place of rest becomes fuller
to say its rest is not really accurate anymore it becomes neither restful nor
stressful it's neither it feels really not so much like a doing but not so much
like a letting go of doing or a non-doing either
it's life this the wonderful flow of present moment life that we're here for and
experiencing in a way that uh feels valuable
that feels purposeful that feels nourishing that feels
clear and and and so just a valuable way of being
and a better alternative than the usual flow of everyday thoughts and ideas and
preoccupations that some of us might have
um and um so here we are
to sit and um
and um maybe begin to appreciate more than we
have each time we've sit down to appreciate this wonderful possibility of being
present and mindful so we begin with our body
and the body's posture and to be clearly comprehen
comprehending the posture you're in some people
meditate sitting in a cross-legged sitting posture some in a chair
some on a bench some people meditate standing
some people meditate walking in the ancient tradition of
walking meditation and some people practice this mindfulness lying down
each posture is called sometimes a dignified posture
so is there some way in whatever posture you're in that you can maybe make some slight
adjustments either physically or maybe mentally from the inside out
that you are sitting here with a kind of dignity
a kind of sense of personal
respect and value a worthiness
and maybe it's being a little bit
more upright than usual or a little bit more open chested than normal
and gently closing your eyes
and then with clear comprehension as if you really know what you're doing
and appreciate what you're doing and there to kind of feel do it and feel it
as if it's nourishing for you nurturing for you
to gently take actively take a few long
slow deep breaths
taking your time to really savor or recognize
this is a deep in breath
and this is an extended exhale
and there might be other thoughts and concerns that you have that keep pulling you away
but maybe there can be a recognition that some of the things you're preoccupied with
maybe is not really to the point right now or even so useful
and they may be a good alternative is to establish this intimate
connection here with yourself with your body
with your lived experience
and then consciously
as another activity to be mindful of let your breathing slowly return
to a normal breath a normal way of breathing
without too concerned with what normal really means just whatsoever seems something that's
easier and at ease with breathing and then
again with a sense of a little bit little bit gentle sense of
purpose and clarity of what you're doing and
and to do it maybe in a way that just feels calming or nourishing
as you exhale relax soften the muscles of your face
relax and soften
around the eyes the temple
the forehead
and just gently softly
but consciously do the same for your shoulders
as you exhale relax your shoulders
and even if you can't relax them a softening around them
and if you can't soften them maybe it's simply an appreciation
of having shoulders being with them
and a softening of your belly
relaxing and if they are already bellies already relaxed
or if it can't relax maybe just appreciating the opportunity
to clearly feel and sense this belly of
ours
and then being aware of belly in a way that is gentle and
generous or appreciative of the opportunity to be present
mindful of something that's an important part of who you are
your belly and in being mindful this way maybe
that's a good alternative to the habits of mine you usually are in
and then in a relaxed calm way with a little gentle sense of purpose
appreciation to just settle in
to experience the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out
breathing in and breathing out
clearly calmly knowing this is an inhale
this is an exhale
where the mindfulness the awareness the knowing
maybe you can feel it as a healthy alternative
to the thought streams you might get pulled into
that is gentle relaxed but dedicated awareness to breathing
allows a settling a calming intimacy
then maybe being involved in your thought streams
doesn't provide
trusting the experience of breathing
and when you're exhaling when it feels useful
quiet the thinking mind
so there's more room to experience breathing more
might it be that mindfulness of breathing is the better alternative
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to turn your attention now outward to consider and think about
the people in your life whatever comes to mind
whoever comes to mind as you do so
people you know people you don't know people who are challenging people who are
that you care for
people who are close by people far away
and then consciously purposefully in a way that
feels nourishing or supportive for you and
see if you can have thoughts of goodwill for them
well-wishing
that may be a better alternative to some of the ways in which you might think about other people
or think about the mind involved in the mind stream of thoughts about others
perhaps you can have some gentle relaxed thoughts of how wonderful would be if others were
happy peaceful safe
and may it be that
this practice that we do today extends itself out into the world that we live a
relaxed but purposeful life
and purposeful and nourishing life where we benefit self and others
we contribute to a better world for ourselves and others may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe and peaceful may all beings be free
and we come may we come to the time we can really share such a world together happy
safe peaceful and free
[Music]
thank you all
so i continue today with some of the teachings from the
foundational mindfulness teachings of the buddha from the discourse and the four foundations of mindfulness
it begins with a very strong emphasis on mindfulness of the body and we know that from other teachings of
the buddha that it seems pretty foundational to him the practice of being connected and
aware of the body and in fact
there are strong statements he makes about there is no experience of awakening without
mindfulness of the body
so this like to read the next exercise that in this
discourse on mindfulness of the body and it goes like this and approximately
like this i paraphrase lightly um
instead of monastics like i'll translate render it as practitioners
a practitioner is one who acts in clear comprehension when
moving forward going forward and returning
who acts with clear comprehension when looking ahead and looking
away who acts with clear comprehension
when flexing and extending one's limbs who acts in clear comprehension
when we're in close and carrying one's outer robe and bowl
carrying one's plates and dishes and whatever one needs
who acts in clear comprehension when eating drinking
consuming food and tasting who acts in clear comprehension when
defecating and urinating who acts in full in clear comprehension when walking
standing sitting falling asleep waking up talking and keeping silent
so here there's many of the ordinary activities of daily life looking looking one way or the other
there is uh walking sitting there is moving our limbs and legs and
feet lifting and stretching and whatever way what they're doing with our
arms we clearly comprehend what we're doing like i'm lifting my hand now to make the point
and clearly comprehending that my hand goes up and i'm making my point
with an italian gesture that i learned growing up in italy the fingers coming together
and the and when going to the bathroom and
clearly comprehends one is present and there for it and this uh clear comprehension is a
very important term it means it's uh the word is some pagana
uh some people translate in different ways but i like clear comprehension that the
the root of the verb is to know or comprehend and and there's a kind of
emphatic prefix to really know so i like the word clear the clear
comprehension and rather than clear knowing because knowing
maybe implies little bit something more simple whereas comprehension is richer in
meaning and in fact the commentaries uh suggest that uh clear comprehend clear this clear
comprehension means to um clearly understand the purpose
of why what you're doing something so it's a purposeful life to clearly comprehend
the suitability of what we're doing the appropriateness the timeliness of what we're doing that we're
living a purposeful in life that is suitable for the circumstances
so we're living appropriately this kind of appropriate response to the situations but doing it with some sense
of purpose not casually not barreling ahead and habits of mind but having a sense of
what is valuable to do where and how to do it that it also means to be um to
understand the pasture of what we're doing the pasture means where we get our nourishment where we
get our nourishment from as we are present for things and that's explained
being present with mindfulness in our direct experience of body feelings mind and dharmas the four
foundations of mindfulness and there's so many different places our
minds can be and we know the mind stream that we live in can be
often take us away in distractions and fantasy get us swept up in irritation
complaining criticalness fear anxiety ruminations of all kinds think lost in
the past planning and anticipating the future and some of that mindstream is wonderful
and appropriate to do and part of the pleasure of life but oftentimes it can be not really so
nourishing and supportive for us and so to live a purposeful life a life that's
appropriate for the circumstance and one that we feel like this is beneficial this is nourishing
supportive for me and for others to be present and clearly aware of what we're doing as
we're doing it is beneficial for the world because when we don't have that clear comprehension
that's when the old habits some of the unhealthy motivations and purposes we have
can can uh be um um you know take over and sometimes we
say what we regret we do if we later feel sorry we did um and we feel maybe we act in ways that
are stressful through the day and we get tired and exhausted in the day by the stress of what we're doing
so what's i think wonderful about this instructions on clear comprehension
effect sometimes called clear comprehension of activities all the simple ordinary activities for their
daily life that all of us are doing all the time
is to um is that it takes the mindfulness
practice of the cushion of meditation it's not only about meditating
uh there's a there's a non-separation there's a holistic quality to how
mindfulness is practiced that it's really involves our whole life all the activities that we do
and uh and then it's in all the activities of life and in meditation that there's the
growth and growing of mindfulness growing or practice and over time we learn more and more how
this practice can be nourishing and supportive moment by moment the way that being mindful being aware
just feels better than the alternative of the mind streams getting involved in
reactivity and that it feels healthy and
satisfying to be way of being here and present and in order to have that satisfaction
it really helps that we know how to be grounded in the body
and so the awareness can flow through the body and be aware in a way that's not colored
influenced by the stressful way of thinking the the unhelpful ways of thinking and the
unhelpful attitudes we have we learn healthy attitudes we learn supportive ways
of thinking and being in the world not in a way that's denying everything and
putting up blinders but actually it's the opposite it's the ability to be present
with an open way to it all the more we can ground ourselves in the clear comprehension
the more we really appreciate the opportunity to be aware of all the different things
that are going on including what's difficult including what's difficult about ourselves
including what's challenging in the world and we do it grounded and settled and open in a clear
way and so this is a training a practice to do this
and so for some of us as we learn begin learning this and meditation and then the great thing is to be able
to take what we're learning here and begin applying it in the
ordinariness of our daily life and having these ordinary activities of
daily life not be done unconsciously or an automatic pilot but be the training ground the supportive
ground for living a spiritual life to use language maybe that i don't use a
lot but to do it maybe in the wonderful in a way that's
evocative or captivating for you or gets your attention to live a life that's um in all the
little details of everyday life is sacred and so
to see to experience to the sacred
in going forward and returning
participating in a sacred way with looking ahead and looking away to experience the
sacred in bending and extending one's limbs
to really feel the sacrament of putting on clothes wearing them
carrying things that we carry with our hands to feel the sacredness of
the attention the presence the engagement in eating drinking
tasting to discover the sacredness of all the different aspects of our life as
we live it that moves through us this way in which the lifestream for evolutionary times
come down through us and created all the different ways that we have to be we have to live in order
to sustain our life including defecating and urinating
and to feel the sacredness the specialist the nourishment of walking standing sitting falling asleep
waking up talking and keeping silent all of them
all these ordinary activities that all of us are involved in every day
much of the day that here is where we discover this valuable
stream of life activity that is maybe better
than some of the alternatives of the mental mindstreams streams of attitudes and and
preoccupations that is so too so easy to fall into
may you really discover and value your ordinary activities as a place to
cultivate a sacred life of freedom generosity and love and
nourishment so maybe for this next 24 hours that
you can now maybe explore um how bringing attention to
all the little activities of life the little and big activities of what you're doing
how that can be nourishing for you and appropriate for you and how to do them with a sense of purpose and appropriateness
and and may you be delighted by the opportunity to do this so
thank you all very much