so good day warm greetings to the meditation session we'll do now
and i'm quite actually quite happy to be sitting here and sharing this time with you
and as an introduction to this sitting one of the really key parts of
mindfulness of breathing is not the breath but rather is
the mindfulness that we bring to it i like to think of mindfulness of
breathing as being the meeting place of the body breathing and the
awareness that experience it that knows it and so the mindfulness the awareness how
we bring our attention to the breathing is a essential component part of this
practice and sometimes it's a good idea to spend a little bit of time
studying investigating just the nature of the how we are mindful
how we are aware and one interesting place is when the
mind wanders often thought and when we notice that how are we with
that are we critical are we upset discouraged or might it be possible to be
rather matter of fact about it without any real emotional reaction at all just oh
mind is wandered off that's what's happening and then to
begin again with the breathing where the beginning again the returning to the breath is a
pleasant event that
rather than jerking the mind back hurrying back getting back to scourge in a discouraged
way there's something about returning welcoming back the breath
or starting again with the breath or if you bring you bring your back your mind back to the breath
that that movement is is harmonious it's gentle it's useful has a feeling of calm
maybe even a feeling of pleasure so that maybe in a way you begin looking
forward to the opportunity to start over again to begin again
here and then how we are with the breathing
and i think of it as having both having a light touch
but also a touch that's committed apparently the latin roots for the word
commit comes from the same root as the word mitten it has to do with touching
touching with something but to touch it so being committed but being light
the light touch but a light touch that's continuous right there stay there
stay there the uh
sometimes the analogy has been used of picking up a bird that's been stunned
maybe come in the house and you have to take it outside and you want to hold it in such a way
that no way do you hurt it but you also hold it clearly you hold it
kind of not a firm is the right word but you really keep it in your two palms of your
hand so you stay connected to it and then once you're outside you let it go
so this commitment to the bird that's tender and soft commitment to the breath where we're
seeing if we can stay there continuously but with a light touch
so the mind begins to be light and soft and calm as well
and of course the mind will wander away and then to experiment with finding a
way to begin again that's enjoyable that is
harmonious with the process of meditation and when the mind you notice the mind is
wander off notice that in a way that's harmonious with the meditation so it's all about
the how how are relating to what we are knowing and now that's
really one of the key aspects of this practice so with that taking uh
assuming your meditation posture
and before we begin with the further
perhaps you can take a few moments with your mind to see if you can
find a way of knowing being aware mindful that has some
feeling of ease to it not in a hurry but also not held back
and then with that mindfulness take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe three quarters full so you don't get winded or strained
and an exhale that in a relaxed way
is longer than usual
breathing in in a gentle long exhale
without going so long it's a strain
breathing in and exhaling
and then letting the breath return to normal
and take a few moments on the inhale to feel
the muscles of your shoulders
and on the exhale to relax the shoulders
on the inhale to feel down your arms and your elbows
hands and on the exhale to relax the arms hands
soften
as you breathe in feeling any tensions or holding in the
chest
in the exhale to relax the chest
breathing in and feeling your belly
on the exhale relaxing the belly
breathing in and feeling your legs knees and feet
and exhaling softening relaxing
on the inhale feeling the muscles of your face
and on the exhale relaxing
and on the inhale maybe feeling the energy or the pressure tension
associated with thinking and on the exhale relax
the thinking mind
and then as if you have all the time in the world
but without delaying
center your attention on the body breathing
wherever the breathing is most clear for you pronounced or most enjoyable
the belly the chest or the nostrils
or some people prefer to experience the whole breath body
the global experience of breathing
and as a little experiment
let go of the focus on breathing maybe think about something
and then see if you can come back to being with your breathing in a way that feels where the how you do
it is pleasant or relaxed or
harmonious with a peaceful meditation
and then as you're with your breathing how are you with it how are you relating
to this to your awareness
are you straining are you uncommitted
can you be committed to your breathing in a soft way
but committed where awareness of breathing is
welcoming receptive
maybe as if you and your breathing are walking
together hand in hand friends walking in a park
holding each other's hands lightly gently lovingly so awareness
is together with your breathing
and if your mind wanders off
tend carefully with how you begin again
with your breathing how you return to be accompanying your
breath hand in hand
receptive to breathing in and breathing out
when you find yourself lost in thought experiment with beginning again with
breathing so that beginning again
is enjoyable or a pleasant thing to do
what would it take to land back on your breathing
to receive the breathing again
so that you enjoy doing it
so
as we continue meditating can you allow the experience of
breathing to come in more fully
to awareness
as we let go of thinking there could be more room to experience
the fullness of a single breath
as inhale fills the body with air
so it fills awareness
mindfulness of breathing is the meeting place
of the body breathing and the knowing of it
and how that meeting happens
is central to this practice
to have the meeting be clear definitive
as complete as possible and peaceful calm
light soft
allowing things to become quiet quiet in the mind quiet in the body
in a tender contact between awareness and the body breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to carefully allow whatever calm or subtleness you
might have or allow whatever
challenge you might have and how that is touches you or touches
your heart
and open up that sensitivity to the world around you
bring into your awareness the people of your life
your neighbors people in your town or province
people you know and don't know
imagine that they're all held
in your expansive tenderness openness
and how we are in relation to other people is at the heart of
refuge in sangha how we are
and without any obligation without any one even knowing
can you find within you the well-wishing for others
the idea that it would be wonderful if others were happy and peaceful
and that you wish it for them
and is if you're a lighthouse shining the light of
well-wishing across the earth sit here for a few moments
spreading the light of your good will into the world
a good will that may be is can be expressed in these words
may all beings be happy
may all beings
be safe
be peaceful may all beings be
free and may it be that in even the smallest
ways or in big ways we contribute to that possibility
[Music]
so for those of you who came to the
meditation just now thank you for those of you who came at
the 15 minutes earlier and had this longer sitting and thank you for those of you who might have joined
at the regular time or anytime it's always what you're welcome to come and
what's wonderful about this electronic medium for meditation
together is that it's uh everyone enters the meditation room and
in a sense quietly so
so some of you will find i see that the idea that the 15 minutes extra meditation is a lot
longer and certainly if you're used to one
length of time it takes a while to kind of get used to the the longer period
and once after a while it becomes normal the longer period it can seem to go quite quickly and and
anything shorter it feels like we're not quite you know finished maybe so it's well worth
doing the stretch so hopefully this week is is um nice for you and if it's not nice
i hope that it's educational you learn something about yourself that you wouldn't have learned otherwise
so you know in the overall series on this
mindfulness of breathing we're halfway through the 16 steps
but we're kind of taking this week to a kind of review or just kind of begin
over again in a certain way and beginning and over again is not
really starting over completely but meditation it's often useful to
think we're always beginning over that often you know our lives are ups
and downs we've been active in our life and we sit down to meditate and we don't sell them we just drop into
you know the depths of where we were before but rather it's always kind of a beginning over
and now learning how to be a beginner learning how to engage in it in a in a way that is harmonious with
meditation or supports the enjoyable settling in
is part of this art and not to be in a hurry not to be striving but to be diligent
and to be you know wholehearted and showing up in a way that ah this is really good to be here
and in the instructions the buddha gives the preparation for
the first step is the is the instruction to establish mindfulness
and this idea of establishing awareness i i like the expression awareness
establishing attention here i've asked a number of people how they
understand this idea of establishing awareness and many people respond that it for them
it means to allow for it to enable it awareness or attention is a kind of a
capacity that in all our conscious moments is operating and to establish it is to open up more
fully to what's already here and and maybe to center oneself in that
awareness to be rooted in here
some scholars have said that the pali word for establish could also mean to stand next to or
stand close to um it's to uh to really accompany something
and now this idea of having awareness uh established like it's like it's really
rooted here in the present moment and to do that a fair amount of what we
have to do is to let go we have to let go of the ways that thinking
preoccupier so much that we don't even know we're aware we get pulled into its drama as its
stories its concerns and there's something about letting go
enough of the storylines the thoughts the ideas the preoccupations
so that we're clearly cognizant that i'm here in the present moment
and something as simple as i'm here in this body i'm here in this place
begins to establish and um and so the question is uh
you know more fully for you what does it mean for you to establish yourself here in awareness
and attention and how do you do that establishment that that you're finding a place that's
wholesome finding a place that's a healthy or helpful or even
healing a way of being really being here in the midst of what's going on it might be that there's a lot
of emotional turmoil or difficulty in physical pain there might be challenges that go on
there might be challenges around you in the environment but if it's appropriate to be meditating
what does it mean to establish yourself peacefully or another way of saying
which i like quite a bit for myself is the idea of becoming sitting and practicing without
being in conflict with anything and what does it mean to sit here
without conflict and so then you know we're kind of looking around and seeing where is their
conflict where am i caught up in responsibilities or desires or
resentments and what are these and not to necessarily to make them go
away or to let go of them if it's not easy to do so but what is it like to be sitting in the middle of it
established and so this image of sitting in the middle
and just being present for the experience i think i've said this recently my son
when he was um he went into kindergarten and he was kind of young for the kind of in the
younger end of i forget exactly what he was but i think he was still four or something
and four and a half maybe and um and he went to kindergarten and and
the first month or two he would find a small little kids chair and place it right in the middle where
all the kids were playing in the classroom and he would just sit there and watch
everything that was going on and it was only after a couple of months they left his chair and started interacting and playing with the kids
and no one ever felt that he was troubled or upset or afraid he was just that's what he did he just
sat right there confidently in the middle and just took it all in and this whole new environment
and so he established himself in the room of you know probably chaos kids kindergarten kids
playing and running around and so to establish oneself
to root oneself here to i know some teachers who have
emphasized that simply having your two feet rooted you know firmly on the ground
or in the cushion meditating your butt firmly on the seat that's you know that's really where the
heart of it is really here established here i had one one teacher who
gave this wonderful teaching and he said that a successful period of meditation
sometimes he said sometimes because it could be so wild and so maybe agitating or
what's going on within as we meditate that a definition of a successful period of meditation
is that we did not leave our seat and he said sometimes like the rodeo but you
stay in your seat stay on the saddle and and the reason he called it a success is
that we don't give in to it we don't give up because of it
and sometimes just simply hanging in there and staying it doesn't look like it's a wonderful
meditative experience but it takes a uh we're cultivating a lot of strength a lot of stability
and the ability to to keep our seat to hold our ground here i'm staying here
and and so what's the nature of how we establish
awareness what's the nature of the way that we practice awareness practice attention
and this took me a long time to understand for myself because i had a lot of agendas sometimes
when i was practicing like sometimes i had the agenda to get concentrated and i was pushing and
straining and trying my best and judging myself and and comparing myself to the when i was
meditating in the room with other people kind of part of me was comparing myself with others those you know and trying to catch up or
be as concentrated as them or be as mindful as them or so or as still as them or something and all
this swirl of comparative mind swirl of needing to accomplish something needing to prove myself
and then there was a the attitudes of not liking what i saw in myself and being upset with this and that
that happened and the mindfulness then had a sting to it that it wasn't just being mindful of
something but there was little barbs like i was like poking at myself or criticizing myself
kind of together with being mindful and slowly to learn to simplify and
simplify and simplify the awareness all this extra stuff that we bring along
so much so that some people can would say that the whole process of meditation like the whole process of the 16 steps
of anapanasati is a process of simplifying awareness so it becomes comes into its pristine
purity or its pristine simplicity just aware
to see clearly without the seeing having any filters without the seeing
having any obstructions to it and just to see just to see
and to trust that that's enough is supported with the idea that the actions how we take care of
things that will come later first we're learning this ability to
see in this clear simple way and that allows us to see better what
can be done and what should be said or can be said there's more wisdom that way
so finally this is a quest for simple awareness tranquil awareness that
is committed and established and just stays here with the experience um maybe it's inspiring for you to
remember the little saying that if you want wisdom the wisdom of how to live in this world
become tranquil have your awareness established
in its simplicity and learn how to be content with that that's enough that in them for now it's
just enough to sit here and be present later can come the action the response
so establishing awareness so thank you very much and
let's all of us continue with our awareness practice thank you