okay so why don't we go ahead and get started welcome
to the monday evening sid and dharma talk with the insight meditation center i'm
kim allen and i'm delighted to be here with you this evening
so why don't we go ahead and get started with the sit so finding a posture that's
upright also relaxed
sitting in position sitting posture so you can feel your seat against the
chair or the cushion or the bench and your legs or your feet against the
floor so there's a sense of the stable foundation
on which you're resting really feeling the stability of where
you're sitting and if you're comfortable doing so you
can close your eyes just gently allowing the eyes to close
so that the attention comes inward you're feeling the body from the inside
perhaps on the next out breath softening any
obvious areas of tension you can also shift your body back and forth a little
bit or forward and back to find
a central point where you feel like you're balanced
on the place where you're sitting so there's not very much effort to hold
yourself vertical if you're sitting vertically
and then it can be helpful at the beginning of a sit to just consciously
go through the body and inviting ease and softening
what can be softened especially at the end of the day when we may be carrying some tensions
from our activities of the day from what we needed to do to to get
here to the sit so softening the muscles of the face
the forehead around the eyes the jaw
just letting the expression on the face be soft and easeful
softening the eyes and the eye sockets they tend to get a little tight when
we've been looking at the computer screen
even releasing any tension from inside the head
maybe right behind the eyes from focusing the mind thinking
just allowing that to release if it will just inviting that
down the neck into the shoulder area
softening the shoulder joints letting the shoulders naturally drop
so the shoulder blades slide down the
back
relaxing down the arms and hands
and down into the chest area the heart lungs front back
sides of the ribcage
releasing the diaphragm [Music]
and all down through the belly area just letting go of any obvious tension
there
and i like to simultaneously invite some ease in the muscles of the low back
so that it's if what's on both sides of the spine is falling away to the front and to the
back
down into the hip joints softening a little further into the seat
and down into the legs releasing any bracing
softening the knee joints ankle joints all the way to the feet
so we've invited ease throughout the whole body i'm just returning attention to the
sense of sitting the whole body
sitting
and orienting our mind toward meditation [Music]
intending to stay present
not with the idea that it will be 100 mindfulness
or just carrying the interest the intention of being with our experience
allowing the mind to gently rest on the sensations of breathing
it may be that we've done breath meditation a lot or
feel like we must by now know everything about our breath
but i'd like to encourage a sense of freshness newness
every breath is unique what would it be like to sit with the
breath and not know already what the breath is like
bringing some curiosity and openness
as we settle in further it can be helpful to notice
something about how the mind is now
is it generally a little dull tired
the end of the day or is a bit restless and agitated
is there a dominant mood or emotion going on in the mind or the heart right
now just to know what that is
i'm bringing that same sense of freshness
to our mind and heart we may have felt tired many times
or we may have felt sadness
or even joy many times but what about this time
i'm going to sing again [Music] noticing afresh how the mind is
curious if it might be slightly different than we felt before
now
as you keep sitting if you begin to feel any sense of
ease or peace stillness even just a little bit
it's fine to turn toward that with even some curiosity
what is this stillness like this ease
opening to it gently so as not to disturb it
but that too can be seen [Music] with fresh eyes as if we haven't felt it
before
when we sit with the body and mind in this way with a sense of
seeing what is new or treating it as something open and fresh
there's a remarkable feeling of friendliness that can come a sense that we are
making friends with the body and the mind
more so than if we just treated it as the same old thing
that we've sat and meditated with for a long time
somehow that freshness and openness
creates a kind of intimacy it feels like having a good friend
in the zen tradition it said not knowing is most intimate
so if it feels right you can smile a bit at your friend body and mind as they are
at this moment i'm just resting for a few more minutes
b
and as we come into the last minutes of this sit
perhaps reflecting if there's anything new that you saw in your
that you hadn't really been aware of before just by having this idea of freshness or
newness did you see anything that you hadn't
seen before doesn't have to be major just any little
thing
you