ah hello and welcome again and again warm welcome
to each of us every single one of us so so for this edition of happy hour
like to invite us to to explore this idea of happiness
so with practicing metta with practicing loving kindness
cultivating cultivating good will for ourselves and others
the four traditional phrases are may may you be safe may you feel safe
may you be happy may you be healthy may you have ease may you take care of
yourself happily or may i of course so first one having to do with safety second one with mental happiness
second and the third with physical happiness which is health and the fourth wish having to do with
um ease like our lives flowing with ease taking care of ourselves happy kind of in the
worldly way so so last week we spent some time exploring
um this idea of offering safety this wish of safety may i feel safe may i be safe may
you be safe feel safe etc and weeks we took some time exploring that just landing with that
like what does that mean how what does that open up and um based on your reflections
dear saga it seems to have been a an impactful and helpful exploration
to just i see some nods yes thank you just really stay with this
with the safety explore that that first wish of meta as the basis for everything else and if you're wondering
what that was you can go to audiodharma and it's recorded wednesday and friday
of last week so so now um the invitation is okay
let's consider let's let's hang out a little bit and explore as we cultivate our hearts
and goodness and good will this wish of
this wish for happiness may i be happy may you be happy
may may i have a heart full of joy may you have a heart full of joy
so so happiness for on the face value yes it seems pretty
basic this we want to be happy we want others people who we only care
about that can start there people who we care about you know we want them to be happy there's a sense of
reflective joy reflected happiness and and some people might say
the goal of life being is to be happy um some might say that and and in some
ways also um let's consider that
if the goal is just to be happiness in and of itself the goal of life is just to be happy by
any means necessary then it can become really contracted
whereas various studies point out to when we actually are um
there's a sense of engagement purpose kind of being engaged in our lives uh
and many other factors but then a sense of happiness arises so the point i
want to make is that when we wish ourselves happiness when we
wish others happiness here to really bring this nuanced
awareness that it's not a grabby it's not an attached to outcome may i be happy i
still want to be happy i'm so miserable i want to be happy oh that can actually make the heart more
contracted or if we were wishing it for others may you be happy i so want you to be happy
you're dear person to me i want you to be happy i'm going to call you afterwards and see if you're happy now because i've
been wishing you happiness did it work did it for 30 minutes so when it's grabby when it's so there's
tightness there is um such tight attachment to outcome oh the heart
gets squeezed there is not the real happiness gets squashed even though we might be wishing
happiness so considering that this wish for happiness is really an offering it's a gift
it's a gift it's it's an invocation it's just it's it's a lightness now may
you be happy may you be happy it's a gift of generosity it's a gift of goodness
with no strings attached that we offer others and similarly let's see
what it feels when we offer to ourselves with this invocation may i be happy
may this heart of mind contain joy ah and let it be an
aspiration an aspiration it uplifts our heart instead of may i be happy may i be happy i
i i'm wishing myself to be happy right you feel the difference i'm making a bit
of a caricature but it can be true after we do it for a while some contraction could be like oh i'm
doing metta and i'm realizing gosh i'm really miserable doing meta oh well notice how you're doing it
what's the the emotion with which the the relationship to
the way we're doing it it's not just the object but
the relationship the way so well i've said plenty to set the context
and we'll just hang out with this wish for happiness and feel it in our bones bring it up um
etc but yeah let's keep that frame in mind so without further ado
let's start practicing together so ah so
inviting you to get into your meditation posture landing in your body
you could be sitting or lying down [Music] no difference see what your body needs
and whether sitting or lying down let there be a posture a sense of
integrity to your spine for your spine to be straight
ah landing in the body and gently
if it's comfortable for you closing the eyes turning your gaze inward
resting resting landing
spend the first part of the practice
just arriving connecting with the breath in the body to settle the mind
to arrive bringing awareness
to your lower abdomen
letting the breath be received in the lower abdomen
received on its own one birth at a time
you don't have to pick up breathing as a chore or a task
it's been happening all this time just let it unfold simply
receive let awareness as if awareness is a butterfly resting
resting and your abdomen
rising and falling with the breath
the natural wave
this is the wave of the ocean rising and falling
and with each out breath
ah let go let go some more
ah let the body soften
all the muscles in the face nick and shoulders
arms hands chest
abdomen sit bones
legs offering their weight to the earth
when the thoughts arise as they will and it's okay
gently smilingly whisper to them in your mind thank you
but not now i'm giving my heart my whole body
my mind this practice
in this moment taking refuge as to taking a mini vacation
please come back later thank you
not now not now
hanging out intimately lovingly with the breath
and the body for a few more minutes
not now not now
here here
the breath receives nourishing the whole
body
appreciation for this moment of just sitting
or lying down and breathing the simplicity of it the refuge
now as we continue
to receive the breath in the body
the abdomen the lower body sense of embodiment
here here connected
to the earth
conjuring up bringing
to our embodied mind filled sense of
the image of someone who's dear to us we have a simple
relationship with them ideally
until we care for and we want them to be happy
ideally someone who's alive
for this particular practice choose someone who's alive right now
someone whose presence do you feel safe
there's a sense of ease
maybe when you consider this person or this being could be a pet
or a child maybe a smile shows up on your face
you wish them well
there is a natural good will natural sense of connection with this
being bring them to mind as clearly as
possible hearing their voice or sound if you're
auditory you're visual seeing them in action
moving as if they're in front of you
noticing what comes up in your heart just a simple wish for well-being
happiness
for this being
for the purpose of this practice as we explore
maybe imagine them with a sense of happiness and so well-being
like they are fully inhabiting their body
their goodness they're shining they're shining the sense of happiness
perhaps
contentment
just imagining so we feel into it
knowing that there also might be areas of this dear person's life which right now are
challenging because all of our lives they're all aspects we all have aspects
that are challenging it's part of the human condition
so as we wish them happiness it's not that we're trying to
push away make those challenges go away we acknowledge
their challenges and yet from the goodness of our heart we offer
this wish without any strings attached
whatever the condition is right now for them some happiness a moment ago we imagined them happy just
to feel into it and now letting them be in their natural
condition and sharing this wish as a gift
from our heart may you be happy may you be happy dear when i wish you
happiness acknowledging fully well knowing that
there are challenges in your life in everyone's life
and i share wholeheartedly without attachment
without clinging i give you this gift of my good will
my love for you my care for you may you be happy
i wish you happiness may your heart have joy may it beam
i wish that for you
may you be happy dear
continuing to connect with their felt sense with their image
and your heart's connection to them
notice your connection to this being your good will for this being
may you be happy
may you be joyful
may your heart beam with gladness i wish that for you dear one
and notice when you connect
when there's engagement of your heart with wishing
another well another being happy to be happy
how there is reflected happiness in your own heart showing up notice if you
feel a little more glad more happy
through offering this generous wish of happiness to another
notice if it's the case
offering the gift of happiness this wish makes us happier disengagement indirectly
and now imagining this dear being
with their goodwill for you they wish you happiness they have goodwill for you
they offer it as a free gift generosity of heart and let yourself receive the
gift
even if you may think you don't deserve it
your mind is getting in your way receive the gift
the kindest response to generosity is to receive it fully
not deflect
imagining this dear being saying the phrase of mentor for you may you be safe
may you be happy may you be joyful
let yourself receive it
receiving this blessing
this gift in your whole body
dropped in not to your head but your whole body receiving the gift
may you be happy may you be joyful
may your heart beam with gladness
whatever the conditions of my life in this moment i receive this wish
and notice how sometimes if we're a bell these wishes
and strike the bell the right resonance ah something might awaken
sense of appreciation gladness our heart
receiving the generosity might feel glad
from a person from a being who cares about us
[Music]
and now adding your own voice to those of the dear being wishing
yourself happiness may i be happy
may i have joy in my heart not in the clingy grabby way but just
wishing yourself goodness with generosity this being that is you
letting it be an aspiration may i be
happy with all the conditions of my life
all the goodness in my life all the challenges in my life may i be happy
i wish myself happiness not in spite of but together with all of
it it is possible
to have a heart of gladness in the midst of it all
in the midst of it all of course
when did yourself be showered by your dear being and your son
may this being that is me who is me
may they experience joy
for the sake of myself and for the sake of others
service of myself and others
may this being who's made me happy
glad
huh
turning the generosity outward both inward and outward
letting this light this goodness shine
from your heart touching yourself first and then touching others
beaming all over the world
may all beings including myself may all beings be happy
knowing full well and in this moment some beings are happy some beings aren't
and yet offering this wish generously
generously made all beings everywhere i wish for every being to be happy
generosity of my heart may all beings everywhere
have gladness not keeping it for myself or just my
loved ones but generously wishing it for everyone
as if you're sharing these flower petals streaming them
throwing them blessings all over the world the globe
notice if your own heart feels more full more glad
sharing sharing goodness wishing it for others
serving others in your mind in your heart and through
that becoming more glad
may all beings everywhere including myself be happy may
all beings everywhere including myself
be free
[Music]
thank you all for your practice
so wishing gladness wishing gladness for others
for those we hold dear for ourselves receiving it from others sharing it with
all beings everywhere so so much to
explore so much to discover in this practice and love to hear your reflections
if you like to type them in chat if you type them to everyone publicly i'll say
your name as i read them if it's just to me it'll be private i can read them but not saying your name
or it could just be just private private invite it to me i won't read it out or you can raise your hand and
unmute yourself and share what did you discover in this practice your relationship to
gladness wishing it for others for yourself did you notice when you were wishing
maybe i'll plant a question ah great now i guess please john
thank you nikki jo let me open my video too hello so one thing i realized was that
as i was pushing happiness for myself and for uh others is that i
realize how my mind is conditioned to think i can be only happy if i have certain
things like if i have health or if i have a partner or if i have a certain body
and then i realize that it is very beautiful this practice you
are not conditioning on anything that's saying just like go directly to the happiness because i'm
sure if we achieve those we find other goals to postpone our happiness
too that was very nice brilliant brilliant thank you so much
for sharing that beautiful insight exactly i'll be happy only when only
when it's so common we are conditioned exactly oh yes i can't be happy and yes
no actually i can be happy with all the conditions of my life because there's always be something joseph goldstein
a a famous teacher in this tradition says if it's not one thing it's another
there's always one thing or another there's always something so just um so this this yes we can be happy
with all the conditions beautiful thank you thank you nerius and linda thanks you too for your thank you
for your insight thank you mark please
i have been taken by a line i read this afternoon
eddie hillson who died at auschwitz at the age of 29 wrote
if you don't understand why you're here that all outer experiences
are like a passing show as nothing beside the great splendor inside us
then things can look very bleak here indeed 29 years old
thank you mark
hmm i am so touched by that thank you for bringing that in so wise
so wise so wise there's so much in that quote to
explore so many teachings it can be a whole one hour-long dharma talk there is so much
there to explore um yeah there's so much to explore in
that it's both the freedom inside you know really the freedom inside the
freedom inside and and this passing show that she talks about is really an
insight into impermanence into emptiness many mystics we've practiced like oh yes
there's there is a world and yet it's a passing show there can be so much freedom inside
in spite of conditions thank you for bringing that in mark thank you so much thank you
and maury christine asks for a copy of that quote if you felt if you're part of the google groups
if you wanted to share it on the groups or in chat that'd be lovely i think
the sangha would appreciate it thank you mark um alanis says exploring how nature can
be a benefactor yes yes absolutely beautiful thanks for bringing that in and um
and one reflection private reflection thoughts of the person i was trying to give meta to already being happy
happy enough kept coming up ah um so was that
it was that supporting your practice or was it becoming a block you're welcome to
unmute yourself if you'd like to reflect or if you want to type in chat you're welcome to but
maybe i'll say something that if if it is if it came up in terms of oh they were
happy enough they don't need my wish oh notice if that's if that's an edge
because we're practicing this generosity as a generosity of our heart
as a generosity of our heart again not attached to the conditions outside and
in fact if they're happy then it could be um
it could become the practice of mudita happiness for another person's happiness so the generosity could be explained that way
got it hindering yes you wrote yes so in that way see if if it can actually can
is the edge of the practice of mudita vicarious joy happy for other people's happiness because that's
where you're ending up with this practice it sounds like yeah and another reflection depression
is frequently my companion practicing receiving someone's wish for my happiness made me believe in it a
little more yay beautiful that's that's very sweet that makes my heart happy
um hearing that how that landed so so dear ones let's turn let's
turn now to practicing in small groups and the invitation
is to um to start with 30 seconds of wishing
happiness for each other and then um share as much or as little as you
like to share about your practicing holding each other with kindness holding each other with with safety
so here's where the rubber meets the road and i'm opening the groups here we go
okay all the rooms are closed and everyone is
back welcome back everyone so we've got a couple of minutes for reflections what
you um noticed when practicing together especially if you haven't spoken yet or
haven't spoken for a while would love to hear your reflections please don't be
shy what did you notice yes ariana please
hello hi i was just sharing at the very end um i was chatting you earlier and had a
difficult time during the meditation but when i came into the room those first 30 seconds of
giving meta to the others in the room that that was just wonderful that was so it
felt just so so easy and so natural whereas the meditation did not as much
for me today unfortunately yay yay that's i
just makes me so happier thank you so much for sharing that because that is so important right both to see that and also whole to
to allow yourself to be beautifully witnessed in this way and for the benefit of others because
both parts are practiced the first part is practice silently and the second part is practicing community and
both parts are just as important and sometimes yes the first one kind of prepares us
it does us in a way we can't quite just like yeah maybe we think it's not working but something is working
and then you go into this community and oh wow it just it's flowing it's it flows with
ease so um i'm just i'm filled with with joy with happiness hearing your
your practice report thanks for sharing that alana that's lovely and
sarah says well said with a heart yes beautiful thank you sarah dear and neil says the
practice was lovely and the conversation was nurturing and intimate oh who could ask for anything more
thanks everyone thank you all for showing up for practicing for
for ourselves for others and for the whole world we don't do this
practice just for ourselves so so may all beings be happy may all
beings be well
[Music]
thanks everyone for showing up and practicing and