hello everyone and nice to be back here with you and uh
i want to begin with a analogy that i've taught before but i
think he makes the point well when my son was in
preschool so he was three and four years old
uh sometimes i'd visit the school wonderful school and the wonderful teachers
and it was fun to watch the kids running around chaotically in
the various rooms of the preschool and and it certainly was chaos and a lot of
joy watching and watching them but also seeing the joy in them
and at some point it was time to change the schedule to change what the kids were doing to get them ready for something
else and one of the teachers would stand in the middle of the
classroom and he would just stand there very still upright and the kids were running around
him and through his feet or all kinds of things they were doing but he was just standing there and then he would begin
to whisper talk very quietly and it was remarkable to watch then all
these little kids begin to kind of slow down
sit down gather around him until after a minute or two
all the kids were sitting quietly and had gathered together around the
teacher and then he would tell a story and they probably knew that this was the deal they recognized it
but this way of getting their attention was it was not you know a command like
you know he didn't uh you know was commanding them just you know shut up and come here and
um there was nothing like that he was just standing attentive in the middle of it all
and being quiet and all the kids gathered around and got quiet themselves
so this is a nice analogy for meditation practice that um
we are in a sense establishing ourselves
with awareness at the middle we're establishing the awareness we have the attention
we're going to use to be here becomes established kind of at the center center of our being center of
here where we're sitting and all the ways that uh all the ways that our thinking
and our feelings and everything gets us scattered spins us outwards the outflow and the scatteredness and
about thinking about the past the future fantasy um the way that feelings keep us activated
and engaged and thinking and story making
because we have a awareness centered and established in the middle it kind of works as a gathering point
things start getting collected it's kind of like there's a little bit of a gravitational force
that uh without any more um
insistence then gravity may be in some ways something that because begins things begin pulling in coming in getting
settled gathered and it's kind of a special thing that
what we have to do is stay aware stay present in the present moment
and then this gathering begins happening it's collecting of ourselves and all the desperate parts the scattered parts
um collect together so we don't have to do so much the work of bringing the mind back
we don't have to do so much work of you know jerking the mind back or
being disappointed in ourselves all we have to do is to come back to being aware be here
and i like the word just here for that just here but here
open and aware of what's here present for what's here and then things begin
you'll probably see that things will slowly begin to come closer and closer and
there's less a tendency to wander off or or get involved in the scatteredness that'll still happen but just come back
to here to hear and perhaps to do that with a
with a quietness within not a forcefulness not a
not a you know in insistence not a
expectation just like the way that a loving kindergarten teacher would stand
there loving the kids being quiet and being present and beginning to tell a story that
gathers them together so um
assuming a posture
that allows you to establish mindfulness
establish awareness
lowering your gaze relaxing your eyes
not looking at anything in particular loose focus
and then gently closing your eyes that's comfortable for you
and taking a few long slow gentle breaths imagining
that as you breathe in it's like you're spreading your arms
wide to gather yourself to gather
all the scattered pieces and as you exhale you you bring it all in close in let it
settle as you relax on the exhale
breathing in deeply
a full embrace of all that you are
and the exhale letting it all relax here back to the
center
and then letting your breathing return to normal and on the exhale
relaxing different parts of your body with the idea that in relaxing
something is gathering settling back into the place of awareness
relaxing the face
on the exhale softening the shoulders and as you soften your shoulders
settling back into a place of awareness
being here
and relaxing your belly maybe almost as if you relax your belly
and it settles and there's a groundedness in here
a rootedness here
and then centering yourself in your breathing
being here not so much reaching out
to the breath to breathing or directing yourself to the breathing
but more being aware being present being available for what's happening
here and now
and more like allowing the breathing to find you
as if the sensations of breathing in your body
are arriving in the awareness that knows your
breathing
and when thoughts override your attention to breathing
re-establish the awareness the knowing
that receives the inhales and the exhales
as if breathing is part of the gathering together
and over time you'll notice that even the mind that begins to think
will feel like it too is known
as if it arrives in awareness and there's no need
to wander off with the thoughts
everything is arriving in awareness supporting
present moment awareness
and as part of welcoming the breathing into awareness
you can say the wording as you breathe in
but maybe with the idea of welcoming it as it arrives
you can say out as you breathe out welcoming the sensations
that come with the exhale
you might think of awareness as a place of rest
where all things gather together
to rest in the embrace of awareness
allow things to arrive in this restful place of attention
knowing
and for the next three or four breaths
see if you can relax more deeply
on the exhale
maybe relaxing something deep in your core
deep inside
that's agitated or
tense activated
deep relaxation
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
there is a wonderful reversal that can happen with
awareness that if you
do not direct your attention outward
if you don't direct your actively your concerns to outward into the world
but you allow yourself to be receptive so the world arrives in awareness
it's kind of like you're settling back and just available for things to be known
and when you do that with others and we're not distracted or preoccupied
with doing and directing and making and fixing and
protecting but deeply relaxed receptive available
to receive the experience of others
that makes room that allows for a deeper experience of
love of care
friendliness good will
the more we are receptive to the world
the more room it allows for these positive feelings for the world
and so at the end of this sitting to
allow the world to come back to you
of your community your friends your family colleagues neighbors
people in your neighborhood and out across the lands where you live
and to receive them to know them to be reminded of them with no obligation
nothing you have to do except to allow your heart to receive
their presence
and perhaps with a relaxed heart the heart then responds
with warmth tenderness care
and orientation of being friendly
and to give voice to this warm feeling of care friendliness
you can allow your heart to in a sense to say these words
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may you your heart from your heart from your inner life
may their flow naturally easily
and inspiration to contribute to the welfare and happiness of all
beings may this generosity
spread out from us out into the world may all beings be happy
[Music]
so hello everyone and um here we are on monday
and for this week's uh theme and for the next actually maybe four or five weeks i
would like to uh go progressively through the basic instructions that
we give here at imc for a mindfulness meditation week normally we'll do a five-week
introduction to meditation course some of you have probably done it with us
and it's available the course on audiodharma and
the and it follows a sequence where it's five five weeks one evening a
week the first week we talk about just introduction to mindfulness and
then mindfulness of breathing and then the next week we talk about
mindfulness of the body as people settle any meditation the body
often becomes very
loud or clear often because it gets uncomfortable if you're not used to meditating
and then the next week we talk about mindfulness of emotions and then mindfulness of thinking
the fifth week there's a range of things that are talked about and um and that sequence is meant to
kind of slowly later steadily make later groundwork to a time when all of all those ways of
practicing all those areas are integrated together into a hole where we're practicing mindfulness
where depending on what is compelling what is predominantly what's happening the most
we might be aware of breathing the body the emotions thoughts and other experiences of our
life and this ability to develop an awareness that's available mindfulness is available
to the full range of our human experience is the goal of mindfulness practice
and that's uh valuable for many reasons uh one reason is valuable is then we
have a heightened attention to so many areas of our life things don't become remain things don't
remain unconscious things don't remain unknown or kind of
sidelined everything sooner or later comes through the the view the
the knowing of awareness and seen clearly also um
as we do this practice over time we start appreciating more and
more what it is to be aware what it is to be mindful and in particular
noticing all the extra uh baggage we bring along in this that
we put on top of the simplicity of awareness the expectations we have
the idea that we have to do a lot of things the idea of the being an agent and i
have to prove myself i or i i shouldn't fail and this is you know that it's all
up to me me myself and mine to do it we might come with fears around being
aware and being aware of what's coming along it might be more of this kind of things we bring along with it
we might have um you know really big goals like you know ambitions around meditation that we
bring along and as we become more and more aware of all this extra stuff we bring along
we can start kind of shedding them and discovering the simplicity of awareness itself
and part of that simplicity eventually is that awareness exists can be present
without us doing it and an awareness becomes kind of autonomous
from our doing it our role is to allow for it to stay
close to it and it's a magical time a special time to feel that awareness is just kind of
the nature of who we are and we don't have to insert the self and agency and doing
into it and there's a shift in mindfulness that for someone who's a raw beginner
the practice does involve doing we're engaging in something that changing the direction changing the
course of our how our life is going from just letting ourselves wander off in thought and desires and aversions and
just kind of be caught up in things to waking up
to not being lost in the world but being
present in the middle of our experience they're really present really centered here
and and there's a doing coming back and and so applying ourselves to the breathing applying ourselves to the body
to these different areas that we pay attention to there's a sense of app like applying oneself and doing it
and partly that's because it's a it's an alternative to being lost
as that builds over time this sense of autonomous awareness
independent awareness becomes stronger and stronger and then awareness is more like receives
experience things arrive in awareness awareness is not something we have to do
it's more something we allow and there can be a sense that things just arrive
or arise within awareness and awareness
becomes freer and freer of even the sense of me being a doer the doer the
agent in a sense awareness becomes independent of of the usual ways in which we identify
who we are me myself and mine and the
and so the awareness um and so the mindfulness instructions that
we give have two sides to it it can have the side of
um something we do and uh so it's prescriptive this is what
we do and that's often the case for for certainly for beginners but at different phases of life different
levels of what's happening in our life it it's it's always coming and going these different ways of practicing
depending what's needed at a time if we're very experienced practitioners
really frazzled and agitated they might be better off applying themselves in the meditation
but as so prescriptively the other way that mindfulness works is the instructions work it's more like
they're not instructions what to do but instructions what to notice so it's descriptive of what arrives in
awareness when awareness is established awareness established it gathers together or allows to arrive the
experience of breathing the experience of the body the experience of emotions experience of thoughts
and there's a radical shift from being a doer to being an allower and that allowing allows for a different
way of participating in the world that's still very effective but very different than
you know being all up to me myself and myself to do and be and all this stuff
so in these next days i'm going to talk more about breathing and what i want to do for each of these
try to do each of these five days of each week of this series i want to
repeat the same kind of theme around each of them so that these become
a little bit more familiar regularly available to you at different times to really
understand different facets of this practice so on mondays and i'm not going to do
much time now but mondays the theme is going to be relaxation
and tuesdays the theme will be recognition wednesday's theme will be
respect thursday the theme will be restoring
and friday will be released so we'll look at each of these things hopefully and
and look at these different aspects of the practice in relationship to
breath body emotions and thoughts and then whatever we do the following weeks
and and so uh relaxation with the breathing we did
that a little bit in the guided meditation part of the function of coming back to
the breath over and over and over again and the mind wanders off and we come back is that
if we return to the breathing is the breathing then is the anchor for
having awareness established and and we relax it isn't so much that we
force ourselves back to the breath but it's more like we welcome ourselves back to the breath over and over and
over again so the breathing the regularity of breathing takes the energy away from the other
from ways where tents tense around our thoughts tense around our emotions caught up in things
and the more preoccupied we are in thinking the more attention there is in the system more force and pressure there
is and this gentle returning to the breathing returning to be aware of the breathing
begins to take away some of that energy that goes in keeping the mind and the heart and the body tense from our
concerns and then in addition the regularity of breathing helps us to relax the rhythm
of breathing for many of us and so you can even help that by
allowing yourself to relax on the exhale relax gently openly
for some people this focus of breathing is difficult sometimes that's
that's normal enough and it's just a process to work through that and be gentle and
patient and and not make a problem out of how difficult it might be the tension or
the holding patterns or the breathing or controlling the breath or something and it's well worth kind of spending
time to see if you can kind of work through it for some people if the
the breathing is not really the appropriate object for attention um
and um i've known people for example who had a maybe a near-death experience of
drowning or something else it was very difficult for them where breath was really a challenge
and so that the memory of that or the impact of that is such that breathing never really
becomes a good place to meditate and so for them sometimes body
just being rooted in the body kind of being grounded here in the body in some open way is much better there are other
options as well but but it's really nice to work through some of the difficulty if possible
around breathing and relaxing is a big part of it learning to relax with the breath
so that's the plan for this uh next period of time and i'm hoping that this instructions
and teaching i give will work both for people who are beginners or new but also they'll be
support for the people who are quite experienced in practice as well
the beginning practice is the practice and so in some sense the more mature people become in this practice
the difference between a beginner and a mature person is that a mature person is a better beginner
a more thorough beginner and finally i gave kind of said some of this but also
a little bit more yesterday morning for the sunday morning talker at imc a talk that was kind of done as an introduction
to this series that we're doing here now so some of you haven't if you haven't heard that you might go and listen to
that half an hour and it also sets the stage a little bit for what we're doing
so um thank you for today and i'm looking forward to sharing something that is so
something i love quite a bit so thank you