and so one of the orientations or
perspectives on practice in the teachings of the buddha
is an orientation oh i wasn't recording
so one of the perspectives on
practice in the teachings of the buddha is that he was oriented to
towards the consequences of our actions so there was a sense that
noticing little bit or caring a little bit for what the consequences of what we do is
important and so some orientation into the future
about the potential the likely results of what we do is part of a wise way of living
and of course we have to be very careful with that and it's balanced with the tremendous emphasis on the present moment in this
practice as well but it's not ignoring the future and
consequences and so to sit down to meditate in the morning
it might be that we do have a sense of the day will go better we'll be more centered calmer maybe
wiser and so there is some appreciation that the motivation even to meditate because
of the benefits it brings our lives and then there's also the consequence
in the short term it's possible to have a sense that if you sit down to
meditate and what you want to do is to
be in a super hurry to get into a deep state of concentration and
and because there's important things to do and in life and and so you're going to just
really huff and puff and strive and get all sweaty and contracted and tense so you
can get quickly concentrated that doesn't work and so have some sense
that yes i want to get settled here in my meditation but it doesn't work to strive or to push or
have a lot of expectations demands to be measuring how i'm doing as i go along
every few seconds what has a good consequence is just be very relaxed around
the consequences at this point and being relaxed about not trying too much to make something happen
is the better way to make something happen that's useful in meditation and so there's still some consequential
thinking but it's recognizing you know how i am in the moment is important
and that it makes a difference how i am that if i strive in meditation i'll have a headache and
that will persist through the day if i can be at ease that creates more ease and it sets up a nice thing for the
day if we get closer in and
and into the present moment the sense of the consequences of our practice
has more and more to do with the present moment we can feel the difference between uh being critical about
how we're paying attention to the breathing versus being relaxed around it
and you can feel the the immediate consequence sometimes called instant karma the immediate quality the that one of
them has is more dukkha suffering and one is more open and
and feels better and feels satisfying and this ability to differentiate between what is
satisfying and not satisfying in how we enter the moment it gets
closer and closer to something very intimate and close here and now and less concerned about
the future but to be able to discern that difference and see
is it are we are we involved in um um you know
are we too lazy in meditation and so the mind is drifting off too much and
a little bit more energy is necessary a little bit engagement are we a little bit too much
constantly making commentary about our meditation and always kind of questioning and doubting
it and is that really that's not really so useful and you could feel that that doesn't feel good
and perhaps having a provisional confidence in our meditation um a just uh
you know provisional until more evidence comes it's actually more useful for settling and so again there's a
sense of the immediate consequences there and for this meditation i'd like to point to something more subtle
and that is that as we practice like mindfulness of the
breathing there's a very there can be a very subtle
after effect of
be a moment of being connected to the breathing like if we follow the breath all the way
that knowing of the breath being connected to it it's kind of like an after image there's
a kind of or kind of like a if you go out into the water and stand in the sun and get warm
that warmth will persist if you go back into the shade for a little while there's the the after
effect of warmth that remains so there's an after effect of doing the
practice act after effect of kind of after image
after sense after feeling that persists a little bit beyond just the moment of being mindful it's
very subtle and and even if you don't feel it
the sense of being open to it or receptive or
to to feel that as well kind of in the peripheral of attention
to be a veil or to be available to be open and receptive to allow an after effect or the glow of
the practice or the the the after warmth
remain or the softness or the calmness or whatever it might be to let the goodness of the practice kind
of be available for you to persist into as if you were making space
in your body for that after effect that the results of the practice
so you're not making it happen you're not demanding it happens the subtlety is that of kind of staying
open available for the practice
to somehow work on you or radiate into you or
persist a nice feeling of something and whether you feel anything or not is
less important than that sense of presence and availability receptivity to something
be kind of of allowing yourself to be practiced by the practice
to allow yourself to be affected by the practice in a way that's not exactly
your doing it's the consequence of what you're doing
the after effect and if what i'm saying is too subtle or too
bizarre for you just forget what i'm saying but um so with that
taking a upright metaphorically or literally
upright posture
and taking a few moments and closing your eyes to feel your body
kind of roam let your attention roam through your body
familiarize yourself with what the experience of your body is right now
and then to see if you can adjust your
kind of your attitude your orientation that with your body and heart and mind
you're available
you are available to be receptive
to to the practice that you're available
to be changed
you're available for some deeper qualities of practice to be registered or to
waft through you
and then very gently with this receptivity availability
take some gentle but deeper breaths maybe slowly
as if you're receiving the inhale into that availability
and filling that receptivity on the exhale long quiet exhale
and perhaps you recognize that quieting the thinking mind
increases the receptivity the availability to really take in the experience
of practice of meditation and the more you're thinking the less
room there is to be available to sense to feel
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and in terms of feeling the after effect being available to linger and feel it
it might be extremely subtle but notice the after effect as you relax
different parts of your body as you exhale softening the muscles of
the face
and what's the feeling that comes with relaxing those muscles
as you exhale softening and relaxing the
shoulders
and in these little moments of softening relaxing the shoulders what good
feelings remain for a few moments what after effect is there
relaxing the belly
softening it might be possible to soften the hands
the fingers
might be possible to just gently just a little bit flap your elbows to loosen up
any tightness or holding in the arms
it might be possible to relax and soften
the muscles of your back so maybe those
muscles kind of release down your back
and now opening more fully to your
breathing at the end of the exhale
for a moment let there be a very brief pause
not a pause that is a strain but just long enough so the beginning of
the inhale really wants to happen and you
allow it and rece and better so you can better receive the
inhale
being available for the influence the inhale has on your
body and mind receptive
not just only to the sensations of breathing but maybe to the afterglow or the
radiance or the something that spreads from your breathing as you inhale
and as you exhale allow the exhale the release to
occur ride that release ride the exhale
gently allowing it all the way to the end
and especially as you get to the end of the out breath being available to feel
the influence that exhaling has on you
more widely
being receptive to the inhale
being allowing for the exhale
available to allow the influence of mindfulness of breathing to spread
through your body
as if your body is a receptacle that receives the practice
and whether you receive anything or not is less important than
this openness and availability as you breathe
and if you become aware of other things besides your breathing
perhaps you can become aware of them body sensations feelings thoughts in this
open receptive way that's available
to feel not the influence of our feelings and body sensations but the influence of
being mindful aware aware of body emotions
thoughts
where being available and receptive is almost a quality of the mindfulness
itself
and perhaps feeling the goodness
of this receptive open mindfulness
practice
in some subtle way small way can you adjust how you have a continuous
mindfulness continuous awareness of your breathing of your experience
so that that mindfulness has a good influence on you
that it's nourishing supportive that the after effect the influence
is beneficial or if you notice that the after effect
the influence is not beneficial can you adjust it
so that how you're aware seems to have a nice influence
here and now in the present moment in this body and mind
letting the thinking be quiet so you can better feel the subtlety of all this
sometimes the beneficial influence of the practice
can increase slightly if you very slightly make a small
half smile turning up the corners of your lips
and allowing for the receptivity being receptive to the influence the
good influence of pleasure joy
that supports being present
as you receive the inhale receive the global
nourishment or influence good influence that might be here from meditating
as you allow the exhale allow the nourishment or allow the
global goodness that might be here throughout the body
in the mind in the heart
letting your awareness take it all in on the inhale
the awareness allow for it on the exhale
and then as we come to the end of this sitting take a moment to feel
grounded in your place of meditation
if you're sitting upright to feel the sitting bones your bottom
firmly on what supports your weight if your feet are planted on the floor to
feel the solidity of your feet on the floor
whatever way you can really use your body weight to really feel grounded settled
established here and then together with that
to be open and receptive to be available to feel and sense and
take in the experience of the world around you
without being unduly influenced been duly affected by that
but grounded in the present moment and open and receptive
and then bringing to mind some people of your life
friends family neighbors people in the community and places you
frequent and imagine that you're with one or some
of them in this way both grounded and
established in the present and open and receptive
secure in your groundedness available to be open and receptive
to take in the experience of another person
and maybe feeling or sensing the other person knowing the other
person from some place inside that
is tender or gentle or kind loving
without losing your groundedness without leaning forward or
approaching the person or needing to say anything just this place of being grounded and
receptive have thoughts of good will for them
feelings of good will in which you wish them well
may you be happy
may you be safe
may you be peaceful and may you be free
and imagine that this is the stance that you can have towards everyone
that you are firmly confidently grounded in yourself
and open and receptive to take in the humanity of other people
and then to extend your heart to all beings may all beings
be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free and may the benefits of our practice
this morning contribute to that being the case
[Music]
[Music] you