so so formally hello and welcome
to happier dear sangha so
today in the united states
is um a holiday this is a holiday weekend and this monday is a holiday and it's
it's called labor day it's the day to celebrate labor the working
working force with working the labor of all all who labor who work so
so with that that's kind of a very uh general description of the holiday
and um so [Music] so
for the given that particular theme what i wanted to to use that theme
but but change it shift it um for us to um
to practice appreciation appreciation and gratitude for all labor for all work all
gifts um both all the
the labor all the the gifts that anyone has given us
both knowingly and unknowingly um as well as appreciating our own labor
and the word labor perhaps is kind of laborious it sounds a little heavy
but um but maybe we can think of it
as something light for example you know i'm wearing this this this shirt here
because of so many people's contribution so many people's contributions
around the world that this shirt has made its way
providing um support from the elements to this body there's
been the designer there's been the person who has produced it you know
if it's cotton you know the person who's who's the farmer who's
produced the cotton etc etc all these contributions all these human contributions
and also it closer to home all of us every single one of us are
us human beings whether we've had um parents who've been loving or not as
caring and yet for the first four years of our lives all of us human beings
are [Music] pretty dependent we're actually completely dependent on the care of
others so it has taken a lot of labor has taken a lot of labor
for us to even survive to make it to this point
[Music] so [Music] appreciating the labor the contributions
of of people who have supported us friends as well as maybe coaches etc etc and as
well as our own labor our own contributions our on our own work
our own practice our own
maybe studying or work or whatever we have done to make to bring us to this
point and for the practice today the invitation is to turn off our judgment this is not the time
to start judging of course the judgmental mind can be there but we can
choose we have a choice we have a choice which way to go and if we notice that
we've gone down the road of judging others well they didn't work so hard and
they should have done more like why would we come back we are intending we are inclining our mind
towards appreciation we're cultivating appreciation
this is the work we're doing right now there might be another time for discernment um etc etc but right right right now
given that our minds tend to be more judgmental than appreciative
normally we are going to choose to strengthen the muscle of appreciation
and again not to say there is not a time for discernment et cetera et cetera and that has a right
place and time but not judgment there is there is a um sharpness there is a
acerbicness in judgment that that is not helpful doesn't serve
similarly for ourselves when we turn today to appreciate ourselves
don't start unleashing all kinds of
judgments and self-recommendations onto yourself to evaluate everything you've done
as a shortcoming turn your mind towards appreciating appreciating what what has been done
what what you've been able to do so so that is the frame that is the frame
for today's practice and i've spoken enough so so let's turn
let's turn to [Music] practice appreciation for all our labors
and everyone else is together and i'll lead us as usual so let's let's begin
[Music]
let's begin by landing by landing in this body
landing in this breath
and letting go in this moment choosing to let go choosing to put down
what is not helpful what doesn't serve in this moment
and softening relaxing into the body
relaxing softening into the breath clear sit bones
allowing your spine to have a sense of integrity to be
upright rising up from your sit bones
from the stable base sitting with integrity
tall yet relaxed the muscles soft and relaxed
as always we start with settling arriving
just this
breath received in the abdomen in this moment in time
just taking cherishing this moment as a moment of
refuge
connecting with the breath in the body
in this moment
as we receive the breath each in breath each out breath
appreciating this body
and the way it works the way it functions all the internal functions
it's not just the breath
the autonomous nervous system functioning
all the chemical biological functions
systems actions
that support this being who is me who is us
functioning
without thinking about it too much just receiving the breath
and what is whatever sensations
reveal themselves present themselves to you
and as we connect with the breath with the body so connecting with appreciation
for this body functioning working
as well as it does which may not be perfect
breathing digestion hearing
seeing tasting smelling touching
healing etc
so many functions
to be grateful for
and now turning turning your awareness or attention
to someone someone who's easy in our life maybe a parent maybe a teacher a coach
a benefactor someone who's been there for us
we feel gratitude appreciation for their work for their labor
perhaps previously unappreciated or unseen unacknowledged
and letting a sense of appreciation for their work for their contributions
for their labor to be an open-hearted one
it's a gift that may be continuing or was
previously gifted and by receiving it graciously continuing to receive
openheartedly
we honor the gift honor the labor
honor the contribution receiving it wholeheartedly
with appreciation
and you're welcome to invite more benefactors if you wish
in this circle of appreciation
spending time with each person
not jumping quickly from one to the next which can get the mind a little
unsettled if we jump too quickly spending a little bit of time with each
i remember it's not the time to get judgmental and consider all the shortcomings but to be
generous cultivate generosity in seeing the good
cultivating generosity and the appreciation
and now if you wish expanding the circle of appreciation
to categories of beings maybe all farmers all farmers in the world
all fruit pickers vegetable pickers etc etc
all farm laborers all over the world who've had
any hand supported
the food you eat have eaten so many people so many beings
maybe bringing to mind just one or two
maybe appreciating the work of
all drivers in the world everyone working in transportation
supporting the movement of food of goods
feeling the interconnection with so much of humanity
maybe choosing another category it's meaningful to you maybe from your
profession all those who've laid the foundation
for what you do or maybe all writers
whose writing whose work you have appreciated
no including yourself including this being who is you
appreciating your work your labor your contribution
to yourself and to others your interconnection with others
through not just your work but living your life
simply being
being a friend being a neighbor
a child or a parent a sibling all the functions
seeing others appreciating your contributions your work your labor
you simply showing up
and beware of judgment if you consider you're showing up your
contribution to be subpar or lousy thank you thank you judgmental mind
not needed right now
letting yourself letting this being who's you to be appreciated to be seen
for your gifts
contributions in this interconnected wipe of humanity
you are needed you are needed
you are needed
your participation is needed
and for the last moments of this practice period
feeling the interconnection opening
appreciating the interconnected web and how all
our contributions our participations all the labor all the love
is needed
and may our contribution
be of benefit to ourselves in the whole world
may all beings be free may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so we have time for reflections
for questions
time in the sangha to share your insights observations
as a gift to participate with everyone
and you can raise your zoom hand if you wish you can also type in chat if it's just
typed in me i will not read your name it will be private and if you
uh type them to everyone i will read your reflections ah and jerry has shared with me that
today is also yes is the jewish new year
so happy rosh hashanah so as a part of our practice also
appreciating the work the labor the contributions
of all the the the jewish community around the world
so any reflections on this labor day rosh hashanah
ah dawn says thank you the sentiment you are needed was a gift
thank you don yeah and you're welcome to raise your hand to say more if you wish
and rosie please
um do i just speak yes please okay um
well where i went to in my mind was with my grandmother and my
sister who were um carers for me in the absence of my mother
and i got in touch with so much love that i uh experienced as a child
that i hadn't um really reflected on in that way
um and so then when i extended that to a group it was
uh women that have given birth because we all came and that's labor right because
we all came from from someone that gave birth to us so um
we had this all in common and then the next group were
teachers and because i saw their influence on me in my life
and i really did see because i'm a teacher now a high school teacher i really did see
the connection between the care i received from these women in my life then um all the
mothers and then the teachers and now what i do and oh it was beautiful big web of interconnectedness
uh yeah like a map it was lovely so thank you
thank you racio it's such a beautiful reflection and thank you so much for
sharing this beautiful web that came up for you in your practice and i love this other definition of
labor yes libra we've all come through wombs of mothers they've all labored
we thank you for that that resonance that's beautiful and and and so much
love and in so many different ways and we've all had teachers so many teachers
beautiful thank you rosie oh lovely terence says
reflections on the labors of the buddha lovely and the lineage of the teachers
that have connected us with the teachings wow indeed yeah
yeah the labor labors of the buddha it wasn't easy for him
the story goes that after he was awakened he didn't want to teach it just it was too
hard he thought nobody's going to get what i want to teach so
and it was hard and all the the lineage all the teachers and all the
practitioners and being practitioners yourself you know that yes sometimes practice is nourishing and rewarding
sometimes it's it's hard it's challenging it's difficult so
so connecting with that thank you turns that's a beautiful reflection love that any other reflections any other groups
that came up for you would love to hear
or anything else jeff please
um i just felt a real um um expansiveness of of my heart
um you know finding the gratitude and the appreciation for you know entire groups
of people just it was just such a a big feeling you know just an
expansiveness i almost felt like you know my heart wanted to kind of beat out of my chest it was it was really
beautiful thank you thank you beautiful thank you so much
lovely you have time for one more reflection before i return yes diana i do see your
hand i usually don't hear there we go
i have difficulty uh and can you hear me yeah
okay i have difficulty with one thing which is that my contributions have been huge i know
them uh think about it in so many ways um
but it would be nice to have something recognized at some point you know yeah i
just uh it's just there's just i i'm not it's not about that it's just like
uh i'm a really good friend to someone or it's i go through life
and and not feeling um [Music] and just like being there
and i just heard this thought that that may be a healing thought for me the previous speaker talked about his own
expansiveness of heart maybe
it may be within me being closed off and [Music]
not seeing others appreciation of me or something like that i don't
diana i think you i i love how you circled around you know your insight
as you're speaking out loud into oh yeah maybe that maybe that's what
needs a little more leaning into and opening up to
the bigger part yeah beautiful thank you for your inner wisdom
answering your own question i love it when that happens
thanks diana beautiful so um
jeff if this is quick here before we go into groups yes
it is quick and this this was um just to address diana's point um that um i i used to be a real people
pleaser and uh you know that was it was i was really looking for a lot of recognition and it wasn't until i
started a lot of self-compassion practice and started to really um appreciate myself for who i am and
appreciate kind of you know what i've accomplished that i stopped looking externally for that validation
and that was of a real huge part of of of my transformation so just share that with you thank you thank you jeff for
sharing your journey your your journey journey in this way and how this has has lit you up beautiful yay
yay so dear ones speaking of sharing our journeys with each other and supporting
each other um in this sangha now we turn we turn our attention
to practicing in small groups of roughly size three or so
and as always we'll start with 15 seconds of silent meta for one another
and then um you say you'll speak as little or as much as you wish
appreciating yourself appreciating others um
in sharing their practice and sharing your practice if this is this this being in groups is
a labor of love is a labor of love hopefully not too laborious but maybe leaning into the love
appreciating yourself appreciating others so take care of yourself take care of others and the rooms are open
here we go and the breakout rooms are going to close in three seconds
and folks are back welcome back everyone so
we just have a minute for any um yes can if i see your hand
please yeah i i have a lot of appreciation for
my kundalini teacher i studied with for years and years because he didn't want
to be a teacher either but when he was given the gift from his teacher
he taught us to honor his own teacher but a lot of times he didn't want to be
there but he did it in honor of his teacher and i have a lot of respect and love for him because of that
that warms my heart that that absolutely warms my heart
thanks for bringing him into the circle kenneth yeah
yeah beautiful ah so honoring appreciating all labors all
contributions ours others and all the labors i love how earlier roizy brought
in the laborers of our mothers laborers a different definition of laborers
that's going to stay with me for the rest of the day so thank you all thank you all for
showing up for practicing for contributing your labor of love
to this sangha by showing up supporting yourself supporting each other
may all beings everywhere benefit from our labor of love
in our practice may we awaken may we be happy may we be
free and may all beings everywhere be happy and free
thanks everyone thank you all so i will