so i'll start over and say good day and warm greetings
and in this buddhist meditation practice that we do the mindfulness practice
it involves a really a great appreciation
of the present moment certainly appreciation of the potential here but also of the richness
of this experience now of course the past is important and
without any um connection to our history
our story our past life is pretty truncated and i see it now that i spent time at a
memory care center and seeing what's like for people who have no really long term and sometimes
short-term memories and and of course the future has its
role in anticipating the future imagining the future
you know is a huge important part of human life and has its important place
but compared to the importance of the past and the future they pale in significance to the present
it's almost as if the present moment is three-dimensional and the past and the
future is two-dimensional and to really enter into this three-dimensional four-dimensional
kind of rich area of the present moment and it's kind of like stepping into a
gate into a new garden into a new place and you really get into it fully
and and so to really appreciate the present
moment and to do so to have the skill and the ability and and the focus to do it for a period of
time like for these minutes we're going to do meditation and um and then
in some ways it makes the past in the future that when it's useful and to be involved in those
thinking about them it makes them richer actually and enhances it rather than detracts from it
to be really in the present moment really know how to be here and now
and of course you'll get pulled into thoughts about the past thoughts about
the future about fantasy reflections and um
and the art of it is to really really recognize
and that can't underscore how important the recognition is it's almost like waking up oh
wake up oh this is present moment phenomena i'm thinking about the past and the
present i'm thinking about the future in the present i'm fantasizing or
abstract ideas in the present it's like a wake up oh is that powerful
oh like you open your eyes oh that's what's happening and in that kind of the present moment
that's what's happening here then we're no longer swept into the future swept into the past or into
fantasy and this is where the whole um beginning of uh of waking up
occurs and in that clear recognition we find some of the qualities of
great awakening we find qualities of letting go not clinging not holding on
so perhaps in this sitting you can be we can begin to
begin but maybe you can gently without striving or being too agitated
about it give yourself a greater appreciation of
being here turns out you are here anyway in the present moment this is actually
where you are so join it really be in it
feel it sense it breathe with it moment after moment so taking a
alert relaxed posture
and gently close your eyes
and gently slowly take some
longer breaths in a long release with the exhale
long slow inhale and release
with the exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal and relaxing
more of your body on the exhale but a relaxation that is in your mind
maybe you think of it is relaxing into the present into the
present moment experience here in the body
and then letting your letting go of relaxing and
gathering yourself in the present moment with the breathing
with the breathing as the center of your universe
more so than your thinking mind
that kind of gathering of attention
around the experience of breathing
and here
the breathing being a touchstone to the present moment
in the present moment a touchstone
to our direct experience our lived experience
the experience we have moment moment that is a manifestation of being alive
and here and now
staying close to the present momentness of whatever comes into
awareness the present momentness of thinking about
the past and the future see it all as present moment
your breathing is always in the present moment
riding along with your breathing breathe with whatever else is happening
breathe with the mind thinking about the future about the past
breathe with your emotions
breathe with so that the present moment experience of breathing
keeps you in the present
are you recognizing
that you are in the present moment that your thoughts are present moment
experience
so
one of the wonderful things about the present moment
is that we all arrive there at the same
time we share this living
vital lived experience of here and now
if we're present for it
if we allow ourselves the opportunity to really be here
and as we come to the end of the sitting this deep allowing of the present moment
allowing ourselves to be there becomes a way of being present for the
people in our lives it's a way of being present for
others as well
and to be present for others without being caught up in the past or
thinking about the future what we want but to really be here to feel and sense
and know another person and to know ourselves
in the presence of another person
then there is an avenue for care for respect
for kindness friendliness for appreciation
and for caring for each other may what we learn in meditation
about being present be applied to being present for
and with the people we encounter or the people we communicate
with in whatever way we're in touch
and may it be that whereas we're present that we offer the world our respect our
appreciation our kindness
so that our way of being with others
manifest or enact even in the smallest ways
the wish that others may be happy
that others may be peaceful
that others may be safe
that others may be free
may all be all beings
live in this present moment life free and happy
so today i want to tell a few stories from a little a storybook that i wrote called the
monastery within and many of the stories have to do with the abbess of the monastery
and the first one i'll tell is that the abbess one day
called together all the new monastics of the monastery
um who'd been there for less than six months and maybe at a time when maybe they
start getting a little bit restless or a little bit wondering why they're there or maybe
even they've gotten used to the routine and maybe starting to get on board and remembering their
life before the monastery and you know its allures and pleasures
and she called them together and said pack your bags because i'm going to take you on a
pilgrimage to the holy sites of buddhism now these monastics knew about the holy
sites in india the place where the buddha was born where he was enlightened where he first taught and where he died
these are considered the most holy spirit places and for theravadin buddhists and
people do pilgrimages there and visit and so they oh great we're going on a trip so they packed their
bags ready for travel and and so they climbed onto the
monastery bus and off they went and first the abbess took them to a hospital
where they visited the sick and they were surprised by all the different kind of sicknesses that people were
struggling with there and some pretty severe they had a chance to go through the icu
and even the emergency room and it was kind of almost mind-boggling to
see the extent of injuries and illnesses
and then back on the bus and they went to a old age home and
they saw what for them most of the monastics were young what seemed like their ravages
old age of people who could no longer care for themselves and who some of them couldn't walk
anymore and some of them had all kinds of you know challenges and decreased
capacities of all kinds and and it was pretty impressive for this young monastics to see
and then they went back on the bus and the abbess took them to a hospice
where they saw people in the stages of dying and and some of them scared of dying
some of them kind of disconnected from the whole experience some of them not really present anymore
and semi-aware semi-conscious and all kinds of challenging ways of
dying and and some that already died and they spent time in next and one
next to a bed where a corpse was lying recently dead person
and then the men the the habits took them back to the monastery and the monastery had an infirmary where
there was one old sick monk
and i spent time with the sick monk and who seemed very present and had a certain kind of
seemed very tired in the illness he had but he seemed very calm and seemed like
he was kind of very engaged in his practice as buddhist practice that he spent years doing and
he was just continuing in bed and they could feel the sincerity and the intentness of
his engagement with his practice in his life and he seemed like he was just as content to
practice in bed as he was anywhere else and then they went to
um visit a very old nun and 96 years old and um
in a wheelchair and but there was a sparkle of uh
in the eyes of joy and that kind of kind of they looked closer and seemed like her eyes
were kind of marveling at the mystery of it all and that the light of it almost like she was surprised to be alive and delighted and
and had no fear and no regrets and just was there and content way and this deep contentment
was palpable for the new monastics
and then they went to um the um hospice of the monastery
and there in fact there was a monk who was uh who's dying and um and there was such
peace and it was clear the monk was in some pain but there was so much peace and
they entered into the room and it was so peaceful and so calm that everyone got quiet and
everyone felt like they just should bow deeply there was something reverent and profound
about the presence of this person who'd spent decades in the monastery practicing and the
level of peace and there was no iota of fear
and then the abbess took them back to the courtyard of the monastery and they sat down there and under a big tree
and the abba said now you have seen the sacred sites of buddhism
knowing these practice well
plunge into the monastic life plunge into the practice you've come to do and you
too will become the sacred sites of buddhism
so that's one story and so it's
kind of sacralizes something that's common in almost every
day sickness old age and that can both be a catalyst for
practicing for really getting to the bottom of what it means to be alive and get to the bottom of the just
the origins of our suffering that we have in this life that we live and can really also be the catalyst for
waking up and finding our freedom and our peace
the second story involves a monk who was known for
having a very deep seemingly deep peace and acceptance of life and and a deep
trust in just that in life itself and this monk one day
one time we went off to the edges of the monastery edges of the wilderness and the forest away from the others
where the monastery had a few meditation huts and monastics will go out there to meditate
for weeks at a time and so he went out there and as uh
and um and um
and there was a kind of a clearing in the woods with a kind of a grass meadow
in front of his meditation hut and one day he heard a deer crashing
through the woods and collapsing on the meadow in front of his
his hut and clearly the the deer was injured and and just kind
of collapsed there but soon behind the deer there came a
lion uh and then i said oh said the monk uh you know this this line
i guess is maybe that's why it's injured it's attacked by the line the lion's gonna eat it
and the lion came along and the deer seemed completely relaxed at ease and just kind of there accepting
its condition almost just there and could see the lion but was
not afraid was not trying to get up to run away and just just was seemingly just there
and the line came along and the lion proceeded for the next two days to stand
guard over the deer to keep it safe from other predators and whatever's there
so the deer could heal well enough to get up and to you know walk away and and
that was a pretty impressive thing to see and so the monastic said oh yeah this is this was
an affirmation this was like proof that my practice of deep acceptance of
everything and if i just accept life as it really is then um then the life will provide the dharma
will provide things will arise and and but the art of it is to really accept
so some weeks later there was a nun who was staying at a hut
not very far away and uh for some reason um the hut caught
on fire and um and the monk saw that and he said
oh look at that and first it was just a small little fire on the roof and then it got bigger and then he's amongst
it because he was into this acceptance things and just allowing things and letting things arise from
just uh watched and was a little curious but just watched what was happening and the fire got bigger and bigger and
then he saw the nun come out of the hut and try to get some water and tried to put the fire out
and she got a little injured in the process and but uh to no avail and the whole hut
burned to the ground and just with ashes when it's over it happened very quickly and so by time
that it was burned the it was only after it was burnt that the the monks nuns the abbess came to see
what was going on and and so the abbess came to the to the monk and said what happened here and he
explained what happened and and then the habit said why didn't you help
oh well i was really inspired i saw you know how profound it is to just accept
things and he saw what happened with the deer it explained what happened with the deer and the tiger
and the abbess got angry and said and basically said
it's time for you to leave the monastery and return to the world
sometimes it's important to be the deer and just accept your condition and
sometimes it's important to be the lion so you have to leave and only come back
when you know how to be the lion
so naive acceptance sometimes we have to accept the fact
that we are lions here to protect the world and care for the world with our strength and our power and our
abilities and that to have a policy of just acceptance and
allowing and just being at peace with everything is really uh to live a truncated life and denies a
whole part of who we are in a sense we're both the deer and the lion
and don't be afraid to be either one but to do have the wisdom to know
which one is appropriate at any time so
may you discover your monastery within meaning your wisdom inside your place of practice
and and may that be a gift that you give to the world
thank you oh and then for next week right now i'm
thinking that uh in some ways i'll continue with this stories for next week
but a whole different genre of stories and that is to their stories from the buddha's life
that uh um you know our teaching stories or the context for the buddhist teachings
and so i thought maybe we'd pick some of these stories from the buddha's life that in
which appear some of the important teachings that he gives as a way of kind of combining the teachings and and the ancient kind of
stories from the canon so that's that's what i'm thinking now and i look forward to our time next week