okay so why don't we go ahead and get started
so settling in for our period of meditation
and my aim for this particular sit is to
begin by evoking some um
equality that i'll describe as we're doing it and then um after
offering several options for how we might evoke that we'll sit mostly in silence and you can
do your regular practice and observe how it was to
sit in the presence of the the quality that we're evoking
okay so settling in and closing the eyes gently if that's
comfortable for you just allowing the attention to come
inward
feeling the body sitting
maybe feeling where you're being supported so your seat against the chair or the
cushion with a bench or if you're lying down
just feeling the support and allowing yourself to be supported
letting go into the support of your seat and ultimately of the earth
feeling that stability that groundedness
allowing the energy of the body to settle downward in case it was up in the head bringing
it down farther into the body
and even from the body we can sometimes let the energy sink down into
the earth
kind of a feeling of rootedness
and then the body may feel like
a tree rising up or if it's more flexible it can feel
like a sea plant rising off the sea floor floating in the water
let's do whatever degree you can feel that allowing that sense in the body
and allowing the mind to come into presence
so mindfulness being aware of
any sensations in the body
checking in with the current climate in the heart the mind
how are you
or whatever's there is fine we just want to include it in our awareness
there's a mood or any emotions or thoughts
we can let them be there but intend to bring the attention into the
present moment
to whatever degree possible finding a way to rest
with whatever is present for you right now
so as we continue sitting together
i would like to evoke a sense of refuge
or [Music] confidence in practice
or for some of you the word faith may may work
classically there are many many ways to to do this
you may have a personal one but i would just like to invite
i'll offer a few of them you can see if something works
so as we sit we may consider
that we are following a long line of practitioners
that goes all the way back to the historical buddha
when the buddha sat in meditation was not so different
from this he too had a mind and a body
and when he started out it was pretty much like ours
and yet he found awakening
we may be inspired
you may consider further that
the buddha offered teachings instructions for how to be
with our experience what a gift
even if you're a new practitioner quite new
you may already have a sense that what we learn mindfulness
awareness of the body these are so helpful [Music]
given that we didn't really get an instruction manual with our mind and body
you can be inspired by the dharma
it really does work
in small ways and maybe you even know in large ways
it's good to be doing what we're doing right now
we can also be inspired or supported
by the sangha by the other practitioners on this path
we're supported by a lot of people
who have practiced through the ears who are sitting with us right now
model for us the goodness that comes from practice
some are teachers sometimes it's just nice to know that
there's a bunch of other people sitting out there at any given moment there are people all over the world somewhere
meditating
we can feel like we're joining a vast stream
of practice that will carry us
these are the three classic ways to connect with a sense of refuge
buddha dharma and sangha
and i'll look for two other brief reflections that are also
in the teachings
we can also consider our own
ethical conduct our own goodness
the fact that we try to live well
we try to live a life that is non-harming
that includes some care for others
a way of being in a world that is somehow peaceful or
beneficial
this is meant to be inspiring to us that we live this way that we're contributing in this way
so we can feel happy
with our good intentions and our good actions
and we can also be inspired by our own generosity
what we give
if we have a sensibility that being here is not just about taking but about
offering material resources our time our
attention [Music] our compassion
countless acts of giving throughout the day
the world really operates on this kind of generosity simple moment to
moment couldn't function without it
and we contribute this too is meant to be inspiring to us
so it said that any of these simple reflections
leads to a gladness about the practice
a sense of confidence this is a good thing to do
and we can just rest in that sense and use it as a
bolster or a way of fostering
clarity and mindfulness as we continue to sit together
so choosing your usual practice breath or body something else
just seeing if this sense of refuge and confidence
can inform the way you continue to sit
foreign
do you find that sitting with a sense of refuge or confidence in the practice
informs your meditation
is there some additional clarity to the mind or focus on what
you're doing [Music] or a deeper sense of compassion
any difference i'm just noticing that
so if you found that there is a positive impact
from connecting with your own sense of care sense of
faith in the practice you might consider that that
can positively impact others also
even without needing to say anything explicit
carrying with you the sense that the dharma is an important part of your
life that mindfulness is
something that can inform the way we go through the day
just carrying that in you
can help others they too may feel a sense of connection
to the present they may feel your harmlessness
an intuitive subtle way
your benefit and goodness in the world is increased when you know that in
yourself
it's kind of a hidden side benefit of all this practice that it does
go out
and that too can feed back and be a source of happiness for us
so perhaps today [Music] you could just carry in your heart
the sense that this practice is important to you
just carry with you the clear knowledge that mindfulness harmlessness generosity
are valuable and trust that that will inform those
around you also
bye [Music]
[Music]
so
okay so this week
um we're doing a theme that i'm calling the dharma of uncommon lists
and we started yesterday with a list of five and today we'll have a list of four
and so on so the um and there's a lot of good dharma in
these in these lists this one actually may not be so unfamiliar
so today's list is a set of four qualities that are praised in lay practitioners
like us and they appear together this set of four
in several different ways they appear as the basis of spiritual friendship
they appear as qualities that should be emulated
and they also are listed as forms of inner wealth
so these four are confidence or faith
virtue generosity and wisdom
so you've likely heard of each of these separately or in other contexts
but it's interesting to consider them together as a set if you will
so here's the quote from one of the sutas that talks about them as the basis of
spiritual friendship so it says and what is good friendship
it's when a person resides in a town or village
and there are householders or their children who may be young or old but are mature
in conduct accomplished in faith ethics generosity
and wisdom that person associates with them converses and engages in discussion and
they emulate the same kind of accomplishment in faith ethics generosity and wisdom
this is called good friendship so [Music]
we see that we are encouraged to associate with and emulate people who
have the sutta says sada which is the quality that can be translated as faith but also
confidence ethical conduct or virtue generosity and wisdom and altogether
that set of four is called conduct which said that these are people who are
mature in conduct so first i'd like to just talk about
each one of these and then we'll kind of put them together so the first one sata
confidence or faith i've come to like the word faith but i i didn't used to
and so i can understand if that word has some aversion for you so it's fine also
to use confidence or trust and it's typically stated
classically in the teachings as confidence in the buddha's awakening that's interesting it's uh so it's not a
blind devotion to a religious figure from the past it's really the confidence that the
buddha was able to find a way through the labyrinth of his mind to awaken to
a place that is free of great hatred and delusion but more broadly and this is also
implied in the in the teachings we could say that faith or confidence is is pointing
toward a sincere acknowledgement of higher possibilities
if you will so it's kind of the opposite of something like cynicism
or sarcasm or other ways where we diminish
our own or other's potential so gil talked last week about
self-respect for example and in my experience genuine sata
genuine confidence is rooted in some degree of self-respect we have a sense that we are able to do
something good we're able to meditate we're able to practice mindfulness
we're able to be in the world in a way that is somehow beneficial or at least to intend
that to move in that direction so some suitors say that um
this is a quote there are beings who are inspired by things that are lofty
it's kind of nice so we recognize we can recognize that there are things in the world that are lofty that are
pointing toward something [Music] jenny
and i remember one time being on a retreat that gill was teaching and he said that we should feel happy about
being on retreat because there are people in the world who are inspired simply by knowing that
there are people who go on retreat and so we are fulfilling that for them
so to have this kind of confidence or faith i think is a form of wealth like it says
in the teachings it enriches us to have a sense of
potential so then the second quality ethical
conduct or virtue this translates to the word sila
it's fairly straightforward the text says here a noble disciple abstains from the destruction of life
abstains from taking what is not given extinct abstains from sexual misconduct
abstains from false speech and abstains from intoxicants which are the basis for
hebesis so ethical conduct is the basis of
friendship and it's a form of inner wealth because it directly protects other beings and it also protects us
from our own difficulties and also it protects us by bringing what's called the bliss of blamelessness
[Music] i think you heard a lot a few weeks ago about celeb when yin for the whole week
on that so what i'll just say now is that this is a
time right now both specifically the holiday season but also this time in the
pandemic in our society when we really need people who are genuinely
positive forces in the world beneficial not the fake positivity of denial or
sugar-coating things but genuinely possessed of
some well-being and some sense of acting well in the world and even just just
doing our best with good intentions can do this for us ethics is actually meant
to be a basis for our own well-being which then translates out into the world
so i actually have a lot of faith that all of us are are working in that
direction [Music] so then moving on to generosity
the word that's translated that way is actually chaga which is the
movement of mind the intention in the heart toward giving you may have heard
the word donna which is more the actual gift that's given but chaga is the mind state that informs
that and the the text around this the sort of classical language is quite nice it says
here a noble disciple dwells at home with a heart devoid of the stain of
miserliness freely generous open-handed delighting in relinquishment devoted to charity to
lighting and giving and sharing it makes me happy just to read that you know it's so needed at this time
when it is or or even feels like a time of scarcity or threat or a high degree
of uncertainty psychologically the tendency is to hold
on or withdraw when actually exactly the opposite movement is what is beneficial
so generosity this chaga this inner movement toward giving helps us to give even when we feel like
we don't have very much so this is a good season to of course reflect on and practice generosity when
we can and then we go to wisdom panya
it's interesting that this is placed alongside the others sometimes people think of wisdom as
far off or some high accomplishment but it's placed right alongside these other three
and the texts say here a noble disciple is wise
she possesses the wisdom that discerns arising and passing away which is noble
and penetrative and leads to the complete destruction of suffering so that's interesting too buddhist texts
often equate wisdom with seeing impermanent impermanence and constancy
for our purposes now we can point out that people who pay attention to the way
so many things in life arise and change and pass are more likely to be able to handle
surprises or shocks when they come people who have a sense of the flow of life
how things come and go can stay calmer when there are large shifts such as what we've seen recently
in the world so i think this kind of wisdom is fairly natural when we've lived a life of
awareness we've paid attention to things how can you not notice that they come they go
even the even the body isn't constant from moment to moment and surely throughout our lives we've seen many things around our
eyes in the past but we can have some wisdom about that some groundedness some stability for
others so now let's consider them all together as a set this is a set of four
so we have confidence virtue generosity and wisdom so you can see that this encompasses
both individual and relational qualities it has a connection to the material
world as well as to the mind it encompasses everyday actions as well
as penetrating insight that can be quite deep so
recall that in the discourse about these four as the basis for good friendship they were collectively called being
mature in conduct so there's an element of maturity in
manifesting all of these we have to have some integration of the practice and of
our understanding in order to be able to do all of these well and maybe that there are some of course
that we do better than others another thing about these four qualities
is that they don't decrease if we keep practicing them and they can't really be taken away by
others they persist and they grow through all the ups and downs of life
so even if we go through periods where we have more wealth and less wealth periods where we're healthy and periods
where we're ill even as we get older and our faculties just diminish and we can see that the
body is winding down these four qualities can be continually increasing
they don't actually decrease so they're worth encouraging in ourselves and others you can see why
they're called inner wealth because they're really independent of the external
wealth that we don't have as much control over so we can also emulate these when we see
them in others if we see we have a friend who is very generous
you know without comparing ourselves unfavorably we could aspire to
be as free as they are in the way that they give or if we see someone who's very wise
and you know they just seem balanced and they seem able to flow along with things
they seem clear about what they're seeing we can consider oh yeah they seem to
really see things well maybe maybe i could um emulate that also so we're meant to help
each other in the practice meant to share in this so maybe
maybe you're visiting with people right now at this holiday time
we often are and i wonder if you can find one or more
of these qualities in some form in each of the people that you are
visiting with right now so even even if you have a history
of a difficult relationship with someone perhaps you can think of one way
that they express one of these qualities maybe they have some degree of
confidence confidence in what's good or maybe they have some kind of virtue
some kind of ethical conduct you know they're careful about not taking what's not given they're
careful about being truthful when they speak something maybe they have a streak of generosity
in them a way in which they give their attention their time physical
things or they have some kind of wisdom that you see in them a glimmer of it from time to time
so focus on that focus on the goodness of that person maybe even emulate it they don't have to
be perfect goodness knows we aren't all perfect or an exemplar of all four of
these qualities it's good enough if people are showing just a glimmer of one of them
take that as the basis for being with them in a kind and clear way
or if you're by yourself at this time of year we can it's good to reflect that these four things
are forms of inner wealth and they can be grown through meditative development through reflection
so either way this is a great time to be growing these particular qualities
of faith virtue to generosity and wisdom i hope this set of four may inform your
day and your week and maybe carry you into the new year so thank you very much
see you again tomorrow