so warm greetings for our meditation time
together and um
as i sit down to be here with you all and i'm thinking about
two things that uh and that is sacred presence
that which is present that feels deeply respect worthy inspiring
meaningful and sacred absence the absence which is
special respect worthy inspiring
and in this practice uh there's a very important role of absence what i call today
sacred absence and to recognize the absence of
clinging attachment hate preoccupation
and to recognize that absence is special respect worthy inspiring
it really helps open up this path of meditation and then with that sacred absence
the way that we are aware of what is present can have a sacred quality
maybe not exactly because what we're attending to is maybe sacred in
some way but the way that we're present for it our sacred presence our presence our attention
has qualities that are sacred and special and not to be overlooked
and there's always something here as we meditate which is absent
and uh if you go back even you know over your recent life
there have probably been things that you've been caught up in reacting to
consumed with driven by troubled by that those troubles and
those preoccupations maybe they've faded away and they're not here anymore
and it's possible to somehow be aware of their absence
and in that absence to have more room for awareness for
attention in that absence to receive
more fully the experience of breathing in that absence to connect more fully to
breathing and even in the much short term
if you're thinking about something in meditation and you're able to let go of it there's the absence of that
thinking there might be the absence of the drive
to think or the desire or the resentment or the whatever it was inspiring the thinking
to start recognizing the absence is a very important part of the deeper
dimensions of this anapanasati
and then not just to recognize the absence but recognize it as an opportunity to
bring have a sacred awareness a greater awareness and for the purpose
of this meditation for our breathing simply aware and
kind of committed to breathing in and breathing out
with awareness awareness awaringly
so to take a assume a meditation posture
and close your eyes
and and here we are there's a lot of things
absent just being used to meditate
for the time being the absence of maybe the busyness of the day or the
concerns that we have to things we have to do during the day
physically those things are not here now in our body working them
maybe some other concerns that you have for the day you can put up on a shelf and put aside for now
and let them be absent because they'll be picked up later
to help let go of things to be here to take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe three quarters full as you breathe in
and four fifths emptying the lungs as you exhale
and as you exhale to relax the body the whole frame
letting your breathing return to normal and relaxing
some more on the exhale and not only feeling the release of tension and holding
but to appreciate the absence of that holding
so to soften the belly
perhaps you can soften your chest
yeah relaxing and softening your shoulders
and calming the muscles of your face
and cooling down the
agitation associated with thinking
calming the thinking mind
and then appreciating absence not so much that you have to think about
what is absent but maybe there's some way you could intuit
the absence space the absence the freed up time the freedom thinking
the freedom attention
that's not preoccupied with the things that you have been preoccupied with
and here to allow this absence to become fuller
letting go of thoughts ideas
an absence which is related to the simplicity of this moment
just here now in
the sacred absence in which you
make room for your body's
breathing allowing in a sense the experience of breathing
to fill the space of awareness
a sacred absence that allows for sacred presence
a sacred attention
and when you find yourself thinking and you let go of it appreciate
whatever absence of thinking that then follows
and allow the breathing into that absence
so breathing begins to fill more and more
your field of awareness as if awareness fills the universe just
breathing
keep filling the absence with your breathing your experience body's experience of
breathing so that this sacred absence is not filled with
something else filled with thinking and wanting fantasy
so
whatever you're caught up in and thinking about beyond the edges of it is also
sacred absence
let go of your thoughts and preoccupations your tensions your holdings
let go into the great absence
fill that absence with the experience of breathing
allowing yourself to become very simple and quiet just breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
one form of sacred absence
is to make the heart as wide as the world
make lots of space in your heart in your care and your love and your
good will so there's a place inside of you
for all beings
and so to clear the space within
so that there's room for you to consider relate to
hold in your care others
and for them to fill the space of your heart
means to be very simple allowing them to be as they are
maybe a sacred presence
that everyone is respect worthy everyone in some way may be
independent or even how they're behaving some way deep inside something beautiful
and inspiring even if it's just a seed that's waiting to germinate
in sacred absence it within you that allows you to receive
and be present in a fuller caring way for others
and you don't have to say these words but maybe a care and a good will
that these words express or touch on
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we live caring for the welfare and happiness
of those around us
may this meditation practice
provide inspiration and ability
to walk through the world with care and good will
may all beings be well
you