so please gather yourself and prepare for
our meditation together
perhaps taking a long slow deep breath
and on the exhale allowing the body to soften
closing the eyes if that's comfortable for you
and just settling in [Music] to the sense of the body sitting
or if you're lying down in the sense of the body lying
maybe feeling how intimate it is to be in touch with the
body from the inside we do it all day in a sense i don't
always appreciate the sort of
close warm feeling of that
so connecting in with the body
perhaps softening [Music] the eyes and the eye sockets
the face all the little muscles on the scalp
softening down through the neck and the shoulders
letting the shoulders drop down naturally
down into the chest area sensing the three-dimensionality of the
rib cage front back sides
down into the belly
sensing how when we bring our attention into certain areas of the body
there's a way in which they come alive
somehow they were waiting for the illumination of awareness to
vibrate to offer some feeling to us
down into the hips the legs
even feeling into the knee and ankle joints
and including the hands and the feet
so the body sitting
sometimes as the stillness of the body settles in
then the motions of breathing become the most prominent thing we can
feel sensing the breathing body
the air coming in going out it's very simple
natural and yet we don't always bring attention
in an intimate detailed way
allowing the gentle sensations of the breath to calm
[Music] the feelings in the body
when we treat the body with this kind of gentleness and open attention
there's a response inside if we treat the body as a friend it may
begin to feel like our friend
sense it's what's closest to us
so finding some rest in the home of the body
even if there's discomfort or tiredness or stiffness
there can still be a sense that the mindfulness of that
is helpful supportive
there's a way in which the body is also
one of the ways that we can connect to the mind
so much information in the body related to the mind
you may sense that you have some emotions present
[Music] some mood that's coloring your
experience right now [Music] feeling into how that is
manifesting in the body
sometimes we feel heat in certain areas
associated with our mental state
we feel tightness sometimes
fear will cause us to raise the shoulders up in tension
or anger can be felt as heat and tightness in the stomach area
many emotions are in the throat area
could we get curious about the way in which our body's current
manifestation the current feelings we have in the body are related to our mind state
our emotions
having that curiosity about the body
is a way of not being so entangled in those particular emotions but instead
learning about them being with them in a kind helpful way
perhaps allowing the in and out breathing to pass through any areas of tension
just resting with this dynamic experience of the body
um
[Music]
and when the mind gets caught up in thinking
analyzing remembering planning
we can just gently reopen awareness to the experience of the body
body is always in the present moment
and it might be interesting in today's exploration of mindfulness of
the body to notice
if when you've been thinking there was any impact on the body
in the same way that emotions can bring tension and heat and
other changes to the body so too
thinking has effects effects
it's interesting to learn for ourselves what those are
do certain tensions appear certain changes in sensations when we've
had a bout of thinking
so in this type of exploration it's it's okay to get caught up in thought
because you're learning afterwards what impact that had
hmm
[Music]
you
and as mindfulness of the body deepens further
perhaps as the mind gets a bit calmer we may be able to feel
the sensations associated with thinking as it is occurring
is there a particular place from which thinking seems to originate
your body
often it's in the head
is there a change in the sense of the rest of the body
while there is a thought going on [Music]
is there a change in how mindfulness feels when it is
knowing a thought or knowing the body when there isn't a thought present
and as we stay with mindfulness of the body
we may begin to sense that the body also has
deep sensations of peace available to it
the peace and ease that we've cultivated in our mind
can be felt through the body
perhaps as a deep stability
or as a beautiful space within the body
it's something that feels very true and reliable and
beautiful
perhaps a refuge
so we may come to value the body
mindfulness of the body as our friend in a way
something we might bring with us throughout the day
helping us to stay balanced and open with the people we encounter
perhaps remembering also that they too have bodies
they too work with this physical part of being
it's one thing that connects us with others
and if we have made our body our home somewhere safe
something that gives us useful information something that supports us
and there's a way in which we also are supporting others
when we bring our full bodily presence into our life
we help others to stay connected and stay present in some way
we can't always see it
but it's a very worthy effort
so perhaps as you go about your day or evening
you can consider how the body might come along with you as a
friend
supporting you to be present be of service
be more kind loving compassionate
generous all of which bring beautiful feelings in the body as well as the mind
only all beings learn to be at ease
in their bodies
so for those of you who may have joined a little bit later
you can see that gill is not here and i just want to pass along that he is
fine he was planning to be here but then he had to travel unexpectedly
so as i said everything is fine my name is kim allen and i'll be here for the rest
of this week i know that gil was planning to speak this whole week on the topic of patience
so uh this monday's topic of staying true under stress is perhaps relevant this
week it's um always a bit stressful to have a rapid change in circumstances or
a change of plans so that's something that we can all practice embodying
us along with gil for this week and then i also thought that
it might be more meaningful for you to explore the topic of patience if you have to wait until next week to
do it so we'll have a different theme for the next four days
i'll be talking about different ways of using the body
as one's field of practice and um i'm calling this series the depth
of the body because we may not realize just how profound this very
basic body is so today i will
talk about mindfulness of the body as a friend
a way that we can have a support for our practice at all times
and then tomorrow we'll talk about um the four bodily knots
it's an um a list found in the teachings that's not taught very often four bodily
knots and then thursday we'll talk about the body as a support for concentration
for the gathering and stilling of the mind and on friday we'll talk about the body
as a vehicle of insight even liberating insight
so today is mindfulness of the body and the buddhist teachings
are just filled with ways that we can cultivate and get support
from mindfulness of the body and in particular there is a story
about the time that the buddha died and his cousin and attendant
ananda you may have heard that name he was very distraught naturally
he had been of course not only was he the buddha's cousin but he had been his personal attendant for
at least a couple of decades at that point and was of course very connected to him
and it hurt him deeply that his cousin had passed on and he
wasn't sure what you know what he was going to do after that and so but he did eventually go on with
his practice and became awakened and at that point he composed an awakening poem
as a number of the elder monks did and this is a little section from ananda's awakening poem
i'm completely disoriented the teachings don't spring to mind
with the passing of our good friend everything seems dark
when your friend has passed away your teacher is passed and gone there's
no friend like mindfulness of the body
so it's interesting right in that moment he came up with the idea of mindfulness
of the body as a friend so i want to talk a bit about mindfulness of the body as a
friend there are many ways of course to engage mindfulness of the body
many of them are talked about in the um discourse called the sati patana suta
the most basic instructions that we have about cultivating mindfulness of of all
different realms of experience but there's quite a long section about mindfulness of the body
and this this teaching includes a number of areas
one of them is the simple mindfulness of breathing in and out as we did during the meditation
one way this can be used is simply to calm the body it's always available the breath you
know it's something that we can touch into many different times during the day or
especially on the cushion and it's often at least as long as you haven't had difficult experiences with
the breath it's often a way to calm the body because it's a kind of a natural
rhythm coming in going out we can feel some ease through that
so this is one way that mindfulness is can be seen as quite friendly
there's also in this suta the mindfulness of postures [Music]
so literally knowing whether or not you are sitting or standing or walking or lying
down whatever posture you're in you just have conscious awareness that
that is the posture that the body is in i think it's a great way to start doing
mindfulness of the body practice in daily life so for example you could notice right now
that whatever posture you're in are you sitting maybe and do you know just take a moment to
know that you're sitting how you know that because you can feel the body in that posture
and you might notice that just breaking this to mind has a slight clarifying effect on the
mind there's a little sharpening of attention when we know a posture we're in
and since we're always in some posture this is a great way that we can
sharpen our mind up at any moment bring it into the present if it's in somewhere
else and just being clear about how we're how our body is disposed as
the way the suta says it and then another very
simple way to be mindful of the body is mindfulness of actions so this gets more specific to knowing what
it is we're doing at a given moment and the pseudo lists all kinds of things of
knowing that we're extending our arm or pulling it in knowing of course which posture we're in
knowing if we're talking or not knowing we're eating chewing swallowing even urinating and defecating
everything is included nothing is left out of what it is that we're doing
and so this is of course the yet another way to connect in and just be present
but i would say it goes farther in the case of knowing our specific actions then this practice becomes a basis for
ethical action so when we are noticing what we're doing
we can't help but be more aware of the quality of our actions
even when we bring in you know the supposedly neutral awareness of what we're doing
you know just knowing yes i'm raising the cup to my lips and having a
sip of water it's very natural as we do that
to also notice the quality of that action are we doing it in a hurried way are we
angry while we're doing it do we have an intention of harm in some way
so these things become much more available when we have mindfulness of actions
so this is really our friend right looking out for our ethical quality
so just recognizing what it is that we're doing as we're doing it is a great support for bringing more wholesomeness
into our life and then
as we get more familiar with these top-level actions of ways of being
mindful of the body and of course they can go very deep i don't mean to cast them only as surface level they can go
very deep but a new layer starts to get revealed when we tune into the subtler aspects of
the body you know there's kind of an energetic presence to the body often we feel it maybe more in
meditation but as we as we practice that it becomes more available in daily life
so sort of like the way we can't really hear you know bird song
or quiet music when we're standing on a busy street we don't always feel this underlying
energetic sensations of the body if we're rushing around in our daily life
but as we learn to feel them on the cushion they become more available to us off the cushion
and these these energetic sensations are more where those emotional
feelings are housed you know the the rush of energy that we feel when there's
anger coming up in the mind or the kind of slight heaviness that we feel in the
body when there's sadness or depression this is great information the way that
the mindfulness of the body if we carry it throughout the day can help us connect with our mind you
know sometimes in the press of being with other people or being on the computer or something else
our mind is going very fast and if we aren't tuned into the body we can miss
some of what's going on for us and then we may react in ways that we don't understand or regret later so the body
has a lot of information in it as we and if we practice that on the cushion then we'll be able to bring that more into
our interactions so feeling the emotions and then one area that i emphasized in
the in the sit that i find i found very meaningful in my own practice
is to check in and tune into the relationship between thought and the body
it's not often emphasized but thinking actually does have an impact
in particular i've noticed that when i am thinking a lot on the cushion and i'm
trying to meditate but my mind is busy each time i return to
present moment awareness whatever my object was i noticed that there is kind of tendrils
of tension that run down from the head down into the shoulders and the chest
and into the neck can feel these um ways in which the thought has
tightened up certain channels in the body somehow and so if we can tune into that a little
bit sooner we may not get lost in thought quite as easily and also we may
learn to think in ways that are a little bit more healthy sometimes the
extreme tension that comes in with thought is because we've really gotten wrapped up in a story about ourself or a
thought of revenge or some other kind of thinking it's not actually very helpful
for our practice and there are there are kinds of thought that are more helpful than others
and you know for example thoughts about the dharma or thoughts about
ways that we can be helpful or things like that ways we could support people still thinking but it is
you know more conducive to our practice more in line with wholesomeness and
those kinds of thoughts you will notice don't produce quite as much tension
in the body in the belly or the chest or the throat so again we have
information coming in through mindfulness of the body that we might not have if we try only to see the mind
body is a great gateway into the mind so this is once again our friend our
friend mindfulness of the body helping us out in our practice helping us to learn more about this experience of
being human so that we can bring forth the best of that in our life
so once we start to see the body as a helpful experience to pay attention to
and we gain some skill in tuning into a variety of aspects of it like
physical feelings and the quality of our actions and also the more subtle energies that
tell us about emotions and thoughts then we're setting the stage to explore
also many other dharma practices that use the body and those are going to be the topics
that unfold as we go on with the week so we'll continue with that tomorrow
and i look forward to seeing you then if you can come
so be well you