so as i've been talking over these last
days about the 13th step
of mindfulness of breathing being
you're being the observation
settling back and observing the
inconstancy of phenomena
how things are constantly renewing but
also constantly passing
and that appearing and disappearing of
our experience moment by moment
certainly sometimes it's unfortunate
that things pass away
sometimes we're very fortunate that
finally it's no longer here
and sometimes we're fortunate that
things are
are arising and sometimes it's
unfortunate what's arising
it's painful or something and sometimes
it's neutral
so there's no particular um
prioritizing or valuing or or how to say
it
putting a value on the particular
arising of passings that occur
it's not it's not a discounting of
things it's not a
celebrating of things necessarily it's
just
seeing that actually this is kind of the
nature of
when we're really settled really
peaceful not overlaying concepts and
ideas on top of experience
can we can kind of um that's what we
experience we're in the flow of our
experience flow of
sensations and experience
and but the great value of it is not in
and of itself like we're supposed to
celebrate it or supposed to
be depressed by it or something it's uh
that we can't it's it becomes a
reference point
for how valuable it is not to cling to
any of it
not to contract around any of it not to
resist any of it
and especially and in meditation
in real life you know there's certain
things that should be held onto
or resisted perhaps but in meditation to
really learn to free ourselves from
any movement of being for against
holding on or pushing away
and because the kind doesn't work but
also because
this ability to observe and not get
engaged and attached to things
begins feeling so good i feel that's
where freedom is
and uh and the core kind of uh
catalyst for freedom in the teachings of
the buddha
is this experience this deep insight
into inconstancy
and so the way in which the more free we
become
the more inconsistency is a support for
greater freedom
the more free we are the more we see
recognize how we're
trying to hold on to what is constantly
changing or how we've
left the flow or how we you know like
put our hand out the window of a car and
we have wind drag
we're going to have wind drag we put our
hands into the river and trying to stop
it
we picked up a bunch of handful of water
and we left the river
thinking we have the river still there's
all these ways in which we recognize
that we've we've kind of left the flow
of inconstancy the flow of life
because we've gotten excessively
attached or involved or
clinging and so see that in meditation
and to see that we're actually better
off uh
backing off better off not clinging that
it's not so
interesting to cling or to want and so
there's a begins to be an
inner psychological change that happens
and
some of that is starting to become a
a relaxing the search
relaxing they're trying to do something
or get something
or relaxing the need to know
and searching to know and because all
that is kind of
is too much it's like leaning forward
when we can just settle back
in the sense and then the
uh all these attachments we have starts
we start feeling them as being wind drag
we start feeling them as being
um interfering with the the
radiance of the heart the beauty of the
mind the freedom of
of of our lives and we can see that
they diminish us the clinging the
attachments that we have things we hold
on to and so there starts to be a fading
away
disinterest and a fading away
of uh jealousy and envy and conceit
and and craving and
hatred and resentments
you know you can go on the list is long
of things that we begin recognizing oh
this doesn't really serve me this
i'm not so interested in this anymore
it's not like i have to be a good
buddhist and this is bad that i'm doing
this that i have to stop doing it
it's more like i'm no longer interested
in this
this is less and less interesting to do
i've been resentful for
30 years and i think that i'm getting
tired of it i think i see
that it's not so interesting i've been
chasing after
having the perfect physical physique for
decades and at some point i'm not really
interested in
presenting myself always with the
perfect human physique whatever that
might be
and we start losing interest in it uh
always wanting to make more money or
have status or
i don't know what to all these things
we're kind of chasing there's a healthy
kind of
oh wait a minute this doesn't serve me
this is not the best place to be this is
not the most wonderful way to be
to be preoccupied with these things i'm
beginning to know something better
i'm knowing something about freedom and
ease and peace
and i want to stress over again that the
primary reference point for what i'm
talking about here now
is in fact meditation because
outside of meditation you might argue
well wait a minute
isn't it okay to do it here or here we
need to do it here
i don't want to get into those
discussions what i want you
is to really discover that in meditation
you don't have to be
pursuing the perfect physique more money
more status more
whatever it is that you're trying to do
in meditation you can feel it meditation
itself it's
better easier just to let go or not be
involved
and then to really have an experience a
qualitatively high experience of freedom
of ease of peace where we're no longer
grasping or holding or resisting or
tightening or contracting
that becomes your teacher rather than
debating me
with me about wait a minute aren't you
supposed to hold on here or
resist that it's not so interesting to
debate with me
it's really for real spiritual life you
should be debating with yourself
when you have this deep reference point
for peace
deep deep reference point for freedom
that's that's where it gets really
interesting that's where it really
comes alive this practice of freedom
and uh and really kind of explore and
find out what
what is really true for yourself
so with this uh observing and constancy
then there's a fading away of the
interest in some of our attachments
and then there's a fading away of the
attachments themselves
and and so
the word for the 13th
step of anapanasati the pali word is
v raga v i
r a g a and uh
there's two different translations of
this word and the one that i'll
stress today is um it means the fading
away
when observes the fading of the fading
away of these attachments
and the fading away of
of our interest their our addiction to
uh addictive interest in in certain
things that are not really serving us
anymore
and so they're fading away or fading
away and this speaks to something very
important about this path of liberation
in buddhism
that sometimes there's a tendency to
want to look for
you know a sudden experience that the
key to it all that just unlocks it all a
number free forever
just like but a more mature way of
seeing it is that
a lot of it has to do with just fading
away fading away
a wearing away dropping away
drop by drop everything
dries up or falls away the evaporating
of it
phenomena of our attachment and
so raga the root of the word viraga
can mean a dye that we call our cloth
with
and the raga the prefix means of fading
away or separating of that dye
and so one of the meanings is to fade
away the dye you put
you know you dye some clothes and you
leave it in the sun for too long and
it gets bleached to get the color fades
away and so or just time
fades it away and so the fading away the
fading away
and um and this uh when we really feel
the
the um unsatisfactoriness the
the offness the the
discomfort of attachment of clinging of
addiction of
all these movements of the mind that we
have
and we start to feel ah
this is lightening up it's loosening up
there's a
lightening a lifting a lifting of a
cloud and
letting go relaxing and then the
mindfulness practice is to be available
to that fading to be
open to that fading to allow for that
fading
because if we go right back into
clinging we reinforce more clinging
we strengthen that capacity to cling and
attach and resist and
be addicted to things but once we start
feeling this process of fading away
then the mindfulness practice is to be
available to that fading
available to it so we don't reinforce
the opposite
so one trains
breathing in observing
fading away one trains breathing out
observing fading away
and uh and uh
so that's one of the meanings of the
araga and then tomorrow
i'll talk a little bit about the second
meaning which is
dispassion and uh
at least that's all you often how it's
translated into english
and um and probably not a very good
translation but
that's for tomorrow so
thank you and this comes to an end