so
hello everyone thank you for being here
and
today the theme is release in relationship to emotions
now this uh process of being with emotions
to do so in a healthy mindful way
uh increases our capacity to feel wholesome emotions
and one of those is joy delight kind of happiness
and it's useful when engaged in mindfulness to
remember to allow for joy
it's maybe easy to overlook easy to think other things are more important
but some degree of joy supports the process of waking up here in the present moment
and we might think about that to release letting go
is really works really is significant or
appropriate when there is something in the family of joy in the process of letting go of
releasing it feels good it feels right and
so in these five kind of kind of kind of underlying themes threads
for each of these weeks it's relaxation recognition
respect restoration and release
each of those steps has a little bit of release in it each of the first four
and each of the first four and having a little bit of release it might be possible to look for
a peaceful joy a peaceful delight or well-being appreciation
that maybe is not evaluative it just kind of feels like it's part of it
so with relaxation it's one thing to relax and appreciate
and feel that feel the good of it but maybe it's possible to also appreciate a little little joy or
delight that oh this is good this is a good fortune to be able to let
go to release all that recognition is also a kind of release
because when we learn the simplicity of recognition really simply just knowing something in and of itself
and then for that moment at least we've stepped away from being entangled
with it judging it uh identifying with it it's just recognizing oh that's that
so if there is pain someplace in the body it's difficult to be with pain i don't
want to belittle or minimize the difficulty but in the moment of recognition
there is a kind of freedom there's a kind of letting go and it may be less just a fleeting moment of the
recognition but to learn to recognize the letting go the release that happens in their
recognition and there's that potential in recognition
to respect what's happening is also a letting go of our disrespect our entanglement our cotness
and um and there too there's a kind of releasing of something that made the relationship maybe more
complicated need to be and i think of deep respect to reality to ourselves to others
that there's a release that is joyful there rather than being subservient to offer
respect to someone it's actually a freeing of ourselves
restoration to feel to allow for the movement of energy in the body
the healing the processing the the unfolding of of our life to trust it
and open to it and feel the goodness of how that unfolds is also a kind of release getting out of
the way and all this kind of sets the stage for
appreciating the the joy the value the wonderfulness of really being free
and which is release so i'm going to guide you in this today
a little bit more of an exercise perhaps in two rounds of release
of going through this process of uh these four or five processes with
idea that each time there's a kind of release and once just kind of do to settle in
and once in relationship to emotions
so um and i apologize to those of you who want more silence for this and hopefully
you'll get it another time meditating on your own so
to us to assume your meditation pro
posture and
lower your gaze and lowering your gaze can you relax your eyes
and with your eyes relaxed if it feels appropriate to close your eyes
and with your eyes closed can you relax your gaze some more
letting your eyes rest in the eye sockets
and to make smoke with the eyes closed maybe you can be a tune and tune into
your body a little bit more make small adjustments in your posture
and then as you take two or three four deep inhales
let the exhale be a release of letting go a long sustained
gentle letting go as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and to go through the body to relax it some more as you breathe normally
but as you relax if it's possible to relax these parts of the body
see if you can have some enjoyment of that or some joy or appreciation delight
it could be very very faint but see if you can recognize the goodness of letting go of relaxing
so softening relaxing the muscles of your face
softening relaxing the shoulders
as you exhale relaxing the chest
and as you exhale relaxing the belly
and as you exhale a global relaxation throughout the body
and then to recognize
as simple and relaxed uncomplicated way that you can
recognize how you are in the simplest way
and it is such a way that there's a little bit of letting go in their recognition
letting go of our judgments and entanglements
letting go of being foreign against
recognition that's a kind of opening to experience
that has some modicum of a joy
good feeling to let go of the entanglement and just
recognize just let things be as they are and recognize them
and however you are right now can you respect it
letting go of anything that could be that gets in the way of respect
let's let's letting go of anything that
doesn't honor
whatever experience you have at this moment of being alive
any judgments or stories you have about who you are and what's
happening it doesn't respect the
aliveness of the moment
and then to allow the restoration
to trust that there's something here within you
that if allowed to process will heal and repair and
cultivate develop unfold healthy way
to let go of being the engineer of our experience let go of
more judgments of it or resistance to it and feel the goodness the joy of
allowing this our system
to find its way
and then we come to release and with every exhale
let go let go of thoughts let go of
preoccupations let go of preferences
and in the letting go can you recognize
some degree of joy or goodness in doing so
and then ever so gently
see if you can make a very small smile with your lips
smile of joy and see if turning up the corners of
your mouth produces any pleasant feelings for you
however subtle
and if there is any pleasant feeling or any joy
relax into that keep the half smile
but relax into the pleasure of it the joy of
it recognize the joy the pleasure
in the smile or in just being alive breathing down
and in recognizing it staying simple with it letting go of
complications and doubts and protests
respecting your embodied capacity
to feel joy well-being happiness
breathe with it
and allow for restoration healing allow for some kind of
whatever wants to happen as this simple joy
calm quiet joy or well-being is given space to be here
and then release any grasping or holding
release any resistance or any stressful feelings related to
how you are and maybe feel the quiet joy
of release
and then in the middle of it all centering yourself on the breathing
and the more you give yourself over to breathing
the more all five of these processes the five hours
have a chance to grow and unfold trusting yourself with the breathing
letting there be a joy and breathing in and breathing out
you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting there's a letting go
releasing that allows us to turn our hearts out to
the world not as a duty or an obligation
but that the alternative is to stay closed or stay
limited and to allow our freedom
our liberation or release have a chance to become full
we also want to allow our capacity to feel
to know to empathize
to be open to the world around us to the people we know our neighbors our friends
strangers people in our community
and what is it to let go and so that we can capacity to
empathize to feel to know to connect
can grow
so they can be a channel for our good will
our care for the world and to turn our attention to
offering care to the world at the end of a sitting is a way of
supporting protecting even our freedom
may it be that through our care
that we promote the happiness of others
may it be through our care that we support the safety of others
may it be through our presence that we offer
a peacefulness to others and may it be through our own freedom
that we help spread a spiritual freedom in this world
may all beings everywhere be happy
so here on the fifth talk on mindfulness of emotions
where we've talked about release release in relationship to emotions
i think i said this at the beginning as well that um some emotions
are a product or arise together with stress with tension
and in some emotions a flow with the lack of tension the lack of
stress and generally the unwholesome emotions the ones that are
afflictive that are painful to have or which motivate kind of harmful activity in the world
that those come with stress and so as we release the stress release
the tension the tightness uh those afflictive unwholesome emotions
tend to have less energy less juice less nourishment to keep going
the emotions the sense of well-being that we can have when there's no stress
no tension that then that tends to support to make room for the wholesome movements
and so the absence of stress tends not to
result in more afflictive emotions but rather the beneficial emotions the
supportive emotions and nourishing emotions love joy delight happiness
care compassion contentment
gladness tranquility and calm and
a whole slew of things like this and
the um so this release to really learn how to release and let go
it doesn't leave us kind of emotionally neutral kind of like a blank
what it does it might be initially that way for a little while uh as a transition because if we're really used
to swirling and fear anxiety swirling and anger resentments swirling and desires
and ambition that we're comfortable some people are comfortable with that
and so when they let go of that there's the energy the motivation this the charge that they've been living their
life on is lacking and nothing has replaced it yet and can feel blank for a while
but it's kind of like you know giving up coffee and having spent three days adjusting to that until
kind of a natural vitality comes back same thing with as we switch from spending a lot of time with afflictive
difficult emotions it may be a lifetime there's a
transition but as that transition unfolds and the the lack of tension and stress is there
that makes room for these beneficial emotions and um and uh
and then they uh i know so i think that's kind of i find it kind of humorous or delightful
that as these beneficial emotions arise any movement to cling to them to resist
them or want to hold on to them is stress
and is the very opposite moves us in the opposite direction from
what they're all about so it's kind of like uh you know uh
you know rubbing a cat putting a cat against the against the
the hair or the way the hair lays down and all the hair gets kind of bunched up and rised up rather than flat down
or going against the grain of the wood uh to cling to these emotionally good
emotions so it's kind of like a tendency to want to hold on to them or do do do with them it's there but at the
same time you know you can't do it it doesn't make sense to do it it's not appropriate to do it it's actually
and so it's kind of i find it kind of humorous to be in that in that middle spot there and
and uh and you know and then just you know just delight and just that oh i can't do anything with it i
can't hold on to it i have to let go i can't make it mine i can't you know be in charge of it in a certain
way or claim it and it's a there's that there's freedom in relationship to them
so but some people don't understand or haven't been told or learned
that as we practice those matures and as it letting go deepens
the connection to our inner life deepens to life deepens that there's also joy and well-being and
happiness it doesn't have to be dramatic sometimes has a quiet feeling to it
but to avail ourselves that to make room for that release is not only about what we let go
of it's also what we make room for and
and in that making a room for there's a lot of peace and i think the two words two concepts
of the buddha most commonly uh used to describe how someone is when
there's been a deep letting go deep release is peace and happiness
and peaceful happiness happy peace peace and happiness
and i don't think we can go too wrong with those in the forefront especially
when those are the very conditions that allow for our deepest
or fullest forms of care for the world to operate as well because there's nothing it interferes
with it there's no blocks to it so to let go deeply
and uh in relationship to emotions uh to let go of the stories we have
about it to like go over the preferences we have about the our emotional life to be able
to tease apart all the different component parts of what's happening when we have emotions and find the place of
holding and sometimes the clinging and the holding is not in the emotion itself
but in the in the way in which we relate to the emotion the knowing the directedness of
attention the uh the attitude we have about it the ways we're
thinking about it and so sometimes we have to kind of turn away from the emotion per se
and look more at the attitude more at the the directedness of mind or the
the engagement of the mind in the emotion to find a place where something can let go and relax
and um and to let go to relax to
release and to appreciate every moment of release
so it becomes that's kind of a positive reinforcement for release we start recognizing that
release letting go is a healthy thing a good thing to learn to let go enough so we learn
the skill of letting go we learn when it's appropriate to let go to learn we learned how to let go
appropriately one of the things i had to learn was if i let go
but there was i was kind and i was kind of emotionally neutral he would come back and bite me i didn't
really hadn't really let go to really have let go in a healthy way that
there had to be some modicum some degree of joy or lightness
that came in the wake of it so to release
let go and you might try it you might try when you have emotions of
all kinds especially when you're in the grip of them are strong
maybe you have to kind of pull yourself away from the situation you're in go for a walk or sit down or something
and and just kind of maybe go through these you know just
letting go in a deep way maybe go through these five hours um and some people really like going
through a systematic process that keeps them engaged and focused and so
to relax recognize respect restore and then release but all those
are a form of letting go and um and uh or involve some degree of letting
go release so
thank you for this in my experience my practice life
one of the byproducts of release letting go of releasing releasing the stress
is a profound gratitude it's a tremendous feeling of gratitude and and now it's one of the i think i've
been one of the great gifts of this practice and it's a gratitude which
often i haven't sometimes i feel grateful for particular things the practice the buddha the
community i'm practicing with many things but the one that kind of gratitude that
i've i find the most i don't know somehow meaningful or satisfying or
profound or something joyful is the gratitude that it's just grateful
for no reason just grateful and just just a feeling of gratitude
gratefulness and um so emotions
done a week on emotions and i hope that this has given you a new
perspective on how to live with emotions practice with emotions appreciate emotions
and and that it supports you and brings you a greater
sense of well-being and maybe even some gratitude for this life of ours
so thank you all very much