i'm going to today i'm going to discuss
the
seventh step of anapanasati
seven steps of breathing in and
breathing out the buddha's teachings on
breath meditation
and the way it's worded it says one
trains oneself
breathing in one experiences
uh the activity of mind
the mental formations the construct
construction constructing activity of
the mind
and in the simple ways is called the
activity of the mind
breathing out one experiences the
and this is a really rich topic what the
mind is the
holy word is chitta ci tta
and it's um you know
a rich and wonderful topic and i'll
touch on some of it as we go along here
but in
simple terms in english we might call it
the mind
and but one of the
main activities of the mind for many of
us
is thinking and
and to uh so to become aware
of thinking and there's two different
ways to become aware that i'm
emphasizing here
one is to become to observe it
just to know what's happening and the
other is to
really experience it uh to feel the
experience to feel what it's like to be
thinking
and both are important and to learn to
recognize and know and observe thinking
is many times a stepping stone to
feeling it and experiencing it more
fully
so as always with this mindfulness of
breathing there's always this
the rhythm the background beat or the
foreground beat
of breathing that's we're getting
centered on and focused on
and and
settling in on and uh and the breathing
protects us a little bit
from getting caught up in the world of
thinking
to be resting or focusing or
stable on the breathing then as was more
more stable
the more awareness can begin to open up
and be more expensive more inclusive
to be able to take in more and more
what's going on
and and was a stable
attack stable present presence attention
to breathing
it's possible to be aware of thinking
without being bothered by thinking
without making it into a problem or i
think it said you know it's wrong to
think in meditation or to be upset
about it or to call it even a
distraction
and the reason why we can why it's
easier not to be bothered
is because there's not a very strong
pull into that world
we don't get lost in it very much but
it's also true that even if we do get
lost in it
we're better off not being bothered by
it
being upset being agitated because we
think
is a recipe for perpetuating the
thinking
the more agitated we are the more the
mind tends to want to produce thoughts
and ideas
stories and so the art of not being
bothered not being upset
not being attached to thinking but also
not being aversive to thinking
not making your thinking your very best
friend
and not making thinking your enemy
either
it's just thinking is happening and to
be aware of thinking going by
and the classic image in buddhism is
having thoughts drift by
like clouds and an endless sky
it's just clouds and i love the metaphor
of clouds for thinking
because you know you if you put your
hand into a cloud
you don't get anything maybe get a
little bit moist but you know there's no
solidity there just like you can put
your hand right through
and it turns out that thinking is not is
actually less solid
than a cloud and uh there's no
you know it's it's a it's kind of a
virtual reality thing
their thoughts but it's the
what we invest in our thinking the
attachment the engagement the all the
energy we put into it
that makes thinking sometimes actually
more
solid and more real and more important
than almost anything else in our lives
we can get so wrapped up in our stories
and our ideas and our thoughts
and and the paradox here is that the
more
energy we put into thinking the more
we're trying hard to
you know anxiously think or be attached
to it
we actually think less effectively
um the most creative the most innovative
the most
wise the most loving the most beneficial
way of thinking
tends to be without a lot of extra
energy
there can be a choice to focus on some
things to think about in daily life
but to do it with an easy relaxed mind
and that ability to stay focused and
very relaxed
allows the thinking mind to be most
productive most creative
maybe there are exceptions but
for many people it's the exception to
every ever approach this idea of a
you know a creative mind that's relaxed
think thinking relax thinking
and so to learn not to be bothered by
our thinking
is very important one of the useful
skills to learn in meditation
to have this wisdom not to be caught up
in it or foreign against it to have a
certain equanimity
and to be patient with the mind wonders
often thought to keep coming back
keep coming back starting over again
starting over again
but at some point now it was at the
seventh step of anapanasati
with the idea that seven step now
there's some stability there some
centering on the breath ability to stay
with the breathing more continuously
and of course that comes and goes that
ability
and many of us will start at step one of
anapanasati
um regularly and like i'm just beginning
and that's completely fine but at some
point as we settle in
maybe the end of a long sit meditation
or maybe
you know conditions come together where
there's enough stability here
that we can becoming aware of thinking
and um in a way that it's like clouds in
the endless sky we just
there's a kind of almost we don't get
too caught in it we don't get focused on
it but we are aware
and there's a few things that are
interesting to notice when we can do
this
one is to notice whether we think more
in words
or more in images
and some people it's one or the other
and some people come some combination of
both
and but you know maybe one predominates
over the other
and because once you recognize uh
what your primary quality of thinking is
you can investigate something more and
that is
where does that operate so where is the
if it's avoid inner voice which is
speaking
where's the loudspeaker or where's the
inner mouth that's doing the speaking
the vocal cord or something
sometimes and people generally feel it's
behind
their forehead it's kind of somewhere in
the area of what we call the brain for
many
modern people in the ancient world it
seems
still to the modern world in in places
in buddhist asia
and if uh people associate the heart
center with where
where they're where they are thinking
and maybe some of you do as well but i
think a tendency in the
in the modern west at least is the point
to the head
and partly because you know the brain
has such a big role in thinking that
you know we gravitate towards there and
associated with air but you know the the
work the words might be spoken somewhere
inside
and or if you see if you're thinking in
images
it might be like a scene just in front
of you with the eyes closed
it might be like a projection screen or
or a scenery that's in front of you
there's
kind of some directionality it's there
that we're sensitive watching it
and that sense of a location for the
inner voice
if you can find it or the directionality
of seeing an image is a
is a is a means by which to know or
start noticing the extra energy that
goes into thinking
if it's an inner voice there's often a
kind of contraction and tightness
and pressure if there's a lot of extra
energy that goes into thinking
if it's a lot of imagery there might
also be a contraction or tightness
but it might be in a different location
for some people it might
actually be around their physical eyes
even with the eyes closed
because they're seeing of an image
there's a kind of
habit maybe of engaging the eyes to kind
of focus on the image
and so there might be tension in the eye
area
but by noticing the location where
thinking seems to be occurring
it's also possible to notice how much
energy is being expended for this
and the and the emotions that might be
connected to the energy
and so um to um
you know start seeing there's more to
thinking
than just the thoughts more to thinking
just the images
there's the energy that's involved the
tensions that are involved
the pressure there is the interest
that's involved with thinking
the curiosity the the being glued or
lobbed
you know locked onto it sometimes it can
be the feeling
there can be some emotionality connected
to thinking
that's may sometimes the emotions are
the fuel for it or the source for what
we're thinking about
and so it's possible to to step back
in a sense settle back and just observe
thinking
and without necessarily observing the
content of the thought
the content is often not so important
for the purpose of meditation
but the associated aspects of thinking
the energy the tension the
directionality the location
the emotionality to it the interest we
have to it
all those not to study them and get too
active but all those
you can step back and kind of observe
and and that gives you access
to the instructions to experience
the mental activity so in this case
to exp to experience what it's like to
be thinking
or to say it differently to really feel
it
feel it somatically physically almost
even though it's mental there might be
some the sensations
of thinking and
and this and this allows us to not be so
and the more we kind of disinvest
ourselves from the story and the ideas
and but
without dismissing the thinking and
experiencing different parts of thinking
thinking that by itself tends to become
quieter and stiller
and and as thinking becomes quieter and
stiller
then that's then we may be able to
better
more fully stay with the in-breath and
the out breath
focusing on the body breathing and
and do so maybe with more sense of ease
more sense of well-being that comes
along just the simplicity the
contentment
being content just to be present and
breathe
more often than not the discontent about
life and the impatience
belongs to the realm of thinking and
or fueled by thinking
so
this is not an instruction to get really
busy
to notice and focus on thinking but
rather to stay with your breathing
and and don't be bothered by it don't be
troubled by it
but as it becomes relevant
to touch into an extreme being
experiencing
feeling what's happening as you breathe
and and maybe with the idea that you're
breathing
through the thinking breathing with your
thinking so the breathing supports
you're not getting caught
in whatever you're thinking about but
you can just observe it and feel it
so um
may you develop a new relationship with
your thinking
don't assume that the way that you think
is the way it has to be
there might be wonderful delightful
relaxing creative and
wise ways of thinking they could
take a very different form than how
you're thinking these days usually
so thank you very very much and i look
forward to seeing you tomorrow