so today is the part two of
the equanimity factor of awakening
and um
you know it's also part of this series
on
mindfulness of breathing which the
buddha presented a little bit like a
path
that as we stay present for our breath
that we're cultivating and deepening the
meditation practice
um with a deep relaxation of the body a
deep relaxation of the
mind until
we're not just focused on the details of
our life the particular activities of
the body
or the mind but we start becoming aware
of
the mind state the state of mind the
quality of our mind
the feeling of kind of the gestalt or
the
wholeness of awareness that can just be
here holding it all
and it's a fairly you know mature
place in meditation that we might fall
into occasionally where
the the the mind state is more salient
more
prominent than the particular details of
what's happening in our body or the
details what's happening in our mind
all of these all of the all of the above
are important
but to be more holistic
in the practice to some point to get a
sense of that the whole
the mind as a whole the mood mind state
that we have
and those mind states have various
characteristics
uh when we get more and more settled
when the mind feels more
whole or expansive or clear the greater
clarity and mindfulness
and the seven factors awakening are part
of that
and the last one equanimity is part that
when the mind when we're really stable
in a strong awareness with a strong
sense of being aware in this
in our mind state a healthy wholesome
mind state
it tends to come with a strong sense of
equanimity
and equanimity being very simply not
getting caught in the reactivity of the
mind
of being for and against things and
and it's a wonderful capacity
we still might be for and against things
might have those thoughts or
impulses a little bit but equanimity we
just simply don't pick it up we don't
get involved they just pass through
they're just
fleeting kind of impulses of the moment
that come and they go
and um and we don't we don't pick it up
we don't get involved
and it can lead to a tremendous social
good
because uh when we don't uh
respond socially into the world by our
reactivity by the quick impulses of
being foreign against things
then uh we're more likely to be
impartial in a really healthy
understanding of impartiality where we
treat everyone equally or
we don't treat people through the filter
of
our desires and our aversions kind of
leaning into unwanting or
pulling back because we don't want or
something
we don't so easily get pulled into our
preferences
and so a sense of justice a sense of
impartiality sense of being someone
who's safe for other people becomes more
and more
more stronger the the more we have this
equanimity this ability to
not get caught up in our reactivity or
these impulses of being foreign against
all kinds of things
there might still be wise being foreign
against things
but that wisdom builds on equanimity
on being stable and settled it's not
impulsive
there's a clarity and a wholesomeness in
how we respond to the world so
equanimity
is both something for deep meditation
and for
everyday life it's a really a
great boon for life in deeper and deeper
meditation
that's some place where some people can
really feel this state of equanimity in
a very powerful way
that gives us a feeling for it and then
a support
of what it's like to bring that into our
daily life
but in the anapanasati process it's very
much
the reference point for it is in
meditation
and so in meditation the equanimity is
what allows the mindfulness
to be uninterrupted to just stay in the
flow of awareness
here here and we don't find ourselves
drifting off in thought and coming back
two three minutes later
we don't find ourselves getting caught
and preoccupied by what's happening
now we might be very attentive to what's
happening but we're not caught by it
and so the steadiness of mindfulness it
just kills the course
holds the course keeps walking keeps
engaging step by step
equanimity sort of allows that
steadiness and continuity of awareness
and equanimity that upekka
as i said yesterday has a lot to do with
wisdom
so having an overview of the situation
and it's not a wisdom that's
acquired knowledge that we bring with us
and apply
but rather something that we deeply
understand as we go along
and there's a variety of things uh one
can be
that it's not worthwhile getting being
reactive it's not being worthwhile being
caught up in
in thoughts or thought up in our
reactivity it's just not valuable for us
and we can feel that
and sense that directly the other is
that
we can have a clear sense feeling for
the impermanence of phenomena the
inconstancy of it how things come and go
and change and to really
understand that means we don't then
relate to things
as if they're going to be there forever
or if they're
you know something that's fixed that has
to be fixed something fixed that has to
be fixed
and uh and so having a clear sense oh
this is impermanent this is change as
well
uh you can let us set back and just be
willing to just be present be aware
the wisdom of not taking all these
things personally that i'm not unique
that my experience is not unique that uh
many people have meditation probably all
the experiences we've had
one way or the other others have had as
well
and it's one of the primary roles of
sometimes of a meditation teacher
is to normalize people's experiences
and for the most part to normalize just
make it ordinary it's okay
it's just part of the process so we can
keep coming back
to the equanimous mindfulness steady
mindfulness that
doesn't get perturbed or agitated by no
matter what is happening no matter the
fear
or the pain or the suffering or that
we're experiencing a meditation
it's all normalized in a certain way
so not taking it personally is one of
those ways
and so there's a variety of kind of
wisdoms that come into play that's
really supports this ability
to stay equanimous balanced unagitated
in our experience the
but also this equanimity comes from a
sense of balance
and balance has something to do with
inner strength
to be cultivate when there's a strength
of mindfulness a strength of
concentration is a strength of stability
then uh it's kind of like we have
a a
you know as a stability we have a
something that holds us down keeps us
grounded
um allows us to withstand the winds of
the mind the winds of change and
things that come and go and to and to
develop that strength by the continuity
of meditation meditating
maybe almost every day and regularly and
developing this
the mind is an instrument that can be
developed and strengthened and trained
and not everyone develops their mind
everyone trains their mind to be a
strong
be strong and part of what ongoing
regular meditation practice is about
is not just showing up and being mindful
of stuff and accepting of stuff
but also developing an inner strength a
capacity to let go
a capacity to really stay present and be
steady with experience and not
wander off in all kinds of things a
strength of concentration a strength of
even joy
so as we get stronger and stronger we're
not buffeted so much by the winds of
change the winds of what goes on
and so we're more able to kind of hold
the course and hold the course and so
as the uh as the ninth step of this
anapanasati mindfulness of the mind is
to
um start experiencing and sensing that
we have this amazing resource this
amazing
thing called chitta called mind that we
want to care for
that's a reference point for a
well-being
a wholeness that any kind of suffering
we have
is a subset of and so when the mind is
really
spacious and open expansive present
we're aware of the cheetah in a more
bigger way it's much harder to take our
greeds or attachments or lusts or
addictions our hates hostilities regrets
resentments
our fears as being all there is
they all become a piece of the puzzle
they're not the whole puzzle
the whole puzzle feels more like the
mind
that can be aware of it all
and and there's a lot can be uh a
feeling of great goodness great
rightness
great kind of in that kind of sense of a
mind or
this inner life which is whole
and um and so whether it's completely
whole
or feels completely kind of as
satisfying as i'm saying here
uh that keeps coming now as we continue
the practice of anapanasati
step 10 is gladdening the mind or
feeling the satisfaction of the mind of
being connected to this mind that feels
more whole
and then the the um the 11th step is uh
samadhi is concentrating the mind or
unifying the mind
which we'll talk about soon enough and
that's what makes the mind even more
whole
so it's a fantastic process here and
and i know that it's not easy to
experience
all these things i'm talking about but
part of the confidence in practice is to
know
that you're on a good path and
and part of the equanimity that comes
with practice is the confidence
this is a good path to be on i can just
walk this path
steadily keep going i don't have to be
too concerned about how far i've gotten
because i know i'm on a good path and
and i'll keep walking so
thank you for today and i look for
forward as i almost every day do now
of coming and sitting and teaching here
with you
thank you