so so hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour
this uh this first day of uh of summer june 21st
and first day of oh that means winter in the southern hemisphere wow okay
so we've just turned the corner here we are so
so for today's practice um [Music]
yeah so what i'd like to invite is to consider
um is how our way of seeing
our way of seeing really creates really fabricates friends
enemies dear ones neutral people it's it's it's in so many ways
these categories these are categories fabrication of our minds
haven't you noticed that actually someone who maybe at some point was in one
category then becomes in turn you know maybe they say something that
that upsets you and then instead of being your dear person for a few days they become your difficult person and maybe resolve
it and they become your your benefactor again or your dear friend or
or just these these categories are so um elastic
elastic and and how the same person can be our uh both perhaps benefactor
good friend as well as or uh challenging the person we have challenges with
same with us we can be our own you know we can be in all these different categories
so so these categories aren't fixed aren't really
fixed they're they are a way of seeing a way of relating a way
of seeing another through our lens through the lens of me myself and mine how you make me feel
today or this month or this year or this decade [Music]
and and um again a particular person is neither
challenging or neutral or or dear just because of because of who
they are but how how we see them so there is really this is one way one way where the
practice of emptiness
now as i bring this word please don't get scared like oh my god now she's going to talk about emptiness and i don't know what the heck that is and
those are higher teachings and relax i already explained to you everything i was going to explain so if
you understood what i said that's it so this is one aspect of emptiness avoidness
co-fabrication creation the way that we see the way that we see the world it's
really empty it's really empty it's not an inherent property
of the people it's just the way we see them we make them we relate to them in these ways
and these qualities again it's not inherent in the person it's we fabricate it given the way that
we see in a given moment it depends on our way of seeing
and they're not inherent so so that's where one of the ways that
the practice the realization of emptiness voidness is just it's it's so elastic it's so free it's also
free it's much less fixed than we take it to be actually this practice of emptiness in
this way brings so much freedom so much ease it brings freedom
oh yes it's the way i'm seeing it's the way i'm fabricating so given that it's my way of saying
given that it's so malleable well why don't i malleat
why why don't i make it into uh why don't i see everyone as a friend i
have a choice so what if i saw everybody as a friend
what would happen to my perception what would happen to this world that i
live in if everyone was a friend if i saw everyone if the way of seeing the way of
fabricating was a friendly one how would my experience of being in this
world operating how would it shift and change so
so with that as the preamble i also want to give credit this idea
came up to share with you as i was listening to a beautiful talk by my favorite teacher of mine rob berbea
passed away last year and this talk is was entitled um
love healing and emptiness and it's from 2010 and i trust later deal neil will look it
up later and we'll share with you for any one who might be interested again the name is
love healing and emptiness it's on dharmaseed and it's by rob burbea
so so with all of that and having given credit to giving i'm an academic so it's important to
give credit where ideas come from well it's important for everyone but anyway let's
start our practice our formal practice of guided meditation so so
i'd like to invite you to get into your posture
whatever posture might be supportive for
you whether sitting lying down standing or
even walking
turning turning your gaze inward first to arrive and settle
in the body
letting go letting go of all the words that have come
before all the busyness of the day
all the plans of what you will do later today this moment just taking refuge
and just being
the radical choice in our society
in this world to just be and not do for a moment
letting go of doing
opening up relaxing softening the whole body
opening to non-doing
receiving receiving the breath
as it moves through the lower abdomen
sit bones the legs the feet
relaxing softening letting go of all these parts
softening [Music] relaxing the abdomen
letting the chest
be refreshingly filled with the breath
and empty the neck and shoulders ah softening
feeling heavy
letting their weight to be pulled down
by the earth by gravity ah as if tension
tightness is dripping down relieved
let go of
so too for the muscles of the face
behind the eye
behind the jaw connecting the jaw
inviting awareness to be close very close
right here just in the body right here not far
intimately feeling sensing creating all the sensations
if you notice the mind is resting on the thought and the plan memory okay
it's part of this practice nothing wrong with thinking per se
just for the purpose of this practice or calming
settling
in this moment
inviting the awareness to stay close in the body
to bow to the thought thank you please come back later i'll be waiting
for you but now i'm giving my heart to this practice
bringing the awareness to the body to the breath
receiving
just settling arriving for another few minutes before we turn
our attention to metta
now as we stay embodied
as we allow awareness to connect with the sensations of this
body sitting connecting [Music] the cushion of the floor
connected to the earth connected to the air through the breath sense of
embodiment right here right now in this body
not leaving the body letting it be our anchor
and now inviting inviting into our minds i
the image of felt sense
of a dear friend someone with whom we have an
uncomplicated relationship ideally just there is a sense of
friendliness
goodwill we appreciate them we like them
we wish them well maybe they make us feel safe and happy
when we're in their presence
whatever the nuance might be for you
and if it's challenging to find someone in this category it's okay to bring someone in who's a benefactor
a dear person maybe even a child or a pet
just the sense of friendliness ease
bringing them into your mind's eye as if inviting them to come and sit with
you
so if they were right in front of you
letting a sense of meta ease friendliness
that naturally arises
could show up as a smile could show up as gladness could show up
in your heart area heart center areas oh sense of warmth care good will
we're just happy to see this person this being in your mind's eye and from this
from this place wishing them well you can use your own metaphrases if you
have them or i'll offer them for
metaphases traditional ones may you be safe
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you have ease
may you be safe
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you have ease
you're welcome to keep the phrases or let it be silent
what's more important today in this practice as we explore in this way
is to have an image of felt sense of them just the way you see them
looking at them with friendly eyes
noticing what happens in your heart when you look at them with friendly eyes
does your heart feel more expansive more easeful more peaceful
more spacious
we're happy again notice what the nuance is for you
as you envision this being with friendly eyes
seeing them as a friend
see what happens for you notice notice
now having primed our heart we'll do a wholesome what's called bait
and switch now as the heart is warmed up with this
sense of friendliness seeing through the eyes of friendliness
bring the image felt sense of someone else who's kind of neutral for you someone you know
maybe you've seen
and replace your friend your dear being with this new
image and see if it's possible what if you just saw this person
with a friend in a friendly way as if they were a friend experiment
in this moment see what it feels like
as if they were your friend as if they were dear to you pushing them
well in the same way
and like surfing we can surf the wave sometimes for a long long long time
the energy may not dissipate but if it does you can always go back
to your friend dear friend and prime your heart again and do the bait and switch
so experiment see what happens
i'd like to invite you to come back to invite your friend your friend again
sitting with them seeing them
friendly eyes friendly gaze
the way you see them with kindness with care with goodwill
with meta
yeah letting your heart feel what it feels your body
pay attention
and i'd like to invite you having primed her heart again now imagine the scene
from somewhere you've been recently perhaps maybe you went for a walk simply
near your home and there were passerbys neighbors walking by or maybe you went
to a store to buy something a grocery store
or another store or somewhere a park somewhere where they're a bunch
of people you have this felt sense of oh yeah there were people around
what if we saw them which we took in their minds eye
different people that perhaps we interacted with or we just saw
looking at them seeing them with friendly eyes
with good will may you be well may you be well
as if they were a long lost friend perhaps we didn't know this was a friend of ours
what if silently brought the image of each of them up and said hi
how are you i wish you well i'm friendly i see you as a friend
maybe flashing an inner smile
see what works for you
as if you had a friendly relationship a connection with age
of these beings as if you knew them
as if they were your second third fourth cousins hello cousin hi you were seeing them
at a reunion you've never seen them before
with friendly eyes friendly eyes wishing you well
we are related in this web of common
humanity
notice how your heart feels how your body feels
greeting friendliness all these long-lost cousins
you're related to through the web of common humanity
may our practice in cultivating our hearts and goodness and kindness and
meta be a cause and condition
for awakening [Music] for goodness for ourselves and all
beings in this world
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so i will change the settings in chat so if you like to share
your reflections in chat to everyone i'll say your name out loud if you just type them to me privately i
will only read the reflection not your name you're also welcome to raise your hand
your zoom hand your physical hand i may not see
if you like to share your insights reflections questions
complaints it's all welcome especially if you haven't spoken for a while
love to hear from you friend
hi i i found the suggestion to think of strangers as cousins to be very
apt and useful i i have a lot of cousins and you know my intimacy with
various cousins have changed over the years some being quite close and then a rotation
and somebody else will come to the west coast and they'll be very close and there is something almost
arbitrary about that that there i can feel that we've
decided that we will be friends that we will be close it's uh just because of the accident of
family but now we make a commitment um through through that accident and uh
that experience seems to be a useful way for me to imagine
the boatload of people i was thinking about who i was around yesterday who
were as various and as indifferently composed as my family is
thank you fred thank you so much for saying that as beautifully and as
eloquently as you said all of that yeah it's a commitment you make into
way of seeing the way of relating otherwise it can be kind of random beautiful thank you i
love that and actually that suggestion when i suggested for me it it um brightened
the practice also it brought more dimensionality for me saying all the people i had seen earlier
today like oh yeah hi cousin hi it's just
yeah thank you for that yeah lovely yeah yeah
other reflections what did you what else did you notice claire please thank you
i wasn't so much noticing i had a very funny coincidence so that i wanted to share with you
i have a friend who is a huge fan of proofs and somehow rather i got on the phone
with them today and instead of my usual annoyance with them
i decided to look through stuff i didn't just and i just googled and i came up with a quote that i
thought would just blew my mind changed my whole perception and it's so
relevant to what you were talking about it reads the real voyage of discovery consists not in
seeking new lands but unseen with new eyes
and i thought that is just amazing because that's been so true for me and it's exactly what we
were talking about and it was the theme of my whole day it's really weird yeah yeah exactly it's
beautiful thank you for sharing that yeah a way of seeing with new eyes not new
lads but new you know would you type it if you can in chat or
say it one more time claire the whole quote great thank you
yeah so so i will go to merry christine's question
how do you see an abusive person with new eyes yes very good question so
um the i think the way of inviting to see
with friendliness is um is to see their humanity in this case
to see their humanity it doesn't mean that you um become a you know a
doormat and say oh just friends i'm just going to forget about everything you can abuse me but but allowing yourself to see their
friendliness their long-lost cousin who are causing harm you still see them oh yes they're a
cousin you know they they're related they're you want them to be well and
yeah you're going to keep your distance from from this cousin but you wish them well
yeah thank you christine very important question yeah thank you oh yes beautiful
and thanks for putting that in chat again claire the real voyage of discovery consists not
in seeking new lands but seeing in new eyes seeing with new eyes beautiful
lovely yeah the other reflections
as i wait for you i'll share that with this practice towards the end i felt
much happier i felt my heart being really expansive just kind of yeah just the delight of
the people i had seen earlier who were kind of two-dimensional for me they were just people
neutral people and then they became oh wow so
so so in fact they became dear i was wishing them well so i think tomorrow when i go
to the same place i'll go for my daily exercise swim if they're there like oh i'll see them
with different different eyes like oh yeah this person swimming next to me in the lane oh may you be well
so her for me was quite lovely too so so how about
we since i'm not seeing any hands and i'm not seeing any um uh new reflections
let's turn uh we'll save some time for on the other end when we come back
from small groups for reflections and right now how about we engage with our
cousins our long-lost cousins whom we will meet in a small group a couple of our cousins
who will have the privilege to connect with or reconnect with in small groups so let's
uh practice i'll make out the make the breakout rooms and how about uh we start with
the 15 seconds of silent meta for um for our
cousins and after that then you can share as much or as
little as you wish let's see okay the rooms are created and i am
going to open them now here we go okay
welcome back everyone okay the rooms are closed welcome back
and we have a few minutes for reflections questions your practice is
important especially if you're new and uh would love to hear from you
what did you discover was there's something new that you discovered about yourself about what worked for you what
didn't what what happened either during the guided meditation or
in the practice meetings
you can erase your zoom hand or type in
chat
lisa please thank you yeah i was noticing that it
felt like really like freeing or lightning to be given permission to
to notice which i did anyway but that like the categories change
for the person that i might or being i might like pick for a
category that the complexity it's like allowing for the complexity of that
the change depending on my view and the conditions of
that moment going into my view it just felt like even though i i could know that yeah somehow it's
like oh you saying it and offering this meditation it just was like
felt like being given permission for that and i really really appreciated it and it feels
like this is a super rich teaching that yeah i want to like be with more so
thank you nikki yeah thank you lisa one thing that i'm hearing what you're saying don't
mute yourself just yet because i want to follow up with what i'm hearing if i hear correctly is that there's a
sense of this acknowledgement that yeah this is what happens with these categories that they're kind of
random depending on how we see them you know one person can be a friend another day and a
challenging person who is challenging etc so that actually gave you permission it
brought some ease is what i'm hearing to say oh yeah this is this is how it works it's it's
it's it's okay this is how it works for everyone right this is and it's based on how we see others
and it just keeps shifting and changing and that can allow a sense of okay this is how it works
given how i see so okay how can i it actually opens up practice opportunity
did i kind of hear that correctly what you're reflecting on yes completely like the it's okay
and and then um yeah like the warmth is
can i don't know somehow can flow between these like categories seeing that one day
or that half day it was like that and then that later hour it was like that and it's like
what and just noticing my own rigidity around but it should always be the same
i and i don't that doesn't feel good but i noticed my like well then i can just check off that box
you know and it's like hmm that's not yeah this just like feels good somehow and
yeah yeah i would like to be with be with this more i can feel like i can be with this for a little while as a
practice nice you just added another aspect to it which i want to highlight which is not the rigidity of it doesn't
have to particularly this is how it works like so not fighting against how it
actually the mind makes these categories this is how it happens and opening up to working with it and
another thing that i just thought about sharing actually as a as an invitation for all of us is as
different people we relate to as they shift and go between these categories can we still see them as our cousins oh
yeah this is the cousin who's still my cousin but you know today you know we're still related we're still
connected in this web of humanity and you know through our human family we're still connected and today yeah
it's just it's kind of this way it's the weather condition so yeah thank you lisa and jeanne says i
just enjoyed meeting some new cousins so that's very sweet thank you genie so the time has come
for us to to end our time together so i thank you all thank you so
much for your practice and cultivation for the sake of yourselves and for the sake of all those beings
whose lives yours touches may all beings be happy may all beings be free
thank you