so oh i've missed you it's just so sweet to
see you and and uh to be in community together it's especially during the
holidays and with um yet another covet surge
um [Music] i appreciate this sangha so very much
and tonight as i was getting ready to teach i was thinking yippee i get to speak happy hour sangha yipi so
there's a sense of gladness gladness in my heart um
so so the theme that i like to when there's so many themes i don't know which one to
choose or so many themes that i like to invite us to to
practice with um and one of them is this this turning
towards joy turning towards joy of
sangha joy of community here you are practicing whether you are
right now joining on zoom or youtube or
or maybe listening later on audio dharma there is a sense of coming together
people who are coming together with you um and you're welcome to put each other on
on on um uh gallery view so that you can see each other uh there's just a sense of coming
together this collective there's a sense of yippy here we are we're coming together
feeling each other's presence from across the world
from around the world and there are so many good things in in
life in this challenging period there are many
challenges and there are also many blessings and the blessing of this
zoom online youtube sangha um is definitely one of them and i know
that many of you have talked about that previously that at times you had even thought i remember jerry
actually saying that sitting retreats sure if it's okay to to bring this i
remember you sharing during happy hour that sitting retreats at ims in various places when when teachers would talk
about sangha sangha and thinking oh driving and traffic and there's nothing
close and it's so hard and here here is this gift of community
practicing with fellow practitioners just the ease the joy the beauty of that
this is your community and if you're new to this community if this is your first time or pre your new year welcome
you're part of this community you're oh we warmly warmly embrace you and
welcome you as a part of this this community stuff
so with that let's turn our attention let's turn
um our mind
to our bodies let's sit
however this body wants to sit or lie down
and arriving arriving
in this body in this moment in time
if you're sitting on the chair why don't you move your feet a little bit just
find or move your legs to find a stance in your legs
that's really firmly rooted to the ground and if you're sitting on the cushion
you're welcome to also in the chair to move maybe swing
to the left and right forwards and backwards
just really feeling your connection to the earth your sit bones connected to
the earth i am here
i am here as earth
i serve as my witness as the earth may serve as my witness i'm here
landing landing here
planting
relaxing the body relaxing and receiving
relax and receive
relax and receive the sensations of the body
connected to the earth
melting softly melting
relax and receive the breath
the movement
as if waves of the ocean [Music]
calming soothing settling
if you find the mind flutters
here and there [Music]
a little butterfly tension flies this way back
come home come home sweetie come home
home home
calling yourself home to your heart
see if a gesture of putting your your hand
your palm your heart center that's the feeling
of connecting of centering you centering connecting with yourself
coming home home in your heart come home sweetie come home
it's okay you can rest at home
letting your body relax and receive the breath
just this breath this one right here
get to know it befriend it open to it
ride the wave the joyful
joyful riding of the breath as if you're a
breath surfer like a wind surfer surfing the wave
like a surfer
there is joy delight in just being here
here aware
the heart the mind bright with awareness even for a moment
here
there's a joy a goodness a gladness
it could be subtle
can we give a gift
of our presence to ourselves in this moment
relaxing receiving the breath
every cell of the body relaxed
ah letting go
and receiving
whatever is offered in this moment the breath sensations of the body
not past not future right here this moment is enough
this moment is more than enough it's joyful joyous
to be deeply rooted and connected
here
this
can you feel your feet on the ground your bottom on the cushion your hands
on your lap your breath
and your lower abdomen
and now i'd like to invite you
continuing to sit embodied feeling the body here
we're going to open up to being found
being found by joy we're not going to go out and looking
for it to search want
but we're going to send an invitation out
a love letter to joy dear joy
i'm here sitting present in this moment as best as i'm able to
my heart is open my senses are open
if any point you'd like to
come visit i'm available
see how this shift in perspective sort of going out and looking
for gladness
instead of that just simply sitting here
relaxing open
just this breath just these sensations
let yourself be surprised
sit back relax receive the breath
of the miracles all the miracles of this moment
the miracles of life this mystery
called life
receiving the mystery in this moment
through your breath through the fingertips
your toes
through your belly through your ears
through your heart
open senses open
your heart open your senses open
here
maybe just maybe for a split second
you might find yourself happy with joy
for no particular reason there may not even be any thoughts
any rumination just happy
glad to be here
or simply glad not for any reason
gladness arising the joy the joy of the present moment
the joy of the present moment
here just here
and then you find judgment arises you don't know what you're doing you don't know how to do this
you're distracted etc so please smile
the judgment the judgmental mind thank you for your opinion dear thank you
smile
[Music] and you are here again begin again every moment a new beginning
here just here the joy of this moment
and if you like sitting receiving
the joy of this moment here just here simplicity
opening up opening up your heart your senses
to this community who's practicing with you
and soon on youtube maybe later in time
an audio dharma
as if you were bowing to them to each other
others bowing to you and your mind's eyes your eyes are closed
noticing if there is a delight a joy of spiritual friendship even if you may
never speak or haven't spoken you're supporting each other just
knowing you are here you are here i am here
it brings a lot of joy for me in my mind's eye seeing the sangha
across across the planet earth in so many
different places all of us interconnected
bounding to you bowing to each other
joy arises joy rises thank you
thank you for being here thank you for practicing with me
thank you for sharing your goodness
and sharing this goodness far and wide
generously with all beings everywhere
may all beings be joyous be happy be well
may all beings have the gift of peace may all beings be free
including ourselves
thank you everyone thank you for your practice
so we have time for reflections
questions comments the invitation is if you like to share
your practice for the benefit of others what worked what was surprising
what didn't work it's all okay especially if you haven't spoken for a
while community you can also type them in chat or raise
your hand type them to me alone i won't read your name so it'll be
anonymous if it's typed to the community i will read the
[Music] name also bill says that felt good
i'm glad me too yeah oh
melissa says thank you for the beautiful practice i felt so much warmth in my
heart ah that's beautiful that is beautiful thank you melissa
from victoria british columbia yeah
the other reflections mark please
this meditation tonight has been right on the subject that i've been
working with all day today this morning i read a line
a quote from eddie hillson who died at auschwitz in her twenties and she wrote
there about there she said most people here are much worse
off than they need be because they write off their longing for friends and family as so many losses in
their lives when they should count the fact that their heart is able to long so hard and
to love so much among their greatest blessings and the author of this book went on
to say a line that just rocked me and has been with me all day
she said our engagement and participation in the
world begin to shift from viewing this world as a field of consumption
get that field of consumption to experiencing this world as a field of
appreciation and that's exactly what eddie was talking about
instead of looking at the losses of her family and friends in auschwitz she
looked at the appreciation that she was able to love them
so much
that is profound thank you mark and thank you so much for sharing that
i'm so moved hearing those words and the beauty the wisdom
of both words consumption you know the wanting the consumption wanting needing the
the loved ones appreciation appreciating them appreciating that you have a heart oh
that that gives me chills beautifully put beautifully put and bill asks mark what
is the name of this book please oops you mute it you can put it in chat
if you like or you can unmute yourself whichever you prefer it's in
the magnanimous heart by the ryan helen levinson
who's a teacher at ims and cambridge insight medicine oh yes that's right great thank you for
that beautiful and deborah says thanks i needed that
it's lovely another reflection thank you for the soft and
loving guidance touching my hand to my heart is proving to be a sure fire way
to ground into presence and meta oh that's lovely that is so lovely
and a couple of other reflections jane thanks
uh with appreciation to me and the sangha oh bowing deeply to all that's beautiful
image from our practice bowing deeply to all thank you jane bowing to you and your practice
melissa says the queue smile at your at your judgmental mind thank you for your
opinion dear and begin again it was helpful for me i'm glad to hear that
and also melissa says mark that is mind-blowing thank you for that
yeah so saint jerry says very helpful to ask us
to stay in the moment not the future and not the past yes indeed
yeah and anton asks what is the standard time for meditation practice any time you can
practice is the standard time for a meditation practice this particular
sangha starts at 6 pm pacific time one more reflection two more reflections
now says reflecting on the joy when practicing together and the difference when practicing alone
yes yes isn't that amazing isn't that amazing and beautiful now i i feel that
also practicing together there's a sense of beauty and grace and just landing
together that that i definitely sense and feel thank you for naming that
yeah um one more reflection inviting joy in felt like preparing my
home for guests oh that's lovely anticipating their arrival but not knowing or caring when it would be oh i
love that that is such a sweet reflection inviting joy
and felt like preparing my home for guests anticipating their arrival but not knowing or caring when it would be i
love that that is such a beautiful way to practice with this with this invitation did you notice how different
this was than going out and like thinking you know in some ways actually this this relates to what mark shared
earlier it's um it's not so much about going out and
thinking about what i'm grateful for or what i appreciate which which can be a beautiful practice in its own way but
but this is just the simplicity of just being here just opening the heart
and being content there's a sense of contentment that can arise with the joy of just this
moment just here just here so dear ones we are approaching the time
to invite us to actually now meet in small groups you have bowed to each other in your mind's eye and now you can
bow to each other in small groups which is so beautiful so if you can't stay please do meetings are
short you know six seven minutes and especially with our theme tonight i think it'll be lovely to continue this
practice in small groups and if for some reason you have to leave that's understandable
no judgments but please don't leave because you're afraid of these lovely
groups of people but okay so here we go i'm going to create the breakout rooms
and they are open now and please take care of yourselves take care of each other
okay the rooms are closed everyone is back
and we have a few minutes for reflections
comments questions appreciations the floor is yours so
you're welcome to raise your zoom hand because if it's your physical hand i will not see you
um [Music] and you can also type in chat
what did you notice what came up if anything you'd like to share for the benefit of the sangha
greg please uh thank you for the suggestion to uh
gently and lovingly reel your mind back in when it goes off on its little
thought excursions um i'm sort of in the habit of commanding
my mind to come back and having some degree of frustration about that but doing it in kind of a soft and loving
way it's a nicer internal dialogue so thank you for that
you are so welcome greg and um just to say that this um
actually this way of beginning again just beginning again
thank you thanks for your opinion and just beginning again and dropping whatever there was before without
animosity without beating yourself up this
is a crucial insight this is a crucial
insight this is when practice really starts to deepen because up until then we're throwing all
these perfectly good moments after these moments of being distracted which is fine but learning to be gentle with
ourselves learning to just arrive that's where the practice is
knowing that the mind will wander that is normal that is completely normal
but what you do the moment you realize the mind has wandered that's where it determines
practice versus self-flagellation that's mindfulness
mindfulness which has meta in it mindfulness always needs to have meta with it woven in it so that is a moment
of mindfulness so so practice mindfulness which met which has meta in it already so when i say mindfulness i
already mean meta so practice mindfulness not self recombination so in
that moment especially that's really important so i'm so glad you
raised that and really came home for you and i hope it comes
from home for everyone to really see that the crucial moment
so so the time has come for us to bring our session
uh to a close of practicing together it's been so sweet
and um this is the uh i'll see you in the new
year and for wednesday and friday we have wonderful uh
uh teachers who'll be supporting the sangha new year's eve and also on wednesday and then i'll see
you on the other end on the during the new year so so
let's dedicate the merit of our practice may all beings be well may all beings be
free including ourselves
[Music] thank you all