so good day warm greetings
and here we are to continue on our adventure in uh
mindfulness of breathing and the last tetra at the end of this
whole sequence of settling in deeper and deeper
is to come to a place where we're able to
observe things in a
non-interfering way non-reactive way and whereas
observing by itself might not seem like a very interesting way of meditating perhaps or a little
bit detached it comes after
a process of calming relaxing the body and mind and liberating ourselves just enough
with our reactivity and our preoccupations and our busy mind
so that rather than letting go at this point we can let things be
and letting things be can be seen as a very generous thing
to not interfere to not assert the self and not assert one's preferences and
desires and aversions but to really just kind of have the
peacefulness to observe and some things we observe are difficult we
might be anxious we might be upset we might be
you know agitated in some way but it is possible to come to a place
where we just observe that and we let it be we don't have to let go of it because we
can just let it be um and uh
and and watch it see it and so
the last tetrad is just observing things coming and going and starting
to become attuned to the fact that in some way or many ways in profound ways
our experience is constantly shifting and changing and arising and passing
and to now not be interested in the content of our experience the content of our
thoughts the content of our feelings but rather to be interested in the
process by which they arise in their past they come and they go we're switching to process rather than
content is a big shift for the human mind and to observe
to let be and in a sense we're learning to ease up on our
experience not to get rid of it but to be able to observe it in a peaceful way
so beginning with a meditation posture
that allows you to both have some alertness but also to feel at ease in yourself
some easiness
and to gently close your eyes
and to take a few long slow deep breaths
long slow deep breaths to feel yourself
fill yourself with awareness and to relax to settle in
and to settle in as you exhale to some place within that feels stable
a stability stable in your body
stable in your heart
maybe stable in your mind
not looking for great stability but rather
becoming a little more stable than you were stable here definitively
here and now in this place at this time
and then letting your breath return to normal and
perhaps as if there's waves of relaxation through your body
relaxing the muscles of your face
as you breathe the waves of breathing are like waves smooth washing through your face
softening relaxing
waves of relaxation through the shoulders
waves of relaxation through the belly softening on the exhale
and waves of relaxation through the whole body
and then letting yourself sit quietly here
and let yourself be easy be at ease in your body
or if your body feels uneasy ease up on how it is
allow things to be but ease up around them it's okay
breathe with it ease up and just observe
experiences of your body
and set your heart at ease
maybe you can feel gentle tender soft
in the heart here and now at ease or if the heart is uneasy to ease
up on that it's okay and for you to observe this is how it is
as if a as if the observing is accompanying the uneasiness you feel
with care and compassion
and as you exhale setting your mind at ease it's okay to be here now
and if the mind is uneasy ease up on that
so you can maybe just observe
be at ease in how you observe
no need to strain or be afraid as you open up to observe
phenomena
the observing itself is a place of safety
we begin approaching a place of non-reactivity non-harming
just observing phenomena
and one of the things you can observe
is how you lose your ease how you lose your calm
how you go in the opposite direction then easing up
be sure that you don't overlook the moments of
contraction and agitation
reactivity but when you see it when you know it meet it with relaxing
meet it with easing up
with observing this is how it is now
letting it be
but not being it letting it be but not becoming
the reactivity
and all along breathing in and breathing out
as if breathing is the rhythm of the universe
that washes through you through
everything
[Music]
so
[Music] ah
noticing ways that you've been caught that you get caught in thoughts and
feelings and experiences in the body
we're being caught or preoccupied or concerned
is going in a different direction than being at ease easing up
simply observing
with the help of breathing
let breathing help you not get so caught in things stay with the rhythm of breathing
so that you're in better position to simply observe the comings and goings of
reactivity preoccupations
contractions comings and goings of what you want and what you don't want
the coming goings of wanting and not
wanting
[Music]
um
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to appreciate the possibility of easing up
and one way this easing up is so helpful is to
help us recognize in inner safety
that as we sit and meditate we don't need to be talking to people or
interacting with them and be out in the world driving our cars on dangerous freeways
that for these few minutes of the meditation
you don't have to solve your problems or
engage in the difficulties of life it's a safe time just to be let be
and it's also somewhat private what goes on inside
so in the safety and privacy without anybody needing to know
can you open your heart tenderly caringly
to feel good will to have kindness love
first for the people in your life it's relatively easy to love and have good will
and allow you yourself the luxury of feeling that privately
without the any complications of it being done publicly or
overtly just feeling the simplicity of your care your kindness
your appreciation of others
perhaps breathe with it breathe through those feelings
make room for it
and with this simple useful connection to your goodwill
perhaps it's easier now again in the privacy of meditation
to have thoughts of well-wishing for others
it would be quite wonderful if they could be happy and peaceful
safe and that they they could thrive and
have a good life
and then to give words to this good will this well-wishing
may they be happy
may they be safe
may they be peaceful
may they be free
and may our well-wishing extend outwards throughout the lands
and seas and in all directions how wonderful it would be if all beings
could be happy may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be safe
may all beings everywhere be free
and with the support of our meditation practice mindfulness practice
may we in our way in ways that we can contribute to that being possible
[Music]
so my friends we continue with this anapanasati
and the topic is the 14th step one trains oneself
breathing breathing in observing
fading away or a different translation is one trains breathing in observing
fading away observing dispassion
and this word translated as dispassion
the word is v raga v-i-r-a-g-a
you know it doesn't quite work for some english speakers because over time the word passion has
acquired many positive associations and connotations definitions in english in some circles and the
original i think the original meaning of it that the passion of christ where it meant suffering is kind of lost
but i think still there's remnants in english that the passion can have negative connotations you know it's a
is a source of suffering so you know someone say someone has a passion for power or
passion for sex or a passion for you know something you know that it's an
intense engagement in something and intense engagement
can be um very painful so the um so i want to talk a little bit
about this uh dispassion this uh b raga
uh maybe with a indirect way so buddhism is often considered a
religion and once it's called a religion it's reasonable for people to
try to understand what are the fundamental tenets and beliefs of this religion and in doing
that it's kind of looking at the generalizations just being universal statements about things
and and so one of the universal statements is that buddhism emphasizes that
everything is impermanent or inconstant usually people say everything's impermanent
and then we have this universal statement and then we're contending with this universal statement like is this
really true and is this always the case and and this seems like you know or maybe
rather depressing way of seeing everything or all kinds of reactions to this almost like a philosophical statement
general statement as if it's you know some universal truth that buddhism teaches
and so looking at this in a universal statement says
yes you know they understand buddhism is one approach i think the the practice approach to
understanding buddhism is not to understand buddhism in the abstract but not begin there but to begin with
oneself and one's own experience and um and
uh so to the degree to which buddhism emphasizes the possibility of being free
from suffering then we begin with ourselves and look what is
the suffering here that i have what's my pain emotional pain what's
happening here and they say it's possibly free of it well how could i become free of it
what does it take and um and in and in this very personal kind of
exploration and feeling and being here then buddhism says well if you really
look carefully at your experience you'll see that there's a very close
connection to uh the experience of
inconstancy change transiency impermanence
and our ability to ease up from our suffering to soften it to
calm it down even to have it fade away and disappear and so we see then
in this kind of going from this direction where personally the purpose of seeing and constancy
is not to have some universal theory and belief and philosophy about life but rather it's a pragmatic
practical idea that that in the observation of change and
inconstancy this is an antidote this is a medicine for what buddhism calls suffering
and there's something that eases up when we can really kind of feel the flow and be in the current of
change and whether impermanence and constancy is a universal philosophical universal
metaphysical concept or other is really besides the point
it's the point is that we're pointing to inconstancy and permanence because of
its value and helping us loosen up lighten up free up the places we get caught
and uh and that's enough we don't have to then make it a big leap of philosophy to make a universe
versatile claim about now i know something about you know the fundamental nature of the universe the
physics of physics of the universe that everything is impermanent and changing all the time
it's an interesting idea but that idea is not really what you know buddhist practice is about
so so but as we see things shifting and changing and transitory
nature of phenomenon and we get more interested in the process of change
the process of inconstancy then we are with the content of our thoughts content of our
feelings many times we're focused on the meaning of things or the content the purpose the what's
really you know the ideas and the particularity of what is going on
uh but in a sense at this point in anapanasati we're stepping back and in particular
what we're thinking is not that important just to see the thinking itself is an inconstant phenomena it comes and
goes probably you've had some of your thoughts repeatedly they've come and gone for
days and weeks months years and they just come and they go and after a while if you see how much they come in to go
maybe you ease up about it and so then
so then and also with our emotions sometimes the
meaning of the emotions the story around them even the emotion itself what emotion it is and what it means to have that
emotion and how it reflects back on ourselves as a human being comes into play
and but at some point meditation we shift from all that complication to not even
caring whether it's sadness or joy but rather tuning into how the process
of how it it is shifting and changing and morphing and
and moving and coming in and out of existence and how
attention awareness picks it up and puts it down gets distracted by the train whistle
and for a moment is not sad because it's just a train whistle and then we pick up then we're aware of
sadness again it's that is arisen and then we hear more more whistles and
you know it's all this kind of going and coming and going and it's that coming and going that
begins to loosen up it's like it's like a lubricant that begins uh unsticking the ways in
which we are kind of uncontrollably
caught in our emotions or in our activity and our motivations
so and one of those is raga and raga can be translated as passion or lust um
but it's translated as lust some people feel like it limits it too much to sexual
passion and um but one way of it's uncontrollable the one definition in the poly tech
society dictionary is um uncontrolled excitement
so there's something about i like to think of it as drivenness when there's a driveness to our draw you know to our drives a
driveness we're driven by lust driven by
greed driven by hatred and ill will and uh there's some way in which
something has taken over control and we're not in control anymore this power of that level of
passion and um describing the way i the way i do
it seems kind of dramatic but in all kinds as we get quieter and quieter in the mind
we see the subtler and subtler ways in which we're caught in the grip of certain driveness anybody who's been to
meditates tend to see that you know that how it's surprisingly how much we get swept away in our thoughts
or pulled into our thoughts caught in our thoughts that represents a little bit of a kind of uncontrolled excitement or
interest or engagement as we settle back into um
into just observing we can see that um this doesn't serve us to be
involved in this uncontrolled drivenness and cotness and preoccupation and so there starts to be
coming this process of disinterest losing interest and continuous doing that
i've had the same thoughts for months now i'm not interested in doing it anymore i have the same preoccupation with
certain emotions and feeling as if they're the most important thing and i'm not so interested in anymore and
i don't want to give much more attention to these things i've given so much attention to them i've been kind of driven to pay
attention to my anxiety and i think it's okay to put the anxiety to the side and
i know i'm anxious but i don't have to be so driven by it and i can ease up i can just observe it i
cannot be so involved or entangled with it and so the movement to being non-driven
movement being no the dropping of compulsion is this uh thing called v raga this
fading away this dispassion and it's very closely connected to freedom
it is a kind of freedom and after a while we begin appreciating that
freedom is sweet freedom is a breath of fresh air freedom
is a kind of joy and delight and vitality and a kind of health
a healthiness and so to begin to feel that be have a feeling for a sense of freedom
as we observe there's freedom in the observing
and that freedom the observing is a guide a support to lose interest or lose our
preoccupation with our drivenness with the things that we're caught in
and so there's this fading away of compulsion of a a um
a that a process that some translators will translate as dispassion
a movement towards this passion towards freedom the word viraga is a celebrated term in
india more often than not it's a kind of akin to it's in in to liberation itself
the freedom itself and um the end of raga the end of compulsion
drivenness lust in all its forms passion and all its
negative forms and um and it comes when a peace it can
come with a peaceful way i like to think of this whole process as a process of
settling into ease easing up relaxing softening fading away
into not not into nothing so much but fading into a peaceful happy
healthy liberated way of being so breathing in
observing fading away breathing out observing this passion as it comes along
here so um thank you
and um we'll continue with this and i um i believe i
apologize i didn't check my calendar but i believe that on friday we could do another session where afterwards if you want to stay and ask
some questions that was very nice last friday and and as we're doing the sign up on asati
maybe it's nice to for you having more questions about this so thank you all very much