so good morning everyone and good day
and i marvel at uh what we're doing here in
these mornings our electronic meeting and
and that we should somehow have this connection over great geographical distances and
and to be breathing at the same time practicing mindfulness at the same time
and each of us being here in our own unique place and
being here [Music] in this broad
global way as well and to have this dual hereness it seems pretty profound
that we somehow simultaneously are
present for our immediate experience and we have this wondrous and
very significant connection to this here which is broad and wide
and encompassing maybe the globe and so thank you
so the here of mindfulness practice has a lot to do with being mindful of the body being here in this
body and if all you did was just recognize that you're here in this body
that this is the body this is the experience of the body over and over
again the mindfulness would grow and develop in all kinds of ways that it does not
doesn't have to be so complicated or sophisticated just just their simple recognition here in
this body and in a sense the task of mindfulness
is to bring the mind into harmony with the body
the body is always in the present moment the mind it may be is often not it's thinking
about the past about the future about fantasy not really connected to what's here and
now and if we want the body and mind to be in harmony to work together which is really the best way of
operating in this life and then it's the task of inviting
welcoming the mind into the body
into accompanying the body allowing the body to accompany the mind
have these two operating in the same place at the same time
and the principle seems quite simple the actuality is that
the mind has a mind of its own and has strong things it wants to do
and when that's the case then it's possible to bring the body to the mind
which means really feel physically feel the physicality of a distracted
mind of a preoccupied mind of a of a of a psycho
emotional system that is fueled by by emotions feel
what's happening that keeps you from the body keeps you from being present but feel it in the body welcome it into
the body invite it into the body invite the body into what's what you're feeling so it's
constantly coming back and and creating this intimacy between
the mind and the body so the body is really so we really become more and more grounded
in this body so taking a assuming
entering into a posture a bodily posture that supports you
both in being present but also supports you in entering more fully into mindfulness
of the body almost as if you can be aware from your body through your body
all the nerve endings that exist throughout the body
is where awareness begins
sometimes we think awareness begins in the mind but awareness begins in the nerve
endings and what is it to relax into all the
nerve endings throughout the body and allow the awareness to arise there
so then gently closing the eyes
and to make this connection to the body fuller
to invite ourselves into the body you might take a few long slow deep breaths
feeling the increase of bodily sensations as you breathe in deeply
maybe throughout the torso
sometimes a deep inhalations you can feel the lifting of the chest and the shoulders
if the belly is relaxed you can also feel the pushing down into the sitting bones
and this combination of lifting and settling moving up and moving down
on the inhale and then relaxing and coming back to the
center with the exhale
letting your breathing return to normal
and allowing all your muscles that are not used to hold your up up
hold you upright let all the extra muscles
fall away from their bones if you are physically sitting upright
you can think of your spine as a post from which hang
all the muscles of the torso and whatever is not used to hold the
post upright let it hang from that post
the shoulders the muscles of the shoulders
no need to hold them up or tight but as you exhale relax the shoulders
in the back ribcage as you exhale let the back ribs also
relax and fall away relax away from the spine
maybe on the exhale there can be a releasing and relaxing in the small of the back
may be subtle
and as you exhale to soften the belly
maybe the belly doesn't have to work during the exhale
letting the diaphragm do all the work
which is mostly the work of releasing the diaphragm releases itself and
and softening the muscles of the face relaxing the face
sometimes if you feel carefully the face you can feel it's tired the muscles are tired from all the work
of expressing ourselves
to release and relax the muscles of the
face
and then to release the tensions in your brain
the tightness and pressure associated with thinking if it's there
on the exhale relaxing the thinking mind
quieting your thoughts
and then maybe as the home for the meditation you can drop into your body to wherever
you feel you're breathing as you meditate
but wherever it is be aware of it as sensations physical sensations of the
body and the task is to let the mind let the
attention the presence of the mind
be connected to this body breathing
appreciating the opportunity to have the mind accompany the body
and the body accompany the mind for them to be working together
with the same focus
then when you notice you when you notice you've lost that connection to the body because you've drifted off in
thought re-establish this intimacy this connection to body
this is the place to be
one breath at a time
if you have even the slightest anxiety about the meditation
maybe it's helpful if you could know that
it's trustable this practice trust it
it'll work itself out find help you find a way
there's no need to try to do it right
especially if you allow yourself just to feel it in your body whatever is here
let the body be the home for here and now
let the body show itself to you nothing you need to search
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps for a few moments can you allow yourself to be even more
fully centered in your body
perhaps feeling how your weight is supported by something the
chair your cushion the bed
feeling the stability of that support
how that's stable support affirms that your body is
here and now
and staying rooted in your body here
without leaning forward or leaning back without getting
pulled into the world of thoughts too
far bring into your hearts the world around you
the people in their circles around you and your neighborhoods communities
places of work towns countrysides
countries and continents and the whole globe
and you rooted here in this time and place aware and open to this wide world of
living beings and you are one of them
and in the awareness of this wide circle of
beings to sit here rooted and grounded with an open heart
and for these last minutes
to dedicate the benefits of this practice we've done
and may be open to the possibility that that dedication can be for
all beings for the welfare and happiness of others and that this might be your wish
that's in some way or other known or unknown that your meditation and the way you
live your life can be such that it leaves the world in
a better place may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
here we are
and yeah
no sound thank you everyone saying it so i jumped ahead
before all the buttons were pushed
so um for this week what i'd like to do is to talk about
um mindfulness of the body to make that the theme
and maybe as a theme it can be your theme as you go through the week that um you can um
so mindfulness of the body is one of the foundational basic
practices for mindfulness it um is
it's the first exercise in the discourse on the four foundations of mindfulness
the most basic teachings from the buddha on mindfulness practice and in that
there are six there's seven exercises now there are six exercises associated with mindfulness of the body
and uh here in the seven a.m sittings we've done the first one which is the first tetrad
of anapanasati so we did that in january and so i won't do it now this week
and and we'll do the remaining five and i'd like to think that these
remaining five are built on the foundation of the first exercise that those four tetrads of
mindfulness of breathing and we kind of have been the focus so much mindfulness of breathing
for um in the 7am sittings that we'll take that just is already kind of
established and then we'll go on to the other exercises
and now mindfulness of the body is such a wonderful practice it's a
provides so much one of the things important things it does which i'll emphasize today
it's a protection it's a way of being protected as you go through your life and because
when you're grounded in your body you're much more able to pick up a wider
range of what's happening around you the body is kind of like an antenna that
picks up through our all the different
forms of perception that the body is capable of including the perception inward perception perception to the emotional
reactions responses we have we're able to pick up what's going on
and how we're responding and when we feel there's danger when we feel that there's something to be concerned
about not only externally but also internally
when when we're in danger of losing our ethics
when we're in danger of losing our peace when we're in danger of acting on
something which would later regret acting on greed or
hatred or delusion and the body is a repository of so much
uh evidence for what's shifting and changing in us that uh sometimes it's the early warning
sign and sometimes it's the body that gives us indication of what's going on before the mind knows because the the
body is more attuned to our subconscious and uh in the mind sometimes is not so s
to tune to it maybe because we're preoccupied in other things rushing ahead and so many times in my
life so because i have a habit of checking in with my body
do i notice that i'm rushing or notice that i'm tense and or pulling back and
holding holding myself back from a situation and i don't notice that in the mind
because i'm thinking about things or i want things to be a certain way or you know i'm reacting and
living in the reactivity but because of the habit of connecting to my body i feel and sense what's going on
better and in the subconscious or the early kind of beginnings of things and so it keeps me
safe it keeps me from getting lost into that world of things so the body is a great protector for us
mindfulness of the body is if we stay connected and so the second exercise of of uh
mindfulness of the body in the four foundations of mindfulness is mindfulness of posture and that
doesn't take a lot of refined attention to the body to be aware of posture it's um so in terms of people who
they're many people who are not so connected to their body and there's a lot of reasons for that and
maybe we'll talk more about that as we go along here but but maybe at least we
can kind of recognize the posture that we're in and the bar for this posture mindfulness
is pretty low and so i'll read you so you can really know
believe me that how low the bar is the buddha says again
when walking a practitioner knows i am walking
when standing one knows i am standing when sitting when one knows i am sitting
when lying down one knows i am lying down so that seems like a pretty low bar do
you know that's pretty you know pretty obvious i hope that we're standing walking sitting lying down that
you know that you're doing that but you have to don't underestimate that tremendous value
of knowing this really knowing it so not just knowing it casually and
passing but to really kind of recognize have a clear recognition
i'm standing now i'm sitting now i'm walking it begins to
or laying down it begins to um create space in the mind for more present
moment awareness it interrupts the mindstream that were sometimes an automatic pilot
thinking and wanting where it interrupts the kind of preoccupation time times with emotions
uh rumination around him that's emotionally based that uh we get lost in
it's kind of like taking a sacred pause oh this is what i'm doing and then maybe
take time to feel this i'm standing here i am it's a chance for
the body to regroup to be organized to get connected to get grounded here i'm sitting before i start speaking
right away let me get grounded in my seat if you're about to speak at a meeting or
someplace maybe take a moment to feel yourself here sitting and in preparation so
you're not so completely caught in what has to be said so you're more receptive to the environment as
well because the more we are grounded here in the body the more the body awareness is
more available for what's going around as well around us
and um but certainly the mindfulness of the posture can be more refined
when we're standing are we leaning forward are we pulled back are we collapsed in
some way when we're sitting the same thing are we
sagging into the back of the couch removing ourselves from the conversation we have with someone
else or are we sitting upright so we're available and present so there's more of us
able to meet the person we're talking to or be present for the act of speaking or
whatever we're doing sometimes if we're to collapse in a chair
it might feel relaxing but there is sometimes a loss of attentiveness and presence and
involvement with what we're doing so you know and if we can sit in a
pos or sit or stand in a posture that is balanced and upright then um
there's we're available to more information what's happening to us like there's a greater range we notice
if we lean forward we notice if we're pulling back we're noticing for collapsing
but if we're always collapsed there may be less less variation that's possible uh it's kind of like if
we're in the midpoint it's like like a we feel the pendulum moving this way in that way but if we're stuck
on one end of the pendulum we don't have that refined sensitivity what's going on when we're walking
how are we walking what does it say about our mood our emotional state so all these different places what's
happening and when we're sitting when we're walking standing all these as well
are we doing so in a way that's physically healthy for us is it the one that is most puts the body
most at ease the least amount of tension being held to hold the posture
so it's a fascinating world the emphasis on posture and so
the buddha emphasized it you can keep it at a very low bar just to know your postures to go through
the day or you can be more refined about it and notice the details of posture and how
maybe you've lost a balanced posture and what does that tell you about yourself and and how is it that coming back into
a balanced posture protects you and keeps you more balanced
so you can do what you need to do in a better way
the virtue of this for this exercise is how incredibly simple it is
when walking know you're walking when standing know you're standing when sitting know you're sitting and
when you're lying down know you're lying down but this knowing is really know it
and see if when you if what what space is created with clarity arises
what um information then becomes available to you that if you don't just know it in
passing but you really in a sense stop and really know it over and over
again through the day so if you're inclined for this next 24
hours why don't you try to make a practice of mindfulness of posture
study of it study yourself through your posture study mindfulness that arises with
posture and how different postures support greater presence and greater mindfulness or lesser of it
just make a study and and if you have the occasion you might talk to other people about
what their experience of posture and mindfulness awareness of posture is in their lives
and you might get some fascinating conversations there are certain professions where posture is you know a key to what they how they
manage well and um and may the day be a wonderful day
of discovery and appreciation of this body of ours so thank you