all right so hello and welcome everyone to this rendition of happy hour where we
come together practice cultivate our hearts
our minds so [Music]
so for the theme for today um so many
themes it was hard to choose one for today but the one that i'd like to invite us to
practice with is is something actually that i've been
sitting within practicing with since our last time together um
i didn't teach on friday uh hillary substituted but on wednesday i shared um
forgiveness practices and and i wanted to do more forgiveness
which might still be coming up in part of the series and then that that evening um violet
shared something a quote that she had read which was a sense of gratitude looking
at uh what things that are available in your life that you
would have loved to have in the past and now now you have them they're they're part
of your life and the way that violet was breaking which was beautiful uh so giving her credit was um
i think with with the uh forgiveness practice we did a forgiveness for self and can be
challenging and yet what she was sharing was that it um she found it to
that she was much easier on herself there was less much less self-judgment than there would
have been a year ago now after a whole year of doing loving
kindness with happier these practices she realized wow there is so much more
kindness so much more care so much more ease for for herself and and this quote
something that you uh looking back something that you wish you had
or rather from the perspective of your past self you and looking saying oh i would love
to have the sometimes in the future and you realize oh actually you have it and there's a sense of gratitude for
for what arises so not just for uh cultivating meta but for so many other
ways so this is a great great tool you know great way of
shifting perspectives shifting perspectives because we tend to zero
in on what isn't going well what we don't have we
look at our lives from a perspective of oh i what i want to have in the
future the person i want to be and this is lacking this is not good enough whereas
one perspective here is looking at ourselves from the past perspective oh i would
have loved to have this for example this cultivation of the heart i would have loved to have
more this more that more whatever it is and realize oh that's actually here in my life i
would have more or a gift of covetous oh i wish i had more time to myself i wish i had more time to myself guess
what we've all had a lot more time to ourselves or maybe maybe not so much if you're a
caretaker but but so that would be one invitation that i like to work with tonight
um other invitations is with gratitude practice when we um think
of what actually the things that we take for granted today on the radio and npr i heard this
report of the very first experimental operation uh using gene editing
in the body so they're taking genes out it's actually in the body and the first couple of people who have volunteered
have are legally blind they have very very limited vision so they're able to
actually do the operation editing their genes
in their eyes in their eyes and this you know for
for those who have vision we take our vision for granted and and
yet hearing um the the people who had volunteered
with joy with hope uh who had very very limited vision
tunnel vision essentially no peripheral vision as they were describing um just made me today i
realized and i've been sitting in the space of gratitude in so many ways from the perspective of the past and
perspective of all the things we take for granted so so so much to to gladden the heart
so much to glide in the heart with to find support so i think i have said plenty
uh let's let's engage in this practice and see what comes up for us so so like to invite you to settle into
your meditation posture ah landing
spend a few minutes just arriving just arriving
letting go of all the words of all the activities
all the busyness
letting inviting the gaze of awareness to turn inwards
with the breath in the body and the lower abdomen each
breath received calming and settling like a lullaby
one breath at a time
inviting each muscle of the body starting from your toes your legs lower legs
knees your sit bones to relax
to give their weight to the earth to settle
your abdomen hmm my chest
the next out breath for the neck and shoulders
arms and the hands to let go
of their weight
for the muscles of the face the forehead
eyes in their socket to rest chin to cheek the cheeks
the muscles behind the ears
taking a refuge in this moment with the breath
here just here
and if thought arises
simply noticing
what has arisen and with the next exhale let it go
thank you but not now i'm giving myself to this practice please come back later
and come back to the breath to the body this is enough this is plenty
simplicity of this moment
when one engages with the simplicity
fully alive and present
is enlivening delicious
see for yourself
c
relaxing softening letting go of any tension in the body
with each out breath
here
now
continuing to feel
sensations of the body sensations of the breath
in the body so as i'll invite you
the next few invitations please stay connected to your body
feel your body your feet your hands your sit bones
connected to the cushion your abdomen
inhaling exhaling
while embodied let it spring let us spring
invite connect with the version of our younger
selves maybe when we were a kid
imagining when i went when i grow up i would love to
maybe it's a skill you wished you had or a training
or a line of work or a degree
or a sense in yourself maybe more confidence
maybe a knowledge
something connecting with that young version of
yourself in fact as your embody inhabiting
inhabiting that desire of the younger version of yourselves
as if you were looking forward into the future as a kid
when i grow up i would love it if equality that you have right now that
you wished for that you hoped for connect
with that hope that wish
they are us for this gift
now after you've connected with that wish
from the version from the younger version of yourself that perspective
now traveling in time again to this present moment when that has been accomplished
it has been attained
see if can be appreciated now more fully more wholeheartedly
with gratitude yes
but perhaps you take for granted is already here
seeing appreciated from the perspective of your past self
take some time relishing
and be mindful so that your thought your mind don't go on the
wild goose chase of things that you still want or you've
lost intent part of this practice is setting
intention intend
to bring back your mind your thoughts to this practice not lamenting not
self-judging choose not to do that you have a lot more choice
in this practice then you realize so exercise your choice stay
stay with the invitation for gratitude for what is here not what
is lacking
being fiercely compassionate with your own mind
not allowing it to go astray out of love and care for this training
for yourself
now let us travel back in time again you can go back to any time in the past
it could be childhood could be any time any other time
where your past self had this wish or if i could only have this gift
this ability this cultivation
or perhaps i was free of this challenge only
a time that there was this wish
which now has been satisfied so going back and connecting to that wish
i only had this or if only i didn't have this
challenge
deeply connecting with that aspiration with the aspiration for the gift
and now traveling again forward in time to your present self
for this gift this goodness has been attained
you are living your past dream
let yourself relish
in your own time let yourself travel back in time
see a younger version of yourself with an aspiration
a wish for something in the future
connect connect with that aspiration
after you've connected with it come back to the present where that gift has been attained
it's been accomplished
let yourself relish this gift in your
life
c
let yourself relish take time with relishing
what is present in your life what goodness there is
specially appreciated through the telescope of time from the
vantage point of the past
relishing relishing appreciating
the goodness
this present self this present life circumstances
it could even be last week or a month ago
there was a wish for something an
aspiration
there is so much goodness in each of our lives
if we simply look
may all beings everywhere know the goodness
in their lives know the goodness of their hearts
may all beings everywhere be free
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so
so much can arise with this particular way of practicing not just
gratitude and fullness of the heart just noticing all this goodness but we wake
up to so many ways in which
these gifts accomplishments goodnesses in our lives are here
the cultivation that perhaps we wished at some point to
appreciate them more and also maybe another aspect could be we get to see oh yes there was this
intention setting there was an intention setting in the past and now oh it's come to fruition
and it gives us aspiration it aspires us inspires us for further intention
setting for goodness for for our future self
so a lot came up for me as i was practicing with you so
much goodness in my own life and cultivation things i was taking for granted and looking from the
telescope of the past like wow here it is for example i remember
years ago um before before i had i think i had started practice but
but uh after the first few years of my practice there was still a lot of existential angst for me
about meaning of life purpose of life and that's one of the reasons why i went into
intense practice [Music] and through months and years of silent
meditation and practice and and various teachings it just all
all resolved itself all the existential angst and the questioning the fire
got resolved so there's a sense of i appreciate that for this being there's
a sense of ease um with with living dying
being not being that is a product that that a younger version of me would have loved to have it's like okay
it's it's been it's here so there's a sense of appreciation i hope that for you
also in this practice you discover different things so i'd love to open i'd love to open
um yeah for for comments nicholas says my heart lit
up when you said that we have more choice than we realize that's good and you can't end
it there's some symbols but that's so cute thanks nicholas that's lovely so appreciate your reflection
yeah and you have more choice than you realize exactly
it's the way that we choose to see it's a way of seeing the way we choose to see
way of saying so i'd love to invite you like to share in the reflections that came up for you
um trudy i won't see people okay some uh let's see i need to
go down and find your name if you raise your zoom hand it makes it a lot easier let's
see here there
okay trudy you're on
i asked you to unmute yourself
okay now i'm unmuted um i wanted to ask you i heard that um
you have taught um a class about um dying or
at end of life and if that's true i'd like to to know more
the name of it and where i could learn more about it yeah
yes i teach about mindfulness of death a lot trudy i teach
silent retreats day longs etc and the place you can find recordings
would be on audiodharma okay lungs and you can also find uh talks on dharmaseed dharmaseed.org
and audiodharma.org you'll find plenty of talks wheat seed
dharma seed d a a dharma and seed as in seed that you plant oh thank you
so much yeah i'm really interested so thank you you are so welcome trudy
your interest other reflections other questions
maybe what came up for you with this practice through the lens of time did it
work for you did it not work for you would love to hear neil please
so i mean the biggest discovery was i really wish for the wrong things when
i was younger you know i i mean you know you know i
wish you know people would stop bothering me you know i mean that was like one of the things you know particularly my ex-wife
right and it never occurred to me that i should just look to not be bothered by her you know right
you know i have no say over what you know other people do and just a whole bunch of stuff you know
right but you know finding some way to like be at ease with myself
you know even if it's only partial you know is you know yeah it never occurred to me it
was possible yeah yeah well thanks for sharing that
neil and also what i'm really appreciating in what you're saying is that it didn't occur to you then and
yet there was a wish not to be bothered and here an older version of you there is a
discovery you have discovered oh there is a way actually not to be bothered so i i take that as a yay
because the younger version didn't want to be but but didn't quite know but the older version has so much more
wisdom so yay here it is it's been accomplished
isn't that beautiful neil i take it as a yay too yay absolutely thanks so much for
sharing that beautiful i love this lens yeah
great stephanie says it was so beautiful to
see that even though my dreams have not come to fruition as i imagined as a younger person they are here in my life it was also
nice to have a sense of continuum of my dreams from then to now like my
life is not so fragmented as it sometimes feels thank you nikki oh thank you stephanie
really appreciate that reflection so powerful um
i think that's something that can come up um
when we see yes maybe not everything is here but there's there is this continuum
there is this continuity there's the sense of aspiration seeds that were planted just it yeah
beautiful beautifully set stephanie thank you and ruth i'm gonna ask you to hold on so
that we come back because uh i want to make some time for the prac small practice me so
we'll come back to you right after the group okay so please hold on great so dear ones let's let's turn
to practicing in small groups of three and we'll start with 15 seconds of
silent meta silent appreciation goodness for the younger version older version the
person you see on the screen and then you can share as much or as little as you wish
about how this practice was for you um and of course always holding yourselves
with kindness holding each other with kindness uh importantly so i'm going to create
the rooms okay welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed and as promised let's go to ruth before i invite others for the
reflections ruth please there you are kindly unmute yourself hi
um so the comment i wanted to make was sort of a little bit of um
during the meditation a little bit of an aha um so the the intentions that
that came to me during the meditation were the really big intentions that i
had when i was young intentions about having a family intentions about having
work that i had passion for and i've i have cultivated gratitude but there
was a kind of a closing of the loop that i don't think i really had then the loop closing
the loop was oh i i had an intention and then i made it happen
and the gratitude you know it's like bringing that full circle um uh
so that's just what i i wanted uh to talk about it's bringing the whole
uh bringing the experience of setting these really long term like multiple year
intentions that you know yeah i i did make that happen so i feel like
that felt really really pretty good yeah beautiful thank you for sharing that beautiful
lovely aha moment it's a beautiful aha moment of aspiration just
this what you shared and somewhat i would say similar to um what stephanie shared the sense of
continuity and also it came up for me too oh yeah there's a sense of aspiration that can continue like oh yeah here is
this being sitting upright from the intentions of the past oh no i can carry that into the future too so
beautiful thank you ruth for the way you you shared your aha moment lovely so dear ones
um yeah jerry appreciates your your aha moment also ruthless lovely
so dear ones time has come for us to bring to a close our practice together
so thank you so much for coming and practicing together
we do this work not just for ourselves but for all beings everywhere whose lives
we touch may all beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone