so
so let me talk a few minutes about this
uh
what's often called the investigation
factor
um so not quite loud enough someone says
so let me see
[Music]
so i think now is it better now the
sound
okay so let me
say a few minutes here about the
investigation factor of awakening
and it's usually called investigation
and people who look into this
will say that it's probably not the
right best translation
but it's a pretty good one overall it's
an overarching
generalization because
it involves uh a exploration
a discovery a deeper discernment
of what our experiences and
this process of exploration is in
english is often called investigation
and but investigation if it means a kind
of a deeper probing in searching
it's not what we're what is referred to
when we're doing this
vipassana practice but rather it's a
state of
openness and receptivity to allow
the experience to show itself fully to
us
and for me it's represented by the
question what
what is happening here what just what is
it
but we never look for an answer
as more that the what prompts a clear
looking a clear discovery
of a kind of a silent kind of
sensing or feeling or looking or
perceiving
of what is here and and in doing so
we're beginning to
in enact or tap into
our capacity for freedom that
uh it's so easy to be
caught and entangled by our experiences
by our thoughts by our feelings by
what's happening in the world
and there's so many ways we get
entangled so many ways in which we get
attached we get
reactive to how things are and when
there's reactivity
reactivity by itself is the is not is
not
freedom to respond
with choice to respond with wisdom can
it be an enactment of our freedom but
but to react is not so if we're always
reacting and being pulling around by our
thoughts and
hijacked by our thoughts if we feel like
we're a victim of experience
then we haven't discovered freedom
and one of the ways it can begin this
freedom is in acts of mindfulness
to be mindful of what's here but also
acts of mindfulness can also
grow to be a little bit stronger forms
of freedom
which is investigation to uh
to see to discover what is here
and the kind of core investigation
that's part of vipassana practice
is uh is what further on the retreat
inez talked about yesterday dhamma
vichaya
and vichaya comes from the word prefix v
i
and then the root word c-a-y-a
and um chaya means to heap up to
accumulate
and v means to separate and human beings
have an
amazing and a very important capacity to
generalize to
lump things together to to
hold concepts of things altogether and
and they're useful but also they can
limit our ability
to see clearly what's here to discern
distinguish
the details of our experience so if i
say that i had
um a you know
a difficult morning with the technology
then well that's a generalization but
what specifically was the experience
like of being here with
technology for this morning some of it
was quite delightful and
enjoyable and inspiring to see the
people in the retreat to
see the people on on youtube and
and with the chats for example and and
some of it was quite nice to be
exploring for me exploring the dharma
as i spoke it was nice to sit and
meditate well
while there was some quiet for me and i
was meditating
and and then there was the issue of
the technology that there's so many
different
devices and things here that i got
confused about
which charging battery charger that
was supposed to be at home and what was
supposed to be here and so the
so this with the you know it suddenly
went dark my laptop and
it wasn't actually unpleasant experience
at all it was just kind of it just was
what it was
and um suddenly this was there and there
was an issue to look into
and probably the most unpleasant part of
it all was
needing to ask my wife for some help
when she's busy at home and
and also wondering how i was going to
get back and having running in time for
the zoom people
and then the awkwardness of realizing
that you could hear what i was saying
some of you once
on youtube and um
let's see you know what what impact did
that have on people meditating and
but that was all very particular and as
i distinguished all the different parts
of it
i wouldn't say it was a challenging
morning here
it was it had its unique challenges its
own particular things
but i didn't lump it all together as
like a lousy morning with
technology it was all these little if
i wrote out the details the distinctions
of moment moment what was happening
there were challenging parts and not
challenging parts there were pleasant
parts maybe some parts that were not so
pleasant
and this ability to begin distinguishing
and not lump
and in sense buddhists are you know if
you know the distinction between lumpers
and splitters
buddhism thrives on on being splitters
on really seeing more and more carefully
what's really happening here
what are the details rather than
generalizing about things
and so this idea of this uh disability
this clarity of mind
that gets cultivated through mindfulness
when the mind gets clearer and clearer
and the details the particular
particularities the details of
experience the
unique little component parts of
experience
begin revealing themselves more and more
and more
and where that becomes particularly
important is when the capacity to
distinguish to see the particularities
the details of what goes on
is is
goes together with wisdom the wisdom
factor
and the wisdom factor is uh the
one the many things that are considered
wisdom
the factor of wisdom in in this practice
we do
but one of the core aspects is being
able to make the distinction
between what is helpful and what is not
the distinction what is wholesome and
what is not
what is healthy and what is not or the
distinction between what
has a an ouch in it or an ah
this is good or a distinction between
what is where freedom is or where
freedom is not
that distinction is a is the what wisdom
is capable of making
mindfulness puts us in the clarity that
we see things as they are
and see them clear and clear and wisdom
sees
what is useful and what is not and that
distinction
is where we discover the path where we
discover
uh where the choices can be
and so the simple distinction between
being entangled in experience
and being free when we investigate it
with wisdom we see actually it's better
to be free
than entangled and so to the degree
which we have in a capacity
we put effort and energy into going in
the direction
of freedom and in this case investigate
or
discern or see more clearly what the
experience is
and so it said that the the the
investigation factor of awakening that
clarity of mind that can really see the
details
of experience not lumping the
generalization of what it is
that that ability
then inspires the effort factor of
awakening the energy
because we see oh this is the direction
to go
this is where freedom is this is where
peace is
this is where um
the lack of stress the lack of suffering
is found
and that's inspiring to make that choice
and go in that direction
to go in that direction is another
manifestation
of our capacity for inner freedom
and as we walk this path we keep
discovering more and more ways
in which we can manifest or enact
our freedom until at some point freedom
becomes a state
that we live in as opposed to
something we find in the details of our
you know of how we live and the choices
we make in our life
so the investigation mindfulness
leads to the capacity to see
clearly that's called discernment
making distinctions investigation
and that in itself then is a
prompt or a catalyst for the effort
factor in practice so that the effort
factor of awakening can get born and
and come to fulfillment
and that'll be the topic for the next
topic for the retreat and the next topic
for
youtube and like tomorrow morning
so um thank you and
and i think this hopefully this uh
little technology issue today um
wasn't too much of a of
a was you know interruption at all and
it all worked well enough for everyone
so thank you very much and and
so we'll continue