so good day
and in a sense continuing with the theme of
patience for the week and yesterday talking about
patients under insult or not giving in to anger
we might feel angry but not to give into it
and
sooner or later when people practice mindfulness they probably will encounter
within themselves anger resentment
feelings of hostility towards other people
and these are important areas of practice to be present for
and to learn how to be present without giving in to them or collapsing into them
but also to learn how to be respectful of them to not condemn them or condemn oneself
that these states are present and then to learn to be wise about them
and then what i talked about yesterday about really seeing the difference between the thoughts that have to do with other
other things other people that take us away from our present moment experience
uh that's such an important discovery because you really see that difference
and then to be able to appreciate the value of presence the value of being
right here and not going into stories and ideas that are not here
this allows for a possibility a very important possibility
of in a certain way becoming larger
than our angers larger than our resentments
so rather than figuring out how to let go of them
or how not to have them we learn not to be
a victim of them we learn not to inhabit them or
let them take over and this idea of becoming big
a really you know it's a it's a way of inhabiting our experience
with a fullness and habiting it without
these ideas of other but also these ideas that we carry about
ourselves that diminish us that make us feel like we're less than
or inadequate or wrong or or
or even the ideas that i'm right is a kind of narrowing and limiting of
who we are and as we sit in mindfulness sit and practice and breathe
and learn to recognize these thoughts of other these also these thoughts of about
oneself that limit us that box us in that puts us into
a becoming being someone being someone
and it isn't that we need to become no one and nobody but we don't want to be limited
by these ideas and so to to learn to shed
the limiting ideas is part of the advantage of letting go of thoughts and coming back
to hear and inhabiting here so that it is
there's a fullness here
so to feel careful with the posture you take
or caring about the posture you assume for meditation
that it's a posture that maybe in some kind of way
would allow you to inhabit your
largeness your fullness not a posture that
there's a even a slightest tendency to collapse or shrink
but a more of an uprising especially for sitting upright
they're really inhabiting that uprightness
sometimes if you're sitting with the backrest it's helpful to kind of readjust a little bit so that
you're sitting a little bit straighter
to gently close the eyes and part of the
and and entering into the fullness of ourselves
it can be helped by this deep breathing at the beginning of this meditation
not forcefully not a way of activating ourselves
so much as inhabiting a fullness of being
taking a deep breath in which expands the chest and lifts the
shoulders maybe expands the belly so physically we become a little larger
but to kind of
use that largeness to become more embodied here
and on the exhale long relaxed letting go
to let go of thoughts to let go of ideas
opinions and some of your thoughts and ideas
maybe are just fine but it's so easy to have self-limiting thoughts
and so for a few moments just let go of all thoughts so that
even the self-limiting ones fall away or come down
so feeling a fullness of being as you inhale
and letting go of limitations as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and spend a few moments roaming around in your body
feeling the fullness of your body the three-dimensionality of your body
the substance of your body
the vitality of your body
a broad awareness of your body
that supports breaking free from limited ideas of self
self as inadequate or self as a victim
self as troubled self as
angry or resentful all those things might be there
but you can be bigger than it you encompass so much more
in your body your heart and your mind and to sit quietly breathing
in the expansiveness of your being
maybe with each inhale feeling the movements of
breathing in throughout the body or at least the torso that expands and fills you
and on the exhale letting go of your
thoughts calming the thinking mind
preoccupation with thoughts interferes with feeling or sensing the
fullness the largeness of our being
that is sometimes experienced better with the eyes closed
because it frees us from the thoughts ideas we might have about
who we are and we allow ourselves to feel
our being from the inside out expansive open unlimited
with every inhale being quiet and still to really feel
the fullness and then on the exhale to let the
thinking mind become quiet soft gentle
coming back into the fullness of your being that is lost when you're involved in
thinking
the fullness of being that might reveal to you
what is lost when you're preoccupied in thought
and as you meditate if you can find within
a sense of confidence
or maybe finding the place in your body that you most associate with confidence
maybe in infinitesimally infinitesimally
adjusting your posture so the posture expresses confidence
and then breathe with the confidence breathe through the place that
confidence lives in you
perhaps allowing your thinking mind to be quiet
or not taking away by taking a few moments to assume
that it's okay for you to sit quietly with
a quiet sense of confidence
in the fullness of your being
and imagining that any resentments you have
slide off your fullness of being slide off your
confidence like drops of water slides off a lotus leaf
not holding on to any resentments not holding on to any
anger not denying its presence
but not inhabiting the resentment letting it be like drops
running off the sides of a leaf
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to appreciate that this practice that we do
can help us to be free
or unstuck unlimited by anger or resentments
that it can give us a very different relationship where we're not
living in the anger or living in the resentments
and perhaps we can even let go of them
and in doing so become someone who
is safer for the world
someone for whom others do not need to fear because of their anger resentment
and in this way
this is one way that we can benefit the world from our meditation practice
so that we don't impose assert our anger onto others
our hostility
and may it be that our practice
is for the welfare and happiness of others may it be that
we consider how this practice and how we grow and develop in the meditation
how it can be up how it can live in the world
to make the world a better place may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so that guided meditation was
meant to support the topic i'll talk about now
another aspect of patience or this pali word kanti
and that is forgiveness forgiveness of insult
and forgiveness is uh held up as being a great ideal a
wonderful thing to be able to do and of course it's not easy
and there can be protests of all kinds
and there can even be some ways of practicing forgiveness which is not so healthy not appropriate
even so in the buddhist sense
of forgiveness forgiveness involves two things two
primary things it involves
letting go of resentment letting go of anger
towards someone or that has hostility for others
that's the first thing and the second thing it involves
opening up our good will to others opening our hearts
becoming friendly or well wishing for others in a genuine way
and we don't have to be loving that's why maybe loving kindness can seem like a little bit too high of an ideal
you know it's hard to love everyone but it's possible to open our hearts and
have good will to wish people well maybe from a distance
and and those two movements letting go of anger and then opening up the heart to include
let other people be in our heart to be a heart open to them that is good will
and the first one letting go of anger um is
you know one of the reasons to do it is for your own sake
so that you don't harm yourself resentment is a simmering
suffering it's a simmering injury that we do to ourselves
and us anger can that anger towards someone anger because someone has done something to us
that maybe it's you know long past the actual event um it's be kind of injuring yourself
there's a story that jack cornfield tells of two former prisoners
and one of them says to the other have you forgiven your captors
and the second one says no never they did horrible things to me
and then the first one says well then they still have you in prison
so this would be to be trapped in anger and resentment is a kind of prison
and it limits ourselves and i've known people who've had resentment for years
until they realized that the person they're resenting had gone on with their life
and maybe even forgotten who they were and and so the only one who was being harmed
by the resentment was themselves and they said wait a minute this doesn't make any sense
to live this way in some ways i'm doing my enemy a favor by continuing to
put salt in the wound or something so learning to let go of anger
or at least put it aside learning to let go of being a victim
or at least not being the victim not inhabiting it
making that our identity that i am you know you know that the whole whole definition
of who we are becomes around the injury that we received
and and so this idea of meditating as a way of reclaiming
a fullness of being uh reclaiming a largeness
and we discover in meditation how much our thoughts ideas concepts judgments
that we have makes us smaller limits us keeps us in check keeps us bounded keeps
us caught sometimes even in prison a kind of prison
and so to be learned to let go of thoughts learn to see thoughts and let them move aside or learning to kind of
become more embodied more fully alive may fully
uh in embodying inhabiting our life
so that maybe we still have resentments and angers but they get pushed a little bit to the
side are a little bit uh appendages to we are who we are not who we are
and uh they become you know maybe like a a jacket we wear
it still has role and is present and we can't deny it that's there
but uh you know we we don't we don't we're not we are not our jacket
we are so much more and so to begin to shift our
relationship to anger to resentment so that we're not caught by it
and this of course is a slow process is not done automatically or quickly but even the idea even the wish
the dedication to no longer be caught by anger resentment to work with it and
find a way through it is the beginning of becoming larger it's the beginning of becoming free
uh and to appreciate that out there there's there's some freedom there's some
taking agency there's a stepping away from it and becoming more
so this idea of ability to let go of anger and resentment and there might be other all kinds of
thoughts these other thoughts othering thoughts that uh keep us trapped in the anger
like you know i'm doing the you know i can't do the the person who hurt me i can't you know
do them a favor or i can't i can't condone them or i can't
um get let them get off the hook for what they've done and
and all those might be true in some ways but it doesn't mean that we have to close our heart to them it doesn't mean
we have to stay with our anger our wisdom our understanding our memory of what happened
might lead us to behave a certain way around the person like say well if you continue that kind of behavior i can't
be with you or i have to be cautious with you because i was hurt before
or some you know who knows all kinds of things have to happen in the world but
but we don't have to be trapped in the anger so forgiveness then in buddhism is
letting go of our resentment and anger and the advantage of that to the word forgiveness
is forgiveness kind of implies we're giving something to someone else and that makes it a little more
complicated the social relationships and the nature of the injury and what happened and
and maybe maybe we're not ready to give anything to people but we can let go for our own sake let
go of the anger the second step is this loving kindness this good will
is because if we keep our hearts closed to other people we're also in some ways limiting ourselves we're injuring
ourselves and to really appreciate that gives us a reason to have good will
that's not an argument that they deserve to have our good will or they don't deserve it or something
independent of whether they deserve it or not which is maybe a silly silly topic
you deserve you to not to be limited by your thoughts by your contractions by
how you are limited and so for you to open up the heart works so much better
when there's good will it's freer it breathes easier so then to come find that's not it's not
easy to do this but this is a practice to find that okay where can i have the good will
and if those two things can be done letting go of anger and having good will
in shorthand we can call that and and then the forgiveness practice of
buddhism maybe is more accessible so sometimes we forgive others
for how they've harmed us and some people will do that in meditation practice and even have a
words they say that classically would be something like for whatever harm others have done me
intentionally or unintentionally i now forgive them and now when you hear that word forgive
you understand it to be letting go of anger and opening your good will
it's also uh can be a beautiful thing to request forgiveness
there's there's often we have to be large enough big enough to um
let go of our conceit let go of our of our
or even some certain kind of negative pride
to ask for forgiveness and and so it's a beautiful thing sometimes
you know for whatever ways that i have harmed you intentionally or unintentionally please forgive me
um and um and then the person we're asking maybe they can understand what it means is please don't hold your anger against
me um it isn't that you have to approve what i've done or didn't you know
somehow get me off the hook entirely for what i've done that might have hurt you there might be consequences
but it's kind of like asking please could uh could you accept me again without your anger
and offer some some level of good will as we find our way forward with the challenges we have
and then also towards oneself for whatever ways that i have harmed
myself knowingly and unknowingly may i forgive myself
and for some people this is the most difficult one but the i that does the forgiving
is the i that is beginning to discover how not to be limited small
being the victim but actually begins to breathe freely and openly and holds everything
um makes space for all of who we are it's a coming from a place of strength
and largeness of great capacity to be present for our
experience without being caught in it and so as we practice mindfulness we are
slowly over time developing a greater capacity greater strength greater sense
of unlimited quality and confidence here
that all the things that detract from that they don't necessarily go away
but they become smaller they become appendages they become something which we take into account we're wise about
we're caring about we're compassionate about but we're not defined by it
and to not be to be defined by the things that limit us
is a fantastic thing and maybe it helps us to live a life of we're ready
to forgive ready to let go to not live in the anger not live with resentment
and to open to goodwill for the world and what a great thing
to become someone who's safe for others they don't have to be afraid of our resentment but they know
to live with our resentment but they live with our good will
may we live in this world offering good will to all that we meet
thank you