c
hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour
hi and if you can hear me okay if you would give me thumbs up audio
okay fantastic great welcome so
we have a theater too to say hellos and
to warm up the space with our voice with our hellos i'm nikki i'm in mountain view
california now i'm seated oloneyland today cloudy outside a little drizzly
so who's here who wants to say hello
hi i'm susan um i use she her pronouns
and i'm on unseated alone land um the by the mo the amu matson
tribe and the waswas awaswa speaking peoples and um i'm really grateful
to be with you all really really grateful thanks thanks susan
grateful you're here practicing sangha welcome hello mari christine from
down under from sydney australia how's the weather on your end today
tell us in your summer and hello oh warm she says it's great
and hello from dallas from dallas glad to be with the sangha says bill
and hello violet from rainy san francisco
yep drizzly down here i guess more rainy up there anybody else wants to say hi before we get started
oh we have elsa hi says jonathan from walnut creek and kevin says hello from millbrae plain
rain okay brain in the bay area hello from dawn from beautiful islamabad
good morning to you don lovely to to have you from beautiful islamabad
how's the weather tell us and hello jesse from san rafael
is it raining in santa fe jesse yeah light spring rain yeah
same here hi from nancy in redwood city and it started raining here and my newly
planted plants are delighted oh yay nice and dawn says great weather in
islamabad lovely nice oh this is so sweet to get these weather reports from different
places in the world different time zones sweet
so let's get started oh yes and we have clifton saying hello
greetings from uh warm greetings from bangkok how's the weather in bangkok clifton tell us
if you would kindly uh put it in chat in youtube all right so let's get started
and thank you neil from new hampshire putting the information about
happy hour google groups where information can be shared and
connection with sangha members can happen so i changed the settings before we get into
the little dharmat and guided meditation so there will be
no accidental unmuting here let's change those settings
and all the chats will come to me if there's anything urgent you need to communicate
and starting the recording for the sake of audio dharma
okay great so ah welcome to happy hour
and for today's practice together um i'd like to offer a practice
of um conti as we continue exploring and practice the formal practice of
opeca opeca equanimity cultivating equanimity
and the category we'll work with today is the benefactor
and benefactor is someone who's supported us who's been there for us in
some way and maybe not in every aspect of our
lives but they've supported us and it could be a friend who's been for us in challenging times could
be a parent could be a [Music] relative it could be a coach a teacher
someone whom we feel this relationship oh there are there are benefactors we've benefited
from their goodwill from their support in some way in our life again it doesn't have to be continuous
and all the time but maybe at some point either right now or at some point in our lives this benefactor has been of
support to us and regarding the practice of opica
practice of equanimity as as a cultivation practice since it is
the fourth brahmavihara up the word itself in pali
relates to meaning having it a wider perspective having a say bird's eye view
having seeing more fully having perspective so the idea of
cultivating equanimity is when you have a wider perspective instead of having a narrow perspective of
oh this is awful this is terrible they will never change or it's all my fault or their fault you
know the the or the rumination that our our human minds tend to do the loops we
tend to fall into if we make our perspective if we intentionally make our perspective
wider to look more more
fully as if you were sitting on top of a mountain and saying everything that's going on is happening
everything that has happened in the past will happen in the future right now for all beings this sense of
large perspective ah the heart relaxes the heart relaxes
when you see the perspective of what has been what may become the impermanence
all the causes and conditions the heart can relax with the space of equanimity equipoise
so we'll as always we'll start with
settling in with our breath our bodies
for the beginning of the practice for the first part roughly the first 10 minutes and then
we'll turn our attention to as i will guide us into cultivating
equanimity turning our hearts our minds towards equanimity for the life of the benefactor
so let's let's practice so i invite you to get into your meditation
posture whatever it might be if you need to lie down
that's what your body needs that's okay
if you need to sit up straighter
or relax allowing your spine to be
straight
landing relaxing softening into this body
relaxing your feet
feeling your feet on the floor connected
rooted
relaxing your legs
letting go of any holding tightness lower legs and upper legs
relaxing your sit bones
from the inside
letting the entire weight of your torso drop ah tear sit bones
further relaxing your legs
any tension being held in your lower abdomen
your groin area ah let it be dropped
inward into the cushion
hmm
let your abdomen feel soft
receiving the brush receiving the breath
softening relaxing
your neck and shoulders
dropping the weight of your arms
letting your hands
be soft any tension melting
inviting any holding tightness in your face
to melt
the muscles of your forehead behind your eyes
behind your cheeks your chin muscles of the jaw
the next out breath
letting the tension drop ah even more d player
feeling the entire body relax relaxed and soft
the breath received in the lower abdomen
here here now
if you notice the center of gravity has gone up into the head thinking
thinking provide the center of gravity to be
lowered lowered lord
to the lower abdomen sit bones inviting the thoughts the thinking to
sell in this moment no need
right now for these thoughts gently telling them thank you not now
come back later releasing letting go dropping
in
just this breath taking refuge
away from thoughts preoccupations in this moment
collecting gathering yourself
safely right here receiving the breath
in the abdomen settled grounded
sensing feeling this body
stable grounded connected to the earth
being breathed
now like to invite you as you feel your body
your legs your feet your sit bones connected
to the floor to the cushion in lieu of the earth earth on earth embodiment so important
in all practices especially practicing equanimity
sensing the body feeling the stability of groundedness
connection the touch points
so you feel the body and the breath moving through
imagine you were sitting on top of a
mountain and well connected to the earth
you have a wide perspective
sitting being breathed relaxed
comfortably with a 360 degree view all around
of the valleys
rivers trees
greenery the sky
clouds sense of having a wide perspective
let your body relax with the spaciousness
spaciousness all around
as far as the eye can see
spaciousness sitting and being briefed
in this body
as of the sense of spaciousness of vision proverbially
having a wider perspective expansive spacious perspective that
makes the heart to relax open up not feel confounded
into a narrow tight perspective but a wide perspective
of seeing so much possibilities perhaps even
this represents seeing the causes and conditions so many influences
of events the unfolding of events
past to present future
space and time spaciousness of space and time
just sitting being breathed letting the body be relaxed in this
spaciousness being apart
of all this
now this sense of spaciousness bringing to mind
your benefactor a benefactor someone who's been
there for you supported you in some way in your life
a teacher a friend even a parent a relative even a pet
that you feel is your benefactor your supporter someone who's been there for you in some
way
bring this person to mind this being
under this wide perspective allowing yourself to connect
with one aspect of this being's life that is
somewhat challenging
challenging for them
let yourself connect with this benefactor with a sense of care
sense of gratitude sense of good will
you care for them
and you're concerned also for their well-being
and you feel their challenge
for this practice just as you're connecting
the sense of good will care holding presence not turning away
from this benefactor sense of connection to them
holding it with care and with a sense of spaciousness of equanimity
see if this kind of a relationship can be established
connected acknowledging appreciative caring
caring for the person the being and spacious spaciously holding their circumstances
i love her a few
sentences a few phrases of equanimity
and stay warmth in this practice or choose whichever
works for you
i care for you but i can't control your happiness and unhappiness
whether i understand it or not things are unfolding according to a lawful
nature
may i were you or we
accept the arising in passing
of things with equanimity and peace
i care about you
and i trust that you have your own journey
staying connected to your body sends of spaciousness as if sitting on a
mountain top connected to this person to this
benefactor this being
your appreciation and care for them and holding their challenge
with equanimity equipoise
may i may you may we accept be at peace with things
as they are
and for the last couple minutes of this practice
letting there be ease acceptance equanimity with whatever rose
during this practice period whether thought arose distracted mind
sleepiness restlessness
may i accept may i be at peace with the comings and goings of events
in this mind and heart
may i accept be at peace have equanimity
old spaciousness and relaxedness
whatever arose which cannot be changed
i appreciate that i showed up that i practiced as best as i was able to
and have equanimity with the rest
may all beings be at peace
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you all for your practice
so i'm so calm i can barely speak
so i'd love to invite you to share reflections about what you
discovered in this practice today you can type them in chat
if you type them practice and then privately to me i won't say your name publicly i will say your name
you can raise your hand your zoom hand because i may not see you if
you raise your physical hand to share your questions your reflections
for the benefit of the sangha so many different aspects and elements
to this nicholas please um an image that
was helpful or kind of resonated for me is i sit with my my one palm in the other palm
and the image was kind of you know the person is walking on the
earth and the earth is kind of this vast thing supporting them right and there's a care and the earth
meeting your feet like every step you take there this meeting gets so there's a care but it's very vast right it's not like
the earth is fixated on each little step that you take and i kind of just felt like
the there was a kind of vastness in my palms like my palms could kind of hold the person and kind of meet
with the same spaciousness that their feet meet the earth that helped me find kind of a lot of big
space to hold them and still care for them
beautiful thanks for sharing that nicholas i love i'm feeling into what you just
described this palm holding the other palm this physicality
of you actually feeling this ah the sense of support and then that connecting that
physicality that embodiment which i keep saying i sound like a broken record
this embodiment that you experience then bringing up the sense of ah stepping or being each step on this
earth being supported uh and this vastness is so much space um
you know the spaciousness of earth in a way which as i say that i think of there is a suta where um the
the four elements so the the air element the spaciousness of how air space is is
so supportive and then the earth the expansiveness of earth uh being so supportive so the earth
element in this case that you brought into your practice so beautiful thank you for sharing that
that's lovely thanks nicholas
any other reflections ah and i see on youtube when i invited clifton to
share how the weather was in bangkok it came in later when we had started the practice smoggy and humid here today but
there's blue in the sky that's almost like equanimity practice yeah smoggy and human but blue in the
sky can all be held in the expansiveness of the sky
so other reflections other questions what did you notice what
came up for you what was easy challenging it's all good
all welcome
nancy says embracing the individual choices others make even though they may differ
from what we would do yes yeah yeah and for the heart to be
at peace with with those choices and with the unfolding that each being has
their own their own journey as we wish them well so
continuing to have the sense of care for them but this sense of spaciousness of space
earth etc so yeah i appreciate that
yeah any other reflections
questions comments complaints what did you observe
susan says i know that i need to hear about embodiment a trillion more times
thanks susan i will say it a trillion more more times every practice session
can't it's so important in practice i can't emphasize it enough
i think in my practice also when i discovered how important embodiment
and one reflection coming in i had a repetitive aloof voice that kept
repeating not my problem not my problem not my problem every time i tried to picture another
person's troubles okay great so glad you shared this this is fantastic
so this will come up of course this will come up as i've mentioned near and far enemies so this
near enemy is uh it's kind of like not my problem kind of like aloofness not my
problem not my problem so so the invitation here if that comes up for you and for for others because it
will come up in this practice someone when you're practicing is to to first really connect
take a step back and go back into the sense of connection with the person
your care for the benefactor that you really care this person for having been there for you and being here
for you and really connecting with their humanity when that's really really established then
that might be a good time to then slowly bringing in the problem they're facing and then see
if that might be a gentler way to connect in this way so
that's an invitation there i hope that's helpful so
and kim says a thought of problems came into my head and i slid into practicing
equanimity with the issue and found spaciousness and peace ah nice
nice so the the practice of equanimity in this case turned to the
problems that came into your own head um and problem solving and ah economity
equanimity lovely great and that's perfectly fine too turning the practice where it's
appropriate where it's needed lovely so
[Music] dear ones ah with equanimity and spaciousness of
heart let's turn our hearts to supporting and practicing
spaciously with each other
so the invitation now for the small groups is will
spend 30 seconds first with silent meta just wishing the others
well 30 seconds of silent meta connecting with their humanity
knowing that they're wishing us well in the same 30 silent seconds and then opening up to whatever you like
to share and i see a question that just came in i'll address this after we come back from small groups
so um yeah and see if you can have equanimity
and spaciousness either with a sense of space or sense of embodiment physicality the earth element
supporting yourself and inviting others to feel supported in your heart
in this way so let's see here
almost that you can practice continue to practice equanimity while i make the groups
here we go okay they are open now here we go
enjoy
you
uh
okay
ugh
have a nice evening
okay welcome back everyone
welcome back so we have a couple minutes for reflections
oh actually i'll address the the question that came in just before we went into groups and
um and then i see marie christine's hand is up so so the question that came through was
how to help someone who's suffering and at the same time let them let them and understand that they have their own
journey that's a great question it's it's the both end right it's the both end of caring for
someone supporting them compassionately not saying oh you have your own journey you're suffering it's okay
you have your own journey we're not saying oh you know it's my i need to fix this for
you it's both it's it's really finding the balance and that's what makes being
human and having relationships and having a a compassionate heart makes it
interesting because you want to care of course and support for others but but realize that yes they
have their own journey so it's it's both and and um yeah there might be more to your
question might be more interactive but but i think at this point i'll leave at that and if there is more you can raise your
hand and can discuss but um marie christine please
i was explaining to the group that you know whilst we might be saying in equanimity um you
know i care for you i wish you well but i'm not responsible for your happiness or your sadness i kind of
think but we're not islands and what about the responsibility that perhaps i should take
if maybe my actions of the wrong speech have actually caused unhappiness i know it's quite common now to get to say oh you know you
can make choices and your study are responsible for how you feel but we're all interdependent and what
happens to that part where i have to take responsibility because maybe i put my foot in it and i've actually upset someone
yeah yeah yeah yeah exactly yeah so so this uh you know there are so many
different practices and there's the right practice at the right time and and having equine
you know trying to say what may you have equanimity with me having hurt you is you know obviously is not a very wise
way to go about it so yeah it sounds like this might just be the
the it's a hammer right this may not be the right so this might actually need a
what is the pliers like oh let me take that nail that i just put and let me just take that out
instead of i don't know the main was a terrible metaphor but you get the picture right yeah
so um so yeah thank you yeah thank you so much murray christine thank
you yeah any other questions reflection from the person who had
asked the earlier question if if there's any follow-up you want to type or raise your hand and
[Music] and we can follow up on that you're welcome too i'll
give it a moment
okay all right so so
thank you all for practicing these practices both for your
own benefit and to serve all whose lives you touch directly and
indirectly may all beings be happy may all beings be free
including ourselves
thank you all and now as it's become our tradition
i'm going