good evening welcome welcome good evening and of course i always have
to say this well if not good evening good morning good afternoon good day whenever you are listening to
this or watching this
yeah what a pleasure it is to practice together
so we'll start with a guided meditation
and just to come into the body the invitation
is to bring our awareness to the experience
of being here now
that is what does it feel like to sit and know that you're sitting
feeling the pressure of the chair or cushion against the body
or maybe you're sitting on the couch sitting on the bed
whatever it might be just feeling connected
grounded
and when the mind wanders away as it will we just very gently
simply begin again noticing the pressure against the body
the places of contact
and of course this body is breathing
so we might bring our attention to the sensations of breathing
we don't have to change it manipulate it breathe in any special way
we're just noticing what is the experience what are these
sensations what does it feel like to have an in-breath
can we notice the beginning the middle the end of an in-breath
what about an exhale how does that feel what does that feel
like
and if we set the intention to be with the sensations of breathing
of course we notice that the mind isn't necessarily stay
where we set the intention
so we might do a gentle inquiry
what is it that pulls the mind away
for example might there be
a quiet idea
that says this would be so much better if only
blank if only the neighbor's dog were more quiet
quieter if only
the temperature were a little bit cooler or warmer
if only i had a different type of cushion to sit on
if only my knee didn't bother me
do we have these ideas desiring something to be different
something to be changed to make it just
right
can we just allow it to be how it is how our experience is
without demanding comfort or ease
but instead is there a way in that which we might find the comfort in ease in this moment
by putting down relaxing softening
this may be quiet demand that things be different
can we allow things to be as they are during this meditation
can we do this in a kind-hearted gentle way
just noticing if we have this strong wish for things to
be different so that we might meditate properly or
something like that
is there a desire for things to be perfect
it's perfectly natural
can we allow that desire to be there
so being with the sensations of breathing
and noticing what takes us away
and we might notice that we have a desire for things to be different
thinking if only this were different then i could meditate
we're just noticing
learning to recognize when we have this feeling of if only
this were different this persistent feeling we need
something else we need something else to be able to
settle into this moment to be happy
whatever it might be
and to be able to notice this natural inclination of the mind
without following it all the time
if ever without fall succumbing to the seemingly
authority of this like i can't possibly
being mindful while i'm also having this experience
while i'm the refrigerator is running too loud or
or my back is bothering me whatever it might be
as we learn to notice the way that we often have this if only thinking
increases our capacity to recognize well is it true
maybe this isn't ideal isn't perfect doesn't match my preferences exactly
but can we be okay with it and increases our capacity to be with
discomfort things not being exactly as they are
and with this increased capacity we can bring wisdom the best version of
ourselves to more and more situations instead of collapsing around them
or doing some behavior or saying something that we might regret
later just because we're feeling uncomfortable
a big part of this practice is increasing our capacity to be uncomfortable in this way
might we bring some wisdom to not only our experiences but to be
able to support other people maybe in their experiences too
so that our practice can be the benefit not only for ourselves
but for those we come in contact with spreading out to all beings everywhere
[Music]
good evening good evening welcome welcome warm
a warm welcome to everybody wherever you are whomever you are
a number of years ago i heard an explanation or a discussion about mindfulness practice
i had a big impact on me i felt like when i heard that um i had like a click
like oh now i understand something and i've even used this and taught this
when i'm teaching them mindfulness and that is this idea that
we we can use an image of that when there's perhaps a really slow stream
in fact maybe we're on a hike and we there's a little bit of water we have to cross over and we're not even sure
is this water moving or is this just uh like underground
spraying or something like this and then often what you can do right of course is like put a stick
and then you can see if there's a little bit of a wake that comes after it or you can see the
water kind of like part around the stick so it's an indicator of oh
yeah it's moving and shows you which direction it's moving but it wasn't obvious until you
put the stick in the middle and held the stick still
so in the same way mindfulness like when we choose an object of meditation such as the breath
as we often do not until we choose to kind of have the
mind be right on the breath so until it's kind of like putting the stick in that we notice oh how often that the mind is going off
and doing other things everything except being mindful of the breath right
but we wouldn't have noticed unless we had set the intentions at the anchor of being mindful of the
breath we wouldn't have noticed how our mind is often wandering all over the place and following this and following that
being distracted by this or something like that
so in this way we can consider that mindfulness practice is a great way to really learn about
ourselves to learn about what takes us away from the breath
what is so compelling that we can't stay there and when does it happen so
mindfulness practice is a great way to have some greater understanding
and in the same way just like having a breath helps us to
become more clear about when we're not on the breath
and the same way we can consider ethics as a way for us to notice what's
happening when we are considering doing something that might be questionably ethical
maybe we wouldn't even notice some of these things we would notice the large ones
but maybe some of the more subtle ones we wouldn't even notice unless we had set the intention to
behave ethically of course all of us want to behave ethically but
there might be a way in which when we set our intention with commonly known as
the precepts that we start to notice all these little ways in which we might be
rationalizing or somehow not really stain with
our intention to be ethical
and i'm bringing this up or i want to talk about ethics a little bit here
not in some moral heavy-handed way
there are so many different ways we could approach ethics and morality and the polly word is sila
there's so many different ways and could give a whole you know combination
of a whole series of talks in different ways but one way i would like to look at it tonight
is the relationship between sila and suffering that is that sometimes
the way in which we are deviating maybe i'll say from the ethical precepts
which i'll talk about in a moment is a way to help us understand some of our sources of
suffering either that we're causing for ourselves or maybe that we're causing for others
but it's a way to understand ourselves
to practice with ethics is to an opportunity for some reflection but why am i doing what i'm doing and
why do i not want to do this other thing that i don't want to do
and i would like to propose that we don't have to use it in a way with judging ourselves oh i'm a bad person
because of x or that person is a bad person because of why
i would like to say that's not so helpful i didn't actually be increasing the suffering but instead can we
look at um our relationship with ethics and the way that we behave as a way to
support our wanting to have less suffering in our lives
so many of us come to meditation practice with this wish to have less suffering
and sometimes there can be a little bit of bewilderment like why is my life not unfolding in a direction that i want it to or why
do i still have um so much suffering discomfort in our in my life
so this can be dare i say a tool ethics can be a tool that might help us to unpack and
understand ourselves better as i said there's a number of ways in
which we can talk about ethics both the specifics about it as well as the
role it plays and meditation practice the role it plays and buddhist practice
but right now i'd like to focus on the its relationship with suffering
we know that the buddha is concerned with suffering and i'm using suffering as a generic
word to cover this really broad range from a little bit uncomfortable
to great harm terrible harm so i'm using this generic
word to cover this whole range in the buddha i mean he's a famous
saying right that he only taught about suffering in the end of suffering so we could use that as a lens through
which to view the ethics about okay how is this related to suffering in the end of suffering because of course
also the buddha said right the first noble truth there is suffering
all of us have it it's part of the human condition but maybe we can look at it or work with
it a number of different ways so one way that we might look at ethics
or sila is through five precepts that are commonly held
by lay buddhist practitioners monastics they have a whole another set
i'm not going to talk about them in addition to these five so the five precepts perhaps many of you
know them is first is to not kill living beings
the second is to not take that which is not freely given sometimes you know not stealing the
third is to use our sexuality in a wise way not to
harm with our sexuality the fourth is to not harm with our
speech and the fifth is not to use intoxicants that lead to
heedlessness so i'd like to unpack these a little bit
not so much to talk about the precepts themselves even though i'll say a few words about them
but what can we learn about suffering kind of using these as a
way to investigate suffering
maybe something else that perhaps many of you know that there's the suffering that leads to more
suffering and then there's the suffering that leads to less suffering
so how can if we're going to have separated our life can we have more of the suffering that
leads to less suffering and some people might say some of the precepts is that maybe it's
uncomfortable to do some of these things but it creates the conditions in which
our life can unfold in a way that supports well-being in a way that supports happiness
so this idea of the suffering that leads to more suffering and the suffering that leads
to less suffering the precepts are such a rich place to explore this
oops sorry i'm not touching the microphone there hopefully that wasn't too loud
so can we use our relationship with the precepts as it may be a starting place to look at
what's underneath our wanting considering to break a
precept i'm assuming that none of us are murderers necessarily or
terrible thieves or rapists or some of these things
but maybe some of the more subtle ways in which we might
rationalize or bend the rules a little bit something with the precepts
but to notice as part of our practice how does it feel before
like when we're considering breaking a precept
how does it feel while we're doing it how does it feel afterwards is it
increasing our suffering or is it decreasing our suffering
and maybe i'll put in there recognizing that part of this suffering is maybe to recognize that it
takes time that when we learn about ourselves we when we start to learn and i'll speak
more specifically about this in a moment but when we start to learn about ourselves when we investigate
our relationship with the precepts or when we're about to break them and we see oh wow i didn't realize
this about myself and yet i hear i am still doing this this behavior that of course is the
suffer is a type of suffering but hopefully it leads to less suffering
okay the first precept to not kill a loving living beings not
loving beings either sometimes we could expand this to not
harm in fact we could generalize all five precepts to say not to cause harm
but the first one we could say not killing and we can ask why do people kill
if we were to think about um killing other humans of course there's like fear perhaps
underneath that or a wish for control or wish for power
so if we f find ourselves in this murderous rage
maybe there's some something in there about this fear or maybe there's a
feeling out of control and wanting to gain control or something like this so is there
something for us to explore if we find ourselves with this i
even the idea of breaking a precept but of course there's not only other human
beings what about um for certain pests
that um we might have this want to kill them for to protect our family or protect our
resources you know for termites for example and for us to really explore
well what is my relationship to killing leaving beings if i'm going to
use an exterminator with termites for example i'm not going to tell you what to do but
just to notice what your thoughts are what your thinking are how does it feel
and you know and to use it as a support for practice
what about with uh ants and insects sometimes it might just be habitual
maybe we grew up that when there's a mosquito we just slap them and kill them or flies
or something like this or with ants or but is there a way in which
we might make an effort to keep our living spaces really clean so that
ants don't have anything to eat so when the scouts arrive those ant scouts they're not sending
back word that there's plenty of food or water i guess maybe too
so i don't have the answers to this but is there a way in which we can explore these precepts and our
relationships to them so not only in our behaviors and activities that we are doing
but also in our meditation maybe we might notice that when there's
uh some discomfort in the body we might have this feeling like we'll do anything to make this go
away this feeling like i don't know a little bit of feeling out of control like just make it
stop just noticing if that comes up and is
there a way that we can hold our discomfort so that we don't tip into this
having feeling things insisting that they be different
can we stay with that discomfort can we allow that discomfort to be there of course
honoring our body honoring our limitations being wise not harming ourselves
but is there a way also in meditation that we might explore this uh some of the discomfort
that might support our wanting to harm or kill others and can we increase our capacity to be
with that discomfort what about this second precept
not taking that which is not freely offered
so we might notice probably we're not uh most of us aren't thefts of
big obvious things but maybe we take things from the office maybe when we visit people's houses
we i don't know maybe we take shampoo or something like this even though it's not really offered or
or maybe we take people's time they're busy and we feel like we really
have to tell them things something or they want to uh we want them to advise us and but they don't
really have time then or i don't know all these different ways in which we might take things that are not
freely offered and do we rationalize it oh they won't notice
oh they have so much money they can totally afford it i can't afford it
or is there a way in which we don't we're a little bit numb to ourselves and we're but now i'm not
feeling what does it feel like to take things that are not freely offered is there also maybe a sense of um
self-righteousness or i'm so important it doesn't matter i'm just going to take what i want everybody else doesn't
matter so much is there a little bit of self-righteousness that's in there
again we're looking at this now so that we can judge ourselves but just as an exploration of where is
their suffering and if we're taking from others and it's
not really freely offered i would like to suggest there's some suffering there
either there's some suffering because our desire is so strong that we feel compelled that we have to
take things in order to be happy or maybe it's just that we're not
sensitive to the boundaries of what's ours and what's others and that not being sensitive to boundaries can
create suffering in so many other ways in our life if not by uh taking things
or maybe we have a strong sense of lack i don't have enough i don't have enough
i need more i need more i need more i need this and this and this and this and this and it doesn't matter whether it's offered
or not i need it so that's another way in which there
might be an exploration around this precept to not take that which is not
freely offered which is a little bit more strict than just not stealing
but that which isn't freely offered and whenever we're tempted to or we do
just to have this reflection what can we learn about ourselves
and in meditation we can notice that if we have this feeling in meditation
like oh i need this in order to meditate properly i need that
or this feeling things have to be different i need more or things to
somehow be other than they are
can something we can explore in meditation and that might be something that might
be supporting our wanting to break a precept
the third precept about being wise with our sexuality
so the precept assumes that sex is between consenting adults
but we'll just lay that as a i think that hopefully that goes without us saying and um
when it's explained in the sutras it's really about honoring commitments
and honoring vows and
and protections that are in place for people
and if we find ourself wanting to break a precept make a commitment a vow
is there what's underneath that like what's what's supporting fueling that maybe there's
a sense of loneliness that we're trying to fill maybe we don't feel connected to
others and we're trying to have sex
inappropriately in it with inappropriate partners just because it's outside of a commitment or it's causing somebody to
break a commitment about either yourself or your partner
is there a sense of loneliness or maybe we need some reassurance
of our attractiveness or worthiness or something like this
and many of us want to live a life of of love but are we using our sexual energy in a
way that promotes that that allows that to happen
or if we're having a lot of casual sex with consenting adults of course then we can just ask
dazar how does that support our meditation practice or our life
so in this way we can as i've been saying we can use the precepts as a way to help us reflect on our behavior and
the decisions that we're making again not in a way that we have to say i'm a bad person
i'm a bad buddhist but as a support for practice what can
we learn about ourselves might we find a way in which there could be less suffering with this reflection
and then the fourth a precept to not use false speech so not to lie but
maybe we could expand that to like write a speech many of you know includes not only should
what we're saying be true but it should be kind it should be timely and it should be
beneficial to be helpful for others
so we could have this reflection why do we tip the truth even
if it's just a little white lie is it because we want to be liked
is it because we want to get our way maybe we want to we don't feel like we
can speak directly so we're kind of we're manipulating people to believe something so that
they'll behave in some particular way or are we trying to hide something that
we're ashamed of
i'll say it maybe for me that very early in my practice i took on this precept
of not speaking falsely you know always telling the truth and i really learned that oh yeah those
times when i wanted to tell the little white lies or shade the truth or omit things
or it was because there were things that i was ashamed of i didn't want people to
know i was embarrassed maybe ashamed's too strong a word i was embarrassed or
telling little white lies i'm late because the traffic was so bad but no i'm was late
just because i was disorganized and didn't get leave the house on time or i
couldn't figure out what to wear and or you know something like this and
once i had that insight and i said no no if i want to have this commitment to speaking the
truth it turned out to be a relief to kind of like change my behavior so i didn't have to be embarrassed about it anymore
and just the quality of my life just went way up in a way that i would have never
imagined just from this little um wish to look at why am i telling little white lies
here and there and part that's partly kind of my
motivation for this dharma talk too is just this encouragement that when we start to look at them and we
like maybe pull one little thread we might discover all kinds of ways in
which suffering was a not a suffering was being created but maybe pulling a thread helps us to
have some greater understanding in which there can be some less suffering
and then maybe i will also say that it's not in the buddhist teachings
but also with speech i'll just put in something about the importance of listening to
we might ask ourselves why am i not listening sometimes why do i not give my attention to others
why do i find myself looking at my phone instead of listening to people
i could also be a rich reflection then the last one is to not use
intoxicants that can lead to heedlessness so there's obvious intoxicants like
alcohol and drugs and but there's lots of other ones that we use to check
out or numb out or push aside we might use food shopping surfing the
internet watching youtube videos or work as a way to no longer be present
for our experience
so none of these things are inherently bad or harmful but we might use our wish to
do them as an opportunity to reflect on is there something we're trying to avoid
is there a reason why we don't want to be present for what's happening especially with their recognition right
to not use intoxicants that leads to heedlessness the heedlessness is because
we are much more apt to break all the other precepts if we break this one
the one of but um intoxicants so are we no longer do we feel
burdened by wanting to behave in an ethical way and we want it or we feel
oppressed by it and there's a way that we want to do intoxicants so that we can just behave freely without
any feeling of what might be supported leading to suffering
or causing suffering or maybe something that doesn't cause suffering
so that's just one way in which we might um approach ethics is the relationship between sila and
suffering and self-reflection three esses silas
suffering and self-reflection stila is a way that maybe we can like put a stake in the ground like
if we have this intention to behave this way in an ethical way we can
use it as to notice when do we not want to when do we not do it and what can we
learn from that might only gain greater understanding but what can we learn about suffering
what can we learn about what helps us to have greater ease and happiness in our life
and what doesn't in this way so that our lives may unfold
in a way that brings greater and greater ease and happiness not only to ourselves
but to those around us just imagine just imagine what this world
would be like if all of us kept at least
one precept all the time if we ever could be a model for others
or an inspiration for others so may your practice unfold in a way
that brings greater and greater ease and less suffering and may we use ethics not as a way to
beat ourselves up to judge ourselves but it's an opportunity to learn more
thank you