great all right so hello everyone hello and warm-hearted welcome
wherever you are and however the weather is either internally in this
moment or externally so so for
today's practice for the theme for our exploration
i'd like to invite us to explore the theme of this wish for for health wish for
health and as a part of
the phrases of methods we cultivate loving kindness for ourselves for others
as we tap into the good will that we have for others and ourselves
the four phrases of meta just to review the first one has to do with safety and
we talked about safety last week the second one has to do with um
happiness mental happiness and we explored that on monday so today
we explored the third phrase kind of linger a little bit here today may you be
healthy may you be healthy and strong so let's explore that wish maybe
on friday we will explore the last wish which is for ease or maybe
there will be more of health to explore we'll see so this third wish the third
metaphrase um may you be healthy may you be strong may
i be healthy may i be strong and wishful for physical well-being
so let's sit with that let's explore that so first to consider that these
different phrases of meta they try to explore these different aspects of well-being
mental well-being e safety etc as we've discussed so this physical well-being health yes as human
beings we have a body we all have a body of course we do
and we all experience lack of health because we have a body
there's we have been sick or we will be sick or maybe we are sick right now we all age
of course we do it's a part of part of life
so this wish for for well-being
the sense of physical well-being
it's a wish it's an offer it's it's it's a generosity it's a gift of generosity
regardless of how much health we have or other people have in this moment
so so actually today it's kind of interesting that i'm talking about this thing because today i
haven't been feeling well all day in horizon horizontal and i'll
be all horizontal probably after teaching so it's actually perfect i realize
there's no irony but actually there's this perfection of talking about this wishful for health where they can
be well-being holding lack of physical well-being so there can be a sense of well-being in
the heart and the mind both holding lack of physical well-being
that's one aspect i'd like to invite us to explore that well-being is is
greater is this greater is more pervasive the sense of well-being that
you can say you could be sick you can not feel well but there can still be a sense of
well-being overall well-being that holds that holds that lack of physical health
in that moment so that's one thing to kind of drop in as a possibility
as a possibility another theme to explore is that
um when there is
health or lack of health you know there's it's always relative it's not binary as long as
we're alive there's some level of health there's some level of something that's
working the heart is beating we are breathing so there's always some
level of health so so for example if you're wishing yourself may i be healthy or may you be
healthy wishing someone helps someone you care about and they're not fully healthy so it's not an
irony to wish oh i want may you be healthy oh may you be healthy as much as possible as much as available
so not to try to push reality and and fight with it not to be in conflict
but to offer this wish again another aspect of this cultivation
with meta with friendliness is we cultivate our heart in goodness and generosity
for ourselves for others with this offering this wish may you be healthy
may be healthy as much as possible as much as is available to you may i be healthy may i have good health
as much as possible and oh there's a delight in that just as i say that
and again today as i'm not feeling well oh yeah there's a generosity
may i be healthy as much as it's not all may i be healthy and i'm not healthy and
this is terrible it's not fighting reality it's actually there's there's a grace there is a beauty
even when there is lack of health to to have this wish for ourselves and
for others there's this generosity of this gift
and one last thing i want to bring in as a contemplation today is that
there is there's actually um you know of course there is
there's a lot of gift in being healthy we already know this that's that's
that's obvious that's kind of that's the um that's the apparent but
many of us don't open up to the grace and beauty
and actually the value of not being fully healthy
because there is a place where we can actually open up it we become we we go inside we can
open up to the inner world as long as again we work with the second arrows i
don't want you know the teaching of the first era which is say lack of health second error is what
what we add ourselves oh i don't want to be here this is terrible i'll never never be well i have a lot of things on
my to-do list so as we work with those and actually
allow the relishing of going in of relishing of letting go
and actually this quietness this quietness of mind the solitude the sense of peace and
and um [Music] quietness that is is forced and yet it's
an opportunity in fact on on many retreats i've given the instruction to people
um practice as if you are sick right now because then that sense of grabbing
grasping clinging wanting when you're sick it all kind of drops away there's the ease the
mind doesn't have the energy to to fight too much so just there's a
sense of ease that naturally comes in ah when there isn't so much
grabbing and grasping so so so much to explore in this in this
health and lack of it so with that the invitation again would be to explore
this offering this wish for safety i'm sorry wish for health and
playing with that for others for ourselves as much as available
in in this nuanced way not in just a flat one-dimensional way but
being open to all the dimensions that this can open up for us and maybe in ways we didn't
quite expect so so with that i'd like to invite us
all to get into our meditation posture ah landing landing
in the body either sitting or lying down whatever is appropriate for you
creating greeting this body however it is failing right now
inviting the body to be just as it is
it's feeling energetic healthy vibrant
it's feeling tired
not so much energy or unwell however it is hello dear body hi
as if you're greeting a dear dear friend whom you have
ignored who's doing their best who's doing their best
who have done their best
maybe you've been a taskmaster for this friend keep performing
cracking the whip greeting greeting this dear friend
who's been doing this the best they can the best they can
in this moment given all the causes and
conditions
this friend this dear friend
continue to work hard as best as they can right now
breathing [Music]
appreciating that this body is breathing
doing it on its own thank you very much you don't need to force it or do
anything intentionally just loving
appreciating that the breath is breathing itself
the body
breathing the heart beating
inviting this friend your body to relax to soften
it doesn't have to do anything right now
it's worked hard enough all day
as the breath is perceived one breath at a time
letting there be a sense of appreciation love care for this friend hard-working friend
putting down putting away the whip oh sweetheart dear body to your body
i have forsaken you ignored you been demanding
may you be well may you be healthy dear body as much as possible
can go through different parts of the body
announcing wishing well appreciating sense of meta care
love for different parts of the body different body parts feet
dear feet thank you
you have walked many steps today to your feet
so many muscles so many bones
who have been acting working
together thank you may you be well
showering your lower legs and upper legs
your knees
with appreciation
and care good will
thank you for all you do you've done
i wish you well
may you be healthy dear legs and feet
not a not in the graspy way but offering this as a blessing unto
your own body without attachment to outcomes
or as the cultivation of appreciation good will friendliness care
pushing your sit bones your groin area their lower abdomen
with appreciation and care
for their function
as best as possible and wishing them well
appreciating the abdomen and all the
organs
stomach
intestines kidney liver
so many organs
appreciating thinking
may you be well dear organs supporting supporting me supporting this
life this consciousness
as best as you're able to give in the causes and conditions
appreciating the chest
all the muscles bones
the heart
pumping blood
the lungs
thank you you've been working all day
miraculously thank you
i wish you well to your organs
both mine and not mine
we don't exactly choose our organs we just find ourselves in this body when we're
born oh dear organs thank you may you be well
appreciating our arms elbows
our hands our fingers our digits our thumbs
oh they've done so much today
moved they've fed us
they have worked wow
thank you appreciation gratitude friendliness
menta thank you dear friends
thank you team may you be well
our neck and shoulders
[Music] holding up our heavy head thank you
may you be well
thank you for functioning as well as you've been able to
and appreciating the head all the organs
the brain eyes ears nose tongues
mouth so many functions
so many interrelated functions thank you
for helping this being who's me see hear speak
smell think function today
deep appreciation deep appreciation
metta and goodwill may you be well all you organs
may all the organs of this body all the flesh all the muscles all the
bones the sinew the nerves
attendance thank you thank you
extraordinary thank you
i love you i wish you well
may you be healthy
may all parts of this body i wish them well may they be healthy may
this body as a whole be as healthy as possible
as available appreciating the health the well-being that is available already
may i be healthy and strong
offering the wish to all the parts of your body gift of
generosity if it works for you to say may you be
healthy or dear body parts you can do that too
see what works what conception works best what ways of seeing
if you like to experiment with putting your palm in your heart center middle of your chest connect with this
body connecting with itself
may this body be healthy may i be healthy sharing good will
friendliness
may i be healthy may i be healthy and strong
letting the goodness of that wish land
as a blessing
now turning that wish shining blessing internally
now externally choosing one person
one practice partner maybe in this zoom room or someone you've
practiced with before or a friend
may you be healthy sharing this blessing of good will
for their health for their body may your body
have the gift of well-being as much as
possible
may you be healthy and strong
may we both may we both have the blessing of health and well-being
may both of our bodies
be healthy and strong as much as possible
sharing the wish internally externally
and male beings everywhere all beings everywhere
be healthy and strong
may their body support them
in this life
[Music] so
thank you for your practice everyone
so the wish for health so much to explore here so much to explore
i feel like we've just scratched the surface and one invitation as i guided us in this
practice was to appreciate the body part by part we take ourselves
for granted the body works as hard as best as it can so many things
go right we notice when something goes wrong but so many things are going right to
appreciate and that's that's the sense of meta goodwill
friendliness for ourselves so i'd love to invite you
there's much more i can say but let me invite you if you would please
um share reflections why did you notice what came up in this practice for you you can
either type them in chat either privately to me i won't say your name or if it's publicly i'll read your name
or you can raise your hand please raise your zoom hand and you can unmute yourself
so ally
yeah i just um really got present to um
how much i've learned to co-create with my body this last year
um and all that we've been through together and and it really just hit me
um that i've stopped going to war with it and um
just how loyal like it's a miracle and it's um yeah it's tumbling so yeah it was
really really profound for me
thanks sally i am so touched wow the way you put you know the way you put
it that you stopped going to war with it ah
that's powerful that realization that really that shift in attitude
wow yeah not going to war with our bodies oh
beautiful and it's so common of course we do we expect especially when we get sick
that's the that's the hardest time right it's like you've
why are you not performing why are you not getting better you have betrayed me or instead
of oh sweetheart oh you've been working so well this whole time thank you thank you and
i appreciate how the pandemic is there anything particularly about the pandemic
alley if you like to comment on that that has brought this shift as if there's any insight or wisdom
in that way you like to say another to comment on and if not
it's okay whoops there
um yeah i would say i hit um the rock bottom of
my life in just about every way and um their self-trust was built
because i had it was like i had nowhere else to go and and my my body was
there it was the only thing that was really there with me and knows what it was like to walk in my shoes and
um it's you know like when you really think about
all the things that you walk through in your life and
the body witnessing and holding and taking care in ways that we can't
in such micro and macro levels um [Music] yeah it's it's incredible
thanks ali that is profound and and how this wisdom also came from
so much suffering thank you thank you for sharing
claire
thank you um yeah i wanted i put my hand up when ali used the word
co-create because it brought a whole new perspective for me
and uh it reflects on my my own experience i happen to be
unusually healthy it's a great gift and but throughout my
life almost you know since like before i was a teenager i started to treat my body as though it
was a very special friend that i should be very loving toward i've always been good to it
um you know i'm tony i'm i'm now sugar-free alcohol-free
tobacco-free uh the only one i haven't beaten yet is caffeine
but you know you can see i was cycling tonight i work out um you know i do everything you know i
and i i've studied nutrition i take tons of vitamins i mean i really i
i treat it like it's special beautiful i need it beautiful i
definitely co-created i i know i need it and i'm so i'm really good to it i love that and it works and we're
grateful it works beautiful thank you claire i love i love you expanding on
on what ali brought in this co-creation oh darling body i'm going to be good to
you and you'll be good to me and i'll be patient with you you'll be patient with me this is tremendous thank you claire yeah
jerry says it's helped to recognize the in inherent negativity bias of focusing on
one or more aspects of the body that are not working the best rather than being grateful for all the parts
of the rest of the body working so you get a more wholesome perspective yeah thank you for that yeah thank you for
that absolutely and sp on youtube says so refreshing to get windows of meta
through the set i've been swept away often in afflictive states and feel far from brahmavihara is
really longing to abide in meta and wisdom thank you sp thank you so much for that so
so dear ones let's turn our practice um and this wish for
well-being for for health now we turn that externally towards the people that
we see these lovely beings who support us who practice with us yay the rubber meets the road
what is it like to show up in that way wishing for their well-being and then we're co-creating this wish for
well-being the space we co-create the space for each other so so okay our
breakout rooms again let's start with 15 seconds of meta 15 seconds of meta
silently before we um yeah before you start sharing
and yeah let's um i'm going to open the rooms and here we
go okay welcome back everyone
so we've got a couple of minutes for any reflections anything you
realize noticed in group sharing group practice please don't be
shy especially if you haven't spoken for a while would love to hear from you
this is susan go ahead thanks um i was telling my group members
um which is so healing this is so healing oh my gosh what a boon
um i uh kind of in the beginning of the year a lot of my
organs started failing or having massive problems and
i was kind of preparing myself for dying for a while there but it seems like i'm turning the corner
and so um this is kind of right up my alley today so it's um yeah i got a lot
out of everybody's shares as well and nikki thanks tons thanks all y'all
thanks susan thank you susan and all of susan's organs and body parts
for supporting her as well as possible thank you this is profound what you
shared thank you for being here sharing yourself and practicing with everyone
yeah thank you
oh so i think that is a profound note to end on so
thank you all for being here for giving your heart to this practice
supporting yourselves supporting others and the world may all beings
be healthy and strong as much as possible may all beings be free including
ourselves
thanks everyone