hello everyone and welcome to our
meditation together and um
the general theme this week is um loving kindness
in that we're looking at the meta suta at 7 30. and
so to
one of the interesting things to consider very important things to consider when
doing meditation is when we have an unwholesome state of
mind or unwholesome thoughts that arise how do we react to that what's our
response to that and ideally what is unwholesome
what is unwholesome is met by what is wholesome so an unwholesome
state of mind and wholesome train of thinking we bring to it
some wholesome state of mind some wholesome way of approaching it
and one of the simplest ways of doing that is to practice mindfulness
mindfulness is considered always to be wholesome
maybe some people would see it more something neutral because it's non-reactive it's non-judgmental it has a kind of
neutrality and just allowing things to be not being for against it but it turns out that kind of uh state
of mind is uh beneficial and it was onward leading to greater benefits into happiness so just
to simply be aware of it is to bring wholesomeness so we don't have to dredge up
some kind of love or kindness or compassion if we don't feel it
but we can bring forth our capacity to be mindful
recognizing it in its simplicity mindfulness is wholesome
and the word simplicity is important because sometimes we can be mindful but we're also kind of not just mindful
also thoughtful about what we're doing so that the mindfulness is maybe mixed
up with some unwholesome thoughts and attitudes but to meet what's unwholesome with the
wholesome without condemnation without shame without
defining oneself by the unwholesome without being upset just
to see it clearly and if it's possible to be have kindness to it or good will towards
oneself in this state that helps as well but this art of bringing forth a
wholesome to meet whatever is unwholesome so we don't let the unwholesome fester
and uh and get the upper hand so taking a meditation posture
and this word wholesome is wonderfully connected to the word
skillful and so to take a posture that is skillful for you
it's a skillful posture that supports you to settle into the present moment to be
here closing your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
maybe three quarters full full enough so that you really feel your
rib cage expand and stretch you feel your torso a little more fully
maybe even allowing your belly to expand
and as you exhale maybe a little bit longer than usual a
leisurely exhale
letting the exhale with the exhale is settling in your body
then letting your breathing return to normal
and taking a few moments to familiarize yourself with how it is to be breathing in an
ordinary way
and as you breathe relax your body some more
relaxing muscles of your face
letting the muscles of your face fall away from the bones skull
the exhale relaxing the shoulders
the shoulders can fall away from the spine
and as you exhale to relax the belly
maybe softening the belly so the weight of your torso settles more deeply
and then settling in with your breathing
and if there's any unwholesome state of mind or train of thinking
can you let go of that maybe reminding yourself it's not needed
right now
and if you can't let go of it it's okay can you be aware of it simply
a wholesome state of awareness that simply recognize it knows it
so in a sense you are the response you are not the unwholesome state
and the simplest wholesome state with which to respond
is to be mindful to see it for what it
is and then if possible with a wholesome attitude wholesome mindfulness
settle down into your breathing just to breathe in and breathe out
and if any unwholesome states of mind arise
return to what's wholesome the whole also mindfulness of breathing
or a wholesome recognition of the unwholesome state
and as we come to the end of this sitting
one of the ways of considering the end of meditation
it is that it has prepared us to enter the world in a new way
different way and one of the ways to do this is to
turn the attention now towards the world around you
the people in your lives communities people in the world
and see if you can bring up a wholesome attitude towards them
there's many wholesome attitudes but some attitude or way of thinking about
others that sees them in a good light positive light
to be ready to maybe be involved in the world again of people
after this meditation with a attitude of goodwill
where they're seeing and considering people have the capacity for happiness and to wish it be so
and to maybe wish that whatever benefits that has come from this meditation
be used not at the expense of oneself
but as an enhancement of oneself to be used for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so
so we continue i continue then with a
series of talks on the meta suita the discourse on loving kindness
and i say as i'm doing it this week is by dividing
the text into parts kind of kind of four parts and this
coming next part is the shortest part of the text and kind of paradoxically or ironically
in the classic instructions for loving kindness practice which is uh founded a fifth century
meditation manual by a teacher named buddha gosha it's a big book called the
path of purification and that's where the modern practice of
damikane is the most common way to practice comes from this
particular book and it's a big manual on meditation and the
ninth chapter of the book is about brahmavihara meditation the meditations of loving kindness
compassion sympathetic joy and equanimity and um and the biggest discussion about
the is about the first one loving kindness but in the in the section about loving
kindness most of that section many many pages has to do
about um overcoming resentment and anger
because uh i guess the one of the biggest obstacles for loving kindness is if we have resentment towards someone
and it's hard to have kindness or good will towards them or anger towards them and so it's really
a treatise or instructions on overcoming anger more than it is teachings on
loving-kindness so in the metasuta this next part
is about that but it's only four lines and at this time i think i've succeeded
in posting uh this part of the meta suit or actually what we've done so far
in the youtube page where it says little description of what we're doing underneath the video
and if you click on show more i think it will show it to you and the bottom of that is
let no one deceive another
or despise anyone anywhere let no one through anger or aversion
wish for others to suffer so here we have
a call to put aside anything that gets in the way of the good will
but this text is not only about loving kindness it's really about the path to liberation
uh through loving-kindness and the path of liberation cannot be found [Music]
in being angry or despising or having aversion towards anyone especially if that is a wish for them to
suffer certain certain kind of hostility and this that kind of feeling that attitude is
really goes against the grain of um of liberation
because it involves getting unliberated it involves getting
entangled or in bondage or caught not free if we're caught in resentment
or anger and now it's not necessarily all anger
but the anger any anger that involves hostility any anger that involves ill will towards
someone wishing others to suffer
and so in this classic text on loving loving-kindness then a big section is about overcoming anger and
resentment and it's kind of fun to read because he gives instructions about what
you can do and then he says well if that doesn't work then try this and then he says if that
doesn't work try this if that doesn't work try this and um and it goes a whole through a
whole series of you know options and then finally as the last one
if nothing else works then he says
get involved in the practice of gift giving so either give the person that you're
angry with or hostel with give them a gift or allow them to give a gift to you
so either direction whatever is happening or easy um
that that's the final the most you know the last resort for uh for overcoming anger and
resentment and uh i don't know why it has to be last why not just first
but anyway it's the last one and in between there are things like just
drumming up loving kindness for them or thinking about the good qualities the
person has or thinking about how when there's anger and resentment
the person who has the anger the resentment is harming themselves and and they're causing it literally
says is causing damage to oneself that the enemy cannot create
so others can kind of cause us harm in a variety of ways but that to
really we get into the deepest parts of the heart and mind in this ancient text the it's only you
can do that by having anger or resentment or something like that
so there's all these things to do and maybe each of you has your own
effective way of um and an effective and skillful
and respectful way of working with anger and resentments and aversion hostility
i like to think of these states of mind as something that deserves i don't know deserves the right
word but something that's well worth respecting um so not to have an
automatic hostility towards our hostility not to have an automatic aversion to a
aversion or or ill will but to understand to have respect for it sometimes we
respect things which are dangerous and so we respect these things but these states are dangerous
but we respect them partly because of their danger and we want to be very careful with them and so they don't cause uh harm they don't
succumb to the danger that they bring but also
they are kind of like messengers and you don't want to kill the messenger
and the messenger sometimes is that we are hurting in some ways or the
messenger is that there's something about ourselves that feels scared
or the message is that there's something unwholesome going on inside of us and that
unwholesomeness needs attention if we want to find our way to the wholesome and so in
fact what is unwholesome inside of us uh might be the thing that most needs
our good will needs our compassion needs our generosity of spirit
um if we keep pushing away what's unwholesome inside of us or pushing it down
um it just festers and uh it just gets worse and and uh and we live kind of a divided
life between what we're willing to face and what we're ignoring
and um and the um and so anger sometimes is a if you see it as a
messenger and uh and what is the message what's underneath the anger what's behind it
and not a few times part of what anger is is something in ourselves that needs
uh good will that needs to be reassured that needs maybe to be let go of but not
let go with hostility but put down with respect and care um that it comes you know that's there
so this idea of living a wholesome life means to bring a wholesomeness to those parts of
ourselves which are unwholesome so in a sense be our own friend that way
and so when the smeta sutra says let no one deceive another
or despise anyone anywhere let no one through anger aversion wish for others to suffer
that i see this first and foremost it's directed towards ourselves that uh we we don't want to be this kind
of way we don't want to deceive anyone else or despise anyone and
nor be angry or aversive towards anyone and so to really cultivate putting those
down to cultivate the absence of this deception the absence of tricking people or
or presenting ourselves different who we are or getting people to do what we want a kind of little bit through manipulation
or just don't despise anyone respect everyone
don't despise yourself so to to enter this world of our unwholesome
and begin looking how to put it down relax it heal it bring forth what is wholesome
um and um and and put down any hostility
so let no one through anger and aversion wish for others to suffer now
logically maybe or you know it doesn't seem like anyone or any of you want that but to be mean towards someone
to say something slightly mean or even sarcastic critical uh kind of underneath it is a
little bit like poking people maybe or getting back at people or or um you know someone says something
not so nice to ourselves and we kind of respond and kind because we want to get back at them
there's all kinds of small ways in which we are not we kind of kind of trying to irritate
people or get back at them get revenge or something and uh
even complaining sometimes is more than just complaining it's kind of a critique a criticism that's kind of
poking at people and and so the idea is if you really
want to cultivate loving-kindness really want to cultivate the path of liberation there's a profound thing to be done
a health very healthy thing to be done a i would say for a very inspiring thing
to do and that is to um to
overcome any tendency towards hostility to learn to recognize it when it comes
up and not give into it to learn to recognize it when it comes up and meet it with what's wholesome
and and so that our intention the way that we are motivated to live
our life is uh has even though there might be some feelings that are difficult
angry feelings and all that the important thing is the intention them what drives how we speak and act in the
world and in there um have no wish for others to suffer
rather this is the wish this is the intention to come from and that's the section just before that
in the poem may all be happy and secure may all beings be happy at heart
all living beings whether weak or strong tall large medium or short
tiny or big seen or unseen born or to be born may they all
be happy so that's the art of loving kindness is to
discover how to have this be the motivating force inside of us this kind of good will
having put aside the ill will that's there or not acting on it and healing it in some deep way and
so it's a this is a worthwhile very worthwhile way of living and practicing
and and imagine that if you've memorized the metasuta and recited these words
every day this is a classic practice in in buddhism is to memorize a text like
this and say it yourself over and over again and see the effect it has on us
of saying these kinds of words so thank you and
i'll continue tomorrow
you