so
it's a fortunate thing for all of you to be here and
with me i feel very grateful and happy to have this time to share the
practice a bit and the dharma so one of the
ancient ways of meditating is to meditate with the breathing and some of us have done the whole
series now and began since beginning the year on mindfulness of and one of the options with mindfulness
of breathing is to uh keep a constant like the beat of a song that's the beats always going
along and and uh and um so the
uh just stay with the rhythm of breathing and but then not exclude other things but if
something else is uh strong and compelling is to um breathe with that uh strong thing that
other thing that's happening so that we don't get caught up or
entangled thinking about and involved in too much with what's happening we're able to be
aware of it and present but stay a little bit free of it without being entangled and
being loose and easy with it and so the breathing with it keeping a focus on the breathing and
the breathing and keep us limber and loose from keep prevent us a little bit from seizing up or tightening up or around
whatever's going on and this ability to stay loose and easy by staying with the rhythm of breathing
is quite helpful so what i'd like to suggest for today is a one variation of this
is that whatever happens during this meditation
that makes it difficult for you to stay present in the present moment
whatever uh ways in which your mind gets pulled off into thoughts or you get pulled into
your emotions and concerns with your emotional life or or if there's strong physical sensations
in your body in the way in which that just really triggers some reactivity inside of you and you're
more involved in the reactivity than you are being present whatever is making difficult for you
breathe with that just breathe through it breathe with it
and um and see what happens if the massage of breathing the rhythm of breathing the way it was
breathing is kind of uh maybe maybe is a guard against getting caught in the reactivity
caught in the preoccupations the wandering thoughts so if you're having a lot of thinking and
that you've got pulled into your thoughts all the time you don't necessarily have to let go of
it but breathe with it just breathe through it maybe you know 60 of your attention is
on the breathing and 40 on the thinking and and uh and then what happens to your
thoughts when you're not when you're lost in thought then 100 percent of your attention is
kind of going into your thinking but if sixty percent is just with the breathing and you know you're
thinking but you're breathing with the thoughts thinking or breathing through it what shifts for you what happens
so the best of your ability stay with your breathing and of course you'll lose it don't worry
about that then in a funny way that task is to breathe with having lost it
so and so you're right back with the breathing again rather than
being preoccupied or upset that you've lost touch with the breathing just breathe with that phenomena
and then you're right back with the breathing and um so i hope that this way you can enjoy
your breathing and it helps if you enjoy a little bit in a very modest way and breathe with
whatever makes it difficult for you to meditate and if it's easy to meditate
then it should be easy to just stay with your breathing and and get settled and focused and
um entering the entering into that beautiful world of um of being settled on the breathing
so assuming a posture that is suitable for
you for this meditation session and the idea is to take in an
intentional posture that posture that it expresses a little bit of intentionality
and like yes this is the posture i'm in and adjusting the arms
so that they are participating in this intentional posture
adjusting little bit the spine in the back so it too is
intentional in the way the spine participates or
supports attention
and gently close the eyes
and especially with breathing now at the center of this meditation
gently take a few full deep breaths three quarters full
and gently exhale as much air as you can without it being
a stress or a strain
deep breath in and then relaxing the body as you exhale
maybe especially as you long exhale releasing the shoulders
breathing in and breathing out letting your breathing return to normal
and then scan through your body and breathe with whatever
tension or holding you'll find in the body
maybe without immediately relaxing it but just breathing with it
and then continuing to breathe normally on the exhale now relax
the different places of holding and tension in the body
soften attuning yourself to a softening of the
body
partly by recognizing where the body does feel soft or gentle or quiet
and then more fully centering yourself on the body
breathing centering yourself on the experience of
breathing
and gently quieting your mind
perhaps allowing the mind to become softer
calmer
breathing in and breathing out
and then as we sit here this morning if anything takes you away from
fully being with your breathing
continue being with the breath but breathe with what wants to take you
away breathe through it
almost as if breathing is a way of better recognizing or acknowledging
the forces of distraction and preoccupation
nothing is wrong nothing is a problem it's just something else to
breathe through to breathe with as
as it's all held in in awareness
you don't have to let go of anything just make sure that 60
or so of your attention is on the breathing
not on what pulls you into its orbit
your thoughts your feelings sixty percent on the breathing breathing
with whatever is distracting you preoccupying
you
no need to struggle with anything instead breathe with it
breathe through it sixty percent of the attention on
breathing and forty on what's happening
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to say that it's also possible to breathe with others in the presence of others
and to keep good part of our attention staying with the massage of breathing
it's a protection from getting caught in the conversation or caught in
the reactivity or self-consciousness
when with when we're with someone and when we're not caught in reactivity
and thoughts it might be easier to access
kindness and care and generosity
it might be easier to be attentive to the other person attentive in a way
that doesn't box them in or limit them or
diminish them somehow in in our own eyes
but keeps them open keeps them available makes room for them
and may it be that as we go through the day
that our breathing returning to our breathing can also be a returning
to a place of calm or peace or ease
from which we can reconnect to our goodwill
well-wishing for others our care our love our compassion
may it be that mindfulness or breathing supports warm-heartedness
in our encounters with others may it be that this meditation practice
that we do
is applied to improving the life of all beings
may it be that we this practice we've done this morning
may it be for the happiness and the welfare of others
may it be for their safety and peace
may it be for their non-oppression their freedom
and may it be that even in the smallest ways
that we contribute to make this possible
may our care and good will be present
our encounters with other people may all beings be happy
[Music]
foreign
so good day everyone and so this week for these little dharma
talks i'm telling stories buddhist stories and some of these stories contain
wonderful teachings and wonderful messages some of them are like aesop's fables
with uh kind of wisdom fables and there's one that i'm fond of
and partly because i've taught it a lot to children and sometimes i've had children and
telling the story to them i've had them acted out and there's a lot of running around and
sometimes yelling around that goes along with it so i'll tell you this story but please
don't take it just as a children's story some of these stories are have
tremendously great value and this one in particular i think applies to a lot that's happening in the
united states with um fake news and fear and anger and things like that
so um um so it's one of the jataka tales is
one of the classic canonical kind of stories
that kind of like fables that purport to be the past life stories of the buddha when
he was an animal and he's the wise animal in these stories
and so in this story uh there's a rabbit the rabbit's not the
buddha the buddha is coming and there's a rabbit
and the rabbit decides it's a nice day comfortable day middle of the day and
decides to take a nap underneath the tree and
falls asleep is contentedly sleeping napping everything is fine in the universe and
then suddenly there's a large something large falls on the ground
right next to the rabbit clunk boom bang and the rabbit wakes up with the jolt
and concludes that the sky is falling so he the rabbit jumps up and runs along
yelling the sky is falling the sky is falling and comes across other
rabbits and uh and they say their other rob said while you're running
it says run run because the sky is falling so the other rabbits join him and they
run into more rabbits and same story and more rabbits are running and then falling they're all yelling out
the sky is falling the sky is falling and then they come across
a group of deer and and the deer say what are you doing and
the rabbits say the sky is falling run run and first one deer runs then a whole
herd of deer runs and they're all yelling the sky is falling the sky is falling
and they go along further and they come across rhinoceroses and
the rhinoceroses say what are you doing well the sky is falling you have to run run for safety and and uh so first one
runoff is then many rhinoceroses are running and uh and by this time this ground is shaking
because there's you know so much weight and so many animals are running afraid of this falling sky
and then they come across elephants pretty soon there's a huge herd of elephants pounding against the
ground shaking the ground everyone yelling and frantically the sky
is falling the sky is falling and they're heading to a big cliff and if there's another
they're kind of besides themselves in their fear they don't even know where they're going and it's just a hitting sprint's cliff
they're all going to kind of fall right off but uh towering above this cliff on a
another cliff on a kind of mountaintop is a great lion the lion the story is
the buddha and the lion looks down and sees what's going on going on sees the danger that
all these animals are in so the giant leap the lion leaps down
in front of the charging animals and
roars stop and all the animals screech to a halt in
front of the lion and the lion says to them calmly what is
going on here and the elephant says well the sky is falling the sky is
falling and the buddha the lion says well who told you that
well the rhinoceros has told me that so the lion asked the rhinoceros well
who told you that well the deer told me that
asking the deer the deer said brother rabbits asking the rabbits the rabbits all then
turn around and pointed to the first rabbit that's the one who told me told us
and the buddha said to that rabbit where did you get the idea that the sky
is falling and the rabbit said well there was this loud bang something
falling right next to me and the buddha said well take us there
the buddha the lion said take us there and and so with some trepidation the
rabbit led the whole large gathering of animals and the lion back
to underneath the tree it happened to be a mango tree
and laying on the ground right next to where the rabbit had napped was a mango it was a mango that had
fallen off the tree and landed right next to the head of the rabbit
so the buddha pointed that out and said there's no sky falling it's just a mango and
and so everyone relaxed and went back to their
different activities that these animals had so the story of uh not running
from what we're afraid of but taking a good look to investigate what's
really happening here and to ask ourselves this ques very important question from where did i
learn some rumors some idea and where did that
what's the source of that then what's the source of that the idea of understanding the source
for our information is it just our opinion like it was for the rabbit i guess a
wild guess is it rumor is it what we've heard from someone else we don't really know for
ourselves but we've heard oh i've heard a story this you know this is how it is out
there and and then if fear is triggered if anger
is triggered
if it's something we've seen and seeing directly maybe it's reasonable but if it's many
steps removed from the original aren't we becoming like the herds of
animals running towards the cliff aren't we start creating realities creating world
views and understandings and enemies and
scenarios and doomsday ideas that we're running from that we're preoccupied with
that where we lose our sensibilities and how are we going to who's going to
be the lion that stops us that says stop
let's go back and look really take a good look or investigate what's really happening here let's follow the steps
back and probably there's not going to be a
lion or a buddha that's going to jump in front of us but the buddha for us these days
represents our own capacity to say stop ah real healthy stopping
stopping or running away stopping running in circles stopping our spinning out really stop
and turn and look at what is happening turn and look towards the
danger if it's appropriate to look at it to look towards our fear
and there is a kind of courage that's needed in buddhist practice to stop and look at what we're afraid of
to stop and look at what we're angry at to really look what's really going on
here what's the real source of my reactivity my reaction
and um i know in my for me recently i was somewhat angry with someone maybe mildly
but it was kind of a maybe annoyance or irritated or something and i stopped to take a look at it and i
realized very quickly that um a huge percentage of how it was irritated
or annoyed um has to do with the stories that i was making up about the situation
not about the actual situation i didn't actually have all the information it was happening i was guessing and then the guest making
a picture of what it was and then i was reacting to my own picture not to
the person and then i realized oh it isn't the other person i have to contend with
i have to contend with myself and so so that was i stopped and looked
and saw where is it and found it in myself so this so you have the ability to stop
you have the ability to then turn and look and see what's really the source of this
where is the beginning of this maybe it was just a mango that fell on the ground and and to support this ability to stop
and take a good look you have your breathing to have a habit of coming back and just
breathing with the situation breathing not to deny anything or turn away from anything
but the breathing consciously that gives us patience gives a little bit room
breathing room space for the mind to look and investigate and see what's really going
on that we don't have if we're caught up in all the animals of our mind
uh spreading rumors to each other and spinning out and and the whole you know
zoo of her mind is starting to race and run towards the cliff
stop take a look so um the sky is falling
if you think that's the case stop and take a good look at where that idea came from and maybe
you'll find instead maybe just maybe that there's a sweet ripe
mango waiting for you some treasure something some sweetness
and something delicious something wonderful that there's a waiting for you for you
really look deeply at the situation including yourself
so um thank you and we'll continue storytelling tomorrow