okay so so hello dear sanga
hello and good evening good morning good afternoon so many time zones you're
joining from so lovely to see you and to be with you
so so for today's practice
i wanted to to bring in the theme of safety more
as we've talked about safety as a part of meta one of the meta wishes
and it's so important the more i practice with safety and think about it
and and sit with it i realize how important it is
and now with the comment that was made about uh no self versus not self i'm also
inspired to bring that in a little bit somehow tonight weave that into our
meta practice um so let's see how it goes all these
inspirations that you bring into your sangha your uh with the co-creation so
so so these two themes so regarding safety
as um you know already may you be safe may you be safe from inner outer harm may i be safe it's one
of the meta wishes as well as wishes for happiness health
and ease taking care of oneself happily and sometimes some teachers put safety
at the end we start with happiness may you be happy
in the sense that oh happiness is the most important one or we're leading with that
and yet having practiced with the different orders and different variations
over the years it's become clear to me that there is a reason why
may you be safe may i be safe traditionally is the first phrase
because there needs to be a sense of safety we need to offer ourselves
a sense of safety in order for us to be happy and healthy
and have ease safety is fundamental offering the sense of safety
um and there is research by john bulby i think
he's john his first name bulby definitely balbi's the last name um
regarding uh the attachment theory the balbi's attachment theory with with the young
children how safety is so fundamental and how
kids develop with their sense of safety with their
psychological development or their sense of autonomy etc etc so safety that sense of safety
really being fundamental for all of us and we're all grown up we you know we're kids we're
in some ways we are grown up and in some ways we are still those children who need safety so offering ourselves safety
so fundamentally important so
offering safety to our poor minds
so that when the mind wanders off or there is fear
or there is um sadness or
there is suffering or anything that comes up there is a sense of well okay
stop it now enough but offering safety for everything to be for everything to
be to be cared for with metta cared for with metta
with kindness with warmth with with warmth now
so that is the primary theme and then i felt inspired at the beginning where we
had this little exchange about self versus no self which is actually
not self because no self is a denying of
there being a self whereas the buddha never said there is no self there is a
self you are here you have an address you have a profession you have
a body there is a self and yet it's not self it's not personal it's not about
you it's not about me that's one way there's so many different
ways to approach and understand not self this impersonality
this ungovernability so
and one way to feel into this not self is that it's impersonal yes
it is personal i am here there is a self here this person this being whom i need to care for i need to offer
safety to and and
why why do we do this why do we cultivate meta it's not to have a big head it's
not to have a cell to self-aggrandize but it's not about it is about us and
it's also not about us it's about this being who lives and dies and suffers
to serve both this being and all beings
that are inter-connected to us so
maybe that sounds like a koan a bit like what is she talking about don't worry about it don't don't try to think i'll
try to bring these themes in a little bit in the guided meditation and um
for now let it go let all the words go and let's just
start practicing together i think i've said enough to set the frame
and whatever you need will be offered to you in the guidance so let go of thinking let go of
thoughts and let's just practice together let's arrive together
ah so arriving arriving
arriving in this body
jiggling letting go letting go of all the words of all the thoughts
all the thinking that has come let go not needed in this moment
the seeds have been
planted no need to attach even to the dharma
ah release release turning
turning the awareness inward
first land first to arrive
and this body feeling our feet
on the earth on the floor
connected
well rooted i am here just as the buddha touched the
earth the earth mudra we touch the earth
with our feet the floor in lieu of the earth
i am here ah
this being who is me i am here may earth be my witness
and landing releasing any holding tightness
and the muscles in the forehead
letting the eyes rest in their socket
releasing the jaw the chin
muscles behind the ears
can we offer safety offer safety
the muscles of the face oh dear muscles you don't have to do
anything you can release you can relax
dear muscles it's okay you have worked hard enough
it's okay
offering safety
internal safety to our neck and shoulders dwarf
arms and hands it's okay
you don't have to be vigilant you can relax in this moment it's okay
it's okay taking refuge
and just releasing
inviting your heart
the proverbial heart center
home of emotions to feel safe and relax
sweetheart dear heart dear heart it's okay
you can be just as you are nothing is expected of you
any different any differently than
what already is
embracing with loving awareness the lower abdomen
oh dear abdomen it's okay
no judgment no holding you're safe to just be
to just receive the breath
as you already are doing nothing extra
and oh dear sit bones
yes supporting supporting the upper body
yes dear sid bones you can relax feel safe to give your earth give give
your weight ah release your weight
the tightness release your weight onto the earth
you can drop any holding
and so too
bringing awareness
to the groin area
to the upper legs knees
lower legs and feet can be just as they
are releasing tightness tension
this body can be just as it is
whether there is discomfort it's okay
dear body you are loved just as you are
it's okay you don't have to be any other way
if you move if you need to move and shift that's okay too
do it lovingly mindfully
caringly for this body
this body that is mine and not entirely mine
i don't control all of its functioning
it's as if i'm the guardian of
this amazing amazing piece of mystery
entrusted to me
letting the breath be received
nothing more needed
entirely of the in-breath the entirety of the outbreak
is like a soft
blanket
the breath coming in
permeating throughout the body
holding wrapping each cell
each cell of the body
offering safety offering goodwill
there's nothing you have to do
just letting yourself be breathed
and the expansiveness expansiveness of this moment
this breath the possibilities
for safety ease
offered to your body to your heart to your mind
it's okay
and if judgments arise internally externally i can't do this i'm
distracted i'm sleepy i don't know what i'm doing
let the judgments let them feel safe
the mansion of your heart can be spacious
a place of safety refuge for everything to be
see what happens if you don't push things away as bad as wrong
just let them be be a friend to yourself be a friend to
whatever arises the body mind and heart
befriend to the breath sensations of the body no matter how
difficult friendly to the thoughts
whatever they may be offering safety
offering safety
just this moment your heart safe space
for yourself
the phrases are helpful you can use phrases
may i be safe for myself may i offer safety
to my heart to my body to my mind
may i be a safe refuge may i be a refuge
may i serve as a refuge
or i offer myself safety or simply it's okay
it's okay whatever arises it's okay
you safe dear thought
see if offering the space of safety
especially if judgments become disarmed if you smile at them
not believing the judgments what if you didn't believe the judgments
the arrows that are thrown what if you didn't believe them
and you smiled but it happened like it happened for the
buddha the arrows would turn to flowers
before they land
it is said that night buddha's enlightenment
morrow through so many arrows arrows of doubt
the buddha but so much meta
the sense of safety ease that they got transformed to flowers before they landed
the doubts the slings and arrows of our minds
met with a smile met with safety
transformed yes yes
trusting in our buddha nature yes possible for me
here and now
this is wrapped in a blanket every cell of the body
every thought the whole body wrapped the blanket of safety
it's okay it's okay
you can relax you can rest
like to invite you to try something on if you wish
trying on a perspective for a split second perhaps
if you wish as an experiment
what if what if this universe
is inherently safe above and beyond our imagination
in ways we can't fathom
that it is inherently safe living is safe
that dying is perfectly safe
what if this offering safety it isn't about us
doing giving it's just is it's the way things are
through this practice we're acknowledging
acknowledging the dharma with small d the way things are
reminding ourselves of something we deeply know
our heart our buddha nature deeply knows
that it is safe it has always been and always will be
through this formal practice we are just reminding ourselves
something we once knew
so
that fear is perhaps just like what is
in the dream when you wake up from a dream oh it's perfectly safe you're not
dreaming anymore no reason
fear has no foothold as it is
safe
this impersonal both personal and impersonal self
is held in complete safety
and for the last moments of this practice period
however it was sleepy distracted
confused it's all okay offering safety to yourself
for however it was no judgment just appreciation
you showed up you've planted seeds trusting
trusting that they will flower in ways you cannot fathom don't limit
yourself thank you me for showing up
just showing up and offering even a second of safety
may all beings may all beings in ways i can't imagine
may all beings including myself benefit from the goodness
of my heart goodness of my being trusting trusting
in the goodness may all beings be safe
may all beings be free including myself
thank you all thank you for your practice
so in this practice the invitation was
to explore safety this
basic basic tilling of the soil for love for metta
for care for happiness for ourselves and for others
and then inspired by the comment at the beginning of the hour by neil about not-self i also
brought the aspect of not-self and the invitation
of dimensions of safety which are not
typically what we think of and again it was an invitation for you
to try and perspective maybe for just a second
maybe something would open up and if it didn't no problem let it go all good
planting seeds so i'd like to open the floor for
reflections for questions for comments and the spirit of
sharing or the benefit of the sangha what you observed maybe something opened
up for you or something was challenging violet i say your hand is up
hi um i had a whole journey i don't know if i'll be able to
articulate what i'm trying to say um i have this view i've been working with
that pain is unsafe that there's something unsafe about pain
and today as i was trying to offer myself safety there was pain in my body
there was pain in my mind but there was safety
in my awareness so that's where the safety was found so then i was like
okay what's the nature of my awareness can i see what that is like so i can hold on
to it when there's painful stuff going on but it felt very far away from me like
it felt like this like bubble that was like 10 miles away from me and it
almost it didn't feel very close so that i tried to bring the awareness inside like okay what if the awareness is like
inside my body next to the pain and then almost immediately after i started working with that you said something
about like the blanket is in your cells or something i was like oh yeah that
um yeah that's i tried to like keep it in my body and then when you said
this idea that the universe is inherently safe then that
again that's like challenging this view that pain is unsafe because the universe is painful but then you're saying that
in some ways pain is safe so i'm still working with that but
that's some of what i experienced beautiful thank you violet thank you so much for
sharing i am so touched i love the way that
um for you one way you worked with it skillfully is what it came up for you with with
awareness the safety awareness imbued with safety how
profound and beautiful because whatever awareness is aware of is okay this is
safe oh pain awareness is aware of it oh yes it's just a beautiful way and i have
full trust that what you just described in this way of working it will
continue to open up for you i have trust for you this is this is
beautiful this is profound what you described thank you yo
lovely yeah
ah jerry says i found the issue of finding
safety in death profound yeah thank you jerry in that quote i'd
like to give credit to um stephen levine
um this is something that he has said and i
was quite impacted by it but that death is
completely safe i forget i might be paraphrasing but something about death is completely safe and i just love the
way that he says it so yeah thank you for that
you asked could you spell the name of the universal sound you spoke about on october 25th is nada sound n-a-d-a nada
as in nothing zero any other reflections we have a few more minutes you can raise your hand or you
can type in chat if you wish and if you type to me personally i will
only read the reflection not your name so it's private and if you type to the whole group then i will read your name
don i see your hand please well thank you so much the uh
it was a very interesting meditation i confess that
and i don't want to i feel like i'm going to be a wet blanket and but the
saying everything is safe it took away the meaning of safe
and it for me anyway it became sort of a meaningless concept to say everything is
safe i think like well maybe matter is never destroyed and
and sort of in that sense i'm never i'm always going to be around in some form and so i'm sort of safe but
anyway i uh maybe i i sort of got lost why i
don't know confess i hear that and confessing is completely safe don you are completely safe to confess
that it was it wasn't intangible it kind of it became heady i'm hearing and it's perfectly
fine you know that invocation that invitation may not be the appropriate
one and the right one for you and right now in in this way and it's perfectly
okay it's not needed and that's the invitation that i was really trying to say hey if it's not working
don't spin out just let it go there's plenty here already to
to to feast on and yet some seed has been planted instead of arguing
with yourself and saying this doesn't work let it go just don't get into the argument
please and trust that something might open up at some point into a different way of seeing an
insight and if not that's okay too it's all good there's so many paths to
the temple so many different paths this is not the only one so many paths
thank you don for that beautiful confession thank you it's safe for everything like this work this didn't
work what the heck do you mean by everything it's like what does that even mean that's okay too
so so dear ones how about we turn
at this point as we do at this time to turn to practice
in small groups offering each other safety offering ourselves safety
and offering each other safety and it's so beautiful to practice in this small sangha size of three
and the invitation is to start with um 15 seconds of meta
a silent meta for each other and um
and then you can share as much or as little as you wish about your practice
and again offer safety please to yourself and to others take care of yourself take care
of each other and see um what needs to be held witness what needs
to be said what doesn't want to be said it's all okay so
i'm going to open the rooms uh actually wait i'm going to not yet
open the rooms it's shifting around here we go i'm opening the rooms
take care okay welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed we've got a couple minutes for reflections uh if any
so feel free to raise your hand or type in chat and um
while i wait for your hands to go up especially if you haven't shared in a while if you have please pull back lets people allow
people who haven't to pull forward as a way of
taking care of the community as i wait for you i'll say one thing
more about this invocation that towards the end of everything being safe is actually
from the perspective of the enlightened from the enlightened perspective awakened perspective
there's ultimate safety and that is the invitation that i was trying to bring in
to put see for a split second that perspective
could could make sense and and maybe it can't at this point and sometimes it can drop
in something can open up when the mind is ready with these invitations with these invocations
something can open up profoundly so that was my hope um
even if it jiggled something and if it didn't don't worry about it it didn't work so
barbara please
i have my breakout mate if i may say um
um it talked about visiting uh
people in a family in um arizona i think it was
where he was so surprised to see people i'm just going to pause actually before
you talk about that but i just want to make sure it's okay with your partner for you to be talking about what they shared oh okay
maybe he should share it yeah if they want to maybe that's more i think yeah that's more appropriate thank you
pausing for a moment
yeah if that person wants to raise their hand they're welcome to if not somebody else yeah thank you barbara i think it's a
way of offering safety to each other to speak from you know what
i trust that whatever they shared it really touched you and yet since it was in the small group oh okay we'll respect that
and wayne
i um
just want to share uh for people that maybe you read about it
or something but how in schools
are having especially public schools or having kind of been a crisis with
the lack of uh support people and then teachers and
everything and substitutes and uh i can see why
it just it saddens me that uh you know i work in in the
probably the wealthiest middle school in the district that i that i'm in and that i work in and
and i can see why safety is first because there's just so many
it's like a boiling pot where it just at any minute it could explode
yeah thank you wayne knowing that you're a teacher and you deal with a lot of kids um
[Music] yeah safety being very important and now also david on on youtube said it is john
bolby and the attachment theory so yeah safety definitely very important last
reflection i'm going to read it and then we'll close carmen says this meditation definitely
gave me a a thought to think of what makes me feel safe and what doesn't
and breathing is definitely an anchor to help me find out beautiful
breathing as an anchor to find out what makes you feel safe and what doesn't yay
what an important note to end on and and similar to what
violet brought in with awareness with safety being imbued with awareness with
knowing with sati lovely thank you all thank you for your practice profound um
yeah profound shares practice may you all be safe happy and
well may our practice serve us and the world
[Music] thanks everyone