so a warm hello and
and a delight for me to be here be here with you and in this way
and and to begin the day here in california with
meditating together in community thank you for being here
and
as i mentioned yesterday one of the qualities of mature vipassana practice
is the ability well let me say a little differently that mature buddhist practice
is sometimes described as understanding that nothing whatsoever
is worth clinging to nothing whatsoever is worth grasping
and uh so it's a universal statement about all things you it's an omniscience of
sorts you know something one thing at least about all things all experiences are not
worthy of grasping and so this kind of broad
universal kind of understanding
what allows that kind of statement and what supports it and what it comes
out of is a capacity to
have a that where your conscious awareness is 360 degrees
meaning that your conscious awareness is ready to practice with to bring
mindfulness to whatever is happening in your experience
that there's not a division between that which is sacred and profane
uh that which is even in a certain kind of way that the division between what is shallow and
profound it's all equally
the worthy of awareness of mindfulness and
and this kind of all this kind of mindfulness is able to kind of touch and connect to the full range of
our human life as we begin appreciating that it becomes a center
it becomes kind of a home and a kind of place of freedom
but to really make it that way and to make it all encompassing or 360 degrees
there is one area of mindfulness that is often overlooked
so in a conventional way mindfulness is is kind of like a
could be seen a little bit like a flashlight or even a lighthouse shining
a light a flashlight that is flashing its light on different objects of things that we then really
look at carefully really there to take in and so we we turn the light
onto our breathing our embodied experiences our
emotions our thinking like we did yesterday and with that we also open up to sounds
and sights around us and all things that can be experienced
and in a sense it's kind of like a maybe like a flashlight shining light on it in a sense especially when we begin the
practice but at some point the light gets
turned around 180 degrees that we're actually looking at the
quality of the light we're actually noticing not
what we're aware of but how we are aware
not what we're mindful of but the characteristics the felt sense of
the the quality of the mindfulness itself
and generally that takes a while and the awareness the mindfulness kind
of it helps if it's really stable meaning we have an ability to rest and
and abide in the present moment with some continuity over time so we're not just flitting
around from one thing to the other or getting distracted all the time and situations where awareness keeps getting
hijacked by our desires and aversions and fears and fantasies
uh and and awareness really gets lost we get a lot you know it's not not that much awareness we get pulled
into this world of thoughts and things like that but when awareness
doesn't get lost and doesn't get swept away by thoughts and stable and here then at some point
the awareness how we're being aware becomes the salient thing and this is
closely related to how we are there's what's happening
and how we are in relationship to what's happening there's the experience of breathing and
our how we're relating to that experience there is the experiences of the body and
how we're relating to that experience the experience of emotions and how we
relate to those and the experience of the mind of thinking and
how we relate to that and it's in that how where the dharma really opens up because
it's in that relationship where suffering the suffering and buddhism addressing is
in that relationship and so even if they're suffering
how are we in relationship to suffering if we're happy how are we in relationship to it and
that relationship can get clarified and part of that is how we're mindful
mindfulness attention sometimes carries that relationship sometimes it gets entangled and
sometimes it it um you know it comes along side by side
so this meditation i'll point you to some aspect of this
so to enter into a meditative posture
and to soften your eyes some of you might prefer to close your
eyes some of you keep them open but soften your eyes let the eyeballs
rest in their sockets some people find it helpful
to if there is an inner gaze for the eyes gaze backwards and down
so we're not reaching out with the eyes
and to take a few long slow deep breaths the deep in breath is to connect to this
time and place with this body
and the long exhale a time to relax and settle into here and now in this body
maybe on the long exhale you can even wiggle your body a little bit help it relax a little bit more release
and allowing your breathing return to normal
and with this normal enough breathing on the exhale relaxing the muscles of
the face
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
maybe adjusting your position of your hands a little bit if that supports more relaxation in the
shoulders and on the exhale softening the belly
and then maybe bringing your attention to your head space between your ears behind your
forehead and if there's any tension or pressure
or tightness or energy or agitation
associated with thinking i call that the thinking muscle
and on the exhale to relax the thinking muscle
relax the effort to be thinking an effort that sometimes
is quite wary exhausted from a lifetime of
thinking preoccupation and allow your thinking to relax as well
as you exhale as if the thinking mind can ride the exhale
all the way to a quiet place at the end of the exhale
and then
from the inside of your body become aware of the body's experience of
breathing in that location where breathing is
most pronounced or most comfortable
where you have the custom of practicing mindfulness or breathing
as you inhale receive the inhalation
as you exhale
allow it to go allow the exhale to release
receiving and allowing
and as you're gently with your breathing
how would you characterize your awareness of breathing
your mindfulness of breathing
is there any strain to be aware
are you bearing down or pushing to be aware
or are you holding back hesitant unsure of yourself
is there a subtle confidence in your awareness
or is there a subtle doubt or hesitancy
with the awareness are you going out to know the breathing
or you or is awareness receiving the experience of breathing
is there any anxiety that goes along with being aware
a sense of caution
is there any subtle feeling associated to being mindful of i can't
do this this is hard
and if you notice anything that is extra
anything that's more than simply being aware
see if you can let go of it or if you can't let go of it
let it fall to the side
and highlight for yourself the radical simplicity
of awareness that simply knows
simply is aware somewhat like a mirror a mirror that
just is aware of what is in front of it without distortion
or comment or preferences
just aware
breathing in and breathing out
hey
so
uh
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
if we can appreciate that there's always two things happening
there's a what is happening and there's our relationship to it
and this ability we have to recognize the relationship the attitude the
desires intentions the preferences that come along with
what's happening then we can
avoid acting on those attitudes and intentions
that are harmful and we can choose those that are to act
on those which are beneficial because it's a sacred realm this realm
of our how we relate the relationships between
ourselves and our experience ourselves and other people ourselves and ourselves that
relationship is so important
and may it be that this practice of mindfulness
supports us to avoid
causing harm in the ways that we're connected to others and to this world
may we not hurt anyone oppress anyone
diminish the value of anyone and instead may we benefit
may that relationship we have bring benefit bring joy
bring freedom and happiness ease
may we care not only for others and ourselves but may we care about the
care for the relationship between how we relate
and in how we relate
may it be for the welfare and happiness of all beings
may all beings be happy
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so my friends we come to the end of this week and
for these days i've been
somewhat presenting the
basic simplest way of teaching mindfulness that
we do here at insight meditation center and parts of the western vipassana world
and and uh and i want to say now as we come to
the last day that the in so-called instructions and
mindfulness practice so i have instructions to be mindful of
breathing body emotions thoughts instructions to be aware of the four foundations of mindfulness
body feelings mind states and what's called dharmas the inner
processes that either lead to suffering or to freedom
and there's other other kind of instructions this is what you do and focus here and focus your attention this
way and and a little bit it gets it's it's
uh can give the idea that we're doing there's a doing practice
we're doing something with awareness and attention directing it someplace and uh it's a
fine instruction to do that it's wonderful to do it's wonderful to be engaged and fully involved
in whatever the task is at hand and it could be meditation as well
and but the doing sometimes comes with all these extra
baggage there can be a lot of self involved in any kind of doing even as simple as just
bringing awareness to something we're uh we're checking ourselves out as we do it am i doing it the right way am
i doing it well enough and i can't do this and the person next to me meditating is probably doing it
better and or i'm the best one or something all these you know can be very very subtle
almost be subconscious some of these little attitudes of um this is too difficult for me and
and uh and when i was a young student i had this idea that if it was happening
to me it was not the right experience and so i could never get it right because i had a
subtle almost unconscious idea that it wasn't it was never right because it was my you know whatever what i was so it
was kind of painful painful even to say it that i used to be that way or the subtle idea that there was always
somewhere else to be somewhere else that i had to kind of that was the it was the experience to
have and so it's always kind of again this kind of dissatisfaction with what was happening
and um and that came along with that doing and then other times i discovered that
there was such pristine purity or simplicity in the doing
it just like i would i would kind of forget myself in the doing of all kinds of things and
where there was gardening or cooking or or different activities but also the same
thing with this simple mindfulness of breathing just kind of give myself over completely to it and
any sense of me being the doer drops away because i'm so completely in it and it's so simple so
and there's so little attitude but there's still a kind of a you know instructions of where to
bring your attention what to do so in a sense mindfulness instructions
can be seen as prescriptive this is what you do another way of
understanding these mindfulness instructions is that they're not prescriptive but rather the descriptive
that it's uh describing
what awareness is noticing so there's no actively you know searching for
something or trying to do something or trying to get something or make
something happen but it's kind of settling back in a nice easy chair
and just noticing being aware of what comes into awareness
so we're sitting quietly and as loud sound happens outside and that just has arisen in awareness
and that and so the mindfulness describes what we're aware of oh that's what it is
uh not that we're actively describing but it's more like the the instructions are describing it's
like oh okay so if the inhale arises
you know then we know the inhale but not because we're
practicing mindfulness of breathing per se as an intentional act but more that we just know
that this is what's being known we know that this is what has arisen and
and so the description of mindfulness being all-encompassing
means that there's an openness to awareness openness to our sense of presence
that is you could say receptive that just receives whatever is coming
and going whatever is arising and happening but we to say receptive is already maybe
a little bit too much of the prescriptive thing it's like okay now i have to be receptive
the um it's more like uh the
the windows have been opened and what happens maybe we hear the sounds of
the birds or we the breeze comes into the house and it isn't that we're intending for the
breeze or wanting to hear the birds it's just that this is what arises
and so we have eyes and ears and nose and tongue and sensations of
our body and uh as we sit
what is known what is known here what is what are we
aware of what comes into awareness so this kind of way of practicing where
mindfulness is more a description of what we know than in an in a prescription of what to
do is how things begin to shift in practice
when there's enough stability when there's enough ability to not wander off in thought and mind being
scattered and so sometimes there's a you know takes a long time to really
settle down and learn to recognize our just the forces of distraction the hindrances
and the power of the of the desiring mind and
and let all that come to rest and to soften and let go and quiet and so
to be able to just kind of be here fully in the present moment in a simple
very ordinary way nothing special not trying to do anything except just
allowing ourselves to be here and
being open and so then um
then at some point the practice has this more descriptive quality than
in prescriptive quality what helps to get there is that we have
to really know ourselves well and one of the strengths i think of mindfulness practice
is uh is that we are learning to pay careful attention
to recognize many different dimensions of what's happening in the present moment
it's uh you know if the buddha came you know showed up popped up popped out popped into the
modern society just somehow he teleported from ancient india
to the you know modern metropolitan city right in the middle of some big city
say new york city or something and he wasn't prepared for the experience
you know he would be very you know he knows how to be present he's really there for the experience he really
is you know feels experienced knows the experience knows himself well
and he was a walker he walked all over india so he starts walking through new york city but he doesn't know the difference
between a curb and a road or what the lines on the road mean or what traffic lights are and what's uh
he can't read english and so he doesn't know what one-way street is
from you know from anything so
you know he's a lot of stuff he doesn't know and so he's going to get into trouble pretty quickly walking the streets of of of new york
so it's a silly example same way with our minds if we don't know aspects of our minds we
don't even know what we don't know so you know when i was a new
practitioner i didn't i didn't have a self-image of myself as being an angry person
and so there's a way in which i didn't recognize when i was angry it was kind of like outside of my you
know my blinders that i had on or my what i what i would notice
and a whole range of emotions i kind of didn't really recognize as or recognize how to bring them into
awareness and as i got the mindfulness instructions and mindfulness of emotions
i started oh look at that i didn't know that all these things and so my ability to be aware
in a descriptive way in this kind of choiceless awareness way just aware of
what's there expanded now into a new realm
it wasn't so narrow the world of what i became aware of when i used to focus only on my
breathing a lot in meditation sometimes i felt quite present and wonderful and
and sometimes free and in good ways but it was all within a narrow domain
and that as it through my life i've learned to open up and see more and more that um
that it isn't that i now actively intentionally practice with all these realms but they're just there as part of
the territory just like for you if you're a driver and you're driving through new york city
you don't you're not consciously you know actively studying the lines on the road to
interpret what they are and uh or you know or looking at a red octagonal
or maybe it's a six-sided stop sign and kind of what is that it's just like second nature to see that
as you're driving along and um and uh
and so the same thing as we kind of learn the territory learn the vocabulary learn learn the
letters learn the kind of map of our own experience and then the freedom we receive the freedom that
we have in the awareness of all things it starts becoming more and more inclusive
and and so there's a balance between practicing to discover what's
here and practicing just to allow what's here
and those two practices go together really well stays mutually supportive
and sometimes uh it seems like i'm ending up doing one more one sometimes i'm doing more the other
the discovery plot part sometimes is a little more um prescriptive like this is what i'm
doing uh the and sometimes the
um the allowing part the just being free in the middle of stuff um is more descriptive it's just oh this
is what's happening to my experience so
i hope this gives you something what i say gives you something to think about explore and to add some kind
of little more richness to the practice of meditation and the practice of awareness
i hope it doesn't make you busy hopefully you have a sense of the
metaphor of the mind awake aware clear resting and easy in an
easy chair aware of what's happening
so thank you so i have a couple of announcements one is that these 7 a.m sittings will
continue now for the next two weeks in a wonderfully different way in that
this week that i taught was part of a three-week series i'm part of called the harmony of
zen and vipassana and little bit these weeks of teaching to this week i was trying to
teach vipassana in a way that harmonized a little bit of with zen and uh
the um so the next two weeks my dear friends um paul heller and phu schroeder will
give the teachings and theirs and teachers and both senior teachers at the san
francisco zen center foo is currently the abbess of the green gulchen center
and their dear friends wonderful friends and people have tremendous dharma respect
for and their dharma their practice is just really an inspiring thing and
i feel very fortunate that they'll come here and participate in this or 7 a.m community and
paul will do it next week for these five days and then those five days and then i'll do and then if we would do the last five
days and because uh this is the last time i'm going to be here
for these next two weeks i wanted to say that um
on may 8th the uh on a saturday morning we're going to have kind of a new and i
think what a wonderful event for and that is um there's going
to be a um a five-week series
called mindfulness meditation and mindfulness circle for black identified practitioners
and and so if you're black identified african-american and
you'd like to come together with other black and african-american folks
with a wonderful teacher named anne royce who i met this year she's
studying chaplaincy with me and a wonderfully profound and long time practitioner and
she'll teach mindfulness one of the wonderful qualities of one of the aspects of her in terms of the zen and vipassana thing
that we're doing this week is she was a student of suzuki roshi some you know
50 years ago i guess and so long time practitioner and wise woman person
so there's information about this on the imc website and different places the imc calendar
and also on the what's new and imc website so um
thank you all very much and and i look forward to seeing you in a
couple of weeks and but i look forward also being here with all of you as my my wonderful friends
offer their teachings thank you