good evening
i i want to say it's nice to be here
with you all because in my mind
i'm meditating with other people even
though i am
alone in this room
but i i feel the sense i can see the
chats that um
there's others with us here others with
me here
so tonight i'd wanna i would like to
talk a little bit about
how we can bring our mindfulness
practice even to
thinking or thoughts or mental activity
or
often with mindfulness there's an
emphasis on being with breathing
being with the body but
of course we can also be with the mind
and their mental activity has such an
impact on our lives
it's worthwhile to become more aware of
it
and and to interrupt some of the
momentum
it might have some of the compulsive
quality it might have some of the
feeling of getting stuck going round and
round
and because it's so easy to just to get
lost into story
and mental activity
it's abundantly easy to do that we often
don't
fold in mindfulness of
mental activity mental states
until there's a certain amount of
stability and steadiness
so it might be for a lot of our
meditation
that we are just settling
and calming down and so it's primarily
spent with a
mindfulness of breathing and mindfulness
of bodily sensations
but when we feel like there's a certain
amount of stability
and this might not happen until we're on
retreat or
some other extended opportunity an
opportunity for extended meditation
periods
but whenever we do feel like there is
some stability then
we can turn towards
the thinking and the thoughts
without getting completely swept away
in them because of course this
um in order to
be mindful of thinking we need to not be
lost in thought maybe that goes without
saying
but we see both in the satipatana
so these two discourses some of the
primary discourses
that talk about mindfulness both of them
include mindfulness of breathing and the
body
before the mind
so this quality of stepping back
being able to see the thoughts without
getting lost into them
or to see anything really that bodily
sensations or emotions
or is this so being able to step back
in some kind of way is just a
characteristic in general
of how we can go a little bit deeper
with our meditation
and how we can a little bit more
steadiness
or solidity or something like this
so this idea of knowing what is taking
place
rather than just being immersed in it
sometimes in guided meditation i talk
about to sit and
know you're sitting there's a certain
pulling back when we know that we're
sitting
so there's a few ways that we can
look at i'm using this word mental
activity mental state and
i like to maybe like tease a apart three
different
aspects of this
and the first one is not so common
and maybe it's a little bit debatable
but i'll offer it
and that is in the suta that is the
discourse on the establishments of
mindfulness
there's some qualities of the mind
that it says is good to notice helpful
to notice
and one is whether the mind is
surpassable
or not surpassable so the presence or
absence of
surpassability if that's word
what does this mean so
there are some hints we might get if we
look at
the parallels that are preserved in
chinese
for the satipatanosuta and there
the word gets translated as cultivated
or not
cultivated so
one way we might understand this are
probably a few ways but
one way we might understand this is
whether this is our usual state of mind
or a more mindful state of mind
sometimes i think about this or refer to
this as it's more like street
consciousness
i'm just making up this term what i use
this kind of walking around
not being mindful versus being mindful
we i don't know how to describe this but
i think you know what i mean
like we know when we're being mindful
when we're not being mindful
we don't know of course we don't know
so not only that to know whether we're
being mindful but to also know
is there a general feeling like oh yeah
okay
i recognize this mental state this is
what it feels like
to be more settled
or this is what it feels like at the
beginning of a meditation period
and after i've been sitting for a little
while i
believe it'll be different so is it
surpassable or not surpassable
that is is this the edge of our
meditation practice
or is it the beginning there's is it
ways we're
in still in the process of getting
settled
so is this familiar territory or new
territory and this not so much that we
have to always be inquiring um
do i have some attainment am i in some
new place
all the time but so it's not an
obsession
with our progress or our development or
how far we've gotten
but it's just this uh recognizing where
we are
so that we can
know what what to expect maybe what
comes next or
how we might if we know that there's
some
it's possible to get deeper more settled
i'm using these
words more settled deeper
then we might know that oh yeah there's
can be a little bit more letting go that
can happen
there can be a little bit more quieting
that
can happen so that we can
walk this middle way between not having
this
excessive expectations like that's
supposed to be a particular way
but also we don't want to have any
disdain
for using reference points that we have
with our practice
or maybe even some aspirations
we might have for our practice
so that might be the first aspect
of our mental activity or mental state
is just
this very gentle maybe
it's not even worth them highlighting
but to acknowledge there's a gentle
acknowledgement
of where we are in the territory in the
landscape of
meditation so to speak
a second way that we might notice the
interior experience the mental state
is to be aware of this
state of mind or we could use the
expression mental state
so not the content of the mind so much
but the
quality of the mind the mood of the mind
the state of the mind maybe the attitude
i know sometimes um i have this just
general even
even when not meditating i have this
state of mind like
oh yeah i just can't quite think
i think for whatever reason i don't know
why
exactly maybe i'm tired or
feeling frazzled or something like this
and the mental acuity isn't quite there
but just
the general kind of state of the mind
and so to step back from the details and
to
notice the greater context or the
meloo in which our mental experience is
happening
so mental states are subtle
and diffuse they're not we can't
pinpoint them necessarily and say
it's here exactly this it's more of a
vague kind of idea or
experience
so this again in some ways can be an
interesting exploration because we might
have this assumption
that to be mindful of something means
that there's some
precision there's some delineation
i'm mindful of this and it has edges and
it's clear and it looks exactly like
this
again this is implicit probably we don't
have that explicit
but i'd like to suggest that we can also
be mindful of things that are diffuse
and vague maybe foggy
maybe they're just known in the
periphery of our awareness not in the
center of our
awareness a certain a different type of
knowing if you will
and maybe we could use as an example
that
when you're looking at a window
and you realize that the window is
reflecting back
so you can see whatever is being
reflected in the window
and you just shift your gaze or a little
bit and you can also see
out the window so there's two different
views that are possible and
to notice that it's light inside
and dark outside for example
and that's why the window is reflecting
so it's the noticing that it's
light often when you notice that it's
not so much that you
are pointing to one particular
experience or object but there's a
knowing of light
i'm not sure if this is a good example
but it's something like to explore
that there's can be a general feeling or
mood or attitude
and the classical teachings use words
like
the mind is constricted or expanded
that is scattered or concentrated
or colored with greed hatred or delusion
or
not colored with greed hatred and
delusion
or fettered or unfettered
so maybe we might use language like
appreciative or wanting more
or calm versus tense
or light-hearted versus critical
or maybe i um an example i gave
earlier feeling like i can't quite think
clearly i can't
feel like i'm maybe there's just a
feeling of
not a lot of mental acuity and sometimes
there is
some mental acuity and then even that
whole idea well what exactly is mental
acuity
so just pointing to the general feeling
of the mind and to recognize that these
states of mind have a more
pervasive and enduring quality
than just particular thoughts
that is we might have angry thoughts
that appear but they the angry thoughts
might just arise and then pass
away but there isn't a general mood of
anger there might just be a flicker of
irritation
in contrast when we're when we are in in
an
angry mood they're just everything
we feel just a little bit cranky and
irritated with everything this just
general sense but we're not
really angry with everything because in
the midst of that
we might be having thoughts of oh gee i
wonder what's
uh for lunch where are my glasses
is it time for me to get onto that zoom
call
you know we're having all kinds of
completely neutral thoughts
even though there might be this general
mood
of anger that might be colored
by anger
so it's possible to completely ignore
the mind state we don't have to pay
attention to it of course
but i think we all notice when we
wake up on the wrong side of the bed
kind of gives us a general mood
that it does have an impact on us
and often the more aware that we are of
what's influencing our thinking
our behavior the more we can make
decisions about
how authoritative we're going to
take to be our thoughts are we going to
believe everything or
are we just going to notice yeah i'm
cranky right now
maybe if you're that half of the human
population that
hormone cycle and monthly it might be
noticing
yeah okay having these types of thoughts
right now they don't have to be so
authoritative i don't have to believe
them or give them as much weight as
i might at other times when my hormones
are in a different state
so that's the second way is just this
kind of vague
mood or color of the mind
state that tends to be
a little bit uh maybe um
not obvious and
enduring and then a third
aspect of the of what's in the mind
we might call generally mental activity
or maybe more specifically
thoughts but there's a
whole range of things that we
fall under the word uh mental activity
or maybe even
thoughts kind of lump them together but
there's a range
in terms of how compelling they are
how lost we are in them
and maybe the energy or the
movement that's behind them that we
might get really
might be a pressure really to think
about them
there's also a whole range into of terms
of the wholesome or
unwholesomeness
some things that are clearly if we're
having a lot of thoughts of
wanting to cause harm
there's it's very different of wishing
to
end the suffering of somebody thoughts
of how you might
help them find greater peace and freedom
and then there's a whole range in the
middle
so mental activities yet one more way
that we
can pay attention and this these are
associated with the best of the human
experience and the worst of the human
experience
and when unattended just like
our mental state our mental activity
can have such a big impact on us
so i'm making this distinction between
mental state and mental activity
some could argue that maybe we don't
need to but
i find it helpful in meditation practice
to make this distinction
but notice that often the instruction is
to settle or let go or calm
mental activity there isn't the
instruction that we have to get
rid of eliminate mental activity
because meditation doesn't always
require that we have this
thought free mind a thought free mind is
possible
but that happens but usually in a
retreat setting when the mind is
really settled really quiet
so we doesn't have to make the fact that
there are
thoughts doesn't have to be a problem we
can
let go of this idea that somehow we have
to be getting rid of our thoughts
and instead just how can we work with
them if they're arising how can we
disrupt some of the momentum how can we
disrupt some of the unwholesomeness if
they are there and sometimes just simply
paying attention to the
experience of thinking
that is as i did in the guided
meditation
are these thoughts are they images or
are they
sounds and just having that gentle
inquiry can be a way that
takes some of the momentum away from the
thoughts and that might be sufficient
to allow the thoughts to just arise and
pass away
like thoughts do
another way is to bring
awareness to the sensations of the body
and when and or
any sensations that are pleasant there
might be a feeling of ease
or openness or
some sense of well-being or okayness
that's anchored in the body so i'm
talking about okayness
and ease and one could argue that there
those
also can be mental states
and if one can rest in them by all means
we can do that but often
it's easier to rest in physical
experiences of ease and
well-being and certainly in the as i
mentioned in the anapanasati
suta as well as the satipatanos
mindfulness of breathing or
foundations of mindfulness
they is this instructions on
mindfulness of the body and mindfulness
of breathing before the mind
so we can always just go back to
mindfulness of the body
or mindfulness of breathing
if we find that our thoughts have a lot
of
energy behind them or find that they're
unwholesome
maybe we can disrupt them or undermine
some of the
energy underneath them by just
being with sensations of the body
especially if there's any some
sensations that are associated with
well-being or happiness
or some contentment
so maybe just an emphasis um on rather
than having to get rid
of our thoughts we can just have a focus
on what's
helpful and what's unhelpful
what's wholesome and what's unwholesome
what's skillful and
unskillful and maybe to steer the
thoughts
steer some of the mental energy towards
what might be more wholesome more
helpful
so in order to do this there might be a
few
tools we can use and the buddha he uses
a simile
which i appreciate that there might be a
peg
that is in some wood
but um we might imagine that it's
and the buddha says you might want to
remove this peg
and in my mind i'm thinking those dowels
like when you're using ikea furniture
that you're
using to join different uh pieces
together
so something like that
and this buddha simile says that if you
want to replace a peg
that is in wood that you use a
smaller peg and you can
tap it out so if you
if the dowel if the peg is
rotting and you want to replace it
if you want to not have rotting peg
anymore you can replace it with one that
is
fresher and the word in the
similar uses to replace a coarse one
use a finer one so if you were doing the
dowels with ikea furniture of course
you would use a little bit of a smaller
dough to
tap out using a hammer tap
out the the coarser one maybe that was a
complicated explanation of
what was obvious and didn't need that
explanation but the point here is
to replace thoughts
replace unwholesome thoughts with
more wholesome ones
so one might be
to
chant the refuges and precepts if you
find
that your thoughts just feel like they
have this a lot of
energy and there's a um
you're feeling stuck with this
compulsive going round and around not
really going anywhere
we chant the refuges and precepts that
can be
uplifting and gives the mind something
to do
and really can support a sense of
openness and ease
of course don't do it if it doesn't
support a sense of openness and ease
if you find that there are some thoughts
of ill will
revenge or wanting to
give somebody a piece of your mind or
something like this
something that i've done is chanting the
meta suit in my mind
i memorized it and it was a great
support to
use it as a tool to to be chanting the
metasuta
and just the practice of memorizing it
was really
helpful so
i offer this as something that can be
helpful to kind of replace some
unwholesome thoughts
or if not chanting the metasuta
then to just do some loving-kindness
practice
bring to mind the phrases of
loving-kindness and
to do them in a way that is
easy and available and accessible
that is not towards the person for whom
you're
having some ill will but towards a
lovable being
send some good will some benevolence
to a lovable being
so those are some thoughts of some
ways in which you might replace some
unwholesome thoughts associated with um
ill will if you're finding that you're
stuck with some lustful thoughts some
sensual desire that is just not helpful
we can do meditation on body parts
this is what the buddha recommends for
the monastics right to have a life of
celibacy
and i can imagine it's not always easy
to be celibate
so help them and to help all of us
if we're having some thoughts that are
unhelpful and
unwise of sensual thoughts
to think about body parts so usually
when we think about
people's appearances we think about that
as a whole
this person's attractive this person is
attractive but we they become
less attractive if we
consider their body parts for example
from somebody who's a model for
shampoo for example and has beautiful
lustrous
hair it becomes
less attractive if you imagine that it's
chopped off and on your dining room
table
it's the same hair but just to consider
it by itself
kind of shifts our relationship to it
so many of you may know that there's
this practice of doing the 32 parts of
the body
it starts with head hairs body hairs
nails
teeth skin flesh spleen
phlegm spittle snot and urine and it
continues
so right when you start considering all
these things have a person
then that really can shift your
relationship to them
so this is another practice somebody
might want to consider
something else that we might do rather
than
to replace our thoughts is just to say
you know i'm going to think about this
later
right now i'm meditating
and it might need to have some energy
behind it
no i'm not going to do this right now
right now i'm going to meditate i'm
going to bring my attention to the
breath
for example and just to say
later later not that we're never going
to think about it
but just now is not the time
so now that's a
the third way we can think about mental
activity and mental states is to notice
our thoughts
and then not so much that we have to get
rid of them
but can we encourage thoughts that are
wholesome and supportive
and one way to do that is to replace
thoughts
to use a tool and of course if it's
not helpful we don't use tools not to
use it
so these are things just to if we find
that we're stuck and we
need something other than just returning
to the breath
we need something other than just being
with the body
so i just offer this as some ways to
work with our interior experience or
mental experience to notice
the mind state as well as to notice
where we are
in our settling process in our
meditation process as support
that supports for more ease
more freedom so that
can support our being present not only
for ourselves but for others
so that our practice can be for the
benefit of
perhaps in one small way for the benefit
of all beings everywhere
thank you