so good day
and it's a happy occasion to be here with you all and
had the opportunity to meditate together and for me to teach it's a privilege and
i appreciate the opportunity thank you and
we have this wondrous wonderful mind chitta ci tta
that begins to stand out and highlight the calmer the mind becomes
so when the mind is agitated it means it's caught up in its concerns its uh preoccupations
its agitation its um and uh often then it's the more agitated
the mind is the more it's swirling around in its thoughts ideas
feelings and it's the subset it's a particular aspects of the mind
that the mind is focusing on thinking for example or emotions
ideas memories and what we're doing is we switch to being mindful of the
mind is to no longer have the preferential attention to
particular corners of the mind particular activities of the mind
and so as the activities of the mind get quieter and calmer
what's available then in highlight and over time as meditation deepens it
becomes stronger and stronger is there's becomes a felt sense
of the mind as a whole and exactly what that is is not so you know
so important what's important is your own way of experiencing it
some people might prefer to use the word awareness to represent the mind as a whole the
the total gestalt of how things are operating the
the uh the sum total is greater than the sum of the
parts so there's something that marvelous that happens as we open up more widely and fully to the mind
and in this early tradition there are sometimes sometimes his mind stands out so much
and highlight that it's anthropomorphiza anthropomorphized sometimes seen as a
person as if a person can talk to their mind or work with the mind train the mind
it's never seen as the self and this movement of selfing of positive
feelings sensing itself and this early tradition is seen as just another form of mental activity
that can also be calmed down put to rest and as it does so that also frees up the
space for feeling the mind as a whole
or sometimes it's called the state of the mind or the mood inner mood the general mood of in our
mentality or the heart mind and it begins to shift
the orientation of how we live our life and rather than focusing on the
particular concerns we have it gives us the opportunity to care for
and i love this word care compassionately care for lovingly care for the quality
of the mind or the quality of the heart the quality of this inner life that we have that's
what's the gestalt the totality of it that here in the tradition is called chitta mind
and we can begin settling the mind opening the mind
pleasing the mind bringing joy happiness to the mind
and liberating the mind and it's such a phenomenally satisfying thing to switch
from the details and concerns of our life to the present moment experience of mind
and caring for that so with that as an introduction
i will take a assume a meditation posture
and gently close your eyes and
with the eyes closed and feeling your body from the inside out taking a few
long slow deep breaths
deep deep breaths really as if you haven't breathed for a while and finally you get to really fill yourself
with oxygen and then exhale a delightful long
exhale ah here you are
here you are breathing in and breathing out
and then letting your breathing return to normal for a few minutes few moments and just
sit here and feel your body maybe those deep breaths have had a
influence effect on your body
maybe it bodies a little bit more has more sensations to feel
maybe you want to adjust your posture a little bit more
and then we'll do a little breathing exercise
that maybe will help the deeper relaxation maybe at relaxation deep inside
the heart the mind the cheetah
so it involves taking a deeper breath but only about three
quarters full but only as far as is comfortable
and then when you get to the top of that that particular in-breath hold the in-breath a little bit don't
exhale right away and hold it for as long as it's comfortable
and then as you release it as you begin the exhale see if that occasion can be
one of a deep relaxation letting go it's almost like the holding of the
breath heightens the awareness of your body your insides
that there's more available to relax as you exhale
so taking a three-quarters comfortable deep in-breath holding it as long as
it's comfortable and then exhaling with a deep relaxation
and it might be that the exhales can be a little longer than usual
maybe as you exhale you also relax the mind itself
softening opening expanding the mind
and even if you can't relax the mind
as you exhale feel whatever softness that's in the mind
feel whatever transparent boundaries there is to the
mind
and if it's comfortable continue a little bit longer and now at the end of the exhale
pause a bit just as long as it's comfortable before you inhale
so there's a rhythm of inhaling pausing exhaling
pausing that brings a heightened awareness to
your body and mind and a greater ability to relax
settle in
and then let your breathing now return to normal no special effort to pause or hold and
take a few moments to feel and sense your body again
and if there are some memory areas of your body you can easily relax
so softening around the face
releasing the shoulders
softening the belly
and if the relaxing you've done settling in you've done brings any sensations of pleasure
for well-being breathe with a pleasure breathe with a
sense of well-being the tingling the warmth
the glow the
dancing energy
and allow the thinking mind to become quieter
letting go of thoughts so you can have more energy more attention
to feel the body breathing
breathing with the well-being that might be here
however small it might be
and you might become aware of how the mind attention is predisposed
to focus on particular things concerns preoccupations
and if so then you're experiencing a limited aspect of your whole
wondrous mind
without necessarily letting go of your concerns can you expand your awareness
to include more of your interior life more of your quality of
inner life your mind your heart this state of your mind state of your
inner being
something that inclusive because everything that happens happens
within the mind
and then breathe with the mind breathe through it
almost as if each inhale fills the mind with the sensations of
inhale each exhale relaxes and expands the mind
settles it
becoming aware of the global mind the global sense of any
state of mind mood of the mind
the quality of the mind overall
maybe it could include the space of the
mind the space that the mind fills
so you're not focusing on any particular part of the mind
[Music]
a state which has no
boundaries
and if it has a location this mind of yours
chances are that there's a little feeling of contraction or gathering together
that gives that feeling
as you exhale relax that gathering together
soften let the mind rest
out into the vast space all around
mind with no walls no boundaries
mind that involves no conscious effort
that is just there here
if there is suffering suffering has a location
the mind includes all that is beyond the edges of
that suffering that's wider bigger
and to relax outward beyond the suffering
so that whatever suffering there is is held in this wide field
of open mind open awareness that has no
edges
breathing in outward breathing
that goes outwards towards the edges beyond the edges
all inclusive wide broad open
resting into the open space
and as we come to the end of the sitting
with whatever way that you can rest in open space
without the mind getting quickly fixated or preoccupied on any particular
thing just open and receptive allowing things just to
flow through you nothing stops
nothing is held on to
and staying that way the best you can bring to mind
some person that you might encounter today
personally or through some medium of communication phone or computer
imagine that you are quietly
allowing that person to exist as they are without you fixating on it
and anything as if they too can be held
in the vast open mind
in that way providing them to get providing them with a gift
that they can be just the way they are without any interference from you with
your desires aversions agendas reactions
allowing someone to be themselves in the vast open space of your mind
and in doing so imagining that you're doing so does that give you a different
reference point for good will for love
friendliness care even respect for this other person
and if it does now may be wish them well
may this person be happy
may this person be safe
may this person be peaceful at ease
may this person be free certainly free of my attachments
and may it be that other people that you encounter and other people that you have some
contact with or think about today that they also benefit
from this meditation practice you've done today
may all beings be happy may all beings be at ease
may all beings be free
and may we contribute to that
so
uh
so so the topic uh much of this week is
step nine of mindfulness of breathing and uh this is the step where we're
experiencing the mind and i hope that the way i'm presenting
the mind is something that's not not trying to define it in ways that you have to fit your
yourself into the definition but rather that it's um i think it's uh pointing to how you
experience the mind the mental state mind state heart state
that there's a lot of room here for you to find your own way to this and um but one of
the ways to appreciate it is that um we're moving into the the
the the the sum total of how we experience
the mind the pasta practice often has a big emphasis on particularity
really seeing the particularity of the in-breath the out-breath of sensations that they occur
my you know the particular particular activities of the mind as they come in to go
and and and uh but there's also some way that uh
part of the particular is also the the harmonious working of all this together
or the kind of the awareness or the knowing that knows it all and um and exactly whether mind and
awareness are the same knowing is the same or not you know it's very hard to kind of pin down these
things to know exactly what the mind is or consciousness or all these kinds of things that are belong to this rather
i don't know if amorphous is the right word but difficult to define
qualities or experiences of our interiority of inner life and
and you'll see now in a moment maybe why it's difficult to kind of put words on it and to find it exactly
is that um the concepts that we live with the ideas
that we have about our experience actually shapes our experience
we are not innocent bystanders of our experience that whatever happens to us whatever
experience we're having that it's only happening to us we're also contributing to some degree
to that experience that certainly there are clear things that happen
to us so to choose something relatively innocent perhaps if i go out
well i'll give you the example i've taught many times and i was thinking about it today when i was biking down here it was
cold biking down here this morning is um kind of a revelation from you many
many years ago was living in central california and going to college at a
college called davis and um and it was um that is a fog early
morning fog thule fog and in the winter time the cold fog was really cold
and and i didn't have any gloves and i would bike to school and the first five ten minutes of being
in class i couldn't actually use my pen because my hand was still frozen and so you know so
it was so cold so i used to for a while i was biking to school this
way and kind of feeling miserable sorry for myself and it was so terrible
this cold that i felt and and then at one point i kind of had a
memory that exactly the same feeling of cold that i was having biking to school was
as far best of my memory exactly the same feeling of cold i had in my fingers as a kid when i used to go skiing and
and that skiing it was exhilarating it was fun it was fantastic it was part of the richness of the whole experience and i
realized that that how i was experiencing the same sensation
vary depending on the interpretation i had it the context i put on it the ideas i had about it
and after that biking didn't become so difficult anymore i realized that i was adding something
to the experience of cold i was adding self-pity and this is going to be tough and hard and i don't know
what i was adding exactly and then it became just a matter of fact and simple to have the cold
it was still cold and a little bit painful but i didn't complicate it so much with all the
ideas that were kind of subconscious almost i didn't really realize how much i was doing i thought it was just the cold the cold
was the cold was painful was bad but we contribute to the experience we
have interpretations meaning making predictions of what it means we have self-referential feelings about
it this means that i you know if maybe have self-pity about things that are difficult or
self-congratulations for things that are good and these inner movements of the mind may be very subtle we don't necessarily
see them but they are kind of helping to shape our experience
and give kind of the totality the gestalt of it as we practice mindfulness we can start
teasing apart the different component elements that are all glommed together
we can see that self-pity is self-pity it's different than the cold we can see that the the way that we're
worried about the future that comes pulls into the my experience of cold for example
is just my thoughts about the future and we begin kind of teasing apart all this the component elements
and and as we do that we begin actually freeing the mind
we begin rather than glomming on or focusing on it then we begin to free it because not
only is our experience you know like for example me of the cold partly shaped by my relationship to it
but it's also shaping how i might experience the mind the mind gets contracted it
gets tight they get small the mind gets hot agitated
and you can the inner mood the state of mind that we have shifts and changes also depending on
what we're focusing on and how we're focusing on it in relationship to things so we're also in a sense shaping how we
experience the mind or how the mind can be felt whether that's the mind itself who knows what the mind is
but how we experience the mind is what we're really working with in this practice here and so the mind is
also being shaped and and the language of the early tradition
is that the concepts we are focusing on fixating on um creates
limits creates a boundary to the mind an edge to the mind but as we stop focusing so much on the
things and our preoccupations and all this activities of the mind the activities of the mind get quieter and
quieter the shape the the way which we kind of shape the feeling of the mind the sense
of the mind begins to lose its edges its its coagulation its contraction
its its gathering together and it becomes more open
more spacious and after a while you can almost feel like there's no boundaries to the mind or no boundaries to awareness
or no boundary uh boundaries to the state that we're in
and to use a little bit dangerous word from what i said earlier
no boundaries to consciousness and and it isn't so much again important
what all these words point to with a wonderful thing is the experience
of no more edges no more boundaries and the mind starts feeling
large great expansive
and and this is one of the things that can be experienced as we deepen this meditation practice is the
mind becomes expansive becomes wide and then they called it a big mind
and uh as opposed to the small mind and the expansive mind rather than the
contracted mind the and the the more expensive it gets
the calmer it becomes the less agitated it is in the similar that space empty space
you know kind of has no agitation and they say that um
it's um you know that mind becomes similar to space
so less and less agitation and calm it also helps make the mind more malleable and shapeable
because when we're really fixated on something the mind becomes hard maybe even brittle and kind of
fixated also and if you do the same habit of mind over and over and over again for decades
the mind gets kind of locked into being a particular way it's hard to soften it but with meditation enough
time it begins to soften and relax and it becomes malleable and shapeable
and one of the ways the mind can be then more what happens when the mind becomes more
shapeable or malleable or soft and is it's easier and easier to
train the mind it's easier and easier to get the mind focused and
centered settled and and that allows for some of the more
beautiful qualities of the mind to shine the mind that's fixated and bounded and
limited by its agitation and preoccupation doesn't really allow for the luminosity
of the mind to show itself the clarity of the mind the cl the mind
feel that feels clean the mind that feels bright
so this gestalt this wide sense of
the attitude of mind the state of mind the mood of mind the quality of awareness
that is so wide that it includes all things and it includes our suffering
not to deny it but to give it a very different context than if our relationship is
is like a locked on to our suffering and it's possible to suffer of different
kinds and and not lock on
and to feel that the suffering being held or existing in this much wider broader
context has certain kind of ease or calm that also allows to have compassion for
suffering there's space for friendliness and care for it as a that's maybe more difficult when
we're locked into it so there's a lot of benefits to
discovering the this mindfulness of the mind
and for an anapanasati the mindfulness of breathing practice we train ourselves to breathe with the
mind breathing in one breathes with one experiences the mind breathing out one experiences the mind
and as always with andapanasati this rhythm of breathing in and breathing out is meant to keep us
from getting fixated on anything including fixated on the mind so they're
just a fluid and relaxed kind of with the breathing breathing in with the mind breathing out
with the mind um so how about taking care of one's
body by getting mittens or wool socks over hands these days i drive i bike down with mittens on my hands on
with gloves i just was not smart enough when i was a college student
for that even to occur to me i didn't have gloves and never never passed my mind so some of us
you know takes a while to become wise about how to take care of ourselves but in the meantime i got a very good
lesson from my story with uh with the um you know my cold hands
so thank you very much