so warm greetings from redwood city
it's nice to be here i feel kind of quiet at the moment so
to warm up settle down get ready for meditation
the um there's a saying if you go walking in
the wilderness sometimes go backpacking that the
saying is leave only footsteps so sometimes they say leave no traces
or leave only footsteps and in the time of the buddha
buddha commented on that birds leave no traces no trail behind them when they
fly through the sky and this relates to the idea of
the metaphor of seeing for meditation to observe
that um if you are lay on the grass and look at the clouds
drifting by you look see them but you do not disturb them
if you sit to the edge of a river and watch the river go by you see it but you don't disturb it
this is a wonderful thing about eyesight that that
we can see clearly if we can see but we're not obviously
normally interfering with what we see we don't touch it we don't manipulate it
we just observe it so the same thing with the breathing
to observe the breathing is to not be bothered by it
and not have an agenda about it but rather to let the breathing take care of itself
and if you find that you can't help but to control your breath that you're breathing or
you find that the breath is constricted in some way no worry
the idea is to simply very simply be to observe that to be with it
and sometimes settling back and just to watch it even from a distance rather than feeling it sometimes is
really helpful of not being bothered getting out of the way of it and this to do so is
is not passive in the sense of we don't care about what happens
but rather it's strategic in that it allows for the natural system
to come to equilibrium it allows for the natural way of breathing to settle down
an observed observed breath observed breathing
returns to um to harmony in a sense
the buddha said that an observed mind becomes happy
the idea also just leaving the mind alone and letting it kind of settle out
and it points to the idea that we're often with our attachments we're often
engaged manipulating fixing reacting to all kinds of things
and that reactivity doesn't allow for some equilibrium and settling to happen
and so part of the art of meditation is learning how
not to be reactive caught in involved in with what's going on and i like to say
not be bothered by it one of the great teachings i received around
thinking and meditation was a teaching don't be bothered by your thinking
but for this week on breathing see if you can have leave no traces not
even a footstep with your breathing just observe it
as if you're looking at clouds drifting by or waves gently lapping up against the
shore or as if you're watching the the little wavelets of a river as the water flows
down now the idea is to get out of the way of your breathing but clearly stay present for it
and trust that your whole psychophysical system will take care of it as need be if we
really just observe some the miracle of observation gentle
caring loving receptive uh observation of of breathing
so to take a meditation posture
and um sometimes you can pull in the top the
spot the spine between the shoulder blades ever so slightly
in such a way that it it kind of pushes out the chest
maybe a little bit straighter so there's more room for the lungs and
the diaphragm to breathe
and lower your gaze relax your
gaze and kind of an unfocused gaze not looking on anything
and then gently closing your eyes
in the beginning of meditation we can actively engage the breathing
to establish the connection to help relax
and maybe also set up a contrast between being involved with breathing and later
letting it breathe itself so taking a few long slow deep breaths
really feeling your lungs fully the top of the lungs as
well and then a long leisurely exhale
and exhale relaxing the body
and then letting your breathing return to normal
on the exhale relaxing the muscles around the face
around the eyes
and around the mouth
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
and softening the belly
and moving slowly a little bit to a breathing that's simply observed and allowed to breathe
itself ever so slightly at the end of the exhale
pause before you breathe in not so you get winded or something but
just a gentle pause so you can feel
the desire of the body to breathe in
and then allow the body to inhale
and perhaps also at the top of the inhale
a gentle pause so you can feel the pull of the body to
exhale and as soon as you feel that little pull
give into it allow it
the body will breathe itself if you allow it to so to do so
so now don't make any effort with the pause
just allow your breathing to breathe itself
but being a witness to your body breathing
without being bothered whether you are still controlling it or if it feels constricted or difficult
if anything as you watch it be curious about it
or be tender and caring
trusting for now that all you need to do is to
accompany it as a witness just observe
the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
if your mind is actively thinking
see if you can allow yourself not to be bothered by that but also not continue with it
instead when the mind wanders away from the breathing
open the window of the eyes to allow the breathing to appear
the rhythm of the waves of breathing
coming and going
as you watch your exhale see if you can watch the whole exhale
like you would watch a bird fly through the sky
you would watch the whole thought you'd follow it
until it disappears
watch the whole inhale
allowing each inhale and exhale to be itself
another way of talking about watching the breath
is to allow the breathing to breathe itself and see what happens
when you stay close continuous with gently watching
the inhale and the exhale as if you would do it forever
as we come to the end of the sitting
to mention that there are times when one of the
gifts we can give others is to allow them to be themselves
to allow them to be themselves with respect
with appreciation
and this ability to sit quietly in meditation and leave and
allow ourselves to be ourselves in some deeper way than we can if we're
swept away in the floods of thinking
to really be present to see to know to feel ourselves
but let ourselves be ourselves in that process
to learn to do that in meditation we can also learn a higher quality way of doing that for
others to really be present for people
to care for them even
and that be in ourselves being free from needing to fix or judge or
change someone but rather to be with them with the
respect that they can be themselves maybe in such a way that they can relax
and be themselves more deeply than they've ever been
maybe some of the challenging ways they are is because they're not allowing themselves to be who they are
may it be that as we learn this meditation practice
that we can give others a gift of allowing them to be
who they are even if they don't know yet who they are
to accompany to witness to see others clearly
and they feel safe from us
may we become safe for all beings
may we contribute to the happiness and welfare of all beings
may what we're learning in meditation be applied
out into our lives the people we encounter
so that maybe we lighten the load or brighten the day or
reduce the suffering of those we meet may this meditation practice
serve for the welfare and happiness of all beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be free
[Music]
so this week i'm teaching the five r's relax recognize
today it's respect tomorrow it's be restore and then release
and to meditate with mindfulness of breathing to respect it
to offer our respect to our experience and i like this uh
word respect a lot because it's you know in latin that means to look again
to respect something is to give it a second look and uh so we really see what it is in
and of itself to observe it to see it and it also it's different it has a similar
effect as allowing something to be or accepting things to be there but it
has more body in it it has more accepting or allowing things to be
is uh sometimes is quite profound but it's also uh it's kind of like
where were we we're absent in the picture in some way which
has its advantages at times but to
have to see with respect to be present with respect there's something that we offer some kind of dignity or valuing
that we contribute and to come from a place of respect is to come from a place of a certain kind of
inner strength a certain kind of inner presence or something that is quite a
beautiful place to be to be able to give the gift of respect to something
and so this idea of looking again and so with the breathing to watch it to
see it and respect it enough to allow the breathing
to breathe itself and and it's quite something that if we can
get out of the way of the breathing but really be present for it give it breathing room in a sense
to do its own thing that generally we learn so much from the breathing
we learn about the big and the subtle ways in which we are contracted or anxious or
or agitated or afraid or depressed or sad all these kinds of ways
of being affect our breathing and because it affects our breathing
as the breathing begins to be it's allowed to be itself
it begins to kind of move through all these feelings and emotions and attitudes that affect breathing
and kind of like massages them and when we leave the br that when we watch the breathing and leave it alone
respecting it it's an indirect way of respecting and leaving alone
so much of our psychology and something uh and the massage of breathing is not just a
mechanical physical thing it uh it's intimately connected
to our deeper psychological life and if we can allow the breathing for
some freedom to move and relax and to settle and to open
just by watching it and giving it lots of time to do it as i've said then it massages the
psychology it helps those things also come to equilibrium or come to
to unfold in the way that's appropriate for them
um the gift of accompanying of watching or seeing respecting
is really a profound thing some years ago i met a woman who when
many many years ago she had been a
researchers she did research in psychology and in psychology and in particular the relationship between
mothers and their young children and for about two or three years
she went to the home of a mother who was raising a child i don't know if she was single but
she was always home alone and and the researcher would simply show up
and would not talk to the woman but simply be in the living room with her and watch as the woman interacted
with her child the child was you know maybe you know just a little baby initially
until two or three years old and she was there to take notes of what she saw the
the relationship between the two and that's what she was doing the researcher was just studying that and
um and um and after three years of doing that uh it was time to stop and the
researcher find you know spoke to the to the mother and explained she was leaving and the mother was deeply moved and said
that having this researcher come to her house and watch her be with her child was the
highlight of her week and even though they didn't speak simply to be watched be watched and be
attended to and be be treated as someone who's important enough and valuable enough to to pay
attention to is like a is a great gift like food for people
and and uh and so it can be for ourselves i had this similar experience with my
child when he was young when i don't think he really spoke yet but um
i was on the floor with him and he was playing with blocks and uh he was absorbed and playing with
his blocks and he was kind of humming along to himself clearly happy and delighted and i was just there watching
and after a while i got a little bored and i thought well he doesn't need me anymore he's absorbed in his blocks he
hardly knows he doesn't even know i'm here really so i started to get up and as soon as i got out i started to get up he stopped
singing or humming and i realized i saw what happened that he clearly knew i was there that my
accompanying and watching and seeing was a huge part of his happiness his safety his everything was okay in the world and
i had an important role even though i wasn't doing anything or involved in anything just being present and watching
so this idea of doing the same thing for ourselves and doing it through the medium of our
breathing breathing is not a mechanical thing only it's prof it's an intersection
the meeting place the crossroads of so many different parts of our uh emotional
psychological intentional social personal physiological life that we have
that um to be able to settle in and feel the breathing see it respect it
get out of its way and allow the breathing slowly to find its way uh is a is a is a profound thing to do
for our whole being what i do sometimes is uh if my breathing is constricted sometimes if i
live a you know active life doing a lot of things there's a little bit of tension builds
up in the upper part of my chest and then when i sit down to meditate i feel that
that constriction when i inhale i can't inhale all the way and what i've learned to do is
not be bothered by it in fact what's more important is
instead of being bothered what's important is to offer a gentle caring attention to it just observe it
and every time i inhale i make sure that i'm right there to feel and sense and observe
the place of constriction as if there's no problem it's allowed to be there i'm not trying to fix it or be upset by it i
just kind of like patiently as if it's forever offer my attention to that place
and at some point or other something begins to release let go
and and the kind of remarkable thing is oftentimes i don't see it letting go and relaxing it's either too slow or
maybe it happens on the exhale and i didn't notice and
but this for me is allowing the breathing to breathe itself
and uh and i'm calling this respect to watch it to be present for it
to observe it without interfering without judgment without
condemnation for sure but to do it with respect means that we do it as if it's important it's valuable
when we practice just allowing things to be or accepting things as they are they can come without any kind of inner
feeling that this is important this is valuable and i like to
consider that when we learn to meditate we're learning to value everything
nothing is not valuable even the smallest little detail
is not valuable it's one of the things i learned from my zen practice
the school of zen that i practiced in one of their slogans was that or one of the ways the characteristics of that
school of zen was called attention to detail and
that you respect every detail no matter how small and they'll end with a little story
of uh of um i was very inspired by this um
in the long time ago in the 1970s um i was there was a little bit informal
uh well there's a there was a gathering of the uh zen masters in the united states
uh and um it was kind of informal back then i think that maybe there were six of them about
uh that who are there at this little gathering of them there weren't that many back then and um
and um and they were just mostly meeting among themselves
and then it's uh but they had one evening they had a panel where ascend students could kind of see
them in the panel and and um and uh ask questions of them or something it was kind of a unique event
and there's a they were sitting behind a table and and uh someone
would brought them drinks tea or something we're bringing things you know to them
and what stood out to me was that all but one
kind of didn't react didn't respond to the fact that someone brought them some tea and put it in front of them they
just kind of like accepted it as normal there was there was no hostility no it was just kind of a
neutral thing but i remember one of them took the time to turn to the person who brought tea
and kind of bowed to them and expressed their thanks and uh i was struck by that one zen
master took the time to the person who was you know uh
incidental in a sense for the meeting and all that uh deserved their respect and met them and
and about to them and that inspired me so attention to detail everything is important and to respect
the breath to express express respect the in-breath the out-breath the pause
to respect the beginning of the in-breath the middle of it the end of it to be present to observe the beginning
of the exhale the middle of it and the end of it all these details are important
and as we kind of enter into this world of observing just the breathing it becomes less kind of like looking up
into the sky and watching the clouds go by and more like almost like a
the most relaxing microscope you can imagine where you're just kind of zeroing in
on just the details and just the subtlety of it and to and doing so with respect with
care with allowing things to be as they are the gift everything can be as it is
and with our respect is one of the profound things to learn through meditation practice
so thank you very much