and um so one of the orientations or
perspectives on practice in the teachings of the buddha
is an orientation oh i wasn't recording
so one of the perspectives on
practice in the teachings of the buddha is that he was oriented to
towards the consequences of our actions so there was a sense that
noticing little bit or caring a little bit for what the consequences of what we do is
important and so some orientation into the future
about the potential the likely results of what we do is part of a wise way of living
and of course we have to be very careful with that and it's balanced with the tremendous emphasis on the present moment in this
practice as well but it's not ignoring the future and
consequences and so to sit down to meditate in the morning it might be that we do
have a sense of the day will go better we'll be more centered calmer maybe wiser and so there is some
appreciation that and motivation even to meditate because of the benefits it brings our lives
and then there's also the consequence in the short term it's possible to
have a sense that if you sit down to meditate and what you want to do is to
be in a super hurry to get into a deep state of concentration and
and because there's important things to do and in life and and so you're going to just
really huff and puff and strive and get all sweaty and contracted and tense so
you can get quickly concentrated that doesn't work and so have some sense
that yes i want to get settled here in my meditation but it doesn't work to strive or to push or
have a lot of expectations demands to be measuring how i'm doing as i go along
every few seconds what has a good consequence is just be very relaxed around
the consequences at this point and being relaxed about not trying too much to make something happen
is the better way to make something happen that's useful in meditation and so there's still some consequential
thinking but it's recognizing you know how i am in the moment is important
and that it makes a difference how i am that if i strive in meditation i'll have a headache and
that will persist through the day if i can be at ease that creates more ease and it sets up a nice thing for the
day if we get closer in and
and into the present moment the sense of the consequences of our practice
has more and more to do with the present moment we can feel the difference between being critical about
how we're paying attention to the breathing versus being relaxed around it
and you can feel the the immediate consequence sometimes called instant karma the immediate quality the
that one of them has is more dukkha suffering and one is more open and and
feels better and feels satisfying and this ability to differentiate between what is satisfying and not
satisfying in how we enter the moment it gets closer and closer to something very
intimate and close here and now and less concerned about the future
but to be able to discern that difference and see is it are we are we involved in
um you know are we too lazy in meditation and so the
mind is drifting off too much and a little bit more energy is necessary a little bit engagement
are we a little bit too much
constantly making commentary about our meditation and always kind of questioning and doubting
it and is that really that's not really so useful and you could feel that that doesn't feel good
and perhaps having a provisional confidence in our meditation um a uh just uh
you know provisional until more evidence comes it's actually more useful for settling and so again there's a
sense of the immediate consequences there and for this meditation i'd like to point to something more subtle
and that is that as we practice like mindfulness of the
breathing there's a very there can be a very subtle
after effect of
be a moment of being connected to the breathing like if we follow the breath all the way
that knowing of the breath being connected to it it's kind of like an after image there's
a kind of or kind of like a if you go out into the war and stand in the sun and get
warm that warmth will persist if you go back into the shade for a little while there's the the after
effect of warmth that remains so there's an after effect of doing the
practice act after effect of kind of after image
after sense after feeling that persist a little bit beyond just the moment of being mindful it's
very subtle and uh and even if you don't feel it
the sense of being open to it or receptive or
to to feel that as well kind of in the peripheral of attention
to be a veil or to be available to be open and receptive to allow an after effect or the glow of
the practice or the the the uh after warmth
remain or the softness or the calmness or whatever it might be to let the goodness of the practice kind
of be available for you to persist into as if you were making space in your body
for that after effect that the results of the practice so you're
not making it happen you're not demanding it happens the subtlety is that of kind of staying
open available for the practice to somehow
work on you or radiate into you or persist a nice feeling of something
and whether you feel anything or not is less important than that sense of presence and
availability receptivity to something be kind of of allowing yourself to be
practiced by the practice to allow yourself to be affected by
the practice in a way that's not exactly your doing
it's the consequence of what you're doing the after effect and if what i'm saying
is too subtle or too bizarre for you just forget what i'm saying
but um so with that taking a
upright metaphorically or literally upright posture
and taking a few moments and closing your eyes to feel your body
kind of roam let your attention roam through your body
familiarize yourself with what the experience of your body is right now
and then to see if you can adjust your
kind of your attitude your orientation that with your body and heart and mind
you're available
you are available to be receptive
to to the practice that you're available
to be changed
you're available for some deeper qualities of practice to be registered or to
waft through you
and then very gently with this receptivity availability
take some gentle but deeper breaths
maybe slowly as if you're receiving the inhale into
that availability
and filling that receptivity on the exhale long quiet exhale
and perhaps you recognize that quieting the thinking mind
increases the receptivity the availability to really take in the experience of
practice of meditation and the more you're thinking
the less room there is to be available to sense to feel
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and in terms of feeling the after effect being available to linger and feel it
it might be extremely subtle but notice the after effect as you relax different
parts of your body as you exhale softening the muscles of
the face
and what's the feeling that comes with relaxing those muscles
as you exhale softening and relaxing the
shoulders
and in these little moments of softening relaxing the shoulders what good
feelings remain for a few moments what after effect is there
relaxing the belly
softening it might be possible to soften the hands
the fingers
might be possible to just gently just a little bit flap your elbows to loosen up
any tightness or holding in the arms
it might be possible to relax and soften
the muscles of your back so maybe those
muscles kind of release down your back
and now opening more fully to your
breathing at the end of the exhale
for a moment let there be a very brief pause
not a pause that is a strain but just long enough so the beginning of
the inhale really wants to happen and you
allow it and rece and better so you can better
receive the inhale
for the influence the inhale has on your body and mind
receptive not just only to the sensations of
breathing but maybe to the afterglow or the
radiance or the something that spreads from your breathing as you inhale
and as you exhale allow the exhale the release to
occur ride that release ride the exhale
gently allowing it all the way to the end
and especially as you get to the end of the out breath being available to feel
the influence that exhaling has on you
more widely
being receptive to the inhale
being allowing for the exhale
available to allow the influence of mindfulness of breathing to spread
through your body
as if your body is a receptacle that receives the practice
and whether you receive anything or not is less important than
is openness and availability as you breathe
and if you become aware of other things besides your breathing
perhaps you can become aware of them body sensations feelings thoughts
in this open receptive way that's
available to feel not the influence of our
feelings and body sensations but the influence of
being mindful aware aware of body emotions
thoughts
where being available and receptive is almost a quality of the mindfulness
itself
and perhaps feeling the goodness
of this receptive open mindfulness
practice
in some subtle way small way can you adjust how you have a continuous
mindfulness continuous awareness of your breathing of your experience
so that that mindfulness has a good influence on you
that it's nourishing supportive that the after effect the influence
is beneficial or if you notice that the after effect
the influence is not beneficial can you adjust it
so that how you're aware seems to have a nice influence
here and now in the present moment in this body and mind
letting the thinking be quiet so you can better feel the subtlety of all this
sometimes the beneficial influence of the practice
can increase slightly if you very slightly make a small
half smile turning up the corners of your lips
and allowing for the receptivity being receptive to the influence the
good influence of pleasure joy
that supports being present
as you receive the inhale receive the global
nourishment or influence good influence that might be here from meditating
as you allow the exhale allow the nourishment or allow the
global goodness that might be here throughout the body
in the mind in the heart
letting your awareness take it all in on the inhale
the awareness allow for it on the exhale
and then as we come to the end of this sitting take a moment to feel
grounded in your place of meditation
if you're sitting upright to feel the sitting bones your bottom
firmly on what supports your weight if your feet are planted on the floor to
feel the solidity of your feet on the floor
whatever way you can really use your body weight to really feel grounded settled
established here and then together with that
to be open and receptive to be available to feel and sense and
take in the experience of the world around you
without being unduly influenced been duly affected by that
but grounded in the present moment and open and receptive
and then bringing to mind some people of your life
friends family neighbors people in the community and places you
frequent and imagine that you're with one or some
of them in this way both grounded and
established in the present and open and receptive
secure in your groundedness available to be open and receptive
to take in the experience of another person
and maybe feeling or sensing the other person knowing the other
person from some place inside that
is tender or gentle or kind loving
without losing your groundedness without leaning forward or
approaching the person or needing to say anything just this place of being grounded and
receptive have thoughts of good will for them
feelings of goodwill in which you wish them well
may you be happy
may you be safe
may you be peaceful and may you be free
and imagine that this is the stance that you can have towards everyone
that you are firmly confidently grounded in yourself
and open and receptive to take in the humanity of other people
and then to extend your heart to all beings may
all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
and may the benefits of our practice this morning
contribute to that being the case
[Music]
[Music] so the topic now
is the third factor of awakening
the effort factor of awakening or the effort lim the word anga
can mean lim or part and and so it's a
it's a part of the whole and uh so the seven limbs of awakening
the seven factors of electing parts of awakening can be seen as a part of four
seven different qualities or practices or states
of one whole one whole way of being
and one of those ways of being is to engage to to make efforts to do things
so it's not just a passivity of just how we are but there's also an
engagement in our practice in our world
and the word viria that's a v-i-r-a-y-a
v-i-r a-y-a is comes from the word hero
and so a kind of heroic effort
but all these words like effort and heroic effort can lend itself to being exhausted as
soon as you hear them like oh no i have to do all this work now and
tiring work some translators to uh translate this
word for effort and effort factor of awakening as endeavor
and i don't know if some of us if the word endeavoring has a little bit more nicer feeling than the word effort
we endeavor to do something it's what we are engaged in trying to do
to make it really maybe feeling closer in and more less the energetics of effort
i relate this right effort with the word choice that
it's the choices we make as we practice and as we live our life and choice you
know a choice doesn't necessarily imply that there's a lot of effort or strain or work a lot of work it's just a choice the
choice and what we're going to endeavor in and this uh the usual definition or
description of these of the effort factor of awakening is the same description as the effort
factor of the eightfold path and so if you take it as endeavoring
the buddha is here is teaching us what what in this wonderful precious life
that we have what endeavors are worthwhile to do
you know what's what should we do with our life what endeavors and rather than giving an
answer for a particular project you know particular work to do a career to do or
something the answer is it has to do with
the consequences of what we do of how we do it and so those things
that lead to what is skillful or wholesome those things
choose choose those things those things that
lead to what's unskillful to what's unwholesome
don't do those things don't choose those things to do
and what's most skillful in the in the teachings of the buddha are those
things that avoid we're avoiding things that cause suffering
and suffering comes along with a feeling of being caught or trapped or constricted or
clinging to something craving the world's gotten smaller narrower
and we choose to do those things that are skillful which is those things that lead away from suffering
lead to a kind of wonderful happiness and peace that goes along with feelings
of freedom of openness of tranquility
of of goodness of happiness
and so it isn't just any old happiness that we're looking for
because some happiness is like the happiness of winning the lottery is not really a
deep nourishing kind of wellspring of goodness of warmth of peace of
kind of real intimacy with the warmth and juiciness of life it's more
of a surface joy and more exuberance and and
i don't know what promise of all kinds of exciting things and they say that most people who win
big lotteries a year later are less happy than they were before they won it
so what is it that's lasting happiness what is it that lives lasting well-being and so begin having a
sense of what that is not in the big picture like way in the future but to to recognize
this in ourselves to recognize moment by moment
that um if i'm driving my car and there's a light up ahead that's
green but i don't know if i'll make it and then get contracted and focused and
tight and like you know i better get it you know i i'll be late for my appointment
my life will you know be so much more difficult if i don't make that green light and and then we're kind of you know
getting contracted and tight and the feeling in the body and the mind
and the heart maybe it's subtle but is not a very good one it's not a nourishing one it's not
one that inculcates goodness or warmth or peace or love or care for others
but another choice in driving would be you know i see the light up there it's green
right now but probably i can't reach it i'm not sure rather than racing to see if i can get
it what if i actually there's no one behind me right at the moment what if i actually go a little bit
slower and just kind of take it easy and give the light a chance to turn red
and then i can kind of be connected myself to myself in a different kind of way and i can kind of relax a little bit be more
open it can be more receptive to the traffic around me and to the environment and not so
narrowly focused and you get it turns red and you stop and you sit there and turns out then you're
kind of quite contented you did a nice thing for yourself and and so this much some of you might
think this example is ridiculous but we have ten thousands of these small
little choices that we make throughout the day and to begin endeavoring the right
effort is to make wise choices around these ten thousand little things we do throughout
the day including the big choices we make the big things we do
and this this is how we bring mindfulness into daily life is we bring mindfulness to all the what
we're doing and we have not just aware of what we're doing we're aware of the choices we make as we
do them and we we're aware of the options we have
of which direction we go in the skillful or the unskillful
and so the investigation factor of awakening the fact awakening that makes the sees
clearly and sees distinctions includes seeing this distinct distinction between his healthy and
unhealthy skillful and unskillful beneficial and not beneficial
leading to entrapment or leading to freedom
and so right effort is to you know in the effort factor of awakening is that
factor of awakening that's constantly turning towards the healthy choice
but not because it's a lot of work in fact as we get the hang of it it
feels the opposite that's where the least work is
in some ways choosing the unskillful thing that can't if you're lazy or if you're
kind of it's easier just to go along with impulses it can feel like it's the easy
way but generally the consequences are require much more work later much more
repair and stress and all that choose the healthy approach the skillful
and it tends to be just the consequences tend to be good in the future and no repair is needed no you don't have to
de-stress afterwards recover from it and so getting
getting the habit and the ongoingness of being present and making these wise choices to
what's skillful and beneficial tends to start creating a life which has less and less stress in it
less and less needing to recover from the stress the tensions of the life and so there's
more energy there's more vitality for this life of ours than if we choose
the unskillful repeatedly repeatedly and so this effort factor of awakening
uh is um is certainly the individual practices and choices we make
along this line but it's more of a state or a generalized attitude or orientation
for how we live where we're just naturally oriented towards the skillful
naturally oriented towards these choices which lead to our betterment to ease to peace to ongoing well-being
and there's a kind of a momentum in that direction there's a kind of a strength to that
that follows in the wake of the second factor of awakening becoming strong
this really seeing clearly so first there's mindfulness that places us in the present moment then
there's investigation in a sense or exploration or discovery
that helps us to see all the choices we have in the moment when we when you see the
red light green light or the red light ahead as you drive you see oh there's a choice here and
then there's the effort factor of awakening which no something inside of you
with time almost doesn't have to be a lot of reflection and planning and calculating and bringing up the
calculus of stress and freedom but it's uh just
it just feels like oh that's the natural thing to do that's the easeful way that's where the doors are
open that's where the freedom is found and of course we choose that and so the
choice becomes more and more effortless more and more delight and joyful and
my hope for all of you is that if you do this a day will come
that the word effort just brings you a big smile and you're like oh i am so
lucky to be able to make effort wow this effort thing is fantastic
wouldn't that be great and along the way what's happening is you're beginning
to manifest your freedom your ability to be free
to simply choose to be mindful is an expression of freedom
to choose to discover to look more carefully to investigate is an engagement of your freedom
to make your choice is an engagement enactment of freedom
and and so uh and that's very different than being
the victim of our experience or being under carry the burden of the weight of
the world on our shoulders and everything so hard and uphill we're
being impacted we're being piled up piles and piles of responsibility where
there's no freedom but to choose freedom over and over again is not a second nature for many of people
but this is what we're working with and what how we're setting ourselves free in the big sense as well by all these
small movements of manifesting our freedom in mindfulness investigation and choices
we make so thank you and
i look forward to continuing this series