so good morning everyone and or at least everyone on the west coast good morning
and on the east coast later morning and
in europe good afternoon or good evening
as you can see gill is not giving the morning meditation today
i am for those of you who don't uh know who i am i am paul haller
a dharmi teacher at the san francisco zen center and for this
for three weeks this is the second week of a three-week series of called harmony of the passana and zen
and guild suggested that there's three teachers there's gill myself and then foo schrader who's the
average of one of the temples at san francisco zen center and guild suggested that
during this time he would give the guided meditations for the first
week i would do them for the second and then foo would do them for the third so
and then within our intensive we are taking up the topic of the
harmony of the past night and then through uh the its established teaching
of early buddhism of sila samadhi panya and
for this morning i'll translate them as sila as the behavior that supports
practicing and samadhi as the continuous
contact of awareness and then panya the fruits
of sila and samadhi
and it over the course of buddhist teachings in buddhist practice
panya or in sanskrit or prajna has been related to in a variety of ways
and here's what i'm going to suggest to you this morning three ways the first one is
understanding as we bring awareness to
the human condition actually more particularly when we bring the awareness to our version
me version of what's happening
and and we start to see um the world
the subjective world that's created by me
and then the second version of panya or wisdom
is insight we start to
not so much we just draw conclusions but it includes that but it's more that
it's as if we see what's happening in a broader way than just
as as within the world according to me you see something more thorough
more more expansive than just the world according to me
and then the third way is what i'm going to call realization
is where the moment is experienced so thoroughly
that we literally forget the world according to me we forget creating
an interpretation and understanding and just the immediacy
of experiencing the moment has teaching that goes beyond
how we think how we conclude how we judge how we reference our version of reality
our version of the self so these three
and and they support each other so first of all i'll offer a meditation
and and the way i'll offer it is i'm referred to understanding
you know because out of our understanding comes our intention to practice
and actually out of our understanding comes our notion of what practice is
and how to practice it you know
but primarily the great gift of it is this intention to practice
and then it also includes how to practice you know we have an understanding of how
to practice and then
that opens us to how does that understanding of practice
engage what's happening for us in the moment
and the part of the understanding is an acceptance of what's happening for us
at the moment that it's not that we're broken and we
need to be fixed it's it's not that there's a pristine
consciousness that we're determined to create it's more that each moment is itself
and we are engaging it in a way that allows that to be so
it allows that to be the lived reality of the moment
and then so that creates an intention and an attitude
okay this is about being present for what's happening
it's not about control it's not about making something
happen that's not already happening it's about aligning
the mind aligning the emotions aligning the body aligning the breath
with the activity of awareness and being fully present for what that
creates
so so let's do it so if you could
just start by noticing
and if you can in just noticing what's happening
intend non-interference
noticing the difference between noticing doing noticing and being noticing
the difference between doing noticing and being noticing
and then bring that delicate awareness to noticing the body
what physical sensation is most apparent
sometimes we notice a tightness
some part of the body is complaining a little bit
sometimes we can feel the heart beating
and then intentionally
open the body to awareness
traditionally that means an uprightness
a sense of balance
a sense of physical attention
and a sense of ease
and each body has its own response to those notions
noticing the response of your body
with the intention and attitude of being aware of physicality
and then quite deliberately bring awareness to the exhale
and two characteristics i would offer you in relating to the exhale
one is when we're asleep
the breath and the body
dictate how the breath is not the mind
so can you allow the body to
express that kind of breath
it's like rather than having an idea about how you should breathe trying to notice how is the breath when
you just leave it alone
okay a very standard phrase
for relating to the breath in awareness meditation is following the breath
the breath is allowed to breathe and the attention follows that experience
and our noticing is all-inclusive
if our attention is mixed you know
interrupted by thoughts ambient sounds so good
and then the other quality of breath on the exhale is like
like a sigh like softly letting something fall away
and often when we engage the breath like this
allowing it to be what it is allowing it to be designed
by the body not the mind and we release with the exhale
it helps create a capacity to notice how the breath
can have an emotional quality to it
and we can use that attribute of breathing to help create awareness in the moment
and then as you breathe in can the inhale be
allowing whatever is going on in the mind and emotions
just allowing it to happen
inviting awareness of it
it's almost like when we're feeling the texture of it
is there ease in the emotions in the mind is there a particular topic
issue that's causing some disturbance
sometimes there's an unsettledness that doesn't have a particular topic
so as we breathe in this allowing
allowing what's going on in the heart mind of being
it's almost like we're reassuring the heart mind of being
that it's utterly okay to just be what it is
it's okay
and with the exhale so be it
all things arise and pass away
this is the great rhythm of life arising becoming with the inhale
releasing with the exhale
in a tender way in a way that supports
the delicate nature of our mind and emotions
in how they ripple through the body and the breath
and this intention this attitude disposition
starts to make evident
what we are in this moment
starts to make evident the state of mind
this emotionality of being
we're not attempting to change it we're attempting
to be as fully attentive and engaged with it as possible
[Music]
and as we continue this process and
we can notice and acknowledge
with each breath we start over
allowing opening
receiving the mind the emotionality the
physicality
and with each exhale
releasing
and whatever happens is the gift of the moment
whatever happens
the next breath is a new beginning
a new intention a new moment of acceptance
so
and with the beginning of each breath
cycle an intentional
commitment to awareness
to letting the body breathe
the mind be mind
and letting the human organism that you are
express itself in response to that
body and breath and mind
[Music]
you
so
[Music] [Applause]
[Applause]
so this notion this intriguing spiritual notion
that as we practice awareness
it shines a light on the human condition it shines a light on the person we are
how we're constructing the world how we're relating to the world
our version of good and bad or evil or whatever you want to call it
the places where we get stuck the ways in which we get stuck the places where we open and release
how both of those influence
our state of being
so awareness starts to give us enormous amounts of information
you know about what's going on for us and how we're responding
and it starts to give us information about how to relate to that
and so i was calling this understanding you know that way in which
when we start to see something we have an understanding of it
and as we bring awareness to understanding
it helps us refine it no it helps us see oh
i'm tending to look at it this way i could also look at it that way
once i was talking to someone and a woman and a man had proposed to her
proposed marriage to her and but he came from a tradition
a culture where marriage was to a very large extent arranged
and so he said to her you're this sage and i'm this age and my parents
want me to be married
how about it and she was quite deflated you know
i mean she actually she liked the person that wasn't it but somehow
the matter of factness of it this looks like it could work you know
you have these common interests you know
and you know i'm being nudged in this direction you know by my parents um
and she realized that from the cultural background she came from
that romance was very important it was very
significant
and there was a kind of a cultural divide between these two
attitudes well when you get together with someone
isn't it kind of an arrangement doesn't it have a practicality
how will you pay the bills where would you live you know who cooked the food
it's very practical in a way and then in another way
i would say in our western culture and
the um how we're relating to it you know
romantically know so just as an example
of a cultural attitude
and then there's a very interesting way until something brings it into being
it's kind of im implicitly accepted and invisible
and so awareness is to bring into being to bring in through awareness
we become aware of it and we become aware of it by experiencing an incident of it
so our understandings when we pay attention to the process of
practice and our understandings of it you know they will start to teach us
here's what helps and here's what hinders no in terms of awareness
they will start to teach us our own biases
as we experience examples of them
and when we bring awareness to it it both supports the process of practice
but it also is supporting the process of liberation
[Music] because the the lessening of suffering
the mind that experiences in an
appreciative way what's happening the heart mind
that relates to what's happening
with the deep compassion for the trials and difficulties of the human condition
and a deep appreciation for the potential of
living engaged in the world engaged in the self beyond
fixed ideas
so it stirs up awareness stirs up our understanding
in terms of the request of practice the sense of self the details of self
and the opportunities practice offers us
and then the insight
is those moments when we step out of all of that
it's almost like see it oh i have a bias about
marriage i come from a western culture
that upholds the notion of romance
i mean if you think about our culture now um not so long ago i mean
sometimes ritually we still do it the father gives away
the bride yeah
and and now that's sort of becoming alien to us
the notion that marriage was a contract between a man and a woman
we're starting to see well that's just one way to think about it you know
if there's romance isn't that enough does it matter what the genders are
as we bring awareness and we see our fixed ideas
and attitudes the awareness inclines us towards expanding
our thoughts expanding what's possible and then also
inviting us to reflect more fully on what's most important about
being alive
like when we see okay there's romantic and there's arranged
they're both options
and when we see in as in an increasing way then we sort of see beyond
okay what options will we collectively start to see in the
next 50 years
so this um
this way of noticing acknowledging and letting it
inform us in a deep way
how not to suffer how to lessen suffering how to be more open to the possibilities
of life
and then the third aspect of wisdom prajna
that as there's experiencing you know
romance is romantic
until you feel a hard connection with someone
until you feel an affinity you know
the greeks have four definitions for the word love you know
it's as we open up you know there's an experience
and it draws us beyond the conceptual it can even draw us
beyond the emotional and then in another way
it includes them as part of the whole process of experiencing
but there's some some learning that happens through the immediacy of experiencing
you know
when you fall in love you know something of the nature of the romantic
when you look at the nature of love then you start to see okay there's romantic love dysphilia
love brotherhood sisterhood this familial
a sense of belonging to family or tribe
and then there's agape a universal love that includes everyone
and everything
the very process of awareness
opens us invites us to greater being
and this is in one way we could call it
the fruition of tanya or we could call it
the full expression of panya the full
expression of samadhi the full expression of sila no
they're interwoven
okay
so as you go through your day
noticing acknowledging and opening to
um okay this is what's happening
let's be it let's feel it let's experience it
let it teach in a way that goes beyond ideas and emotions
okay thank you enjoy your day