okay great so so welcome everyone welcome warm welcome to happy hour
wherever you are in the world whether it's your first time yay welcoming the first timers tonight
especially or happy hour regulars welcoming you
warmly as you welcome each other
so so for the theme for today's practice together
um the theme of the body and meta meta
loving-kindness cultivating friendliness good will care love there's so many ways
to translate this word metta m-e-t-t-a in poly
many nuances and and the body the body
there's so the the teachings on mindfulness of the body
uh
[Music] is translated as awareness or mindfulness
mindfulness gone to the body kayak
mindfulness of the body is is so important it's really the foundation of
so many other practices um drawn from sati patana sutta the
four foundations of mindfulness so so on friday we did some practice of
grounding in the this sense of grounding as
meta coming to the body coming to the body um as self-care
grounding in the earthiness of the body earth on earth and many of you said that
that was very supportive for you and grounding and and and this sense of establishment
of oh metta as care in in connection connection with the body
so so along the themes of the button and for those of you who who missed it you're welcome
it's on audiodharma.org and also on youtube we can go and catch up and listen but
and no and no catching up is needed whatever is whatever is needed tonight will be
shared with you during the guided meditation so it's all good you don't have to catch up for the sake of knowing what's happening
now i'm just kind of letting you know these connections just for background just for background so tonight
tonight or this morning whatever time zone you might be in um the idea of
both grounding in the body bringing awareness sati mindfulness to the body
as an expression of care for ourselves as well as leaning
into it even a little more now so leaning into it in the way of
oh this body this body this dear body that i
take for granted a lot of the time this amazing body
that functions it heals itself it breathes it
processes food in ways that i have no idea how it even gets done these amazing chemical processes
and also if there's any challenges in the body any parts of the body that are
challenged hurting struggling
to bring more care love meta
to those parts of the body so both grounding in the physicality and
as as a way of met caring for ourselves connecting for ourselves and then really
leaning into that care leaning into that care the body both as a mother and as the
child both ah kind of the stability of oh thank you body you're really comforting
soothing and oh sweet dear body you're also in some ways you're challenged and hurting
so both of those both of those both as the parent as well as the child
so so navigating that relationship tonight is the part of the invitation in
this practice and well let's see what shows up for each of us
might be different we always explore in this way of cultivating
friendliness and goodwill so so without further ado let's
land into our practice together let's land into our
posture if you need to move if you need to lie down
if you need to relax your body soften you need to sit up straighter in order
to ah establish a sense of integrity
a brightness
see what your body needs this unique
expression of humanity
that is yours and not yours
relaxing relaxing
softening into the body
putting down putting down
whatever is not necessary in this moment
thoughts germinations plans not needed right now
i can always pick them up later
in this moment moment of refuge
moment of refuge the simplicity
of this body connected to the earth
feet legs sit bones
and just being breathed just being breathed
my
and each in-breath bringing more presence connecting with the felt sense
of this body and each out breath
ah letting go
landing releasing into the body more deeply
each out breath releasing a little more
can each moment of connecting with this body putting down thoughts not that there's
anything wrong with thinking per se but choosing right now to give ourselves
our hearts completely
to this refuge to this moment of practice simply
connecting awareness knowing
this body sitting connecting stabilizing
calming grounding as an expression of care for ourselves
love for ourselves
affection for ourselves just here just connecting
awareness
turned inward feeling his whole body sitting
all these sensations
of sitting or breathing
noticing how soothing it is it can be
to turn the attention awareness
just connect with the sensations of simply sitting and breathing
a radical act of care and love self-care
connecting with this body in this moment
as a source of stability
care for ourselves
imagining the arche archetypal mother or parent the buddha or kuan yen
the statues sense of care stability
love as if as if your body's embodying that for you
as if your body was a buddha statue kuan yin stable
eliminating care love stability for yourself
tenderly each breath connecting to it
and so too this body
has challenges i'd actually be having challenges right
now they're part of the body in pain
or not quite functioning
in good health perfect health this body too
as a tender as a tender child being held the same way you would hold the
little newborn a baby
just having a hard time perhaps
just tenderly there there sweetie it's okay it's okay
patiently holding the body of a child
same sense of meta directed also to this
body
especially to any parts that are struggling
or have been struggling
they could be physical parts of your body or direct if your body
is in perfectly good health maybe directed to the heart center the
proverbial heart center center the place of emotions
heartache if there's any dukkha that has physical manifestations in your
body any stress
tightness sadness anxiousness
showing up in the body holding that tenderly with meta
there there sweetie there there
so
you get to choose what is more supportive going back and
forth or holding both this idea of the body as the mother
is a stable supportive
source of connection care stability as if a mother
as if the buddha or kuan yin
the embodiment of love and compassion
see if leaning into that is more supportive or holding the body as if a newborn
tenderly body heart mind oh sweetie it's okay
directing love care meta to the body at some point
maybe the two perspectives become one they merge
see what's more supportive for you in this moment
explore
this
each breath both connecting to the body
and soothing soothing comforting
bringing ease relaxation sucker to the
body don't work too hard let it be nourishing
let each breath be nourishing
soothing
i invite you to put a hand the palm of your hand the
middle of your chest your heart center making your physical connection
stance of care
connection you can imagine it's your own hand or the hand of the
loved one or the buddha or going in and your chest it's okay sweetie
calming soothing supporting
connecting let yourself be surprised
maybe put the other hand the other palm on your belly holding your heart center
and your belly
oh dear heart oh dear body
it's not easy it's okay it's okay
for the last couple minutes of this practice
both feeling the sense of stability solid solidity uprightness
of this body this posture
connecting with the support of the earth
and the sense of integrity that's available that holds holds the tenderness
with care with love
tenderness in the body in the heart and the mind
with love and care
may all beings
be well
know their own goodness have all the support there they need
may all beings including ourselves be free
thank you all thank you for your practice
so i'll change the settings so you're welcome to raise your zoom
hand to share your reflections what this was like for you what you discovered
your insights for the benefit of both yourself being held witness is quite profound also for the benefit
of the sangha your insights your observations your questions serve everyone
and also you're welcome to type them in chat if you type them privately to me
alone i won't read your name and just i just read the reflection and if it's
typed everyone then i also read your name
so as i wait for your reflections or your
questions for your hands to be raised i'll just say that again what we did was
at the beginning just settling with the breath and the body taking refuge tilling the soil calming the mind
and then turning to the body both as the support the stability this connection
the body as the mother body as the child or for many people maybe kuan yin or the
buddha works better than the image of the mother so so wayne please
i i find that uh holding putting my hand on my belly
real really helps me stay in touch with my breathing
and and helps me come back quicker from when i notice my mind is
thinking about something so that's very helpful nice nice thank you for sharing that
yeah that sense of connection just the physical physically connecting
with the hand on the belly this the with the breath rising falling great delighted to hear that
um and that's a support that's always available to you i suggest that actually many times actually
to many students that yeah it's fine it's okay to put the hand on the belly and the
sense of connection so delighted to hear that was helpful for you wayne great
and barbara
please
i feel that also you're um
saying that there may be dukkha in the heart center um
as well physically i'm not suffering there is
a heart center at the thought of the covet being more
uh threatening now and in my life that's where my family's
going to be gathering and um
yeah yeah thank you barbara yeah it's the heart
you know the heart center proverbial heart center carrying so much you know the dukkha it has ramifications
in the body you know all these expressions we have my heart feels heavy because we feel it in the
body it feels like ah this heaviness this heaviness yeah yeah thank you for
sharing that and that's something that you know the covet situation of course and
the delta variant our shared humanity no matter where we are in the world
we're sharing this so two reflections coming to me one person says i really
liked the guided experience as if being embodied by kuan yin then the buddha
felt so strong grounded and stable even if just for the moment beautiful
yay i'm delighted to hear that that uh report from the field that's great
that can just bring a sense of stability and another report coming in
thinking of my body as mother slash buddha and sending loving support metta to myself that way immediately
led me to be more protective of my physical body make it strong for long-term care of my
health smiley beautiful i haven't thought of my body in this way enough the rank of it beautiful
reflection beautiful insights both of these in chat and also those who
raised their hands thank you beautiful reflections and very
insightful lovely so how about we turn oh one more one more
coming when you nikki mentioned something like instead of the back and forth
holding both together came very much in handy there was a ping-pong going on
between pushing aches and pains away and befriending them making space for all was then possible
thank you oh lovely it's great making space for all
lovely yeah beautiful thank you for your practice everyone
such lovely reflections and i'm sure there are plenty more reflections and here
and now turning into small groups will have the chance to listen to each other and also share as
much or as little as you like sometimes actually listening to each other brings more up like oh
yeah that came up for me and i totally forgot that i noticed that during guided meditation
so these uh the group practice sangha practice is is very important part of our
practice here in happy hour so so the group size is usually roughly
three people three or four depending and we always start with just 15 seconds
of silent meta for ourselves and for each other for our bodies for each other's bodies
and then you can say and then you can go around
and say as little or as much as you like uh there's about we have six seven minutes in the group
so so i will open the groups now the rooms now take care of yourselves take care of
each other okay here we go
welcome back everyone welcome back the rooms are closed
we have a few minutes for any reflections that might have come up from listening
to others or listening to yourself sometimes when you hear yourself share your practice
new insights come up or no questions or shared understanding or no understanding
so [Music] especially if you haven't shared this evening or recently you're welcome to
raise your hand we'd love to hear from you or you can type in chat
yes wayne i am talking a lot um well it's your first time at happy
hour so you have a lot of catching up did you tell us i was when we were we're one gentleman
mentioned about drinking caffeine in the morning and i i remember i didn't start drinking
caffeine until i was about 22 years old and i was at us
in a sashin at the zen center and i wondered where all the people went
in between or in between the zazen periods and so i thought well i'll follow them out and everybody was
heading to the coffee urn and i was wondering about
um my i guess my answer is that well i should just try now i drink i've been drinking coffee
ever since but uh use you know people i guess that's one of the things
coffee's always been used for is for stimulation and i was just wondering about
mindfulness and maybe practice sometimes without
drinking caffeine yeah i strongly i strongly recommend it i strongly recommend it actually yeah without
without caffeine or where yeah without caffeine without without get to to notice the state of your mind and heart without
caffeine and often when people come on retreat silent retreats and they've been used to drinking coffee
and they intentionally go they stop drinking to really be able to
observe their mind what happens without caffeine and then if they drink the effect of it so
yeah i highly recommend it way yeah thank you yeah definitely good practice
reflections jerry says it is amazing how one feels much less isolated
hearing the vulnerability of others yes absolutely yeah
marie christine says yes this is true jerry and yes and an agreement from patricia
it's so isn't it amazing how much less isolated one feels hearing
the vulnerability of others such a beautiful way to practice in community and melanie says totally
relate jerry my professor wrote this to me in an email once and i think of it often among my own
peers i find that the passage of time eventually corrodes the simplistic and
conformist notion of success that we are fed at a certain age we all
realize that nobody's life has been perfect and that it's empowering to share our
regrets or sadness or failures oh beautiful melanie thank you
for sharing that absolutely absolutely
yes this conformist notion of success it's simplistic and it corrodes and
when we actually share our vulnerabilities our sadness our regrets our pain
our failures and growth we come closer it's part of our common humanity we're all
human yeah so much more there it's it's the first noble truth in buddhism
stress pain dukkha failure challenge is a part of human life it's
part of human life so thank you all such beautiful
heartfelt evening of or morning i almost have to
remember the different time zones or afternoons given australia giving marty christine
of practice with all of you so thank you all for showing up and cultivating
your heart for yourself and others may all beings be well may all beings be free
[Music] thank you