so then express my delighted greetings
to be here with all of you and share this time together
um so
there's many many approaches to meditation and many many approaches to
being deeply connected to this present moment
and one of the most you know common things that maybe i teach here is you know if the mind wanders off come
back to the breathing stay with the breathing something like that and
and so then um another another approach which is
can be both them can be both a means to being peaceful settled in the present
moment and also uh the result of being here
present and in the moment is a contentment and you might
practice contentment as we do the meditation practice just kind of
call on contentment with whatever is happening just or maybe that's too much to say
just being content um at this moment to con
find a contentment uh and that's the direction the meditation is going
it's going to a very profound form of contentment a subtleness
a being at rest with what's here and
not needing it to be any different
so if you have some reference point for
contentment whenever you need to return to the present moment whenever you need to
adjust how you are to be here in the meditation see if it can you could bring it with a
sense of contentment and see if that can help you be more settled and
more present so taking an alert upright posture
and gently closing your eyes
and is there a way directly that you can allow yourself to be content here
not necessarily looking for something or retaining anything but in some way feeling a contentment to
be sitting in meditation to be present here and now
even if things are difficult and to rest into some form of
contentment
and if that's available to you as if you can breathe with and through
the contentment out of contentment take a few long
slow deep breaths
deep breaths that expand the torso the chest the ribcage and a long exhale
where things just settle and relax maybe settling into being content here
not concerned about the other times in other places
just what's happening here and now
deep breath in and out relaxing into your body
and letting your your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale relax parts of your body
softening in the face
softening the shoulders
and relaxing the belly
and then once again is there a way you can settle into
a deeper contentment content to be here in this body of yours
even if there's pain aches if that's what you have to
include as part of the meditation even with that to settle in in a content
place to be just here breathing content to be alive with a breathing body
an aware mind aware of your breathing
aware of the body's experience of
breathing
maybe even content to be
present for each inhale and each exhale
and if the mind wanders off in thought
perhaps renewing your contentment
content to be with your direct experience
one breath at a time
you
and then a reminder to find a contentment
resting in a contentment that supports you
in being with your breathing and being really here
at ease and settled in your body and mind
hear content
you
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
perhaps we can think of contentment that contentment is not a complacency
or some naive acceptance of things that shouldn't be accepted
but rather contentment is being settled in oneself
at ease in oneself so that whatever we do
is not agitated whatever we do is not anxious
or greedy or doesn't come from a place of discontent
and unhappiness within ourselves
perhaps a deep contentment allows us to be better friends
to offer more care and love
to be generous to those around us
because we're not impatient we're not needing things to be different we're not
trying to get away or get someplace or do something different
we can be present here
so that the goodness the beauty the support
of others can be part of our orientation
and what a wonderful thing that our contact to others
comes from a deep contentment in our hearts
content with with being alive and being
present and perhaps when we're content in
ourselves we have more room and space
for well-wishing caring for others
that the end of meditation can be expressed with these words
may it be that all beings be happy
may it be that all beings feel safe
may it be that all beings
may be peaceful may it be that all beings may be free
and may we contribute to their happiness their safety
their peace and their freedom may we contribute to it
out of a deep sense of contentment and ease
may all beings be happy
[Music]
you
okay
um so
to continue our discussion of kusala this week um
this week mostly um
um talking about it as a skill
and and doing what's skillful and that
the buddha uses lots of analogies of crafts people and farmers and animal trainers
to uh make similes for metaphors for comparisons to the developing of
meditation skills or skills along the path of liberation and so because all these similes have to
do with craftspeople and farmers and musicians and
animal trainers elephant trainers like ancient india and the idea of skill
seems like a better translation sometimes than wholesome but these two are closely connected
and one of the skillful practices or skillful states is mindfulness
practice and that mindfulness practice is
the simile for it where it is becoming a skilled cook and so i guess you know bringing
together all the ingredients bringing ourselves completely here maybe we're the pot or something and we're
bringing all these good qualities together so we're really here maybe cooking something really
wonderful
and so this idea that mindfulness is a wholesome skillful practice it's a craft we're developing
suggests as i said yesterday something developed slowly over time and uh if doing that
the buddha had this wonderful quote i was teaching when based on
ethical conduct established on ethical conduct
you develop the four foundations of mindfulness then
whether night or day you may expect only growth in skillful states
not decline so here we have this mindfulness self is
considered to be a skillful skill to develop and as we develop this
skill of mindfulness it brings with it all
it brings with it the development and growth of skillful states and we find another theme from this week
is how much the buddha is emphasizing personal growth development in certain qualities that were
helpful and good for us to have
now there's lots of lists in the early tradition of these skillful states uh qualities of being
and um and in fact there's many more lists and
enumerations of skillful states than there are for unskillful states
it's almost as if um there's only a few relatively few unskillful
unwholesome movements of mind that we can have and and many many different options for
skillful ones and uh and you know unfortunately we spend a lot of time with the ones that
are the few a few of and don't explore the range of all the good qualities that we
can develop and cultivate and but i'm delight in the fact that
this early tradition will list many more positive states and
qualities that human beings have than the list of the negative ones and uh in one of
these lists in the later tradition in the abidama the kind of buddhist psychology
the the unwholesome unskillful ones are called that they're called akusula unskillful but the skillful ones or the
wholesome ones are called beautiful and there are more beautiful states of mind or mental factors or
mental movements of the mind that are possible for us
then there are unskillful ones so we have this great capacity and maybe to some degree it's
underutilized and part of what we're doing is cultivating this underutilized part from
of our mind there's a wonderful list of skillful
states that the buddha taught to his
foster mother and she's the one who raised the buddha and she became came to him as and became
a student became a nun and and she asked him once to teach the dharma teach to offer his
teachings in brief so what are so this always when it's always in the suttas when he's
going to say it in brief it's very interesting to see and very interesting to see gather together
all the brief statements of what how the buddha kind of encapsulates the dharma
and see there's a particular kind of orientation that gets repeated over and over again and
that is practice and the immediacy of our experience now that's where it's all the emphasis is
so so she asks him to teach him teach her the dharma in
brief so she could go off and practice alone so she wants practice instructions
so this is what he told her as for those mental qualities
of which you may know these qualities these states lead to
dispassion not to passion to being unfettered not to being fettered to shedding
not to accumulating to fewness of wishes not too many wishes
to contentment not to discontent to solitude not to crowded company
to arousing effort not to laziness to being unburdensome not to being
burdensome you may definitely definitively hold
this is the dharma this is the teacher's instructions
and now what's interesting about this kind of list is that they're both states or mental activities
ways of being that we can practice we can cultivate
and they're the result of that cultivation they're the result of practice as well
dharma practice leads to these states and so rather than just practicing you know breathing ethics all the different
things of practice to reach those states the idea is to practice those states as well
and we find this uh this way in which the goal of practice is integrated into
the means of the practice the means and the goal are not so separate
in the dharma and if the goal is to be peaceful then we practice peace if the goal is to
be compassionate we practice compassion if the goal is to
be content we practice contentment if the goal is to not be caught in the grip of many
desires then we practice having few desires fewness of wishes
and some of these ideas are
you know interpersonal like being some don't be a burden for other people
if you and that you know we need some some care and how we understand that certainly we don't want people to feel
like won't get can't get support who need the support but but to expect too much from people
or depend on people when we don't need to is to be a burden and um and this idea
of solitude not in crowded company
the ability to be alone and be content is uh one of the great things to
discover it's really skillful to develop that skill that capacity that wholesomeness
to be at ease with oneself to be be comfortable with oneself
to be able to be uh in a room by oneself and just kind of sit there and be content
and and keep one's uh own company be one's own friend
it doesn't mean we have to live as a hermit but that ability means that when when we
are with people that we don't bring our neediness we don't bring our
grasping and wanting them to provide us with all kinds of benefits
and company and support and praise and love or whatever everything because we have a lack
ourselves so we want to cultivate a capacity
to have comfortable solitude so it's fascinating that
to his foster mother these are the skillful states the buddha highlighted as being
essential for going off and practicing alone
so and i think part of it is that these
states as we cultivate them they lead to more and more of the same
and or they're the guide these states are the guide this is the direction we're going and if
we understand where we're going then we kind of start doing those things
those states and practices that lead to that direction so for practicing meditation mindfulness
or breathing to have in mind that it's leading us to being content so let's start kind of finding it and
seeing it now it's leading us to have fewness of wishes is it as we sit and practice can we tap into
this and have that support the very meditation practice itself
leading us to capacity to feel at home when we're alone can we can we cultivate meditation with
that in mind to feel the deep deep sense of subtleness with ourselves
and and so forth on we go um many of the so-called these
these sometimes are called virtues that were being cultivating develop developing um many of them
uh the overarching kind of character of those long many of the lists that buddha
emphasized to develop and practice are peaceful states peaceful qualities and um in the
in this course on loving kindness he talks about being upright straightforward
easy to speak to gentle not proud contented wise and calm
so here's more of these skillful states that are to be cultivated
another list is respect humility contentment gratitude patience and gentleness
so and there's mountain anyway as i said there's many many of these lists
[Music] so
to to cultivate and allow for the growth of skillful wholesome
qualities and it's skillful to develop these states because they themselves are onward leading they
lead to further growth just as mindfulness leads to the growth of skillful states wholesome states
so all other skillful wholesome states bring along with them uh uh companions
and other of other wholesome states so this kind of uh bringing along mutual support of all
these states within us and it's a wonderful thing to start feeling the momentum of wholesome skillful states growing in
us and offering a kind of energy and and
and inspiration and movement for life so skillful
skillfulness may you explore the idea of skillful
you know if you orient your life today around what would be the skillful thing to do
what would be the skillful thing to do uh to support uh these best these qualities of
uh contentment fewnessa wishes unburdensomeness all these kinds of
wonderful things freedom so
thank you all very much and look forward to seeing you tomorrow