so good day everyone and welcome to our sunday morning sitting
and as we begin this sitting i would like to evoke
i believe it's an important principle not only of buddhist meditation that we teach here
and but also of the dharma the teachings of the buddha
that you know certainly i think have been an
important part of my practice life and that is the principle
of simplicity that um
even though sometimes the dharma the teachings might seem complicated if that's the case
the hope we have is that their purpose is to point to simplicity
perhaps sometimes we're complicated because people are complicated and so to explain
to point back to a simple way of being a simplicity of being a simplicity of
freedom that sometimes we meet the complexity
with complexity but to keep in back of the mind you know where is it pointing to
that is simple the simplicity of
non-clinging the simplicity of just being with the experience with
clear vision with clear seeing it's kind of like turning our gaze
upon whatever is happening and having that gaze
be easeful relaxed at peace with what we see the gaze
itself our wisdom might see the complexity of the
situation or wisdom might tell us what should or shouldn't be done
but not to confuse or entangle the wisdom with the gaze
wisdom with clear seeing and to have this foundation of
simplicity as a simple presence
within which wisdom can operate so to take
assume a posture that is appropriate for you
in allowing your body some ease some simplicity
of being hopefully where there's not much
struggle physically to be present
a posture that allows the body to be still
for this duration
and if there is no such posture then it's fine to do this meditation
as a form of walking meditation back and
forth and then giving some care
to settling into this posture maybe moving the body a little bit
rotating swaying back and forth maybe even lifting the shoulders up as
high as you're comfortable and then letting them relax
and settle and then gently closing the eyes
and feeling the foundation under you the solidity
the hardness the firmness that supports the weight of your body
such a simple everyday phenomenon that we live with we navigate through
and which in meditation we rely on to help us settle in
the pull of gravity the weight of our body
is something we yield ourselves in that in the place where the body
makes contact with that support feeling the ground feeling grounded
there rooted
and then further up maybe to soften the belly relax your belly
sometimes when you soften relax the belly let it hang forward and down there's a little bit
more of a foundation a base a groundedness
in the lower torso
and then softening in the chest softening around the heart
as you exhale relaxing the shoulders softening the shoulders
releasing the shoulders to the pull of
gravity
and then also as you exhale to soften the muscles of your face
the jaws maybe by having the mouth
just open a teeny bit more than it is maybe the lips are still touching but
the teeth little bit fall away from each other
relaxing the cheeks and the muscles around the eyes
letting the eyes eyeballs rest in their sockets
and then softening relaxing around the forehead
the temples and even if it doesn't relax easily
maybe on the exhale can be some softening around that area
even if it's just the softening of the way we hold it that we're aware of it
and then behind the forehead between the ears the area of the brain
feeling whatever sensations there might be there of energy agitation pressure
contraction hardness
and if there's any of those things then on the exhale softening
the brain relaxing that energy
and as you do so
quieting the thinking mind
and notice whatever is simple about being here with a modicum of
silence where there's nothing to figure out or attain
or do but to rest with some ease in the simplicity of this moment
uh
and then within the simplicity of the moment to
center yourself in the body breathing with whatever way it's easy for you or
right for you for awareness to be aligned attuned
to the body breathing
and no matter how complicated the mind gets with thoughts and ideas
keep returning to the simplicity of breathing breathing here
and see how simple you can become so simple perhaps that
desires fall away aversions fall away
expectations fall away
ideas of what is should be and shouldn't be fall away
simplicity where in which everything is allowed to be just the way it is
and we gaze upon it kindly
we breathe with it breathe through it without getting entangled
just here sitting breathing
knowing
being simple with how things are
if you've wondered often thought chances are that that's a more complicated world
concerns than the simplicity of just being here
being here alive being here breathing
as if that's enough for just these minutes
and that and then as we come to the end of the sitting
maybe using your imagination a little bit and imagine what it would be like
to maintain a simplicity of being
a kind of radical simplicity with a kind and clear gaze
of what's happening not needing to understand not needing to
fix not needing to explain not needing to defend but to really just be
with clearly with what's happening with someone else
what is it like to sit quietly with someone on a park bench maybe it's talking simply and chatting
but offering just a simplicity of being
contentment and ease with being alive as if for a few moments
at least just to be alive is enough alive and breathing
and perhaps with that simplicity of being maybe our good will can be simple as
well the simple warmth and goodness
friendliness that doesn't have to be actively
expressed and doesn't have to be explained
but a good will and a generosity of spirit
a friendliness and a love a care that maybe is part and parcel of that
simplicity
and maybe staying simple to end this sitting
with tapping into whatever wish you have for others to live well
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
and may it be that we contribute to that
and may it be that our practice contributes to that possibility
so a couple of announcements before i give the talk
the first is that um for those of you who are doing this 7
a.m sitting during the week for this week the sittings will start
meditation will start at 6 45 a.m in california time
so 15 minutes earlier than usual and partly to give more of you who come
a chance to experience sitting longer after all this time of sitting for half an hour
it's also a little bit easier to have um
maybe take in some of the teachings that we're doing on meditation would sit longer and really
settle into them and have more silence during the meditation and we'll do it for seven days including
saturday and sunday because i'm teaching a retreat and i'm integrating the
morning zoom teachings with the retreat as well and and
the topic of the retreat and also for the 7 a.m sittings are the seven factors
of awakening as a support for meditation practice and because i'm on retreat the closing
of the retreat next week is the time for this usual dharma talk on sunday teachings on
sunday so i've invited a wonderful dharma teacher that i taught with just a few weeks ago
taught a retreat from who's from south africa lives there and will teach from south africa
nolita and she was a really a wonderful wise and
kind caring teacher that brings a wonderful flavor
of to the dharma of of our own culture and um so i'm very
pleased that she'll be here and with our kim for our community and uh and uh just like uh
twarey who taught last week tori sala who had the idea that she wanted some
people on zoom to have a living audience to relate to
nalith i believe will do the same thing so probably on the chat or on the imc calendar at some point
there'll be a zoom link as well and so some of you might want to be there rather than on the
on the youtube um and a little bit supports to speak some
speakers because they get to see have some sense that there's people participating
so um
so for this sunday morning talk a little bit in the background or the
foundation of the talk is the idea that the dharma dharma practice points to simplicity
it's a very simple thing and it can be deceptively simple it can be
surprisingly simple what we're looking for we're looking for the freedom from
suffering the alleviation of suffering and and that's at the heart of what the
dharma the whole religiosity of the buddha is about and um and part of the reason why it's
useful to emphasize the simplicity is that people who uh many people will come to buddhism
with all kinds of expectations about what a religion is what they want
um that that is searching for something that's in a
sense outside of themselves and there's nothing inherently wrong with that and
it can be quite wonderful in itself to find a religious life or source that's outside of oneself
but the dharma of the buddha is in a sense found within ourselves and it's
kind of very simple way and and one way that uh
when characteristics of this or emphasis or this simplicity is the the practice of letting go
rather than acquiring more ideas more concepts building up
ourselves and our conceit there's a real emphasis on letting go
letting go letting go but letting go is uh people make it more complicated than it needs to be
and sometimes react to it negatively because on this means i have to let go of all my possessions or
let go of the people i love in my life the in the teachings of the buddha the
letting go is almost entirely or maybe entirely
having to do with letting go of particular mental states or mental activity
that's within ourselves not letting go of things of the world
so the primary letting go is letting go of our clinging letting go of the grasping or the
craving that we have the contractions that come along with some of the desires and aversions we have
and so um that's what we're letting go of and if
we turn around and really look at ourselves deeply we'll see we'll feel that the clingings
the cravings we have um are of way of self-harm the way that we're kind of hurting ourselves uh causing
pain and suffering to ourselves and in the buddhist analysis that's the suffering
that we have the most ability to do something about the suffering that we contribute contribute to through our clinging and
our grasping so that's what we're letting go now when we let go
um there are things that we abandon we impact clinging craving grasping
we abandon hatred aversion hostility and we abandon a certain confusion a
tendency towards confusion or delusion so there are things we let go of but
these again all internal things and there's not a search for something outside of ourselves
a search for god a search for some kind of cosmic kind of understanding or wisdom or
consciousness it's not a connection to something beyond ourselves
which is a wonderful thing that can happen our sense of interconnectedness to life and all that but that's not the heart
of the buddhist spirituality which is um maybe seems very simplistic reductionistic maybe not enough
in the fullness of life and um and that may be but still over and over
again the buddha pointed to this simplicity of letting go of greed hatred and delusion and
for the buddha that's the ultimate that's like that to do that thoroughly fully is this full message that he's giving
um for people who have other ideas of what they want their life to really be about
um then i think buddhism contributes in that it says or offers that whatever your
values are whatever way you want to live and be connected understand this life that we live in
even if you're like you believe in god or cosmic consciousness or you have your fundamental religious
belief is the interconnectedness of life all those ideas
what buddhism has to offer is please don't
don't use those ideas as a justification for greed hate and delusion
don't don't focus on those so much that you lose touch with this deep inner potential
to not have greed hatred delusion let that be the foundation and then you can do all kinds of other
things in a much richer more meaningful way but for the buddha it was really just
this this inner life that we're rectifying or freeing and then the rest of life comes
another way so there's something we abandon but the letting go is not just about what's
abandoned it's also about what is gained and this probably is not emphasized enough
in teachings of letting go letting go is kind of uh on the surface can seem like yes we
let go of something and then at the best where hands are open we're open-hearted or open-minded we're
kind of left without clinging to something but it's it's uh better than that letting go of
clinging grasping craving letting go of hatred and
and hostility aversion letting go of regrets and agitation sloth torpor
doubt letting go of all these things we gain something as a result
and it's kind of like um there's been a there's a dam that filled
with water and then the gate is one of the the gate uh is opened and the water begins to flow
out uh and flows out and fills the river below
and and that just flows and flows and flows and it's a wonderful thing to have the
water flowing and not bottled up by the dam so the same thing uh when we let go something begins to
flow something begins to move through us that maybe has been held back by the greed hate and delusion by the
clinging and grasping and there's the gain of what happens in that flow
when the when something has been released and let go that was covering over or resisting or
blocking something inside and so the
there's a number of things that open up when we let go
and have cultivated awareness and presence and and one of those things is the seven
factors of awakening that um when we have a deep letting go
it frees up a certain kind of energy frees up a certain kind of momentum in our life
that makes available to us much more mindfulness um a clear
this cleared distinguishing of phenomena clear seeing
which we call investigation sometimes in english effort
joy tranquility samadhi and equanimity
and these are not strange foreign ideas to human beings uh it takes maybe
it doesn't take that much an uh reflection maybe to see that they're they're accompanying us to some degree
maybe in small degrees here and there in our life in ways that we don't really appreciate
and so one of the ways the examples the buddha gave for this that and how these seven factors
awakening can arise is when um is listening to uh
the buddha at least giving a dharma talk a great teacher gives a talk and um it's uh it's very engaging and
compelling to really be present and listen closely and like what's being said is so important
so clear so profound that we're really there to find out what is this that's being said
and there's a fullness of attention that is
it's we're satisfying mindful but we're really the tension is really present to take in this experience and
maybe even with all our faculties not just cognitively with the mind but with our our hearts our body or all our senses
as as the thing the ordinary thinking discursive
conversational mind quiets down and we're just taking something in with
clarity there might still be some thinking involved but the thinking is very very simple and
clear that there there's more more clarity in the eyesight and the perception of
things and we see things much more clearly i remember i gave i went i went to uh i
had i've been to very engaging talk sometimes academic talks when i when i started taking botany
classes and i was really absorbed in the details of the botany class and would leave class and and and i'd come
we'll go out into the courtyard in this university where i went and i'd see everything so clearly
everything sparkled and was clear and bright and in a way that they hadn't been when i went in there's something about
cleaning the the filters of our eyes developing a clear seeing
that comes with really being present and not distracted by our thoughts
and then listening to a good talk there's there's some kind of aliveness and energy and alertness
it might even sit up a little bit straighter oh this is interesting what's going on here
and then there's also maybe some joy maybe you wouldn't call it joy at the time but
all the troubles fall away all the preoccupations of life all the way we're really right here
and it just feels so good and delightful to be with the experience
and also uh there may be listening to a dharma talk very reassuring a deep sense of
reassuring oh this makes sense this puts things into place this is the way forward
and something inside of us settles and gets peaceful and quiet and then there's a gathering together of
all the faculties we're really here in a concentrated way which means we're really present with all we have
focused on what's being said and what the meaning is and perhaps also
similar to tranquility it's so reassuring and so so clear what's being said that now i
understand there's an equanimity and a balance and now i understand that there's no value in grasping on
or pushing away or leaning forward or pulling back
there's value in just staying balanced and taking in the experience being present for the experience
without the usual reactivity with it and there's the equanimity
so with letting go uh the the and that kind of the gate of the
dam is opened it's the the water is the seven factors of awakening
and what's remarkable is that these are um can be seen almost as
qualities or aspects of awareness itself as we become more aware in an
unobstructed way it gets filled with these seven factors of awakening
the opposite of this according to the buddha is the five hindrances sensual desire
aversion lethargy and resistance agitation and regrets and doubt
and these have the opposite effect hindrances they hinder they obstruct
they cover over things and so um
it's like closing the gates of the dam and then the water builds up pressure behind the dam i block something and as we get
partly because with the hindrances the focus of the mind is to be preoccupied with something
and to be preoccupied in a contracted and narrow and tight way and so there's no room for the seven
factors of awakening to flow out into the awareness or be found in a clear form of awareness
so the buddha talked about letting go of the five hindrances
it isn't just letting go of them that's important but it's also how they create space or open the gate for
the seven factors of awakening to begin opening or peering or flowing into our presence into our
awareness and so we're gaining something as well
and uh and uh so the letting go of great hate and
delusion is not just about what we abandon
it's also what we gain in other teachings the buddha points to
the five the four divine abodes the four brahmaviharas
is what starts flowing when the uh gate has been pulled away from the
opened in the dam then there's so so there's mehta uh
karuna mudita and the pali words usually translated into english as
loving kindness compassion appreciative joy sympathetic joy and
equanimity and these are beautiful qualities of art
and uh they also are limited by our preoccupations there's no room
for love and care and compassion if we're caught up in things like desire caught
up in aversion doubt regrets and so to abandon those to
release those it isn't just a matter isn't that we have to then evoke this loving kindness
or compassion there's something about the heart that has space now to breathe breathing room
for the heart that tends to then give birth to
these beautiful qualities of heart there's space for them and if there's
space for them they flow and so part of practice is to abandon to
let go so that some of the best parts of our human life
can flow and have a chance to be present and so um
and so the simplicity of all this is that this is this core aspects of the buddha's
teachings is not exactly a religious teaching it's not exactly a um you know my
religion versus your religion it's actually teaching something which um just as uh
i'd like to think of it just practical psychology or practical uh spiritual practice that's available
to anybody regardless of what religion they are and there's a remarkable teachings from
the ancient discourse that points to this that i'd like to read
from the connected discourses of the buddha the book of threes and i think it's um
this course
71 i think
72 and so here a man comes to
ananda the buddhist buddhist one of the chief disciples and asks in this question who's dhamma
dhamma is well expounded and dhamma is can be a word that's
synonymous with religion and in the ancient world it means teachings or religious doctrine or
something like that so whose religious doctrine is well expounded the question one question on who in the
world are practicing the right way the good way who are those people who are prac really practicing the good way
and the true way and then question number three is who in the world are the fortunate
ones and um and so the buddha then go uh
goes on and says that those who teach the abandoning of
greed hatred and delusion um are the ones um
he says this what do you think is that dumb of those who teach the
abandoning of great hatred delusion well expanded or not or how do you take
it and the person who is talking to ananda says well the dhamma of those who teach
the abandoning of greed hate and illusion is well expounded and there are the religious teachings of those who teach
the abandoning of great hate and delusion that's well taught that's a good teaching
and and what do you think ananda continues are those practicing for the
abandoning of lust hatred great hatred and illusion practicing the the good way in the world or not how do
you take it those practicing for the abandoning of great hate and delusion are practicing the good way
and then are those who are practicing who are abandoning greed hate and delusion and really cut them out
really obliterated them to the end are they the fortunate ones and the man
says yes those are the fortunate ones so then there was that what he says next
is uh very nice the that's the householder the man who's asking questions for
of ananda says it is astounding it's amazing ananda
that there there is no that you have not extolled your own dhamma
nor any denigration of the dumb of others but just teaching the dhamma in its own
sphere so buddha ananda is not championing
the buddha's dharma or or dismissing the importance of other
people's dharma which is often what you get if someone says what's what's the best religious
teaching in the world some people might say oh mine is of course but rather than saying something
like that ananda is just offering this principle's idea about abandoning green hate and delusion
and then and then rather than making any claim about how wonderful it is he asks the um the person asking the
question is this well expounded is this the good way is this are these the fortunate people
those who practice it and the man admits that's that's the answer that i was looking for and so
um so this simplicity
of of this inner look and not looking
outside not looking for what's ultimate in kind of kind of religious way maybe not looking for metaphysical
claims of truth not looking for deep understandings of the nature of the
universe the world the cosmos the beginning of time the end
of time there's many answers that the buddhism doesn't answer
but rather to the heart of it is the simplicity of
looking within oneself and freeing oneself
of forces which limit us that block the flow letting those go
and then letting something beautiful flow that's there kind of like it's there waiting for us
though it's not really there it's not like a thing that exists independent of us
it's thing that exists with opening up with the freedom with abandoning with
awareness set free and
and so letting go both involves what is abandoned but also what
is gained and um and so we gain
and then and more often than not what the buddha talks about is
we abandon greed hatred and delusion and then we gain freedom in some places
he adds a fourth thing that's abandoned so there's four things
and this maybe is helpful the fourth one to keep in mind so that we abandon the great heightened
delusion and be sure to keep it really simple the fourth thing to be abandoned is conceit
create hatred and delusion and conceit and and then if we really let go of
conceit as well then having abandoned great hate and delusion won't give rise to conceit
look how special i am i'm i have the most wonderful teachings i have the most
wonderful practice i have the most wonderful attainment i'm the most fortunate one
if making making an eye out of it and building up the self is also abandoned and this is also a
delightful thing that uh opens the gates for what's
uh wonderful in us to flow out conceit is one of those things that closes the gate
blocks the flow in a sense so keeping it simple
appreciating the value of what we can let go of within that which blocks us and limits us and
appreciating what's gained as we let go and really feeling into that and
experiencing those gains and maybe in doing so becoming
recognizing the seven factors of awakening within us maybe recognizing them
in a very small initial way but slowly developing having them recognizing them more and
more and giving space for them and letting them really be a support for
this life of freedom a life that is free of clinging
so thank you very much and uh and may this week be one in which
you discover the value greater value in letting go in recognizing the seven factors
awakening in your life