so hello and welcome everyone to this rendition
of happy hour [Music] so so for today's practice
i wanted to invite us to explore an invitation that i have often given
on retreats to people as a way of practicing and i've heard other teachers in the
past have done this too so the invitation
is practice as if you are sick practice as if you are sick
as if you are ill as if you don't have a lot of energy
and you wonder okay why why would that be a wisdom
invitation why would that be wise at all so the idea
here the idea of course we'll be doing meta but we'll be practicing meta we'll be practicing
meta as if we are sick as if we don't have a lot of energy
and the wisdom here is that we often the way we approach practice the way we approach
practice is often can be often for many of us we bring the
same mind of wanting and doing and getting
and it needs to be the right way and they need to it needs to look pretty and it needs to
be this it needs to be that there is a lot of clinginess a lot of wanting a lot of energy
that we bring to to the both the self judgment judging
practice and the wanting like if it gets very tight and we can get um can
topple over our own shoestrings that we tie so tight so the idea of
practicing as if you're sick as if you're ill is you know consider when you're sick you
don't have a lot of energy you don't have a lot of energy the mind doesn't have
a lot of space for what is extra no space for fighting no space for
being you know cajoling for self-judgment for just all the tightness there's just no energy
for it there's only energy for what is essential
only energy for what is essential
so consider you know when when you were sick last
time or maybe you're not feeling well right now did you want to like call up far you
know flunk friends you hadn't talked to for um years or especially if you had an
argument with them to really work it out oh no just what what is essential what is essential is
care what is essential is care for this person for this being and maybe the people who
are around you just a simple care it gets life gets very simple
very simple when we're not feeling well the ambitions ambitions for more more more they go
away it becomes very simple in fact what is essential becomes
visible and i also wanted to bring this quote from uh from antoine saint-exuberee
in in the book the little prince which we can spend the whole
dharma talk and a whole other happy hour on it but the quote is it is
only with the heart that one can see rightly what is essential
is invisible to the eye what is essential is invisible to the eye so sometimes
when we don't have a lot of energy when we're actually sick ah
the simplicity of what is essential can become more visible to the eye to
the heart so that is the invitation for exploration today
and they'll walk us through it so for this practice you're welcome to be sitting or
you could be down to actually take a position of of not feeling well that sense of oh
i don't have a lot of energy and if you're worried you might fall
asleep lying down one thing you can do is you can have
your arm at a 90 degree angle either all the way up or at 90 degree angle at your elbow like
this if you can see it and if you fall asleep your arm will fall and hit you and will wake you up so
this is one trick you can use if you want to do this practice lying down which i do invite you actually
to try it out especially if you're judging mind things oh it's
practice you know sitting practice is where it's at no the buddha taught four different
postures sitting lying down standing and walking and they're all
just as good you can have ins and concentration and beauty and and a
lot of um dedicated practice deep practice can happen in any of those
four poses so don't let your mind privilege one over the other and if you
think okay it's only sitting no challenge yourself gently like a sick person kindly
challenge yourself to lie down and try see what what lights actually
might come up for you what insights but since you won't see me if i lie down
i'm going to sit up but rest assured i do most of my practice actually lying down
most of my deepest practice and insights have come lying down practice so
so without further ado let's get started let's get started so making yourself
comfortable whatever posture you like to take
ah landing landing in this body landing in this body
and what if this body in this moment uh taking a posture as if you are not feeling well
as if your energy was limited
letting go letting go of ambitions of more more and more in this moment
and as if you were not feeling well as if you were sick
let your body sink ah let your body sink into the cushion
all the tension tightness fighting with the circumstances
letting them sink letting them drain
away
and letting the breath be received by the
nourishing keeping this body alive
as if you were sick each breath
precious each breath not to be taken for granted
the entirety of this breath just this
breath embraced
gently gently received can remember you're practicing as if you
were sick you don't have too much energy for wanting or fighting the circumstances
wanting things to be different just receiving letting go
it's like this right now
explore for yourself the next few minutes
just receiving the breath in the body what does it feel for you what does it feel like for
you to practice as if you were sick as if you were ill
so
there can be a sense of contentedness when we are sick sense of contentment to just
be and breathe be breathed
no fighting no resisting letting go
just receiving the breath
do
practicing as if you're sick
not enough energy in the mind and the body to get entangled
in thoughts you can watch them come and go but not so much energy to get entangled
in them it's watching them come and go
this breath is received the breath comes and goes
and light touch and lightness
that awareness can have receiving phenomena
not getting entangled in phenomena just receiving phenomena
our functioning is reduced to what is essential what is essential
like a sieve only what is essential
is it tended to has participated in
a light touch
when the mind comes up with self-judgements ah not enough energy to get entangled and
follow that thread to beat ourselves up not enough energy for self
flagellation just let that thread go
come back with the sense of contentment the breath the body
with this light touch of awareness
just enough energy to be aware and receive phenomena
let there be a light touch of care
not forceful not tight
just a gentle care for this body for this being
as if you were sick wishing yourself well
not being hard on yourself this is not the time
to be hard on yourself
you wouldn't be hard on a child who was sick you would take care of the child
because having a fever is ill
that attitude that perspective is available to you [Music]
see what it feels like to put it on as if putting on glasses
that you look through
sense of gentle care as if you were sick person as if you were sick right now
this being for this body just [Music]
breathing
if there's enough energy in the supposedly sick body for the metaphases
bring them in and if they feel like a lot of work
don't or you can simplify them just may i be well may i be well
a sick version is an ill person's version
simplified low energy may i be well
to
practicing as if sick so many things can be let go
whatever is extra not needed over efforting can be let go of
simple simply receiving breath
sensations the sense of care and kindness
for this being this body
that is
myself
only what is essential
everything gets simplified when we're
sick
with not enough energy in our minds to go after
what's not essential see if you can feel the simplicity in
your body in your heart and mind
the mind goes after a thought or a story self-judgment ah
i'm sick i don't have energy for this coming back
to the simplicity of this moment
the
to
for the last two moments of this practice period
if there are any judgments arising for what this practice period was whether the mind was restless
or sleepy or filled with thoughts
again as if you're a sick person without the end to fight with yourself ah
letting go letting go of what's not essential
these self-criticisms not important not essential
don't need to be followed or believed letting them go practicing
like a sick person the mind staying with what is essential
may all beings everywhere
be well may all beings everywhere be free in their hearts and minds
thank you for your practice
so so this invitation
practices if you are sick it can quite radical for some
and for some you may not have connected with it and that's perfectly fine not every practice works for
everyone or at a given time maybe we'll work at another time when you try it
and for some people you might find this completely revolutionary the sense of ease a sense of letting go
practicing as if you were sick a couple of other things also to say before i invite and open
the floor for insides
is that at some point in your life you will be sick and this can also serve as a practice
period as a practice for that how do we relate when our mind doesn't have the energy
what is the attitude we will take is it one of wanting things to be different or do one to one that embraces
things as they are and really relishes this low energy state
of how it serves for us to just um engage with what is essential
on retreat sometimes when folks get a cold or they get sick and and they're upset
saying oh i came to practice this whole week and now i'm going to be in bed with a fever and
they're upset um i actually celebrate
that it is an opportunity we learn so much and they usually well they actually when after they turn
towards it and practice with it it becomes such an opportunity for insight becomes such an opportunity i've
had many people um including myself if i remember the very first retreat i was sick on the
first i was bummed years and years ago like oh i came here to practice and then i got this this invitation to actually
use it as an investigation as an opportunity to to see how the mind that doesn't have
a lot of energy how it relates it was so insightful so now using this as a
practice guidance so like to open it now for your insights you can type them in
chat either privately to be i won't say your name or publicly for everyone in which case
i'll read your name or you can raise your zoom hand and i would love to hear your
your insights what you discovered what was this like for you
compared to the usual way so please
what did you notice was it easier to let go of thoughts
habitual tendencies
was there more ease more spaciousness or maybe less what did you notice
arya says definitely more ease nice thanks for sharing that and lisa
please hi hi um i noticed
i was able to offer compassion to my young self
um who was sick during a time
and it was a challenging time
so that was helpful and also made me reflect on my attitude toward
being sick which i actually experienced with the meta retreat with you and i really struggled um
and until getting the instruction it's like a perfect time to practice meta and so that
combined with this i think it's just helpful to see my my own attitude towards myself when i'm
sick and um be able to be a bit warmer
and understanding thank you thank you lisa
lovely beautiful
thank you for sharing your insight
now i saw your hand for a split second did it get resolved i liked it
there you are yeah
hey nikki hey everyone uh what came up for me in this practice
was a question of when am i really well
i think in some ways there's always a reason that there's always reason that somehow
arises on why i can't practice sometimes and and in a way kind of connecting with
this idea of when we are sick kind of reinforces
i think something you've always said nikki which is that uh practice extends beyond sitting it's it extends beyond our
formal ideas of what sitting is so i just wanted to uh to share that with everyone
thank you now yeah i appreciate your reflection it i'd to if you would say a little more
so i can understand better when you said brought up the inquiry or the question
when am i ever well what do you mean by that say you say more so as
as you were guiding us through thinking about sickness for some reason i thought what does it mean to be well
yeah and again you know uh sometimes when i when
i haven't wanted to practice it's been because of one reason or the other and there was a retreat actually that i
was not well uh at and i remember thinking okay i'm not going to practice now because i'm not
well but you know you know if if the practice
is simply observing uh ourselves and meeting ourselves where we are yeah that in a way the idea of being
well and being sick is all just different kinds of practice yeah yeah yeah
yeah i see absolutely i see what you're saying yeah exactly and and with this um
[Music] given that they're all different ways different filters
and with this assuming but putting on what we assume being sick is like this
this low energy state it actually uh i found it to be so freeing so freeing
the times that i've crashed and i have been sick oh the mind just doesn't want to go after what's not essential there's a
sense of just cutting just letting go natural letting go that wow my mind knows how to do this you
don't already know how to do this it knows he knows how to do this
perfectly well i don't need to go into a monastery and become a monk and all that
it knows how to do this so taking on this perspective of sickness can really light up like oh this mind knows
how to let go how to not go after um what's not essential yeah and then
yes and just different ways of meeting yeah thank you now yeah beautiful tanner says
the invitation to come to practice from a place of meekness
almost was a relief oh beautiful thank you for putting it that way
and another reflection sent just to me so i won't read the name i notice myself hold my breath in more a tendency
i am aware of in general and perhaps has resurfaced as a result of not having meditated as much as i have in
the past i have a chronic condition which has caused some pain and while practicing i realized even more my
body has been asking me to take care of myself oh beautiful thank you for sharing that beautiful
insight that realization and frederica says i really recognized
how gentle i am with myself when i am sick beautiful and how i accept support from myself and others
and i really felt how the past year when the world was sick i was gentle with myself and supportive
of myself and it was healthy and i want to hold on to that gentleness as i'm emerging back
into society beautiful thank you frederica that's beautiful insight yeah just gentleness
with ourselves with the whole world yeah lovely thank you all for your reflections and
your insights so rich this community is so rich so
like to invite us to turn to practicing in
small groups in community together now and let's start with um just 15 seconds
of silent meta for these beings who might appear healthy but
are either have aches and pains or some sickness or have been or will be so
starting with this sense of meta compassion for each other
for ourselves and then sharing however much or little you like to share
with each other so i'm about to open the rooms and here we go
welcome back everyone and we have about a minute or two for
maybe a final reflection we'd love to hear from any of you who haven't spoken yet
person who's okay i can see you person who's says iphone i see your hand there you go
hi how are you hi so i think i am new to practice
this is probably the fourth day of the i never practice in this matter
to be honest but it was it was at the end of my work and it just
so vaccinated so much because i was already feeling very tired
what i said and i just feel like i just let it go myself and i feel like
so relaxed i never felt like such a relaxation like that
and i felt more grounded so much and i was able to completely concentrate
it's so funny isn't it i didn't even try anything at all but i was so
concentrated about how i feel so um just wanted to acknowledge that
thank you so much for giving us this opportunity experiencing such a different stage of
meditations appreciate you yeah thank you so much thanks for sharing your reflections and as you were speaking
i'm seeing other people nodding their heads saying yep yeah agreeing with you
it was useful more more concentrated and yes yes this is it you said it so
beautifully that we often think of meditation as okay now i'm gonna meditate no i'm gonna meditate where is really
it's more about letting go it's more about ah just relaxing the
body as if you were in a different mind a different way of being reveals itself
that that is the way to meditate not what we think it is it's another economy it is
not another accomplishment it's not another badge to add another thing to attain it's more
of letting go relaxing and just as you said the mind concentrates
lands the body lands there's nowhere to get
so beautiful thank you so much for sharing your wisdom of course
thank you thank you so dear all thank you so much for your
practice together um we don't do this practice just for ourselves
but for all the beings whose lives we touch may all beings be happy may all beings
be free including ourselves
thank you