so welcome
and a warm hello to all of you
and sometimes when seeing all the locations
where people are sending in their greetings on the chat
i have a kind of very kind of vague imagination of having a globe
in front of me and having lines drawn between all the places that are named and
take into account all the places that are not named and it'll be quite a net quite a
a interconnected net of community of people with similar
interests sitting here to meditate and doing a practice which i believe brings
out the best in people and so it's a wonderful act of
imagination and and that is the topic for this week
the ways in which imagination can support meditation rather than detract from it in a certain
kind of way if we don't use our imagination then we get used by it but
and but it's not just our own imagination we get used by but um there's a lot of people who
are trying to hijack our imagination or plant images and ideas in our mind
advertisers politicians you know all people who are providing us
with imagination imaginary scenarios that sometimes are done very cleverly to really kind of penetrate
deep inside of us and then they remain and and were used by them or influenced
by them and it's also possible to
use our imagination creatively or and use it for the purpose of meditation
and it takes wisdom to do that takes skill to do it in a way that's actually supports the mind to wake up to be
present to become stable and and then at different levels of
stability of stillness different forms of imagination might come into play
so that if you hear different instructions for imagination some of them might not work for you
because either because you don't have a reference point for them or because
they belong to different degree of stability either than you have
maybe less or more something but the buddha certainly
was his teachings are filled with what could be called images of the imagination images of
similes ideas and a basic one for meditation
is um the idea of sitting with the sitting as stable as
the earth or sitting as firm as a pillar
that it's planted deep in the ground so it's not going to wobble at all or being as calm as a surface of a still
lake and there's it goes on and on these kinds of images that buddha uses
which are tapping into the imagination and i'll say this later but part of the
purpose of this tapping into the imagination is because the imagination itself is
tapped into so many different aspects of our inner life the to our emotional life for
physical life kinesthetic life to our motivational life to um
to our thoughts and memories and things and so imagination somehow has a
capacity to contribute to the unification the integration that is samadhi
as we're getting more present and more collected in meditation the process of meditation
is a process of collectedness or unification or some people like to use the language
of becoming whole and imagination can be in the service of that because of what it evokes within us
it's certainly not true for everyone and everyone if people have different ranges of
relationship with imagination but for this week we're looking at the
building on the buddha's use of imagination in order to cultivate stability
but also presence but also gladness to have gladness or a certain degree of
joy in meditation so to take an
upright meditation posture and
to adjust your posture so it begins to feel stable
one of the advantages of sitting cross-legged is the stability of the legs and the buttocks on the
on your cushion a broad wide foundation
anything that supports you the weight of your body can provide a foundation of stability
and to imagine this body that you're sitting in is here like
a mountain
stable strong
unfazed by the wind that flows by or the clouds that wash over
imagining that the mind is like a clear quiet lake calm wind not blowing
water still and the mind is broad and wide
like the wide broad lake
and imagining the moon the heart is like a full moon
fully exposed fully open fully here
the heart shines its light peacefully on all things
and then the buddha uses an image for tuning into the breathing that one
uh tunes into breathing like a woodworker does on a
on a with a chisel on a lathe carving a piece of wood or maybe we
would say a potter turning clay on a wheel
and to make this contact with something which is moving around in
a circle the cycles of in-breath and out-breath
and this image of a someone working a lathe or working
clay on a wheel is partly an image of making contact and
keeping the contact there
so to take a gently with his contact with the body breathing
taking a few long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale maybe like a dam which has opened its doors so water
can flow out to relax your body
so there can be a flow of vitality flow of ease calmness from the places where you relax
relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the arms and the elbows hands
relaxing the chest the belly
and breathing easily be naturally
as if the piece of clay now has become smooth and round
bowl on the wheel and it just feels light and smooth and
easy to allow the turning of breathing in and
breathing out
your whole body is the bowl awareness is feeling
as you breathe breathing in and breathing out
that kind of intimacy with a body breathing
and as you're sitting here bring to mind
gently quietly whatever sense of goodness or
gladness that comes from the simplicity of being here
meditating where you're somehow what's absent
is the busyness of the day
what's absence is the challenges of the day
the crowds of people
driving in traffic
and if you can stay quietly focused on the breathing
and not giving in to thoughts of desire thoughts of ill will
thoughts of anxiety and regrets thoughts of doubt
this begins to feel like similar to being free of debt
or free of an illness
free of oppression
free of being lost in thought
and these ideas of this freedom from these things for the buddha it is meant to be a
source of gladness to take a few moments to appreciate
what is not here right now that feels good to have put aside
and which gives you an intimacy and a peacefulness even if it's mildly so
with here and now and being present
feeling the goodness of this maybe being glad to have these moments to be free of
these things
perhaps making a small half smile
that maybe supports a gladness or a contentment
that's willing to be just here in whatever goodness whatever
pleasure or contentment that is available
as you turn the wheel of breathing in and breathing
out
in a sense smoothing out the bowl of your body
the bowl of clay on the wheel
with the image of a mountain feeling whatever stability is here in
your body resting in that stability as if you're a
mountain
as if your mind is a broad peaceful lake
feel whatever ways the mind might be that way
broad and still even if there are some waves on it
and then whatever way the heart feels like a full moon
exposed open floating in the air in the sky in space
feel that luminosity and freedom of the heart
and they're breathing like a gentle breeze
that blows here and there through the body through the mind through the heart
connecting you to stability and stillness
and freedom of the heart
and staying centered here in this mountain-like body
still mind and open heart
open the awareness up out into the world
as if the stability spreads out from the place you're sitting out across the
surface of the lands
as if a peaceful stillness spreads from your mind out across the
air and across the seas
and as if the freedom and luminosity of the full moon heart
shines all over the globe
and you for a few moments undisturbed by the
suffering of the world but in this undisturbed way
perhaps you can tap into a heartfelt wish of compassion care
wish for the welfare of all beings
may all beings be happy
may all beings be free of suffering
may all beings be safe from all forms of harm
physical mental emotional
may all beings be peaceful
sharing as we share our peacefulness with them
and may all beings be free
as we do not limit them box them in
with our ideas and desires expectations
may the benefit of this meditation together spread out into the world for the
welfare and benefit of all beings
and they do so through our deeds of body speech and mind
may today be a day for spreading for caring for the welfare
of others
[Music]
so there has a has been a strong tendency in the west i think to present the buddha's
teachings in a fairly rational way and to emphasize the the
empirical nature of it and it's really about seeing things as they are
in direct way and and in doing so sometimes we left behind
or go unnoticed the tremendous degree in which the buddha and the buddhist early buddhist tradition
is using its using imagination using creativity of images and ideas
and imagination uh to support the teachings but not just
the teachings but to provide us with a
a different reference point for both the teachings and the practice than simply ideas irrational ideas
logical ideas that the buddha uses lots of similes
lots of poetry lots of images lots of little stories all of which touch into
other dimensions of our inner life than our rational cognitive understanding and um
it touches into our emotional life our kinesthetic life
our motivational life a lot that that part of it can be
inspired can be gladdened um it ties into our memory and our
associations and um so all these capacity and thinking as well
all these different faculties that we have get touched get awakened get somehow
brought into into the field of our dharma relationship with dharma practice
and this contributes the sense of unification that is samadhi cultivating samadhi
developing samadhi is really an important part in fact the buddha said that to see
things as they are cultivate samadhi and samadhi is unification
and unification is the is the bringing together of all our faculties together in a kind of whole working
dynamic working of the whole to really be in harmony that everything's in harmony
so using the imagination is a means to evoke that and elicit that
in support of the meditation practice or support of this freedom
and it is um so it has to be done of course carefully
it can be overdone and certainly people use their imagination for all kinds of things which are not
healthy or appropriate for dharma practice to spend a lot of time in fantasy and
and having a feeling of uh you know the delusions of grandeur of delusions of
great pleasure or you know just kind of you know kind of getting lost in the pleasure of fantasies and imagination or
getting lost in the fantasies of conflict and war and that we have towards with other
people all kinds of things uh you know goes you know really takes us away from this practice
and uh but the imagination that connects us to it we have to get a feel for it does it really connect does it really
help us be more settled more present for experience and it's using the imagination
to eventually go beyond the imagination um it's kind of a stepping stone and uh
and the kind of images that the buddha seems to use tend not to be stories or there's not
ongoing sagas that we're imagining they tend to be very simple like that of
a mountain or the earth or a lake um
the um you know so it's not like a story of things it's just kind of an image and sometimes it's the dynamic
image like the image of an underwater fountain from under in a lake the underwater spring
that's spreading spreading goodness throughout the body you know it's not a story it's just kind
of a dynamic image of what's happening another image that i love i'll do this
tomorrow some of these but so this integration process and as i
said before if we don't use our imagination it's all
too easy that our imagination gets used by others we internalize the images and imagination
that advertisements commercials politicians other people
make up and then we internalize them the way sometimes they're not beneficial for us actually it can be quite detrimental
imagining all kinds of terrible things that are happening in the world that
that uh that just kind of spiral us down and in a way that's not helpful
so it's not fantasy it's not uh to avoid or deny what's going on
run away from life as it actually is that we use imagination and buddhism but
it's really but it's with care about knowing how we do it so it really helps us supports us to be present
if it doesn't help us to be present there's no need to use it and it isn't like you're better buddhist
if you use your imagination but it is available to us support us to get kind of more focused
and so the one of the ways that the buddha
talks about developing gladness and meditation and gladness it leads to joy joy that
leads to tranquility tranquility leads to happiness happiness that leads to samadhi
is uh to appreciate what's absent as we sit and meditate
and in the the main the most common one thing that the buddha emphasizes is the absence of the
hindrances so when people are meditators they are often contending with
their hindrances the hindrance of desire aversion lethargy and resistance
agitation and regrets remorse and doubt these can be very strong very
compelling uh hooks in the mind to be caught up in thinking about these and involved in these
and we can get lost in desire fantasies and aversion fantasies and and you know caught up in resistance and
and our regrets and anxieties they really kind of get lost in these universes that these can create for us
and um and so as we settle down in meditation as we
kind of start getting more focused more relaxed more settled and start letting go of the force of preoccupation the
debate of all these kinds of thoughts that take us away from the present moment
and we're able to sit more a little bit more and more here here in the present moment there comes a
time when the hindrances have abated that they're not so strong anymore
and it becomes relatively easy to stay here and the image i used the other day of a
bowl large bowl i mean it's you know huge maybe a five foot diameter ball
that they have in some kind of children's museums and you put a marble
into that you drop a marble down the edge and that marble will move this way in that way and
until it momentum slows down and then eventually it falls through a hole at the bottom of the bowl or rests at the bottom of the bowl
but if you put a lean into the bowl and keep pushing the marble it keeps going and going going so to be caught in the hindrances is to
keep the marble spinning but to to finally settle down
and let the marbles all settle at the bottom of the bowl and rest you can feel in meditation so good the
mind just hear so at this at this point the buddha talks about
having gladness that one is no longer caught no longer hijacked by the mind no longer as
enslaved by the mind because the mind just pulls us away and has a mind of its own and we just pulled
along and we kind of lose a kind of freedom in the process and so to feel the gladness be glad
about this and here is where the buddha uses the uh teaches this as an act of imagination
an act of in a particular word that he uses that's translating as imagination here can be
a visualization and it has the word seeing anupasana in it
and it's some anupasana with seeing but it's not seeing through the physical eye but rather
through the mental eye of imagination and so he gives five similes for being
free of um of um the hindrances to be really here the
other absence and they are a person in debt who has become free of debt
a person who's terribly sick who has who is no longer sick a person who is in
prison and bondage in prison so even not just
in prison but in bondage you know tied down
who has become freed from prison a person who is enslaved who has become
freed of slavery and a person who has wandered in the desert for a long time
dangerous desert who has come out to the other side and is no longer lost free of wandering
in the desert and so buddha gives these five similes for being free of the hindrances
and it as the reason for these similes is to give a um a reference point
for something would be people would celebrate just be so happy you'd be so relieving so uh joyful
to be out of prison to be out of sickness and all these things unless we don't remember that we're
free of those things if we just like we're free of prison we just go on to the next preoccupation and concern and but to
take time not just to keep going back to the breath and back to the breath when we're present
but take time to really appreciate the goodness or the well-being or the
the delight that being free of the hindrances are being focused and present
so that the goodness of that becomes spreads through the body or opens up more widely or
brings a kind of a gladness that is part of this integration process this
unification process that we're beginning to not just keep doing the laser focus of the mind
if we ever did it that way and just kind of like staying focused focused focused but there's a kind of a
mellowing and opening and settling experience of just softening here
that the gladness can give birth to and as we allow this gladness to
this joy space for it we don't pump it up strongly we don't it's just kind of just natural hopefully
a natural kind of joy or gladness that is available when we take time to feel the goodness of
this what's happening in meditation then that is what uh allows the growth
then of joy and happiness um that is on the way to a strong samadhi
so um so another talk on the use of imagination
and and it takes some wisdom to know what kind of imagination when what to
use maybe when we first sit down what to use when the hindrances have abated but
and not to make a big project of it but to note this available to us and it's like a little aid a little
quiet support that it is meant to support us to to be inspired
to stay in the present moment and to feel the goodness the well-being that comes when we really settle down in
meditation uh we're allowed to be present here and now we're allowed to enjoy it
and uh and this is the stepping stone for going deeper and in some ways in a more powerful way
into this 16 steps of anapanasati which we'll be coming to and but for now
i'm just trying trying to introduce you to this territory of imagination which uh
can come into play when we start feeling settled in meditation that supports the further settling and
uh and absorption in the very practice we're doing
so thank you and i look forward to [Music]
tomorrow