so hello and welcome everyone to happier
so for today's practice um the theme i'd like to invite us to
explore is the theme of
of [Music] mind habits or habits of the mind
our habits of the mind that we create habits of the mind that become habits of
body action etc and um there is a and and how it relates
to meta because in the practice of meta we try to cultivate we try to cultivate
a way of thinking being considering um
[Music] ourselves and others
uh meeting our friends and meeting our thoughts meeting ourselves meeting others with friendliness with good will
with the sense of good will as a way of cultivation
so this quote i want to share with you as inspiration
[Music] is a quote from mahatma gandhi and he says
keep your thoughts positive because you your thought becomes your word
keep your words positive because your words become your behavior
your behavior becomes your habits your habits become your values
and your values become your destiny it's quite profound
uh let me bring it into the space one more time
your thoughts become your words your words become your behavior
your behavior becomes your habits and your habits becomes your values
and your values become your destiny quite powerful it all starts our destiny
or our life this designing our life really starts
with our thoughts starts with how we incline our mind as the buddha
says inclining our minds do we incline it towards loving kindness
do we incline it do we just let it go wild in ill will
towards ourselves judgmental thoughts bad bad bad terrible terrible do we let
it run wild do we let it run wild or with ill will towards others
or do we gently say okay sweetie all right a little time to
for some cultivation for some cultivation and again not to self-flagellate if you notice your
thoughts are running wild that would not be helpful that would be pouring more
gasoline on the fire of ill will because if you you see that right if you have ill will
towards yourself or having ill-will towards yourself or having a world towards yourself or ill-will towards others it's not exactly
stopping the cycle this so it's only through kindness kindness
towards yourself if you notice if the mind is it's going on a tirade against
yourself or against others oh sweetheart sweetheart compassion kindness kindness
a stick is not the solution a carrot might be
so [Music] and one last thing i want to say and bring into the space
is this idea this idea of of our thoughts and
leading to action and our behavior and our destiny etc
really isn't so some so different from the idea of karma in the way that
every thought every action every way you know not to think of karma as this
complicated thing from some past life that we don't even know what we did not in that way
that's not very helpful but in the way of every action every thought really sets into motion
a habit pattern a way of being which then sets into motion
further thoughts further actions further habit patterns so
so in the equanimity phrase is actually
where it is said that we are heir we're owners to our actions
and heirs to our actions owners and heirs i want to unpack that a
little bit actually so it is said that comma is actually the womb from which
from which we spring which is so poetic it's pali it's kama yoni kamayoni so kama our
karma our actions is the womb from which we spring
so powerful and also we are inalienable owners of
our deeds kamasaka for those who like the pali comma
saka so we're the owners we're the owners it's both the womb we spray out
from and we are the owners
and it's also our heritage it remains with us our actions remain with us forever
remain with us we inevitably return to our heritage
and our good deeds are our refuge our refuge that we can take refuge and can be laid the sense of
if there's fear uncertainty we can take refuge in our kama patissarana
so our karma our actions as as refuge so this is such a beautiful
teaching and the last one is our karma our deeds as our friends as our friends
when our minds are serene um when we have cultivated
good thoughts and actions are with a sense of equanimity sense of
peace we have comma bondu b-a-n-d-h-u
comma our our deeds serve as our friends so
i think this is such a beautiful teaching inspiring teaching
it's actually such an empowerment it's a teaching of empowerment
that we ah we're the owners we're the heirs where
it's so so much that we put into place ourselves so
with that let us cultivate some wholesome thoughts leading to some
wholesome actions and and wholesome karma
it's not so complicated so let us practice loving kindness cultivating goodness
together with that as motivation so like to invite you to settle
settle in your body noticing what your body needs in this
moment
letting go of all the thoughts all the words all that has come before
just arriving landing in this moment
in this body this body
this breath the awareness of the body
breath as a refuge in this moment
each breath received to tell the soil
to settle inviting the mind
to land
gently lovingly inclining our thoughts our mind
our heart
to settle here just here
just this in-breath just this out breathe
can we open up can we open up to meet this moment's experience
with kindness whatever is arising in this fear of awareness
whether it's sadness judgment
anger and will tired being fatigued whatever it is
distractedness
can we open open with kindness with gentleness
to this human condition this moment's experience
with gentleness
with kindness and if needed with compassion if there
is suffering if there's pain oh dear oh darling
it's okay it's okay see what is needed
to meet experience with kindness
as if you're sitting [Music] ah sitting in kindness
breathing kindness all around all through
just a field of kindness meeting experience
and if there are no thoughts arising it's just the breath it's just the body this moment
mind is at peace then knowing the breath knowing the
sensations with kind awareness imbuing your knowing your awareness with
kindness with gentleness
with good will warm-heartedness
with love whatever nuance is appropriate for you in this
moment
good
with each breath each moment of knowing inclining our hearts
our minds towards kindness planting seeds of kindness
in meeting the experience in this moment whatever is arising breath body thoughts
pain unpleasant pleasant
openhearted knowing kind knowing
this
kindness turned inward internally externally
and if it is supportive to have the phrases of metta
bring them in may i be safe may i be safe from inner and outer harm
may i be happy and joyful
may i be healthy and strong
may i meet this moment with ease with friendliness
my
safe happy
healthy ease
internally externally
inclining inclining every moment of awareness towards kindness good will
friendliness to ourselves experience
the world
inclining our minds to our true nature our true
nature of love and compassion moment by moment
this
safe happy
healthy ease
predicting it to yourself another being in your life
or someone who is neutral you don't really know them very well
you get to choose what is most supportive right now in your practice
this
trusting trusting every moment of friendliness
is planting seeds inclining your thoughts your actions
your behavior your destiny
this
each moment of inclining the mind towards good will
impacting the way we show up in the world
may all beings be safe happy
healthy and have ease
this
if you notice your mind is distracted or in the thought be kind
be kind at the moment you notice thinking thinking
oh dear mind it's okay it's your nature
to think let's practice midterm this moment
planting seeds of wholesomeness
notice the sense of empowerment wholesome empowerment
in intentionally inclining every mind moment
remind heart moment towards kindness good will
friendliness so empowering
we have choice how we cultivate our minds our hearts
our actions
for the last moment of this practice period
can we cultivate appreciation
as we consider our practice however it was whether there were distractions sleepiness
however it was we showed up we did our best can we cultivate
appreciation for our wholesome action
of aligning our actions with our values
thank you me recognizing the goodness
and sharing this goodness this merit with all beings generously
made the impact of my cultivation this goodness
be a cause and condition for freedom for peace for myself and all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so we have a few minutes for reflections for comments
and you're welcome to type them in chat if they're typed to everyone i will read your name if they're just typed in me
i won't read your name and only read the reflection you're also welcome to raise your zoom hand
what you noticed what were some insights that came up
questions comments complaints it's all welcome
and one thing i'll share as i'm waiting for your reflections to come in is with the uh
quote from gandhi that i read at the beginning i think it is quite powerful connecting that with
karma and the part i think the full quote is keep your
thoughts positive because your words become your behavior become your
your behavior becomes your habit you have it becomes your values and your values become your destiny
so that link that seems like the link one leads to another that's a beautiful
arc to keep in mind and yet to keeping the thoughts positive that
that's the part i'm not emphasizing at all because that almost sounds like
happy happy just be positive no matter what and psycho psychological research actually shows that
false positivity is detrimental to our state of mind and our state of
health um so i want to make a distinction and if that's not clear you're welcome to raise
your hand and ask me to expand more but i hope it is clear
and i don't and i don't think of of this practice of meta as kind of false
positivity that's not the idea here now says orienting towards kindness is
like constantly steering a ship on a wavy sea thank you for your guidance thank you now thank you for that
and uh what's actually what's beautiful uh and very
cogent the observation about the constantly staring a ship because um
it turns out that you if you're trying to get from eight to b even if the c's are calm you always
have to to course adjust you always have to course adjust it's not like you set the
compass and off you go um and um
so we always have to course adjust it's not like we set our intention and values yep i'm going to be kind to myself and
everyone else from now on and done doesn't work that way it's like steering the ship
always always every moment every moment gently gently course adjusting thank you
for that enough other reflections what did you notice
what came up for you what was challenging
yeah yeah
and also they'd be connect connecting this to karma as i gave a little dharmat
at the beginning regarding these different aspects of karma karma being the womb
we being the air of our own karma the friend the refuge all of that
and karma isn't isn't said but in our actions
and and in buddhism actions thoughts are considered actions of the
mind which is pretty cool i think so we have actions of mind actions of speech
actions of the body so we have three different types of action and all of these produce karma so the way we think
we set our our way of being
he said our course in the world so
jerry says i noticed how critical my mind is having not noticed it before i started
today great great to notice it yeah yeah
nice thank you for sharing that
i'll give one more pause for reflections
sarah says where do emotions fit in with what you are saying oh yes
so so with the um
with the practice today with cultivating kindness or
cultivating kindness also towards our emotions
because emotions are energy in motion the reason why they're showing up given
all the causes and conditions so we are kind with emotions
being with them and not pushing them away even if they're challenging or difficult
emotions like for example anger or sadness but meeting them with kindness
meeting them with kindness um and it doesn't mean that we act out of
them because acting out of them or feeding them so continuing to mindlessly
feed the sadness mindlessly feeding the anger is
is the thought you know in that way your the emotions are setting our karma our way of being in the world
as someone who's always angry always sad but meeting it with kindness meeting with kindness it
provides awareness so kind awareness provides this
container for them to be met for them to be
to move through to be processed whatever needs to happen in the body
i hope that answers your questions there next reflection i'm going through a
fertility process and i felt very grateful for my body instead of upset
that it doesn't behave the way i wanted it to i felt grateful for all my body has
carried me through in this life oh that is such a beautiful beautiful reflection thank you for sharing that so beautiful
so to be grateful for the body instead of being upset that it doesn't behave
yeah oh beautiful thank you for sharing that so inspiring and uplifting
yeah and sarah says yes that you're welcome sarah so so dear ones
let's turn let's turn with kindness no not with fear not with ego but with
kindness show up with kindness for each other in small groups
so and as always we start with
15 seconds of silent meta for ourselves for each other
and then share as little or as much as you wish about your practice so
i've created the rooms now and [Music]
they are now open take care of yourselves take care of each other
okay everyone welcome back the rooms are closed so we have a couple of minutes a few
minutes for reflections comments and uh yeah especially if you haven't shared or
spoken for a while would love to hear from you you can raise your zoom hand i wanted to share this version of the
gandhi quote which doesn't mention the positive thoughts because that's not helpful so
you're so this one is briefer you see it in chat your beliefs
become your thoughts your thoughts become your words your words become your actions your
actions become your habits your habits become your values your values become your destiny so
so reflections thoughts [Music] wisdom of the sangha
please
i'd love to hear some voices what did she discover
especially in groups
and please know that when you offer your reflections your insights it's really
supportive of everyone's practice jerry says warmth
oh eileen says i don't seem to greet emotions with menta i'll have to try it
great yay please try it please try it
yeah please fred
i just found a surprising number of people who i wished well
and i didn't need to know some of them deeply
some of them i know very deeply but it's
the wishing well of the people i pass through in life
that's a great blessing itself just the feeling of that for
friends and strangers and loved ones
thank you i couldn't have said it better thank you fred that that
act of the just wishing them well is a blessing in and of itself
what a blessing what a gift thank you for sharing that what a beautiful
reflection and let's end on that note what a beautiful note to take with just
the blessing just the blessing of being able to and and wishing others
well either near dear or or not
and marianne this needs to be quick because we're at time
really quick what came up for me was trust in this in this sangha
felt great beautiful that was the word trust and patience
beautiful thank you trust and patience yay what
beautiful reflections so dear sangha dear dear
sangha thank you thank you for your practice thank you for showing up
for yourselves for each other for all beings whose lives you touch directly and indirectly
may all beings be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves [Music]
thank you all a blessing to be a part of the sangha thank you