so hello and welcome everyone to this
rendition of happy hour practicing together so
so this week we have dedicated happy hour to the practice of appreciation
um gratitude giving thanks appreciating such a
beautiful lovely practice and as i shared with you on wednesday of having practiced it for me
with with you and also throughout the week with the theme of thanksgiving giving thanks
this this appreciation has been coming up not just on the question not just in
the formal practice for me but also in the informal moments which has been
lovely this is really and i hope that has been the case for you and in case in fact you know what let's do this a
little untraditionally if anybody would like to raise their hand and and share you know the moments they
have realized they've noticed in this past week appreciation gratitude coming up in
informal moments and the significance of that let's if you feel like let's take maybe one or two
reflections if not we'll move on yes bill please
um we before we were talking about you know thinking of
what if we didn't have an advantage and what that would feel like and i didn't it consciously planned to do that but in
an awful moment for some reason i started to think of grade school and of a girl i knew who was mentally
and it just struck me how different my life would be if i didn't have mental capacities that
i have now and so i felt grateful for that
and all kind of sad for her thinking of her so um yeah
yeah thanks for bringing this in this this spontaneous bringing up of of
gratitude and appreciation for a gift that you've had which is your mental capacity which you've taken in many ways
for granted recalling someone who didn't have this gift and of course with compassion for
them ouch and how challenging many ways life can be and of course
not to also undermine the strength and the the grace that
that many of us with challenges all of us have different kinds of challenges
and and mental challenges including not to completely undermine that for people who have that
us included any challenge we have and and holding that with compassion and
and turning to gratitude for for what is here so thank you thanks for bringing that in bill yeah
and the other reflections that spontaneously came up for you
i realize i've turned off the chat already so if somebody wanted to type in chat they could okay i don't see in the
other hand so so um oh yes one more hand jerry please
so uh spare me if i've said this before uh
but i read an article this week and it really helped me think about
rather than think about how much i have to do every day i have to do this i have to do that
it transformed it by saying i get to get up and help people each day i get to go for
a run i get to uh see the snowfall as it's did today in
toronto uh so that's a framing it that way
helped me recognize gratitude in so many different ways enough for me
nice i get to i get to yeah wow what a gr
amazing wise shift in perspective instead of i have to i have to i get to
what a great invitation yeah like all of us to to explore that yeah let's bring that let's bring that
into the practice thank you jerry for for planting that seed bringing that in thank you
claire this will be our last reflection before we get into it so please claire
sorry having a little muting problem for okay
got all sorts of sound problems but anyway um i've just been wanting to share since
we've been on this topic for a while that one thing i started doing about
six or seven years ago now i have two friends who are interested in the
issue of gratitude also so we circulate an email every day
of three things from the day before that we're grateful for and it goes among the three of us so it
sort of allows us to stay in touch also in switzerland for example so i wouldn't
pick up the phone and call her all the time but i know exactly what she's doing and what the good things are that are
happening for her and it's been a wonderful it really changed a lot of my ways when i first started i
thought i was grateful but i realized after day two i couldn't think of anything
i really had to focus on the good things that were happening in my life i didn't do that normally i
always saw what was wrong that was right so i just wanted to share that with
others because it's been so helpful to me so thank you claire thanks so much for
bringing that in and uh i also appreciate you um really giving the
nuance of how you know after a while it feels like okay i'm out of things okay
and now i need to pay attention so actually the mind really instead of saying well this is a stupid boring
practice i'm done like oh wow and then your curiosity actually your interest
you stayed with it was which is like any other practice we after we scratch the
surface then it gets juicy it gets really juicy
and that's what i'm hearing you you say and how transformative it has been to actually turn to the good
lovely so you know what let's let's actually bring that in too that seed into our small brew practice
later uh today when we get into groups maybe there would be
groups of three or two or whatever forming from this and and this to share the gratitude practice
that would be fun thanks claire thanks for being here and i've done that before by the way
with someone it's it's it's yeah it's such a great practice oh my goodness yeah so
thank you for that well i think we are warmed up now for practicing appreciation and maybe i
won't say more about it it's it's i think the topic is very well framed but maybe i'll
just say one more thing and that is um
one thing that can also happen with this practice which is uh entering into
another dimension of gratitude um
and also generosity and as we talked on wednesday generosity and gratitude
really are a pair they go together um
and and these two generosity and gratitude
what if we entered into a dimension of holding whatever gifts we have given we have
been given whatever challenges we have been given
oh what is she talking about what every gifts whatever challenges we've been given
that we hold them with a stance with an open spacious
stance of generosity generosity is an open hand
that doesn't hold tightly it's with an open hand that receives and
releases receives and releases gifts are received
they're released challenges are received they're released this hand open hand of generosity
with the sense of gratitude ah can we be grateful also or or appreciate
maybe the word appreciation is more appropriate can we be can we appreciate
also what is challenging what pushes us what
what stretches us what stretches us can we hold it with appreciation
with an open hand that receives and releases
doesn't hold on so with those
reflections seeds from the sangha and reflections
shared let's begin let's begin our former practice so
so let's land let's land in our bodies let's land in
our seat as always arriving
arriving
arriving in this body
with this breath
lighting inviting all the muscles to soften to relax to let go
[Music] our hands arms shoulders
neck our jaw our face our forehead
the chest the back upper back lower back
ah the abdomen from the inside releasing
releasing into our sit bones our bottom [Music]
releasing into the chair to the cushion
our legs upper legs and lower legs
feet releasing
the whole body releasing
and receiving [Music]
the lower abdomen receiving the breath
joyfully appreciatively [Music]
we get to do this we get to sit
what a gift we get i get
i get to sit in this moment and practice
here with the support
i get to take this moment
to rest receive
receiving the in-breath and the out-breath
and if thoughts arise as they will inevitably do
letting them be received with an open hand
ah here's a thought letting them be released with an open
hand as if with a smile thank you thoughts
thank you please come back later
no need for any ruffles
thoughts will come they will go let them be received and released
it's part of this training it's part of this
cultivation of the heart and mind
thoughts are not a problem they give you an opportunity
to practice to practice generosity release appreciation
thank you for coming thought please come later thank you
i get to do this i get to practice
don't miss this moment i get to do this
what a gift what a gift to be able to do this with sangha with
support
what a gift to have met the dharma what a gift this moment is even if there
are challenges in this moment in the body and the heart and the mind
can we open up to this moment to this moment
mystery of this moment being a gift
thank you
if you wish you're welcome to stay
you're welcome to stay with receiving the breath and the body
opening up with appreciation [Music] to whatever is being presented in this
moment
where a stance of open hand generosity
in receiving
receiving spaciously then releasing spaciously
a sense of appreciation [Music]
coming and going
appreciating and non-attached appreciation
not a clingy appreciation an open-hearted appreciation
and if you wish you're welcome to open up
to perhaps reflect bringing on a couple of things
that perhaps you've had an attitude of oh i have to do this
what if you turn and shift that into i get to do this i got to do this
with this open-hearted stance
of non-contracted appreciation i get to do this
wow
i got to do this
inviting your heart your mind to open up to below scratching the surface
when you shift this perspective i get to do this
things you never imagined
well open up if you stay with it if you continue to stay with this stance with
this attitude
i get to serve in this way i get to serve myself
or others in this way
are there any difficult challenging aspects of your life
that open you up to grace to beauty to service in the
ways that if they weren't there it wouldn't be
possible i get to do this because of this i get to do this i get
to grow i get to be more
i get to be wiser more compassionate i get to do this
see if that's available if not don't push it
don't push it it's an attitude of inspiration
[Music] not expectation
hold it all rightly i get to do this hold it lightly
hey
okay
i get to do this i get to do this
instead of i have to do this i should do this i must do this
i have so much heaviness obligation i get to do this as uplift
aspiration inspiration sort of the heavy weight of expectation
i get i get to do this
breathing in breathing out
with the goodness the goodness of this gift whatever it might be
even if it's a gift of darkness i get to explore it
i get to explore this gift of darkness
which i know and trust opens up opens up
this gift of dukkha suffering
that opens up compassion to wisdom
i get to do this
it's completely shifting and turning changing the frame
exploring expressing my full humanity i get to do
this
may all beings everywhere including ourselves appreciate all the gifts
all the gifts of grace however they come
may all beings everywhere wake up
and be free
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so we have some time for reflections
for questions comments what did you discover
the invitation is in sharing your insights your discoveries
as a gift for the benefit of other practitioners
friend please
just want to thank jerry for bringing that up uh turning the have to into get to
it's so applicable to almost everything in my
life everything that i usually use the construction i must i have to
you know some parenthetical uh damn it i now will and it's um
there's so little that's really onerous and so much that's uh
that's a that's an opportunity if not a pleasure i i was just i was thinking of
oh many years ago right around the season i had had some surgery and um and i
couldn't walk for you know for a little while and then when i could walk it was every
step was i get to walk i get to walk down to the store i get to walk around
the block on my crutches and
because it made such a deep impression i've kept some of that so some days you know two decades later i'll still walk
down the street and think i get to walk how delightful so thank you
thank you friend well said
lovely
and yes with appreciation to jerry for bringing his practice in so that we could all
benefit from it [Music] and spend this time really sitting with it
lovely any other reflections
that came up for you you like to share
greg i'm not sure if you're trying to raise your hand that's the the clap but if you're trying to
raise your hand you're welcome to unmute yourself and if not
uh yeah i guess i hit the wrong little icon um
i was really taken by uh when you said i get to experience
the uh sort of paradoxical nature of that
assessment that this is an opportunity to to grow to learn how to cope to learn
how to flow to learn how to turn loose a bit to see the insubstantiality of it etc etc etc but it's so counterintuitive
and strikes against the traditional conditioning of
constraints and challenges i have and and remolding my mind to think that way so it's
it's great stuff and uh i love paradox and i love uncertainty and i love the
mist and this this is a great opportunity to influence all of those things or to experience all those things
so thank you for that yeah thank you for for bringing that in and how that
impacted you this shift in perspective really and this shift is
um you know awakening freedom nibbana whatever you call it it really is about
a shift in perspective when we see and relate to things differently and it's just this in so
many ways that is what awakening is so so thank you and it can happen in so
many ways it's not necessarily just tata waiting for that final moment but it can
happen in so many ways this shift and practice little chef shifts in perspective little by little by little
by little yeah thank you and and one thing that i'll share with
what was something that came up for me this has come up before but tonight um
you know when many of you know that i have chronic illness and and you know many
symptoms and and one thing that came up was oh i get to be sick i get to to experience pain i
i get to do this i get to do this because that's when really i slow down i really
slow down and my mind meets whatever challenge and difficulty pain
fatigue slowing down just i get to be sick i get to do this the sense of
delight because i would probably not be sharing the dharma or a dharma teacher
if it wasn't for the gift of this illness i would continue to be a computer scientist so
so i get to be sick i get to do this yay so with that
marianne says i also appreciate um this tonight very much i thought i get
to be a mother and the difficult times opened my heart more than it ever would
have done yeah nice thank you mariah
yeah and another reflection comes in thanks
the gift of dukkha which seems inescapable is a challenge for me yes
it can be and slowly slowly the shift of perspective can happen little little
in small ways in small ways so
um not to expect that all the time
jerry says i recently have had a cancer scare and missed this bullet gratefully
and this dukkha has helped me help others ah wow thank you jerry thanks for sharing
that yeah that deepening us whether we miss it or not
it deepens us to to serve and support others
so let's say it's oh 6 49 yes this is the time to turn
into small group practice so so i have an invitation before you jump often like
those of you who might want to jump off please don't just hear this first so the
invitation for tonight is to take um
to to to take a page out of the book that
gosh who was um he was yes claire was bringing it up at the
beginning so so the invitation is you can share as little or as much about your practice if you wish and then if
you're up for doing this gratitude practice with another person another two people for a
week just commit to it for one week not for the rest of your lives you commit to
for one week to do it with people you might find yourself in the group
just maybe one other person or two other people whoever is up for it and you can can be in text it can be an email
whatever you're comfortable with commit to do it and for one and it could be at the end of the day or the next day see
what works for you figure it out the two or three of you or maybe four i don't know what you'll see
and just commit for one week what a great practice for one week you get to hear
other people's what they're grateful for and then at the end of the week whoever wants to renew the commitment
um whoever wants to renew the commitment you would for another week and if not
then you'll drop it so so with that i'm going to create the breakout rooms
and um let's see here it is we have
the rooms yes and i'm about to open them here we go take care
yourselves take care of each other here we go okay the rooms are all closed everyone
is back so we have maybe just about a minute for any
reflections you like to share um you can raise your hand or type them
as you wish maybe as i wait i'll share a reflection
from david on youtube who said that um thanks sharon says i learned to do that
years ago one day all at once i lost a job and a beautiful apartment becoming jobless and homeless at once ever since
i say i get to do housework etc so thank you for sharing that
way to change a turn as you say
falling into flight so
any other last reflections especially from your time with especially if you haven't spoken
already stephen i see your hand
raised you're either clapping or you're trying to raise your hand
i'm trying to raise my hand um very grateful and i'm happy i get to
rebuild um it seems like you know not too many people get get the opportunity to
start the concept i guess you could say of like a rebirth of the mind and just be able to
just just learn from a very a very respectful perspective and i'm
very grateful to have this mindfulness i'm very grateful to have the sangha and and to just be part
of a community that that develops a very very
beautiful minded person and unique to each individual so
i'm thankful for that thank you stephen thank you so much for
your words of gratitude for this practice for the sangha for all the
cultivation and opportunities beautiful and that's a lovely note to
end our week of appreciation and gratitude on perfect note so thank you
all thank you for your practice thank you for your cultivation thank you for
showing up for each other uh yourselves and the world all those whose lives you
touch may all beings be well may all beings be free
thank you