so hi and welcome to today's happy hour
so for the theme for today um i'd like to
invite us to explore a a theme we were exploring last week
from different aspects different dimensions and today again from another aspect another
dimension and that is putting down
what is extra what is not needed what is not needed as so so that we can make more space
for ease for peace for love for care for confidence for trust
putting down what is extra so one similarly that can come up is say
if it's in the summer it's already hot and you don't want to be wearing a
wool coat that is extra it's not needed to put it to put it down or the idea of
wind drag wind drag how if you well you're going through we're
all going through life through life and it's nice to have
ease freedom nirvana is another word for ease for freedom going through life
without wind drag and when we add what is not
needed for example hatred extra self-hatred
the hatred of others extra adds wind drag adds one drag or lack of confidence oh i
can't do this i can't do this i'm not good enough when drag when drag how about we just
down to it and gently put it down it's not needed
so so some of the invitations i'll make tonight during the guided meditation is a while
if you notice what's things that are extra coming up oh i forgot to do blah blah blah oh
in this moment that is extra in this moment it's a wind drive let's put it down or
oh i'm a terrible meditator my mind is all over the place i can't do this
it's wind drag thank you ah relax relax soften
allow it to to drop away just sit just sit
and you might need to put down wind drag the what is creating wind drag this extra stuff
these extra layers many many many times do it every time joyfully putting it
down joyfully joyfully
so i think that's enough for a framing for now might say more later
but let's begin let's just set so i want you to ah
land in your body landing landing in your body in this
moment
arriving arriving as best as you're able to
inviting this body to relax to land
first let me suggest something raise yourself up a little bit if you're sitting
tightening as if raising your shoulders tightening lifting lifting lifting a
little bit and then drop drop your body relax
ah drop and now really drop another
level into your sit bones you're really taking your seat on this
earth in this body
this is your seat in this life
your unique seat relax into it inhabit it
inhabit the seat fully
ah both relaxing and sitting tall this is your seat
letting the lower body sink
into the earth the upper body the torso rise up
with the breath with integrity
you're both well rooted into the earth connected deeply
connected gravity pulling you down enjoying
sense aware rootedness
your chest open ah feeling uplifted filled with
breath with air
your chest and your abdomen your whole body
spending a few minutes in your own time feeling well rooted
your feet your legs your sit bones connected to the earth
and enlivened throughout your body with the breath
calming soothing suddenly
releasing putting down whatever comes up it's extra in this
moment sensations are just sensations
breath is just breath sounds are just sounds
and thoughts could be seen as just thoughts coming and going not getting entangled
not getting entangled
if you notice any entanglement
it's extra it's wind drag
smilingly noticing it is that
relaxing softening
the body
noticing that without the entanglement without what's
extra there's more ease more peace
you can just sit just be
so much easier less tiring less exhausting for the body
for the mind
to just sit and be
releasing letting go putting down what is extra entanglements
self-doubt i can't do this my mind's distracted
i don't like this
all the commentaries
it's not needed it's like a warm coat in the summer
don't need to wear it don't need to wear it
your heart your mind is naturally calm naturally peaceful naturally loving
the natural state is a free state
you know this you know this deep down
just sitting putting down what's extra
to make space for peace for care as self-care
noticing if judgments are coming up
extra not needed
smilingly relaxing the body
allowing this extra layer
to drop off and feel the ease space extra space
created for peace
as a way to care for oneself for yourself
for ourselves ah so much more nourishing so much more
loving such such ease
restful
the best protection we can offer ourselves
from the arrows that can cause harm when drag
just sit just here
especially when we're put down
any enmity any self-criticism self-hatred
self-doubt or judgments directed towards ourselves
or others but we put those down especially when we
release them we make even more space for love
care for ourselves and others
paulie the language of the buddha dosa ill will hatred
al dosa the opposite of ill will hatred
synonymous with loving kindness so when you put any of these
unhelpful unprofitable attitudes of the mind down release them
you're making more space for peace for love for friendliness
now i would like to invite you as a bridge between this practice and
the cushion in our daily life
to do a little visualization if you would
as you feel embodied sitting feeling your feet
on the floor your sit bones contacting the earth
your hands your breath moving through your body
bring to mind if you would a situation from today
where there was something you were to do
could be sending an email or washing the dishes
or anything going for a walk whatever but there was some wind drag in the mind
resistance either judgment inner judgment i can't
do this not good enough i don't know what to do
doubt or external
any situation where where there was one drag
feeling your body feeling your breath as you feel into the situation where
there was wind drag i don't feel like doing this
wind drag queen drag
feeling your body what does your body feel like
with this entanglement with this wind drag
you notice more tightness more fatigue
more exertion
more stress more dukkha
now imagine you're putting it down
releasing just putting down whatever this extra this extra
winter coat is in the summer just putting it down and giving your heart
to what needs to what needs to be done what's calling you and just doing it
just being with it
no wind drag imagine yourself doing this just simply doing it
whatever it is immersed in it becoming one with it
just simply immersed without resistance without wind drag
i like to read a poem let it wash over you this reflection
let it drop in as your body is sitting
embodied let it resonate in your heart
in your body poem is called in this passing moment
by hogan base
in the presence of sangha in the light of dharma
in oneness with buddha may my path
to complete enlightenment benefit everyone
in this passing moment karma ripens
and all things come to be i vow to choose what is
if there is cost i choose to pay
if there is need i choose to give
if there is pain i choose to feel
if there is sorrow i choose to grieve
when burning i choose heat
when calm i choose peace
when starving i choose hunger
when happy i choose joy
whom i encounter i choose to meet
what i shoulder i choose to bear
when it is my death i choose to die
where this takes me i choose to go
being with what is i respond to what is
this life is as real as a dream the one who knows it
cannot be found and truth is not a
thing therefore i vow to choose
this dharma entrance gate
may all the buddhas and wise ones help me
live this
vowel
when sitting i choose to sit
that's all
for the last moments of this practice
if any thoughts are coming up of judging your practice
considering it not good enough not worthy enough
these self-judgements these thoughts of ill will towards yourself where extra
are extra not needed putting them down
ah releasing letting go you did your best you showed up as best
as you're able to by letting go of self-judgment of dosa
you makes space for adosa
and paulie synonymous with metta loving-kindness the opposite of illegal
choosing choosing simply just this letting the
extra letting the wind dry go in this passing moment
in this passing moment just this
justice
thank you all for your practice
so for today's practice i was weaving a few different themes
as you probably noticed one theme was this theme of
what is extra putting down what is extra especially what is put down
the extra that's put down if it is it'll will again in polydosa dosa
the opposite of that in poly ah do so you add an a and it becomes the opposite r dose
is synonymous with meta so when you put any ill will doubt uh
uh uh uh all this extra wings especially when you put those down
ah making some more space for peace for ease for love for self-care it's the
most important protection meta we can offer ourselves may i be safe or
may i be safe from all this extra stuff that i keep
hurting myself with and hurting others with ah body can relax the mind can relax
another theme i wanted to bring in is the simplicity of just this with this beautiful poem
called in this passing moment
by hogan bays b-a-y-s it's pretty easy to find for those who
want to find it later and probably neil is going to send it to the google groups he has thank you neil
the theme here is no conflict just this just this
just as if you're sending an email oh all this extras you're washing the
dishes off just immersed in it just immersed with what
is no conflict no wind track again making more space
have you noticed the days that maybe you got the same amount done as another day but if there was a
lot of wind drag a lot of doubt a lot of internally externally you're much more
exhausted by the end of the day as if you've climbed a mountain but it's
all wind drag wind drag lack of freedom lack of freedom whereas putting down
what is extra what is not needed and recognizing what's not needed so so i've said plenty i would love to
hear from you what did you notice what did you discover you can type in that if it's typed
publicly i'll say your name if not just to me then it'll be private reflection i won't
read out your name you can also raise your zoom hand [Music]
ali says in what you created i got the message that the very act of choosing
eliminates so much of the extra then begging the question where am i not
choosing where am i not choosing in my life question mark great i love this context as an
as an access to simplicity and space beautiful beautifully put alley
beautifully put yeah i want to read the this part again
that it begs the question where am i not choosing in my life where where is wind drag
where is oh beautiful thank you for offering this
beautiful reflection ally well said
other reflections please you're welcome to raise your hand also
especially if you haven't spoken in a while i'd love to hear from you or if you have a question or if this was
challenging or confusing it's all okay it's all welcome
anthony i see your hand i usually i don't see people's hand because i see a small strip but here you are
yes nikki um thank you i'd like to say um how much uh i was relating to the
uh to the breath you know to let um let go um and
i just wanted to say the power of the breath you know to once i i connected with my breath
everything else uh went away you know as far as uh my worries and my uh
the stress and whatnot yeah yeah thank you anthony that is really
powerful that that insight of connecting with the breath really it's it's as if again this
image i have this image of wind drag when you're kind of riding the breath you connect with the breath and it's oh
it's so full and it's delicious and it's just putting down other things
uh what's extra can become so easy beautiful yeah thank you in fact that reminds me i
just started to i got a pointer to this book called breath by james nestor which i've just started
to listen to and it's about breath about physiological psychological research that is just
it's amazing this breath so yeah breath thank you anthony
so dear ones how about we turn to practice and community and we'll
leave some minutes on the other side when we come back from groups for reflections and maybe
what comes up when you hear and hold with community these three themes how did they work for
you what you observed uh benefiting from other people's insight and wisdom it's always
interesting even if you feel like you have nothing to say hang in there just listen with with
metta for your own benefit and others it's all okay so so i will create the breakout rooms
and as always let's start by 15 seconds of meta silent meta for one another just
silently before you start speaking just holding yourself holding others with meta
and then you can say as much or as little as you want to say um okay
here we go they are open and enjoy okay
welcome back everyone and we have a couple of minutes for
insights reflections what came up what you noticed uh what you learned
about yourself um oh milan is asking for the google groups
information yes um anything else you're
you're welcome to raise your hand with your zoom hand um
or reflect
yes please someone on the phone is this michael
you are unneeded hi it's michael so i'm happy to report um can you hear me
yeah yeah great um i'm happy to report we all loved the letting go
theme of this evening so deep vows to you and um i was super grateful to be in the group
with these two wise women so it was really pleasant and just
really watered my happiness seeds and my letting go seeds so deep vows and
thank you michael i loved how you put that watering your your um
how did you put it oh gosh every oh your heart seeds wait how are your meta seeds and your
loving-kindness seeds and your letting go seeds that's what you said watering your yeah beautiful
that was just lovely watering your letting go seeds and your loving kind of seeds yay
wasn't that wonderful community doing that yeah great thank you for that
reflection and i'm so delighted to hear that this theme um is uh
this theme of letting go to make space to make space for care for love as a way to care
and love for ourselves it's amazing how connected the theme of letting go
is with meta with kindness even though on its face it doesn't seem like it as neil was
saying last week like at first like wait this is letting go this is not meta whereas it's like oh wait a minute
there's this moistening of the heart as he was also saying there's a moistening of the heart
a gentleness a sense of care so so it's so much fun to discover these
connections between these practices that at first might be hidden so
so dear ones we have come to the end of our practice time together
i'd like to thank you all for showing up for cultivating your heart
for the sake of yourself others and everyone whose lives yours touches
may all being be happy may all being be beings be free including ourselves
thank you