so my friends
that the
kind of subject for this week is
the fifth and sixth step of mindfulness
of breathing which is to experience
joy and happiness in meditation
and it's certainly not easy to
experience that and you can't just do it
just because the instructions say so you
should do so
but to explore this territory of joy and
happiness
meditative well-being and some of the
conditions that support it some of the
things that bring it about can be very
helpful
and so that's a topic for today this
week
and so
um so there's uh the precursor
uh often the suttas for joy and
happiness
is gladness and uh the word is
pamoja p-a-m-o-j-j-a
and uh pamoja comes from the
the kind of the root word we don't never
know if the
root or the etymology is that important
for the people who spoke it but
it's certainly a fun game to play
and so the paw is the prefix can mean
either outward or upward and
the moja comes from the word for face
mukka and um so
the the uh
the idea of you know something of the
face uplifting face
a face that's rising up or maybe a mouth
sometimes the mouth is
closely associated with his word from
for face
and it's the uplifting of the lifting of
the mouth
i think of it as uh uplifting up the
corners of the mouths to make a smile
so is that which and uh lip makes a
smile
or a kind of maybe a beatific kind of
out upward gazing at what inspires us
and in fact and for the buddha the
the he encouraged people
when there's difficulties in meditation
to think about
or imagine an inspiring something that's
inspiring
or but inspiring not in a way that's
activating because the word for
inspiring
also has the meaning for
confidence or peacefulness or kind of
brightness
so that which brings brightness or
confidence
or um or peacefulness
kind of a peaceful confident brightness
maybe
so we'd say in simply in english kind of
inspired
and and and to be inspired
uh when we sit down to meditate involves
activating
the imagination and
and we find that imagination
is regularly referenced
in the teachings of the buddha in
relationship to meditation
and this was certainly very different
than how i was introduced to both
vipassana practice and zen practice
where the explicit and the implicit
instructions
was not to not to be involved in
thinking so much
and certainly not to be involved in
imagination
this was the meditation practice about
just being present for things as they
directly are
unmediated by concepts unmediated by the
imagination
just the experience in and of itself and
the direct sensations direct contact
with things
uh and um and uh and that's definitely
true
but it becomes it becomes true as the
meditation gets more and more centered
in the present moment
and but to get ourselves centered in the
present moment and centered and present
moment with some
joy some well-being imagination can be
harnessed can be utilized for that
purpose
and and so the buddha encouraged people
to
think of an inspiring topic and some of
the things that he
talked about that were inspiring uh
to think about that the buddha himself
think about someone who
you're really inspired by their practice
by their being how they are in their
life
in a way that kind of is inspiring
enough to really want to sit here and be
here and
kind of kind of puts to rest other
thoughts and concerns that
keep you distracted and
or to
the encouragement is to be inspired by
your own virtue
and of course that requires us to be
virtuous
and but the word virtue has
really means virtuous conduct so you
don't have to be
inspired by what you're feeling on the
inside
the buddha's teachings are be inspired
by how you act in the world
and if you're acting in a world without
causing harm if you're not you haven't
stolen any money from the bank lately
or you know it killed any of your
neighbors late recently or
you know done all kinds of things
then that's a source of being inspired
and it doesn't mean you have to be 100
virtuous
but to recognize the way that we are
living a virtuous life even if it's just
for today
not to be burdened by the past so much
and but rather be inspired by what is
good
and beneficial and so to be inspired by
one's own virtue
maybe that's a hard thing for many
people to imagine to experience
but it's certainly one of the teachings
of the buddha and one of the purposes of
being virtuous
is to create the inner context to be
inspired and gladdened and
uplifted so we're more so it's easier to
stay present
and the other thing that the buddha
makes explicit about what's inspiring
is
his mudita
the appreciative joy to think about the
things in the world
that bring you a wholesome nourishing
kind of joy
like so to share in the joy of others
who are doing wonderful things
and um and be inspired by that and so
this idea of being inspired
uh by things is um
is not meant to take us away from the
present moment or it'd be a spiritual
bypass
it's not meant to for us to dwell there
just kind of keep thinking about
thinking about and fantasizing about it
but rather to do it just enough that uh
it really orient us to the present
moment
it brings this uplifting kind of
feelings
and goodness that we're capable of then
feeling
and then writing those feelings into the
present moment
it's sometimes easier to be present if
there's some modicum
of well-being that's here as well
and it's not meant to be again
overriding or a bypass of the challenges
we have or the
suffering we have but it is
helping to create a context where it's
easier to be with the challenges
to work through them and meditate with
them breathe with them
and so the principle here that i think
that supports this idea of using the
imagination
for something that's inspiring is that
is that to to do it when the alternative
is worse
human beings spend a lot of time in
their imagination
imagine the future what's going to
happen the terrible things are going to
happen
imagining the past remembering you know
some percentage of our memory
is fantasy we it's well known that we
don't necessarily remember accurately
what happened in the past we're telling
ourselves a story we spin it a certain
way
we spin it around the things that really
have a charge for us whether it's good
or bad
and we kind of kind of stretching
certain parts of the story the memory to
fill the space of memory
in a way that not completely accurate
and uh and so sometimes that can be very
depressing and
agitating uh certain fantasies can be
not helpful at all and uh so if
we're doing that anyway in the
imagination
then uh it's possible to use the
don't fight the imagination then and try
which might not be working
but harness the imagination uh
to help you be here in the present
moment to gather together
and and then when you're here enough
then you can let go of the imagination
and then sit here and be present
so you know i've in the course of this
teachings i've offered some imagination
imaginary kind of scenarios images to
help for example
as i love this image for breathing of
the
of the waves of the ocean washing up on
the sandy shore
and kind of i have this image of myself
of of the
especially when the waves once they're
washed ashore
there's they're washing up across the
sand and making the sand wet for a while
and then they're receding and then as it
recedes it's
the sand is wet but then the the water
kind of that's
the surface kind of gets pulled into the
underneath the sand and so you get a
whole different texture feeling
of receding and absorbing
and this image of this of then of like
the
i use it different ways in meditation
but imagining the breathing
experience of breathing are the waves
and my
body is the sand or the experience of
breathing
the sensations that come and go the
cycles of
up upswelling and and receding
with the exhale is um washing across the
shore
the sand of awareness and it kind of
that's
that image kind of keeps me there and
involved
i've known some people who have one
person in particular who used
the image of a large bird maybe a
i don't know some large wonderful
majestic bird
flying in the sky and the inhales and
the exhales
were the with the the flapping of the
wings
the slow long just flapping in
the wings of the bird and uh and that
kind of kept her engaged and involved
and
flying along and
so to use the imagination
to help us be connected and then
to use it to help us be inspired
and and to know as i've said how not to
overuse it
how to use it so it's onwardly leading
in the direction i talked about
yesterday that we're going towards
uh doing less and less activity to quiet
or still or
states of mind and um to more
from courser to the more refined more
active to the more peaceful
and so we use these things to support
that process
knowing at some point we have to let go
of it
not relying on it too much not um
overdoing it not depending on it not
using it as a
antidote so we don't have to face our
difficulties or work through them
but rather as a way so that we can be
present
in an effective way
so um so to
particularly i want to end now with the
idea of inspiration
with that which brings a brightness and
uplift
a delight brings confidence
brings trust brings
willingness to engage in practice and
this idea of an inspiring things
and i would encourage you for the next
24 hours
to consider what inspires you
and stay close to thinking about it and
visiting it being with it somehow be
connected to it
or maybe there's many things maybe you
can talk to others
friends or anybody who you strangers
but you have this assignment to talk
about what inspires you and
and you'd like to share a little bit and
hear from them what inspires them and
and maybe in ways that are spiritual in
nature or
has to do with some of the fundamentals
of what gives their life purpose or
value
and in doing so i hope that you have
some wonderful conversations and
and some wonderful um time
uh thinking uh time with yourself
what is it that inspires you and maybe
that you can stay close to that so thank
you very much
and we'll continue a little bit this uh
the way the buddha uses imagination for
meditation
tomorrow thank you