so
this is the third talk
on the theme of oneself
and
began monday with the topic of
self-respect
and perhaps self-respect is uh
maybe sometimes easier to come to than
self-love or self compassion or
but to have a deep respect
and
what we respect
maybe we try to understand it better we
make ourselves available to know it
better
and so yesterday was a topic of
self-understanding
to really understand this person that we
are
what drive us what drives us
what
attitudes beliefs attachments
desires and aversions we have
and how we understand ourselves so that
we can be free or
and today the topic is
not harming oneself
and
i find that uh this idea of non-harming
not harming others not harming ourselves
is such a profound topic
that um
it's easy to be to uh eclipse that topic
with more inspiring topics of
the dharma or spirituality
it's inspiring the idea of love and
compassion generosity
it's inspiring wisdom
it's inspiring the idea of freedom
and
but it's also possible to be focused on
those and not really understand the
nature of harm
nature way the mind works the heart
works that we're harming ourselves and
maybe in
in ways that we
harm others both out of impulsive speech
and action that we never would have
consciously planned to want to do but it
just blurts out of us
but also in kind of subconscious ways
that uh
we're not really aware that uh how we're
speaking in a way to kind of
poke someone or
or
express our hostility or
a little bit mean to someone
and so to um
to value non-harming as a foundation
beca and to appreciate that non-harming
is a profound topic because it applies
to so many areas
to live a life without harm self-harm
and harming others is a phenomenal life
it's a really a good life
and people learn to trust us we can
trust ourselves we can go anywhere we
want without having to feel
self-conscious that we're
causing harm
and it's the foundation for a peaceful
life peaceful world
so um
not harming oneself
there is this um
uh
verse
in the sutras
the buddha says
traveling in all directions
with one's thoughts
nowhere
can one find anyone
dearer
than oneself
in the same way
to each individual the self is most dear
oneself is most dear
therefore whoever loves oneself
must
whatever loves oneself most
doesn't harm others
so sometimes this idea of
you know
holding oneself dear
valuable
holding oneself as being precious
is
maybe seen as being selfish
but uh there's a way in which it's not
and one way is that the more we have
respect and care and appreciate and
value for ourselves
and the value that they would see the
value of not being harmed by anyone not
be suffering not having no one steal or
lie or
attack us or anything and know
that we can appreciate that's true for
other people as well
allow them to be the most the person
who's most precious to themselves
and imagine that they also do not want
to be harmed
and this combination of seeing oneself
as being valuable
and that translating to not causing harm
and caring for others
is one of the wonderful principles of
buddhism
and um
so that's so if you if you um
and uh and then there's a particular
verse in the dhammapada that can be
quite challenging to read
or to
deal with
so that begins with something maybe
that's uh
not so difficult it says
don't give up your own welfare
but the next line says
don't give up your own welfare for the
sake of others welfare however great
and the idea that uh you wouldn't
sacrifice yourself
your welfare for the welfare of your
children or your neighbors or people you
know or people who are suffering more
than you
goes against the grain for many people i
know
but i think that as we understand
ourselves deeply
um it isn't that we're trying to be
comfortable it isn't we're not trying to
but that we have access
to an inner sense of peace inner sense
of
non-harming
we don't harm ourselves through anger
contraction attachments um expectations
bias all kinds of ways which we harm
ourselves
that's where the real welfare is the
real welfare that profound welfare is
how we keep the heart at peace happy
contented even if we're uncomfortable
so
don't give up that welfare
for someone else's welfare but that
doesn't mean
don't
benefit others don't do things for
others just don't sacrifice what's
greatest and beautiful in yourself for
that
keep that and help others
so if a neighbor for example is uh has
an emergency
and you haven't eaten
and for your welfare you should eat
otherwise you'll get a headache maybe
but your
your neighbors
needs to get to the emergency
immediately
so of course you would i would hope you
would sacrifice your meal and sacrifice
the
the absence of a headache to save the
life of your neighbor
but in doing so you don't have to
sacrifice
your heart you don't have to give away
your peace or your
you don't have to get agitated or
contracted or something
and that is where self-understanding is
so important to really understand deeply
where the refuge is within where how we
hold ourselves in safety
in our hearts
by not getting caught in our attachments
so to not harm ourselves
requires a lot of self-understanding
a lot of
sitting quietly and still or
any kind of way to really get underneath
the surface
of how we think
the surface layer of our desires our
wishes our preoccupations concerns
i've had still to this day
i can be in the labyrinth
of
my concerns and thoughts what should we
do what happens here and i have a lot to
do and i have to figure this out
and it's labyrinth that
i call a labyrinth because sometimes
there's no way to get out of it
on its own term terms
but if i sit and meditate
then um
i'll drop down into a deeper place of
knowing a deeper understanding a deeper
way of thinking that's not in a
labyrinth of superficial thoughts or
surface thoughts that
preoccupations were kind of lost in them
and then from that deeper place
then there's no labyrinth then oh now i
understand
myself and what needs to happen and what
the priority should be
so this ability to
know oneself by dropping below
the surface chatter of the mind
and really feel deeply what's happening
in the heart and the body
in the mind
and eventually discovering
understanding the little movements or
the big movements that we have within of
harming ourselves
of being mean to ourselves or being
judgmental or being in conflict with
ourselves
or
um getting caught in desires which uh
and maybe even pursuing them desires
which will come back and harm us uh if
we pursue them
you know some desires some addictive
desires for example
sometimes
uh the addiction
might it might bring pleasure in the
short term but can ruin a life in the
long term
certain desires we pursue
and in the short term they're pleasant
but in the long term
they cause problems
if we um you know if we overeat it's
pleasant but then we have you know we're
groggy afterwards perhaps
or if we have an affair because it's
pleasant to do
then afterwards we realize how much harm
that has caused to other people
so this idea of
you know
understanding deeply
how we get caught in desires how we get
caught in cravings and judgments and all
this
and learning how to give ourselves a
phenomenal break
learning that we there's no need
to be
caught in the grip of desires no need to
be caught in the grip of hostility
towards ourselves there is a this place
of respect
deeply within
where it's okay
to relax
it's okay to just be
it's okay to be here just breathing
below the surface level the flow that
chatter and
and um
below the
desire and hostility level
those are just a level that's just a
labyrinth we get caught in
but to sit quietly learn to let go and
quiet the mind and the thoughts and drop
down to this place that's deeper
and the deeper calm we can experience
the more we'll understand ourselves and
understand when the little impulses
arise
even the slightest one that involves
self-harm has an ouch in it
and then we learn i don't have to do
that
i can let go of that
so
practicing non-self-harm
partly because we cherish ourselves we
value ourselves and partly because it's
just so painful to harm ourselves
and then knowing
that discovering the wellsprings of
non-harming within
is a
foundation
for caring for the world caring for
others we come into the world we meet
others in a very different way
if we have learned the art
learn the skill and the capacity
to
minimize and eventually hopefully stop
how we bring about self-harm
then we and don't sacrifice that
absence of self-harm don't sacrifice
that peace
but
it's a foundation
from which to meet others care for
others and care for the world
and that can be done tirelessly that can
be done with tremendous dedication
so this uh this quote
don't give up your own welfare for the
sake of others welfare however great
yes don't do that
but if you don't do that maybe you'll
have a lot more energy
to
care for
the people in your lives known unknown
and throughout the whole world
so
not harming oneself
thank you