hello friends hi welcome to happy hour
hi good to see you and if the audio is okay you would give
me a thumbs up you can hear me alright
something here great fixed something here on my end
okay great so let's start with our informal but very
important opening ritual of welcoming each other and welcoming
ourselves to this meta space so i'll start by saying hello
i'm nikki i'm in mountain view california on seated oloneyland who's here who
wants to say hello you can unmute yourself if you like or type in chat
hi i'm elaine i'm from belmont california glad to be here thank you nikki hi lane
thank you lovely to see you hi bill from dallas texas welcome pal good
to see you hi hi nikki i'm
barbara from alameda and i heard you this morning and i
thought oh i think i'll like to hear her again oh that's sweet yay good to see you barbara
welcome happy hour a different channel the meta channel great welcome
lovely that you're joining this this really wonderful sangha it's um
kenneth says hi from albuquerque welcome kenneth good to see you again and hi helen hello everyone from sunny
marin hi helen and [Music]
let's see danelle i says hello oh this is claire
claire says hello from new york city but i'm using my husband's computer that's
what's going on okay it's great good to see you claire on
your husband's computer that's sweet and manohar says hi from rayleigh north
carolina hi manohar on on youtube and hello
paul from india oh sweet i wonder what time it is in india right
now maybe pearl you'll tell us sweet our international sangha and i see
mari christine here good afternoon to you in sydney australia i i
usually write a hello but i'm feeling a bit demoralized um things are not going very well with delta here in sydney it's really
spreading fast so i'm feeling a bit of cabinet even a little bit downs so that's why i didn't do my usual hooru
yeah yeah it's so cute thank you and thank you for adding that
that in fact the theme for tonight is compassion for how difficult this year has been
so i'm glad you came tonight maury christine yeah yeah and jamie says
hi from coast me walk land of marin county hi jamie good to see you and pearl says
it's 6 30 a.m here oh sweet happy early morning tuesday morning to
you peru sweet so let's formally get started let's formally get
started and um thank you neil for
posting information chat about the happy hour google groups which is where folks can
share uh information with one another and um yeah
and also quotes and references are shared also on that channel so what's
at this time i change the settings so accidental unmuting will not be possible
and also i change the chat so that it only comes to me host only on zoom and we'll keep it all
quiet unless say my sound drops out or something really needs to be communicated and
um and oh yes i'm michael in scotland at 2 a.m
this is so sweet the international song go all time zones it really warms my heart
all of us sharing this earth together and the last of the preliminaries
turning on the recording for the sake of audio dharma
oh actually you know what i didn't let me
going to restart the recording to this computer there okay so a formal
formal welcome to happy hour everyone wherever in the world
you are in this moment as part of the sangha practicing together
so the theme for today's practice as i was um referring to earlier
as marie christine was saying how challenging it is right now uh with the delta variant
in sydney australia with the lockdown ah the theme for today's practice
is is compassion for compassion for how difficult this
year has been for ourselves for people we care about
for all beings everywhere to acknowledge that to um note
to note the pain to note the ouch with compassion bringing
care warmth love to hold
the pain the suffering for ourselves and for our loved ones for all beings
on this planet for this year so
so i'll say a couple of words about the practice of compassion and how we're going to
do it tonight so as you may know and as a refresher when meta when loving
kindness when friendliness good will meets pain holds
when it meets sorrow when it meets suffering it expresses itself as compassion
so meta plus suffering equals compassion another way
that has been said is that compassion is the love child of suffering and meta
and the practice of compassion isn't one that will make us depressed or more
morose but it lifts the heart because we bring care we bring love we bring affection
warmth to the pain to the difficulty so it's a soothing self
practice of compassion as a healing as a healing venture and the way we will
do it together tonight is first we will bring up someone we care about who's had a tough
time in this past year and the pandemic and practice meta for them
and then turn to ourselves because often we don't see our own suffering and pain
sometimes we do sometimes we don't and what if we treated ourselves
as our own best friend the same way that we see our good friend and
hold them with care compassion hold ourselves with the same compassion
and care and then we turn it outwards for all beings for all human beings and then
for all beings in our connection in our connection in
this world we're we've all been going through this together through this challenging year with
different challenges for everyone different levels different amounts it's not a time to compare to
say oh better or worse we're going to bow to comparison say thank you comparison you're not
needed right now we're just going to tune into the challenge
and with compassion and care without comparing and judging so so with that
i'd like to invite this to settle to settle and arrive in our seat
to start right here right now
landing in our bodies and as always we start this practice together
with some minutes of settling arriving with mindfulness
with gathering and collecting our hearts and minds before we turn to mental and compassion
so landing in the body
reading the feet sit bones
or hands our spine
our face
our breath moving through this body
the breath moving
in breath and that breath
calming soothing
settling the heart with each out breath
settling the body with each out breath
in fact for the next few breaths let's
elongate the out breath a little bit to release to relax to really settle
ah maybe even vocalizing it's okay
ah
one more time localizing together
ah in your own time in rhythm
letting a few breaths be slower than usual the outer breath specially elongated
settled
just settling and landing
with the soothing calming nourishing
breath
as if the breath is an expression of meta of care compassion
nourishing wrapping us enlivening us
wrapping us as if we're the blanket of goodness
soothing calming
and now i'd like to invite you
if you would bring to mind
a dear friend a good friend maybe a relative a benefactor
someone for whom your care your friendliness comes easily
could be someone you know well or someone you don't know that well it's okay
as long as your care flows with ease and there isn't too much complication in
your relationship bringing this being to mind and it could
also be a child or a pet as always
this person this being imagining them
and how challenging this past year has been for them in different ways
bringing their image their felt sense near and dear to your heart
as if they were sitting with you
acknowledging this has been a hard year
this has been a hard year
as you acknowledge the difficulty the challenge for them some ways you may know some of which you
may not know
as if you were wrapping them
the blanket of goodwill the same way one would cuddle a little baby
a blanket of care of affection
or if another image comes up for you that signifies your care
your compassion your desire to soothe
to calm to care
for this being
being in touch with the challenge with the ouch
of the sorrow with the heaviness and yet
not getting lost not drowning in the pain sorrow
letting it be held the uplift
of care of affection
of matter i wish you well may you be free
from sorrow from difficulty
or
may you meet this challenge with ease
may you meet this challenge with peace
or i care about you
i know it's been hard
i hold you with care i hold you with affection with compassion
may you meet this difficulty
the sorrow is heaviness
with ease with grace
i wish you ease in the midst
of what has been hard
either with words imagery or maybe with your breath
maybe each out breath as it flows out of your chest your heart center
imagining that each breath brings them ease
more comfort in the midst of the difficulty
holding them supporting them
caressing them
each breath each out breath
blowing ease care love goodness friendliness
compassion soothing bringing care
calm ease
to this dear being
and now i'd like to invite you
without any comparison and if comparison and judgment step in see them clearly
with eyes of gentle meta bow to them say thank you not now
thank you not needed gently putting them down
without comparison allow yourself now if you will
to be seen through the eyes of this dear being
this friendly person being you've been practicing with
just as you've been seeing them for the challenges they've been going
through this past year and continue to go through
let them see you with eyes of friendliness eyes of care
let yourself be seen let yourself be seen with caring
with compassionate eyes held received
the way they see you and hold you with care it's been tough for you
this past year it continues to be
as it continues to unwind let yourself be seen
with eyes of compassion
let yourself behave be held
at the gaze of care
and receiving wishes of mitta wishes of compassion
as they wish for you may you have ease
may you meet this challenge this difficulty the sorrow with ease with grace
as much as possible
may you be soothed be eased
the challenges you're meeting you have been meeting
may may you carry your load your sorrow
your difficulty your pain your suffering
as much flightness and peace as possible
let their wishes for you be received let them land feeling
i'm in your heart and your bones
letting your challenge inviting your sorrow to be held
to be met but the peace
the lightness of meta and care
acknowledging yourself that yes it has been hard
it continues to be challenging
adding your own compassion your own care to that of your dear being
for you for yourself
as if with each breath
more ease more compassion and care is being breathed in to your heart
into your mind heart meeting the challenge
suffering
and if you like to put your palm in your heart center your chest
it's a soothing soothing calming
a younger version of yourself it's okay sweetheart it's okay it's okay darling
it's okay it is hard it's okay
and the hand signifying both soothing
and strength for yourself
yes it is hard
and yes there is love and compassion
from you to support yourself
strength of compassion strength of care
it's okay darling it's okay it's okay
i am here for you
i'm here for myself not abandoning
myself caring for my own heart
and now turning our care
our metta to me the suffering of the world the form of compassion
outward shining it outward
we are not different i am not different
from my dear being from all beings
and having had challenges not comparing the amounts lesser more not comparing or touching
but all beings all human beings through this pandemic
have had challenges been sorrow for everyone
shining the light of our care of compassion
outward touching ourselves first
bringing healing and soothing to ourselves
our dear being our beings
and shining far and wide
may all beings they are human beings all beings
have as much ease as possible
the midst of this challenge that is the pandemic
knowing that fully knowing that this aspiration is so big
yes we can't take everyone's suffering away we can't soothe the whole world
and yet turning our hearts towards this
aspiration wishing inclining our minds
towards this wish with generosity with good will with love and care
may it be so may it be so as if adding a drop of our compassion
putting it on the altar of humanity as our offering
may all beings everywhere
be free from sorrow and suffering
may they meet their challenge
their pain
with as much ease peace as possible
may all beings everywhere be free from pain and sorrow
may all beings everywhere be well
[Music]
thank you all thank you for the grace of your practice
compassion compassion for ourselves for others for all beings
this difficult year of the pandemic all the pain and sorrow
so we have time we have space for reflections
for what you discovered what you noticed to share it with sangha for your own
benefit and the benefit of others or questions
all welcome you can type them in chat if you wish
if they're typed just to me i will only read the reflection not your name
if it's typed to everyone i'll read your name also you can also raise your hand your zoom
hand your physical hand i may not see
and uh would love to hear from you
one reflection question coming in do you have suggestions for how to
address sleepiness i seem today like i was it seemed today
like i was practicing napping no worries maybe you're tired
maybe you're sleep deprived if that is the case then maybe that needs self-care needs to be
primary and if that's not the case so if you're sleep-deprived then
it's okay it's all right trust that this practice worked in ways
that were needed for you as self-care as self-compassion but
sometimes napping could be an avoidance we don't want to go to compassion place it's too big so if
you're not sleep deprived then then many things you can do
one is to open your eyes bring more energy in the visual field just not staring at
anything in particular but kind of diffuse eyes another
option is to breathe a little more deeply
just to bring up the invigoration of the breath another one is to sit up a little
straighter another one is to stand do standing meditation don't do sitting
so all of these are options that you can do and please play around
with them another reflection lots of tears lots of physical rocking grateful for
your voice inviting me back again and again thank you for that
reflection yeah can be quite quite overwhelming
taking it all in reflection on youtube pearl says i realize that i shy away
from how i relate with suffering as it seems enormous
i wonder how to transform that so maybe
start with a small you know you don't want to take the hundred pound weight
suffering and and your question i'm not sure whether this and please feel free to
expand if it came up this enormity of suffering came up when you
turned it toward the whole world or was it also the same for you when you were doing it with your friend
um and yourself i'm going to assume room maybe it came up when you were meeting
the suffering of the whole world and in that case the thing to do is to
again acknowledge that it is enormous as i was saying it's an aspiration it's not that we're
going to fix it all but it's an aspiration it's it's as if we're praying as if we're
putting our our wishes our compassion putting it on the altar of humanity as
an offering so that's the invitation
to work with it that way and if you want to type more on youtube there's a 30 second delay but but i can
see what might come back one more reflection i felt waves of
validation compassion and peace for a recent difficulty oh lovely thank you for sharing that
one more reflection here is a very very sweet meditation
glad it was supported for you yeah and abraham please
thank you um i you're so very emotional
and it washes over me and sometimes it distracts me
i know i'm also very emotional but i sometimes have a hard time coming
to meet you and so what i found was that i repeated the phrase that you used
for myself and that way i make it for myself and and uh it was like i was embodying
what your cue was and and that i found was was much better
so i don't know if anybody else is like that but that was what worked for me yeah great
fantastic thank you abraham we're all different in many different ways and and
i so appreciate in what you shared is that you are making the invitations
these are all invitations we all have our different style you're making the invitations work
for you to meet you where you are because i can't tune to every single person for
some people it's very very sweet it's very opening lots of physical
rocking and tears and for some people it's like oh emotion really emotional beautiful thank you
april i just love hearing how you you make it work for you
yay yay i love i'm having so much more deta for your practice
yeah and i think you're are you trying oh sweet you see the heart yeah really
moves me thank you thank you for that reflection beautiful
so dear ones we have come to the time when we turn
to meet each other in small groups and let us meet meet each other in small group of
with compassion with how difficult it is now and it has been again no comparing no judging but just
meeting each other meeting fellow travelers being held holding each other might be silent there
may be no words or there may be words so we'll start
with 15 seconds of silent compassion for each other
and after 15 seconds you're welcome to share as much as you like or as little
as you like with each other but your practice um and yeah
beauty of of sangha so the rooms are created and
please take care of yourselves take care of each other with gentleness kindness generosity
and the rooms are open enjoy
to everyone that's it
okay welcome back everyone welcome back the rooms are closed and we
have a couple of minutes for any reflections we'd love to hear from you especially if you haven't shared
in a while you can raise your zoom hand or type in chat what did you discover
let's practice together
especially if you're new we would love to hear from you
if you wish
you're you're able to unmute yourself now if you want oops can't wherever i see your lips
moving but i can't hear you okay there so i'm one who ex i'm new
so i'm one who experienced tears uh and especially when
we put the hand on our heart and you said to
um to feel compassion for your younger self
and that that surprised me because i was focusing towards the beloved person and then when we
turned it inward it was like tears thank you
thank you thank you so much yeah this practice shows up in
places where it's needed where it's needed it shows up in
surprising ways yeah yeah really appreciate your reflection
one more reflection coming in felt so sweet to sit with sangha
big and small felt like coming home oh that is so sweet
what a lovely lovely um reflection to end on felt like coming
home so it is seven o'clock
and let us bring our practice of compassion for ourselves for others to close
so i thank you all for showing up for cultivating for sharing goodness
with all beings everywhere may all beings be well may all beings be free
[Music] thank you