hi hi welcome to happier
so this week we're dedicating our practice to the beautiful practice of gratitude
uh given that in the u.s it's thanksgiving tomorrow thanksgiving holiday
again a holiday with with complicated history um
and i appreciate that um many of us have in the hellos before
it got recorded they acknowledged the lands being unseated
um and and a part of this this reflection
uh in this holiday i have to i'll share an anecdote actually um so when i came to
the us when i was 16 years old i came from iran and um
and um not knowing the history at first of what the solid it was but just hearing that oh this new country of mine
at this holiday called thanksgiving it's a day people give thanks wow what a cool
thing to have a holiday for to have a day that you just give thanks so i like
to bring that beginner's mind that that
naive perspective and just share that because there's there's a uh there's a goodness how can let let us
co-opt it in this way and yes it is a day it is a week it is it's a great
opportunity every day every moment to give thanks to give thanks for so much that we have so much that we
take for granted and
there are so many studies that link gratitude um appreciation i like
actually the word appreciation because sometimes gratitude feels heavy like as i think ben was bringing up on monday
there is a sense that for some folks this feeling that you should be grateful
well you have so much good things going on in your life you should be grateful ouch and that
sense of should a finger wagging that either the society seems to do inadvertently or we tend to do for
ourselves or others like you should be grateful it's actually
can suppress can suppress a sense of gratitude whereas
a sense of appreciation just appreciating appreciating what's good
turning our mind to it and relishing uh relishing really taking a moment to
take delight and appreciation and letting gratitude if he wants to come up on its own to come up
without any shoulding without any forcing of
ourselves that's very very important and if at any point doing the practice
you don't feel grateful that's fine drop it go back to relishing go back to being
with the breath just keep it simple there's no should in this practice
and to continue that train of thought there are many many studies that connect
authentic appreciation authentic gratitude to gladness to happiness
and to generosity and that's another thing that i've been contemplating lately which is beautiful
also studies connecting how connecting gladness happiness to generosity
that when we give actually there's a study that if we spend and participants were given some
money to either spend on themselves or spend it on someone else and people felt happier when they were generous when
they spend it on someone else which is pretty cool and there are other studies that show that
you can train yourself to derive more
joy more delight out of generosity
so that uh when you're actually generous you feel happier just
gives you more more of a helper's high more of a hit let's say and the way you can train
yourself to do that is guess what practicing appreciation practicing
gratitude for what you have actually makes you enjoy generosity more which i think is a
really interesting exercise so um the study so again don't take any of
these on faith try them on for yourself see if this is true in the laboratory of your
own mind you're a human being you have a laboratory called your mind heart body
try it out for yourself so with that oh i want to say one more
thing you know on monday we practiced uh and the guided meditation was about
gratitude for things we take for granted and i just wanted to share a practice report with you and wondered if you had
the same concern later because i noticed oh my mind
turned into gratitude more this week for things that i take for granted and it
was lovely i just enjoyed it so much so thank you all for for
being part of the sangha and this opportunity for us to practice together so
so with that let us turn our hearts our minds incline a little
more invite ourselves um to appreciate to appreciate and maybe
invite just shyly if the gratitude is shy just invited like a little kitty you want to
come out you don't want to come out that's fine and but just be very gentle with this
practice with similar to other other practices so
so with that i'd like to invite us to land to land in our bodies
ah to arrive to begin
by arriving arriving in this moment
in this body
just relaxing the body
without any expectations softening your sit bones
your lower back ah
releasing [Music] releasing the abdominal muscles
internally
releasing your forehead your muscles in the forehead
releasing your jaw
releasing your eyes let them rest
let them rest in the socket
the muscles behind the face
ah
let them soften and relax
relaxing the shoulders the neck
the hands let them be heavy
the fee to let them be heavy
letting the body just
rest
letting the heart the proverbial heart center
place of the emotions let it rest rest
feel safe to just be
letting the breath move through the body
be known be witnessed in the abdomen
as if awareness was a butterfly
the awareness sat on your belly moving up moving down
with every breath
and if thought arise it's okay can you release them with
appreciation not with self-judgment but first appreciating that the thought
has arisen thank you thank you thought thank you mind i have
in mind that works thinks this is what minds do it's
not a problem appreciating this puppy of the mind is
playful say thank you and right now
let's give our heart let's give ourselves to settling arriving
releasing releasing with appreciation
let the body be relaxed and soft
just receiving appreciating
the butterfly moving up and down
sitting on the belly
each breath a butterfly of awareness
remember appreciating thoughts that arise and
then releasing them with appreciation
resting grasping with the butterfly of the awareness
on the abdomen
this
you can stay you can stay with just
the butterfly of awareness the belly
resting calming collecting the mind appreciating no way appreciating
simplicity of this moment
simplicity of a moment of refuge to sit and just practice just be
and if you wish if you like
to follow these invitations that i'm about to give
if you like you can bring to heart
some act of kindness some act of generosity
some act of care connection [Music]
today yesterday something that comes up
for you
maybe you were kind to someone or someone kind who's kind to you
you're a generous to someone or gender someone who's generous to you thoughtful
caring or just a sense of connection
maybe a kind word kind gesture
is he bringing it to your heart to your mind see if there is natural
there's a sense of natural appreciation that arises
don't force it just stay with it relishing it and see what happens
maybe maybe becomes brighter in your heart
sense of appreciation becomes gratitude for this connection
for this gift given or received let yourself relish
take delight delighted and hence nourish nurture
this wholesome quality
an appreciation begets appreciation
letting your heart be open see where else it wants to go continuing with the thread
and what you were just reflecting upon and if the mind becomes too full of stories and
you're not practicing then just come back to the breath to the body settle
[Music] for a few minutes before opening opening up again
depreciating relishing
acts of kindness given or received generosity given or received or
something in your life you're grateful for
you appreciate just breathing it in for a
few breaths breathing out with it
slowly slowly it's not a race stay take your time relish
keep the butterfly of awareness in mind
don't lose it
appreciation appreciating what do you appreciate in this moment
here
you were able to sit together and practice
what to get
there's enough health in the body the mind
to do this practice what a tremendous gift
not looking for what is wrong but inclining the mind
to what is nourishing what is good
if you like you can even open up appreciation for what has brought you to
this this point in life might have been some beautiful gifts
some challenging moments that have brought you here
can there be a sense of appreciation
for the path for this meandering path of our life
picking a few moments
i'm a few significant people
for the last couple of minutes with practice can you appreciate yourself i have gratitude for this being
who's had this journey the ups and downs in this life
appreciating his gratitude as you're stepping out of yourself
giving yourself a hug or whatever feels right for you in this image bowing perhaps
appreciating this being who is you with gratitude that they continue to show up
they continue to show up
as best as they are able to letting go letting go
any judgment
and just grateful for this you're showing up in this moment
you've shown up that's enough that's enough
perhaps having an image of people in your path
having gratitude for you as you've had gratitude for them
them having gratitude for you for this being who is unique
only the way you can be with your particularities
as if they bow to you they give you out
they say thank you as you say thank you to them
offering offering your goodness to yourself
to all beings everywhere
may we wake up to our own
and everyone's unfathomable goodness
may we awaken with grace
thank you all thank you for your practice
the gift of your practice
so if you are willing if you are moved if
you wish you like to share
some gift from your practice today
with the song go what came up for you what have you noticed what was it like discoveries
challenges anything is is okay joe
just that i really like the option of using
appreciation in place of gratitude because gratitude is a lot of work
and appreciation is uh is kind of a simpler level
it's like gill's use of anacompa care
as an umbrella term that includes compassion because care is really easy to grasp
and so anyway uh anyway i like uh i like appreciation thanks great wonderful thank you for bringing
that intro i really appreciate your reflection yeah and
yeah interesting that uh to think of it as an umbrella term because in the way it is the same
appreciation is the same as gratitude but yes gratitude can feel so heavy sometimes so much work for his
appreciation it's just oh yeah it feels naturally i appreciate this and well guess what i'm grateful for it too but yes
yeah that's great thank you for that joe other reflections of their
um [Music] thoughts
yeah dave says i'm most grateful for this emphasis on gratitude because i've been through
an arches jobs route that had me focusing on how much i don't have
and didn't i think there's more to that chat coming but yes thank you it is so
important yes turning the mind to what is good what is here and focusing especially gosh
yeah job search can be so challenging looking looking searching by definition
is is an act of wanting in the world mima i see your hand please
i am had never seen the the correlation between the generosity of someone when you were
speaking about that and how the gratitude is kind of like it goes together when there's an interaction
and i remembered my son my grandson is now going to be 18 but when he was about
seven years old he came to me and he said to me um grandma i have three hundred dollars and i don't
have anybody to share it with he said i asked my mama and my step papa if i could buy them
something and they don't need anything and he asked mr anything you need
and his favorite store was barnes noble and so i told him you know i saw a little speaker
i really really liked it but i couldn't get it that day hey grandma please let me buy it for you
and i remembered uh with this meditation i remembered that experience how it was a give and take because he was being
generous but i was so appreciative even now of the experience with him
and so i'll never forget the day he came over a couple of weeks later with a little bag and he was elated
grandma i bought your speaker and he and i still have it i will not get rid of it because that
experience that i remember him doing it was from the sweetness of his heart he wanted to share
and i could not i don't i could have bought it myself but i didn't want to deprive him of that yes
that's slowly that's beautiful mima and and as you highlighted in the story there's so much giving and receiving and
and when we actually give another person the opportunity to give
it is so um it's that it's such a gift that is such
a gift right to let them be kind oh it's it's it's such a gift instead of
going oh no too much trouble do it for it's just no it's
beautiful that you let yourself receive and it's still to this day it it brightens your heart it brightens
your mind oh that is beautiful thank you for letting me share that oh thank you for sharing this video this is so sweet
yeah it reminds me i'll share it a little story too which actually happened this past week i
was actually um i was writing there was
some reflections and generosity and and a friend texted who lives about
10 minutes ago saying that oh i've made a batch of soup can i drop some off for you and i
thought oh it's trouble and then i thought wait
as part of my act of generosity she wants to so yes please i would love to
eat your soup so she came and brought it and it was just it was both lovely to receive and also the same thing that you
were sharing with with your friend uh with with your grandson yes the giving
others the upper chances of saying oh no to you know don't too much trouble you know it's like we're blocking we're
blocking general we're blocking kindness and that flow of gratitude and connection so yeah
beautiful thank you for that mima deborah says this meditation was a real
tenderizer there have been many gladdenings of my heart this week being
back out in the world more and interacting with old customers people i haven't seen in years kindness
from people and these sessions ah that is lovely
thank you deborah tenderizing it was tenderizing for me also a lot of um
yeah tender memories of people i've been grateful for in my life came up
very tender so thank you all for your practice abraham this will be
the last comment before we go into practice a small pri small groups please
oh you're still muted let's go straight into small groups
that's fine oh you sure okay all right so so we'll come back to abraham when we come out of
the groups you're on you're on cue you're on top so um so okay so let's go into groups if we
would and and the invitation is to
um yeah one one invitation is
maybe sharing if you wanted what something that you felt came up for you that you're grateful for
uh from this practice or maybe something that was tender anything you like to share or not and holding each other with
gratitude these wonderful human beings whom you gonna be in in a in a few minutes of connection with
gratitude and generosity that's in that can you can we feel it in real time this
yeah these human beings are alive somewhere in the world they're practicing with me so
so the rooms are created i'm going to open them and we'll come back and we'll have a few
minutes for reflections on the other end so here we go okay the rooms are all closed we're back
and we have a few minutes for reflections and let's go to abraham
abraham are you still up for it whatever you wanted to share before is it relevant thank you i appreciate it uh just many
many years ago what people were sharing about uh how the giver
wants to give and for you not to receive what they want to give is
is not a skillful thing to do or can not be skillful i had a teacher
many years ago when i was in the midst of a career change and i didn't have a lot of money and
the first year i applied for a bursary so i could attend a retreat and it was wonderful and the next year uh he said
why haven't you applied for the bursary and i said i can't do that every year somebody else needs the opportunity he said you know
somebody has offered the money for a student to go why would you want to take away their karma the possibility
for them to earn good karma uh by not accepting it and i realized
when he said it that he had put the money in the bursary fund and wanted me to be on retreat but i thought that was
a really interesting take you know like why won't you allow people to express
their goodness that's interesting that's beautiful
thank you abraham i love that i love that twist yes exactly why not let them
express their goodness their block their wholesome karma from ripening yeah
that's lovely appreciate that reflection yeah
the other reflections we have a moment anything else that came up for you from this practice
it's so rich
eileen please okay
i think i'm unmuted okay yes what came up for me was that i really appreciate the imagery of
the butterfly of awareness because i've always tried hard to be mindful and what i understood today was that
gentleness works and trying hard like that doesn't work
so that was all i appreciate that very much nikki beautiful thank you aileen that that is
right on the butterfly right that's that's perfect exactly i'm so
glad you brought that up uh it's it's an image that uh for me it
really works this is the sense you know butterfly of awareness is flying just
sitting on your belly it's like oh yeah getting up and down with every breath just so
gentle awareness is just a light touch and just the joy the light so thank you
for bringing that back in and highlighting and i'm so delightful that that that you're finding
that supportive and instead of the bearing down which yeah just hard work and doesn't
help anyway so yay lovely so so thank you all thank you for the gift
of your practice for being here um offering yourself
to this practice to each other what what a gift to practice together
thank you i am so appreciative and grateful for this sangha may all of you may all of us may all
beings be happy may all beings be free
thank you