so hello everyone
and
welcome and to take a moment to just kind of relax settle back
getting ready for this meditation
and um one of the
ways of helping support an ongoing mindfulness a continuity of awareness
through the all the arisings of things in the present moment
is sometimes you want to be aware of what's happening
but also be aware of the influence that has on us and the ongoing impact
and um and so some of it's a little bit getting getting out of the detail of whatever is happening but also aware of
the way the influence the impact the the way it lingers in us for a while
and so for example with tension it's possible to be aware of tension
and also to take time to feel what the influence of tension is in us in us how does it spread out from us and
what uh how does it affect our mood or affect our feelings how does it affect
the area around the place where there's tension how might it affect the mind
but for today i want to emphasize something a little different and that is when we relax
that to be aware of what what's what
replaces the relaxation or what influence the relaxation has
so it's one thing to relax the hand and that feels good but then to really stay
and be really aware of that good feeling oh that's how it is kind of like you take
it in be aware of it let it register more deeply and so as we relax
uh the body the to be aware of the vitality the
aliveness the peacefulness how things get lighter how things become settle down release
um if we feel the goodness of it the wholesomeness the the niceness of
what happens once we have relaxed it it doesn't have to be dramatic it can be quite subtle
but uh that does a few things one is it keeps us in the process of mindfulness of
awareness and also it the benefit of what's wholesome can
register more deeply in us it has a deeper a good influence on us if we do it that way
and the opposite happens with taking in the influence of tension it isn't that we
unless we react to it isn't that we feel worse it actually lightens things up it
kind of loosens and opens the space a little bit so
and that's also this idea of being aware of the influence sometimes it's quite nice to do that on
the end of the exhale the exhale is a kind of a letting go and then with that letting go
is there any good feeling or lightness or openness or
kind of the absence of things it feels really nice it doesn't always the case sometimes the
end of the out breath can be a little bit frightening and uncomfortable but if it is nice
take it take some time to really moment to feel that before the in-breath begins
so um to
assume your meditation posture and
to gently close your eyes
and in a moment take just one long slow deep breath in
and one relaxing long exhale and then feel what the impact that
exhale has on you so go ahead
then do it again and on the exhale relax your body
and take a moment to feel the influence the impact of that relaxation
what's left in the body that's maybe feels nice
taking a deep breath in and relaxing as you exhale
and then to let your breathing return to normal
but then continue relaxing on the exhale
and if you're able to relax these different parts of the body take in the feeling that's there
that comes from having relaxed so relaxing the muscles of the face
the eyes around the mouth
the lips are pressing against each other let them fall away from each other a
little bit or if they gonna touch touch lightly
on the exhale relax the shoulders
and then relax the chest and if it releases a bit
settles a bit feel that influence on you
and relaxing your belly soften the belly
and if anything feels nice about the soft relaxed belly
feel that
and if there's any way that you're bracing yourself with your whole body maybe a little bit
braced on the exhale let go let go of it let go of some of it
and feel how that's like
and as we settle in meditation the body settles and relaxes
the mind settles a bit and calms
feel the resulting
way in which it is what it's like to be alive the energies the feelings the sensations
of the body that seem to
come with a deeper subtleness
a relaxation
allowing like all your pores to be open to receive and feel
the aliveness of the body
and then in the middle of it all
being aware of breathing in and breathing out
as you exhale letting go of your thoughts and letting go into
the body breathing
so
letting go of your thoughts in opening up the body
to receive the vitality the animated qualities of the
body
allowing the bodies feeling sensations energies
to flow through you with the idea that
they blend together to become a whole a harmonious and peaceful
hole of vibration buzzing
that in a sense the body receives allows
and then to feel the body again what's the effect on the body
from having meditated these minutes what has shifted in your body
is there any influence of any calm calm or relaxation
that's happened and what is that influence on your body
and rather than feeling it from the control tower to allow yourself to feel that influence
let the body feel it more fully body receives is a mixed space
in a sense body space the space of the body can become bigger feel bigger have more
room in it and it's easier than to
have room for all the challenges of life
smaller more contracted the body is the less room we have to respond deal with
process the difficulties of life
so to relax into your body
relax your body
and turn your attention outward into the world
whilst keeping yourself grounded and centered in your body
and gently modestly wish well on the people in your life
gaze upon them kindly
stay calm and gaze upon the world kindly
learn from your meditation practice how to be present for others
in an open stable way where there's a room for what's happening
without getting caught in it or reacted to it
so you can gaze upon it all kindly caringly
there's a way in which we care for the world which is a simple
expression of the freedom that comes from the
meditation whatever ease or calm or freedom we have
whatever way that that gives birth to a care and a kindness
let that care and kindness spread out from you into the world with these words
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
so yesterday's topic for mindfulness of the body was respecting the body
and respecting the body is partly also respecting the uniqueness of our own body and its needs
there's all kinds of conditions physical conditions challenges in the body
that um you know are challenging to be with and
and to gaze upon that kindly to be have compassion to respect
the body for what it is and to learn how to take care of it how to care for this wonderful body that
we have challenging bodies and uh the care that we want to live
from in buddhist practice extends to ourselves as well and so
part of what mindfulness of the body can do is as we get more attuned to our body
we can better kind of feel what supports it and what debilitates it what's healing for it or
helpful for it how to best the best posture the best way of being with
whatever is going on in our body and i think the first time i came across
someone who was doing this was when i was a news end student a long time ago
and there was a woman who had uh some kind of knee issues serious knee
issues she'd been a runner and and um and she used her um
her attention they to details attention to her body she was learning through zen practice
to learn to walk in a new way and she'd fight finding to try to find exactly the right play to angle for her
feet and how to come down and put her weight and with that she found a way to walk that for her
situation that prevented her from or meant that she didn't have to go for
surgery i don't know what happened to her in the long term but i do know that
partly i think that inspired her and she went on to become a doctor so this
this you know care to the body and really what is what's the right thing for the body how to be
you know i've had a bad back various times in my life and i found it to be an exquisite time for mindfulness
because it was such a strong feedback loop between the slightest little move which was hurt
or kind of relieved it and so it's right there to stay and be aware so this mindfulness of the body and
respecting the body can give us the information to guide us to find a way to live with this body
more caringly and then wisely
and also one of the things that can happen as we practice is that there
there can be a restoration of a sense of healthiness or vitality or
or harmony in the body as we do this practice that it's not just the practice of
letting go but the letting go is a process of becoming whole
a process of not excluding anything and we can feel that little bit um
what i'm trying to say here is um if we get settled and relaxed in
meditation somewhat calm and a some we start thinking about
something that has some tension in it uh and we feel ourselves sensing up
and it can be com at some point it becomes really clear that following the tension getting
involved in that tension tensing up even more is detrimental it's not interesting
and it's in more interesting to not do it and so to relax to settle back
to come back to that more relaxed state and partly the motivation to do so is we see
so clearly the disadvantages of tensing up
as we see it just starting us this tensing starting to happen we let go and come back
so that's a little bit of a kind of a negative motivation it's also possible to have a more
positive motivation that as we let go we start feeling the benefits of that in
the body and it feels so good to feel this way to feel whole to feel subtle for the
inner life to feel peaceful or calm or settled harmonious
and um and you can feel how when we start getting tense or preoccupied about something the whole sometimes the whole
physical system um starts to lock up or get a little bit tighter the micro muscles some of the
micro muscles in the body tighten up or there's a disconnection
we lose touch with the body i mean it's quite dramatic you know maybe some of you had this experience of
minding your own business meditating calmly and the mind suddenly releases some memory of
you know from the teenage times and you know some
some difficult event that happened and and turns out there's still some charge
around it and and i have to have it happen to me and this suddenly this energy in the
body kind of you know like gets goes upright and i get tense and
and the energy flows into my mind and i'm thinking and having conversations about what happened and
reviewing it and i've lost touch with my body i lost touch with a settled and calm
body and and so it's quite dramatic to see that
movement and it's an education about how easily it is to disconnect from the body
and as we develop mindfulness we're developing body fullness developing capacity to
feel and sense the body not only so we don't tense it but the absence of tension gives rise to
feelings of healthiness or harmony or wholeness that can even be there
when there's the body's ill or or there's pain or there's different
things happening in the body there are challenges in the body there's a whole it's a there's a different kind of energy a
different kind of attentiveness in the body that is peaceful
calm holistic sometimes even cozy that seems to spread and open and
suffuse the body a gentleness that has space
to hold what's difficult that's there as well so we're not preoccupied and caught by
the difficulty but the awareness is holding it more widely and it isn't just the mental awareness
but there's also kind of a bodily awareness that can hold it and the remarkable thing is the body can
start feeling like it has lots of space some years ago i went to a cadaver lab
to spend some time looking at cadavers and um i was surprised how all the
organs was all squeezed in there and like there was almost no space in there um because everything was
packed with these different organs and uh and why would surprise me is that when i sit and meditate
um i feel like there's lots of space in my cavity lots of space in uh in my torso
and just that space gets bigger and bigger as i sit and quiet and sometimes that space feels like it has no
boundaries just opens up and so the the the ex way we experience
the body uh can be different than what's actually there because what we're doing is
experiencing the the it's the is the experience of the body
that's the medium through which we're really creating room and space to be able to hold everything
not to deny anything but to make more room for it and and as things have more room they
have more room to move more move to unfold more more room to relax
but also some things are are healthy that they flow begin flowing more
and um and so this restoration of uh
with the body of having mindfulness support a restoration of healthiness a restoration of
a flowing energy a restoration of of um of um
kind of a spacious calm in the body that can hold the challenges that we have
and and the wonderful thing is as we have more space we have then more capacity to be with
difficulties and one of the great contributions of buddhist practice is to expand our capacity
to be with challenges expand our capacity to be uncomfortable expand our capacity
to be in conflict with people because there's more space for it all
so part of mindfulness of the body is uh not only to be aware of the body but
also to have a kind of receiving allowing
attitude that allows that space to grow that allows the energy to start flowing
more fully and to feel that to feel the goodness that might be there and make space for
it hold it be aware of it not in a
in a utilitarian way like i'm going to do this for a purpose i'm going to make
this happen or something the utilitarian approach to mindfulness has is very very limited
but what's rather than utilitarian approach it's an appreciative mode
to appreciate rather than to make something happen and in that appreciation to receive and
hold and experience the body in a bigger way so the restoration of the whole body
and and so it's one of the great
i've been for me one of the great gifts of meditation practice is um the richness
of living in this body that has come from that uh from the practice
so um may your meditation practice your mindfulness
practice help you
rest in the richness of this living vibrating body and to learn the wisdom
of it and the healthiness of it and its capacity to hold all things
so um thank you very much and
we'll do the last day on the body tomorrow