well hello everyone and here we are and i'm delighted to be here
and see names new and familiar names on the
chat uh so
um
so meditation could be seen as a special place kind of unique
if you'd like where for the duration of the meditation you are
[Music] forgiven for everything
and for the duration of the meditation that you don't have to bring the past with you you don't have to carry it
you don't have to be under the burden of it if you think it's useful to do that then
you know think wisely and maybe it is sometimes but you really allow to put it
aside kind of as if you're forgiven and
and then imagine that for this meditation you're going to meditate uh
from the most ethical place that you know the place that you know where you're
least inclined to cause any harm to anyone intentionally or unintentionally
least inclined to be mean or spiteful or least inclined to be greedy
but that so like this is what you know i would call the most wholesome place that we know
maybe in english we could say the most ethical place and to assume that stance assume that
place that place that you might know already or in or that you intuit or that you
have some vague feeling for a place where you
uh is maybe the ethical source for yourself
and uh and from there that place meditate on your breathing that place as
if you're that's kind of like the central the central uh the center
of it all then gaze upon your experience be mindful of your breathing and
whatever else is going on so assuming a
posture even that may be it's a posture of being confident
in your ethics at least for these minutes of the meditation before and after is a whole other story
but for this time to sit and upright or meditate in a way that you feel
reassured in your ethical stance
and gently close your eyes
and without breathing deeply just breathing simply maybe
tenderly breathe with whatever ethical
sensibility sense feeling that might be here for you
just here and now
perhaps as you exhale to relax any holding in your body
any holding from the busyness or activity of life or of the mind
and then to relax the body as a way of relaxing both the body and
the mind relaxing the belly softening in the
belly
relaxing in the chest
and as you relax and feel the relaxation
begin the process of quieting the mind
and relaxing softening around the
shoulders
and also softening relaxing in the face
the cheeks around the eyes
and perhaps softening relaxing the brain itself or the thinking mind
softening and thinking mind
if the thinking mind if thinking are waves in the mind letting those waves flatten out
so the mind becomes more like a flat surface of a quiet lake
broad and peaceful
and now take a few moments to see if you can connect to some place
in your body
that holds or manifests expresses
a feeling for being ethical
a place where there's appreciation for the absence of tension
that comes when we're not hateful or greedy mean
critical
the absence of contraction or tension the absence of fever or agitation
perhaps the presence of some sense of ease or openness
peacefulness some sense may be of care
respect valuing of others
and if there's a place in your body that this is associated with
breathe with that place breathe with that breathe through it
and let that place be a support a mutual support
with settling in with your breathing
settling into
accompany here breathing one breath at a time
letting the thinking mind get quieter maybe with every exhale letting go of
thoughts settling in
with the ethical goodness that lives within you
whatever you're aware of in meditation
see if you can be aware of it in a wholesome way
in the place of wholesome ethical wholesomeness
each thing meeting it without it with a dedication
to cause no harm to oneself or anything else
okay
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to once again take a few moments here to see if you can sit quietly
acceptingly of your own wholesome core the place
inside that's the source of an ethical life
a motivation to attempt to not cause harm
to others and to oneself
and to appreciate that for this meditation
we're sitting in a wide circle of community of people who are touching in
considering their own core of goodness
their ethical core core of non-harming
and what a unique thing to be in relationship to such a
large group of people with a similar maybe similar orientation for these
minutes
and may it be that the connection we have to our ethical
core that it's a place that we stay close to
so that we can go through the world
in a way that supports the welfare and well-being of others
it supports other people's feeling of safety and support
and maybe even is a catalyst for other people
to recognize their own ethical core one that's so easy to lose touch with
in the busyness and activities of life challenges of life
may it be that our practice today spreads from us
as a catalyst for the welfare and happiness of others
that can come when we treat each other with respect and kindness and dedication to
non-harming may no beings be harmed
may no beings be disrespected
may no mean beings be marginalized or
diminished in value
may all beings be happy and safe peaceful and may they live
in such a way that they breathe easily and freely
and that their hearts sick can sail fly
on the winds of freedom
[Music]
so hello everyone and
welcome to this time for a dharma talk
and today um
i want to uh bring forth some teachings of the buddha which is
timeless teaching for our society and that as in our society in our world
maybe in many countries around the world and down through the ages there have been people who consider
themselves superior to other people and and lots of conflict arises from
that and lots of inequities arise from that people are superior will have
greater access to wealth and power and status and all kinds of things
and it was the same way the time of the buddha and in the time of the buddha there was
a particular we might call class of people
some people considered use the word caste in relationship to them
that were known as the brahmanas and the brahmins at least some of the
brahmins the time of the buddha thought of themselves as superior to others to be the only ones who were
somehow in the way that the universe was created or the world was created that they were
somehow the only ones who are really pure really came from
the divine in the this the divine source of life in a way that was superior to every
other form of life and they should be treated that way and should be treated with respect
and with power and with sense of that they were purer and than everybody
else and and what we find is the buddha
who is often called sometimes called a peaceful sage was very very definitive in
undermining or not standing for this kind of teaching that he was
very strong and direct to oppose this kind of idea it wasn't that he was accepting of
everything or was sat in the background just let these things go along without addressing it that he was very he
addressed it very forcefully i would say especially when people came to him and
asked him about it especially when the brahmanas came to ask him about it
and so i wanted to read first
a passage where uh the brahma brahman is being quoted uh for um claiming that they are
you know the best um the
uh
so sorry sorry i lost my page that i prepared here here someone comes to the buddha for
example a brahmana and said master gotama the brahmans
say thus brahmins are the highest caste
those of any other caste are inferior brahmanas are the fairest caste
those of any other caste are dark only brahmins are purified not
non-brahmanas brahmans alone are the sons of brahma
the offspring of brahma the great brahma who somehow the
beginning of life born of his mouth born of brahma created by brahma heirs
to brahma so that's the claim so it's a pretty confident bold thing to say
and and so people would come to the buddha and make this claim and then in this
case they said to the buddha afterwards what do you think of this and in the sutra that the majima
sutra number 93 where i quoted from he goes through a whole series of
arguments uh undermining that statement and uh
the person who's asking him uh making this asking this question just won't accept any of the buddha's
arguments and the buddhist keeps going and going and going and
opposing or undermining the argument that it's uh that uh it's by their birth that they
are born brahmanas it's by um they're purity it's by their
all kinds of things and so he just kind of step by step goes through it all but there's one uh suta which is um i
think it's very it's a i think it is a beautiful suta it's mostly poetry called the vasata suta it's number 98
in this middle length discourse and this issue of caste superiority of some
people is a big theme in the 90s in the number of these pseudos in the 1990s
in the middle length discourses and this one is 98 and and here
the two brahman students who are extremely learned in the
ramonical lore and know all the brahmanical texts and histories and everything
and um and so um
one of them says that um
they asked themselves a question how is one a brahmana
and one student says when one is well born on both maternal and paternal sides
of pure descent as far back as a seventh generation of ancestors unassailable and impeccable with respect
to birth then one is a brahmana so it's really a matter of birth how you're born makes
you a brahmana and if you had this pure descent from seven generations and maybe before that from
brahma the god brahma himself then you get to claim the superiority
then one is a brahmana now the other student his name is and that's the name of the
suttas of he has a different point of view he says
when one is when one is of good behavior
and proficient in the observances then one is a brahmana
so what makes a brahman is their behavior when their behavior is ethical and to be a brahmana maybe to know their
brahmanical observances and be able to do those rituals and things like that and
so they have an argument and they can't one can't convince the other so they decide to go see the buddha and
ask him the buddha they think is you know well respected he's wise and and
certainly he'll have some good things to say about this and so they ask him that question they
say a dispute has arisen between us over the doctrine of birth
one of us says one is a brahmana by birth but i say one is a brahmana by action
by what one does since neither of us is able to convince
the other we have come to ask you sir widely famed to be enlightened
so the buddha says i will clearly explain this to you
i will explain it to you both in proper sequence as they are the generic divisions of
living beings for their kinds differ from one another so he's going to describe kind of how each
the different species of beings are unique and special to themselves and they differentiated by species kind of
and some people actually translate what follows with the word species to distinguish them
and he begins by talking about the grasses and trees know the grasses and trees as well
though they do not even make any claims for themselves they can't speak for themselves
their distinctive mark is produced by birth in other words what makes them
distinctive uh their characteristic is comes along with being born in as
particular kinds of trees particular kinds of plants for and their kinds their different
their varieties their types differ from one another so they have lots of different species
next come the moth and the butterflies even through the various kinds of ants
their distinctive mark is produced by their birth for their kinds
differ from one another they know the four-footed beings both small and large their distinctive
mark is produced by birth their kinds differ from one another
know that those whose bellies are their feet that is the serpents those long back
creatures their distinctive mark is produced by birth for their kinds differ from one another
note to the fish that dwell in water next the birds who fly with their wings
in the sky so he's going through all these beings
and saying their distinctive mark is made by birth because the repetition of it the contrast of what he's going to say
probably stands out in this oral culture in which he was teaching before it's almost like a song that's being
being being spoken um
[Music] while among the many kinds of beings their distinctive marks are determined
by birth among humans there are no distinctive
marks produced by their particular birth or to say it may be in plain english it's a little hard to know
exactly how to translate this into english the pali but there's no species differentiation there's no
significant differences produced by human being that's distinguishes one person as being superior to someone else
one person a brahmana over someone else based on how they're born
not by the hairs or the head not by the ears or the eyes not by the mouth or the
nose not by the lips or the brow not by the not by the neck or the shoulders
not by the belly or the back not by the buttock buttocks or the breast not by the anus or the
genitals not by the hands or the feet nor by the fingers or nails
not by the knees or the thighs nor by their collar or voice birth does not make a
distinctive mark as it does with other kinds of beings so there's no
no characteristic that we're born with that separates us out from other human beings as being better or superior
from others it makes us a brahmana
separately among human beings nothing distinctive is found in their bodies so of course we know there's lots of
differences in people's bodies but there's no inherent distinction
that is the source or the reason to classify people as being superior or
inferior the name makes an interesting statement classification among human beings
is spoken of by designation so um it's by convention by designation
by con the constructs of the mind that we classify people in particular
ways and as soon as you call it a designation then it becomes a product of the mind
and culture and not anything inherent and so classification of
people is has some usefulness but it's always going to be somewhat fragile it's always good since it is a designation
it's just an a it's just a concept that's overlaying on top of human beings
it's it's provisional it's contextual um it's something which doesn't really
fit uh you know 100 percent all the time and so how to be wise about the
conventions the designations the concept by which we understand each other
um so the buddha is going to say a little bit more about his orientation around this
kind of idea um the humans the humans who live by
husbandry you should know as farmers
those who earn their living through crafts you should know as a craftsperson
those who live by trade know them as a merchant those who live serving others should
know as a servant those who live by stealing you should know as a thief
those among human beings who earn their living by archery know them as a warrior
those who lives by priestly service
know them as a priest and those who rule or a village in realm know them as a
king and none of these he says are a brahmana
so here he's saying that the class of buddha's orientation is to classify people as a designation for people by their
roles by what they do remember one of the arguments of the two brahmanas was people are brahmana by
their action and here buddha says by their action is what we call people
that means that it only really applies when they're doing that action um that's
when it really makes sense and people change what they do and in sense change their roles
um a significant moment with my first end senior teacher i was talking about my
relationship to my father and and he said to me that oh your father
your father was a human being before he was your father
before you were born and the way he said it was like oh don't only see this person who's your
father through the lens of being a father this person has a whole other way of being in the world that's
kind of free of being a father just being a person in a different kind of way and that kind of gave me a different
perspective and i realized how much i had taken certainly my father acted like a
father like you're supposed to if your father i suppose and so it makes sense to call him a father
but someone is a father when they're fathering
someone is a a worker when they're working someone is a barber when they're
barbering someone is a you know a cook when they're cooking and
so and then people can shift to these roles shift these activities and in a sense take on different
designation different names for them that's a little bit how the buddha sees
it but all of that all of that is not does not make a person a brahmana
so now that the buddha is going to say this is what makes a brahmana so rather than rather than jettison
throwing away this concept they had an ancient india of the brahmana as somehow being worthy of respect or i
don't know if superior is what the buddha would say but worthy of respect or having some kind of value special value
rather than throwing that notion away he redefined it in his own way for his own purposes
and this is how he said it
i do not call someone a brahmana based on genealogy or maternal birth
um one who without hatred
endures insults attacks and bondage whose power is patience
that is the one i call a brahmana one who is without anger observant of
good behavior tamed that is the one i call a brahmana
one who understands right here the destruction of suffering for oneself
that is the one i call a brahmana one who having put down weapons towards all beings frail and
firm is the one i call the brahmana not hostile among the hostile
peaceful among those who have taken up weapons not taking not taking
among those who take not killing or making others kill that is the one i
call the brahmana one who one from whom lust and hatred
conceit have dropped away that is the one i call a brahmana one
who utters no rough speech whose speech is articulate and truthful
by which he does not hurt one does not hurt anyone that is the one i call the brahmana
one here who does not take anything in the world not given that is the one i call a brahmana
one here who has abandoned craving who wanders without a home with craving and existence destroyed
that is the one i call the brahmana so many of these factors that the buddha
calls make someone a brahmana has to do with their ethical behavior their action and
these these passages appear a number of places in the suttas both the dhammapada and the sutuni pata so they must have
been popular in the ancient world and the so it's
people's ethics ethical behavior that the buddha is emphasizing and this is over and over again this is
what what the buddha is emphasizing and some of the arguments he makes for why shouldn't she take those who are
born into the brahmana caste class as being brought real brahmins
it has to do with their ethics that some of them kill and steal and and lie
and do all kinds of things and some of them don't some of the people in different
classes of society at that time lived very ethically and whoever lived ethically that was the
brahman even if there was a society put them at the lowest class the buddha wasn't going to see it that way
he saw them as being worthy and valuable human beings that
and so much so that when the buddha created a monastic community
in the community that community there was no differentiation between those who were of uh who came
into the monastic community from their brahmin class from the ruling class from the merchant
class from the worker class any class of life people came from they were folded in and they had equal
role status importance position there and it must have been quite remarkable
in the ancient world to come from a place where there were these social divisions and come together
into community where those divisions had evaporated and people live together without seeing those distinctions
and um so um i'm going to read a little bit more
from here
for whom name and clan ascribe to one are designation in the world having
originated by convention they are ascribed here and there here
again this uh this insight into there's nothing in that in the natural world in terms of
status and positions and places of people you know of people that uh
is inherent but these are designations and we know that in this you know that uh these horrible uh ways
of racism um the race in all kinds of ways was a designation was an invention
that then got kind of uh kind of such a solidified so strongly especially in the
united states that it's uh hundreds these hundreds of years of racism
difficult to shake off the the strength of these concepts these
designations and even people who we know now who consciously um
don't live by these designations there's a kind of and have inherited from a culture all kinds of unconscious and subliminal
ways in which um we still kind of live in this bifurcated societies of where there is
uh people are put in different positions and prejudice and bias is is a regular
experience for them one is not a brahmana by birth nor by
birth a non-brahmana by action one becomes a brahmana by action one becomes a non-brahmana
so that is how the wise see action as it really is seers of dependent origination skilled
in action and its result so skilled and dependent origination means
that they're really skilled in seeing how things occur and exist
independence on conditions that come together that there's nothing really inherent in
anything that um that is that doesn't change doesn't
disappear doesn't come and go and because of that they become skilled
in action the buddha was sometimes referred to
as a teacher of action because for the buddha was so important the
action was the way to liberation it kind of more and more refined kind of
action more more peaceful kind of action way of living that led to freedom but
action how we live is what defines in a sense and for the
the worth of our human being and and the most worthy human being are
those who live most ethically and and those are the ones he calls a
brahmana and then he goes on to say
by action the world goes around by action this generation of people spin
around sentient beings are are fastened
tied up by their actions
which is like the linchpin of a moving chariot
by the spiritual life by self-control and entertaining by this one becomes a brahmana
this is supreme brahminhood so i don't know how this sounds to some
of you i mean to me it's a little bit jarrings to put anyone you know claim that any
individual is his brahman is kind of more worthy than anybody else
and um but it's certainly a very powerful uh critique the buddha had on
the the the racism or the classism that existed
at his time and a very powerful teaching that
still resonates in india to this day among many people as a way of kind of
stepping away from the caste system in 1950s there was a doctor named benkar one of the few
people who in my studies when i was younger i thought had the
moral stature or moral integrity or something to be critical of
mahatma gandhi gandhi was one of my heroes so it's a big thing to say that a bed car is one of the few people that
well if he has a critique i i'll listen and he belonged to the uh back then the
untouchable class this lowest caste in india and in 1954 i think
after a big search for a religion that wouldn't promote this caste system that hinduism
seemed to have promoted india he landed on buddhism and he he did
these mass conversions of the untouchables into buddhism because buddhism was so clearly
buddha was so clearly breaking down these caste divisions
and he was emphasizing ethics and so as i said i feel a little
uncomfortable by this idea of the brahman but i love the idea that
you know to break down these divisions and to emphasize our ethical life or good ethics
life of harmlessness and dedication to not stealing and killing and lying as being a common ground
in which these divisions can break down and soften and rather than thinking of ourselves as
higher or better than anybody else because of that maybe it frees us from thinking
in any kind of higher lesser language at all
but rather to have kind of simplicity and openness and to respect anyone
or to be able to look on everyone as a friend supporting everyone to kind of
maybe discover that in our hearts in our core deep inside is an ethical nature
a life that wants a heart that wants to live harmlessly and that all the ways that we
humans cause harm really come from more of a superficial surface area for life
that falls away when we settle deep down into ourselves
and uh and so that's part of the role for meditation to to shed this
you know superficial and settle into what's deep the place the origin for
a life of ethics goodness that dissolves where we can maybe
contribute to dissolving these painful divisions in our society
of some people being better than superior of more equal than
others it's needed in these times just as much as it's needed in the times of the buddha so thank you