so so [Music]
so for today's practice i'd like to bring in the theme
of something that we do at the end of every practice session
as the expression of meta so what if you have noticed at the end of every session
we dedicate the merit and what and the dedication of merit you
know sounds kind of big dedication of marriage whereas it's just a sense of you know when we say may
all beings be well may all beings be happy and basically offering
offering the goodness any any goodness that has been generated uh trusting that that there has been
goodness generated from our practice even if we um
judge it to be shoddy oh my mind was distracted i i wasn't really here i was
only mindful for one split second but trusting trusting that even sitting
uh first for mindfulness for a split second or just sitting just just the act of coming together and sitting
in the community cultivating and for those who listen to
the audio dharma later for example or any form of practice this this this practice that we do this
cultivation that we do trusting trusting that there is goodness here that there is goodness generated that we're
aligning our lives with goodness and then when we trust that
what does dedicating merit really do well one is
that it it uh connects us with that
um goodness with reaffirming that yes there is goodness even if i was sleepy even if
the body was in pain today that there was goodness but just coming together
coming or coming sitting and practicing there is goodness so it reaffirms that
when we dedicate the merit at the at the end and we share it with others so it
reaffirms goodness our own goodness it's a sense of trust a sense of
confidence confidence in our own goodness which is beautiful it's it's a reaffirmation of
of our own goodness and
another dimension another aspect of this cultivation this dedication of merit
this dedication of goodness that we trust has been generated
is an act of generosity it's an act of generosity
instead of oh okay i'm doing my self-improvement project oh i'm getting
calmer i'm getting better i'm getting kinder eye there's an act of generosity oh i share
this goodness i don't just keep it for myself i acknowledge the interdependence
of all beings i share it with everyone else made serve may be
of benefit maybe of service to my awakening and all being's
awakening and their happiness and well-being so so it's an act of generosity and in that act of generosity
it's also an act of meta it's an act of kindness we're just
sharing this goodness like ah here's here you go all beings everywhere
i'm sharing my goodness i trust there is goodness number one number two i i share
it generously with all of you yay love to you all it's like a love note to
all beings everywhere yay here is my goodness i share it with you yay
as a blessing so in that way this this um
dedication of merit is such a beautiful act it's really an act of generosity an
act of meta an act of trust and confidence also in our goodness so
there's so many dimensions in in this and i wrote a little article which showed up
in lions roar some years ago so later uh i'll send a pointer i'll i'll
ask neil to send a pointer about this uh this sharing of merit so
so so here for our practice today
tapping into trusting that there is goodness sharing it with as an act of meta
and generosity with others and i want to bring one more aspect here
today into today and that is and this is something that i learned
from a a good friend of mine uh who's been a
monk and pride has practiced in asia for
four decades almost and and
when when he did the dedication of merit and kind of traditionally in the buddhist
censors that the um dedication started with dedicating the
goodness to people to our benefactors to our parents to people who have supported us who have
been kind to us in any way well basically our benefactors whether they're alive or whether they
have passed away and there's and also just to say that connects with
my culture the persian culture there's this idea of generating merit and
sharing it with the deceased and i know it's the same way in japanese culture and many other cultures around
the world so sharing it with our benefactors and
then sharing it with other beings in in in
concentric circles opening more and more with more generosity
so so with all of that we'll bring
these into our practices of metta today
so let's begin let's formally begin our sitting sitting
ah and landing
blending in this body
in this moment in time
feeling the connection of our toes
our feet with the earth
i am here i am alive in this moment in time
connected rooted to the earth
feeling your sitting bones your bottom on the cushion
on the chair
letting attention awareness
greet the body
create the bottom of the feet your bottom and the cushion
your hands touching each other or your lap
and the sensations of the breath in the lower abdomen
calming soothing
here
just simplicity
of awareness knowing knowing
this body sitting and breathing
trusting trusting
the goodness of being here now aligning
our awareness with our intentions trusting in the
goodness whatever is present
trusting this connection
is connecting to ourselves
connecting to awareness trusting
i'd like to invite you as you remain
embodied connected aware awareness
connecting holding the sensations of the body of the breath
bring to mind bring to heart bring to heart
bring to body
and appreciation
for your practice
no matter how short or how long it's been
the fact that you are on this path of cultivation
regardless of how self-critical part of you wants to be
thank you not now self-criticism
thank you not now but really seeing
feeling with your heart your practice
over time [Music] as an act of service
as an act of goodness cultivating goodness
cultivating peace
cultivating non-reactivity
cultivating friendliness care
for yourself for others for the world
cultivating awareness presence
cultivating goodness non-suffering
cultivating non-suffering to serve you this being who is yourself
to serve others bringing to heart
appreciation
for this goodness accumulated cultivated
like a garden planting seeds you've planted so many
seeds
some of them you can see the flowers
oh yes i'm less reactive in these situations
i'm kinder in these situations i am more free in these situations
and so many seeds you've planted in this garden
which are germinating in their own time trusting trusting
all the seeds
yes there's always more planting to be done cultivating our garden
and yet appreciating the goodness of what has been planted
trusting yes there is goodness here there is goodness here there is goodness
here trusting the goodness
and sharing with generosity trusting the goodness
and sharing with appreciation [Music]
the goodness with appreciation
first to the benefactors
of your life those who supported
you been kind to you
whether alive or deceived sure let's start with those who are no
longer in the world
as if you were giving them flowers from your garden
knowing that the more flowers you share with generosity with metta
the more flowers grow [Music] the more you share the more there is
the act of giving sharing appreciating helps the
flowers grow
and then appreciating all benefactors in your life
which could also include friends family all loved ones
sharing your gift of menta your gift of goodness with them
as if saying thank you thank you
i love you or whatever version works for you
thank you i care for you
thank you i wish you well
my heart is shares its affection
its care with you
giving and receiving
knowing that gratitude appreciation helps your garden grow
the garden of your heart giving meta
further helps your garden
[Music] girl
you're welcome to lean into the appreciation
of the benefactors or lean into
sharing your goodness your meta generously with them
or lean into one with the in-breath lean into the other with the outer breath you
decide what's best for you
and now opening opening up
from benefactors friends family
to all beings all beings
as if your garden as if this garden of goodness of your
heart as if it could
feed or support the whole world as if it were a vegetable garden
and the more you gave away the more would
automatically grow immediately so the more you gave away the more generosity
the more goodness you gave away may all beings
be well be happy be healthy
have ease have safety the more you give away goodness
ah the more goodness
becomes available in your heart in your garden
sharing trusting there is abundance in your heart
trusting there is abundance even if it may not be readily visible right now trusting there
is more abundance in your being
in your own goodness in your own divine
buddha nature generously offering it to all beings everywhere
sharing your goodness
may my goodness be of service
in ways i can and cannot imagine to others
with age and breath each out breath
trusting trusting there is goodness within breath
the out breath sharing it far and wide
with generosity with kindness for all beings
and for the last minutes of this practice period
appreciating that we showed up we practiced
as well as it was available to us without judging practice
it was what it was we tried we showed up
we aligned our actions with our intentions as much
as it was possible so appreciating the goodness generated
from this practice period trusting trusting
that we've planted seeds seeds were planted
and sharing sharing this goodness that we have cultivated together
right now just now sharing
the merits the beauty the goodness
of it freely generously offering it
as our offering to all beings everywhere dear beings
i offer to you my goodness
my intentions my cultivation
throwing confetti over the whole planet earth
sharing freely here's my goodness
may it be of service may be of service in ways
i can and cannot imagine
may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you all thank you for your practice
so we have time we turn to reflections
to observations to questions another way that you share your practice
with others and many times it has been mentioned in
this community in the sangha when someone shares something it's it's
inspiring for others whether it's a question whether there's a challenge you have or there's something you realized
your mind found a new way to work with something so
you're welcome to raise your zoom hand or type your reflections in chat if you
type them to everyone i'll read your name if it's just to me i will read
only the reflection not your name so so what did you discover
bill says thank you nikki this was very moving thank you bill
would you like to say more and he would love to hear more if you're willing don't feel like you're put on the spot
but if you're willing you're welcome to say more if you like what what came up
for you um i i i was concerned that when you mentioned
about focusing on people that are no longer there that it would maybe get out of hand it got emotional
but it you know i didn't have a true meltdown so that's good um
but it was it just it's very emotional experience it was good so thank you
thank you bill yeah thank you for sharing that in what you shared i i hear a connecting
and a heart opening experience of appreciation especially with those who are deceased which can sometimes become
overwhelming with grief but in this case it didn't sound like okay it was emotional but oh it was more supported
with meta and appreciation instead of the grief and sadness that's what i'm hearing
powerful beautiful bill lovely great that's a great opening in that
direction to connect with that lovely thanks for sharing that
yeah yeah oh nice and reflection coming
appreciation that i was needing this time for reflection one of you says
um there uh oh i see a couple of hands okay vimel please
so i lost my wife to cancer 16 months ago
at the beginning of the pandemic two weeks into the lockdown so she's pretty much on my mind all the
time but today i brought her into focus
to thank her for 44 years together i thanked her parents
i thanked my parents so it was fairly emotional
thank you vimo thank you for sharing
thank you
hmm i take a pause and just let
let vimel's reflection land thank you
thank you
abraham please
thanks um of course it's easy to go to people that
were very supportive that one has a warm connection with
especially in childhood and things like that then it's easy to send loving kindness to them but what surprised me
was how easy it was to send loving kindness to people who had been difficult in my
childhood or in my younger life um people i'd had very contentious
situations with and it was easy and i was grateful for that
thank you abraham ah i feel so much joy as you as you say
this my heart feels a lit with mutita with vicarious joy for you
for your practice to be in a place that this is easy wow beautiful what what grace what grace
really what beauty thank you so much for sharing that yeah
thank you touched barbara please
i appreciated the image that of the garden and
the flowers that you give away instantly replenish and grow in your garden and
they're more and more um that uh resonates with me is beautiful
thank you barbara i appreciate you highlighting the the imagery because sometimes
imagery can really help us again we sometimes it doesn't but sometimes it can really work
in ways to as well as metaphor there's something about embodiment of these experiences
that we have that oh flowers we give flowers to people as an expression of thanks of kindness of just like oh yes
and oh no need for a sense of scarcity there's more
sweet thank you thank you barbara thank you two more reflections that have cuffed me
scattered mine today appreciate your permission at the end to have whatever experience
we had peace arrived somehow anyway yay beautiful beautiful
and another reflection my best friend is in hospice so it was a sensitive contemplation for me too
thank you for that reflection yeah
yeah and for me also i'll share with you that from me also was a
touching tender reflection today um someone
who was dear to me in the benefactor in
in some ways passed away i got news of them passing away and it brought up all the
connections so as i was bringing them and so many beings who've
um yeah thanking them and offering my practice my goodness
to these beings who have passed on so tender sensitive beautiful and here we
are still alive with agency in this world so
so dear ones dear sangha dear sangha let us turn
let us turn now to practice in small groups with one another holding
ourselves holding each other tend and tenderly especially today
especially tenderly today with this practice that we have done
um and starting as always with 15 seconds
of silent compassion silent meta compassion for ourselves for others
and sharing as much or as little as you like about your practice
supporting each other holding each other we don't do this practice alone as you know
we support each other um so see what needs to be held for you
and what needs to be held for others these beautiful beings who have their
own gardens their own flowers so
created the rooms and now they are open take care of yourself and each other
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back and uh we have a couple minutes for
reflections violet please
hi nikki hi everyone hi um in our group we talked a bit about
fear that arises during this practice so when
so this idea of like giving love and i don't know like this garden that keeps producing flowers or this infinite
source of love that you can keep giving and it doesn't run out but when i am trying to
cultivate that and other people in my group also had this experience this like very raw fear comes up in
terms of like this is not a good thing to do this is not a wise thing to do to give your heart
in this way this is unsafe this is not good and yeah just a lot of like fear and
terror that comes up so i was wondering like where do you find
like stability and safety in the practice like when you're sort of opening your heart in this big way for
the whole world yeah yeah so
thank you first of all thanks so much for bringing this up and and um
from the reflection reflection from your group especially um
so so when the sense of primo you know the sense of fear comes up that this is this
is not mean um in that case what i would suggest actually working with it
with the ways different two different ways one is the ways we work with with fear
with uh with meta right because actually meta is an antidote to fear so some
comforting yourself said some it's okay sweetie it's okay it's safe it's all
right it's all right so making your fear feel safe instead of pushing the fear
away or trying to push through it like i'm gonna do this because then the fear doesn't
feel safe or acknowledged it will just throw a tantrum so it becomes rather difficult
to do the practice so acknowledge the fear it's okay sweetie it's all right it's okay it's okay
and and and turning the meta to yourself so there's enough stability to then like
okay there's more stability there's more trust it's okay and then tap dipping your toes into the practice
again in this way you can expand further and further and further so that at some point maybe the fear comes up but it's
not believed it's like it's okay sweetie you can be here it's all right for your darling you can be here too and and
there can be a trust in the abundance both of them can be together so little by little but definitely not
trying to push through the fear but trying to see the fear of just being kind kind to yourself kind of here and
not necessarily believing it it's it's you know when the child that has a
tantrum you you comfort it and you don't say well you're just having a tantrum like get up and
you know go out playing like oh sweetie i know this is hard darling it's okay sweetheart but yet you're older wiser
you know that the sky isn't falling right but at the same time you are very
kind and compassionate to the child who's having a tantrum so with the same attitude does that make sense
violet yeah so send the meta to the fear and then eventually
can hold the fear and abundance at the same time and at some point i think
the fear will will be laid will be laid over time but
but for now yes holding the fear with metta and i'd love
to hear more uh if as you practice with this i'd love to hear what comes up for
you and and what and others too to to navigate this
yeah but not turning away thank you thanks yeah
so so one last question over time but i just want to say so is the fear seen as
protective and welcomed as part of mecca not so much it's not
it's not you know it's it's um so i wouldn't see it as a part of metta
but i would see it again as a part of us part of our patterning
that's having a little tantrum so it's it's not necessarily a supportive
helpful aspect of of our psychology in that way i think
that's i think that's what your question is but for perhaps for scarcity in the past or or fear in the past uh something
that arises anyway i feel like this is a much bigger
um conversation and we're already over time so maybe we'll we'll come back to this
later everyone maybe we'll come back to this so
so so i'll stay tell you what i'll stay a few minutes extra tonight
how about that i'll say a few minutes extra for anyone who wants to stay uh after we're going to close formally
but i'll stay afterwards if anyone wants to continue and discuss this so thank you all for showing up for your practice
may all beings be well may all beings be happy including ourselves
thanks everyone