so hello everyone and welcome to our meditation together
and um
i appreciate all the chats and the greetings very warm
warm very heartening to come here and see them all
so um you know the theme this week is uh the karmic stream and the dharmic stream
and the two are
related and what i'd like to emphasize for this meditation
is that one of the one of the physical ways of
seeing the manifestation of karma or feeling the impact of karma
is in our in physical tension uh
most as i won't say all most forms of
physical tension that we have is a consequence of the karmic
activities of the mind the way we hold on to our ideas our
thoughts our resistances our aversions
and and so as we
relax the body then the more relaxed we become
while we stay alert and clear then that makes room for the dharma
stream to flow the more tense we are the more we obscure it or
lock it from view or or block the stream from flowing
so so part of the advantage of relaxing
is it opens up and allows something to flow something to move through us
something gentle and peaceful something that shows us
the possibility of living with ease with freedom with calm with
peace with equanimity uh all these things that are kind of
that clear the channels clear the obstructions from the flow of
life so to relax at the beginning of meditation
is doing much more than just preparing for meditation it's
beginning to shift the karmic stream so that that
so it doesn't interfere with the development of meditation and the development of that dharma
stream so assuming a
meditation posture
and maybe rocking back and forth a bit
and side to side and maybe even forward and backwards
rotating around partly to relax but partly also to kind of
feel your way into your body until you find a posture
that feels balanced aligned alert
and part of the advantage if you're sitting upright part of the advantage of that for relaxing
is that an upright sitting posture has more room for the body the shoulders
to relax and soften if we're collapsed in some way or scrunched over
it makes relaxing more difficult deep relaxation more difficult
sometimes to relax deeply it take has to take a while maybe weeks or months
to build up a little strength in the torso too so the strength holds us upright
and allows for this deeper letting go
gently closing your eyes
and scanning through the body to see what adjustments can you make now
to let the body be more at ease is there any
tensions or holdings in the muscles that you can relax
maybe in the belly
maybe the shoulders maybe the face
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
let the breaths be long that it gets your mind's attention
let the exhale be long enough so that your mind now gets interested in
breathing more than interested in its thoughts
and as you exhale can you relax deeply inside
and then letting the breathing return to normal
in a way of attuning yourself aligning yourself with your breathing
every time you exhale for the next little while relax gently relax parts of your body
maybe feeling a part on the inhale and relaxing on the exhale
maybe relaxing the muscles around the face
maybe the muscles around the neck maybe there are micro relaxations that
are possible
staying with the rhythm of breathing in and out and as you exhale
relaxing the shoulders
relaxing down the arms into the hands those hands become soft
look at the loose hands you might even kind of
move your fingers slightly to loosen them up there
on the exhale softening the shoulders
and don't expect that you can relax completely just as
far as it'll go even if it's a micro relaxation
as you exhale soften relax the chest
and relax deep in the heart
soften the belly
and down your legs if there's any holding there can you release it
and is there any physical tension
that comes from some mental tension you have mental strain pushing
pressure the pressure to think
and as you exhale relax that as well
and then to now settle into your breathing
as you exhale relax the exhale
relax the parts of the body involved in exhaling
as you inhale
can you slightly allow the inhale to be softer
gentler
relaxing softening
and if you find yourself thinking and drifting off in thought
let go and as you let go let go back into your breathing
and let yourself be centered
with breathing at the center centered on breathing
and with all the relaxation we've done maybe some of the body will feel
the nice flow of energy or nice softness or
and so we're breathing now within a field
that's more relaxed softer flowing
one breath at a time
and as we come to the end of this meditation
the ability to stay relaxed to be calm can be part of our gift that we
provide others if we go through the world anxious
distressed upset in a sense we're teaching the world
that this is a useful way to be
if we go through the world at ease or calm or
confident in our ability to meet the world
we have a very different effect on those around us we see this particularly the case with
young children and their parents if the parents are anxious it teaches
the children that the world is a frightening place
and to know that we can care for ourselves
care for challenges and difficulties so much better if we say come
if we're able to stay relaxed
and to offer that to others as a gift that there's a different way of being in
the world that is not anxious is not upset and distressed dismayed
be the kind of person that people relax around feel safe around
and may it be that through this meditation practice we do that our presence in the world
is a gift to others it doesn't have to be so conscious
or intentional if we're calm if we're relaxed
just who we are
may it be that this practice we do through the practice we do that we're
able to make this world a better place may we support the possibility
for all beings to be happy
all beings to be safe all beings
to be peaceful and all beings to be free
and being relaxed is more likely to support that
than being tense
so [Music]
thank you
so continuing now with this second talk on the karmic stream and the dharmic stream
these two major ways in which our lives can unfold and move what moves through us
the word uh with these words karma dharma kind of built into the word you get a
very different feeling for it um karma has the meaning of action
that's a literal meaning for for for for karma action and with the connotations
of making something like constructing something and uh dharma in its root in its uh
etymological root comes from the me the meaning of to support
so um the karma implies that we're doing and and
dharma suggested their support
and and the dharma stream can provide a tremendous support for us
the karma stream uh the value of that has a lot to do
with the nature of the actions we do and um so um
and so one of the ways of understanding this uh karma stream the karmic stream
is that it has a lot to do with constructing um that
when we act in a certain kind of way we're building creating constructing
our response our reactions our character our personality our habit habits
our dispositions all these ways are being kind of we're contributing we're making something
happen and it takes a work the karmic street a karmic stream
requires effort on our part we have to engage in creating it
uh and sometimes people are weary and tired from all the constant doing and doing and doing that
they do living this karmic stream of actions and reacting
acting and reacting the dharma stream
because it succumbs more of a support it it it doesn't require the same kind of
action there might be things we do in a sense movements we make things we say
but it doesn't come from this impetus this forcefulness of um of making something
it maybe comes more from something that's being expressed rather than holding something up
we're being held up and um and so the uh the um
so the the karma stream is uh tends to be much more volitional
intentional like this is where we're just pretty kind of disposed to do something to make something happen
and and we can see that in our thinking
and there may be an easier way to kind of see it is if you use the principle that
if you're thinking about anything that's not in the present moment
your mind is uh is constructing the memory the fantasy
the future and in that construction there's an impetus there's a maybe even a
compulsion to have something happen to want something to not want something to like
something not like something and and that impetus
that creation and that force behind it sets
kind of creates the nature of that action and the nature of the action creates
what impact it has in the future so if we act with greed
um and that's kind of you know that what goes behind the thinking and then the acting
that has a very different uh creates a very different momentum in our
lives than if we act out of generosity if we chronically act out of aversion it
creates a very different momentum in our lives than if we act out of love
and so to think of karmic stream is something that's being construed always being
constructed built and sometimes in english we think of karma
as the results of our actions and the in pali it's a different word vipaka
or that means the results the emphasis on karma the buddhist
emphasis on karma is on the act of constructing and so we see in the teachings of the
buddha less interested in understanding why something happens
you know something happened and now can it must be my karma in the past people say
that's not very interesting for the practitioner of the dharma rather what's interesting is
given what's happening no matter what it's whatever is happening what is the action
reaction with which we're meeting that or responding to that
the focus is on what we're doing in the present not the reason why the present is happening
that's valuable at times to look at the reasons in the background but for to really get to the heart of this
the karma teaching is to learn how to
act differently in the present moment
where the where the choice is to construct things a little differently
and and so they had what's useful is that if you're interested in
the dharma the dharm extreme if you're interested in freedom if you're interested in this phenomenal
inner goodness that comes with the dharma stream that
you want to act accordingly you want to act and do things that support that possibility that lead in that direction
and so generosity ethics kindness compassion
um equanimity letting go these are all actions that are constructing kind of a better self a
better disposition a better kind of stream of momentum in us
that uh is supportive of the dharm extreme
and so to some degree uh if we're living in the karmic world where we're choosing
the particular actions that we want to live by that those we have a sense are wholesome beneficial
useful and we're learning to let go of those which are not useful it turns out that all the unuseful ones
the ones that are create a negative impact on us
they all come with tension of some kind or other and that tension has an ongoing momentum
that compulsion has an ongoing momentum in our lives when we do
beneficial karma it might have tension it might not it might have a compulsion it might not
and that's a very important distinction because if doing good things is done with
tension the results are mixed if we do good things without compulsion
without tension the results tend to be better and the results here we're talking about
not necessarily the results out in the world but the impact it has in us inside
the impact in in the ongoing momentum disposition um
that through which we act and respond to the world
the dharma stream is mostly something that we allow
we don't construct it it's mostly getting out of the way it's clearing this the blockage in the
stream um and the karma stream we're learning to turn
off the fire hose in the dharma stream we're removing the
the obstacles that keeps the stream from flowing
and uh and the um and uh and then uh this um
because we're not acting with tension then uh dharma stream is to learn to relax
deeply and we're letting go and if we're not acting out a compulsion or attention
we're not really going to be creating this negative karma instead we'll create
instead will allow for the native goodness inside of us
the love the generosity the caringness the the kindness
there's all this wonderful good qualities we have including wisdom
including kind of strong wisdom and strong compassion and strong
adherence and dedication to the truth as strength that is
stable and strong partly because it's not agitated or fragile that the way that tension can
cause and so um and so uh what's interesting is that
when we do the kind of dharmically positive activity
actions that are part of the construction process
conditioning process that that it aligns itself
with this goodness that's inside and there's start and it becomes a time when there's a transition
from what we're doing to what we're allowing what we have to contribute
to what we are and so this inner goodness
as as we do good in the world do good for ourselves it tends to
support the awakening or the freedom or the expressivity of the dharma stream inside of us
and the dharma stream is manifested in many ways
but it's manifested with a tremendous confidence and trust
in joy and tranquility and happiness
an ability to be settled and focused in equanimity
and ultimately in freedom and so
one of the things we learn this is a very important distinction between this dharma stream and the
karmic stream because it helps us to see that we don't have to
always be constructing our world constructing our responses to the world we're not the work of reacting and
acting and doing and thinking and one of the primary constructive activities people are doing
is through their thinking it's a lot of work and thinking and it's constructing it's manufacturing
ideas fantasies stories interpretations of what's there and it's a tremendous burden
if it's just done incessantly and compulsively and it's not necessary to do as much as
most people think the authority behind our thinking can be questioned
and it's a little bit like um someone uh maybe you live in your you know someone lives in a home for years
and they've accumulated a lot of things and furniture and stuff and they live in this home
and it turns out that there's a wall down the middle of the home and half the home
they didn't know was there and then someday someone takes down the wall and they realize wait a minute
there's a whole second half of the home so to understand this distinction between
the karmic stream and the dharma stream is can be kind of like aha
oh there's a whole second half of how to live you'll still live in the karma stream to
some degree but hopefully you live it with wisdom and clarity and just understand how it works
and there's this whole other room to live in that gives you breathing room and space and freedom
and that's the other half that's often missing for people who live only in the
karmic world which is most people and so discover the dharma world the
dharma stream is a great gift and a great
it was just a wonderful thing so um
so we'll continue over these next days on this theme and hopefully as we continue you'll get a better sense of
this distinction and how to practice and work with it thank you very much