good morning welcome to the insight meditation center
hi i am flu schrader the guest teacher of your teacher gil frank style and my good friend
he and i and paul haller another zen center teacher have been incredibly enjoying a
three-week intensive called the harmony of zen and vipassana
and this is our last day so it's nice to have you all here um and
we'll start with some meditation and then i'll give a short talk
so i'm wondering how many of you remember a few years back a story about 12 wild wars
you know it was the name of a team of soccer players and their young coach who were rescued from a dark
water-filled cave in thailand you know a lot of attention was paid at the time under the long planning process
that resulted in their rescue including teaching them how to swim how to use scuba gear and all of that
the part that was deeply engaging for the world press was the technique and and the danger and that
was and you know the fear but at the same time very little attention was paid
that i could tell in the mainstream reporting to the fact that the coach of these boys
ekkapol chanthawong had spent most of his young life from the age of 12 until 22 as a thai
forest monk in a somewhat obscure article called how buddhist meditation kept the thai boys
column in a cave they reported that at the moment that the boys were found they were sitting
there calmly no one was crying or anything and it was astonishing
the article then explained that ekkapol their coach had taught the boys to meditate to keep
them calm and to preserve their energy through their nine days of pitch black isolation
on the day of their rescue each of the boys did an hour of meditation with their teacher before being brought out of the cave you
know one by one as i think we all remember the article included a cartoon that had
been circulated in thailand showing ekkapol with a lap full of tiny wild boars sitting peacefully in
upright meditation just like the buddha that he had been taught to be
so with that story in mind i'd like to offer all of us an opportunity to sit together for a few minutes
remembering those boys and their teacher and also remembering one of the rescuers who died in his effort to help save
those boys he too saman guna is honored and embraced
within this warmly human story think we all know that marketing a
product such as meditation is such a challenge for us you know as it was for the buddha with
so little to show for itself you know we put us not only just sit together a lot
we also talk about just sitting together a lot and we talk in order to encourage others
to give it a try you know as it says on this clever bumper sticker that i've seen in recent
years don't just do something sit there
so only by that something that we call nothing can we discover for ourselves how an
hour of silence sitting even in the darkest of times and the darkest of places
might literally save our lives or even if our lives are not in the end to be saved the quality of
the time we have left might be brighter sweeter and more dear
so please in the time we have left find a comfortable upright sitting posture for yourself
you know lengthen your spine all the way up from the base drop your shoulder blades back and down
allowing the chest to open more fully align your ears with your shoulders and
your nose with your navel take a deep breath inhale
and exhale again and again
as you have your entire life
now rock your body right and left it should feel very good something i
really enjoy each morning is this small detail of kind of stretching
the ligaments around the spine and the neck
also helps to find upright you know sort of like a plumb line that comes eventually settles
into a steady and immovable sitting position
and allow yourselves to just sit you know like the upright wild boars that we
truly are
hey
okay
uh
hmm
[Applause] hmm
so good morning again for those of you who have just joined my name is foo schrader i am the abbess
at green gulch farms and center in marin county california you're all welcome to visit
if you can and as many of you know i have been a guest of gil fransdale your
teacher during this three-week intensive meditation intensive that gail myself and another
good friend paul heller have been offering called the harmony of zen and vipassana
so i can safely say that this has been a wonderful way to share the dharma with old friends who
for a long time now have been intent on following the path the buddha path together
you know with all of you so this is the last day of our intensive we
close tomorrow with the talk that gil and i are going to share on the zen center website and you're
very welcome to join us having spent these last four days of the
intensive talking about right conduct sheila and about the bodhisattva val
and the 16 bodhisattva precepts this morning i want to share with you a story
of an actual bodhisattva the ones the story that brought me closer into
practice and find by the decision to stay
so when i first came to zen center many decades ago now i was told there would be a full moon
ceremony on the roof of the beginner's mind temple in san francisco where i had been going to practice
meditation for about a year i thought the ceremony was pretty strange and
it was also very rigorous there are about 29 full vows full prostrations that take
place from the beginning of the ceremony to the end and a lot of chanting and
as it turned out the full moon ceremony is one of the oldest of rituals that has been continuously
practiced since the time of the buddha the monks who practiced off in science
in solitary meditation when the moon was full they could come together that was like their
clock so they could join together in a clearing and offer their confessions and repentance
and promise to do better so the monks and the nons and the laity
actually would gather four times in the old days uh each of the phases of the moon
but the full moon uh was the one that was most most common and we've recently done that
as well and it continues to this day in order for us also to reflect on our
practice and to recommit ourselves to the holy life and in particular to
the 16 bodhisattva precepts the three refuges the three pure precepts and the ten
grave or clear mind precepts so back to
years ago on that particular evening upon the roof of the zen center the person who was leading the ritual began
by telling us a story from a collection called the jataka tales in which the buddha's
former lives in both human and animal form are recounted
these stories are particularly popular with children and that humans and animals in the stories are
virtuous and brave and their leader often gives their own life to save the lives of others
just as salman guna had done in thailand about five years ago that leader
in a future life turns out to be none other than shakimuni buddha so often the jataka tales include an
extensive cast of characters who get into all kinds of trouble whereupon the bodhisattva intervenes to
resolve all the problems and bring about a happy ending this is the kind of stories i think we all like
best so here's the one that altered the course of my own life
once long long ago a monkey an otter a jackal and a rabbit resolved to
practice charity on the day of the full moon believing that a demonstration of great
virtue would earn them a great deal of merit when an old man entered
the forest begging for food the monkey gathered fruit from the trees and the otter
collected fish while the jackal pilfered a pot of milk curd from a nearby farmhouse
having called out in a not so very loud voice does this belong to anyone well the
rabbit on the other hand who knew only how to gather grass felt very sad and having nothing to offer the old man
until realizing that she could offer her own body by throwing herself onto
the fire that the old man had built to keep himself warm and just as the rabbit leapt into the
air the old man revealed himself to be shakra the lord of the gods
who then saves the rabbit friend by transforming the flames into lotus petals chakra being deeply
touched by the rabbit's virtue uses a nearby mountain to form the likeness of the rabbit
on the face of the moon for all to see it's said that the lunar image is still
draped in the smoke that arose when the rabbit cast herself into the flames
i don't know how many of you have looked at the moon to see the rabbit i think mostly in the west who are
taught to see an old man's face but the rabbit's there it's quite a wonderful full body
the ears the haunches and next time the moon is full take a look see if you can find the
rabbit this story of the bodhisattva giving her life for the welfare of another
had a big impact on me at the time and when my life it had really kind of worn out trying to
get something or somebody who would make me truly happy
so it was a remarkable idea to me that giving could be the true source of happiness for a human being
you know like me rather than getting so the next step was to try and
understand what it means to truly give alongside the bodhisattva vow and
precepts are a set of six practices for training a bodhisattva for a life devoted
to the welfare of others and among these practices is dhana paramita the perfection of giving
the first of what are called the six perfections so these six perfections can be thought
of as the kind of bodhisattva training program a program that was explained by the buddha in
very simple language so that almost anyone could understand and practice them so these six
giving the first morality or ethics right conduct the second patience
enthusiasm concentration and wisdom so they can also be thought
of as antidotes or antibodies to what the dalai lama has called our pathological emotions
greed hate and delusion so giving is what conquers greed
patience conquers hate and wisdom conquers delusion the other three
perfections involved in transforming our afflictive emotions are the perfection of ethics of morality the perfection of
enthusiasm we all need that and the reflection of concentration
so all six perfections are packaged together in a particular order so that each in turn supports the next
for example giving supports ethics as in giving your word or giving your fair share and ethics
supports patience as in for example waiting patiently for your turn
or waiting for negative feelings to subside before you speak or take action
the perfection of patience supports the perfection of enthusiasm by helping us to find a balanced response
to the arising of our human passions our likes and our dislikes
the perfection of enthusiasm in turn supports our ongoing commitment to a life dedicated to the well-being of
others a life concentrated on the practice of the six perfections
a life of becoming who we are truly meant to be bodhisattvas hard at work for the
well-being of the entire world so such a life is manifested in the story that i shared
with you of how the image of the bunny got onto the moon and although we can't really see a vow
or an intention to live by vowing such a vow informs everything that we do
in our life and in society it informs how we work
and the kind of work that we do and our collective effort to take care of it all so work as practice
which is easy to say but it's not so easy to do learning to engage in work as practice
is at times even harder than the work itself this is something we specialize in at
greengulch farm there's lots of work and yet as the buddha famously said
enlightenment is the path is what we do and the path is enlightenment in other
words awakening is a direct reflection of how we are living our life each and every day
the mind that is distracted lustful or hateful can't see the path of liberation
right before your eyes and yet the buddha hangs out with minds that are
distracted hateful and lustful in order to show us the way of kindness and generosity
selflessness and peace the very thing i think we are trying to do here as well
you know hang out with our minds and together show the way to peaceful abiding
together and for zen master dogen the founder of
my tradition called sotozen awakening is seated meditation is the bodhisattva
precepts is learning the backward step that turns your light inwardly
is the practice realization of totally culminated enlightenment
so thank you all so much for your kind attention i've really been enjoying coming to be at gill's place
for this week so i wish you all the best and please take care and please enjoy sitting as much as you
can kevin if there any questions i'd be happy to respond sure um we actually have one from uh
um eric on from youtube he was wondering about the differences
between vipassana such a great question as we've been
talking about for three weeks you know it's so wonderful um you know we share the root we're all
disciples of the buddha you know whatever happened under that tree the morning he woke up and he
didn't really tell us too much other than something like i and all beings are enlightened at the same
time there was a non-dual realization
between what he saw the star and himself it wasn't separate it wasn't
outside of himself and neither was anything else so that's the foundation for buddhism
buddhism means awake for being awake so you know awake-ism
and zen passing are both devoted to awakening you know to what the buddha
saw and how he behaved so that's the other side i think one of the things i've enjoyed
looking at between zen and vipassana is vipassana clearly you know it's as gil
was saying it's retreat practice he teaches people who are on retreat so you can get really concentrated when
you're not doing anything else in the day we have sashings which are very similar i think those two
experiences for all of us are are pretty pretty close because you know human beings are
the same so sitting for a week uh paying attention to your mind is is
uh common ground uh maybe what's a little different and not different because of any reason
other than it's not the kind of teaching that of gil or
many of bakasana retreats don't actually you know take you outside and and do
some work together so zen is really focused on work practice a day of no work is a day of no food
what they said in china the monks couldn't just spend the day meditating they needed to feed
themselves it was a really different cultural climate so by the time buddhism got to china it
became very much ingrained in the activities of daily life and i think we spend a good deal of
our teaching time talking about how to work uh in a meditative you know with with the influence of your
meditation without falling into a kind of enchantment so that you can't actually cut the carrots you know some people
sometimes think cutting carrots in a meditative way is like really slow
you know we'd never get lunch out if that was so so we really oftentimes will put
somebody who's uh more you know seasoned cook on the opposite
side of the table from a new student who's going like this and then the person over there is you know is going like that so we're
trying to demonstrate that speed is not the issue it's focus
concentration like simone beals doing her routine you know she's concentrated and she's moving
so i think that combination of movement and meditation is what these two traditions emphasize
uh there's probably a lot more than that but that's what comes to mind
all right thank you yeah we've got a question
for you since you started practice did you ever leave the practice what precipitated leaving and what
brought you back oh that's good well i left because i adopted a baby
i didn't leave the practice i mean babysitting right uh i needed practice more than ever
having a little infant who was very tiny and kind of um you know she wasn't well she had
some issues at birth she's cerebral palsy and she's uh has other
issues that i don't need to go into but anyway she's fantastic she's going to be 28 next week and we'll be home she lives in
la she's great great human being so for a couple years i was home feeding
the baby doing things that you do when you have a young child um
and i don't think i stopped practicing i just wasn't going to the zendo for that time i was you know
work work practice and then what brought me back into the zendo i still lived in
the community i've been a resident there for 40 years so gratefully so um so i was able to go
back and take a a another leadership position when my daughter was old enough to sleep through
the night so anyway yeah i don't really think i've
taken a break i don't think there are breaks actually once you start to practice yeah and it's like what gill is taught
and i think is really brilliant entering the stream is you know entering the stream
or the current of a river and once you enter the current you're in a life of practice and that's
what stream mentoring really means i'm no longer driven by a life of karma
you know choice choosing whatever is my selfish view i'm actually streaming i'm in the
current of a life a vow of what i promised you know i made promises to live for the
benefit of others just like that story i told about the rabbit i liked that story i thought well i can do
that maybe i could give myself to something that i care about yeah so we never stop really
i do go on vacation
and one final question um the link uh for the saturday talks do you
know where people might be able to find that oh yeah uh zen center website
there's lots of stuff on there and it tells you just what to do what what buttons to push oh that's the san
francisco san francisco zen center yeah
lots of programs there too if you're interested in some of the things we're doing a lot of interesting things these days particularly around a
bipap community and inviting teachers of color and talking about the issues of our day which we have to
do of course great yeah that uh for everyone else here um that
is if you go to the san francisco zen center website it's under the calendar and then if you um look under saturday
may 8th uh so that's going to start at 10 a.m if i'm not mistaken yeah right yeah
okay well thank you very much thank you all uh please take care it's been it's been just wonderful to to know
you're out there even though i can't see you and the youtube people um
anyway many blessings