so welcome to our meditation session together and
and uh as i sit here reflecting on all of you
coming here and um and
thinking about um just all of us gathering i am aware
there's a gathering of our physical bodies we bring our bodies when we meditate
uh the our physical bodies are kind of the vehicle the important
vehicle for meditation practice and while you know it might be silly to say
there is no meditation without the body and to
care for this body to connect to this body to have the body at the center is uh
so important sometimes there's a tendency for many people to live in their minds and
their thoughts and their ideas and and it can create quite a
divide between the body and the mind the body is forgotten disconnected with and
we can kind of kind of nominally be aware that we have a body but to awaken in the body
to discover the body being more alive is is one of the great benefits and
possibilities of mindfulness practice so here we are with our bodies
as our bodies so being our bodies
following the lead of our body in establishing a posture that feels
appropriate that feels beneficial for being
centered and at ease if we can in this body
but not only at ease a posture that also allows the body to become more awake
more alive and to explore through the body
what it's like to live in this body to feel your sensations of body
and as a way of entering more deeply into this body
sometimes body is difficult place to be there can be pain and challenges of all
kinds but still to enter into it you might take a few long
slow deep breaths
where the torso is stretched expanded in the end of in-breaths
where the in-breaths begin deep in the body and there's an expansion outwards
and long relaxed exhale
where there's a coming together pulling in settling of this body
as you take these deeper breaths to quiet your thinking mind
notice how if you're thinking a lot about things even about the exercise
maybe there's a way it removes you a bit from feeling and sensing the body from the
inside and then letting the body feeling the breathing return to normal
and take a few moments to feel the simplicity of the body breathing
and even if you are still directing your breath unconsciously or unintentionally it's
okay just quietly familiarize yourself
to the body breathing
and then bring your attention to the top of your head the crown of the
head and as you exhale feeling the sensations
there soften relax the top of your head and
that kind of relaxing that is further settling into your body
and as if it's if there's a refreshing flow of water flowing from the top of
your head over your body out through your your through your head
let your attention settle and flow down to your head your face
and as you exhale to relax the head the face
the eyes
letting the flow of awareness down to your neck
the back of your neck
sides of your neck the front
as you exhale to relax and settle
the flow of attention down into your shoulders
allowing yourself to feel very simply any tension or holding in your shoulders not to make it
a problem but something to care about lovingly
and as you exhale whatever way you can soften and relax your shoulders
soften the shoulders
and the flow of awareness down into your chest ribcage front and back
and on the exhale settle further relax into your body into your torso
in the whole area of your solar plexus your diaphragm
relax soften
and then the belly soften the belly
as you exhale relax the smaller the back
relax the weight of your torso down into the pelvic cavity
all the way down to your sitting bones
and then to feel your legs the upper legs the thighs
softening relaxing any holding they might be there
tightening the flow of attention down into the
lower legs and feet and similarly relaxing softening
any ways that you might be holding and tighten the arms and the hands
as we relax tension maybe there's more feeling of flow of energy in the arms the hands
and then opening up the attention as wide as is easy for you throughout the body
maybe letting the thinking mind become quieter and stiller
to make more room for awareness to feel and sense discover the body
centered in the body
noticing if it happens how being pulled into
thoughts and fantasies is it pulling away from being centered
in the body
and then we'll sit quietly but breathing through the body with the body
connected to breathing within the body
as if the body
is the source of deep understanding
as if the body is the source
for freedom for being at home
for where we discover the path to peace
for these next minutes trusting the body breathing in the body with the body
through the body with the mind relaxing quieting
softening the mind to just breathe in this body
coming back to your body
and coming back again and again each time you return to settle deeper into it
be content to do so forever long
you can rest in the body awareness resting there
and then do it again
and then coming to the end of this sitting
once again is there more you can do for these last couple of minutes to rest
in your body
to center yourself in your body as is as if the source of
all things source of your feelings your thoughts your intentions
your experience of life begins here in the body deep in the body
and perhaps the resting in the body
is where is also the beginning
of love of kindness care
compassion
and to stay rooted in the body
when we have impulses for kindness and care and compassion
so we don't lose ourselves in the object of our care
we don't lose this connection to our
body
and turning your attention outward into the world
maybe in a sense turning your body inside out
to be present for this world of ours
while being rooted in the body
perhaps we can wish that whatever benefit that has come from
this practice that we share that benefit with others
in small ways big ways
that the benefits we experience are expressed in a care for this world
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we contribute
to bringing this planet into a kind of harmony
an ecological harmony where all beings can be well
so
as we begin this week the theme i had in mind is practicing in
our lives and then you could say that all of buddhism is about practicing
in our daily life in our ordinary lives in our lives and and certainly so many of the
teachings are completely connected and relevant to how we go about our
living our lives but the orientation i have for these talks
this week is for people who would like to
live a more dharmic life sometimes they consider it would be nice to go live in a retreat center or in a
monastery maybe for a while or find some way to live more
fully in the dharma and then maybe it's easy to do and
um in a daily life where there's work and family and busyness and things to do
so what is it that we can do so that we have you know dependent we can see that
receive some of the benefits that uh that a life that's absorbed in a
contemplative life absorbed in a renunciant life absorbed in a monastic life how could we
have some of those benefits in in ordinary lay life that we live in
so for that i want to talk about five different ways we can bring more practice into our lives or live more in
the dharma that i would like to believe is available to all of us and and to really pick these five areas
up that um you'd find tremendous benefit
of uh not only would you find the dharma the dharma would find you and you would
you could you'd create you allow yourself to be a receptive
receptacle for the dharma it might fill you in a
wonderful way so the first of these five is
to be more connected to your body to practice mindfulness of the body
to center yourself on your body and um is one of the things that uh
i delightfully and surprisingly discovered in practicing in different
buddhist traditions that one way or the other they seem the ones i practice seem to all
emphasize being grounded connected to your body sometimes it was not explicit but for
but there was a lot of the body was clear you had to bring it along and practice with your body
when i was practicing zen i don't know if there was a really
active discussion about mindfulness of the body but so much of the practice was embodied
you sat in a particular posture that really required you to be embodied to sit in the posture
if you were eating you did it in a way that was an embodied eating eating
when we eat when we ate more formally it was in practice we would walk in ways that encouraged
more embodiment and connection to our body we would when we were doing work we were
instructed to really put ourselves fully into it and be connected and involved in the
work being kind of absorbed in the work but in a way that our body was really there for it
and and so there was all this emphasis on just being in your body and i learned so much about being embodied
by working in the monastic kitchen when i was a zen student and really being present with my whole body
as best i could it wasn't always easy to um to be connected to
whatever physical work i was doing in the kitchen it was all physical work and so to do it with both hands full
body real connected to doing it absorbed in the physicality of it um you know for do i did it for a whole
year and and um and it really did wonderful things for me and teaching
me how to be in the world an embodied engaged way
the people would teach teach me when i was doing zen in america and also in japan to uh
to you know to do is things with my body enthusiastically
so not just the kind of i had a tendency maybe to kind of use one hand kind of be there for it part of my body
was not involved other things other thoughts and kind of half-heartedly do things
and that did not go over well in zen you had to be really there wholeheartedly and one way
that was emphasized a lot in japan was you always did things with two hands
and so if you picked up a pot of food or you picked up a tool or
if you gave someone a gift whatever it was you'd always do it with two hands so you were fully in it it feels
different to give someone a gift with two hands than to kind of just here here you go and kind of like give it
the only part of who you are but to do it fully um the um
i i love the the anjali the you know putting the hands together and
bowing because it brings you know these two sides of who we are in a sense the left and the right and
the coming all of us are involved that is different than shaking our hands
which is you know only part of us our our bodies involved and i think shaking hands is a wonderful
thing when people come back to do it again um but it has its own value and and
wonderfulness i don't want to diminish its value but uh there's also something valuable
but really coming together and offering kind of like all of ourselves in that greeting
in that respect and um and then to becoming more attuned to
the sensations of the body these sensations of our body are not senseless uh to to
feel like there's you know no sense and no meaning no value and being involved
with the census of the body in fact makes the body senseless we get
disconnected from the sensations but to value them because they are
the carriers of so much information they are the expressions of our
attitudes expressions of our emotions and feelings they are the expressions of our
reactivity and our response to what's happening in the world around us and there's layers and layers of
subtlety that we can be aware of when we're really connected in our body
if we're not so connected at all then just a little bit of connection to the body will
provide the early warning signals of feelings and sensations and attitudes and and information about
what's happening in the world around us that is often there before our thinking
mind is aware of it and uh the first sensations of anxiety the
first sensations of anger or for sensations of of love or
kindness or warmth towards someone there's all these different things that
the body sometimes comes through the body that if we're
busily thinking and wanting and reacting and being thinking about what's wrong
we don't really pick up and so i uh one zen teacher i studied with
talked about the body being an antenna and uh and the more your you tune yourself
to that antenna the more information you pick up and i would emphasize not just the antenna to what's the
information's outside of us our body but also what's inside and you know the the
you know if we're not really a divided being between the mind and the body
the body is a really rich repository of intelligence of responsivity of
feelings of emotions of information that's so helpful for our lives
so to spend more time uh being sensitive to the sensations sensing
what's happening in the body it begins kind of shifting the emphasis
from thinking that the mind is going to solve everything to allowing the body to participate
allowing the body to receive and experience and to help process what's going on
some of the difficult emotions we have can be well processed in the body if we allow the body to feel it can be
difficult sometimes we feel all these things more acutely and that can be painful in a sense
but there's an art to learning how to keep opening in the body opening the body in a wise way in a supported way in
every compassionate way that allows the body to support us to
become free to free up things to release things and part of that is because
any holding in the mind any attachment and clinging we have often gets expressed in the body
becoming tense becoming held with muscles being held in tight and and that tightness tends to numb the
body but as we become more aware of the body it tends to free the places of tightness
first we may become aware of all the tension we hold in our body but that's a stepping stone for the body
to begin to release releasing itself and open up and so the more we can practice you
being in our body when we do things and really being present and more we can become more
aware sensitive to the sensations of our body the feelings of our body what's going on in the body
that is a way of starting to live a more
dharmic life to let the dharma all the benefits of mindfulness and
and wisdom to begin kind of showing itself in being accompanying us through our body
through our life the less we're connected to our body the less the dharma accompanies us
through our life unless we're quite good at at the cognitive aspects of keeping in
mind and thinking about it and that can be useful but and some people maybe that's the primary
vehicle but for most people i think that the
tremendous benefit to being rooted in the body and connected to what's
happening in this body of ours and so if you would like to live
if you would like to avoid having to go and become a monastic and go live a monastic life where you're
going to full-time dharmic life if you would like to live a contempo contemplative life
a dharmic life in your ordinary everyday life then um your monastery is your body
and uh your temple is your body and so keep coming back
being in your body and then i'll continue on this theme tomorrow with a whole other
area that you can focus on if you like that's part of daily life
and in the meantime in these next 24 hours maybe you will
experiment give more emphasis on your body and what's happening there
and how you use it and the feeling sensations what's happening if you allow your body to be more in
receptive mode to feel all these sensations that we have
so i hope you enjoy um if not now i hope this mindfulness of
body will bring you to great enjoyment a great delight in having this physical
body thank you