so the topic continues to be the
13th step of the mindfulness of breathing observing one trains oneself
observing in constancy i will breathe in observing and
constancy i will breathe out just how the instructions are and this observing of
in constancy usually translated as impermanence
is really as i said yesterday is the core insight of insight meditation the core insight of
the buddha's teachings in the ancient texts and the definition of the buddha gave
repeatedly for wisdom wisdom is the perception of arising and passing the insight into
the arising and disappearing of phenomena that is noble and
penetrating and leads to the ending of suffering so
it's the experience the perception of seeing things arise and pass
that leads to liberation to awakening
and uh and so this side and constancy that you the way that in constancy is understood here
is um it is the uh it's defined as over in many
different words in the ancient language that are equivalent to the english arising and passing appearing and
disappearing and
things like that and it's hard to understand to appreciate
how valuable this is to have this experience until one experiences in a very deep
subtle quiet place in meditation that's really where this deep insight is
really it's really insight that works and it's very penetrating and noble awakening
when the mind is really ready for seeing that if an ordinary consciousness walking around the street
someone tells you just to notice the arising and passing a phenomena it probably won't stick it probably
won't be any sense of continuity with that resting in it just being open to it
because you have to take care of too many details walking on the street and figuring out what's going on and
and but in deep meditation to be really at rest and really able to
be centered in a receptive open observing way of the the flow of experience
in awareness that's possible because we're not overlaying concepts and ideas
on top of things we're just there in the direct experience of phenomena of
perception and sensations and the beginning of thoughts and even with the emotions that might feel an ordinary
street consciousness as being continuous we when your mind is very quiet and still we're beginning to feel and sense
the uh how they actually kind of um uh uh very momentarily fleetingly coming into
existence and out of existence there's a coming into awareness and out of a worse awareness the mind picks it up and
doesn't pick it up and um generally what happens is we sew these all these different
moments of arising and passing together into a feeling of constancy into idea
that it's continuous but when we don't have ideas anymore just in the experience
this arising and passing a curse and this is meant to me this is supposed to be liberating um i mean
to do this and partly it's because when we see that things are constantly
in flux that um it's hard to it doesn't make sense to cling to them
to grasp onto them it's like you're seeing the river flow vines clearly moving and in flux
and then you put your hand in there to grab the river and hold it and you grab a handful of the river and
you pull it up and by the time you open your hand to hold the river all the water has kind of squeezed out
of your fingers and run off and you might have a little bit of drops left on your on your uh
on your hand but you don't go with those drops of water and you're in your hand and go up to your friends
on the shore and say hey look i have the river in my hand
if you think you're holding the river because you have those few little drops you know that's no longer the river the
river is partly defined by water that's flowing and those drops are no longer in that flow
and so the idea of picking something out of the flow of experience and holding on to it if we're in the
flow really centered in it then we see it you know we've actually left the flow we've actually now kind of
holding something an idea of something that's just a little drop it's just a little maybe even
i don't know what and some it turns out that so much of what
we um get attached to cling to resist is not actually reality but
uh the the idea interpretation the concept we have of reality
and so to it's hard to explain that to people in ordinary consciousness but to really be centered and quiet and see
the flow of the vibratory flow of the sparkling flow the raindrop being on
the lake appearing and disappearing a phenomena becomes glaringly obvious
that it doesn't make sense to cling to it it doesn't make sense to resist to it but rather is to open to it and just
allow it to move through and and just allow it to flow and move
in there and generally when that happens our relationship to that experience changes dramatically
so even if it's been a very we have physical pain which is very hard to be with
i know but when we really in the ability of being concentrated and still
and feel it all is flowing sensation the pain gets transformed into something
else that doesn't really feel painful anymore it's a flow of this arising and passing of sensations
that becomes a whole different way of experiencing it but it requires the mind being very still
and focused and present and quiet to do that so this is the core insight to see
the appearing and disappearing phenomenon in a guided meditation i was focusing mostly on the arising
and at some point we'll do a meditation just focusing on the passing away of phenomena and then the arising and
passing of phenomena that occurred together but
the um so our relationship to things begins to shift
and uh there's a wonderful um verse the dhammapada
that where it starts with a kind of a quote that all things are inconstant so everything
is arising and passing so even things that are continuous and
from ordinary consciousness seem like they're just unchanging in some way or they're
in the mind's way of experiencing it it's the experience that's arising in passing so we want to be a little bit
careful we're not getting too wrapped up in um the thing that we're perceiving
is inconstant it's the way it's the nature of how experience happens that's inconstant
there's a momentary kind of pixelated nature of reality or this flow of this
flow of experience that comes and goes that is built into the very nature of
how we are aware how we experience things so um so so here the buddha says
all created things are inconstant and the word is sankara
which uh which uh it's i'd like to suggest that what we're talking about is
all created experiences all the ways in which the mind uh
perceives and takes in and constructs our reality
everything everything like that it's just it's inconstant it's in flux and moving
and seeing this with insight and one becomes disenchanted
with suffering one becomes disenchanted with suffering so whoever believes that
they're enchanted with suffering enchanted means and maybe it kind of means enamored it means kind of
caught in this caught on the spell of it somehow if we hate our suffering
we're caught in its spell uh we're in it we're in enchanted by it in a certain way i
guess if that means in english to be under a spell if we hate something we're under its
spell we're caught we're entangled and there's something about seeing the inconstancy of experience
that helps us to disentangle ourselves to become to break that spell to not be so caught
in it and so all things
are inconstant all created things are in constant all sankharas seeing this with insight
one becomes disenchanted with suffering this is the path of purity this
is a path of purity so it's a little problematic this idea of purity but just a few verses before they talk
about purity this way this is the path for purifying
one's vision purifying our awareness our vision how
we see things so it's not necessarily becoming a completely you know a saint inside that kind of purity but
rather it's um uh coming to a place where our capacity to be aware is purified of all the
filters of thoughts ideas reactions emotions that prevent us from seeing clearly
but to really see clearly see things as they are we want to see the inconstancy of phenomena
then this the verse goes on goes on all created things are suffering
seeing this with insight one becomes disenchanted with suffering and here we have the
second of the three characteristics the three are in constancy
suffering and the third is not self and these three characteristics are the
core insights of insight meditation it starts with arising and passing in the in in seeing
the arising and passing there's something about seeing that level of our experience that layer
of our experience that uh gives birth to a clear clear
um insight into the in here that this translator which
is me translates as suffering the word is dukkha and for now it
may be it's could be more usefully translated in this context as stressful but we'll talk more about that
on monday and and then it goes on to say all
things are not self seeing this with insight one becomes disenchanted with suffering
so we'll continue this idea of the three characteristics which are so phenomenally important for insight
meditation that's worth spending some time with it and and this movement of seeing and
constancy observing a constancy has an impact on the meditator and the
impact is a process of disenchantment of breaking the spell of how we're caught or entangled or
clinging or attached to things and where the allure the promise of
attachment the promise that grasping will somehow
save us or do something for us begins to be broken and and so that's uh
so so you might want to today during this weekend look a little bit at
um at this idea of in constancy and arising and passing a phenomena
and see if somehow that casts any perspective on how you might be enchanted with
suffering or caught in its spell so i have a little bit of time today
so we can stop uh formally here but if some of you would like to stay a little bit longer and put some
questions in the chat i'm happy to try to answer and i might not be able to answer them in order
but but if you would like to try i'm happy to stay and
and for a little while
okay
and constancy is not bad news aha nice
so are the transcripts of your talks yes but they're not necessarily coming
uh right away but there's a wonderful team of people who are transcribing these talks in the
morning and i think some of the earlier ones are available now from early in the year or before so
if you go on audio dharma where they're the audio recording of them appear it'll say if there's a
transcription available and they're likely edited luckily so
and and the person leading up that that
wonderful project of transcribing is meg galler who often says hello here in the morning
so thank you so much meg and your team for this great work you're doing
um where does awareness go when we are caught in thinking
a lovely question where does it go um where does it go um
well it depends what we mean by awareness if um awareness is
not the same as consciousness but awareness is conscious awareness
or how to say it if there's knowing awareness we know
what we're aware of we know what's coming into consciousness there's a lot of things we know that are coming to
awareness that we don't really you know clearly fully uh i know that
um like so for example just saying all this i was aware that i have these lights on
here and the kind of studio lights just that i was aware of this light that uh and then i knew oh the light is
on and uh but it wasn't the second kind of the knowing of it is different than just kind of i go
about and not paying attention i don't think about it i don't have any active formal recognition
we're thinking our consciousness our awareness i like to think of it as it gets hijacked and held hostage by our
thinking we get so glued to our thinking that that kind of
self-reflective awareness that we know what's happening and what we're doing we know that we're thinking gets lost because it's so preoccupied so
glued to it so that's probably an inadequate answer and and um but then we'll have to leave for
that can you say more about dealing with pain especially for those with chronic illness
yeah that's a huge topic and for now and um and um it's a very very important one
there's a lot of people who have uh pain and are managing their life with pain and chronic illness and
and uh i think one of the great benefits of mindfulness meditation in circumstances like that
is to help us not add second arrows to it to the when we already have tremendous
difficulty in trying to figure out and working our life with this difficulty to not add shame or self-incrimination
or or or resentment or anger or to not get attached to it
should have been different why isn't it different i should have you know whatever it might be the second
arrows but to learn how to be simpler and simpler and to allow
ourselves to be be ill and painful in the simplest possible way maybe even
an ordinary way as if oh yes i'm sick that's what's happening and then absolutely take care of
ourselves try to try to be well and try not to try to do what we can to
heal the pain or overcome the illness and this is not a passivity that we want to have about it but
we do what we can and sometimes we can't do much but the practice can help us then become very simple with it and breathe with it
and not add extra attention and stress to the already stressful situation
and then as the mindfulness gets stronger and more concentrated then uh it's possible to bring a careful
loving compassionate attention deeply into the pain and the illness to
really feel the direct experience of it and that sometimes allows to be different kinds of shifts
and beneficial shifts and i don't want to say exactly how those beneficial shifts will
look like different for different people and i don't want to set up the expectation that mindfulness can
help make the pain go completely away or the illness go away and that it's healing that way but it it can
be healing for the heart the mindfulness practice so the illness and the pain might not go away
but the heart is healed and that that's the movement of liberation and and then we become whole in a certain
way his closed captioning available for these talks you know i believe they are
through youtube but i'm not i don't really haven't tracked all this so well i'll try to find out but
i believe there's a way maybe down in the settings on youtube you can um
they're there that way and um so
it's oh that it kind of goes by quickly so i miss i can't do
them in order i apologize um our thoughts the central mechanism
as to how we cling to these constant phenomena um i don't know if thoughts are the
mechanism for clinging but at least in my experience
that mostly what we cling to what is our thoughts is our ideas and
and it's not so obvious until you might you know you really see how this works in a deep quiet way
um um so we don't really cling to physical pleasure but it's more like
we're clinging to what what the pleasures what the thoughts the ideas the
that we have about what these the pleasure is doing for us
to get
oh to to get to the deepest levels of insight it seems we have to let go of every to-do list in our life how can we
function in the world if we want to go to the deepest levels of insight great question
yes to get to the deepest level of freedom
you have to put aside or let go of any clinging all clinging
and but we can still hold things without clinging so
you know i can i can be attached to the striker and i can feel i'm attached to it i'm so
you know i should therefore let go of it and i can just drop it drop it but another way of letting it's not the
thing that we necessarily have to let go of when we get let go of attachment it's not the thing
unless it's you know harmful and the striker is not harmful in itself it's the clinging we let go of so then
we can go like this and we can still hold it without any grasping
so in deep meditation we want to put everything aside and so with the to-do
list you would maybe put it on a to-do list on a piece of paper and put it up on a shelf leave it on
your table and and just put it aside and then later you come back to it and
then i look at it and and hold all the things on the to-do list with this open hand an open mind and and then
go through them and have the pleasure of checking them off but don't get uh attached to any of it or clinging to any
of it um so there's you're welcome to keep your to-do list and hopefully the deep letting go and
the deep wisdom of meditation helps you to look at that list and prioritize in a good way and maybe
few of the things on the list are not necessary a few of the things maybe represent
something you're attached to maybe unattached to unnecessarily
there seems to be two kinds of inconsistency how our awareness flickers and then perhaps wraps
things up in a constant narrative the flickering inconsistency of phenomena itself
is that correct yeah yeah that sounds nice
but things are not random the inconsistency of what appears and disappears is not completely random
but it arises because of preceding conditions and and so nothing arises out of nothing
but the conditions come together and then things arise and uh
and so in dharma practice we're actually putting in place the conditions
so that we have more consistency so that we have uh more likely that
we move in a certain direction we grow in certain directions we certain kinds of arising tends to arise
more often so for example if you practice a lot of loving kindness then that sets the conditions that when
you sit and we feel pain we're ready to feel a compassion maybe and love for ourselves
and care for ourselves then we are to be angry with ourselves or angry with
other people because what's happening to us and so it's there's inconsistency but we begin to
shape that inconsistency so it tends in one direction in a beneficial
direction so would you please say more about the
buddha never said no self or he had a sense of self yes so we'll talk about that next week when we get to
not self in this exploration of inconstancy
i have uh i have hopes it kind of goes away
i have uh tetanus i think it's tonight that tinnitus
tinnitus there we go oh it's an idea so where is it i was oh anyway so
anyway i guess i missed the question but tonight is i i've had 10 i have tinnitus so the one of the
best things for me is if no one brings up the word because then if i'm reminded then i start hearing the
ringing in my ears so and uh there are times where i've
been really troubled by this you know really draw me kind of baddy the ringing in my ears
and but no i'm not troubled by it anymore and it kind of recedes and and some people find it useful to
make it the object of meditation and it has a kind of constant constancy that
um that's is grounding for some people and uh and i found it i've never found it
particularly useful to pay attention to it and in fact some teachers actually say
this is one of the things in mindfulness practice you shouldn't pay attention to the idea is to pay attention to everything in
mindfulness but not to pay attention to that so it all depends on the person and uh
you know what's useful and not useful but um i mostly these days
um don't give in much attention and don't you know i've learned not to react to it
not to before against it and just to okay there it is and then
i'll continue with my breathing and sit there and practice and go on with other things and
and i know for some people it's really bad they just have some kind of ambient sound around and that sometimes you know
masks it hides it
it's a challenge to hold one's tongue and only observe yes this is the advanced graduate school
mindfulness to be mindful of speaking and there's so much attachment so much
force and power and desires that come into play in speaking that
but it's so beneficial to bring mindfulness to thinking it's a window into to say in
non-buddhist dramatic terms to really be mindful of our of our talking
and what drives our talking and why we're going to say what we're going to do and what what is the the emotional
motivation for our our talking it's kind of like a dramatic window into our soul into our depth of
who we actually are so it's certainly worthwhile to learn to do
that um
jose meg writes closed captioning equals the oral notes on audiodharma so
um
oh someone says yeah closed captioning on youtube is not available live but seems to show up later on
if things are inconstant and clinging to them causes us to suffer what does that mean for choices of the
heart like marriage and career things are in constant clinging to them causes us to suffer what does it mean
for choices in the heart like marriage or a career well ideally we would
choose marriage or a career without any clinging
and in the flow of things are still make choices that uh the direction we want our lives and
the purpose of our lives the meaning of our lives and what we want to really put our heart
into more than anything else we don't have to just kind of go randomly along with whatever happens and it's a beautiful thing for some
people to have a career or have a marriage that they want to be to devote themselves to be engaged
and other people make other choices that are just as good and valuable
now with something like marriage and maybe with careers as well if we wait until we have no clinging and
no craving no craving no attachment the buddhist idea of attachment craving clinging
before we get married and then perhaps most people wouldn't get married
because that's kind of there's you know there's kind of you know there's not a crime it's not
it's not a crime it's not in buddhism it's not a sin or a crime to be attached and to cling it just means
we're going to suffer some somewhat because of it but one way to approach something like marriage and
career or any choice we make for our lives is to enfold it into our mindfulness
practice fold it into our careful care and attention and compassion for where is our clinging where's our
attachment and marriage it can be a great place to and family and kids a great place
to discover where we're attached where our clinging and craving are that maybe uh is very deep that we
wouldn't see in ourselves unless we were in this kind of intimate committed relationship
and um and then to work through it and come to the other side of it so it can be folded in as a path of the
practice as opposed to we avoid all these things because we're we're clinging um and um
so it's probably best not to choose to go into marriage because you want to work out
your clinging but uh but so hopefully that answers the
question well enough what chapter verse from dhammapada did you cite oh i think it's uh well the
chapter is first it's like in the 170s let me see
it is verse oh 277 that what i read and it's in
chapter 20 the path yeah this is my i'm reading from my translation that i did 20 years
ago or so and and it's a little bit fascinating and a
little bit i don't know if embarrassing but a little bit of regret that
choices english choice you know i was my poly my study of the pseudos was not
what it was now so i would translate some of this differently now and and also the use of gender pronouns
i try to avoid um in order to become more gender neutral i did many things i did in a general
neutral way but sometimes i would if there was two pairs of verses
where in the original it was in the masculine pronoun i would do one with he and the other was
she and at the time i thought that was good but 20 years later you know or
10 years later i understood that it's we really want to try to be gender
neutral more fully because of how many people don't fit into the binary of
he and she and and and so i regret that i left it and
that i mean they didn't know enough back then to make that choice so anyway
oh someone asks meg if need more help with transcription and someone else as well um yeah so
she says you can contact imc volunteer coordinator hillary boris and you can um i think if you go on the
imc's website there's probably a place there for volunteering and you
could just let let hillary know and she'll be the support at all
um okay maybe i'll do one more here are these deep insights only really
possible with lengthy meditation retreats have you read the harper's article about the possible dangers of this
um no it doesn't require deep insights but
if you're if you're uh if you for many people in our tradition at least it's usually
in in in meditation retreats that this really settles in and
really kind of becomes digested or we see it and are impacted in a very good way these deep insights
and for most people and but once we have a clear sense of it and
a familiarity with it then they kind of live in a delightful and wonderful way much more in our daily life as well and
it doesn't require deep meditation anymore to really have it be part of the landscape these
insights and affect us and um i might have read the harper's article
and i think i'm pretty familiar with the modern uh discussion about the dangers of deep
inside meditation and and uh so that's you know
uh generally people who want to go into the deeper meditation experiences it's good to work with a
teacher be close connected so you can ask questions of how it's going some of the some of it can be a little bit disorienting and
but some of the real dangers that happen has a lot to do with with
the attitude and way in which people practice and the people who really strive and
push and tend to uh can have
real psychological problems because they're overriding they're not integrated there's not a relaxation it's
not a a nice broad unification uh
composure or collectedness that leads to that supports and so this
anapanasati practice is really a fantastic practice because it creates a really good
foundation for these insights i think some of the people who have these
end up in a little bit of psychological trouble somehow leap frog over creating the
foundation of practice they're in a hurry there's a gung-ho and and so they experience this
the deep experiences of inconstancy before they really have the psychological support and well-being and
stability to make good use of it and so if they already have a little bit psychological
instability it can make it more unstable so this is a known phenomena
that can happen and one of the things that one of the reasons why
having some connection to a teacher and meditation retreats is where that can happen if you have that connection and support
if something like that happens so thank you all very much and then for
this morning and your questions i appreciate them and i'm sorry if i didn't answer answer all
the questions and i value them all thank you