and offer my warm greetings and and
one of the things to appreciate as we do buddhist meditation to buddhist practice is liberation
itself and freedom and liberation freedom takes many forms some of them we don't associate with the
grand words like liberation and and
freedom and the so things like relaxation calming
but as we relax the body and relax the mind as we comment these things there is a letting go we're
releasing of ways that the body and mind has been tight been clinging been
contracted and that's a variation of the
more more i don't know to say more
significant forms of releasing of clinging which is the buddhist liberation
to become liberated to become enlightened is to really have very deep letting go a deep releasing of clinging right down
to the core of our being and and so it's all a variation it's all
a range a spectrum of releasing something
that we're talking about here and so we relax the body and we and then to appreciate don't just
relax the body as we start to meditate but appreciate the consequences of the relaxation
the the the relief the openness the ease the space the the lightness
uh the release of vitality that might come with relaxation
uh when we relax the mental formations relax the mental activity the tensions
and the contractions of the mind uh it's not just a matter of relaxing it it's also appreciating the consequence
of that the greater ease or lightness or space or or openness
that might be there and so also when we let go of thinking
that that some people let go of thinking and immediately go back to the breathing as if but just take a few moments
to let go of thinking and to appreciate um whatever goodness that comes from the
space the openness the lack of contraction lacks of tightness the
lack of compulsion that might be there in the letting go
of the thoughts and so one of the ways of practicing meditation then at some point as we
settle in further is to just appreciate letting go letting go
letting go of anything the mind wants to pick up on or get involved in and just let go any kind of attention to
any kind of pulling attention to emotions and thoughts as much as we respect these and include
them as part of meditation there is an art to also letting go of any
preoccupation with them any prioritization of them any extra interest or even any interest in
them everything is allowed to be as it is we're not dismissing anything what we're
really letting go of is the clinging to things the tightening and the tension around
what's happening so at some point meditation just the process of letting go
letting go letting go and and uh so
assuming a meditation posture
and i often suggest closing the eyes at the
beginning of meditation and as you do so you might take a moment
to see if you can appreciate how the relief for the eyes not to be
engaged in looking and seeing maybe there's a that gives a
kind of a rest for the eyes and if the eyes are not don't feel
restful maybe it's possible to um
let the eyes eyes rest in their sockets almost as if you're looking down
and backwards and then taking a few
somewhat deeper breaths so you can really let go and relax on the exhale
really emphasizing softening the body
calming the agitations of the body
and then letting the breath return to normal
and then to as you exhale to continue to relax the
body calm the body but to take a few moments to feel
the goodness whatever nice feelings this greater vitality that come from relaxing
feel the resulting calmness tranquility in that part of your body
relaxing the shoulders the belly
the face
sometimes it's possible to relax the whole body
and sometimes it's possible to calm
a body-wide feeling of agitation
a calming wave through the body with as you exhale
and also gently tenderly as you exhale
to relax any agitation calm any agitation in the mind the
mental activity
letting go relaxing any tension or contraction in the mind
or in the or in that part of the body associated with your mental activity
to calm the agitation of the mind
and then to let go of your thoughts or at least let go of your involvement
with your thinking appreciate
that there's more space in the mind to be aware
when we let go of our thinking and let that space of awareness
be filled with the experience of breathing
breathing in and breathing out
and then as we continue sitting this morning with every exhale
say the word letting go let go not as a command
but as a invitation
for us to let go of something that the mind is has taken up
to let go of the energy of holding on or picking up or being involved in anything at all
just let go and on the inhale appreciate
the goodness the spaciousness the openness
of that letting go
letting go and the exhale
appreciating
the good results of letting go
and just keep letting go as if for these minutes meditation
everything that arises everything that you know nurses known
is another thing to let go of to be open and fresh for the next moment
just let go
let go
let go as if letting go is the most important thing to do nothing to hold on
to nothing to be concerned about
just let go
so
what are you not letting go of
what can you still let go of to be thorough and letting go
um
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps to appreciate the greater letting go there is
the more space there is for love
the more space there is for good will kindness
tenderness the more there is the opposite of love
the less room there is for love
the more time and space is taken up with clinging and reacting and being preoccupied
they're less time there is less space there is for friendliness
not the love or friendliness that is an obligation or something we have to
muster up but rather something deeper more
simple and that comes out of the tenderness gentleness
of our hearts our minds
to let go so that without work and without
obligation we can receive other people into our
hearts in the place where there's tender friendliness
sometimes in buddhism there's an expression tender compassion
and again without any obligations or is there a place in your heart
in the simplicity of being here having let go
where your heart's tender good will
could if it wanted to be expressed in the words
may others be happy
may others be safe
may others be peaceful
may others be free
and may i live a life
that supports that to happen
may this meditation practice we've done together today
may it be so that we can live a life that benefits
and supports the welfare and happiness of all beings
may all beings be happy and free
[Music]
so then we come to the 12th step of the 16 steps
of anapanasati the practice of mindfulness breathing in
and mindfully breathing out and the 12 step is breathing in
one liberates the mind breathing out one liberates the mind
and so it's the 12th step out of the 16th so it's usually said not to be the full
complete possibility of liberation that buddhism champions but it is a significant
experience of freedom of liberation of letting go that
that that makes an impression on the mind makes an impression on us it's
educational it's opening it's inspiring it kind of begins pointing the way now we know something
we didn't know before and the um
so the um
now remember it's a 12 step so what that means is that the first 11 steps are in a
sense a preparation for this step if we simply heard the only instruction for buddhism is to
let go let go let go i don't know if that would be so useful for people to hear
and also it might not give the right idea of what letting go is about it
might feel like oh just let go of everything i have and have nothing as a result and be impoverished impoverished in some way
and if i let go there's nothing left and i'll just be kind of depressed and miserable or something
the letting go happens after the first 11 steps which are preparing the ground and
opening the field and setting up a sense of well-being where letting go has a very wonderful
context and we understand the tremendous value of letting go because of the wholesomeness the
beneficial states that we're experiencing so so to kind of review this little bit
how to contact how context is set up for letting go
so the practice begins with just simply mindfully breathing in and out helping the mind calm down helping the
mind get focused helping us to show up and be present for our experience and i think
for most people that's where the bulk of the practice is even people who practice for a long time
they sit down to meditate and they're they're at step one and two
and uh and uh this idea that there's a progress you're supposed to always be at the
growing edge of this 12 16 steps is a kind of a just unnecessary
source of stress and and misunderstanding and it's easy easy than to miss ourselves in
the process and not really connect to ourselves the idea in mindfulness practice is to really
become ourselves be ourselves really be honest about what's here and learn how to rest and be present for it
and this idea of just breathing in and out through it all is a way of supporting us to not resist
not try to escape not try to avoid what is here but to really
be present and face what's here and work through it and just breathe with it and relax and
heal and open up and and release the things that have to be released
and but as we do this practice then at some point we begin feeling recognizing that we can relax the body
sometimes the body just relaxes itself in meditation often you don't have to do the relaxing
but the mind body becomes more tranquil more calm and and that's a feels like a good thing
and the more we practice the more calm and relaxed the body becomes as the body becomes calmer and more
relaxed let go some of the tension we have some of those feelings of well-being can
well up the sense of contentment the ease relaxation itself is can bring a kind of joy and happiness
and so the practice begins kind of inching its way into feeling some joy happiness contentment well-being
that sets the stage to better appreciate the tensions of the mind the
mental activity how there's the stresses that are there and so then the practice when we start
seeing that we start relaxing the mental activities calming the agitation of the mind
relaxing the mind relaxing the mental muscle the thinking
muscle and and so the mental activities which can be swirling around and be fragmented
and uh be going off in different directions begin to settle down and the mental activity starts coming
into harmony with itself and in in harmony and unity with the settling process of meditation
and then we come into the third tetrad all having to do with the mind the
cheetah and the cheetah can be understood as the heart mind
it's kind of like our inner life you know it's uh not would not be
appropriate buddhist term but maybe for a way some people some
modern people use the word soul kind of the deepest kind of places inside our
inside our psyche inside of ourselves it might also be the soul kind of them but the mind the heart the
mind heart is you know what buddhists talk about
and uh so we start recognizing that we have this inner life this inner mind this inner
quality of life the mood state that's inside and we start becoming the caretaker on
that and because of the earlier steps of panasati
this begins to feel good to be connected to this deep you know if i use the western word soul
to really for some people i think really kind of feels like a homecoming more than if you say say mind
or heart but uh does heart mind really feel oh this is good this inner state
the state of being and there can be a gladness of satisfaction a deep satisfaction deep
contentment of being home being connected to something deep that's not kind of
spinning around on the surface of our thoughts and ideas and scattered in our mind but we're really
starting to feel whole and unified and that process of becoming unified and
unscattered undispersed continues into the 11th step with with samadhi with unification with
steadying this whole mind state comes and gets gathered together and and there's a lot of well-being that can
come some of the greatest forms of joy and happiness come from samadhi from a mind that's
unified and settled and connected so by the time we get to the step 12
letting go liberating the mind the um there's just a tremendous amount
of of uh well-being there's a feeling of being really at home connected and so rather than
letting go being an impoverishment a diminishment of ourselves it's we start really seeing that what
we're letting go of is in fact what diminishes us is in fact what impoverishes us that
there's something about the mind getting caught and preoccupied
obsessing about things spinning around in thoughts and ideas holding on to fear oddly enough we can
cling to fear uh clinging to upper to resistance clinging to
all kinds of things that we resist and hold on to and cling for dear life clinging to self and self-image
clinging to hurt all kinds of things that people will cling to but it's seen
on this reservoir on this foundation of well-being of goodness of freedom or
clarity and so it's really clear that that clinging is is a separation from that well-being
letting go just feels like of course i'll let go letting go so obviously a diminishment
so obviously a source of suffering so obviously a source of stress of course i'll let go
and so sometimes the letting go the liberation that happens here is uh so innate that it's not something
we have to do we just keep staying present breathing with the experience
and and just letting things be letting things be and something will just let go by itself
because it takes a certain kind of mental involvement
to remain clinging and if we just let things be let things be even our clinging
it will self-liberate at some point the self-liberating capacity of all
things and so so we come to the the 12th step and
uh we come to the time of liberation of letting go and it's at this point where some people
find it just really a wonderful thing to just sometimes when you sit down to meditate
just let go let go let go just whatever arises let it go let it be
let it be don't be involved don't pick it up don't get reactive to it don't pull away
just let go let it be let it be let it go and um and um
you know and so we let go of everything let go of even we let go of even
mindfulness being aware we let go of self we could get let go of knowing we let go of um even letting go
at some point just let go and don't and let go of being the agent
of it let go of having an agenda let go of trying to be complete
or getting enlightened even um just let go let go there's some that's as if that's
all there is let go of um of uh needing to let go even
just wherever it is possible the next moment let go of this let go this um
and um so um
so this twelfth step of an apanasati breathing in liberating the mind
breathing out liberating the mind so that's um
and that is the is the entryway to the last four steps of an apanasati
and so letting go and liberation here is not in you know the end of the
story but in some ways it's the beginning of a story and they say that some sometimes it said in
kind of folklore buddhism that the buddhist path really begins
when we have a qualitative experience of letting go of liberation that we know oh this is what it's about
this is what freedom is possible this is what really feels good and feels inspiring and feels
this is worth and this is such a qualitatively good
experience such a rich experience such an experience that's filled with potential for compassion and
love and freedom and goodness and lack of causing harm wanting to cause harm in
the world this is a good thing so um so um
that's where we are on this process and we'll continue it um on monday and uh
and and over this weekend uh why don't you uh talk to some friends
about what they've learned about how letting go is useful and when letting go is useful have
conversations about the benefits of letting go and how letting go can be done in
wise ways and and look for opportunities to let go look to look and really start to explore
all the different dimensions that you can find of when and how and where letting go
operates for you or can operate for you and if we do that then
we'll have a better foundation for our continuing our adventure on next week monday thank you