good morning everyone and good day
so welcome to our 7 a.m sit and the dharma
let's see and the sound okay there are some of you if you can
let me know
okay
so we'll get started momentarily and so uh
yeah feel free to just checking with the with the sangha maybe say hi and
um and said to yourself since you're here a couple of minutes earlier
yeah thank you for those who let me know about the sound um
yeah so we'll begin momentarily just um
for now i wanted to invite you to consider you know coming to your sitting cushion
sitting chair maybe just as if you're
coming to a quiet temple
began to maybe evoke a sense of care gentleness
as to sit down and so we'll begin just in a few moments
so we'll begin this morning with the arriving sequence
maybe ima imagine yourself arriving
at a quiet temple a temple of this body
allow some a gentle
setup-ness as you settle in into the space
i remember going to the temples in kyoto japan
it's as if i am walking into the temple almost like a tiptoe
it's quiet
here arriving here
i have a little care
care for this body
the space it's in
taking your seat
right here and now
and temporarily we can leave behind
any thoughts about the future and the past
arriving here in this moment
the sense of arriving may be expressed
as bringing mindfulness front and center
becoming president
available
available to the sound sound of my voice
and be in sound
being available to the movements of the breath
without sense of the sitting posture
or whatever the posture you may be taking
aligning aligning from ground up
being supported by earth
also being supported by the grand of a wholesome intention
my teachers sometimes use this term resting on the ground of a wholesome
intention
aligning with our aspirations our values
integrity within
maybe you have a sense that you've arrived here home
in this body the temple of this body
inviting the felt sense of earth element to come in
however it may be for you
maybe you're feeling the pelvic bones making contact with earth
right underneath of us
the hardness of the teeth
weight of the shoulders and arms
being available to the experience of the earth element
right here in this earthy body
sitting like a redwood
rooted uplifted
maybe a sense of stability
steadiness can come in
earth element is stable
and some small and big degrees unmoving earth element
as in nature to settle
if you feel a hint of stillness
as you sit in the bones
letting go of the tendencies to try to figure it out
let the body let the body
does what it does body knows
body feels
mindfulness of the body in and of the body itself
not in the head
with the steadiness and stillness
in the earth element as a backdrop
making ourselves available to the movements
the contrasting movements of the winged element
air chi in chinese
movements of the bride
rising and falling of the belly
expansion and contraction of the torso
[Music]
receiving the felt sense of the wind element
flowing through the whole body
maybe you feel vibrations tingling
winged moves
the felt sense of the stillness may still be in the backdrop or the
foreground of your experience
as you experience the movements of the air element
you may feel aliveness
as you breathe in and out
there may be a vivid sense of a vitality
and stillness and movements can co-exist
right here in our experience
i expand to include the felt sense of a water
element today
notice the moisture inside the mouth
maybe in the palm
maybe moisture in the eyes
water takes a shape in whatever the container
they're in
you're sitting a water element takes the shape of sitting
lying down water elements take the shape of lying
down fluid
permeating throughout the body
the body is still quiet
it may feel like we're sitting in a quiet lake
i'm moving
the body has energetic wavy
experiences may feel as if there are ripples and
waves in the body
for the rest of the meditation
feel free to stay with whatever may be prominent for you
the arriving sequence earth element
winged element or water element
are the combinations of all of this
dropping out of the concepts and ideas beliefs
of what all this are
let the body speak for off
feel into the body sensing
into it
the tempo of this body provides a shelter
and protection from getting caught
in endurances grasping aversion and delusion
this last a few moments of our sitting together
we offer an inner bowing to the temple of this body
and this mind this heart we're offering shelter
protection and safety
safeguarding inner integrity inner virtual
inner goodness
uh
hmm thank you all for
meditating together i felt the sense of uh goodness from
just being here with you all and practicing together
what a fortune great fortune
so today i wanted to continue our
reflections on sila and today i will be
extending this to the third precept
we've been going through this one by one and the third precept is
undertaking the training rules abstaining from misconduct related to sexuality
and again i wanted to invite all of us to explore this from an inside out
framework and using this framework of a triple a aware abstinence
and a line aware of the inner forces
and becoming clear of the cons consequences of hosam are
unskillful and then we learn to abstain training to abstain
from those that are unskillful and wholesome
and then we allowing ourselves so what that is a wholesale and that is a skillful
and so this particular training set uh a training precept
the direct poly translation of one of the terms significant term in
this precept comma refers to sensual pleasures
and so maybe the literal translation of this precept is
more like undertaking the training of abstaining from misconduct
in regard to essential pleasures and sexual desire
and so this has a broader implication than the common interpretation
which is usually abstinent from misconduct in sexual relationships
and so today i wanted to explore this maybe a from a
broader perspective they are not exclusive of each other in any way
but i would like to include a broader perspective as well
as we cultivate mindful awareness i like all of you have been doing this right
and we can begin to see how essential desire
arise out of um sense context
may be related to seeing seeing some beautiful
appearances clothes hearing some sound or voice
that somehow attract us i remember on hearing many stories about
the personal romance on retreats i think some of you may have heard of this as well i may have even
experienced this you know our retreats right and there's not much else to going on
on retreats so our mind can get caught up
just by watching a person somehow the way they take a cup of tea
or drink a cup of tea we can get really caught up
by some romantic fantasy
it's not until the end of the retreat when the person begin to speak or do
something different and then we kind of all of a sudden it hits us
what happened here right
so um so the forces are common and potent
within us if we are attuned
with our awareness and those momentary essential desires
it's just kind of like a ripples and then big they ponder for water
but they come and go and they ripple outwards they kind of settle
without getting manifested into anything significant at all
and yet without clear awareness and clear knowing
this kind of a forces can get an upper hand now we can get caught up
and we can write out this kind of desires and and manifest into
un-wholesome bodily and verbal actions
and so as we began undertaking the training of cultivating awareness
we can become become
aware we can know this forces
and then from externally uh we may take under we take this training um by undertaking the
training of abstaining from sexual misconduct
we don't want to play with the fire right and it's kind of like um [Music]
we don't want to get it burned so being aware has a lot to do
with how we have how we can cultivate capacity to undertake this training
rules
so it probably and i wanted to just name how potent this force is
it probably goes uh and the kind of harm they can have
on human beings and there's no denial to this
um and we all know that the misuse of this kind of forces
sexual energy essential desires lead to deep trauma deep pains distress
for ourselves and for others and i was looking up at some statistics
yesterday and in one of the statistics statistics i googled and
i don't know how how true the information is but it feels uh reasonable and so it says
40 40 plus percent of the women in u.s has encountered sexual violence
and 20 of the males in america have been the victim of
sexual violence
isn't that amazing and i i thought this might be low
growing up with a sexual body
and there much harm can be done as i was stunned by the statistics
and those are probably more reported and i'll report it might be even higher
so just imagine you know one out of maybe close to two women
might be uh might have encountered the sexual violence
and yet those are deep forces within so when we are hurt and harmed
so much dukkha can happen some people have a lifetime
kind of a hurt and harm buried within
and yet because of the potent force um it's also easy for us to get caught
i recently read something from sharon salzberg one of the pioneer
teachers in the terrible western tarabata tradition she shared about a
uh an encounter and she said and that
in her article a friend once was in at a community meeting at which a member
was being rather self-righteously denounced for their sexual misconduct
and my friend's comment was who in this room has never made a fool
of themselves over sex in fact no one raised their hand
isn't that kind of stunning
so sexual forces are very powerful forces
i wanted to say a few words about how we relate to this forces inside of us and
whether it's essential desires misconducts
in relationship to this kind of forces and maybe unskillful actions that we
[Music] experienced and taken in the past i invite you to all
also engage in the practice of not shaming ourselves or others
not blaming ourselves or others because we all know
that shaming and blaming are only adding thoughts and
wounds right and this applies to all the other
precepts the whole training of vasila
shaming and blaming is unskillful and unhelpful
i instead the very fact that the sealer is a training it's pointing to how we can learn
through coming to know these forces coming to know the implications and
consequences of this forces and so we can train
and learn to not get burnt again and again
and this is the gradual training takes the patience
lots of care and gentleness kind attention
a wailingless willingness to learn
just think about it kind of how you might treat your children if they make a mistake we know they have
potential to correct them we don't just tell them that's it you
know you're a bad boy bad girl forever right
instead we all know that children has potential to grow and mature through
learning in the same way
we are ever growing and maturing too even though physically we're kind of you
know a doubt adults
unless the forces a sexual energy and sexual forces
are also life life caring they feel the love
of our partners and our families motherly fatherly love we usually don't associate this with the
sexuality because somehow i guess nowadays sexuality gets
reduced to appearances and sensuality only
and it's undeniable though that the sexual forces are also life-giving
caring so in practicing this training rule we have
a choice to honor and respect care love for life
and not to diminish life so this speaks to how we align align
ourselves to respect and care for our own bodies and others
so i want to end uh with again this coat that i've been coating from
this mangala suta the sitter of the blessings and i'll share this
link maybe in a day or two and it says caring for mother and father kindness to
children and partners and this is the highest blessing
so may we all respect ourselves and others and may this cultivation benefit all
beings so enjoy your practice and
whatever the activities that you take today and so we'll meet here again tomorrow
thank you everyone and take good care bye