hi everyone hello and warm welcome to happy hour
so for today's practice um you we're going to continue
one more time one more session with practice of mudita it's been so sweet to
practice vicarious joy happiness for happiness of others um happiness of
ourselves others just happiness for happiness because we usually our our default
mode in this human body and mind is to notice what's challenging what's
difficult um and turning our mind intentionally to what is good what is a
blessing um in our lives in other people's
lives it doesn't come naturally and yet when we do that we turn intentionally to
the good and celebrate blessings goodness happiness in the world whether
ours or others the heart feels uplifted and boy do we need uplift in our heart
especially especially in these challenging times um especially in these tough times
so this is a wholesome practice of gladdening our heart and mind um um it's
skillful means it's it gives us more um stability to be with what is
difficult of which there is plenty in our lives so by turning to what's good
we're actually building building more resilience so this is a way of
not shying away not turning away but
intentionally inclining the heart and mind to what's
good to build resilience so that we can be we can hold what's difficult with
more ease because if we always just turn our minds as as our minds want to just turn to what's ne ne difficult and and
challenging as our minds tend to do as human beings evolutionarily we're more
tuned to what's difficult and what's hard than what's good imagine our
ancestors walking in the savannah if they missed something good if they miss
the berry in the environment they would still live another day they would be
hungry but they would live another day and there would be other berries right
but if they missed the negative signals in the environment the bad the
challenging The Woolly Mammoth that was about to eat them they wouldn't Live
Another Day so guess who passed down their genes to us the ones who were
particularly tuned to scary difficult challenging
signals in the environment so we have those genes we
have those capacities we are more tuned to what's difficult what's challenging
what's scary what's fearful and not as tuned all of us beings not as
tuned um to what is good what is a blessing so we need to in we need to
balance our hearts and Minds by intending to what's
good so that's what we're going to do in our practice
tonight by turning to what's good in our lives and others and celebrating them
yay with happiness balancing balancing the uh natural tendencies of our minds
and hearts so let's get started so I like to invite you ah to
land to land in your
seat if you need to sit up straighter if you need to lie
down to shift and move and as always we're going to start with about 10
minutes of settling with the breath and the
body calming soothing settling the mind the
body right here right now inviting
the body to settle
relax soften
feeling your feet on the ground connected to the
Earth your legs your sit
bones your hands touching each other or your lap
the breath moving through the
body especially palpable the lower
abdomen the lower body to help us settle settle and connect
just this breath Refuge taking Refuge
huge the in breath and the out breath just this
moment just
here
e e
if a thought is arising ask do I need to be thinking this right
now do I and with with a smile with kindness seeing the
thought saying thank you not now with
gentleness with gentleness and yet wholehearted
intention coming back to the breath connecting
settling
e
e e
connecting with the entirety of the in breath and the entirety of the out
breath for
how delicious to take refuge just sit and be breathed nothing
else simple In This
Moment
e
e e
now I like to invite you to bring to your heart to your
mind some blessing in your life right now maybe
something that's good as you're sitting practicing In This Moment
there's always something good there's always a
blessing choosing to turn your mind to
it to let it in to your heart to your body
there goodness in your life
let your heart relish deeply
Savor is goodness e
and inviting your heart to stay
with whatever goodness arises in your mind in your heart for a few
breaths to relish Savor celebrate take
Delight feel happy for this goodness for this
happiness
e e
filling your heart with each breath with the
goodness that is in your life
turning your mind to
it celebrating glad for your own
gladness happy for your own
happiness
e
e e
now bringing to mind someone who's dear to
you for whom you easily feel kindness and care and
warmth and bring to mind some goodness in their
life that they're happy about they're grateful
for let yourself feel gladness happiness forther happiness as
if it were your [Music]
own as if you're the one celebrating as if you're the one
happy blessed with this blessing happy for their happiness
I'm happy for your happiness you can say
silently may your good fortune may your
blessing continue may it increase may it never
end whatever version works for you or maybe simply without words celebr
reading glad happy for their happiness
and this person doesn't need to be happy in every aspect of their life but this
blessing grateful for this one blessing in their
life feeling them happy feeling them grateful for this blessing
happy for their happiness celebrating with them in your
heart
and now bringing to mind someone who you don't know very
well you stand in for all of
humanity a quote unquote neutral person maybe a neighbor you see walking
by someone who works at a store where you
shop or a delivery person it's when you don't have a
complicated relationship or any history
with bringing this person to mind appreciating that this person is
just like you they want to be happy they don't want to
suffer just like you they have a deep complex inner
life that's very compelling to them just as yours is to
you with worries and fears and loves and hopes and
aspirations with happinesses just as you're happy for your blessings
they too celebrate they're
grateful and imagining them happy for a blessing in their
life and since you don't know them well you can imagine something it's
okay imagine something in their life they're grateful for
that that they hold dear maybe it's a
relationship a child a friend a
partner maybe it's a good news they got maybe it's Health recover ing from an
illness seeing them happy grateful
celebrating ah and as if it were your own as if this
person was your dear being celebrating Happy for their
happiness hello dear fellow human being I'm happy for you
may your happiness your good fortune made it
continue May there be more for you maybe there may there be more in the world or
happiness may your well-being happiness Good Fortune continue never
end and
increase e
and now bring it to mind
someone you have a little bit of an entanglement with not the most entangled
relationship in your life someone you have a little bit of challenge
with and realizing this person too just like the
previous person they're not so different from
you they just want to be happy not boning the
harm the challenges the
hurt and as if we were able to separate the actions from the humanity of the
person for just this moment seeing that just like you they
want to be happy they feel grateful for happiness
is in their
life just like you they don't want to
suffer and seeing them happy for some blessing for some good fortune in their
life and allowing your heart to celebrate be happy for them
in this Regard in this way expanding your heart in its
generosity I'm happy for your happiness in this way in this regard
I celebrate your good fortune with
you
e e
may your happiness continue may it increase may it never
end see if it's possible to feel into that even if we split
second let too
challenging can always go back to the previous categories
the neutral person your dear person or
yourself turning your mind to goodness to blessing and
celebrating feeling happy for anybody's happiness as if it were your own
generosity celebrating happiness in the world anybody's happiness
and for the last moments bringing all of these beings together in
your mind's eye yourself your dear being Conjuring them up
the neutral being and the person you're having
challenges with Conjuring them all up as if sitting with
you feeling into all these happinesses all these good Fortunes in different
ways shapes nuances may all of
us may all of our blessings
continue may they increase May they're never may they never
end feeling happy celebrating for all our happinesses
extending to all the beings who are practicing with you right
now on zoom and on YouTube and elsewhere in the
world may all of us and to all of our
people that we've conjured up may all the happinesses
may all of them continue for all of these
beings happy for all this happiness May there be more in the
world and expanding further may all beings
everywhere whatever blessing or happiness they have in their life
may they continue may they increase may they never
end knowing full well there is impermanence and yet by sharing this
wish we're cultivating generosity of heart with simpath pathetic Joy with
mudita for all
beings may all of our gladness
continue happy for all the joy and happiness in the world may there be more may they never
end
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your
practice so
I just changed the setting so you can type in chat if you wish either to me in which
case I won't say out your say your name out loud or can type in chat to everyone
your observations your questions your
comments your complaints it's all welcome you can also raise your hand
um your um Zoom hand if you like to share something
especially if you haven't shared in a while if you have recently shared it's nice to um hold back and let other
people who might be a little more shy and holding back to to uh pull forward
so
so what what did you notice how were the different categories for you did you
notice differences moving from yourself to the dear person celebrating
them their happiness um etc etc Nicholas please
I don't hear you Nicholas oh is that better oh yes now I can hear you okay great yeah I was
saying that um mudita for myself is quite challenging right now because I've had ringing in my ears for a few days
and um you know that when we talk about focusing on the negative you know there's that pull to only see that and
all of my experience and it's very helpful I think to recognize the joy in others lives um
and I found that turning to everybody not just turning to somebody who was easy not
just turning to somebody who was a little challenging it it was a nice affirmation that there's joy in
everybody's life so of course there's also joy in my life that's available it's very
helpful nice nice beautiful thank you for sharing that Nicholas love it
um the the see seeing at first as you said
it was challenging to see the joy given that the tenus ringing in the ear has been so challenging and then by turning
and realizing oh yes there is joy in everyone's life then it actually made seeing the joy and the blessings in your
own life more available lovely beautiful thank you for sharing that may your your
wisdom the way you worked with it and the what you discovered may it support other people in their own Discovery um
as as we discover these ways other people might think oh if I have difficulty seeing joy in my life well
maybe I'll do the same thing I'll try for other beings so that's lovely Nichols and I'm loving your your your
kitty moving back and forth in front of the camera oh my God that that brings me joy
for you in your life that you have this lovely little kitty oh my God they're so
cute they sweet thank you Nicholas it's
lovely yeah yeah and one of you shared in in uh chat that yes there's
hesitation in Sharing knowing that this is recorded um if if you like to share
in chat and just say send it to me I can read it out loud um without saying your
name if that makes it feel more comfortable or you can raise your hand and I won't say your name if you you can
you can just unmute yourself actually I just changed the settings so if that works for you please do if not it's all
okay it's all okay any Reflections any observations or
questions
okay all right Jamie please I was holding back because I can
be talkative here so thank you for the time um
how how do I get U into how can I really feel mudita when I'm not feeling
someone's happiness you know I found that if I understand the cause of
someone's happiness it's it's very easy for me to you know feel happy for their
happiness but you know if I didn't have that um if I couldn't see into the
source of it it it wound up feeling um like uh like
meta you know I couldn't really say I'm happy for your happiness I just it
didn't ring true but I could say Hey you know may it continue may it increase you know with with loving
kindness yeah there's that little step more for Mita exactly yeah yeah yeah I appreciate the
question so um tell me which of the categories was
it challenging in what we're raising all of them one of them let's let let's speak about something specific
um um neutral a neutral being who you know I don't really know or have a
relationship with and you know so the further from got it proximity to me even
my difficult being was I I could conjure up a little mudita for my difficult
being I know what's going on in her life I see got it how about your deer how about your dear being easy oh okay great
good to know okay so so dear person you can feel into their life yes great easy
and then even the challenging person you're having challenges with yes because you know brother it's really
you're highlighting the neutral person that just not so much connection great okay very concrete so so this is what I
would recommend J to play to to play around with this um imagine this this in
order to find your way into it um think of something that that is is
you Relish in your life that's something that's you know you have a roof over
your head you know you have a comfortable safe home and ah and imagine
you know when you didn't have that for example and now you have it how happy you feel about it what a blessing in is
now imagine them oh and it's okay you can use your imagination it's okay you can be creat creative in this imagine oh
they they didn't have that they were sharing a home or something and it wasn't Comfort and now oh they have
their own like oh this is how it makes me feel I just Delight in it oh they wow
they they probably feel the same way I happy for your happiness so that can build the
bridge that's creativity you're welcome yeah you're welcome and it can be very you
know again use your creativity it could be very fun and nourishing in this way appreciate the
question so okay dear ones it is time for us to
get to meet each other in small groups and and share so the invitation I have
for practicing groups is um first let's
by the way how is it let me ask you um if you remember or maybe I'll ask you afterwards after you come out the group
because you may not remember I'm going to ask you to spend about 30 seconds without words at the beginning just
having mudita for other people's happiness imagining they have some
happiness even if you don't know what it is the other couple of people in the room with
you just doing real time would for them and then when you unmute then each of
you shares something that you're grateful for in your life is it is you're happy for and then you can
practice real time mudita for each other um and then you can share anything you
like so you could do that one round and then you can share anything about the practice if there is time after that so
I will create the breakout rooms here we go it's it's so happy making by the way
to hear about other people's happiness and good fortune this is such a happy making um practice so here rooms are
open enjoy okay the rooms are closed and everyone is back so we've got a couple
of minutes I'd like to ask you actually first um how how is the 30 seconds of
Silent mudita how is that and you can actually you can give answers with
reactions you can either say let's say yes or no the the yes is the green like
that it was it's good or not so good is the the X the red so I want to get a
sense of if the silent mudita works okay oh
great okay nice all right so no Nos and
one two three four five six okay great majority are saying yep good
great yeah Emily says I like it because I feel like it encourages a pause and
thoughtfulness in Sharing lovely thank you and I see some of you nod
um great wonderful so so we'll keep that great yeah it that's true and it does
take away from the group time Kathleen says which is quite brief and yet if it brings more presence so great fantastic
any other Reflections would love to hear your Reflections you can type them or you can raise your hand what what did
you notice feeling happy for other people's happiness
this shared mudita in
group let's hear from one person if you would be so kind as to share what you
notied anything I can share
great I hit the jackpot because I was in the in a room with my son and Shani and
Neil so it was kind of like a
party oh that's so sweet oh that just makes me happy that brings mudito for me
I see other people are putting hearts and clapping and with
the other other mudita Isn't it nice when we turn our hearts to mud daa gladness for other
people's gladness is just keeps showing up right it keeps showing up you just
have to prime the pump and here it is it keeps showing up thank you so much for
sharing that Kim so that so that myself and others could fil with detto for your
joy you're so happy laughing celebrating hitting the jackpot partying I see
Neil smiling I don't see all of you unfortunately but uh that's very sweet
that's very sweet that's very sweet so dear ones we have come to the end of yet
another happy hour as Click and Clack the tap and brothers the radio show they said you wasted another perfectly good
hour well I'm joking of course it's it's lovely it's lovely to practice with you
so thank you so much for showing up for doing this practice of the heart this
cultivation not just for your own sake but the sake of all those whose lives
you touch may all beings be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves thank you