so warm greetings from redwood city
and as we continue this
series on mindfulness of breathing
the mindfulness practice has both a deliberate side of the practice
and that which is non-deliberate or to say it may be
maybe in a clearer away that which is active that we do and that which is
passive that we allow for and the balance between those two shifts and changes as the practice goes
along so certainly if a person has never heard of meditation before
and they maybe read a book about it and say i'm going to meditate they have to actively put themselves
maybe into a meditation posture and kind of get themselves started and
change the maybe the the momentum of their mind even from what
they have been doing to have the momentum of the mind being being little bit
different now the momentum of the mind is to be present to be present without a
lot of thinking about things or reacting to things but to have some ability to stay present
and maybe to stay present in a very simple way in the present moment with something like the breathing just
being with the breathing staying on the breathing and and so there's a deliberateness to
that there's an active quality to that that um that needs to be there
as the practice deepens or as it were able to stay more and more in the present moment
there's uh less of the deliberateness is needed um it's almost as if the deliberateness
is set in place the motion to let go of all the distracted forces
all the different things we might be doing and uh and so now we're kind of at rest staying
here present and we don't have to do any more deliberateness in it and so to borrow from an ancient
metaphor um if a um
someone who herds sheep a shepherd is you know the sheep have
gathered all over the mountainside and the shepherd deliberately travels around
the mountains searching looking trying to find the sheep to gather them together
so there's a deliberateness and active looking for those sheep once all the sheep have been gathered
and they brought back to down by the river where they're in the
core pasture area is perhaps and they're all gathered there and they're happily eating in the
in the pasture then the shepherd can lean back against the nice
trees trunk of the tree and the shade on a warm day maybe looking out across the pasture
and then there's not much deliberateness in the looking anymore there's not much intent to look and find
and find the sheep now the shepherd can just sit back and gaze in a kind of more receptive
open passive perhaps way of just kind of
gazing upon and rather than looking for the sheep
the shepherd is content just to see the sheep to allow the seeing to happen without
needing to search or look to be intentional so the same way with mindfulness practice as it
initially there's an active quality deliberateness the training come back focus be there and
and with time uh everything gets gathered together all the desperate parts of ourselves
that have been lost up in the mountains and wandering around have been gathered
together come back to the pasture where they can kind of
eat what's nourishing and supportive the buddha called mindfulness when it's really gathered in
and centered on the body the feelings the mind and the mental processes
to be a pastor for the meditator and everything's gathered together here and now what we can do is we're not so
active but we just we just observe there's
there's seeing but no looking in sense that looking being the active
engagement of the eyes and seeing is just what happens when we allow the eyes to operate
like the difference between listening which is active and hearing which
doesn't have to be active it just we hear something without trying to hear it
so the emphasis today is um is to kind of begin appreciating
the the way in which mindfulness can be a passive receptive quality
that doesn't require so much work it's not so deliberate because a deliberateness has brought us
to the point where we can let go of that deliberateness and um and so at this point the buddha
actually uses the language of observing just observe
and so this is the direction we go today in the
meditation so taking a comfortable
upright posture upright meaning engaged and
intentional the deliberate posture even if it's laying down
and then taking some long slow deliberate breaths deliberate way
of deliberate ritual almost
of turning towards this experience here and now
and deliberately as you exhale to relax the body settle in
deep breath in and then settling into this body
letting your breathing return to normal and then to
as you exhale deliberately bring your attention to different parts of your body
and deliberately actively relax those parts
so and sometimes a sense of deliberateness is a way of being definitive or
clear that this is what i'm going to do now is be here in the present moment
so bring the attention to the face and relaxing on the exhale
all the muscles of the face
softening around the eyes
and if the eyes are trying to look
intentionally searching for something maybe let the eyes rest
soften the eyes in their sockets
into as you exhale
to soften the chest
bring the attention to the shoulders soften the shoulders
bring this the attention to the belly and as you exhale softening the belly
and then bringing the attention to the global body whatever way is easy for you
to have a global awareness of the body
and as you exhale relaxing the body
and there can be a deliberateness around the mind as well
to bring your attention to the mind where you feel the mental
activity and thinking the most
and as you exhale to soften
the mind to quiet the mental activities
calming the thinking mind
and part of the reason we get pulled into distractions
is because there's some emotional force motion emotions that
they're kind of pushing us in a direction or evoking the thoughts
and whatever
anxiety there might be see if you can relax it and soften
in a way that's reassuring to yourself it's okay to be here
relaxed
if there's excitement or desires or aversions or resentments
annoyances that are driving your thinking
on the exhale perhaps you can gently lovingly settle those
quiet those
and then to settle into your breathing to deliberately maybe even
lovingly
turn your attention over [Music] to the experience of the body breathing
making room in your body for the body to breathe just the way it does
lots of breathing rumor to breathe as you're breathing as
the breathing is breathing itself
whatever way your breathing is okay make room for it feel it
hang in there with it
and then imagine that you're at ease resting against a
trunk of a tree looking out upon
a pasture perhaps an expanse and simply see the breathing
in a receptive allowing non-deliberate way
but more receptive way
from the kind of observation
it doesn't interfere with what's being seen
seeing just allows the breathing to be as it is
simply as something to be seen to be observed
as a naturalist would observe
animals and nature without disturbing them just observing them
without judging them just observing
settle down settle back and observe the inhales and the exhales
allowing everything else around you to settle down and relax
because all you need to do is to observe your breathing
when your mind wanders off intentionally deliberately bring it back
and then when you're back see if you can relax the deliberateness
to observe to just sit back and watch observe the breathing
observe your experience in the present moment
as an uninvolved non-interfere observer
just observing
so
when we actively are intentionally deliberately
looking we might not notice the things we're not
looking for but when we're seeing settling back
opening up relaxing we might see a wider range of things the observation the observing
might be broad and more inclusive
as we come to the end of this sitting i'd like to say the same thing is true
for love as wonderful as
intentional deliberate love and acts of love can be
there is loving which is not so deliberate intentional
it's more of an open field like observing
just observing the scenery there's something about
love when it's not directed not so deliberate
that can grow wide and broad and encompass so much more than what we're
direct directing our love towards
and so with our good will to bring these two together love and
observation to settle back and just observe the
the layout the scenery the broad open non-interfering way
can make room for our love to be the same
broad expansive encompassing without interfering
without directing without needing
sitting in with our trunk our back against the trunk of the tree
looking out across the pasture with a love a good will a kindness
for it all the full expanse of love
so in the last moments of this sitting perhaps you can feel your way or
to a way of kindness good will love which
needs nothing from others which is secure in itself
that can just be broad and encompassing at all
broad and non-interfering kindness good will
expressed in the words may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and resting in this kind of good will
may we deliberately express this good will
in some of the details of our contact with other people
may we live this day for the benefit of others
and for ourselves
you