so good day everyone greetings
and you know we've come together to do this
meditation and
the obvious thing is that the act of coming down to meditate sit down here to
be here to meditate together is an action and
meditation itself is a kind of action or in the traditional buddhist language
it's like it's kama karma which literally means action
and many people associate meditation with being rather than doing but the movement
to let go to allow itself to be that is also an action that we do something we're doing we let
go so we can be and um and the
buddha tended to define people if they if he defined people
or described people by what they do not by how they are in a sense of
how they're born especially in ancient india that born into a particular caste was not
interesting for the buddha but how people acted and behaved did they behave ethically or not
and now this is all leading up to the idea that um that in meditation sometimes people
focus a lot on their experience and they maybe they're not having a good experience and so they're trying to have
a better experience or let go of something that seems you know not good and
and fix it or something and and or try to do something that creates a great
experience and so they measure themselves by how they are and in
another whole approach is to let let be in a certain sense how you are
and now focus a little bit more on what you do the actions so in meditation there are
two actions related to concentration that are important there's the action of
beginning again the action of the mind wanders off and we place it back in this case on the
breathing and we connect again with the breathing and the second act action is the action
of hanging in there with the breath once we're we've landed on the breathing to continue
on the breathing and uh and and that's a little bit of an action
to do so and some people don't engage that way
and so they're able to connect to the breathing but they quickly wander off again because there isn't that second action okay now
stay there linger there hang out there get to know it better feel and explore the breathing really
stay present and now so that's one whole thing
but the other thing that's the one what i want to stress today is that the orientation around
action is to do it in a way that's nourishing
to do it in a way that's enjoyable that's wholesome that nourishes us has a good influence
on us so that it's not just the action to do something quickly and get it done with but to do something
with an action that has a nice influence so it's nourishing it's wholesome for our system
so the very ideal way in which we the mind wonders often thought the way we come back from that where we
recognize that come back resist reconnect to the breathing that's an action
that we try to do it in a way that's wholesome that's nourishing that's pleasant that
has a good influence on us so he wouldn't jerk the mind back we wouldn't
attack the breath again bear down we wouldn't be ambitious with greed and
and uh for some kind of meditate meditation states uh we're not expecting something
demanding something it's more like like almost like a
tai chi movement you know that the movement itself is satisfying the movement itself is
meaningful that we come back and we just enjoy the coming back because it's nourishing and wholesome
and like we come back with care with love with with um
and then the second action of sustaining the attention over time hanging in there not bearing
down not keeping the mind in check not reigning the mind in all these forceful things but how can we
stay in a nourishing supportive wholesome way a caring way and this art
and this exploration of how to have the actions we do in meditation the mental
actions be nourishing be satisfying be
you know enjoyable gladdening for us is part of this art and uh so learning exploring thinking
about this as we meditate so that um you know we are not so goal oriented
with the action but rather maybe like tai chi or beautiful qigong practice
where our dance practice we're just doing the movement is so satisfying and meaningful that's
the important thing not where it gets us and so the movement of landing and staying on
the breath the movement of of staying there and sustaining it
that's that's what supports uh a nourishing samadhi nourishing
concentration um so to
assume your meditation posture and prepare yourself for the meditation
a bit to consider how you can be here
in a wholesome way how you can be here so that
you enter into your the activity of meditation
with a sense of beauty or nourishment or wholesomeness
not in a hurry not resisting anything
not expecting or demanding that your meditation should be a certain way
and then beginning right away to see if you can land on your breathing
connect to your breathing in a nourishing way in a nice way wholesome way
so the very way in which you take in the breathing and aware of it
has some maybe spaciousness care [Music] love tenderness
some way of being as you would be with a a good friend you care for
and the way you attend your garden when you're in love with your garden
and then in this caring nourishing way taking a slow gentle deep breath
allowing yourself to take in and feel the goodness of a deeper breath
and the goodness of allowing that to happen
and then relaxing as you exhale
relaxing your whole body
letting your breathing return to normal
and can you adjust a little bit your state of mind your state of your heart
just a little if that's all that's possible so you have a nice attitude a good
attitude wholesome
as if you're getting ready to
do tai chi or mental tai chi or mental gardening
and mental caring for something that you
love perhaps by relaxing the thinking mind
softening the energy of thinking
relaxing the muscles that are connected to thinking the pressure the tension to be here
and then gently calmly connecting to the beginning of the
in-breath receiving the beginning of the in-breath
and then sustaining the attention for however short or long the in-breath
is so you're there with a full in-breath
sustained attention
connecting with the beginning of the out breath
and then sustaining the whole out breath
and these two movements of connecting
receiving the beginning of each in-breath and out-breath and then to
sustain the attention on the full out-breath the fallen breath
can you do that in a wholesome way nourishing way
it is an action can you make it an action which is free of greed or hatred
or delusion confusion free of
wanting it to be different
pushing something away aversion
is simplicity of maybe generosity
love and care
and the attention to the breathing
and to support the sustained attention through the exhale especially
you might count the exhales
a gentle careful count of one that maybe gets stretched out the whole
length of the exhale one [Music]
and then the next exhale two
if you lose count start over again and count up to ten or up to three
or up to one
exploring the wholesomeness and nourishment
of attending to the breathing
so then as we come to the end of this sitting
what do you know about having your mind be wholesome
nourishing
a mind which feels satisfied
and if the mind is not that way
can you remember that the mind is a
collection of mental activities it's not a thing
what can you adjust mentally your way you think what you think
what you're oriented towards what you're expecting hoping for
so that how you are mentally or heartfully
feels as if it has a good influence on you maybe if things are hard that what has a
good influence is to be forgiving
or to be friendly
or to be generous towards yourself
to have compassion for the challenges
to appreciate whatever wholesomeness is here
nourishment there is here
and let that be a reference point stay close to that or either feeling it or imagining it
and then again imagine that you're with someone who is challenging for you
but you don't have to speak or do anything you're just sitting in the same room together
and staying close to your nourishing mind your wholesome mind and heart
without having to do or say anything what happens if you take in the other
person the challenging person
if you think about them is there some way that
then there's a chance for your care your friendliness your tenderness
to be touched by that other person
and you staying close to that place where you feel wholesome
a way of being that feels satisfying for you
so not getting caught up in shoulds and shouldn'ts he said she said the resentments
the fears just staying close to what's wholesome for you
has a good influence on you
and then imagine that you do so for the whole world
that you include the whole world and your wholesome heart your wholesome mind your wholesome
awareness
that wholesomeness is the reference point for how to think and feel about other
people may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
so
before i begin this talk i want to mention that
the way i calculate and uh next monday it'll be one year
anniversary of having done these early morning in california these
daily sittings weekday sittings meditations and teachings
kind of remarkable that it's lasted a year and and um and remarkable
for how for many of us how wonderful it's been to do this so i thought that next monday we could
do a community meeting to acknowledge celebrate this one year mark
and we haven't done it for a long time and
my own personal life has meant that i can't it's been hard to do add more things like that but um i can
do it next monday and uh so we can um
so it'll be there'll be a zoom meeting so after we finish here at about 7 45
you'll be given access to a zoom link and then we'll switch over to the zoom and be able to meet and
hang out and talk and maybe break up maybe break into little groups and so you can chat a little bit with uh
this youtube community and maybe meet some of the people whose names appear on the you know in the chat
and then we can also talk a little bit about some of the maybe some of the questions and issues around our little
community and this meetings and uh the continuation of it and all that planning to continue
and um so so next monday the 15th
so one of the foundational cornerstone teachings of
the buddha and that intimately connects to both meditation and living a daily life is
the idea of wholesome and unwholesome sometimes it's translated skillful and
unskillful more informally i like to translate it as helpful and unhelpful
that that there is a way of of and it has to do with the
actions what we do that we and some of those actions don't really maybe in english we don't think
of them as in actions but more like states wholesome states but they still have a kind of a little bit
they're an activity of the mind in the background somehow and so um these are these are
states of mind actions of the mind activities of the mind ways of being that feel like as if
they're nourishing and that word nourishing is a is a word that the buddha used that's
different things different mental states and mental activities operated as food as nourishment for
ourselves so it isn't just simply generosity's generosity generosity is a wholesome
state a healthy state that is nourishing that has a good
influence on us so loving-kindness is that
mindfulness is considered a wholesome state that is nourishing and and has a good influence on us
tranquility is a wholesome state wholesome way of being that is uh as a
nourishing it nourishes us nourishes more tranquility and and so this idea of both of
nourishment wholesomeness comes into play now in the third tetrath of the 16 steps of
anapanasati in a number of ways the
tenth step is gladdening the mind and this gliding the mind some people's translated as satisfying the mind or
or enjoying the mind and this comes with the ability to feel
the goodness the delight the enjoyment not just of pleasure but of this nourishment this
wholesomeness that can happen and this comes with as we no longer
fixate or focus on the details of our inner life
but begin looking at the big picture and that's what uh being experiencing the mind as a whole
we're not preoccupied with the past preoccupied by the future our desires are focusing on particular emotions that
we have that are really troublesome for us all reasonable things to do at times but
to um but as we go deeper and deeper into meditation we're relaxing and letting go and not
fixating on things that there's a softening and a deepening and an opening
that begins happening that we've become aware of the the general the quality of our inner
life and another way i'd like to translate chitta the mind or the heart
the whole the holistic a whole quality of the inner life and as we let go a lot and going through
these deeper states of meditation we tap into um
we tap into a sense of wholesomeness a goodness and some nourishing nourishment
something it feels very satisfying just to be here and now this becomes a valuable
thing to experience this becomes something to imbibe to feel to allow itself to be influenced by
and so and so to understand that the buddhist teachings is based on this
movement towards the wholesome and to the degree to which we do what's wholesome do wholesome things in our life uh
skillful things do things which are ethically wholesome that is psychologically wholesome
that leads to a sense of being whole rather than being fragmented a sense of
being inclusive rather than holding things at bay and holding things in check
this becomes very important as we start moving into developing samadhi or unification the
eleventh step of anupanasati breathing in one unifies the mind
breathing out one unifies the mind another translator breathing in one steadys the mind
breathing out one steadys the mind another translator breathing in one
concentrates the mind breathing out one concentrates the mind so these words
unify steady concentrate are all in the domain of this
fourth this third tetrad when experiences the mind one gladdens or satisfies the mind and
then one concentrates unifies the mind and the sequence points to the fact that
it's a lot easier for the mind to get unified to gather together to get organized to get settled to be
steady um when there's a feeling of when the mind feels like a satisfying place an
enjoyable place to be the heart is wholesome and good
and so we're not recoiling from inner pain or struggle or angst
we're not afraid of ourselves and and trying to avoid parts of ourselves
we've come to the place where we're now we're inclusive the mind we associate more with the
inclusivity of the big mind rather than the particular details we
might still have particular details that are difficult for sure but it's not where we're locked into or
what we're preoccupied with we respect it but where now the mind holds it all
in a more expansive open way and then expansive open mind that is is where we begin
feeling something allows for something wholesome and satisfying and deep to happen
and so rather than huffing and puffing to get concentrated it's more like da this is good
the mind wants to settle the mind wants to go into uh
into uh you know be more subtle doesn't want to be scattered in fact to be scattered to go into the
past and the future to be caught up in thoughts to become narrow again or
locked into something again it just starts feeling not doesn't really feel interesting it's not like it's like why would you
and there's not much juice much energy to to be distracted because it feels so
good to be here right here so maybe my way i'm talking is kind of grand
and grandiose a little bit seems like a little bit beyond what's possible for you but what
i want to emphasize is that we are kind of moving in the direction of an
inner goodness and inner wholesomeness and inner some kind of way that inner life feels satisfying
and i like to use the word we feel at home in ourselves oh i'm home it's so good to be here of course i want to be here
and it's with this mind this way of being that when we connect to our breathing
that we do it in a way that feels satisfying tender caring we appreciate the opportunity to
start again rather than being a burden and rather being dejected or dismayed that we
wondered often thought we feel ah yes i come home this is good
and then when we sustain the attention it's not because we're struggling to do it or holding things at bay
it's because we are ah this is good i'm home and this feels nice to be here in the
present moment so the um it's called the initial
application of attention this connecting and the sustained application of
attention this sustaining attention ideally it's all you all kind of nourishing
and maybe each of you can have a different um um reference pointer example that
supports you for this uh i used in the meditation idea of doing tai chi
tai chi of the mind coming back to your breathing hanging in there with breathing those
gentle flowing movements of tai chi where the point isn't to get to the end of the tai
chi movements as quickly as you can the point is there's an action we're doing tai chi
but we're each moment we're just is complete in itself is we're really into that part of the movement
for some of you might be gardening maybe you love gardening or just being and weeding and planting just
doing it there's not you're not in a hurry to do it it's just tender it's nourishing it's
maybe it's kind of a parental feeling of your plan so just kind of tending and
caring maybe it's a craft maybe it's caring for someone who's sick that you do
do it in a loving way so you might think about what example you have in your life of doing something which
has qualities of wholesomeness nourishment
satisfaction inner goodness that is the that represents for you the
movement we're going the downhill slope the pull of gravity of meditation
this is where we go going and and with that we cultivate unification
we cultivate a steadiness a deep subtleness in what some people call concentration
so enjoy yourself enjoy your mind
and or provide your mind with a way of being that
the mind enjoys let your inner actions inner attitudes thoughts and feelings
be something the mind really appreciates that the mind feels ah this is good the mind says oh i like
being with this person i like being here i don't feel like i need to run off anymore
because the way this is operating for this person this is really good and maybe your mind will
stick around and stick around for your breathing and for your meditation in the present moment
so thank you all very much and i look forward to tomorrow