so welcome another warm welcome to everyone from everywhere
joining here together in this 7 a.m pacific time sitting
and so i'm going to begin so just allow yourself to settle in
maybe take some generous moments to settle into a sitting posture as conducive for
a little bit of a meditative practice
and this week i wanted to maybe offer a
guided meditation that starts with what i call the arriving sequence
and this is something i learned from some of my teachers
dana de palma and tuarey salah and then philip moffat
who's their teachers our teachers and so this arriving sequence
uses the three a's arriving
and then uh being available
um and then becoming becoming available
and then aligning so those are three words and you probably will begin to hear
repeatedly as we go along in this five days of a meditation practice
and so we'll begin with a writing sequence and then uh in this week i wanted to
offer some words using the elements
elements that make up our body as part of our meditative practice
so earth air water fire and space
and this is going to be a build up from the first day and all the way to
on the friday and so if you join in between you will
pick it up because we will be repeating some of this as we go along
so let's begin
arriving
arriving here and now
maybe the word arriving evokes some sense of
beginning to settle in
and sometimes i have the sense of coming back home
after a long trip arriving home
maybe putting away the bags add
a big jacket in the same way as we arrive
maybe we put away the plans the projects memory
we arrive at the present moment
experience over here and now
maybe that's felt as the contact of the body with the chairs and the floor
there's some long deep breath that's happening right now
arriving home the home of this body
take a few moments to just checking into yourself
maybe the sitting posture
maybe how you are in your mind
not as a way to evaluate judging it
just to receive what is happening here now
as you arrive make yourself available
to the lived experience that's happening right now right here
in this body
being available is pointing at
the sense of receiving experience
as they arrive and pass
and not demanding it to be any way just making ourselves available
to whatever is happening right here
and then we align align our being with a wholesome
cultivation
aligned with our inner integrity inner dignity
sometimes for me aligning may be experienced as
i throw so slightly a little bit of uplifting in my torso
making ourselves available to the physicality of our bodies
i invite you to maybe turn attention to the third sense of earth element in the
body
maybe you're feeling the firmness
as you make contact with earth and floor chairs
hardness of the bones
your tongue pushing against the teeth partners of the teeth
earth element is a heavy
maybe subtly that settling downwards
making ourselves available for the felt sense of earth element
letting go of any big ideas about what this is
however it's about in the body
it is okay
the earthy body resting on earth
maybe you feel some sense of the steadiness as you rest in
the earthy body
there is a stillness in the earth element
on moving
look at foundations of a building
and the mind wanders away and always invite ourselves to arrive
again
being available to the first sense of earth element
in this body
being available is like letting go of any exertion or
control rather open our heart and mind to
receive
noticing our experience that may be pleasant and
unpleasant
maybe pain or discomfort in the body
and pay careful attention to see
how are we reacting or responding
to the experience of a pleasant and unpleasant
or they are pushing away resisting wishing the unpleasant to go away
are their signs of ease openness
kindness
do all of this
the buddha offered a teaching to his son rahula
you said to your son young son
meditate like earth when you meditate like earth
pleasant unpleasant experiences will not occupy your mind
so we won't get caught when we meditate in the stillness and stability
that's manifested in the earth meditated like earth
steady stable
unmoving
as we transition into the short tarmet
for this mornings i invite you to continue
maybe to stay in a meditative mode if you like
and so i intentionally didn't ring the bell
as an invitation for you to maybe receive this teachings
in a different way maybe
and so this week i wanted to share
some words about selah
i called these mornings of the teachings the blessings of vasila
sila is a pony term that's often used to translate as a virtuous conduct
a virtuous behavior and one can think of it as
behaving virtuously through one's bodily and verbal actions
and so there is an outer expression of sila
and that may be an um natural extension of our inner being
and the inner integrity i have mentioned in our sitting
the inner care inner tenderness
and so this week i wanted to offer the exploration of vasila from
this inside out kind of orientation
and this is not the only way that we used to explore sila
and i thought i try something different in fact
the classic teachings of facilla often began
from refraining harmful actions externally
and then kind of from outside in but i thought that
many of you have been uh practicing and this is 7 am
sittings and maybe many other ways so i thought maybe we'll do something a
little different about sila just an inside out kind of orientation
and also wanted to offer a free framework for us to explore this
and that is the framework of triple a and i'm calling again another
aaa 3a that's different from our meditation triple a
so this is three a's are aware ab sting
and a line oh i see uh there's some um messages
about whether the sound is okay um and if there is a couple of people can
just type in the chat box and see if my volume is okay and now
okay so i do see a few people saying okay
um i'll speak louder hopefully that'll help
you for letting me know also and so this triple a aware
abstinent and align um
okay so aware means that um
as we cultivate mindfulness we become aware of our inner dynamics
and inner forces and that operate inside of us
we notice some dynamics and forces that may lead to
harmful consequences harmful outcome and then we abstain
from the harmful actions and harmful forces
and then line says that we align with
wholesome qualities so as we become aware we can also pay attention and see
how the whole sum can come about and so as we begin to notice this
and we can cultivate align ourselves with the wholesale and skillful
in our actions in our behavior and so this is the framework i'm going
to use and to explore this aspects of fasila
the classic teachings of sila especially for the lay community
are often as referred to as undertaking the training
rules of five precepts and today i'll share some reflections of
the first one which is undertaking the training rules of
not taking the lives of a living being or not killing living beings
and so you may all wonder why bother right especially right after
a meditative practice and none of us are killing anybody or
any living beings so why would we explore this
uh well and to answer this question i wanted to
maybe unpack on the poly term that's related to this particular precept a
little more the pali term on
panettipata in particular has this sense of the very vivid sense
of exerting some kind of violence kind of
like a striking down um a living being which would lead to
um taking the life of a living being and so for me uh the sense of
violence aggression is what this precept is also pointing at
and so let's explore this uh from the uh the inner perspective we talked about
in our guided meditation i invited you to
maybe take pay attention and becoming aware how we might relate to our
inner experiences that pleasant unpleasant experience that happened in us
in particular the unpleasant experience
i'm just kind of curious what you might notice it's very often that when
there is unpleasant whether it's pain and discomfort in the body
often there can be an attitude of pushing it away wanting it to go away
or sometimes we even have you know maybe subtle sense of
aggression towards it if we had a um
an option to somehow get rid of that we would have done it right
and so there are some of those kind of anger forces that can happen and as we become aware of them
we see oh you know this can happen within us
and this kind of forces when it gets manifested externally
it can express itself as aggression or violence version
and so for example now we may all have had this experience
that um you know a bee or a fly is a buzzing around us non-stop and it's not going away
so yeah and we all kind of abide to this
first precept and not wanting to kill kill the bee or kill the fly but we can
act um maybe at some point we get really frustrated and we'll kind of pull we
throw our hands up and and you know what uh from the perspective the b and the fly and this
gesture might be life-threatening or
some sense a little violent
so as we tune in to our inner dynamics we can begin to see oh
how we relate to unplugged unpleasant experience
internally can get manifested externally
and so this preceptor invites us to begin to really tune in to some of these forces
and abstain from externally externally not killing living beings
but also maybe pointing internally are there some
different ways to relate to unpleasant experience
in the sutta that i quoted on about the teachings of
the buddha offered to his son rahula and it reads like this
i'm going to read this piece again
rahula meditated like the earth when you meditate like the earth
pleasant and unpleasant contacts will not occupy your mind
so what is pointing at is that as we cultivate
mindful awareness our inner capacity grows
we can begin to have a choice of not being moved by the experienced and pleasant of
unpleasant maybe we you know use the word um
equanimity for it maybe we can be equanimous to our
experience that are pleasant and unpleasant
and so this is a form of alignment a line with a whole sound qualities
kindness compassion equanimity i remember that many years ago when i
was learning meditation from a chinese numb
once she was offering me a meditation instruction
right in the courtyard of um tatakata meditation center
and we were standing right under a uh a tree
and then there was a bug falling off right on hero
and i was about to jump out but she very gently using the cup of the hand
picked up the bug and gently put it on the ground
that was a very powerful teaching for me i thought to myself at that moment wow
there's something very precious and beautiful in her
and so this brought me much trust and confidence in the teachings of the buddha in the
buddha dharma and sangha also lots of trust in this teacher of my own and chinese
nun offering the teachings because the way that she expressed to
herself offered such a possibility of the kind
of a heart and mind in each of us
and so the flip side of not killing is to offer our deep respect
and the appreciation to all beings all living all lives around us
and all lives are wonderous on this planet
we are only an aspect of this whole ecosystem
so our lives are intertwined with the different species and nature
so who are way to decide on how other lives must live or not
and so align with kindness align with
gentleness align with respect
and so this is three aspects of aware becoming aware of our inner dynamics
and um taking actions to abstain from that is
unwholesome unskillful and harmful and then um
aligning ourselves with that is wholesome and so the practice of this first
precept offers much protection and safety to oneself and to all beings
so as such this precept is a true blessing
very very much true blessing for all beings
and so i want to share this a few words and to end today's tarmet and this is from the
mankala suta and the suta for blessings and it says the buddha said that
desisting and abstaining from evil diligence in good qualities
respect and humility this is the highest blessing
so may you all be blessed by your virtuous conduct and you practice
so thank you all for being here and um i see there are maybe some challenges in
terms of a volume and sound and i hope i'll do something uh today to
help resolve this um we'll continue tomorrow so thank you so much everyone for being
here have a wonderful rest of the day i'll see you back tomorrow
in the morning here pacific time