welcome welcome everybody hope that you're well
and i'm happy to be practicing with you with you all
so to begin our meditation
just arriving this moment
arriving to this constellation of experiences
and feeling into the body what is it like to be here and now
at this moment
i like this expression to sit and know you're sitting
to sit with some balance some ease some alertness some uprightness
maybe checking in with the body and see if there are any obvious places
of tightness or a little bit of discomfort
can we gaze upon them kindly with our mindfulness
it might be that if we bring some kindness some warmth
some non-aversion to those aspects of our experience that
are uncomfortable
they might unfold differently under the gaze of kindness
no guarantees
this is such a part of mindfulness practice it's bringing our awareness
to whatever is arising including the uncomfortable aspects
allowing the awareness to rest on the sensations of breathing
feeling the expansion contraction as the body breathes
we might feel that in the chest maybe in the belly
maybe we feel the air going in and out of the nose
and when the mind wanders as its want to do
just very simply gently begin again
allowing the attention to rest on the sensations of breathing
and when we find ourselves replaying a story lost in a fantasy
a memory or planning we just very simply begin again
with the sensations of breathing
can we do this without annoyance or irritation or exasperation
when we realize that we've been lost in thought
just very simply gently begin again
it doesn't matter how many times
we need to begin again
so much of what mindfulness practice is about
let's just beginning again having the patience
to hang in there
and allow the awareness the attention to come back
to the sensations of breathing however many times it needs to
what would it be like to bring patience to our practice
recognizing that it takes time for the mind to settle
maybe you've had a busy day lots of planning lots of decisions or
problems that to work with can we just bring patience
this recognition that things might be a little bit uncomfortable or not
settled but that's okay we just
begin again
learning to be patient with our practice in our practice with
our minds is a way that we can make room for them
to be the way that they are sometimes our minds are busy restless
sometimes they may be drowsy or foggy
but many of us who have a meditation practice know if we just exercise a little bit of patience
and very gently begin again with the sensations of breathing
and the mind settles
so how might we bring this lesson of patience to other areas of our life
so that our practice can support us and those we come in contact with
so that our practice is for the benefit of all beings
everywhere
so a very warm welcome i wish that you are all
safe and have some well-being
really warm welcome
so tonight i'd like to continue on this exploration of the pyramids
these ten qualities that our support for awakening and support for our
improved or for our general well-being
last week i spoke about loving kindness which was a little was out of sequence
but i gave the dharma talk on loving-kindness because i had taught about loving-kindness in another
setting and it was what was on my heart and mind
but now i'd like to go back to the sequence of the pyramids these ten qualities of generosity
ethical behavior renunciation wisdom
energy patience truth resolve loving-kindness and equanimity
so loving kindness is number nine but now i'd like to go back to number six patience
and maybe i should say from the outset as i was thinking about this talk and doing some reading and
listening to other dharma teachers you know how did they approach uh patients it became abundantly clear
to me that oh this is the parame for me i hadn't really noticed it so much
before but how much impatience shows up in my own life
so i'm humbly sitting here sharing this with you this recognition that yes in particular
i think patience is something for me to to work on and to practice with and it
shows up in so many different ways maybe it um shows up in all kinds of
different ways for you too and i'll talk about some of that this evening
but patience is sixth in this list of parmies or perfections these qualities
that we can perfect quote unquote as a support for our lives and as a
support for awakening so patience comes after energy
viria and we might say that patience and viria counterbalance each
other that is that is
when i spoke about the pyramids of energy i shared this um the simile
about the goldsmith so that is that the and the buddha gave this simile
saying that when a goldsmith wants to work with gold they heat up a crucible
a um a container and when it's hot they put the gold in there
and sometimes the goldsmith blows on the gold to heat it up sometimes they sprinkle
water on it to cool it down and sometimes they just stand by
so pointing to this need for sometimes heating things up with energy sometimes cooling them down and
sometimes just standing by and we could say that this just standing by is patience
so the permeate energy is about arousing energy kind of like allowing
energy to arise but also to balance it with patience
that is that it's practice isn't only about applying more and more energy i think we all know this
but sometimes we don't think about a counterbalance as being patients that is this way
that we can allow things to unfold
to kind of like stand back and look on and see how things are going does it need a little does the gold need
a little bit more blowing on or does it need a little bit of water to be sprinkled on cooled down
one thing that i appreciate that in this simile about the goldsmith buddha continues with the simile and
says that when the gold is the right temperature when it has the right amount
of malleability then the goldsmith can make earrings or
necklaces or bracelets or garlands out of it we might imagine that it takes patience
also to make jewelry earrings can be really small you know some some
minute uh fine details some fine work take some patience and some steadyness
just to work with the gold any artisanal activity we might do whether
it's knitting or crocheting or sewing or
woodworking or sculpting whatever it might be this certain amount of patience is
required in just the same way that the way we kind of like are shaping our minds
with mindfulness practice
yeah sorry sorry that i am i had to cough there i'm frantically looking for the
mute button so that i can not cough into the microphone
and but if we might say that if one is too patient however and then
one doesn't make any effort then just letting everything take its own course just standing by
then we can get bogged down into maybe this sloth and torpor or laziness
or slovenliness or sometimes you know just if we have is our standard approach just
to not put any energy forward some of us might not have energy due to
illness but to not put any energy forward whatever amount that we have
then we might just feel that our life kind of drifts away and it doesn't we don't accomplish
things that are helpful for our lives that help our lives unfold in a
direction that we would like to go towards greater and greater freedom so
what we need is a delicate balance some energy some effort some endeavoring
as well as some patients standing back looking observing seeing what's
happening without interfering
so those of you who are familiar with this simile of the goldsmith might know that actually the buddha says that the
standing by and looking on at the gold is actually equanimity he's not saying that it's patience so we
might ask what is the difference between patience and equanimity they both have this quality of
looking by or you know not being pushed to jump into activity
so patience we might say is not acting on our impatience
it's not acting on our irritation our annoyance our exasperation our wish for things to
be different so we might note we notice we might sense that there is a
some discontent a little bit of uneasiness this might be obvious with some really strong
restlessness or it might be subtle might be really subtle just this little nagging feeling
that sometimes the mind has this restlessness of this is boring
what else is you know what else can i um conjure up in my mind that's a little
more interesting or there might be a sense of i wish
something else was happening that's not quite right this kind of feeling of things not being
quite right we could say this impatience why aren't i awakened completely yet
so patience allows us to go through these all these
experiences of life these these little annoyances irritations
exasperations without acting on them so it's not
saying that we aren't experiencing those that's all those different uh
expressions of discontent but we're not acting on them
we're staying with what is we're not acting out
in contrast equanimity is when we're not actually experiencing
irritation exasperation annoyance if this
discontent that wishing that things were different and a desire for things to be a certain way or an aversion to the way
things are equanimity is when those things simply aren't arising
so maybe from the outside patients and equanimity look the same but patience is allows us to be with all
the experiences of our life we're not always equanimous we probably
won't always be equanimous until we're completely awakened so patience is a way that allows us to
engage with the completeness of the human experience
and allows us maybe is an expression of some wisdom that we might bring to our experience of
things having some dukkha things not being exactly as we would like
and i appreciate that sylvia borstein she calls patients this unglamorous courage
the quiet moment-to-moment adjustment to unpleasant circumstances this
recognition that this does not match my preferences
but i'm not going to act out
so in this way practicing patients require some unpleasant circumstances
it's not like that we can practice it in the absence of unpleasant
circumstances you know it's not like a quantifiable object it's not a commodity
that we can just get an abundance of and then draw on it later even though
sometimes our language might be that i'm feeling short of patience or i'm getting to the end of my patients
i'm losing my patients we have these expressions but instead patience is a quality that
arises in the midst of some difficulties
just like courage courage and patience these qualities that
we develop and when in the midst of our lives and our daily lives
and so we don't need to devise situations in which to cultivate patients
or present themselves freely and i've been thinking about this
patient's back when i was um a research scientist
and i often would want to kind of create shortcuts on my experiments
i felt like oh incubate overnight oh i don't need to incubate this overnight i can just do it for two hours surely
that's enough and and then the experience of you know
experiments not turning out so now when i look back on that just the
way that kind of impatience shows up and i didn't really have the
patience then to really follow the protocols and trust
that you know following the instructions in these ways might be helpful even if it takes longer
maybe we have the same way with cooking oh i don't need to marinate this
overnight it'll be fine if i just cook it the way it is
unlike these research experiments the food still turns out fine but it turns out differently
so what are some ways in which uh impatient shows up for you
maybe i'll share another thing for me sometimes while i'm driving i find myself as uh not very
kind hearted but sometimes when i find myself behind somebody who's going
on the freeways going way below the um the speed limit i find myself you
know a little bit irritated like and i find myself saying out loud the rest of us are on the freeway
so a little bit of you know irritation that shows up so patience how might we take different
just so many small little opportunities that we have in the day to say oh okay here's my chance
here's my chance to practice with patience what does it mean to not try to pull out
our phone and immediately entertain ourselves what does it mean to not give in to the
impatience and allow it to tumble forward and get more and more irritation and said
can we just notice oh yeah this is what impatience feels like
maybe i'll say something else that i noticed in myself that
sometimes um when i first started a meditation practice and i was a yoga practice
i was just getting more and more accustomed to bringing my awareness to what my body was doing and
how it was oriented in space you know kind of really firming up this mind-body connection
and one thing that was really noticeable for me is that sometimes standing in line
grocery store or whenever i'd be standing with my hand on my hip
you know okay like maybe with my hip jutted out with this idea you know if you were to see me you
would see like oh that person's impatient but i didn't even notice that i was impatient until i noticed the
posture that my body was in so again what are some ways in which
inpatient shows up with for you not so that you can beat yourself up about it
but so that we might say oh okay practice the pyramids it's a practice
that's really encouraged to do in our daily life so what would it be like to have a
little more patience in this moment
so in our daily life but also in our mindfulness practice if mindfulness is not a practice about
patients i'm not exactly sure what is the fact that mindfulness requires
patience is an early lesson right when we start practicing mindfulness maybe
the first lesson is to realize how out of control our minds are and maybe the second
lesson is oh yeah this is going to require some patience
just bring the mind back again and again
and again over and over we do meditation session after
meditation session we go on retreat after retreat we listen to dharma talk after dharma talk
just like any skill just like any thing that we wish to learn it takes
patience
so chances are that we started a meditation practice because we had some expectations
we wanted to feel better we wanted to embark on a spiritual practice
perhaps and chances are that our expectations
weren't met the first time that we meditated but maybe there was a hint
of something of the possibility that our expectations could be met
but when starting our practice we realized oh when i have these really high
expectations perhaps i had this pleasurable meditation experience and
i'd like to have that experience again we we all have this experience of wishing for that to happen again
and then when it doesn't this feeling of frustration or irritation
so can we bring some patience to that of course we want things to turn out a
certain way of course we have expectations this is the human experience
as our mindfulness practice grows as our maybe our wisdom
practice grows we can start to see how creating and holding onto really tightly to
expectations is creating the conditions for suffering but we only see that
or really learn it after we've seen that countless times how many times
but patience allows us to watch our experience of mind and body
over again and with this kind of watching the mind and the body we discover how we are perpetuating our
suffering how we are perpetuating our difficulties
whether it's the big giant big giant difficulties or the small ones
what role does our mind have and and contributing to the suffering
as a society we certainly want things to happen quickly the insta pot just the name of this
right was a sensation i know a number of years ago people were talking about this new cooking appliance with this
name instapot like how can we not want something that's going to instantly cook things not only do we want things
to happen quickly but we want them to be pleasurable and predictable
but with patience can we be willing to just simply practice
can we be willing to embrace our mindfulness practice as an opportunity to simply meet each moment of our
experience as it is without insisting that the moment be
different without insisting that we be different
and just like sometimes we notice that at the beginning of the meditation period our mind might be really restless
the body might be uncomfortable but with with some patients as the
meditation session progresses most often there's some settling there's some more
ease that arises so with that kind of recognition that if
we hang in there then there can be some greater ease and
there can be some greater wisdom some learnings as the mind starts to settle down we
start to see where the impatience if i can use this word is showing up as some aversion or some
desire some of these root
the word is defilements but i don't like this word defilements some of these root tendencies that we
have that humans have
so with patients we can start to hang in there long enough that we can
start to see how we contribute to some of our suffering and then we can soften or let go
some of those ways in which we contribute to our suffering
so also we can have patients in our interactions with others
patients just how things how situations are unfolding patients in our mindfulness practice and
patience with how we interact with others
patients pre is a way that it protects our good qualities in the way that
perhaps anger which we might say is the opposite of patients if patients is some cool
standing by patients is some fiery engagement
and in the way that anger we might say or do things that are destructive
including our sense of well-being or destroying our relationships or
our sense of our self you know the we might um have regret and remorse
anger can easily lead us to be off balance
and to maybe there's like this blind anger of
lashing out which we are disconnected from our wisdom
maybe disconnected from ourselves in the moment in some kind of ways and lashing out blindly is
never the way to solve problems but instead with patience we can solve problems
and this gets um highlighted in a story that the buddha
tells to some of his monastics
so the buddha is telling the story about the this battle that went on between the
gods and the demons and i guess maybe in ancient times or something like this
and you know as is the case for these types of stories the gods win the battle and the demons lose
and then the ruler of the demons his name is vaipachiti is brought
to the ruler of the gods sakka
demon hurls all these insults at the ruler of the gods and while this
is happening the ruler of the gods sakka his charioteer so somebody who is part of
his army is nearby and sees that the ruler of the demons
is insulting his king the king of the gods
so metalli is the name of the charioteer
so mitholi says to his king the king of the gods o sucka is it from fear
or from weakness that you put up with such harsh words in the presence of a
pachitti so matali is i can't believe that
he's that uh sokka is not fighting back it is not
spewing um angry insults even though he won the war the battle
and vapor chitty i guess is in um irons or it's in harnessed in some way so the
charioteer can't believe that this happens that uh sakka
is not fighting back maybe i should say that this is verse it written in verse and for me it
has a little bit of a feeling of a shakespearean play it's not exactly that but has a little
bit of that kind of feeling so the charioteer says osaka
is it from fear or from weakness that you put up with such harsh words in the presence of apachetti
saka responds it's not out of fear or weakness that i'm patient with vaipachiti for how can a sensible
person like me get in a fight with a fool
the charioteer responds but fools would vent even more if there's no one to put a stop to them
a wise person should stop a fool with forceful punishment so the
charioteer clearly doesn't like that sakka is just being patient thinks he
should have punished the king of the god the king of the demons
saka responds i think that this is the only way to put a stop to a
fool when you know that the other is upset be mindful
and stay calm when you know that the other is upset be mindful and stay calm
metalli just can't agree with us and he responds i see this fault in just being patient
when a fool thinks he puts up with me out of fear
then the fool will will go after you even more like a bull chasing someone who runs
away then osaka responds let him think
he puts up with me out of fear if he wishes goals
culminating in one's own good none better than patience is found
of goals culminating in one's own good none better than patience
is found patience and when experiencing
insults in this example but how many other
situations in our lives might patience be the right response
when our minds get overrun and obsessed by anger or whatever it might be
we might feel miserable and want to get rid of it but we can't because these thoughts keep bubbling up
can we have some patience and just like our meditation practice that recognizes okay with time
the mind can settle the heart can soften
if we create the conditions in which some settling can happen if we have the patience
then we can come back maybe to our bodies to the moment and allow our greatest wisdom to arise
this last line of goals culminating in one's own good
none better than patience is found so may you find patience when you need
it for any of your difficulties that you meet in these days and might we meet some difficulties with
patients that allows things to unfold in a way that brings greater ease and well-being not
only to ourselves but to everyone to others so that our practice
might be for the well-being of all beings everywhere thank you
you