good morning friends welcome once again
and uh this morning we're going to continue with this exploration of the elements
and yesterday we started with the earth element
and today i want to continue with water element and i have a
quote a sort of transitional quote for us from a native american elder who was
at standing rock and unfortunately i don't know them their name but this is what they said
in the beginning there was first stone then there was water when the two came together they created
a sacred sound that sound is the life energy
so spoke about earth yesterday this being made up of the mineral of the dust
of the substance of the earth but clearly
if we were just earth we would just be piles of dust piles of dirt
nothing nothing uh much could happen with that and it's the water
it's like you know you take dirt and you add water and now you've got something malleable something that
can hold together that has cohesion that can has a fluidity
potential to it no longer brittle and this is us we're mixed this mix
of the elements and profoundly so the earth and the water
and when we work with the elements as i spoke with about some yesterday we're
using them to break down this story of separation and isolation this story of i
me and mine and we do that working with the elements in
a number of ways and i just wanted to name those before we move into the guided meditation
that part of what we're doing is changing the conceptual story that we carry around
we are all we are all living by stories we have stories that we tell ourselves
and we tell each other in our mind and many of these stories are centered around i me and mine and as
we practice with the elements we are inviting a change in this story
in this conceptual story we're also when we work with the
elements feeling we're bypassing the story all together at times we're
feeling directly this through the other sense gates besides the thinking one we're feeling
into the body and sensing the element of earth and today the element of water as we feel it
and know it through our sensory perception and we've i've added in sound today
because i have a little waterfall behind me so we can feel the water element in us directly and
this is part of what we do when we are practicing with the water element and then we also play with
the element metaphorically or poetically sort of bridging this gap from the story
into the body into the experience of it so you'll hear in the
guided meditations of the elements that we go back and forth at times we do touch
into the conceptual trying to change the story that we're carrying and then at other times we're just feeling directly
in the body and sometimes just touching sort of like sparking a different way of seeing and
knowing so i wanted to start with the poetic
this is a poem from rosemary watula trauma called the great beyond
and once again the invitation to see beyond the self the way water knows itself
not only as river and lake but also as fern as cloud as cat
forgive me for believing i end with this skin these ideas these imaginings
sometimes i forget to choose vastness forget to know the self
as cliff as mataki as crum how is it i so often miss the invitation
how is it i overlook that i am lemon asteroid ren
so let's do a little remembering so go ahead and find your
meditation posture
settle in feel your contact with the ground sense through the body
relaxing opening
letting your eyes close if you're comfortable with that
and as you relax you might just start to notice that there are places where there might
be a kind of rigidity or a frozen-ness and as you relax them
there's a softening in that relaxing you're connecting with
the water in that part of the body allowing it to
come into its more fluid nature not holding it
freezing it in place but instead opening it
feel your legs in contact with the ground
notice how they are for that how they're affected by
both the pull of gravity and what they have contact with the way that they're formed
pooling soft
you can start to sense the
water the wateriness inside your body
drop letting the water drop towards the ground
feel this play of the earth element in the water as you feel the area of the hips and the lower belly
letting the lower belly soften you might notice its
viscous malleable nature softening towards the earth
can feel the earth element in your spine and in the uprightness
and then letting the softness of the belly of the shoulders pulling down
this internal lubrication
dropping down towards the ground
and yet it stays cohesive nothing's going to turn into just a
puddle held together [Music]
and yet soft
notice that the movement of breath in your chest and in your belly is made
possible by this flexible
and yet cohesive combination of water with the earth
as you breathe the water element allows the expanding of breath
coming up into the area of the mouth and throat and here you can feel the water
element directly you get a little taste quite literally of the inside
of your body of this wateriness that is all through us
coming up to your eyes even if your eyes are closed you can
notice that your eyes have very slight movements as your eyeballs rest in their
bath of water
and you might even notice in spite of the hardness of our skull
this felt rigidity that inside you might even sense that
your brain is resting letting it soften and rest
in its fluid bath
letting yourself feel this fluidity in the body perhaps you can
sense in places the pulse of the blood moving through your
veins our internal irrigation system
all this wateriness here in us
coming from the water you have drunk
coming with the juiciness of fruit that you've eaten
this water with the heat rises into the sky travels through the
sky and clouds rains down flows in streams
underground and somewhere comes to surface and comes
to you
and as you drink it you're just a temporary location of this water it's passing through you
we're like a little eddie in this flow of the river of water
whirls in this corner and then it flows back out
evaporation through our skin through our breath through our pee
you two are part of the hydrological cycle the water's simply coming
in for a time passing back out
you might just let yourself feel hopefully you have some idea where your
water comes from and let yourself sense that water
falling down through some reservoir [Music] flowing through you
back out again
this endless sharing of the water
it's so easy when it comes in to think that it's me i mine
but it's simply water passing through
no inside no outside just water
when we as if as fish first decided to walk on land we brought the ocean with us inside the
saltiness of our blood is the saltiness of the ocean
we carry the ocean with us and we rejuvenate it and refresh it each glass
of water we drink
we like every other creature we're water creatures
let yourself feel in the little micro movements even as you sit still
the little micro movements of the body of the breath
you can feel the fluidity
notice if any part of your body becomes rigid holding
if there's some contradiction in that to our natural fluid state
and then it softens again in its true nature of water
of softness cohesive
and yet fluid
so
simply water flowing through
no inside no outside
not yours
feeling the softness
so cohesive yet fluid nature of the body
notice the little micro movements the movement of the ribs in the breath
and the belly feel your own wateriness
you share this wateriness with all the other living beings
with the rivers and the oceans
let yourself also feel this blessing of the water
this aliveness that it carries
every cell in your wat in your body touched by water
nourished allowed to move and change
allowing allowing it to do its work
the pliability of your skin the lubrication in your joints
all the blessings of water
so
feel the softness the fluidity of the body
as it continues to soften the micro movements
the breath
so
[Music]
so [Music]
the water elements we're made up of 60 to 90
water apparently depending on your age when we're younger we have more
water in us the more we're juicier and as we get older we're more earth we're more ground
but we're still more than half water
and hopefully in that meditation you are starting to feel that combination that beautiful combination
that the water element offers us this cohesion of holding the earthiness in us together
and yet it does it in this completely pliable flexible way
water is such a magical thing the way it takes the shape
of everything that it poured touches you know everything it on a river it takes
the shape of the river in a cup it takes the shape of the cup
in our bodies it takes the shape of our bodies
and the buddha i read you part of a quote yesterday about the earth element and i want to
read you he talks about the water element he talks about the elements very similarly but here's what he says about
the water element and i want you to notice
in particular where he talks about internal and clinging so
notice that as well as his list of what the water element is and he's again speaking to his son
rahula what rahula is the water element the water element bait may be either
internal or external what is the internal wall water element
whatever internally belonging to oneself is water watery and
and clung to that is bile phlegm pus blood sweat fat
tears grease spittle snot oil of the joints urine or whatever else internally
belonging to oneself is water watery and clung to
this is called the internal water element now both the internal water element and
the external water element are simply water element
pointing and that should be seen as it actually is with proper wisdom thus
this is not mine this i am not this is not myself
when one sees it thus as it actually is with proper wisdom one becomes
disenchanted with the water element particularly as mine
and makes the mind dispassionate towards the water element
and he's speaking here very clearly how internal it we name it internal
when we cling to it when we're not clinging to it it's neither internal nor external it's
simply water water flowing through
and we can feel this
identity this me isn't it amazing that we call this sac that we have so much
ownership and so much idea about this sack of water that
is right here more than half water but somehow this water
is mine is me but not the other water
clinging it's like we freeze it's like we make the water instead of its natural
fluid we freeze it in place and we can feel this in our concepts in
our way of moving and acting in the world when we're frozen when we are
rigid cut off
very much like frozen water
clinging to who we are and what we've done our roles our identities our stories
it's so easy to see in a river if we look at a river and we give it a
name nearby here is the colorado river and we give the colorado river this name
and we can easily see it's not hard to notice that
oh the name colorado river is an idea concept that i have but the water in it
and how it is and if you live near a river or you've been in it you see that it changes not just the water in it but
the banks the the sediment the color the volume it's all
constantly changing and it's so easy to see that our name for it the colorado river is just a
concept that we overlay on this constant oscillating changing thing and
we're like that i'm a river named susie
and you are a river with your own name constantly changing everything flowing
through and when we freeze ourselves or freeze
other people into some limited view as if
we were static and the buddha so clearly pointed that
it's making this static nature that makes us believing believing in that static
nature that causes our suffering so can we recognize our own fluidity our
transparency that's coming through us feel this water this sacred water
flowing through us this giver of life
we are vessels of sacred water
part of the cycle moving around impermanent let yourself just shift your
posture a little bit just sort of move a little bit and feel the fluidity in your
joints feel how you're just kind of like a pool
a little stream that's moving a little let yourself sense your body
this sacred water we carry it's so lovely to think that
human beings our whole time and animals too organized right where we lived based
on water we lived by water we lived where there was streams where there was
water to drink water to move on i was
not long ago i was down in um last winter i was down in phoenix and
there were these houses that had been built that apparently
the people who built them knew there was no water you know they couldn't dig wells there's no city water available
and so the water has to get trucked to their house and put into a holding thing
and i i could feel in myself a kind of dis-ease in that
like there's a way oh we're we're supposed to be connected
into the cycle and now now we've had to like
those people have to have their connection into the hydrological cycle go through a truck
and uh and drive down the highway and there's something that when we feel in our
bodies and feel the clouds and the water flow through
the sacredness of water robin wall kimmer in a book you may be
familiar with braiding sweetcrafts talks about the the error of buying bottled
water like we've interrupted its cycle and we're not letting the whole thing
come through and turning it into a commodity this most sacred of elements
they're all sacred but this sacred element
this this element of water gives us the opportunity
to feel how powerful water is and how pliable water is
there's a beautiful story from ajahn chah where he asks
someone he asks a group of people you may know the story he says have you ever
seen moving water everyone's like yeah i've seen moving
water and he says have you ever seen still water yeah we've all seen a pool of water
and he says have you ever seen still moving water
and how can we in our practice be this moving
flexible pliable water element and yet
there's a stillness of like a still pool that the pool
is letting the mud and silt settle out to the bottom water
pure water has a clarity to it
letting yourself feel the simplicity and clarity
of water as it enters and flows through you
and we like the world we live in is full of disruptions of water floods and
droughts we've become very aware of the disturbance of water and yet
when it sits it stills it calms
one last aspect of water that i just want to drop in is water as like the juiciness of
aliveness the juiciness of meta really that
is what um we share you know we often say oh my you know
that's a juicy person or i need more juice in my practice we're feeling
this nourishing abundant quality of the water
the way when you water a plant you're giving it love you're giving it
appreciation and it has the opportunity to grow
i'll end today with a poem from rilke
may what i do flow from me like a river no forcing it and no holding back
the way it is with children then in these swelling and ebbing currents these deepening tides moving
out returning i will sing you as no one ever has
streaming through widening channels into the open sea
so may you be a widening channel or as rosemary said at the beginning a wren
an asteroid or a lemon feel your wateriness
so i encourage you today as i suggested yesterday exploring your
earthiness as you go through this day feel very much in your own body
in your joints as you move around that you are water
you're part of the cycle of water in its juiciness moving through their day
enjoy that let the drink of water when you drink when you drink it in feel the streams
the ocean come into you and i wanted to let you know today we're
going to end at the regular time and tomorrow the next three days i'll end at the regular time like this and then
we'll also continue for those who can for 15 minutes with questions if people would like to bring those
so we'll still end it quarter till and then have the option of continuing
for those who would like so may you have a juicy watery filled day
be well