so good day to everyone and here in redwood city there's a light
rain it brings me much
both joy and a kind of intimacy of just with life and wonderful times
and
so here we are to sit here and you're here
everyone has their own here and some ways for each of us to say here
is uh is something we say in common and also is unique to each of us because
of the different location that's here for us different place that we sit or meditate
and in part of meditation practice is on this anapanasati is
gathering ourselves together here and as the practice uh develops
there is an emphasis on concentration uh an english word which uh doesn't
really do justice to the poly words that uh are
sometimes translated as concentration or concentrating and um but the word samadhi the one
one one associated word is um ekagata
and it's a word that sometimes is translated as a one-pointedness
but uh if it's one-pointedness it's kind of like the um it use an
ancient analogy of of a
all the rafters of a small hut that maybe is more or less a round hut
they all come together up into the point of the singular point to the top of the roof
and and so everything gathers everything points everything reaches for that point
and that point in a sense if it's a circular building is that if we look from above it's at
the center of it all and everything else radiates towards or comes towards it i guess
and so everything moves towards the singular focus but focus
suggests in english too much that a strain duality between us and what's what we're
focusing on and laser focus or something and rather i think of it more if you use rather
than a hut you know the roof but just a circle concentric circle
and and the the the center of it is where
the mind everything is focusing everything is gathering everything is circling around and it's all included in
this concentric circles of our lives body emotions thoughts
mind everything is somehow included but everything is gathered
to this around the center so sometimes we say in english on
meditation practice to be centered and so we're centering ourselves here
with everything included but resting at the center and um so one of the uh
ancient techniques for centering ourselves and really kind of being into gathering ourselves and everything kind
of coming in around something developing concentration
is counting the breath and i suggest we do that for this sitting
and uh the way that i was taught which i did for i still do sometimes is to
count the exhale and um and then the next exhale gets the next count so one two
three up to 5 up to 10 and at 10 start over again be completely
relaxed about not forgetting losing count or getting
distracted at the first opportunity just begin again at one it doesn't matter if you only get to two or even in just
two gets to one before you lose count start again at one and one teacher
one person i knew who practiced in japan his and teacher taught them to count up to one and then over again
and and uh and then kind of but don't just make a count a little uh
voice in the mind that counts but rather see if the whole mind the whole being
can somehow one like all of you is included like if maybe if you were singing or
something and you uh all of you is included in the singing one it's kind of like really there with
the exhale and with the release of the exhale kind of settling and gathering together
and the complexity of counting up to 10 requires a little extra attention to keep count
that makes a little protection from wandering off too easily into thought and you're more likely to catch yourself
thinking perhaps you notice you're not you've lost the count because you have this very clear
kind of task but the main thing to do is just gathering together this the whole mind settles and lands
landing on the center and the center is the place where you most experience
the breathing so the belly or the chest or the nostrils or whatever
just gathering settling one so taking a posture for meditation
where you can somehow begin centering yourself
in your body and centering yourself
around where you're going to experience your breathing
the inhales and the exhales
the predominant place to experience breathing and then from this predominant place
the center of it all take a few long slow deep breaths
and this as we do this the exhale
use that to really settle in let go
release yourself into the body that's breathing into the place where breathing is felt
deep breath in and exhale relaxing the shoulders
softening the belly
releasing the tensions in the face
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and familiarize yourself to with that part of your body where your
feel your breathing and imagine that that's at the center of
it all center of the universe and that as you breathe from that place
awareness spreads outwards throughout your body and maybe even beyond and as you exhale
awareness settles back in do that
and then with a very soft quiet voice
but with a voice that includes
all your being on the exhale
use the count one
and if you want you can just do one each time as if each breath is complete in itself
and or you could keep it simple or simple
enough and just count to three and then start over again
and if that works well you might count to 10 and if you get to
10 you could
start again and while they want to try to keep the
count the important part is the settling in
to the center
relaxing any centrifugal force out into outwards into thought into feelings
that takes you away from being centered on the breathing
not fighting anything or resisting anything just not giving it attention
not getting involved where attention goes where your
involvement goes is following the count
in centering yourself here in the breathing inviting all of who you
are to be included
so the count is not just a little word in the mind
but it's an expression of your whole being willingly fully here
quietly here with the breathing
as you do the count spread out the pronunciation of the
count long count one in such a way that maybe it begins
quieting the rest of the thinking mind
like you're gathering yourself around to say something intimate and soft and
warm-hearted and as you do this soft one
center your body on the breathing
land fully with your whole being on the experience of breathing
giving yourself over to the counting and experiencing breathing
as if it's the only thing to be done for the next minutes
letting go of your thoughts except account
and then in the last couple of minutes of this sitting
to let go of the counting and just sit here with the breathing
enter into the breathing center yourself on the breathing without
the counting and see if you're a little bit more centered and
connected
and then at the end of the sitting to remain as centered as you can
centered inside of yourself rooted in your weight of your body and
the weight of your attention into the center of breathing
a place of balance where you're not easily pushed around or
caught up in things and being so centered
now open your awareness up to the world around you
to the communities that extend out from where you are neighbors and townspeople and
people in your county your province outwards into the world
open yourself up to consider the people you might run into today or communicate with today
and from a centered place where maybe nothing has to happen
at least for now sitting here no responsibilities for them no
requirements obligations just a centered experience
that includes other people awareness of them thinking of them
imagining them
and in this kind of way of not being obligated or
not being required to do anything or react or talk to them to open your heart
to evoke your good will your basic capacity for friendliness
care kindness and love
maybe that's related to a tenderness within
and to whatever degree that you could have this good will for others
feel how it maybe also is rooted in your centeredness in your calm
or your concentration
and then imagine that it radiates out from you as a warmth as a light
as a care may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we appreciate how being centered and balanced and
non-reactive supports this possibility for the world
may our practice be for the welfare and happiness of all the people we encounter
communicate with today may the world benefit from our meditation together
[Music]
uh
so the 16 stages of anapanasati
each stage each step along the way i think it's nice to think of it as
being complete in itself to not be so concerned about making
one's way through these steps but to be fully with present for practicing with what is
and content with whatever the practice is whatever the focus is for the time
but then as it develops practice sooner or later the body starts feeling settled and
unified the whole body we're breathing with and relaxing the whole as we develop kind of
ability to be a little more content and happy to be here then we have a kind of a
a feeling of well-being that makes it easier to both notice
what's going on in our mind the mental activity and to relax it to tranquilize it and it's nice to have
a sense of well-being so we can look at some of the craziness that goes on in some of our minds
and not so we're not disturbed by it or troubled by it or reactive to you know the unusual things
that we can think and do and feel but see it as just a
you know mental activity as opposed to making it personal or material which should judge ourselves
and so to experience the mental activity and to relax it and calm it down
kind of in a little summary that's the first eight steps of anapanasati
and then the whole practice of these 16 stages takes a dramatic shift with step nine
experiencing the mind and it's kind of like this is a pivot into a deeper dive
into our you know maybe we could say our spiritual life and the word
mind cheetah is a you know it's usually translated as mind
or mind heart or even heart sometimes and uh it probably is to use to kind of
be a little bit of heretic buddhist heretic border on it
is that the word mind is the cheetah is so important in the teachings of the buddha and so generally respected and that
it's the closest thing we get from the buddha to something that we would maybe in english called the self
and but the self this idea of self is in put in buddhist kind of orientation
is all seen as um represents some activity of the mind some idea interpretation some um thing we're
holding on to and so there's a kind of a desire not to get
involved in this whole idea of self and what is the self and who am i
that that investigation is considered more complicated and more stressful than is useful for deepening a
meditation so we get to put the self idea aside but the cheetah the mind is kind of what
takes its place but the mind is not a thing the mind is a the aggregate the gestalt
of all the mental activities in the way that we experience that
and so it's a fluid thing it's not nothing not a thing to get attached to or to reify into like a solid thing
it's dynamic and fluid and it gets very clear as we go deeper and deeper in meditation
how fluid and changeable the mind is and how the experience of mind changes in different levels of
concentration different levels of clarity and and it's fascinating to watch this
how we sense and feel the mind kind of oscillates between sometimes being contracted and small and sometimes being
expansive sometimes being you know all kinds of ways
but uh when the ma when the body gets relaxed the mental activity is relaxed
generally the cheetah the mind state tends to become very welcoming very wholesome very
wholesome nourishing feeling it's like we've discovered a treasure inside as treasure of well-being of
goodness of wholeness of intimacy that that is a kind of a state rather than a
thing and it's a dynamic state it's not something that's easy to hold on to or cling to
i mean we can have desires for it and all that but if we get close to it we realize there's nothing here to cling
to or it doesn't make sense to cling because if we cling to this this mind
we're actually getting involved in a mental activity which is a subset of the mind and any
kind of to too involved with these activities of mind the thoughts of the mind the interpretations of the mind
certain arrows and collapses the freedom the openness the fullness that is the sense of the mind and that's
why in step 10 uh we we're allowed we can satisfy the mind we
nourish the mind we gladden the mind with this sense of wholeness the sense
of being complete or centered or that can happen so there's a sense of
well-being a certain kind of well-being and this is the foundation this is the
uh for when uh the practice of anapanasati switches to something we can call an
english concentration practice or that concentration practice is a separate practice
but where uh the that we can develop concentration in doing mindfulness of
breathing in mindfulness are breathing out because we center ourselves we have this
this mind state that we're intimate with and feel and we take the whole mind state with us
as we center ourselves on the breathing or the breathing becomes the very wind
that moves through the mind state kind of the massage that moves through it and it becomes the breathing becomes
more and more the place in which we gather ourselves the place in which we the concentric
circles of our life hold counsel hold uh gather together and
be present for and supported for um it's not like you're sitting at the
center of a room and there's concentric circles around you
and uh all your best friends and family and supporters just come there because
just to be with you and hold you and and love you and you know show that you're you know
that you're you know you know you can you can you're good you can rest in yourself you can be
at ease and so we gather together all of ourselves and um and the word for uh
that usually translate as concentration for step um 11 of anapanasati
is is not actually samadhi it's a different word that looks like samadhi i think i didn't look and get
exactly right but sama sama hitti or samahati and
it more literally means a gathering together a gathering together or a settling
a settling ins here and so breathing in one settles
in breathing out one settles in breathing in one gathers oneself here
breathing out one gathers oneself here and this gathering centering settling
is difficult to do if we're preoccupied with thoughts and ideas and feelings
emotions it works best when those are uh we're relaxed enough about that we're
not tight or contracted around that or nervous about those things that those things can still happen but
we don't want we don't have to be involved in them they can be in the background or on the side or they
can be in the outer chairs in that circle of all our supporters there or as we get more and more gathered in
the thoughts and feelings and emotions all kind of get started getting oriented
as supporters for this process of the mind being centered in on the breathing so if we are thinking
they're very simple and innocent thoughts about staying with the breath feeling the breath if there are
emotions happening or feelings they really feel connected to the process of being settled it's
like almost part of settling the goodness the wholeness the wholesomeness the nourishment
seems to flow with or out of being settled on the breathing and being with the breath
so this process of settling of gathering together gathering in every all of who we are it
continues this process of becoming whole in the first tetrad
experiencing the whole body and then relaxing the bodily activity in the in the second tetrad
experiencing um the mental activity all the activity and relaxing it
contributes to that sense of the mind as a whole the gestalt of the mind
and then go further settling everything begins to come in and when it gets really sweet
the sense of being settled and deeply connected and not distracted by things
then when there's a sound or something else happens in the body a sensation it just seems to be soft and tenderly
held and included it's not a problem it's just kind of part of this wonderful
landscape of of subtleness of softness of intimacy of care of of attention
so um samadhi is a sometimes called the unification
unification of that mind making it whole so i'm very aware that
this is not easy to experience and describing it this way can set up expectation or striving for it or
comparative thinking like i'm not any ever going to be in that kind of state
so if those kinds of things happen that's why the earlier steps of anapanasati is so important
because we're always staying attentive to the stresses and the strains that happen in the body around our reactions
and then relaxing those we're always attentive and sensitive to how we get trapped and caught in our
mental activity our thoughts our judgments our our interpretations are expected you
know and uh comparative thinking and we're always ready to relax those and this is so
important these early steps of anapanasati to always keep them close by always being content just to do those
and that's the massage that we do to always go back catch ourselves
do the earlier steps again and massaging ourselves and then we come back into a nice mind
state a nice way of being and then we get caught again and there's a massage back and forth and
rather than thinking of this as a mistake or a problem and we're supposed to be always at the growing edge of the
practice it's actually this massaging and going back and forth and discovering ourselves
and works our slowly is working out the kinks slowly working out the wrinkles that need to be ironed out
so we get more and more whole and holistic and settled in this practice so don't
don't be concerned too much if these teachings we do now for
deeper and deeper teachings don't quite work for you they'll work in some way don't you can
trust that you might not be aware of it consciously and always be content
to do whatever step that you're on and will continue so um
thank you for today and we'll probably continue for a while now if at least a few days into the week
with the samadhi and concentration thank you