okay it's good to be with you all
my name is devin devin berry i'm actually in northampton massachusetts
i'm happy to be here with the insight meditation community in redwood city um
and we'll do a guided meditation for about 25 minutes or so and then i'll offer some short reflections afterwards okay
so allowing yourself to settle in in a comfortable posture whatever that may be whether
that's sitting on a cushion or a chair or lying down standing if you prefer
and resting the body alert yet as comfortable
as possible in this moment
and maybe gently closing the eyes
maybe getting a sense of the body the body sitting on the cushion maybe your bottom
on the cushion or feet on the floor hands on knees
just any of those contacts contacts
getting a sense of the body resting on the earth
maybe that's a sense of the body breathing expanding and contracting almost like a balloon
perhaps noticing warm or cool air at the nostrils
maybe one of the other anchors rise and fall at the chest or in and out of the belly
allowing attention to rest there coming back with some sense of
gentleness or kindness when the mind wanders off
allowing the breath to be as it is
maybe noticing with a slight sense of curiosity or alertness any
sounds in the background just allowing them to come and go
so
you
may the merits of this practice benefit all beings and bring peace
thank you thank you very much for joining us today
devon and uh devin so devon began his practice with
uh tiknot han's plum village sangha and has been practicing insight meditation since 1999.
he teaches that insight meditation society where he was trained as a residential retreat teacher devon
has a love of long retreat practice as well as daily life practices that point to the
liber liberated teachings of the buddha devon co-founded both the teen and men
of color sangha at the east bay meditation center in oakland california he also co-founded deep time liberation
an ancestral healing journey that explores the impact of ancestral legacy and intergenerational trauma on
black americans devin is a board member for inside world aid and
bar center for buddhist studies he recently relocated from the san francisco bay area
to western massachusetts and teaches nationally devon is the father of two daughters
thank you for joining us today devin really appreciate it thank you good to be here with you all
so i wanted to offer some brief reflections on meta and
i'll say this wasn't actually the plan coming in but i received an email late last night with the subject
heading that said why meta and it was really late at night and i deleted the email by mistake so i
didn't actually read the email i just saw the subject head y meta and i think it just must have
been in my mind stream so i have been uh was thinking about it all night and i
thought about it this morning while i was out on a walk and thought this is a good inquiry a good uh
piece of information for reflection it's something i realize that i haven't actually reflected on in quite a while
in my own meta practice and and then going back and looking at the email i did in fact
find from a yogi a friend of really wanting to know
why would he be doing this practice why why why should i do this practice and and and i think for me it had been
pretty easy to answer it was just sort of it was that you know i've said over and over again it's this um
um wish for good will and kindness for myself and for everyone else
and i think he was looking for a little more a little more than that and so i was just sort of
um going back and letting that inquiry sort of land in the body to
really get a sense of of what it was
that has driven me to this practice or or leads me to to to meta practice and it is a i
consider it a foundational practice for myself and one that that i that i love to share and
talk about with others and encourage other other folks to do and i think it's really it's sort of um
well actually having that wide method is it's a really good thing just to clarify intention with with any of our practices
and with meta in particular i think clarifying the intention the the
intention in meta seems to be or at least i i see it as the um the engine right so this this
intention is is the engine that that then drives
um the condition
and action and how we engage in the world it right it's sort
of the engine that conditions the action that colors how we engage the world
and what i've seen over the years so there are these categories in meta
oftentimes that that we work with if we work with them in a systematic way of the
self benefactor you know someone that is supportive of you or inspiration to
you or has has inspired you mentors teachers that sort of thing dear friends um the difficult
person or category those you know those folks that we may have a little charge with or or a little difficulty or challenge with
and the neutral category and the thing that came to mind to me most is is that neutral category those folks
that that i don't know and i'll come back to those in a bit how that was um led to some pretty
profound shifts in my own practice i wanted to get to a little bit the first thing i thought when this why meta
came up is something that i've had posted on a refrigerator for years it is
in this way that we must train ourselves by liberation of the self through love we will develop love
we will practice it we will make it both a way and a basis take our stand upon it store it up and
thoroughly set it going and that's from the mutant nikaya
and sort of use that as a aspiration or a little mantra to actually um
get back to what this practice means for me what i'm doing with this practice and i think my initial
difficulty with meta was i had lots of blocks and there was lots of anger and agitation and resentment and it was the
last thing i wanted to do and of course it was the thing that i probably both needed to do um so that's been a helpful support for
me and
many of the suit is mirror so some of what i was saying about the the intention and clarifying intention and uh
meta as a as a practice that conditions action and moves to heart a
lot of that is actually mirrored in the sutas and so i wanted to look at a couple of them and actually look at
the origin story of meta itself but one of the from the early sutas
in the way that um one of the first instances that we know of of the
meta being used or being spoken of in the sutures is also from the samyut nikaya
so the monks so the monks went to the park of the wanderers of other sex on arrival they exchanged courteous
greetings with the wonders after an exchange of friendly greetings and courtesy as they set to one side
as they were sitting there the wanderers said to them friends so gotama the contemplatives teaches the
dhamma to his disciples in this way correct come monks abandoning the five
hindrances the corruptions of awareness that we can discernment keep pervading the first direction with
awareness imbued with good will likewise the second likewise the third
likewise the fourth thus and above below and all around everywhere in its
entirety keep pervading the all-encompassing cosmos with an awareness imbued with goodwill
abundant expansive immeasurable without hostility and without ill will
so we see that as one of the early instances of um the buddha and the buddhist disciples
talking about meta and how it was practiced at that time
so there was something um also that that interested me early on
with with with meta and the suit is was the origin story itself where
during one of the rainy seasons and there are 500 monks 500 being lots of monks not necessarily
an exact number always uh 500 monks in the forest during the rainy season
they went to practice and had been there for a few days and all seemed to be well and
they're practicing making headway in their practice and the tree spirits and
devas and other beings in the forest at some point became a little agitated and and upset
because they weren't sure how long these monks were going to be staying and being there and so this as the story goes they begin
emitting horrible smells and sounds and doing all sorts of things to
scare the monks and it worked the monks were terrified and uh they all packed up and
ran off and went to see the buddha and the buddha of course sent them right
back to the same forest and this time he had mentioned that they that they were in the forest without
protection and so he sends them there with protection and what he sends them with is the
metasuta so they go back and practice and so they're practicing meta they're chanting
the metasuta and of course this allows them to really settle into the
practice it settles the mind the tree spirits the devas the beings and all of these other creatures begin to see the monks as
not being so mad and they seem to also be affected by the meta that's happening and they
begin to actually support the practice that's happening and of course as in many of the stories
in the sutures the monks became enlightened and so the protection that they actually
sent the that that the buddha actually sent the monks with was what we know
as the meta suta and the mata suit i believe is the only one of the brahma bihar's
these divine abodes these uh the one of the four brahmana baharas these these practices of the heart
we call them in today's vernacular it's the only one with it with a dedicated discourse
um i want to take a look at that for a second so it says this is what should be done
by one who is skilled in goodness and who knows the path of peace let them be able and upright
straightforward and gentle in speech humble and not conceited contented and easily satisfied
unburdened with duties and frugal in their ways peaceful and calm and wise and skillful
not proud and demanding in nature let them not do the slightest thing that the
wise would later reprove wishing in gladness and in safety may all beings
be at ease whatever living beings there may be whether they are weak or strong
omitting none the great or the mighty medium short or small the seen and the
unseen those living near and far away those born
and to be born may all beings be at ease let none deceive another or despise any
being in any state let none through anger or ill will wish harm upon another
even as a mother protects with her life her child her only child so with the boundless
heart should one cherish all living beings radiating kindness over the entire world
spreading upwards to the skies and downwards to the depths outwards and unbounded freed from hatred
and ill will whether standing or walking seated or lying down
one should sustain this recollection this is said to be the sublime abiding by not holding to
fixed views the pure hearted one having clarity of vision being freed from all sense desires is
not born again into this world so that was the
detects the crux of of what the buddha had given these monks to practice with in the
forest and when i think about
so he gave them this protection practice right so we often view meta as being a a protection practice
and i think when i look at that inquiry of why meta some of that is actually to be able to protect myself
it actually allows me allows us to be with mindfulness allows the mind to
to settle somewhat and allows us to be able to release the heart to be able to
open the heart with this sense of safety that our practice
helps us to cultivate and so when when i was mentioning before
about the the neutral category the neutral persons and beings i really
feel like i've gotten to see quite a profound shift in social connection actually
out and about in the world so really taking my practice off the cushion and into the world and so
before moving to new england i i lived in uh san francisco for a number of years and all over the bay area
the last few years i was there before moving i um gave up my car so i was riding cow
trains and barred and riding a bike and walking and and ubers i spent a lot of time in ubers
back and forth to the airport and that sort of thing and actually used that as an opportunity to
practice meta with the neutral person so every time i got into cars right i was
with someone that i didn't know hadn't seen before and what i noticed actually is oftentimes i was in the car
with someone that had some piece of buddhist iconography on the dashboard or hanging from the
window or something and so i actually used that opportunity to to practice meta
for them and occasionally would mention something about the uh um the iconography that
that they had the little buddha statue or prayer prayer flag or something or quite often someone would ask me you
know where i was going when i was you know headed to the airport with them and oftentimes it was to retreat and so that
led to a conversation about about uh meditation or buddhism and that thing and so for
for a number of folks this was you know what they knew from their home countries and so it was a really
beautiful connection and what i'd seen over and over and over again is that this person that was
neutral someone that i didn't have a charge with one way or the other that i didn't know had never seen often times would never
see again this was someone that moved from that neutral category to the
friend category not necessarily a dear friend in a couple of cases yes but but they were able to move and
it was based on um this being able to settle the mind some
with degrees of mindfulness and and using the meta practice and actually wishing this
other person good will and kindness and friendliness and being able to model some of that and there were a
couple of different occasions where the person that was driving me to my destination we
ended up i stopped for coffee with one one i actually invited
to my house to the surprise of everyone else in my house for sure and it was quite a beautiful
thing to be able to pop into the back of this car with this
person i'd never seen before to be able to practice over the course of whatever that ride was
10 20 30 minutes and feel like i've made a deep connection
with this person upon getting out of the car and i've seen that time and time again
with the metro practice not necessarily that but it just allows me to actually one see the blocks that are there where i'm
hesitant um or where i've created a projection or story about someone
and also has allowed me to um as the buddha sent
the monks back into the forest with this antidote to fear it has served as a as an explicit example of an antidote
for fear in my own mind dropping that into the mind stream and so some of those are the why meta
for me and also it points to something else that that another beautiful part of the
sutures that i love the purpose of my teaching of the holy life of the dharma is not for gaining merit not for good deeds nor
rapture nor concentration but for the sure hearts release this and this alone
is the reason for the teachings and as i stay close to that and as i as
we stay close to this aspiration of practicing for the sherhart's release whatever the practice
is then it allows us to connect with ourselves it allows us
to connect with others around us and i believe given the the times that
we're in right and it's going to be different in all the times but the times that we are particularly living in i think this is actually quite
um an important and quite profound thing to uh to keep close from the tavija suta
just as if a mighty trumpeter were with little difficulty to make a proclamation to the four directions so by this
liberation of the mind through the development of loving-kindness one sets an example leaving nothing
untouched nothing unaffected and this really speaks to right
the sending of the emotion of care and love in all directions nothing untouched nothing unaffected
nothing out of earshot and that helps to keep in mind that
i'm not picking and choosing and in the not picking and choosing right it doesn't matter it's like
white male cis bodies black bodies trans bodies queer bodies everybody it does it matter who it is
right and at different times meta can serve as a purification practice of their little
blocks or or um um little things that come up in the mind
that we don't particularly like or difficult so it's able to point out some of those
things and as those things come out come up then um
skillful means to be able to hold those with mindfulness and probably compassion as well so at
times it's like both of those brahman bahar practices end up being two sides of the same coin that i often
use as something difficult or challenging comes up in the mind when i'm doing meta whether
i'm doing it in a formal sense or whether i'm doing it off the cushion
and i think with the y meta as well it um
when i think of it now actually quite a bit of the why is around um i used to always talk about and heard
the term stealth meta right so much of what i was talking about and with the the the neutral person or the
neutral beings was stealth meta right it's not me sitting on the cushion it's not us sitting on the cushion but it's
us out about in the world practicing meta and i think part of the why that i'm interested now is really
um blurring that line removing that barrier of not actually their my formal practice and my
uh stealth meta practice being one and the same not separating them at all
and really being able to in the same way that we rest attention on the breath or that we rest
attention on sensations we rest attention on those phrases rest
attention on images rest attention on the felt sense of benevolence good will kindness
friendliness and in doing that it really blurs the
line there isn't there isn't a separation of that practice at all
so there's one other thing
so there's um these 11 benefits of meta and i believe this was later on
the sudimaga this is which is roughly i believe
don't quote me on this roughly i believe five five hundred two thousand years after the time of the buddha these 11
benefits were
we will sleep well we would wake up feeling well we're not likely to have
nightmares our body relaxes and our face is joyful even animals and celestial beings feel drawn
to us spirits protect us fire poison and weapons will not harm us
the mind immediately becomes calm our complexion brightens we die with a clear mind or unconfused
will die in peace and i've always found those interesting it's not so clearly there are some in
there and i'll jump to one right away that that the very first time i heard it whereas fire poisons and weapons will not harm
us right that's not one to test out and so i i i think i in in in my mind
i've really viewed it as looking at it in regards to to greed hatred and delusion rather than
rather than some very explicit things um but the sleeping well and waking well
is one that actually you can immediately try out and experiment with it's one
oftentimes that i use in terms of listening to the chanting of the meta suit in pali or in english or
chanting it myself uh listening to talks on the brahmi viharas
before bed it's really interesting to see what changes occur
or noticing changes the next morning and doing this over quite a bit of time
or actually being quite conscious and intentional upon waking to explore that inquiry of
goodwill friendliness benevolence to all beings and it seems that the more that we're
able to actually string together um as many moments of of kindness
as possible right then that continuity of mindfulness is there that continuity
of meta is there and actually there's a pretty profound shift that occurs right and that's one that
you don't have to believe that's one you you you try out for yourselves so and i'll leave you with this this is
another that has been supportive of me because it feels like much of what we're
creating when we're creating this this field of meta and working with this on a regular basis it's sort of this
uh we begin to work with the soil of friendliness and there's this beautiful 14th century tibetan poet longchimpa
out of the soil of friendliness grows the bloom of compassion watered by the
tears of joy sheltered under the cool shade of the
tree of equanimity out of the soil of friendliness meta
grows the bloom of compassion karuna watered by the tears of joy mudita
sheltered under the cool shade of the tree of equanimity
so holding those uh that highest aspiration of wishing ourselves and others good
will friendliness and kindness
is the why of matter or has been the why of meta for myself of late
thank you all very much appreciate it