so warm greetings from redwood city
and as we continue this
series on mindfulness of breathing
the mindfulness practice has both a deliberate side of the practice
and that which is non-deliberate or to say it maybe
maybe in a clearer way that which is active that we do and that which is
passive that we allow for and the balance between those two shifts and changes as the practice goes
along so certainly if a person has never heard of meditation before
and they maybe read a book about it and say i'm going to meditate they have to actively put themselves
maybe into a meditation posture and kind of get themselves started and
change the maybe the the momentum of their mind even from what
they have been doing to have the momentum of the mind being being a little bit um different uh now the moment of the
mind is uh to be present to be present without a lot of thinking about things or reacting to
things but to have some ability to stay present and maybe to stay present in a very simple way in the
present moment with something like the breathing just being with the breathing staying on the breathing
and and so there's a deliberateness to that there's an active quality to that that that needs
to be there as the practice deepens or as it were able to stay more and more in the
present moment there's uh less of the deliberateness is needed
it's almost as if the deliberateness has set in place the motion to let go of all the distracted forces
all the different things we might be doing and uh and so now we're kind of
at rest staying here present and we don't have to do any more deliberateness in it
and so to borrow from an ancient metaphor um if a um
someone who herds sheep a shepherd is you know this the sheep have
gathered all over the mountainside and the shepherd deliberately travels around
the mountains searching looking trying to find the sheep to gather them together so there's a deliberateness and
active looking for those sheep once all the sheep have been gathered and they brought back to down by the
river where they're in the core pasture areas perhaps
and they're all gathered there and they're happily eating in the in the pasture then the shepherd can lean back against
the nice trees trunk of the tree and the shade and a warm day maybe
looking out across the pasture and then there's not much deliberateness in the looking anymore
there's not much intent to look and find and find the sheep now the shepherd can just
sit back and gaze in a kind of more receptive open
uh passive perhaps way of just kind of gazing upon and rather than looking
for the sheep the shepherd is content just to see the sheep to allow the seeing to happen without
needing to search or look or be intentional so the same way with mindfulness practice
as it initially there's an active quality a the training come back focus be there
and and with time everything gets gathered together all the desperate parts of ourselves
that have been lost up in the mountains and wandering around have been gathered
together come back to the pasture where they can kind of
eat what's nourishing and supportive the buddha called mindfulness
when it's really gathered in and centered on the body the feelings the mind and the mental
processes to be a pastor for the meditator and everything's gathered together here
and now what we can do is we're not so active but we just we just observe there's
there's seeing but no looking in since that looking being the active
engagement of the eyes and seeing is just what happens when we allow the eyes to operate
like a difference between listening which is active and hearing which
doesn't have to be active it's just we hear something without trying to hear it
so the emphasis today is um is to kind of begin appreciating
the the way in which mindfulness can be a passive receptive quality
that doesn't require so much work it's not so deliberate because it liberates has brought us to
the point where we can let go of that deliberateness and and so at this point the buddha
actually uses the language of observing just observe
and so this is the direction we go today in the meditation
so taking a comfortable upright posture
upright meaning engaged and intentional the deliberate posture
even if it's laying down
and then taking some long slow deliberate breaths deliberate way of
deliberate ritual almost of turning towards this experience here and
now and deliberately as you exhale to relax
the body settle in
deep breath in and then settling into this body
letting your breathing return to normal and then to
as you exhale deliberately bring your attention to different parts of your body
and deliberately actively relax those parts
so and sometimes a sense of deliberateness is a way of being definitive or
clear that this is what i'm going to do now is be here in the present moment
so bring the attention to the face and relaxing on the exhale
all the muscles of the face
softening around the eyes
and if the eyes are trying to look
intentionally searching for something maybe let the eyes rest
soften the eyes in their sockets
into as you exhale
to soften the chest
bring the attention to the shoulders soften the shoulders
bring this the attention to the belly and as you exhale softening the belly
and then bringing the attention to the global body whatever way is easy for you
to have a global awareness of the body
and as you exhale relaxing the body
and there can be a deliberateness around the mind as well
to bring your attention to the mind where you feel the mental
activity and thinking the most
and as you exhale to soften
the mind to quiet the mental activities
calming the thinking mind
and part of the reason we get pulled into distractions
is because there's some emotional force motion emotions that
are kind of pushing us in a direction or evoking the thoughts
whatever anxiety there might be
see if you can relax it and soften
in a way that's reassuring to your selfie it's okay to be here
relaxed
if there's excitement or desires or aversions or resentments
annoyances that are driving your thinking
on the exhale perhaps you can gently lovingly settle those
quiet those
and then to settle into your breathing to deliberately maybe even
lovingly
turn your attention over [Music] to the experience of the body breathing
making room in your body for the body to breathe just the way it
does lots of breathing rumor
to breathe as you're breathing as the breathing is breathing itself
in whatever way you're breathing is okay make room for it feel it
hang in there with it
and then imagine that you're at ease resting against the
trunk of a tree looking out upon
a pasture perhaps an expanse
and simply see the breathing
the receptive allowing non-deliberate way
but more receptive way
from the kind of observation
it doesn't interfere with what's being seen
seeing just allows the breathing to be as it is
simply as something to be seen to be observed
as a naturalist would observe
animals and nature without disturbing them just observing them
without judging them just observing
settle down settle back and observe the inhales and the exhales
allowing everything else around you to settle down and relax
because all you need to do is to observe your breathing
when your mind wanders off intentionally deliberately bring it back
and then when you're back see if you can relax the deliberateness
to observe to just sit back and watch observe the breathing
observe your experience in the present
moment as an uninvolved
non-interfering observer just observing
when we actively are intentionally deliberately
looking we might not notice the things we're not
looking for but when we're seeing settling back
opening up relaxing we might see a wider range of things the observation
the observing might be broad and more inclusive
as we come to the end of this sitting i'd like to say the same thing is true
for love it's wonderful as
intentional deliberate love and acts of love can be
there is loving which is not so deliberate intentional
it's more of an open field like observing
just observing the scenery there's something about
love when it's not directed not so deliberate
that can grow wide and broad and encompass so much more
than what we're direct directing our love towards
and so with our good will to bring these two together love and
observation to settle back and just observe the
the layout the scenery the broad open non-interfering way
can make room for our love to be the same
broad expansive encompassing without interfering
without directing without needing
sitting in with our trunk our back against the trunk of the tree
looking out across the pasture with a love a good will a kindness
for it all the full expanse of love
so in the last moments of this sitting perhaps you can feel your way or
to a way of kindness good will love which needs
nothing from others which is secure in itself
that can just be broad and encompassing at all
broad and non-interfering kindness good will
expressed in the words may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and resting in this kind of goodwill
may we deliberately express this good will
in some of the details of our contact with other people
may we live this day for the benefit of others
and for ourselves
okay
okay so
we continue with this series of talks on the 16 steps of mindfulness of breathing
and we're now coming into the last tetrad that i tried on um
observation on observing the last tetrad is the last steps
13 14 15 and 16 and they have in common all four steps
the introduction of a new verb a new and that's the verb to observe
and it goes something like this one trains to observe x
or tr on trains observing x when breathes in
when trains observing x when it breathes out and so in these last four steps there's
something we're observing and and we continue with the breathing
and there's something about the continuity of mindfulness or breathing which is allowing us to observe things
but helping us not latch onto them helping us not to cling or hold on
there's a kind of way in which by staying with the breathing there's a continual kind of letting go
that breathing is where the mind is resting and we notice all kinds of things happen but in a
certain way we're kind of letting go of our involvement letting go of any prioritization or
doing anything with it or changing it or or thinking about it
we're just kind of going along with the breathing going back to the breath being with the breath and it's a way of keeping
ourselves soft fluid relaxed letting go
and allowing the psycho physical system and have a break from our active
involvement our active deliberate kind of engagement and doing and wanting
and uh and letting something deeper to happen that could only happen if we get out of the way
and so in these last four steps this is uh represents represented very
strongly by the work this verb to observe the idea of observing
and it's the first time in the panasati this discourse 16 steps where observing comes into play
and and if you go if you read through the
teachings of the buddha in the suttas we see that most commonly observing as a
practice is a very well developed practice when the mind is able to be really centered
in the present concentrated a strongly concentrated present mind is the one that begins
doing the practice of observing and um so there's a lot of preparation in in
the 16 steps you know the first 12 are preparing ourselves for
this capacity to to lean back and just kind of watch and just observe
what's happening without being involved some translators translate this this
verb anupasati as contemplating and
contemplating uh in in the way that i relate to that word is closer to
thinking reflecting about something thinking about something it suggests a kind of more active
thinking process observing which is actually the etymologically
what the word that anupasati the prefix means towards something and the pasati
means to see seeing and uh and so put him together
we're we're gazing onto something seeing looking towards something in a sense and
but because of this uh i think observing works very well as a as a translation
we're observing and observing does there is a kind of deliberateness kind of uh
uh in observing but it's not quite the same as as actively looking
it's just settling back and just being being an observer and i liken it to being a naturalist who
goes into some kind of natural setting to observe some natural behavior of animals or
birds or something and it's very important that the naturalist not interfere with a life there and
somehow stay kind of unrecognized by what's happening so they watch nature unfold without the
interference from the humans and just but and then just to observe
and so earlier in in these 16 steps it begins with
breathing in one nose one is breathing in breathing out one nose or breathing out
so this idea of knowing is one of the attentional faculties we have to know
as we begin knowing the breath and no we never stop knowing the breath we recognize with breath we bear with the breathing
but then we're also what's happening we're experiencing things we're experiencing the body
we're experiencing joy and happiness we're experiencing the mind we're experiencing gladness we're
experiencing subtleness steady concentration and we're experiencing
uh liberation and this experiencing is also a little bit passive it isn't that receptive it isn't
so much like we're doing something we're just allowing yourself to experience knowing also
we're just knowing something and we're not judging it or criticizing it we're just knowing it clearly
and these two activities of knowing and experiencing are here to ground us here in the
present moment and so at some point then it shifts to
just observing and and so this is where the art of
deeper mindfulness is to observe and um in the other mindfulness
discourse of the buddha the sati patana there there's a lot of language of
observing and there also if you read the text carefully it's there the observing is the higher stages
of mindfulness that's where observation comes in and and so it was earlier
than knowing the experiencing is kind of grounding us in the present moment helping us stay present
learning to develop concentration to be resting in the present and when the ability to be focused and
present in the moment is becomes easy and light and we feel really grounded and
centered here that is when observation becomes stronger
and because we're going towards being less and less
intentional deliberate even less and less
activated or active in the mind because the more activated we are in the
mind the more kind of waves or agitation or clouds there are over our capacity to see clearly
and so as we get quieter and quieter and quieter what we're left with is this ability
just to observe and then we learn to trust that to settle back okay now i'm just observing
i'm not needing to interfere or again not judging i don't have to fix anything or adjust
anything or make anything different i'm just just watch just watch
and you can feel that in this kind of very centered place that
if we start reaching out to do something to fix something to judge something or think about something
it feels a little bit like we're losing something we're losing the open field we're out losing the
freedom we're losing the peacefulness of just observing and so it's very clear that observing
is a better place to be in this deeper states of meditation
and it becomes very important in these final steps because we really want to get out of the
way and not overlay concepts ideas
judgments should shouldn'ts on top of our experience we want to really be able to take it in
things much closer to actually how they're perceived now actually how before the experience
before a lot of judgments and concepts and generalizations that we make about things just to observe just to observe
and so uh so there's a turning
with this last tetrad from the practices that are more meant to
be concentrating settling focusing to now we're switching to vipassana
observing is uh where the personal insight practice begins
and uh and classically inside practice is built or or is done
on the foundation of of a mind which has gotten very stable
concentrated still joyful happy soft at ease
content safe and liberated from the hindrances
and and so and now the mind is ready for inside practice and the inside
practice is built on this capacity just to observe just observe the experience and
in fact vipassana the word that we translate as insight has the same
verbal root as anupasana vipassana and and pasuna in vipassana
again means to see and the v is usually understood to be a prefix here meaning um
to see clearly or to see in a it's kind of a prefix of emphasis to really see or
clearly see or to observe to clearly observe to clearly
be aware so um
to observe and that's the that's the medium through which
we're going to explore these next four sets of practices of mindfulness of
breathing then someone asks why is vipassana often
taught as an intro to mindfulness it also works that way and it doesn't
have to be done only um with the strong base of concentration
and um and so it can be done at fact practice directly but a lot of what people are doing when
it's practiced directly and immediately is sorting their way through all the ways in which they are not concentrated
and so they're beginning to become wise about the hindrances about distractions and and so rather than kind of more
directly getting concentrated there's a concentration through a lot of understanding and wisdom
about all the things that keep us going distractedly so then we can settle and
and with wisdom rather than settling with sometimes they say settling with faith
when person just is dedicated just being simple and focused
and but sooner or later if you start with mindfulness the
concentration is brought in and mindfulness and concentration become partners
if we start more of the concentration then later mindfulness is brought in so they become the partners
so both are true and both are valuable and this anapanasati
can be seen as kind of a hybrid of these two with a lot of emphasis on the settling
relaxing concentrating that that sets a stage for
a strong mindfulness so thank you all very much