good morning or wherever you might be maybe it's
afternoon maybe it's some really early in the
morning
for those of you who don't know me i'm diana clark i'm
sitting in for gail this morning just so he can have a day off
this morning and so for those of you on youtube
they will be back tomorrow at uh 7 a.m
for those of you on zoom you know who i am so uh warm welcome
warm welcome
as a little introduction i heard this from gil
some time ago and i liked this uh idea that
when we're practicing with anapanasati when we're practicing with the breath
we might think of it as in the same way that we go for a walk we might go on a
pilgrimage and we keep walking one step after
another we keep walking whether we are going
whether we are there's things to notice there's
landscape there's buildings there's other people but because we're on a
pilgrimage we just keep walking
doesn't mean that we're not noticing other things but we keep walking maybe sometimes with a little bit more
emphasis on noticing the way we're walking and sometimes the attention shifts a little bit to the way
that we are noticing whatever there is to be noticed
so in the same way with anapanasati practice that is
mindfulness of breathing practice we stay with the breath
just like we might keep walking
and we might notice things the landscape of our experience if you
will and but we keep with the breath we keep
noticing sometimes it's in the foreground sometimes it's in the background but we
keep noticing the experience of breathing
and then to take this analogy a little bit further we might say that when we're walking we
might encounter stray dogs and some of them are so cute and we stop
and we pet the dog maybe for weeks we completely forget that we're walking
on a pilgrimage maybe there are barking dogs that
we ignore they they don't really seem to be a problem so we
don't give them any attention we just keep walking
maybe there are some barking dogs that we meet and we open our hand we show them our hand
to show that we're safe that we're okay we're safe for them
they don't have to be worried about us
maybe there are some dogs that come up to us and we clearly say to them no
go home
so through all these different dogs that might visit we just keep walking
so that's what i'd gil offered this initially and i kind of like this idea
it might be different experiences that arise but maybe there's some way that we can
just stay with the sensations of breathing
okay so before our guided meditation
just taking alert posture
a posture that expresses our intention to practice
as well as some warmth some care kindness
so some uprightness but that doesn't have some coldness or
or hardness to it
and to connect with the experience of
breathing
feeling the breaths
noticing the quality of the breaths
are they smooth are they rough
maybe the breaths are long maybe they're a little more short
maybe the quality is maybe some deep breaths or maybe they feel a little more shallow
we're just noticing
feeling the rhythm of the breath
an in-breath and then an out breath
and then is there a way that we can stretch our awareness
expand our awareness to include the whole physical body
this expanding stretching of the awareness helps us to
not get lost into our experience or contracted around
something it might be helpful to
imagine sometimes with the exhales a little bit of blowing up the awareness just like we
might blow up a balloon in a relaxed easy manner
having the body be the arena of our attention
again nothing in particular needs to be happening we're being with
sensations of the breathing and with the body
can we offer our attention to different parts of the body
the face
the shoulders
the chest
the belly
it might be that bringing our attention to these
different areas allow a certain amount of softening
relaxing letting go of the tension
maybe not also we don't have to make it a problem if
there's still some tension some holdings
but is there a way that we can let go of some of the holding patterns in the
body maybe with the exhale there's a little bit of release
very subtle
this relaxing calming is more associated with allowing letting go
then with any
doing
we might check in and see if we're creating any new tension by
expectations we might have
we can't notice any pleasant sensations that are associated
with breathing
this can be very subtle but maybe there's a little feeling of
smoothness maybe there's a little feeling of
letting go with the exhale
that has some pleasure with it
maybe there's some pleasant sensations associated with the
just being intimate with our breathing
maybe there's a feeling of contentment
a vague feeling of okayness
this may not be our dominant experience it may be just a corner of our
experience
can we tune into this aspect of our experience
any sense of okay-ness contentment pleasantness
and allow this to be a support
being settled in the body feeling the sensations of breathing
you can now turn towards the mental experience
a gentle inquiry are there any thoughts
some mental activity that takes us away from the present moment
experience
and just like we did with the body and with the breath we can notice
the experience of this mental activity
rather than trying to make it go away
perhaps they have a lot of energy associated with them
or maybe not so much energy with this mental activity
are the thoughts more discursive writing novels so to speak
are they very simple descriptive just a single sentence
maybe somewhere in between
just noticing the quality not so much the content
there might be a sense of constriction or tightness around
the breath i'm sorry around the breath but also around the
mental activity maybe there's a sense of ease
spaciousness openness can feel into that associated with the
thoughts the mental activity is there a tightening or a
opening
maybe there's a sense of pushing or pulling not liking liking this
movement of wanting we can notice that
also
maybe there's a sense of looking for something searching
how does that feel what is that experience
letting the content of the thought take care of itself
more being with the experience
of having these thoughts
maybe we're identified with the thoughts this is me
this is mine
no matter which way we are experiencing the thoughts as we breathe in
as we breathe out can we relax soften
these mental activities
letting the activities of the mind come to rest
maybe the breaths themselves are can reassure the mind and
some kind of way that the mind doesn't need to be so
active
not getting involved with the thinking but trusting the breath
not all mental activity needs to stop
we're just allowing a calming a softening of whatever is
happening in the mind
we can do this by being aware of mental activity without getting involved getting tangled up in
all the while in and breathing out
staying with the sensations of breathing
allows the settling of the mind and the body
the calming
so that we aren't pushed around
by this mental activities or
sensations in the body so that we don't spend all our
energy reacting to
responding to trying to take care of trying to make different our experience
and instead we can be with our experience
sometimes that includes being with others
if we have a certain amount of calmness then we're more apt to really be able to deeply listen
to what others are saying to us really be present for others
as well as for ourselves in a way that perhaps
we might be a refuge for others if we're not agitated if we're not busy
with ourselves
so may our practice be a support for us
and for those around us
may all beings find ease and happiness
may all beings know peace
you