so good morning
and welcome to the
beginning of the week and a new theme
for these morning teachings
and the theme is the seven factors of
awakening
and it's following
the practice and the teaching of
experiencing the mind
experiencing the mind state the mind
state or the mind being
a broader experience of our inner
interiority our inner life
than noticing the particular activities
of mind that are operating for example
thinking
or particular emotions going on
and the state of mind is kind of like
the mood or the atmosphere or the
general state of uh
way we are our b state of being almost
and and so as we become
experience a state of mind more fully
we start becoming aware that there are
different
states of mind that we can experience or
qualities different characteristics
features of the state of mind
and these seven factors of awakening can
be seen
as both as particular practices we do
and also as a state's
qualities or characteristics of the
state of mind
or the state of awareness that as that
state of awareness state of mind becomes
more highlighted
and becomes more noticed and something
we can rest in and feel
then we can start noticing
these qualities of awareness these
qualities of our state of mind
state of awareness and um
the um so there are seven of them
and the first is usually in english
translated as mindfulness
the second in english usually is
investigation
then effort joy
tranquility samadhi
usually translated as concentration and
equanimity
and these are considered the crown
jewels of buddhism
they are sometimes actually likened
apparently in ancient india
a a monarch had seven jewels that kind
of
were the represented the monarchy
and uh and may and so in buddhism those
seven jewels
are the seven factors of awakening
kind of a curious metaphor that's found
in the ancient texts
is that the um it's like this
a monarch that uh
has seven special sets of clothes
suits to wear at different occasions and
and so in the same way that a monarch
has a special maybe affluent
sets of clothes to wear
so buddhist practitioners as they
develop
in practice have these seven factors of
awakening
as their suit it's a kind of strange
metaphor but i think that
maybe what's suggested by it is a suit
is something you wear for a while
instead of clothes you wear it for a
while
and so these different factors of
awakening
at different times different ones of
them represent the state of mind we are
in
and we kind of wear that state for a
while so there can be a time
when mindfulness involves a great sense
of
clear awareness and the clear sense of
awareness stands out
and that's the state of that's the
primary characteristics of our state of
mind
other times it might be that there's a
great sense of tranquility or a great
sense of joy
or great sense of unification or samadhi
or a great state of equanimity that
stands out of these sec seven factor
awakening each one can stand out
and be the primary characteristic
or it's possible to be aware of all
seven um
kind of imbalance kind of all kind of
working together in a certain way and
we can recognize them together and and
or maybe
see how we need to bring them into
balance
and many years ago when i sat a long
retreat
at some point in the practice these
seven factors awakening stood out in
highlight
and which they can and when the mind is
really settled and at peace
then these become the some of the
primary characteristics of what
we notice in mindfulness because
everything else is kind of abated and
gotten quiet and still and peaceful
and these seven factors are what remains
and i found myself that i was kind of
balanced i was actually instructed to
balance them
bring them into balance and at some
point the teacher said
i've noticed that when you talk about
bringing these
seven factors of awakening into balance
you never
talk about equanimity it seems like
you're always
tinkering with them and uh and then i
realized yes
i was always kind of thinking i had to
fix them and get them just right
and i had no equanimity around whatever
state i was in
and that helped me kind of to settle
back and become more equanimous
so the first of these seven factors of
awakening is um
ancient pali word for it sati
and translated a number of different
ways and
mindfulness is the most common in
english
and um but the way that
mindfulness practices come to the west
there are many things that are
called mindfulness all of them may be
appropriately so
but sometimes what mindfulness is uh is
referred to as a clear recognition of
what's happening
so it's a cognitive act act of
recognizing
hearing if you're hearing my voice right
now or
or recognizing there's pressure on your
butt if you're sitting on a chair
or that the recognition oh
my hand is cold but my torso is warm
and so there's the clear recognition of
things and sometimes that's represented
by
using mental notes where that
recognition is a little bit more
highlighted
and and focused with the mental noting
sometimes what's called mindfulness is
feeling experiencing sensing experiences
and some teachers really emphasize not
uh
these languages of feeling feel your
your breathing sense your breathing
experience what's going on and um and so
it's set more
sensory and so we're kind of resting in
the sensory capacity of the body to be
to be mindful to be aware
and sometimes what's uh emphasizes the
power
observation and and uh
and what's the just simply observe
what's happening
and but don't interfere with it
and all those three recognition
feeling and observing are emphasized by
the buddha
as practices that we can do but it's
but it's not necessarily what he calls
sati or mindfulness
he calls these other words for those
activities
and and but what those other activities
are they're part of
mindfulness practice
because they're the practices that lead
to
sati lead to a state of awareness
and what we're looking for is we
practice these things clearly
recognizing what's happening
focusing on the breathing feeling the
experience more fully
um observing the experience as it's
happening
is what we're moving towards is a state
of awareness
and uh the sometimes it's been
translated when it becomes a state
pikabody sometimes used the translation
of lucid awareness
and there's a sense of lucidity a
clarity an
openness a luminosity
it's all these metaphors that people try
to use to describe
the the state of mindfulness
and it's not easy to be there it's not
easy to rest in that state or be with it
and that's why in the process of
anapanasati deepening practice that with
time we get a sense of
of this the state of mind we can also
then become aware there's a state of
awareness that's
almost coterminous with the state of
mind it's almost
almost the same thing or occurs within
the same domain
and so sati mindfulness as a state
that we allow for and so i think that
the word english word awareness
is my preferred way of then translating
sati
and um we can and we are aware
we say i am aware and
and so to kind of paraphrase descartes
i i am aware therefore i am
and um and the and the word i am
uh almost applies kind of almost an
identity
uh like this is this this kind of
defines me
so this i am aware kind of suggests this
broad kind of way of
being or just existing in a certain way
existing in awareness
not easy to rest in or be with
but it is possible and one of the ways
to
get to that is to begin
living at the speed of mindfulness
and this is a particularly
valuable to do while on a retreat where
you know nothing really has to be done
there's no hurry to do anything
hopefully and and where there's more
time to take it easy
and just kind of do things maybe at a
slower pace than usual
and so to practice at the speed of
mindfulness
means to or say it differently to
practice at the speed
of awareness and what i mean by that
is to
do things whatever you're going to do do
them at the speed
that keeps you close closely aware
of being aware that that you're
cognizant of yourself being aware as you
do
it in whatever way awareness is for you
in a particular time through
the recognition of what you're doing as
you're doing it by sensing and feeling
it as you do it
or simply observing it quietly from the
kind of in the
back of the mind or something that um
you um you sense it and feel it so
so um the um
so you so you the speed of mindfulness
speed of awareness
is to stay close you know you're doing
it you know you're
part of it you're allowing something to
register in the present moment
around the experience as opposed to
doing things so quickly
that you're ahead of yourself you're
into the next thing you're more
thinking about the next thing and then
just really beating for each thing you
do
and so it doesn't necessarily mean you
have to do things slowly i
i was a fast order cook after i came
back from
three years in a zen monastery and i
learned to be very aware
spinning around and doing many things at
once in the kitchen working fast
in some ways i found it easier to be
aware there because
i would just let go of all my
distractions just be in the dance of the
kitchen
so it doesn't necessarily have to be
fast as slow
but generally especially on retreat
generally for most people that's the
kind of beginning the access point for
that to happen
so the mindfulness
the first factor of awakening and
sometimes seen as a particular activity
of mind
practice we do and sometimes as a state
and hopefully the activity of doing it
the practice
leads to this lucidity of awareness the
state of mind a state of being mindful
state of being aware
and that you'll feel the goodness of
that and the freedom of it
and the benefits of doing that
so thank you and
and we'll continue
these morning talks with the factors
awakening tomorrow