warm hello from redwood city here at the insight meditation center
and
the imagination that is wonderful that thinks of so many of
you spread out across the continent and the globe
um getting ready to this myth for this meditation and kind of a gathering together of
a community of meditators as much as gathering together our bodies
and minds to be here
and now to be here in the company of others meditating
and i think it's important to appreciate that one way or the other we don't meditate
alone that um we're finding our way
as a community as a as society as a
in all kinds of ways that that exists
so yesterday this week someone had been
offering these single words that maybe for some of you might be interesting to keep in your
in your in reserve for your practice both on the
cushion and meditating and also in daily life and
you know i started off with the word now and uh it can be a powerful word
if it helps place you in the now in the present moment in a way that is supportive and
helpful and attentive to what's here
and then tuesday was the word here wednesday was the word yes
it's a very you know it's a positive word and to be able to associate the practice of mindfulness
with this positivity of yes it sometimes really helps us to settle
in here and today i'd like to introduce the word no
and maybe not a popular word but it can be a very wise word
that not be said with aversion or hostility of any kind
or a kind of not even very careful it's not a kind of dismissal of something
but um if we're in meditation we say we can say no
to habits of mind that we know all too well don't serve us are not helpful
that we know it's to our detriment or we say no
gently kindly in a sense of not now this is not the time
to to trains of thoughts and thinking which
are not to the point what we're doing when we're doing this precious work of settling in here to develop clear
presence in the present moment so we can say no and it's that clarity of no it's
different than the positivity of yes yes it's kind of an opening and allowing almost
but a no there's a clarity to it not this no
and then there's all kinds of underlying beliefs that go underneath assumptions that go along
underneath our way we operate the way we think the way that we act and motivate us and one
of those is all kinds of ideations of me myself and mine
ideas of self i need to do this i need to do that desires that we have and beliefs and
desires are important and they are all these things have value but when we meditate
sometimes it's appropriate to gently lovingly say no this is not the time no
not this not this not this this is not what they get caught in this is not what to get
concerned with not this and sometimes when something occurs in meditation and we start
focusing on it sometimes it's not present momentum awareness we bring to it but rather it
begins to be retrospective thinking analysis discussing it to ourselves
and then we kind of lose the thread of the present moment and so just know
no so if you'd like on this this meditation today
you might experiment with a clear
statement of just no to certain things that take you away from the present moment certain things
that get you entangled with the present moment habits of mind which are not useful
and uh it's kind of like mine sometimes it's like a two-year-old child that is going to push against the boundaries
push against the limits to find out where it's safe where the boundaries are
and sometimes a clear no to a two-year-old will actually settle them they'll give you clear because now they
know where safety is they know what's allowed and there's kind of a clarity there
so sometimes for the mind too it needs to hear the no it needs to hear not this
so so that's my suggestion for today so
um so please uh take a meditation posture that is
suitable for you and it could be many different types
and i like to think that the principle of a posture is that one that is comfortable for a period of time
but also alert
that promotes alertness of course much of the alertness is coming from the mind
so almost any posture might work
and then to soften the gaze of your eyes
if you're looking at your monitor as i speak you might continue but just soften
the gaze maybe even slightly out of focus if it's a relaxed thing to do
and maybe even then taking your gaze and pointing it down 45 degrees
towards the floor maybe and maybe imagining that you're looking
at a mountain far in the distance or and just kind of relax and soften the
gaze letting the eyes rest in their sockets
and if it's comfortable for you you can also close your eyes
and then to gently
carefully taking a few long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale to relax and settle in
to this body relax and settle in
to where you feel some stability or safety or well-being
in your being in your body in your heart
and letting your breathing return to normal and continue maybe for the next three
breaths to relax your body face shoulders belly
and maybe for the next three breaths maybe if it's possible
to relax the mind calming your thinking
releasing any pressure or attention to think
and then to settle into the body's experience or breathing
maybe as if the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out are like the gentle waves out on the ocean
in which you gently are floating up and down on it lifted on the inhale
gently lowered on the exhale
and feeling their rhythms breathing in and breathing out
as if it's a rhythm that can allow you to relax and
feel comforted or feel safe
settling into your breathing and if there's anything that takes you
away from your breathing thoughts maybe even feelings
if it seems appropriate you can gently clearly say no not that no
and continue with your breathing
but if it doesn't know it doesn't make it go away or stop then maybe make it the object of
mindfulness and it isn't so much you're saying no
to whatever it is that's happening you're saying no
to your involvement with it you're concerned with it
so that your concern can remain you're breathing
the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
if you are thinking more than you're meditating
say no to thinking remind your mind
not now no
and always when you need to begin again with your meditation
you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to take a few moments to see if there's any ways that you have
benefited from this sitting even if you're restless or it's been
challenging there are the ways that you are a little
bit more attentive or connected to yourself
are you a little calmer than you were before
did you learn something about the value of no
that help might help you better to say yes
to mindfulness to being present
there is a no that is a no to what takes us away from
our own goodness our own well-being
our own our own care and good will
and at the end of the meditation reflecting a little bit about how we might have benefited
or maybe having confidence that even if we don't see the direct benefits
there are unknown benefits from doing this
practice and whether the benefits are known or unknown in the last minutes of the meditation
to dedicate them to the welfare and happiness of others
somehow imagine that they spread from you out into the world
and somehow or other direct and indirect channels of contact
with others the benefit of this meditation practice may it be that it spreads out across the
lands and seas to touch all beings
so they benefit as well
may the people in afghanistan benefit from our meditation
maybe by increasing our capacity to care and to
be inspired to improve the lives of people there or
maybe the peoples who are we can support and help much closer
may our our care extend to the people of haiti
with so much struggles in some ways
maybe people who feel forgotten by the rest of the world may we not forget them
may we care for them and may they receive the benefits or practice
places in the world where their covet is rampant
still difficult in india and indonesia and
thailand and many places
may they be held in our sphere of goodwill and that we wish that our practice benefits
them as well and most look most most local more
locally to here in california the many people
who've been impacted by all the fires here
lost their homes their communities
may it be that our practice here is for the welfare and happiness of all
beings including ourselves and as we benefit may it benefit others
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
so today is the fourth talk on faith
and um the word sada in pali
is sometimes translated translated into english as confidence
and one of the reasons for this is that one of the primary purposes for this
sada this faith is to have the confidence to engage in practice
the confidence that you can engage practice make a difference
and many times in the teachings of the buddha it's clear that someone when someone
learns the dharma well enough to have faith the purpose of that faith
is so they begin their practice so it's not faith in some
belief or something you're supposed to carry with you and then apply to your life you know in terms of a
idea but rather it's a it's a confidence that there is
something worthwhile to do and it's worthwhile to practice worthwhile to be mindful to develop
our meta or compassion or our equanimity or our clear seeing of what's happening
here all kinds of things the practice of generosity
so um the um so this idea of confidence
and um um
so one of the things that as practice develops and we begin having
some real feeling for what this practice is about then there's a particular kind of
confidence that can arise that maybe for the people who haven't experienced it well enough
it might seem foreign or uninteresting or kind of bland or kind of not really
so important because it's the absence of something and how can the absence of something be so
something to be confident in then that confidence is in the absence of clinging
absence of grasping or the ass the absence of
attachment when attachment means clinging or grasping
and so to have confidence in non-clinging
and and this is a can be very helpful to understand this that
at some point it's not always so clear what to have confidence in there's all kinds of questions about we
might have or challenges we have but it's but at minimum at some point we
can have clear confidence that it's not worthwhile to get attached
to get to cling to grasp onto uh things and uh and to have that clear experience
of that because not because it's a belief and for people don't have the experience
of non-clinging there can be all kinds of protests about why clinging grasping attachment is
useful and important but if you have the experience of it then non-clinging then we have a clear
then reference point for watching feeling how cl clinging when it comes back in
is to our detriment grasping as it begins working it up is actually a
diminishment of ourselves or limiting ourselves or or
get interfering with the best qualities of who we are to come forth into the world
and so at some point we start experiencing the benefits of non-clinging how wonderful it is
and then the practice can be maybe maybe the confidence is not completely strong about it yet
and then practice has a little bit to do with the questioning the debating
about how important is it to not cling is it okay not to cling maybe you're
supposed to cling maybe in these kinds of areas we have to be allowed to grasp or to get attached
and and how about here and here and so there starts to be a natural
questioning a debating uh exploration about where do i fit you know is it okay
not to cling is that really valuable or and so and so rather than being struggle and
think that this is wrong to have this debate or this question i believe that at some point in practice that becomes a
healthy part of the practice questioning debating taking both sides being the devil's
advocate looking at this deeply and and seeing and if you find you know a
really good reason why you need to grasp it it's for your betterment and betterment of others there's no one to
stop you but if you really are mindful and carefully attentive and really
experience the the peace the well-being the benefits of non-clinging
you might start to start having confidence in non-clinging
have faith in it trust it and so then the faith the sada
is not a belief system it's not in something that
you know you've been told is a good idea like practice and but now it becomes something that
becomes a very important reference point for our lives and this is the reference point we could
say it's peace we could say it's a sense of happiness or freedom
but uh to to call it that um
kind of takes that the gaze the focus away from what brought it what brought that peace
and happiness and well-being and uh and what brings it in some very
deep way is the non-grasping the non-attachment the non-clinging
and uh and so to keep an eye on that then you can right there at the juncture
at the place where the real work exists because very few people become totally
free and totally peaceful once and for all most people can have a taste of it and
then they get caught up again and but to remember to have confidence and non-clinging
puts you at that juncture where the practice really uh has some very great value that's
where the work is and it isn't that you have to let go but maybe it's the confidence to
non-cling allows you to look at clinging in a deeper and deeper way to really be present for it
to realize this is important if if the emphasis is on freedom or peace or happiness
then if we lose it then like then we try to get it back perhaps we don't know quite where to do and
and where the focus might be so non-clinging but if the focus is on only
on non-clinging or we only think about that then we might not appreciate all the benefits that come from non-clinging
so ideally we're kind of looking at both and aware of both for someone who just begins to practice
i think that the benefits of non-clinging and the well-being that comes from it is right there at the
beginning perhaps or early on but in various maybe i don't know i don't want to diminish the value of it but in maybe
small ways maybe mundane ways ordinary ways just the shoulders relax a little bit
that's a letting go and a sense of well-being that comes there's a little bit more calm in the
mind but as practice gets deeper and deeper
or fuller and fuller then the the value the experience of non-clinging becomes richer and richer
and at some point the confidence becomes phenomenal strong confidence where we realize
that there's nothing that's worthwhile
losing the non-clinging for that all the things we need to do and
take care of in this world we can take care of better with non-clinging
it's a difficult place to have confidence in because many times the world family friends people in the world
expect us want people want us to be get anxious or get caught or participate
in the attachments that they're involved in and to show that we care by getting
afraid or anxious or being angry or upset by things but
and so it's a little bit hard when the people around us expect us to behave in ways that call back our clinging
but to really discover strong confidence in clinging and non-clinging
and not to succumb to the social pressure pressures to be otherwise this is also another place where you know
it's not easy and that's where the debates come up or the explorations or the
deeper looking at what's going on that's necessary but you know keep having
coming back and i think the one way to understand the path of buddhist practice
it's a path to a greater and greater appreciation of non-clinging greater and greater confidence in it and
non-clinging and in doing so discovering the the tremendous
what follows in the wake of that the tremendous sense of well-being freedom happiness
peace clarity there's many words for what follows in the wake of non-clinging
and um and we don't want to raise any of it or or
latch on or cling to any of it and by keeping the focus on non-clinging
then we don't cling to what is wonderful but not long non-clinging opens our door
the door to what is wonderful and and then if you stay close to
non-clinging maybe we won't cling to what's wonderful and may it be that you share your
wonderfulness your goodness you're not clinging
share it with others in such a way that you are being generous supportive helpful
and so it's really clear to yourself that this practice you're doing is not just for yourself but it's also for the
welfare of others confidence and non-clinging
so thank you and then a couple of announcements
so first one is maybe in the wake of what i just said i've been very moved by
the crisis in the world right now and uh and the one that's kind of
closest to my heart to the moment is what's going on in haiti
and a neighbor to the north american continent if you listen and often as i said earlier a kind of
forgotten country with tremendous poverty so close to a country that has
tremendous wealth and i wondered if um our youtube community
uh could band together in our goodness and generosity and
here's opportunity to take our practice and benefit the world and uh to raise funds for the people of
haiti and there's an organization called partners in health that does a lot of
on-the-ground work with local healthcare workers bringing supplies and medicine and med
medical workers to partner with them works with local communities very intimately so they're really in harmony
with what's going on so what i like to propose is you could certainly make a donation directly
but i'd like to propose that tomorrow friday and maybe sunday also for the imc
community more widely is maybe if you make a donation any
donation you make to imc through the kind of the
online button i think it's on the youtube page ref the link to it
under the that any donations imc will turn around all of it
and uh and give it to partners in health and that would be lovely if we could uh
come together like that so tomorrow and sunday so i'll announce it again tomorrow
and the other um announcement is that tomorrow after our
little dharmet that i do i'll provide a zoom link and then we can have a community meeting
of those those of you who can and just to check in and ask questions and you can ask me questions about the
teachings i've been doing or something and we'll do a little breakout groups have a chance to meet each other and
many of you are only seeing each other's names and greetings and and um so maybe for about 45 minutes or
so and um the zoom link will be in the chat but i'll also put the zoom link a few
other places including um on the imc calendar for this event or for you know
imc calendar for tomorrow and also in the what's new in imc's uh home page
that um you'll see a little announcement for it and there'll be the zoom link as well and it's possible that the it'll be
password protected and if it is the password will be meta m-e-t-t-a
so i'll see you all tomorrow thank you