okay so hello a warm warm hello dear sangha
wherever you are in the world yay
so for today's practice together
um like to invite us in the practice of menta
and considering meta as a way of
homecoming coming home to ourselves only coming home to ourselves
no matter what is going on whether we feel
challenged tired over exuberant whatever it might be
going on it's all okay it's all okay i'm coming home
coming home to to ourselves with
showing up for ourselves with a sense of showing up showing up even if sometimes
it might be so hard to just do that and and it's okay for all human beings there
might be times that it's hard to show up and we still do it we just crawl we crawl and
show up like okay i'm here now what ah it's okay it's okay
you've showed up you've showed up you've showed up you are here you're whole
you're home in your body your home in your heart
ah and landing with things just as they are so
so relating to meta not as a grim duty not as something that we should
cultivate that we should do it's a should but it's coming home
there's nothing that needs to be done if you tonight as i lead it if you feel like
using the phrases great if you don't want to use the phrases don't
this is just sense of kind presence kind presence coming home
coming home reconnecting with yourself connecting arriving being
with with care and that sometimes that's enough that's all we need sometimes
there's more energy for more for cultivation for phrases for for
yes and sometimes just just holding just holding
what is here so whether today
you're in the space where you just want to be with what is gently just ever so
gently or if there's more space to expand and hold it's all good
but i'm leading us into a more gentle way of
just being with just being with whatever arises whatever needs to arise coming
home coming home and welcoming whatever is here even if it's a
whole crowd of sorrows as in the poem translated from roomie by coleman barks
even if it's a crowd of sorrows that greets you it's okay they're guests they're guests you're home
just being home comfortably home [Music] so
that is the setup for our practicing just coming home
to our body to our hearts with kindness
ah all right gang dear sangha let's practice together
in a formal meditation posture which again might be an easy one tonight might be
lying down if that's what this body needs so
so i invite you to choose your meditation posture whatever is appropriate for you
sitting lying down standing [Music]
whatever posture where this body
is comfortable for meta
it's important even more important for the body to be comfortable
and if you need to shift and move during this guided meditation
it's okay do it with mindfulness do it with kindness
not jerking your limbs around which is kindly
as if your limbs your body is a treasured treasured beloved being ah moving it
for relief and now landing landing in this body
greeting
ever so gently greeting
reading the sensations
of the breath
in the abdomen
greeting any tightness or tension
present in your face
in your jaw greeting
gently with kindness
any tightness in the shoulders arms hands
exhaling
creating the exhale
breathing breathing your heart
your heart space
whatever is present
whatever is showing up at home is okay
making friendly space
relaxing around it
reading the legs the feet
the sit bones contacting the cushion or the chair
it is so nice to be home
connected to the home that is this body this heart
this mind with awareness spacious kind awareness
nothing more to do nothing more needed
than to just feel at home
relaxing softening
landing in this body whatever is present is okay
what makes this home is an attitude
there could be aches and pains unpleasant sensations or thoughts or emotions
and yet
with the perspective that this is a holy mansion
it's a hallowed sacred dimension
this being that is you body heart and mind it's spacious
plenty of space for everything to be
just as it is in the different spaces in the wide spaces
and for you to feel cozy
at home
with yourself
feeling at home feeling at home with your arm
your jaw your forehead your legs
your abdomen melt with ease feeling at home
and if you like
if there is a particular space a place
a physical location maybe your bed or a chair
or a place in nature if there is a place that you feel
particularly comfortable cozy safe at home
you can imagine yourself in the space and if nothing comes up don't don't worry about it it's fine
this is enough
feeling at home
with this breath this breath
the abdominal cavity feeling spacious
here here
at home in this moment
connecting with awareness
every moment of kind awareness
is a moment of being home
deeply connected settled rooted
see if you would like to experiment
put in your hand the palm of your hand
and you're just the proverbial heart center
breeding yourself at your own door
home welcome home beer you're at home it's okay
it's okay
sometimes when we need nourishing and healing in our heart
for this being who is ourselves it's okay to stay home
not leave home animals
who are injured or hurting they stay in their lair or when we are sick or
in the body or needing care we stay home we stay close to home where it's
comfortable safe to nourish ourselves to be ready
show up in the world again so it's okay to be home feel connected just
in this moment for meta with meta for this being filling our own
cup filling our own cup
before we fill other people's cups
[Music]
pump
can we feel home
connected present
welcoming kind to ourselves and whatever is arising
feeling home [Music] connected
safe making a safe space for ourselves
the first phrase of mid-ties may i feel safe from inner and outer harm it's
a wish for safety that's one way to practice it by
expressing the wish another is to feel at all can we feel at
home our body heart and mind with mental
we feel it invite ourselves to feel at home
this is meta a different expression of it
the more we feel at home with ourselves
with meta and kindness the more we can appreciate
be present for the mystery that is our lives unfolding
this feast that is our lives
i will read a poem
by derek olicott call love after love i have read it before
and you might have heard it elsewhere let it wash over you
with this invitation to feel at home
love after love
the time will come
when with elation
you will greet yourself
arriving
at your own door in your own
mirror and each will smile
at the other's welcome the time will come
when with elation you will greet yourself arriving
at your own door
in your own mirror
and each will smile at the other's welcome
and say sit here
eat each will smile at the others welcome
and say sit sit here eat
you will love again the stranger
who was yourself give wine give bread
give back your heart to itself to the stranger who has loved you
all your life whom you ignored for another
who knows you by heart take down the love letters from the
bookshelf the photographs the desperate notes
peel your own image from the mirror
sit sit
feast on your life
you will love again the stranger who was yourself
give back your heart to itself to the stranger who has loved you all your life
whom you ignored for another sit
feast on your life
thank you all thank you for your practice may we all feel home
welcome ourselves home in every moment
of being so
as i mentioned during the guided meditation
i mean the meta phrases we the first one is to wish ourselves
and others safety may you may i be safe from inner and outer harm there's the sense of
may you be safe there's this wish for for that so another way the way we
found ourselves in ted today is feeling at home feeling safe
again for most people maybe not for everyone but home has a sense of connotation of
safety ease meta love so
really holding ourselves greeting ourselves
at our own door as derek wellicott put it this feeling
of being at home is a way of expressing meta metta is not one thing it's not just the
phrases it's just there's so many ways to practice cultivating good will
kindness well-being for ourselves
so that we can offer it to the world filling our own cup so that we can then
offer it to the whole world so so with that
i'd love to invite your reflections kenneth says nikki thank you so much it
was exactly what i needed tonight thank you ken i'm delighted
delighted and if you feel moved to say any more you're
welcome to unmute yourself if you wish and if not it's okay
it's the floor is open to reflections comments
jesse says such a lovely poem thank you for sharing nikki you are welcome jesse it's it's a favorite poem of mine so
beautiful and i trust i know neil will send it yes he's giving thumbs up to the google
groups afterwards for everyone's reference thank you neil thanks jesse
any questions anything you discovered what was it like actually this way of
feeling home home simply home connecting with yourself you're welcome to raise
your zoom hand uh yes don please
yeah um thank you so much and uh i i couldn't help but smiling at the
beginning uh when you uh talked about just showing up and uh that's about what i did tonight
and um uh but it was great and it was um as somebody just mentioned
just uh just what i needed and um so i i thank you so much and um
and i was thinking a bit about uh this sort of um letting b
and or making space and it's sort of harking back to our conversation last friday about
you know tonight is or other sort of issues that one might be having and um
and so it was really helpful for me as i was sort of
just incurably stiff back and just going oh welcome steph back
and um thank you thank you don
thank you for that reflection and and beautiful that you showed up you
showed up that's that's that's all there is to life showing up for
ourselves feeling at home thank you don for those wonderful reflections and also
connecting this to our conversation on friday with making space and
welcoming yeah bill asks how do you welcome unwelcome
house guests like anxiety oh yes yes yes yes
claire says what a wonderful concept i'm not sure if it's about that but i'll assume it is yes of course that's
exactly the idea so so anxiety too
um [Music] pain anxiety tinnitus you you name it
making space for all of these especially anxiety
if you try to push it away if you if you try to um
you know anxiety can be like a wild horse with energy
and if you try to put it in a small pen and contract it it actually or or push it
away it doesn't quite work so treating it as an unwelcome guest
bill and others would be actually giving in more energy it causes more suffering
whereas the guest is here already you know anxiety is visiting right it's
like you can't ignore guess that's like it's it's delusion if you try to fight
reality if you try to fight a guess who's here you're not gonna win i mean
or rather if you try to fight reality reality always wins
so so a um a guest such as anxiety is part of
reality so not fighting not trying to push it away but being
skillful with it giving it space giving it space similar to tinnitus so how what does
that look like for anxiety imagine that it's a wild it's there's a
that the wild horse again if you put it in a small pan it'll kick the door open
but imagine you give it a whole white pasture and i've had many practitioners report that this method actually this
way of treating it works so and i've explored it myself so the
anxiety can be there oh yes run around yes but there is so much space
there is feeling at home anxiety can be there it's not the focus
it's not the only thing that has that gets the megaphone
um so that's the way you would work with get there are no unwelcome guests if you
if you call them unwelcome then you're already working with them in the way
that um that's that's that's giving them more
energies like trying to push them away and just pushing away as i described in detail on friday actually hooks them up
hooks them in place trying to push them away helps them in place
laura asks about tinnitus yes uh we talked about tinnitus and similar
things on friday so that is on audio dharma and also on youtube so you're welcome to
to check out all of that so and now the time has come deborah let's
come to your hand i just saw your hand let's come back to it after we come back
from bruce because it's time for groups i want to make sure there's time spacious time for us to
have reflections in in sangha this is such a
lovely saga and i know that folks appreciate showing up for each other so
again tonight showing up for yourself showing up for each other
in groups and starting with 15 seconds of silent meta
and then sharing as little or as much as you like just showing up that's all it takes so
rooms are created take care of yourselves take care of each other welcome back everyone
rooms are closed and we have a couple of minutes for reflections and
deborah's hand was up so deborah i invite yes great fantastic here you are
i hope it is still relevant to people but when you talked about anxiety someone brought up anxiety it reminded
me of a beautiful story that a friend a spiritual teacher peter rangel said
he said that one time he and his little boy when he was like six years old was in his hot tub
and it started getting really dark and the little boy got really scared and his dad said well that's just fear
and the little boy said hello fear and then a little while later
he said goodbye fear and then the next night
they were there and he didn't say anything about the fear he just said hello fear
so you reminded me like we can just say hello anxiety and then it takes it away
from enveloping us in some way sometimes yeah it's i i love
that story deborah thanks for sharing and in this way it's also it's not an unwelcome guest right it's transforming
by seeing and saying hello fear hello anxiety hi welcome here you are yeah my old friend
my old friend my more and more my more and more present friend
and that also is humor right way of working with it yeah yeah thank you for sharing that that's beautiful
lovely so dear ones we and uh i think i saw one
hand that appeared and disappeared any quick comments
going once going twice okay all right so
it is seven o'clock and thank you all for your practice for showing up
for yourselves for each other and being at home
with yourselves and with this sangha may all beings feel at home may all beings feel their
own metta greet themselves at their own door and be free
and happy
you all