so warm greetings and welcome to our adventure with
breathing for today and um it's a kind of a lifetime adventure to
practice meditation and life attuned to breathing and in touch with your breathing and
aware of how your breathing is going in any given time and it's awareness of breathing
helps us to uh avoid spending unnecessary energy
in as we go through our life especially the unnecessary energy of tension or anxiety or
or ambition over efforting many of the ways
that we because we become stressful has to do with an over
exertion of energy in the muscles that they're tight too much and also in the mind and so
that gets all that gets translated into the breathing the breathing gets shallow gets tight it
moves up into the chest rather than deeper abdominal breathing behold our
breathing and so being attuned to the breathing and breathing in a easy relaxed way is a way to
um to not over effort in our lives
so to assume a meditation posture
and to close your eyes
and to feel the weight of your body against the surface
that's keeping you from falling to the center of the earth
your chair your cushion the floor your bed whatever it might be and feel
the contact of your body against this surface
and maybe rock side to side sway forward and back
or in some way kind of and then settle in
wiggle in a little bit to really settle into that spot where
there's a surface holding you
and then take a few moments to feel the edges of your body
your skin both where your skin touches your clothes
where the skin touches
your cushion chair and also wherever the tingling and vibration the warmth and
the coolness the sensations on the skin become apparent as you're
sitting here kind of a global wide
awareness of sensations along yours all over your body on your
skin
maybe it's a flowing sensation a tingling a vibration
maybe there are some sensations that fleet in and out of awareness
spark in and out of awareness as your attention roams around
and then notice where the contact of your skin may be against
your clothes or if you're lying down against the surface
you're lying down on no to feel we're breathing has an impact
we're breathing in the inhale the expansion of the chest or the belly
lifting of the shoulders causes more contact
with your clothes or some surface
and you can feel the sensations of movement of contact
feeling the rhythm of sensations of the contact of the body breathing
moving as you breathe against your clothes or your
back of your chair
maybe even there's this very subtle movement a sensation of all the way down to
the cushion you're sitting on
sensations in the front ribcage the back rib cage
the sides of the rib cage
maybe even the belly
and then bring your attention inside of your body maybe not far from
the skin bring your attention a little bit inward
to where you usually experience your
breathing
feeling the movement of sensation the changing sensations with the inhale and exhale
and as you exhale
relax deeper into your body soften the shoulders
as you exhale let this the belly become
softer
as you relax the holding in the body the tension you're relaxing or the extra energy
you're expending
softening relaxing in the face and there's less energy going into
holding the muscles
relaxing the shoulders and the arms unless energy is expended
in paradoxically with less energy expended in tension
more there can be a feeling of vitality or maybe even flowing energy
the same thing is true in the mind the thinking mind if there's any tension
or pressure agitation there maybe as you exhale
you can relax let go
expend less energy conscious energy
in mental activity
it turns out the mind works much better more creatively wiser
when less anxious or tense energy everything goes into it
and then settling in to the body
breathing
and here too the art of meditation
is to stay committed with breathing without a lot of extra
energy without any strain
and for some people it can be helpful the notion of being receptive
to the inhale
and to allow the exhale
maybe relaxing a teeny bit at the end of the exhale
to have a little pause micropause
so that is you're more sensitive to receiving the beginning of the inhale
how the inhalers how the inhale
now the inhale arises on its own
receptive to the inhales allowing the exhale
as maybe you would floating
on the sea gently
being lifted and gently lowered by the small waves coming and going
allowing yourself to be held
the buoyant water
allowing yourself to float on the inhales and exhales
some effort is needed to be receptive and allowing
while at the same time letting go and
allowing the breathing
to come to awareness
letting go of your interest in thinking
and letting your interest be
in floating on the gentle waves of inhales and exhale
like you're floating on your back on a wide peaceful sea
gently being lifted and lowered by the peaceful waves
relaxing the tension associated with thinking
the pressure the contraction
allowing the thinking to become quieter
so you can trust staying with the breathing more fully
and if you can imagine yourself floating on the your back on a peaceful sea
imagine that as you're looking up into the sky and a few clouds are drifting by in the
blue sky that way stay
connected stay floating on your breathing
but notice whatever thinking is happening
like thinking your clouds drifting by
not to be involved with the thinking but to have a kind of a view from a
distance
where there's very little energy
it used to be thinking letting go of the extra energy to think
to be involved to be engaged in thought relax the energy of thinking
the efforting of thinking and while you stay with the inhales and
exhales without a lot of effort
be aware of the thoughts that flow
through
and notice that as you're thinking do you think more in words
or more in images
or is it kind of equally both
and then and in recognizing whether it's more words more images or equal those of both
is it easier for you to notice your involvement with thinking the
energy expended to think the tension involved in thinking
and if so as you exhale
can you relax and quiet that energy that effort
and as you do so
settle more into your breathing
our bodies and our minds
operate more harmoniously
when we stop using unnecessary energy
effort
the very
effort to try hard at something unnecessary
it's counterproductive it interferes with the natural wisdom
the natural sensitivity and the natural harmony
that's available when we don't apply unnecessary energy
and before we learn to not do so it's useful just to recognize
when there is unnecessary energy in the form of tension in the body and
the mind in the thinking
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting perhaps you can intuit or feel
oh without without tension
without this extra energy of tension and pushing and trying there's more room in us
for happiness for well-being
or there's more room for us for love for good will
compassion
and to end this sitting being open to
the joys and sufferings of this world
and to be open to it without resistance
to breathe with it
to be willing to be a companion
to the world's joys and the joy the world's sufferings
to breathe with the world and in doing so
before needing to do anything more complicated perhaps you can be your kindness
spreads out from you to the world
a simple kindness which wishes well for others
wishes the best for them may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings
be free
this
so i'm going to today i'm going to discuss
the seventh step of anapanasati
seven steps of breathing in and breathing out the buddha's teachings on breath meditation
and the way it's worded it says one trains oneself breathing in one experiences
the activity of mind the mental formations the construct
construction constructing activity of the mind and in the simple ways is called the
activity of the mind breathing out one experiences the
activity of the mind and now this is a really rich topic what the mind is the poly word is chitta
ci tta and it's um you know a rich and wonderful topic
and i'll touch on some of it as we go along here but in simple terms in english we might
call it the mind and um but one of the
main activities of the mind for many of us is thinking and um
and to uh so to become aware of thinking and there's two different
ways to become aware that i'm emphasizing here one is to become uh to observe it
just to know what's happening and the other is to really experience it
feel the experience and feel what it's like to be thinking and both are important and to learn to
recognize and know and observe thinking is many times a stepping stone to feeling it and experiencing it more
fully so as always with this mindfulness of breathing
there's always this rhythm the background beat or the foreground beat
of breathing that's we're getting centered on and focused on and and
settling in on and uh and the breathing protects us a little bit
from getting caught up in the world of thinking to be resting or focusing or
stable on the breathing then as we're more stable the more awareness can begin
to open up and be more expensive more inclusive to be able to take in more and more
what's going on and and with a stable attack stable present presence attention
to breathing it's possible to be aware of thinking
without being bothered by thinking uh without making it into a problem or
think it said you know it's wrong to think in meditation or to be upset about it or to call it even a distraction and the
reason why we can why it's easier not to be bothered is because
there's not a very strong pull into that world we don't get lost in it very much
but it's also true that even if we do get lost in it we're better off not being bothered by
it being upset being agitated because we think is a recipe for perpetuating the
thinking the more agitated we are the more the mind tends to want to produce
thoughts and ideas stories and so the art of not being bothered not
being upset not being attached to thinking but also not being aversive to thinking
not making your thinking your very best friend and not making thinking your enemy
either it's just thinking is happening and to be aware of thinking going by
and the classic image in buddhism is having thoughts drift by like clouds and an endless sky
just clouds and i love the metaphor of clouds for thinking because you know you if you put your
hand into a cloud you don't get anything maybe you get a little bit moist but you know there's no solidity there
just like you can put your hand right through and it turns out that thinking is not is
actually less solid than a cloud and uh there's no you know it's it's a
it's kind of a virtual reality thing their thoughts but it's the
what we invest in our thinking the attachment the engagement the all the energy we put into it
that makes thinking sometimes actually more solid and more real and more
important than almost anything else in our lives we can get so wrapped up in our stories and our ideas and our thoughts
and and the paradox here is that the more energy we put into thinking the
more we're trying hard to you know anxiously think or be attached to it
we actually think less effectively um the most creative the most innovative
the most wise the most loving the most beneficial way of thinking
tends to be without a lot of extra energy there can be a choice to focus on some
things to think about in daily life but to do it with an easy relaxed mind
and that ability to stay focused and very relaxed allows a thinking mind to be most
productive most creative maybe there are exceptions but
for many people it's the exception to ever approach this idea of a you know a creative mind that's relaxed
thinking relax thinking and so to learn not to be bothered by
our thinking is very important one of the useful skills to learn in meditation to have this wisdom not to be caught up
in it or for against it to have a certain equanimity and to be patient
with the mind wonders often thought to keep coming back keep coming back starting over again starting over again but at some point
now it was at the seventh step of anapanasati with the idea that seven step now there's some stability there
some centering on the breath ability to stay with the breathing more continuously and of course
that comes and goes that ability and many of us will start at step one of anapanasati
um regularly and like i'm just beginning and that's completely fine but at some
point as we settle in maybe the end of a long sit meditation or maybe you know conditions come together where
there's enough stability here that we can becoming aware of thinking
and um in a way that uh it's like clouds in the endless sky we just there's a kind of almost we don't get
too caught in it we don't get focused on it but we are aware and there's a few things that are
interesting to notice when we can do this one is to notice whether we think more
in words or more in images and some people it's one or the other
and some people come some combination of both and um but you know maybe one
predominates over the other and um because once you recognize uh
what your primary quality of thinking is you can investigate something more and that is
uh where does that operate so where is the if it's avoid inner voice which is speaking
where's the loudspeaker or where's the inner mouth that's doing the speaking the vocal cord or something
um sometimes and people generally feel it's behind their forehead it's kind of somewhere in
the area what we call the brain for many modern people uh in the ancient world it
seems still to the modern world in in places in buddhist asia and if uh people associate the heart
center with where they're where they're where they are thinking um and maybe some of you do as well but
i think a tendency in the in the modern west at least is the point to the head and partly
because you know the brain has such a big role in thinking that you know we gravitate towards there and
associated with air but you know the word the words might be spoken somewhere inside
and or if you see if you're thinking in images it might be like a scene just in front
of you with the eyes closed it might be like a projection screen or or a scenery that's in front of you
there's kind of some directionality it's there there were since are watching it and that sense of location for the
inner voice if you can find it or the directionality of seeing an image is a
is a is a means by which to know or start noticing the extra energy
that goes into thinking uh if it's an inner voice there's often a kind of contraction and tightness and
pressure if there's a lot of extra energy that goes into thinking if it's a lot of imagery there might
also be a contraction or a tightness but it might be in a different location for some people it might actually be
around their physical eyes even with the eyes closed because they're seeing of an image
there's a kind of habit maybe of engaging the eyes to kind of focus on the image
and so there might be tension in the eye area
but by noticing the location where thinking seems to be occurring it's also possible to notice how much
energy is being expended for this and the and the emotions that might be
connected to the energy and so um to um
you start start seeing there's more to thinking than just the thoughts more to thinking
just the images there's the energy that's involved the tensions that are involved
the pressure there is the interest that's involved with thinking the curiosity the the being glued or
lobbed you know locked onto it sometimes it can be the feeling there can be some emotionality connected
to thinking um that's may sometimes the emotions are the fuel for it or the source for what
we're thinking about and so it's possible to to step back
in a sense settle back and just observe thinking and without necessarily
observing the content of the thought the content is often not so important
for the purpose of meditation but the associated aspects of thinking
the energy the tension the directionality the location the emotionality to it the interest we
have to it all those not to study them and get too active but all those
you can step back and kind of observe and and that all gives you access
to the instructions to experience the the mental activity so in this case
to experi to experience what it's like to be thinking or to say it differently to really feel
it feel it somatically physically almost even though it's mental there might be
some the sensations of thinking and
and this and this allows us to not be so and the more we kind of disinvest
ourselves from the story and the ideas and but without dismissing the thinking
and experiencing different parts of thinking thinking that by itself tends to become
quieter and stiller and and as thinking becomes quieter and
stiller then that's then we may be able to better more fully stay with the in-breath and
the out breath focusing on the body breathing and um and do so maybe with more sense of
ease more sense of uh well-being that comes along just the simplicity the
contentment being content just to be present and breathe
more often than not the discontent about life and the impatience belongs to the realm of thinking and
uh or fueled by thinking so
this is not an instruction to get really busy to notice and focus on thinking but
rather to stay with your breathing and and don't be bothered by it don't be
troubled by it but as it becomes uh relevant
uh to touch into an extr being an experiencing feeling what's happening as you breathe
and and maybe with the idea that you're breathing through the thinking breathing with your thinking so the
breathing supports you're not getting caught in whatever you're thinking about but you can just observe it and feel it
so may you develop a new relationship with
your thinking don't assume that the way that you think is the way it has to be
there might be wonderful delightful relaxing creative and
wise ways of thinking that take a very different form than how you're thinking these days usually
so thank you very very much and i look forward to seeing you tomorrow