hello everyone thank you for coming to this gathering
of our extended meditation community to spend
this time meditating exploring the dharma it's a fantastic thing in life to
explore the dharma or explore this the delightful i like the word
dharma but at delightful profound significant
ways in which our mind works and how we interact with the world and
and how um how the dharma works through us
in the sense that how does uh the goodness
that is part of our psychophysical system how it can work really well when we're
able to get out of the way properly and allow for something to move through us
so um today i'd like to offer suggest a
little bit more of an exercise than meditation still meditate as usual but
a little emphasis on this exercise that's part of it and that is
become be a little bit more attentive to when the mind wanders off in thought
so uh just notice it this is to say don't think intentionally but to uh
do your meditation but when your mind wanders off in thought really notice that
that's what's happening and then see if you can notice
the impact that your thinking has on you
what uh what influence does that thinking have on your body on your emotions
uh what emotions uh uh what what is it what is it is it uh completely neutral what you're
thinking about or does it have an influence on you in some way does it any residual feelings
that come with it so for example if you're imagining
you're thinking frightening thoughts is there feelings of fear that come from
that if there are uh angry thoughts other feelings of
anger or if there are desire thoughts
does that stimulate something in your physiology that you feel in your body a little bit that
upwelling of energy of desire perhaps so what's the impact desires have uh
thinking has on on you often if we just notice thinking and
note it and let go of it we haven't noticed that it has left its traces in us
and the more powerful the thinking the stronger those traces are and so and so much so that if
they might remain somehow in terms of tension in the body contraction in the body or
certain mood in the body that might last quite a long time after
the thoughts are finished they've left their traces
and um so so that's the exercise so
assuming a meditation posture
and one of the possibilities with your posture
is to assume a posture that seems to have some strength to it or some
solidity to it sitting cross-legged on the floor or
sometimes likened to or compared to being like a mountain
so the tripod base provides a firm support
if you're sitting in a chair you know that um how can you sit in the chair so there's
a little bit more solidity or a sense of being established
here in this body so the body is not treated incidentally
or is a something to forget when you're meditating meditating
but the body itself is put in a position where there's a sense of presence like it is here the body is
here with you
if you're not used to this uh it might seem a little bit awkward at
first but it's a wonderful support for meditation
to receive the body's help
in becoming established stable in the present moment here
and gently closing your eyes
relaxing the body
then in a leisurely way taking a fuller inhale than usual
as if you have all the time in the world
and a longer exhale
feeling the expansion of your chest all the way up to your shoulders
as you breathe in
maybe noticing a little bit the more subtle expansion of your back ribcage
and as you exhale relaxing at all
and letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
on the exhale softening the shoulders
and on the exhale softening
in the belly
and then establishing your attention on your breathing
wherever it's most comfortable to do it in the belly the chest the nose
and as you exhale to let go of your thoughts
and if you can't let go of them perhaps you can let them become quieter
calmer
and then receive the inhale letting go with the exhale
and if thoughts occur reappear during the inhale
recognize the thinking and notice
what influence they have on the rest of you do they come along with a mood or an
emotion or with any tension or pressure
what impact does that thinking have
and then on the exhale let go again
if you're thinking what impact does that have on your body
is there any tension or pressure anywhere contraction
does the energies in your body seemingly shift
depending what you're thinking about
and if you notice the influence thinking has on you
in your body and your
feelings mood in the mind itself
is there some way that that influence
encourages more thinking
some way that it has within it
an impetus to think more
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to pick up your thoughts again more actively intentionally
and to think about the people of your lives people in your
communities locally and far away and around the world
into consider
thoughts with of goodwill to have thoughts of well-wishing and
care and appreciation of others
and perhaps after this meditation session
calmly openly generously you can think about other people
with appreciation
with care
and to dedicate these 30 minutes
dedicate the benefits from meditating here to dedicated to the welfare and
happiness of others may any ways that you have benefited
that we have benefited spread out from here into the world
to benefit others may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so continuing on this theme of
the karmic and the dharmic streams of our lives
and for most people the primary the one that's primary in their lives
the biggest role is the karmic stream and people don't understand what this is
and so they don't recognize it as such it's just business as usual
but the karmic stream is um i'm what we can experience directly for
ourselves and not the abstract ideas about it or ideas that what happens over lifetimes
and other grand ideas like that but to start becoming sensitive to how
it works moment by moment how it unfolds in our lives and um
and a couple of things about this karmic stream is that it uh is kind of a self-genera
perpetual motion machine it's kind of self-generating uh that um
it's uh it uh it creates the conditions that prompt more of the same
creates the conditions to create to have more karmic activities
and what makes something karmic is that it it
it conditions us it affects us in such a way that there's a continual motion
at one after the other kind of like there's no stop or or if there is stop it's ready to kind of
it's there in the background as an influence to rare up and and effect further
and um and one of the best places to see this uh is in our thinking because then we can
see it operating kind of really moment by moment or really up close
and you see it when uh one way to see it is when kind of then
is when thoughts are like monkeys
where the analogy that's classically used is a monkey is swinging in the
trees and the branches and as soon as it's grabbed one branch it's already moving to grab the next one
and um and so we're up with one thought and already there's a generation of the next one and
moving on to the next and the next and um and uh
and what we think oftentimes if it's karmic as a karmic way of thinking
that karmic way of thinking leaves traces has an effect
it it generates further thinking it generates a
disposition it creates a mood for thinking in the future
that thinking is very seldom just light empty
you know just a a whiff of thought that has no leaves no traces has no influence on us
uh oftentimes in daily life our thoughts do leave these traces leaves this influence on us but we don't
they sometimes are kind of subtle each individual thought but the accumulation of many thoughts over a day over months
can be huge and so it create it can create almost like a
disposition in a person or a mood in a person and sometimes these thoughts
the way that influence on us encourages more thinking another way as we did that exercise a
little while ago about noticing what influence thoughts have on you
um but you could also do it the other way you can say what is the mood
what's the uh the emotion that's present for you
and how's that influencing your thinking it goes both ways it's kind of a cyclical and this is kind of the often
the cycle of birth and death can be seen in these cycles of the birth and death of
thoughts that so when what comes first is it an
emotion or a mood that gives birth to thoughts or as thoughts
give birth to the mood or the emotional state and
and so it can be both and sometimes it's productive to look and see what is the influence that thinking has
on us and other times it's useful to look and see what is the influence of our mood into
the thinking and but if we start seeing this cycle we see
that thinking is not free thinking is not free of any impact there's a way in
which it generates the very mood which prompts more thinking or generates the kind of
physical tension that prompts more thinking and there's an analogy i like using
occasionally and maybe you've heard of if you take a a
tube of toothpaste and you keep squeezing it the paste will keep coming out and even
if you want to stop it coming out and you keep wiping it off the opening the wiping the paste away it
keeps coming out and and what you have to do is you have to stop squeezing
and then it might stop and so sometimes our thoughts are that way that if we're squeezing if there's
tension and tightness and pressure within us we can let go of thoughts forever but
the pressure to think will just generate more thoughts more thoughts
and so what creates that pressure it might be there was a thought a certain way of thinking
that uh frightened us and so that there's tension in the body from that fear or that anxiety
and that anxiety then gives birth to more so the um there's also positive karma
good karma beautiful karma that could be great and that is to um
if we have beautiful thoughts we have thoughts of generosity of love of appreciation of other people
if we have thoughts of wisdom and then
those thoughts have a different kind of impact on our body on our on our emotional life
and so to um and so sometimes you can feel
the impact that how it what's left behind and um sometimes it you know it has to be quite
strong the impact to really feel it if you're not really subtle and tuned in carefully
um if uh and sometimes it's really clear that the leftovers stay with us
if um you know if we really have a strong bout of resentment and um and the jaw clenches
and so there that clenching of the jaw is the influence that thinking has on us
if um uh i've had i've i've um
and sometimes i've had uh beautiful wonderful thoughts of appreciation of other people
and the love for them and i felt this warmth that kind of begins kind of traveling through me
that began with those thinking and imagining the people that i love and feeling the warmth that goes on here
and anyway so the good ones as well again both of them
and now one of the qualities of karma both good karma and uh
and so-called bad karma difficult karma this momentum is that um
there's there's there keeps being this momentum keeps being this kind of uh
uh something is operating that's pushing us along karma is kind of a
a momentum that keeps reappearing keeps reoccurring keeps surfacing in us
and uh and if that karmic stream is strong or if our thinking is strong and active and a lot of pressure to think
then um uh it limits the operation of the dharm extreme this
other whole side of who we are and so um and so to even even to have beautiful
karma and good karma operating kind of is a is operating a little bit
it's kind of filling the space that if we can create more space
then there's a whole other way that operates that um uh it comes from something i'd like to call it shire
inside of us something that's quiet or something that's easily eclipsed and this is the the the upwelling
of of our native goodness or upwelling of
the unfolding of the dharma within us and a lot of this has to do with um
you know there's a little bit you know this language of inner goodness and eight goodness is kind of you know some people raise their eyebrows around that
or this idea but uh it uh the karmic stream
that the dharma extreme has to do a lot what what gets left over when we stop
the karmic stream when it pauses the karma stream is little bit like sisyphus
pushing a boulder up the street up the mountain and it goes up and up and up and always
rolling it up the mountain and now the what the what the boulder wants to do is roll down to the bottom
and so when he gets it to the top it rolls down he has to push it up again and um and uh
so the karma stream is kind of the pushing of our boulders pushing over our desires our wants our concerns our
wishes uh moving ahead doing things with the mind the wanting mind that
desirous mind the a verse of mind and all these kinds of the things that are carrying the
thinking along uh and even even even uh the subtle or desires of love and generosity are
carrying it along and and so it creates a kind of
it's a work for the mind karma the karmic mind is always working
it's always constructing and so when the when the karmic uh work the
constructing mind stops and there's space for something else to happen
there starts to be an unwinding the boulder rolls downhill the tensions in the mind the tensions in
the body begin to dissolve and when all these tensions
are dissolved it allows for something else to arise and one of the things that can arise
is a great delight and joy at this relaxing at this kind of having
breathing room again having a sense of like space and allowing a deeper feeling
a felt sense connection to ourselves a discovery of kind of a feeling of wholeness that's very hard to
feel when karma is operating because it tends to karma always limits the buddhist
languages karma karma creates definition and limits to who we are what's going on
that doesn't allow us to see things as being whole and as we relax those limitations and
the feeling of wholeness feeling of freedom feeling of ease begins happening
and then the quality of the thinking changes and now sometimes thinking has a quality
of being more spontaneous in a certain way wiser
more intelligent thinking has a way of feeling that uh it's light
and it doesn't leave traces it doesn't it's not a self-genera
generation it's not like monkeys one after the other a thought arises and it's there
and and it's easy and light and um interesting
but it doesn't there's no pressure associated with it and
and uh the mind has a greater capacity for creativity and
wisdom and even things like kindness and love um but not the one that is grabbing from
one thing to the other so
um so this is my attempt to try to kind of
point you to some newer understanding of how the mind might work and how karma and
dharma might work and perhaps i don't have it exactly right for you and
but i'm hoping it's well enough that you can now investigate for yourself that you do the exercise the exploration
for yourself and see how what what is what is gil talking about here and what are these two streams
do you know anything about these two streams can you recognize something that's this self-j generating perpetual motion
machines of thoughts that are pushing and wanting and building and creating
and and this stream where that arises without desire without
pushing and pressure but as um his uh delightful
expression of freedom so um
thank you and um i look forward to continuing tomorrow