so a really warm welcome
really warm welcome
it's quite something to be practicing
together i know i'm i'm actually in this
room by myself
but and perhaps you're in your room by
yourself too
but somehow we're practicing together
with the wonders of technology
so tonight i want to talk a little bit
about
these five strengths
five strengths and i'll start with
the story that comes from the suit and
the mahaparinibana suta
that is it's the suta that describes
the last few months of the buddha's life
and it's quite remarkable that the
buddha knows
when he's going to die and he proclaims
i'm going to die in three months
and then after he makes this
announcement he tells ananda his
attendant
to go assemble all the monks that are
nearby
all his followers and then the buddha
addresses them
and these aren't the last word he says
before he dies but um it's nearly
and he says those matters which i have
discovered and proclaimed
should be thoroughly learned by you
practiced developed and cultivated so
that this spiritual practice may endure
for a long time and be for the benefit
and happiness of the multitudes so he's
describing that what they have learned
what their practices
have been he wants this
his teachings to be
passed down through the generations to
endure for a long time
so they should practice them it's not
just so much memorizing all the
teachings but to
practice them
and then he says and what are those
matters
he says you know those matters which
i've discovered and proclaimed
and what are those matters and here he
summarizes his teachings
and he summarizes it in this way the
four foundations of mindfulness
the four right efforts the four basis of
success
the five faculties the five strengths
the seven factors of awakening and the
noble
eightfold path so it's a list
of lists and some people know this
as the 37 if you count up all those
different elements
there's 37 37 wings to awakening 37
aids to awakening sometimes also called
the seven
sets there's uh seven elements in this
in this list of lists and of course
there's a total of thirty seven things
so the
bori pakia de ma these
uh aids to awakening
so in that list there might be a few
things that you're not familiar with
foundations of mindfulness for right
efforts
five faculties seven factors of
awakening a noble eightfold path
plenty of dharma talks about these and
in the drama books
and certainly sprinkled throughout the
sutas but there's two that totally not
quite as well known one is the four
bases of success the
idi pada i'm not going to talk about
those this evening
i'll just say and a little aside those
are
really really difficult to translate and
to understand and even the commentaries
they're kind of like
there's such a different
interpretations of them and
it's not entirely certain that they
offer anything unique so that's often
why
teachers and scholars haven't really
fleshed those out and then the second
item in these
seven sets the five strengths
sometimes called the five powers
what are these
these are defined as the same
as the five faculties
that is faith energy mindfulness
concentration and wisdom
this list of five
i've given a number of dharma talks on
these and
um the first talk that i gave
was talking about when you cultivate
these five faculties you
slant slope and incline to nibbana in
the same way that the
ganges rivers slants slopes
and inclines towards the east
so kind of has this sense of
inevitability if you cultivate this and
it leads towards awakening
i gave a talk on like heedfulness
is or diligence is another way we might
understand it
is a key part in how to cultivate these
and one way we might understand this
list of the five faculties
and the five strengths
that begins with faith and ends with
wisdom
one way we might understand it it's the
progression of going from faith to
wisdom
passing through energy mindfulness and
concentration so using those as
tools to go from faith to wisdom
and i gave a talk on the importance of
balancing these different faculties
and in particular we can balance energy
and concentration this gusto we might
have or striving that we might have
has to be balanced with concentration
sometimes energy can be up and
concentration
can be down and is there a way that we
can have them work together
and then i gave a talk on the importance
of balancing faith and wisdom
not to be too much letting wisdom
slide into just knowledge accumulation
of knowledge
or faith lead to some dogmatism or
constriction and of course this
recognition that mindfulness
is the one that helps us to balance
energy and concentration
and faith and wisdom so now this is my
fifth
talk and this introducing this idea of
the
five strengths
of those seven sets that i introduced in
them
and then when the buddha is he's
summarizing his teachings
the five strengths the five powers are
mentioned
the least often
and for the most part they seem like
they're the same as the faculties so
why would what purpose do they serve and
perhaps it's why we don't hear about
them in
dharma talks and in dharma books
but here's a suta
that talks about what is the difference
between a faculty and a strength
and in the suta the buddha gives a
simile
of a river and he says suppose that
there's a river
and i'm paraphrasing now suppose there's
a river
and there's an island that's in the
middle of the river
and if you look one way you can see okay
the river splits and on one side
is part of the river and on the other
side of the island is another part
and then downstream they come back
together so you can see
where in this way if you look this way
this like maybe straight onto the island
you can see there's two streams of water
but if you look upstream
before where the island is you can see
there's one stream of water
so in the same way we can look at the
as these as these qualities
faith energy mindfulness concentration
as wisdom
as faculties or see them as strengths
depending on the way we look
depending on the perspective we take
for like are we looking straight on at
the island or are we looking upstream
or maybe even downstream for that way
so if we look at them as faculties we
can consider them
as something that needs to be developed
and cultivated
and certainly there's a lot of
talk or a lot of the teachings really
support this idea
that these are capacities that we have
but they can be
cultivated and developed in which they
might be
more perfected or come to fruition
or allowing them to blossom
show up in different ways so the
emphasis
is more on there's more to be done
they should be developed and cultivated
in contrast the strengths
or can we appreciate
what's already here what we've
already done and from this
standpoint from this frame of reference
we might be able to recognize that
because we have some faith
it's able to withstand its opposite that
is distrust
because we have energy
it's able to withstand some of its
opposite that is laziness
because we have mindfulness it's able to
withstand
some of its opposite that is
heedlessness
and because we have some degree of
concentration
we're able to withstand or over not to
be overcome by
some of its opposite that is distraction
and because we have some degree of
wisdom we're able to
not be overcome by confusion
it doesn't mean that distrust or
laziness
or heedlessness or distraction or
confusion never happen
it's just more the stance that we take
that is appreciating what is here
qualities that we already have
and what function they may be serving
how they might
be supporting us so often we
tend to be dismissive or ignore
those things that are cultivated and
developed and we tend to focus on
what we need what we should be doing or
what's not quite right
but what the buddha is pointing to here
is that these same qualities can be
viewed in different ways
something to be developed and not my
language
or something to be appreciated
and of course this brings to mind the
quote by
suzuki roshi which goes something like i
don't know what it is exactly
but the quote is you're perfect
just the way you are and
you could use a little improvement
from one perspective you're perfect
there's this
beauty and grace and perfection that we
all have
and not but and
maybe we could use a little improvement
so can we
hold both of these in our minds
can we appreciate both of these
sometimes it's very difficult because as
humans we have this negativity bias
we have this
and we have this um this word just
escaping me right now we have this
inclination
to look at what's wrong what needs to be
fixed and
of course we do of course we do i need
to coffee just
here just a moment here
yeah i just had a tickle in my throat
i'm not sick i just
had a little tickle in my throat
so we might have this inclination of
looking
at what needs to be better or somehow or
fixed or something like this
or we might be just
naturally or haven't have an inclination
where we tend to
notice that the glass is half empty or
we might notice that the glass is half
full we
i don't even know if it's really
possible to have a completely
neutral lens a neutral perspective
from that simple simile of what the
buddha taught
we're looking at the river one way and
we could see where it's split
and we can see the two streams of water
we look at it in another perspective and
we can see
where it's one stream of water but we're
always have one
at a perspective we can't see the stream
without
having a perspective
so we have a tendency to
when we have a tendency to lock onto
what's not quite right what needs to be
fixed what needs to be cultivated and
developed
sometimes we might use these types of
words as a
way to beat ourselves up a little bit
don't get me wrong i don't want us to
give let us all off the hook there are
things to be cultivated and developed
but can we notice that there's more
than just that there are things that
are that qualities that we already have
and that we can shift our perspective
and to see both to see the beauty and
perfection and to see
some work that night that might need to
be done
some room for improvement so to speak
often what happens if we have the
inclination to see
problems that's just the way that we
view the world is like just
one thing after another you know that
has to be fixed
then there might be a way in which we
are
seeing a perspective in which we might
be taking
which kind of uh increases the
problemness
so to speak of the experience
that is that if we see something that's
not quite right
there might be a sense of self that gets
reified that gets constricted that gets
solidified and
i have to be the one that fixes that
thing or
i have to fix this about myself or or
that person has to fix this thing and
there's kind of a way in which there's
this clumping or this narrowing down
around the sense of self either myself
or
some other self blaming them or blaming
ourselves
blame is a way in which we really often
can solidify
things to become kind of rigid in our
views
of ourselves or of others it's kind of
innocent
we're not meaning to harm anybody but
there's a way in which if we're
inclined to notice the way in which
things are problems
that goes along with kind of the
solidification
of a sense of self or a blame even
though it might be
kind of subtle and then
there might might be making more problem
than is needed for example
if we don't have the solidification
around a sense of self
then there might be more of an
opportunity to consider well what are
all the conditions that came together
that caused this event this experience
this happening
maybe i find myself
eating mindlessly cookie after cookie
after cookie
one way might be to view this or to
experience this
is to really kind of blame myself
diana you're always eating cookies
what's wrong with you you know it's not
good for you and there's kind of when
are you gonna
stop doing that you sh you know better
and you know there's a kind of this
blame that happens and it's all about
diana
and her not doing well around the
cookies
but there could also be there's a
certain relaxation around this idea that
there's a problem
there could be this recognition of well
okay you didn't have a
a proper lunch and you're feeling
tired didn't sleep well last night and
the cookies are right here on the
counter
and you're a little bit nervous about
what's going to happen
next so of course you ate the cookies
right so kind of pulling together some
of the conditions
so that we can see what's happening as
opposed to
like making a rigid sense of self
so in the same way can we appreciate
some of the qualities that we
have some of the strengths that we have
without having to make a strong sense of
self around it
and without having to only focus on the
problems
to be a not a glass half empty or
a glass half full but in order to have
the flexibility to see
yeah i can look at it this way it's half
empty and
there's a person or a self that's to
blame
i could look at it this other way that's
maybe a little bit delusional
and doesn't see that there's anything
that's a problem
maybe doesn't even pay attention but can
there be a third way
that can appreciate that the conditions
are coming together and
maybe there's a way in which there are
some of these qualities these faculties
that are
beautiful and are supporting and
maybe there's a little bit development
that can be done
you're perfect just the way you are and
you could use a little improvement
so this idea of this negativity bias of
course we have this you know
evolutionarily we
um are the
uh ancestor we are our ancestors
if they didn't take care of things that
were life-threatening of course then
they wouldn't have
passed their genes onto the next
generations and we wouldn't
have inherited them so of course there's
this
human tendency but
it's um i appreciate very much what rick
hansen says
about this idea about the negativity
bias that he
says that uh positive experiences or
maybe even appreciating ourselves a
little bit like
teflon it's actually difficult to do
the ways we've been socialized in a
little bit of our biology
so this idea of the strengths these five
strengths
faith energy mindfulness concentration
and wisdom
to appreciate when they are there
and to recognize that they might be
counteracting some of their opposites
that they are counteracting some of
their opposites
it takes a little bit effort so rick
hansen says that positive experiences
like teflon
they can just be wiped away
in contrast unpleasant negative
experiences are like velcro
we tend to stick to them and the mind
likes to ruminate and go over them
and this is often where kind of the
blame comes in
kind of like i can't believe he said
that i can't believe she
said that i can't believe they said that
i can't believe i said this
so something along those lines a way
in which there's
we can get sticky and can get stuck on
there and
find ourselves maybe going around and
around
so is there a way that we can recognize
when this is happening
and to allow both to be there allowed
this
to see the flexibly with it in a
flexible way
both up the river so to speak and
straight on
when there's an island
so one way to view the
these 37 aids to awakening this seven
sets is that they're in numerical order
a couple of sets of four a couple of
sets of five one group of seven
and one group of eight
another way and to view it
is um as the path
that is it starts with mindfulness
and goes through effort and then these
bases of success which
are can be related to concentration
and then the faculties and the strengths
the seven factors of awakening and then
the eightfold path
so if we view it as a pattern as a
progression starting with mindfulness
and ending with the eightfold path and
maybe i'll say a little thing here is
the noble eightfold path
which also can be translated as the
eightfold path of the noble ones
and there's is a valid way we might
interpret that as
the noble eightfold path is just the
expression
of what it awakened people
do how they are in the world
so if we use that model of the 37
aids to awakening then the
strengths come after the faculties in
that list
that is it's after there's a certain
amount of
cultivation development of the faculties
then the strengths
come on board and are as a support and
are really flowering and blossoming and
leading to the
factors of awakening
so what isn't about
the faculties leading into this
strengths
maybe it's when faith in our own
capacity
and in this path of practice
is really strong faith is one of these
elements that is not in any the other of
these seven
sets we see
energy mindfulness concentration and
wisdom and some of the other sets but
faith is the one that's unique
maybe when we use that as a strength
it's a way in that it really can support
our awakening
so our inner critics may sometimes
rise up and say we shouldn't think about
our strengths
we should really just be working on what
needs to be developed and cultivated and
have to do better or strive do more
but i think that the buddha is pointing
to here
that the strengths we to recognize what
we
already have capacities that we already
have
and how they may be operating in our
lives is a support
for awakening as a support towards
finding greater ease greater freedom
greater peace and not just for ourselves
for others so that we can be a support
for others
so may you find
an opportunity to notice that we can
be flexible in our view we don't always
have to be
focusing on what needs to be done what
isn't quite right
we can also notice and appreciate what
is working
what is doing okay so that we might help
others
so might you have an opportunity to
exercise to use this flexibility of you
this flexible view
thank you