i want to tell a little story
there was once a family who went for a vacation to
another country turned out to be a buddhist country and they were there for a couple of
weeks and there was a teenager who in the family and she
noticed that their vacation spot was right close to a buddhist monastery
so the first week she kind of just noticed and you noticed it was particularly calm and peaceful place
that strucker is unique the second week she decided to kind of
venture in and see what's going on in there and uh fortunate for her she met the
abbess pretty soon as he came in and they struck up a friendship and
then they he went back to see the abbess every day and abbas taught her a little bit about meditation
but that wakes up quickly and she was going to go back to her home country which was not a buddhist country
and she'd never heard of meditation before so she asked the abbess you know when i
go back to my country how can i
you know how can i continue this and learn more what this meditation is all about
and this was of course before youtube so so uh
and all that so so uh the app is said oh and you go back to your country
ask around for different people who are you know you're wise people you think are wise
and ask them if they can point you to the first someone they think is
wise a wise person who really knows how to listen
and then learn how to listen from that person and that was the instructions that was
the alternative to meditation learn how to listen and this idea of listening
uh is something that's very uh it keeps repeated in many religious traditions as
kind of representation of the kind of attention that
we bring in this kind of life of ours of practice and it's represented i think in my mind
that by the idea that the direct disciples of the buddha
in the holy word is sabaka which means the people who heard the
hearers and to be able to hear and there's something about
having the ability to hear the dharma literally by hearing it back in the old
days there was no books there was no audio dharma there was um
and so it was only her dharmas only could only be heard in someone talking about it
but not just hearing the dharma as a spoken but to hear the dharma in everything to
hear it in the breeze that goes and the rustling of the trees or in the hum of the air purifier or
something to he what is it to hear the dharma so i wanted to read
a little poem that
a verse that is by one of the early buddhist nuns named uttama
and it's slightly abbreviated i took out some of the technical terms that would maybe not mean anything for anyone
or most people not attaining mental peace
and with no control of my mind i approached a nun
who was trustworthy she taught me the dharma
i listened to the dharma as she instructed me
i listened to the dharma as she instructed me for one week i sat cross-legged in one
spot filled with joy and happiness
on the eighth day i straightened out my legs and shattered
the mass of darkness she woke up
so the turning point from her distress was hearing
listening to the dharma as it's being taught and
so listening how do we listen why is listening so important
the when i think about listening i think about
listening both externally but also listening internally and the importance of that is that i use
this metaphor this idea that the world that we can perceive
around us is kind of infinite it's like you know it spreads out wide
and big this world of ours and if you stand on top of a mountain and
look out across the world it's you see the vastness of it you know how big it is maybe and there's so much to perceive
but if you look inward to yourself is actually equally vast and big
and uh it turns out this little human body that we have um is when you but you when you kind of
bring the inner eye to see or the inner ear to really listen to what's here it
can feel just as vast it's as buried and multitude multifaceted as
the external world and listening sits right at the junction
between this external world this internal world and
and you can listen both externally and internally but the place standing there at that
junction and where the listening happens either way it's not like a
straight pure separation to an internal and external world the internal world that we have
is it influences how we listen to the external world how the external world is with us and
our experience with it influences how we experience the internal world and to and to be centered in the
listening um and really attend and be open to what's
there sooner or later you'll be start your different times your attention will
sometimes go more to the external world but sometimes goes more to the internal world
to the point where some point we realize that the two are not so separate from each other we're not not
not distinct from each other that how we are in the internal life
affects how we listen to the external world our listening our perception of the
world is seldom innocent seldom just pure and simple and
we're just seeing things just as they are but often we're listening or perceiving
for certain things we have our agendas our concerns our bias that we
bring along in how we perceive the world how what we
listen for so to stay with the idea of listening
some people are might be primed to listen to the tone of other people's voices
because a tone tells them whether they're safe or not and so they're that's what they're listening for that's what they pick up
and what other people never occurred to them that for some reason they that that's not an
issue for them and uh and so they're listening not for the tone of the voice
but they're maybe listening but what are they saying that
reflects back on me i hope they're saying good things to me and they're speaking to me in a way that they recognize my wonderfulness and greatness
and and if they don't let me tell them about it and uh and other people are listening
for how that how because they have maybe a lifetime history of this
of how they're going to be disrespected or ignored or not seen or not understood or overlooked or
diminished or some place of their value and so they're primed to listen to that listen for that
so so we we perceive different things for different purposes
if you're walking down the street and you need to buy a pillow
you'll notice pillow stores or you know but if what you're hungry
you might be looking for a grocery store and yes that's what you notice
or you know so that we kind of sometimes have we look according to what we want
what we're interested in what our history is what our associations are
certain sounds certain voices certain something we have histories of
of that and so if you know if you lived in a foreign country and had wonderful experiences with people speaking that
language and you hear people you know down there walking down the street speaking that language like ah oh yeah that's so good
and our history of that language influences how we hear and the impact it
has but if it was a difficult uh experiences with that
that language maybe if you were in a war zone and it's traumatic to hear that
language around then it can re-trigger some of those fears and concerns and pain
and uh in the listening so as we as we go into this more and more deeply in this practice
we start seeing that listening we stand at the junction of listening to the external world and the
internal world we start seeing the two aren't so absolutely separate
and that's where we begin seeing the dharma experiencing finding the dharma
not because someone's teaching the dharma but how we can find the dharma in every place we go every experience we
have because that's where we can see are we clinging
are we resisting what are we bringing with us what what are we adding to the situation
and some of we're adding might be appropriate and wonderful some of it might actually
be harming ourselves and other people some of it might not be particularly
harming in the way we think about harming but it's a kind of a wind drag it's kind of a
it kind of uh like you know interferes with our freedom or
our ease and peace so something is so kind of pretty subtle
maybe and um i've noticed in my mostly i see this in my meditation these
last few weeks is something i've become kind of more acutely aware of than before
is um how much time comes into play uh in my conceptions of the moment and
how it interp penetrates or is kind of there initially kind of unconsciously
it's kind of like oozes in to how i perceive what's going on in the moment
it can be so simple that as i exhale i'm aware that the exhale is going to
come to an end that's time right it's an idea of time a concept of time
and i can see like i can just let go of the just the simple thing of the exhale coming to an end
it's just an exhale n doesn't have to be part of it at all it's as if
it's timeless just the exhale and i could see the little added edition
of time the concept of time that added on top of it some people might feel what made you
what do you mean gil added on type on top of it time is real
we live in time kind of uh yes but i uh but my conception of time is my
addition uh it's just like for example if i'm sitting meditating
and uh and someone says well the roof of the building is real
does that mean i'm supposed to be thinking about the roof all the time roof roof sitting here roof roof roof
roof ruff ruff you know real you know you know you know ideally when you sit
and meditate at imc none of you will think about the roof when you're sitting here
and um except now that i brought it up you'll always think about it when you come
so same thing with time yes the roof exists but you don't have to think about all the time you can time exists you don't have to think
about it and there's so subtle the addition to it and and even something like uh sometimes
i'll relax when i meditate and i see it even there too that i'm a little bit ahead of myself
to the end of the relaxation or to the what's going to how good it's going to be when i am relaxed
just you know it took me a half a second ahead of myself or something but um i am you know living in this extra as
opposed to just feel the relaxation be with it just don't don't have time as if everything
that occurs is here forever kind of or just if this is its moment
and i really be here for it so the same thing so listening it's all these things that come along with
listening all these associations memories meaning agendas
preferences that come along so as we learn to sit back and listen
deeply then we're also learning to listening to ourselves
there's a story of a man who came to a therapist and said you know
my spouse is always angry and it's so difficult to live with my spouse and
i've been trying to deal with this for years but i think i need some help here from a therapist
and the therapist said well have you ever tried listening to your spouse well no
well go go home and listen so the person did and came back the next week
to the therapist and said i've been listening but it doesn't change anything okay i'm glad you've been listening now
go back and listen to what's behind the words your spouse
speaks where are those words coming from so the person went back and spent
another week listening and listening what was behind the words and came back to the therapist and said
oh this made all the difference in the world there's peace at home now because
i realized that when my spouse was angry for me i had to you know i felt attacked
and my you know i kind of assumed i had to attack back and i had to have a fight i had to protect myself
but i listened to what was behind the words i realized my spouse was afraid
and when i realized the fear was there and i asked if we could talk about it
that just changed everything and there was no more any fights in the home and we had a whole different
conversation so to listen deeply to ourselves that way
what's behind our words so many of us live in conversations
live in memories live in projected futures and concepts and ideas
what happens if we listen to ourselves deeply and uh and in doing so
maybe hear what's behind the words if we're some people are phenomenally
you know in the world of thinking and stories and imagery
it's a fine story sometimes a fine world sometimes to be in but what happens if you listen to what
makes you think and listen to that what do you find and what happens to
you know if you listen deeply there to what what makes you think what makes
you your impulse to be and once you're there
and discover that i bet also then you'll learn to listen to others in new ways
because what was making you spend a lot of time thinking
probably is influencing how you were listening as well certain subtle agendas or concerns
but so this idea of settling back and listening deeply deeply
and you know i grew up speaking norwegian
and there's a word in it just like in english there's a word for hearing and a word for listening
and listening the word is but if there's a academic norwegian
dictionary academics
dictionary that has a definition for um for this listen that i really love
it's uh it's um make an effort
and i've never known maybe other dictionaries do this too but part of the definition is in parenthesis
so i don't know why you know but okay so it says make an effort and then it says in parenthesis
and keep quiet [Laughter]
maybe it's apprentices because you're supposed to say it quietly or something so make an effort and and
keep quiet to pick up perceive sound
what a great definition to listen but uh to be quiet
as you listen and the reference point i have for that is listening to a very quiet sound far
in the distance and i think some of us if we try to do that we even close our eyes and get
really quiet and kind of quiet our thinking mind so we can really hear the subtle sound
but uh but what happens is it possible to quiet the inner the chatter
even if it's just for two moments
and uh what happened that's that and that suggests that's a way of beginning to hear the dharma in
everything it's in that quiet we can pick up and experience
better where the stress is where the compulsions are where the preoccupations
are and one of the marvelous things about being quiet for one moment or two moments it doesn't have to be long
is that it could be just long enough to see how difficult it is to be quiet
and and as soon as you start seeing how difficult it is to be quiet that's where the dharma can be found
that's where we see where there's compulsion and clinging and desire and fears operating
and rather than being upset at seeing that in the dharma we kind of celebrate oh i
saw it i see it more clearly than ever before and some people have specialties
specialize it you know being critical about what they see like all good new all cell phonologists bad news
but in the dharma we're training ourselves to kind of learn to appreciate
seeing the compulsions the agendas the fears the angers the greed the desires
that we get caught in we appreciate it not so we can do it better
but so that we could listen to it and listen to what where does it come
from what's even deeper than that and to listen in such a way that the
listening has a lot of space in the room one of the things i love about listening
and i may hopefully there's not a good argument that it's different than this
you can make probably some argument but there's something about listening
that that you're not touching what you're
listening to you're not you're not um interfering in a certain way
it's just you almost i think of listening as making space to allow oneself to hear
and uh and so there's a kind of a peacefulness or non-aggressiveness hopefully in the listening
there might be times when listening is aggressive and maybe even problematic but then
what i'm pointing to is what inspires me about listening is it's kind of like uh this ability to
have perception that doesn't require any kind of interfering
with what's happening it just allows things to be as they are but they're heard
but but but to really know how to do that well
then we have to also hear ourselves listen to ourselves to see where
the extra baggage we bring the extra judgments and values and preoccupations
we have because seldom listening is seldom innocent
but if but to have this sense this is as this clear reference point
of the possibility of listening without interfering
and the reference point for that for me is hearing the difference between listening and
hearing is that listening is uh requires some effort as a norwegian dictionary says
you know make an effort um the uh
uh it's some directedness to listen but to uh to hear
uh uh we can it's uh hearing and listening sometimes is synonymous in the way we speak but
sometimes hearing is doesn't have that directedness
it doesn't have the effort we can hear without having to think about or want to
hear what we want you know a loud car goes by we hear it but initially we're not
planning to hear it choosing to hear it directing ourselves to hear it we just hear it the bird sings and we hear it
and there's something about just hearing and leaving things alone and being able to relax and open just
here that is is a wonderful reference point
for seeing when we can't hear when we do it when we do get involved
and caught up in our thoughts and ideas of what's going on and that's one of the functions
of mindfulness meditation this path of buddhism
is not to kind of fall into some wonderful bliss state a wonderful place
of peace and just kind of like have a kind of enlightened retirement
and i have it made and that's you know if only i could be kind of rest in peace then everything
will be okay the purpose of the dharma is to have just enough peace
so that we can see what takes us away from it and that's
where we see the dharma that's where we hear the dharma and uh
and so when we listen to the trees rustling or the birds or the rivers glowing or the rain
falling
we're not just hearing the rain the leaves rustling we're also if you listen well
we're hearing that there's a mutuality a cooperation in the hearing it's us and our memories
and associations and all kinds of things that come along with the hearing
and this and some if we don't have any attachments and clinging and fears and all these extra kind of
suffering producing things as part of it it gets to be a very rich world
to hear and listen and perceive the natural world around us and the social world around us
it adds a kind of deeper dimensions to it what are we listening to
it's kind of co-created it's kind of like we're it's not just completely
out there is not completely in here but something is happening in the interface and the
connectivity and the ways in which we somehow overlap our lives or
co-create our lives together co-create with the wind blowing in the trees out there
and and what is that what is that world what is that life
a life that's not so maybe so self-centered but it's not
exactly self-forgetting either
so to listen to listen deeply to hear
to allow the
so to be able to hear the dharma not only and when it's dharma's being taught
by someone but to be able to hear the dharma all the time wherever we go
the dharma is available if we've learned how to listen and then we become a disciple of the
buddha a a listener
so let's all listen and remember also to listen to each other
and maybe to listen to what's below the words of what people say so that we can love
in some deeper way what's behind the words and
may listening be a vehicle for care and compassion and love
in this world that we live in so thank you very much
and uh for those of you who are on youtube
we've started now a few weeks ago to have a zoom room that's open
after the talk where jan and barry kind of host it and they do some breakout groups and
just to have a discussion about the talk or about the dharma or get to know each other a little bit
so and i think that the the link is i think it's in the chat
at the very top of the chat and also i think it's going to be posted in a few minutes or moments or is it again now
thank you martha and then also
if it's also on the imc calendar you found the home page of imc there's a calendar
you can find a link there to the zoom room so thank you and
we do have a little bit of time left before the official ending of today does any of you have any comments or
questions that he'd like to make at this point so brian
well thank you that was a wonderful talk and you know a lot of my work has been with listening to the world so it was
very appropriate the problem is that when i listen to my body my body won't stop complaining
it says oh you're finally listening to me your shoulder hurts you're you know
it's uh yeah and also i have really bad tinnitus so whenever i listen i hear the tinnitus so you know there's a lot of
things that that are difficult for me when i actually listen to my body
yes so so that what you're calling the difficulty yeah
that's where you find the dharma okay so i wouldn't shy away from experiencing that
difficulty but for you to discover what what do you mean by difficulty what exactly is happening
because uh a painful shoulder one you know one way of just as a way of
thinking about it it's helpful to think kind of provisionally that a painful shoulder
is just a painful shoulder there's no difficulty
the difficulty is what you're adding so what is that and uh so i would spend
i'd i'd encourage you that you seem to sit well and still uh i would encourage you to uh
in meditation at least spend time being very patient with the physical pain and
listen to it and feel it and discover what you're adding that's extra
and the advantage of that is that once you can find what's extra the resistance the judgments the fears or whatever the
expectation or whatever that extra that um that's very respectful for our body then
you might be able to listen to your body more deeply and then you might be able to discern that there's subtle subtle or not so
subtle shifts you can make in your posture or how to take care of this part of yourself better
also you might discover that the body has self-healing powers and sometimes some of the places of
tension will begin to unravel themselves or soften or open up
or you start discovering that i guess this pain will be forever
but the problem was not the pain the problem was all the tension i added around it
and i can soften the tension that's around it and then it becomes simpler and simpler and it turns out i can be
peaceful i can be at peace with the pain once i've kind of you know settled some of the extra layers
so i don't know if how i worded it is meaningful for you but no maybe that's that's wonderful that's wonderful yeah
take your time a lot of compassion and care the only one thing i would suggest for you
is some basically suggesting you know sit in pain
is uh what i suggest for you is only do it sit with the pain when you feel um
you want to okay this is this is a good exercise it's useful i understand why i'm doing it
i see how i understand really understand this this is a there's a way in which this is beneficial for me
and it's not easy to do but i feel motivated when you no longer feel motivated
or feel or understand how it's beneficial probably to take a break you don't have to force yourself to kind
of you know bear through it at all costs so so just be
caring for yourself too that way thank you
thank you dearsonga so in my ten years of practice i've gone
from someone who's unable to listen to being very very can you hold the quote at my oh sorry yes okay so my 10 years
of practice i've gone from not being able to listen to people to listening so deeply
that i've become very reactive so i was wondering if there's
a difference or if there's a passive listening active listening what i do i'd call it reactive listening
great great well i congratulate you for listening deeply that's a review that's a really great thing to learn how to do and chad
said i don't know you well enough but what i suspect is happening is that you've come to a deeper place
inside of you that the what you hear is is uh striking it so what i mean by
this is that if i hold my hand like this and someone comes along like this
uh you know there's resistance it hits something but if my hand relaxes
then this goes right through it doesn't stop and so or if i had like there's lots of
space and things just find their way through so you're probably getting touching something very deep inside of you that
those things are striking and so discover what they're hitting and if you can find out what's going on
what's because it doesn't have to hit anything so what is that that it's hitting
um and uh and then then i think you're probably what's wonderful sensitivity and
capacity to perceive and feel and others might even get more acute but it's just
gonna not land anywhere it's not gonna hit anything and you'll feel more porous
and you won't be unfeeling if you do that but you'll actually be more more capable of holding what's going on
thank you that makes a lot of sense yes because i have ptsd so yeah
one of the things we're trying to do in this practice i would say suggest and i think
listening is again a nice metaphor for this is we're uh we're expanding our capacity to hold
life experience so rather than necessarily solving the problems or fixing things that happen
we're making more room in the mind the heart the body to be able to hold things
and to be present for things as they are and so sometimes we were so preoccupied
with ourselves with our concerns our life that there's very little room and then if there's very little room in
there then sometimes i feel like i have to change the world so that everything can be okay
and the other people have to behave better so that can be okay but as we learn to open up the ears to
listen and there's that turns out there's lots of room and hearing to hear all kinds of things without
being reactive to it there's lots of rooms in the heart amazingly lots of room in our love
that can just be really spacious and it isn't it doesn't
forgive people for what they say sometimes it's like you know everything is good but
we don't have to then it doesn't have to we have to react to it because we have
so much space so thinking of meditation as increasing our capacity
is i think a useful orientation
so any last last one anything else anyone wants to
well thank you all for coming and and uh
i hope that uh you'll come back soon and stay stay uh
we'll probably make soon uh maybe in a few days um an update for the registration and
things for how we do it here at imc and what we're opening for
so uh you know i think all of you have registered so um therefore you'll get an email
within you know with the updates for november probably will open a little bit more at imc and
we might change a little bit how we do this sunday morning and and uh
so so that information will be you know will come through those emails people who are registered
and the reason we do it that way is we don't want to make it too public when we're open because that's a little bit
of a challenge for for the managers if people who show up
without having been that we know that they're uh you'd have been vaccinated
and also we want to try to keep the numbers at a proper number and we might slowly increase the number
but uh but when i keep on i keep keeping to keep tabs on that so we don't want to
have people wandering in so it's through getting being registered and getting that emit that email that
you find out what's actually happening so thank you all very much