hello and welcome and we're here to
do something relatively simple
to sit quietly
being attentive to our present moment experience
to make it a little bit more complicated we do it through our
direct capacities for attention capacities for
direct awareness through the senses of our body through our body
aware of the present moment through our body
where the present moment through our capacity to kind of
mentally observe or perceive what's happening in the present moment
the simple mental perceiving that's prior to stories prior to
interpretations prior to commentary judgments
staying close to this place of direct experience
immediate experience being simple enough to be there
and the part of the fruit of practice is to begin appreciating
this simplicity of being simplicity of attention settling into it
enough that we realize that some of the alternative ways of being
are less beneficial are less
satisfying that to get swept up in stories swept up in
analysis commentary judgments swept up into the future in the past
becomes less satisfying than the simplicity of being here
so it's not a matter of convincing anyone that it's valuable to be
here in a very simple direct way but rather for each of us to discover
that for ourselves by having enough connection to this present moment
that we notice we see we recognize
that the alternatives are not as satisfying maybe not even not as beneficial
not as peaceful happy
or not as insightful not giving us clear perception of what's happening
so you might consider this today that we're sitting here
to be to have a very simple presence to rest in a simple attention
just enough don't be does not be dramatic just enough to recognize
that when we lose it it's less satisfying
it's alienating we lose touch with ourselves we get into fantasy
we get into ideas of what is right and wrong and what should be happening and
we give rain to our anxieties our fears our desires
in a way that is not they might be pleasant some of things we think about
and do but pleasure is not the same as a deep abiding satisfaction
as if we're really at home in this universe and this at home in ourselves at ease
to be reassured with just being present here
that buddhist word for reassurance is the same as to breathe easily
to be able to breathe easily here and now
so to assume a meditation posture
that will support you in this simple present simple attention to hear
and to relax your gaze
you're looking at the screen then perhaps drop your eyes
downwards so you may be you're not gazing at it
and soften your gaze
and then maybe even close your eyes
and everything we need to discover the dharma for ourselves
is here
in the in your body your heart your mind
not to be figured out but to be revealed as
your attention gets simpler and simpler just here
so to enter this world where the dharma is found you can take a few long slow deep
breaths as if you're choosing to embody
your body
as if you're planting yourself here in the soil
of your physical experience
then letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale to relax your face
softening around the eyes
the jaw it might be helpful to let your lips
fall slightly open
and as you exhale to soften relax the shoulders
release the shoulders to the gentle pull of gravity
as you exhale softening in the heart
many times our desires and fears
take us out of our hearts
and to relax and soften back into the heart
and to soften the belly
to spend a lot of time with the belly tight and contracted
is often a symptom of not being present
but being concerned about other things
and then breathing normally with the exhale
appreciate the exhale the release the relaxing
the movements tingling as you exhale
maybe as the end of the exhale you can release relax
so that you exhale a little bit longer
without effort just relaxing
and as you inhale
appreciating the inhale
and if it seems appropriate for you to center yourself in the body's experience of breathing
simplicity of attention with the breathing not ambitious
not trying to do a lot or attain anything as you sit here
except appreciating the simplicity of attention
here to the breathing [Music] to your body
to the present moment
and if anything takes you away from that maybe
there's a way of seeing it that you understand that it's less
satisfying than settling into a simplicity of being
where you have a chance to breathe easily
be at ease in a deeper way
just here in the simplicity of the present moment
as we come to the end of this sitting
if you have some appreciation for
some simple way of being present here and now for your experience for yourself
and how that might be better than the alternatives that your mind might
where your mind might take you
chances are that that alternative that is not as satisfying for you
might not be so satisfying for others as well
that maybe there's something about being at ease
assured confident settled in the
simplicity of our being
that is a gift for the other for others maybe it's a
way of helping others to be at ease around us
maybe it's a way for us to be more attentive to others in a simple direct
way maybe it's easier for us to access
our care our love our kindness good will
maybe it's easier for us to experience the suffering of the world
without being swept up in some of the alternative ways of thinking and feeling
they're not so useful for us or for the world
and so as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps there's something about how you are
having sat for these minutes
that can be your gift so you live this day or the next day
a little bit more inclined to contribute to the welfare and happiness of others
and may it be that growing out of our simplicity of being
that we live so that all beings may be happy
all beings may be safe all beings
may be peaceful and so that all beings
may be free
so today is the fifth talk on patience
and um in offering and today's topic is um
the patient acceptance of truth
or the acceptance maybe it means the basic the willingness or the openness
to stay close to the truth so patient acceptance of the truth
when i began this series i
introduced it by saying that i wanted to try to have the reference point for patients for this discussion
not a directive that just you know from 0 to 60 you should be patient without any
other context but rather that many of you have been meditating for
some time and have been in dharma practice for a long time and so the hope is that it has given you
some reference point for a way of being that is satisfying
that is worthy of staying close to some way of being true to oneself true to life to
and that this meaningful to stay close to and then a recognition that as the mind
the heart departs from that gets involved in other things other reactions desires
attachments addictions aversions resentments hostilities
fantasies fears anxieties
commentary complaining all kinds of things the mind does that
it's less satisfying than what we've tapped into
it's less meaningful it's less true and and so to be patient is not to overlay
patients on top of our experience not to bear down and tighten up and not react
but rather patience is staying true to what we know is valuable is coming
back and staying with it staying close to what we know as valuable
and not giving in to these forces of anger resentment
impatience that that might come along as dharma practice deepens
so does the contact our contact with something that feels truer and truer
our contact with uh deep sense of peace and ease
happiness well-being that can kind of well up from the inside
that's not dependent on the thing experiences in the world not dependent
on on what happens around us with other people not not this doesn't depend on getting a
raise at work or winning the lottery or it doesn't depend on
you know what other people do and but really it seems to well up from the inside out
and it's become something we carry with us a sense of well-being that um
ideally becomes strong enough that we're not buffeted by the experiences around us and we're not
dependent on the world around us to behave in a certain way or not dependent on people to be a certain way
because we carry with us the stability and this well-being
and so as that deepens and deepens uh we become more clearly aware
that what takes us away from it and we become more clearly aware that
this is true here that being less selfish is a true thing
and so the patient's acceptance of these truths of
this deeper well-being this the value and not clinging the value of not being hostile
the value of not being selfish self-centered the value of not clinging and holding on
to things these kinds of things are seen as being true
so in buddhism this kind of truth statement or true is less to do it's not propositional
truth so much but rather the truth of how we respond to and be with whatever is happening in
the world that we don't be with it with clinging or hostility we don't be with it by
overlaying layers and layers of stories and commentaries and reactions and bias
and so the patient's acceptance of truth is difficult sometimes
to stay close to the truth of non-clinging st stay close to the truth of
it's not worth getting involved in ambition
and busyness it's not worth getting so busy trying to save the world
from all possible catastrophes that we're not going to be effective
the so to be to to recognize all kinds of things we recognize that how we are
are not a useful good way of being and to be patient with that a patient acceptance of that
sometimes is the hardest form of patience because what we're working with now is being patients with these inner
impulses we have that that can be quite strong the
conditioning we have the the attachments we have and so to see that our attachments arise
and have the patience acceptance of what's truer so that we don't give in to our attachments
to see that the delusions arise in our mind biases arise in our mind and to see it
with the kind of clarity that they if this is not truth true what's true is not giving in to them
not being caught in them and so and there can be a tug of war it can be kind of like wait a minute uh you know
this is the this is how i've lived my life or this i won't be safe if i don't act this way or react this way
and so this patience acceptance of the truth and this goes deeper and deeper and
sometimes some of the deeper acceptances of truth have to do with
really being beginning to see how changeable how
inconstant how impermanent this world that we have as it is and
and that can be kind of frightening it's kind of like we want some stability we're gonna hold on to something
and so the patient's acceptance of not holding on not clinging in the middle of this world of
impermanence it can seem a little bit frightening but we've learned over time
that uh we you know it doesn't really work to cling it doesn't
really work to hold on tight it doesn't really work to resist
the changing uh nature of this reality we live in it doesn't work to try to keep yourself
young forever and um at some point
uh you know we can't hold on or cling we have to kind of patient's acceptance we're getting older
patients acceptance of these kind of basic human existential truths that we
at some point are put very close to directly to confront and and meet patients acceptance that we're
dying patients acceptance that there will be loss patience acceptance of
um even with loss that it's not worth getting
there's a ways of being that is simply not worth it that the reactivity to that we normally
what maybe we would have and we're being patient so we don't succumb to these ways of being
that we know we've learned are not useful not supportive
so in this way uh what i'm pointing to is that we're learning to become our own
reference point for practice we're learning to recognize in ourselves
uh what is valuable and what's what it's valuable to stay close to
so that when it's time when we need to be patient with ourselves it's because we know something
valuable we know something important and we've experienced it
and we might lose touch with it but our memory still says wait a minute i know that this reactivity i have is not the
way forward i think that at least need to be patient to not give into it
the patient's acceptance of truth is this acceptance that it's not uh is the
truth that this is not worthwhile doing so i'm not going to say what i'm going to want to say i'm not going to do what
i'm feel compulsed to do i'm going to be patient with this
and that occasionally these acts of patience requires a lot of
you know effort um you know say the pull to addictions
can be so strong the pull of desires pull of hostility the pull of things
have to be different and so it's okay to succumb to my anger or something like that
are so strong and one of the ways that one of the very interesting things to do
in being patient and not giving into it is to uh feel the strong compel sit and be
quiet maybe in meditation maybe sit down in the chair and feel the strong compulsions arise
and and that might they might come with a whole army full of lawyers
that tell you you have to act it has to be this way but sit with it all
kind of like a rising wave until the wave has crested and you find yourself in the back of the
wave and and then decide what the wise thing is
to do but when you feel the compulsion to act or to speak it's probably not the best
time to do so because chances with compulsion there is not wisdom and you're not
connected to something that you've learned is a valuable place to talk from or to act from
the valuable place of wisdom from which to participate in this world of ours
so this idea of being patient with compulsions because we know something be truer and we accept that
and so we don't act by the compulsion and then ride the wave until you find yourself on the backside
and in the middle of these compulsions it can feel impossible to wait it feels like it has to be now
but it's just a wave it's just everything has its time
everything has a half-life and will eventually pass away and to become confident in that truth
patience acceptance of the truth that all compulsions will pass
all attachments will pass if we allow them to and so
learning how to be patient and not giving in to them is um
you know is a gift for ourselves and the world
so patience acceptance of the truth so you might consider
today what have you discovered
that is more important that's more true that you want to stay true to
what have you discovered that's true that teaches you what not to do what not
to say what not to react to not as not because you're and you're not
not you're not avoiding reacting that way or speaking that way as repression
but rather because you know the opposite is true that
that you lose yourself in the reactivity that what's most true about yourself is
is not found through that reactivity that can feel so compulsive
what do you know what have you discovered that's true for with by which or for which it's
useful to have patience acceptance and um
so thank you and um one more talk tomorrow on patience