so hello from imc in redwood city california
and you know special greetings to all of you
who are far away from here in different states different countries across oceans it's
kind of special to have this kind of gathering of people from all over
so um there are two
heart qualities that uh go together a little bit like the
two sides of a hand and that is um
generosity and gratitude that when we experience acts of
generosity towards us then sometimes a natural
movement is to feel grateful appreciative and thankful
and when we are generous and sometimes we are then the recipients
of gratitude of thanks appreciation
and it's possible to sit in meditation with gratitude and with generosity
and have that part of the meditation and one of the simple ways of doing that is to
appreciate that when we inhale that we're receiving life
sustaining oxygen without which we wouldn't live and while there's not someone
intentionally giving it to us this planet has been set up in such a way that
we're a constant recipient of life-sustaining
life-sustaining substances that keep us going and alive and conscious and one of those is the air we
breathe in and perhaps in some ways we can think of the carbon dioxide we breathe out
as you know for us it's waste product but for other beings it's like trees and plants it's what they
need in order to grow and develop
and so we heard that we're part of this cycle of giving and receiving and perhaps that can be
also a cycle of gratitude and generosity just in the breath and one of the things
that i like about this is that the breathing is so simple
and so easily easy for most most of the day to kind of many of us to be out of mind not really
noticing it or appreciating it really in meditation we have the chance of
becoming attuned to the simplicity of each breath each inhale in each exhale
each inhale is a miracle each inhale is uh something we can be grateful for
or appreciative and inspired by and each
exhale also as a miracle is a wonderful ways in which we are participating in
this whole natural interconnected interdependent
world of um that we live in and to feel and sense in each breath
gratitude for this breath and even if it's hard to breathe even if the breath is a
little bit of a struggle to be grateful for the body that knows well enough
even is struggling it's finding a way for us to keep us alive this body knows how to do it
knows how to breathe usually and so to to you know be grateful for this body we
have that's keeping us alive that's keeping itself alive
and to have this cycle of gratitude and
generosity and i offer that this i offer this to you today um not as a moral injunction for
gratitude and generosity but uh it's also it's a way of um
of maybe getting more interested in breathing and focus on the simplicity of this it's
so easy to drift off in other thoughts and concerns and preoccupations of all kinds and
but to kind of get gathered together and have you really centered here just in the simplicity of breathing then
some even a deeper gratitude and appreciation a deeper flow of generosity that comes
from a very quiet centered settled heart and body mind and it's kind of then we
really start feeling this miracle of life when things get quiet we're really just just
here no longer thinking about the issues of our life
the concerns of our lives the fantasies of our life so to
with this body that we have body that we are body that is here for
to assume a meditation posture
and for many of you may be a familiar posture and the familiarity of it
is comforting
and gently close your eyes
and to take a few long slow maybe gentle breaths
long and deep so the whole body gets when your inhale gets
stretched and engaged especially the torso rib cages expand
slow because it's calming and settling to do it slow and
it's it's conscious to do it slow and deep
to awaken our ability to be consciously here and now
and gentle so we're not in conflict with anything or struggling or aversive or
desirous just gentle here maybe here in a way that's nurturing
nourishing and then let your breathing return to
normal
and as you exhale to relax the muscles of the face
as you exhale relax the shoulders
and as you exhale softening the belly
taking a minute or so to do soft belly meditation
keeping the belly somewhat soft as you breathe in and breathing out
and then to gently quiet the mind
quiet the thinking maybe you're thinking can even be slower
softer
or there can be a soft and slower way of
holding the thinking mind
perhaps as you exhale you can relax the thinking muscle
the energies and agitation and tightness pressure associated with thinking
and then settling in
to the experience of breathing
where each breath each inhale is a miracle
each exhale is a miracle
and as you inhale perhaps very quietly
a silent quiet gratitude or appreciation
for the gift of this breath this one inhale
and the exhale a simple
release letting go that's generous it's a giving
giving of your ears outwards to the rest of the
world any giving to your body releasing and
relaxing gratitude breathing in
generosity as you breathe out all in the service of the mind
becoming simpler and quieter here just here
breathing in and breathing out
so
hmm
and then as we come to the end of this setting
what might you learn from this sitting what might you learn from meditation in
general about the source of generosity inside of
you
not any requirement to be generous but when there's generosity within you
can you identify a source place within it
or if not a place what's the feeling or the atmosphere inside of you that
most supports the arising of generosity
and also gratitude
in the busyness of life preoccupations of life we ought to easily lose touch with the
source of goodness within us
and in our meditation perhaps we can touch into it some
in such a way that it reorients us to a dedication or inspiration
to live from this source or this way of being
and it helps to give life to this way of being the source
this attitude the subtleness
to in a generous way
based on that generously wish well for others
turn your regard outward into the world and look upon all beings kindly
look upon all beings with wishes that they be well and happy and
peaceful
and to consider how could you today as you go through the day
how could you live to contribute to the welfare and happiness of others
even if it's a smallest thing even it's smiling at someone or
opening the door
and with all the many people here who meditating this morning what a great
impact we can have on the world if all of us
contribute to the welfare and well-being of even just one or two people today
may it be that this meditation that we do that the goodness of it spread from us
out into the world contributing to the world where all
beings can be happy
all beings can be safe
all beings can be peaceful
and all beings can be free
they all beings everywhere be happy
[Music]
so today i'll continue with telling stories that
means birth and so that they are the tales of previous births
they say of the buddha former lifetimes many of them when he was an animal
and um and he so they're kind of like asap
fables fairy tales that uh as many of them have characteristics of kind of fairy tales we tell children
and and sometimes i think these fairy tales um as wonderful as they are for children
uh you know maybe they're really meant for adults because adults can apply them understand the deeper meaning
of them and and um and maybe uh adults have the best chance of
living out of the values of some of these wonderful tales so the tale today is
called the golden goose and it's a very similar to a european tale of the
the i think the goose or the chicken that lays golden eggs and maybe it points to the idea that
some of these uh ancient stories fables um uh were pan-cultural they kind of
maybe traveled and moved through the world and because of
people were inspired by them or they were meaningful so in the buddhist version of this there
was uh two farmers a husband and a wife and their two children
who eked out in existence they worked really hard on their farm and just barely could grow enough to
support themselves themselves and their children and and it was a tough life
on the edge of poverty edge of starvation and at some point and i'm going to
change the gender of the usual stories and i think that some of the
ways ancient stories are gendered are you know it's optional and and i think
some of the fables are probably getting a little bit tired of always being kind of the same stereotypes in the
gender so maybe it's okay to change and so at some point uh the wife
who um started to feel sick and she got progressively sicker and
sicker and at some point it was clear that she wasn't going to survive she was going to die
and she was laying there in bed and she made a resolve that she would come back she'd be reborn in
such a way that she could come back and support her family
and now so she died and the night after she died the children had a dream
and the dream was that their mother came back to see them and said dear ones
soon i'll be coming back in a few months i'll come back and i'll support you make sure that you're
okay and you don't starve but when i come back you won't recognize me but
by what i look like but i'll identify myself for you and you'll know it's me
so the children woke up the next morning and told their father about this wonderful dream and the
father kind of who was already quite heartbroken from the loss of his wife and said oh dreams just make
life more difficult to get disappointed and all that and you shouldn't you so we could forget those kinds of dreams
but the children didn't forget the dreams they um kept the dream alive and but they would
talk among themselves too about their dream and how their mother would come back
and then um many months later um this goose started waddling up the path towards the
farm and goose was quite large and fat and
and was um the head was peculiar and that um its feathers were golden golden
colored and um when the the farmer saw that was
like oh food for our dinner this is finally where i've been hungry now for days and he went out to
capture that goose but the goose kind of knew what was happening and and
ran away into the forest and hidden safety but later in the day the
goose came back out when the farmer when the the was kind of away or cooking or something
and um and came up to the children who were playing outside and said to the children my dear children
i'm your mother and i've come back and i'm here to take care of you and
this way that each day pluck one feather
from me but only one feather and hold the feather up to the sunlight
and it'll turn to solid real gold and you'll have
that gold you can sell and it can support you and take care of you the family so the it's
and then the goose said take you know do it right now and so the the kids plucked one feather and held it
up to the sun and sure enough poof it turned into metallic gold and
and so they ran back to their father who was cooking in the kitchen and said look what we have we have um
this goose came along and and uh told us that you know if we held up its
feather plucked it would turn into gold and we could have that gold and uh but there was a caveat the
goose made sure that we could we were only supposed to pluck one feather a day and so the
the farmer was quite surprised and show me and went out and they saw the goose outside
and and the kids said again but you only pluck one feather
so the next day they went out and they plucked a feather and for sure enough holding up the sun it turned to gold they did it every day and
pretty soon uh they didn't become phenomenally wealthy but they
had enough wealth to live safely and comfortably and it was a good time for them they had no food and clothes and
their welfare was kind of basically taken care of and but in this circumstance at some point
the farmer um felt was getting more more and more comfortable
but there was a discontent you know well there's maybe a fortune to be made here
and get really wealthy from this um this goose what if i pluck
all the feathers out then they'll just have this big fortune and who knows what i can do then and um and
the kid said no no you can't do that just one feather a day and so the farmer waited and thought
about it and thought well you know there's it's dangerous if i just let the goose you know live around here the wolves and
the foxes might come along and and gobble it up and then we'll have no feathers at all
so it's better to harvest all the feathers now and have wealth than it is possibility
of losing it so when the kids were uh were off someplace playing
the farmer went to found the goose and grabbed it and and um pulled out grab
fistfuls of feathers pulled all the feathers off the goose and put them in a basket and then held
the basket up to the sun so they would turn into gold and lo and behold nothing happened
and distraught the farmer then scattered the all the the feathers on the ground so
all of them would somehow get direct sunlight nothing happened and the farmer yelled
out in despair oh no the kids heard and came running over and
they saw what had happened they said oh no mother told us that we only take one
feather from the goose at a time your mother the farmer said no no and
and then the farmer said well you know their feathers will grow back so they waited some days or weeks or a
long feathers did grow back but now they came back came back gray and dull gray
rather than his golden feathers that had been colored feathers but before and if they took a feather out and held
the sun nothing happened and after some time the goose just kind of flew off and never came back and
the story was a complete disaster because from the feathers they already had they did have enough that gathered
enough and so for their basic well-being for the rest of their time so they
continued living that way the kids grew up well enough and continued
but greed here we are we're all of us are the recipient of generosity each of us you know the world in a sense
is like a golden goose and the world the earth
provides us with feathers that we can harvest and take care of and live well
but then we get greedy and afraid of losing it and uh
us human beings gathered all together and what more and more and more and sometimes we have definitely on this
planet for hundreds of years even back in the time of you know two or three thousand years ago
um over-consuming over-farming land and destroying it so that
uh the civilizations that grew there of uh died out because they
uh they uh the land became infertile so there's a tendency of human beings to
overdo it to take too much and more and more and more and then destroy the very thing that is
providing us uh this is happening again today in this world and
that the the drive to consume to have to want to gr to have greed that um
we're not we're not carefully contenting ourselves with the one feather just what's enough to let us live well
and happily but to strive for always more and more and more
and so what is your golden goose what are the feathers that you collect
and and when is it that you
maybe take so much that you take more than is given more than is
sustainable and you maybe even destroy the goose i wonder how many people have gone into
debt that way and and consumed and somehow then can't repay
their debt they're in trouble so
meditation is one of the ways of learning how to abide
in a deep contentment a deep satisfaction a deep sense of well-being
and peace that's not dependent on material goods and wealth and having more and more and
more things but rather it's a way in which to grow in a healthy kind of way more and more
the buddha used the word abundance when you refer to some of these inner qualities that can develop
and perhaps the real gold is the goal that's within and that if we learn how to
connect to the inner gold we'll find out that we have all the gold
we need to have a happy and contented life may your heart be the golden goose
thank you