so each time we sit it's very very helpful to
initiate awareness in a deliberate fashion if
you think about how awareness is usually interwoven
with all the things that come up in the consciousness all the attitudes all the emotions
the concerns and awareness is simply
attending to them and so especially in seated awareness
we we start in a very deliberate fashion it's it's almost like we're gonna give
ourselves a deep reminder of what
the request of awareness is that we're going to
initiate quite deliberately the process that calls forth awareness
you know we we're gonna attend to it with intention
we're going to attend to it with
a deliberate non-attachment to what arises
and along with that we're going to attend to it with a thorough acceptance of whatever arises
it's like we remind ourselves this is not manufacturing what's supposed to happen
it's simply creating a disposition that's available
for what's happening
and as we initiate we invite the positive factors of being
that will support the awareness
and this commitment
establishing this as we begin you know
sometimes called clearly knowing
but not so much unknowing simply as a cognitive process but including that
but more than that we invite
our mental disposition we invite our emotional disposition
we invite how we're holding the body we invite
how we're letting the breath happen
it's a combination of many factors [Music]
we don't really need to know them and list them and then
initiate them we we need to um or what's very helpful for us is to
establish a fertile ground that invites them to arise
and so as we go through the the details
the details of posture the details of breath
the details of open awareness to engage it all very deliberately
it's like reminding something deep within you
that this is a commitment that
is part of who you are it's part of what you are
and we let that commitment do awareness
we let it simply connect [Music]
to what's happening
we let it invite a steadiness
and experiencing of what's happening
rather than being lost in fraud or thinking up what's happening
with the minds in charge and it will have a running commentary
on what's happening you know
can we invite the body and the breath
into a saddledness
that it starts to soften
that disposition of mind that wants to continue its narrative we're not suppressing it we're not
resisting it just inviting the state of being
the deliberateness
and then deliberately inviting awareness of the body
noticing how it is
some part of the body feel creaky creaky or stiff
and then like a body scan
starting with where we make contact with our seat
and becoming aware of the lower back
opening the front of the body
letting the spine lengthened in uprightness and ease
letting the shoulders widen
like we're opening the heart
available to what may arise
and letting the head
well the tin made the chin the back of the neck may lengthen
the head is upright
in feeling the deliberateness of this
body sitting in the midst of everything
that's happening
and letting the breath happen
with each inhale and the tension that's inviting
maybe even in encouraging the chest the stomach the abdomen to
soften and open and receive the breath
and allowing a pause between inhale and exhale
and as we breathe out
the quality of releasing
and as we tune into this rhythm of breath
can it be deliberate can it be steady in a way
that there's presence at the start of each inhale
present in the pause presence in the exhale
presence in the pause
it's not an imposition
it's not an assertion of control
it's the simple act of sustaining awareness of breath
and actually sustained awareness
inviting the clearing
it notices what arises
notices when the attention stays in the body and
the breath
notices when it gets caught up
in thinking or feeling or some combination of
thoughts and feelings
whatever happens
it's our being's effort it's our humanness expressing it's
aliveness
it cannot deliberate attention
can it can it offer a kind of
reassurance
good awareness is the close ally of being alive
it deeply nurtures
that cellular impulse to live
it understands the impulse to think and feel
and let the mind get caught up inside
can you quite deliberately return to the steadiness
of allowing inhale and pausing
and releasing on the exhale
[Music]
and if the thoughts are constructing a reality
just notice and acknowledge
then that awareness
returning to the senses
physicality sensation of breathe
and even if the thinking is tending to draw being
up into the head
can the deliberateness of breathing
invite it back down into the body
so
[Music]
oh
there you are
um
so this deliberateness of being
it it finds its expression
in our body often
it has a kind of a centering feeling to it
sometimes we call it keeping us grounded you know
and then the very process of staying aware of the breath and keeping the breath soft and deep
helps the breath to become an ally in in how we're noticing
oh is that deliberateness and centeredness and the kind of
authority or trust that it has is that staying present
or is the body tightening in some way
either through fear aggression desire all sorts of ways
and the core teaching is that these are not something that we're doing wrong
these are not uh qualities of being that need to be suppressed or eradicated
it's more to come into a deep understanding of what it is to be human
that these are human tendencies and that each of us has our own version
of them
that when they fall into a reactive mode
they make our life mysterious and difficult when we go into reaction
we don't quite know what caused this reactiveness
and we don't quite know what it is to be reactive it's just a surge of energy
it has all sorts of assumptions within it
and when we can draw towards that deliberateness
the very same process can in the deliberateness can invite
what's called clear knowing oh
when that happened i had this fearful response
and my fearful response initiated aggression or aversion
and so in our seated meditation it's it's a wonderful opportunity for us to
discover the subtle details of what it is to embody that deliberateness
that it invites a kind of okay this is what's happening you know
it invites the kind of confident acceptance
okay this is what's happening it's pleasant it's unpleasant
um i'm feeling like there's a sensation of opening to
this person there's a sensation of closing away from this person
[Music] but with the deliberateness and the
clear knowing it it gives us a sense of agency
and as it does that something deep in us sort of recalculates you know
maybe this is not a matter of life and death that requires and a reactiveness
that that has an urgent immediacy
that this there's room to pause okay yes this is what's happening
the noticing and acknowledging become organic how else would you approach a
human life other than just being present for it
and letting what's happening register and be known
and it also it invites the very practice of awareness
it invites it as an ally to our well-being rather than an
imposition on something within us that's struggling to survive you know
we're struggling to survive and then we come along and say you should be aware this is not good
enough you're not good enough what you're doing is not good enough
it offers a different equation a different consideration
okay this is what's happening okay this is the response to it
okay this is the behavior that's coming up
we start to cultivate a very interesting factor for ourselves
the confidence the trust
to relate to life just as it is
we start to create the trust to allow ourselves to have the feelings for heaven
okay i'm really annoyed by that
and then if we embody that annoyance it has teaching it has a description
of existence it reveals in its clear knowing
what about that is annoying how in this moment does annoying feel
appropriate what kinds of
impulses does annoy being annoyed tend to create within me
and then noticing and acknowledging they ripen they become more possible of including
more of who we are
and then often we're quite surprised how generous and kind and thoughtful we
are it's like it's like it comes to us as a surprise
that often that very ne that negative emotion that annoyance
was associated with defending something virtuous
and then also the knowing allows us to also notice and acknowledge
the times when i say we heard some
very difficult thing
the surge of covered infections in india and the lack of
medical capacity to treat them
and something in us is hurt by that
something in us feels connected to the human race in all the countries
of the globe and doesn't want others to suffer
and we feel it and we discover often to our amazement
our kindness our concern
and then we hold all of that up our instinctive kindness
and our contractions
and in our deliberateness
it becomes less idealistic you know i'm practicing awareness
to be pure i will be unsullied by the stuff of the world
in fact we discover oh this human existence
is so multifaceted there's so many ways we're all responding
i don't know if we could say we forgive ourselves and we forgive the
world
i don't even know if we could say we accept ourselves and accept the world
until we also accept
the turmoil of it all you know
feeling pain by the lack of medical supplies in india
feeling grateful for something inspiring that you read
for some exchange that you had
feeling uneasy by something that happened in your life
kind of deliberateness that each period of meditation
asks of us the deliberateness that it asks of us
moment by moment
can we stay close to that
can we find it in the simple activities of our daily life
can we watch it resonate and respond to what arises in our daily life
and this is quality of shraddha confidence and trust
it's not that we we know we're right
or that we have a mastery
or a compelling agency it's it's more that we're learning to be
part of that we that in our awareness we initiate
something and and is as it blossoms
it reveals it expresses liberation
and and as we engage in this way
the what comes up for us starts to appear more as a teaching
even our own reactiveness hmm
look at the urgency with which i got caught up in that
we can feel the depth of the conviction
the determination of it
and even though we might not approve of it we might find it's harmful for ourselves and for others
we can have some compassion for it
and we're not so surprised when it appears that others are having their reactiveness
so this sense of deliberateness that invites and noticing and
acknowledging sometimes it can just be
almost factual but if we keep inviting it we start to see
the thought patterns we start to see
the emotionality of our responses we start to see
the unexamined insistence of a
reactiveness but we also we're inviting them into awareness
awareness is becoming our ally
awareness is becoming how we will live how we will nurture this life
okay thank you
enjoy your day