so good evening
here the last
monday
evening year of the year
and uh
one announcement is that for the next
two mondays we won't meet here at imc
so we'll start hopefully start again on
the 16th of january
and it just felt like it was uh
the wise thing to do to be a little
cautious during this time we don't know
what's happening with the omicron and
and
there's some theory that it might peak
in about two weeks so i don't know if
it's the right time to open then but
we'll have a little bit more sense so
yeah you can look on the website and see
if it's open then on there
and i think this i think will be the
17th of uh january
and uh
and we might require everyone to be um
fully vaccinated this time you might
meet the boosted as well so you might
have to resubmit your vaccination card
and uh i think it's just uh
who knows how necessary all these things
are but hopefully it's good for everyone
to know that we're being as cautious as
we
it's as cautious as we can be and try to
make everybody safe for everyone
and
so i find it
rather
amusing
that
the english word for the current last
month of the year
they say it's the 12th month right
and
but the word december comes from the
latin word that means ten
it's tenth month
so if you know latin it must be very
confusing
and
november
means ninth in latin october means 8th
september is 7th
and so
you know we're marking
a little bit confused in the english
language about
what we're actually
commemorating here
and uh
and we just passed this the
the
solstice
which is kind of a
kind of a real event in terms of
the planets and the sun and everything
but
this new year's eve that we celebrate
this break with this transition from one
year to the next
it's not a thing that really exists
i mean it's not like it doesn't mark
anything that's
unique
that happens in the stars the sun the
earth
it's just a kind of arbitrary day that
somehow was used to mark the end of
an arbitrary
year
where we're confused about the names of
the months
and nothing really will change between
you know you know in uh
from the 34th of december to the 1st of
january except the clocks that somehow
and the computers and all this will mark
the time is being changed but
in the in the non-human world there's
nothing really that happens
of any particularly
import as far as i know
and even when you know
we were fortunate to live in
i think we're fortunate to live in this
bay area which is so cosmopolitan and
cultures and people from all over the
world
and you can kind of go around different
weeks in the bay area and celebrate
different new years
different cultures societies celebrate
new years at different times
some other have some market by the lunar
lunar calendar not the solar calendar
so i like this thing about reflecting on
new year's eve this way
is that
we see that it's a convention
it's just it's a
construct of the human mind
some people who made up this
calendar and we live by it
and
but
but i don't want to dismiss it because
the construct is a convention
but the conventions and constructs that
we have we have so we can share our life
together
they've been they're kind of or they're
made by people so that they can kind of
support each other or kind of be on the
same page the same year and the same
kind of communication together in a
certain way
and
and if we share some of the same
conventions
the conventions link us
they make a connection between us
and so
i don't know how many of you might stay
up until midnight on the 31st
but i don't know if people still do this
when i was young
there were people who would stand on a
chair
and when midnight came they would jump
into the new year
off the chair
it really worked
they got there into the next year just
and the people didn't jump got there as
well but maybe somehow you got there
better when you jumped
the um
but still it's something that people do
together some people party some people
come together and
and
there was a time when people came
together much more in the last couple of
years
and i think it's important for people to
come together and i thank those of you
who came here today
to sit this together i find it precious
that we're meditating together thank you
and we share these conventions
and they link us
they link us and kind of organize our
lives and we kind of
share
the conventions and share the life in
some ways
but it's more for me it's more important
it isn't that they link us
but rather they're channels of
communication
and the question is
what are you communicating when you use
shared conventions
and that is what i find is most
interesting about this what i'm trying
to say today what are you sharing
what are you communicating
when you use a convention
when you use when you simply say
how are you to someone hi how are you
and it's a lot of people in english
don't really want to know how you
they say how are you they don't really
want to know how you are
you you say oh i'll tell you sit down
you have an hour i'll tell you
they don't really want to know they just
want to know that it's kind of like a
convention to say hello and i i see you
and uh
and so you say you know you play the
convention sometimes you say fine
and then how are you and the fine and
then you can go on to the
business you have to do it's just a kind
of little dance you do get connected
maybe a little it can be a little
communication or friendliness or
recognition there are some cultures
where they say hello by the word for
hello is i see you
isn't that kind of nice
i see you
and um
and so
uh
we're communicating through the
conventions that we use
and and uh this i find precious
and what do you communicate
when you use the conventions when you
say hi
how are you when you say happy new year
happy holidays or whatever you say
you're participating in conventions that
we share
and what are you communicating what is
traveling in your words to the other
person
is it friendliness is it kindness is it
recognition
is it a feeling of shared humanity
that we're in this journey together
we're accompanying each other
that we're
caring for each other that we are
respecting each other
or is it something else
now here in redwood city i've heard of
there heard terrible things be
yelled.car windows to people walking on
the sidewalk
that communicates something else
do not say how are you to someone
you know maybe that communicates a
little more of an indifference
some different feeling
so what are we communicating in the
conventions
so one of the things that happens when
people practice vipassana mindfulness
practice
there's a kind of deconstruction process
that goes on
we're kind of slowly deconstructing the
conventions we live in
some of the conventions get
claustrophobic some of them are not
helpful for our own hearts and minds
some of them are
burdensome that we live under some of
them are just part of just our lives
but as we sit and get quiet in
meditation calmer and calmer
the calmer mind
is no longer
participating at all the conventions
and for some brief moments perhaps in
meditation
a good percentage of the usual
constructs of the mind thoughts ideas of
who i am and other people are and what
i'm supposed to do and what i'm supposed
to accomplish and
my to-do list is forgotten
my
concerns of work are put aside for a few
minutes
and we experience a calmness or
peacefulness and letting go we
experience our life our world ourselves
of uh to some degree free of all the
constructs the ideas the
the beliefs the to do's the
identities that we live by
and it can be a relief
to put it all down
and when the more we can do that
the more than we can see
we can recognize
when we reintroduce the conventions
when we reinduce interpretations we
introduce thoughts and ideas and
projections and assumptions and
judgments
and
that we have about ourselves others the
world around us
and that's a special place
to be able to watch how
we
these things come back in
so if you
feel pretty calm in meditation
pretty peaceful and things are pretty
good and quiet and
you leave meditation to go out here to
find your shoes
and
you see your shoes
probably none of you have these kinds of
thoughts but you see your shoes and you
say oh
they're those old tired shoes
of mine
that really are embarrassment to the
human
to humankind
and i hope no one notices
you've now introduced a whole series of
conventions constructs and ideas
to watch it come in
to watch the mind pick it up oh they're
in my shoes they're tired and old
they're
and watch it as thoughts coming up
and be quiet enough to see it arise
and say no thank you
say i don't need to go there i don't
need to pick that up
this is optional
you could just then drop it and speak
quietly put on your shoes they probably
will get you home
another option you have
is you can see your shoes
recognize that you're going to
spiral down in some kind of
self-loathing around your shoes
so i'm not going to do that
instead you can look at your shoes and
say you know i've had those shoes for a
long time
they've take care of me in many many
places and
we've been through a lot together
maybe i'll just thank my shoes
thank you shoes
i'm grateful
before you put on your shoes you bow to
them
and maybe that's a silly thing to do
but what a world of difference it is to
live in a world
where we
look at our shoes and have loathing for
the shoes ourselves embarrassment
versus when we feel grateful for it our
shoes what a difference
which which world would you rather live
in
if you have those are the two options
i know i would better i'd prefer to live
in the grateful one
so we come to new year's eve
another convention
and there's a lot of things people do
for new year's eve that doesn't interest
me whatsoever
and there was a time in my life where i
maybe would have been a little bit
dismissive of what people do
i think some things people do probably
not so healthy for themselves
but i don't want to dismiss people
anymore don't want to dismiss and be you
know i don't want to live in a world
where i'm judging people i'll look at
that and what they're doing
i'd rather live in a world where i
appreciate people and value them and
i'll say oh look at that
people are having a chance to celebrate
people are coming together
humans need to be together some of them
do
and wish them well may they be well may
they be safe
and if those are the only options those
two to be dismissive or to
think
well about them and wish them well
i'd rather live in the latter
think it's better for me and it's really
bad it's the kind of world i'd like to
live in
and so this idea that we live in the
world of conventions ideas and
constructs an idea of what's going on
some buddhists want to dismiss it all
and say it's all empty it's all not real
we want to stay with close to what's
real
and some buddhists will say well
maybe they're not real in some kind of
absolute way
but they're real enough in the sense of
we have a choice
how to use them
and use them well
you make choices like that all the time
you sit down at a meal
you could probably eat your soup with a
knife
or the fork
but it's a little more useful to you eat
your soup with a spoon
that's a convention this idea it's a
choice we make
so we can make the same we can make
choices with how we use our words
how we use our evaluation of people and
circumstances
and that is one of the powers that come
from meditation
if you in meditation have learned to get
quiet and peaceful enough
to have put to rest some of the
judgments some of the ideas some of the
projections some of them
activities of your mind
just enough so you can see them when
they get when they reappear
and see them as reappearing oh there it
is it wasn't there now it's come
and don't give it
authority don't take it being real
the thoughts the judgments
but rather see them as thoughts three
them as judgments see them as
evaluations
the fact that you see your shoes as old
tired shoes
maybe they've been around for a long
time
but then to follow that in the wake of
that of oh this is embarrassment
it says oh
is that true just because i think it
doesn't make it true
because i think it
it's not so much but is it true or false
but in that i think it
is it helpful or not
in that i think it
how can i
use it
for something that's beneficial that
makes this world a better place
and this you know tireless
or continuous
dedication love devotion
to making this world a better place
why not
why not do that
i believe that there are people who
seemingly are continuously
doing the opposite
continuously thinking about and how to
make this
maybe they're trying to make a better
life for some people but they're making
it other people miserable
but what if we make it make us world a
place that we care for people and trying
to make it good for everyone
and you might say that that's a moral
choice
i'd like to say that it's
it's a
not a moral choice exactly but rather
it's the
more healthy choice
for our hearts and our minds
and so even as simple as how you go
to put on your shoes as you leave here
if by the time you get to the shoe rack
and you remember wow
but if i rush home right now
i think if i you know really raced home
and gunned my car and maybe hopefully
there's no police on the freeway and
just really get there i'd get back just
in time for the beginning of the tv show
that's a choice
or
see the those thoughts arise and say
wait a minute what world do i want to
live in do i want to live in a world
that's rushing and dangerous
or is there better things to do
is there healthy things for my heart and
my mind a healthy way to drive healthy
way to leave stay connected to myself
and like that is that is that that kind
of questioning
is the kind of questioning that i
believe comes from doing buddhist
practice
buddhist practice is not a magical
pill that you just do the practice and
everything will be glorious and
wonderful
but buddhist practice is one that gives
us the
the
knowledge the material the capacity
to see what we're doing moment by moment
to choose
the healthy option
in their words we speak and the actions
we do
and even the thoughts that we have
and to do that
in in
a regular way ongoing way
begins to kind of change
the inner and outer environment
there's less stress
there's less fear and anxiety
there's less tension that we carry with
us
and there's the opposite
the rewards are huge
the benefits are fantastic
to live in that place
in the present moment
where we can see
how we live
the choices we make
and to choose choose the ways that are
healthy for you for ourselves and for
the world
do things beneficial for self and others
and all the conventions we use the
communications we have
to never dismiss anything
but always to see how can we this be
used how can this be a channel
where i can spread goodness
freedom
kindness
compassion love
so we come to this end of the year
beginning of the next year
and we have all these conventions that
we do and one of the conventions is to
kind of review the year
and to set an intention for the next
year
and it's a nice that's that can be a
nice thing to do
and
what i hope is that
we keep making that resolve that
intention over and over again
it's it's how we live our lives it's not
something we do once a year
and so
it's a life and buddhist life is a life
of
making choices resolves intentions
all the time
but not in a way that's tiring
but in a way that's obvious
it's so obvious
that if you're going to drink soup
you do it with a spoon
to try to eat the soup with a knife
it's
you know
maybe once a lifetime it's okay to try
but it's
you know
it's a goddess you know
which is the easy choice
the spoon
it becomes that natural that easy
to live this life of choice to live the
life
of
being in the present moment to care for
what we do
each step along the way
so new year's eve
maybe to this year then if that what
i've said today if they
had any meaning for you maybe you can
infuse and view
new year's eve in whatever way you're
doing it alone or with people or
anything
it was something new or more dedication
how can you live this
new year's eve intention
new year's eve event
in a way that becomes a channel a canal
a
doorway
for
[Music]
the best in you
to come forth
always choose the best in you
and live by that
that's the opportunity that we have
so thank you very much for being here
and being part of this and
sharing this sitting and
it is i don't take it for granted after
this year and a half of the pandemic
that we come together and
sit this way and to me it feels very
special and
thank you for sharing this with us and
this time and i look forward to
seeing you again having a chance to do
this again
hopefully in a few weeks
you know the information about it will
be on the on the website so just keep an
eye on the website and
under what's new or the calendar or
something
so thank you all very much