so the warm hello from redwood city here at
the imc and um welcome to our morning meditation
here and other times around the world and thank you for the
people who are greeting on chat it's lovely to see your names
and see your location and and to receive the greetings
when i was practicing in burma i practiced with a teacher named upandita
and his series of his talks were translated and published in english
with a book titled the state of mind called beautiful
a state of mind called beautiful and of course we can be in many
different states of mind but the idea that we can also have a state of mind that's beautiful
i think is quite inspiring and in fact this is what this anapanasati
is working towards and buddhist practice in general is for us to discover
or cultivate um a state of mind which is quite luminous beautiful
inspiring in and of itself and one of the i've been fortunate to
see many beautiful places in the world and inspiring sunsets over the sea
and all kinds of things and the thing that i've that seems that i
have for me has been the most beautiful thing to see is the beautiful mind
and why that's incomparable with the beauty of nature or beauty
other kinds of beauty i can't quite explain but maybe because
it's so subjective or so intimate while the same time as not being
personal something quite wondrous and uh
so with the ninth step of anapanasati the direction is to experience the mind
and so it's shifting from what it's kind of
like shifting from what to how and if i really want something if
i go to the supermarket and i really need something quickly
maybe we're having a big family dinner and everything's dependent
upon getting you know having salt and there's no salt at home and so
everything's gonna we need to get salt so i'm sent to the store to get salt and
i've never bought salt in the store i bought many things but somehow i can't remember ever having bought salt
and but i'm in a hurry and guests are coming and and and so all i'm focused on
is getting the salt and i'm searching the aisles searching the
names of things on the aisles to see where they have the salt and and i don't notice anything else in the
store but looking for the salt and and then when i finally get the salt i just focus on getting to the checkout
counter and the shortest line and my mind is completely consumed
with the thing that i want and nothing i don't really notice too
much anything else because it's so important to get that salt so it's all about the what the mind has
and um but maybe the end of the day if all this busyness of something i sit
down and then i realize how i am
and i realize that i'm tired and maybe tense from searching for salt and
and the residue is still in me and all that and so i can feel a little bit how i am
but the initial how i am has to do with why i feel kind of tight in my shoulders and my belly i'm
weary in my face and and i feel a little bit discouraged that i should
pitch a big thing that got caught up in salt and so it's still about a what even i'm
feeling conventionally how i am but as i settle in and step back i notice something
that's very different and then as i notice how i am how the mind is
how the mind is that's processing all this how the mind is that knows
how the mind is as it knows searching for salt how the mind is when it knows how it
knows i'm tired and weary how the mind is and it's kind of like
the mind is the container or the reference point for receiving experience
and it's the state of mind it's not a thing but it's still a state that we can
feel and uh and that is when we that's where
the beauty begins to show itself and something very special about that shift
to the how rather than the what's of our experience the the how which is the how we're aware
how the mind is as it operates
so with that we'll do a meditation and we'll maybe at some point shift me
more to this how and so taking
a assuming a meditative posture
and of course how you are can begin right away how are you in this body
how are you in your posture
and to answer that question there is the mind is involved in a what
the particular sensations of the body
the position of the body
and then how is your breathing
and how are you with noticing your breathing
do you have a reaction to how you're breathing a response
is there a for and against something or wishing it to be different or want to make it different
what happens if you simply just know you're breathing know how you're
breathing
closing your eyes
and if it makes sense go inward into your body and feel the places where there might be
tension and holding
perhaps you can relax the shoulders release the shoulders
relax release the belly
if there's some way to relax or adjust your hands so they're more relaxed
release your hands adjust your hands so
there's no tightness in your hands
and is there can there be a softening in the face
in the easing up of all that we hold in the face
around the eyes and the forehead the
cheeks perhaps imagining there's lots of space
in front of the face behind the face
for the muscles of the face to release to relax
for the face to rest
then how's your mental activity
do you feel is there a lot of energy and thinking or
is the mind sluggish
is there any tension pressure
and if there is tension or pressure can you release the mind
release relax the thinking mind
quieting your thinking
and how is your mind what how is it what's your mental state
or the state of your heart heart mind
which is very closely related to how is your how are you aware
how are you receiving experience
oftentimes what the mind is focused on is the objects of our desires
objects of our aversions or the vague
kind of objects of our confusions
can you feel the part of the mind that is free of desire
that is not leaning forward or stretching forward
focused on having or getting the mind that's free of desire
maybe it's a back corner of the mind or a deeper layer of the mind
or something at the center
maybe it's something that doesn't have a lot of distinguishing characteristics
a feeling of absence
is there a part of the mind which is free of aversion
part of the mind is not about something not focusing on
something that's not liked
a place where there is no aversion and because of that maybe the mind is
not so concerned with what
a place where the mind can rest in a peaceful place
and can you become aware of a place where the there is no confusion
even if there is confusion as well someplace where there is no confusion
because the mind is not
focused fixated on a subject something it wants doesn't want
something is trying to understand
the part of the mind that can be at rest with itself
and then becoming aware now of your overall state of mind
the state of mind within which everything you know is known
but a state which is always more than what is known
so it's not something that we know as much as something we feel
a wide open expansive
feeling of the state of mind
and so that you don't get too involved in this state of mind looking for it
wanting it
fixating on it as you feel your state of mind
also be aware of yourself breathing in and breathing out
maybe as if breathing in and out you're breathing through the state of
mind we're breathing at the very center of the state of mind
with a state of mind so wide and broad that it includes breathing within it
breathing in experiencing the mind
breathing out experiencing the mind
and perhaps as you shift
from focusing on what you're thinking about
to experiencing the mind experiencing being aware
that this mind this maybe this awareness
maybe begins to have no sharp boundaries no edges
somehow it's related to the spaciousness around
to space not the same but
it has qualities of clarity like space or spaciousness like space
perhaps stillness like space around you
breathing in experiencing this
the mind breathing out experiencing the mind
as you exhale letting go of all the things you're thinking about
all the what's of life all the objects of thought
and then on the inhale experience
your overall state of mind
through a role state within which thinking occurs
but as a state that's broader than our thoughts and ideas the whats
exhaling letting go whatever you're thinking all the what's
inhaling and feeling the
broadness the peacefulness
of the state of mind that contains all things within it
like a room contains all things within the room
and then as we come to the end of this sitting bring to mind some person who
you have an uncomplicated relatively uncomplicated relationship
and bring them to mind so there's some image of them or sense of them
idea of them but rather than your thoughts and
memories and desires concerns about about the person
allow the person to just to sense the idea the image of the person whatever
sense you have to just rest
in the openness of mind within this general state of how you
are there's nothing you have to do about the
person but just let them be
included in your state of mind through your image your idea your sense of them
so you're not actively relating to them rather just being with them
in your mind with your mind
if we're relating to them with our desires and our concerns then we're involved with what
but if we just allow them to be included in the how we are resting there
not actively relating or wanting or not wanting
just allowing the person to be in the peacefulness of the state of mind
and now maybe you can with some tenderness or care
can you now evoke a mood of good will of kindness for
this person of generosity
maybe wishing them well is almost too much
but imagining them well
feeling the goodness of their well-being
you know gently keeping them in your open spacious attention
now wish them well may you be happy
may you be safe
may you be peaceful
may you be
free
and is there some way that you can learn from how to
include someone in your state of mind in this kind of way it is in fact
a way to be close to your good will for others
rather than rushing into the whats and the shoulds and the doings
as you meet people today in your life
take your time to let them be known
to receive and listen and sense them
in a generous state of mind
and then perhaps other things can happen and those other things might be related
to your good will may this practice of ours support us
to meet the people of the world with our good will may all beings be happy
so