okay so hello hello and welcome to happy hour to this rendition of happy
hour wherever you're joining we are indeed international from so many time zones around the world
so for today's practice
i'd like to share um a quote that
i saw earlier today that um moved me and inspired me and i'd like to
share that with you and this quote is from francis of assisi
and francis of assisi says remember that when you leave this earth
you can take with you nothing that you have received
only what you have given a full heart
enriched by honest service love
sacrifice and courage let me read it one more time
we'll use this as the basis of our practice today remember that when you leave this earth
you can take with you nothing that you have received nothing that you have received
it's quite profound nothing that you have received only what you have given
a full heart enriched by honest service love
sacrifice and courage so this quote
moved has moved me so much and it also stopped me in my tracks today as
many of you know i i love teaching and practicing mindfulness
of death and this practice of mindfulness of mor of
our mortality realizing that we are going to die we're all going to
die it's all everything is impermanent but especially our
life is impermanent and as we stop
through our day as we stop in moments and realize we are going to
die and everything that we are concerned about getting getting in
life getting in life as francis of assisi beautiful he says
um we take nothing we take nothing that we
have received we take nothing that we have received
and really what
what we the only thing that we take is what we have given
and what we give really what we give is a heart that's enriched by service
by love sacrifice and courage
so
let's see oh yeah we have the zoom bomber okay we are going to
there remove this person there
okay all right well thank you for the heads up neil i appreciate that so
all right back to where we were so
um
so with realizing that it's only what we
only what we give it's only what we give and what we give really what we
cultivate what we take away what we cultivate is a heart full of love is a heart full of
love so so that is the inspiration for our practice that's the
inspiration for our practice tonight cultivating cultivating generosity
cultivating generosity cultivating a heart that gives
so in our practice tonight what i would like to invite you
is um
after getting settled as always we start by getting settled in our bodies
with silence with spaciousness and then the invitation is to bring in
the contemplation of impermanence to bring in the contemplation of our impermanence
and from that perspective giving giving what we give since this feeling of love
this feeling of generosity of our hearts giving giving um to cultivate to cultivate that
so that is our practice that's the invitation
so so let us begin let us begin our practice let us begin our practice
so landing landing in our bodies
landing in our bodies
landing
in our feet contacting the earth
our sit bones contacting the cushion the chair
our hands contacting each other
landing arriving arriving and letting go
of whatever has come before
letting go of whatever has come before the thoughts
planning
and arriving arriving in this moment
arriving right in this moment
arriving in this body in this moment
allowing the breath
allowing the breath to be received allowing the breath to be received
the lower abdomen
allowing the breath to be received
so now i'd like to invite you if you would
to release to release some more to let go some more
to release and let go
have any contractions
worries concerns just this moment
and you know you can't always bring them back after this practice period
but for now what if
what if you released just simply released
the same way that we would release
release all that we have received all that we have received
in some moment at some point in our lives we will release everything that we have
everything that we have been given
everything we have really re received we will release
the only thing we quote unquote take take with us in
quotes
is what we have given these are wholesome
karma our good actions our good deeds our kindness our love
the way we have lived that's all that's all we take
it's all that travels with us
the way we are remembered
and the hearts of people we have touched
from this perspective we are here we are alive we have this gift of life
and this opportunity to give to give love
to give care
and the practice cultivating loving-kindness cultivating menta
inclined our heart inclined our mind
to give to give love to give kindness
both in action and what we in the actions of the mind and what we think
actions of speech the way we speak and actions of the body the way we act in
the world
from this place of release of generosity of cultivating
giving giving
bring to mind bring to heart
people you care about could be just one or two
it could be a group whatever works for you start maybe start small
as if you were giving gifts you're giving you're giving away
love with generosity i wish you well
may you be safe may you be happy
may you be healthy
may your life unfold with ease
noticing that this gift of care love friendliness
worm is also a gift to yourself
notice if your nervous system relaxes unwinds
resettles with this gift of kindness
bringing to mind bringing to heart
beings or beings
for whom meta loving kindness flows with ease for you
may you be safe from inner and outer harm
dear being dear one may you have safety
may you be happy and joyful
may you be healthy and strong
and may your life unfold with ease may your life unfold with ease
tuning into
how good it feels to be generous with kindness
expanding our heart in giving
giving love in an act of service
offering offering kindness
care good wishes goodwill
could be two one two two or maybe a circle a circle of beings
may you all be well
you have well-being i care for you
i wish to live my life with kindness
generosity care
is the biggest gift i take
expanding expanding the circle of
kindness good will to include more
for people more beings
maybe all beings may all beings be safe from inner and outer arm
especially the harm they cause themselves
sharing goodwill may all beings be happy
have joy
may all beings be healthy
in their body enjoy good health
expanding expanding our heart the capacity to wish well
and being generous may all beings have ease take care of themselves
happily
as we expand our kindness good wealth
as we rest as we relax release our heart our body into generosity kindness
let us extend our good will also to those beings being or beings who
are zoom bombers in our zoom room tonight
persons who are hurting so much they don't know any better
than to disturb disrupt ouch out creating creating on wholesome karma
and wholesome actions disturbing others may they be well
may they no goodness and well-being
may they be safe from inner inner harm inner arm and outer harm
may they be free from pain and sorrow
may they not hurt hurt people hurt people may they not hurt
may be graced with love internally externally
may they be free
free from enmity free from ill will
free from pains
may all beings everywhere have goodness
may their hearts be at peace may they feel loved
may they give love freely
may we model
what we wish the world to reflect
may all beings including myself this being who's me
may i have a loving heart may i be free
from enmity it will
may i be safe from inner and outer harm
may my heart be expansive generous
knowing knowing that nothing nothing i receive
nothing that i receive i will take with me when i die
which is inevitable ungovernable
may the generosity of my heart be expansive the gifts that i give
the cultivation of goodness
may be the way i show up internally with my thoughts
externally with my words and actions
i offer myself care love forgiveness
as much as possible offered to myself and the whole world
may all beings everywhere
be well
may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you everyone thank you for your practice tonight
or this morning or afternoon whatever your time zone might be so so
we have time for reflections for comments for questions and i uh
before we begin i want to thank and acknowledge neil and now who
offered support while we had these loom bombers too to remove them lock the room
wish them well so
so bill says wonderful session thank you
thank you bill thank you for being here and practicing yeah
so what came up for you what would you like to share if you would as an invitation
to to support uh to offer whatever has come up
as as a gift to the sangha um whatever was
insightful whatever was challenging anything is welcome anything is welcome
in this session anything deborah says i learned from your example
thank you debra yeah
neil says it was lovely the way you offered compassion to the zoom bombers it's so easy to be irritated by a
knowing people thanks for for being a beacon of compassion thank you neil and debra um
[Music] it's i mean it really we
as i was saying and what what i was offering it's it's heard people hurt people so you know
someone or beings if their entertainment is dis disturbing
so you know meditation session there must be so much pain just imagine
how much pain they must be and you know we're irritated by them for
a few minutes right but they live they live in that body in that heart in that
mind how how painful it must be that that is your your entertainment the way
it just it's so painful so of course of course i mean how else can
how can compassion not arise how can compassion not arise
may they be free may they be well may they be free from suffering
the floor is open for any reflections you're welcome to raise your hand
um [Music] you're welcome to type in chat in the
other reflections anything is welcome
also about the um let's see i see joe's hand is up
the zoom hand there you go joe please
so a couple of years ago i was in a day-long class not a not a not a retreat
with no john jeff and i can't remember the context but the
subject came up of compassion for people who hurt other people
compassion for i mean traditionally they're called enemies not not you're usually called difficult beings now
how can you have compassion for somebody like that who's hurting others and he he offered a metaphrase that
might be useful which is may you find the causes of happiness and
act on them and you said you could wish that for anybody
it's very easy to wish for anybody so i thought they'd throw that out i i do that's part of my
meta practice now yeah beautiful beautiful yeah thank you for sharing
that joke yeah causes of happiness exactly and yay may i say that happier
is a cause of happiness for for me and and many people so yes yes thank you
thank you um and he says may we open our hearts with
the offerings of our benefactors to trust them and not be suspicious of their motives yes
indeed indeed and we have appreciations coming on
youtube from richard challenging much gratitude
challenging said due to busy mind but was able to settle into a bit of the tenderness and heart space offered here
yeah and from barbara after a busy day
appreciating wisdom and compassion in this space and susan right view
and emma joining from sydney after exercising great good afternoon to you
and i think i saw maybe mima's hand earlier physical hand yeah okay
sometimes i do see physical hands here yes there you are mima please
um i was noticing um that coming to this method
practice with happy hour with this sangha i've noticed some internal changes within me
they're very subtle i look for
certain reactions that i used to have that i don't have anymore and it's so much easier uh to feel compassion
um and it's almost like before it used to feel strange because i'm fairly new to the practice but um
now i'm i can notice it more and i can get really comfortable in it and it's really sweet
it's it's a good experience and and i noticed like i've had a hard day today but coming looking forward to the coming
to you know to the practice i just let everything go and and feel
full like i'm being fed and i i so appreciate everyone i appreciate you too
nikki thank you thank you we were feeling so much appreciation for
for what you shared your report your practice report and observation over
time this is so beautiful thank you oh and i saw hearts
in the space and appreciations for what you shared oh
sweet pepper says vitamin meta so cute
yeah now says i was moved by what you mentioned in the guided meditation on
taking nothing with us when we die it makes me wonder if the only thing we really take are these ideas and how far
they might lead us yes yeah and you know if we
um if we
uh before for those for those who um uh are open to the eye to the
multi-life model or rebirth to the idea of rebirth
um our wholesome karma follows us follows you know or that where the wholesome
karma is what the karma the the potentiality of our actions is what gets
reborn into our next life so really that is what not the self but that's what we kind of
follows us so these ideas these generosities these services
um yeah thank you enough it's something that i want to continue
to sit with being being met with a sense of mortality
kind contemplation and depress is the last reflection before we go into groups please um
my thought is that the focus isn't about what we
take with us as much as what we leave like not the position possessions that we
leave but all the good actions and generosity
that we've um practiced during our life that
to me i don't know there's just it's just a slight distinction because i really i'm not sure we take anything with us i
think but but if we focus on what we leave
um the intangibles that we leave behind i think
i don't know it works better it works better for you yeah tonight yeah i appreciate that and and
i think those are two different perspectives yes and for again what i'm gently bringing in
is for for some people they are open to this multi-life
view and rebirth and in that case yes it is what you kind of take with you um
and for some no it's it's a sense of the one life model and you know there's a
sense of don't know mind so both of those frames let's be open to either or both and if
we feel challenged by one ah let's have a doughnut mind about the other because the to what we
leave that's an easy one i agree of course you know we can all sign up to that one that's what we leave and what
we take i know it's like yeah do i think i don't know about that okay cool let's let's let's have a don't know
mind about that or not it's all good
yeah they were just happy to take it with me to the next life too
that's great so dear ones we have come to uh the invitation for us to enter and
practice in small groups together size of three take care of yourselves take care of each other sharing as little or
as much as you you wish and remember you don't take anything well
anything you have received you don't take with you so so i'm creating the rooms and we're
ready and opening and here we go take care of yourselves take care of each
other
okay welcome back everyone we have just about one minute so
um i like to invite burning comments especially if you haven't spoken
uh tonight or for a while you can raise your hand it's best if it's your zoom hand because physical head i'm not going
to see
going once
the last minute reflections nuggets
okay well we're going to end with a reflection from
maria maria m on youtube says the quote what we take with us will stay with me this
week a pivot point for me so so that'll be the last word what do we
take with us or leave so thank you all thank you for
coming practicing together cultivating kindness generosity ah what what a gift
what a gift we give each other um to practice in this way thank you
you all be well safe and cultivate gifts to yourself to
others that you take or leave
[Music] thank you all