okay so hello formerly hello officially hello
and welcome to happy hour it's lovely to see your faces see your names
feel your presence getting together this hour in this moment in time
for practice together so so for today's practice i want to invite
us to explore practice and
specifically practice of meta loving-kindness
as an act of generosity to ourselves and to others
what happens if we take on this perspective
of generosity of spirit when we practice
what happens with say quote-unquote distractions
can we be generous to distractions or to sounds
to quote-unquote distracting sounds loud sounds what happens
when we take on this spirit of generosity towards ourselves
practice as an act of generosity towards ourselves and towards whatever
is coming up in our environment and towards others
how may that shift the way that we show up
in this moment in this practice and in general
how we show up for others for loved ones
for colleagues for friends for people we don't know at the grocery store
if we take on this perspective of generosity so we practice
we practice what does it feel like to take on perspective of generosity
as a perspective of meta as a perspective of good will that we cultivate towards ourselves
towards others so that is the theme for today
how generosity of spirit and meta are synonymous in many ways many
dimensions and it's for us to discover how that shows up for us what it means
to us so so without further ado
let's practice together let's lend in our bodies
in our hearts and our minds can we
show up with generosity for this body in this moment the sense
of care whatever is arising
can we be generous towards it
feeling a sense of spaciousness it's okay you can be here
if there is pain in the body the heart
not feeling stingy about oh this is mine this is my space
this is my practice time what if we shared it
if we relaxed a little bit and shared it with whatever shows up
not giving the house away not giving all of our attention away
but making space making room
it can be stably present
and with this attitude of generosity of spirit
landing landing
merced bones
landing
in the chair the cushion the contact points
turning the gaze inward and just receiving the breath
for a few minutes in the lower abdomen
the relaxed body relaxed body
arriving suddenly
as emotions as thoughts arise
how can we be generous with ourselves
not self-flagellate not judge ourselves but have a sense of
spaciousness of generosity
thoughts can arise and pass the heart can be free
not grasp
generosity as this action
of opening a hand giving away not clinging
relinquishing can that gesture of an open hand opening
hand be the gesture of our heart our mind
with whatever arises
can we freely give away love care
warmth to ourselves
to whatever rises this fear of experience
can our bodies relax our heart relax
into this gesture of the open hand
gesture of generosity
there's not so much doing to be done in this practice
but just to land relax into
sense of kindness generosity to whatever rises
with ever rises
things don't have to be pushed away
into some idea of perfection
with judgment thoughts emotions can arise and pass
there can be openheartedness
spaciousness relaxedness with the breath with the sensations of
the body that's all
a generous heart is a loving heart
a loving heart is a generous heart discover this explore this for your own
heart mind
remember the breath the body is always available
there's a reference point it's a grounding
in case you find too many thoughts arising
into needing grounding come back to the breath
the ease to the generosity of the breath
it's an anchor is grounding
if the thought arises i'm not doing this right i don't know
what i'm doing i'm no good at this it's confusing
can this thought be believed
but treated as a guest with generosity not with ill will
[Music] hello old pattern of self-judgment
hi it's okay i see you
i don't push you away i don't hate you there's plenty of room
this space of generous heart i won't give you the megaphone but you
can be here i don't believe you but you can be here
ah
what happens if we treat doubt
ill will self-judgment with an open hand of generosity
and relax relax back into
space of ease and kindness towards ourselves
towards whatever rises
you can just be receiving the breath with kindness with
generosity
towards this being who is you who is me who's showing up in this moment
as best as they're able to
what if this person this me is treated
like your best friend
someone you love you care about you're generous towards
no rush nowhere to go they can just sit here and breathe
feel glad feel content
trying on this way of being not doing but being
try it on for size again and again
receiving with generosity with appreciation
each and every breath
and offering kindness generosity every sensation every thought every
emotion giving and receiving
this field of kindness field of generosity
you know you know how to be generous
you know how to be kind to yourself
to whatever arises trust trust that you already know
if at any moment there is trouble connecting with it remember the gesture of the open hand
the hand that opens and giving
ah feel
feel the gesture of the open hand be the open hand
in your heart in your body in your mind
first and foremost to yourself
trust trust the goodness of cultivating kindness
and generosity towards yourself
as a stepping stone for others
notice notice how much
easier
this meditation can become
with a mindset of generosity to ourselves
especially when we discover we're lost in thought
there's sense of ease
instead of yanking the attention back or judgment if there is ease
ah so much more joyful
to be sitting and practicing so much more nourishing
for the last moments of this practice period
appreciating ourselves with kindness with generosity
thank you me thank you ah
you showed up you did your best thank you
and relinquishing letting go opening the fist
if it's holding any judgment
and appreciating with gladness
this practice period may the goodness
may the goodness of our practice support us and all beings everywhere
in gladness goodness kindness generosity and freedom
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
hmm so [Music]
generosity and meta generosity and loving kindness
so i noticed that i feel a lot more at ease
a lot more content and happy with this style of not so much doing
but sitting being this with this spirit of generosity towards self towards whatever
arises and we have time for reflections if you'd
like to share what you discovered what was it like for you
your questions your comments you're welcome to type them in chat or raise
your hand dawn i see you please
um thank you so much nikki um at one point maybe
a third of the way through you uh mentioned something about perspective perfection and i was in some
reverie and i just sort of latched on to that and i thought
that's really interesting and i don't know the context and anyway
i always be delighted maybe i'll just have to like replay this tape and
but uh if you happen to recall yeah yeah yeah yeah sure
sure what i was saying and it's interesting just before i say that it's
it's so interesting that sometimes these words these they resonate so how the word perfection
really appreciating how it served as a mindfulness bell for you
which wow that's nice that's interesting and um
and yeah and it's all good i appreciate the comfort and
and also another thing i want to reflect on is that i still appreciate in this uh practice space of happy hour there's
so much comfort and ease there is no shame with mind wandering that's one mind to do and i so appreciate you
bringing that in there's such a sense of ease and safety that just gladdens my heart in the way that that you bring
that in and this help because that is so important for every practitioner not to
feel shame or bad or like not it's that's what
minds do they fall into these reveries and then they the moment of awakeness happens so thank
you for bringing that in dawn with the benefit of all beings also anger
and now that what i was talking about um was um the invitation was not trying
to push away which again i guess continuing around along the same theme
you know when we realized that we're lost in thought with don't don't try to push it away with
you know or when emotions come up don't try to push it away for some perfection like what we imagine
this perfect yogi is supposed to be
that's the idea like can we have generosity kindness not this idea of the
perfect yogi actually along the way of getting there
we're actually having a lot of ill will so just pointing that out
and if i may uh just one piece onto that about sort of perfection i i
sort of go sort of at one point you're talking about this
kind of self-judgment and and i just you know just sort of underlying i had so like this
man i'm sick i just turned 60 and jesus i'm just like starting to really
get serious with practice what the hell you should have been doing this three decades ago before that
and i sort of had this like crazy dialogue
yeah yeah um and you know there's so many
so many things we can have these unhelpful dialogues about because it's not getting us anywhere right it's it's
throwing perfectly wonderful moments of awakening after moments that we have not been awakened
so instead wow what a gift that i've actually discovered this i could be
going through my whole life and not be doing this so
what what a tremendous gift what a tremendous tremendous gift it is so
that's the invitation i would have yeah thank you don
any reflections yes
we're glad you're here we're glad all of us are here any reflections any questions any
comments
maybe what we will do today we will go into our
small sangha practice discussions first and then maybe when we come out we'll
take more reflections so so with that i'd like to invite us all
to as we go into small groups to engage with a sense of generosity for
ourselves and for others what does that look like what does a sense of feeling of
generosity look like for ourselves and for others with with the sense of meta and let's start with
15 seconds of silent meta silent generosity for ourselves and
for others so i'm going to make the rooms and if you're on the edge
if you're shy about being groups with others please stay
and see how it goes be on the edge of your disk a little bit
of discomfort and um but if you have to go
no problem no judgment no worries it's all good so
creating the rooms and they are open now take care of
yourselves take care of each other okay here we go
welcome back everyone the rooms are closed lovely so we have a couple of minutes
for a new reflection so it came up i see lots of smiles that makes me happy
so yeah please don't be shy especially if you haven't shared in a while
i'd love to hear your reflections especially oh i see a heart oh that's sweet
um yeah please we'd love to hear from you
whether you're new or you you've come back after a while we are so happy you're here
why did you discover with this mindset of generosity what was it like for yourself
or maybe showing up with sangha
yeah clinton thanks thanks to my partners with your
generosity of information and personal experience oh that's sweet
generosity is so expanding yeah jerry says
it is feeling is it as expensive right this is expansiveness of the heart
that's why the buddha taught generosity as the as a primary practice
it's not it's not just about giving money your resources it's it's such
an important internal practice discovering this internal dimension of generosity so expansive
it's really a liberative practice
yeah friend i see you and it's seven and so
i'm gonna ask you to yeah naked succinct please
i've found today after doing a meta meditation this morning that i was
uh much more open to uh being a more generous correspondent on
the phone with several friends that i was speaking with and
not needing to step in and say too much myself when i could when i could feel someone really
wanting to talk and just letting the line go out and out and out and it felt very good
nice lovely i appreciate hearing that the sense of how actually your practice of meta in the
morning gave rise to a sense of generosity they are so connected beautiful thank you fred
yeah report from the field um generosity seemed more warm and loving
than just acceptance as ken kenneth and yeah
and dave says today i counted myself and including myself in the zoom meeting instead of wait i think that's a partial
comment mima i see your hand and let's make this one succinct too
please i think one of the things that um resonated with me tonight with this meditation was that i
need to work on becoming more mindful on that generosity is like you said it's not just about giving money
it's like um becoming more mindful of um how it comes through the from the heart
on uh taking time to listen to someone or including someone like i i could see
that now it's it's vague yes but i think it's i think i'm
trying to get the sense of that yeah thank you for that yes thank you for that yay
oh that makes me so happy that yes that's it yeah yay i am so happy that's it's this
important inner dimension of generosity is so expansive well thank you all you've made my
evening with your practice with your insights and i am so much happier after
this happier than i was before so thank you for your practice for showing up
your cultivation your goodness support awakening of ourselves and all things
everywhere [Music]
thanks everyone