so my friends welcome to the our meditation time together and i offer
my warm greetings for this opportunity to be with you even in this format here
so thank you for being here
and there is a um
i think many of you know that one of the characteristics or hallmarks of buddhism supposedly is the
emphasis on wisdom and and one of the one of those little
kind of phrase that captures an important aspect of wisdom is that
if you want to be wise be intimate if you want to be wise
be intimate and so here sitting in this meditation what does it mean what would it mean to
sit here intimate and one of the meanings of
intimate is innermost to sit here with what's innermost
not to reject everything else but to have that what's innermost be the seat of awareness be the
way in which everything is known innermost i associated with a place of
quiet and calm and stillness if there if it is associated with
thoughts there are the quiet thoughts that clearly arise out of that quiet or that
stillness or that peace peace clearly arise out of what is not
thinking so this intimate intimacy with what's innermost
this is maybe a way to discover wisdom so to
is assume a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and begin with gentling yourself taking a gentle
approach to settling into your body
the first dictionary definition of intimate is pertaining to
friendship so to become your own
intimate to be intimate with yourself to be friendly here
and then to maybe gently or calmly taking a few long slow deep
breaths long and slow that's comfortable for you
that has a good feeling like almost like a relief to exhale long and as if there's an
ah as you exhale and a deep in-breath
that really is almost like a recharging a filling a relief to take in
all this oxygen
and on that exhale long exhale to settle in more into your body
maybe by relaxing the shoulders
the belly
relaxing the hands the arms the elbows
so they're not locked or held tight
relaxing the legs the knees
softening in the buttocks and the hip joint
releasing yourself to the pull of
gravity
and then to soften the face
maybe as you bring your breathing back to normal
so you also as you exhale in normal exhale
releasing the holding of the face which is a doing an
activity for the existing expressions of the face
so the cheeks relax the eyes relax the jaws
letting the face rest
and also on the exhale to relax the brain the mind
there too the mind can be ever busy ever churning away its thoughts its concerns
its anxieties for these few minutes
to give your mind a little vacation to break your thinking mind and allow it give it
permission to relax to soften
to ease up
and then to find within some place with deep inside that
feels you're in like your innermost approximately your innermost
place of being
from the inside out to become intimate with yourself intimate with
what is on the inside and in doing
so can you find a place that's
deeper central core
where there's not so much thinking the surface thoughts of our lives
are more like the waves on top of the sea
and as we go innermost it's like being under the water where it can be quieter
and stiller and expansive and open
and then from some innermost place
from there to be aware of breathing
from their sensing and feeling
breathing the body breathing
and what would it be like for you to be intimate from the inside out
to the experience of the body breathing
and whenever you need to to quiet the thinking mind soften your
thoughts and switch from thinking about thoughts
that are distracting to thoughts that are intimately involved
with the experience of breathing
that are connecting supporting you to be riding
the experience of breathing in and breathing out
so
um
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting imagine
that you are centered in the place that's most innermost place
within an intimacy with yourself that was deeper than your appearance
deeper than your history your background deeper than the things you do during the
day or say your mannerisms deeper than your beliefs
someplace deep down inside that's core maybe is associated with a
tenderness or vulnerability a place that from which
love and compassion can come or a place that we can offer love and
compassion that needs it
and imagine now that you can look on others
and only see what's innermost in them
that which is deeper than their appearance their background their history their
beliefs their mannerisms that all you could see
was something that's inner innermost
and you saw them from what's most intimate and innermost in yourself
and all the associations you have with appearances and mannerisms beliefs
have been put aside as you're in what's deep in you
somehow tunes into what's deep in others
and perhaps in this way maybe the only thing to do
is to love the other is to have good will
a generosity of spirit a care a
shared tenderness
and may it be that what we learn from being intimate with ourselves
gives us new eyes in which to see others
and so we see them as being much more than what meets the physical eye
and what you hear as they speak
maybe it gives you a sense of something that's deeper inside
it allows you to have a different kind of respect and love and good will
so that when you offer your good will you're speaking to this part of others
and may it be as we come out of this meditation
that we dedicate the meditation practice the sitting
to a willingness and interest engaging gazing upon others
aware that they have an innermost life innermost tenderness
and may we then be interested in their welfare and their
happiness
may all beings that we gaze upon all beings that we know and don't know
may they be happy may they be safe
may they be peaceful and may they be free
and may we respect others in such a way
to support their happiness and well-being
may all beings be happy
so what i'd like to consider and explore
for this talk is some aspects of desire
as i've said before i think that the more proper term for
human beings would be human desirings because their
desire is part and parcel and intimately connected to human life and there's no life human life without
desire that we're going to supposed to get rid of desire have no desires is unrealistic
but to become wise about desire is one of the tasks of buddhism and to
learn how to be free of desires free from the desires not that they're gone
but we're not caught in them and we have freedom in relationship to them
and so the um
so in order to become wise about desire it helps to become intimate with desire
and as i said a little while ago that if you want wisdom cultivate intimacy and there's some
something some aspect of intimacy some way of being intimate that touches in and brings us to the
place where wisdom has a chance to operate and so if you want to be wise about
desire be intimate with desire and to explore this topic i want to talk
about a subclass of mental movements in the family of desire
and that and start talking about the outermost
the most abstract abstract in a sense to that which gets closer and closer to
something that's more and more intimate inside and so perhaps this talk it would be a
little bit of a journey from uh outward to inward to what's innermost
so maybe he'll follow along and maybe you can imagine or feel what i'm talking about
and how it works for you giving me a little bit of the maybe the benefit of the doubt or
a little bit of the focusing on what i say that might be
relevant for you or what you can identify with or recognizing yourself and certainly some of the things i say
you might have aspects of it that you disagree with but on this journey it might be
better for now to just kind of find recognizing yourself oh yeah i know that this way
so uh this journey into exploring desire uh has to do with three parts
it has to do with uh what we desire why and why we desire
and how we desire so what what why and how
and and so the aspect of this is to have a goal
desires usually have a goal something we want something we want to accomplish something we want to
do and and goal having a goal is an important part of life
and people have all kinds of goals that they want to accomplish but a goal in my vocabulary
is a what it's the the purpose of the desire it's the what
what we want to get what we want to see happen we use the word what to describe what is the goal
you might ask them and what is what is the purpose or what's the goal
and so for example um as i did this morning
you might go shopping for a relative for food and um and the goal was to go
shopping and um so you know what are you up to i'm going shopping i'm going to the
store and in fact i was able to go to the store and buy what i needed to do and so i accomplished the goal
and um but you know that's the it's the talking about that way it's somewhat
removed for me it's somewhat abstract it's outside of me shopping is outside of me in a sense uh
the goal buying something from my my relative is a you know it's a worthy goal but it's kind of you don't
really learn anything about myself except that i was going to do this task
and so we can also ask um why am i doing it and so uh the why has to do with a
purpose and when we start talking about purpose we're talking about something that's maybe a little bit closer in more
intimate more integral to who we are than just the goal
and and so the purpose maybe for going shopping was uh
my relative is sick and i needed to i wanted to get i was asked to get something to support
her in her time of illness and so the purpose was to support and offer aid
to a relative who is ill and so so you would if i just said it my
you know purpose was to go by x y and z you wouldn't uh you know that's the goal
you wouldn't really understand the purpose but you're getting the purpose oh now we're understanding something about maybe what
is motivating gil and what's happening here and and then you could ask deeper but why
are you doing that and you keep asking the question why and in a certain kind of way that goes
through layers and layers inside you can ask well why are you doing that oh because i care for my relative i love
my relative and and so it's out of my care
that's that's why i'm doing it and so now you know something a little deeper about me or you're kind of going
in closer and closer in and so you could ask um what's the
purpose and it's really useful not to answer it with just one answer
if you have a desire to ask what is the purpose of why i want to say what i'm going to say
why i want to say what i want to say or what's the purpose of this activity i'm doing what's the purpose of
this way of thinking how often do you ask yourself why am i thinking this way what purpose
does it fulfill and then even if you get an answer one answer
ask again ask again because there might be multiple reasons uh multiple motivations inside purposes
we're trying to accomplish and um and then or you might ask more of
a secondary one you might have one answer i'm you know why why are you shopping
because i'm shopping in order to support a relative but why you want to support a relative
because i care for the relative the relative is sick and and you know and why do you care for a relative and why do you want
to support a relative because it just it's the kind of heartfelt wish of course i would do that
and uh and so you keep asking and you can get deeper and deeper questions it takes you on a journey can take your
journey to be something more intimate and deeper and just have the logical answers being
the only answer the first answer only one it might miss something
of the bigger picture or the intimate picture or something of what's going on
so that there's the purpose and then deeper than the purpose there is um the how are we how are we
when we're doing something and the question how implies i think always brings us into
the at least my vocabulary in this question always brings us into the the activity itself the not ex
you know kind of like into the present moment the action how we're doing it is how we embody it how we go forth with
it and where its purpose is little bits you know abstract a little bit removed from you know can
be a little bit removed from something it's inner but when you talked about how it it kind
of really comes closer and um and so
how am i doing it am i doing it in a hurry am i doing it slowly am i doing it uh with resentment am i
doing it with delight and joy with generosity how are we doing it and um
and um are you doing it in uh you know trying to do the minimum you can or
you're trying to do more than you can so there's all these questions about how
and uh and so how do i go to the store in the morning to go shopping
uh so part of it is with care part of it with certain delight it was early in the morning and
and it was kind of quiet and calm time to be going and it was also um i was going with
with the feeling of you know a certain kind of good feeling about knowing that i could
do something for my relative and was happy to do so so and then um
and then being in the store and uh there are a few other shoppers there there was the clerk there
early enough there was just one and um and uh and how i was there
i was not being there with you know you know trying to be have a human connection with the person at the counter in spite
of the masks that we were wearing and and um and uh
you know so how was you know trying to be friendly trying to have good will trying to be connected
to the whole situation that was in and so how but how goes deeper and deeper you know so
really how were you this way how are you that way and and now we come what's deeper in uh
maybe than uh the question you know related to how is the attitudes that we have so
you know i could have done something how i could have done fast or slow but then how i did it the what attitude
went with going fast maybe it was the attitude of being fast was that i was impatient maybe the attitude of was i was overly
eager i really wanted to do something so i'm really rushing because of my strong desire maybe even greed
or maybe i'm slow because i just really enjoy it i like being present and being
in the experience fully or maybe i'm slow because i resent doing it and uh and now you hesitate and i'm not
really putting myself into it i'm dragging my feet so there's attitudes that
now attitudes were coming in more intimate more closer down deeper down what are the attitudes we
carry what is the mood of the mind what's the attitude that the heart has the mind has
and are those attitudes attitudes of the moment or are they part of our
character part of how we've cultivated and how we live the the patterns of mind and
thought and beliefs and emotions that characterize how we've chosen to
live our life and uh and now different from personality
which maybe we don't have much choice about that but character we have some choice and it's been shaped
by either by society and events and experiences of our life but also it's been shaped by that all
that small and big choices we've made about what kind of thoughts to emphasize what kind of desires to emphasize what
kind of ill will to emphasize what the habits are that we're building up of behavior and ways of being
and these all contribute to ongoing
attitudes that we carry with us and so now we're talking about something
that can be really deep and these attitudes sometimes can be subliminal or not obvious to us all the time they can
start becoming invisible to us because we carry them with them all the time but to sit in meditation and get quiet
and start seeing when i get quiet and intimate with myself what in some deeper way are the
underlying deeper attitudes that are operating for me and how might
those attitudes relate to the desires i have and how i pursue those desires
and the deeper deeper we go in buddhism and you might not agree with this but in
buddhism it's considered to be three fundamental unhelpful
unwholesome roots for our attitudes and three wholesome ones and all
wholesome beneficial impulses come out of these three roots the wholesome roots and all the things
which are unhelpful harmful that we do for others or things that are unhealthy
derived from these three unwholesome roots the unwholesome roots is usually
translated in english as either craving or greed some occasionally
it's a strong another word in pali that maybe is closer to lust but the strong desire com
you know that somehow there's a contraction there's a loss of freedom in the movement it's
kind of unwholesome there's some kind of maybe selfishness involved connected to it maybe there's um
an overriding of wisdom that goes into it with greed and so the other
unwholesome root is ill will and often in english we say the
word aversion for this but it could also be more dramatic it could be hostility so it's very mild or can be very strong
and but there can be an underlying momentum movement attitude mood of aversion of hostility
of pushing away not wanting that if that's the seed the root for
behavior it tends to be a behavior which expresses that it will in in forms of hostility and and causes all
kinds of difficulty and that can be towards oneself or towards others
and the third unwholesome attitude is um root attitude is delusion confusion
where we're just confused in a sea of not knowing and doubt and uncertainty and and not making sense of things and
jumping around in different ideas and not settling on anything and when there's confusion and delusion
then it's easier for greed we're not connected to wisdom there's no
wisdom in that no clarity and so that tends to then
support more greed and more ill will the healthy attitudes and
our generosity good will and wisdom and so
generosity is this a feeling that that openness and availability and
open-handedness open-heartedness that's a spirit of kind of being both open to the world around us
but also um i want to use the word manifest
manifesting actualizing for them something for the world it's a movement which is connected to
wisdom and makes room for wisdom a closed hand
is not open to experience something in the palm of the hand but if we open the pan then we can
experience something in the palm now it can be stroked by someone for example
we can clean the palm we can't clean it if it's closed so same thing with the heart or the mind
with greed something closes down with generosity something opens and it's available for wisdom
available to be cleaned and then um good will
instead of ill will is uh also this opening movement something
that liberates us it frees something inside it frees us from the contraction the closeness
of of um
of uh what goes on for us so uh i got distracted because i saw
this somewhere with no bell i guess i didn't bring the belt and the sitting did i
so maybe no bell no end and uh so
so ill so good will and then wisdom and wisdom also itself is an opening
movement because one of the primary forms of wisdom is not
the wisdom of not clinging the wisdom of not suffering then wisdom of non-harming
so these are think of these as attitudes then do we go about with an attitude of
generosity an attitude of will an attitude of wisdom attitude of discernment of
seeing clearly or do we have an attitude that somehow closes wisdom limits wisdom and so is it greed
is it ill will is it delusion and
and so or is it fear that somehow is connected to those three
it's fascinating that fear that's unhealthy has is considered because has to be
rooted in either greed ill will or delusion so how does that work and is there a
different kind of fear that's rooted in generosity and good will or love and wisdom i think there is
that's why fear doesn't fit in either it doesn't it's not placed in just one or the other
it's just the unwholesome or just a wholesome but it depends on the roots that support the fear
so attitude so so attitude is more intimate than the goal
attitude brings us into something close in to what's innermost and what makes us tick and what influences us and
influences how we see the world and how we see ourselves and to sit in meditation or other ways
of beginning to find no deep you know being defined
the underlying attitudes dispositions in which we operate in and to learn how to not be caught by
them not becau not be limited by them not be closed by the unhealthy ones
beginning to open and open and open and my sense is that the unwholesome
roots of greed hate and delusion they themselves are not what's most innermost they
themselves are a little bit more surfacy and as those fall away and as we keep
opening generosity love good will
and wisdom they belong to uh that which is most innermost
most sensitive maybe most shy at times most tender most uh maybe most
quiet and so it's only by getting quiet or settled or intimate and willing to have a
certain tenderness that these generosity and ill and good will
and wisdom really can shine and be part of our life
so certainly we can have goals we can have purposes
we can focus on how we are but don't get don't be too caught up in
the goal don't be too caught up in the purposes
pay attention to how you do things it's a huge key and important part of mindfulness practice
and as you pay attention to the how at some point come in and really begin discerning what are the underlying
the deeper attitudes which are fueling or influencing
how we're going about our life and there in those attitudes is where
you can start discovering freedom it's when the attitudes become free then the
desires that flow for them are free as all as well and we become free
so that when we have desires of generosity of goodwill and wisdom
then hopefully then we have a sense of how to remain free with those
for our attitudes to contain freedom so our desires
can be free so that our purposes can have qualities of freedom and the
goals can be intimately involved with freedom as well
so i hope that this has given you something to think about and explore on
yourself and some questions to ask yourself as you go about questions about why
what of why and how and take the how question and go as deep
in as you can you come to your you can see if you can find the underlying deeper attitudes dispositions that um
animate your life and see if you can
switch to be more and more have those attitudes be the wholesome
roots may that journey of exploration
be empowering and freeing for you thank you