hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour
and if you can hear me okay if you'd give me thumbs up oh thank you mari christine i see your thumbs up
so uh let's let's take a moment wait i still need to
fix a few settings here give me one moment
ah okay
disable waiting room
okay here we go doing the various okay here we go
so all right good well let's let's start our hellos um if you want to share how the weather
is that would be nice too i'm nikki i'm in in mountain view california unseated
oloneyland and today is has been a sunny warm
we'll walk 65 degrees fahrenheit so who wants to say hi you're welcome to unmute
yourself and say hello neil in new hampshire it's 55 and
sunny and windy ah nice i see the background is kind of is
that windy is it oh my god this is so cool i love your background
it's great welcome neil
marie christine how's the weather in down under 22 celsius she says but breeze
is cool ah entering your summer period right or
wait no fall you're entering fall that's right yes the other way around yeah yeah yeah yeah
hi bill in dallas it's trying it's trying to rain here
okay trying not quite succeeding great
anybody else wants to say hello i see terence is unmuted hi terrence
hello hi nikki thank you hi thank you welcome
anybody else wants to say hello and check in hi kenneth from albuquerque how's the
weather where you are kenneth you and tell us
uh it's good it's uh a little windy but it's about 65 out nice
yeah similar to california here except for the wind hi fred from canada how's the weather up
in canada fred it's uh night right now oh it's night
right now okay so w where in canada are you fred i'm in eastern canada oh eastwood
friendship oh yes quebec area yep that's it
tends to be chillier i think right around this time it's a bit chilly yeah yeah nice welcome
lovely to have you thank you great anybody else wants to say hi and
share how the weather is in their piece of the world
this friday this is kind of fun
okay no more takers i
all right so let's get started oh yes thank you neil for sharing
information about happy hour google groups
where folks can connect share information and also receive you know poems and and
resources that are shared online um are shared on the google group so
please join if you if you like to stay connected and this is the time that i
change the settings so i accidental unmuting will
not be possible during the guided meditation and talk if there's any thing to chat will come to host only i'm
setting changing that setting and also turning on recording for the sake of audio dharma
here we go great so hello again everyone and welcome the warm welcome to
happy hour hi so for this friday edition
of happy hour after another week um in this
interesting world of ours um so a couple of themes
one is one theme i'd like to to invite us to explore tonight given that it is friday i think i'll
have a quieter happy hour with a lot of space so there could be a lot of silence
to settle in with the body with the breath and just have the sense of refuge of
of quietness that's one thing that we'll explore and another theme i like
to bring in from wednesday so wednesday we explored
the theme of safety offering safety may i feel safe may i be
safe offering safety to ourselves and others and then towards the end the um
with the reflections it came up that oh
offering safety is a precondition or perhaps even
synonymous with love when we offer safety to someone and let them be just
as they are they can be themselves it's a way of loving them it's a way of allowing them to be
completely safe and guess what it's the same for
ourselves offering safety to ourselves
completely to whatever is coming up might be challenging emotions
might be challenging physical sensations
to allow them to be however they are in the moment instead of fighting with them to make
them go away there is this idea of offering
safety to our fear for example or offering safety to our disappointment or sadness
instead of squashing it wanting to wanting it to disappear enough now enough no no
offering it safety okay yes you can be here you can be here it's fine and there can be resilience there can be
[Music] spaciousness there can be actually love holding it all so that whatever we're
offering safety to doesn't become the focus doesn't there's
first of all there's no battle there's no battle and also there's plenty of space for a
lot more to arise for for gladness for happiness for ease and peace to be
there so so those are the two themes
tonight within this context of meta meta loving kindness friendliness love
that we explore towards ourselves so i think that's enough
for setting the stage let's practice together
ah so i invite you to get into your meditation posture whatever might be appropriate for you in
this moment moving maybe see what your body needs
to sit comfortably or maybe to lie down comfortably
ah landing landing with this body
landing with the breath inviting the body to relax to let go
letting go of whatever thoughts
preoccupations concerns have come before
landing in this moment intimacy with this moment of being alive
that has never been and will never occur again
relaxing into this body with each breath
embracing as if we're embracing this moment with ease not with tightness
same sense of ease embracing this moment
as if you're lying in the hammock comfortable with ease feeling safer
your body relaxed a warm breeze
grieving the warm breeze outside
creating the warm breeze inside your breath
and letting go of the thoughts that are rising right now there's nothing wrong
with thinking per se but just now as we're trying to settle and arrive
thanking the thoughts thank you please come back later right now i'm giving myself
wholeheartedly to intimately sense
feel be open to
refuge
solitude busyness in this moment
letting this moment be a refuge
refuge a safe haven offering your heart your mind a
refuge turning away from busyness
feeling safe
contained
content the simplicity of this moment as refuge
what would it mean
for you to fully offer safety to yourself in this moment drop in that question
into your body
so that emotions feel safe
the body however it is showing up with fatigue aches pains
excitement story whatever it is
for all of it to be completely okay just as it is
no part of you rejected in this moment
parts that disappointed
etc etc it's all okay
fully embraced received one breath at a time
making yourself a safe refuge for yourself
breathing in safety breathing out safety
in what ways offering your heart
safety feel synonymous
with offering your heart your self-love and acceptance
especially with respect to self-judgment
can you see how offering safety to yourself
can be synonymous with self-love self-compassion
ways in which one is the precondition or perhaps
similar to the other
a soft gentle smile is an evolutionary way we signal
safety to strangers to others
what happens if you share a smile with yourself an inner smile
offering yourself safety
and care see what happens
experiment
you're welcome to explore phrases if you wish or continue without phrases
may i be safe or may i feel safe
from inner and outer arms
may i be happy
and joyful
may i be healthy and strong
and may my life flow with ease
may i have ease in my life take care of myself happily
and now what if we were turning to safety and offering others
safety can we make ourselves a safe haven for others
so people in our life
feel safe with us at ease with us have no reason to be afraid
in our presence may i be safe
may i be saved
and sharing the safety goodness with others turning it outward
may all the beings whose lives i touch
may all of them be safe feel safe
giving this gift of safety this wish freely
cultivating our heart knowing too well that life is uncertain
without attachment to outcome externally we offer this wish
knowing it may or may not be realized but we offer it nevertheless
a wish of goodness
may all i come uncontact in contact with directly or indirectly
may all the beings in my life
be safe feel safe
knowing full well that may not always be possible but sharing the good wish the good will
standing further may all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere
may they feel safe be safe
sharing the generosity of our heart and good will
and into all beings including yourself or self may all beings including me
feel safe be safe from inner and outer
arms
may all beings including myself be happy and joyful
thank you
male beings everywhere including myself be healthy and strong
may all beings including myself have
ease
and for the last moment of this practice period
offering safety to yourself to whatever rose the past
30 some minutes of this practice period whether there was sleepiness
distractedness it's okay you showed up as best as you were able
to offering safety instead of self-judgment
to yourself
may all beings including ourselves be safe from inner and outer harm
may all beings including ourselves be
free [Music]
thanks everyone for your practice
so we explored
as promised on wednesday following up on practice of safety offering our
self-safety and other safety as a precondition for love
see what it feels like this offering of safety to ourselves so it's synonymous with care with love
to ourselves also what it feels like when we offer it externally
i'll share one reflection and as i was practicing with you i found this particular emphasis to be so
soothing calming really just as a sense of refuge for
for this being who's me just very calming and soothing
grounding so would love to hear your reflections you can type them in chat and if you
type them just to me i will consider them private i won't say
your name when i read them or you can just say private and i won't even read them
or you can type them to everyone in which case i'll read your name or you can raise your
hand your zoom hand you love to love to hear some reflections what did
you discover how did this go for you did you notice
some things about offering safety to yourself with self-judgements
with emotions with body pain what happened what happened
eric says soothing is the word it was like a warm bath for my neurons i love it
thanks erica that's how i feel too
bill asks how does one offer safety to negative thoughts
and yet discourage these same thoughts
yeah it's the same way so what i bring up the image i like to
bring up is um so with a child
or the young child um who's misbehaving perhaps or or not be
i don't want to say misbehaving but you know there's something behavior that's challenging
you know you don't beat up the child to to shape them up right you want them to
feel safe you want to offer them safety and then with as
they feel safe so that so that they wouldn't hide any mistakes from you because if they're not
safe they will hide mistakes from you they'll hate you they'll run away
no they won't so you need to offer the the child inside you safety and say oh
sweetie this is not a good idea please don't do this so it is a it is a wise balance so
you offer safety instead of trying to push them like beat yourself into shape
yes you're safe you're doing the best you can and yet you have a certain
um you have certain values or intention so you turn you try to learn you try to
steer the ship you're trying to to learn um again back to the example of
the child you want to be clear of what is desirable what is desirable and yet you do
you don't want to beat up the kid so that's the same idea bill so you offer safety
like oh i see you i see you i see you i see yes yes this is not very helpful
dear this this this as you put in your question negative thoughts um this is not very helpful dear yeah i
see where this is coming from i see where this is coming from cause and conditions and yet it's not very helpful it's not very inspiring
so that's what i suggest working with them
and yes
love your comment erica yes lovely and then ben says it is so important for
parents to take care of their inner child yes indeed jerry says it helped when you said that
life is uncertain and this made it realistic then wishes of goodness and safety to yourself and
to others made this real despite the uncertainty
thank you jerry yeah i really appreciate how that landed for you exactly so we're not trying to
disregard um impermanence yes it is impermanent it's
we don't know and yet we offer this wish of safety and goodness and bill says thank you you are welcome
bill hope that was helpful for you yeah thank you all for your reflections
and for your practice yeah also gratitude coming on youtube
gyro from sending your name right here welcome glad you're with us on on youtube
so dear ones the invitation for practicing in sangha is to practice and see how we can
offer ourselves safety and offer other safety can we make ourselves safe for others
just listening to them with care and also offering safety to ourselves so
that we don't have self-judgment oh i shouldn't have said that oh and if that comes up it's okay can you
offer that safety offer yourself safety with that this is a really important practice so i hope you stay and practice in this
way this is a great sandbox these small groups that we do with supportive
community which we can then take to the world if you have to go you have child care etc thank you for
practicing come back soon but if you can stay please do all right so i will create
the breakout rooms and here we go um
[Music] let's see
all right so the rooms are being opened now
let's start with 15 seconds of meta for each other here you go
god that's so cool hi everyone welcome back
the rooms are closed so we have a couple minutes for reflections
for what you notice what you learned so please you can raise your zoom hand if
you like or type in chat how was it what was it
like what did you discover
i would love to hear your your wisdom if you would be so kind to
share your wisdom or questions with the sangha
i see some smiles
jerry says just wishing the folks in the group meta made me feel safe ah
great great insight jerry that i love
you um saying this because actually when we wish meta for other people we feel safe
isn't that amazing isn't that interesting so what you just shared is is really profound
really profound in fact it is said that that's why the buddha
taught uh this practice to begin with for safety for a sense of safety you you
wish meta for others you feel safe it's it's wild so great great i so appreciate you bringing
that that in um bill says i found this a very satisfying experience thank you very
calming you're welcome bill glad you're here practicing sarah says to me safety and love aren't
the same thing but safety is a prerequisite for feeling love and giving love beautiful thank you sarah for that
exploration to see that for you one is the prerequisite of the other great
whatever you discover is is fine is great is your own discovery there's no right answer here or wrong
answer gita says for the first time for me the need to say i in all of this
diminished it was less personal the relationship to difficult emotions
ah very interesting would you say a little
more guitar why you what do yeah sorry i'm muting myself it was interesting because when
i tried to be in my body and experience the space for
emotions the ones you mentioned and then you brought in the phrases of
may i feel safe suddenly i thought it wasn't necessary it just was felt more natural to
experience this as there is safety or may there be space for safety which then
also made it less important to distinguish between being safe for others as and self to my
for myself um i conceptually i guess that makes sense
and it's quite common i think to talk about uh
in our in our general sort of community may there be safety or may there be this but i must
admit for the first time i was seeing that there is a possibility of dropping the eye
fantastic fabulous thank you for sharing that yeah beautiful may there be safety just
feeling your safety well when that self-referential frame just as you described it that drops in there is
no need for it it's just offering safety internally externally
just safety internally it's beautiful thank you guitar i'm delighted
yay yay that that insight came up beautiful kathleen says it seems that
being and feeling safe with myself will enable the vulnerability needed to
love more beautiful thank you kathleen great insight yes and jeannie says wish machine turns
healing oh oh may you may you heal may you heal terence yeah
yeah so i i was about to read that publicly but maybe i want anyway
it is time it's 702 so thank you all for your practice may you all be safe
may you all be may there be safety for everyone all of us all beings
everywhere may all beings be free may all beings be happy including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone what a pleasure and privilege to practice with you thank
you