so good day everyone and welcome to our sunday morning sitting
and as we begin this sitting i would like to evoke i believe it's an
important principle not only of buddhist meditation
that we teach here and but also of the dharma the teachings of the buddha
um you know certainly i think have been important
part of my practice life and that is the principle
of simplicity that
even though sometimes the dharma the teachings might seem complicated if that's the case
the hope we have is that their purpose is to point to simplicity perhaps sometimes we're
complicated because people are complicated and so to explain to point back to a
simple way of being a simplicity of being a simplicity of freedom
that sometimes we meet the complexity with complexity
but to keep in back of the mind you know where is it pointing to that is simple the simplicity of
non-clinging the simplicity of just being with the experience
with clear vision with clear seeing it's kind of like turning our gaze
upon whatever is happening and having that gaze
be easeful relaxed at peace with what we see
the gaze itself our wisdom might
see the complexity of the situation or wisdom might tell us
what should or shouldn't be done
but not to confuse or entangle the wisdom with the gays
wisdom with clear seeing
and to have this foundation of simplicity as a simple presence
within which wisdom can operate so to take
assume a posture that is appropriate for you
in allowing your body some ease some simplicity of being
hopefully where there's not much struggle physically to be present
a posture that allows the body to be still
for this duration
and if there is no such posture then it's fine to do this meditation
as a form of walking meditation back and
forth and then giving some care
to settling into this posture maybe moving the body a little bit
rotating swaying back and forth maybe even lifting the shoulders up as
high as you're comfortable and then letting them relax
and settle and then gently closing the eyes
and feeling the foundation under you the solidity the hardness the
firmness that supports the weight of your body
such a simple everyday phenomenon that we we live with we navigate through
and which in meditation we rely on to help us settle in
the pull of gravity the weight of our body
is something we yield ourselves to and that in the place where the body
makes contact with that support feeling the ground feeling grounded
there rooted
and then further up maybe to soften the belly relax your belly
sometimes when you soften relax the belly let it hang forward and down
there's a little bit more of a foundation a base a groundedness
in the lower torso
and then softening in the chest softening around the heart
you exhale relaxing the shoulders softening the shoulders
releasing the shoulders to the pull of
gravity
and then also as you exhale to soften the muscles of your face
the jaws maybe by having the mouth
just open a teeny bit more than it is maybe the lips are still touching but
the teeth a little bit fall away from each other
relaxing the cheeks and the muscles around the eyes
letting the eyes eyeballs rest in their sockets
and then you're softening relaxing around the forehead
the temples and even if it doesn't relax easily
maybe on the exhale can be some softening around that area
even if it's just the softening of the way we hold it that we're aware of it
and then behind the forehead between the ears the area of the brain
feeling whatever sensations there might be there of energy agitation pressure
contraction hardness
and if there's any of those things than on the exhale softening
the brain relaxing that energy
and as you do so
quieting the thinking mind
and notice whatever is simple about being here with a modicum of
silence where there's nothing to figure out or attain or do
but to rest with some ease in the simplicity of this moment
uh
and then within the simplicity of the moment to
just center yourself in the body breathing with whatever way it's easy for you or
right for you for awareness to be aligned attuned
to the body breathing
and no matter how complicated the mind gets with thoughts and ideas
keep returning to the simplicity of breathing breathing here
and see how simple you can become so simple perhaps that
desires fall away aversions fall away
expectations fall away
ideas of what is should be and shouldn't be fall away
simplicity where in which everything is allowed to be just the way it is
and we gaze upon it kindly
we breathe with it breathe through it without getting entangled
just here sitting breathing
knowing
being simple with how things are
if you've wondered often thought chances are that's a more complicated
world concerns than the simplicity of just
being here being here alive
being here breathing
as if that's enough for just these minutes
and that and then as we come to the end of the sitting
maybe using your imagination a little bit and imagine what it would be like
to maintain a simplicity of being
a kind of radical simplicity with a kind and clear gaze
of what's happening not needing to understand not needing to
fix not needing to explain not needing to defend but to really just be
with clearly with what's happening with someone else
what is it like to sit quietly with someone on a park bench maybe it's talking simply and chatting
but offering just a simplicity of being
contentment and ease with being alive as if for a few moments
at least just to be alive is enough alive and breathing
and perhaps with that simplicity of being maybe our good will can be simple as
well a simple warmth and goodness
friendliness that doesn't have to be actively expressed and
doesn't have to be explained but a good will and a generosity of
spirit a friendliness and a love a care
that maybe is part and parcel of that simplicity
and maybe staying simple to end this sitting
with tapping into whatever wish you have for others to live well
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
and may it be that we contribute to that
and may it be that our practice contributes to that possibility
you