so warm greetings from greetings for the
this meditation session our time together and for the beginning of this week
and as we begin get ready for this meditation
i would like to offer a wonderful principle
of practice and that is that the dharma practice unfolds
most harmoniously when the means of practice
contains some of the goal so that the means are not dramatically
different than the goal but that the goal is found in the means itself
in the practice even for someone who is practicing for the first time today that it isn't that there's a goal
far in the distance that we can attain so much as i mean there is but that
we can discover uh some of those qualities even in the first time we sit down to
meditate and it's many qualities of awakening
but one of the qualities of awakening is awakening itself the simplicity of being aware
of what's happening and simply being aware being aware without an agenda without
trying to go for a goal and attain something
a quality of awakening is an absence of greed
an absence of insistence and ideas of should i have to do this i should do this it
should be this way i want to attain this i want to do there's a kind of it could be a drive
to want and awakening also has an absence of resistance
an absence of being in contention with reality sit and meditate
free of contention and so here we are
and to be aware with the generosity of allowing each
thing that arises each experience we have to allow it to be as it is
liberation the goal of practice maybe is understood less as you become
liberated as it is everything becomes liberated from you
everything is becomes free of your needs your expectations your projections your ideas your
your associations and that's particularly valuable when
it's really being having an intimacy and a connection to what's happening here with ourselves
to really be intimate and here and connected and deeply respectful enough
to allow each thing its freedom so to begin this process to
take a to enter into
to enter into our posture
and to gently close your eyes
too gently
now enter into your posture and make small adjustments
both to feel more comfortable in your posture and maybe more alert
but also to awaken in your body to bring a sense of
attention alive in your body itself
and take a few long slow deep breaths
these long slow deep breaths at the beginning can be a ritual reminder that awakening happens
here and now that awakening is some aspect of being
fully present here
now
and as you exhale to settle into now and here
curious interested in this awakening and freedom
that can only be found here and now
and letting your breath letting your breathing return to normal
relaxing your belly
relaxing your chest
relaxing your face
awakening the goal of practice has a quality an aspect of deep
relaxation or an absence of tension
contraction and to relax at the beginning of meditation
is not an elementary beginning practice
to begin the process of being attuned and in harmony
with awakening itself
and then to settle into the body breathing
what is it what would it be like for you to have an intimacy with your breathing
with the body's experience of breathing
where that intimacy and attention shared qualities of freedom
liberation freedom from shoulds
freedoms from resistance to anything
freedom from contention and struggles with how things are
freedom for need from things freedom from needing things to be different at this moment
an awareness that grants each experience its freedom
freedom from us and our ideas and desires each particular thing that occurs in the
present moment in our body and our mind and our hearts
allowing it to be without being
involved in it entangled
just letting it be here
in its own simplicity
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to see if you bring into your mind the people of
your life the ones you know of the ones you imagine in the world
the peoples of your community and if you imagine meeting them
with an awakened mind or awakened heart one in which there's no fear
no contention no opposition no hostility no
defensiveness no greed being settled and content and happy in
your own heart and to open your heart to
meet and be aware of people around you
and what would it be like if there are qualities of liberation or freedom
awakening in how you meet others
how you encounter them an encounter that's free of
clinging need resistance just present
but not in danger of succumbing to the demands of others
not in the danger of
getting entangled in those relationships because you're at home and resting in
your own awareness
and perhaps then in the safety of an awakened heart
to offer your good will to others
your sense of care and generosity
may it be that people i know could be happy
may it be that they could be safe
may it be that they can be peaceful and free
may it be that they can feel deeply safe and at ease and happy in themselves
and may it be that from whatever awakening or inner freedom
we have that we live our life for the welfare
and benefit of others
may we ourselves and all beings
share in happiness safety peace and freedom
so in these almost 70 sessions we've gone through
the 16 steps of mindfulness of breathing
and the most famous discourse where i have where these
16 steps occur is actually in a discourse that has much more in it
and it has a second half where the practice is discussed as how it
follows up how it continues after being well established in 16 steps
or it continues and describes part of the wider kind of unfolding
that happens while we're doing the 16 steps and somehow the second half presents
more richness and fullness to it and partly it does so
by harmonizing bringing together and showing how other aspects of early buddhist
practice come into play in doing mindfulness or breathing
and in particular there's two and that is the four foundations of mindfulness how they how
the four foundations of mindfulness are fulfilled through this breathing meditation and how it leads to
the seven factors of awakening and um inherent in this discussion
that's a here's you know this second half of the instructions or this description of
practice is uh is something that's called the
onward leading nature of the dharma there's a very famous description of the
dharma where it says that it's uh immediate
inviting inspection onward leading to be known for oneself and um
but this onward leading uh the word for onward leading could also imply kind of like it carries it carries
us along so uh it isn't so much that we're the agent
of developing and growing in the practice as as we enter the dharma stream
we enter the stream of meditation and somehow the meditation the dharma carries us along
and a kind of very simple way of understanding that this in one aspect is that most people
spend their days preoccupied maybe with tension and attachment wanting and the mind racing and spinning
and afraid or or angry resentful all kinds of ways in
which we're caught in phenomena and activities and and so there's a lot of tension
physical tension emotional tension mental tension and if we begin to relax
that all that preoccupation all that entanglement with everything then um it isn't just that we
then nothing happens but there starts to being an unwinding a dissolving
of fading away of attachment and that fading away that's a dissolving
of attachment begins to change there's an onward movement onward moving
phenomenon and that as we change things open up within us that qualities
and capacities we have that were submerged or repressed by our fears our attachments our
preoccupations our entanglements have a chance to begin showing
themselves and they become stronger and stronger and um it isn't so much that we're trying to
make them become stronger but they begin unfolding and moving and uh and we it's wonderful to feel
in meditation slowly day by day or whatever way we might feel it that
there's a kind of an opening um a kind of um releasing a growing and
maturing of something quite beautiful inside that
is kind of like a plant that has finally come into the sun sunlight it's been in
the dark for a long long time and the plant grows and it just flowers
and this natural uh kind of that description of a flower coming to full blossom
is part of it is inherent is inherent in the in the teachings of
the buddha where there's kind of over and over again a reference to an organic movement growth unfolding
flowing of phenomena as we enter into this dharma path
the one of them is in fact the growth of a fl of a plant we can cultivate the plant but we don't
tug on it to make it grow uh a frequent frequent metaphor is that
of a of a river or stream coming down from a mountain if it rains in the mountaintop the rain
rains enough then the rain the raindrops start to flow down the side of the mountain
they join together and form little streamlets and streamlets become streams the streams become rivers the rivers
become you know bigger and bigger until finally they come down to the plains
and become wide big silent rivers just flowing along into the ocean and
that water has its natural flow and flow of gravity and that metaphor is used for the for
getting into the stream the flow of the dharma it will carry us along and as we kind of
go into the dharma these qualities become bigger and bigger something inside of us becomes bigger and stronger
and also much more silent and the metaphor of silence is the silence that happens within when
there's no conceit when we're not no longer caught up and preoccupied with me myself
and mine it isn't doesn't mean that we're physically silent but it means that there's a silencing of
this kind of extra agitation that uh spills over into the world in
all kinds of noisy ways and so this flow down the river uh
that uh entering the stream is one of the metaphors that uh with the first experience of
real liberation real freedom a person has changed forever because now they know what the stream is they know
where the current is they know the both directions and how to be in that current
that's going to carry us onward to full liberation and so um the onward leading nature
of the dharma in the anapan assad and there's one way that concentration
practices onward leading and another way that
insight practice is onward leading and the two go together and the concentration practice is
armored leading is described as the there's the arising of gladness
when we're no longer caught up in the hindrances no longer the mind is no longer
distracted all the time and the glad that we're finally present
that gladness is the condition out of which flows
joy and if we really feel that joy it's a condition that out of which flows
a deeper tranquility relaxing a calming
and with that deeper calming there is happiness and with happiness there arises
concentration and the way that this these five gladness joy
tranquility happiness and concentration are talked about in the suit dozen in buddha's teaching
they are not something that the meditator is doing and making happen directly but rather
we're creating the conditions where this onward leading movement through gladness joy tranquility
happiness and concentration can unfold on its own and
and and then that's the concentration path the inside path as described best i
think by the last four steps of the mindfulness of breathing that there is
um insight observation observing
inconstancy there's a fading away of attachments that depend on things
having more constancy there's the ending cessation of
certain attachments and then there's the letting go the relinquishing
of you know of our investment belief in those attachments
and so this that also is described more of a natural flow it's not something we do but something
we're observing and watching happen and so in anapanasati the
the flow of practice moves through concentration and then
leads this insight of deep observing observing and the but the
what the meditator does all along mostly is just staying with the breath being with the
breath and there's a little intentionality to just stay focused stay focused in the
breath which is expressed in the repeated way
in which the grammar of a for the phrase is uh having to do with being mindful of
breathing occurs it says one trains
two says and then there's a quotation like this is what i'm doing and saying to myself i will breathe in
when trains i will breathe out one will engage over and over again no
matter what happens as we go through all these 16 stages we're not getting sidetracked by anything
we're allowing all the other things to happen in the onward leading nature and we're recognizing allowing the the
tranquility the relaxation the joy the happiness the gladness the concentration the
liberations the observations that happen but each all along the dedication is
simplicity of just staying with a breath i will breathe in i will breathe out
i will stay connected to it this is where the home is for people doing mindfulness or
breathing it's not exclusive the attention is open and aware
so that this wider field gets allowed to manifest and to grow the dharma that's
onward leading can appear but to keep us relaxed and not caught in
anything not preoccupied we keep staying with the breath in a relaxed
open committed way not clinging to it but just kind of staying open but
staying there so we don't get drift off and get caught in other things
and if we have this relaxed open uh steady continuous dedication
love for devotion for just breathing one breath at a time and of course we'll get
distracted but just whenever we can to come back i will stay here with the breathing
this is what i'm doing then this we start entering into the dharma which is onward leading the
flow that begins to unfold and uh and one of the things that it
unfolds into this is uh uh the
the uh the core aspect of the four foundations of mindfulness
and um and how this mindfulness of breathing connects with four foundations will be the topic for tomorrow
so uh thank you so much and um and i hope that
you will be open to
not being the agent of change not to be the one in charge of making things
happen and fixing things all the time but you go through the day with some room to allow things to unfold
to allow yourself to unfold to make room for yourself and room for
the dharma that you can't do if you're just constantly caught up in being in charge or being the agent or
being the subject of your preoccupations so thank you