so good morning everyone and welcome and
there is a um some of us a surprising aspect of
this meditation practice and uh
there's a pro one of the surprising aspects is that it benefits a lot
from not doing anything or undoing a lot of the doings that we
do stress is often a symptom of
over activity in the mind the heart it involves tension and stress always
involves some kind of something is activated and so to be stressed or be tense
something has contracted or gotten tight or overused or exhausted
turns out that a lot of emotions that emotions that are stressful
are not just uh sitting around we're just sitting doing nothing and they kind of just
glide through effortlessly and are there for a while effortlessly at some point they effortlessly leave
the difficult emotions are uh activities they're processes that
are maybe we don't say that we personally are involved in are doing
but something about our being is involved in doing them we're activated in some way and
chasing after certain thoughts involved in certain thoughts involved in certain desires and
involved with memories and involved with aversions and preferences
and uh and so a big part of meditation is undoing
is beginning to let go of all the doings the activities that what goes on
and some people who have a strong habit for doing will overdo meditation
they'll just transfer their tendency i have to fix something i have to do something and make something happen
and engage in an overactive way to meditate and that just keeps us
agitated so an important part of meditation is learning to
the art of doing less sometimes teachers will say do nothing
but be alert alert and nothing else
the um and uh so
i wonder for this meditation whether [Music]
we have to do some things we have to for example sit down and assume a meditation
posture and ideally take time to find a posture that is
suitable for being alert given whatever conditions you have physically and mentally
emotionally but to promote alertness to be
aware in a way that feels like we're clearly aware
and to remain that way but to remain that way maybe by mostly
letting go of all the other doings that take us away
if we start thinking about something yesterday think about yesterday then we're involved in an activity
if we're planning for tomorrow not only are we involved in those thoughts but it might be fueled by
anxiety and that anxiety is not
effortless it involves something in our system which is activated and doing
and so what can we let go of
what can we stop doing and the ending of a lot of doing
is not nothing but allows this psychophysical system that we are
to operate in the most healthy way possible it's stress and excessive doing that
interferes with the natural kind of healing and healthful healthness
of this being of ours so
um to assume then a comfortable alert posture
and to begin with relaxation is um
his process of beginning to let go of a certain kinds of doings
certain kind of activities that are not only physical but express something that's happening mentally
and so to gently close the eyes
and so that the relaxation maybe can be a little fuller
you might take a deep long inhale so in that deep inhale
you really feel more of the body than you usually do
it's like entering more fully into the realm of your body as you breathe in deeply
and with that connection to your body on the exhale to let go
to relax
for a moment or two to do nothing except to
let go and let go with the exhale
and then letting the breathing return to normal
and on the exhale
i kind of think of the inhale as more of a doing and the exhale is more of a not doing
letting go of doing so on that exhale
to relax more of your body recognizing doing so you're relaxing
something deep inside as well maybe you can even
sense and feel how relaxing the body does something
good for the rest of our inner life
relaxing the muscles of the face
relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the belly
relaxing maybe the whole body in some global way
on the exhale maybe just maybe you can release the grip of
anxiety you might be holding
maybe you can release the grip of resentment
or hostility you're holding
and maybe you can let go of any way you're holding on onto or
leaning into sadness and grief
and then to settle into your breathing
in a way of doing less with breath meditation
maybe do less is too
at the beginning of the inhale
to imagine that the body is receiving
the sensations of breathing in
that you're not actively going how to feel the inhale
your awareness is receiving
your settle back and open up and receive
and that at the top of the inhale
to allow the exhale
to allow the exhale to begin
and get out of the way allow it to proceed
receiving the inhale allowing the exhale
and if the mind starts getting involved in thinking that's a doing
that's not needed and maybe you can relax the thinking
mind
relax the reactive mind
relax the stress in the mind
and then receive the inhale
and allow the exhale and all you do is accompany
this process of breathing stay there accompany it intimately
ah
[Music]
be being alert enough to notice when you're doing something
unnecessary
unnecessary thinking unnecessary acting unnecessary stress
and either let go of it or lessen the intensity of it
quieting the mind
and the receiving of the inhale can be expanded to sitting here doing
nothing but receiving the present moment
trusting there's so little to do but be aware of how things occur
receiving it
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
there's a wonderful reciprocity of receiving and giving
not the giving that is willful or assertion of self or trying to do the
right thing but rather
it is the giving that wells up from this
receptive quiet non-doing place with which we can be aware
the simplicity of giving
where they say that they talk about the emptiness of the giver the receiver and the gift
meaning the lack of a lot of assertion judgments needs
the absence of reifying self or other and
close to a natural welling up of generosity and care and
love compassion and may it be that on this day
that you explore a little bit what it's like to
be in a receptive mode to take in situations you're in more
fully without the assertion of self for the contraction of self
to receive do less then
see if there's a natural giving
a caring a good will that might be there as well
and may it be so may this practice that we do tap us into the wellsprings
of love of care generosity goodness
that is found within us so that we can live this life
contributing to a better world for everyone
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be free
and may we contribute to that
[Music] thank you
so continuing on the theme of emotions
i think if us english-speaking people might have a lot of focus on emotions
some people more than others some people that's where their life
primarily is focused the reference point for the life less than what they're thinking about is what
they're feeling and some people have manifestos that they
have composed maybe in their head about celebrating emotions the importance of them and really kind of
really get into them in a big way some people are afraid of their emotions or they
feel like they have to keep them very private and are very you know
reserved about showing anything or even knowing it through themselves
and you know hold their emotions at bay so we can talk about it that way as if
emotions are something i find it uh fascinating that if you go
back i've gone back and tried to search in the language of the buddha
for a word that's equivalent to the english word emotions and it's hard to find maybe you can kind
of squeeze something out and say it's similar to what we call it english word emotion but the fact that there is no
word or it's hard to find a word that really fits points out that maybe the english word
emotion is just a convention it's a label it's a kind of a way of
categorizing a certain realm of human experience and that we in
kind of in our local english cultures um have you know if you take the the pie of
human experience and that pie can be sliced into many different kinds of slices many sizes and
different choices about where the lines of the pies pieces are made
so we take the whole human experience and as a whole
and it can be divided and looked at in different ways and maybe different cultures have different slices they take
out and for some reason here in the english speaking world we have this slice called
emotions but it's not something that's inherently like a thing or a
set thing it has kind of vague boundaries what actually is an emotion
um so uh the uh
the uh but i think one of the things to be looking at when we do this practice is
not to have a clear opinion or you know or a policy around emotions but
rather to always look more closely to see emotions just kind of like a pointer just gets us into the territory
of something and then we need to kind of study it more carefully be more present explore
it more deeply and as we explore it one of the things
to notice is what are the emotions that come along with stress
come along with some kind of attention
tightness contraction something that feels unpleasant what emotions come along with
a whole realm of what can be called dukkha in buddhism stress tension unpleasantness pain
suffering and and which of them come without
and when in your life is there an emotion that is kind of stress-free
a state of mind an emotion a mood a feeling that comes without any stress any tension
any tightness any unpleasantness any dukkha or suffering
and and which are the ones that are more painful which are the ones that are more pleasant and enjoyable
and and the ones that are stressful and sometimes in buddhism are called
afflictive because of the pain that they cause it doesn't it's not necessarily a value
judgment that they're wrong or bad it just means that that's what they come with
and if when they're afflictive when there are are um
come with stress the interesting question is um does the stress need to be there
is is the stress in addition to the emotion or to what's happening or the
state is even the emotion itself that we're having in addition to something that's
happening that covers it over or or or
overrides in such a way that we're not really in touch with the deeper wellsprings of what's happening in our
life the offsprings of wisdom receptivity registering seeing what's happening
and and probably what you'll find is that there's a lot of extra doing
when we are involved in these reactive emotions afflictive emotions
these um ones that are kind of uncomfortable or stressful
and if we can see it as a doing as an activity then we can put a question mark at the
end of it and say does this doing this activity need to happen
and and uh and sometimes even pleasant emotions
enjoyable ones or ones that are celebrated um they're not stress free
because of attachments or clingings or agendas or wants or desires or fears
that come along with a pleasant one as well so this idea of becoming sensitive to
the stress sensitive to the unpleasantness that comes along
has a great value because then we can begin addressing it we can begin or
undressing it maybe is a better word we can begin undressing the extra layers
of activity that we put on top of situations it takes a fair amount of trust
to not do takes a fair amount of trust to settle back and allow ourselves to feel and
sense and step away from the doing the activity the straining the directing of
attention the mind feelings that goes on but the the
the gift of that is that this psychophysical being that we are
moves towards health when it's not stressed out it moves towards a deeper sensitivity
and deeper wisdom about our life
when when that wisdom is not overridden or eclipsed
by overactive mind over stressed mind over
agitated mind and i've certainly had an overstressed over-activated over-agitated mind
and at least in me i could see that it fools me
and it fools me this way that um uh it pulls me into thinking what i'm
thinking about is really important what i'm concerned with is really important and i have to and it's really you know i
have to be involved in it i have to be thinking about i have to be chasing after it or fixing doing something
and it's a kind of a self-fulfilling idea because as i feel stressed
the i feel uncomfortable and then there's a reaction i have to fix this discomfort so i have to have to
think more get more involved in all this and something has to happen here because
that's part of sometimes the the the call of stressful say something needs to
happen here and so there's a pull into being more stressed
and then if i go and relax it settle down meditate
that then i find that actually i was tricked into thinking all this stuff out
that the stress was uh was it so i had a huge influence impact on
how i see the world how i see myself the situation that was not wise and that in
fact it might have been a little bit diluted and so to be able to undo
to not address something but to undress something in the mind just quiet down
settle down become more peaceful and practice kind of an undoing
meditation as an undoing as a as a rather than a doing
rather than addressing the issues of a lie of our life it's a kind of an undressing the issues of our life
and um so that and then something begins to flow or move or
arise that restores us to emotional health
that is a restoration of a deeper sensitivity a deeper understanding a deeper wisdom
that can only be there if we're settled and peaceful only be there or say it differently so
we don't over emphasize the importance of being peaceful because that can be dangerous too if you hold on to that as
being the way to be so much of this uh ancient buddhist
wisdom has not so much about being something even like being peaceful
but has to do with um of trusting
not doing not doing greed not doing attachment not doing hate not doing delusion
not doing stress not doing not pumping up
anxiety not doing our emotions not leaning into them and feeding them and fueling them
with the stories that we do there's this deep undoing and um and
then there starts being room for the blood to flow more freely in their body it's not contracted by
tension in the muscles there's more ease for the neurons perhaps
to to uh you know flow more smoothly and and um
without being i don't know what happens with them but everything flows more the feeling of flow is
a very common experience as they settle in deep and well
so so as we relax we talked about on monday
as we learn to recognize more deeply as we learn to respect these emotions
that we have then at some point at some point we can begin
to allow in a deep way trust in a deep way
so that we don't have to do so much it becomes an undoing a non-doing
and a non-doing is not inconsequential it allows the wellsprings of some of the
best qualities we have to come forward and you know it's not your best
qualities if it comes with stress it comes with feelings of unpleasantness and
tension contraction if it comes with forcefulness and assertiveness
the most beautiful qualities are not assertive but they are powerful
and they're freeing so restoration of a healthy emotional
life it's one of the great things to do so thank you
very much and we have one more talk on emotions tomorrow