okay so we'll go ahead and get started
my name is kim allen and i've been teaching at imc for a while diana
is teaching a retreat this evening at insight retreat center so i'll be stepping in for her
so why don't we go ahead and begin as usual with a guided meditation so
allowing yourself to settle in to have a sense of arriving
maybe taking a long slow deep breath just allowing the body and mind to
settle on the out breath
if you're comfortable doing so you can close your eyes
just gently feeling the body in the sitting posture
upright and also relaxed
so we allow the attention to come inward
you can begin to connect in with the body
inviting ease through the body
so softening the muscles of the face around the eyes around the mouth
relaxing the eyes and the eye sockets
releasing any tension in the jaw
down through the neck
letting the shoulders gently drop
relax soften
down into the chest area the belly
letting the belly be round soft
all these places where we tend to hold tension
letting go of any bracing in the legs
and extending awareness all the way into the hands and the feet
inviting softness and ease through the body
and then similarly we can invite ease in the mind
so we bring in a gentle awareness mindfulness of our experience
in a very simple way
even if parts of the body or the mind are not at ease we can be at ease with that
offering simple attention
often we will notice that there are thoughts in the mind
thinking going on
it can be so easy to wish that the thinking weren't there or
to feel somehow that the thinking is getting in the way
of meditation
if only my mind weren't thinking then i could have a peaceful sitting
but this very wishing for it not to be there as a way of also being agitating for the
mind
so perhaps beginning this sit with the idea that thinking is not the
enemy
actually thinking is very normal
that's what minds do
so perhaps seeing the thinking as a natural process when we notice it
ah there it is again
gently letting go and knowing knowing the thought
it's enough to be mindful that there is
thinking
even a simple thought like thinking is what minds do or thinking is natural
it's a thought but it's a beneficial one
actually not all thought is unskillful
so continuing to rest the mind and the body the breath
i'm seeing any thought that arises simply as natural
it may be that simply having this less aversive
view of thought already reduces its intensity
even when the mind gets caught up as soon as we realize that
just recognizing that thought is normal
perhaps adding a good thought about the fact that we're sitting here
meditating i'm returning to the breath of the body
no sense of diminishment of our meditation
sitting with the normal flow of mind and body is meditation
you
as our connection to the breath and the body
becomes even a little bit more continuous as we sit
it may become possible to breathe through any thoughts
that arise in the mind
we sense the feelings of the breath
even while the thought is there
like wind blowing through a cloth that's out on a line drying
thought is there and the breath just passes through it in and out
another way of seeing it is to imagine the breath or the body in the foreground
and any thoughts other such movements of mind to be in
the background
still somewhat there but just in the background
just gently favoring the present moment experience
letting the thoughts ripple in the
background
from time to time checking in again with the body
softening any tension that may have built up
allowing the breath to flow throughout the body
and even through the thoughts that arise
imagining that we could relax the thinking muscle
and in the last five minutes of our meditation together
i will offer a reflection [Music]
question the aim is not to think about it
but more like when we drop a stone down into a well
[Music] a sound will come back
and we just let that ripple through the body the heart the mind
and then go back to the silence
so i'll ask the question [Music] and you just see what comes back listen
to it but let it pass by and then i will ask the question again
what about the dharma touches my heart
what about the dharma
touches my heart
perhaps the answer was simple perhaps it was different first
and second time perhaps it had no words and was just a
feeling or a body sensation
these reflections are a skillful use of the
thinking mind the mind with language
once more what about the dharma
touches my heart
so a warm welcome to everyone here
as i mentioned earlier diana is away for the evening teaching on retreat so i'm
happy to be here with you this evening my name is kim allen
i want to talk tonight about thought perhaps in a different way
though then you may have heard we definitely use thought all the time
in daily life but it's also easy in meditation
to see that thought is usually what distracts us in some way we lose our mindfulness
because we start thinking so then it's easy some people conclude
from this that thinking is always bad or that the aim of meditation is somehow
to eliminate thinking thinking wine can only be a hindrance
but actually that idea is not in line with the buddhist teachings
the buddha had a more nuanced view of thought and its role in the normal functioning
as well as in the awakening of the mind there's a place for thought on the path
of development so he identified which kinds of thought
are actually unskillful and unhelpful and he also talked about kinds of
thought that are helpful that are skillful some of them might even be necessary
along the path of liberation so i will talk somewhat about
unskillful thought because it's something that we're very familiar with and it's an important
thing to to have some sense of how to work with but i want to leave plenty of room
to talk about the helpful kinds of thought and conceptuality that we can do
because we don't get to hear about those quite as much and there are a number of them described
in the buddhist teachings now in the end what you may have heard
from teachers is correct in that the ordinary thinking and conceptualizing mind
is a hindrance to freedom at some point and it will be let go
maybe we'll even develop some alternatives to it along the path but nonetheless even concepts and
thinking have a function along our path of meditation and in
daily life i think we're going to need our whole mind to awaken
and so that would include thought so let's look more carefully at what is useful in the thinking mind
and what is not so starting with
how we often experience our mind at least at the beginning of our spiritual development and often for
many people at the beginning of a sit all along the path what we experience is a lot of
discursive what's called discursive or obsessive excessive thought where the mind is
going over conversations it's making plans it's worrying about what that person might have meant by
what they did yesterday we're sort of caught up in that and it usually comes with a lot of
largely unseen views about the world and about ourselves
and all of that and a lot of this thought is kind of running along habitual patterns
most of this kind of thought is not especially original and we've probably thought it before
and if we look more carefully we can see that a lot of it is about myself and is essentially
based somehow in wanting or not wanting or not being very clear so this kind of
unhelpful thought which i'm just going to call discursive thinking this is the kind that is um
at the beginning of a sit shall we say and it kind of dominates our mental experience and so because of this
thinking it's a bad rap it just sort of gets a blanket statement of ah this is not useful let it go
try not to think try to get concentrated and not do that
but with that kind of attitude if we have that idea that all thought is
like that we set up a lot of aversion in the mind and this can actually just further entrench our
tendency to think right as soon as we say you know don't think of a purple elephant that's all you're going to think about right so
if you say don't think or stop all those conversations in the mind and get concentrated
there's a way in which that's not an effective approach yes so it's unfortunate because some people
can get caught in this aversive dynamic of hating their thoughts for a long time
and but if we look at the early buddhist texts there's a more nuanced understanding of
the thinking mind thinking as i as i said in the guided meditation thinking is what minds do
it's a normal function of the mind so this kind of normal ordinary thought
that we have sort of top of mind can be skillful
or unskillful it can actually be either one of those so i would say that maybe the initial
task of practice is that if we have a lot of the discursive kind of thought is that we somehow have to
reduce that and enhance the skillful part uh which is no form of right effort
essentially so instead of thinking in terms of let's get rid of all the thought or let's
quiet all that down how about if we try to change the balance so that more of the thought was skillful
and less of it was unskillful that's often a good way to start so we
can start to explore this different kinds of thinking by distinguishing
the content of the thought from its qualities let's say so the content
is what we're thinking about it's about our friend or that thing that happened yesterday or
the problem we have with our work that's the content of the thought but then the qualities have to do more
with the energy behind the thought how intense it is uh the manner of the thought what's the
tone of it and the experience of that thinking you know how are we relating to it in some
way so the kinds of thought that are hindering our spiritual practice the ones that i
mentioned earlier they have a certain set of qualities that we can identify
um most obviously they're disconnected from present moment awareness discursive
thought is about then and there it's not really about here and now
so they feel kind of distant or vague they're yeah they're not connected
secondly they tend to be sticky they they catch the mind and draw it in that's why we get
sucked into this kind of discursive thought again and again it has a hook somehow a stickiness to it and then
thirdly the energy of it is usually somewhat driven you know there's a feeling of i've got
to play this out you know i have to play out this conversation i have to think through this problem i have to
devise some idea about this i have to figure out why this view is correct
there's a sense of um yeah of drivenness to it so that's also
useful to know so all of this adds up to seeing oh when
we see the qualities of this unskillful thought it becomes clear why we get drawn into it so easily it has a lot of
qualities that are going to pull the mind away from a more subtle experience like the breath or the body
so we can understand that yeah it's going to be hard to turn away from discursive thought
so you can not maybe not blame yourself for that so much so instead of trying to get rid of this
kind of thought i like to talk about reducing the intensity of discursive thought as kind of our
first task in practice if you will there are a lot a lot a lot of methods for this
in the in the buddhist teachings it's clear that this has been an issue for people for a long time
so again you're not alone if this is something that you experience so it's not a focus of this talk they'll
talk about a lot of methods for working with discursive thought that
could be a whole talk in and of itself but i'll name a few of them since it's good to be reminded
so they include first and foremost breath and body awareness and that's why we talk about that so
much that's why those are the first instructions i found this to be these to be the best
remedies for discursive thought in fact the buddha says a meditator
should cultivate mindfulness of breathing for cutting off distracting thoughts that's a quote right from a suta so the
buddha was talking about this quite directly to his disciples
so breath and body are are a good choice because they're always
in the present moment they immediately take away that quality of discursive thought that is
not in the present moment that vagueness that it has but also really um there are other ways
that we can reduce the intensity so for example we can use our thinking mind for something
else we can start directing the energy into thoughts that are about the present moment and
this is the point of noting practice so you may have heard of noting practice where sometimes as we sit
we gently name or label the experiences that we're having
oh experience of sadness and experience of pressure experience of heat experience of
joy just noting as we go along a little you know simple word that goes
with what we're experiencing and that redirects some of the energy that could have gone into
unskillful thought it directs it into thought that's about the present moment it's that
simple so it reduces the intensity of that other kind of thought uh techniques like counting the breath
are the the same thing we're using our our thinking mind to be thinking about
the present moment and then um you know once we've gained a
little bit of traction we can actually turn mindfulness toward the thinking process itself
this is another good way to continue reducing the intensity of discursive thought so we can kind of turn the good part of
of our analytical mind against the part that's trying to pull us away so we can
actually gain some insight about thought by looking in this way we start to for example discern those three
qualities that i talked about earlier the uh the nebulousness the stickiness
and the drivenness of unskillful thought all of that can come about as we start
to be able to see thinking with mindfulness
so this means we can start to answer questions like how do i know if a given thought that's
coming in is one of these discursive or obsessive thoughts that's not useful or
or if it's something that would be okay you know more more beneficial to have and
we can see quite clearly that generally discursive thought just is
directed toward itself it generates more and more dispersion and it doesn't ever resolve
doesn't quite resolve meaningfully whereas in contrast thoughts that are more skillful it's
very easy still to be aware of the body it's pretty easy to breathe through them like i talked about in them
in the guided meditation so there are qualities that we can discern immediately as a thought starts to arise
as to whether or not it's going to be a discursive one and we should be very careful or if it's a somewhat more skillful
thought and we'll talk in a moment more about what kinds of skillful thoughts there are that can arise
so we can start to have just a little bit of wisdom about our thinking we could start to have more
distinction about what kinds of thoughts there are and know that some are useful and some
are not so i would say that the sort of initial part of dharma practice
and maybe the initial part of the sit for many people is to start using our analytical mind
skillfully in order to reduce the impact of this uh discursive kind of thought that's
that's vague that's sticky and that's driven
but actually we can go one step further and we can start looking at
uh certain kinds of cognition that are actually praised in sutas this is sometimes a revelation for
people to realize that they there are kinds of thoughts that are worthy of developing in their own right
so i want to focus now because i think it's rare that i it's spoken well up in dharma talks that
thought has spoken well of so let's let's talk a little bit about skillful thought
thoughts that actually help cultivate the mind so the buddha praised learning
quite highly in the sutures learning is offered as one of five
highly meritorious qualities that we can have that are said to be a form of inner
wealth in one suta in another suta it said that these are qualities that
fortify the mind so they literally strengthen it or build it up
somehow so here's the five faith or confidence virtue
learning generosity and wisdom it's an interesting list
isn't it so we have four qualities that are maybe more
common you've heard them in other lists faith virtue or ethical conduct generosity
and wisdom these are qualities that are named all over the texts and we might aspire to be developing those
in ourselves but what about this middle one learning what is that and why is that named along
alongside virtue so learning is as important as not killing not stealing it's importantness
giving it's as important as wisdom so
it's quite amazing so what does this mean now what is meant here by by learning
the word that's used there in uh in pali is actually a word that means
literally what is heard so it has to do with things that we have that we have heard
and you can understand this from the way that things were taught in the buddha's time it wasn't
that they had books most people couldn't even read or write for that matter
so if you wanted to hear teachings you wanted to learn teachings you had to go here a teacher
it was about what you could hear and the opportunity to hear the dharma was very precious actually
and so this quality of learning though is not literally just hearing like i was within earshot and it
entered my ears it has to do also with a being a little bit more active given that we couldn't take notes we couldn't
listen to the recording later we couldn't go consult a book
so learning in this this thing you've heard what is heard includes also
some sense of active listening so paying attention and kind of taking it in and integrating it
into what we know and it also includes memorizing it to some degree
remembering it well not literally memorizing it although that was done but remembering it well enough that you
would be able to use it the next day if you heard a dharma talk and had forgotten it by
time you walked home it wasn't as useful as if you could remember something about
it so this quality of learning that was praised is to have a kind of an intelligent interaction with the
teachings and that and that is what starts to change our mind
what is what starts to develop the mind in a sense so this kind of learning we can still do
you know we do it through listening to dharma talks online through taking notes maybe through reading dharma books
through reading sutas by exposing our mind again and again we may not remember everything
so well maybe not as well as they did when there was no other option but nonetheless as we hear and learn and
listen to things [Music] they kind of get into the mind in a way
and start to come into our thoughts more often you know teachings will come into our
thoughts i like to tell a story where one time i
was just in the kitchen doing washing the dishes or something and i i broke a cup and um
you know normal enough thing to have happen but immediately what came to mind was
the quote from ajahn cha where he says oh i enjoy my cup very much but for me the
cup is already broken you know indicating an understanding of impermanence but it's
you know it's a line that i had heard or read a number of times and when i broke the cup my mind said ah the cuff was already
broken so it's just a simple moment where i could have gotten angry or
you know said a swear word but instead this thought of the dharma came to mind and that's you know that's
one of the fruits of this this learning that's praised and that's a useful kind of
of uh use of the thinking mind the intelligent mind the cognitive mind the linguistic mind
all those things that we might associate with thinking which is not which is supposed to be bad but it's not
it can be used well there are also many beneficial ways to use the cognitive mind on the cushion
so the buddha for example encourage reflection on
various inspiring themes that will invoke confidence and joy so in one of the
sutas he he offers six different themes that we could reflect
on during sitting and those include the qualities of the buddha
qualities of the dharma the qualities of the sangha our own virtue our own generosity
and the fact that there are beings with well-developed minds in the world so those are the six
themes and it's interesting it's also interesting to note that the
where i said beings that have well-developed minds what we reflect on is the fact that they
have those five qualities i just mentioned we reflect that there are beings in the world who have faith virtue learning
generosity and wisdom and just knowing that there are people like that
can be inspiring and it's skillful to think about that so any of these themes is said to bring
about according to the suta inspiration and the meaning inspiration in the dharma
and joy connected with the dharma so it's interesting isn't it that
qualities heart qualities like faith like motivation and like joy
can emerge from thought so as an example um what is what are
these reflections there are specific words given for how we would reflect on each of these six themes and the one for
the for the dharma is like this the dharma is well expounded by the blessed one
to be seen here and now timeless inviting verification pertinent
to be realized by the wise for themselves so it's six qualities of the dharma and
we could just reflect on those even during sitting it's okay to reflect in this particular
way it's kind of like the question i asked what about the dharma
touches your heart in the guided meditation so there's a way in which we can use the
thinking line to uplift the heart and it says further in the suta that when we are thinking in this way
the mind is headed straight and it doesn't get distracted it's not tangled up with great hatred
and delusion and in fact it will go not only toward joy but also eventually toward concentration
which is interesting also if certain forms of reflection can eventually lead to concentration
so then we can also look into the cognitive mind's ability
to ask questions and explore the dharma in various ways so i'm talking now about
inquiry as a way of clarifying the teachings and also going deeper into our
experience so the suit does report cases of meditators sitting in meditation and it
will literally say in the suta while the venerable so and so was sitting in meditation
a certain train of thought arose in his mind his or her mind
and sometimes it will say at that point they went to ask the buddha a question
or maybe they continued meditating and later they went to ask the buddha a question about it so there are times
in which thoughts can arise kind of out of our sitting practice that are relevant for the dharma
dharma questions related to the dharma or understanding the meaning of the teachings
and we don't need to call those unskillful and say oh thinking oh bad i got distracted from the breath
again you know you don't necessarily go off on a long discursive thought trail about that but
you can remember okay my mind came up with the thought about the dharma maybe i'll look into that later
maybe i'll ask the teacher about that later that that's okay there are thoughts about the dharma that are
that can be taken seriously essentially we want to take take it seriously when our mind starts inquiring into
the meaning of the dharma so then a more modern inquiry practice
is like what we did in the sitting where we can drop in a question and it's not expected that we're going to come up with a
clear definitive answer that we could write down and carry around yes i know the answer to that question
it's really more intended as a a way to lead the mind deeper into itself
i've noticed when i do those repeating kinds of questions that sometimes the first few times i ask it i get an answer that
i kind of already knew you know kind of a cognitive answer
but then after maybe if i if i say okay thank you and i rest for a moment and ask again
i start getting answers that are no longer at the surface level maybe i didn't know some of that maybe i
surprised myself oh [Music] i didn't realize that that is also touching me about the dharma
something else and something else and eventually maybe there's even a kind of a visceral response that doesn't
have a word associated with it anymore and then we know that we're that inquiry
is leading us deeper into the mind deeper into the heart and it's helping to integrate you know
the cognitive mind with the heart with the body and that kind of integration is useful
along the path so it is clear i think from this that
well-directed thought about the dharma relating to practice has a place on the path
but it is true that this is not sufficient the buddha does say many times that the teachings cannot be fully
understood by the cognitive mind i'm going to read two different translations of a passage that's
repeated throughout the suttas about this one translation is like this
this dhamma is profound peaceful and sublime unattainable by mere reasoning to be
experienced by the wise and another translation says this
principle is deep hard to see hard to understand peaceful sublime beyond the scope of
reason subtle comprehensible to the astute
so we start to get the sense that although there is good thinking along
the path we're going to have to develop other dharma qualities also
so the next level of skillful thought if you will is to begin uh directing the attention to
stabilize the attention uh into samadhi into some gathering of the mind
so letting go even of what could be called thought and arriving at more just a continuous
attention so some of the initial factors that support
concentration are qualities that are called applied thought and sustained thought so where we direct the mind it's
interesting that it's called thought but this means directing the mind toward the meditation object
so it's the breath placing the mind on the breath placing attention on the breath or the
body for example that act is actually a cognitive act we are intentionally directing the attention
but it's a more subtle kind of mental act right than thinking way more subtle than discursive
thought which is way up at the sort of top level so we start to see that there's a refinement
of how we're using the cognitive mind and it begins to invoke other dharma
qualities such as samadhi concentration we can also use thought to cultivate the
heart qualities like the brahma viharas that's a word for loving kindness
compassion appreciative joy and equanimity these are not exactly thoughts but they are things
that can be evoked through repeating phrases which are thoughts through directing the
mind to the feeling in the heart you know these are other ways that we use our cognitive
mind to cultivate very skillful qualities on the path that are taking us much deeper than the level of the thinking mind
amazingly thought can even be used to evoke the
seven factors of awakening there's an amazing suta that says that
when one this is about speaking about an advanced meditator
dwelling thus withdrawn the meditator recollects the dharma and thinks it over
it literally says recollects the dharma and thinks it over on that occasion the awakening factor of
mindfulness is aroused how about that so for someone who's
meditated for a while who has some understanding of how the thinking mind works it's possible to think about the dharma
in a way that evokes uh mindfulness wow it's a very surprising suta
and very interesting one and it goes on to say that the other factors of awakening can be evoked this way also
so it's quite stunning so i like to say that as um
as we refine the cognitive mind from discursive thought which we let go of
and replace with more skillful thought we then start to cultivate more and more wisdom-related dharma
qualities and we come to have what i like to call the mind of dharma where the mind is just operating in a
frame where it thinks about the dharma when it breaks a cup where it calls forth the brahma
bihar is as needed where it understands what activity would be
ethical in a certain situation our mind starts to become useful to us
really functional really beneficial for continuing to walk the path
and we can cultivate this kind of mind simply through beginning with skillful thoughts
beginning by reducing the intensity of the unskillful thoughts and starting with the skillful ones right up at the
surface level from that all of the rest can unfold all the way to the qualities of wisdom
insights and awakening but i hope this talk is at least giving you the
idea that the thinking mind is not all bad you don't need to get rid of it
any more than one needs to get rid of a child in order to become an adult so it's a natural process
and it begins simply with replacing the unskillful side of the
discursive mind reducing the intensity and replacing those with more skillful thoughts that
will then lead the mind deeper so may your practice bear great fruit
and may you come to love your cognitive mind
as a tool on the path thank you