so good evening everyone
sorry to speak into the silence some of you are already sitting
speak into the silence to so we can all return to the silence
there's something very profound about that sometimes in meditation we're not
going into meditation or going to some state but we're returning
we're returning to a place that maybe is when we're
most at home in this world or most at home in ourselves or most settled
so welcome and uh i'll just say a couple of words or
mostly sit in silence and that is that
when you're sitting here and your mind starts its usual noise
don't struggle with that but see if you can hear or feel or perceive
the sweet stillness or silence that includes the noise includes the
sounds in other words reorient your attention from whatever you're thinking
to what you know what you're aware of
that doesn't require thoughts what is your experience
like when you don't use words to answer the question
who are you when you don't use thoughts to answer the question
what is it that's beyond or around or in the middle of thoughts
of thinking when you don't use thoughts to answer the question
when something else answers and as you sit and meditate maybe you can meditate without something else
that's some other awareness that is aware that knows
that doesn't really require thinking
so assuming a meditation posture
and sometimes after i sit down i begin with the posture of my eyes
glancing down towards the floor at a 45 degree angle and while the eyes are still open
to have the eyes become soft
not looking at anything in particular
and then gently closing the eyelids
and gently quietly relax with the exhale
soften the shoulders
soften the belly
and perhaps you can soften the muscles of your face
and relaxing the thinking muscle
and then settling in settling in to your breathing
and settling in can mean that you relax your mind
the relaxed mind settles in to
the body
and gently seeing if you can have your attention
if you can steady your attention on your breathing
on the body breathing
and then hang in there with your breathing
steady whenever you wander off
steady yourself again on your breathing
one breath at a time
and as we come to the end of the sitting
i feel quite touched to be in a room of people meditating with their masks on
touched because i feel it's a way that you are caring for me
you are caring for each other and that it allows me to care for you in
some clear way and may it be that
this happens often that we can do two things at once
you can do whatever you're doing and you can do anything well you're also caring for others
and being cared for cared by others
may it be that this practice that we do
supports or develops our ability to be inspired
to care not as a duty or obligation
but it's something that is like medicine to our own hearts
and from our care you have well wishing for others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
well welcome it's nice to see you all again some of you again some of you for the
first time in a year and a half and uh it's wonderful
to be meditating here with you and thank you for coming as you were coming and as i
we started here i felt quite happy and kind of feeling of contentment to be sitting together
i hope it was nice for you to be here and
so thank you
as i went through my day today i thought of a story
that i kind of reflect on every year
and usually in september because it's a sign to the people we trained we have a training program for it to be
an introduction to buddhist chaplaincy so people who are going to offer spiritual care
and it's the first uh we give these dharma stories to them and uh they're usually quite short
but the assignment is to write about it reflect on it and kind of use a story as a basis upon
which to reflect on oneself and and one's own relationship to people and its own experiences that we've had
and now but i was thinking about that today
partly i was thinking about it because i think one of the things that evoked it was that yesterday we just finished
teaching our first in-person retreat since the pandemic started at the retreat center our retreat center in
santa cruz is a week-long retreat and it was quite wonderful and we had
you know a coveted protocol for it so everyone was vaccinated everyone had a psr test before
it started everyone had an antigen test when they arrived everyone wore a mask
and then during the first two days and then after two days we had the second antigen test
and if everyone was negative then we would we took off the masks so
most people chose to take off the masks when they
could some people chose to keep it on and when i sat down the first time to teach
a room full of about 40 about 30 people we had people spread out
i just didn't feel right to teach with a mask on because there were people sitting relatively
close by and just seemed like the
projectiles from the voice that we're supposed to have you know spreads out across the room
and so i thought well given the covet times i think i don't think i want to
teach with the mask on i went with mask off so i put it on to teach like i'm
teaching now and then today i read that
santa cruz county is now requiring us to have masks the whole time we're there for the next retweet it starts next
sunday we'll be masked the whole the whole week and i just feel like it's a way of
caring for each other and uh and we're not just caring for each other
we're caring for the people that we will encounter when we leave and
count to people they'll they'll encounter and you know the way that this invisible force we have this invisible
force that's spreading across the lands right this virus and uh so i just felt like
of course i'd wear a mask and it kind of feels it's kind of a nice feeling to maybe
because of this care so the story is that we gave the first month of this
chaplaincy training is an ancient story from the early times of the buddhism time of the buddha
and there was a monk in the monastery who had gotten quite sick and had
dysentery and uh one day he was found
in in his bed or on the floor somewhere just uh
kind of laying in his own poop playing in his own
excrement because he was too sick to take care of himself and probably had diarrhea and different
things and and so someone
told the buddha the buddha went to see him and the buddha asked him you know why
why aren't the other monks taking care of you
and he's the sikh monk said oh because i'm useless to them i'm useless
and so the buddha went to had a head with another monk they went got water
and towels whatever they needed and they cleaned up the monk took care of him and
nursed him for a while and then the buddha called all the monks in the monastery together for an
assembly and he said very simply he said now that your monastics you kind
of left the the worldly life you have no mother or father to take
care of you now you have each other to care for it now you have each other to care to care
for each other and uh oh first yeah before you said that he said i hear this this we met
this yeah i just want to see this monk who was sick and laying in his own excrement
and why didn't you guys take care of him and the monk said oh because he's
useless to us and so then he gave them a little talk he said you know you have no mother
father there's no one you know if no one's to care for you except for you to care for each other
and then he said in an ancient indian kind of world view a very powerful statement
he said those who would care for me should care for the sick
and why it's a powerful statement is that in ancient india in some degree
today in india the guru is considered to be uh you know such
carries so much merit so much power so much charisma so much spiritual stature that people you know
kind of sometimes uh stumble over each other in order to serve the guru you can
get a lot of it's very very meritorious thing to do and it's very beneficial to offer that care to the guru and
and um and here the buddha was saying those who would like those who would care for me
care for the sick he was equating the caring for the sick for you know the caring for the guru for
the great teacher and that was a quite that's quite a powerful statement about care the value
of care and caring for others and uh
and uh and the other sad story about you know the monk felt he was useless
how many people you know have been in some unfortunate circumstance and
felt like they would they didn't really count they weren't really worthy or somehow they didn't belong or
or you know that they weren't worthy of anybody's care or attention and kind of went off and
by themselves and how many have treated others that way
i mean our society is made up if you want you to do a kind of a national survey
and there are lots of people who are ignoring others and not caring for certain people
not taking their suffering into account and causing suffering to other not just
simply not caring but and
and this call to care for others is such a fantastic thing
if we understand kind of the essence of it that to care
is good for our own hearts to care i feel like it's such a fortunate thing
to be able to care for people being connected to people and
and i remember how surprised i was when i first discovered this this new feeling that i had never had before
i was i was on a group hike kind of in the
day hike in the in kind of the wilderness area that it was kind of hard to uh
they're going it was hard we had to climb over some very large boulders and little teeny little cliffs and
you know it was you know for someone who was not in good shape or was elderly or something
it was quite hard to uh you know it was a little hard he needed help so i noticed this one a woman who needed
help so i just stayed behind made sure i was never you know that was on the back near where she was
and whenever it seemed like she needed help i was right there to kind of give her a hand or something
it seemed like a simple thing to do but i started feeling uh not good not good about myself it wasn't like i felt
proud or anything there's this kind of tingling warm feeling that her heart has
happening in my heart and it was like i just couldn't wait to do it again for her
to help her because of this it was like it was like i don't know i was going to say candy but i don't know if that's
the right thing to say but it just felt so sweet and so pleasant so enjoyable to feel this
tingling warm feeling every time i had a chance to to care for her and help her it was a very
simple thing to do just help her over these boulders and i felt that many times since
and so rather than caring for others being a burden or a drag
it's it's something it's like it's opening to something inside of us that kind of maybe makes us sing or gives us
a good feeling so these masks that we wear
you know i read also today that they're expecting
that the covet surge is going to happen this winter for a variety of reasons partly because of thanksgiving and partly because of christmas and kind of
a repeat what happened last year and which was pretty bad last winter in spite of the fact many people are
vaccinated now and and so again i thought about that story and this idea of caring for others
and what if we will go through thanksgiving as if we had it was up to us to care for
the whole nation because who knows the pathways but with this this invisible force
travels right buddhists have been relying on thinking about invisible
forces for a long time the invisible force of good will invisible force of kindness the good
visible force of generosity that spreads out and comes back and turns
travels around and has you know amazing effect on the world
and now we have a society that's all concerned about this invisible to the eye this force of this virus
and uh you know it's people who don't know that they have it you know
are bringing it to people who shouldn't have it because they're easily compromised and get sick
so to to to care as if ever to care as if everyone counts
to care for everyone everyone is important everyone matters
and these masks i feel is a symbol of kind of caring for everyone
and we don't know we'll never know these invisible pathways by which our
life affects other people you know it could be that someone has
asymptomatic with coped and they
i don't know they don't wear a mask and go into a
store and lean over someone who's pulling out something from the shelf and somehow
they're that spreads to the next person and they never know it spread to the next person
and that person spread it to the next person and next person was someone who
got sick maybe even died so these invisible ways in which we
affect each other now and and to care about that
but caribou not because it's a limitation not because we are
uh limiting ourselves but the opposite it's like kind of an unlimited life
to live a life where we don't try to protect ourselves i don't know protect ourselves but we
don't try to live with a conceit it's all about me and what i want my preferences
but rather kind of in certain a very healthy way be able to put aside
excessive self-preoccupation which is kind of stressful anyway
and instead allow the chance for this movement of the heart this movement of
care love kindness compassion friendliness for others
so i i know i'm i'm inspired by this idea i feel like it's been part of the fruit of my buddhist practice
i can i've watched it kind of slowly grow over decades you know this movement of
of uh just feeling pretty natural and of course i think this way
so for me the idea of wearing a mask getting vaccinated in such things just
seems like it's just a natural expression not for caring for myself but caring for everyone else
and i feel kind of fortunate i mean it's terrible this virus and it's terrible that so many people are sick and dying
but i feel given that's the case i kind of feel that i'm in a fortunate
position that i'm able to have the ability to to do simple things
that express his care and so that's you know and i said at the
beginning when i came here and saw all of you with your masks on it kind of made me happy
that kind of made me wow is it so pretty pretty nice that uh other people are doing this it is the
requirement to wear it when you come here so so didn't maybe make too much out of it but but um
but anyway it made me kind of happy and content
so no one's useless no one is unworthy of our attention our
care and and what would happen if we lived in a world where we cared for everyone
and even the people we don't know and and
if that was the orientation we had i think we'd probably all be happier
so those are my words for today and uh we have you know time if any of you would like to ask any questions or
make your comments or anything you'd like to say it's your it's your turn now that we're finally in
person
are there any other teaching stories that come to mind um relevant to the covet situation
the covey situation
well it's probably not this is this one's also been in my mind today i don't think because of covet but uh we can
probably make a nice connection that we that's one two these wonderful thing about stories you can kind of interpret
them so maybe maybe we can make a connection there's a story of um i've told this
plenty of times but i like it a lot of uh
in in india they have these uh ugly little troll like
beings called yakshas and so there was one of these
ugly little troll like yaksha tree spirit kind of thing that
made his way up into the heavenly realms to where the great god of the highest heaven brahma
the palace was and went into the palace one day when the great brahma wasn't there and
and hubbled along and hopped up onto the brahma's chair that chairman is thrown
and no one sits on brahma's throne with brahma so the other gods in the court
got you know kind of upset and so you have to get down from there and the more upset and more angry they
got at the yaksa the bigger and bigger and more beautiful and radiant the yaksha became
and so after a while they got frustrated didn't know what to do anymore they couldn't get him off and he was getting
big and strong so they went and found brahma and said brahma
this thing is happening back at the palace and on your throne and uh oh it's okay i know what to do
so he went back to his palace and stood in front of his throne and stood firm sir the front of the yaksha
and bowed to the yorkshire very deeply and said very kindly and friendly you know
i'm happy to see you and i hope you're comfortable up there and things are good for you and
you and your family and and as he did that they actually got smaller and smaller and smaller and
smaller until at some point poof the yaksa disappeared and then brahma went on his throne
and he said and explained you know this was an anger eating
yaksa the more angry you get the more food he has the bigger he grows
so if you want to kind of deal with him what you do is you're friendly and then he shrinks and he disappears
so it's kind of sad story that he has to disappear but but um so
can you relate that to the covidien yeah i think so can you explain
there's a lot to be angry about but it doesn't feel good
and uh and what does it feed uh feeds itself anger feeds anger it
makes me better at noticing things to get angry about but then
getting past the preoccupation with the stuff that i have the right to be angry about
getting past that feels so much better great and the anger gets nothing done
anyway so if you're angry and your anger is making yourself anger angry angrier
what if i got angry at you also would that would that help you grow even
more no oh no it wouldn't help anger grow oh it would help my anger grow yeah yeah
yeah yeah i'm not my boot in nature so we could all help and really kind of
stir it up and really get it going here yeah
well sometimes i think there's you know this is one of the trends in our society is people are feeding each other's anger
and this anger yaksha is growing and then some of it's related to this kova right there's a tremendous amount
of anger and hostility and that is related to this and i don't i think it's feeding the wrong thing
including the people who are angry at the people who are angry
so that was my attempt to tell anybody anybody else had another interpretation of the story
anything else any would like to bring up
well this expands a little bit on your story about the masks um
yesterday i had thanksgiving dinner with my goddaughter and her family and um
it was a very caring gathering we've been doing this now for
about 30 years and none of us had masks
i mean we were all vaccinated and things like that so
so it felt safe and
i i really did feel cared for you know i and i felt like i could care for others
um my goddaughter has a three-year-old daughter so i'm a grand godfather as well
um yeah so i think there's
there's a lot of ways that we can show care for each other and
i just wanted to offer that and you know kind of in the spirit of thanksgiving
beautiful wonderful yeah there's there is an infinite number of ways we can care for each other
mostly what i want to share is the tremendous appreciation i have for
the opportunity to sit in community and
as i was going through the day-to-day driving i
had this feeling of of gratitude and this sense of
driving and the sense of sliding through the air
and that feeling was so common in the past before
covering before i would come and have plenty of practice
and i was re-recognizing myself
as i was having this sense of of gratitude
in um and felt the appreciation for
re-encountering the practice appreciation for re-encountering the practice yeah nice
nice because i lost so much of it during this time
and thank you for coming today so we can be together yes
and your name is uh i'm ji young um
it's nice to be here in person um
i just wanted to add what came to my mind when i was listening to this
i think to me that uh the tree spirit it's uh it's actually war
it kind of works around fear and i guess like if there's a more uh element that i
can go crazy about like being afraid and like
whatever choices that i make out of fear
sometimes it can look like
i i'm i might it can be a same choice that i can make out of care too
but i wouldn't feel the same and i guess listening to you it's um
it's nice to see the possibility of that putting in care
nice yeah so if i understand you interpret you so it's possible to wear a
mask out of fear yeah and it's possible to wear a mask out of care it's the same behavior
but you might as well get the credits for the for the care
this is you know it's kind of free you're doing the same thing and uh
and uh and the credit you get is in the heart when your your heart knows it feels very different if it's upper is
that is that to the point yeah and also that's kind of uh
my ongoing inspiration i guess um
is this meditation practice i i guess i i'm still in a phase of kind of taking
care of my uh kind of uh it's just just fear is everywhere
and i just cannot get rid of it but i guess i'm kind of uh this is good
way of exercising that the more i try to push away that it's
gonna actually become bigger and like a more like like the tree spirit yeah absolutely yeah so
i think probably underneath the yaksha he was so angry the anger eating he was probably afraid
and so the friendliness was creating safety and let something relax yeah so the meditation is definitely a
way to meet our fear in a different way than than being afraid of it or angry at it
great thank you thank you um so uh i i uh this is actually my my
third time um coming to imc in person now so i came last monday and then i came yesterday and
today and um you know i've been such a long time and um it's just i'm just having so i'm so
happy and uh when i heard that there was a you just they were saying there was an in-person retreat irc that also just
made me so happy like um and uh
and you know and yeah the the wearing mask part it actually doesn't doesn't bother me it's it's it's okay and and i
i love the way that you kind of made it feel even easier and and even more wholesome to to do that um
and i'm also just kind of noticing the impact so like yesterday and today i could just kind of feel myself sitting
and it was almost like you know there's just like being in the room and being other people meditating it's just like almost like it's like
it's like uh you know polishing or something like or you know shaking
things up more than it would otherwise and um and today like when i was i was driving and i noticed like a really
unpleasant emotion a very unpleasant feeling coming and all the thoughts kind of swirling
around trying to like you know i don't like this feeling i don't want to feel this feeling
you know this means that you know why why again and why now and i realized
it was a feeling that you know i notice it a lot in meditation retreat and and you know by really
paying attention to it and caring for it and really having a lot of continuous mindfulness it does kind of heal
there's healing um you know but then in the day-to-day life i think it's coming a lot and and the
way i react is by just kind of trying to avoid it or not think about it or distract myself or something like that but i'm just already feeling
that you know just coming to this this uh um imc just three times or it was it was um is already like
oh wow you know reminding me of this possibility of you know mindfulness in everyday life so i'm just so happy fantastic what a great
story i love that i love it thank you come and come again
well it is really nice to be with all of you and i really value the chance to be together meditate together
and uh and so maybe i'll see you again and uh
i'll i'll probably i should be back in two weeks because i go off and do another retreat diana will be here again
next monday and take good care of yourself and care for
others thank you