so good day
i'm happy to greet you to this meditation session together and and to be here with all of you
and i love seeing the names and locations people are from that are in the chat and
those who don't see it it's quite impressive from all over
so um one of the ways that buddha characterized his own
teachings or his own yeah his own teachings is that he
realize his teachings rely on direct experience they rely on his own direct experience
and that's in contrast to the people that the religious leaders on
his time who teachings were articles of faith they took it on faith that they received you know they
received it from someplace else they received it from the tradition
whatever tradition they came from or from sacred texts or they the teachings they had were
based on what they liked with their preferences or the teachings they had were based on
what they have reasoned out for themselves that would seem logical to them themselves or those that were sure based
on intuition some kind of intuitive knowing
or those that were based on one's own teacher my teacher said this
and instead of those other sources of knowledge the buddha relied on what he
could know directly and that's the what the this buddhism
the buddha pointed to for each of us and so this idea of of sitting in
meditation in the present moment is to place us with the in the place and the location
in time and place and with a kind of attention
that is connected or sees or is present for our direct experience
direct experience of the body direct experience of the eyes the ears
the nose the tongue and also the direct experience of what we can know that's
unfolding happening in the present in the mind
and there's something about something we can see in the present moment directly
that cannot be seen anywhere else and that is what this practice is
helping us to discover we can know something for ourselves see it for ourselves
and so this practice becomes a very fortunate practice in that it turns
out that it's possible to really feel at home in the present
moment direct experience it's possible for that to be a place where
our preoccupations with the past and the future our ideas and fantasies and preferences
and and the stories we tell ourselves that are
some some of them are quite painful that all those recede into a kind of
deep sense simplicity of being a contentment of being here and now
not for its own sake but but rather it turns out this is the way of being
that coincides with really being able to see things as they really are to really
connect have direct experience so perhaps those few words will
maybe inspire you to be curious about what your connection to direct
experience might be what is your experience and can that be a place where there's a simplicity of
being not something you have to work out logically not something you have to
believe by faith not something you have to have preferences for
liking or not liking just something to be settled and breathing
breathing in the middle of it so to assume a meditation posture
that is supportive for you of being attentive in the
present moment generally it means to
have a posture that expresses some alertness even if you're not lying down there
might be some way of adjusting your head your chest your spine
your arms where there's some intentionality involved to be here
and present
and to then also relap relax in this posture
not to slump
but to relax the muscles which don't need to be tight
i kind of settling in and so to take a few long and slow deep
breaths
relaxing as you exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal but to feel that breathing from the
inside out to be aware of your the body's own experience of breathing
and here's where direct experience comes into play
you don't have to be concerned with your preferences for how breathing is like
or the tradition of how it's supposed to be or
some logic of reason that you've worked out about how you're supposed to breathe
it's enough just to be familiar with the breathing as it is
perhaps as you exhale
to relax into the body breathing
especially on the exhale relaxing into the breathing body
and whatever occurs as you're meditating now
how do you know it as a direct experience
as the immediate experience of now
direct experience doesn't need any thinking about the experience it's just a knowing
mindfulness
almost a silent awareness of what is happening now
in the body as you're breathing
in the ears as you hear
in the eyes as you see
in the mind as there's mental activity
as you think the content of your thoughts are not important but the
direct experience of thinking can be known
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
the ability to
prioritize the direct experience we have can give us a very different
relationship to other people than if we experienced other people
through our judgments our bias our projections
the colored glasses we wear the cobwebs through which we see
and to clear away much of the distortions or
assumptions or bias in which we see people and to be
present simply fully with the direct experience
of another person
is a way of sharing in the humanity of our lives
it's a way in which hopefully what's deep inside of us
can sense what's deep inside of another their humanity their
suffering their joys
their fundamental value as a living and breathing human being
and may it be that this practice of meditation
helps us to see others in new ways in ways where we feel and sense and
share common humanity
that form of direct experience where
it's easier and cleaner
for there to be good will and generosity kindness towards others
care and may this direct experience of this
life inspire us to live for the welfare and
happiness of others in whatever way is appropriate for each
individual
may this practice we do together
support the happiness of others provide people with greater senses of
safety
of peace and open the doors to freedom
may all beings be well and happy
[Music]
so so for uh this week so
little dharmets and i would like to continue with the idea of stories but this time to
tell the stories of the buddha from the suttas from the ancient
literature that we have in our tradition they purport to be the
direct records of the buddha and not some of the common stories that
are often told about the buddha but rather some of the ones that contain some wonderful teachings
and some of the stories are not great stories but they're stories that contextualize
the teachings and it can help them to stand out a little bit and highlight and so the first one is is a
discourse discourse this ancient word is sutta s-u-t-t-a and it's called the
chunky sutum and uh it's spelled usually in english c-a-n-k-i
and it's number 95 in the middle length discourses
and um i'm particularly fond of this suta and when i teach some of the courses i teach on the suttas themselves
on this ancient discourse especially when i teach courses on middle length discourses i
like to start with this one and the reason for it is that i the kind
of the pivot of the text that kind of the story kind of pivots on
and therefore maybe the most important part of the text is a teaching the buddha gives on the
preservation of truth and how do we preserve the truth and to
offer that the beginning of teachings on this ancient ancient studies of the studies of the
ancient teachings is how do we study these texts and preserve the truth as we do it stay
truthful in a certain way and not to accept them naively the
teachings not to accept them as true because that's what's in the text
how do we relate to these teachings if we don't have our own direct experience of them
and how do we talk about it so the preservation of truth and um so the story has to do
with um brahmanas visiting the buddha and the brahmins were and we have in
this text that kind of represents a little bit the tension in ancient india between the brahman caste and the
sometimes called the warrior or the noble caste the katya chatrias that the buddha came from
and india was very hierarchical culture everything was stratified according to
hierarchies and uh there was a vying for top position among the brahman class which was uh
often the scene is that whether the this the brahmana priests the priests the
brahmanical religions some of them who were phenomenally wealthy and controlled lots of territory
and and then the uh the warrior noble class that were often the rulers
and um so in this text i um a uh the buddha is camped out
near a town where there's a brahmana named chunky who's phenomenally
wealthy he's been given land it's like like a maybe a lord of you know a
medieval lord you know given by the king whole big territory to be his own and to
the wealth of it was his the people in it were working kind of for him and things like that
and he's also very learned in the vermontical lore
and um one day he hears about um the people in his the other brahmanas in
his town here that the buddha is nearby and there's a good report about the buddha he's
supposed to be you know a wonderful teacher and so
they all decide to go visit the buddha and hear his teachings however there's a
group of other brahmanas 500 it says visiting the town from other places and they get upset
that chunky this kind of ruler of the territory this great brahmana is going to go visit the
buddha and they say it's inappropriate for you to visit the buddha because you are so wonderful and they
go through all the ways in which he's wonderful and and the buddha should come see you
because you're so elevated and you shouldn't go to the buddha and the brahman chunky says oh no no
the buddha is actually more wonderful he lists all the special qualities of the buddha to argue
yes it's appropriate for me to go see the buddha not the buddha to come to me so they all go to see the buddha and
they're sitting there having a conversation about the dharma or something
and there's a 16 year old brahman priest a student of the brahmanical lore
teachings sacred texts who is sitting amongst them and he keeps
interrupting the buddha and at some point the buddha says to him
and exactly the tone of voice and how he said it we don't know and how to translate the word uh into english we don't know the body
translated as the buddha rebuked the boy for interrupting the conversation between the elder
brahmins and himself one meaning for the for the word is that
the buddha stopped and just simply stopped the brahman the young boy that night 16
year old and said you know you shouldn't interrupt when the elders are speaking
and then one of the elder brahmans maybe chunky says oh it's okay venerable buddha that this this young
man is one of the most learned of the brahmana students we have he's
memorized all the ancient texts and the histories of the past and philosophy and he knows it all
please now you know it's okay that he is part of the conversation and in the very formal polite culture of
the time of the buddha probably what the buddha needed to do in order to have converse with the 16 year
old he needed to have clear permission from the elder brahmanas to do so otherwise it would be rude to
them that he directed his focus to this 16 year old so he has that permission so
the buddha looks at the at the at the 16 year old and 16 year old says oh good the buddha is now ready
to hear my question and the 16 year old says
it's been said among the brahmanas that our texts our sacred texts
are the only ones that are true and all everyone else is wrong
it said he actually says it's uh the brahmins say that definitively our texts are the only ones
that are true and everything else is wrong so they're kind of definitive this is clear
and what does the buddha think about this and the buddha in this kind of circumstance does what he often does
which she asks counter questions and he asks
the 16 year old the student what is there any brahman
in the current generation who has directly known and seen the truths of these ancient
texts they really know it for themselves through their direct experience and the student says no
and what about their teachers the generation before them and the generation before them
did they any of them say they directly knew and see saw the truth of these teachings no they
never said they directly stew it themselves and if you go back seven generations
nope no one said no and seven generations have said they directly know and see for themselves
and if you go back to those people who composed the sacred literature did they ever make
a claim maybe in the literature that they directly knew and saw the truth for themselves
and the students said no there's no proof that they claim that they themselves saw it directly for
themselves so then the buddha makes a kind of a big claim big big
statement he says sound seems to me that the brahmanas
are a little bit like um well before i say this earlier in the text
chunky when he's describing the great qualities of the buddha he says the buddha never harmed any and
and so this what's about to be said because it could be seen maybe a little bit offensive but maybe there's a way of understanding it that
it's not offensive but it's just um you know just
doing kind of an aikido move with uh what the the maybe the conceit or the arrogance
of this student who believed that this is the truth that he had and so the buddha said um well it's what
you're saying then it's kind of like a row of blind people one
holding the shoulder of the next the one in the front can't see the one in the middle can't see and the
one the back can't see and the brahmins are a little bit like like a row of blind blind people
going along so the the um
the the student then says well you know but we have it on faith we don't know and directly know and see for ourselves
we have it on faith and the buddha says well what's known on
faith may be true but it might not also be true there's no no certainty about just because it's
sake on faith that it's true ah but it's in our or it's in our oral
traditions in our texts and that buddha says well just because it's part of the tradition
it might be true but it might not be true there's no way of really knowing just because it's traditional and then
the buddha says there are five things that may or may not be true
things taken on faith things taken as being true because we like them we
prefer them things taken as true because they are the tradition things true because we've
reasoned them out for ourselves they're logical and the last one is because there's some kind of intuitive
understanding of uh that we intuitively feel or sense that these are true and he said in each
of these circumstances sometimes it might be that it's true and sometimes it's not and there's no way really of
understanding which it is based on those sources and and so the the youth says well how
do we preserve the truth then and this is the pinnacle of the text and why i like it so much
the buddha says that we preserve the text but we preserve the truth by
stating the basis upon which we make a claim so if we take something on faith
we say it is my faith that this is true if we take it upon our preferences it's
my preference that this is true if it's based on the tradition the text
or something our teachers or something then we say it's based on the tradition this is what
the tradition says is true and then i reason it out for myself that's why i think it's true
or i just have an intuitive sense that this is true and so we're like then we're not making
a claim about what is true we're making a claim about
how we've come to understand what we think is the truth we're not claiming it's true we're
claiming that we have faith or reasons to believe it so
and then it's possible to be in dialogue with people people understand what we're basing our claims upon we can
go back and look at the texts or we can examine their reasoning or we can appreciate the faith that someone has
and this idea of really being clear about the basis upon which we take
something to be true it's my interpretation it's my this or that i suppose i'm claiming it's true
this is a pivot the pivot of the text then the student says well if
how do we discover the truth for ourselves and the buddha then goes on and says
well in that case if you want to discover it for yourself go find
he actually says a monk a biku who's come to your village or something and spend a long time checking that
person out that teacher out make sure that that person doesn't exhibit any traces of having greed
hatred and delusion that might skew how they talk about the truth where they
might be motivated to twist or bend the truth a little bit for the purposes of their desires or
their aversions or their illusions so really check someone out first when
you're confident that they don't seem to have exhibit any kind of greed hate and delusion that uh would maybe skew how they give the
teachings then listen to their teachings and reflect on them and really take them in and think about them for
yourself and find what's going on and then once you really have reflected
them deeply then engage in the practice and do it wholeheartedly
enter the practice into the world of the direct experience until the direct experience opens up
that you discover the truth for yourself and then this brahmana student says well
is that all there is just a discovery and the buddha says no there's one more step and that is the arrival at truth
so not just discovering what the truth is but arriving at it now what the buddha is doing is talking
about the discovery of the truth he's kind of doing another move by aikido at least this is my
interpretation i'll say that so i preserve the truth and that is he's saying that um um
he's doing is rather than talking about abstract truth he's pointing the the student to how you
could practice to experience the direct experience that buddha values the most
and and uh and it's through practice that that's uh uh accomplished mindfulness practice
concentration practice and all this and then once you have the discovery of truth then to arrive at truth the buddha
says then you do the same thing over and over again you do this repeat the same practice repeatedly
again and again until it gets you're fully integrated into it then there's no separation between
yourself and the truth and you in a sense become the truth it doesn't say that in the text but
become the truth so um and so then everyone's happy
that's the end of the story so it's not a necessarily a great story but it's a
it's i think a fascinating story of setting up the context for why it's so important uh to
emphasize the preservation of truth among people who hold on to the truth
out of faith or out of traditional reason or something and there is another way of going about it which is
not just to take teachings even buddhist teachings on faith or because in the texts and therefore it's
true that's always provisional that what's not
provisional is when we've actualized it for ourselves and really thought this is what i know i've experienced myself
the direct experience we have ourselves of it now i know
and then we could arrive at truth but keep practicing what we've discovered
so that's the story and i hope that you appreciated that
and i'll say tell some other stories for the rest of the week so thank you
you