so good day everyone and the way we could say perhaps a good year
and kind of like good morning good beginning of this new year for us on this
7 a.m sitting and teaching so i'm happy to be here for this anniversary day and so we'll have a zoom
meeting afterwards and for those of you who don't want to be on zoom
i think i'll just keep the youtube on and you won't necessarily
get all of it but you'll get half of it of myself responding and talking and a little bit and and um and
uh the zoom link is the is at the very top of this chat and i'll
post it near the bottom when we finish here as well it's also found on the imc
website in two places in the calendar section of it from where it's listed as an event and
on the what's new there's a little notice also in the bottom right hand side
of the home page and if you use those links you have to use the password which is meta m-e-t-t-a if you use the link
that's on the chat you got a picture right there and i won't turn it on until i finish here so
there might be a minute or so in between
so so
as a child i spent a lot of time swimming in water and i loved to go underwater and
swim as far as i could without and holding my breath and that explains maybe a little bit why i
um a little bit i pay a tiny bit attention to
people who do free diving and people who do records for free diving
underwater the longest the deepest distance down into the water or or in
the ocean or perhaps a whole you know swim the longest underwater or be longest underwater
and i think they're one of the records i believe for staying underwater without breathing is about 11 minutes
so it's kind of phenomenal that people can train to do that but one of the things that people who do
that learn to do is to quiet their thinking
because thinking takes up a lot of oxygen you need a lot of energy and to think and um and so they
they're certainly aware and engaged what they're doing and very hyper attentive to what they're
doing in a very particular way um but uh their ordinary
um energy draining battery draining uh app has been turned off the
discursive thinking the commentary that they do
and so this also happens in meditation it's one of the reason why in deeper meditation it seems that we stop
breathing because there's very little need to breathe when this
heavy app that we have that's really kind of going on all the time in the background and
you know it's one of these apps that kind of take over and and work even you know
behind the scenes uh our thinking app so to uh to as we get into meditation
the idea is to enjoy it settle into it and settle into that
enjoyment into the contentment into the quiet into the peace of it even if it's just hints of it
kind of orient kind of a paradigm shift where we're orienting towards something else
besides our thinking and we're orienting towards the breathing and the peacefulness the
quiet the stillness the the joy and the contentment that comes
from developing samadhi and with that there's a shift away
from the thinking mind the commentary mind the dis having discussions and plans and
memories and all that and so to appreciate the value of that appreciate how good it feels to let that
part of the mind go quiet and if these deep sea divers can do it certainly we can do it as we do our own
kind of version of deep sea diving which is dipping into samadhi deeping it
dipping deepening into this kind of states of goodness and wholeness
that don't require us to think think a lot and when we realize how safe it is and
good it is and nourishing it is then we begin to let go of the the tremendous
interest the mind has with this app the thinking app so
to assume a meditation posture
and to relax tremendous amount of what we're doing in
the going into samadhi is in fact relaxing letting things become tranquil
not only letting go and relaxing the body
but also taking some of the mental apps offline they're not needed or energy drains for
human battery and they can come back online again
later but we're letting go or relaxing
doing less and less except for us settling in steadying
ourselves on the breathing and enjoying it
so taking a few long slow deep breaths on
the exhale thinking of it as turning off
so much of the unnecessary apps we have running the tensions in our body
softening the shoulders especially
softening the belly
and if you are taking some deep slow breaths then as you stop that appreciate that
you are letting go of that effort
and now you're just letting yourself breathe in a more easy way
and then to continue relaxing the body a
bit the surface body of the shoulders the
face the belly
and deep in the body the deep holding resistance bracing
the deep holding ourselves
even holding ourselves together
and then to also
orient yourself to the quietude of the mind
let's let yourself become aware in the ways of the mind is quiet
clear relaxed
and as you exhale settle into that quiet
letting go of the thinking mind and if it doesn't let go completely it's
okay for now let it recede into the
background
and then with the mind let the mind land on your breathing
and have the mind the attention
find uh establish yourself to be steady on the breathing
steady the mind on its focus on the
breathing and much of our physical experience of breathing
is in fact silent doesn't require thinking the silent feeling and sensing
of the body steady yourself on that experience of
sensing the changing flow of sensations as you
breathe
as you exhale letting go of your thoughts and letting go into
a quiet steadiness on breathing
and if you use any thoughts at all let it be thoughts of counting the
breath counting up to one or up to 3 or up to
10 or simply the word yes
so said so quietly in the mind that it's almost like you imagine you're saying it
steadying yourself on the breathing and whatever good feelings that come
with the quietude and steadiness breathing in and breathing out
appreciating the quietude that's here even if your mind is
thinking a lot look past it
to the quietness steadiness of attention on breathing
a paradigm shift away from your thinking mind
to a quiet steady awareness of breathing
and whatever goodness is in that attention
switching from thinking to a quiet seeing
a quiet sensing aware of breathing
steadying yourself on the breathing
[Music]
and then as we come to the end of this sitting appreciating the paradigm shift from
thinking to seeing
seeing with the quietness of the mind
so we're not seeing through the filter of our thoughts ideas opinions
but we're seeing through the quietness
steadiness and safety of
simply seeing simple awareness of what is
and in the maybe the comfort and safety of meditation
can you turn the gaze of this quiet
steady seeing awareness
to the people in your life
those who are close and you have contact with those who are far away and you don't have direct contact those who you know
personally and those who don't
and see if you can simply from meditation gaze upon them
quietly silently without the judgments and the stories
anticipations of what it means just gazing on them quietly
and see if that gaze that awareness can be kind that in the quiet and safety of
privacy of your own meditation a kind steady gaze
be still and gaze upon all everyone kindly
not complicating it with your stories ideas memories plans
just the simplicity of others
and perhaps that kindness then can be expressed in the words of
kindness you might repeat after me
may they be happy
may they be safe
may they be peaceful
may they be free
may all beings everywhere be happy [Music]
[Music]
you