so hello everyone who is here today with the youtube and
listening maybe into the future as well
and then some ways we span
geography across the globe and we also spend time into the future with how these
recordings work it's kind of an amazing thing that we share and feel a connection to so much
there are some maybe some of you have heard me say many times i like to divide our experience of life
what goes on in with our life moment by moment into two
areas there is what is happening and there is how we are with what is
happening or our relationship to what's happening and mindfulness practice i put in the
lighter camp mindfulness is a practice of showing up and being attentive to what is happening
and to engage in mindfulness with equanimity
has the function of staying with the mindfulness staying
with a relaxed dedicated sincere attention to this moment
attention to nexus being present being available for the flow of the present moment as it
keeps appearing and arising for us moment by moment and
and one thing that helps to have equanimity to just stay present stay with the
mindfulness moment by moment is to not think that you are unique
that uh not think that you're that what your experience is
is unique enough that it's an exception to what all humans experience
not to dismiss what you have what's happening to you or make it not to make it kind of unimportant
everything is important you're important but what's also important is the steadiness of how we
are the steadiness of mindfulness when we're practicing mindfulness to not
it's kind of like we have the bumper sticker that says i stop for nothing when i practice
mindfulness meaning i don't get involved and get entangled and start thinking about things and
just a bare recognition oh this is what's happening now this is what's happening and or
available to experience this is what's experiencing this is what's known now this is what's being experienced now
just steady steady steady like when i went on a walking pilgrimage
a good number of years ago and it was only two weeks but
the idea was just keep walking when we walked just keep walking and walking and walking
didn't matter what the ex experience around us was just you walk and you walk so we
are mindful we're aware we're aware with equanimity that allows us to just
continue without getting sidetracked without getting stopping for something and getting
entangled and retro retrospective thinking so to
begin this pilgrimage of mindfulness pilgrimage where
we don't we don't walk we sit we remain stationary in a
stationary posture that works for you
and to tenderly close your eyes
and maybe tenderly in your heart open to yourself
closing your eyes and opening your heart
and taking a few moments to appreciate yourself and value yourself
that perhaps that is why we're meditating because we value our well-being
and this is a way of finding a valuable important form of
well-being happiness freedom from suffering
and to take a few long slow deep breaths
and exhales really settling in here with yourself in yourself
for yourself here in this body
here in this heart
here in this belly
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and because of maybe with a sense of self-care self-appreciation
to as you exhale to continue to relax what can be relaxed in your body
face shoulders stomach belly
and then letting then settling in just to your breathing
no walking pilgrimage it's the feet that walk
it is a stationary pilgrimage of meditation
can you it's your breathing breathing in and breathing out
and to have the simplicity of breathing be something that we
allow to come into our awareness
a simple sea of breathing is where awareness lands
two metaphors for awareness awareness which receives allows
awareness which lands connects whichever is
most useful for you and then with equanimity
that doesn't get alarmed or caught up or annoyed or
think that something is unique and not part of the practice
everything is part of practice everything is for the next moment of
awareness to trust it's enough
just to be aware to trust to just take the next moment
for what it is even if it's very similar to the previous one
just stay stay
the equanimity that allows a steady continuation of the practice
come back to that continuity
if things are challenging
breathe with it so that your awareness
rides on the currents of breathing
relaxed available present for the experience without getting entangled
as you meditate nothing is extraordinary enough
to stop to think about or get involved in everything is ordinary enough
that it's just one more thing to be aware of to be mindful of
in a steady ongoing receptivity of awareness to what is one breath
at a time
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to tenderly calmly
open up to the sufferings of the world
and to do so equanimously
meaning that we care
we feel for the suffering we're concerned with it
and there's no need to give up the steadiness of our mindfulness
steadiness and confidence in remaining rooted in awareness
so that we don't get pulled into our reactivity our thinking our predictions
our sense of obligations and should and what shouldn't be
in equanimity it allows us to stay open
so that care and goodwill respect and kindness
can flow through that awareness through the field of mindfulness
and may it be that as we learn how to be more aware and mindfulness
more mindful with equanimity with calm with balance
may it be that we can show up for the challenges of this world
and stay close to our goodwill well-wishing kindness friendliness
compassion may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
peaceful and free and may my heart and mind
have this good will this well-wishing for others
so that in some way or other it spreads from me spreads from each of us into the world
that we encounter today may our love and compassion
spread from this meditation session out into our communities and out into
the world may all beings be happy
[Music]
you