so good day to everyone and welcome to our dharma time together
and um so for this uh sunday morning meditation
i'd like to use an analogy a little bit of rough analogy
is that if you put black duct tape around a light bulb
and then turn on the light bulb there might be no light coming into the room
if you take a little pin hole make a little pinhole in the duct tape you get
you know little stream of light going out in one direction but if you begin peeling away the light
that the the tape you get more and more the light going more and more wider
wider kind of directions if you take the duct tape off entirely
then you have um you know the light shines out in kind of like 360 degrees all the way around
so if our awareness our capacity to know and be present is a little bit like the light we turn
on our capacity to to see turn on the light
the capacity to be aware but we have uh something that we're caught up in and
preoccupied with it's like we have the the light can't shine or can't
be open fully in all directions and if we're completely lost in fantasy
or lost in distracted thought it's almost as if there's you know the duct tape is completely surrounding
the light and the light is only there for itself it's self-absorbed in a certain way
and all the lights bouncing on it bouncing on inside the bulb
but as we meditate we learn uh we appreciate how limited it is to be caught up in
preoccupations and thoughts even if those thoughts are grand in nature and
you know have phenomenal wonderful fantasies of traveling around the world
everywhere it's still ingrown in inward directed as we begin to let go of our
thoughts and big glow of our preoccupations there is slowly and steadily an opening up of the light opening up of
our vision our capacity to see and at some point it really becomes really clear the difference
between having it be wide open all the duct tape off and when it's that we start covering it
again and that movement of oh now i'm kind of it's gotten narrow it's gotten
contracted it's got become even self-absorbed that doesn't feel so good it felt really
nice to have the awareness uncontracted unlimited
we might still focus on a particular thing like the breathing but we do so without there being a
tightening and narrowing there's more like rather than the the attention going really
focused in a tight way it gets really focused in an open way kind of like the open palm of
the hand the most sensitive part of the one of the most sensitive parts of the hand is right here
at the center of it if we kind of get focused this way you know tight and focused we don't
avail ourselves of the most sensitive part but if we're really relaxed and open
then the sensitive part meets our experience our breathing and then um
so this is an effort to use analogies to emphasize the sensitivity the care
to letting our awareness be open be wide be relaxed
be be uncontracted untight unlimited
you know unlimited in a sense by the restrictions we put on it by our
desires our clingings and our versions that get you know hyper focused and so if that
made sense to you then we can practice that and if it doesn't make so much sense you don't have to worry about it too
much or at all so assuming a meditation posture
that is
relaxed then open
with the chest maybe it'll open
gently closing the eyes and taking a few long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale maybe there can be a relaxation that
it kind of the kind of maybe relaxation that a
a flower does when it opens its petals from being a tight bud to being an open
flower so to relax and exhale and
let things open up
on the exhale relaxing the belly
relaxing the chest
softening the shoulders
softening the face
breathing normally
and imagine that you're turning on the light of awareness so that it shines
360 degrees in all directions
and then at the center of that is a sensitive spot that's there to meet
the experience of the body breathing
breathing in and breathing out
being intimate with breathing
but without contracting or getting tight with awareness without the mind
bearing down or tightening up
and this kind of intimate sensitivity is often associated with being receptive
open receptive to all things but with the center of it all center of
awareness receiving breathing in and breathing out
and perhaps as you get caught up in thoughts or fantasies
you can feel how you lose that openness that
maybe is lose a spaciousness or lose a
receptivity and without being critical of that
relax and receive again open again
breathing in and breathing out
so
are you absorbed in thought so the light of awareness is
obscured
what is it like to let go of your thoughts
so that the light of awareness
is on 360 degrees very open present
with its sensitive center
centered on the breathing
so
you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps to consider how the how as we become more
aware more present more open to our experience
there is a place within of sensitivity heightened
awareness sometimes associated with a tenderness
a place that is receptive and
and that to meet the world with this
receptivity this tenderness this sensitivity
this is a way that we evoke
the sentiments of care caregiving
respect good will for others
and to end the sitting with some orientation
to look upon others be ready to be present with others
from a place of receptivity care tenderness
that inspires or reminds us of our capacity to love others
to have to be friendly
kind compassionate
then may it be that our through this meditation practice
that we are giving more and more developing more and more capacity
to gaze upon the world kindly
to become a friend of the world a friend of others
and in our friendship with all beings may we wish for the happiness
of others
for their safety and their health
for their peace and their freedom
and with our friendly disposition may each of us in our own way and
appropriate for each of us contribute to the welfare and happiness
of all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
may all beings everywhere
have their hearts settled and at peace
so good day everyone and as an announcement for before before the
talk um you know we're getting to the point where
imc is seriously considering opening uh for our doors here our physical doors so
people can come here together and meditate and engage in the dharma and
we were planning to open in a week from today on august 1st so i think it's a prudent for us to
delay that opening and continue online the way we have
the and the
and part of the reason for that is that this delta variant that uh is spreading
and we don't quite understand the implications of it and the impact it
has that the degree to which even people who maybe have been vaccinated
can be asymptomatic carriers of it and what it means for us to come together here and
you know somewhat close confines and as it's still kind of growing the delta variant and the cases are
growing here in our county here in california i think that the prudent thing to do is
to wait and ideally we would wait and i think until
the local county health department rescinds the request that people who
even vaccinated people when they come together indoors that they would
wear masks so i don't know if that's the standard we want to keep but at least for now that's the request and
with the delta variant i think it's just better to wait and um so i think we'll we'll just keep
it open or in you know undefined when we'll open and probably will have
at least a week's notice that we can announce it here and our other uh online
um or other online offerings and also we'll
we'll update the calendar we'll update also on the imc website about what's happening so hopefully to
keep it keep track of these things you'll know those of you who are interested in
coming locally and being here in person
so you know we've gone through many of us all of us i guess uh many many months
now of this pandemic of covet 19
era and um and you know when it first started here
and we went into shelter and place in california back in march or april i gave a talk about this being a time
for kind of the shelter in place was kind of like a retreat and
the many of the dynamics and that the patterns that happened on retreat would probably unfold for people on this
enforced retreat of the shelter in place and now we're coming to a different
phase of it it's not clear exactly what phase it's premature to say that we're
completely open again and it's over here in california at least in parts of the country and parts of the
definitely parts of the world it's raging and surging and you know tremendous
suffering that's continuing with this virus
and um but to have some reflection uh what are the lessons from this what
are the how do we grow and develop under the impact
of this powerful event that's happening to us all
and so that's a little bit inspires this talk today and uh and i want to before i specify
what the theme is i want to say that one of the first things that really
impressed me about the circumstance of the beginning of the pandemic beginning
of shelter and place is that um
the same behavior looking like outside can look exactly
the same it could be behavior which the main motivation is for individuals to protect themselves
and the same behavior that looks exactly the same would be to behave in such a way as to
protect others so what i mean by that is that we're all
you know subject to being maybe getting sick from the virus and so we
might want to stay away from people who have the virus we want to shelter in place we might want to live apart and
that's what many of us have done now for many months and somewhat many people somewhat isolated
existences for this time and so it can be motivated by protecting oneself
however all of us are capable of being a vector for it the transmitter of the
illness we know that the people can have the virus and be asymptomatic
they have no idea that they're carrying it and they're just walking walking transmitters and
and so one way to protect people our neighbors our friends our family and others
is to uh not walk into public not walk into their
situation not go to a wedding not go to visit grandchildren or
visit grandparents or not to go into places where we might be a transmitter
so both behaviors look exactly the same and what struck me at the beginning of
the pandemic is that if we could if we were motivated by care for others
rather than only protecting ourselves that i think that caring for others is
uh is really good for the heart it's really a wonderful kind of medicine
and support there's a kind of a radiance or goodness that comes from that
and of course protecting ourselves is not wrong and some people have a higher need to do
that than others for many different reasons and that needs to be the focus
but even there it's possible to both protect oneself and at the same time do it for the sake
of protecting others and and so this idea of being able to do both
uh we don't have to choose one or the other and that's kind of the theme of what i'd
like to say here is that the buddhist practice is a practice that
i'm hoping i very much staked my career in practice and teaching on this
that as we develop in the practice that it becomes a natural thing
to want to care for others or to be friendly or be supportive or have live in the
world in a compassion in a world of suffering in a compassionate way and and not to do it in a way that is
oppressive not to do it in a way that is stressful but really from the abundance
of the heart from a sense of the peacefulness the openness the heightened kind of 360 degree radiance
of awareness and the heart of compassion that meets the world with our sensitivity and
responds to it in some way and that and that this is an integral
part of buddhist practice is this uh growing to become someone who will
uh in one way or the other in particular for each person how it's done live for the welfare and
happiness of others and for some people it's uh caring for their family
that's what for some people is caring for family and neighbors for some people it's
offering whatever they have to offer that brings joy and happiness to the world some people it's to do
to be actively involved in service roles where we're helping others and involved others and some people are
activists and involved in social action and some people humanitarian efforts is all
this whole range of things that people will choose that's a lot depends on their karma and their disposition and their
circumstance what's the right way but it's always of somehow having a
heart that cares for the world so when the buddha after the buddha was
first awakened and soon thereafter he set forth out into
the world to teach what he had learned and after some period
he had gathered around him 60 people 6-0 who
who had been transformed by his teachings and the practices taught
and they became fully enlightened fully liberated and at that point he told them and this
is a quote this is a passage that's quoted often it's kind of beautiful he instructed them he gave them the
final instruction it's kind of like after all the instructions and all the practice
they all end up here as a final and that is to go forth
for the welfare of the world welfare of the beings the
people of the world go forth for the happiness
of this world of beings go forth out of care
for this world of beings and people no two of you of you go in the same
direction spread out and live for the practice and teach
for the welfare and happiness of all people and all gods
the word gods here it's possible it means sometimes the word dev deva means
kings so go for the four for the welfare of all beings all humans ordinary humans and those who
are in ruling position who sometimes need greater greater
remedial support for learning how to be free and really understand what freedom from
suffering really is and um so i i love this little passage
that uh that the instructions are to go forth for the welfare and happiness of the of the world um that that's that's kind
of like it's like the north star of what buddhist practice is aiming towards uh this is the final
instructions and um and then if we go to a whole different
set of teachings which is uh also emphasizes this care for others and care for
oneself and this is the buddha's teachings to his son so he had a son who spent much of his
growing up under the guidance of his father from the they think about from the age 7 onwards
and at some point the buddha gave him this instructions that could be
seen some people say well this is kind of a child appropriate kind of teaching but
because it's so simple and so to the heart of the matter it may be easier to understand and all
the rest of buddhism can be seen as an expansion of this particular teaching
it's uh it seems the way the story is go is told that his young son maybe seven eight
nine years old was caught telling a lie
and and so the buddha
addresses him about this and says you know that if a someone on the spiritual path tells
a lie it kind of undermines the value of their practice
and really empties the kind of reservoirs of goodness or dharma inside of a person that really
would allow a person to grow and develop so he kind of kind of little bit strong strong language like this like that it's
not really that someone who's on the path should never lie
and and after he does that he says this he says what's the purpose of a mirror
and his son says oh the purpose of a mirror is for reflection to see yourself in the mirror and the buddha said in the
same way the dharma is like a mirror the purpose is to see yourself and to reflect
yourself more clearly and this is how you do it before you
say something before you do something and before you intentionally think about
something you should reflect you should look at that
take a good look at yourself with these criteria is what i'm about to say will it cause
affliction will it cause harm to yourself
others or to both self and others
if you say it if you do it or even if you think it will it cause harm and if it does
don't do it if it doesn't cause harm if it's for the benefit of others then
please go ahead and do it while you're doing something or saying
something or even while you're reflecting and thinking about something also use that dharma mirror look at
yourself and ask yourself the question as i'm doing this is it for my own harm for the harm of
others or for the harm of both self and others and if it's harmful stop doing it
if it's not harmful if it's for the benefit of others and self then keep doing it
and then he says after you've done something after you said something after you've
finished some action that you've done after you've spent some time thinking about
someone or someone something you should also use a dharma mirror to be released reflective life
questioning yourself looking at yourself considering the impact the consequences
of your behavior and and did it cause harm to yourself
did it cause harm to others did it cause harm to self and others
if it did then go find someone that you respect a lot the ancient language is a wise person
find a wise person and let them know this the alchemy the
chemistry of the inner life is such that if you if you've caused
harm and usually like not exactly a confession but just kind of make it acknowledged in the presence of
something else it changes the some inner relationship to it all it's easier for you to kind of not
succumb to the same thing again it's it's more likely to be if you're accountable in some healthy
way um and uh and you're not in your little not public to everyone but
you share it with someone else then you're a little bit more accountable to that person to yourself it's a little
bit more like a fuller recognition that creates the conditions that you're more likely to be
careful in the future so he said buddha said go tell someone
and then but if it's uh after you've done something and it's uh
has not been harmful to anyone for self or others has been beneficial then just go about your business happily
that's that's great so what we find here at uh at the
if teaching his son when his son was just a kid is kind of like the most beginning level
of dharma practice dharma teaching that here also we find a concern
emphasis on the concern of being care careful for the welfare of others to not cause
harm in the world to anyone including oneself and
it wasn't only about not harming harming oneself only doing things beneficial for oneself
it's equal concern for self for others and then this third category
self and others which i understand that's that includes kind of we as a as a
community we as a as a group as a dynamic of people who work together the
relationship between us and um so one way so we see here in
these two examples how integral it is to the teachings of
the buddha the concern for the welfare of others and well-being of others and
the concern with not causing harm to others or and to ourselves and that
all along from between the beginning instructions to the final instructions to go forth for the welfare of others
we see over and over again that we come back to this idea that um that the dharma has a lot dharma
practice maturing in the dharma has a lot to do with how we care for others as well
and with the example that is what i was inspired by at the beginning of the pandemic
perhaps also we begin discovering a way of having this care and
sensitivity and carefulness for the welfare of others to not cause harm
that doesn't feel punitive that doesn't feel constricting it doesn't feel limiting
but actually it's opposite that as we go forward that um and consider others that we're
doing so from this openness this uh uh uh you know uh
uh uh inclusiveness this um uh unconstricted place unlimited place
un uh whether we're not our concerns are not narrowed and tight
but our concerns come out of an openness and a wideness and a receptivity all the way around and that
and there's a way in which when we're excessively concerned with ourselves
our own cons you know our own well-being our own you know protecting ourselves or
benefiting ourselves as i said earlier sometimes that's completely appropriate and necessary
and should be appreciated as such but human beings also have a tremendous
capacity for being selfish for having conceit and when that happens
then the self-concern feels like a narrowing a tightening a shutting down
and this is one of the great advantages of meditation is we can have a experienced
experiential a felt sense experience of what it feels
like to be start closing down constricting tightening the tension and the stress of
selfishness the tension and stress of conceit of excessive self-preoccupation
and uh and and a felt sense experience that when we open up there's a way
of caring for the world that is absence of stress absence of a kind of
tension that feels has a kind of a
uh a rightness to it a nourishing to it a
a freedom to it even if what we're encountering in the world the suffering in the world is quite uncomfortable
and this kind of the goodness of this the support of that and so i think that kind of inherent in
the dharma practice is a learnings perhaps a slow learning
of the disadvantages of shutting down closing down or having this very strong
um division divisiveness boundaries between self and
others that is actually kind of harmful to oneself
and it leads to ways easy ways of harming others that those begin to dissolve begin to
soften to open and it isn't that the boundaries completely dissolve exactly
uh between self and other that distinction doesn't completely disappear but it becomes one that is there's a
sensitivity and openness and intimacy without this strong reference to
me myself and i here and openness relaxation freedom
and um and then one more teachings of the buddha around
this it's such a i think a very important topic to think carefully about and that is that
the buddha gave this teachings about four different ways in which people
might orient themselves towards others or to benefiting others the first one is
to have no interest in the welfare of either oneself or others the second is to be interested
in the welfare and happiness of others but not oneself
the third is to be concerned for the welfare and happiness of oneself but not be involved in benefiting others
and the fourth is to be concerned for the welfare and happiness of oneself of others and of the whole world
and then he goes on to say that the last of these uh is the foremost is the best and that
it he says it's kind of like um uh if you take milk and it gets in the inc
you could be it gets curdled into curds and then from the curds you can make
ghee and from ghee apparently you can get the cream of the ghee like the
the the best parts of the ghee if you separate it maybe or something and at least the translation that i have
says that then finally you get to the cream of the ghee and and the last category the person is
concerned for both self and the whole world that's kind of the equivalent of the cream of the ghee kind
of person the foremost person but what's interesting is that there's a hierarchy here
between these and and where caring only for others or caring
only for ourself fits into these categories is fascinating i think
because the second best is to care for oneself without caring
for others third best is caring for others but not oneself
and this i think is a little bit jarring it was a little bit jarring for me when i first saw it for some people's jarring because
sometimes there's a message that we should really care about others first before ourselves we shouldn't be selfish
and caring for others is really the highest kind of virtue we can have but i think in the buddhist analysis
that if we care for others before we have developed ourselves developed
our own capacity and understanding of liberation of freedom before we've
kind of freed ourselves of some of our capacity for attachments for clinging
for hostility and irritation and cynicism and and resentment and
that then it's all too easy to cause harm when we're involved in supporting other
people but if we practice for our own benefit first
then we learn at some point what the highest benefit is we learn what the human capacity is for
real deep thorough going fully embodied heartfelt well-being and peace and
happiness that's what the dharma is moving towards and then when we want to support
and help others we have a reference point of how deeply and fully this is possible
for people that we can point to that or we can support that or we have a north star
of what we're trying to do for them and uh and so
um but the best of it all is if we live our lives caring for
ourselves caring for others and caring for the whole world and so here we see three different examples
of the buddhist teachings where caring for the world is integral to it
and in the last one i told first about sending people off to fully mature people to care for the
world there's the idea is that when you're fully liberated you ha you've experiencing for yourself
the best possible way of living in this world the greatest happiness the greatest peace
so there's no need to kind of focus on oneself in the same way anymore to attain that what's been attained and
then what's next is to care for others so whether one is beginning in practice
or in the middle of practice or at the end of the whole cycle of practice
that in the buddhist teachings at least that this
inclusion of the well-being of others is important and and in the first beginning teachings
to his son tremendous care about the consequences
of our actions what's the impact that we our lives how we live has in the world around us and one of
the things that the coronavirus teaches us is that that impact might be
invisible to us how we buy consumer goods
uh you know we don't see the impact of the on the people who
mine the resources we don't see the impact on the countries and the peoples from whose who made it in fact
sweat houses or in factories we don't see the impact in pollution and the environment in the communities
that are impacted by that and so to be concerned about the impact the consequence of our actions on
others can also start to involve a care and sensitivity to the unseen ways
that we impact the world because it would be nice if we could live in the world without
any harm caused to this world both seen and unseen known and unknown
what a great thing it would be and what a great thing is to meet people and know there are people in this world
who are living with this kind of care and this kind of sensitivity because they're free because they
matured and developed and they know how to do this in a way that nourishes the best in our
hearts so as we come to the end i know the end
we've come to this this phase of the pandemic i think it's a wonderful time to reflect
a little bit about how how beneficial it is for self and for
others to include in our practice the welfare and happiness of others as
well so thank you very much