so a warm welcome to everyone here
as i mentioned earlier diana is away for the evening teaching on retreat so i'm
happy to be here with you this evening my name is kim allen
i want to talk tonight about thought perhaps in a different way
though then you may have heard we definitely use thought all the time
in daily life but it's also easy in meditation
to see that thought is usually what distracts us in some way we lose our mindfulness
because we start thinking so then it's easy some people conclude from this that
thinking is always bad or that the aim of meditation is somehow to
eliminate thinking thinking mind can only be a hindrance
but actually that idea is not in line with the buddhist teachings
the buddha had a more nuanced view of thought and its role in the normal functioning
as well as in the awakening of the mind there's a place for thought on the path
of development so he identified which kinds of thought
are actually unskillful and unhelpful and he also talked about kinds of
thought that are helpful that are skillful some of them might even be necessary
along the path of liberation so i will talk somewhat about
unskillful thought because it's something that we're very familiar with and it's an important
thing to uh to have some sense of how to work with but i want to leave plenty of room
to talk about the helpful kinds of thought and conceptuality that we can do
because we don't get to hear about those quite as much and there are a number of them uh
described in the buddhist teachings now in the end what you may have heard
from teachers is correct in that the ordinary thinking and conceptualizing mind
is a hindrance to freedom at some point and it will be let go
maybe we'll even develop some alternatives to it along the path but nonetheless even concepts and
thinking have a function along our path of meditation
and in daily life i think we're going to need our whole mind to awaken and so that would include
thought so let's look more carefully at what is useful in the thinking mind and what is
not so starting with
how we often experience our mind at least at the beginning of our spiritual development and often for
many people at the beginning of a sit all along the path what we experience is
a lot of discursive what's called discursive or obsessive
excessive thought where the mind is going over conversations it's making
plans it's worrying about what that person might have meant by what they did yesterday we're sort of
caught up in that and it usually comes with a lot of largely unseen
views about the world and about ourselves and all of that and a lot of this
thought is kind of running along habitual patterns most of this kind of thought is not
especially original and we've probably thought it before and if we look more carefully we can see
that a lot of it is about myself and is essentially
based somehow in wanting or not wanting or not being very clear so this kind of
unhelpful thought which i'm just going to call discursive thinking this is the kind that is
um common at the beginning of a sit shall we say and it kind of dominates
our mental experience and so because of this thinking it's a bad rap it just sort of gets a blanket statement of
ah this is not useful let it go try not to think try to get concentrated
and not do that but with that kind of attitude
if we have that idea that all thought is like that we set up a lot of aversion in the mind
and this can actually just further entrench our tendency to think right as soon as we say you know don't
think of a purple elephant that's all you're going to think about right so if you say don't think or stop all those
conversations in the mind and get concentrated there's a way in which that's not an effective approach yes
so it's unfortunate because some people can get caught in this aversive dynamic
of hating their thoughts for a long time and um but if we look at the early
buddhist texts there's a more nuanced understanding of the thinking mind
thinking as i as i said in the guided meditation thinking is what minds do it's a normal function of the mind so
this kind of normal ordinary thought that we have sort of top of mind can be skillful or
unskillful it can actually be either one of those so i would say that maybe the initial
task of practice is that if we have a lot of the discursive kind of thought is that we somehow have to
reduce that and enhance the skillful part which is no form of right effort
essentially so instead of thinking in terms of let's get rid of all the thought or let's
quiet all that down how about if we tried to change the balance so that more of the thought was skillful
and less of it was unskillful that's often a good way to start so we
can start to explore this um different kinds of thinking by distinguishing
the content of the thought from its qualities let's say so the content
is what we're thinking about it's about our friend or that thing that happened yesterday or
the problem we have with our work that's the content of the thought but then the qualities have to do more
with the energy behind the thought how intense it is uh the manner of the thought what's the
tone of it and the experience of that thinking you know how are we relating to it in some
way so that the kinds of thought that are hindering our spiritual practice the ones that i
mentioned earlier they have a certain set of qualities that we can identify
um most obviously they're disconnected from present moment awareness discursive
thought is about then and there it's not really about here and now
so they feel kind of distant or vague they're yeah they're not connected
secondly they tend to be sticky they they catch the mind and draw it in that's why we get
sucked into this kind of discursive thought again and again it has a hook somehow a stickiness to it and then
thirdly the energy of it is usually somewhat driven you know there's a feeling of i've got
to play this out you know i have to play out this conversation i have to think through this problem
i have to devise some idea about this i have to figure out why this view is correct
there's a sense of um yeah of drivenness to it so that's also useful to know so all of
this adds up to seeing oh when we see the qualities of this unskillful thought it
becomes clear why we get drawn into it so easily it has a lot of qualities that are going to pull the mind away from a more subtle
experience like the breath or the body so we can understand that yeah it's
going to be hard to turn away from discursive thought so you can not maybe not blame yourself
for that so much so instead of trying to get rid of this kind of thought
i like to talk about reducing the intensity of discursive thought is kind of our
first task in practice if you will there are a lot a lot a lot of methods for this
in the in the buddhist teachings it's clear that this has been an issue for people for a long time
so again you're not alone if this is something that you experience so it's not a focus of this talk they'll
talk about a lot of methods for working with discursive thought that
could be a whole talk in and of itself but i'll name a few of them since it's good to be reminded um
so they include first and foremost breath and body awareness that's why we talk about that so much
that's why those are the first instructions i found this to be these to be the best
remedies for discursive thought in fact the buddha says a meditator
should cultivate mindfulness of breathing for cutting off distracting thoughts that's a quote right from
suta so the buddha was talking about this quite directly to his disciples
so breath and body are are a good choice because they're always
in the present moment they immediately take away that quality of discursive thought
that is not in the present moment that vagueness that it has but also really there are other ways
that we can reduce the intensity so for example we can use our thinking mind for something else we can start
directing the energy into thoughts that are about the present moment and this is the point of noting practice
so you may have heard of noting practice where sometimes as we sit we gently name or label
the experiences that we're having oh experience of sadness and experience of
pressure experience of heat experience of joy just noting as we go along a little
you know simple word that goes with what we're experiencing and that redirects some of the energy
that could have gone into unskillful thought it directs it into thought that's
about the present moment it's that simple so it reduces the intensity of that other kind of thought
uh techniques like counting the breath are the the same thing we're using our our thinking mind to be thinking about
the present moment and then um you know once we've gained a
little bit of traction we can actually turn mindfulness toward the thinking process itself
this is another good way to continue reducing the intensity of discursive thought so we can kind of turn the good part of
of our analytical mind against the part that's trying to pull us away
so we can actually gain some insight about thought by looking in this way we start to for example discern those three
qualities that i talked about earlier the uh the nebulousness the stickiness
and the drivenness of unskillful thought all of that can come about as we start
to be able to see thinking with mindfulness
so this means we can start to answer questions like how do i know if a given thought that's
coming in is that one of these discursive or obsessive thoughts that's not useful
or or if it's something that would be okay you know more more beneficial to have and we can see
quite clearly that um generally discursive thought just is
directed toward itself it generates more and more discursion and it doesn't ever resolve
doesn't quite resolve meaningfully whereas in contrast thoughts that are more skillful
it's very easy still to be aware of the body it's pretty easy to breathe through them like i talked about in them
in the guided meditation so there are qualities that we can discern immediately as a thought starts to arise
as to whether or not it's going to be a discursive one and we should be very careful or if it's a somewhat more skillful
thought and we'll talk in a moment more about what kinds of skillful thoughts there are that can arise
so we can start to have just a little bit of wisdom about our thinking we could start to have more
distinction about what kinds of thoughts there are and know that some are useful and some
are not so i would say that the sort of initial part of dharma practice and
maybe the initial part of the sit for many people is to start using our analytical mind
skillfully in order to reduce the impact of this discursive kind of thought that's that's
vague that's sticky and that's driven
but actually we can go one step further and we can start looking at certain kinds of cognition that are
actually praised in sutas this is sometimes a revelation for people to realize
that they there are kinds of thoughts that are worthy of developing in their own right so i want to focus now because i think
it's rare that i it's spoken well up in dharma talks that thought has spoken well of
so let's let's talk a little bit about skillful thought thoughts that actually help cultivate
the mind so the buddha praised learning
quite highly in sutas learning is offered as one of five
highly meritorious qualities that we can have that are said to be a form of inner
wealth in one suta and in another suta it said that these are qualities that
fortify the mind so they literally strengthen it or build it up
somehow so here's the five faith or confidence virtue
learning generosity and wisdom it's an interesting list
isn't it so we have four qualities that are maybe more common you've heard them in
other lists faith virtue or ethical conduct
generosity and wisdom these are qualities that are named all over the texts and
we might aspire to be developing those in ourselves but what about this middle one learning
what is that and why is that named along alongside virtue so learning is as
important as not killing not stealing it's important as giving it's as
important as wisdom so it's quite amazing so what does this
mean what is meant here by by learning um the word that's used there
in uh in pali is actually a word that means literally what is heard so it has to do with
things that we have that we have heard and you can understand this from the way
that things were taught in the buddha's time it wasn't that they had books
most people couldn't even read or write for that matter so if you wanted to hear teachings you
wanted to learn teachings you had to go here a teacher it was about what you could hear
and the opportunity to hear the dharma was very precious actually and so this quality of learning though
was not literally just hearing like i was within earshot and it entered my
ears it has to do also with being a little bit more active given that we couldn't take notes we
couldn't listen to the recording later we couldn't go consult a book
so learning uh and this this thing heard what is heard includes also
some sense of active listening so paying attention and kind of taking it in and integrating
it into what we know and it also includes memorizing it to some degree
remembering it well not literally memorizing it although that was done but remembering it well enough that you
would be able to use it the next day if you heard a dharma talk and had forgotten it by
the time you walked home it wasn't not as useful as if you could remember something about
it so this quality of learning that was praised is to have a sign of an intelligent
interaction with the teachings and that and that is what starts to change our
mind what is what starts to develop the mind in a sense so this kind of learning we can still do
you know we do it through listening to dharma talks online through taking notes maybe through reading dharma books
through reading sutas by exposing our mind again and again we may not remember everything
so well maybe not as well as they did when there was no other option but nonetheless as we hear and learn and
listen to things [Music] they kind of get into the mind in a way
and start to come into our thoughts more often you know teachings will come into our
thoughts i like to tell a story where uh one time
i was just in the kitchen doing washing the dishes or something and i i broke a cup and um
you know normal enough thing to have happen but immediately what came to mind was uh the quote from
ajahn chah where he says oh i enjoy my cup very much but for me
the cup is already broken you know indicating an understanding of impermanence but it's
you know it's a line that i had heard or read a number of times and when i broke the cup my mind said ah the cup was already
broken so it's just a simple moment where i could have gotten angry or
you know said a swear word but instead this thought of the dharma came to mind
and that's you know that's one of the fruits of this this learning that's praised and that's a useful kind
of of uh use of the thinking mind the intelligent mind the cognitive mind the linguistic
mind all those things that we might associate with thinking which is not which is supposed to be bad
but it's not it can be used well there are also many beneficial ways to
use the cognitive mind on the cushion so the buddha for example encourage
reflection on various inspiring themes that will
invoke confidence and joy so in one of the sutas he he offers six
different themes that we could reflect on during sitting and those include the
qualities of the buddha qualities of the dharma the qualities of the sangha
our own virtue our own generosity and the fact that there are beings with
well-developed minds in the world so those are the six themes and it's interesting um
it's also interesting to note that the where i said beings that have well-developed minds
what we reflect on is the fact that they have those five qualities i just mentioned we reflect
that there are beings in the world who have faith virtue learning generosity and wisdom and just knowing that there are people
like that uh can be inspiring and it's skillful to think about that
so any of these themes is said to bring about according to the suta inspiration in the meaning inspiration
in the dharma and joy connected with the dharma so it's interesting isn't it that
qualities heart qualities like faith like motivation and like joy
can emerge from thought so as an example what is what are these
reflections there are specific words given for how we would reflect on each of these six themes and the one for
the for the dharma is like this the dharma is well expounded by the blessed one
to be seen here and now timeless inviting verification pertinent
to be realized by the wise for themselves so it's six qualities of the dharma and
we could just reflect on those even during sitting it's okay to reflect in this particular
way it's kind of like the question i asked what about the dharma
touches your heart in the guided meditation so there's a way in which we can use the
thinking mind to uplift the heart and it says further in this suture that when we are thinking in
this way the mind is headed straight and it doesn't get distracted it's not tangled up with great hatred
and delusion and in fact it will go not only toward joy but also eventually toward concentration
which is interesting also if certain forms of reflection can eventually lead to
concentration so then we can also
look into the cognitive mind's ability to ask questions and explore the dharma in various ways
so i'm talking now about inquiry as a way of clarifying the teachings
and also going deeper into our experience so the sutas report cases of meditators
sitting in meditation and it will literally say in the suta while the venerable so and so was
sitting in meditation a certain train of thought arose in his mind his or her mind
and sometimes it will say at that point they went to ask the buddha a question or maybe they continued meditating and
later they went to ask the buddha a question about it so there are times in which
thoughts can arise kind of out of our sitting practice that are relevant for the dharma dharma questions related to the dharma
or understanding the meaning of the teachings and we don't need to call those unskillful and say oh thinking oh
bad i got distracted from the breath again you know you don't necessarily go off on a long
discursive thought trail about that but you can remember okay my mind came up with the thought
about the dharma maybe i'll look into that later maybe i'll ask the teacher about that later um that
that's okay there are thoughts about the dharma that are that can be taken seriously essentially
we want to take take it seriously when our mind starts inquiring into the meaning of the dharma
so then a more modern inquiry practice is like what we did in the sitting where we can drop in a question
it's not expected that we're going to come up with a clear definitive answer that we could write down and carry
around yes i know the answer to that question it's really more intended as a a way to
lead the mind deeper into itself i've noticed when i do those repeating
kinds of questions that sometimes the first few times i ask it i get an answer that i kind of
already knew kind of a cognitive answer um
but then after maybe if i if i say okay thank you and i rest for a moment and ask again
i start getting answers that are no longer at the surface level maybe i didn't know some of that maybe i
surprised myself oh i didn't realize that that is also touching me about the dharma
something else and something else and eventually maybe there's even a kind of a visceral response that doesn't
have a word associated with it anymore and then we know that we're that inquiry is leading us deeper into
the mind deeper into the heart and it's helping to integrate you know the cognitive mind with the heart with
the body and that kind of integration is useful along the path
so it is clear i think from this that well-directed thought about the dharma relating to practice
has a place on the path but it is true that this is not
sufficient the buddha does say many times that the teachings cannot be fully understood
by the cognitive mind i'm going to read two different translations of a passage that's repeated throughout the sutas about this
one translation is like this this dhamma is profound peaceful and
sublime unattainable by mere reasoning to be experienced by the wise
and another translation says this principle is deep hard to see hard to understand
peaceful sublime beyond the scope of reason subtle comprehensible to the astute
so we start to get the sense that although there is good thinking along
the path we're going to have to develop other dharma qualities also
so the next level of skillful thought if you will is to begin uh directing the attention to
stabilize the attention into samadhi into some gathering of the mind
so letting go even of what could be called thought and arriving at more just a continuous
attention so some of the initial factors that support concentration
are qualities that are called applied thought and sustained thought so where we direct the mind it's
interesting that it's called thought but this means directing the mind toward the meditation object
so if it's the breath placing the mind on the breath placing attention on the breath or the
body for example that act is actually a cognitive act we are intentionally directing the attention
but it's a more subtle kind of mental act right than thinking way more subtle than discursive thought which is way off
at the sort of top level so we start to see that there's a refinement of how we're using the cognitive mind
and it begins to invoke other dharma qualities such as somatic concentration
we can also use thought to cultivate the heart qualities like the brahma viharas
that's a word for loving kindness compassion appreciative joy and equanimity these
are not exactly thoughts but they are things that can be evoked through repeating phrases which are
thoughts through directing the mind to the
feeling in the heart you know these are other ways that we use our cognitive mind to cultivate very
skillful qualities on the path that are taking us much deeper than the level of the thinking mind
amazingly um thought can even be used to evoke the seven factors of awakening
there's an amazing suta that says that
when one this is about speaking about an advanced meditator
dwelling thus withdrawn meditator recollects the dharma and thinks it over
it literally says recollects the dharma and thinks it over on that occasion the awakening factor of
mindfulness is aroused how about that so for someone who's
meditated for a while who has some understanding of how the thinking mind works it's possible to think about the dharma
in a way that evokes uh mindfulness wow it's a very surprising suta
and very interesting one and it goes on to say that the other factors of awakening can be evoked this way also
so it's quite stunning so i like to say that as
as we refine the cognitive mind from discursive thought which we let go of
and replace with more skillful thought we then start to cultivate more and more
wisdom-related dharma qualities and we come to have what i like to call the mind of dharma
where the mind is just operating in a frame where it thinks about the dharma when it breaks a
cup where it calls forth the brahma bihar is as needed where it um understands what activity would be
ethical in a certain situation our mind starts to become useful to us really functional
really beneficial for continuing to walk the path and we can cultivate this kind of mind
simply through beginning with skillful thoughts beginning by reducing the intensity of
the unskillful thoughts and starting with the skillful ones right up at the surface level from that all of the rest can unfold all
the way to the qualities of wisdom insights and awakening but i hope
this talk is at least giving you the idea that the thinking mind is not all bad
you don't need to get rid of it any more than one needs to get rid of a child in order to become an adult
so it's a natural process and it begins simply with replacing
the unskillful side of the discursive mind reducing the intensity and replacing
those with more skillful thoughts that will then lead the mind deeper so may your practice bear great fruit
and may you come to love your cognitive mind
as a tool on the path thank you