so hello everyone and welcome
and uh we're here to
be mindful of our present moment experience
here while you're first paying attention to me
that who is there for you it's amazing this uh connection we have
to through youtube and online and and what it means to
teach mindfulness and being in the present moment and over such long distances
but certainly you're at you are where you are and that's where mindfulness practice
comes alive yesterday i talked about a simple
technique for mindfulness that some people like to have kind of a nice rhythm of a little technique to
that uh to do and also it represents some of the qualities from the aspects of mindfulness
and that was to be here to relax and then to recognize
so to establish oneself here to relax into here
and then to and then to recognize what's here and
that is the act of recognition is quite important so
another way of doing this that's related and maybe it could be done
afterward the first one in the same meditation and that is um
to relax let go to recognize what's here
to recognize what the experience of the moment is and then to
let it be let it be
and as we kind of continue in this relax recognize let be
the relaxing becomes extra becomes work becomes just keeping yourself busy
and it's just been nicer just to recognize what's here and let things be
as meditation goes deeper and deeper and quieter and quieter then maybe even the recognizing seems too
much and the primary thing to do is just let things be
and this letting be is uh is a
is a
kind of in the family of letting go it's a form of letting go and a
very profound form where we're letting go of things needing to be different than how they are
in the moment at least in meditation certainly in life we have to change things but in meditation
that we relax and then at some point the freedom comes
because we're not picking anything up we're not reacting to anything or we're
not believing the reactions or getting involved in them that the ability to recognize
is strong enough that we recognize whatever passes through whatever is happening and we find
ourselves letting it be not being for against it not
being wanting it or not wanting it just here
rooted here letting it be so letting b is a quite a profound form of letting go
and it um it uh in some ways it's more wise
than the action of letting go that when you do the letting go um it just uh
we're just there letting things be and and one of the advantages of that is
that at some point things let go of themselves rather than we letting go
and the ability to just be to let things be in the field of recognition
and and then see that things are let go of because it's trust is so
deep the ease is so deep our non-involvement is so thorough
is quite inspiring quite inspiring to see what how things can unfold without us having to be the
agent for the change so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing the eyes
and taking a just a little bit deeper breath than usual
just a gentle deeper breath almost as if you're
being tender to yourself as you breathe
breathing in breathing out
as you exhale to relax
soften
and letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale to relax the muscles of the face
on the exhale relaxing the neck
and then the tops of the shoulders
and then deep inside the shoulders
exhale relaxing the chest
deep in the chest
and relaxing the belly
softening the belly
on the exhale relaxing the hands the arms
and then the legs and the feet
and having relaxed this way
now become aware of your breathings centering yourself in the body breathing
and recognize how you are
recognize how it is to breathe how it is to be in your body
and let it be
recognize how you are in your mood and emotional state
no matter how subtle or how big
and let it be and breathe with it
sometimes breathing with things we can accompany our difficult states
without being for against easier just let it be
a company
so as what other whatever rhythm that's nice for you
relax recognize
and let be
and if relaxing is too much then just be breathe
recognize let be
experimenting with how is it you can be present
knowing what's happening but give it space
allow it to be itself without being involved
to recognize clearly
is to begin the process of letting be
when we only recognize
and then as we come to the end of the sitting imagine yourself comfortable and safe
at ease being with someone maybe someone who is
suffering in some way challenged
imagine that you are present for the person
but you allow the person to be
would it be like for you to take in someone to really pay attention and to recognize
someone without being involved with wanting something or
not wanting something fixing or any kind of way of asserting yourself or
judging the other person just letting the person be
and taking them in experiencing them more fully
offering them a chance to feel safe around you and feel like you want nothing more than to
be be available and be present allowing the person to be as they are
that sometimes is a profound gift sometimes people do not do not have the
experience of someone who is with them and allows themselves to be
it may be our ability to sit and meditate breathing with how things are letting
things be learning the art of letting be the deep art
will support us and how we the gift we can give others
offering them the kind of respect the kind of love where we recognize someone
and allow them to be who they are
maybe in such a way so it's easier for them to find their own way
without our interference
in the innumerable ways that we can in this practice that we do can
translate into caring for others maybe may we be motivated to care for
the world motivated to live for the welfare and happiness of others
and the welfare and happiness of ourselves
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
so the topic for this week has been the karmic stream and the dharm extremes of
our lives and many people are swimming in the karmic stream only
that's all they know and by all because they that's all they
know that they think that's all there is
and so they're constantly navigating negotiating that that world
and uh we can do wonderful things in the karmic world
uh the and terrible things the
buddhist tradition divides up the activities of the karmic world into two
areas that which is unhealthy or unwholesome
and that which is beautiful and and the encouragement is to do the
things that are beautiful those things are healthy they're wholesome
because it's for your own benefit and for the benefit of others
and so learning how to live without hate without greed without delusion
without criticism and animosity or resentment or
equals acquisitiveness to learning to live with generosity and
love and kindness
but the car for something to be the karmic stream
the karmic stream is based on um as its root
a certain kind of attachment very can be very very subtle
and maybe the easiest way to understand it is attachment to self
some kind of idea of ourselves as being somehow
a solid or substantial or a reference point
and or the subtle attachment to maybe not to ourselves exactly but more
basically uh the there's two base three basic attachments that kind of propel the
whole karmic world and it's not easy not to use easy to see it's uh to really tap into it to be
usually very attentive and sensitive um at the deeper levels
and uh one of them is attachment to sense comfort and sense pleasures
human beings are very oriented sometimes in a very deep way to be comfortable
and to be of pleasantness it's kind of very closely related to being safe
the other is a very subtle attachment to existing to being alive
to being and then a very subtle attachment to not being to not existing
some people and it takes the form something if you watch your own mind stream
and you're watching how this karma plays out in your own mind you can watch and track what you're
thinking about and you can see is your thinking involved with something to do with
comfort and discomfort make things pleasant or unpleasant
is it in some way uh an uh in a certain assertion of identity
is there some uh being someone in your is that part of your mindstream an identity
or is there a movement to not have an identity to not be seen a certain way not be presented some way and not be
recognized certain way and this movement towards being and non-being
to sense pleasure in the buddhist tradition is considered deeply deeply rooted
so that even beautiful karma has that attachment as well
and and so we can only go so far we can in the in the beautiful karma
with good karma we are shaping our future we're shaping
and conditioning ourselves as you can watch your thoughts and see the thoughts that you have kind of condition the next
thought the next thought and and kind of can keep certain minds mental preoccupations going in a way
that can have a negative influence on us or a positive influence on us
but it always involves work it always involves mental activity and over months and years and decades
it takes a toll there can be a wariness a tiredness from always navigating negotiating existing non-existing
identity non-identity pleasure comfort and all that the dharm extreme
uh is uh is not like a dualistic radical different
way of living than ordinary life you might be doing many of the same things
that you do in ordinary life shopping and cooking and caring for family or friends or going to work and all kinds
of things you might be doing but um
it's done without this attachment without any attachment but inc at the at
the deeper level if the dharm extreme is really matured then
there's no attachment to sense pleasures comfort no attachment to existence even to life
and also no attachment to non-existence non-identity to not being alive
one navigates lives a life could be fully
unconcerned with this attachment this preoccupation this fear this desires around these
three areas on the way to that dharma stream
it's learning how to let go of coarser attachments and how to do
care for friends family go to work take care of ourselves do all the things ordinary things people do
but to learn to do them without attachment without clinging to anything and
and but even the subtler ones and so then we find ourselves able to do these things without this layer of work
in the mind of navigating negotiating the self in the middle of it all nabbing and
negotiating how to make ourselves comfortable in the middle of it all it releases a whole level of
preoccupation and the buddhist reference point for this is
there's freedom one goes about the world free and
one does the things that ordinary things that people do that may be appropriate for you
but there is a freedom in doing it there's an ease there's a peace there's an absence of a certain
agitation or contraction that exists always exists in the karmic
stream and to be in the dharma stream is to begin appreciating
how it's possible to live in the world without clinging an attachment
and so it begins with maybe beginning to letting go of bigger attachments
maybe it begins by meditating for some people it's eye opening to begin meditating and realize how much of the
ordinary preoccupations of the mind and how they translate to bodily tension can
be put down and can relax and become quiet and it can be a life changer to realize
how much extra uh preoccupation the mind is spinning
and churning and ruminating that can be put down can be relaxed
and uh and so we begin seeing where it's possible and then the dharma stream is that is to
see that as an open door that as we relax as we let go as we don't act
with attachment the absence of attachment clinging craving resistance is kind of like an
open door that's inviting you hey come here come take a look at this
and and so the dharma stream is found by stepping into that through that door into that new stream
and in the teachings of the buddha reality
is always inviting you welcoming you into this new stream
into the dharma stream there's a wide open door that's ready for you
if you can put down your burden put down your attachments your clinging
and you get to keep your life perhaps because it's not this is not a judgment
about what people do in their lives it's just an idea that do them without clinging
if what you do in your life is completely dependent on clinging
you're doing it because you cling then how you live your life might change
as you let go of clinging and i'm pretty confident that
it'll be for your own good to do that and for the good of the people around you it's not a good
con not a good result to live a life and do things in the world that are
propelled with attachment and clinging that need to have craving uh as part of it
and even that fundamental one the uh attachment to being alive
or the attachment to not wanting to be alive or attachment to identity and non-identity
happiness is not found through identity happiness is not found being preoccupied
with life or death there's a way of putting this down and experiencing a profound peace
and which will help you live your life peacefully and happily and
and wisely and that's maybe one of the key reasons to to put down the attachment so we can live
wisely in the world and live in a way that is really beneficial for others maybe even
inspiring for others being an example for others that's
possible to live a life that's not anxious possible live a life was not greedy or a
life that's resentful or hating and it's a wonderful gift gift to the
world to give that example and now i think one of the clear ways to see it
is in raising children if children see the model of
hate and greed and fear then that's what they think is needed to
live this life but if they have a different model what a gift it is to the children
and uh it's a gift to yourself because if you can live this without this fundamental attachments if you
enter into the dharma stream and really trust it then
when it's your turn to die and if and if you die in a conscious way
chances are you won't be afraid chances are it won't be a difficult thing to do because you don't you're not
attached either way so the dharma stream and the
and the karma stream if you're going to do the karma stream
do it well do it beautifully bring beauty to the world which
spiritual beauty walk in beauty
and uh and one of the ways to walk in beauty to do that is that to realize also that the the
beautiful karma is a precursor support is as a
can point the way to the dharmic stream and uh
and the beautiful stuff that we do just gets done better when it's done
from the dharm extreme so
hopefully this is an interesting distinctions to explore your life understand your life
and as i've said repeatedly one of the primary reference points i'd suggest for you for really studying
these two streams is in your moment-to-moment uh tracking of your
thought streams what you're thinking about and uh right there you'll see all you need to know
about um to really get a sense of the karma stream and the dharma stream
may your thoughts flow in the stream where there's no attachment
so thank you very much and i look forward to being back here next
monday