so for this sunday morning talk
a little bit in the background or the
foundation of the talk is the idea that
the dharma
dharma practice points to simplicity
it's a very simple thing
and it can be deceptively simple it can
be
surprisingly simple uh what we're
looking for and we're looking for
the freedom from suffering the
alleviation of suffering
and and that's at the heart of what the
dharma the whole religiosity of the
buddha is about
and and part of the reason why it's
useful to emphasize the simplicity is
that people who
uh many people will come to buddhism
with all kinds of expectations about
what a religion is what they want
that that is
searching for something that's in a
sense outside of themselves
and there's nothing inherently wrong
with that and
it can be quite wonderful in itself to
find a religious life or source that's
outside of oneself
but uh the dharma of the buddha is in a
sense found within ourselves and it's
kind of very simple way
and um and one way that uh
uh one characteristics of this or
emphasis or this simplicity
is the the practice of letting go
rather than acquiring more ideas more
concepts building up
ourselves and our conceit
there's a real emphasis on letting go
letting go letting go
but letting go is people make it more
complicated than it needs to be
and sometimes react to it negatively
because on this means i've let go of all
my possessions or
let go of the people i love in my life
the
in the teachings of the buddha the
letting go is almost entirely or maybe
entirely
having to do with letting go of
particular mental states or mental
activity
that's within ourselves not letting go
of things of the world
so the primary letting go is letting go
of our clinging
letting go of the grasping or the
craving that we have the contractions
that come along with some of the desires
and aversions we have
and so um
that's what we're letting go of and if
we turn around and really look at
ourselves deeply
we'll see we'll feel that the clingings
the cravings we have
are of way of self-harm the way that i'm
kind of hurting ourselves
causing pain and suffering to ourselves
and in the buddhist analysis
that's the suffering that we have the
most ability to do something about
the suffering that we contribute
contribute to through our clinging and
our
grasping so that's what we're letting go
now when we let go
there are things that we abandon
we're in patent clinging craving
grasping we abandon hatred
aversion hostility and we abandon a
certain confusion a tendency towards
confusion or delusion
so there are things we let go of but
these again
all internal things and there's not a
search for something outside of
ourselves
a search for god a search for some kind
of cosmic
kind of understanding or wisdom or
consciousness is not a connection to
something beyond ourselves
which is a wonderful thing that can
happen
our sense of interconnectedness to life
and all that but that's not the heart
of the buddhist spirituality which is
maybe seems very simplistic
reductionistic maybe not enough
in the fullness of life and
and that may be but still over and over
again the buddha pointed to this
simplicity of letting go of greed hatred
and delusion
and for the buddha that's the
ultimate that's like that to do that
thoroughly fully is this full message
that he's giving
for people who have other ideas of what
they want their life to really be about
um then i think buddhism contributes in
that
it says or offers that whatever your
values are whatever way you want to live
and be connected understand this life
that we live in
even if you're like you believe in god
or cosmic consciousness or
you have your fundamental religious
belief is the interconnectedness
of life all those ideas
what buddhism has to offer is please
don't
don't use those ideas as a justification
for greed hate and delusion
don't don't focus on those so much that
you lose touch
with this deep inner potential to not
have greed hatred delusion
let that be the foundation and then you
can do all kinds of other things
in a much richer more meaningful way
but for the buddha it was really just
this
this inner life that we're rectifying or
freeing and then the rest of life comes
another way
so there's something we abandon but the
letting go is not just about what's
abandoned
it's also about what is gained and this
probably is not emphasized enough in
teachings of letting go
letting go is kind of uh on the surface
can seem like yes we let go of something
and then
at the best where hands are open we're
open-hearted or open-minded we're
kind of left without clinging to
something but it's
better than that letting go of clinging
grasping craving letting go of hatred
and
and hostility aversion letting go
of regrets and agitation sloth torpor
doubt
letting go of all these things we gain
something as a result
and it's kind of like
there's been a there's a dam that filled
with water
and then the gate is one of the the gate
uh
is opened and the water begins to flow
out
and uh and flows out and fills the river
below
and and that just flows and flows and
flows
and it's a wonderful thing to have the
water flowing and not bottled up by the
dam
so the same thing when we let go
something begins to flow something
begins to move through us that maybe has
been held back
by the greed hate and delusion by the
clinging and grasping
and there's the gain of what happens in
that flow
when the when something has been
released and let go
that was covering over or resisting or
blocking
something inside
and um so the um
there's a number of things that uh
open up when we let go
and have cultivated awareness and
presence
and and one of those things is the seven
factors of awakening
that when we have a deep letting go
it frees up a certain kind of energy
frees up a
certain kind of momentum in our life
that makes available to us much more
mindfulness
a clear this cleared
distinguishing of phenomena clear seeing
which we call investigation sometimes in
english
effort
joy tranquility
samadhi and equanimity and
these are not strange foreign ideas to
human beings
it takes maybe it doesn't take that much
an uh
reflection maybe to see that they're
they accompany us to some degree maybe
in small degrees here and there
in our life in ways that we don't really
appreciate
and so one of the ways the examples the
buddha gave for this
that and how these seven factors
awakening can arise
is when is listening to
the buddha at least giving a dharma talk
a great teacher gives a talk
and it's uh it's very engaging and
compelling to really be present and
listen closely and
like what's being said is so important
so clear so profound
that we're really there to find out what
is this that's being said
and there's a fullness of attention that
is satya's mindfulness really there
that and it isn't that it's we're
self-consciously mindful
but we're really the tension is really
present to take in this experience and
maybe even with all our faculties not
just cognitively with the mind but with
our
our hearts our body or all our senses
as as the thing ordinary thinking
discursive
conversational mind quiets down
and we're just taking something in with
clarity there might still be some
thinking involved
but the thinking is very very simple and
clear
that there there's more and more clarity
in the eyesight and the perception of
things
and we see things much more clearly
i remember i gave i went i went to i had
i've been to very engaging talk
sometimes academic talks when i
when i saw taking botany classes and i
was really absorbed in the details of
the botany class
and would leave class and and um
and i'd come we'll go out into the
courtyard in this university where i
went
and i'd see everything so clearly
everything sparkled and it was clear and
bright
and in a way that they hadn't been when
i went in there's something about
uh cleaning the the filters of our eyes
developing a clear seeing
that comes with really being present and
not distracted by our thoughts
and then listening to a good talk
there's there's some kind of aliveness
and energy and alertness
it might even sit up a little bit
straighter oh this is interesting what's
going on here
and then there's also maybe some joy
maybe you wouldn't call it joy at the
time but
all the troubles fall away all the
preoccupations of life all the way we're
really right here
and it just feels so good and delightful
to be with the experience and also
there may be listening to a dharma talk
very reassuring
a deep sense of reassuring oh this makes
sense this puts things into place
this is the way forward and something
inside of us settles and gets peaceful
and quiet
and then there's a gathering together of
all the faculties we're really here in a
concentrated way which means
we're really present with all we have
focused
on what's being said and what the
meaning is
and perhaps also similar to tranquility
it's so reassuring and so
so clear what's being said that now i
understand there's an equanimity and a
balance and
now i understand that there's no value
in
grasping on or pushing away or
leaning forward or pulling back there's
value in just staying
balanced and taking in the experience
being present for the experience
without the usual reactivity with it and
there's the equanimity
so with letting go uh
the and the kind of the gate of the dam
is opened
it's the the water is the seven factors
of awakening
and um what's remarkable is that these
are
um can be seen almost as
qualities or aspects of awareness itself
as we become more aware in an
unobstructed way
it gets filled with these seven factors
of awakening the opposite of this
according to the buddha is the five
hindrances
sensual desire aversion lethargy and
resistance
agitation and regrets and doubt
and these have the opposite effect
the hindrances they hinder they obstruct
they cover over things
and so
it's like closing the gates of the dam
and then the water builds up pressure
behind the dam
i block something and um as we get
partly because with the hindrances the
focus of the mind is to be preoccupied
with something
and to be preoccupied in a contracted
and narrow and tight way
and so there's no room for the seven
factors of awakening
to flow out into the awareness or be
found in a clear form of awareness
so the buddha talked about letting go of
the five hindrances
and it isn't just letting go of them
that's important but it's also how they
create space
or open the gate for the seven factors
awakening to begin
opening or peering or flowing
into our presence into our awareness
and so we're gaining something as well
and uh and so
the letting go of great hate and
delusion
is not just about what we abandon
it's also what we gain
in other teachings the buddha points to
the five
the four divine abodes the four
brahmaviharas
is what starts flowing when the
gate has been pulled away from the
opened in the dam
then there's a so there's mehta uh
karuna mudita and upeka the pali words
usually translated into english as
living kindness compassion
appreciative joy sympathetic joy and
equanimity
and these are beautiful qualities of art
and they also are limited by our
preoccupations there's no room
for love and care and compassion if
we're
caught up in things like desire cut up
and aversion
doubt regrets and so to abandon those to
release those
it isn't just a matter isn't that we
have to then evoke this loving kindness
or compassion
there's something about the heart that
has space now to breathe breathing room
for the heart
that tends to then give birth to
these beautiful qualities of heart
there's space for them and if there's
space for them they flow
and so part of practice is to abandon to
let go
so that some of the best parts of our
human life
can flow and have a chance to be present
and so
and so the simplicity of all this is
that this is
this core aspects of the buddha's
teachings
is not exactly a religious teaching
it's not exactly a um you know
my religion versus your religion it's
actually teaching something which
um just as uh i'd like to think of it
just practical
psychology or practical uh spiritual
practice
that's available to anybody regardless
of what religion they are
and there's a remarkable teachings from
the ancient discourse
that points to this that i'd like to
read
from the connected discourses of the
buddha the book of threes
and i think it's um
this course
71 i think
and so here a man comes to
ananda the buddhist buddha's one of the
chief disciples
and asks him this question who's dumb
dhamma is well expounded
and dhamma is can be a word that's
synonymous with religion
and in the ancient world it means
teachings or religious doctrine or
something like that
so who's religious doctrine is well
expounded
the question one question on who in the
world are practicing the right way
the good way who are those people who
are prac really practicing the
good way and the true way
and then question number three is who in
the world
are the fortunate ones
and um and so the buddha then
ananda goes on and says that
those who teach the abandoning of
greed hatred and delusion
[Music]
are the ones um um
he says this what do you think
is that dumb of those who teach the
abandoning of great hatred illusion
well expanded or not or how do you take
it
and the person who is talking to ananda
says well the dhamma of those who teach
the abandoning of greed hate and
illusion
is well expounded and you know the
religious teachings of those who teach
the abandoning of great hate and
delusion
that's well taught that's a good
teaching
and and what do you think ananda
continues
are those practicing for the abandoning
of lust hatred
great hatred and delusion practicing the
the good way
in the world or not how do you take it
those practicing for the abandoning of
great hate and delusion
are practicing the good way
and then are those who are practicing
who are abandoning greed hate and
delusion and really cut them out
really obliterated them to the end
are they the fortunate ones and the man
says yes those are the fortunate ones
so then that was that what he says next
is uh very nice
um the the householder the man who's
asking
questions for of ananda says
it is astounding it's amazing ananda
that there there is no that you have not
extolled
your own dhamma nor any denigration
of the dumb of others but just teaching
the dhamma
in its own sphere
so buddha ananda is not
championing the buddha's dharma
or or dismissing the importance of other
people's dharma
which is often what you get if someone
says what's what's the best religious
teaching in the world
some people might say oh mine is of
course but rather
than saying something like that ananda
is just offering this principles idea
about abandoning green hate and illusion
and then
and then rather than making any claim
about how wonderful it is
he asks the the person
asking the question is this well
expounded
is this the good way is this are these
the fortunate people
those who practice it and the man admits
that's
that's the answer that i was looking for
and so um
so this simplicity of um
of this inner look and not looking
outside not looking for what's ultimate
in kind of kind of religious way
maybe not looking for metaphysical
claims of truth
not looking for deep understandings of
the nature of the universe the world
the cosmos the beginning of time the end
of time
there's many answers that the buddhism
doesn't answer
but rather to
the heart of it is the simplicity of
looking
within oneself and freeing oneself
of forces which limit us
that block the flow letting those go
and then letting something beautiful
flow that's there
kind of like it's there waiting for us
though it's not really there
it's not like a thing that exists
independent of us
it's thing that exists with opening up
with the freedom with abandoning with
awareness
set free and um
and so letting go both
involves what is abandoned but also what
is
gained and um
and so we gain and then
and more often than not what the buddha
talks about is
we abandon greed hatred and delusion
and then we gain freedom in some places
he adds a fourth
thing that's abandoned so there's four
things
and this maybe is helpful the fourth one
to keep in mind
so that we abandon the great hate
delusion
and be sure to keep it really simple
the fourth thing to be abandoned is
conceit
greed hatred and delusion and conceit
and and then we really let go of conceit
as well
then having abandoned great hate and
delusion won't give rise to conceit
look how special i am i'm i have the
most wonderful teachings i have the most
wonderful practice
i have the most wonderful attainment i'm
the most fortunate one
the idea of making making an eye out of
it and building up the self
is also abandoned and this is also
a delightful thing that
opens the gates for what's
wonderful in us to flow out conceit is
one of those things that closes the gate
blocks the flow in a sense
so um keeping it simple
appreciating the value of what we can
let go of within
that which blocks us and limits us and
appreciating
what's gained as we let go and
really feeling into that and
experiencing those gains
and maybe in doing so becoming
recognizing the seven factors of
awakening with that in us
maybe recognizing them
in a very small initial way but slowly
developing
having them recognizing them more and
more and giving space for them and
letting them really be a support for
this life of freedom
a life that is free of clinging
so thank you very much and uh
and may this week be one in which
you discover the value greater value in
letting go
in recognizing the seven factors
awakening
in your life