so a warm hello from redwood city here at
the imc and um welcome to our morning meditation
here and other times around the world and thank you for the
people who are greeting on chat it's lovely to see your names
and see your location and and to receive the greetings
when i was practicing in burma i practiced with a teacher named upandita
and his series of his talks were translated and published in english
with a book titled the state of mind called beautiful
a state of mind called beautiful and of course we can be in many
different states of mind but the idea that we can also have a state of mind that's beautiful
i think is quite inspiring and in fact this is what this anapanasati
is working towards and buddhist practice in general is for us to discover
or cultivate a state of mind which is quite luminous beautiful
inspiring in and of itself and one of the i've been fortunate to
see many beautiful places in the world and inspiring sunsets over the sea
and all kinds of things and the thing that i've that seems that i
for me has been the most beautiful thing to see is the beautiful mind and
why that's incomparable with the beauty of nature or beauty
other kinds of beauty i can't quite explain but maybe because it's uh so subjective
or so intimate while the same time as not being personal
something quite wondrous and uh so with the ninth step of
anapanasati the direction is to experience the mind
and so it's shifting from what it's kind of
like shifting from what to how and if i really want something if
i go to the supermarket and i really need something quickly
maybe we're having a big family dinner and everything's dependent
upon getting you know having salt and there's no salt at home and so
everything's gonna we need to get salt so i'm sent to the store to get salt and
i've never bought salt in the store i bought many things but somehow i can't remember ever having bought salt
and but i'm in a hurry and guests are coming and and and so all i'm focused on
is getting the salt and i'm searching the aisles searching the
names of things on the aisles to see where they have the salt and and i don't notice anything else in the
store but looking for the salt and and then when i finally get the salt i just focus on getting to the checkout
counter and the shortest line and my mind is completely consumed
with the thing that i want and nothing i don't really notice too
much anything else because it's so important to get that salt so it's all about the what the mind has
and um but maybe the end of the day if all this busyness of something i sit down and then i realize
how i am and i realize that i'm tired and maybe tense from searching for
salt and and the residue is still in me and all that and so i can feel a little bit how
i am but the initial how i am has to do with why i feel kind of
tight in my shoulders and my belly i'm weary in my face and and i feel a little bit discouraged
that i should pitch a big thing that got caught up in salt and so it's still about a what even i'm
feeling conventionally how i am but as i settle in and step back i notice something
that's very different and then as i notice how i am how the mind is
how the mind is that's processing all this how the mind is that knows
how the mind is as it knows searching for salt how the mind is when it knows how it
knows i'm tired and weary how the mind is and it's kind of like
the mind is the container or the reference point for receiving experience
and it's the state of mind it's not a thing but it's still a state that we can
feel and uh and that is when we that's where
the beauty begins to show itself and something very special about that shift to the how rather than the what's
of our experience the the how which is the how we're aware
how the mind is as it operates
so with that we'll do a meditation and we'll maybe at some point shift me
more to this how and so taking
a assuming a meditative posture
and of course how you are can begin right away how are you in this body
how are you in your posture
and to answer that question there is the mind is involved in a what
the particular sensations of the body
the position of the body
and then how is your breathing
and how are you with noticing your breathing
do you have a reaction to how you're breathing a response
is there a for and against something or wishing it to be different or want to make it different
what happens if you simply just know you're breathing know how you're
breathing
closing your eyes
and if it makes sense go inward into your body and feel the places where there might be
tension and holding
perhaps you can relax the shoulders release the shoulders
relax release the belly
if there's some way to relax or adjust your hands so they're more relaxed
release your hands adjust your hands so
there's no tightness in your hands
and is there can there be a softening in the face
in the easing up of all that we hold in the face
around the eyes and the forehead the
cheeks perhaps imagining there's lots of space
in front of the face behind the face
for the muscles of the face to release to relax
for the face to rest
then how's your mental activity
do you feel is there a lot of energy and thinking or
is the mind sluggish
is there any tension pressure
and if there is tension or pressure can you release the mind
release relax the thinking mind
quieting your thinking
and how is your mind what how is it what's your mental state
or the state of your heart heart mind
which is very closely related to how is your how are you aware
how are you receiving experience
oftentimes what the mind is focused on is the objects of our desires
objects of our aversions or the vague
kind of objects of our confusions
can you feel the part of the mind that is free of desire
that is not leaning forward or stretching forward
focused on having or getting or the mind that's free of desire
maybe it's a back corner of the mind or a deeper layer of the mind
or something at the center
maybe it's something that doesn't have a lot of distinguishing characteristics
a feeling of absence
is there a part of the mind which is free of aversion
part of the mind is not about something not focusing on
something that's not liked
a place where there is no aversion and because of that maybe the mind is
not so concerned with what
a place where the mind can rest in a peaceful place
and can you become aware of a place where the there is no confusion
even if there is confusion as well someplace where there is no confusion
because the mind is not
focused fixated on a subject something it wants doesn't want
something is trying to understand
the part of the mind that can be at rest with itself
and then becoming aware now of your overall state of mind
the state of mind within which everything you know is known
but a state which is always more than what is known
so it's not something that we know as much as something we feel
a wide open expansive
feeling of the state of mind
and so that you don't get too involved in this state of mind looking for it
wanting it
fixating on it as you feel your state of mind
also be aware of yourself breathing in and breathing out
maybe as if breathing in and out you're breathing through the state of
mind we're breathing at the very center of the state of mind
with a state of mind so wide and broad that it includes breathing within it
breathing in experiencing the mind
breathing out experiencing the mind
and perhaps as you shift
from focusing on what you're thinking about
to experiencing the mind experiencing being aware
that this mind this maybe this awareness
maybe begins to have no sharp boundaries no edges
somehow it's related to the spaciousness around
to space not the same but
it has qualities of clarity like space or spaciousness like space
perhaps stillness like space around you
breathing in experiencing this
the mind breathing out experiencing the mind
as you exhale letting go of all the things you're thinking about
all the what's of life all the objects of thought
and then on the inhale experience
your overall state of mind
through a role state within which thinking occurs
but as a state that's broader than our thoughts and ideas the what's
exhaling letting go whatever you're thinking all the what's
inhaling and feeling the
broadness the peacefulness
of the state of mind that contains all things within it
like a room contains all things within the room
and then as we come to the end of this sitting bring to mind some person who
you have an uncomplicated relatively uncomplicated relationship
and bring them to mind so there's some image of them or sense of them
idea of them but rather than your thoughts and
memories and desires concerns about about the person
allow the person to just to sense the idea the image of the person whatever
sense you have to just rest
in the openness of mind within this general state of how you
are there's nothing you have to do about the
person but just let them be
included in your state of mind through your image your idea your sense of them
so you're not actively relating to them rather just being with them
in your mind with your mind
if we're relating to them with our desires and our concerns then we're involved with what
but if we just allow them to be included in the how we are resting there
not actively relating or wanting or not wanting
just allowing the person to be in the peacefulness of the state of mind
and now maybe you can with some tenderness or care
can you now evoke a mood of good will of kindness for
this person of generosity
maybe wishing them well is almost too much
but imagining them well
feeling the goodness of their well-being
you know gently keeping them in your open spacious attention
now wish them well may you be happy
may you be safe
may you be peaceful
may you be
free
and is there some way that you can learn from how to
include someone in your state of mind in this kind of way
it is in fact a way to be close to your good will for
others rather than rushing into the whats and
the shoulds and the doings
as you meet people today in your life
take your time to let them be known
to receive and listen and sense them
in a generous state of mind
and then perhaps other things can happen and those other things might be related
to your good will may this practice of ours support
us to meet the people of the world with our good will
may all beings be happy
so
so i find that one of the inspiring topics in the teachings of the buddha
is the teachings around cheetah so ci tta which
is often translated in english as mind or sometimes it may be in context is also translated as
state of mind and maybe there's no difference between mind and state of mind
the mind here as i said yesterday is not a thing it's not like we can see the mind in
some clear like take a microscope in the brain and discover where the mind is the mind is
more of a gestalt it's more of a the sum total
of our mentality of how the mind works and so it's not a thing and so because
of that maybe because of that the buddha never
talks about letting go of the mind he talks about letting go of a form of
feelings of perceptions of mental activities and he also talks about letting go of
something that we've come to understand in the west as consciousness the pali word is vinyana
and it's possible that vinyana should not be translated as consciousness
there's a whole history of about maybe three four hundred years or so 300 years
maybe of the western use of the word consciousness it's kind of a coined in just you know
in relatively recent times and um but it's uh it's kind of entered
into our languages word consciousness and the idea of it probably in a deeper deeper way in the last
hundred years or so and we take it now as many of us as kind of second nature's obvious what it is
and and it's often held up in religious circles spiritual circles meditation
circles as something really ultimate and there's ideas of cosmic consciousness ultimate consciousness
different uh states of consciousness altered consciousness and so it gets really there's a lot of
it gets that word consciousness gets a lot of association a lot of power a lot of
projection a lot of a lot of expectations and hopes around this word
and and a lot of people will feel that somehow a broad state of consciousness is
somehow ultimate and really profound
and i certainly don't want to diminish the ultimate feeling of it the profundity of
of states of consciousness states of awareness but what's fascinating is that for the
buddha whatever that is if it's vinyana this word that he we
translate his consciousness he says let go of that let go of that and um and sometimes he even treats it
as a kind of a problem clearly it's problematic this vinyana is what we translate as consciousness
and um and but he never says that about chitta
about mind maybe mind should be translated as consciousness but consciousness also has a sense in
english of something that knows and the state of mind i'm not sure exactly if it's
something that knows but it's a broad a tone or mood or
feeling or sense of the mind and sometimes that state of mind can feel fragile it can feel sluggish it
could feel agitated contracted and certainly sometimes the state of mind
doesn't feel good and in fact some of the some of the sufferings the dukkha
that this buddhist practice is meant to alleviate is experienced as kind of a vice-like
experience of the mind or the heart where it's really tight irritated
mind is like rough sandpaper perhaps or um you know the mind you know just feels
just so miserable in our minds oppressed by it so sometimes the mind
can feel that way but the mind can also feel the opposite of that we experienced and the word cheetah
is a very fascinating word that this is what used to to translate as mind because the word
has many other meanings or homonyms same sounding words word we would spell
the same way and but the dictionary for cheetah also
has the word for brightness as a definition for cheetah also wondrous or wonderful
and so there's maybe a little kind of idea that the mind is something really
not exactly in itself but has is related to something wondrous and bright
sometimes the mind is called a luminous in buddhism teachings of the buddha or
clear or clean the mind it becomes clean and not that the mind is inherently any
of these things because the mind is not a thing that can be inherent to anything
maybe it's a little bit more like a hologram or you know or yeah
something that doesn't quite exist by itself and you could put your hand right
through the mind if you ever see it it's not quite not there but it's um
it's still a mood a feeling a sense that is can be very powerful
very significant for us and so significant that as i said often
when the mind is suffering it's really oppressive when the mind is happy or peaceful or
clear the mind feels quite wondrous quite bright and open
so um so the uh and much of the buddhist
path of practice is real is is done in terms of the mind
and that's uh sometimes it's done so instead of personal terms instead of saying i'm
training myself uh it's we're training the mind we're
developing the mind and we're liberating the mind and this is i find fascinating that
plenty of times the buddha doesn't say that a person gets liberated
rather the mind gets liberated and some of you might find a little bit
uh disappointing that find out that you will never get liberated and um that's not the name of the game
um but your mind will get liberated and at your job whatever you are whatever the you is a job is to help
the mind experience liberation to be free to bring it to some kind of beauty
and this this idea that the mind has the potential for beauty for luminosity for brightness for
cleanliness i find phenomenally inspiring and and but also that my other things
even more inspiring is that the mind is not a thing because it's not a thing
it's malleable it's shapeable it uh it's uh we're never stuck with our mind
might be stuck with our brain and um in whatever way the brain works
but to the mind we're not stuck with the mind it's uh it's the it's kind of the field
within which our practice uh has its effect its influence
that as we develop as we develop more concentration more mindfulness more letting go more
equanimity more wisdom more strength in the practice
in the mind that the mind begins to um to um whatever then
we call the mind say the mind is starts to have a wondrous feeling wonderful sense that we
can experience and and one of the things i also find
wonderful about this word cheetah the way it seems to be used in the suttas is that it's very personal the
experience of it so don't go looking at a buddhist text or listening to a buddhist teacher like
myself for a definitive definition or exp or
description of what how the mind is experienced and then try to make sure that you have that
experience too or feel bad because you don't have it the way it's described um
you're the your mind you are shaping your mind your the this this thing that's being
constantly morphed and changed and shifted that's something that's arising within you with all the cause and conditions of
how your inner life works and how your attention works and what you focus on
and what you're how you're thinking or conceiving it's a dynamic thing so it's very
personal so it's more discovery of how you experience it
then you have you don't be concerned about discovering what the right way to experience the mind is
or what the right mind is or how the mind is supposed to be
but you can as we feel the mind become aware of a mind that is has an ouch to it
and a mind that has an ah and this very technical terms in gil
language ouch and ah is meant to kind of give us lots of room to not get caught up in the
details and try to be right or wrong or it's a very simple thing ah that
that's an ouch that the state of the mind doesn't feel good that's not doesn't that it's and now and or this feels good
and the direction of buddhist practice is in the direction of the ah
direction of the beautiful mind in whatever way that you define or experience or see beauty
luminous mind clear mind clean mind spacious mind peaceful mind
so it takes a while and i'm not still you don't have to kind
of be in a hurry to experience some of the wondrous ways the mind can be experienced
but as the anapanasati develops and as we become calmer and more settled going through the steps
especially after step eight where we're pivoting mental activity relaxes it means we're
not so fixated on the what's what we're thinking about and wanting and but we're beginning to rest back into
the into the easy chair of the mind we're resting back and just
allowing and feeling and sensing the overall state of the mind and
breathing with that breathing in experiencing the mind breathing out
experiencing the mind so thank you and we'll continue tomorrow