so hello everyone and welcome
to our time here to meditate and explore some of the teachings
so the topic for this week is the mind and the state of the mind
and but not just the mind itself
but the mind that we're mindful of that uh the mind state the quality of
the mind the quality inner quality of our state being that
it's one thing for it to be what it is and it's something different to be aware of it to be mindful of it
i like to think of mindfulness practice as the meeting of two things it's meeting of
life experience of life whatever it might be and
uh mindfulness a kind of awareness which is a little bit intentional
especially initially a little bit um full
uh dedicated devoted attention to whatever is
to itself devoted to attention but the meeting of attention and experience
and so it's one thing to breathe it's another thing to breathe mindful breathe
mindfully it's one thing to have a body it's one another thing to be mindful of the body
to have the awareness meet the experience of the body and uh it's one thing to have
experiences of mind and to be aware of him for today the kind of general state of
the mind and um and so the
the what i'd like to emphasize today is something very simple about the mind the
mind state the mood or the disposition of the mind
it has many flavors many aspects but the one today is that a mind can be
the mind state can be one that is contracted
or it can be scattered it can be dull and sinking mind or it could be
over energized and kind of uh kind of
spinning out and and uh jumping around so uh one is called the sinking mind
sometimes that's called um uh
overactive mind and uh and so
or sometimes the mind feels contracted and small and tight just kind of caught up in its little concern and there's no
nothing outside of it and other times not just not not the opposite is not exactly expanded that's
for later but the opposite is to be scattered and distracted and fragmented and
and just jumping all over the place so what happens
if we're mindful of that we're aware of
that so um and so the kind of the label i like to
suggest you can choose your own for these two states but uh uh contracted mind
and scattered mind and if you're caught up in thought even if the same train of thought it's kind of like more like a
scattered mind distracted mind contracted mind or
distracted mind maybe that's maybe a good pairing
and and so when you find yourself kind of sinking mind dull mind contracted mind
recognize it as such when you have a scattered mind a distracted mind an over energized mind
recognize it as such and
recognize what it's like to be mindful of it
what changes when you settle back and clearly recognize it
without reactivity without judgment without stories what it means just a very simple
like you're taking awareness i'd like to think of silent awareness and meeting the state of the mind
and um and if your mind is not any one of these two scattered dull
um sinking sleepy if it's not distracted scattered
fragmented um and then maybe just uh appreciate what the mindfulness is like what
awareness is like then so i'm hoping this instruction is very
simple so it's either contracted or scattered
or there's an experience of what it's like to be aware of that the mind that's aware of itself what
happens to the mind then if this instruction is too complicated for how your sitting is going and how
you're used to sitting you can just not worry about it but
it might think of it's little addition to your practice and maybe not doing it all the
time but once you start getting settled into it
so assuming a comfortable posture
and in the comfort of this posture adjust it so that it's also alert
so the posture brings a kind of wakefulness or
a little bit of energy that supports attention
scanning your body making now small maybe not so small making adjustments in
posture shifting a little bit
rocking little teeny bit back and forth or sideways and
twisting yourself a little bit just kind of come
finding a midpoint where things feel balanced
gently closing your eyes
then taking a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing as you exhale
letting your breathing return to normal and on the exhale
relax different parts of your body release them
the holding
and then settling in with your breathing and taking on the next minute or so
to be as simply present for breathing as you can with not any agenda but just seeing for
one minute you can hang in there experiencing every in-breath and every
out breath without strain but with devotion dedication
as if it's the most important thing of for this minute
and then settling in again with just breathing quietly
noticing the general quality of your mind state
this your mind state state of mind
seem contracted or dull
sinking
does your mind state feel scattered or distracted
fragmented and jumping around
and if it's one of those two things or if it's something else
to be mindful of that to be aware of it to have the me there be a meeting
of the state of your mind and the awareness of it
an awareness that's simple almost permissive of how you are
so just simply aware of your mind state
and what happens when you do so
to meet your experience
in such a way that your experience feels safe
from your judgments your over-involvement your fixing wanting something different
to be a good friend to your experience by
meeting it simply for what it is
and becoming aware of the quality of your mind your mind state
with a simple meeting of it this is how it
is noticing if it's contracted or scattered
dull and heavy
or distracted over energized
and what happens to your quality of your mind state when it is met with awareness
taking the time to step back and observe the state of your mind
quality of your mind sinking mind or over energized mind
dull mind active mind
and then allowing it to be that way but to observe it clearly
a meeting of awareness and the state of your mind
recognizing it clearly what happens to the state of mind as you
do so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
if you've learned something about awareness
meeting experience
to let your awareness meet the world or how you
construct the world that we live in
turning your attention outward and simply meeting it as a witness
as someone who cares but is without being over-involved or
under-involved without being for or against
just to see and meet be present first and foremost
to know the world in whatever way that comes to mind
and to perhaps drop into your heart
maybe the feeling center or the place where you feel
good will kindness generosity or
care compassion or love
what might be called the heart center
and then meet the world now from the heart center
meet it with your care and kindness good will
gaze upon the world kindly
gaze out across the lens with goodwill and care
and it's a powerful thing to end meditation practices
with reflecting upon evoking even this good will and care for the world
for others and to connect the meditation practice
with benefiting the world
and then so then in in may it be that in intentional and
unintentional ways in ways that you know in ways you don't know
may it be that this meditation session can be for the welfare and happiness
of others may it somehow spread from each of us
individually and from all of us as a group may it spread out across the lands
as a movement is a
domino effect of goodness generosity
care and love may it be
that somehow our practice is for the welfare and happiness of the world
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
me
so for this third talk on the third foundation of mindfulness
mindfulness of the cheetah wonderful term
and here we're taking it to be the mind state the general quality of the mind
and here the mind doesn't necessarily limit it to what we think of as the mentality
related to the brain the control tower but rather
some kind of the general state of being a state of mood
that once we settle in and relax and really feel ourselves deeply
what's the general quality of our being that we have and that's probably closer to what this
mind state is though sometimes it does feel very closely connected to the mind in some
identifiable way and exactly where this is it doesn't matter too much
it matters more that we are meeting and being aware of kind of the inner quality of our being or state the state that we
are in and but when meditation gets deeper and quieter
the body becomes more and more subtle and sometimes the sense of body kind of
disappears and or not really prominent very much at all and so what that which is left seems
much more belong to kind of a mental world or that part of the
beingness which is not so body centered and um
and uh and so maybe then it's more clearly recognized as the mind state
anyway so as the this uh instruction in the
uh there's a eight sets of instructions or eight pairs of of things to notice
in this four uh third foundations of mindfulness and what's interesting is that
how the it's a particular aspects of the mind the mind states which are emphasized
and i think the reason for that is these are the parts of the mind mind states that are
most useful to notice for the purposes of the path of liberation
if you're really interested in becoming free notice these aspects of the mind
and that's uh distinct from maybe other ways that people are interested in their mind uh their preferences their
their expectations their um you know they have all kinds of
priorities about what you might want to pay attention to the content of the mind the stories we
have in the mind or what it all means but the the description here is very simple
so as i said yesterday it begins with knowing the mind when it's with greed or
without with ill will and without
with delusion and without those are the first three the fourth one of these eight pairs
is to notice whether the mind is contracted or scattered
or exactly what these words mean in pali is not really that clear
the commentaries associate um contracted with sloth and torpor and uh the scattered with agitation and
restlessness and remorse and things like that so
you know we each find ourselves in relationship to these words but something very simple
a sinking mind that gets dull and duller or an over energized mind that's
restless and scattered or a mind that gets really small
it's fascinating to be aware of ourselves kind of really consumed with some preoccupation or really
caught in something and in that cottness or preoccupation the whole state of the mind seems to get
very very narrow and small and uh just like this becomes the bl and end all everything's kind of
kind of wrapped up around uh contracted around some black hole in
the mind that it just you know the gravitational pull is so strong that
um light doesn't come out just because you were so wrapped up in something and um
and so um um so so you know and then sometimes the mind just seems
like it's scattered or someone's has their mind in the clouds or
uh someone is just really really feels spacey um not because we
feel spacious but just spacey and like hardly here but the mind is kind of drifting and
vague and so these are all kind of words that kind of maybe touch into what
the buddha is talking about here and contracted or scattered
and and of course the mind can be other ways but a mind that has
agreed in it our mind that has without greed might be one of these it might be
scattered or it might be contracted and small or it might be expense expanded it
might be energized and agitated and distractible or it might be really kind of
tight and small and focused on its desires same thing with ill will a mind of ill
will might be contracted or scattered a mind of delusion might be scattered contracted or scattered
so this is let's so these things can co-exist but to simply tap into touch into
this this quality of the mind that somehow feels dull contracted or scattered or
over energized and to begin to notice the range of ways in which this works it
can be very big the different uh or it can be very subtle the way this works
and then notice what happens when you're clearly mindful of it
this is where the magic begins happening what happens if you
cannot be for or against your mind state it's easy to be against something that feels uncomfortable or not so nice
but what is it like for you to to not be forward against it or before
and against it and leave that in there put it up on the shelf put that aside for now
and just bring simple clear recognition
to the quality of your mind state and to meet scattered mind a scattered
mind to meet contracted minds contracted mind
as if you're as if you are getting a phd in quality states of mind
and you you have to write a whole you know excuse me for a moment
as if you're getting a phd and you have to write a whole you know chapter on what a scattered mind is like or
contracted mind is like so you have to be a naturalist you have to really kind of stay present
for it and not disturb it too much just be there with it
but what we're really getting a phd in is not in the scattered mind or distracted mind
but we're getting uh a stud or studying what happens when awareness
meets that non-reactive awareness non desirous awareness non-aversive
awareness simple awareness very simple it just meets it
touches it recognize it observes it
what happens to this quality of the inner of your inner life of the mind
when it's known when it's seen in this simple way it's so easy to get pulled into the mind
or be reactive to the mind especially if it's uncomfortable or doesn't feel good
or if it feels really great and also get pulled into it and celebrate it
but what happens is magic of just meeting it and seeing it that's what we're studying here
and so there's a shift of paradigm from being so interested in
what we're experiencing because what we're experiencing is important and we have to kind of adjust it or fix it
to being more interested in the experience of awareness of
experience it shifts the paradigm and shifts the direction like for example it can make
us more less selfish because when we're looking at the experience itself and and
trying to get just the right experience or reacting to it so much of the self comes along
but if we just sit back and just know the mind state oh this is how it is
um and then what happens in that meeting does uh
this this contracted mind begin to open up does a scattered mind begins begin to
settle does the dull mind get a little more light and
does the distracted mind it can
you know get less distracted you know what happens in that meeting that's what's interesting
and so as i said yesterday that we're talking about the third foundation so it assumes that for the really to do
this in a refined way it re assumes that the mind is fairly quiet and stable
we've developed some concentration some stillness and so we don't want you don't want to
be ahead of yourself you want to just practice in what's appropriate for you so sometimes it's appropriate just to do
mindfulness of breathing or mindfulness of the body and settle in and let go of your thoughts
and come back and if the mind is too energized maybe it doesn't work too well to do mindfulness
of the mind but as uh it gets settled that's where it gets more interesting
to start becoming aware of the mind and it tends to happen naturally by itself so you don't have to be ahead of
yourself if you just follow to keep doing the practice
with time as i said the body becomes more subtle or more settled or calls for less attention to itself
at some point meditation becomes um not so much concerned with pleasant
and unpleasant sensations anymore and that concern kind of recedes a little bit and then what's kind of left is to
become aware of is the quality the state of the mind and um so that's what we're exploring
this week and so in the next two days i'll talk about the final four pairs
of uh mind states that we that the buddha taught and there's a shift now from the
first four to the second four and this second four tends to be now
more the states of meditation or the states of mind that begin opening up or
appearing when we really learned well to have this non-reactive mindfulness
awareness meet our experience including meeting all the different vagaries of how the mind states might be
but as we learn that meeting then the mind begins to shift and change and
to be able to recognize how the mind changes is little bit the task of these last four for the next two days
and so one thing i've been fond of as i've talked today is talking about this meeting of
awareness and our experience awareness and the mind and how it brings the hands
together into this namaste into this gesture of respect and as you explore and consider your own
mind mind state maybe as you go through today you'll kind of check in with and see how it is and
maybe you think of it as this meeting as something like a bow respect
that we meet with respect our experience so thank you very much
you