so everyone who's here i'm here up in uh the sierras on my
uh kind of a long weekend vacation with my wife and um and uh
it's a little different place than imc i'll be back there tomorrow and i think the delay
between the my transm my speaking and and you all hearing me is uh
is about 30 seconds which is different than what it has been at imc
so hopefully this all works fine and you can hear me one of the
interesting things is we have a bird that's chirping at a very regular
basis intermittent when it starts doing it but it
it some people say it sounds like an alarm going off
and it's been doing it it doesn't much of the night and uh it's kind of endearing for me
hopefully it'll work for all of you and
so and i'm here in an oak woodland the oak
tree is behind me
nice to see your names familiar names and others thank you rocky for loving the birds i
appreciate that and i think michelle has no sounds but
maybe it's on your end you have to maybe restart and uh yeah
there's a um there's a very long tradition maybe from
the time of the buddha of practitioners practicing in
the wilderness in the forest sometimes actually called forest
monastics and there were no retreat centers the
way we have nowadays
and uh so here we are and uh when you're in the wilderness you
have all kinds of
natural life that comes along and the first today is
this bird that's chirping
so
so those of you know california northern california we've been hiking this weekend along the south fork
of the yuba river and uh including uh going into the river
which was um cold but refreshing
and it seems like the wi-fi connection is quite strong so that's we don't have to worry about
that
and
maybe we should use this uh i should take a photograph of the scene and use it as a backdrop for
our usual youtube it's quite beautiful
here
so william asks is anybody here with me i know i'm alone sitting outside here
i've thought of broadcasting from the woods near redwood city but i looked around to see if i could
find good enough cell phone coverage that uh
somehow i could do it you know connect my computer to
my cell phone but so far i haven't found the connection strong enough anywhere
and i don't know whether using my phone for this purpose would work anyway hmm
so the wi-fi spot this cell phone cover is good at natural bridge state park
yes she'll go down there sometime
so it's at seven o'clock here in the sierras so we can start
so those of you just logging on um we're up here for a little vacation long
weekend vacation and so in order to
meditate with all of you doing it from the place where you are
and now there's a variety of birds around here what you hear is uh it sounds like an alarm it's a bird
that goes on good part of the night it's a lovely sound i think but i don't know how it comes through in the computer
and there's some other uh doves here and other kind of bird sounds that we have so uh
chances are that uh um we're getting a little bit of experience
that meditators have had down through the centuries of forest sounds wood sounds when they
practice in the woods yes there's a beeping sound that's the
so it's a bird that's mostly doing a constant
chirping on a regular basis the first night here we thought it was
some kind of alarm going off in the house oh and there i don't know if you could
hear the chicken the nearby rooster
so let us start and [Music]
one of the benefits of medita meditating in the nature natural
world is to appreciate that [Music]
that we are supported in meditation by nature
now the more and more different bird sounds i don't know how much of it comes through some of it's faint it's getting a
symphony of birds including the one that's keeping the beat so the natural world is
found within us and around us and sometimes the word
dharma is translated as nature
and the different meanings of the word nature and sometimes even people will
see people translated as natural law and one of the things that we are
discovering in dharma practice is the way that the natural processes
that exist within us even around us support can support us
we can learn to be in harmony with them and so practice is not just about
our efforts we certainly have to make some efforts but some of that efforts is to place
ourselves in the in the net in nature in the dharma so that the dharma and nature can
operate in a way that's harmonious healthy beneficial for us and
even liberating and so to partly dharma practice is
partly getting out of the way so that which is unwholesome
that which gets in the way of the natural world or interferes with it in ways that are harmful for us and for the world around
us uh have come to an end and what is beneficial and harmonious
can operate so taking a natural natural
taking a meditation posture
and
allowing your eyes to close
knowing for a few moments that this human body that we have
is as much nature as the woods and the birds and
the natural world around us
we come out of the natural world we are intimately part of it
our body is made up of 100 recycled materials
that come from that the world around us
and to take a few long slow deep breaths
the natural world is filled with rhythm and so here we have the rhythm of
breathing the life-giving breath that we fill our
lungs with
and that our body then expels the co2 to allow for fresh oxygen to
come in
letting your breathing return to normal
and taking those moments to relax your
body relaxing the belly letting the belly
soften relax the relaxing of the body
is part of this process that allows the dharma the nature to work within us in a harmonious way
relaxing in the chest and the heart
releasing the shoulders
and softening the face
letting the eyes rest in the sockets
and then attuning yourself to the natural rhythm
of your body breathing something your body has known to do
since the time you were born
through breathing we are participating
in the process of nature
so and perhaps as you exhale
to let go of your thoughts your concerns
let go of your worries and let go into a deep
trust in the dharma
in that natural process those natural processes within
that will support us
you
oh
so
thank oh
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps the sounds that you hear around that are around me
the birds the dogs the rooster the turkey vultures or the turkey of the
turkeys and
i don't know if you heard the crunching of the deer they're they're stepping around
that we share this world with so many other beings
and to sit and really feel that we're connected some deep way with
other human beings that support our lives and
that we're here with other creatures and
and to live with an open heart to do it all
to live with a sense of care and mutuality that arises because of our
gratitude and to live in gratitude for how much it
is that supports our lives
the trees around that plants that make the oxygen for what
we depend on
the natural world that provides us with our food even if it's grown by farmers
and to feel we're part of this really a part of this world
an intimate connected part to the process the natural process of this world
and to open our hearts and our good will
to well-wishing
for the well-being and the welfare of this world
of all human beings
and of the planet itself of gaian
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
and may we find a refuge in the dharma
so that we can be a refuge for all beings
we could be someone for whom who is safe a refuge of safety
for everyone may all beings be saved
so thank you all for meditation i don't have a bell
so maybe the bird sounds can be our bell today
i don't know how much of it you hear maybe everything but
there's been a wide range of bird sounds
so
so for this monday monday talk i begin a new five
part series and in some ways it continues from the
long series we had on mindfulness or breathing that mindfulness of breathing meditation
in general not just mindfulness of breathing
to really kind of settle in and discover the value of meditation
we discover that it's not all about me myself and mine in fact to be
involved in thoughts and ideations of me myself and mine limits our ability to settle deeply in
the meditation to in a way get out of the way for our um
to get out of the way of our meditative process to get out of the way
of what feels more and more like a natural process of the dharma moving through us
and uh and at some point we begin to appreciate that how powerful it is
to no longer interfere unnecessarily with the natural process of the dharma
within and the unnatural ways or the unhealthy ways
are to have to be caught up in our thoughts our
preoccupations to be lost in thought or to be caught in that what often is
the motivating factors for preoccupation it could be greed it could be resentment
ill will it could be doubt it could be anxiety and fear it can be conceit
a high high number high percentage of our of many people's thinking has me myself
and mine at the center of our thinking that they somehow that concerns ourselves
and of course we want to make ourselves safe of course we want the best for ourselves
and that somewhat paradox is that the less self-preoccupation we have
the more the self who we are more happiness and well-being there is
for us and so we begin slowly to learn that
there is um another way of living that is not
centered on self it might be centered
on this body and mind that we have it isn't that we discount this being
that we are but the ideations the ideas the identities we take on
of me myself and mine we begin to see that even those are those of them which
were are true enough those which are useful at times
interfere with our deep well-being
and i've often when i've been in the natural world like i am now uh
become acutely aware of how some of the preoccupations and concerns
i have living in an urban environment seem to just fall away and it doesn't
matter so many things don't matter so much that i need to get concerned with
maybe in the in the urban environment in the cities there's much more ongoing concern about
how other people think about us how do people think about me
if i spilled my breakfast all over my shirt
i probably wouldn't feel very comfortable walking around my neighborhood but if i spill
on my shirt from camping it's kind of unfortunate but there's all kinds of levels of
preoccupations i don't have of me myself and mine what other people are thinking
and rather i stay in touch with or stay connected to an ease a peacefulness an openness
a feeling that's more closely related to the natural world than what we might feel as part of an
urban environment maybe our social times
so then if you're following what i'm saying then we start feeling their safety
there is support there's guidance there's a profound wisdom in letting go
of self-preoccupation letting go of distractions letting go
of um greed and hatred and delusion
and that what results from that letting go is a vitality is a wisdom
is a safety is an inspiration that we want to make part of our lives
that this is the center of my life this is what makes sense this is how i want to live i don't want
to get swept away again in distractions and greed and fear and
all the things that i get caught up in i want to live in this natural mind that
natural heart that's at ease with itself that allows to be operated without contraction
without recoiling and without
constantly being foreign against everything
and this strong orientation the strong wish heartfelt wish to stay close to this to
make this the center of our lives for buddhists is often
represented by or expressed through the notion of going for refuge
and it's represented by going for refuge sometimes in the buddha dharma and the sangha
where the buddha in most simply is the exemplar
and the dharma is his is his teachings
that arise out of his awakening and the sangha are the witnesses
who have discovered who have seen for themselves that what
he teaches and what he is the exemplar for is true
so that's one very traditional way of understanding refuge there are other ways that the buddha
taught about refuge that have to do with other things besides the buddha dharma and the sangha and
there are six things and one of them that's a big surprise for
some people to hear that oneself becomes one's own refuge
in this process another is one's actions and choices become a
refuge another is the four noble truths are a
refuge and the last refuge that the buddha talks about
is refuge in the refuge of a deep letting go
of greed hate and delusion an ending of them so during this week
i would like to talk about refuge and
[Music] doing so is for many people is a topic of deep faith certainly is for me
the ancient tradition talk comment the ancient uh terror and tradition the commentators
talk about refuge exists in the in the seat of our emotions
which is said to be the heart that it's a heartfelt phenomenon
it's an element of the heart this refuge that it's a maybe it has more to do with a feeling
and inspiration than almost anything else
but it's not only a feeling it's not only inspiration it's not only a religious sentiment but it's one that is
intimately connected to an understanding
and wisdom that we get as we do this practice and that's why the more people practice the more
understanding they have of where true refuge is
it's also refuge is also very closely connected to our motivations our sense of purpose
that refuge provides a direction for our lives a purpose for our lives it's an
orientation and part of the and having all these
things together a deep faith a deep heartfeltness a deep understanding
a deep sense of orientation and purpose that we trust means that when buddhists
go for a refuge they often will feel just that idea
reminded of this there's a trust or a faith and a knowing
that they immediately feel like oh there's safety they immediately feel that there is a
sense of of um of uh there's a context
for our lives of safety there's a net there's an order there's a lawfulness in this life
there's a natural process that i can trust and so it's going for refuge is an
affirmation not of a blind faith not of a blind adherence
to a religion but it's an affirmation of what we're growing into what's growing and
developing within us that we begin understanding and have faith in and have a connection to
that is so meaningful that for some people it becomes the center of their lives
maybe even they would say it's the most important thing in their lives
but not more important because other important things have become less important they can if they really
are important keep them as just as important but something about the refuge and the dharma
because it's so heart-based maybe and so beyond and bigger than any kind of
self-preoccupation and self-concern it's uh it feels like almost like the
world it feels like we're part of something that's bigger than ourselves
that connects us to all the other things that are important to us in fact as we become freer
and as we become more compassionate through practice then it provides the inner freedom we
have and the compassion we have um benefits
all the other things that we take as important in our life so to take the dharma is the most
important actually i would think improves the quality of our relationships
to all the other things that are worthy of keeping important in our lives
and to have it at the center of our lives the refuge sometimes the idea is that refuge is a
passive thing it's not passive it has to do with
how we live our lives and how we engage in the world around us
and it's a and this they say in buddhism is a gem
as a treasure so that'll be the topic and uh
this talk here today was kind of a introduction to it and um won't spend so much time
on buddha dharma and the sangha that'll be a topic for tomorrow and some of you have heard lots of talks
on that and though i'd love to do a whole series of talks on that
i want to kind of cover that these different areas of refuge that the buddha pointed to as a way
of kind of really understanding the full depth and range of something
that can be the at the heart it can be our
heart to our lives and um in doing so
that uh we become a refuge for others not that we are making them to buddhists
but rather we are a person for whom people feel safe with
and uh inspired with that there is another way to live that's not based in greed or hatred
or based on fear so thank you thank you for
allowing me to share this beautiful place that i'm in and and a nice coincidence that
we're in the natural world for talking about a refuge in the dharma i think of the
natural world and refuge as being somehow closely connected
so thank you very much and i look forward to continuing tomorrow
tomorrow i should be back at imc