welcome everyone we'll go ahead and start with the sitting and today
i'd like to offer a little bit of a guided meditation in
what i sometimes call receptive awareness
this is a style of practice where
rather than choosing what we attend to such as
picking an object like the breath or the body or hearing and allowing the attention to rest there
instead we kind of settle back and receive
what is already happening so mindfulness as a
factor of function in our minds
works both in conjunction with
a directed attention so we can choose to direct our attention
and attend to something in particular like the breath or we can essentially settle back and allow
the processes of body and mind to choose what
to attend to it's kind of in a way like
i sometimes give the analogy with receptive awareness that it's kind of
like the breath in a way that we can consciously choose to breathe we can
breathe in say okay i'm going to breathe in and we can breathe in so we can we can control the breathing in that way we
can aim the attention and choose when to breathe in and when to breathe out
but we can also let go of that we don't have to consciously remember to breathe it will
happen and the the um mindfulness
can function like that we do not have to in mindfulness does not require us to
be choosing something in order to be mindful this is something that i i had to learn
i thought that if i wasn't choosing what to be mindful of i was not being mindful
and so there's a little bit of a learning process in terms of
recognizing when we are mindful when we're not choosing the object of experience
and so the guided meditation i'll offer will will actually start with a little bit of
directed attention and explore what it means to receive that experience instead of
kind of trying to look at anything about it and then we'll broaden out
to the place where we are simply kind of settled back letting go of choosing any particular object of experience
and receiving just receiving
form of meditation practice and i think all forms of meditation practice are supported by
relaxation so we'll start there actually with a little bit of
guiding the attention through the body and exploring a relaxation of body and
then we'll move into exploring the receptive awareness
practice and so we'll begin with some relaxation
checking into your body and seeing if there are places
in the body that are holding tension and seeing if there can be a relaxation
of the body it can be helpful to do this in a kind
of a systematic way
perhaps starting with the head and face seeing if
the head and face can relax
relaxing across the brow around the eyes
the crown of the head the back of the head the jaw
the neck and shoulders
seeing if perhaps the arms and hands can soften relax
relaxing the chest and upper back all those muscles around the rib cage
sometimes as i notice this area and relax those muscles very naturally a deeper breath happens
and that deeper breath can sometimes support even more relaxation of those muscles
relaxing the stomach across the muscles across the
stomach in the abdomen the middle and lower back
relaxing the hips the legs
feet
and then sometimes it's also possible it's not always available but
sometimes it's possible to explore a relaxation more deeply in the
core of the body so as i name some areas more deeply
inside the body just see just touching into those areas and
seeing if there's an invitation if the body is willing to accept the
invitation to soften so maybe
maybe the inside of the throat can relax
maybe the heart can relax
maybe the stomach and the intestines can relax
one of the benefits of the body relaxing is that it supports it
creates conditions that support the mind to be able to relax
so maybe two the mind can relax a little bit
letting go of mental tension that might pull you into thoughts of past or future
sometimes gill uses a lovely analogy about relaxing the mind
he says as if the brain were a muscle maybe the brain can relax
from this place of whatever relaxation is available in this moment
allowing exploring the possibility
of receiving the breath letting the breath come to you
no need to see anything in detail or notice anything in particular about the breath
this breathing is happening
awareness can receive that
a very light simple way kind of settling back with the sense of not looking at or
trying to find anything but just willing to receive the breath however it is offered
in this moment
one of the basic instructions for mindfulness of breathing breathing in
know that you're breathing in aware of breathing in
breathing out know that you're breathing out simple
simple instruction aware while breathing
as we explore receiving the breath
there also may be other experiences that are
revealed by awareness at the same time
while breathing perhaps there's also awareness of a broader sense of the body
a relaxed body and mind support this kind of attention
perhaps too while aware
of receiving the breath and maybe also some sense of the broader
experience of the body aware that hearing is happening
you've been possibly taking in the sound of my voice this
whole time without effort receiving
our system knows how to do this
we can perhaps settle back and allow
awareness to receive naturally
the breath the body and hearing
if you're still connecting with the breath that's fine
this kind of receptive awareness might allow
that connection with the breath but then also aware that other things are happening at the
same time hearing and the breath
body sensations and the breath
perhaps even recognizing emotions or moods
and the breath
even thoughts can waft through
allowing awareness to receive
the human experience
the experiences of body and mind that are already happening
right where you are
you could explore if you haven't already
letting go of any kind of attention or holding to kind of that
thread that connects to the breath and just explore
receiving whatever is most obvious in this moment
that might be body sensation a particular sensation in the foot or hip or
face it might be a broader sense of body a vibratory energy through
the body it might be hearing
the breath or an emotion
a mood a feeling
with receptive awareness we
may find that the attention shifts from one experience to another
sometimes slowly sometimes as a flow for a little while hanging out with the
breath and body and then attending to hearing
and back to the body sometimes you can feel like a flow of
sensations and thoughts and feelings
and other times it can happen more quickly this shifting can feel almost jumpy
like the attention is rapidly shifting between experience and that's okay
if that happens sometimes it's settling back and just recognizing
lots of changing things are happening we don't have to track
we don't have to track all the different things
just exploring being aware and receiving
experience
and of course the mind will wander it will get lost it'll pick up on one of those
things that the attention is drawn to it'll start thinking about it
an image or a thought will arise in the mind and it will catch the attention
and we'll get lost and at some point
there will be a remembering you'll remember
possibly supported by sitting in silence with your eyes closed hearing these
words you'll remember
about being present again
in that moment in the receptive awareness practice there's nothing in particular to come
back to with receptive awareness when awareness arises
when mindfulness returns we open to what
that experience is first of all what is it like for
mindfulness to come back noticing that moment
it's a great moment
awareness arises effortlessly in that moment you didn't have to do it
that's a lovely reminder of what it's like to be aware without
trying to be aware just awareness appearing
and what is happening in that moment
what is awareness receiving in that moment
often in that moment from a return from wandering of the return from the mind
being lost in thought often what's happening in that moment
has been shaped by the thoughts that were happening
and so that's useful to be attentive to in that moment what what has been the
impact what has been the effect of thinking
on your human system sometimes if the mind has been wandering
into charged thoughts thoughts about things you have to do or
things that happened that had some challenge to them
what will be shaped what will have been shaped is a little bit of a response to those thoughts
perhaps some of those emotions or feelings related to
those things you need to do or the things that happen that were charged
so that is useful to recognize
just being with receiving the body
receiving the moods the emotions in that moment
and perhaps if it's supportive remembering that relaxation supports our
capacity to be mindful to be aware
sometimes after the mind has wandered off into thought sometimes the mind kind of more drifts
out of the present moment
it just kind of picks up on some thought and it's drifting or floating
and then when we remember we may not even really have a clear sense of what the thoughts were there
were more dreamlike or random kind of thoughts
but what's the effect what is the impact sometimes i've found when the mind has
drifted out of the present moment if i'm not judging the mind for having
gotten lost that moment when mindfulness returns
from that drifting sometimes there's more ease more relaxation more spaciousness
in the mind
more ease more peace
that's useful to notice if that's what has happened
after the mind has wandered that ease that peace
can also be known its effect on the body the mind
and often there can be a sense of some pleasantness there that supports
our willingness to be present
and if it has been supporting you after the mind wanders and you have
explored this effect of the wandering on your experience
if it's has been supporting you in terms of the receiving to
receive the breath again receive the body
in a soft gentle way that doesn't exclude other experience but has that
perspective of and
hearing and the breath body and the breath
moods emotions and the breath
exploring receiving
the human experience
with a perspective or an attitude of allowing
allowing how you are to be just as you are
and sometimes if there's a perspective or if there's a resistance to what's happening or
wanting to hold on to something that's happening that too is just another thing
happening and maybe that can be allowed
there's this experience and there's resistance oh that's what's happening can that be
received allowing
the non-allowing
being with
your experience
moment after moment
so
[Music]
thank you for joining us today andrea
andrea fella is the co-teacher at the insight meditation center and the insight retreat center
he's been practicing insight meditation since 1996 and teaching insight meditation since
2003 he's particularly drawn to intensive retreat practice and has done a number
of long retreats both in the united states and in burma during one long practice period in burma
she ordained as a nun with said janaka andrea is especially drawn to the wisdom
teachings of the buddha and her teachings emphasize clarity and practicality
andrea is a member of the spirit rock teachers council and teaches residential retreats for imc and
other retreat centers around the country welcome andrea
thank you kevin it's nice to be here and to see
some faces in the zoom room some that i recognize hello everyone
and welcome to everyone who's streaming on youtube nice to see
all of you from around the world good morning good afternoon good evening
wherever you are
so today i thought to reflect on
being aware while thinking
we often in meditation practice have a
kind of a conflict or a sense of
struggle around thinking that if we're practicing a concentration practice for instance where we're
attuning to a particular object of experience and trying to stay
with that experience then thoughts
what we how we relate to thoughts in that case is we notice that we're thinking we set aside
the thought we come back to the object or we might if the thinking is strong
explore what's the impact of the thinking we might look at a little bit of the the effect of
thinking on the body or the uh um the
effect of thinking on our emotions we rarely in meditation we we rarely get many
instructions about what it means to be aware while thinking
we often in meditation are instructed let go of the content of the thought you know let go of the of what's happening
in the thought and turn to let turn to the experience that's that's
happening and so i just wanted to explore a little bit around this terrain
of being aware while thinking because it is a big part of our lives
we use thoughts to navigate
our world and if we haven't
explored or practiced or even had the sense of the possibility
that we can be mindful aware while thinking there's like huge parts of our day that
are off limits for mindfulness practice if we think that while i'm thinking or
engaged in something even something quite um active like you know writing an email or
something like that then there's a lot going on in our day
that we won't be able to explore connect with with mindfulness
so in the guided meditation i offered an exploration of receptive awareness
and this this kind of awareness is is i find very
um supportive particularly in daily life practice it is my main practice whether
i'm in sitting meditation or in daily life but it's the same practice whether i'm in sitting meditation or in daily
life the instructions are the same just receiving what's happening moment after
moment receiving and being aware of experience noticing where the attention is drawn
including with thoughts
one one one big difference or one big uh place
to to kind of be curious about is what does it mean to be aware with
the content of our thoughts and this is this is this is again in our
in some of our more focused meditation practices we don't generally engage with content we're usually trying to drop
below content and explore more the bear experience
but again in in navigating our lives how how content affects us
is really um a big part of where we get caught and
lost and a big part of how we struggle in our relationship to
the ideas that come at us the political ideas a big place where we
get caught in struggle the relational uh experiences we get caught in i wanted
my friend to do this and they did this and we we respond we we um
we have a lot of struggle around the content of our
experience and so learning how to navigate this terrain not saying okay content drop the content
and just come into body and but what is it like to be aware with content
so a great place to begin this exploration is right in the meditation
um as i explore as we explored in the guided meditation when the mind wanders and returns from
wandering this is a place where we can begin exploring the effect of content
on our experience so in the guided meditation
um i encouraged after the mind had wandered you know after the mind had wandered um
noticing what was present in the in the because when the mind wanders as i said
when the mind wanders it's wandering often into thought it may be wandering into some charged
thoughts kind of active content of mind it can be it can wander into into charged thoughts
it can wander into more drifting thoughts those are two classes or categories of
thinking that are useful to kind of recognize the difference between so the the active kind of thinking often
has a very strong effect on us when we're kind of charging out to think
about something so when the mindfulness returns there when the mindfulness comes back
the experience of the present moment where mindfulness has returned
will have been shaped by the content when we've gotten lost in the content
the experience of the present moment will have been shaped by the content of those thoughts
if you've been thinking about a conversation you had with a partner or
a co-worker that had some charged content
when your mindfulness returns very likely that content will have shaped
some of those same charged feelings so this is a beginning place to begin to
recognize okay content affects experience those thoughts when the mindfulness
returns often we know when the when the content is charged often we are aware of the the content as
we come back we know that we've been thinking about that conversation and uh what
the the content of that was so we know that the content was there and then how has that affected you
and so this is a beginning way to uh in that moment as as mindfulness returns to be aware of the thought
with the content and how it affects you at the same time so this again is a kind
of more receptive or broader kind of awareness you're not aiming at one particular area
of experience trying to say look at the body or see what the emotions are it's
more there's this thought that's been happening receive the effect that it's had and it
may be a little bit in the body a little bit in emotions you may notice many things
so it's a kind of a broader receiving of what has happened
having had those thoughts also with receptive awareness in the
practice of receptive awareness that continuing just you've become aware you've noticed
this has been the thought here's how it's affected the body the mind
then just continue to notice what what else is happening after a certain
period of exploring oh that's wow that's what happened
then something else might arise you might hear the dogs start barking next door and the attention goes to that
that's fine there's no place or object or thing particularly you need to come back to
now in the place when you have returned from a wandering
especially if the content has been charged you know there can be in in noticing the
experience noticing what's there there can be a kind of a pull back to figure something out or try to fix
something or figure out how to respond to that person so there'll be there may be some tension
in in the system what can i do maybe you can notice that too
the feeling of of those thoughts kind of propelling the mind to want to
do something so notice the wanting notice the desire to fix to figure out
to control that too can be can be known
and if at some point the pull to the thinking feels so strong that it's like
hard to resist then it might be useful to come back to something where you land like like we
started in the guided meditation land and receive the breath for a few moments
receive the breath as a skillful means to support the mind remembering what it's like to be back in
the present moment and to support perhaps letting go of that pull to the thinking
but giving yourself some time to explore what it's like to be
and what i mean by the pull to thinking is the pull to thinking and not being mindful of it
if the thinking is happening and you can be aware oh wow the thought of wanting to do this
you know wanting to figure this out oh and that's how this is affecting the body and mind
oh and this thought what about that thing i could oh and there that's how that's affecting the
body and mind that's not being pulled out of mindfulness and so there's a learning here
that what does it mean to be aware while we're thinking
we so often might have the view or the idea that if we are thinking
it means we're not being mindful but this is where this kind of receptive awareness practice which
explores just being aware of whatever is happening can potentially support us to recognize
well i'm aware i know that i'm thinking
and so awareness is here we can be aware while thinking
and in that being aware while thinking it it is often a little bit of a broader
awareness and it's it um there's the awareness of the thought
the awareness of the content of the thought and awareness of how that whole
set of thoughts and ideas that content affects the system
so it's it's it's not a a close in or focused awareness it's much broader
there's this this these thoughts and this is how i am with those thoughts
carol wilson uses the phrase 360 degree mindfulness which is a beautiful expression of
just taking in the experience not just
thinking or seeing or hearing or body sensation but the cli the kind of the whole picture
said the teacher one of the main teachers i've learned this practice of receptive
awareness from um he used a phrase 50 50 mindfulness
where he said 50 of the attention on what you're doing the content of what's happening
and 50 of the attention on how you are with that so that there's not the sense of the
content being something outside of the mindfulness not the 360 degree awareness
encapsulates that to some extent too so aware of content and how you are with
that content so that moment of remembering does begin to give a sense of what it might be like
to be aware with content
so it can be useful as i said to kind of recognize different kinds of thinking
the active thinking or the charged thinking where the mind feels like it's just rushing out of the present moment
grabbing onto those thoughts and there's some energy to thinking about them
we can call that active thinking and there's another kind of thinking that's more the mind just kind of drifts
out of the present moment no particular emotional a charge there it's just like the mind
just picks up on something it just floats out of the present moment often maybe a sense of
random thoughts in that place or hypnagogic thoughts dream like thoughts can happen in that place just a drifting
so they're very different those two um in terms of the experience
the active thinking you know with the active thinking it's it's useful
um to recognize you know kind of the charge that happens
with the active thinking so really it may be it may be useful in that situation to know there's the
content and and recognizing kind of the category of content you know planning or remembering or
fighting or judging or fantasizing if the if the content is really really
strong not to say completely step out of the content but also
let more of the attention be in the body and in the mind than in the content
because the content may be kind of the sticky place there but you know staying connected with the
content to some extent oh the mind is really caught in that plan stu is in that plan and and wow the mind
is spinning with that plan
with the drifting kind of thinking often in that situation
as i said in the guided meditation you know in the in the um in the active thinking when we remember when we return
from thinking often the uh experience will have been
shaped by the emotions the thoughts the content of that thinking
so often there will be have some agitation that will have arisen and that's a useful thing to kind of just
check into especially if you're exploring this in daily life i'm kind of talking about it more in the sitting
meditation but i'd like to also point to bringing this into daily life in daily life if you notice that you've
woken up into active thinking often there's a little less you know in the sitting meditation we
don't we don't have as much to do we're not as potentially having to make a decision on
the spot about something so we can explore a little bit more you know okay there's these thoughts and
here's how they're affecting the body and mind in in daily life um with active thinking
if you wake up into active thinking you know you're walking down the street and suddenly you realize your mind has been
like pulled into this whole scenario a useful exploration there can be
just a simple check-in so noticing wow the mind is is kind of caught and it's
spinning and just notice kind of the agitation of body and mind that may be there
just in a kind of a simple way you don't have to do a detailed exploration the receptive awareness is
really useful for this too the the receptive awareness in daily life can take in a much broader kind of
experience kind of the the the 360 degree awareness or the wide
angle lens it doesn't have to land mindfulness doesn't have to land on specific experience it can't be much
broader and so in the awareness of thinking in our daily lives just notice
oh this is what's happening so yesterday i was taking a walk
and i was noticing some thoughts about not wanting to be taking the walk i was noticing that i
was tired that and i know that when i'm tired it's actually a really good time to take a walk but there was resistance
there was resistance to taking the walk and so i was noticing the mind i was noticing the the thoughts about
that and what i noticed is that when i you know so sometimes the mind would get a little caught in it
a little tight and it felt like there was a squeezing in the mind so that was a simple kind of piece it's just this
feeling of of squeezing and then and then noticing those
thoughts i just was hanging out with them i wasn't like saying oh let's go let go of that squeezing it's like oh
the mind is squeezing with this thought and then as in being with it it's like for a few
moments after a few moments the squeezing would let go and it'd be like oh yeah not wanting to
take this walk and yeah it's just it's okay you know just not wanting to do this is happening
but there's not the extra resistance to like the the the trying to get out of
the walk while i'm walking and so just the way the mind works so the the mind
could see that squeezing and just like oh yeah wow the mind is really wow look
at look at how hard the mind does not want to be here and then it would release
and then it would come back and i just watched this process just watch this process multiple times
i'd say maybe 10 minutes into the walk it it had finally the the mind had
finally let go of those thoughts of i don't want to be doing this i don't want to be doing this and it was just fine to be walking
i could have powered through the walk in any case you know kind of repressed all of those thoughts and just powered
through the walk which is what i used to do but then you know the mind kind of is in
that situation the mind is kind of reinforcing the aversion it's reinforcing those
those thoughts of if i just bear down and get this over with it'll be okay
you know it's kind of just reinforcing all of that encouraging
reinforcing that oh look i bore down and i got through this and here i am done
with the walk that that really worked but you know it's like you can get done
with the walk without bearing down and forcing it to so so you know just to explore that the
possibility of being aware with the thoughts as opposed to the idea i need
to get rid of the thoughts in order to be okay just aware of those thoughts aware
while thinking there's a lot that we can see in this terrain
especially in the um the sitting practice when we explore um
being aware while thinking in the sitting practice noticing thoughts arising
we can start to see how those thoughts are conditioned we can see a thought will often arise
based on something that has been has happened i thought you know we hear a sound
we have a perception we hear a bird outside
and then we perhaps recognize the kind of bird oh that's a crow
and then we see an image perhaps we even see an image of the crow and imagine what the crow is doing and then we start
thinking about crows we start thinking about the crows in our backyard and
what they do there and and then the mind maybe gets lost
so we we start to see and we can start to see two um that's that's a that's a very
habitual way for our mind to get lost but we can actually be aware of how that all happens and notice that it is
conditioned how a thought a perception will
create a memory we'll think about that memory and then perhaps that memory can create
emotions so all of that arising from
a perception leading to thought we can stay present for the process
and sometimes as we stay present for the process very naturally what happens is
this is kind of funny and paradoxical but very naturally what happens is as we attend to the process of thinking
very naturally the process of thinking begins to diminish like we see we see the we see the
thought we see the um we see the perception of crow we see
the thought of crow we see the mind start thinking about crows we feel an emotion and and we recognize oh yeah
this is all a conditioned process and with the awareness instead of then
launching into the emotions and further thoughts that are spurred from that emotion
the whole thing can sometimes fall away
and so in a paradoxical way being able to learn how to be aware while thinking
helps the mind to engage less with
reactive thinking to engage less with unnecessary thinking
this is something i've seen happening a lot in my in you know a real
lessening in my in my life around the mind just kind of going off into random
you know thinking because i'm i'm i'm much more present and so the there's there's a lot more of
a sense that the thinking the thinking that happens more is the kind of thinking that's useful
what do i need to do today how do i need to do it what what would i like to bring to this what what kind of
attitudes or mind states would i like to bring to what i need to do today can i be kind
today with what i need to do can i
recognize when i'm caught in reactivity
so another another way and especially in daily life to begin to explore this
terrain of being aware with content
because this again this is a huge place this is a huge place where we tend to
lose mindfulness or just not think it's possible to be mindful is to um
slow it down a little bit you know the thoughts thoughts happen pretty fast i'd say thoughts thoughts are pretty quick
moving and so it's not always that easy to catch thoughts and to be aware while thinking it is possible
and the more we practice with it the more possible it becomes but to practice with the content of our
thoughts often at first we we do notice that we're thinking and then how does it
affect us so it's a little bit of that back and forth we can do the same thing in daily life
around content and a great place to explore this
with reading and writing so with reading
essentially you're taking in the content of someone else's mind unless you're reading your own stuff in which case
you're taking in the contents of your prior selves mind so you're taking in the content you're
taking in content so how does that content affect you when
you read so with reading you can slow it down and i play with this sometimes especially in
in reading the news it's like read a headline how does that land
take in the content how does that content affect the system
words are so powerful for us
a single word can shape your experience
single word can have an effect on your experience
and so reading a a headline multiple words
with the concept embedded in that that can have a very powerful effect on
your experience and so become aware of that so read a headline
how does that land so you can slow it down with reading
read a couple of sentences read a paragraph pause so this might take um a remembering you
know perhaps you could if you if you um do your
news reading online maybe you could put a little reminder to yourself somewhere to try to try to practice with this help
yourself try to remember to do this what does it mean how does this content affect
the body the mind read a few paragraphs check in
read some more check in notice if you start getting charged
perhaps if you start getting charged and the mind starts kind of picking up and running out of the present moment
justifying your position denying somebody else's position maybe that's a time to
really let yourself settle in again it's like okay wow really charged right now this is what it feels like to be charged
with writing we can also slow that down some with writing you are
you know investigating or looking at the content you're trying to share the content of your mind with somebody else
or with yourself so it's it's more aligned with or more like
thinking in a way it's a slowed down thinking process to
put things down in writing and so you can explore this also it's like while writing
you know maybe have have a practice of while writing
a text or an email or a tweet
how does it feel what how is this content these thoughts affecting
this system is there agitation or is there ease
while creating this content that simple check is there agitation or ease with this
content hugely helpful it can be that simple you don't have to
know the details of what the kind of emotion is or just like is there is there energy like this or is the energy
like this so recognizing
that with the content that you are thinking of sharing and potentially also you know this is
this is a way into um exploring being mindful while speaking as well
you might also reflect before you send that text or tweet or email
how might the person who is the audience receive it
so kind of like it's almost like in that moment putting yourself in their shoes feeling like the recipient of it
how does that land if you were to receive this
communication again using mindfulness with content
there's some other kinds of thinking and just talk a little bit about the drifting thinking first
which i mentioned in the guided meditation with drifting thinking has been a
wonderful practice for me it's been delightful actually
what in my own experience um i've seen is often that kind of thinking
comes where the mind just kind of drifts out of the present moment it's it's like there's a there's some settledness of
mind you know there's there's some subtleness because the mind isn't picking up on its habits it's tendencies it's just kind of floating
and there's there's a when it gets into that kind of floaty
space sometimes we just lose touch with remembering to be mindful there
and so that kind of floating quality when we find ourselves having floated out of the present moment
and waking back up into that then what i've seen often you know so
like the the recognition of the content of thoughts there is usually not that relevant
what the content of those thoughts is is often kind of random or dreamlike or nonsensical and so the content isn't as
much to it to to work with there as it is potentially kind of recognizing
how you've noticed those thoughts so there's different modalities that we
can think in we can think in
images we can think as if we're talking to ourselves we can think as if we're hearing
somebody else talk to us so hearing and seeing are two of the big ways most of us think
you know through as if we were hearing or seeing so there's an internal sense of hearing or seeing
there's also we can also think through any of the sense bases so we can think as though we were
kind of in a kinesthetic way we can when i was um when i was a dancer i
would also often like play the dance through in my mind
and so it's a form of thought you know you know as if i were doing it and i would feel it it would be like feeling
it in my body that's how how i would think through the dance so there's that
possibility of thinking kinesthetically
then as an example of that maybe right now if you if you're if you're sitting down
you could just explore imagine imagine
standing up is there just a little bit of a sense of
in the body some kind of sense of that experience
sometimes you can experience that or recognize that sometimes not just that's a that's maybe a little
pointer to what it's like to have that kinesthetic thinking
so we can think in these multiple ways and so with the drifting thinking it can be useful to recognize how was
that thinking how is that thinking happening
images words and then we can start to recognize
perhaps we can start to recognize instead of being caught by those images or thoughts
sounds in the mind we can recognize oh the mind has got these images going and again we don't have to stop them
it was so interesting to me when i learned this on on a retreat to just see oh the mind will put up these like it's
like a slideshow it's thinking about being in prague when i was traveling in in czechoslovakia and i get
these images these these like still images of various places i was and and it lasted for like you know five ten
seconds and then it stopped and i was present for the entire slideshow it was it was quite a
delightful experience actually remembering remembering that experience
there was a little bit of the flavor of having been there but because i was present the mind
didn't kind of pick up on those thoughts and then go off into being in prague for 15 minutes
it lasted for about 10 seconds and then it went on and so if again aware while thinking
aware of this process of thinking so those drifting kind of thoughts sometimes useful to recognize how they
are experienced the modality in which they are experienced
and if the mind does drift out of the present moment gets lost in the wandering
then that moment of returning you know as as i expressed in the in the
guided meditation again sometimes if the mind has drifted out of the present moment
when we wake up when our mindfulness returns from that
drifting if we do not have if we do not have the
attitude or the idea or the agenda that the thinking was a problem it's just like oh mindfulness is back
what's happening in this moment if we don't have any sense of it having been a problem for the mind to be drifting and
not mindful then what often happens after a drifting is that the mind is
actually more at ease and more relaxed than it was
before the mind drifted and this is this was a huge
help for me it was almost like i was feeling like my mind the mind was
i was i was definitely you know an over striver really hanging on to that mindfulness
trying to stay present moment after moment doing doing the practice so hard
so much so much attachment to the practice and as i began to be curious about this
moment when mindfulness returns and seeing the the mind returning from
the drifting it was almost like what it felt like the mind was doing was telling me you're
working too hard here i'll show you how to relax and if i was available for that lesson
when the mindfulness came back it was like oh this is what it's like to be
mindful and at ease at the same time this is what it's like to be
relaxed while being aware and so that that exploration around the
drifting mind can be really
enlightening it can be really really uh supportive for helping the
mind recognize what it means to be at ease
with mindfulness
so yeah i see it's about we have about five minutes left
and um let's see if there's any questions those of you in the zoom room you could raise
your zoom hand i think or use the chat those of you on the
live stream could type a question in probably i'm not able to get to many questions in just five minutes but but i
think kevin will moderate the questions if there's any questions
yeah we'll give people some time to raise their hand or
put questions in chat on youtube or if you feel like it you can uh put your questions in chat and zoom as well and
we'll take them there
hey uh tom and dana um if you guys want to come off mute and ask a question we
can go ahead hi andrea hi
when um when i'm aware of my thoughts and the breath i also am aware of this
base note of anxiety so there are three things cooking
what should i do [Laughter] so you could ex you could explore it by
just knowing all of it so there's the the thought you said you said the breath the thought
and the base anxiety you could just explore wow that's what's happening you know just like okay yes
and and is is the content of the thought kind of connected with that anxiety you
know so is it is or is it something else you know is something else because sometimes
sometimes the thoughts are kind of popping out of the base of of our emotional terrain
and sometimes they create our emotional terrain there's a kind of but it's conditioned both ways and so
kind of curious about well what's the relationship between those thoughts and
the anxiety is and if if the anxiety feels strong you know then
it's possible that with the mindfulness of it you know that the the attention might kind of gravitate towards
that side of the experience in being aware while thinking we don't have to preference also don't have to preference
the content it's like with receptive awareness it's more wow i become aware
the breath the thought the anxiety what's most obvious
here
what's most obvious and what do what where does the attention kind of feel like it's most drawn to so that we
don't have to we don't have to choose what to pay with a receptive awareness it's more like
we don't we don't have to decide where we direct the attention it's more like can i allow this to be as it is and
what is most wanting attention right now if the mindfulness can hold that
if if the mindfulness if if the mindfulness doesn't get lost while holding that so if there can be an
allowing sense of oh yeah this is what's happening and that anxiety is there these thoughts are
there here's the breath if the mindfulness can hold that kind of a patience and a trust
that there is learning that's happening but if you find that the attention is kind of drawn into the anxiety and
starts thinking more thoughts then it could be useful to um direct the attention to something
that where you can stay present maybe with the breath for instance or if the
breath feels tied up with the anxiety maybe with hearing so that there's some skillful means if
if it feels like the the mind is pulled into the thinking and it's like it can't not go there then
it's useful to to do some directed attention to something that that allows you to to to stay present but from what
you described it sounds like there's some capacity to just know all of that so some of it is trust
you know trust that there is learning happening here we like to be in charge of the learning you know
we like to we like to know what we're learning sometimes we don't get to know that you know sometimes the buddha talked
about the practice being very gradual very um
you know moment after moment the mindfulness just meets experience and he speaks about the wearing away of
the um the reactivity being like the wearing away of the rigging of a rope that's held up on
dry land after being at sea for six months you know just like the the sun the sand the wind
kind of wears away those the the rigging and you know after six months it's going
to be more worn after two years it'll be kind of broken and rotted through
and so the um you know the mindfulness functions like that moment after moment
minute after minute hour after hour even day after day we may not see
what's being let go or what's being worn down and so some patience and some trust
that the practice of being aware is
enough being aware with the quality of mind that is allowing it to be
as it is and that that exploration of um
knowing that what that experience is where the mind
can be present and not pulled into
that's that's the crucial piece be curious about what is this experience
when there can be that curiosity the learning will kind of naturally naturally unfold there
so thank you for the question and i'm sorry for the rest of you who put in questions it's time so
thank you all for your practice and may the benefits of our practice
together be shared with all beings everywhere may all beings
be healthy happy safe and at ease may all beings know
peace thank you all