so good day to everyone hello and welcome
to our sunday morning meditation and talk and thank you for those of you who are
doing greetings on the chat and it uh it's very nice for me
and then i start feeling a real connection to to to those of you who are listening and
and i appreciate the warmth that's being expressed
so um
as an introduction to this meditation today
there's an interesting difference between
the body and the mind the body in a sense has weight it's
substantial and has certain weight we can ask how much do you weigh
and we're referring to the weight of the body the mind wide ranging
filled with the all kinds of ideas and motivations and memories
the mind being different than the brain the mind has no weight
but more specifically the thoughts in the mind they have no
weight they're weightless if you feel your hands maybe you can feel the weight
of your hands maybe your hands are
pushing pressing the weight of gravity is their weight is being pulled by gravity
into maybe your legs or into the other hand or some part of your body and you can feel the weight in the sense
of the hand but your thoughts have no weight your
judgments in and of themselves have no weight your memories your predictions
and about the future have no weight but they can be quite weighty we can say
i'm way down my by my concerns and weighed down by
my thoughts and it's not the thoughts themselves but rather it's the contracting the
tensing this pushing the striving the energy that we apply to our thoughts and ideas
and judgments and memories and fantasies that that's where the
in the sense the sub substantial nature of them comes alive or that's where the weightiness of them
comes in that way that we relate to them we contribute the weight
but in and of themselves our thoughts have no weight
and to realize that to make that real in ourselves to really
feel and sense the weightless quality of these
then we can get a feeling for freedom we can get a freedom
a sense of how these float that there's no boundaries to them or no
substance to them or no boundaries or no um no way that they just kind of
can come and go they can dissolve and appear they float through in a sense
and everything else is our contribution our intense interest in them or
alarm or or horror or fear in relationship to them or
are wanting and not wanting and contracting and pushing away and this goes on and on
the ways in which we relate and for this meditation maybe you can
become aware a little bit of that distinction between the weightiness that
you contribute and the weightlessness of your thinking
of your ideas and thoughts
the ways that the substance substantiality of our
tension and holding on reactivity
and the non-substantial nature of these thoughts themselves
and one of the things to discover then is that our thoughts
are not bothering us but in a sense we are bothering them or
we are being bothered by them and to discover
how not to be bothered by thoughts and ideas
is to begin discovering how to be free from them
so assuming a meditation posture that supports you to
be alert and relaxed
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
breathing in breathing out
and as you exhale
to relax and soften
relaxing and softening the muscles of the body contributes to a feeling of fluidity or
softness or lightness in the body that's not there if we are tense and
tight
letting your breathing return to normal
taking a few moments to feel
your embodied body feeling the sense of
embodiment in this body
the weight of the body the substance of the body
and then as you exhale gently exhale
softening the muscles of your face
letting those muscles the face fall away from the bone in the skull
letting your softening your eyes
as you exhale softening the shoulders
releasing the shoulders to the pull of
gravity
exhaling and softening in the belly
and maybe when you inhale can you keep the belly soft and expensive
and then also as you exhale see if you can relax any tension or
pressure that's around the mind in the area that you most identify with
the mind maybe it's the same as the brain
area the head
if there's any tension contraction relax soften let go
the tensions the pressure energy agitation of the mind is not
really of the mind that's of the body
participating reacting engaging
the mind has no weight
it has no boundaries no center
and the thoughts of the mind the judgments the ideas of the mind
have no weight no substance
their weight and substance is contributed in our reactions to them our relationship to them
in and of itself to allow the simplicity of thoughts the
weightless insubstantial nature
allowing them to be without being bothered by them
without bothering them
and one way to do this is to let the attention your attention
flow into your body into the breathing body
resting awareness and the inhales and the exhales of the body
so that the energy of awareness doesn't contribute to the heaviness
or substantiality of thoughts
and thoughts maybe at some point will begin to just float
and feel very thin and very light
nothing we have to be involved in instead let yourself be centered
in the body breathing
you
there is no need to give weight and substance to whatever you're
thinking about leave the thoughts alone
if you don't pick up a boulder you won't feel its weight
if you don't pick up a thought
it has no weight
you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to consider when thoughts have no weight no
substance we're not contributing pressure
or resistance contraction around them
then the heart is not eclipsed when the thoughts have wait they eclipse
the warmth of the heart the radiance of the heart
and perhaps softening relaxing the mind
in these last moments of the sitting to feel censor
whatever capacity for warm-heartedness
heartfelt goodwill that you're capable of
and without adding weight to your thoughts
lightly openly
let that heartful heartfelt warmth
open up widely into the world around us to the world around you
the people who are closest to you physically and emotionally
circles of community from outwards across the land
and without any weight of reactions or judgments or planning
the simplicity of an open heart
wishing that this meditation that you've just done in some way or other
may it be in service of the welfare and happiness of others
may it be that the benefits that have come from sitting quietly
may you share those benefits with others may they spread from you
so that we contribute maybe in small infinitesimal ways
but we contribute to a global
possibility that all beings may be happy
that all beings may be safe
that all beings may be peaceful
that all beings everywhere can be free
and may it be for our own happiness and safety and peace and freedom
that we offer weightless care and love for this world that we share
may all beings be happy
so hello everyone again and
here we are on august 1st of 2021
and today was a day that we had the plans here at imc
to open up our doors so people can come together in this event this sunday morning talk
was meant to be the first public talk at our center
since um mid-march 2020
and uh it seemed like over the last few weeks that
the course of the pandemic was taking such a direction that it wasn't wise to open up
or it didn't contribute to for our community in important ways
where we want to try to be careful not to be
transmitters or enable the transmission of this coronavirus and that somehow
being sheltered protected and closed this way hopefully is seen as
an act of love and care compassion for this world for ourselves and others
so um but it kind of is a poignant moment to have planned to open
and then now not opening and makes me reflect on the the impact that
this pandemic has had that uh for all these months
and i think it's important to be deeply respectful of the impact but to
appreciate understand the
the impact that it has on each of us as individuals as a community as a global
community that and it's not uncommon for people to
feel that that the ongoingness of this
pandemic has worn them down to some degree and there's a kind of tiredness
source kind of wariness from the lack of contact with a lot of
people [Music] the isolation some people feel the feeling of of um
you know the the feeling of compassion the feeling of distress
around what's happening in our society in our world as a whole and i think of these months that we've
been in the pandemic as kind of a
you know i think some of us to have experience to be aware of a greater
range of suffering greater range of challenge locally and internationally then maybe
many people experience over a lifetime maybe not since world war ii maybe or that
there's been something like this some people have evoked the aids pandemic
as being another time where it's been global impact and
um but i think that one of the things about this pandemic is how that's remarkable is how much we it's
shared by everyone on the globe uh i think there's very few people who
are not somehow impacted by it and maybe there's a few you know this uh i had some little bit
of indirect contact with a south pacific island
and where it doesn't seem to have reached the shores so they're free of it but they've closed
themselves off to the wider world and and so that has an impact as well
so um
and i can imagine that from a lot of people it felt like finally it's over but then it's not over and
and so one of the important things is to care for ourselves
not to allow the weight of this
current events to weigh us down to to stress us to uh to the
for the wariness of it all to kind of begin wearing us down
and so how do we do that how do we how do we
not allow the accumula this experience of this ongoing pandemic to accumulate its impact on us
and that's a little bit the topic of today or very much the topic and uh
and uh and for me the reference point for this is meditation the way that meditation can help and
other people some people have other means that are similar to meditation to do the same thing
and that is a means by which we can start fresh every day it means by which
the accumulation of stress the accumulation of weariness or resistance or
or sadness or distress that might be felt that
it doesn't accumulate it doesn't build but in but rather than that's the opposite that we're able to put it down
and for some period of time to really put it down and and to
live free of it without it even if it's just for a few minutes to have the experience so that we can
start fresh we can be re refreshed renewed um
and so then uh we've interrupted the the building the accumulation of the
tremendous weight and the ongoingness of the experience and
it's very easy for many of us to be caught up in the in the world when
the agitation or the churning of the mind and thoughts and live in them as if
that's completely natural and normal and what else is there to do and and
you know and so we're it's kind of like a labyrinth we can't get out of because the thoughts are just kind of thinking
themselves and and maybe sometimes the thoughts are thinking about how to
be free of the very thing we're thinking about and it's kind of like stuck kind of and um
but meditation to really be able to get still focused concentrated in meditation to
have mindfulness be a stepping away from preoccupation and thoughts involvement with thoughts are
gonna getting a little distance from them and freedom from them and maybe allowing the thinking to quiet
and still or it's to shift the center of where we live in our being
from being centered on thoughts to being centered in the breathing or in the body
and and to feel that shift and and so that we're not feeding our
thoughts we're not living in the thoughts we're not swirling around in those thoughts
and the analogy for this is
whipping up a cream or using an egg beater to whip to to beat
up uh egg whites that if you um take either one but you keep
stirring and churning and beating and bringing air into the egg whites or air into the
cream slowly over time the the cream the egg whites become stiff
and and they get stiffer and stiffer until they get so stiff you can take the beater or the fork whatever
you're doing and lift it up and you make little these little peaks because it's firm enough that it stays
upright and so the same way with our minds if we're constantly using
the egg beater an egg beater of the mind or a fork in the mind kind of constantly
stirring and stirring and stirring that the mind starts becoming stiff
it starts becoming heavy and and feels substantial and feels sticky
and stiffer and stiffer and so there's not much flexibility and fluidity with our experience because of the
stiffness of the mind and now with the stiffer the mind becomes the more we're
globbed on or coagulated around thoughts ideas concerns coagulated stiff around our suffering
the more circumstances impact us or the or we're more fragile in a sense
we can the stiffness is vulnerable to being broken or being bumped up against or that
doesn't happen if the liquid is really so soft and smooth and you put your finger through the cream
and it just kind of like you know just it's smooth there's no resistance to the finger going through the cream
and um the um before it's been whipped up in a sense or the egg whites
so um so this idea of of letting the mind become soft uh fluid
not stiff not coagulated is that's where the accumulation is the
accumulation of tension accumulation of of impact of chronic thinking
chronic uh you know and sometimes uh people suffering gets exasperated
by this whipping around of the eggbeater in the mind of our fears our plans our resistance
our resentments our all these kinds of things our desires our frustrations
and so to learn a way to put that down to to stop
the egg beating to stop the churning and allow the the thinking mind to get
quiet so that for a brief moment maybe or for a short period of time
we're not riding on the wave of chronic thinking we're not being pushed by the tides of
of of thoughts that are coming and coming and coming and it's kind of like we're able to
settle or stand on dry ground and we're no longer the the
momentum of thoughts are not we're not caught in it or spinning in it or swirling in these thoughts
and this allows us to feel deeply refreshed allows us to feel at ease at peace
and it's a wonderful piece and refreshment that's very hard to understand if we're
churning in our thoughts the thoughts they want something and to not want can seem like a betrayal
to not uh wanting it seems like we have to be forward-looking reaching
in or pulling back and protecting ourselves or doing something in order to find ourselves to be safe to
get what we want and the idea of doing nothing of just letting go fully and being
peaceful from the logic of our thinking mind this doesn't work the the somehow the
the unconscious logic of thinking is that you can't really afford to stop thinking
thinking is what where the solution is going to be thinking is where the where it's all constructed and made
and where it exists and thinking has so much weight and substance and authority
that we can't we have to stay there and the authority insists like you have to stay here be in your
thoughts and figure this out but if we can put it all down and step
away from it and discover that the place where there is no weight where there is no authority like that
and uh and feel like that's a center then something can relax
there there can be discover some capacity for peace and ease letting go and that refreshment then
it's kind of like um then we're fresh then we start up and we're not abandoning the world but then when we return to the
world after our meditation then we're there in a fresh way in a clear way in a
hopefully renewed way and then it's easier to engage in the world around us with our
family friends work the world whatever it's easier to read the news
and and not be overwhelmed or not have it kind of like be one more
thing that gets folded into the churning of the mind the way the egg beating of
the mind that we do and that it just becomes something we take in more deeply something news
and take in the suffering around us so in a beneficial way it impacts our heart but if the mind is
spinning and churning taking in the suffering of the world is probably
counterproductive not useful i think that the pandemic i think has
been an opportune time to be a witness deep witness heart witness
to this the human condition on this planet we're learning so much about injustice
so much about the suffering and and so much about um
um you know about death and sickness and
it's huge what's happened to our planet with it pandemic how do we become a better person because
of it how do we not get weighed down by it how does it awaken compassion love
good qualities in us so those qualities can meet the world i think it's very hard to do
that if we're stuck or in this churning we're staring up the mind beating up the mind
whipping up the mind over and over again like you would uh egg white sir
we have to stop the churning we have to stop the incessant uh spinning and agitation of
the mind or at least slow it down dramatically enough so that there's time for us to be
refreshed time to come open the eyes again and the eyes are not
so clouded by all these thoughts ideas judgments and fears
and in a sense this capacity of meditation to put ourselves you know to get renewed or refreshed is
also get renewed from ourselves where we're we're not being disloyal to
ourselves that we're not continuing to think about our suffering our problems our concerns
um it's actually if we some of them some of our preoccupations are all about
me myself and mine and and to be able to really put aside
even if we are suffering there's a lot of suffering that we're experiencing many of us
and uh and not to diminish that and not to deny that it's there but if what we're doing is using the egg
beater of the mind just to just spin spin spin the thoughts and ideas
then um the um
it's not really um useful for us we're just adding suffering upon suffering
it is okay to stop the egg beating it's okay to stop thinking about oneself for a while
and get kind of renewed and refreshed and and then we can come back
now in buddhism one of the egg beaters one of the that that is one of the core things that
buddhist practice is trying to free ourselves from is the egg beater which is the
this the um see as things get stiffer in the mind
the stiff some of these stiff things in the mind become the egg beater
and one of the stiff things in the mind that becomes the egg beater is our idea of self our ideas of self
so we have you know it's pretty natural for human beings to have a sense of eminence i am
uh there's a centeredness here in in our being
that's normal natural but that centeredness and being centered here and feeling a little bit like through
our body this substantial nature of our being the vitality of life that's flowing here
in this body that's fine but then we start
having thoughts ideas judgments uh projections um
biases that we add and build and we add to that and that's this so egg beater of self
we're adding to that building on it the baggage of i have to be this way i have to be
that way being a person like this means that i have to be treated this way or shouldn't be treated that way or i
should be treat myself this way or i need to have that happen or this has to happen
just more and more ideas about self and these layers and layers some of them
are fine ideas in and of themselves but it isn't the ideas that are the problem
but rather how the egg beater of self is churning and spinning and making the
more and more solidified sense of self idea of self holding the
self contracted and one of the great blessings and benefits of meditation practice
is that to stop the egg beating of self st you know retire the constant
preoccupation and spinning around me myself and mine and even let that become quiet
and it's not a disloyalty to self but it's a recovery from the stress of this egg beater
that's going and it's a remarkable thing to discover that there's a vitality a clarity an
openness that's possible for us and they're an engagement even in life that's possible
without that stiffness of me myself and mine the stiffness
of uh that that help starts making a substantial self or a
a weighty self a weighty self
whatever the self is if you want to have a self or self ideas or identities that
we have they belong in and of themselves to the weightless world
of the mind as soon as we there's a way to them then we've
contracted we've gotten tight heavy if we if they get if we get heavy and
substantial there's been the eggbeater of the mind has been stirring things up
meditation going for a walk in nature reading a nice book taking a nap
um you know there's all kinds there's different ways that different people have but to do it something in some in a
thorough and deep way that sometimes something unlike meditation can do where we completely put down the egg
beating the egg beater of self
churning that goes on and to discover a peacefulness a quiet a radiance an
openness where there's no reference being made
to me myself and i where there's no reference to anything
that has any weight the reference is if anything is through
something that feels open weightless light
free relaxed where we learn to recognize that the egg
beater the spinning the churning that goes on incessantly the in the mind
has quieted down
and it's so important to give ourselves some time to do that because then we
think more wisely then we're ready to see more clearly then then there's space in
room for the heart for our capacity for goodwill and kindness care
compassion warm-heartedness
so you might if this talk is you know as is something you can relate
to you might start paying attention
to when you're spinning your thoughts spinning in the world of the mind beat is egg beating
and whipping up your thoughts in ways that things become mentally heavy and
substantial and thick and stiff even and to notice
how it might eclipse the warm heartedness of the heart how it might eclipse the
kindness the generosity the natural goodness
of the heart of our being that in and of itself also has no weight
in and of itself has no substantiality unless we pick it up that way with
clinging and pressure and wanting it pick it up with self the goodness of our
heart that has not been churned or by the egg beating of self where the goodness
just allowed to be there simply relaxedly openly
here and so look and start noticing the distinction
between when you're churning and when the churning has stopped when you're spinning and thought and
when you really let the thing that stepped away from that world of thought and are at
more peace than it is here it's a very important distinction and
the more you can see that distinction the more access you'll have to a degree of
freedom where not only maybe you don't need to recover so much or renew as much
but you actually stay renewed or you stay relaxed and open because you're not
continually accumu not continually accumulating more and more of this tension that comes from
whipping up the egg whites in the mind
so um i hope you have a chance to each day to do something that really
renews or refreshes the mind i think it's as important as brushing your teeth and
so please and i think you'll probably find that
you'll live a much more effective life so that way so thank you
very much and and i do i am looking forward to being with all
all of you certainly all of you but too many of you when we do open our doors here and we
can meet in person and that day will come and until then i offer you my
warm regard and well wishing and hope that you take
good care of yourself and good care of the world thank you