hello everyone and welcome and welcome to this meditation
session and um
one of the ways of maybe getting a little more feeling for
the potential of meditation is to have a very clear
bracketing putting aside of the past and the future
when you meditate now the past and the future have their
certainly have their importance in human life and in fact it's a bit of a problem if you
don't remember anything of your past in the future but there's also something very valuable
about putting it aside so that you can have a very
different experience of yourself or experience of life without that reference of the past and
the future that to understand to really experience
something qualitatively valuable about the present
and so we're not forgetting about the past but we're putting it aside for the duration of a
meditation session it will come back thoughts will come about the past and
the future but in mindfulness meditation we're not interested in those thoughts
but we are interested in recognizing them as present moment phenomena
here is a mind that's thinking about the past here's a mind concerned with the future
here it's like this and for this it's for this it's kind of
like for the duration of the meditation you're forgiven
about whatever happened in the past whatever you did in the past you don't have to be blamed for anything
when you're meditating it's kind of a time-out zone a neutral zone
and it's like in the old days people would go into the church for sanctuary and
the legal authorities couldn't go and pull a personality was in the
sanctuary of a church so you are in the sanctuary of your meditation
and you're safe here now from the past everything is forgiven for now
you don't have to do it after the meditation and you don't have to think about the future
for a time being meditation you're not responsible for the future and what will happen and don't need to plan
so that just here just this experience it's kind of like
here is a door and you walk through that door to a deeper intimacy deeper connection
to the lived experience of the moment so take so entering into this door
through your body and entering into a meditation posture
and part of the value of being intentional with the meditation posture
it's beginning this process of entering into the present more fully
and doing so through your body
and also stepping through this door of the present moment into the present
stepping out of the past and stepping out of the future to just here to take a few long slow
deep breaths
breathing in deeply
and relaxing the body as you exhale long
exhale
and if you take a long exhale a long ride into the present
let there be a momentary pause at the end of the exhale
a fuller acknowledgement here
maybe a silent acknowledgement feeling here
letting your breathing return to normal
and because the body is such a wonderful vehicle for sliding into now
as you exhale
relax your belly
and sometimes if you relax the belly all kinds of other things throughout the body will relax as well
as you exhale relaxing the shoulders
and softening the face
and perhaps also calming the mind
cooling the thinking activity
quieting your thoughts
and as part of present moment experience
there is awareness of the present
awareness is always a present moment event
if you are aware the awareness is occurring here and now
and for these minutes you are allowed you have permission to put aside the
past and the future enter and to enter into the door
through the door of the present moment
not to attain anything or get anything or make anything happen
but to abide
aware mindful
of your experience as you hear
and letting the comings and goings of breathing
support you to be here as breathing is also a present moment
phenomenon
riding the breath riding the sensations of the body breathing
like riding on the present moment
so
putting aside the past putting aside the future
for now for now so you can be here
whatever the now is for you now it'll never be exactly this way
again it's worthwhile resting
awareness grounding awareness
in this unique lived experience of now
letting the thinking mind take a break
just aware just
mindful
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
from time to time when you consider other people or
even more so when you're together with them
it's useful to put aside the past
and put aside thoughts of the future
so that you can really see the person in the present
certainly there's a time and place for the past and the future to be considered
but there's also a time and place to put those aside
and to meet someone in the fullness of how they are in the
present with whatever fullness you are
in the present
to connect to the humanity of another person
as they are in the present moment with a beating heart
breathing lungs with blood coursing through their body
with their vulnerability and their strength
with their good qualities and not so good qualities
to just to be there feel and sense and be with a person
and having that capacity can be a vehicle or a means
for greater respect for the other her greater care and friendliness
a greater good will well-wishing
greater empathy maybe even a sense of shared humanity
sharing in the difficulties and the joys of this life
from time to time to put aside the past and the future
so that we may have greater goodwill and compassion and love
kindness for the people we're with in the simplicity of the moment
and may it be that this meditation practice we do
supports us to be present with others
in a fuller deeper richer way
and that we bring a heart
that is inspired by the welfare and happiness of others
may we live contributing to the happiness the safety
the peacefulness and the freedom that others can have
may this practice spread from us the benefits of this
practice spread from us for the welfare and happiness of all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy
so
you