good morning good morning hello everyone or good afternoon depending where you're coming from or even evening
nice to be with you i'm francisco gable and i'm here in berkeley california
and uh i'm going to sit with you together here
and um so let's just jump in and get started and do our meditation
[Music]
sometimes at the start of a meditation a good idea to
get a line with uh kind of a north star a north organizing star that um
that's lighting us along the way that's imbuing us with light
and for this meditation let's make that north star be
something like unshakeable happiness or immaculate happiness
why not it's a good guiding light to point to
happiness and joy for the reason that it allows us helps
us to to see and move through this path together
move through the pieces and parts of our minds and hearts
and it provides a resting place for the mind that stabilizes the mind
if we have just a light general orientation toward some form of joy and happiness
in this moment
sometimes if we sit with that it helps us to find uh deeper levels of
stillness and presence as we
slowly and firmly and assuredly move through see through and breathe through
all the different phenomena that come and present themselves
so to start this meditation taking your meditation
posture however it is most comfortable and conducive to being alert
and a little bit diligent with little zeal from joy maybe
closing your eyes if that feels good to you
and going in and we're going to
receive the touch of this body it's just a general sensation of the
body noticing the breath
such as it is
and noticing where it might be more comfortable to rest your attention
in the cycle of the breath as it arises as it's present as it ends
breathing allowing breathing to happen
all on its own
and almost as if you were being touched by a soft delicate finger
or a feather or something very comfortable and soothing
let's receive some touch sense from this body
turning our attention to the crown
relaxing as if we're just being touched
the earlobes
the back of the neck those occipital bones
just receiving whatever is there
the chin
the chest bone
feeling the touch of both shoulders
and those two bony things back there the scapulas
feeling them as if they're like two floating clouds just floating the touch
of floating clouds behind our back
continuing further down feeling the belly button
maybe just a gentle soothing touch that [Music]
eases
and the bony sit bones
how might they feel more relaxing
the top of the thighs and the back of the thighs
and the top of the knees and the bottom of the knees both of them
like a gentle soothing feeling receiving whatever's there
or not all along we breathe allow the breathing to just
go in and out on its own gently
proceeding down to the shin bones the bony front part
the calf muscles in the back of the shin bones
the top of the feet and the soles of the feet
relaxing if it's possible how it's possible soothingly
receiving any gentle waves of sensations
and if there are unpleasant sensations
noticing them
maybe saying without words oh
it's okay i care about you it's okay
we're together here
and continuing with the rhythm of the breath in out
air moving in you're moving out
air persisting while it's present and then exhaling ending
[Music] sometimes uncomfortable sensations just
kind of evaporate away on their own
sometimes they don't and we just engage them with a caring
really really soft awareness
letting them being here with all of this all of these touches
from the body all over
and to return to our intention of joy and happiness in this moment
receiving the overall well-being of the body breathing
sensing feeling
noticing there's a joy of just simply the body being
nothing going on no doing of any sort
right now for just a little bit just breathing and sensing
these soft touches all the touches
allowing them to settle
calming as much as as possible
but receiving that calm
maybe at the end of every exhale there's a little bit of calm
to be noticed
at the beginning of an inhale that brings in wonderful air
is a calming
this is joyful for the body to be seen
and it's mostly calmness
it's good to be touched
by the body's sensations
and calming relaxing releasing
the mind can stabilize
in this calm joy of the body in its wellness its well-being
and finally to continue with the theme of joy and happiness
touching in on that happiness of the body and the mind calming and stabilizing
together tuning in to that
pleasant sensation of the mind stable
calm when it is
in the moments when it is
and with this same happiness of mind
resting on that along with the breath the in and the out
joining the two together to what notice
it's like we're bolstered our noticing is bolstered
with this soothing happiness in out
and we can observe
the other things that keep arising from that point
from the whole space of the body and the mind and joy and calm and stability
we can observe the many trains of
different appearances of thinking
and from that vantage point you can let them just be there
maybe observing them gently caringly joyfully
saying how interesting
let them play along
perhaps resting on a foundation of
resting on a foundation of happiness in joy embodied
continually being touched by that touch of the body
in its many many many sensations of goodness
let's practice this way for the time that it remains
being touched by the touch of the body's sensations
being touched emotionally in the heart that we're touched
by so many sensations with the through the in and out of the breath
the body's natural joyfulness and all its wellness full of well-being
are those touches of life moving through coursing through
knowing the pleasant feeling of a mind that's resting within this
joyful stability of body
yourself be touched by that mind happiness
a pleasant feeling of mind
[Music]
me thank you so much for joining us this
morning francisco and being here with us talking to us i just like
to introduce francisco so francisco is a student of andrea fella
and gail franz though he also studies and teaches early buddhism with biku
analayo thanks to a devoted engagement with dharma francisco made a remarkable recovery
from an accident in 2003 that rendered him disabled he has a special interest in teaching
underserved groups and he is highly committed to bringing the dharma to the greater spanish-speaking world
thank you very much for joining us today francisco appreciate it
it's a delight to be here with you all thank you so much for having me uh welcome to the morning sit um it's a
real pleasure for me to be able to to share a little bit of these teachings
together here and um i'd like to talk about um about uh
joy and happiness uh immaculate happiness let's just put it all out there
and uh to lead into this uh this topic i wanna share a little story
about the buddha and from the discourses it's from
this uh charming little discourse called mark wonderful and marvelous
yes wonderful and marvelous and so it's you gotta imagine the setting
uh the monks are all together in a big assembly hall and uh they're sitting around chatting
they've had their alms meals so they're satisfied and and they're sitting around trying to
outdo each other on stories about the buddha to see who could
come up with the greatest stories of the wonderful and marvelous qualities of the buddha
and they go pretty far out uh out there each one trying to outdo each other with bigger and higher
and bigger achievements about the buddha and then
the buddha comes in and asks them what were you all talking about and uh and then they recount all the
wonderful marvelous qualities and some of these things are crazy interesting it's uh how the buddha was
born well i'll redo a little bit of the tenero
i heard and learned this from the blessed one's own lips
mindful and fully aware the bodhisattva appeared in tucsita
heaven and then to see the heaven he's
he does all kinds of things and to see to heaven before he descends to his mother's womb and
makes her totally pure and wake was born walking and standing and a great light
and shining light appears in the heavens and each one of these comments ends and
and this too i remember as a wonderful and marvelous quality of the blessed one
so this goes on and on and on uh and and then uh the buddha speaks and uh
but before he speaks look look how over the top uh these things are uh i heard and learned
from the blessed one's own lips when the bodhisattva came forth from his
mother's room then a great immeasurable light surpassing the splendor of the gods
appeared in the world with its gods its maras and its brahmas in this generation with its recluses and
brahmanas with its princes and its people and even in those abysmal abysmal world
interspaces of vacancy gloom and utter darkness are you there
where the moon and the sun mighty and powerful as they are cannot make their light prevail prevail
thereto a great immeasurable light surpassing the splendor of the gods appeared
and then it ends this too i remember as a wonderful and marvelous quality of the buddha and then the buddha speaks
so this is all kind of like a setup for the buddha to have his word and then the buddha says
that being so remember this as a wonderful and marvelous quality
of the blessed one here for
the tatagata himself feelings are known as they are as they are
present and as they disappear
and then he says the same thing about perceptions and thoughts so you might think wow what a come down
um when all these wonderful qualities but this is the wonderful quality knowing feelings
and the feelings that they're talking about that he's referring to are the feeling tones it's not
feelings as an emotional feelings it's feeling tones so he points to feeling tones above
every other wonderful and marvelous quality of all possible because and he
points to this throughout many of the discourses it's like he keeps pointing this arrow
to feeling tones feeling tones feeling tones
and feeling tones contain these
these different categories but one of them is the unworldly feeling
tones those pleasant unworldly feeling tones
and uh i'd like to point a little bit of attention to those
today because um well why not uh i it seems that uh to me
that we just kind of are very dutiful and diligent here in our
practice and and sometimes don't really orient so much
toward uh the joy and happiness of the practice and rest in the joy and
happiness of the practice and have that maybe be the guiding light
have that maybe be the starting point of everything that we do in this practice
we're kind of riveted by so many so many facets of dukkha so many facets
of the afflictions the pains the difficulties
the sufferings the challenges the confusions of thinking
that embroils us and we're kind of swimming in this environment that's
telling us to well maybe we need to do more maybe we need more security
there is more it's not really just enough being here and breathing
um what could be there but a lot is there maybe we touched a
little bit in our meditation that in breathing and sensing and noticing
and feeling there's a joy that is found that is
probably always available if your body is mostly healthy
because this body is resting in this field of wellness and well-being and uh
we can tune into that and we can be oriented by that by the practice
because that joy becomes a happiness a happiness that allows us to see the
mind allows the mind to show itself and that's what the feeling
tones help us do uh feeling tones help us to see
what's going on at the core they're kind of a map to the core of our being by sensing and noticing
because we notice feeling tones as uh in the body and the mind as unpleasant
pleasant or neutral and each one that we notice and there are
billions of them to notice billions of them to notice in our experience
and as we notice more and more and more of them we get to the roots of the things that
lead to the most unhappiness and that's why we're pointed to them each joyful each
pleasant feeling that comes has a root of
kind of wanting more wanting more that root of greed these are latent roots roots in us so
it's the latent root of aversion the not wanting and then there's the latent root of
ignorance of delusion and so each feeling that we sense into allows us to get to those
roots allows us to see them kind of evaporate again and again if we
if we rest on them like we maybe did in our meditation a little bit
and so that then we can come to that kind of emotional tone of insight
what does insight feel like when it's happening we
see more through seeing our feelings and seeing our feeling tones seeing
what's going on in there how involved i am
with my desires how involved i am with my little cravings because feeling
tones have this powerful link that helps us to see very far far into ourselves
each feeling tone is like a product it comes with a whole product of our
mind of our intentions our histories our
deepest roots of wanting clinging not wanting aversion
and just by noticing that oh that's unpleasant we can stop
that whole link of that leads to the craving that then goes on goes on
so when we notice we can really penetrate through which is why we
develop more vision because we begin to see more how much how much
how much how much we are embroiled and knotted up by the senses
and and when we can come to the joy the joy of enjoy the body
without sensual desire we get to know more what it's like to
experience the pleasures of the mind those pleasures of the mind
the happiness of the mind that is not tied to uh anything sensual
uh that's kind of the flavor of insight that we like to to touch into
and um and we could touch into it a lot more than we do
uh by orienting toward a happiness simple happiness simple joy of
being in a being present doing an argument and being more present
than being in the argument for example noticing a beautiful sunset
and appreciating it more because it's beautiful and because we can see it we're seeing
that we're seeing it because it's a changing phenomena we see the changing aspect of it and
we appreciate it all the more because we're connected to an appreciating
seeing and unknowing so knowing is something that keeps increasing by
knowing our feeling tones how do we feel feeling tones are not the same as
feelings obviously feeling tones are is the tone
of different contexts the ouch the ooh
i like that uh there's a touch of sense oh i want more coffee
and then there's a oh yeah i want a second cup that second
mental little thing we add to everything that we push and pull or
ignore and we ignore a lot a lot
so the more that we notice and go with that through the
flowing of the stream of the sensations involved in all of this because this is all a
living flowing experience we can sense that that's why the body is
so important to show us that there is a ton of
touch going on and there's a ton of touch that gets interpreted as
pain for example and uh and it is painful
and then we can get close and notice it we receive it and notice it and maybe
with time notice more and more how it transforms and in noticing that transformation our
our vision increases because we're sensing the change we can sense the change and every little
bit that we do it just keeps adding up and uh and it's just a glorious thing because um
well it helps us to get out of some of the really bad things in life
like major depression for example um just comes to mind uh i came into this
practice with clinical major depression i didn't even know what that was i couldn't understand the
category the diagnosis when it was placed before me and
and it took a long time to really work that out i had a major depression for a very good reason
i had a big accident and became disabled overnight i got a disease
that made my spine and the equivalent of a 95 year old person's spine and it was
collapsing and producing a lot of pain and i became disabled and basically withdrew
from almost all my life so yeah i was very depressed and it was a it was a long process of
of finding joy again i couldn't understand the word joy for a long time it was the most complicating thing in
the world when someone asked me how are you for years and years and years people ask me how are you
and i could i never knew how to answer that because i always hurt physically and i was depressed
and it took a long time to understand being depressed depression is very tricky to see sometimes and um
so finding the word good i'm i'm good took some
long long long years of care and treatment and meditation
attention to those deep inner inner recesses of
affliction that were looking to be noticed and understood and
reorganized accepted and healed
and by coming back into the body this practice is a body-centered body
mindfulness as maybe you probably have heard many times i hope mindfulness is a
body-centered activity half of the practices of mindfulness
are about the body and the other half are about the mind and right in the middle
is our feeling tones the body is this field that registers
what's going on in the mind and it's this mutual registration that we
begin to understand and know more by touching in allowing to be touched
letting ourselves gently understand the touch of the body the
registering of thinking in the body how it shows up and sensing it
sensing it and getting to know emotions gosh getting to know emotions
that took some work for me being able to understand uh not
ignore not be comp where emotions are are interesting they're on this range like
for example anger we are either we really know anger we're really full of anger or we
can't feel it at all um and there's this this range of emotions
and teasing out emotions um through the help of the practice
because each tone is full of a tone that's creating
eventually overall moods our moods are big complex cognitive processes
that we can start teasing away a lot with understanding the tones the tones
of our the tones of what we think is unpleasant and pleasant
and it sure helps a lot to be rooted in a joy and we
often find the joyf can find the joy in the body or the mind if the body is
not available understanding the pleasantness of
the present beingness so to speak just being here
for a moment just being with this and just really being with this without
without thinking about it um to appreciate it a lot more because i can
just be with it to be with this nectarine that i'm having
for breakfast without thinking about anything um to just kind of be with that
that's the unworldly pleasure to know to know that we are
experiencing to be able to see that we're experiencing and that seeing is evolves through a mind that's stable
a mind that's stable that's finds a stability in happiness and joy
it's this um this kind of fountain of giving the stability that's provided
by by tuning toward happiness um which we kind of don't do
uh so much um not as much as we could and we are swimming in a place that
mostly is giving us the the signal to to
to to not be here in full body to do more you got to do
more you gotta do more in order to be relaxed you gotta do more in order to be
liberated we've got to work hard at meditation so we can have this concentration that's
going to solve all my problems or the worldly things of security
and worries but we can provide for ourselves and
that's what i've learned in this practice the most how much i'm the custodian of of this world of mind that i'm in
and and that i build it and i create it by simply
noticing sensing and feeling
and being maybe that's just being being
that way being without doing
just noticing learning to notice what i'm noticing sensing understanding the sensing
through and through and through and and being emotional uh understanding
where we are it's very helpful to understand where
i am in my emotional state about it being right now
to um be able to understand it first of all so that it can flow along
instead of being blindly constantly possessing the whole mood of my mind
the mind that we liberate is this vast thing that has uh this one this wonderful
knowing capacity of emotion uh and it's much more it's much much
more than that but we have to work through emotions it's good to
be intelligent of what leads to my emotional state um what do i add
and again it comes down it can come down to the feeling tones uh what is
what is the been the driving set of uh feeling tones that have been driving me
this morning where they can do how conducive are they
to happiness to the happiness of insight the happiness of being in the present
being in the practice um being in the presence of just the wisdom of
how things are flowing through coming back to flowing through flowing
through flowing through i was um look at the time here
last uh last week week before last i was getting uh a test uh one of those i have to
check my bod i have all kinds of physical spinal things that need a continuous checking
and i was checking the visual field they were checking the visual field and this big machine it's just really
cool big it's like a big eye and you look into this machine at these
little dots um and then there are four little dots that you look at to
move between the one dot and then the four dots and then they give you this little clicker like a little video game
and so you're supposed to click on this every time you see these other little dots all over the place
and they're checking to see the periphery of the field and so
it's like this cool game and but what i noticed was that he they kept
saying keep looking right at the dot and uh notice the field all around
and just click when you see the field and i thought it was so interesting
because we talk about knowledge and vision we talk about vision we develop this vision
of seeing um but the vision of insight is not at all like this
vision of my eyes it's it's somewhat like it but
it's doesn't have a specific location it body sensations are all over the
place and and then the mind sensations once the mind is liberated
um the mind this is the mind that knows space endless space this most endless
benevolence where's that it's not in this little
field of vision it's this embodied mindful experience that comes from
understanding and familiarizing ourselves with the endless flows of the energies of the body
changing and contracting and
always linked up to a feeling tone and each time we disengage a feeling tone we
release the flow and are more aware and more aware of
more body for example more aware of more mind when the mind is stabilized and
the pleasant feeling the pleasant feeling of knowing the changing
sensations is a very helpful guide they call it immaculate happiness
to have this understanding of the kind of the emotion of
insight so i hope
that maybe you might tune in a little bit to
the joy that is present the wholesome joy that is present around
within here and there in little bits every little bit counts because
it's around a lot more if we have a living breathing body and we're not doing
and we're not thinking and we're not wanting and not wanting and we're simply
just noticing sensing and feeling
there is a surgence of joy from well-being that's available
and a happiness of mind happiness with a very pleasant feeling and it's a
wholesome pleasant feeling the pleasant feeling that is not attached to
the doing and the clinging and wanting more and the not wanting that joy that's
attached to insight to watching the flow being with the flow of the sensations of pleasant and
unpleasant of the mind and the body so i hope that um maybe
we can tune to that as well as our other diligent practice parts um
and uh take advantage of this living life
that's the living life and it's going to end
and then there will be no more of that so um we can enjoy that now
and there's a lot to be enjoyed here and now of this life with a capital l
and on that note um i'd like to just dedicate uh some good feelings of
this moment um to a teacher of mine who died very recently in the last past few weeks
dr bing kung-hu he was a qigong master who was the
trainer of many many many many teachers around the world and i was very blessed to live
close to him here in berkeley and he was my teacher for a long time and really helped me to get back on my
feet literally because i didn't walk for three and a half years and
so i want to send him the good vibes of merits and with a lot of gratitude
because in this tradition here we we're doing this for ourselves and for
others always already at every moment it's an internal and an external practice
so the more feeling good that we do the more we extend that to others the
more feeling of the wholesome joy the more room we create for others to uh just be how they are
so may you be very very joyful may you be very very
happy this week and may our practice nourish others that we touch
may everyone be peaceful may everyone be joyful and may everyone
be at ease thank you for your attention and you have a great week
thank you very much francisco um
we've got some question i'll take one or two questions like gil does and then we'll wrap it up so feel free
to post any questions you have in chat on youtube if you want to you can post it in the chat there
and um francisco for
give people a few moments to you're welcome i see thank you so much
welcome you're welcome thank you thank you thank you have a wonderful week
so uh francisco so shauna has a question uh she said uh how did and this is something that i'd
be interested in hearing too is like how did you kind of move through your depression um
you know that you were going through um i think just specifically for me like i'd like it'd be interesting to
see like you know was it was it just like an epiphany all of a sudden or like were there setbacks since you
tried to you know how did you stay the course through
kind of coming back out of well you've answered my question wow
that smells like you know about depression but a lot of people know about depression um and
depression is very difficult to to know uh because uh sometimes it's different
it's difficult to see it and uh mine was very clear
and so it was a very long process of persisting and enduring and
persisting and i have to say that it was very supportive to have love in my life
that helped me to endure and persist um without it i would not have been able to
continue um it was uh such a it was such a bad situation for me
because of my body because of i lost work and because of the pain that did not
improve at all for years and years and years despite all the pain medication in the world
it just seemed like i was just getting losing more and more capacity and not and going downhill entirely
and in pain uh i i pretty much uh i didn't pretty much i sat my family
around and we talked about ending my life because it just wasn't worth living so i
had suicide ideation for many many years so it was pretty
complicated and just like all our knots we begin to just tease them out
you know we try to tease out one thread at a time we just tease them out and
persistence and endurance is so so key to to to keep
unthreading and finding the trust that each which she thread it builds the
foundation of stability and um slowly i learned to find stability
mostly through my mind and my body and when that stability started to build
it really started to heal things fast i think the body
and the mind for me was about coming back to the body because the accident had taken me so far
out but the body is this tremendous repository of life
and being and um nourishment that that holds us
together that provides a big big space field for um
for the worst of the mind terrors so learn how to learn a lot from
each layer of knot and going back into its deep old roots
and finding bigger knots there that needed to be unknotted and understanding how they
came to be and incorporating them into the present moment giving them room
that's where the body really helped me to give them room to be all here together
and learn learning to just sense and and feel
um and noticing noticing again and again to just um come back to these simple things of
this practice so the practice uh this practice is huge
uh it's there's so many supports i was supported by tons of things of this practice you know
we have these big fat books and they're full of these beautiful
helpful guiding points for going on and
thriving because you we do become liberated in this life we do have this extraordinary mind
that is a mind heart that is vaster than anything we can suppose and uh
it's it's really a wonder of life
yeah cindy also had a question uh maybe this would be the last one um so what led you to the dharma was it
a person or a reading
it was a person it was a yoga teacher who taught me back care yoga and
showed me how being quiet and how nourishing being quiet was
and then i just went to mbsr mindfulness-based stress reduction
because that's where they put the people who are really sick and you can't do anything more with them
i was in you know not walking and stuff so i ended up there and had my first day of silence in an mbsr
and after that i was hooked forever onto this practice and and just started
looking into it and getting very very very engaged much to
my poor good fortune wait when you say like to be quiet like
what can you kind of like uh just elaborate on that i guess concept
well silence like like that moment of silence
taking a breath we take a breath and we're just silent doing one breath
and we take two breaths and we're silent for two breaths and we take three and
on and on each one that we are intentionally just with
the sensation itself is a moment of silence
just being with with it as it is um you know before
the train the deluge of thinking uh presents itself and as what
it is but there's something else just that
thank you so much have a great week