this weekend i learned that in a south african
country uh in south african con language that the word for hello
is i see you and the
african person who told me this speaks the language i said that i see you has a kind of opening
impact it's kind of a different way of connecting to people than saying hello and and then this idea to be seen
and it is little you know a little bit odd too i can't see any of you that i'm i'm speaking to but i do see the
chats and i so much appreciate the greetings and the connection and i sit down here and
delighted to begin the mornings this way
so maybe in a figurative way i see you and offer you my greetings and uh
so um in important ways
the breathing how we breathe the experience of breathing is a reflection of what's happening in
the mind the mind is tense the breathing is tense
certain emotions in the mind or in the heart stimulate the breathing in one way and
other emotions do it a different way it's also to some degree true of the body as a whole there's something about
when we sit down to meditate some way in which we experience the body which does in fact
express or mirrors what's happening in the mind and it's kind of a profound thing to
appreciate this or to actually see how this works it's not obvious maybe in on the surface but then the
it works in the other direction that as the breathing changes it changes the mind as
the mind as the body somehow changes it changes the mind
and i say this as we begin as we often do with relaxing the body as a way of
entering into meditation and but relaxing the body and adjusting the
breathing are not just done for the sake of physically settling in and being here
it also is a kind of a an influence a healthy good influence on the mind or
the heart so for example as we relax the body perhaps that has a maybe we feel a
little bit safer maybe we feel a sense of safety or at least less fear or less anxiety
or less tension less and that as feeling less tension in the
body uh allow that to translate or to weft or influence the mind feeling less
tense as well and so the relaxing the body is
part of also preparing the mind for meditation and i'll talk more about
this during the talk so to take a to assume a meditation
posture and gently close your eyes
and with your eyes closed to spend a little bit of time rocking back and forth swaying back and
forth to see if you can find just kind of stretch and kind of awaken your body a little
bit and have a sense of your body in space and then maybe feel the contact with
your sitting bones if you're sitting against your cushion or chair
and then come to center looking for a way of sitting that feels like your
weight of your body is balanced in some way if you're sitting upright
that the weight of your body is centered over the sitting bones you're not leaning forward or or not um
you know your center of gravity is not behind you but because you're leaning backwards
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
not only to feel your body more fully but to establish the connection between
the mind and the body more consciously
kind of create open the channels the communication between the mind and
the body
feeling the rib cage stretch and expand as you breathe in and feeling the same rib cage maybe
collapse or contract as you settle in when you exhale
and then as you exhale long deep exhale see if you can relax and soften
your body
shoulders belly and as you take a long exhale
and relax the body let that have an influence on the mind quieting of the
mind relaxing of the mind
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and see that if we also do some more relaxing and see if there's some way maybe subtle
way that relaxing the body
has an influence on relaxing the mind as well
so beginning by on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
as you exhale softening the shoulders releasing them to the pull of gravity
maybe the weight of the arms encourages the shoulders to release a
little bit
perhaps relaxing your hands any tightening in the fingers
and as if the mind participates in the relaxation
relax the chest the center of your chest your heart
center
softening the belly
and as it softens the softening in the
mind
softening in the lower waist and lower back
and relaxing the thighs
and then to feel your body in some global way
and then as you exhale to relax the whole body
easing up in any way in which you're bracing yourself against life
and then bringing your attention to your forehead
behind your forehead and the area of the brain
feeling any tension or holding pressure that might be there
agitation and as you exhale
relax
let the thinking muscle relax the tensions and pressure associated with
thinking associated with worrying
associated with wanting
and then once again feel the global body
in whatever way that's easy for you to the degree to which it's easy
perhaps you feel subtleness or a tingling or
aliveness warmth some energy
coursing through your body
maybe even you can notice some feelings of contentment
or peacefulness in your body
and then within the body as part of the bodily experience become aware of breathing
and gently maybe slightly at the end of the exhale
relaxing the breathings maybe you breathe
exhale a little longer
at the top of the inhale a subtle relaxation releasing
maybe the inhale continues a little more
and then can you make some small adjustments to the breathing so breathing is more
pleasant more enjoyable not dramatically but just a little bit more
breathing a little slower a little faster a little longer or shorter
looking for whatever subtle pleasure there is
in your breathing
and quieting the thinking mind
so there can be more intimacy with the experience of breathing
and if there could be if there is any coziness
contentment just being here in your body
or satisfaction
being connected to your bodily experience directly
even if it's uncomfortable
maybe you can allow the mind and heart
to share with some of that contentment or coziness or satisfaction
content just to sit here breathing in this living pulsing body
there is an intimacy and deep connection between the mind and the
body that functions more deeply or more
clearly when the thinking mind is quieter
gently letting go of your thoughts
appreciating the ways in which the mind can be quieter stiller so
there's a richer connection awareness of the body breathing
and the goodness of breathing where the relaxation of the body
can have a nice influence on the mind
perhaps there's a way you can soften your belly more relax it
to settle your breathing further
and to reassure the mind and heart
breathing in and breathing out
and then when we breathe
we breathe together with all breathing life
we share it with all of everyone else who's breathing
it's our common humanity that we all require breathing
to not only to live but for their whole inner life to be
functioning well
and while we might wish at the end of the sitting for all beings to be well and happy and free
we could also wish them to have an easeful breath
for their breathing to be easeful and comfortable
relaxed open breathing
because this way of breathing is deeply connected to being happy and
safe and free
may all beings have an easeful breath
may all beings breathe with reassurance and safety
may all beings feel delight
with their breathing as they breathe
and may it be that we live together with other people
so that we do not we're not the cause and condition
for their breathing to be tense
shallow tight may we be a condition and a cause
to support others to breathe at ease happily and peacefully
and perhaps we can coexist with an easeful breath
and the best in all of us has a chance to come forth may all beings
breathe peacefully
[Music]
so i'd like to make a couple of announcements before giving the talk
i mentioned some time ago that i'd like to offer you a chance to have some longer meditations
in the morning like we're doing here we've been doing this for a long time and
some of us together and some of you are ready for sitting for more than 30 minutes some of
you are yeah you're ready and it'd be actually be helpful to have a little longer sit
and also for this topic of anapanasati i think that mindfulness of breathing having a little
more more practice with it and a little longer sitting would be good as well
and so what i like to do is in two weeks i think i believe it's uh the 15th
of february on the 14th i begin a retreat and and so i'd like to
integrate the morning sitting with the retreat and the retreat with the morning
sitting and have our sitting start at 6 45 california time
so 15 minutes earlier than we usually do so we can have 45 minutes together and
and and i still still do the guided part but there'll be more time for silence from
settling in and i think this will also be very good because of the topics we're coming to um the
uh by then i think we'll be maybe at steps
9 and 10 which has to do with aspects of really really experiencing
the mind and so anyway so that's coming up
and you can certainly join us at 7. there's no problem with that i think but if that's what your schedule allows
but that's the plan we'll do that for one week and
and so i'll announce that a few times or so make sure people know about the change and the other is
that um the retreat that i'm doing at that time and the following retreat at insight
retreat center the um we've kind of arranged to have
uh it's full the retreats but for but we have arranging to have spots for auditors and if some of you
would like to participate in the retreat and happy especially if you've been on a retreat before and know the you know the basic routine of how to
practice that way you're welcome to sign up to be an auditor and and uh in doing so you might we have
auditor teachers we have a teacher for it that is available to have uh drop in
group discussions with it with the um the auditor so they feel a little bit supported
and but that auditor teacher won't give any teachings they'll just be there to support the auditors
so um so anyway so some of you might want to do that and participate and i think that
the theme for that retweet starting on the 14th of february is refuge and so we'll go through the
idea of refuge as a as a wonderful topic itself but also as a
support for the deepening practice of meditation on retreat
so
so last week for ana panasati talked about the steps
five and six five is um breathing in experiencing joy breathing
out experiencing joy and then six is breathing in breathing in
experiencing happiness breathing out experiencing happiness and uh the movement from joy to
happiness is a move towards tranquility the mind the body becoming more tranquil
where the joy factor is a little more energetic and the and the happiness
quality is more subtle more peaceful tranquil kind of sense of well-being
and that movement from something is a little more energetic to this more tranquil is characterizes
the whole process of deepening meditation in buddhism that we're going from coarser states to
more refined subtler states of being we're going for more active ways of engaging
and as the mind settles down we're moving towards a clarity and an alertness and a
peacefulness that where there's things become
the mind becomes less active more peaceful more softer and so the quieting of the mind the
requiring the activity settling and settling is kind of the movement we're going here
and and that's kind of like so the principle of going from coarse to refined or more active to more tranquil states
and tranquil doesn't mean that we go sleep or that we become dull the movement is to a
tranquility that's quite alert or has a lot of clarity to it um but there's less activity and it's
fascinating process to see this and one of the things we start seeing is this relationship between the
mind and the body and and
so the first tetrad steps one to four are kind of about the body and
and but it's not the physical body in and of itself it's more the body that um that we
experience with experience is very much
influenced by what's going on in the mind and there's a reciprocal relationship
that as uh the mind as the body settles down we get more focused on the body and it
relaxes more the fourth step is to relax the body that also has a
relaxing effect on the mind and other effects beneficial effects in the minds it's reassuring for the mind it
brings a sense of safety to the mind peacefulness to the mind subtleness focused in mind it's easier
to be in the present moment and and then we go into the second tetrad
now with steps six seven eight five six seven and eight
that um now we're beginning to enter into the world of the mind uh that is not separated from the body
these two are inter interlinked but we're moving into the area of the mind and the qualities of joy and happiness
are a bridge between this because the joy and happiness is felt in an embodied way
and uh and but it's very much influenced by the concentration level of the mind the
focus of the mind the peacefulness of the mind and and then there's a reciprocal relationship as there's more joy and
happiness that courses through the body then that reassures the mind more and allah
and reassure a reassured mind will feel like it doesn't need to think so much and ruminate so much and
can get quieter so kind of this bridge with joy and happiness between
the kind of the body and the mind is really worth lingering with and developing and
and uh and i know it's a little hard for us from oftentimes to feel joy and happiness and short notice
and just will it up like that but um even if you don't feel this during this
time when this section of the of the practice um it maybe just
imagine it or not imagine you're having it but but develop a kind of a intuitive sense
of it or learn these teachings and sooner and later hopefully you'll recognize a little bit this
meditative embodied joy happiness well-being that can happen as we as we practice and some people are
surprised or delighted that they're given permission to feel pleasure in meditation
permission to feel joy and happiness and um and definitely this is really the
considered to be very important foundation for moving forward
um in many many places in sutas the buddha actually describes a process
of of steepening practice that is called the gladness the gladness
sequence or the gladness pentad because those are five steps and these are acquiring gladness
in meditation and then it the description is is very kind of intransitive or passive it's
like from we're not doing the next steps they just flow as one becomes
mature it flows into the next flows into the next we do our practice and the practice
begins practicing us something begins shifting and changing and we don't have to be so responsible
except to be really present for the experience so with the gladness there arises
joy with the joy when it's mature there arises a tranquility of the body
with the tranquility of the body there arises happiness and with the arising of happiness
they're there with the maturity of happiness there rises uh concentration unification
being really unified and sitting and feeling very whole here in the present moment and this
wonderful kind of pattern the gladness sequence gladness joy tranquility happiness and
concentration unifi samadhi now what's interesting and what i want to emphasize today is
the the first step is feeling a sense of gladness
and the gladness comes from being inspired by something and this uh the buddha really
understands the value of becoming inspired being glad and being delighted
by some aspects of what's happening in our practice or in our lives so that it kind of that certain kind of
gladness that we don't get lost in our thoughts and stories and imagining over and over again what happened
but we use our imagination just enough to have that gladness begin settling us
into the present moment more and more settling us into them into the body
and this use of the imagination to help us to not make us go wandering away but using the imagination
to allow us to be inspired is one of the supports for meditation practice
and and how that inspiration can be not forced not imaginary not
an avoidance of the present moment but really a support for really connecting in a deeper and deeper way
in an honest way with what's really happening in our lives what's really present is one of the great benefits of dharma
practice to be able to be present even for difficult things with some form of well-being
some form of may sometimes joy delight gladness that holds it all not to be
removed from this challenges and suffering of the life of life but to really in some sense be receptive
to it in a really deep way and not be a victim of it not be oppressed by it
but to have compassion and love as a possible response
so what i'd like to do for the next maybe a couple of days and we'll see how far we go is talk a little bit more about the
buddha's emphasis or use of imagination focus on teachings on imagination
both as what gets in our way for meditation interferes with it but also in ways in
which it supports meditation and and and this seems like a very nice
bridge between the mind and the body this part we're talking about joy and happiness but
because this imagination is very much to do with this happiness and joy qualities and and to how to
evoke joy and happiness with gladness with uh what inspires us
through by thinking about it or something so that's a topic and and uh and hopefully you'll get a sense
as we go through these teachings that how it's useful in connecting you
to uh this steps uh five and six joy and happiness and creates a very good foundation
for the continued settling uh becoming more tranquil the mind becoming
more peaceful it's a preparation for that so we can look and start looking more deeply at
the mind itself and the and the quieting settling pacifying of the mind so that it becomes
an instrument of awakening so um that's the introduction for
this week and i look forward to our time tomorrow and and um delighted to um
to share this time with you thank you