so good day to everyone and here in redwood city there's a light
rain it brings me much
both joy and a kind of intimacy of uh just with life and wonderful times
and
so here we are to sit here and you're here
everyone has their own here and in some ways for each of us to say here
is uh is something we say in common and also is unique to each of us because
of the different location that's here for us different place that we sit or meditate
and in part of meditation practice is on this anapanasati is
gathering ourselves together here and as the practice develops
there is an emphasis on concentration an english word which doesn't really do
justice to the pali words that are sometimes translated as concentration or
concentrating and um but the word samadhi the one
one one associated word is a uh yeah and it's a
word that sometimes is translated as a one-pointedness but uh if it's one pointedness
it's kind of like the um it use an ancient analogy of um of a
um all the rafters of a small hut that maybe started more or
less a round hut they all come together up into the point of the singular point to the top of the
roof and and so everything gathers everything points everything reaches for that point
and that point in a sense if it's a circular building is that if you look from above it's at
the center of it all and everything else radiates towards or comes towards it i guess
and so everything moves towards the singular focus but
focus suggests in english too much that a strain and a duality between us
and what's what we're focusing on and laser focus or something and rather i think of it more if you use
rather than a hut you know the root roof but just a circle concentric circle
and and the the the center of it is where
the mind everything is focusing everything is gathering everything is circling around and it's
all included in these concentric circles of our lives body emotions thoughts
mind everything is somehow included but everything is gathered to this
around the center so sometimes we say in english around
meditation practice to be centered and so we're centering ourselves here
with everything included but resting at the center and so one of the
ancient techniques for centering ourselves and really kind of being gathering ourselves and everything kind
of coming in around something developing concentration
is counting the breath and i suggest we do that for the sitting
and the way that i was taught which i did for i still do sometimes is to
count the exhale and and then the next exhale gets the next count so 1 two
three up to five up to ten and at ten start over again be
completely relaxed about not forgetting losing count or getting
distracted at the first opportunity just begin again at one it doesn't matter if you only get to two
or even in just two gets to one before you lose count start again at one and
one teacher one person i knew who practiced in japan his and teacher taught them to count up
to one and then over again and um and uh and then kind of
but don't just make a count a little voice in the mind that counts but rather
uh see if the whole mind the whole being can somehow one like all of you is
included like if maybe if you were singing or something and you
all of you is included in the singing one it's kind of like really there the
exhale and with the release of the exhale kind of settling and gathering together
and the complexity of counting up to 10 requires a little extra attention to keep count that makes
a little protection from wandering off too easily into thought and you're more likely to catch yourself
thinking perhaps you notice you're not you've lost the count because you have this very clear
kind of task but the main thing to do is just gathering together this the whole mind settles and lands
landing on the center and the center is the place where you most experience
the breathing so the belly or the chest or the nostrils or whatever
just gathering settling one so taking a posture for meditation
where you can somehow begin centering yourself
in your body and centering yourself
around where you're going to experience your breathing
the inhales and the exhales
the predominant place to experience breathing and then from this predominant place
the center of it all take a few long slow deep breaths
and this as we do this the exhale
use that to really settle in let go
release yourself into the body that's breathing into the place where breathing is felt
deep breath in and exhale relaxing the
shoulders
softening the belly
releasing
the tensions in the face
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and familiarize yourself to with that part of your body where your
feel your breathing and imagine that that's at the center of
it all center of the universe and that as you breathe from that place
awareness spreads outwards throughout your body and maybe even beyond and as you exhale
awareness settles back in to that
and then with a very soft quiet voice
but with a voice that includes
all your being on the exhale
use the count one
and if you want you can just do one each time as if each breath is complete in itself
or you could keep it simple or simple enough and just count to three
and then start over again
and if that works well you might count to 10 and if you get to
10 you could
start again and while they want to try to keep the
count the important part is the settling in
to the center
relaxing any centrifugal force out into outwards into thought into feelings
that takes you away from being centered on the breathing
not fighting anything or resisting anything just not giving it attention
not getting involved where attention goes where your
involvement goes is following the count
in centering yourself here in the breathing inviting all of who you
are to be included
so the count is not just a little word in the mind
but it's an expression of your whole being willingly fully here
quietly here with the breathing
as you do the count spread out the pronunciation of the
count long count one in such a way that maybe it begins
quieting the rest of the thinking mind
like you're gathering yourself around to say something intimate and soft and
warm-hearted and as you do this soft one
center your body on the breathing
land fully with your whole being on the experience of breathing
giving yourself over to the counting and experiencing breathing
as if it's the only thing to be done for the next minutes
letting go of your thoughts accept account
and then in the last couple of minutes of this sitting
to let go of the counting and just sit here with the breathing
enter into the breathing center yourself on the breathing without
the counting and see if you're a little bit more
centered and connected
and then at the end of the sitting to remain as centered as you can
centered inside of yourself rooted in your weight of your body and
the weight of your attention into the center of breathing
a place of balance where you're not easily pushed around or
caught up in things and being so centered
now open your awareness up to the world around you
to the communities that extend out from where you are neighbors and townspeople and
people in your county your province
outwards into the world
open yourself up to consider the people you might run into today or communicate with today
and from a centered place where maybe nothing has to happen
at least for now sitting here no responsibilities for them no
requirements obligations just as centered experience
that includes other people awareness of them thinking of them
imagining them
and in this kind of way of not being obligated or
not being required to do anything or react or talk to them to open your
heart to evoke your good will
your basic capacity for friendliness
care kindness and love
maybe that's related to a tenderness
within to whatever degree that you could have this good will for others
feel how it maybe also is rooted in your centeredness in your calm
or your concentration
and then imagine that it radiates out from you as a warmth as a light
as a care may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we appreciate how being centered and balanced and
non-reactive supports this possibility for the world
may our practice be for the welfare and happiness of all the people we encounter
communicate with today may the world benefit from our meditation together
[Music] you