so warm greetings from redwood city
and it looks like it's going to be a
beautiful blue day blue sky
and uh the vast blue sky with no clouds in it
is sometimes seen as a metaphor analogy for
our mind and to begin appreciating the
sense of settleness wholeness clarity that can come through
meditation practice arouses arouses evokes
a sense of delight or satisfaction or being pleased
in this opportunity to sit with oneself to sit and meditate
and and that is the 10th step of these 16 steps
is being pleased or steeply satisfied or delighted the word can mean rejoice
and there's something about stepping back a little bit and appreciating this opportunity to
meditate and then as the meditation as we become more
centered in the moment with ourselves becoming more whole more whole here then
there is um
hopefully some deep sense of beings of satisfaction in this process
so here we are and
we've been doing this some of us for a while now and so to take your usual meditation
posture or the one that is the right
for now and gently close your eyes
and even if you're agitated about something if you're sitting in your regular
meditation posture is there um
something comforting about doing so
something settling or something familiar that's
feels good to be in this posture
if you've been doing this little ritual of taking a few deep breaths at the
beginning is that also something becoming a little bit comforting or settling or familiar
that you can get settled into so taking a few long slow deep
breaths and as you exhale
to relax maybe a long slow deep long slow exhale
settling in here
the deep inhale is a chance to feel the fullness of the body the
width and breadth of the body or the wholeness of the body that's always more whole than the parts
always greater than the particular places of discomfort or distress that we might have to take a
deep breath in that spreads the awareness through the body so the awareness is
more encompasses more than any particular issues we have
and to exhale to let go of this intensity of some of
the thoughts and concerns soften and quiet the mind
soften and quiet the heart and the inner your inner life
settling in
and then taking breathing normally
and to some degree the process of meditation is a process of coming to a kind of wholeness
where all things are kind of held together without any
and divide within us everything has a place
and the relaxing of the body moves in that direction
on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the shoulder
on the exhale relaxing in the chest
and on the exhale relaxing the belly softening the belly
and perhaps on the exhale there's a way of releasing the whole body
releasing the way we might be bracing ourselves we're releasing the way we're
leaning ahead of ourselves
and then feeling the breathing
for a few moments familiarizing yourself
with your breathing the experience of it
and then whatever pleasure or joy
well-being that might be here even if it's in the cracks between
other things breathe with a pleasure breathe with a
well-being tingling in the body a warmth the glow
feeling of pleasure and the breathing maybe
or as you relax a kind of spread of
energy through the body that has a pleasant quality
breathe with a pleasant
and as you exhale relax the mental activity
quieting your thinking
relaxing any tension or contraction in the thinking mind
maybe relaxing the thinking mind on the exhale
and letting the mind become broader wider quieter
kind of like the waves on a vast lake the waves quiet down and the top of the
lake becomes still quiet the flatness the calm
stretching wide out towards the horizon so the mind gets quieter
and then be breathing with your mind state noticing the general mind mood
the atmosphere of your inner life breathing with it
allowing it to be the way it is but being mindful of it as you breathe
maybe appreciating
that a mood or a state is broad wide
maybe has no boundaries
his soft transparent translucent
that mind state is not a solid thing it has no weight
maybe no color
maybe appreciating
the insubstantiality of mind state
breathing with it breathing through it
and rather than letting your mind drift off in thought
let your mind be concerned more with the breathing
breathing in the middle of this wider hole of body and
feelings and mind state
appreciating the breadth and the width of this whole
and then is there anything about sitting here now if you really settle in really connect
to the direct experience of meditating that has a feeling of satisfaction or
goodness to it something that's pleasing or something that makes you feel glad
or delighted being delighted in the being on the path
of practice having a practice being settled
not caught up in the busyness of the day
breathe with what is pleasing not so much the ideas of it
but maybe the ideas give rise to
an embodied feeling of satisfaction joy delight
in this experience of becoming moving towards wholeness or subtleness or ease
more peacefulness
and breathe with that satisfaction that delight and breathe with it in a way
that helps the mind become more quiet
a quiet breathing
with the inner delight and satisfaction
of being here now
instead of caught up in activities and concerns and thoughts
the goodness of just being here meditating
stepped hand of anapanasati is breathing in
delighting the mind breathing out delighting the mind
and how might you look out onto the world with eyes of the
light how might you look upon the world
with eyes of kindness and love
how might you look out from your heart
sharing delight sharing joy as if it's food
for the for the hungry
as if it is a missing resource in our lives
to no delight to no joy
and to look upon others having delight in them
appreciating others with respect and love and and may it be
that our delight and appreciation and respect for others
that we concern us ourselves with their happiness their safety
their capacity to be at peace in this world their freedom and may our delight
our joy and others our appreciation of their beauty and their the wonder wonderfulness of
others be contagious and support others
so that all beings may be happy
all beings may be safe so that all beings
may be peaceful so that all beings may be free
and may our delight and joy the existence of others support that
you