hi everyone welcome to happy hour hi
and if you can hear my voice okay give me thumbs up fantastic great audience
all right good good good so hello and welcome
to happy hour so let's as always start informally as we
always do saying hello to each other helling saying hello to ourselves
uh welcoming ourselves to this space and i start by saying hi i'm nikki i'm in mountain view
california unseated oh looney lad and you're welcome to unmute yourself if you
like to put your voice in that would be nice let's do that we're a smaller group
so far so take it away who is here
hi nikki it's it's ken hi ken hi
i just noticed that you're not on the calendar today what
oh oh is that what went wrong let's let me check hold on a sec maybe
that's what the problem is oh no
wow uh we're supposed to be on the calendar some oh my god
okay let me fix that right away wow somebody erased us by mistake
wow okay well i just put us back on the calendar huh
wow okay well thanks so much ken for that update that's why we're smaller crowd
today people are like oh it's cancelled it just disappeared
oh my god there's some things going on just to say i noticed earlier today there
um or was it yesterday i noticed there were lots of events added in the wrong time
for this week and next week and um so i think whoever tried to fix those
uh additions probably went a little overboard and erased happy hour oh my
god that explains it thank you ken appreciate that well who is here
uh hi i'm trisha
i am i live in manhattan beach my friend from new york um claire comes and she shared about it so
i thought i'd join today awesome welcome welcome thanks
who else wants to say hi hi it's fred from oakland um
my screen tells me that i'm on youtube although i clicked into what i thought
was zoom and apparently this is zoom i guess
yes you had to make it okay yeah seems like we're a little things
are a little funky tonight but people are joining bit by bit thanks fred yes
you're on zoom you're at the right place at the right time the right channel
uh bill in dallas i'm glad i'm not the only one that makes mistakes
likewise jerry in toronto they make lots of mistakes [Laughter]
hi bell and jerry it's clear in new york one of my favorite lines is one of the
joys about being imperfect is the joy it brings to others
yes exactly that's right yep we all make mistakes so
to air is to be human and mark and poppy say hi from squam
washington hi mark and puppy hi good to see you and and jesse is from san
rafael anybody else wants to say hi oh we have men hi neil good to see you
sarah and flagstaff hi sarah welcome
it's great and we have mandy from rainy hudson valley in new york
and william uh from chicago joining us on youtube we also have a smaller crowd
tonight on youtube i think probably did they didn't see it on the calendar it was erased so
oh well here we are so anybody else wants to say hi before we
get started it's kind of sweet i came from rainy defino hi
he came from rainy to phoenix he's great so all right violet in san francisco oh
hi violet good to see you
and yeah versus glad my notifications work so as not to miss you oh yes so we do
have folks getting notified on youtube yay joining now that's awesome so
so let's get started and hi lydia from baltimore thank you neil for sharing
information about the google groups uh in the chat where folks can join
you get quotes and resources and can connect with folks offline
this time i ask you to please mute yourself if you are unmuted
and the last thing i do the change is to
turn on recording for the sake of audio dharma here we go
okay great so hello and welcome everyone
hello and welcome to happy hour so for today's
practice theme um [Music]
i wanted to invite us to consider the practice of metta practice of
cultivating kindness loving kindness warmth good will so many different ways to relate to and
translate this this lovely word from paulie metta
m-e-t-t-a to relate to it as generosity to relate
to it as generosity um this week
i'm subbing for gail at the seven a.m sits he's hiking and on vacation so and the
theme i've chosen to explore in the morning to invite everybody's minds to swim in is the the
theme of generosity which is a deep deep practice it's not just about
giving um material items but it's a deep
practice of letting go and and cultivating an attitude of generosity
um an attitude of let of letting go relinquishing
relinquishing with good will it's not letting go like oh i have to let go you know when you think of met
for example meta or may you be well may you be happy you're letting go of
your good wishes of this well-being you don't want to keep it all for yourself
right it's an act of generosity this practice of metta may you be safe may
you be well you're you're blessing you're generously wishing you're generously offering
you're generously offering this uh
this good will for others and also generously offering it for yourself not
to exclude ourselves generosity doesn't mean that you just give it to others and not to give it to yourself but to also
generously oh may i be happy may this being who is me he may be happy may
may i appreciate the blessings of my life may i rejoice in the blessings of my life may
i have well-being so there's just some sort of generosity that is part of meta
so so that's what i'd like to invite us to explore tonight as we practice meta
this aspect of generously generously opening our heart
and offering meta first to ourselves and then to others actually maybe we'll
start with the dear being and then somewhere in the middle there we bring ourselves in
sometimes that's easier to to to do that so so
let's begin let's get started with our formal practice
so so landing landing in our chair landing in our
cushion
this chair this cushion offered
can we accept it can we land in it with accepting generosity with graciousness
ah maybe even saying thank you chair
as if we were giving a little bow to the chair thank you for supporting me
supporting my weight dear cushion dear chair
relaxing inviting the body to relax to soften
starting from our hands softening
keeping their weight off to the earth
dividing our arms our hands
hands wrists lower arms upper arms
to relax soften
our neck shoulders our face our jaw
dividing the chest the upper back to soften relax and
receive the breath
the lower abdomen lower back too [Music]
giving their weight to the earth
making space for the breath
this
do
relaxing into the chair cushion they're sit bones
bottom on the cushion
releasing the weight of the lower legs and feet onto the earth
do
just receiving [Music] this in-breath this out-breath
in their entirety
tilling the soil inviting the mind to settle in your eyes
as we receive each breath
receiving the gift of each breath
in this body in this moment
can we invite ourselves to appreciate the breath the life-giving breath
soaking it in relishing it as a gift of generosity
offered to us not taking it for granted
not rushing for the next breath or trying to hold on any longer comes and goes
gifts come and go relishing each comings and goings
of this gift bestowed to us every
minute
this
and as if we were giving ourselves
a gift just as the breath is offered as a gift
because generosity is a gift that we give others and we give ourselves
to bring to mind someone who's dear to us someone who's easy
bringing them to our mind's eye
and as if we had a bag of gifts
generously giving them gift after gift
gift of metta gifts of goodwill
blessing them with these wishes of goodwill may you be safe
knowing that life is unsafe or the world it's human
being human it's not inherently safe there changes all the time anything
can happen at any moment and yet i offer you a wish of safety
i wish i generously
from my heart wish may you be safe
expressing my intention for your well-being as this wish
not hanging on to it just sprinkling it giving it freely
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may your life unfold with ease
feeling the goodness of the generosity in your heart
with each wish of metta for this dear being
now she'd like can we allow ourselves to be
seen through the eyes of this dear being
with their eyes of generosity and let ourselves be the recipient of generosity
can we accept their gifts of good will graciously not to deflect say oh i'm
unworthy i don't deserve
the kindest way to show up when someone offers
generosity is to receive it graciously
can we receive generous meta good will
good wishes offered
from a dear person dear being open our hearts
and receive them graciously with gratitude appreciatively
imagining your mind's eye that they say to us may you be safe
we let it land may i be saying
imagining they say may you be happy
we open our hearts and let it land yes may i be happy
imagine them saying may you be healthy
ah graciously receiving this gift yes may this body may i be healthy and
strong imagine them
wishing us please may you have ease
in your life receiving it
yes may i have ease may my life unfold with ease i wish that for myself too
so receiving with generosity graciously offering it to yourself this
mentor
graciously receiving
smilingly receiving
and offering generously offering
this bottomless
well of metal the more you give yourself
to your dear being the more there is the more good will
gets generated doesn't run out
feeling the abundance of your own heart
showering yourself showering your dear being with goodwill friendliness generously
may both of us be safe etc etc
now if you wish you can shower
not just your dear being in yourself but others
generously with your good will feels so good to be generous in this way
maybe offering it to the sangha
all these travelers who support you with their practice what they're showing up
maybe bringing each being to mind their face their name
wishing them well
and if imagery works for you you're welcome to use images
maybe you have a bag of seeds seeds of mint
you're you're throwing sowing all these seeds from this bottomless
bath
maybe it's flowers you're tossing
in the past we've used the image of playfully especially when it was hot i
guess in the summer showering them
with cooling waters of meta
with a hose play for me whatever image works for you
showering maybe showering them showering others with metadust like fairy dust
that touches their heart
your wishes of good will
friends family colleagues
people whom you don't know very well
neutral beings maybe neighbors people you see at the grocery store
and definitely let's include the person who mistakenly
deleted happier from the calendar imc calendar tonight showering there with metta may this
volunteer be well be happy
done their best
all human beings just like us just want to be happy just want to do
their best in this life
we all make mistakes may they be well may all beings
all of us humans all beings
beware
it is said that generosity
and meta glad in the heart free the heart see if your heart is a
little gladdened more glad compared to when you arrived
it's a little lighter it's just a little freer
appreciating your own heart's abundance
and offering the merit the goodness of your practice with generosity to all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you for your practice everyone ah
practicing mitto as an act of generosity brings two
beautiful practices together and it's happy making i feel happier and more at
ease my body heart to mind compared to when we arrived
being very very tired tonight i feel refreshed by the practice of metta's
generosity i would love to invite you
for your reflections for your questions
fred please
hi nikki hi so i had great difficulty at the very beginning
reposing into uh the gratitude for being here and
um i'm i'm a little self-conscious about going back into this again but this is
what i'm experiencing just you know seven weeks now into my ears ringing all the time
i'm just very very uncomfortable and it's really hard to feel
um [Music] the gratitude of sort of physical existence
and um i did feel something shift
slightly as i started to think of my beloved person that it wasn't it wasn't difficult to to
wish met up for them and then it was
entirely possible when i pictured that person then
looking at me and knowing that that she would wish with with great
urgency that i be safe and happy and well and at ease
so that was that was a really significant turn i won't say it you know
it eradicated what i was feeling before but it was different and um
and i appreciate that and i guess i also want to ask you then
if you have a more advice of how to
when i'm physically overwrought and exhausted
with this constant ringing is there um
do you have an advice about how i might try to step into
the physical pleasure of existence which i could tap kind of easily
before seven weeks ago yeah thank you
thank you fred first really feeling for you and i'm so sorry
this is it's it's challenging tinnitus is challenging
ah and [Music]
as i hold with compassion what you're going through i also celebrate with
mudita or what you just shared with this transition noticing this shift
which is profound which is profound this
shift and just a little more lightness not being in that state
so so holding both of those holding both of those yes it's challenging and wow
notice this shift it was possible to wish well not to keep
being in the state of uh over wrought or you didn't say any of
these but like really really challenge states you know it was possible to step out of that hooray hallelujah to offer
meta for dear being and then see them offering it to you beautiful
yay this capacity i celebrate what you're sharing this is profound i really
want to highlight it and um so that is beautiful yay
yay really leaning into that leaning into the possibility because
that really opens up even more possibility of what is possible for you
right now in this moment in this heart and in this mind and in this body and with everything
that's going on that yes it is possible a little more freedom is possible right
here right now right yes yes exactly it was possible yeah it was
experience yay and surprise yes beautiful surprise right
yeah i appreciate you smiling yeah um and these are mini nibana's these are
mini moments of freedom freedom is like this more freedom there was more contraction and pain and being
overrun ah now there's the heart is opened i've i've stepped out of myself
wishing this person a while the ringing is still present but there's less suffering in that moment
and oh yeah thank you one other thing i would say so so that
really i want to point that out just for you to see that yes there were you've
you are capable it just it's it's here already the freedom is here for you
and then the so in one more thing all to say uh also to add
the moments when there is exhaustion and overwrought well yay you already know
this practice of menta for the dear being helps you step out of yourself out
of this the the the prison-like feeling of this so that
you know that that's possible and surprisingly wow and then wish you all for me and then there's just some
lightness the buzzing can still be there but you can be above it
there's some level of transcendence right
yeah um and also sometimes it could be so so
this is enough maybe i shouldn't even mention this next thing but but i'll say it
um sometimes it could also be skillful to turn your awareness if you wanted to explore this
other invitation also turn your awareness to something that is
pleasant in your body because i'm willing to bet there is something that's
feeling good maybe it's the i don't know the weight or the warmth of the hands or
something just feels pleasant and warm or cool or turn your attention to that
not allow tinnitus to be the only game in town i mean as human beings
there's so many sensory informations that we receive as you well know every
second and perception can be selective select something else turn the channel
thank you very much thank you fred wayne i see your hand
i i just want to uh thank everybody and thank
you nikki and the teachers at imc i am so grateful for the practices that you've given me
and and all of us um they this has been the most difficult day
i've had in a long time and it was so helpful to uh
just try and stay in touch with my body and and uh think of
think of uh giving
feeling compassion for these parents that were giving me help
so anyway thank you
thank you wayne thank you for showing up for being you're
supporting yourself and also knowing that you are a teacher right now in these very very challenging times good
heavens these very very challenging times thank you for what you do
for so many students so many parents who in your words gave you hell
today and and in this practice sitting with opening your heart and holding them with compassion that is
wow i i feel chills if every teacher uh practiced in this way as as you do
would transform it would transform not only the lives of the teachers but the students and parents so thank you for
doing this for everyone you know you know i also feel a lot of yesterday i did a hour and a half long
men's retreat with james barres and some other fellows that i've done once before
and and that's very very wonderful that's great thanks for sharing that wonderful thanks wayne
and on youtube richard uh says thank you fred attend your sharing
i'm living with tinnitus since two months ago and sending you metta for your difficulty so
thank you for for sharing fred and um [Music]
richard and i trust many other people appreciate the the shared the shared common humanity of
of tinnitus and similar conditions that are ongoing
so dear ones the time has come for us to share with generosity our presence
with each other in small groups so i'm going to create
the small groups now and as always we start with
um [Music] 15 seconds of meta
silently for each other and then you can share as little or as much as
you wish about your practice be kind take care of yourselves take care of each other
it's a tender sangha their rooms are created and now they are open
enjoy
okay welcome back everyone we have about a minute for
any reflections questions that have come up especially if you haven't spoken today
or recently please don't be shy love to hear from you
you can also type in chat if you wish but it's nice to hear your voice
anything you noticed about the practice neil [Music]
please so [Applause] you know it it this was just such a
beautiful imagery right when you know you're you're giving affection to someone you care about and
and then suddenly you're like receiving it um it was it was lovely
you know everyone on in my small group thought it was lovely it was just wonderful thank you
thank you neil thank you for engaging and practicing in this way and
and your heart your heart finding it lovely you as well as everyone else in your group
all the practitioners these are just invitations and what you make of them is what you make
of them so so we share we we share the gratitude for each other
thank you neil yeah and thank you all i'm just
absolutely delighted makes my heart so happy for for your gift of generosity as
as neil and others have have mentioned which is your practice which is what
you're offering to each other to yourselves and to the world just makes me happy yay generosity
brings happiness so thank you for the gift of your generosity
and let's dedicate the merit of our practice tonight may all beings
know the goodness of their own heart may all beings be happy may all beings be free
[Music] thank you
oh and i forgot to restart the recording bummer oh well mistakes happen