so i wanted to express again my great appreciation of coming here and reading all the names and chats
that uh in the chats and some names that i recognized from long ago and some
i'm recognizing from here this uh since we started doing this on youtube
so so wonderful to be with you
so um one of the important things to be mindful of
is or to be aware of is that what we do with our attention
has a big impact on how we are conditioned the habits we build up the dispositions
that we kind of build and create the kind of conditioning that influences us
and one way to see that is that where we direct our attention has a big
impact on what we register and therefore are conditioned by influence by
so if we spend our precious attention and spend a lot of time focusing on negative thinking that's kind of
debilitating or critical or a lot of hostility or resentment a lot
of self-criticism a lot of greed that we're kind of being reinforcing
that tendency so kind of influencing us it's kind of like smoothing the channels inside of us for
doing those things making it kind of normal almost and uh so we're more predisposed to have
those thoughts in the future if we bring our attention to something
which is wholesome then that's what we're cultivating and being influenced by
and of course we don't want to have blinders on and ignore what's negative the difficulties we have
and the way we take care of this and mindfulness is
it's the vehicle through which we're aware of both the positive and the negative
and so rather than being focusing on what's negative and being involved using attention to be
involved in it we can know it um through one of the four
foundations of mindfulness we can know it as a physical phenomenon in the present
we can know it as being unpleasant or pleasant whatever it is in the present we can know the mind
state as being kind of contracted or distracted or the or the
mind state that's settled calm and open we can know whether
in being involved in that we are entangled in something or whether we're kind of spacious around
it and so we're not actually bringing not ignoring what's happening
but we are recognizing um
it but through something which is wholesome through something which is a nourishment and that is what i want
to emphasize today is whatever is happening whatever you're meditating on today
can you kind of look around to see how how to feel it how to be with it in the
present moment in a way that's nourishing that feels good that is freeing and opening so even if you're
involved with something negative something difficult and there is a way that you can kind of look around in your
body your mind your heart and find out how is it you can hold it in a way
that the very holding it is a positive influence on you
so that's the task for today so
uh so if you can uh um assume your meditation posture
and part of it is to take some long slow deep breaths so that you can
see if you can find a way to settle into this body
a settled body is a way to
connect to what is wholesome nourishing nurturing
even if there are difficult things happening
taking a deep breath in and settling your heart
and then we'll sit there quietly relaxing settling in
and stay whatever is happening in the present moment can you find a way to breathe with it to
be aware of it to attend to it in a way that is
beneficial nourishing
through the body through the heart
through an awareness that is opening
breathing in and breathing out here and
now
foreign
you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to take a few moments to appreciate
that one of the really important aspect of
mindfulness practice is not what you're aware of
but how you're aware of it
it makes a big difference if you're aware
driven by greed or hatred resentment
fear anxiety or if the awareness is infused with
non-greed non-hatred non-resentment non-anxiety
if the awareness itself
is pleasant is enjoyable is appreciated
he's receptive and open he is not straining is
at ease and peaceful
to be aware in an open
useful way and as we come to the end of this
sitting perhaps that can be our gift
to the people we encounter that we are aware of them we meet them
and know them and are present for them
in a way that is non-violent non-harming
in a way that is not imposing or
pressuring or not anxious or
preoccupied or closed
perhaps with a support of our mindfulness practice
we can be aware of others in a way that is nourishing for
ourselves and therefore
friendly and receptive and kind appreciated by others
may the very way in which we perceive and sense feel are aware of
others
be beneficial to ourselves and to others
before we have to figure out what to say or what to do
just how we're aware can be our gift
at ease in ourselves at ease in the eyes that look and see
may we walk through the world with gift bestowing eyes with gift
bestowing awareness
and in so doing may we contribute to the happiness the safety
the peace and the freedom of others
may we not underestimate the tremendous value
of non-harming awareness that is really present for others
may all beings be happy
thank you so for today's um
talk on clear comprehension some pajama clear recognition i would like to um
i'm happy to talk about the third form of clear comprehension which is uh clear understanding clear
recognition of the pasture and uh pastoralistic
strange expression but it's uh this is my i think my favorite of the clear
comprehensions and um pasture refers it's a word is gotchara
g-o-c-a-r-a and poly go is the uh word hollywood for cow and
probably it's a cognate kind of indo european languages have the same source and charo is what
means like means where the coarse the cherry at the mandala chariot but the
the um the course the place the place the location the field
the place where the cows go to eat so pasture and
uh so it's what what what feeds us what nourishes us and um
and so uh to recognize in as we do our activities
what is the pasture where is the nourishment that can come from anything that we do
the um because everything we do in a sense is conditioning us everything we do
isn't is the nourishment for something so in specifically the pasture in
is the four foundations of mindfulness that the body is a pasture for we get
nourished and supported if we know how to bring attention to it the attention to the feeling tones of
experience to the mind states to the dhammas the mental activities that go on in the mind
all these things are nourishment for ourselves but the way at their
nourishment is when we're aware of them in and of themselves the the body
in the body the feelings and the feelings the mind states in the mind states and the mental activities in the mental
activities and what this means is a kind of expression from the suttas
and what what this means is that we're aware through the vehicle through the through
the the channels of direct experience through these four means
not through the thinking the proliferation of thoughts the ruminations
the fantasies the complaining the anxiety-producing thoughts that might be
spinning around for us and those are not nourishing
and even if the thoughts are wholesome they might not be the place of the greatest nourishment
but to be aware of whatever is happening through the channel of the body
and to learn how to through the body feel things in a way that feels wholesome so it's
how we're aware that's important but we can discover that sometimes through the body
and the body becomes the pasture we can become aware of it through the feeling tones whether things are
pleasant or unpleasant and even unpleasant things there's a way of knowing it
a way of being present for it that oddly enough can be beneficial and nourishing
if you're aware of unpleasant thing is unpleasant and we're reacting to it and contracting
around it and angry with it or despairing around it then it's not nourishing
but if we go through it and just feel the unpleasantness the unpleasantness and unpleasantness
independent of our reactivity oddly enough that those unpleasant things begin
entering into the beneficial mode they it provides good good conditioning for us good food for
us in a certain kind of way because we're becoming free of it
and then um the um if we're aware of the mind state that's
present so it's all having to do with present moment awareness of the mind state
and that present moment as soon as we're aware and clearly recognize the present momentness
of the mind state that recognition is no longer caught up in the other pasture we can
walk in the pasture of you know as i said rumination
complaining judgments fear anxiety the thoughts that are spinning and pulling us around negative self-thinking
is very harmful and it isn't that we should just push it away or be aversive
to it the magic of mindfulness practice is that we recognize it that's there
but we don't feed there we don't let it influence us and one way to do that is
to know where the pasture is a clear comprehension of the pasture
of the good place to be uh to be aware through the body where feelings and feelings to be aware
without through the without the channel of these spinning thoughts that we might have
and at different times different pastures are the most beneficial sometimes the
best pasture is the think is the body and we just really aware and sense and feel through the
body sometimes the pasture best pastures recognizing the feeling tones
uh the pleasant unpleasantness and neutrality of the experience sometimes just be aware of the mind
state the attitude how the mind how awareness holds it and sometimes it's uh better to be aware
of the the uh the operating of the mind the attachments the clinging the freedom the
the different wonderful qualities of mind that are present
and so uh to have clear comprehension of the pasture
where we feed from and as i said for the buddha the best pasture is the
four foundations of mindfulness and then i'll repeat because it's so important
how we're aware is where the best nourishment comes and so if we
don't have to avoid paying attention to what's difficult but how are we aware of it is that is the point
and if we're aware of it through these four pastures it can be beneficial in nourishing the
awareness not the negative states of mind not the negative thinking it's how we're aware which is nourishing
but then it's a little different with um wholesome states beneficial states
then there's a kind of double benefit that how we're aware of them would also not
wear without greed or holding on or expectations but how we're aware of them
is uh is beneficial and they themselves make good food they themselves are good
conditioning so it's a way of not being conditioned by the negative
but to make room to be conditioned by the positive all in the service in the traditional
buddhist sense of developing greater and greater uh strength of mindfulness stability of
attention in the present moment on the way to becoming free
and if we can become free in how we see become free and how we're aware uh
our atta our attention to others can become a gift um people can trust us that when we're
present with them that we don't have agendas of our own that we're imposing on them
we're there to see to be present and and share as
common human experience of being alive in this in this challenging and wondrous world
so thank you very much and um and how we're aware of the challenges of
the youtube and sound that's the art of it not whether or not the
video is choppy or not but we'll see if we can get it fixed for
tomorrow thank you