so formally hello and welcome to this tradition rendition of happy
hour so for today's practice um
i'd like to bring in something that's thematic
and and also bring in some
buddhist practices into that so okay so what do i mean by that right so
so it's the it's the olympics as we all know and um
and uh i was quite touched by hearing learning that one of the
athletes simone biles who is a young [Music]
gymnast and if i heard correctly on the radio she's the most decorated
[Music] female gymnast
anyway so she decided to pull out and and not compete
for because of mental health and what i heard is that it's very
common for for gymnasts etc well not very common but you know the reason why they would
pull out of competition that the olympics at this at this stage usually is because of an injury
it's physical health it has never been mental health
um and her making that statement really that that courageous
statement of self-care um is so inspiring it's so inspiring
to really not just take care of our physical health but our mental health
um and of course we can imagine how much pressure an olympian like her would be under
and of course we all have pressures in our lives of different kinds so
so self-care self-care of course i mean we know this in many ways we already
know this as practitioners and yet it is wonderful to see it in the zeitgeist and i think olympics
being an international event that unifies all of humanity
to see an olympian at this level really take a step to take care of herself for mental
health is i just wanted to bring that in i wanted to bring that that theme in is worthy of our happy hour to
to give a nod to for all of us in this community for all
of us taking care of ourselves physically emotionally mentally
self-care self-care and not being ashamed of it there is no
shame in self-care there is no shame it's it's so important and it's actually an
act of courage it's really an act of strength and and you know we can see it perhaps for
simone biles you know and i see for her wow that's very courageous yay you go girl you know
pulling out for mental health wow what an act of strength right
i can see it for her you can see it for her i trust you i trust you can now see if you can see
it for yourself if it's possible for you to see it for yourself
you know if if there's a day you're just not it's so too stressed out it's just too
hard would you would you think of it oh no i'm going to push through i'm just going to push through and know
oh my mental health is not important enough i'm not sick i don't have an illness
do we not see it for ourselves do we appreciate it for others but not for ourselves
so that's one reflection i like to bring up for us too to sit with to sit with this happy hour
appreciation of self-care the courage the courage the courage of self-care
and the other theme i want to bring in is
one practice to offer ourselves self-care there are many ways to offer
self-care the practice of meta compassion presence
and the way to like i'd like to invite us to explore tonight is is one of um
holding presence holding presence in
a physical in the physical body so just as the buddha you know there is
the image of the buddha the the one of them the common images statues
or the mudras the the mudra this this hand movement of the buddha
touching the earth grounding himself ground pick himself
as if oops i think my computer just for
all right my computer just froze here we go so the mudra of of the buddha touching
the earth grounding it as earth may be my witness i am here i am
here i have the right to be here i am here so connecting with the earth the
sense of stability stability of the earth touching the
earth touching the earth with our bodies
and also feeling the solidity of the body the earth element
in the body throughout the body so that's another thing i like to bring in
because at times when the mind is going all over the place or
it's just very challenging this can be a support this can be a support this
is grounding oneself feeling sensations of the earth
grounded in the earth the earth element in the body throughout the body throughout the body
can be very grounding so i'll bring that in the invitations as we explore tonight
so so let us continue
up i hope my audio is still coming through
i feel coming through your image keeps getting frozen but as long as the audio is coming
through uh that's great okay so let's get into our practice posture let's start our
practice together
so
landing in our bodies
landing in this moment
connecting with the felt sense of this body this body connected to the earth
by the earth touching the earth
rising up from the earth feeling our spine
this sense of integrity sitting upright
well rooted to the earth with our feet our legs
our sit bones
resting on the earth resting on the earth
earth on earth resting on the earth
earth on earth
earth giving itself giving its weight to the earth
the whole body this body has earth element
parts of it solid
heavy resting on earth
feeling supported by the earth
as if we have an image of this body sitting this whole body
turning the gaze of our awareness internally all throughout the body
feet set bones abdomen chest
arms and hands neck and shoulders face
our own time feeling the settledness the solidity
it'd be such a sense of comfort coming home to the body
especially be stabilizing
calming soothing to the heart to the mind
feeling this comforting solidity in our bones
the touch points
even places in the body where it feels empty vacuous
see if you can feel the sensations
solidity of the earth element and if it's hard feel the solidity of the areas
surrounding this part of the body
as if supporting saying it's okay it's okay you're supported
whatever tenderness there is the heart and the mind and the body can
be supported with the stability the solidity
[Music] the rootedness of the earth element
elsewhere in the body wherever accessible the touch points
maybe the whole body is a whole block if you're looking at yourself
seeing yourself
this entire body the solidity uprightness integrity
rising up
if you've never tried this it would be helpful especially if you're stepping out of
yourself for a moment and have an image of this entire body and stepping back
stepping back into solidity the whole body
earth on earth
and with this sense of presence solidity earth element
earth sitting on earth
feeling connected to the earth
supported by the earth you belong here
can we feel the sense of support
this earth element both connected to the earth and the
solidity of in our own bodies comforting supporting
caring loving grounding
imbued with a sense of meta with care
it's okay it's okay
and to hold to allow for the courage to recognize we need to care for
ourselves physically emotionally mentally
it's an act of courage
to connect and care make space
and wherever a sense of stability is available whether it's throughout the body just
feeling the contact points the feet the legs
or the hands that's enough
if you like you can experiment with putting the palm of your hand
your heart center
connecting with yourself making a connection solidity sense of touch
feeling sense of care support of touch
contact this elemental
you can imagine it's either your hand or the hand of a good friend someone who cares about you touching you
supporting you let yourself be surprised
your body knows the magic of dutch
as if borrowing from the strength of the earth
element this body the strength the support
the strength of compassion of care
and shining out the meta in the remaining minutes of this practice period
as we feel supported
by the earth feeling the solidity of this body
letting the care the good will
shine out touching this body first and shining out to all beings
who need to take time for self-care
for mental health care emotional health
may they be well
may all beings including this being who's me
of all the resources the support they need
to take care of themselves happily
may all beings including this being who's me
have mental happiness and ease
may all beings including myself
recognize the need for self-care
and when
it is needed
and to take care of oneself happily with ease
hey all of us beings
have well-being
goodness and ease
may all beings everywhere
have mental and physical well-being
be free from suffering
thank you all
so we explored the theme to begin this
theme of self-care with not just physical care but mental
mental suffering mental health and then one way one way to actually
express that bring or bring stability sense of care holding
is through this practice of the solidity of the body
grounding the body the earth element and both from my teaching and practice i
found i found this to be so important have you noticed that sometimes if
there's a lot of mental distress mental um
unhappiness agitation you know the body feels as if it it contains smoke as if the
body is just you know there's no solidity in the body
as a human have experienced that and i've also experienced and witnessed that for
many practitioners especially if they're in very difficult mental states so bringing this this
embodiment sense of grounding in the body with the solidity earth earth on earth the buddha sitting
on earth touching the earth so that's one aspect that's so important
just the sense of meta care feeling the body the whole body the whole body
solidity a brightness support the calming soothing lovingness in that
the scent and something magical nurse in the sense of touch
in the sense of touch you know again as as little babies newborns
when they're cuddled they they calm down they there's the sense of
oh they when there's pressure in their joints when they feel the solidity right
when they're held tight oh they calm down they calm down they feel the sense of
love and care and for us it's similar so touching ourselves touching our heart
center with our hand holding ourselves or just mentally
mentally touching ourselves all sense of solidity throughout the body
is both can bring up a sense of stability as well as sense of care meta
it's there's so much here there's so much both science here as well as as
practice of of us experiencing on our own oh yeah i feel more stable more
supported ah earth on earth
i belong here
so there's so much more i can say but i'd love to hear from you so um you can raise your zoom hand
please to share what it was like for you for the benefit
of the of the sangha you can also type it in chat and bill please
um yes hello um i i really enjoyed the sense of being
embodied and i just wanted to say that not too many weeks ago i i wasn't able
to really do that but i think you've helped me a great deal there and i want to say thank you um
you're welcome thank you yeah it's it's very um satisfying would that be the right
word maybe sure absolutely it is satisfying to connect to be embodied
yeah absolutely beautiful thank you for that bill and you wanted
to say something else i thought yes um i i think i've said it
oh okay stop okay great thank you bill i'm delighted i
i am yay i feel mudita vicarious joy for your ability to
to feel embodied after these many weeks of of practicing i do remember the times
you would say i'm not embodied so yay [Music] i cheer you on fantastic and the whole
sangha cheers you and i see smiles on people's faces this is so sweet thank you bill
and someone on the phone please
hi everyone this is melanie i usually join on video but i decided to call in by a phone today um i've been thinking a
lot about simone biles in life watching the olympic olympics and gymnastic really closely
and um for those of you who follow it more closely simone actually said that she withdrew because
she got what's in gymnastics is called the twisties which is like when you basically lose sense of where you are in the air
and it's like so incredibly dangerous for gymnasts because they can like land on their head like they don't know where they are um and so i thought
that was just so relevant to this practice like this idea that she withdrew because she had like lost sense of where
she was and she needed to like reconnect her mind with her body and and how much that connects to meditation
and just having that awareness of like oh my mind and my body are are too separated right now i need to
like you know withdraw and focus on myself and bring them back together so i i really admire her and i think it
is just like so related to this practice yes thank you so much melinda for adding
this detailed nuanced detail and oh my goodness i i got chills as you
were describing the the connection which i hadn't heard
of yes connecting knowing connecting to her body which is what we did tonight inspired by her
beautiful thank you so much for bringing this nuance and i'm i'm touched and so heartened
thank you for that comment trevor please
yeah hey um before i joined tonight i just got into a huge
blowout with um with my family you know like it rarely
happens in that manner my dad has stage four cancer and he's potentially one of the most
difficult people to deal with in terms of just uh
not in touch with himself at all and and just um not willing to just very stubborn very
old school stubborn and um
even before the blowout i had just been talking with a friend about how i have to have that sense of equanimity and do my
best to take care of myself and know what that means and what that
looks like to practice that and um and to uh to give
to his treatment and and and love for him what he needs
without any expectations and that's a very difficult thing to do with a very difficult person
and just feeling the the intense [Music] just real bodily discomfort and uh
almost pain that that comes with that kind of level of blow out so
um yeah just uh just thank you for having these every every night even
though you know so rarely here thank you trevor thank you for being
here and practicing for both your own sake and the sake of your
dad and your entire family and everyone whose lives you touch
yeah it's it's hard what you describe is very hard
holding you with care compassion as you hold yourself with with the stability with the
grounding that i know
i trust you can have for your own sake in your practice and everyone else
yeah thank you thanks trevor thanks for your practice and and dropping in
tonight especially after the blowout hope this was supportive for you
great yeah ah so dear ones
let's turn our attention to practicing in small groups oh one
more reflection an hour before the sitting i came across a word um
so i looked up what it meant it's the mudra of touching the earth oh great thank you that's lovely bumis
parsha mudra i didn't know the name of it now i know boom is parsha mudra thank you for that
lovely so let's turn to practicing in small
groups with solidity connecting with the earth embodiment for ourselves supporting each
other and learning from each other so as always we'll start with 15 seconds of
silent meta for ourselves and each other and then sharing as little or as much as
you'd like to share about your practice so here are the
rooms they're created and i will open them now hello everyone welcome back the rooms
are closed and since we um i think we took uh time at the other end
with reflection so it's seven o'clock and and um i'll close
our session um actually by making a correction i think i said simone biles
is the most decorated according to wikipedia i correct myself she's the
most decorated american gymnast and one of the greatest and most dominant geminists of all time so i just wanted
to correct if i remembered wrong or accolades anyway so thank you all
thank you for your practice we'll close the session and i'll stay a couple minutes extra if you'd like to stay and
share reflections i'd love to hear if there's things that you discovered with this practice that
were new for you so that um for the benefit of myself and and sangha so thank you all for your
practice for showing up and cultivating this practice for
yourself and sake of all beings everywhere may all beings
be connected to their goodness to their body feel supported
on this earth may all beings be free [Music]
thank you
foreign