so good morning good day good evening hello everyone
and here we are to do this morning meditation or
together and a little bit the topic of
theme of this session of mindfulness meditation
is what's called investigation or exploration a process of discovery
and as one of the seven factors of awakening it's sometimes said to be the most
important one for the purpose of awakening
for the purpose of freedom and there's something about
choosing to explore to discover
to investigate what our experience is
which is an expression or a manifestation of freedom
no matter how difficult something might be to choose to take
take another look at this to step in a sense step towards it to
see it better or sometimes we step away from it to get
a better view of it it's always to discover to see to
investigate and when we do that we're not a victim
of experience when we do that we're not under the
control of experiences around us within us
when we do that we are our attention is not being hijacked
by our hindrances or our neurosis or our fears whatever it
might be and so this ability to decide okay what
what is this what is this experience i'm having
and not to answer that question with words not to answer that question with
an explanation but to answer the answer it with
um with
a clear seeing to answer it with a clear
perception feeling for what's happening
so taking a meditation posture
and in some sense this expression of freedom which is to take a
good look begins with caring for your posture
choosing to use this wonderful resource of attention
to scan through your posture
and to
make small adjustments
that not only help you be more settled and more relaxed
but also a little bit more alert physically alert
ready to discover ready to see what's here
and then to take a few moments to discover your own breathing
without doing any different breathing just notice how it is for you to be breathing
to explore it to feel it
and as you do so maybe you can notice a difference between being
entangled with your breathing and
wanting to be different or concerned about it or and simply discovering it
simply becoming familiar oh this is how it is now
without being for or against
without being analytical and
preferences just discover it in its own way how the breathing is
and then having done so now to take a few long slow deep breaths
as a way of establishing yourself in this body
here and now
and then as you exhale long exhale
relaxing settling in releasing yourself
the tensions of the body
and then to
let your breathing return to normal a little bit more it's useful to release
and relax the holdings of the body as you exhale
and often enough the tensions and holdings of our body
give pressure or give yeah maybe a kind of pressure to the
mind to keep thinking about things being preoccupied and as we relax
the body there is less of that pressure to think
softening the face around the eyes
softening around the shoulders
releasing the shoulders maybe adjusting your hands a little elbows so the whole arm is a little bit
more at ease
and perhaps softening the belly
and then settling into your body breathing in whatever way breathing is most
compelling or easiest most pleasant for you to attend to
in the belly in the chest and the nostrils
wherever it might be
and then very simply
choose to be with your breathing
to discover how it actually is now
distinct from how you want it to be
in a sense to explore it to discover it to investigate it
feeling the freedom in that choice
that you're exercising your your ability
to direct your attention to discover and feel and get to know
better
noticing the difference between the bodily experience of inhaling
and exhaling
noticing a difference between the experiences of breathing where there's some tightness or
constriction and where there's some looseness and releasing
to investigate it to explore it means to let feel it on its own terms
step towards it to just get to know it better without it needing to be different
without trying to fix it just know constriction here looseness here
and discovering a little bit what it's like for you to be aware of
your breathing what it's like for you to explore
investigate the experience of breathing
not to make anything right or wrong but how is it for you to discover
the kind of discovery that of a naturalist
simply discovering something in nature patiently observing it as a natural
phenomena noticing how you are in relationship to
mindfulness or breathing as a natural phenomena
if there's resistance or reluctance eagerness
if they're straining or complacency whatever it might be
discover it notice it and let it be that simple
the simpler the discovery is the more freedom there is
freedom to let things just be as they are freedom from our internal reactions of
things just being aware discovering
seeing and then returning to the breathing
maybe seeing how simple the discovery can be just discovery just seeing
not seeing anything special or hidden but just how it appears
just how it shows itself to you
if you get lost in thought that's just another natural phenomenon
and you the naturalist that's studying it seeing it
this is how it is
and then settling back into your breathing
a silent discovery a silent dis investigation of breathing
where there's an intimacy or a clarity
about the different sensations that come into play as you breathe
and to follow along
to observe in the distinct sensations of breathing in and breathing
out distinct sensations of
the beginning middle and end of the inhale beginning middle and end of the exhale
discovering your breathing
and very easily with ease
maybe you can feel the freedom the independence that you bring to your
experience by choosing to discover it to see it
more fully more clearly
without it needing to be anything different
even when our thinking is pleasant if we get preoccupied and lost in
thought there is also a loss of freedom
but to wake up our capacity to discover
what's happening here
is to enact our freedom
and asking the question what's happening here is not to be answered per se
but to encourage taking a gentle clear
look what is happening here just seeing and feeling and
just what's obvious no need to
think or probe just discover
what is showing itself to us now
to investigate does not need to involve a contraction or a tightening
of attention or the mind it's more useful to have it be involved
in opening an expansion of attention of awareness of the mind
it's open and receptive
and you know and it's possible to let this investigation factor
come to its fullness in simply being mindful of the breathing
breathing with greater intimacy and
clarity discovering
the obvious experiences of breathing in and breathing out
with clarity and
distinctions
with a quiet mind a mind that gets quieter
the more we discover
so to bring this sitting to an end
to use your freedom and investigation
your ability to discover be open be available
to you see if you can use it to have that freedom of openness of
discovery for others to allow them to be
as they are because you are free
so and i see that you could hear my phone
calls with my wife so perhaps you can hold all this in investigation and
freedom and simple discovery how it is and
so in doing so may all beings be free
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be safe
and may all beings everywhere
be happy
so so let me talk a few minutes about this uh
what's often called the investigation factor um so not quite loud enough someone says
so let me see [Music]
so i think now is it better now the sound okay so let me
say a few minutes here about the investigation factor of awakening
and it's usually called investigation and people who look into this
will say that it's probably not the right best translation but it's a pretty good one overall it's
an overarching generalization because
it involves uh a exploration a discovery a deeper discernment
of what our experiences and
this process of exploration is in english is often called investigation
and um but investigation uh if it means a kind of a deeper probing in searching
it's not what we're what is referred to when we're doing this vipassana practice
but rather it's a state of openness and receptivity to allow the experience to show itself
fully to us and for me it's represented by the question what
what is happening here what just what is it but we never look for an answer
as more that the what prompts a clear looking a clear discovery
of a kind of a silent kind of sensing or feeling or looking or
perceiving of what is here and and in doing so
we're beginning to in enact or tap into
our capacity for freedom that it's so easy to be caught
and entangled by our experiences by our thoughts by our feelings by what's happening in the world
and and there's so many ways we get entangled so many ways in which we get
attached we get reactive to how things are and when there's reactivity
reactivity by itself is the is not is not freedom uh to respond
with choice to respond with wisdom can it be an enactment of our freedom
but but to react is not so if we're always reacting and being
pulling around by our thoughts and hijacked by our thoughts if we feel like
we're a victim of experience then we haven't discovered freedom
and one of the ways it can begin this freedom is in acts of mindfulness to be mindful of what's here but also
acts of mindfulness can also grow to be a little bit stronger forms
of freedom which is investigation to uh
uh to see to discover what is here and the kind of core investigation
that's part of vipassana practice is is what further on the retreat
inez talked about yesterday dhamma vichaya and vichaya comes from the word prefix v
i and then the root word c-a-y-a
and chaya means to heap up to accumulate and v means to separate and human beings
have amazing and very important capacity to generalize to lump things together to to
hold concepts of things altogether and and they're useful but also they can
limit our ability to see clearly what's here to discern distinguish
the details of our experience so if i say that i had
a you know a difficult morning with the technology
then well that's a generalization but what specifically was the experience like of
being here with technology for this morning some of it was quite delightful and enjoyable and inspiring to see the
people in the retreat to see the people on on youtube and
and with the chats for example and and um some of it was quite nice to be
exploring for me exploring the dharma as i spoke it was nice to sit and meditate while
while there was some quiet for me and i was meditating and
and then there was the issue of the technology that there's so many
different uh devices and things here that i got confused about which uh charging uh battery charger
that was supposed to be at home and what was supposed to be here and so the so this what the you know it suddenly
went dark my laptop and it wasn't actually unpleasant experience at all it was just kind of it just was
what it was and um suddenly this was there and there was an issue to look into
and probably the most unpleasant part of it all was needing to ask my wife for some help
when she's busy at home and and also wondering how i was going to
get back and having running in time for the zoom people and then uh the awkwardness of realizing
that you could hear what i was saying some of you on on youtube and um
and let's see you know what what impact did that have on people meditating and but that was all very particular and as
i distinguished all the different parts of it i wouldn't say it was a challenging morning here
it was it had its unique challenges its own particular things but i didn't lump it all together as
like a lousy morning with technology it was all these little if i
if i wrote out the details the distinctions of the moment moment what was happening
there were challenging parts and not challenging parts there were pleasant parts and maybe some parts that were not so pleasant
and this ability to begin distinguishing and not lump and in sense buddhists you know if you
know the distinction between lumpers and splitters buddhism thrives on on being splitters
on really seeing more and more carefully what's really happening here what are the details rather than
generalizing about things and so this idea of this disability this
clarity of mind that gets cultivated through mindfulness the mind gets clearer and clearer
and the details the particular particularities the details of experience the
unique little component parts of experience begin
revealing themselves more and more and more and where that becomes particularly
important is when the capacity to distinguish to see the particularities the details of what goes on
is um is um goes together with wisdom
the wisdom factor and the wisdom factor is uh the one the many things that are
considered wisdom the factor of wisdom in in this practice we do
but one of the core aspects is being able to make the distinction between what is helpful and what is not
the distinction what is wholesome and what is not what is healthy and what is not or the
distinction between what has a an ouch in it or an ah this is good or a distinction between
what is where freedom is or where freedom is not that distinction is a is the what wisdom
is capable of making mindfulness puts us in the clarity that we see things as they are and see them
clear and clear and wisdom sees what is useful and what is not
and that distinction is where we discover the path
where we discover or where the choices can be and so the simple distinction between
being entangled in experience and being free when we investigate it
with wisdom we see actually it's better to be free than entangled and so to the degree which we have in a
capacity we put effort and energy into going in the direction of freedom and in this case investigate
or discern or see more clearly what the experience is
and so it said that the the the investigation factor of awakening that
clarity of mind that can really see the details of experience not lumping the
generalization of what it is that um that ability
then um inspires the effort factor of awakening the energy
because we see oh this is the direction to go this is where freedom is this is where
peace is this is where the lack of stress the lack of suffering
is found and that's inspiring to make that choice and go in that direction
to go in that direction is another manifestation of our capacity for inner freedom
and as we walk this path we keep discovering more and more ways in which we can manifest or enact
our freedom until at some point freedom becomes a state that we live in as opposed to something
we find in the details of our you know of how we live and the choices we make in our life
so the investigation mindfulness leads to the capacity to see
clearly that's called discernment making distinctions investigation
and that in itself then is a prompt or a catalyst for the effort
factor in practice so that the effort factor of awakening can get born and
and come to fulfillment and that'll be the topic for the next
topic for the retreat and the next topic for youtube and like tomorrow morning
so thank you and and i think this hopefully this uh
little technology issue today wasn't too much of a
was you know interruption at all and it all worked well enough for everyone so thank you very much and and
so we'll continue