so hello and welcome everyone it's good to see you again missed you
makes my heart happy to sit with you and be back in the space of happy hour
so for today's practice i'd like to share a poem
as inspiration and the poem is by relka
those of you who sat the retreat i shared this uh the retreat last week
two weeks ago that now i'm losing track uh i shared this
poem in the evening as a talking to bed poem that's one of the
poems so and i've been reflecting on it it's such a beautiful
poem so it's very short here we go the poem is by relka
reiner maria rilke and the name of it is in my life in my life
and term for resources it's from rilka's book of hours
love poems to god so
so the poem is i live my life
in widening circles that reach out across the world
i may never i may not ever complete the last one
but i give myself to it i may never i
may not ever complete the last one but i give myself to it i want to say a
few words and then we'll do meditation
so in this practice when we practice the brahmaviharas we
practice them in widening circles as you've noticed we start with ourselves
we go to our benefactors our good friend the neutral person
person we're having difficulty with they all being so all
widening circles we practice expanding our heart we live this practice in widening
circles that reach across the world as rilka
says the last category all beings reaches across the world our good will our
kindness reached across the world and we may not ever complete the last
one the last circle completely with every being in every condition every
situation but we give our hearts to it we give ourselves to it it's an act of
dedication it's an act of honoring it's an aspiration
not an expectation that we will make sure every being everywhere is
definitely okay and it's it's an aspiration we give our lives
to cultivating this goodwill this friendliness to all beings everywhere
and given that meta compassion the practices of the
heart are intertwined with awakening we can also think of this poem
as a dedication to awakening that we may not ever complete the last
stage of awakening in this life we might we may not
as upandita the title of his book this the the master of meditation master
upandita the title of his book was in this very life in this very life so who knows
maybe in this very life and yet if we do not get to complete
the last one this last circle the last stage we give ourselves to it we dedicate
this moment to it our life to it it's a part of our path when we are sitting when we're walking
when we're interacting with others can we bring kindness to mind can when we're interacting with
ourselves can we bring kindness to mind can we be kind can we be
aware can we not be caught
so now with those words i like to read the poem one more time
and let it land let it land for you and er in any way that it inspires you
and it provides aspiration i live my life i live my life in
widening circles i live my life in widening circles
that reach out across the world
i may not ever complete the last one but i give myself to it
i may not ever complete the last one but i give
myself to it
so with that inspiration of giving ourselves to it our hearts to it let us
practice so getting into our meditation posture
whatever it might be lying down
sitting up straighter see what is most supportive to you
and landing in this body in this moment
so turning our gaze inward at first
the breath with this body to arrive to settle to relax
to greet this moment to greet
this body however it is inviting it to soften to relax
to settle
after thoughts are rising concerns stories ask yourself
do i need to be thinking this right now
ah i'm smilingly with humor
letting the balloons of thought go opening your hand let them float away
ah let yourself sink into this body oh
feeling comfortable comfortably supported
by the earth giving your weight to the earth landing
in your chair your cushions no need to contract or hold up any
muscles yourself
do just taking a few minutes to arrive with
the breath in the body for the mind to settle
to collect
how is the heart right now
how is the body in this moment
how is the mind just lightly lightly curious
aware
of whatever is arising
arising and passing it's okay
so
[Music]
now i like to invite you with this reflection for practice
considering considering your life
the arc of your life
living living your life
living my life
as real ka says in widening circles living our life
what does it mean to live my life
to cultivate my heart
my mind
the aspiration to live our life in widening circles
not an expectation with pressure but an aspiration
a dedication to dedicate our life
our bridgening our growth
to these expansive expanding widening
ways of being relaxing widening circles
living
loving caring [Music]
being friendly
being open
being curious
being generous
being happy for others happiness
being compassionate with pain
and ever widening expanding circles
as if with each breath being breathed
into our abdomen into our heart center in the middle of
our chest as each breath in breath and out breath
touched to our aspirations any of the aspirations i mentioned
growing in generosity and kindness
in gladness in widening circles
imagining each breath touching into this aspiration
and expanding to widening circles
and we may never complete the last one
but to give our lives our hearts to it it's an aspiration as a direction
this is important to me this is how i want to show up in the world where i
want to be who i want to become
in the widening circles expanding
into a more expansive complete realized version of myself
setting intention aspiration reconnecting with the aspiration with
every breath
reconnecting reaffirming
our aspiration intention with each breath
what is your aspiration the way you like to grow
in widening circles
in wisdom love equanimity
generosity connecting with each breath
with these widening circles
i'll read the poem one more time and let it wash over you
i live my life in widening circles
that reach out across the world
i may not ever complete the last one
but i give
myself to it
and for the last minute of this practice period
reconnecting with our aspiration our intention for our life
these widening circles
and seeing ourselves
and image just for a moment as if a visitation
from the future from a future version of ourselves
who has traveled was grown lived
in these widening circles of heart and mind
looking at us this image of us aspiring us inviting us come come yes you can
yes trust trust
trust that you can
you have all that you need in this very life to wake up
and perfection of love and wisdom
trust trust
you can do this
[Music]
so
thank you for your practice we rarely if ever do
[Music] a meditation a practice on connecting with our intention
with our aspiration and yet it's such an important practice
to engage in to reconnect who do i want to be
how do i want to show up and give our lives to it give our lives to these widening circles
of development [Music]
and to have an image of the possibility of an invitation from the future if
but yes it is possible for us
so i'd love to invite you if you wish sharing any reflections that
came up for you [Music] what you discovered when you notice any
questions complaints it's all welcome
please raise your zoomed hand you would
or you can type it in chat if you type it to me in person i won't say your name if it's public i
will say your name yes dawn please i am i just want to say thank you so
much that hit me wow oh really well and i love the
sort of the try to describe it but it's the exploitation at the end to trust
and you can do this thank you thank you don
yes you can do this you can do this
the floor is open
neil please so first of all that was quite lovely um
at some point you know i found myself worrying that i was gonna you know not
be able to achieve my desires you know i found you know perhaps you know another way to say it was i
felt overwhelmed by the you know the magnitude of what i was wishing for
you know and i seem to be able to kind of back away from it but i wonder if you have any you know tricks or tips or something
yeah yeah thank you for that i really appreciate you bringing that question in that aspect of of
overwhelm and um and how to work with that and not to
problematize that yes with any with many of the other
practices that we've talked about in order for the practice to find its
stride sometimes it goes too far in one direction and too far in one other direction right
and what you're describing is is it going in the direction though oh
my goodness i want i want this is extraordinary and and not the the other direction
could be many different things for example one not connecting with one's aspiration like oh i can do it
also so there are many different places so so no problem just notice that that's
where you are as you have noticed i'm saying this more generally not just for you neil but notice you know this is what's
happening okay so what can be the healthy relationship and the healthy relationship can be ah
oh this is beautiful neil self oh this is beautiful all these beautiful aspirations so let
the heart be buoyed and the same way that say you know if for example what i'm holding
here are the aspirations if i were holding them really tight like ouch right instead of oh aspiring to so
notice that contraction in your heart in your body notice it physically when there's like i
want i want which can lead to the overwhelm but what if you hold it lightly as oh
that is beautiful as a sense of like brightness of heart beautiful what gorgeous aspirations what
beautiful aspirations what sacred aspirations to be lifted up by them instead of being
weighed down by them which is kind of what you were describing kind of weigh weight down with the overwhelm of it
thank you thank you neil thanks so much for bringing that in
and jerry asks why are we filled with self-doubt regarding aspirations
yeah um [Music] yeah good question
i think what the what you're bringing up i think it would be a couple of ways i would invite working
with that one is actually maybe doing it as an inquiry if there are doubts ah doubt interesting
what's let me get to know you what instead of pushing it away but really
getting to know what is the doubt what's underneath it getting to know the doubt so
investigation dhamma victoria which is the second factor of awakening so having curiosity about the doubt
let me get to know you without believing it but having curiosity about it and then
another is to just call it it's doubt it's just doubt it's just doubt not
believing it so calling it out so so as you're asked why are we felt so
an investigation might actually reveal itself and you know doubt is
just a voice in our heads right so what i was inviting you at the end was
just a different way of seeing just shifting and as human beings we really
underestimate the power we have to see things differently so
the voice of doubt comes up habitually for whatever reasons in our past history
conditioning doubt oh can i really do this i can't do this then bill we believe it
so okay we'll say well thank you don't really appreciate your opinion but then actually what if i bring up i
can do this yes yes in this very life yes trust
i am a human being just like all the other human beings who woke up just like the bunda
we share 99.99 of our dna i'm not so different he was a human being i'm a human being
i can expand and grow in love and compassion in way of course
yes i can so just bring that thought up you have choice and see what that feels like experiment
with with um with wholesome wholesome thoughts
um so just a couple of thoughts there so i'd like to invite us to
to share our our beings are the way we show up however you're
showing up with our aspirations um and to aspire
each other to inspire each other in small groups and it's so beautiful to uh
share to be in this way to to to witness other people and to be
witnessed with our aspirations with our doubts and to be held with compassion and with
trust that others can have in us yes you can yes you can see what that can feel like
in a small community of trusting each other supporting each other
in in committing and committing to your aspiration it's just a commitment it's just a
giving ourselves it's a dedication it's a dedication so
that's the invitation and let's start with 30 seconds of silent meta for each other holding each
other with care silently in small groups and then you can share as much or as little as you
wish so let's set up the small groups and
let's see here okay about to open them here we go
so we have um a few minutes left for reflections what
what came up what did you discover please
flourish the floor is yours
i see lots of smiles
what was it like
this particular day or evening this conversation
sarah please it was just nice connecting with other people
even though i i was really tired i almost left before we broke out into groups but i'm
glad i didn't yay so nice so nice right
it's energizing just lovely to come yeah yeah thanks for sharing that sarah
beautiful yeah yeah don yeah thanks for your reflection enjoy
time he would meet me trend nicholas sweet any other reflections what was it like
to to share to witness or be witnessed in your
aspirations and this this theme for tonight anything that was interesting
noteworthy i'd love to hear your wisdom even
even though even if you may doubt that it's wisdom but we'd love to hear it yes person on
the phone please
um it's michael and i really enjoy hearing the wisdom of
my sangha zoom mates and and also i must say
not to future think but i'm pretty excited because i think we're doing a metro retreat next week deep house
great thank you michael always good to hear from you yes
we are doing a meta retreat um uh well it's actually wisdom retreat
it's actually wisdom retreat come to say yes diana and i are teaching a wisdom retreat which of course
there will be meta infused in it but yeah and and i won't be here on friday
because this week you know my head is spinning i'm teaching a lot this period so the yes starting
tomorrow i teach a retreat at spirit rock um on practical emptiness
the womb of love and compassion i believe is the title so i will not see
you on friday but i will be back on monday and
well any of you are sitting there retreat i think there are some of you i'll see you i'll see
you tomorrow so so thank you all thank you all for your practice
for showing up supporting yourself and others in the sangha and practicing
for all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all
beings be free as we practice in widening circles of aspiration
thank you all