thank you for being here it's delightful for me to be able to come here to imc and
sit and practice and be able to teach so it's wonderful
and um one of the kind of north stars the guide
orient for this orientation of mindfulness practice is uh
the possibility of clarity of clearly knowing what's
happening in the present moment and it takes a while maybe for new practitioners to learn this clear
knowing but um and have a sense of what that means and i get a feel for it a sense kind of a
a inner kind of recognition of what clear recognition is clear knowing
and to appreciate it and to appreciate clear knowing
and then maybe it's easier to come into this quiet or non-discursive
uh meditative mode of being where we're not chasing for states of mind
we're not trying to make ourselves concentrated particularly the concentration definitely is a good
thing to happen but we're relying first and foremost on our ability to clearly know
and not to chase after clear knowing but to clearly know what is obvious
so it's not like a lot of work to know but then appreciate what that clarity is like
and even if we are unclear the mind is tired and fuzzy um and perhaps
it's good enough just to clearly know that and to appreciate something about this
clear simple simple knowing that's possible
so to assume a meditation posture
that the posture itself encourages a little
bit of embodied alertness
embodied attentiveness
and to take a few long slow deep breaths
and those breaths can be easy relaxed
leisurely just a leisurely longer breath than usual take your time doing it but don't
make yourself winded or strained in doing it
three quarters full and a long leisurely exhale
and in this long exhale to settle in and relax your body
and then letting your breathing return to normal in the core practice of mindfulness we
don't do any special breathing anymore it's just a kind of a warm-up
but part of this settling in then with the normal breathing can be continuing to relax the body
as you exhale to soften and relax around the face
to soften and relax the shoulders
to soften and relax
the belly
and then to just settle into the simplicity of the body breathing
and in doing so
see if you can know something about the breathing
with clarity clear recognition it can be as simple as clearly knowing
that you are inhaling
clearly recognizing that the exhale
clearly knowing the sensations that appear as you breathe in
and knowing the sensations that appear when you exhale
and if you're practicing this clear knowing just simple knowing
see if you can adjust it so there's no strain
there's no reaching to try to attain something or get something or
avoid anything
if your mind gets involved in thinking step back and clearly know that that's
the case where the knowing is not further thinking
but rather a kind of quieting calming
awareness but clearly knows
this is thinking
and then begin again with the breathing
whenever you return to your breathing notice if you return to an inhale
or an exhale
so
is there available to you a kind of clear knowing of the moment of
what is obvious that the clear knowing itself feels
peaceful quiet calm
at ease with what is known words simply knowing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to take a moment or two to clearly recognize
where you're sitting the location here in your
seat and that there's a you can be grounded in your place
rooted here in clearly recognizing and
not drifting off in thought to other places other times but to be here
now
but then to open your attention to the whole world around you
while you stay rooted while you stay embodied here
and take in that across the world
locally and far away there there are fires and smoke
hurricanes and rain
heat and drought
there's illness of all kinds
coved and people and lock down
people struggling with illness
war and poverty and hunger
to sit grounded here
losing the embodiment and groundedness in here
not getting swept up in the conditions of the world
but in being grounded to have a greater capacity to witness it
to be present for it all
and through this practice that we do may we find
the ability to balance being grounded and centered in the present moment here with us
here we can find our inner freedom
and
be mindful of what's happening in the world around us so that we can live for the care of the
world that our ability to
support the welfare of others is also part of our
how we can live our life may it be that this meditation practice
we do together supports us
to be more capable in living for the welfare and happiness of others
and for ourselves may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
so good day to everyone
and i just finished yesterday teaching a week-long retreat
on through zoom it was online retreat
lovely to teach this with lovely to be part of it
and the theme of the retreat was the topic of clear comprehension
or clear recognition and so i'd like to kind of
follow continue with that theme since it's kind of fresh on my mind and on my heart
and it's an integral part of mindfulness practice in fact sometimes the teachings
of the buddha the word for mindfulness sati
and the word for clear comprehension clear recognition
some pajama are treated as a compound sati sampajana
and you know they're kind of maybe all part of the same they're closely and
intimately connected to each other our capacity to be mindful
gives us or awakens or makes room for our capacity than to know what's happening
and this ability to really know not in some complicated way but to
really recognize what this is what's happening this is what is is a kind of superpower
it's that valuable it's that significant once we can stop and clearly rest we
have to stop but once we clearly recognize something that makes room for it to register for
all kinds of other understandings to follow there's less confusion
sometimes there can be a clear kind of relaxation oh now i understand what's happening
oh it's like that uh the clear recognition of something
that allows for sometimes the next step to occur the next thing to happen but if we're fuzzy if
we're not really clear what's there then we can't build on that or can't grow from that or can't let it somehow
register or be felt or be processed in some deep way and the clearer we can know what we're
feeling what's happening with us what the impact has been on world events for us
all kinds of ways that the clear recognition clear knowing makes room
for the heart to move on and open up and process in some way
and it's a great support for mindfulness practice and in fact
in the teachings of the buddha the primary function of clear recognition is in the teaching in the practice of
mindfulness and to practice clear recognition of of all aspects of our life as we go
through it so that we stay close to
always kind of being cognizant always being conscious of what we're doing as we doing it
so rather than buddhist teaching so if you're walking clearly know
that you're walking if you're standing clearly know you're standing and sitting down clearly know you're
standing and it's so simplistic this little instruction that it can seem like you know i'm more
sophisticated than that i don't have to kind of slow down for anything just to recognize that i'm standing or sitting
but uh to remain close enough in with awareness to really track and be conscious of
what you're doing what you're doing as you in your body also what you're doing in
your speech or what you're doing just before you speak be so you're conscious of what's coming
you start living a mindful life but you also start living a life where
you're more close to the place where you make choice about what to say what to do
and to stay that kind of close in and clearly recognize and be conscious live a conscious life
is a clearly important part of buddhist spirituality
now as the buddhist tradition developed over the centuries they developed
an expansion of this idea of sampajana clearly recognizing clearly knowing
that's uh where they listed four different things you can clearly know
and and this i think of this is this is now a little bit stepping away
from the clearly knowing breathing or clearly knowing standing or walking or clearly knowing how we're feeling in the
moment it's a but it's a clear knowing of something that's definitely part of
human life but it's a little bit more higher order a little bit more a little bit more involved than the
simple moment moment experience that sometimes happens in mindfulness meditation
so these four kinds of clear things to clearly know something we're able to clearly know and
and clearly knowing it we get so much benefit and this is where it becomes kind of a superpower
so the first one is [Music] clearly knowing the purpose of what
we're doing clearly knowing the suitability
what's suitable to fulfill that purpose clearly knowing
uh how we get nourished from that it's called the the pasture
the place where the cows go and eat go chara how do we clearly know how we get
nourished by engaging in the purpose what we're doing
and then uh the fourth one is clear comprehension of non-delusion clear comprehension how to go forward
without the overlay of projections and bias and fantasies and stories
that make the whole thing so much more complicated so to uh and in many cities
and these can be understood these four or they can be practiced as uh in the form of questions
what's the purpose of what you're doing right now what's the purpose of why you're going
to say what you're going to say to ask and to ask that question repeatedly
is in all kinds of circumstances uh begins uh bringing clarity to what
drives us what motivates us also gives us an opportunity to adjust
the purpose that uh we might have a you know a um
a simple answer right away now sometimes uh people who've been
practicing some forms of buddhism like to you ask them what's the purpose
and they don't like to get into a complicated purpose they're just like oh you know why are you you know what purpose are
you going for a walk and um you know like today i went for a walk this morning
and someone could have stopped me said why are you going for a walk and i could have said i'm walking just
to walk but that wasn't actually the case i had another purpose in mind for the walk the
purpose was to begin thinking about this dharma talk to give today
and so the purpose was thinking and then for about the talk and so then what is a suitable way to walk if that
was what's in mind well i when i think about my dharma talks i tend to walk a little bit slower
than i would if i'm not doing something like that so i knew that i was you know a slower pace
and it was also not to spend a lot of time looking around and
and noticing a lot about the different things in my neighborhood but to kind of walk and be attentive but
allow myself to kind of stay close to the kind of uh flow of thoughts about different ideas
about this case clear comprehension and how to do it in a way that is
nourishing and so if i'm worried about the talk
or if i'm so pulled into the world of the thought and the ideas then i'm not nourished by it but if i take my time
walk slow i did walk slowly and stay connected to my body as i walked in my
to my kind of inner experience as i walked in as i thought about it
then there's a way in which that thinking uh kind of uh was in harmony with
something within and it was actually very pleasant and enjoyable to uh to do this
and then um i wasn't deluded about what i was doing i was very consciously aware of what i
was doing i had chosen what i was going to do and i was in i was engaged in that
choice and and it felt kind of uh it was like it was a clarity and simplicity to
what i was doing that i felt it also was kind of nourishing and satisfying
so that's going through so so this these four kinds of clear comprehension can be used in all kinds of
circumstances in life and and sometimes we do something for one
purpose and and if we reflect what's the purpose of doing it we realized that actually
there's a higher purpose we could do this for if i realize it's time for me to
cook for my family so the purpose is to cook for my family well that's nice but if i reflect and or
ask myself the question for what purpose are you cooking then i could say well i'm cooking for my
family but i'd like to offer offer food to my family that's nourishing for mind and body i'd like to
be able to offer it with love and then i orient myself to the cooking in a different way than if just to get
the cooking over with so i can go on to other things so um
and to live a purposeful life is actually one of the orientations for doing buddhist practice
in buddhism and for doing buddhist practice there's many purposes for why people do it and
but it helps have a clarity of what that purpose is if we're vague about doing buddhist
practice if we're doing because we have a general idea it's a good idea
we might still do it and might still benefit from it but there isn't such clarity
about how we engage how to do it in a way that supports the purpose
there isn't a clarity to understanding the purpose and then prioritizing that with other purposes
that we have there are many good things to do in the world but it's hard to do all of them in
fact to spread ourselves itself thin we don't do anything really well and so for example in the case of
buddhist practice if this is a high enough priority in a person's life and they know that
then then they can easily hopefully organize their priorities in terms of
what they mostly engage in something for some people buddhist practice is the dharma life is the most
central thing in their life and so then uh it makes sense if it's that
central to really give yourself over to it to give time for it
and not spend a lot of other time doing other things and so you never get to the practice itself
so uh this is not a requirement to do this it's not like meant to be in
an obligation but um to ask ourselves the question what is the purpose
that i want to live my life for what's the intention what was the organizing principle i have
if there's clarity around that then we can put ourselves behind it
but then how do we put ourselves behind it how do we engage in the purpose we do and for that
uh it's good to reflect on to contemplate suitability
so clear comprehension of what's suitable so it could be that
your dedication is to meditate every morning for an hour but maybe you have new kids at home
and uh simply it's not possible to do that and you keep trying to do it and it just becomes frustrating and
present resentmaking to do that so this idea of of that the purpose of living a buddhist
life means you have to meditate for an hour every day when the circumstance doesn't allow for it easily
means it's not suitable to do it that way maybe what's suitable is to engage in the domestic life of
caring for kids by bringing in mindfulness to that or bring in
generosity care compassion to it to really infuse the activities you have to do
with the practice rather than having the practice be something separate
or it might be that the way to practice
what is suitable for this body and mind some people some of us have physical conditions health issues or something
that maybe we have to adjust to how we practice sometimes we have had a difficult life
and the difficult emotions that persist from that means that what's suitable to do
mindfulness is to do it gently very gently with maybe a lot of
self-compassion someone else who has a mind that drifts off into fantasy really easily and spend
an ordinary amount of time developing the habit of fantasy they don't need gentleness maybe and
compassion maybe they need is a certain definitiveness okay now i'm going to practice and for them maybe practicing
definitively every hour you know for an hour every day is really what they need in order to really begin breaking the
habit of always being in fantasy so these are simple examples but the idea that to take stock take of our
conditions and to begin appreciating what supports me what's a helpful way for me
and in this way we become our own teacher and really we need to become our
own teacher that's the direction we're going in this practice and having a clear sense of purpose is
part of this task and then having this question of what is suitable and what's suitable given the conditions
around me if um you know again if a neighbor has need maybe it's not
really suitable to practice freedom and compassion and presence by sitting in meditation
ignoring the neighbor it probably might do actually be more undermining a practice to hold
something at bay like that just so i can take care of my own practice maybe as a practice is supported more by
letting go of my practice and caring for the neighbor
so what is suitable here what is the question and then uh the next thing is to
consider uh where do i get nourished from this where where's the pasture to
and the buddha was very clear he always had an answer for this and this maybe is not a little bit surprised for some of you
the answer is in the four foundations of mindfulness the answers found in being mindful
of our embodied experience being mindful of the feeling tones the
feelings of experience being mindful of
of the mind states we have the feelings and the attitudes we have and being mindful of the inner mental
process that are operating in our relationship to our experience and
and what this does is that it brings our attention close in
this is where the idea of being grounded and rooted here in our direct experience and realizing here is where we get
nourished sometimes we want other people to make us happy other people to provide us with
what we need other situations experiences and they certainly can be supportive and
helpful and wonderful sometimes but to depend on the external world
to depend on certain kind of uh stimuli uh alcohol drugs
uh food in order to kind of feel uh spiritually nourished is kind of a dead end
and the remarkable thing is that um the very it's not this remarkable thing
that if we practice mindfulness to stay close into our experience
our mindful experience is generative of a sense of nourishment a sense of
well-being that's where we find our centeredness our peace or happiness even
and and so the very system that gets nourished is a system that
generates the nourishment and this is a remarkable kind of
kind of system where through mindfulness
this very psychophysical system that we are part of generates the sense of well-being that
nourishes the system itself so it's self-generating in a certain way
as opposed to again needing something outside so the clear comprehension of the
nourishment of the pasture in the buddhist teaching is to stay close to mindfulness stay grounded here
don't lose yourself stay conscious of your lived experience
as you go about doing what you're doing so you can stay so then you can one thing you can notice when you get
stressed when you get exhausted when you get tired and then you don't just push keep
pushing yourself that way but you also uh you can recognize
that not only by avoiding stress but by being relaxed with what you do
there's a deeper inner well-being that can come as well
and then the clear recognition of non-delusion some people think it's a little hard to recognize delusion and non-delusion
but when we stay close to the four foundations of mindfulness when we stay close to our experience in our some
degree of calm or subtleness then the mindfulness is strong
we can watch the arising of thoughts and most illusions
are ideas or thoughts that we that are created by the mind
and if we stay close enough to watch thoughts arise watch ideas and projections arise
then we can start seeing oh it's not inherent in the situation that i'm that this is how it is this is just the way
i'm seeing it it's the way i'm interpreting it and sometimes with that ability we can
see it clearly there's a fantasy clearly i'm deluded here i've had the
same idea you know a thousand times and it's never proved to be true
and and so maybe i should stop thinking thinking it
but to watch thoughts arise and have the mindfulness to see it
the mo it's the watching the mindfulness itself which is the non-delusion
and to begin appreciating that there is a place of clarity of witnessing
that in and of itself sees clearly and in that clarity
it's not uh prior to the filters through which we see
and that's where non-delusion is and that's a place that's very close to non-clinging
non-reactivity so to to learn this place of non-delusion
and have that support us and it's very closely related to this idea of that this whole
enterprise begins with of clear recognition clear knowing
clear knowing has a lot to do with clarity simplicity not all these layers and veils
of ideas and interpretation and to learn this idea to relax and soften and quiet
and to see the simplicity of the moment allows us
then to have clear comprehension so some of this clear comprehension is
very simple these four different categories and some of it
comes from a contemplative life a life of being reflective and thoughtful
and in buddhist life buddhist spirituality is not just a life of
mindful attention to the moment what's going on it's also a life where we spend time
quality time thinking about our life reflecting about our life reflecting about purpose
of particular things we do reflecting on the purpose of our life itself
why we do you know what what what do we want to dedicate our life to what's most important for us today this week this year this lifetime
to spend time staying close and reflective in a calm relaxed contemplative
kind of spirit kind of spiritual kind of way to reflect about suitability what's the
most useful way to accomplish this purpose given the causes and conditions around
me how do i approach this how do i do this so i'm nourished by it
when we're nourished by it then we're able also to support other people better
we actually have more resources within to live for the benefit and welfare of others if
we are nourished and then now to practice non-delusion
where is the delusion where is the non-delusion where the projections where are the agendas where the expectations
what are the associations i ever bring with me from the past that maybe cloud the water
to really kind of look and see what's happening here so a contempt a life of contemplative
reflection about and these are four things that are useful to contemplate
and one of the things you could do is he you know you can journal about it you can go for walks and think about these
things figure out where you can have quality time and for some people this quality
reflection can happen in conversation with friends
talking about purpose exploring it discussing it
and you know suitability and all this and it is a kind of superpower because once you're clear about purpose
and you really have you know this is really what you want to do then
you can organize other things organize your life yourself okay this is what i'm going to do i'm going to do it
wholeheartedly even if it's just cooking a meal if that's the purpose
and you the purpose is to do it you know do it in a suitable supportive way
to do it in a way that's nourishing maybe you just want to give yourself over to just cooking when you're cooking
and for the purpose that you have or maybe it's for what's really important for how your life energy what
you want to do with your life to make it a priority to really know what that is
and get behind it is a superpower so much can be done
behind a clear sense of purpose so thank you
very much and and may you this next week reflect little
bit on the value of clear comprehension