okay great so hello and welcome warm
welcome so for this edition of happy
hour um I'd like to invite us to explore meta loving kindness love
friendliness so many different nuances of of this quality of the heart um um to
explore this from a selfless
perspective so I just finished teaching a retreat on emptiness and part of that
was exploring um the self how self is the reference
point of everything in our lives and in our thoughts and in our senses and what
if we notice that and what if we play around with shifting perspectives and actually I see many of
you who are on Retreat so this will be a continuation of our exploration on the
retreat and for those who weren't on the retreat no problem whatever you need
will be shared with you so um coming into it with beginner's mind so
so you know let's just get into practice I won't say much more let's just explore
with with an open mind with beginner's mind and see what arises so so like to
invite you to get into your meditation posture whatever that might be if you need to shift and move this body
if you need to lie down if you need to set up sit up
straighter see what your body needs shift move to a
cushion and first and foremost as always we are arrive and land with the
body with the breath to
stabilize the attention
stabilized calm the
mind to arrive with sense of seclusion
quiet silence
internally turning our gaze
Inward and opening to perceptions of the body
sitting [Music] Sensations as the
feet connected to the Earth touching the
floor maybe the legs the underside of the
legs contact points feeling the contact arriving arriving really connecting with
the Earth with each
breath relax relxing relaxing softening giving the weight of the
legs feed to the
Earth similarly for the sit bones
and the abdomen lower abdomen relaxing softening
and opening expanding
awareness relaxed awareness to include not just the lower body but the upper
body
the [Music] trunk the chest neck and
shoulders ah the arms the hands relaxing
softening and all the muscles of the
face the entire body receiving the
breath the entire body being breathed
no need for a breather or a doer breathing happens on its own thank you
very much
allowing your awareness to be expansive to know to know the
breath sensations of breath in the
body without the need for a control to but perceived
received in itself in the abdomen in the feet in the
chest sensed in and of
themselves
e
e e
and if you notice thoughts [Music] arising as they will
arise notice the self
reference the self- referential frame of
reference noticing it kindly gently without any
judgment with curiosity and openness oh interesting look at that
with kindness as if you're looking at a friend's [Music]
thoughts and gently asking wondering if the frame of reference of the self could
be relaxed jiggled
released as if letting go of helium balloons they can just float be on their own without you needing to hold on to
them as me or mine say what happens be
curious and then always coming back the breath in the
body being sensed as the anchor calming and
settling
e
e e
and notice if this inquiry curiosity about letting
go of the self- reference creates more ease more
space
e
e e
can the sensations in the body for example if there's any fatigue or or
aches can they be [Music] felt and and of
themselves as if awareness wasn't localized was spread in the body itself
not localizing the control tower of the head
could even a slight loosening of identification bring more
ease be curious don't push it
though
e
e e
and what if this loosening even for a moment this
Letting [Music] Go the self frame of reference When the
Thought comes up maybe judgmental thoughts self
judgmental
thoughts letting go of the frame of reference you you you me me
me just for a moment letting the thought float or if or if it's a sensation or
ache in the body just letting it float and be that letting
go that moment of loosening releasing
see if you can open up perhaps explore on your own
that moment of releasing can open up to
vast vastness of Love of
care of
compassion as an entry point
again you can start with a thought maybe
a thought that has some clinging some Dua some pain challenge in it or
something in the body pain and ache sensation notice the frame of reference
of the eye me my see if it's
[Music] possible for this thought or sensation to just be as it is
floating letting go of the self as the eye as the frame of reference my me I am
this I am that and in that moment of release see if there's an opening
up into ease goodness
care love compassion however it might show up for
you
experiment e
if the thought comes up I'm not getting this this isn't working use that see if
you can jiggle the frame of reference of that I'm not getting this this isn't
working for me release the
eye relax into what opens up the
spaciousness e
relaxing into opening up
to space of Goodwill
as if you're Landing as if Landing
resting the mind the
body relaxing into spaciousness of goodwi
for
e
e e
when the eye is released the heart the mind the Mind
heart can land into spacious
spaciousness of openness of goodwi and
ease can the self reference be released for even a split
second regarding a particular sensation or thought be
curious e
and for the last moments of this period of
practice thoughts are coming up self- referential thoughts about this
perod of practice I was [Music]
distracted I was sleepy I was uncomfortable I didn't get it I I I
notice the self judgment if any self reference of the
eye and see if the statements the self reference can be
loosened thought can be just floating safe that opens up releases something
into spaciousness and the opposite of self judgment which is meta
[Music]
thank you thank you for your practice so with the invitations
today I admit for this session they might they may have been a little more
on the subtle side needing little more settling of the Mind
stability of the Mind more quiet of the Mind quiet in the mind for an opening
for this exploration um to to give
fruit so I'd love to hear your Reflections if even for a split second
this letting go of the frame of reference of the self opened up for you
there was an aha and then opening up to a space that was
more spacious more easy more filled with
meta and friendliness if if that were the case
for you even for a split second would love to hear from you if you would be so kind to share Don
please thank you so much Nikki um it was um
it was challenging practice and uh yeah subtle and for me and maybe for others
but for me I tried to of just change like physically change my point of
reference and and sort of look at myself maybe from the perspective of a friend
of mine and or somebody else and and to sort of observe sort of the pain or the
sort of the thoughts or whatever is going on and it sort of whatever was inside me
was sort of floating up the pain and whatever and was sort of this self-contained thing that people could
see anyway that image was helpful and um yeah that's all yeah
okay thank you Don I really appreciate how you're explaining that's that's a beautiful way to explore the shifting of
perspective wonderful this is is lovely um great that's one way to try this
shifting of perspective as you were saying like wow what if what if Consciousness wasn't localized here it
was from the perspective of my friend outside or compassionate being and then you and then you said it was helpful is
it okay to say a couple more words how what was the nature of it being helpful what happened yeah so um I uh I often
have a lot of doubt and um about about many things in during meditation I have
doubt about hey am I doing this right and uh um and and I get a like a tension
and it's like this it's like right around my belly button this s like this
and and it's just like anyway that was released a little bit and it U it sort
of floated up um yeah nice nice so what I'm hearing is
that it was the sense of Doubt am I doing this right which is Habitual self-doubt and and this shifting in
perspective it there was a release it it released both physically and the doubt
itself there was just a release into more ease into what I would call more
freedom yeah exactly lovely beautiful
yay thank you for sharing it this is exact what I was pointing to what I was
pointing to and which is exactly that shift of reference it's like oh something releases physically as well as
in the mind to more ease into more spaciousness and what I would invite you
is notice if in that ease there is more ah there's more kindness there's more
love um if you notice that or or or next time to to to check it out
yeah thank you yeah thank you Don um VI violet
please hey um I had a few interesting experiences and a question um I had this
moment at some point your invitation was something like along the lines of like your body
doesn't need you to breathe like breathing is going to happen and it felt
like like all of a sudden my sort of conscious self was who like it's like
they were like a CEO who thought they were in charge of the show and then all of a sudden it was like being at like a boardroom table looking at like all the
people who were actually doing the work for you the whole time it's like I thought I was in charge of everything
and then all of a sudden I was like oh my foot like my foot does work without me like I don't it's doing its own thing
and that's and it's what I realized recently if I've know noticed like when
I'm when I have awareness of like parts of my body it's not actually awareness
through the sensation I actually even like when I'm sitting it's like I'm looking at it from where my eyes are
like my knee I'm looking at it from where my eyes are I'm not actually like going through my body to the sensation
of the knee um and that's something I've been and
it's hard when I do walking meditation now I try and like I like wear like a really big scarf so I like can't see my
legs at all so that way I'm not like looking at them I'm like feeling them so the question I have is um I have a lot
of back pain and what was helpful with this was like taking the self out in
terms of like sensation sensation like these are like Sensations without like a
me that they're like damaging or like it's not like they're like hurting me um this isn't like an injustice to me
that I'm feeling this pain but then I've also been using a lot of like self-compassion and equinity to help
manage the pain and then at the end when it got really strong I tried to shift to that but then that felt like they were
not aligning like the experiencing the back through like no self and then like
trying to do self-compassion like I couldn't they didn't seem compatible so I was wondering about that yeah
excellent thank you violet really appreciate your observations and
insights and the question too um beautiful so couple of things one is
about what you shared about oh the CEO that notices oh there are other people in the room that are doing the work
so I trust you might have heard of this teaching of anata not self that self is
not what we take it to be and there are ways that we can have insight into we this self self is a little actually
different from this uh standard way we take it and there's so many different ways to have insight into this nature
of this not self or self being different and what you just described is one way
so beautiful this is just this is this can be a very powerful way of seeing that can continue to open up for you so
continue to sit with it let it let it flourish including way you're talking
about with the back pain oh Sensations it's just Sensations being sensed um
unpleasant of feeling tone is being sensient of itself which can be very
powerful again along the lines of an not self um and then when you try to bring
in self-compassion it's like wait a minute these frames of reference AR quite working exactly so the way with
the this Paradigm self-compassion can work is that actually
compassion it's it's what I was leading in the meditation into that that freedom
this different shift and perspective actually has love and compassion in it
there's no giving of it to ourselves so I invite this for you to kind of like
sit it sit with and it may not be obvious right now but but it's like it's
in in the awareness of this sensation itself there is there can be a sense of
care and love in it without the reference of self it's a different way
of practicing does that kind of make sense a little bit so the awareness
itself is the meta in compassion yes it's in there it's infused it's
infused awareness infused with meta yes
both yeah and yep yep no self-
needed thank you thank you Violet lovely Nicholas
please um I've been playfully exploring that
when thinking arises that contraction of oh you shouldn't be there why are you
there why is that thought there why am I thinking those there it's a very fast contraction and your invitation um
something playful came up which is meeting that contraction with the question says
who who says you shouldn't be there um and
it it's fun it's fun it's a nice little space there in that
question nice so what I'm hearing is is with the contraction of oh you shouldn't
be thinking then it's kind of like oh who says who is the judgmental mind like
who is this it's like kind of questioning this frame of reference like ah it's bringing some humor some
gentleness and oh that that that question for you releases the frame of
reference a little bit and brings more freedom and ease is that what I'm hearing you yeah
exactly lovely and and in that there is compassion there is love because when
self judgment drops away there in that ease there is there's more meta in
inherently even if we don't call it out so I want to point that out to you to kind of notice that the next time lovely
I'm I'm loving Nicholas you sharing this as well as other sharing their ways like da sharing the physical you know the way
um he found the shifting of the perspective so each of you finding your own way working with this lovely so the
time has come for us to to um practice in sa such an important way to practice
in small groups and share our Reflections share of ourselves share our insights and share our confusion
whatever it might be and benefit from the wisdom of Sana and and and be held
witness and and give and receive because we don't wake up we on our own and
Things become even more clarified in in this friendly way that we come together
so I will create the breakout rooms and the invitation is let's start with 30 seconds of Silent meta for each other
just 30 seconds of holding your people who are in your room just with care with
eyes of friendliness and then um you can share anything you like um as little or
as much as you wish about your practice and I'm going to open the rooms now here
we go okay welcome back everyone it's good to
see you and I see some smiling faces some Smiles on your faces so we have a
couple minutes for any Reflections um that came up what you noticed
um in your practice with Sana please especially if you haven't spoken yet or
recently invite you to speak from your own experience please don't be shy
hi can type in chat or raise your
hand yes Erica please and then
Neil I can just share a quick thing I shared this in my group as well um but
as we were meditating this group walked by and you could hear them laughing and
um you know usually when I hear people laughing you know I think like oh their Joy that's like distinct from my joy and
maybe I feel a little left out or I feel like oh I'm why is the joy why don't I
ever have joy or whatever you know um but because of the invitations in this
um meditation I could like feel their Joy kind of like what Don was saying it
was like a kind of loose particles of joy you know that were not theirs but
were just available and I felt like Oh I like that Joy is like available to me
and like participating in that joy that was a nice that was really
nice thank you for sharing that I wow I feel Goosebumps as you share that it
just this is the what beautiful practice the the the the power of this um you
know when the self is in there my joy your joy oh it's Joy there there's joy
and and the Heart the mind the the heart mind the chit awareness Consciousness
can participate can instead of this self- reference thank you Erica that's lovely
beautiful yay makes makes me happy gives me joy Neil
please so it's more than a 30 second answer I fear um
you know I find myself thinking a lot about Free Will and self-determinism and
such and you know the more I think about Lack of self and things are based on
causes and conditions you know the more I feel you
know yeah I don't know like like yeah you know yet I yet I still find myself
motivated to do things yeah you know and I'm I'm kind of stuck there I don't know
yeah yeah yeah and I'm going to give a 30 second answer to be continued so so
the idea here is is not that there is no self that's not the teaching at all and
in fact now Garian is said if you take the emptiness teachings if you take them from the wrong end it's like taking a
poisonous steak if you a PO poisonous snake if you grab it on the wrong end so
it leads to nihilism and confusion so that that's where we'll we'll head so
it's not not self that there is no self it's it's more complicated that the self
is there is a self you exist of course you exist and yet it's the it's much
it's much more open much more complicated much more free it's both
it's neither real nor non-real um anyway that's that's getting more than 30
seconds but um what can I say that could be helpful besides that yes there is a
self that the teaching is is not a negation of self um and with the idea of
Free Will um yeah Buddhism has a lot to it kind of obviates the whole Free Will
idea through I mean there's a lot I've thought about this a lot and there's a lot of writing that you can also find on
the web um but the idea is is there is
oh this is going to be so much longer than 30 seconds to be continued Neil to be
continued so let's continue this another time this
is 702 I I do want to bring it to a close I have so much to say about this but we'll give a good D and talk about
this sometime anyway thank you all thank you so much for your questions for your curiosity for your practice for your
heart may all beings be free happy
um joyous including
ourselves thank you for your practice and