hello everyone and i spread my warm wishes best wishes
to all of you in all directions from here and all around the globe so thank you for
being part of this
so um
the topic of this week is delusion and i think it's
helpful to uh keep in mind or consider at least
that delusion uh the way it operates in a conscious way is
through thoughts through the thinking mind we have ideas delusion has
to do with ideas of what's there whether it's verbal ideas or we see
we have imagery or of things some people think more in images than in
thought than in words and um and so the
um uh one of the you know
we'll talk more later about how to practice with delusion but for now i'd like to keep it very simple
because simplicity is the is what highlight can help us see
delusion uh when the mind is complicated with lots of thoughts and ideas it's
much harder to see it's kind of like a piece of cloth which is filled with stains it's
hard to see one more stain but if the cloth is stained free then a
single stain stands out so a simple mind sees more clearly
what's going on because we can see when it you know when things arise when things
appear and so in that delusion has its uh
you know connection with thinking i want to offer a very simple practice
around thinking today and that is that as you meditate if
if or when you have thoughts you find you notice
yourself thinking this is an important part of mindfulness to notice we're thinking and
sometimes we use mental note thinking thinking or we just clearly are aware of thinking
and then return to the breathing but today when you notice yourself thinking
gently perhaps lovingly say two words and those two words are
not now just gently not now now is not the time to be involved in
these thinking now is the time for a quieter calmer uh awareness that is not
thought-based so maybe it's a sensation based or sensing based or
or observing based just kind of perceiving more directly not through the medium
of discursive thought not through the medium of conversational thought or analytical
thought or story thought and so when this more
active thinking of discursive thoughts and train of thinking begins
just tell yourself not now not now and then about halfway through
i'll offer two other words we'll switch to something else but uh but just not now
and if you have long long periods of time when you're not really involved in thinking then you don't have to say those words
but when you find yourself oh now i've been thinking i'm swept i'm pulled into that world not now
and kind of like step back step away um and then return to your breathing and
stay with the physical sensations of the body breathing and when the next thinking comes up not
now and if you have to say not now you know every two seconds
you know because thoughts just come keep coming do so gently lovingly so that not now
is a bomb for the mind and heart of the medicine so that the not now
is a calming reassuring offering some degree of
ease of peace of of uh equanimity to what's there so you're not
fighting your thoughts or just not now and that repetition of not now that really that
different relationship to thinking than you normally would have maybe we get pulled into it or you believe it or
react to it maybe something will begin to shift
so taking a upright
posture metaphorically or literally
and gently close your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths and as you exhale
imagine that you're letting your concerns and your thoughts drift away
as you exhale those drift away and you settle in to your body
breathing in breathing out
and then breathing letting your breath return to normal
and for a next four or five exhales continue to relax
open your body wherever it's possible to soften and
relax
and then settling into your breathing
settling into the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
settling into the body's experience of breathing so you don't have to be up in the
control tower watching or controlling
it's almost like awareness is centered in the body
in the body's experience of breathing
and then in a way that seems peaceful
or peacemaking even tell yourself the words not
now see if you can say those words in your
mind quietly quiet calm inner voice
not now
and when you begin thinking gently say those words
there's no not now means this is not a time for those thoughts
they can they can be picked up later not now
without ambition or forcefulness without even expecting
thinking to stop and if thinking continues just gently
say it again and again allowing there to be an openness
a peacefulness in the moment after saying it
a moment of open awareness
and when there's no more thinking where the thinking is not compelling
return to your breathing
you
me
and then
to offer you two other words that you can say instead of not now
you can say the words maybe not
these words can still carry the meaning of not now maybe they can be short for
maybe maybe not now
but also they can be maybe it isn't so maybe it's not true
maybe not so as you find yourself thinking
peacefully say the words maybe not maybe it isn't so
then allow yourself to become free of whatever those thoughts
are
and begin again with your breathing
me
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
take a moment to let go and do nothing
including not even thinking
nothing you have to do or be or [Music]
become just a few moments here of letting yourself rest as deeply as
your psychophysical system can rest at this moment
or maybe just putting to rest the effort to do or to meditate or to be
or to figure anything out
and then to bring your attention to the part of your body
where your good will lives where love or
care compassion
kindness is born
the part of your body that resonates with it or vibrates or
opens in the presence of loving kindness
and putting aside any thoughts that interfere with your basic simple
good will including the thought that it's not here now
and turning your to the your gaze to the world around you
to the people in your lives in your communities across your lands
around the globe
and wishing them well what a wonderful world it would be if
people were happy and peaceful if they weren't motivated by their anger
hostility greed fear
what a wonderful world would be for all of us if
the heart was motivated by its happiness
and so to wish welfare and happiness for all beings
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
and free and may all beings be
free of the delusions that give birth to
fear and greed and hatred
may all beings be free of the delusions that keep them locked into their
limited view of other beings
free of delusions may we all care for each other in this world
may all beings be happy
uh so the topic of today the third talk on
delusion is practicing with delusion and um it can be hard because
sometimes part of the nature of delusion is to not know that we're deluded to not know we the
delusion kind of camouflages itself as truth or as this is the way things are or and so
it can be hard to notice delusion but it's possible to see delusion for it
for it's what it is it's possible to become free of delusion and
it's a really worthwhile goal because so much of the suffering of the
world has some quality of suffering and that and harming how we cause harm in the world
has uh some connection to delusion
so [Music]
so first it's helpful to have some wisdom
that uh is an antidote to delusion and there's many pieces of wisdom that
are useful and um one of them is
there's a i learned this as a sufi story uh the man came to a sufi master with a
ring and said can you inscribe in this ring uh some piece of wisdom that's always
useful for me and um and so
a week later the men came back to get the inscribed ring and it said this too will pass
and so that simple expression this two will pass uh can somehow cut through a certain
delusion of permanence or or expectation that it should be always this way or it will be this way and
it can free up uh one of my favorite little stories about the bringing wisdom is i heard the story is
coming from china and the way that approximately the story is told it can be many little variations
is there was a farmer who was quite old and frail and can barely eke out in
existence on his farm but he had us a son a strong young man who could certainly help a lot
they were still very poor but their young son can do a lot of the work
and uh and they had an old donkey that a weak donkey that somehow was their
main way of plowing and taking care of the farm also and one day the donkey died and the
neighbor said oh this is terrible i'm so sorry you know this is a terrible thing
and uh you're so poor and the old farmer says um we shall see and
then one day the sun goes up into the mountains to collect firewood and he finds a kind of a wild horse up there that's
strong and stallion and and is able to bring it back and the neighbors say oh you're so lucky
and the old man says we shall see and as the son is training the horse he
falls off the horse and breaks his leg and the neighbors say oh no you're so unlucky
and the farmer says we shall see and and then the local king recruits all
the young men to go fight a hopeless war against a neighboring country
and but because the son broke his leg he's not recruited and the neighbors say
oh you're so lucky that your son's not going off to war and the farmer of course says
we shall see and so there's a wisdom to we shall see not to be caught in the
conclusions we can make and and think that this is the way it is so bringing some wisdom and there's many
kinds of wisdom we can bring but wisdom and understanding like that only goes so deep it's a nice
medicine it's a nice counter force to our tendency to delusion but vipassana practice involves a deeper
look at it and i think of vipassana practice in relationship to
delusion is a little bit of a practice for people who are well established in their mindfulness
because and so just developing mindfulness is an antidote to
delusion because as we develop the capacity to recognize moment by moment what's
happening so we can recognize oh this is an emotion i'm feeling sad or happy or angry or
peaceful uh there's there's a freeing moment in that clear recognition
and uh and we're not entangled so much and so all the different beliefs and ideas we have that entangle us
are kind of put down and that's a little protection from the deluse delusive ways in which we're
involved in our emotions and feelings same thing with the thoughts as we learn to recognize we're thinking
just a simple label thinking thinking or remembering or planning
uh that also that clear recognition begins uh freeing us from the automatic way in
which associations beliefs expectations prejudice bias come you know are are
are involved in how we relate to our thoughts the quick ways that we believe it or we're horrified by them or
whatever it might be in the the compelling way we feel like we have to think we you know it's necessary to think
and just thinking oh thinking thinking it's such a peaceful thing to do but it can be so freeing
as we begin finding this freedom and simplicity and strength and mindfulness
then it comes a time when uh we're able to better and better notice
the arising the the beginning of a particular idea
and because we can see it arise we're not kind of just lost in the sea of thoughts we're not just kind of
being swept along in the great currents of many thoughts but we see the birth of a thought that is a
fantastic place where we could um question it where we say is that so
maybe not or let's see or um we can see you know oh that is a
thought it's just a thought it's not necessarily
true it's not necessarily a reality and so for example if you see a person a
stranger and and somehow that stranger reminds you of this really strict elementary school
teacher you had who you were really afraid of and the person looks like the teacher
and so the thought comes up the feeling the emotion comes up and thought comes up that um oh this is a dangerous person
if we're not if we're kind of just going along and not noticing where these thoughts come from and they just suddenly are there
it's easy for the mind to somehow just assume this is true and take it as being a true idea of
what's out there the person is dangerous but if we can notice oh there's a
oh that person is dangerous that thought arises and we see it just as a thought then
it's a powerful moment to both question the thought is it true but also to take a second look
to look again what is really there in front of me who is this person i don't know who this person is
it looks like my my elementary school teacher let me take a good look and in fact the
person you know that i look carefully at the person um the person seems quite friendly
and um and so but it being able to see the rising of it we can question we can see
we can not assign so much authority to every thought and we're more likely to question in a
healthy way what's there as we begin looking at these thoughts
that arise we begin recognizing some of them are regular patterns
of uh of the same kind of thinking and the when when people practice
mindfulness a lot they start seeing patterns of thoughts like their their pattern
is that they always think the worst is going to happen or they always think that people don't
like them or they always think that um they all you know that they should get
what they want it's about all kinds of ideas like that and um when we start seeing patterns
then if we start realizing wait a minute this is just a belief i carry
and to always apply this belief onto all situations it is a kind of delusion it's a it's an
imposition of ideas on something which is not necessarily appropriate
those ideas and so then we can start looking at the pattern say oh there's that's it has
a quality of delusion to always be seeing through that filter
and then we can use our mindfulness to look deeper and see what's underneath that what is
the emotion that's driving that is there loneliness is there insecurity is there fear
is there some kind of delusion of grandeur or wanting to kind of create a sense of self that is a little bit of
a fantasy and it can be some desires we have some thoughts we have uh come from a fantastical way in which
we want to kind of create an idea of who we are that is all good or
we create ideas about ourselves that are critical of ourselves and so once we start seeing the patterns
of thinking and delusion we have we can start dropping down deeper into the emotional level and
the places we that are the sources within for why or how we think this way not by
analyzing it but we feel our way in so practicing mindfulness of thinking
in a deeper and deeper way connects us to the sources underneath where delusion is born and
and this also then gives more freedom and a chance for something to resolve itself
or release in a deeper and deeper way most illusions that we have have their
genesis and some clinging something we're attached to and uh delusions without attachment
generally are not as dangerous as delusions that were very attached to them
so there's a lot of words about how to practice with delusion but the simplest way is uh
is to learn how to be mindful in the present moment and to be able to track this the flow of
present moment experiences we're having so that in that flow of present moment experiences
we see well there's the arising of a feeling sensation now there's a thought
and to have a settled mind that can watch this arising of thinking
and then bring some wisdom to it and maybe one of them is maybe not
maybe it's not this way or we shall see we shall see let's wait let's not come
to some conclusion and so to learn how to have thoughts arise
and not take them as being conclusive is a powerful way of popping the bubble of delusion
because the danger of delusion is often at the authority we give them
and if we don't give them authority it's easier to kind of see them for what they are
so uh practice mindfulness it's such a great thing and and if you feel like practicing
mindfulness is too much work it's really it's not in
essence not really work it's rather um trusting that we can rest and
be present for the the deep capacity we have to be open present and aware of what
is happening in the present without just open and present awareness and we
discover over time that this is the place of non-work in a sense
that everything else is just a lot of work a lot of agitation and stress in the mind
so enjoy your mindfulness develop it
and let it become an intimate part of who you are thank you