okay so we'll go ahead and get started
so welcome to the imc monday night sit
and i hope you're doing well this evening or whatever time of day it is for you
and we'll begin with settling in to the sit so finding a posture
where you can be upright and also relaxed
somewhere where you'll be comfortable for the half hour or so that will be
sitting
and just gently allowing your eyes to close
and bringing the attention inward to the feeling of the body sitting
or if you're lying down or standing whatever posture you're in [Music]
just taking a moment to gently let go of whatever we were doing before coming
here
and allowing the mind to be present
sensing into the body perhaps the contact point where your
seat is on the chair or the cushion
legs or feet are against the floor or maybe you're lying on a surface
or just feeling where the contact is where you're being supported
i'm finding some balance there so sometimes if i'm sitting i'll rock
back and forth slightly just a little bit or forward and back just to find that
central balance point where the body can be upright
if you're lying down it's also possible to tune into the straightness of the spine the balance of
the body against the surface
and perhaps on the next exhale letting go a little bit farther into
that support allowing it to support you
and it can also help to deliberately soften some parts of the body that we often
hold tense perhaps the muscles of the face so
letting the expression on the face be soft
softening the eyes and the eye sockets they tend to get a little tense when
we're looking at a screen
and softening in the throat the neck
feeling into the shoulders
we might let the shoulder blades slide down the back so that the shoulders are dropping
without rounding forward
down through the chest area
feeling the front back and sides of the ribcage
down into the belly area letting that be
round soft
we can let go of any layers of tension [Music]
down into the hip joints and into the thighs
softening the knee and ankle joints
i'm connecting into the feet and the hands
so just inviting ease through the body
when the body has some ease it's actually easier to be mindful
and then perhaps returning to the area of the chest
having a sense of openness or even a slight lift
to the heart area
as if someone were touching our back right between the shoulder blades
gently
this focus of the bodily posture
can actually evoke a slight sense of confidence in the mind
just a reminder that we're doing is
valuable worthwhile effective
can be very supportive for practice to touch into our degree of confidence or trust in this
practice which we all have to some degree since we're doing it
maybe just for a few breaths letting that confidence pervade the body and mind
and then settling back into
the breath or the body your usual object of meditation
noticing if there might be a slight sharpening of the energy in the mind
when we feel our confidence in the practice
to whatever degree
and as we settle a bit more into the meditation
you may begin to notice the quality of the attention in the mind
how is the mindfulness
if there's a bit too much energy in the mind
you may wish to calm it down a bit
focus the mindfulness a bit more
whereas the mind is a little dull
might sharpen up the attention [Music] perhaps through a stronger connection to
the body
noticing what the mind feels like when it has mindfulness present
and it may be that the mind is still quite busy
minds will do as they do but to whatever degree you have a sense
that the mind is a bit more gathered gathered together than it was when you
started you can appreciate that
perhaps there's even a subtle joy
in being present with experience
some ease some joy some peace to whatever degree these are present
appreciating them allowing that to pervade the body
um
[Music]
and as we move into the last five minutes or so of this meditation
you might bring to mind the knowledge that you carry
the benefits of dharma practice or meditation
perhaps even just in the course of this sitting you've been reminded of the value it brings
and that in turn feeds back to the confidence that we began with
so just bringing that knowledge to mind and then letting it fade back and resting again in your
meditation object
letting this understanding resonate in your system
and as we gently approach the end of this sitting
perhaps bringing to mind any wish that you have for
the benefit of others through your practice
do you have some intention that what you do here will benefit
yourself and others and both out in the world
just bringing that to mind
okay so this evening i'm going to start
by tracing backward from the world
into our own mind and i'm doing so in a particular way
so you can start by looking at the world
and we see in many ways something of a lack of wisdom
people making choices that are not necessarily for their own welfare the welfare of others
and the welfare of both there's a text that says
a wise person of great wisdom does not intend for their own affliction for the
affliction of others or for the affliction of both rather when they think they think only
of their own welfare the welfare of others the welfare of both and the welfare of
the whole world but we see that this doesn't always happen
and we might ask well why is that well it it does take a particular
clarity and focus of the mind to be able to see
how we can be of actual benefit how is it that we could act for the welfare
of ourselves and others so we need to have a clear understanding of how things unfold
how to think how do things work and this requires some stability of our mind in order to to do
that but we may not have that and so then why is that you know why
don't we have an ongoing stability of mind and clarity about how
things work well often this has to do with not
paying close attention and not remembering actually what's important to us
and so it takes some continuity of attention to see how things work which means that we have to remember to
pay attention but of course you know this is not easy in human life
often we're distracted by our phone our relationships our
emotions our self-image other things that come up and to be sure our world right now does
not make this easy for us to to have a clear continuity of attention
but truthfully it will never be easy there is no time
in the world when everything is simple and easy so now is as good a time as any
but we don't you know we don't have this um remembering to pay attention
and then why is that well um in many ways it's it's just easier to
go along you know to gather up our energy for a directed
purpose and to be consistent and persistent about that may not be as high
on our agenda as just being comfortable or fighting against
things or acting out our identity you know we have other agendas in our life um
and so we don't put together the energy to kind of gather ourselves toward this
purpose of paying attention carefully so that we can act well
um and so then why is that you know why don't we gather ourselves up well i think there are a number of reasons
maybe we don't think it really matters maybe we don't know that paying attention has a good effect or
we may know that external things are still out of our control but we may not really
believe that it can have that much effect to change the way we are in the world or maybe why don't know that real
happiness is available through our inner life through cultivating attention and other such things
maybe we don't realize that there's any alternative to either fighting or complying with how
things are so what i've done is
go backward through a list in buddhism it's called the five
faculties so um starts with
the order i went in to go backward was wisdom you know we start with why is it
that we're not able to bring benefit to the world which is one of the definitions of a wise person
well we don't have so much concentration so much stability and clarity of mind
and then why is that well there's not there's so much mindfulness available to us and why is that well we
don't bring up the energy and the persistence and consistency to
create that mindfulness always and why don't we bring up that energy well we may not
have faith or confidence that it's worthwhile in some way
and so this is a scenario for how things can unfold in ways that are not so favorable
but the five faculties this wonderful list of faith energy mindfulness
concentration and wisdom are actually available to us all the time and they can be used well
we may not think they're available all the time but these are actually ordinary qualities of mind
the buddha didn't say that these are special things that come into being through dharma practice we all have them
to some degree and the reason that we have them is they're they're actually the qualities
of mind that we use in learning skills whenever we're learning something new
which we do throughout our life we bring to bear some combination of these five
and they're they're not that means that they're not automatically spiritual qualities so we have them but they may
not be connected to our spiritual life and they become spiritual
when they are applied to the task of freeing the mind so in buddhism
liberation of the heart is considered the best benefit that we can offer you know at the top of that list of wanting
to benefit ourselves and others and both the liberation of the heart is
considered the greatest benefit that we can offer and so suppose that we want to begin
acting out of our own benefit for the benefit of others and for the benefit of both
it might take some time to really come into that and cultivate it but we can
so i want to talk tonight about these five faculties in their spiritual form
so the way that we bring the dharma dharma to life through our life if you
will the way the our life itself can enliven the dharma
and just to let you know in advance we'll spend most of the time on the first faculty
this is the groundwork from which the rest can unfold but we'll touch into all of them
so to begin this journey of becoming a real benefit to ourselves and others
will start with what in pali is called satta or faith
or there are other translations also but before i get to those this is the
idea that there is another way you know there is another way to live our life besides
just running around and being busy and chasing after pleasures or our identity
other things um and so so we have this word sada this idea of
faith this doesn't mean um blind faith but there is some
initial movement towards something that we don't know some idea or aspiration that we have
sometimes people use trust or perhaps later we would use confidence i'll probably use faith
this evening just because it's an easy word to say and because i've come to appreciate it but i'm aware that for
some people that word doesn't doesn't work so you could substitute one of the other
ones this is from rodney smith another teacher
the first moment of our spiritual journey may begin with a glimpse of a possibility that offers relief from all
this stress we hear a talk read a book or deeply sense something that suggests
there could be a different way to live this touch calls us from beyond toward a
mystery that re-prioritizes everything and provides a context for our struggles
this calling does not fit neatly within our conventional lives but we cannot
shake it off a spark has been ignited but we are not sure what to do about it
so this is kind of the very initial spark of faith that we might have and
often it's ignited through suffering of some kind suffering has a way of pulling aside the
veil of our life where we're just going along and you might consider if there's some
some experience like that that you've had so rodney smith uses this word
calling and this calling which is a positive response to suffering
i would say is another word for faith and interestingly it's also the first glimmer of wisdom
but it needs to be unfolded more before we get to that the first glimmer of faith is also the
first glimmer of wisdom so then how do we unfold this how do we
go forward from this first spark that we're getting so there are plenty
of external suggestions if you will for objects of faith and they're helpful
sometimes we need to start with something that comes from the outside or some suggestion from another in buddhism
we would usually refer to the initial object of our spiritual faith as
the triple refuge or the triple gem of buddha dharma and sangha
but the you know we could even talk a bit about these terms so the suit does talk about
faith in the buddha's enlightenment not necessarily the person of the buddha
but we have a sense at a heart level that freedom is possible
and we we have some sense that yeah somebody somebody really did this maybe this is really true
maybe there's somebody who has done this and knows what they're talking about and describing it or offering instructions
for it and so then we would connect with those instructions with those teachings and
this is the the dharma the dhamma and we can come to have faith
in the process i guess of the dharma um we can't maybe see or even imagine the
end point of where we're headed toward but we trust that it's going in a good
direction this is sometimes how i think about faith in the dharma eyes
well i don't necessarily know what this process is going toward and sometimes it can be a little uncertain
or uncomfortable what it is that the dharma is asking of us but i do have trust that it goes in a good direction
and that it's worth following in that way so that's the kind of confidence we
might have in the dharma and the quality of the teachings
and then in addition we can find either a teacher or some mature spiritual friends who are
actually embodying the qualities that we respect and value so we have some kind of a
living example of what the teachings are pointing toward and hopefully
some guidance about how we might be able to follow those ourselves so we also have some trust or confidence
in the sangha and then i'll mention also that
as we're exploring this quality of faith or confidence or trust
there's a connection between faith and joy in the teachings and so
i'd like to emphasize that we need some kind of positive basis
and we can we can ask ourselves you know what what might we do each day to nourish
joyful faith this positive sense of aspiration or
sometimes even excitement about walking the path i think of this as as i think of this
i'm reminded of a time that i practiced in sri lanka for a little while
and i noted that they have a very faith-based practice maybe more so than
we do definitely more so than we do here in the west at least in the inside movement and i found it quite delightful
i was staying at a monastery for example where at a certain time in the morning the
monks would come walking out of the monastery for alms in a neat row
walking together with their bowls mindfully could see in the way they were walking and we were at a retreat center
actually that was just next to the monastery so we would watch we could watch them come out from kind of a
position on the walking paths of the retreat center and when the monks came out
the retreatants would stop walking meditation and just watch it's kind of a cultural thing that we would just watch
quietly while the monks went by and one day one of the sri lankan yogis
turned to me she spoke english and she just said with a smile on her face
it's so nice you know since she just meant you know being there and watching the monastics
go by so there was some kind of this nice feeling that we were celebrating in this
faith-based quality of the dharma and it nourished our retreat practice for sure
so all of these you know ideas or external cues or
you know reflections that we have or watching monastics are meant to serve
actually to strengthen our inner sense of faith so these outer ideas are
actually meant to point toward our inner sense of faith the actual feeling in our own heart
i have a friend who was doing tibetan practice and one of
the ways that you begin that is to do sometimes people begin by doing a hundred thousand frustrations
so we don't do that in our tradition but it's um you know it's something that takes a while to do of course and this
person found that um this discipline of doing lots and lots
of frustrations each day and adding them up to make sure he was getting to a hundred thousand
um resulted in him being very clear about his deep motivation for undertaking this
practice you know you have to be connected with that in order to
continue all the way through that many frustrations so he started to realize that was the point of them it wasn't
that he needed to you know get his body in shape to be able to do that although he did
but he realized oh okay what this does is it really instills that inner sense of knowing why you're doing this
practice so this is very healthy good way to start
but nonetheless as we go along this quality of faith will get replaced
slowly by knowledge as we have direct experience in the practice
there's a story in the theravada teachings of sariputta the buddha's chief disciple
where the buddha asks him if he has faith that developing the five faculties
will lead to awakening and sorry putta says no and he then goes on to explain though
that he has direct knowledge that developing the faculties leads to awakening and so he doesn't need to have
faith in a statement like that so there is this understanding that they
proceed from faith through the others to wisdom to knowledge and you know we may want to be careful
between you know jumping too early to the conclusion that we know something and you know maybe
instead just deciding that we know something well enough to to keep going but nonetheless there is this this
transformation and then there's also an image
that's given you know in the teachings that says just as at a crossroads on a level
ground a great banyan tree becomes the resort for birds all around
so the person endowed with faith becomes the resort for many people
monastics and lay followers alike so then this same suta says later that
people who have this quality of sadha will get more opportunities so people
will ask them to do favors for them which connects them and gives them the
chance to do generosity and it even says that people with faith in the teachings are
more likely to receive teachings somehow teachings will come their way because they value them
so the idea here is to consider what the quality of confidence or trust
will attract into our lives this is interesting right we're not talking about blind faith at all but a
very clear sense of what we value and placing that at the center of our life
as a way of honoring it and so this is a teaching on causes and conditions
faith is a quality of the mind or heart that can be cultivated and which has real effects then on how
our lives unfold so if we have faith in the teachings or
confidence or trust or conviction then our practice will unfold differently than for the case of not
really having that hard connection while established so how does this work
in the context of these five faculties the next one after faith is
energy or effort so when we understand that something is important to us and we have some
confidence in it that it will bring good effects then we demonstrate that by
acting upon it if you will so this second faculty of effort
is often equated with perseverance sticking with the practice having some
continuity and that takes some some energy since the mind might not be used
to devoting itself to the dharma or to practice in this regular way
and i find that these middle three of effort mindfulness and concentration
kind of form a set that play off of each other um doing things plays off with paying
attention and they mutually reinforce each other in kind of a
virtuous circle if you will there's a little bit of an iteration that goes on where you know we put in
effort uh initially but then we have to pay attention to the effects of how we're
practicing and how our effort is working out and then we through that we realize that
we might need to make effort slightly differently or we might need to change it over time and then we again pay
attention to that and over time we have a gathering of the mind around the effort that it's making
the attention that it has the intention behind the aspiration that we're carrying so concentration is
slowly developing the gathering of the mind and all the while the mind is letting go of things that are not useful
for its effort and so the perspective it has and the playing field if you will
keep changing so i think i don't want to present the five faculties as just a
linear chain that we have to do one and then the next and then the next it's more that they
really begin to mutually reinforce over time so when the attention and the effort are
getting harmonized we can feel the mind settle into this more unified state
as if all the disparate components of it get aligned it's a state of
high energy and high attention at the same time so this is this
fourth quality of samadhi concentration as the fourth faculty
so in in life somebody can feel like sometimes what's called flow
we know what we're doing our energy is well directed and without tension and there's a stability such that we
can't easily get knocked off course so this when the mind is in a
state like that is when we get to experiential learning and that becomes integrated into our
system which is also what wisdom is about so
when we're kind of able to manifest what we originally had faith in
this is wisdom being able to act with benefit for ourselves others and both
somewhat paradoxically although there was a lot of setup to get to this point
of being able to manifest what it is that we were first valuing the state
actually feels quite natural so we start to get a sense of the dharma as a way of life we have to do all this
set up just to be natural if you will so i want to kind of bring things
together at this point we often talk about the dharma as if it's a fixed thing
but in its most basic definition dharma actually just means nature
so the dharma arises in our life in the way that we evoke it
and part of the art of dharma practice is to learn how to be natural
so we mostly present ourselves prevent ourselves from being natural we need to stop doing the things that are getting
in the way of being natural and being in line with the dharma and cultivating the five
faculties is one way to get into this alignment so that the they're sort of supportive
dharmic forces carrying our life along [Music] i'm relating this now to an image from
an essay that gill wrote and i like it because it talks about needing a skill remember that the five
faculties come into play whenever we're learning a skill so he writes
the way the dharma arises can be compared to floating in fresh water
floating is a learned skill that depends on our having both the intention to float and the skill
when we float we may say that the water supports us but in fact the water alone
is not sufficient to keep us from drowning if we don't know how to float and we
thrash around in fear or only relax and trust the water won't hold us up
so the dynamic interplay of the water and our body and our intention and skill
creates the floating so then he analogizes this to the dharma
as a support for our lives the dharma is like the floating the dharma is not found simply by
letting go any more than floating safely in water simply requires relaxing there are
certain skills and intentions that need to be present for the dharma to appear and to function
and it's through the way that we live that the dharma can have a role in our lives
i like that a lot and i i picked it out in particular because this floating image i think with some
not too much effort you can pull out all the five faculties from from that
short reading i did so we do have to relax and trust we're not thrashing around in the water
but this isn't the only thing we don't stop with faith we go on to make some kind of intentional effort
so having some energy in our ability to float or to bring the dharma into our
life and we'll need to be paying attention as we do that to our body and the water and
how that's um how the floating is working and then we'll need to balance all the
different factors the dynamic interplay of the water our body and our intention
all of that means that we're gathering ourselves around this idea of floating
and so we have a concentration factor and then through all of this we come into a genuine experiential knowledge of
how to float so it becomes easy um and then similarly we can gain this
intuitive knowing of when and how to do things in order to float on the support of the dharma
so we'll end by going back through the five faculties in our life
so as we begin to trust in approaching life in a different way than
we do when we're just busy and scrambling around we have some trust that there's another way
then we will start to make effort that's more harmonious it's less about just getting what is
pleasant and getting rid of what is unpleasant and more about developing what is wholesome and renouncing what is
unwholesome those are very different kinds of effort so we move toward this cultivation of
the wholesome and then it's natural that we'll be more attentive and we have to watch and remember to stay present in
order to keep our mind and body in a good state and then as we do that we will see more
and more clearly and will feel more and more aligned and stable in our heart
and as we have that stability of attention we'll be able to see how it is that we can actually be of
benefit how it is that our life can be more aligned more harmonious with the
values that we have and the fruition of that is that we will be of benefit to ourselves others both
and the whole world so we will come to embody wisdom
so these five faculties really do lead to a harmonious and balanced life and when
they're applied to the dharma they can also lead to liberation
we can come to maybe at least have faith in that and i hope that someday we will all know
that for sure so it's not maybe so easy as i laid it out in that nice
arrangement and yet it is kind of easy you know kind of like floating
not so easy but pretty easy when we when we get into it
so these are my thoughts for this evening on the five faculties and life
and i wish you all very well in your ongoing cultivation of each and all of
them thank you be well