so welcome again we'll begin on the evening sit
and so today what i thought ah share is a practice
that a buddha often praises in his teaching that is mindfulness of
body and so in our sitting today
we'll be working with this aspect of becoming aware of our body in
different ways and there are a total was of seven different
practices that's been introduced um that are included in mindfulness of
and so we'll do some of this today as you arrive
i invite you to you know however you are coming to this meditation
maybe just begin to pay attention to your general posture if you're just
settling down sitting maybe just becoming aware that you're
sitting as a way to arrive arrive into the space
and if you're still standing or walking in some way
just noticing the posture you're in maybe you're lying down
simple awareness and global awareness
and then momentarily as you take a seat sitting down
allow the whole body to arrive
maybe the sense of arrival can become obvious
when we really know that we are here
maybe feet are touching the ground
maybe the back links against the chair
are the legs against the cushion
buddy and feel and sense that all parts of the body
have arrived
arrived here in the space
torso arms hands
and face your head
and neck aligned on top of the spine
may be supported by earth
what does it feel like when the whole body has arrived here
maybe the sense of a bubbly energy is the sinking settling down
maybe the thoughts drifted in the background
as you begin to settle
allow your awareness to rest on the breath in breath
and out breath as you breathe
becoming mindful of the in and out breathing
so awareness is very simple
simply noticing if the breath is soft and gentle
with a soft and gentle breath
now the breath is a little rough
it's a rough breath
if the brush breath is shallow just know it's a shallow breath
however the breath is simply knowing it
as is
not trying to change it manipulate it control it
it's simple annoying
easing into the breath
as the breath travels moves through the body
allow the body to be massaged
maybe the whole body can be more at ease
and sensing and feeling the breath
moving through the torso
maybe the sensations of the breath rolling
on the back or in front
around the chest and belly
maybe the breath is massaging inside of the ball of the body as well
temporarily we can put away the thoughts and plans for now
it's becoming intimate and curious
with this embodied experience
embodied experience of the breathing
as the mind settles
one of the contemplations that's taught as part of a mindfulness
body is to contemplate the different parts of
the body this body that we call as the body
is made up of different component
parts from outside of the body our hair
nails skin
moving inward there's flesh
underneath of the skin
and the bones feeling the hardness of the bones
there are organs inside
different fluids
blood fat
saliva this body is made
of all these different parts
there's a different parts of the body there's no inherent beauty
or ugliness it's just what it is
different parts coming together
we can also contemplate and reflect the elemental nature of our bodies
this body is made of earth water fire
and air
earthy quality of the body maybe you feel the heaviness of the body
hardness of our bones
[Music] firm relatively still and scented
what's the felt sense of air element
in breath and out breath
maybe vibrations
tinkling
temperature
maybe you notice the warmth of the palms
and the coolness
on some part of the skin that may be
exposed
what's the felt sense of the water element
maybe there is a sense of the harmony of the whole body
the whole body feels coherent harmonious
brought together by the water elements
in this body there is element of the space
space inside of this body and all around
this body is held within the space
letting go of the bigger concepts of the body
we drop into the raw felt sense of the body
elemental sensations
movements
pressure around the neck
some tingling on the fingertips
maybe vitality humming in this body
all that we experience are ever changing
breath rises and passes away
different sensations
appear and disappear
the whole experience
maybe you like the flux of wavelets
sounds travel through
thoughts bubbles up and burst away
sensations in the body
get soaked bubbles
let go of any attempt to try to hang on
to a particular experience
let loose all the experiences
[Music]
so mindfulness of body something i have in mind to share
tonight and so in poly canon text and the buddha often
praises and um talks about the mindfulness of body
he says the mindfulness of the body when cultivated and developed is of a
great fruit and a benefit
so i thought i'd share a little bit of the teachings of a mindfulness body based on the poly canon text
specifically and this uh suta and the title of the
suitor is mindfulness of the body and the susuta can be found
and in machu nikaya 119 for those who you know might be
interesting looking it up so much money kaya 1 19.
so mindfulness of the body is also often emphasized
in secular mind mindfulness meditation teachings
and in secular mindfulness teachings and often the teachers would start with
mindfulness of body for example mindfulness of breath are becoming aware of
and the sensations in the body and through this kind of awareness of what
is happening in this lived experience in the body we began to cultivate our capacity
to live in the present moment with more clarity
the mindfulness body however in the poly canon teaching
is much more on extended expansive and has a profound
implications and so buddha on one buddha taught
mindfulness of a body and the whole sequence of the practices that's introduced
in mindfulness of body are meant to lead all the way to full awakening liberation
in addition to many other benefits and that may be available to oneself
and so i want to share a little bit about this sequence of practices that the susuta
talked about and some of them are not very
not often taught in secular mindfulness teachings however they can be quite profound
and so this mindfulness of body teaching consists of seven different practices
and that are ordered in a particular sequence i can be thought as a progressive
sequence to cultivate mindfulness in somebody
and through which through the sequence of a practice one can have um a great clarity
into the very nature of this body which is according to the three key
insights and that is an impermanence
non-satisfactoriness of this body and that cannot be identified as self
anata so through these forms of insights it
becomes possible to have a complete destruction of defilements and that leads to full
awakening so what are the seven different
practices so i'm gonna give you this list of the
seven first and so you maybe orient your mind a little bit to this list of seven and then i'll walk
through each of this and in some form of a sequence and to say a few words about each of them
so this list of the seven uh in poly canon text it starts over the
mindfulness of breathing and however in the chinese parallel
of the poly canon text mindfulness breathing actually is number
three in this sequence and which i'll say a few words and um
the sequencing a little bit later but i just started with the list number one
mindfulness breathing the second one is awareness of the four
postures that is walking standing sitting down and lying down
the third is awareness of the bodily activity and that is if you're bending down
you know you're bending down if you're eating you know you're eating if you're cooking you know you're
cooking and so whatever you're doing in terms of bodily activities
and you know that this is happening so that's number three awareness of the
bodily activities number four is the contemplation of the
anatomical parts as a different parts of the body
contemplation of that this body is made up of different parts component parts
number five is contemplation of the four elements earth water fire
and air in other suitors it also talks about the fifth element which is space but not
in this particular suta and number six is the corpse
contemplation contemplation of the different stages of decay
of the dead body corpse number seven is the four jhanas which is
the four stages of samadhi
and so it's very interesting to look at the sequence to see what is happening with
this sequence and then for me it made a little more
sense that the mindfulness of breathing is number three and the whole sequence starts with
something that is relatively easy to know very simple intuitive and
quite global and so for most of the folks who began to practice engage in a
mindfulness body practice that's the first few are relatively easy
easily accessible so for example being aware of our postures
and we all know that we have some sort of posture and we're aware of it and so the practice is
to simply know that oh you know i'm standing right here i'm
standing or on if you're lying down just aware that you're lying down very
light weight noticing just know and then on the awareness of a body the
activities is also something very um relatable and maybe
comparing to the first practice it has a little more detail and so you are you're now paying
attention to different activities as you uh go about your daily life and so
um it's maybe has a little more detail than adjusted the four postures
and then after that um mindfulness free thing so now we're settling down to a more
settled state of being where we began to pay attention to some
details of the activity and as a whole sequence of seven unfolds and
you get a sense that there is a um a growing sense of settledness
and the subtlety and um collectedness and so the
strength of uh samadhi and mindfulness began to build up as we
practice in this way starting from the first practice mindfulness of
awareness of the posture awareness of the bodily activities
and yet you know the practice doesn't have to go in sequence exactly like this you know
for most of us and we may practice in one particular one uh in different situations
and then just practice with that for quite some time so for example becoming aware of
on the bodily postures and bodily activities and it was a
you know a practice that i engaged in for quite some time and especially at the beginning of my um
meditation practice i didn't have a regular formal
meditation sitting um but um i was still interested in cultivating
mindfulness and so i incorporated just noticing
my activities as i go about and living my life in daily life
and it has an effect because becoming aware of our coarser level
postures and body activities in action it began to cultivate and tone our
mindfulness muscle and as we actually sit down
when we begin to sit down if we had cultivated this mindfulness
in our daily life by noticing various activities as we we do them and
the sitting meditation can be more easily settling so one can settle down but much
more quickly but if you know during the day um
you know whatever you're doing you're very preoccupied with thinking this thinking that and and you
know for example if you're cooking uh instead of noticing that you're cooking and you
know taking this spatula of flipping and the pancakes you're simply thinking about
all kinds of things and then we have lost opportunities to really begin to
atone our mindfulness muscle and as we sit down and to do our formal meditation
our mind can still have this momentum to jump here and there i'm busy uh engaging in all kinds of
um mental activities so this uh first few a couple of
mindful body practices can be a great way to really set the
conditions up for us to go into more formal meditation practice
but they they can also be complementary to formal meditation practice and some people do formal
walking meditation on retreats or daily life and that itself
can be a a very meditative meditative process as well
and as this process goes on the next um practice that's being
introduced is mindfulness of in and out breathing
in this particular suture mindfulness of a breathing and that's being described here uh
includes um the four steps of mindfulness breathing that is
noticing in and out breathing as it is and as you breathe in and out
begin to calm and settle the body and so in our meditation uh before this
talk um we did a little bit of that and kind of as we began to breathe in and out
this process itself can begin to settle the body and allow the body to become
quieter and calmer and some of you may know that um
mindfulness breathing itself and can be a whole system a
comprehensive process of its own that leads to full awakening
and that process consists of the 16 steps that go through mindfulness breathing
that allows the body to come calm down and then allow the mind to settle and
then um go through the process to cultivate the joy and this trunk
tranquility and um also leading to seeing on the inside and the nature of our
experiences and so that that itself is a 16 step
of process in this suta it's the first four steps and that are
related to calming and easing the body that's being brought here
and then but it has an effect because as we go through on this mindfulness breathing
process when our bodies become to come down the next few
practices that are introduced become more relevant become more available to
us and so for example the next practice that's been introduced
in the susuta is the contemplation of the analytical parts
so this is a a contemplation that is
not taught often in secular mindfulness some teachers also teach contemplation
of analytical parts but it's not very popular and and yet in and the mindfulness of
body teaching and it's quite a significant um
practice of its own so what you can um one way to understand this particular
teaching is that as we become a calmer in relationship to our body we can begin
to see this body in a bit more uh raw form rather than a bigger conceptual
framework of what this body is you know whether it's beautiful or ugly kind of all this other conceptual things
begin to kind of fade out but we can begin to see
this body as it is in terms of its componentary
and parts and so the classic teaching is to see this
body in terms of the 32 parts or 31 parts starting from and the
uh exterior part of our body you know body hairs and
skin the nails and then go through this process and and begin to contemplating internal of the
body also and all the way to um you know our flesh
bones fat um and the body liquids even including our urine
and um so you you know you ask why why do we do this contemplation
and that's probably not very popular because if we began to look at this body
in this way often our immediate reaction could be you know some form of aversion of
repulsiveness and so maybe that that's kind of why
it's not very popular teaching uh in contemplation of our mindfulness of the body teachings
but the buddha prescribed this specific teaching
as a way to really point at some strong forces of craving illness in particular
craving for essential pressures it's not very hard to see that
uh that you know many people and most of us probably have a strong
clinging to our bodies one way or another
i'm aware and that even for kids when they are very young they will
begin to have some sense of how they wanted to be seen from
the image perspective you know what to wear and how long a hair is
and as and the kids grow older you know in teenager years young adults
body images and you know can be become so defining for who we are
i can certainly relate to this myself and as we get older we we can get
very obsessed with our health our the aging process
and so it's not hard to see that you know that there can be a lot of cleaning and grasping
in relationship to this body and the buddha has um really seen this
that in you know kind of a human psyche and so he prescribed
this kind of contemplation to begin to see this
as is not something to be um cling to as you know beautiful
or repulsive against as ugly but just as this is what
what is what the body is made up of
and yet you know as we began to engage in a practice like this the
contemplation of the analytical part there can also be some danger because
for those who do have a very negative and repulsive relationship
with one's own body and this form of practice can can lead to
um i don't know depression or it may be even self-harm
and so it's a wise to really tune in to what kind of attitude we may have
and maybe even work with the teachers and to engage with this kind of practices so
that one can move with this practice move into this practice
with a more balanced mind in the suta and the simile that is being
used to describe this particular form of practice is that as if
one is looking into a bag of mixed lentils and mixed rice
and and knows that you know the red lentil is red lentil black lentil is
a black lentil and this is the way to look at you know here the body has all those different
parts just like you know the bag of lentils and rice mixed up here and so there's no
attitude of um indulging or attitude of
pushing away and so it's a very neutral way of looking at things as is
and so that's contemplation of the analytical parts
now moving from there the next practice that's being introduced in this
sequence is the contemplation of the four elements
and so what is happening is um in this stage now one
once contemplation of reflection or observing of this body
is now moving into more of a felt sense of what this body is
now this may not be very obvious if one just began to practice
mindfulness body because it's not very common for one to relate to this
body at this level which can be not very intuitive
or hard to be accessible at the beginning but if we practiced
as and this sequence unfolds we began to see that once mindfulness
maybe began to grow one is able to let go of some of the higher level
concepts and ideas but now one is able to drop into
the raw and felt sense of what this body feels like
so the elemental natures of this body the firmness of the earthy part of the
body and the air are movements of them
of the body and then the space all around us inside us
and so contemplation of the four elements allow us to begin to cultivate even
further what this body is in the elemental level the raw level
and so this particular practice based on the contemplation of the four
elements and can also cultivate a strong sense of
ease and settledness and so this allows the next
practice to begin to become accessible so the next practice is
a corpse contemplation again this may be something kind of a provocative in
our modern um secular mindfulness teachings
and rarely you would hear people talk about corpse contemplation
yet the corpse contemplation serve on
a very um how do i say it very um critical step in this
cultivation and that is it's moving into a different
form of a perceiving the nature of this body
usually when we come to the notion of a death most
of us most people will have some sense of a denial even though we
all know that the death would happen but one would refuse to see it
but through this a process of cultivating how we see our bodies in this sequence
of our practices when it gets to corpse contemplation
a mind may be more settled and began to be willing to see
oh this body is of nature to age of the nature to be
sick and of the nature to die and even when this dead body
um even when the death happens this dead body go through its own
decomposition process will eventually go back to earth go back to nature
and since through seeing that this it can lead oneself to an insight into impermanence
unsatisfactoring of this body and the not self nature of this body
this body is not something that we can hang on it's not something permanent
and so this corpse contemplation began to bring in kind of front and
center this inside way of seeing inside way of seeing
the nature of this body anitra dukkah and anata
and when we began to be able to see this body in this way
there can be a profound sense of letting go as well
and so in this sequence and the seventh practice is that of the four genres
it's a cultivation of the four stages of samadhi
and this is impossible because when we began to see the nature of this
body there can be a strong sense of letting go letting go of grasping and cleaning
and when the clinging and grasping are let go of
a deeper sense of well-being can bubble up joy tranquility equanimity can become
available and that can become a platform for us to lead into
full liberation awakening and so this process that's described
prescribed by this particular suta that includes you know from a very
simple lightweight practice of being aware of our body postures body
activities to our breath and to noticing and reflecting
contemplating that this body has made component parts and all the way to begin to notice
that there is a felt sense of this body
which is very elemental nature of this body
through this then the the uh samadhi becomes available to us
and this can lead to lead to um destruction of defilements
so this is really kind of a holistic system and that covers the uh
the entire spectrum spectrum of our practice
and this practice has a lot of benefits and the susuta itself i have highlighted
10 different benefits you know ranging from no longer being a victim of a desire
and a discontent no longer being a victim of fear and dread and have a stronger
capacity to endure the vicititudes of climate and hunger and disagreed and
disagreeable conditions all the way to
destruction of the developments as i mentioned before and it's a very
profound teaching and so i do hope that tonight's practice
and and this dharma talk is uh um a bit of an inspiration
for us to engage in this practice uh with a lot of curiosity and
maybe some dedication and so may this mindfulness of body
practice bring much benefit to all of us and to all beings thank you for being
here tonight and i wish you all a wonderful evening
or a wonderful day wherever you are so thank you