welcome to our meditation time together and i'm happy to be here with you
one of the aspects of meditation that
is obvious if it's pointed out is that most people when they just
decide to meditate do something different with their bodies
they bring their bodies to a particular place they place their bodies in a particular posture
and um and it's one of the first things we do is this uh bring our body along
and um and if that can easily be overlooked
but the tremendous value on
the body's role in meditation and in life in general is one of the
things that zen and vipassana have in common
and in in all my practices of zen and there was this kind of implicit and
at times explicit way in which it involved a growing
center of gravity center of life being rooted in the body not in the mind and in vipassana the
same thing one of my teachers in thailand um made an assad at the end of a dharma
talk one day the talk had ended and people were leaving and he kind of looked up and said oh and by the way
don't do anything that takes you away from your body and and
to go back to teachings of the buddha he stresses over and over again how
important mindfulness of the body is now mindfulness of the body that little
word of is a little bit ambiguous it can mean for some people that
there's a tension attention is directed to the body and therefore it's of the body but another way of
understanding it is that mindfulness of the body is the body's
mindfulness that becomes a little bit clearer if we translate the word for mindfulness that's the
word sati i don't know if it's really mindfulness is the best translation in english and i often prefer the word
awareness for it and and so we understand that mindfulness
of the body is the body's awareness and we're beginning to center ourselves
in the experience the body has of our life the way the body is aware of itself
and and this is a wonderful shift out of being mind-centric
where we're or thinking centric which is where many people live their lives
and to shift and have the the center of our lives not our thoughts these thoughts have still very important
part of life but not have them at the center and have the body at the center
and uh and uh and the body is a place where we have direct
experience much more so than if we just think about things
so to training to be present for the body's experience of
itself so to begin this meditation i'll do a
little warm-up in a sense and then i'll do a little exercise of mindfulness
bodies mindfulness bodies awareness that maybe gives you a feeling for how this
entering into the body in a deeper way to be aware of breathing even can operate
so to assume meditation posture that's appropriate
for you
and that posture is also a little bit of an attitude a posture that has an attitude of
attentiveness of being embodied being
so there can be a rootedness a intentionality
in being here in and with the body
so the body is just nothing aside to be made comfortable and forgotten
the body is in a sense the meditation hall the temple
and some of you will feel more comfortable with the eyes open
the meditation and some of you can gently close your eyes
it might be nice to take a few long slow deep breaths to settle in
maybe extending the exhale to allow for greater release in the body
really relax on that exhale
exhaling and letting the shoulders soften
the belly relax
and then letting your breathing return to normal and taking a few moments to
become aware of the body's experience of itself as
if awareness is not up in the control tower but awareness lives in the body
an awareness is closely associated with sensations
or more precisely the sensing of the sensations
and as an exercise bring your attention into your left hand
and become aware of the sensations in your left hand
there might be coolness and tingling and warmth
pulsing vibration there might be a contact of the hand
against another part of your body pressure and
weight
feeling the sensations in your hand in your palm of your hands the back of
your hand
in your fingers
and allow the hand to have its own experience as if the hand is getting to know itself
feeling and sensing the sensations
by which we know the hand and perhaps this exercise is it's useful
to close your eyes if they're open so that the only real
data coming in for the hand is the in the hand itself we don't
see the hand we just feel it
and with the eyes closed maybe there's no clear sense of a boundary of the hand
within the buzzing changing shifting sensations that make up the hand
the hand is open boundaries
just the hand
and you might have ideas about your hand thoughts and histories and memories of
your hand but that is to to bring those up it
means to go back into the mind and there's a way in which putting all
that aside there's a generosity in allowing the
hand to be just as it is at this moment
in a sense no future no past no judgments just the sensations of the
hand some pleasant some unpleasant
are allowed to be just as they are
and now shift your awareness your attention
to wear in your body you usually experience your breathing
and not so much that you are focusing on the breathing from the
control tower
but rather you're becoming aware of the general area in your body
where you tend to experience breathing
and as you are feeling the hand feel this general area
the sensations that are there
some sensations might be closely connected to
the experience of breathing and but there might be other sensations there
and let that part of the body have its own experience of what's happening there
noticing the particular sensations that come into play
that appear and disappear
and how that area about your body maybe has no clear boundaries
in awareness in its own experience
it's kind of open boundaries allowing the permission to be there
with no future and no past
where we're not centered in our thoughts and judgments about it all
those can recede to the background and instead
to let the center of experience be the body's experience of breathing
and if you find yourself drifting off in thought very simply recognize that's happening
and recognize how it's taken you away from the immediacy of your embodied
experience of breathing
and then begin again centering yourself in your body
in the breathing body
where the boundaries to the body's experience of breathing is open and can
in fact include all other things happening in your body
maybe peripherally nothing is held
nothing is pushed away or denied or but centered in the body in the
breathing allowing the body to have its own
experience breathing with it all breathing in and breathing out
are you in the control tower of thinking or are you in your body
what happens if you
center yourself
in the body and the experiences the bodies have
having the immediacy of the body
with no before and after just now
and as we come to the end of this meditation
for the next few out breaths as you exhale relax
your body further release any holding in your face
any holding in your shoulders
in your chest and your belly
and if there's any global way in which you're bracing yourself against life
perhaps at the end for a few breaths can you relax that
and relax into your body more fully
and when we're relaxed in our body at ease and at home in our body
it can give us a greater capacity
for kindness friendliness
good will
and to consider at the end of the sitting how is it that
the benefits of this meditation
or the challenges of this meditation can inspire you to contribute to the
betterment of our world
that the deep letting go of meditation
is not to take us away from the world
but to be more open aware of this world that we live in
and to care may it be that
we contribute to the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and as we relax deeply into our own bodies freeing it from our tensions and
tightness and holdings may we support
others to do the same may all beings be free
so one of the surprises and treasures of
practicing buddhism for me has been a growing and still growing
the delighting or valuing the body the experience of the body
and um and there's a difference but what i just said between the body and the experience of the body
and i think at the heart of what is most significant for dharma practitioners is
the experience of the body more than the body itself
and um and it's hard to separate out these two things the body
and the experience of it but this is at the center of uh
kind of the tremendous appreciation that the buddha and nothing much of buddhism has
with being really centered or connected to one's body
is that it's not the body as a physical object as a physical thing
but rather the experience the body has of itself and we see in the ancient teachings of
the buddha that he used at times different words if he was referring to the physical body
in and of itself or the experienced body the body that we can experience
and so the physical body the one of the words for his physical body
in ancient languages sarira s a r i think i r a
and uh in sanskrit it's sharira it's often translated into english as a
relic a relic of someone who's died and that bone or some kind of little
something from left over from the cremation and it's a long custom in different
schools of buddhism to save these relics and maybe put them on the altar
and and sometimes the word sharira is used actually to refer to a corpse
but it's what it refers to also for a living person is the physical the pure physical
body itself the word that's used for especially in
meditation practice that's used for body is kaya
k-a-y-a and people who do zen practice know this word because it's often chanted
this nirmanakaya the sambod kayak
and
and this word kaya in their earliest teachings when it's talking about the meditator
it refers to the body as it's experienced and how we experience the body is partly
dependent on the state of our mind that and this is a fascinating part of
being a meditator is to feel how the state of the mind changes
and the experience of the body changes and sometimes even the posture will change
depending on how concentrated the mind becomes how focused and still and quiet
and and the mind stops becoming claustrophobic and caught up in its thinking and
thoughts but becomes spacious and open and more quiet and soft
it can have a huge transformation in how we experience the body
and the experienced body to it often becomes soft and transparent or very soft boundaries or
no boundaries at all and even sometimes the feeling of the body can disappear entirely in
meditation and i've actually opened my eyes
in meditation to see if i the physical body was still there because with the eyes closed there was no
evidence of it the mind was so still and so quiet
and and this interplay between the mind and the body is uh so intimate that
in buddhism there's a tendency not to make a strong duality between the mind and the body
but to see them kind of as a unified whole and one of the place that unified whole
plays out is in the is that the emphasis on being present for the
body's experience of itself an experience which is not exactly right to say that way but an experience which
is conditioned on the quality state of the mind and of course it goes the other
direction as well that the state of the body affects the mind if we're in a lot of pain that can have
a big impact on the mind we can get contracted we can get caught up in certain thoughts and judgments and
fears and projections and all kind but it's not necessarily so
and one of the great lessons i had from sitting zazen where at zen center where
i wasn't supposed to move i would have a lot of knee pain and i noticed after a
while that the pain actually got worse if i had self-pity for myself
i think you know what was happening was these little micro muscles would tighten up when i had the self-pity and the only way that i could
manage with the pain was if i let go of my self-pity and uh and then this micro muscles would
relax and then the pain was manageable and uh and i found that the less i got caught
up in my thoughts and my reactivity in my mind and my projections and
into the future what this all meant that the pain in and of itself got
simpler and simpler and simpler and to have a simplicity of physical
pain without the add-on of reactivity showed me how much the experience of
pain was a product of the quality of state activity of my mind
not all of it of course and the buddha himself said that when there's extreme
pain then it's the pain of the sarira the pain of the corpse of the
of the the pure physical body but many times these two are real you
know the mind and the body have such a big interplay with what we experience as pain and discomfort and all kinds of
things in the body that um and so one of the things we do in vipassana practice is learn to center
ourselves in the body to um to really allow ourselves to experience it
and the body's experience of itself and um and as we do so it
has an impact back on the mind and because these two are so closely related
and it has a huge impact on the mind in fact the conditioning and the shifting and changing of the bodily experience
is a reconditioning of the neurotic mind or the fearful mind or the traumatized mind
even and so to begin to soften and relax
and so the buddha was very explicit about this he talked about cultivating a mindfulness of the whole
body opening up becoming aware of the whole body not just the body that's breathing
but the whole body kind of like a global experience of this body's experience of itself and a global
experience is one where the mind is not contracting or fixating on any
particular thing or creating a boundary to the body but just kind of open to experience it all
the buddha also talked about as the mind does get settled and concentrated
that if there's any feelings of well-being that dwell up feelings of joy and happiness that to
take and spread that throughout the body and allow that those feelings to spread
and and so the experience about it begins shifting dramatically and i think this
is partly in mahayana what's being referred to in the three bodies of the buddha
that there are three different ways of experiencing the body depending on what's happening in the
mind and the mind state that we have and
it becomes such a delight such a joy to
rest and experience these kind of bod the body becomes freer and free or a
liberated body there is an ancient mahayana sutra
that emphasizes that liberation doesn't happen in the mind it happens in
the body that the awakening is a embodied experience
more than a mental experience but in fact what we know now is that you can't really separate these two the mind and
the body so in vepasana practice one of the ways
that there's many ways in which the mindfulness of the body is practiced but one of the ways is to
is to bring the kind of attention that i suggested to you in that exercise with a
hand to bring that to whatever is the compelling physical experience of the moment if
there's some predominantly compelling experience in the body either pleasant or unpleasant
that's more compelling than the breathing then it's fine to let go of the
breathing not keep that focus but bring the same kind of careful attention
careful kind of sensing and feeling into that part of the body that has this strong sensations
and what happens is if you if over time different parts of the body will speak
up and show itself and it's kind of like doing body work
over over months and years and by bringing this careful attention just opening the attention open allowing the
sensations to be there not reacting not forcing them not spending too much time relaxing around
it either just feeling and sensing and slowly the body begins to wake up
and become more aware and more uh sensory sensate
ascentian body as opposed to a conceived body and body that we're
thinking about so much of our self physical self-consciousness
has to do with ideas and images about what the body should be like or can be like and
comparison of my body with other people's bodies and it can be so much pain that goes on
our society around body and skin color and all kinds of things
having to do with the body and meditation is one of the ways to free ourselves at least personally
from all these ideas comparative thinking and concepts and allowing the awareness of the body
arise from the inside out and we find out the body is much happier
than often we are much more content when it flows and we have the experience
from the inside out so mindfulness of the body
is the body's awareness of the body is the body's awareness and one of the things in meditation
practice is to learn to abide or rest in that experience of the
body and when it's the most compelling part
of it or the center of it we can stay with the breathing because it's an embodied experience to
breathe and breathe with all things
breathe with the body all of the body so um i hope this made some sense and
i hope it also uh points to one of the places where zen and vipassana overlap in some ways
this emphasis on body and and the importance of it in the practice
and in the kaya and maybe what we can call
our own dharmakaya so thank you all very much