so greetings welcome to the meditation
and
it's a happy sight to see the stream of uh good mornings here on the chat it's just kind of a
wonderful kind of river of goodwill and
i love seeing the familiar names and i love seeing new names and very nice
so one of the hallmarks of buddhism and buddhist practice
is the his freedom and freedom is a little complicated to
appreciate because it's very easy to feel that
freedom is unfettered unlimited uh
ability to act on our desires to act on our
compulsions to give room to whatever we're feeling wanting
disliking just just our feelings just kind of to flow freely and fully
and and then act on them and that's not quite what the freedom of
buddhism the freedom of buddhism is the freedom that
is not ego based or conceit based it's not the not the freedom that allows
unfettered expression of our desires and our
animosities and our fears but rather
it's uh it is a freedom that's deeper than that that allows for
something in their depths that's independent
of greed and hatred and delusion independent of the
whole complex of emotions and impulses that come out of what could be called conceit
and to allow that to be free free of us in a sense but it is coming
from our depths it is a hugely you know integral part of who we are the dharma
the dharma that we are a dharma that flows through us
so in in uh and that's one of the reasons why provisionally mindfulness can be
understood as getting out of the way or as
giving a pause of just allowing things to be
and seeing them being aware of them making room for whatever is here and a progressive process of just
getting out of the way and allowing our inner experience to flow
and that allowing is not acting on our impulses or compulsions but it is
listening and sensing and feeling in to what's what's deeper what what can we
what freedom can we give to what's deeper and more integral more intimate um
that which lays at the kind of the foundation of our life or that which comes from someplace within
that is more wholesome maybe deeper than the place of unwholesomeness or
unskillfulness things that are based on compulsion
and uh and to have the trust to allow ourselves not to act on compulsion but
to make room for something else then what comes from fear or
compulsive desire or compulsive animosity resentment or what kind of swirls around and gets
trapped in the cycles of fear that might exist
so to pause to allow to get out of the way of one's
own experience so to begin this process
we take a pause in our daily activities to meditate
and to not so much to make something happen but to discover what is here for us
and have that discovery keep it be equivalent to keep opening
doors to what is here so
taking a posture assuming a posture that allows you your body to pause
from usual activities
for most of you it's probably a stationary posture so the body is still
and that allows us to tune into be aware of the sensations of the body
that are maybe more subtle than what would be
the case if we're doing a lot of movement
and one of the things that we don't pay much attention to in daily life can be the ongoing rhythm of breathing
and so to maybe take a few long slow deep
breaths
perhaps not aggressive breaths not too forceful but some deep
gentle breaths full breaths three quarters full
in a long exhale a long release
and as we exhale the end of the exhale to relax the belly baby relax the chest
and then
letting your breathing return to normal with no special effort to breathe in
special ways in this process of beginning to get out
of the way and allow
what is in a sense the natural processes of the body
to do to uh to be free of our in interference or wanting or trying to make something
happen
and allowing the breathing to breathe itself
and if that's not possible don't worry about it allow that
and perhaps as a way of continuing to settle in on the exhale relax the body more fully
wherever in your body your attention lands as you exhale
soften and relax
the idea of releasing can also be helpful here releasing the place in the body that are
contracted
and then letting letting go of the effort to relax or
release and to really just allow what's here
hello and
discover what your experience is now
seeing if that discovery that noticing
can be spacious or allowing or
maybe even gentle
and noticing that gives room for your experience to be what it is
without being involved in it judging it thinking about it analyzing it
coming in close so it's the direct experience
the experience as it manifests in the body
the physicality of whatever is happening for you emotions and a lot of thinking
discover and make space for the physical way it feels and senses in the body
perhaps quieting your thinking so there's more room in attention
to discover to feel to sense
and at the center of what
is arising appearing is the comparing of the inhales and the
exhales
and to allow those experiences to arise in freedom
from ourselves our desires our wantings expectations
judgments however the breathing is
let it be
and whatever your experience is let it be but let it be
in a as clear an awareness as you can
with knowing ah this is how it is
and as we go along new experiences will arise things will
get strong and loud just keep getting out of the way to
allow each thing to be known
just known for what it is
in a sense granting freedom to
every thing that the mind can know as it's known in
the present moment
knowing what's happening and allowing it getting out of the way so we're not
participating in it just aware of it
and then to come to the end of this
sitting the ability to
be sensitive and aware in a deep way or
sensitive to the deeper what's happening within us that's deeper
than the ways we might feel overwhelmed by life or frustrated by life
deeper than the contractions of fear the compulsions of desire
the fever of animosity
to feel our way deep inside to where there is
a kind of space and ease and peace from which flows
are good will from which friendliness has a chance
simple ordinary kindness
these simple ordinary feelings of good will that so easily get
eclipsed by all the preoccupations of the mind and
her life
and to have some sense some intuition
of a place of kindness and good will and
care and love compassion
that is not an obligation but rather something that also
lives in us something also that flows and arises
and it's something that's wholesome and good that's beneficial for us
to give expression to some of the wholesome aspects of who we
are grow when we give them expression
and so at the end of a sitting to give expression to our appreciation
our respect our care for others
by uh by wishing them well
and by wishing that our meditation practice
supports us in our care for the world
may it be that this practice we've done today
may it be for the welfare and happiness and support of all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
to continue this topic of refuge refuge is uh
arises in us when we understand that there is
a profound support for our lives that there is a way of being
that provides a sense of safety that provides a sense of
purpose a direction and orientation for our lives when we understand that some understand
that understandings that some kind of clear insight that um that we have
this is can be this basis or the support for how we live our lives
so refuge is considered to be really valuable in buddhism and as i've been saying that
in the early buddhism and teachings of the buddha there are different things that are highlighted as
worthy refuge and certainly what we most commonly know about is the buddha
dharma the sangha yesterday i talked about having oneself
as a refuge and today talk about action the activities
the buddha also said that we have our actions as our refuge
so it's not just a matter of you know passively allowing and
being present and and being the recipient of some deep inner
or outer kind of support for us and then trusting that we don't have to
do anything dharma practice is an active practice there is there is doing
that's part of it but hopefully what we're doing is learning how to do how to act in ways that are wise and
healthy and nourishing and that are free of strain
obligation pushing being busy and free of kind of conceit or self
kind of consciousness that is the self-conscious kind of
self-consciousness is that's equivalent of being self-preoccupied
and so action is very important in the teachings of the buddha so much so
that a few different locations uh the buddha is referred to in this ancient text as a teacher of
action and um the i guess there were people at the time of
the buddha teacher spiritual teachers at his time who felt that actions were inconsequential
that no matter what you did it didn't really have any long-term benefit or effect or
repercussions and some people interpret that to be that you can just do whatever you wish it
doesn't matter how immoral and ethical it is it doesn't matter other teachers at the time of the buddha
said nothing matters so you shouldn't do anything actually not doing nothing just non-doing radical non-doing
is the way forward the buddha had a teaching that some actions are
worth doing and some are not worth doing and over and over again you see in his teaching sometimes very emphatically
when people ask them a question like do you believe in restraint do you believe in
non-action do you believe in this or that he would answer the question
by saying i teach the doing of what is wholesome
and the not doing of what is not wholesome so in terms of restraint i teach the
teachings of restraint then it's a wholesome restraint not the restraint that is an unwholesome
restraint do you teach non-doing i teach the
non-doing of what is unwholesome but not the non-doing of what is wholesome
do you teach you know that we should always do x
he says no i teach you should always do x that is wholesome but you should avoid
that which is unwholesome or unskillful and i like to use the word helpful or unhelpful or healthy and
not healthy for this kind of distinction the puteri makes repeatedly between the wholesome and the
unwholesome and and when we do wholesome things in a wholesome way
when we do the beautiful things in a beautiful way when we do
ethical things in a way that doesn't harm ourselves or harm others so that doing an ethical
thing is actually a nourishing thing beneficial
that that is how actions can be our refuge now one of the actions that puts
is emphasized in in buddhism is the action of straight strong
simple mindfulness something that i call i consider synonymous with awareness to be
consciously lucidly aware of our experience
and mindfulness has a quality whatever almost all ways that mindfulness is
taught that it is an awareness and knowing a recognition of what's happening
that is not interfering with what's happening that is allowing each thing to be seen
clearly without be us being entangled with it without being
caught in compulsions of desires or aversion for or against it so that one of the
synonyms of mindfulness or close synonyms or characteristics of mindfulness
is letting things be just letting things be
and so some people like to talk about a pause even a sacred pause of mindfulness
that we don't kind of hurtle into the future into the next
moment in a speeding along
going from one desire to the other reaching out doing uh being so busy that we the mind
becomes claustrophobic or spinning or you know it's hard to notice um
even what we're doing because we're we we do we act we talk even before we know what we're going to
say or do and it can feel great that way because it can feel like we're free just to say
whatever we want we're free just to do whatever we want and so there's kind of no limitations no
frustration but in buddhist language that's not real freedom
and so by pausing from the incessant activities of the mind the excessive
activities that we do to pause for a moment provisionally so
we really see what's happening here and let things be and really have a clear deep
or full way of recognizing that what i'm thinking what i'm about to
say what i'm about to do is not really so wise is not really so
healthy is not really so wholesome or skillful helpful
maybe i could not do it or we're sensitive enough to feel and
know oh this is a wholesome thing this is beneficial this is nourishing so the mindfulness
practice has a passivity to it if we're allowed to use that word
of making space and allowing and learning to feel what's moving through us
and then as we live our lives when we have to act that uh then we're informed by a clear
understanding of what is wholesome and unwholesome and the sacred pause of mindfulness the
space that we give to know a tear it gives us the opportunity
to choose between those two the sacred choice and that buddhist
practice is definitely invo involves a degree of living a life of choice
not because we're always busy and always having to analyze and figure out but because we are deeply in touch and
feel and sense and connected to ourselves to recognize what is wholesome and
unwholesome what is helpful and not helpful healthy and not healthy
and it becomes easier and easier more natural and easeful to go in the direction of
health to go in the direction of the wholesome that which is nourishing for us
it's almost like with time it's like a ball let loose on a hill will roll
downhill over time we will keep moving into what's wholesome
because that's what our heart our inner system that's the directionality that's the way it's leaning so it's not like being
really busy and making all these choices all the time but it's placing us and
putting us in the place of cho where choice can happen and sometimes we make a conscious choice
and sometimes we can feel the wholesomeness within us is choosing this is what's good this is
what's helpful and and that becomes our refuge
because when we do what's wholesome what is uh kind of synonyms in buddhism
for wholesome is what's beautiful another synonym is the dharma
what is dharmic and the the word dharma here in this context means that which if you look in the
dictionaries english diction english poly dictionaries the english definition is what is
morally good and uh what has what is connected to a good
quality a good way of inner way of being a goodness to it
and so to when we choose that when we go in that
direction of the good of the of the healthy of the beautiful
that has a that supports us that leads us ten leads us to a grow
inner growth of what's healthy and wholesome it creates conditions that support the
best in us to come forward and to live it creates conditions for discovering
greater and greater freedom and peace and love and compassion and it
tends to support uh reciprocity reproductive
okay i can't say it today a way in which uh the world reciprocates
and uh the um not that automatically or absolutely
reciprocates but the world tends to respond to wholesomeness and goodness
with the same we become the world becomes more and more of a refuge in a
place of goodness for us when we enter the world in that way
so the buddha said our actions are our refuge that they're so important to pay
attention to and as i said the buddha was in addition to being a
teacher of freedom he was a teacher of action and for the
buddha those two are closely connected that the actions which are wholesome and
nourishing are also the ones that create that lead us to the freedom that he was talking about
that support it so we have actions as our refuge as well
so one of the deep principles of buddhism early buddhism is
be a caretaker of your actions be a carer a lover of your actions in
the sense that if you really love something you want to do it the best possible way
and so you might consider for these next
24 hours how is it that action how do you know how do you recognize how
actions your behavior what you do can be a refuge for you a support for
you a protection for you a guide for you a place of insight and
deep understanding you have actions as your refuge
thank you