so welcome everyone and wonderful to have you here
and more people are coming so but i wanted to uh before uh
so welcome this is what i have to deal with regularly
forgetting to turn the sound off so um in a
in a few minutes uh you know we'll turn the recording on
and uh to record it but also i just wanted to make a few announcements before we start
and uh both for all of you here and also for the people who are on youtube
it feels like the sunday morning community has now expanded dramatically
because of the pandemic and the youtube and so
but how to integrate these two is not so obvious to me uh with the
pandemic it became clear that it would be useful to with online to do a lot of these guided
meditations to have a connection and to everyone in support and
but before the pandemic we used to come sunday morning and sit in silence there was no guided meditation
so now that people are coming back in person again what do we do and we still have this online we still
have the online community who's participating in music maybe extremely expecting
uh the don't guided meditation and so how do we do this so i i don't have
an answer but uh but it'll be what it is as we as it unfolds
and uh and also uh we still have a mask mandate here in san mateo county when people gather and
maybe even after the mandate's gone for a while we want to be careful with this so the people on
youtube you know will be seeing me with the mask on but uh to my our surprise i think the
quality of the sound is okay going through the mask is that right for the people here we tested it last week and the consensus
of the few people are here right kevin was that i actually sounded better [Laughter]
so um so
so i think uh as introductory words
and uh then i used to have i still have a laptop here but i used to
i used to have a big 27-inch monitor here so i could kind of be a little bit track the chats and all that but
i don't have the monitor anymore now but i have my laptop in front of me so
and people online are saying yes it sounds good it's fine with them that's good to hear
maybe the mask will never go off and uh
so okay so
yes oh let me do it today and then we'll
see what happens next time so why don't
you can start recording and then we turn it off before the you know the audio recording
at the end of the sitting so then i can offer everyone a little
bit more formal or welcome so those of you here thank you for
coming i don't know if it took a little bit of bravery to come but if it's not not so
much and uh it's wonderful to have you and uh and having
you know it's limited numbers coming and i see you all as representing them with the wider community for who you are so
maybe you just think you're coming as yourself but in my eyes you come as a representative of a community that's
actually grown in a sense this large number of people have been watching
online is part of our community now it's expanded and so i appreciate those of you who are online that you're here and
hopefully the transition to being or doing live is harmonious enough for you and
for the online people and and maybe you'll you'll consider that the people are here it's about 25 people here
that they are kind of representing you as well just a
sense of that there are embodied people out there in this world after all
and here you are so thank you for coming so
we'll meditate and uh so
if you would give some love and care
to your meditation posture and then loving care is not
only to be comfortable but there's something about love or care
that you want to sit in such a way that there's a potential for a greater aliveness
greater attentiveness that's embodied
and so for some people that means sitting up a teeny bit straighter than you normally would
and uh maybe sitting up a little bit more and
so that uh the chest can be a little bit more open
and so if you take a few deep breaths there's more room in the chest
for the lungs to expand and so
to take a few long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale to settle in to relax
and part of the function of attention to posture
attention to deeper breathing is
is to connect to the embodied aspect of mindfulness
sometimes i wish we had translated the word sati not as mindfulness prioritizing the mind
but to body fullness and so to whatever degree that's
available to you to
spend a few moments here becoming embodied connected to your body
and then gently letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhales continue this process of embodiment
by relaxing into your body and letting your body relax into itself
you can soften and relax the face
the forehead
around the eyes and jaw
okay
exhaling and relaxing the shoulders
laying the shoulders settle back into the body
rather than maybe being lifted
and when you relax and soften your belly
maybe feeling the weight of your body settling into the pull of gravity
settling your body your with your belly more deeply into the
bottom of your torso
and one way that people become disembodied
is through a lot of thinking but a lot of thinking often has an
embodied equality there can be physical tension or
pressure agitation associated with that thinking
it might be on the forehead in the brain
sometimes in the jaws or the shoulders even the hands sometimes it can be slightly tense
and if you're able to recognize the physical
effect of thinking a lot
perhaps on the exhale you can relax
that tension pressure
in a sense relaxing
and one more time kind of coming back into your body and more fully
and then keeping a tether of attention
a connection to the physicality of the body
breathing a gentle connection to how the body experiences breathing
and as long as you can stay connected to the physicality of breathing the movements of the breath
maybe you don't have to worry so much about what thinking you have especially the thinking is in the
background and not interfering and if thinking does interfere
maybe relaxing the thinking muscle
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to mention that i find sometimes that meditation feels like being turned
inside out sometimes to a minor degree sometimes to
a great degree that as we
become more settled here in our bodies in our experience
with maybe a kind of inner stability or calm
sometimes there can be a greater sensitivity
so then when we turn our attention outwards towards the world
we feel and sense or perceive that world in it
with that deeper sensitivity
and hopefully with a deeper stability openness
and as we get turned inside out and we turn our
sensitivity our calm our stability
to bring to mind the people in our lives
in our neighborhoods in our communities across the lands
and if there's no obligation to be caring for them or be compassionate
is there some kind of care good will
however small that flows from that inner sensitivity
when we perceive people from a place of stability and column
and if there is some good will some care
that seems to flow from the embodiment or the calmness or the
subtleness perhaps these following words
can help you feel more connected to it
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may acting on this care for others
contribute to your own freedom and happiness
may you care for the world and for others in a way that
cultivates well-being welfare and freedom
for yourself may all of us contribute to each other's
happiness and freedom
uh
so hello everyone and welcome
so this is the first hybrid dharma talk here at imc
so with some of you here about 25 of you here today thank you for coming
and for the people online thank you for being here appreciate it very much
and uh we're still in this our county has a
mask mandate and also out of caution so we're even giving the talk will be with a mask
and uh i find it kind of cozy to meditate with the mask on actually
i keep my mouth slightly open and uh the humidity of my my
feels kind of cozy for me and uh so anyway each person has unique
response to this mask thing and meditating with it
and uh so um
so the whole so we're beginning to shift here and hopefully this shift in this direction
will continue and we'll slowly open up more and more and here at imc and
offer start offering some of the programs we offered before and new programs and
so the
but for those of you online it means that some of the format will shift probably a little bit
and uh we'll see how much guided meditation i do it used to be before the pandemic that
we didn't do it sunday morning and now um so we'll see if how we continue or don't
continue with it and then uh the other thing is that um
i felt like during the it was all on zoom or on youtube it felt
too long to speak for the full time we used to do sunday morning i felt like
just i felt more appropriate to talk less and so it was a half an hour on sunday and but the old format was uh closer to
45 minutes or 40 minutes or something it was more variable we we were scheduled to go until 10 45 so
for those of you who are on youtube uh that'll that'll shift we'll go back to the 10 45 ending and whether the talk
will be that long or not or whether we talk for a shorter time and have a question period for q a and
it's variable depending on the situation so for today um the talk i want to give
i i want to do i'll tell you what i'm going to try to do
uh i want to first recite a four line verse that captures what the buddha
had to teach in a nutshell and that kind of sets the stage for the
talk and then i want to kind of uh just name
this whole period from march 7th or something like that until now that we've been closed
uh and what a big impact it's been in our for individuals for our society and
and here we're coming together after we've all been through this thing that people will be talking about for decades
you know what were you doing back then it was like when i was young younger people who
said where were you when john f k died when he was killed john f kennedy
and people would you know talk about oh i was there you know or 9 or 9 11. where were you what
happened then people were talking about what were you doing during that pandemic and it'll be kind of like a reference point
and then um i want to talk a little bit about one of the little
subsections of our society a big subsection of society that had its own impact around the pandemic
but which is the medical field but but in particular i'm inspired by medical
ethics and uh the kind of the what we can maybe uh tap into and learn from that as
buddhist practitioners and and also as we open imc about how we can be as a
community perhaps that uh would give us kind of a different orientation for how maybe
we can be as new opportunities opening up to kind of open up in a fresh way a new way with new perspective and so i
wanted to borrow from that medical ethics and see if we can maybe get a different angle on what we're
doing here and then at this time try to then apply that also to our practice
and into imc so that's kind of the plan
so um that so the verse uh is uh
is kind of significant because it the last verse the last line
says this is the teaching of the buddhas so it's something plural in buddha's you
know some idea that this buddha has been buddhas for you know periodically down through the
eons the buddhas appear in the cosmos in buddhist cosmology
but they all have this teaching and it's kind of so the teaching is
don't do any harm very simply it's not quite literally exactly right but it's close enough for now
don't do any harm do things which are wholesome
purify the mind this is the teachings of the buddha that's it you should memorize that
don't do any harm do what's wholesome purify the mind
and this is the teachings of the buddha if you want you can forget about memorizing the last line
and so that's kind of kind of the background for with this today
and uh you know i think that uh we shouldn't underestimate
how big this whole pandemic time has been and continues to be
for probably all of us some of us have been in more fortunate circumstances during this time
and some people have not and but even the people unfortunate circumstances i think it's probably a
much bigger impact on the psyche on the heart than most of us can realize
and if you have been impacted by it in all kinds of ways uh you should probably also assume it's probably bigger impact than you actually
realize uh at this point that um you know it's uh remarkable to
me that just in the united states um one and five hundred no it's all right
i think it's one in five hundred americans have died from covet
it's uh quite something it's quite a large amount of people
700 000 people and the
in the world it's almost 5 million people have died and that's just the people who've died
and there you know there's a ripple effect those people who lost someone if you didn't lose someone you loved and
cared for and probably you know someone who has and you know it's not so far steps away
and then there's other effects of uh the pandemic that you know you know ripple out that have been difficult you
shouldn't there was a health we certainly just covet has been hard for people who didn't die
and uh and then there's uh but there's all kinds of other things you know like i had several family members in
hospitals were different not for covid during this time and it was hard to have them in
hospitals or because you couldn't visit sometimes and then there was kind of certain kind
of fear around like what does it mean to be in hospital this time just around this time especially
before the vaccine came out and uh and then not not going to the
doctors or not having access to the doctors and uh i had to have a tooth extracted
and it turned out it was hard to find as someone who would do it because everyone had put off i did i put it put off for
things right all these people put off things and so then finally when i got around to it everyone
had was getting back in the summer and uh doing things so
this has been the biggest recession in the united states since 1930s
so the people economically have been impacted huge people have lost their jobs and
some people their homes and all kinds of things so just the pandemic's been huge and
then in addition to that maybe and kind of compounded by it the tension of it all
is some of the social challenges of the of these last years
the you know the the you know the tremendous focus on racism and the pain of that and
the disparities that exist in this country that have become more and more evident
the tension between different political factions has gone up much more dramatically and so much has been
politicized in the way that maybe it was never before and so regardless of what side of a
political divide we sit on we feel the tension and the challenge of it
and then there's uh here at california and other places all these fires like fire after fire after
fire and um and uh it's quite impressive
and other places there's floods and hurricanes and all these challenges and
and then just a challenge of some getting getting supplies supply chains being disrupted and you know and like
what does that mean we can't get the things we usually want and there was a time
pandemic that was kind of some people are kind of frightened about getting just basic goods
and uh so these these are all challenging times and one of the places those challenges were huge was in the
medical field before the vaccine hospitals and
even after the vaccine it's been quite challenging and there was a time 100 you know 100 years ago
a year ago that feels like a long time when there was a real emphasis on
medical workers being heroes superheroes
you know and i think they deserve that name because it was quite a dedication to show up at the hospital and work
before the vaccine for example just do what it took to try to meet the people who came who were dying and very sick
and offer the best care they could and and now uh in some places in the country
they're still doing that and they're surges but now they're also they're dealing with hostility
from people who don't believe in vaccinations or don't believe in the medical establishment field feel
excluded or feel criticized or feel somehow they're going to be abandoned by it and so they're angry
and one friend of mine who works in a hospital in in some
senator that to go to work just to go through uh protests outside the hospital and these are people people who hate to
hate us we're just going to try to save lives and we're hated for what we're doing
so so there's you know so and some of them say i've read that some of them will take off their uniform and
their badge when they go shopping in a grocery store in some communities because if they're seen as a medical worker
people express hostility to them so that makes it the job of you know
offering medical care much more difficult when you you know they were heroes a year ago now in some
communities they're the opposite so the with medical i've i've been i've
had some conversations with people and i'm on an ethics committee for a local hospital so
i hear a little bit of this as well and um and one of the things that inspires me
is how often the medical people i've talked to evoke medical ethics
um and um and one way they they've talked about it is uh
they're they're commit they're committed to care for anyone who comes in through the door
to the emergency and anybody who comes they're going to offer the best care they can and they're committed to that to offer
equal care and one of the people said explicitly it means that if someone has been a
rapist or had murdered someone our job is to offer the best care we can we don't turn
anyone away we know everyone's treated equally um whether they're vaccinated or not
vaccinated we're committed to caring for them best we can it's not our our job to distinguish who should get or we
should not be getting care and uh and this kind of is complete
willingness and or willing a commitment to just be available for everyone equally and
and to care in these challenging circumstances i think is quite inspiring to me
so in the field of medical ethics there are four principles
for medical care and they have kind of latinish kind of
big name words in that field i'll tell you kind of the big words
and they are because medical folks will will use these big words because it's part of
their understanding so the first is autonomy
the second is beneficence the third is non-maleficence
and the fourth is justice and uh autonomy means as we in that kind
of setting as i understand it refers to the idea that um every patient
uh has the right to make their own decisions unless they have something like dementia
or something they can't but uh
and then there's a you know if someone can't make a decision for themselves it usually evokes often invokes the ethics
committee the hospital to really consider is that really the case and make sure that it's not the whim of someone who
that's really really caring for that sense of autonomy that people have
and uh and uh so that's kind of a fundamental value at least in this country around around
medical ethics and then beneficence means that the dedication is
to do what's uh beneficial for the patient for the person there whatever is beneficial to support them and help them
and is it does it help the persons that benefit the person non-maleficence means do no harm
and occasionally there's a conflict between those two and so you know then sometimes the
medical ethics committee is brought in to discuss that or we have to say you know
what to do if there seems to be a conflict and then uh and then justice in this
context seems to mean that a fair use everything's offered fairly to everyone
it's a fair access to the medicines procedures everything in the
hospital especially is offered equally to everyone with no distinction between
any kind of you know economic status you know any any kind of distinction
race whatever everyone is treated equally and so that's sometimes a challenge
because sometimes there's limited resources in hospital and so um and so how do how does it
limited resources distributed in a fair way to everyone and so again sometimes
the ethics people in hospital have to come in and really kind of consider this carefully and
figure out how do we do this and this became particularly important during the cove at times
when hospitals reach their you know beyond their peak limit and how do you do they had triage kind
of situation set up because they had to figure out how to do this as
far as fairly as they could but they couldn't do everyone because it was impossible and so how do you make this
decision so uh so it's it's a little similar to that
buddhist verse do no harm the non-maleficence
the buddhist thing is do what's wholesome which can be considered what's beneficial
do what's skillful what's useful helpful and uh
but the uh the two things which are not you know in that verse the same way is this idea
of autonomy and justice and and
i find that you know this idea of and you know one of the challenges around autonomy especially if we take it
outside of the hospital setting to grant everyone in the autonomy it's it lends itself or can be very supportive of a
certain kind of selfishness and uh whatever i want i'm supposed to be autonomous and i can get what i want
i want what i want and and there's a lot of selfishness a lot of self-centeredness
but some of that autonomy and some of that insistence on being able to make choices for oneself is also very healthy and
appropriate and how do we distinguish between that and find our way with it
and uh i don't have a good answer in the abstract but i think that that's one of the advantages of embodied mindfulness a
really careful and settled attention is that we can start feeling very very carefully
what is beneficial and what is harmful what promotes stress
and attention and and undermines our well-being
and what promotes it and it turns out that selfishness undermines our well-being if you're
really attentive you can feel that a healthy sense of autonomy healthy sense of self
you can fee you can feel and sense the difference and what that when it feels right and the greater the mindfulness the more
settled and focused we are in meditation i think that it's remarkable how the better and greater reference point we
have for for finding the difference between these two modes of being
and so and so eventually in meditation the
sense of autonomy becomes more and more interesting because in the end
it's not that we become autonomous but that like i look how i'm autonomous person
i'm going to be my own person in a sense but rather it's the awareness
that becomes autonomous it's awareness set free
and sometimes they talk about in buddhism the mind set free the mind liberated from
through my the mind liberated through non-clinging but i like to think that what exactly
the mind is is a little complicated but i have this clear clear idea that if we
understand it to be awareness that we're saying awareness is becoming autonomous
and what's it becoming autonomous from it's becoming autonomous from ourselves
any kind of baggage of self any kind of association beliefs we have about it
so i give you an example from myself is that at some point
in my practice i recognize that that i could be aware of things i could be
mindful and be present but i recognized that that mindfulness came along
with um an attitude like with baggage of kind of it kind of penetrated or
kind of suffused the awareness itself and that was something like um
whatever i'm whatever i'm doing whatever i'm aware of it's the wrong thing
well i if i'm if it's happening to me it's not the right thing
if it's um if i'm being aware i'm not aware the right way
so so uh and it was kind of subtle but it was kind of like a policy that
mind had made up and so and so as i got quieter and quieter at
some point i could see that that i was operating through this filter of that all the time
and it kept my awareness my mindfulness a little tense a little
pulled back from the experience and and so as i started feeling being this
pulled backness this tense tension and how the awareness is and the kind of contraction around it
that had to do with this kind of view then i was able to relax that
and for a short time i actually played around with kind of just assuming the opposite
you know if it's happening to me it's okay if i'm aware i'm doing it just right
and that was actually useful for a little while to have that kind of try the opposite because it helped help me
stay free help me find a different way and then at some point at some point
they started to stop doing that and it was easier me to have this kind of awareness than be autonomous
independent from this policy these ideas this baggage i had about what i needed
to do what was happening to me my judgments about things and so it became the awareness started
to become simpler and simpler and this idea of awareness becoming simpler without any baggage associations
judgments even a sense of self that came along i'm the doer of mindfulness was part of the
wonderfulness of this kind of awareness set free so
so you know to have the awareness be autonomous is uh
kind of comes along with this liberation process in buddhism
but the fourth medical principle of uh justice is a and fairness
how does that play out in buddhism and i think that's one of the ones i think
our society has maybe the greatest need for is uh as a society community
is a community a society that's fair that somehow everyone seems to have a
fair access to to the opportunities that
many times only the people who are very fortunate circumstance has available to it
and how does imc offer itself fairly to the world how do we make we give access to a wide
circle of people so that it feels like we're just open and available and
and uh and how do we if we turn imc inside out if we turn
ourselves inside out as i said in the meditation is that as we settle and as a today so
awareness is set free it's also setting the heart free it's also this great deeper sensitivity
as we go down to out into the world and it doesn't make sense to meditate
be subtle and peaceful and calm and be kind of open and sensitive to what's happening
and then leave the meditation and immediately shut down immediately kind of get caught up in our
desires and our business of stuff and and kind of then have a barrier to
really block to really feel and sense and be and care for this world around us
and it doesn't make sense because it's a way of not caring for ourselves when we when we shut down we close up we
get so preoccupied and caught up in our thoughts our feelings our concerns our business
we lose something about ourselves and this is something also that can be felt if you're mindful
but sometimes we're so distracted we don't know that we're distracted but if the mindfulness becomes second
habit second nature and you're really sensitive and aware you feel that as we get caught up in
distractions uh it actually is a kind of
kind of harm a kind of self limiting there's kind of a undermining of ourselves of something
that we discover in meditation perhaps or in other ways that feel so healthy and so appropriate and so wise
to be settled and peaceful and present and so even though social world is a
complex and difficult world part of the task of mindfulness practice is to learn how to bring this kind of
presence and attention open-heartedness perhaps into the world with others as well
and so to turn ourselves inside out so the part of that sensitive to us like
like if we go walk around with a closed fist the most sensitive part of the hand is protected
that's very nice no one's going to harm my sensitive hand ever again because i'm going to walk
around this way but that doesn't make sense right and but you want that sensitive part of your
hand to be available you know if you have a cat you want us or if you want to touch the shoulder or
someone who feels kind of has in difficulty in their lives and just i'm here with you and
or hold the hand of someone you care maybe care for like a little maybe there's a
little kid in your life and so the kid wants to hold your hand no sorry i'm keeping my sensitive part of my my
hand you know safe no but you know so you're available for all kinds of things so the same thing
with the heart with the inner life if we keep it closed up
then we limit ourselves but if we turn ourselves inside out like the hand turns itself opens up
but then we learn how to be stable we learn how to not contract
we learn how to take care of ourselves from that place we learn how to
recognize all the subtle policies and attitudes that we have brought with us
to being aware to being attentive and we realized i mean there's a lot of
reactivity beliefs judgments that are sometimes quite subtle
that in ordinary life most people don't see because they're so busy with
you know too busy with doing things but the advantage of getting quiet and still in meditation
is we can start seeing these subtle ways things attitudes we bring along that
often don't make us safe this lack of safety that many people
feel some of it's real the world's an unsafe place but for many people also
the greatest danger for our safety is not the other people but ourselves
and so to understand how we bring our safety with us not insisting that the
world become a safe place for us which is a little bit of a difficult
you know a little bit complicated issue but sometimes we become less self the less less safe if
we insist that other people make us safer but how do we carry our safety with us
how do we discover that it's a challenging thing not easy but it's uh boy is it a powerful thing
to discover that and then it's easier to be open-hearted it's easier to have this keep our our
sensitivity open and allow other to allow ourselves to be to register
the presence of other people the existence of other people and let it register in that place within
where we care uh where there's good will where there's
generosity and but not in a way that we're obligated to care not in a way that
we're obligated to be generous or have good will because i think that doesn't work so
well what's phenomenal and kind of a miracle is the degree to which sometimes we can
feel that it's just a it's part of our nature to have good will it's part of a natural
kind of flow or natural responsibility to feel warmth to feel care to feel good
will and uh and to stay close to the close to that place
where that it just seems to flow it arises and
in a non-obligatory way and one reason to stay close to it
is that um the that's where the freedom is
that's where this uh autonomy is found the autonomy of
awareness set free the mind set free and you you kind of can't have it both
ways you can't discover this radical liberation this radical autonomy that
liberate that mindfulness brings about and stay closed and shut out
and be distracted from being sensitive to this world and so
how do you know but to how to discover to do both you know that's the art of buddhist
practice and and then
and if we're sensitive if we have this open-heartedness then i think it's easier
to figure out justice to want justice for each other to want
to be fair and how we use our resources and our activities and not just live for ourselves
but to live for ourselves and for others and this is uh
one of the central principles i believe that the buddha taught
that to live our lives for the welfare of our self
the welfare of others the welfare of self and others and the welfare for the whole world
this the buddha defined a wise person as someone who has those four concerns
concerned for the welfare of themselves for others for self and others and for the whole world
and and it can seem like a big heavy thing to be told that like i got to get busy
now that's a lot to do but again it's coming from that place
of freedom it's coming from the place of autonomy of of subtleness that we did hopefully discover through this practice
so it's not a duty it's not work it just seems to be an expression natural expression of what's already in
there when it's been set free when what's here
and um and certainly that's uh it was a big surprise to me when after some years
of my practice in my early years when um uh
there was more integrity in this psychophysical system that i am
when i wasn't self-preoccupied it was more integrity when i was just
available or the system was available to be responsive to the world around me
and then and that response that seemed to just arise to surface uh kind of effortlessly
and then to act on that to live live live from that
so what does it mean for us as a community in uh imc as a community and now is
a much larger community than we were before the pandemic with all the people online what does it mean not as
individuals but we also come together in community it's kind of special to be here
those of us are here in person and it's been special the sense of community that's formed
on youtube over this time and uh so what does it mean that that's the
uh when the buddha said the wise person thinks about the welfare of self welfare of others and the welfare of
self and others the self and others i see to be i can i think of as the we the
community that we are and and how do we care for this community and how do we live as a community and
care for each other and uh and how is a community
uh do we turn ourselves inside out and so our community sensitivity is
is also out into the wider world and uh caring for this wider world that
we live in wider community so how does um
how does it look and uh for us to have these four principles
available for you know the foundation of our community of autonomy and all the different things it might
mean non-harming
be dedicated to do what's beneficial to welfare for all involved
and justice fairness and how do what does that mean and what does it mean in a social way and for the
wider communities that we're part of and what does it mean like we're here in redwood city
what does it mean to be part of this redwood city community san mateo community california community
is the what what kind of issues comes up when we think about fairness or justice
as an expression of who we are as a concern or that we have and carry with us
i don't have good answers for that but i would like to believe that asking that
question is part of this natural expression of this autonomy this place of subtleness
of being turned inside out by this practice
so here we are uh
in person here we're still very much evidence of living in the pandemic times
all of us are wearing masks and but we've come together
in a community in a way that for some of you perhaps this is the most number of people you've been together with in this
kind of way maybe for a year and a half um i think the
i've been in one group that was maybe a little bit bigger than this in august but that was only a couple of
months ago right and uh you know there are months i hardly had any any contact direct
contact with people outside my family and uh so it's a big deal and here we
are coming and i want to mark this time we're coming together in community and
and imc as a as a connected community is grows
because of this and uh you're contributing to not just being here
and you're connected you're contributing to that not just for those of you here but i think it's also a sense that
people are not here i kind of are now feeling that something is becoming
embodied or something is growing again that has not been happening for many months
and so in what way can we be mindful of community and what's happening in
community is uh one of the you know one of the
i think interesting and important questions at this time so that's what i have to say
and uh any of you would like to say anything that uh we have about six minutes or so
and uh anything that you'd like to ask or bring up or say and there's two ways
of you can do it you could or three ways you can try to speak loud but then i won't be heard by
the people on on youtube there's a mic here we can pass to you or
if you wanted to have the minimum physical contact the mic that's on the stand back there um oh you know you you stand hold it the
mic is held by the stand all you do is push the button on and once it's on it can stay on
so i don't know if anybody would like to say anything or ask something
there's some very nice expressions of gratitude and warmth coming from the youtube community
that's a bill do you mind using that
i want to say how helpful it is for me to be back here past year and a half my
discipline when it comes to meditating at home
as cratered and my life is good but my mind you know
state of mind isn't as a quantum economist as it could have been uh i seem to need to uh have this
structured setting great yeah i mean the community makes a big difference and just be honest so uh lovely to be back
here thank you great great to see you and have you back thank you so harry richard there
hi richard so uh my experience has actually been somewhat different
i had kind of wandered away from the community because you had moved one direction i had moved away and it's a
little farther to get here and when i found out that the daily sessions were online i began
started my practice again and it actually has helped me tremendously and i've really enjoyed
being part of the larger saga nonetheless it is still wonderful to be
back in person and this is very important and i think i'm going to renew my
intention to connect more more often in person
wonderful but thank you very much for creating the the larger song as well and
i certainly hope that that will continue great thank you and then someone over here i saw and then
molly yeah i just wanted to say gil that um
that has been a pretty easy time for me i think it sounds strange but cheryl and i live in a senior retirement community
of about 200 people and of course we had you know isolation and all that kind of stuff and now we're able to get together
in the dining room but what i want what i really noticed was how helpful
my 50 years of meditation has been and 25 with you in this community it's made
a very big difference and helped me to stay pretty equanimous and and that being said there are times
when i've lost it from time to time glancing at my wife for the youtube yes that that that's
occurred but you know i feel like this is this has been um uh a learning and growing experience for
me great thank you and i appreciate your help in that thank you yeah i think we would expect some testimonials that
50 years of practice you know even two years would do it though i
remember the first five years i'm thinking wow my life is things are falling in place and and i think that my
just my mindfulness and one of my early teachers said that it turns up the volume on your intuition nice and i
think that was true for me so maybe
thank you sure um when you announced that you were going to be opening the center i felt a
little bit closer oh when you announced that you were going to be having sessions we could sign up uh once a month or whatever
i felt extremely privileged because i know that there are hundreds if not thousands of people on
the internet that would just give anything to be able to come here and
experience this and to live here and i've always felt very welcomed and
one of the things that you said today struck me um when when there have been really
difficult circumstances in my life at one point before coming here
i felt like i was coming out of my skin and it was a terrible terrible feeling
and then after coming here the message that you gave today was
that you i think it was something to the effect that you're turned uh your insides are turned inside out
and you feel comfortable and it's just a wonderful way to be in the world
and i want to thank you for all of your support fantastic thank you
i also feel so lucky to be here and privileged
i'm also really appreciate your asking the question you did at the end of the talk
uh and it seems to me maybe you use this phrase yourself but it's asking how this community can turn inside out
and we were at a memorial service yesterday at a christian church very activist christian church
and the talk that was given was very moving and the kind of moving of talk that throughout my life would have had
me go right onto the streets in march protest and i had really mixed feelings because
i thought how it was very lovingly given but how that's dicey stuff when you
have that kind of great passion and how and it's harder
in a buddhist perspective to have the equanimity and yet to act so i
really appreciate your ending with that that very hard question i don't have any answers
thank you great thank you right behind you there
um i just want to say you know thank you for you and the bigger community which helped me get
through not just last year but many years and unfortunately i lost my father
earlier this year to go with and being in a different continent i couldn't even go
but i think what kept me was your meditation and and a lot of the teachings i would go and listen to some
of the you know the talks you had in in those like grief or those kind of um
context so i think all i want to say is it's been thankful to be
even though remote but i never felt you know i was remote because you know i would listen to them all all the time
and the meditation every day i think kept me going so honestly thank you thank you so much i love hearing that
so maybe maybe that's it for anyone no no you want to say something
animals yeah yeah i also want to give voice to the
people who have during this pandemic not have had the ecs experience
and i will never it's only the privileged only they're privileged to have had this
experience i remember a gentleman from india being interviewed
during the pandemic and he was asked was he worried about covet
and this is unforgettable he said are you kidding me i'm worried about my next meal
yeah so only the privileged i think can share this kind of sentiment
yeah and um and so how to hold that
yeah great yes thank you that punctuates very much very nicely
how do we live in this world in community with each other what does it mean to feel community with
everyone and how do we know the whole range of
joys and gifts and challenges and sufferings that this community hawaii
community we live in has and how do we share with that how do we
connect to it how do we know it and how do we contribute the welfare of everyone
a wise person is concerned with the welfare of them of
themselves welfare of others welfare of self and others and the
welfare of the whole world may we all become wise
so thank you very much