so uh warm greetings to everyone and uh
feels feels wonderful that we're gathering here for our meditation
together and just saw a message from
i think one of our members is having heart surgery today and uh jay so we wish jay well
and hope that that all goes well and um
so uh we sit here
holding all of ourselves everyone in our hearts including those going to surgery and having challenges
today of all kinds and
perhaps it's a
this final step of mindfulness of breathing
is very closely associated with generosity and i'll talk more about it during the
talk but the
when we remove an obstruction for someone like say we open a door someone who
can't do it themselves and remove that obstruction just that opening a door
is an act of generosity if someone has a
splinter in their foot and they can't get it out themselves it's an act of generosity to
get some tweezers and and remove the splinter and so
the removal the letting go the stepping away from
those movements of the mind which don't serve us can be seen as an act of generosity
not as a indication that aversion or pushing things away or
or or some negative thing about anything in a sense
but rather it's just such a healthy thing to remove the splinters of our life
to move the ways that we um you know harm ourselves and we have a
clearer sense of that harm even the subtlest forms the more
settled and peaceful we become in meditation the more meditation feels
a place of freedom and love and peace integrity wholeness
the more quiet and still the thinking mind becomes
the more um we recognize movements of generosity
we move we recognize the splinters that we can take out and letting go of thoughts doesn't so much
come from aversion but comes from of course let me help out here let me let go of
these thoughts these ideas when we get contracted or caught in
desires and aversions of course here it's a generous thing to
do it's not doesn't have to be done with the obligation to let go it doesn't have to be done with
hostility towards what we're letting go of any more than opening the door
are we hostile to the door or pulling out a splinter we're hostile to the splinter
rather it's an act of generosity so to sit today
maybe with a spirit of generosity
and so to begin with a posture posture itself the care we put into our
posture maybe rocking around swaying a little bit making small adjustments
can be seen as the beginning of meditative
generosity as we give attention
to our body to ourselves
and we might take a few long slow deep
breaths and as we settle in maybe
even it's a giving in a generosity of
letting go of tension and letting ourselves
give ourselves the goodness of being stable and settled here
and with a feeling of generosity of care of goodwill towards oneself
tenderly maybe as you exhale relax the body
perhaps softening in the belly
perhaps softening and relaxing the belly with a reminder to the belly
it's okay
as you exhale relaxing in the heart a generous feeling even if the heart
aches or is challenged in some way to hold it
with a generosity good will compassion and allowing the chest and
the heart to settle and relax
relaxing the shoulders maybe even moving the hands a little bit
if it frees up the shoulders and the elbows a little bit
and as an act of generosity to your face which has muscles which are in working
for us all day long one way or the other those
muscle little muscles are expressing themselves and generously
give those muscles a chance to rest thank you for your service and now
you can rest relaxing the face
then offering your attention to the
breathing
as if attention is a gift a precious gift that's worth giving
giving over to the breathing
as if the body breathing
loves the gift of attention
and if you notice you notice yourself thinking caught up caught up in thought lost in
thought see it as an occasion to be
generous to give up your thinking
to let it go so that you can return to
a way of being that's more intimate more connected here and now
a way of being present it is more satisfying than being lost
caught up in thoughts
generously returning yourself to yourself
in the letting go of thoughts opening the doors of the heart and the mind
pulling out the splinters in the heart
so as we sit here today if it can help you become quieter and
more focused more present
you might practice giving away your thoughts giving up
letting go releasing
relinquishing all as movements of generosity
generosity perhaps associated with a deep quiet place
inside of you
let go of your thinking generously
in that in letting go of them you can [Music] return
to some intimacy and peace some sense of stillness here
that's better than being lost in thought
giving yourself the gift of that better
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
if it is in fact a form of generosity to
give yourself the chance to settle in come to a place here in meditation that
clearly feels like it's for your own welfare and well-being
then i also might consider that this generosity towards yourself
can simultaneously be a generosity for the world
that somehow settling in in such a way the best qualities of who you are
come to the forefront or are not eclipsed
then the world can also benefit from these good qualities of yours
beginning perhaps with generosity being generous to the world around you
not necessarily generous with things but generous with your attention your
heart generously letting go of the
obstructions inside of you from having a clean presence with others
to offer them the best of who you are
and if we offer the best of who we are then we benefit others while we benefit
ourselves we are benefiting ourselves where we benefit others
when we give the best that we have coming from in a good way
then we benefit as well we better benefit further
at the end of a meditation session or a buddhist event there's dedication of
merit and it's understood that if you give away your merit
you produce much more merit for yourself
if you can in a clean appropriate way offer
the best of yourself to others the best in you can grow
may it be that any of the benefits that we receive through this meditation today that we
remove the obstructions from letting that be shared with the world around us
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
so we come in this series of talks to the
consider the final step of anapanasati the 16th step of mindfulness of
breathing and the way it's worded in
english the most common translation into english is something like
observing relinquishment one trains
i will breathe in observing relinquishment
one trains i will breathe out and this word relinquishment
that translates a pali word patini saga
b-a-t-i-n-i-s-s-a-g-g-a that has a double meaning
it means a kind of letting go relinquishment and it also means generosity to give
and in some contexts in the teachings of the buddha it clearly means
being generous and not just that's so nice this passage i'll read it to you
and
so a noble disciple someone who has come now towards the to
the end of this 16 steps
noble disciples recollect consider their own generosity like this
it is truly my good fortune and gain that in a world
of people obsessed with greed i dwell freely generous
open handed delighting in giving devoted to
charity delighting in giving and sharing
and the expression delighting in giving the word giving is the same word as this
final step in anapanasati of relinquishment
so there is a letting go a deep letting go that's
almost an act of choice if
now if you review these last four steps of anapanasati
is that as we settle in having gotten concentrated and quiet and still
then we come to a stage where it just feels the best just to not be
working meditation anymore we don't have to work and we just settle
back and just observe we're observing we're kind of like in the process of life the flow of life and we're just
observing the transiency and the changing nature of moment-to-moment experience
and now there's a fading away of clinging and greed and wanting and that fading away happens up
to the point where the greed and the hatred that we have
seizes and stops and wow to have a qualitatively hike experience
of the stopping of these unhealthy movements of the mind and heart and wow this is good this is
right this is health this is freedom and inner psychological freedom
and and then knowing that seeing that having wisdom about that then
saying i'm i would like to be done with this i no longer want to invest in these
kinds of ways of being i don't no longer believe in them i no longer stand behind
being greedy or hateful or resentful or complaining or jealous or
or you know having any kind of annoyance or hostility that i'm keep getting
living in cynicism and um and uh and not we don't do it
punitively it's not like we feel bad about ourselves but now we know something much better
and so we're letting go of what is unwholesome and and if you look carefully read
carefully the teachings of the buddha he when he talks about what we let go of
he doesn't talk about letting go of things so much hardly at all or if at all like we don't
let go of our material wealth or let go of our friendships our
relationships what we're letting go of what we're relinquishing our inner psychological states
things inside of us and they're clearly the ones that harm us what the buddha calls
unwholesome or unskillful and he says that explicitly in one place
he says
if one if when one gives away something
unwholesome mental qualities grow and wholesome mental qualities waste away
then i say one should not give away in this way and the word giving away here is that
word relinquishment so so the word give
captures the idea that it's an act of generosity and so i'll read it a different way if
one relinquishes anything and then unwholesome mental qualities
grow and wholesome mental qualities waste away then i say
one should not relinquish in this way but if one gives away if one
relinquishes something and unwholesome mental qualities
waste away and wholesome mental qualities grow then i say one should give away one
should relinquish in this way so this is not blind
relinquishment it's not the blind letting go of something just but we hear they're supposed to let go let
go of everything it's really we're letting go of that which
interferes with our betterment interferes with the best qualities we have
we're letting go so that the better qualities of who we are can come forth and we have a much
clearer sense of what those are and what gets in the way what are the obstructions
when we get quiet and peaceful now one of the one most wonderful meditation instructions that i received
many years ago from this wonderful english bhikkhu monk named ajan amaro
and he said something like set yourself at ease and then notice
what takes you away from that and that was the instruction no 16
stages that's so complicated so just recognize to set yourself at ease and i think i
understood that to be whatever modicum of ease that's accessible just if it's the simplest
kind of just softening and relaxing but then the important part the wisdom part is to notice what takes you away
from that and then consider is it really worth it is it really for your betterment to lose
whatever the ease you have it's through that then through then deepening the ease appreciating the ease
deepening that ease deepening these coming to more ease and more ease we get better and better recognition
of the goodness that's here within us to be better recognition of when there's an unwholesome direction
and when there's a wholesome direction that we're going when it's uh for our betterment or for
the opposite and so we come to hear the lasting last stage of anapanasati
um there is a real real deep relinquishment now
where something we're really ready to put something down
and and be done with something enough of this already
and even though we can't necessarily stop certain mental habits that we have or
tendencies we have it's a powerful movement to have made an inner choice
inner turning and say i no longer stand behind this i don't longer believe in this kind of
behavior and we can do that without any aversion
hostility feeling better about ourselves we can do it with joy
delighting in this word relinquishment delighting in it that now i'm going to move in a good
direction just i know there's a better direction and to know that deeply is one of the
great gifts of this practice great gifts of life and uh and to be
inspiring so rather than seeing our four inner foibles and inner you know old habits coming back
and feeling depressed or upset by it there can be a stance a recognition
oh here it is again and now i get to practice this is what this practice i know what
practice is about now the practice i know there's a direction amount of direction
on a movement and a journey to really i know what freedom is i know what this is not where it's at and now i
have an opportunity to practice with this and that is a fortunate thing anyone who
has the practice has good fortune anyone who has a
practice is involved in a path of great goodness and benefit
and so to celebrate and delight in the fact you ever practice more than being upset by the fact that
one more time you got angry or irritated or greedy or something just keep
turning it over to appreciating it and looking for the generosity and the
goodness and the delight in the possibility of on being on a path
of liberation or freedom of letting go
and so no matter where you are on the stages of anapanasati these 16 stages
each step in the way is good for itself is good enough in fact the ancient
commentaries said that each step of the 16 can be a complete step in itself they
they contain within each step contains within itself the path to all 16 or so if you stayed
at the first step of just breathing in long knowing you're breathing in long the other 15 steps kind of will follow
along as you really settle in and just do that one get concentrated doing that
but it doesn't matter just the fact that you're whatever your stage you're at that's the right place for you that's a
good place and that's where your delight and pleasure and joy can be
that uh you're so fortunate you have a path you this is your step now this is your
movement your ability to practice
and the further you go the more you'll understand what's wholesome the more you understand what's wholesome
the more with generosity the lighting and generosity you can give away give up
the unwholesome and i use these words like the give up in the kind of original apparently
meaning of the word which is to offer something up on an altar or the
original meaning of sacrifice to make sacred or
the original word of surrender then the latin i think maybe in the french as well the
roots of the word is to also to to give something
give up so um so that's his uh we've come now to the
end of these 16 steps and this the discourse on anapanasati has
further things to say about this and what is most interesting for me about the next
kind of instructions of this uh six after the 16 steps is how um the fruit of the practice the
liberation of the practice becomes more and more the the basis for the practice and how
liberation becomes a basis for practice is the topic for next week so um
so thank you for all this and um i can take a little bit of time
for taking some questions if you'd like and anything really but if you'd like to ask
me 16 steps or anything about this i will try to do my best to track the
questions if they come
and
any additional advice on how anapanasathi can be
practiced in a relaxed open way without turning it into a linear checklist i'm i'm turning this as i sit
great yeah i think that every meditation practice we do all these funny habits of
the mind will come in and kind of take over and sometimes the practice starts becoming mechanical
sometimes maybe a linear checklist where am i and don't be discouraged by this but
learn to recognize it and then figure out a way to not do it
and um and sometimes i've done some similar things like and i've just kind
of backed off and i just gone back to the very beginning or um just just come back and just not try to
do the practice of an apanasati and just open my awareness and
then my kind of my my my one of my kind of
great default for practicing when you know it seems like nothing's
really working is uh to tell myself the word here h-e-r-e
and just say here and it's uh not a command like to a dog it's just the recognition i'm here and i
say the word and then i open my attention to just recognize what is here
and sometimes what i recognize is my mind is out of control and spinning around oh here this is what it
feels like to have a spinning mind here this is what it's like to be upset
here this is what's like to be agitated and it's a gen there's a
generosity in that here in that in that opening oh this is what it's like
nothing has to be any different it's just a clear recognition of this and i'll do
that for a while and then at some point things settle down or if i got a mechanical or a checklist
approach to practice then i can kind of i've stopped doing it and then i can start fresh again
okay
it's a lot of thank yous i appreciate them it's very nice and
is it to be expected that grief would come with disenchantment ah no it's not to be expected
but it's pretty common and so i think we should just that sometimes when we do this practice
we realize that even when we let go of things we know are unhealthy there can be a grief to for the going
away of something that's been our companion for a long time or or there's a grief around what we lost
because we were caught up so long in some unhealthy way of being and we have to grieve first before we can really
move on there was a psychologist who did a lot of this practice
and his his take on all this is that um
the path to liberation is one continuous process of grieving so it might have been true for him it
hasn't been true for me and but but grief is definitely can be an important part of this whole process
and it's not to be um pushed away or feel like it's
unfortunate to have grieving and i did give a talk last sunday on grief sunday morning talk here so
i talked about liberating grief that might intrigue you if you didn't hear the talk to hear it
the folds and the unfolding yeah
what is the source of the excerpt you read about generosity today it's um
it's a it's a my own translation so it's all i have
here is the reference it's from the numerical discourses of the buddha chapter six um suta number 25.
it's very nice to read all these little comments and thank yous and and
it's really a wonderful thing to share this path and this practice together with all of us here
grief arises in unexpected times yeah for sure
i think some some i've heard teachers say that if you don't if you haven't had a good
cry you're probably not really on the path to liberation
at some point or other it does not all the time but
can you please clarify again the relationship between 16 steps of our practice off the cushion as well as while meditating yeah well
that's a good question i generally don't think about too much
about the 16 steps in daily life i do i spend a lot of time
because i spent you know much of my adult life meditating on my breathing and and it's kind of
been the kind of the foundation of my meditation practice that um it uh it spills over into daily
life where i'm frequently kind of attentive to my breathing or
include my breathing whatever i'm doing and awareness of it and and so it's been a great gift in my
daily life to track and watch my breathing when my breathing gets held or tight or
constricted and how it shifts and changes and sometimes it's the first indication
i have that i've gotten caught or stuck or reactive or hot and something
and so uh just being familiar with the breathing and connected to it and then being able to
come back and and relax their breath and have an ease full breath as i go through my daily life has been beneficial in many
many ways and whether i'm on any particular step of anapanasati in daily life i
don't really think about so much
it's the 16 step open awareness
some people might experience open awareness with the 16 steps but i wouldn't want to identify the two
together because letting go the deepest letting go we do is just a
phenomenal absence and to give it any kind of uh
description that is something even something like open awareness
just little bit diminishes it or misses the point a little bit
oh what is the pali word you said at the beginning meaning generosity so the uh
the word there's uh there's three different pali words that mean both uh letting go
or relinquishment translators often translate all three of them as relinquishment but also mean generosity and
and the one for that that's uh this sixteenth step one of panasati
gga and then there's chaga c long a ga and then there's vosaga
v-o-s-s-a and so it's a wonderful thing you see this that this
is the close association in poly with letting go and generosity
okay so this is wonderful so i need to stop and uh thank you all and and
we'll continue this uh exploration of an apanasati in context
of liberation next week and i look forward to it and and also maybe i mentioned this but
i'm teaching two retreats coming up that are not part of imc it might be interesting for you one is
the uh they kind of actually kind of at the same time some of them so i'll be moonlighting one to the other
uh one is um the san francisco zen center i'm doing a
kind of a interesting dialogue retreat it's not a full retreat but it's um like
all day long but it's a you know a couple hours a few hours a day and on the weeks a few days of the evenings and the weekend
that's um that uh kind of a lot of this dialogue between uh two of the senior teachers at san
francisco zen center myself on the harmony of vipassana and zen
and that starts on 19th of april and it'll be folded into the 7 a.m sittings
so um i'll do the first week and then paul heller and fou schrader will
do the other two weeks instead of me teaching this seven a.m
so you get a taste of the retreat just by coming here at seven a.m and the other is uh i'm teaching a
retreat at spirit rock online for for six days
starting april 25th and and that should be a quite a lovely
retreat and i love these online retreats and
so okay thank you