good evening good evening it's a pleasure to be here with
you all this evening or maybe it's not evening where you are maybe you're listening to this or
watching this sometime later whenever it might be welcome
welcome so we'll just do a little bit lightly guided guided
meditation taking our meditation
posture a posture that
reflects Our intention of settling
in and being up ight these two different
movements be finding a balance
between some ease and some comfort and some alertness
maybe there's some wiggling that happens as we find our
seat and just allowing the mind and the body
to arrive here the body is here
but sometimes the mind is
elsewhere it can be helpful to feel
connected to this experience
feeling the pressure of the cushion or chair
bench couch bed against the body
and feeling any uprightness that is if you're in a
meditation posture feeling the pressure of the chair cushion but also the spine
being upright the head being over the
shoulders
we might notice that the body is breathing
there's a certain
Rhythm to the movement of the chest or the
belly certain Rhythm to the air going in and out of
the nose
what is it like to connect with that
Rhythm the expansion over the chest or belly
and and then the whatever is the opposite of expansion the shrinking
the
nonexpansion stretching and then the non
stretching for
we might notice that the breath is long and
slow or maybe it's a little bit fast and
shorter maybe deep or shallow
we're just
noticing can we trust that the body knows how to breathe
we don't have to do anything
special e
and when the mind wanders as it will
do we don't have to make it a problem just very
simply gently begin
again can we begin again with
a environment of warmth and
care e
rather than meditation being one more place where
the inner critic might pester us
can we have
meditation be a place of safety Sanctuary for our mind and
hearts a refuge for our mind and hearts
a refuge that allows what our experience
is to be there
without insisting that it be
different a refuge that has warmth and
care e
a refuge that treats us with
respect and honor honors the
experience
e
for
e e
what is it like to
meditate in such a way that it feels like a
refuge a sanctuary a place of safety
allowing the mind and the heart and the
body to
rest and to feel safe
is there a way that we can practice that we can
meditate that supports us
and allows not only for us to feel this sense of Refuge Refuge creating a refuge
a place of safety but also for that to affect the
way we show up for others affect the way that we
behave things that we say in
communities that is to help them feel safe help them
feel like there's a refuge so that our
practice isn't only for
ourselves but it's for those we come in contact
with and perhaps even those who come in contact with those who come in contact
with us and this way we can extend
or expand the sense of ease that comes when
there's a sense of safety and
refuge so that our practice may be for the benefit of all
beings everywhere for
[Music]
so welcome welcome a really warm welcome to
everybody wherever you might
be and whatever situation you might find yourself in as you're listening to this
or watching it as the case may
be so want to mention that a book just came out just got published called be
the Refuge the subtitle raising the voices of Asian-American Buddhists it's written
written by the amazingly talented chenz Han and I know chenz and I know a lot of
work went into writing this book and pulling it all
together and on Sunday afternoon February 28th IMC is sponsoring an event
to discuss the book so everybody's invited to that and this book is a part
Memoir from trans as well as it's a result of her Research
into the experience of Asian-American Buddhists and it's quite
touching so I can recommend this book and of course with a title of be
the Refuge um she discusses this or you know in this in the book and without giving
away the details of the book I'll say that a person in the
book um describes how they were to turn their practice toward being a refuge for
others there such a beautiful idea I think this it's kind of this act of
generosity this act of recognizing the impact that we have on
others and this wish to be a refuge for others and some ways maybe that kind of
uh summarizes the Buddhist practice is to find a way in which we
can be a support for everybody in some kind of way but in the book this uh individual
talks about creating a space where people feel calm and
positive in a way that they are taking care of each other rather than creating
agitation sometimes there's this um bonding
through mutual outrage I think uh Kim Allen I heard her say that and I
recognize that there certainly have been times in my life when you know my
friends were like yeah and can you believe this also and that oh my gosh and not only that this and then we just
kind of rattle ourselves up more and more but what is it to create a space
where people feel calm and positive not by being ply Anna not by denying what's
happening but to recognize that tremendous value is there by not
creating conditions that makes people more agitated or more feeling ill at ease or
more worried or anxious or whatever it might
be but to be refuge in a way that to create a space either literal or
metaphorically create a space where people can feel some well-being some
calm and positivity and then in in chenine
book this individual also talks about one way to be a refuge is to create
communities that are refuges for others where people can find comfort and
well-being and sometimes that's through Affinity groups people coming together that maybe
look similar or have similar beliefs or have similar background similar
ethnicities similar experiences similar preferences whatever
it might be similar ages so Affinity
groups is one way we can help create a a refuge to help be a refuge is to either
create uh communities that perhaps don't exist or if they do exist to show up in a way and that we can convert them into
a place that is a refuge and of course it's not only Affinity groups there's all kinds of
kalanam groups good spiritual friends and people
that live in this similar geographical area that before covid
would meet in person to talk about the drama I'm imagining many of them are
meeting online now and for some of these programs we
have at IMC we kind of try to facilitate a little
bit uh the creation of Home groups which are kind of like this kalana groups these ideas small community where people
can practice together and discuss and explore different
topics and of course there's even these uh when we're on the zoom meetings I
know for some teachings that we do here at IMC with some of the programs that
are on Zoom we break people up into breakout groups you know maybe two three
four five six people and those of course are also kind of a little bit of a community
and what would it be like if we had this idea that kind of to be a refuge is to
help create a community wherever we might find ourselves where people can
feel safe they can feel some comfort and some
ease for us to have this movement of the heart to be inclusive and to be generous
with our attention and our time
so trening Han she describes this in her book uh be the Refuge raising the voices
of Asian-American Buddhists there's all kinds of great stuff in that book that's but also we can look to see what do the
suas have to say what does it mean to be a refuge for others we often associate
this word refuge with taking Refuge take refuge in the Buddha Dharma
the SAA not so much this idea of be a
refuge and there's a suta that's uh in the poly Canon and it has a parallel
that was also preserved in
Chinese and uh it talks about this idea of being a refuge and as is often the
case or maybe even always the case that when there's a sua that's in the poly Canon and there's a parallel that's got
preserved in Chinese that there's differences between them and so I'll be focusing on what the
part that's the same uh between these two
sutas so in this suta the Buddha says to a
Brahman it is here Brahman that you should bathe to make yourself a refuge for all
beings it is here Brahman that you should bathe to make yourself a refuge for all
beings so maybe we can unpack this a little bit what is the Buddha talking
about about bathing and making on a refuge so maybe I'll um start by saying
this expression make yourself a refuge if um we look at the poly I can't read
Chinese so I not sure exactly what it says in the Chinese but uh if I look at the ply the translation maybe more
literally would be make yourself a place of safety or make yourself make a a
sanctuary or something like that it's not the same word refuge sa that we um
when we take refuge in the Buddha Dharma Sanga but uh a number of English translators have used this word refuge
and I rather like it so this idea
of making yourself a refuge for all
beings so this idea of bathing comes from the context of the
suta as you might imagine so in the suta the Buddha is with some monastics and he
sees in the distance that there's a Brahman so a Brahman at this time and in
this setting and this is um we could think of as a priest for the dominant
religious Tradition at that time in Ancient India so somebody who was a not
only a practitioner but somebody who was um an upholder maybe we could say of the
tradition of the dominant religious Tradition at that time which we might call
brahmanism and so the Buddha is with uh some monastics and he sees this Brahman
in the distance that's um approaching him and knowing that the Brahman will
over hear what the Buddha is about to say the Buddha begins his talk uh
directed to his monastics but also kind of directed towards this Brahman and he
says that there are these six different types of impurities or
defilements in the mind we can think of this impurities or
defilements we could think of this as um one way that I is a I find helpful to
think about that are things that are extra like we don't need them they're
not helpful and so for me that's one way I like to think about it defilement and
impurity sometimes has this feeling of this
puritanical uh way uptightness or something like that to some of the
associations we might have with these words I don't know if that was the
associations that were um with these words in Ancient India but I like this
idea of things that are extra and that we don't need
them and that budha gives these 16 I'll go through this list don't worry
I'm not going to unpack them all or anything like this but just to give you a sense what are these uh this
list covetousness and unrighteous greed it will anger resentment offensiveness
contempt Envy stinginess deceit fraud
obstinacy aggression conceit arrogance vanity and
negligence so we might um summarize perhaps this uh list of 16 as
maybe greediness of self selfishness or I want more or I need
more or maybe it's aversion of will hostility kind of like get away from me
or get this away from me or maybe also um this self assertion or a conceit we
might also think of it like don't you know who I am kind of thinking and I would say with the exception maybe
it's that last one negligence negligence is just maybe not to applying ourselves
or not being careful or attentive or something like this so maybe the first
15 we might summarize and you might recognize this
idea of I want more I need more or get this away from me or don't you know who
I am and these are manifestations of greed hatred and delusion some of the core
foundational defilement but the way that um the
Buddha is using these the words that he's using right he's not talking about you know just the core fundamental ones
with uh some of these words of aggression or stinginess or Envy or
arrogance vanity using some of these words there are some of the ones that
are um maybe we might think well these are just minor
manifestations of some of these deeper things that are extra defilements
impurities but um I appreciate what neopan Tera who is a who was a an elder
in this tradition like his book The Heart of buddh meditation was one of the first and pretty foundational books
written in English came out in the mid-60s about uh theas
practice and uh he writes how much more pleasant and
harmonious will be human relations individual and communal if there is less
pettiness and peevishness and fewer vanities and jealousies and less self
assertiveness and words and deeds so that was kind of one his way when he looked at this list of 16 thinking like
it would just be so much easier to get along with other people whether it's just one other
people or whether we're in a group if there was less of these things these um
16 different qualities and we also might consider that there is a connection between these
qualities and the deeper roots of greed hatred and
delusion and so to work with where they show up and maybe what we might
consider minor or we might consider surface level to work with them and how
they get expressed in our daily lives is really a way in which to work with the
the deeper ones the the foundational the root
defilements so then the Buddha in the suta he can he can um he continues after
talking about this list of 16 defilements he says if you know it's a
defilement abandon it seem so straightforward right makes
it sound easy of course it's not easy but this is why we have a meditation
practice and why we have a Buddhist practice not just meditation but all of them all of the elements of the eight
path or the gradual training that is to recognize if you
know it's a defilement if you know that this is something that's extra that's
not helpful that doesn't lead to Greater freedom but instead leads to less
freedom and to some suffering abandon it so what are some ways in which we can
lessen the attachment the clinging the stickiness
some of these uh expressions of the of greed hatred and
delusion so if you know it's a defilement sometimes we don't know sometimes these are a habits of
mind sometimes we're so used to thinking well of course
I'm filled with arrogance because everybody else is an idiot what do they
know or I don't know maybe that's an exaggeration but are there some ways
that maybe we weren't quite considering that they were impediments to Greater freedom and
greater ease and then the Buddha and the suta
continues and he goes with a describing Brahma vajar
practice probably many of you if not all of you are familiar with this practice it
begins with imbuing the mind with loving kindness this is good will
respect benevolence care friendliness
love for others and oneself not just others and
oneself and the way love and kindness practice is described in the sutas which is a little bit different than how we
practice it like when I do happy hour um to um relying more on the way loving
kindness practice is described in the commentary so a little bit um after the
time of the suit does but in the suit does is to imbue the mind with loving kindness this
warm-heartedness if you will and then to pervade it in 10
directions four directions we can think of as the Cardinal north south east
west and then four directions are the intermediate H Northwest Southwest
northeast southeast and then the two directions above and below all
directions so to imbue the mind with loving kindness and then pervade 10
directions with this warm-heartedness and then with a mind
that is boundless exalted immeasurable and welldeveloped
and find myself smiling when I'm talking about this because sometimes right if we have this
loving kindness practice and we're able to really feel fill the heart and mind
with this Good Will and to be sending it out and
including ourselves with it it is such a way in which we can have
in which we are not expressing a aggression or stinginess or deceit or
contempt or resentment all these other things that are in this list of
16 so in the suta it's not clear if the Buddha is um saying first abandon these
16 defilements and then practice the Brahma aaras or it's and practice the
Brahma vajar or maybe we might even understand it that practicing the Brahma
vajar is a way in which we can help us to abandon some of these 16
qualities so many of you know where the Brahma vhar is I um first started talking about loving
kindness but it also includes compassion sympathetic joy and
equinity there say four movements of the heart um we might say so I won't go into
detail about what that is but but this just a recognition that it's a sense in
which there's um maybe a sense of fullness or a sense of um maybe some
safety and some that itself can be a
refuge so then this uh then the Buddha and the Brahman start discussing
bathing and purification so the Buddha
says Brahman so now he's directing his attention to the Brahman Maybe by this
time the Brahman has walked there and has sat down that's not explicit but that's what's happening in my mind is
that now the Brahman is sitting with the monastics and is listening to what the
Buddha has to say and the Buddha says Brahman this is what is called bathing
the inner mind instead of bathing the outer body so the Buddha is making a
real distinction to purify cleanse remove what's extra from the
mind making that's really different than purifying cleansing removing what's
extra on the body external body and the B the Brahman replies by
saying Goa you should go to the bahooka river to bathe cuz one who bathes in the
bahooka river becomes purified and eliminates all
evil so we can we learn that this Brahman was a person who their practice
their spiritual practice was to bathe in particular rivers and sacred rivers with
the belief that that didn't matter so much what actions you did as long as you
included the action of bathing in the river and then all you all the bad or
inappropriate unskillful UNH wholesome everything that you had done would just be washed
away then maybe as a as a little aside I'll say there's a another suta it's um
from the terata some of you might be familiar this is the verses from the
nuns and there's um some there's a nun
right now her Name Escapes me I think it's Puna who um also encounters a Brahman
who has this uh practice that um just um
as long as you bathe in the right Rivers you can do whatever you want and I'm I'm chuckling because uh
the nun says to the Brahman something like this I'm paraphrasing well if that were true then wouldn't all the turtles
and the fish and I think COC crocodiles and serpents wouldn't they all be
perfectly pure and if that were true wouldn't all your good deeds also be
washed away so I appreciate very much that this nun doesn't just speaking truth to power
here this Brahman but getting back to this suta where um the Buddha is uh speaking to
this Brahman about there's to do this inner cleansing this inner
bathing if you will rather than outer and then the Buddha um says to
inverse for the pure in heart and I looked at the ply it's is this word is
heart as opposed to mind which is um I don't know it's a
beautiful thing actually to think about having this pure of heart maybe with the loving kindness
practice is a way that helps us to have this purity of heart or the Brahma vajar
practice for the pure in heart it's always the spring festival or the
Sabbath so the Buddha is saying we don't have to wait for special days that we go
bathe in the river to be cleansed of things that um wrongdoing if we are pure
of heart then every day is a special day for the pure in heart and clean of
deed their vows will always be fulfilled we don't have to go bathe in
the river and then the Buddha says it is here Brahman that you should bathe to
make yourself a refuge for all beings it is here that is abandoning
those defilements and practicing loving kindness which maybe isn't a surprise
for any of us the part of the Buddhist practice is these two movements of the heart two
movements of the mind that allow us to show up for others to create safety for
others to be a sanctuary for others it also points to this idea that
behaving ethically is much more than just following the precepts but also to notice any contempt
or domineering or ER arrogance that we might have and for us to think about that what
are some ways we might create safe spaces for others create safe
communities or if we find ourselves as part of a community how can we support
the that Community to be a place that's inclusive that honors and recognizes and
respects everybody from whatever background they have however they're
showing up and then maybe I'll close with this
um last um an excerpt from yet one more
suta that's this verse where the Buddha says one whose mind all day and night
takes Delight in harmlessness who has loving kindness for all beings for them there is no there is
antigon antagonism with none I'll say that again one whose mind
all day and night takes Delight in harmlessness who has loving kindness for
all beings for them there is antagonism
with none that is we can be a refuge for
others thank you