so
what i'd like to consider and explore
for this talk
is some aspects of desire
as i've said before i think that
the more proper term for
human beings would be human
desiring because their
desire is part and parcel and intimately
connected to human life and
there's no life human life without
desire
that we're going to supposed to get rid
of desire have no desires
is unrealistic
but to become wise about desire
is one of the tasks of buddhism and to
learn how to be free
of desires free from the desires not
that they're gone
but we're not caught in them and we have
freedom in relationship to them
and
so the um
so in order to become wise about desire
it helps to become intimate with desire
and as i said a little while ago that if
you want wisdom
cultivate intimacy and there's some
something some aspect of intimacy some
way of being intimate
that touches in and it brings us to the
place where wisdom has a chance to
operate
and so if you want to be wise about
desire be intimate with desire
and to explore this topic i want to talk
about a
subclass of
mental movements in the family of desire
and that uh and start talking about the
outermost
the most abstract abstract in a sense to
that which gets closer and closer to
something that's more and more intimate
inside
and so perhaps this talk it would be a
little bit of a journey
from uh outward to inward to what's
innermost
so maybe you'll follow along and maybe
you can
imagine or feel what i'm talking about
and how it works for you
giving me a little bit of the maybe the
benefit of the doubt
or a little bit of the
focusing on what i say that might be
relevant for you or what you
can identify with or recognizing
yourself
and certainly some of the things i say
you might
have aspects of it that you disagree
with but on this journey it might be
better for now
to just kind of find recognizing
yourself oh yeah i know
that this way
so uh this journey in exploring desire
has to do with three parts it has to do
with
what we desire
what and why we desire and how we desire
so what what why and how
and and so
the aspect of this is to have a goal
desires usually have a goal something we
want something we want to accomplish
something we want to
do and and goal having a goal is an
important part of life
and people have all kinds of goals that
they want to accomplish
but a goal in my vocabulary
is a what it's the the purpose of the
desire
it's the what what we want to get what
we want to see happen
we use the word what to describe what is
the goal
you might ask them and what is what is
the purpose or what's the goal
and um so for example
you as i did this morning you might go
shopping for
a relative for food and
the goal was to go shopping and
so you know what are you up to i'm going
shopping i'm going to the store
and in fact i was able to go to the
store and buy what i needed to do
and so i accomplished the goal
and um but you know that's the it's the
talking about it that way it's somewhat
removed for me
it's somewhat abstract it's outside of
me
shopping is outside of me in a sense
the goal buying something for my my
relative is a
you know it's a worthy goal but it's
kind of you don't really learn anything
about myself
except that i was going to do this task
and so we can also ask um why am i doing
it
and so uh the why
has to do with a purpose and when we
start talking about purpose we're
talking about something that's maybe a
little bit closer in
more intimate more integral to who we
are
than just the goal and um
and so the purpose maybe for going
shopping
was uh when my relative is sick and i
needed to i wanted to get
i was asked to get something to support
her uh in her
time of illness and so uh the purpose
was
to support and offer aid to a relative
who
is ill and um so
uh so you would if i just said that my
you know purpose was to go buy
x y and z you wouldn't uh you know
that's the goal
you wouldn't really understand the
purpose but you know the purpose oh now
we're
understanding something about maybe what
does motivating gil
and what's happening here and
and then you could ask deeper but why
are you doing that
and you keep asking the question why and
in a certain kind of way that goes
through layers and layers inside
you can ask well why are you doing that
oh because i care for my relative i love
my relative
um and uh and so it's out of my care
that's that's why i'm doing it and so
now you know something a little
deeper about me or you're kind of going
in closer and closer
in and so you could ask what's the
purpose
and it's really useful not to
answer it with just one answer
if you have a desire to ask what is the
purpose of why i want to say what i'm
going to say
why i want to say what i want to say or
what's the purpose of this activity i'm
doing what's the purpose of
this way of thinking how often do you
ask yourself
why am i thinking this way what purpose
does it fulfill
and then even if you get an answer one
answer
ask again ask again because there might
be multiple reasons
uh multiple motivations inside purposes
we're trying to accomplish
and um and then or you might ask more of
a secondary one you might have one
answer
i'm you know why why are you shopping
because i'm shopping in order to support
a relative
but why you want to support a relative
because i care for the relative the
relative is sick
and and you know and why do you care for
a relative and why do you want to
support a relative
because it just it's the kind of
heartfelt wish
of course i would do that and uh
and so you keep asking and you can get
kind of deeper and deeper questions it
takes you on a journey
can take your journey to be something
more intimate and deeper
and just have the logical answers being
the only answer
the first answer only one it might miss
something
of the bigger picture or the intimate
picture
or something of what's going on
so that there's the purpose and then
deeper than the purpose
there is um the how are we
how are we when we're doing something
and the question how
um implies i think always brings us into
the at least
my vocabulary in this question always
brings us into the
the activity itself the
you know kind of like into the present
moment the action how we're doing it
is how we embody it how we go forth with
it
and where its purpose is little bits you
know abstract
a little bit removed from you know can
be a little bit removed from something
it's inner
but when you talked about how it it kind
of really comes closer
and um and so
how am i doing it am i doing it in a
hurry am i doing it slowly
am i doing it with resentment am i doing
it with
delight and joy with generosity
how are we doing it and
and are you doing it in you know
trying to do the minimum you can or
you're trying to do more than you can
so there's all these questions about how
and uh and so how do i go to the store
in the morning to go shopping
so part of it is with care part of it
with certain delight it was early in the
morning
and and it was kind of quiet and calm
time to be going
and it was also um i was going with
with the feeling of you know a certain
kind of
good feeling about knowing that i could
do something
for my relative and was happy to do so
so
and then um and then being in the store
and uh
a few other shoppers there there was the
clerk there early enough there was just
one
and um and uh and how i was there
i was not being there with you know you
know
trying to be have a human connection
with the person at the counter in spite
of the masks that we were wearing and
and um and uh
you know so how was you know trying to
be
friendly trying to have good will trying
to be connected
to the whole situation that was in and
so how but how goes deeper and deeper
you know so really how were you this way
how are you
that way and and now we come what's
deeper in uh
maybe than uh the question you know
related to how
is the attitudes that we have so
you know i could have done something how
i could have done fast or slow
but then how i did it the what attitude
went with going as fast maybe it was
the attitude of being fast was that i
was impatient
maybe the attitude of was i was overly
eager i really wanted to do something so
i'm really rushing because of my strong
desire maybe even greed
or maybe i'm slow because i just really
enjoy it i like being present and being
in the experience fully
or maybe i'm slow because i resent doing
it
and uh and you hesitate and i'm not
really
putting myself into it i'm dragging my
feet so there's attitudes that
now attitudes were coming in more
intimate more closer down
deeper down what are the attitudes we
carry what is the mood of the mind
what's the attitude that the heart has
the mind has
and are those attitudes attitudes of the
moment
or are they part of our
character part of how we've cultivated
and how we live the
the patterns of mind and thought and
beliefs and emotions
that characterize how we've chosen to
live our life
and and different from personality
which maybe we don't have much choice
about that but character
we have some choice and it's been shaped
by either by society and events and
experiences of our life
but also it's been shaped but that all
that small and big choices we've made
about what kind of thoughts to emphasize
what kind of desires to emphasize what
kind of ill will to emphasize
what the habits are that we're building
up of behavior and ways of being
and these all contribute to ongoing
attitudes that we carry with us
and so now we're talking about something
that can be really deep
and these attitudes sometimes can be
subliminal or not obvious to us
all the time they can start becoming
invisible to us because we carry them
with them all the time
but to sit in meditation and get quiet
and start seeing when i get quiet and
intimate with myself
what in some deeper way are the
underlying deeper attitudes
that are operating for me and how might
those attitudes
relate to the desires i have and how i
pursue those desires
and the deeper deeper we go in buddhism
and you might not agree with this but in
buddhism it's considered to be
three fundamental unhelpful
unwholesome roots for our attitudes
and three wholesome ones and all
wholesome beneficial
impulses come out of these three roots
the wholesome roots and all the things
which are unhelpful
harmful that we do for others or things
that are unhealthy
derived from these three unwholesome
roots
the unwholesome roots is usually
translated in
english as either craving or
greed some occasionally it's a strong
another word in pali that
maybe is closer to lust
but the strong desire com you know that
somehow there's a contraction there's a
loss of freedom in the movement
it's kind of unwholesome there's some
kind of maybe selfishness involved
connected to it maybe there's an
overriding of wisdom that goes into it
with greed
and so the other
unwholesome root is
ill will and often in english we say the
word aversion
for this but it could also be more
dramatic it could be hostility
so it's very mild or can be very strong
and but there can be an underlying
momentum movement
attitude mood of aversion of hostility
of pushing away
not wanting that if that's the seed the
root for behavior
it tends to be a behavior which
expresses that it will in
in forms of hostility and and causes all
kinds of difficulty
and that can be towards oneself or
towards others and the third
unwholesome attitude is
a root attitude is delusion confusion
where we're just confused in a sea of
not knowing and doubt and uncertainty
and
not making sense of things and jumping
around in different ideas
and not settling on anything and uh
when there's confusion and delusion then
it's easier for greed
we're not connected to wisdom uh there's
no wisdom in that
no clarity and so that tends to then
support more greed and more ill will
the healthy attitudes and
our generosity
good will and wisdom and so
generosity is this a feeling that
that openness and availability and
open-handedness open-heartedness that's
a spirit of kind of
being both open to the world around us
but also
um i want to use the word manifest
a manifesting actualizing for them
something for the world
it's a movement which is connected to
wisdom
and makes room for wisdom a closed hand
is not open to experience something in
the palm of the hand
but if we open the pan then we can
experience something
in the palm now it can be stroked by
someone for example
we can clean the palm we can't clean it
if it's closed
so same thing with the heart or the mind
with greed something closes down with
generosity something opens
and it's available for wisdom available
to be cleaned
and then good will
instead of ill will is uh
also this opening movement something
that liberates us
it frees something inside it frees us
from the contraction the closeness
of of
of uh what goes on for us
so uh i got distracted because i saw
this somewhere there was no bell i guess
i didn't bring the belt and the sitting
did i
so maybe no bell no
end and uh
so um so ill so
good will and then wisdom and wisdom
also itself is an
opening movement because one of the
primary forms of wisdom
is not the wisdom
of not clinging the wisdom of not
suffering
wisdom of non-harming
so um these are think of these as
attitudes then
do we go about with an attitude of
generosity an attitude of goodwill an
attitude
of wisdom attitude of discernment of
seeing clearly
or do we have an attitude that somehow
closes
wisdom limits wisdom and so is it greed
is it ill will
is it delusion and uh
and so or is it fear that somehow is
connected to those three
it's fascinating that fear that's
unhealthy
has is considered because has to be
rooted in either greed ill will or
delusion
so how does that work and is there a
different kind of fear
that's rooted in generosity and good
will
or love and wisdom i think there is
that's why fear doesn't fit in either it
doesn't it's not placed in just one
or the other it's just the unwholesome
or just a wholesome but
it depends on the roots that support the
fear
so attitude so so
attitude is more intimate than the goal
attitude brings us into something close
in to what's innermost and what makes us
tick and what influences us
and influences how we see the world and
how we see ourselves
and to sit in meditation or other ways
of beginning to find
no deep you know being defined
the underlying attitudes dispositions in
which we operate in
and to learn how to not be caught by
them
not because not be limited by them not
be closed by the unhealthy ones
beginning to open and open and open
and my sense is that the unwholesome
roots
of greed hate and delusion they
themselves
are not what's most innermost they
themselves are a little bit
more surfacy and as those
fall away and as we keep opening
generosity
love good will and wisdom
they belong to
that which is most innermost most
sensitive maybe most shy
at times most tender most
uh maybe most quiet and so it's only by
getting quiet or settled or
intimate and willing to have a certain
tenderness
that these generosity and ill and good
will
and wisdom really can shine and be part
of our life
so certainly we can have goals we can
have purposes
we can focus on how we are
but don't get don't be too caught up in
the goal
don't be too caught up in the purposes
pay attention to how you do things
it's a huge key and important part of
mindfulness practice
and as you pay attention to the how at
some point come in and really
begin discerning what are the underlying
the deeper attitudes
which are fueling or
influencing how we're going about our
life
and there in those attitudes is where
you can start discovering freedom
it's when the attitudes become free
then the desires that flow for them are
free is all
as well and we become free
so that when we have desires
of generosity of goodwill and wisdom
then hopefully then we have a sense of
how to remain
free with those
for our attitudes to contain
freedom so our desires
can be free so that our purposes
can have qualities of freedom and their
goals can be
intimately involved with freedom as well
so i hope that this has given you
something to think about and explore in
yourself and
some questions to ask yourself as you go
about
questions about why
what of why and how
and take the how question and go as deep
in as you can that you come to your
you can see if you can find the
underlying deeper attitudes dispositions
that um animate your life
and see if you can
switch to be more and more
have those attitudes be the wholesome
roots
may that journey of exploration
be empowering and freeing for you
thank you