so now does it seem to be seen the videos working and
takes a moment for you to reply to the sound being here
i found a setting where i could increase the bit rate which seems to be what
youtube's saying was not strong enough i doubled it so
hopefully now it says the stream is strong so
so here we are
so we'll sit mostly quietly today but i do want to emphasize the role
of recognition and imagine that you're maybe that
you're sitting in your usual way and but that imagine that it's
um as if you're in an easy chair or in leaning against an oak tree
looking at a river or pastoral scene and you're at ease and content and happy settling back
and in the subtle back you're observing you're just allowing what's happening to appear for you
no reaching out no trying to figure anything out no trying to make anything happen
just settling back and letting everything just resp come to you and show itself to you
and your awareness your is open your eyesight is receptive your hearing is receptive
all the perceptions all doors are open to receive
and then in the most easy way possible relax almost as if it's from the
deep inner place of relaxation of ease but with a little bit of
clarity use a single word
to recognize what it is that's arising in awareness
no hurry but just an irregular kind of stream for recognition a thought
body sensation sound inhale just very simple in this kind of
relate back way and the recognition is a little bit the the the tether to the present moment
so you don't wander off just you stay there you stay there [Music]
so let's um sit that way quietly and we'll find our way
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting one way or another
we have a
connection a relationship to other beings other living beings other
people some people we know
we know of but there are plenty of people who are important for our lives and our
lives are cared for who we don't know and will never know
but the circles of people who do things that support our lives the circle of
living life on this planet that keeps us
alive is in some kind of way
part of us inseparable and one of the ways to
care for ourselves is to care for all these people all these beings
and one of the ways to care for all these beings is to care for ourselves
and a way to do both simultaneously is to sit quietly
with good will in all directions good will towards oneself good wills to
the world simply a radiance of goodwill circles
of goodwill that spread from us
turns out that having good will is one of the best
nourishments we can offer ourselves
and may each of us start our day or continue our day end our day wherever you are
remembering that you have a capacity for goodwill for well-wishing for kindness
and as we go forth from this meditation may we go forth with a wish that all
beings be happy that all beings be safe
that all beings be peaceful and that all beings be free
may we benefit from this wish as much as others do
[Music]
so to continue these thoughts on these talks on some pagana clear
comprehension or clear recognition and um i love this particular word
because of how it overlaps with the simplicity of mindfulness practice just simple recognize how things are
and the richness of a contemplative life a life that's lived
reflectively and both have a role and a place in our lives
there are times where i thought that the way that buddhist meditation has been taught in
the west especially in vipassana sometimes in the zen world i have the sense that
there's such a strong emphasis on non-discursive awareness
simply being aware the simplest possible way and letting go of thoughts and that
there's a as people get that message that they're not supposed to be thinking at all
and certainly in meditation it's helpful to quiet the thinking mind and have
become really quiet maybe still but for a wider life
there is a time for a quiet mind a still mind and there's a time for
reflection and contemplation and i think of a reflective life is one
that it can become when i use the word contemplative as a
life of reflection deep reflection i associate very much with calm
calm reflection uh considering thinking about our lives and pondering and in a way
that uh is just it's intimate and and cozy and nice just to do to be
engaged and reflect contemplation the nature of our life what we're up to
and so this clear comprehension uh both these areas quiet kind of
non-discursive awareness and then also this contemplative life in a sense
and so the first yesterday was of the four kinds of uh clear
comprehension is clear comprehension of purpose why we're doing something and the second
is a clear comprehension of of
suitability of what's appropriate how to engage in something what actions
what behavior what ways of thinking perhaps that are suitable for the purpose we have
and uh it's um you know there's this analogy that if
you try to squeeze oil out of gravel uh you won't
it won't work if you want oil you have to take you know olives or sesame seeds or
something and really squeeze them to get the oil out and so in the same way so we have to kind of
know what's suitable for the purposes we have so if you're trying to
become kinder and you do it through
aggressive straining it's kind of like trying to squeeze oil out of the gravel we have to kind of
find the suitable way to be or what the right approach for something
and i think this reflection on suitability what's right for me
what's the way that i can do whatever i've set my mind on uh given my weaknesses and my strengths
given my interest giving given what uh nourishes me and benefits me and given what the situation
requires what's needed in the situation what's suitable what's the right thing to do
and and so it's a life of reflection and questioning suitability
as opposed to looking for a policy looking for what is the right way to do
something maybe if i just get the manual and just follow it like you know meditation by
the numbers or buddhism by the numbers you know one two three four five and just um but uh but it's uh
it's not something wrote it's not something there's a fixed way that we should do things
but rather if we do things as is appropriate for the circumstance of who we are and the situation and so
being reflected about suitability what's the right way to do this so if the uh one's purpose
is to follow the buddhist path to greater and greater
forms of liberation freedom to follow the buddhist path to really kind of clarify and
and and and bring it to an end our suffering we can ask
that that's a great purpose now what's suitable for this um if it's uh if we spend a lot of time
uh watching movies on our computer uh and we justify i need to relax i need
to relax so that i can you know get on with buddhist practice
but if we spend an inordinate amount of time doing this relaxing watching watching movies
it probably is not suitable for the purposes of becoming free of suffering it might give relief from some of the
suffering but it doesn't really get to the bottom of it and really penetrate it and so what do you do in your daily life
what are the activities you're involved in which are suitable for the purpose you
have and which are not if your purpose you have uh is you know
one of many things you're doing and you've slide it in here and there and then the idea of suitability
varies but if your idea of what your purpose of life is is
really like this is what central orientation the central thing i want my life to be about
nothing else matters or say it differently everything matters but everything has to
matter through the lens of my dedication to living a life of freedom
my dedication to living a life of compassion and care and that that's the purpose of my life
and so what's suitable is to you know what would be suited what's a suitable way to express that and live that in my
life and do i infuse everything i do with those qualities or do i limit what i do and only do
those things that are really for that purpose and and it's possible to live a life
that everything we do is organized around the principle of compassion or care for self and others everything's
organized around the principle or the purpose of to becoming free of suffering and
and to have the flourishing of wholesome states within not in a selfish way a hedonistic way
but because this is really beneficial for self and other it's better than the alternative
to keep suffering and being contracted and stressed and and if we're really clear about
having a central purpose like that then um uh and then what's suitable to support
that what's it what do we what can we how can we live our life then in a way that we clearly see and reflect that this is
the way that supports what i'm trying to do in my life and leads me to further and further along this path
like this and and perhaps there are things you we in
that kind of contemplation we realize well this is not suitable this is not helping me this is kind of a waste of
time and this life of ours is quite precious and we don't have that much time to be alive
and and time goes by quickly so i might as well do the things that are
most meaningful most purposeful uh including uh if we
understand the path of liberation is um to enter into like meditation where we
let go of the preoccupation with meaning the preoccupation with purpose
because we have it and it's there to really sit and be present for our experience in a deep intimate
way so suitability uh what is suitable
and and that also involves in our work life our social life
and there's a way that uh in zen practice sometimes they um ask a question that's i'd relate to
the suitability um and it's i think it's a beautiful question
to a way to go through one's life and that is um what's their request here what are we
being asked so if um i mean even in inanimate objects things
there's a feeling in zen what is being asked for here what's the request so rather than coming from our desires
our wishes our um what we want uh and asserting ourselves on others and
in the world it's rather what is the what is suitable in this situation what's the appropriate
response in this situation what is the request of this situation and so as uh i remember a very uh
tiny little event that happened you know 45 years ago or so um
i was kind of a just getting interested in zen and i went to the los angeles zen center
i was in l.a and i just went there for an evening i think there was maybe a some meditation and a dharma talk and so
there were two sessions of meditation and then in between we did the slow kinhean the slow walking meditation
around this small kind of a living room where everyone was meditating and people
are meditating on these black meditation um
futons these little uh it's called zabutans these mats and um
and the person in front of me uh was walking slowly in front of me and i was walking slowly
behind and and i saw the person bend down to
straighten out one of those black meditation mats it was slightly gotten crooked and you know they're all kind of
lined up kind of nicely and i thought that was bizarre why would one care enough to
you know straighten out the mat you know and and uh it made a big impression on me that that kind of attention to detail
and and i imagine that uh if if you ask what's the request
here uh what's being asked in this situation uh what's being asked is to straighten
the mat slightly so exactly where the request is coming from uh
you know it's probably somewhat from our own inner sensibilities understanding the
situation and projected onto the scene of our what what how it is to be a human
being there but it's still coming from someplace deeper than just me myself and mine what
i want and and so what is being asked of me in this situation
and and finding a way forward so suitability having a sense of purpose
and knowing what's suitable for that purpose is part of this uh clear comprehension
a reflective life and so one of the things you might try doing
for the next uh 24 hours is to reflect a little bit about not
only your purpose uh in the things that you do but also uh
the suitability this is it uh appropriateness or the
uh the um
how supportive it is the things that you do through the day are they suitable for your purpose are
they supportive of some bigger purpose and value that you have and uh and in this kind of reflection do
you benefit as a result is it nice for you is it supportive for you is it suitable um
so thank you very much and continue here tomorrow