good evening good evening welcome welcome
hmm nice to be here
so we'll start with a guided meditation
as a way to support our practice and
to support our being here now
so taking our meditation posture
and having the body and a posture that expresses our intention to meditate and
also has some ease has a certain amount of
relaxation
and then tuning into the body as it is at this moment
maybe in a global sense feeling tired or
restless agitated or calm
happy sad
maybe we're not sure
and then tuning in to some more particular experiences
the pressure against the body of whatever we're sitting on
on our lower legs our buttocks our back
perhaps our feet
we're here now
and then allowing the attention to land on the experience of breathing
feeling the movements of the body associated with breathing
the chest the abdomen
it's subtle but we might also notice a little bit in our back
or perhaps the feeling of air going in and out of the nose
in a relaxed easy way without straining
just noticing the sensations of breathing
and when the mind wanders of course the mind will wander
and when it does we just very simply gently begin again
and when the mind wanders we might notice
that sometimes there is a a wish for something more
sometimes might be planning what we're going to do or obtain
or we might be imagining how it would be so much better if only
dot dot
and when we find our mind lost and or pulled in this direction
we might just a little query ask ourselves
what in this moment is truly lacking
in the spirit of can we bring our attention back to this moment and
the fullness the completeness of this moment as opposed to focusing on what's absent
or what's not matching our preferences
at this moment is anything truly lacking
maybe you'll have to modify the question
in a way that resonates with you
does there have to be this sense of lack this sense of not enough
if it feels too complicated too burdensome
to be noticing when we're wishing things to be different or
planning what we're going to obtain or acquire or do next
and then responding with the question what's really lacking what's truly
lacking is anything lacking that's really
important
and if all of that feels too burdensome just being with the sensations of
breathing
we're approaching our meditation in this way
to help support a sense of it's okay in this moment
we don't have to have we don't absolutely have to have
these things that we're thinking about or planning or right now we're just here
meditating
sometimes we have a sense that we just need
more maybe we're not even clear more of what
but can we settle into this moment and let go of the idea that we
need to have more
and instead to notice the fullness the completeness of what's here
right now
so much harm gets created sometimes very subtle but harm
for ourselves for others by our always looking wanting more
when we put that down it not only supports us but supports others are not demanding
things from others and supports our communities our planet
if we can quiet abate the wanting more mind
so that in this way our practice can be a support not only for ourselves but for others
on the planet for everyone
so may all beings be free from suffering and the causes of suffering
you
welcome welcome warm welcome wherever you are sometimes it's fun for
me to imagine there might be time in the future when somebody hears this even myself sometimes i want to remind
myself of what i've said and talk so sometimes i even listen to these things years in the
future whenever it is welcome
so all of us whether it's explicit or implicit whether it's obvious or we
stated out loud or whether it's just kind of in the back of our minds propelling us we all have some goals
some achievements maybe we could say or
some things we'd like to have in our lifetime
and in buddhist practice in early buddhism there's this idea that we can lose the
goal of awakening to be enlightened
and maybe in another talk i'll talk about uh some of the wisdom of that goal and
how to hold on to it and maybe how some of the other buddhist traditions approach it may be a little bit different
but putting that aside for now i'll assume that we all have this goal
whether it's implicit or explicit to have more freedom more peace more ease more well-being
the fact is that most of us come to this practice because we have a lot of
dukkha we have a lot of suffering we have something other than freedom other than peace other than ease
so we come here and do these practices with the intention of increasing
if not just abiding in wellness increasing the sense of okayness in our
lives and so we might ask well how can we
achieve this more freedom more peace more ease part of it of course is a meditation practice
but how can we achieve our goals and i heard a talk recently from james
clear it's a best-selling author where he stated
we don't rise to our goals we fall to our systems
i don't know that kind of like struck me maybe i had a certain resonance that just because we have
goals doesn't mean that pulls us up and helps us to achieve them
we fall to our systems i haven't read this book by james clear so i'm just
basing all of this on these little snippets i've heard so i'm filling in all the details just
according to my interpretation but this idea that we fall to our systems
means in my mind that when we're under stress or what we do repeatedly over and over
that's what creates the conditions for the outcomes that we're going to
experience so that just because we might have a goal if we don't have the systems in
place that are consistent with that goal
then it's not so likely that we'll meet it maybe this is obvious and goes without
saying maybe i also say that something very much that i appreciate about buddhist
practice is that this goal of freedom and so much about the practice is
finding freedom and the way that we approach our experiences
and the way that we frame interpret our experiences
the things that we do things that we say so we might ask if james clear is saying
we don't rise to our goals we fall to our systems well what what are our systems
and i was thinking about this in terms of this buddhist practice oh maybe before i do
say that i'll say a little bit more about something that james clears says
he tells this story which was quite in i thought was quite remarkable and
i'll share it with you and perhaps you've heard this story elsewhere or already know about this
it tells the story of um the british cycling team and they had hired
a new performance director and i guess the british cycling team back in the
1990s and before hadn't done well and like in the tour de france for like over 100 years
they hadn't won it and didn't do very well in the olympics
and in fact um i think he says that some well-known uh psych bicycle
brand refused to sell bikes to the british team because they didn't want their brand of bicycle to be associated
with this team so okay i guess they're pretty bad so they hire this new performance director who says
okay we're just going to do one percent improvement we're just going to look for
a tiny small little improvement in lots of different places
so the way the story that james clear says is they did all the obvious ones you
know lighter tires and making sure that their
bikes are in tip-top shape i guess but included things like changing their
jerseys to some that are a little bit more lightweight a little bit more aerodynamic but then he said that they also made
these little one percent improvements in places that you wouldn't expect such as asking all the
athletes to try out a lot of different pillows and which pillow did they sleep
the best with and then they would take this particular pillow with them
when they had to travel to compete and then they hired some surgeon to come
in and to demonstrate the right way to wash your hands maybe all of us after coming through
this pandemic we know how to wash our hands um 20 seconds warm water but maybe you
know back then to really make sure they knew how to wash our hands to make it less likely that they would get a cold
or get a flu and i guess they have like these big giant trucks that carry all
the bicycles and they painted the inside of it white so that they could see
if there's any dirt and clean it all up so that the bikes would always remain clean and not have anything that
would jam up the gear so to speak so one percent these
little bit of changes in all these different areas and then the prediction was made
by this performance director that they should be able to win the tour de france in five years if they just consistently were making
these one percent changes
and i guess this turned out not to be true but in fact it only took three years to
win the tour de france and then i guess the british cycling team was just a force to be reckoned with
and did really well at the olympics so it wasn't only the tour de france it was the olympics the women's cycling team
the men's cycling team so i just think this is a powerful story
because i'm sure everybody who enters the tour de france i'm sure every single cycling team has the same
goal to win but what systems do they have
so i got to thinking about you know which systems do we have in our practice and buddhist practice
some of them are obvious but one i'd like to suggest are the pyramids
and the first i've been giving a talk a series on the
pyramids and the first is generosity just this movement of the
heart and maybe the movement actually of the hands too but to not be stingy
but instead to share whether it's resources or time or giving people the benefit of the
doubt part of that's kind of a system we might have in our life it's this movement
towards generosity as opposed to kind of like grabbing and holding on
and stinginess the second part of me is ethics
that is to behave in a way that create creates the conditions for
more more well-being not only for ourselves but for others to follow these precepts that buddha
offered as a way to help support our practice help support our lives
and as i spoke about in the talk about ethics that we can use ethics not only as a
guideline for how we should behave but also as a way to as an indicator for ourselves
of when when are we tempted to or considering to not behave ethically
what is going on in our lives what's going on in our minds that makes us think that it's a good
idea to behave unethically and then the third one is
renunciation so this idea of renunciation is one of a
system that we have that is it's kind of the opposite movement of acquiring acquiring
acquiring or it's the opposite movement of following every single desire that we
have and and obtaining or satisfying every desire without any thought of
whether it's wholesome or worthwhile or helps bring us closer to our goals or is
in alignment with what's important for us
so the parmesa is one set of systems and i'm going to talk a little bit more about them but we could also think about just one
way is this idea of systems or habits what are some of the habits
that we have in our lives and james clear that he's a best-selling
author and the title of his book is atomic habits and i guess it's been a number one in
the on the new york times bestselling list for a while i don't know actually how long but
so what habits do we have we also have our beliefs
maybe you know that our belief that it's a scary place out there
or not i believe that people are intrinsically good or they're always
trying to trick us or you know some kind of our beliefs are also maybe some of our
systems our habits of thought our habits of interpretation
also our intentions we could think of as our system so we all know that right
intention is part of the eightfold path it's the second step
and right intention that is you know what is our what's underline our actions what
direction do we want to go and right intention highlights
that if we want to have some freedom achieve our goal of awakening liberation more ease more
peace to have the intention for non-allest non-greed
non-hatred and non-harming because this recognition that lust and hatred and harming
ourselves or others is not going to support our going where we want to go
so of course another way that we could say one of these intentions non-lust
non-greed is renunciation it's part of an intention and then just for completeness
i'll say that also good will and harmlessness or the other parts of our right
intention so maybe um i'll
share this quote to kind of like unpack a little bit what this means renunciation because
most of us we hear this word and uh it's not a warm fuzzy feeling it we have this feeling
maybe that it's um going to be about denial or uh um um
no like somehow uh the word now just slips my mind
so i'll just go to the next thing here is um asuta here's asuta reference and i'll
set it up that there's this monk who is often when he's meditating like off
in the woods or in an empty head by himself he's um saying to himself oh what
bliss oh what bliss so apparently he's really happy and he's
just saying out loud oh what bliss and the other monks
hear him saying this and the other monks are talking amongst themselves and and they say oh without a doubt
venerable buddhia badilla over here he must be dissatisfied with the
renunciant life being a monastic because it must be that when he's
remembering the pleasures of royalty he formerly enjoyed that he's
frequently saying uh what bliss o what bliss
so this monk used to be a king and now when he see now he's a
monastic and he's meditating and apparently he's really happy and everybody else is assuming maybe
because they're the suta doesn't say this i'm imagining that he's annoying them or disturbing them because
he's so happy and meditating he keeps on saying oh what bliss
so the monks go to the buddha let's say venerable buddhia over here is always
saying oh what bliss and the buddha says okay bring him to me
so venerable badiya comes to the buddha and the buddha says is it true that
you're saying oh what bliss all the time while you're meditating and he says
yes sir yes venerable sir and the buddha asks why
i was so here we go so here's what the buddha says is it really true buddhia that even in
the wilderness at the foot of a tree or in an empty dwelling
empty hut you frequently say oh what bliss yes sir but why do you say this
and here's his reason formerly as a layperson ruling the land my guard
was well organized within and without the royal compound within and without the city
and within and without the country so he describes how he was well guarded there at the palace
in the city and even in the whole country and he says but although i was guarded
and defended in this way i remained fearful and scared and suspicious
and nervous but these days even when alone in the wilderness at the
foot of a tree or in an empty dwelling i'm not fearful scared suspicious or
nervous i live relaxed unruffled
surviving on charity and my heart free as a wild deer
it is for this reason that even in the wilderness or at the foot of a tree or in an empty dwelling
i frequently express this heartfelt sentiment oh what bliss a weblist
so renunciation is pointing to this a king who has you know
everything presumably that he could imagine but still didn't feel quite safe partly
you know having so much is perhaps there's more to lose but this recognition of that kind of the
nervousness or the anxiety that's associated with
trying to protect so much so we might have a lot but then it
doesn't necessarily mean that we have more ease and we all know this there's a part of us that know that
even we get more and more and more it doesn't lead to more and more happiness
i've told this story before but it was really powerful this was years ago but had a big impact on me it
was when i had just finished graduate school and
just had to have like a a real job and one thing that i purchased
was a jacket that i really liked it was one of those that i just put on and i just felt good
in it it fit me well and i know i just really liked it
it was a little bit too expensive though but i purchased it anyways kind of maybe to
celebrate like now i have some income and i don't remember exactly why
how i justified it then so i had this jacket that i would like to wear but then
oh my gosh this jacket you know clearly i owned the jacket but it started to own
me oh okay i can't uh drink i sometimes would like drink i
have a drink in the car with me when i was driving like oh okay i can't do that anymore because what if i were to spill and get on my jacket
or if i'm at a restaurant a cafe coffee shop with somebody and i want to
take my jacket off it's too warm and i put it on the back of the chair oh then i get nervous everybody's walking by
they might i don't know spill something on it or something like this more and more this
just became so burdensome to own this jacket because i couldn't really afford another one and
so you get my you get my sense here we all know this that there's
just acquiring more doesn't mean that things are going to be better
in fact simplicity right is often what kind of supports the
most ease and well-being there's a reason why we retreat centers residential retreat
centers the rooms are really simple
really simple small simple there's a reason why this schedule is very simple sit walk
have a meal do a yogi job sit walk sit walk
it's really simple and i would say for me this is one thing that i love about being on retreat is i love
just having this small little space just a few things and everything is so simple
it allows a sense of freedom a sense of
unburdened being unburdened so can we reframe when we think of this
word renunciation or relinquishment or
excuse me we can think of it as a system to support awakening to support more
freedom we can think of it also as maybe we
could reframe it as non-addiction
that is we often use this word addiction whether we have literal addictions which are
serious matters and really bring a lot of suffering to a lot of people
and then sometimes we kind of informally use this word addiction but these
really strong habits that we have attached to behaviors
or movements of the mind that don't really serve us
and yet we can't quite stop or we can't um disrupt the momentum of them
so if we think of this idea of renunciation as non-addiction maybe there's a way that
we can tease apart and take away some of the energy behind
some of this habits we might have that's not supporting us not helping us
not creating the conditions for more and more freedom
and the buddha when he highlighted in particular kind of our addiction to
sensual pleasures that is things that smell good and taste good and
sexual experiences things that feel good or sound good particularly music or things
like this and he was highlighting that our never-ending pursuit of one sensual pleasure after another
is not the way to the greatest freedom the greatest happiness
instead renunciation this way of being able to not follow these urges
these desires that we have and because it was in my view because it
was so difficult it's not something that's so easily done he spoke about in so many different ways
and different settings but for now i'd like to just maybe say a few
words about well what can we do with how might we work with this desire that we have for
sensual pleasure recognize it it's of course we have this it's
human to have this and we might even say we kind of evolutionarily inherited this
desire for sensual pleasures good tasting food good uh pleasurable physical experiences
and so one so it's definitely all of us humans have this and one way that
the buddha expressed this or pointed to this was the description of these
creatures called hungry ghosts perhaps you've heard of them that these creatures with these
really big empty stomachs really big stomachs and then these
really thread like mouths and necks so there was they could only get just a
little bit of food or sustenance in this thread thin
mouth and neck and this big belly would never be satisfied
so these hungry ghosts are perpetually always wanting more
in some ways the human experience is like this because and and we intellectually we understand
that there might be no way to satisfy this eternally hungry spirit so to speak
yet we persist we have this maybe this misguided striving to satisfy this never-ending
craving this force of desire is really powerful
it's really powerful so what are some things that we might do
one is just to notice how often this pursuit of sensual pleasure is leading us around
the what we acquire what we obtain what we buy
is it all about pleasurable experiences how we spend our time is it all about
trying to get that maximized comfort sometimes at all costs
to be sure there's nothing wrong with having sensual pleasure what i'm
pointing to is the never-ending it's not never-ending satisfaction it's never
satisfying it's never enough this never-ending craving
so is there a way that we can put that craving quiet it down subdue it
and be without it simplify things one is to notice
another is to maybe respond to some of these urges that we have in a skillful way
when we pay attention to them and to notice like oh yeah i really want that
maybe we could say no thank you in our mind no thank you so kind of
acknowledging that this urge has arisen but we're not going to follow it right now
so that could be another way that we might say to ourselves not now kind of highlighting that
there's not necessarily anything inherently bad with what we're desiring but maybe the
time isn't right for us to maybe we don't need to eat more food maybe we don't need
more clothes maybe we don't need that other gadget gizmo thingama thingamajig
or we could ask ourselves what in this moment is truly lacking
like what right now we might be planning in the future we need something but
right now what's truly lacking
or maybe we could say this is good enough it's good enough yeah maybe it would be
just a little bit better if i acquired and obtained and got more
but this is good enough so this is not easy it's not that we'll
do this you know five times and then our urges will go away
but if we do these small moments of disrupting this momentum of following
our desires repeatedly these small moments repeatedly
this will make a difference this is a system that we're creating of not always
succumbing to desires that it creates the possibility for so
much more to happen if we're not tangled up in following all of our
desires maybe just like the british cycling team we just you know it's just a tiny little
bit of improvement disrupt not following this desire and then not following that one we have so
many of them not in a sense that all desires are
banned but to be skillful in them and to be able to say sometimes
this is good enough no thank you
not now what in this moment is truly lacking
and in this way if we can subdue some of our desires and the buddha
pointed out that so much suffering is linked to our desires then this can create the conditions for
our goal for more freedom it can help create the system and
which they were not being pushed around so much
and the more freedom that we have the more our capacity grows to be with
difficulties and to help others to help ourselves to bring in the best version of ourselves
forward so in this way practicing renunciation
we could reframe it as non-addiction as not following the siren's call
every time can be this practice of renunciation can be for
our benefit and for the benefit of others thank you