so hello everyone and
here in northern california we greet you from a rainy place finally it rained
significantly last night still raining a little bit
so um one of the
great areas of discovery in doing buddhist practice
has to do with the family of actions families a family of things we
do or that happen that involve letting go
and today the topic is release and letting go
sometimes is not popular sometimes it's misunderstood and
in buddhism primarily the profound movement of release of letting go
is not letting go of anything that is real
but letting go of the ways that we cling to it so we're letting go of clinging and all
the different variations of it so we letting go of
the kind of resistance that is also a kind of a compulsion
and so when we say let go sometimes let go let go let go
we don't necessarily mean letting go of the thing but of the holding to the thing
so if we say let go of the body it's um it's more like the way that if you tend
it to a injured animal and then when you're ready
to release it into the wild there's natural habitat that you might say you let it go into
the natural habitat and rather than it being a loss
for the animal it's a gain it returns to its natural way and to release our body like you would
release a bird into the air to let go of the body
so the body becomes free and one of the really wonderful things
about this liberation of that's at the heart of buddhism
that in some very significant way maybe initially perplexing way
is we're letting go we're liberating not ourselves
but we're liberating everything else from ourselves
if it's all about personal liberation it actually misses the boat it misses the
you know it doesn't really it's not really the full freedom but to
let everything go let's set everything free
of our clinging or grasping or conceit or selfishness or self-involvement
and this so this can happen with the body too we let go of the body we release the body
we discover how to let the body be
without any clinging resistance tightening
pressure that we exert onto the body
so this sitting today we'll have to do we'll talk and i'll tell you probably use language like letting go
but hopefully with this introduction you appreciate that we're not letting go of the body
but rather we're setting it free from the ways that we interfere with it or
live in a more difficult way with it so
to support the freedom of the body so that it's not restricted anywhere or
collapsed anywhere it's helpful to take a posture
that is open
where everything is nothing is
collapsed or so usually if you're sitting in a chair
or cushion it's usually to sit with a spine straight enough so the chest is a little
bit open and maybe even the shoulders
have a little bit of a movement of not being pulled back but they kind of
allow them to allow them to move back
lowering your gaze and letting your gaze be soft and
relaxed
and that itself is a movement of letting go
the involvement with the eyes that distracted by the mind searching looking trying to see
and if it's comfortable for you you can gently close your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale to appreciate the letting go of the
it happens there the releasing of the breath the releasing of the
inhale the settling relaxing as you exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal
into take the opportunity with the exhale to relax further
to relax the muscles of the face
releasing any pressure that's exerted on the eyelids
any pressure exerted on the forehead
perhaps tightening in the jaw can be released maybe letting the
open the mouth a teeny bit to separate the teeth a tiny bit
and relaxing around the mouth
there's any pressure of the lips touching can you release the pressure
and on the exhale to soften the shoulders
release the shoulders
and to relax the belly softening the belly
on the exhale to relax the legs the thighs
and perhaps the arms and hands and fingers if you feel any pressure or tightness in
the fingers you might even slightly wiggle them
in all these steps of relaxation are movements of letting go of release
releasing the body from the influence of the mind
the holdings and clingings tightenings of the mind
settling into the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
as you exhale relaxing the thinking mind
any pressure or tightening associated with thinking
letting the mind maybe the brain spread out wide like a surface of a wide
still like every exhale
surface becoming calmer the wave stiller
and for every exhale now letting go of your body
releasing your body the hold of the mind
any clinging grasping
any preoccupation with the body judgments
as you exhale let go release
release your body from any ideas you have about the body
and don't worry too much about exactly what you're letting go of
just on the exhale release the body
let go letting the body be still
like a gentle sweet unmoving body
that from within is released set free
every exhale
anywhere in your body where there's even the slightest sense of tension or
stress pressure
see if you can release that
and if you can't release it see if you can
let go and make space around it
and in the last minutes of this sitting whatever your mind is involved in
let it go release it
and then do it again and again
let go and then let go for the next thing the next thing
let it be a release a relaxation
deep to your very core let go
let go and if you're trying too hard to let go
let go of trying hard
and the greater we the more we release the body
the more letting go we have in the body is free
the more the body becomes porous
and things nothing in the world that happens
gets stuck in the body nothing happens in the world
gets caught in the body
the more we hold on to things the more there's something
way in which things get stuck in the body or impact the body
to release deeply so we can be available in the world with
with love with care
so that we can be present for whatever whatever way someone else is
because we're porous
or we're open spacious we have lots of room
so we don't react contract
retract ourselves
and may we go into the world
dedicated to being present for others
in a poorest way in a spacious way
that allows our good will our friendliness our love
to not be agitated or not be contracted or not be lost
may our ability to be present and mindful support us
in caring for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
thank you
this last talk on the week of mindfulness of the body
focuses on release and uh release is one of my favorite
words for liberation or freedom because it uh
has this this idea of um setting something free it gets released
and um and it has this kind of dual thing where
freedom maybe has the idea of you can go do that whatever you want
and letting go has a little bit more kind of the weight of what's been let go of
but for me release is in between that where clearly something has become free
free of something but there's also the feeling of this kind of opening up to
to just openness and a kind of freedom and
anyway so we have a release and um each step along the way of this
week we have these five different areas of mindfulness
we have relaxation recognition
respect restoration and now release but each of the first four
have within them something we're releasing so relaxation maybe is the most obvious
where uh we're releasing tension holding maybe stress there's something where
something is letting go and when we relax and some people don't maybe focus so
much on that what's let go of but rather uh the goodness the nice feelings of the
relaxation the comfort of it then um
the um recognition
involves a kind of release as well letting go as well and that
recognition is very simple it's just recognizing just how things
are in the moment without the complications of history
without the conversations of uh of uh projections into the future
without the complications of um of you know the complicated world and
complications of me myself and mine uh but just allowing something to be itself
allowing an itch to be an itch just recognize the itch it can be hard to be let go of all the
reactivity to it but that's the goal is just to itch an itch a warmth just a warmth
a twisting just a twisting a heat just heat
the um when i was in japan studying zen and
kind of one of the teachings i got there was something like when it's hot just be hot
when the weather is hot and when it's cold just be cold um so
whether that's exactly should why you should live your life i'm not saying but it's the idea that in the recognition
we're letting go of a lot of the complications and just letting things be in their simplicity the pristine
simplicity of each moment so it's a lot of letting go the respect we're letting go of
disrespect with disrespect here might mean um having an agenda
around things uh having uh being in charge bossing our life around like it
has to be this way or that way i have to get rid of this i have to get this happen it shouldn't be this experience
it should be some other way but the respect is to is to just
give permission for each thing to just be itself and so to respect to see again
so there's a letting go that allows us to have this seeing again just allowing ourselves to really be there in the
simplicity of things and then the restoration to allow things to restore
there has to be uh we're letting go of again ways in which we restrict ourselves the ways in which we limit
ourselves or hold back or resist ourselves or box things in or contain
things and um and there has to be space for things to restore
like if you uh if you um if you have too much uh
uh too many plants growing in a fl in a flower bed then the seedling that you want for it to grow will not grow
healthy in a healthy way to allow it to grow well you have to kind of make a clearing so it has
some light that comes through and then today it's release
and um and i think it's a profound topic and it's not
you know it's easy to talk about it simplistically or easy to talk about it as if it's easy thing to do
but um you know generally in almost any circumstance we find ourselves there's
something we can let go of something we can release maybe not what we want to release what
but maybe we let go of the wanting to release maybe that's where the the beginning of
freedom can happen and then we practice relaxation recognition respect maybe a restoration
instead of letting go of what's difficult to let go of and
so one of the things we're releasing is the body from our ideas of the body
and the tremendous amount of suffering in our culture around how the around ideas of body
body image and um and you know to be body conscious
sometimes just to be frozen and caught up and uh with how we're supposed to look and
and uh or how we don't look or and uh you know and the argument our societies around us support us in this
kind of very painful way in which the body gets this kind of uh
this whole agenda ideas of what it shouldn't be and so it's one of the great gifts for
our body to do something like meditation and let go
of all the ideas we have about the body let it be itself
so the other day we did that exercise of mindfulness of the hand where we're just feeling the sensations
of the hand and some people do that exercise will see the difference between
the ideas they have about their hand and their fingers are too much this or too much little that their hand is
through this to that the fingernails are just not quite right or just all these things about the hand
that the mind has ideas about and it can be kind of debilitating and
preoccupying but if we let go of all those ideas and just feel the hand for itself
the hand itself doesn't have a problem being whatever it is it's just a just a hand
and to free the hand to feel itself without the burden of all these ideas
so to learn to release the body from the ideas we have on top of it
part of the release of the body is to release the tension that's in the body
and generally you know most tension that we feel in the body
tightness and most stress we feel in the body is uh is a
byproduct of tension and stress in the mind and so the poor body has to kind of deal
with all the stress and tension and sometimes it becomes chronic and can be quite debilitating
and so to to release the body from the hold of the mind
so that we again can allow the body to restore itself or or heal itself even
and so to begin to appreciate how much we can release the body let go
not of the body but let go with the body
let the body participate in this deep pro the process of letting go of all this unnecessary and
maybe pain producing suffering producing activities that the mind does
and meditation is one of the great laboratories to discover how this works and
how to discover greater and greater release and relaxation and depth
um there was a apparently debate in buddhism at some point down through the
centuries whether enlightenment happens in the mind or happens in the body
and probably it's you know not a tremendously wise debate because it
probably happens in both places simultaneously but uh but the fact that some people
would really identify the body as a locus for liberation i find quite inspiring
it's also inspiring they found it in the mind maybe wherever it's found or whatever that doorway into liberation is great
but many people don't consider that the body is
kind of the location where freedom occurs and maybe part of this debate arises
because in the ancient buddhist teachings of the buddha he emphasized
repeatedly that there is no liberation
without mindfulness of the body and he suddenly has all these synonyms
for liberation and now some of them are quite you know lofty like there is no
attainment of the deathless without mindfulness of the body there is no experience of the
unconditioned without mindfulness of the body that somehow this mindfulness of the
body and navigating through it and discovering freedom through the body is such a huge part of this tradition
so i think as i began this week i want to end with the idea that
maybe sometimes we should think of sati usually translated as mindfulness
we should think of it as body fullness and that
how to live in a full body in the fullness of our body
and take time to do that when i teach retreats i sometimes
meditation retweets i sometimes give the instructions to
to walk around do the activities of the retreat
at the speed of mindfulness because often we do the speed of the mind
and you get caught in the mind the activity of the mind some people kind of zip around kind of fast and do things quickly
but the speed by which we can stay present for our body present in our experience
pretty present for our body fullness so to do things at the speed of
body fullness the speed of staying connected to your body know what's happening in your body
don't get disconnected your body this is a great exercise
and uh you might if you'd like uh spend this weekend
before next week we're going to do mindfulness of emotions and it turns out that the more you're
mindful of your body the easier it is to be mindful of emotions so you might want to spend this week at
this weekend kind of reviewing or looking over or practicing
body fullness seeing what it's like whenever it's appropriate in your weekend
to operate at the speed up operate at the speed of body fullness
mindfulness of the body thank you very much and i'm looking
forward to being back here on monday