and today um i will share the uh the suta that i've been uh
speaking about for this week uh maybe towards the end uh so we don't
all have to get occupied by reading the sutes but i will be sharing a link
at the end
so maybe just take a few moments to settle in
we'll begin with the arriving sequence again
if you like you can close your eyes
gently softly
arriving
as if you're arriving in a quiet meditation hall
bring some gentle kindness softness
and quiet as you settle in
taking seat
really taking your seat
feel the contact of your body with the chair or the floor
know that you're sitting
arriving here on your seat
leaving the contact of your feet on the ground
supported by earth
maybe there is a sense of the whole body landing
landing here and now
maybe a few long deep breaths to allow yourself to settle in
becoming available however so slightly
to the lived experience right here and now
sound movements of the breath
contacts of the body
being available evokes a sense of opening up
the awareness to receive
not wanting anything to happen
not driven by our preferences our wishes
just open open up
surrender to whatever shows up
allowing ourselves physically from ground up
sitting like a redwood
align our heart to mind along with the uplifting body
align with aspirations
align with a good will
align with non-harming
for me i feel a sense of the ease at ease
when there is that inner alignment with integrity
value and goodness in our heart and mind
softly and gently open to the felt sense of the earth
element the contact of a bones with the earth
firmness dance
settling downwards
resting in the valve sense of earth element in this earthy body
maybe the sense of assessability may come in a strand
like the big pillar
holding a structure of this body
feel the quietness of the bones
stillness however so slightly
the earth element in the backdrop of our awareness
becoming available to the felt sense of air element
winged moving through our bodies
so rising and falling up the belly as you breathe
expansion and contraction of the torso
different kinds of vibrations and buzzing in the body
dropping out of my ideas beliefs
feel and sense into
the elements
alive
flush each moment flush
i'm here we open and expand our field of
awareness to receive space
space that holds the earth element this body
space inside of the body and outside around us
gentle opening and expanding
to receive space
space all around where the sound travels
be a felt sense of a spaciousness in your being
however am i show up
for me there is a slight opening of the torso
slide opening of my shoulder blades
being available to space
there are different qualities of the felt sense of space
likeness
openness
and sometimes there may be slight brightness to it
or darkness
however it shows up for you
different elements are held in space
relax and ease into the space
there may be a different kind of a stillness related to space
a delicate kind of a space stillness
quiet
as if you can hear the sound of a silence
experiences can arise and pass
in this vast spacious field
and the space is unmoving unmoved
for the rest of her meditation you're welcome to stay
with space or receive
any other experiences that may seem prominent for you
releasing concepts ideas
match yourself melt away into the space
the buddha said to his son rahula rahula
meditated like a space when you meditate like a space
pleasant unpleasant contact will not occupy your mind
space doesn't tremble by the things that happen within it
the vast spaciousness
all experiences are free to be themselves
emotions thoughts sensations in the body
free to flow in the vast field of
spaciousness
if there is any form of well-being
oh some goodness that are bubbling up
allow them to permeate in the vastness
let your whole body and mind and heart be nourished
by the sense of a well-being
however much there is available to you
you [Music]
[Music]
welcome everyone feel quite sacred
to be in the space with you all the vast space holding out of us
meditating together
allow that goodness to touch you
and maybe support you on the path
so today we're going to continue our conversation
on sila and then we'll speak a little bit about
the last precept and then maybe do a
review on the whole territory of vasila
so this last precept many of you would know this
it's about undertaking the training rules of abstaining from intoxicants
drugs and alcohol that leads to heatlessness or cloudiness of our minds
well we all know that the danger of cloudy minds
right when our mind is not clear
and acting out from that kind of a cloudyness
dawnness we know we know what it feels like we know
what may happen so there is a real danger of that
and so this precept is inviting us to become really um clear
about this and say oh you know i'm not going to
play with the fire here this is like um i keep on using the
young children kids as examples i have my background my son is playing guitar you
might even have heard this um in our meditation
um and so it's like i'm telling young kids not to touch the hot stove
because it'll burn and if the kids really listen and then don't go anywhere close to it
they may never get burnt and over time they really know you know there is a danger and they understand
and so the same thing with this particular precept
it's pointing to the danger of a cloudy mind
and asking us well you know we've all heard so many stories
about what happens when one is drunk or um
get intoxicated i and the much harm has been done in so
many different ways so abstain from
taking drugs and intoxicants that clouds our mind
but there is also a deeper dimension of this particular precept
which is that the precept is pointing at the care and protection of a clear and
pure mind and heart
this is where the cultivation of awareness coming right
the precept invites us to cultivate awareness to become sensitive
to the conditions that leads to cloudiness dullness
and the conditions that leads to brightness in our mind and clarity in
our mind and heart
and so that's a dimension that invites all of us to
begin to pay careful attention to in fact it's not just intoxicants and
drugs and alcohol that clouds our mind and we you may have noticed even some
food or certain activities that can cloud our mind and cloud our being
or the way we take our food overeating and under eating
it can also lead to doneness and cloudiness
of our bodies and mind and so this cultivation of mindful
awareness is to begin to tune in to kind of those forces that may happen
within us and begin to learn to cultivate
the conditions that support and alert clear
mind and let go of the conditions that leads to
heatlessness and cloudiness of our mind and some of you may have
seen this that even you know for
nowadays if people you know play i don't know hours
of video games when they come out of their room
you look at them you know you just kind of feel there is sort of i don't know the tiredness
around on the person um [Music]
it can kind of create a different forms of energy when we engage in
activities it really kind of um does our mind
i remember one time when i was attending a conference
in las vegas that was a big casino with lots of big conference rooms and
one early morning i um was getting into the elevator to go down
to the conference rooms and there was a person walked in with a bucket of coins
it was very clear that the person had probably played a long time overnight or knows maybe a
whole night and the person looked very tired
when i looked into her eyes there were no sparks
at that moment i felt uh wow this felt lifeless
and so as if this hours and maybe whole night of gambling
had taken the sparks of life out of the person
so begin to pay attention to our activities
how we engage in our activities contribute
becoming conditions that can lead to dullness and cloudiness
of our mind and heart and we learn to abstain from them
and similarly in this meditation that we just did
maybe you have some experience a felt sense of clarity
and felt sense of alertness aliveness
sparks of our lives and so we began to know although these
are the conditions that brings the sparkles of our lives
life in us
and so with this kind of a clarity in our heart and mind
we can cultivate the entire um sila
domain that we've been talking about the five precepts
the more we become clear and uh aware
the more we can allow the depth and the richness of the practice of vasila
to mature in us so in this way
while cultivating sila not as a some form of a dogmatic holding
of you know we shall not do so and so you know this and that
or you know i'm getting a hundred out of a sela test
or we huff and puff and say oh you look at me or judging other people
i didn't do this and look how good i am
that's not what the sila practice is appointing to instead
the practice of sicila is an integral part of cultivation of
our whole heart and mind it's integral part of the dharma path
that leads to awakening freedom from dukkha
and when our bodies and verbal activities are aligned with
wholesome qualities of our mind and heart our actions and the speech
become a natural expressions of our heart and mind
and they bring much benefit to ourselves and to the world
and so i've been sharing the bits and pieces of this mangala sutta the suit of
blessings in this past week and so i wanted to maybe read you this
as a whole and this has many pieces that um
speaks to the cultivation of sila and then towards the end
also speaks about the cultivation of the fruit uh
i guess the fruit of cultivation of fasila samadhi and panya heart and mind
together so you receive this blessings and
there are many translations so i'm going to share the link uh just in a moment
and and the translation that i've been sharing uh is
based on banti sujato and this is not the only translation so you can look at
the different translations and see if some of this speaks to you
and for me not a single translation kind of speaks uh everything um
[Music] connected with me in a way that um
i would say different translations may connect with me in different ways so feel free to explore that
so here are the blessings so it starts by
saying that there is a deity who showed up at the in front of the buddha asking the buddha
to declare the highest blessing or the greatest of blessings
so here we go so i have heard at one time the buddha was staying near
sabahti in jittas grove ananta pentika's monastery
then late at night a glorious deity lightening up the entire gita's grove
went up to the buddha bowed and stood to one side
that deity addressed the buddha in verse many gods and humans have thought about
the blessings desiring well-being declare the highest blessing
the person the deity is asking the buddha to declare the highest blessing
buddha said in the first one i'm going to use an alternative translation here which
i associate a little more it says not to associate with the fools but to
associate with the wise and honoring those worthy of honor
this is the highest blessing like we are here together
living in a suitable region having made a merits in the past
being rightly resolved in oneself this is the highest blessing
education and the craft discipline and training and well-spoken speech
this is the highest blessing caring for mother and father
kindness to children and partners and all stressful work
this is the highest blessing giving and a righteous conduct kindness
to relatives blameless deeds this is the highest blessing
desisting and abstaining from evil avoiding alcoholic drinks
diligence in good qualities this is the highest blessing
respect and humility contentment and gratitude and timely listening to the
teaching this is the highest blessing patience
being easy to admonish the site of aesthetics and a timely
discussion of the teaching this is the highest blessing
austerity and celibacy seeing the noble truth and the realization of extinguishment
this is the highest blessing though touched by worldly conditions
their mind does not tremble sorrowless stainless secure
this is the highest of blessing having completed these things undefeated
everywhere everywhere they go in safety this
is their highest blessing
so may you all find the true safety within
may all beings find safety within
thank you so much everyone i'm just truly delighted spending all these days with you