so
in doing uh this buddhist path
doing meditation practice
it's certainly helpful to relax
to calm the places that are over
activated to relax the places that are
overly tense
to bring tranquility to the ways in
which we're
anxious or agitated
and sometimes then the emphasis emphasis
is on the relaxation
on the rel on the calming
but one of the things that's very
important to
develop on this path of practice
is a skill is a heightened sensitivity
to the tension to the agitation
to the the ways in which we
uh
get tense
and the reason for that is that we want
to become skilled at we want to be able
to recognize it well
and clearly so that it becomes something
we
pick up early as it begins
or so that we become more aware of the
more subtle ways in which
we get caught and cling if we're only
focusing on the relaxation and the calm
we might not become experts at
perceiving attention
and now all the tensions we feel
tension in the body not maybe i
shouldn't say all but most of it
probably represents some way that the
mind is clinging to something
it's fixated on something it's pushing
on something
in the mind and the much of the physical
tension that we have represents
something deeper in the mind
and the surface tensions of the mind
that we might feel when we're really you
know anxious or upset
or tense around something also
represents probably something deeper in
the mind some deeper
place of holding of clinging of
attachment
and so even though it may be talking
about physical relaxation
what we're relaxing is something that
has its source
in the mind deep in the mind the
clinging in the mind
and so the idea is to start becoming
more sensitive
to clinging to tension and that has many
benefits
one is that it can help us go further
and further and deeper and deeper into
practice because we've gotten used to
we've gotten
familiar with all little ways that that
clinging appears in our body and mind
and heart
but also we can
it's also a protection for ourselves
that it protects our practice because
it's very easy
to practice with tension practice with
attachment
and we don't see it so i mean
paradoxically a person
could get the instructions just relax
your tension
and they get so serious about the
relaxing and that
they tense up around let's do let's have
to really do it well here
the teacher says to relax and by golly
i'm going to relax i'm going to be the
best relaxer
anywhere and then we relax certainly we
relax part of the body but the mind has
gotten tense in the effort to push
anything any instruction people get in
practice
we can get attached to the instruction
any idea of what might happen in
practice we get attached to
wanting that to happen or attached to
somehow clinging
kind of a negative clinging to oh that's
not happening to me it's not possible
for me
that doesn't relate to me or that's not
right
so there can be this tension is holding
on to that
in a way that limits our freedom
and so if we start becoming skilled
at recognizing tension then we recognize
the very
tension that's involved in how we
practice what we're looking for
wanting to have happen in practice and
so it becomes a protection
that we're not ahead of ourselves in
practice that we're not trying to make
something happen or
expect something to happen that's not
actually what is happening
the default is always to come back to
what is happening
and in doing that again we recognize
maybe how we're tense
recognize the pushing the striving the
contraction that might be there and then
as we
let go of that then there's an influence
that has on us
and part of this recognizing tension
deeper and deeper is that we can
recognize what is not
tension we can recognize the impact that
has on us to let go
to soften to relax and we can recognize
that there's
more happening here than the tension
i've certainly had the experience of
being overly concerned with my tension
in my body and mind
that or overly concerned with something
i'm supposed to do
like focus on the breathing that i
didn't notice that in the wider picture
of what's going on
there was in fact some subtleness some
calmness some
uh peacefulness some actually some some
very subtle kind of delight and just
being here
and i was so fixated and concerned with
my preoccupation
and so this idea of relaxing and opening
the attention to feel the influence of
relaxation the influence of
tranquility allows us to feel some of
the other goodness that's here
some of the other things that are
actually going well for us
and and this is
the because as as
this anapanasati deepens we want to
uh broaden the attention to take in the
bigger picture as well
of what's happening so the joy
and the happiness of practice the
contentment
belongs to this kind of little bit
bigger picture
and it might be subtle nothing dramatic
and we might then get fixated get
attached to having joy
attached to having happiness and or
disappointed that we don't have it
and that's tension and if we
again if we are skilled at looking at
tension we'll catch it right away
so it doesn't trip us up oh there's
tension
maybe rather than looking for joy i
should look for i should really spend
time
feeling that tension so he can relax it
can soften
or let me not be limited by the tension
let me kind of uh
open up the attention wide or not in a
fixated way
but in an open relaxed way
and so the um
and then but then as we open if we do
feel some of the goodness of the
relaxation some of the goodness of
the practice that's occurring uh i think
of it as the atmosphere
uh the or the mood of a room or the
atmosphere of a situation we're in we
we can go into i've gone into some
places and the atmosphere is clearly
peaceful and i feel like i'm being
washed in peacefulness
i go into other atmospheres of your
social atmospheres and just feels
immediately feels very
tense the whole thing so the kind of the
atmosphere within us
and and take in the atmosphere of the
goodness
even if it's subtle and breathe with
that
not to deny other things not to lose our
ability to notice when we get tense or
tight or
contracted or resistant or
all the different expressions of
clinging but as a way
of creating a nice atmosphere
that supports the further letting go of
clinging
that gives us confidence that gives us
some sense of
the rightness of the moment as opposed
to it's so easy to focus on the
wrongness of the moment
some people are really experts at this
and and this is not to make a polyanis
view everything is good
but it's to create an atmosphere that
allows us to hold and be with the
difficulties
in a way that we don't get fixated or
cling to them
or resist them too tightly
so all this is a way of saying that part
of what we were doing in this practice
is becoming an expert on tension
and so even though if the emphasis might
be on relaxing
don't become tense because you're trying
to relax or because you can't relax
keep remembering that recognizing and
learning to feel
sense and becoming more of a connoisseur
all the different flavors and textures
of tension
of clinging of holding of attachment is
actually a very important part of the
practice
and the so you want to take some time to
feel it and get to know it
and and not to be in a hurry to relax or
not
not in a hurry to to get rid of anything
that's uncomfortable
because the lesson of what you what you
learn
by really feeling it fully
is you learn how to be prepared better
for next time
how to catch it earlier how to protect
yourself from being caught in it
next time so
part of this buddhist path is to become
skilled
intention not skilled in tensing
um because we don't want to be you know
learn better how to tense
but uh skilled and recognizing tension
and seeing it when it's there seeing it
sometimes almost when it's beginning
and the last thing i'll say about this
is that importance of not confusing
tension with intentness
sometimes there's an intentness that has
a certain energy and engagement
that um and wholeheartedness
that doesn't have the quality of
limitation or
or debilitation that tension or clinging
has
but it's really present there can be
intentness of the body and tentness
of the mind i'm here this is what i'm
doing i'm involved in this
but there's no tension there's maybe a
tautness but no
contraction or tentness
and um so because sometimes people when
they hear relax
relax their intentness they relax their
healthy tautness and they become moved
towards becoming just a
slouch just kind of move towards
becoming just a
you know too limp to really
let the vitality or practice operate
so certainly
relaxing calming becoming tranquil
peaceful is a support for this practice
but don't overlook the important work of
becoming skilled at recognizing tension
and um and maybe take some delight and
satisfaction
as you become more and more connoisseur
of all the different ways that you're
tense and rather
being disappointed when you see it you
say oh fantastic
i get to study this and get to know it
better
it's not so pleasant right now to the
tension in and of itself
but in the long term i'm much better off
to really
become the student of tension before i
focus too much on relaxing
so thank you and uh
so uh tomorrow morning as well
we'll have this uh 6 45
64 45 sitting and a little talk
at 7 30 and tomorrow diana clark
will lead it she's my co-teacher for
this retreat
i'm teaching this week and and i'll take
the morning that early morning off
and and she'll come in and offer
something for the sitting and
and then we'll continue with this
anapanasati
uh with step nine uh moving forward now
on monday thank you