so good good morning to those of you joining us now we're going to be waiting until 7
to start our meditation together so please relax and enjoy uh
being together for a few minutes
uh
we've actually got some people on youtube saying good morning um from tucson columbus ohio santa fe
uh nancy says ohayo gozaimasu welcome welcome um sir people uh
just kind of announcing we are not having a kind of uh we've got some people in the waiting room but
um uh today we'll just be doing youtube so um if you want to post your questions
there um we'll be passing them on to foo at the end of her
um darmat this morning
just a few more minutes and then we'll start
um
you
good morning from berkeley santa cruz orches island washington eugene oregon
good morning good morning all of you welcome
oh lancaster county pennsylvania
magic
okay if i'm gonna go on mute and feel free to go whenever you're ready all right thank you kevin yep thank you
very much well good morning all of you it was wonderful to hear all the names of the places
where you're coming in from you're probably a little surprised to see me this morning uh knowing that this is gil fransdale's
program that he does in the mornings and if you haven't heard already gill and paul haller who was teaching
last week and myself are sharing these three weeks during what we're calling a
zen and vipassana intensive and we've also been sharing this morning program very very kindly
offered by gil so we can introduce ourselves to you um so my name is foo schrader and i'm
the abiding abbess at greengulch farm zen center in marin county california
gill was a young student here a young farm apprentice many years ago and so i've known him for a long time
and i have admired him ever since as a teacher of vipassana style
meditation practice gail welcomed us to participate in this program to share
our own versions of meditation instruction so first of all i want to say that i
have never done a western-style vipassana retreat and therefore i am not familiar or trained in guided
meditation i have however done many many years of zen style meditation and that's what i'm
here to share with you this morning and for the next four days so throughout this three-week intensive
gil paul and i have been focusing on one of the three classical categories of training
through which the buddha taught the dharma he taught ethics or morality sheila
meditation samadhi and wisdom the first two weeks we focused on
meditation and wisdom and this week we are focusing on ethics and morality
which are basically the guidelines by which we humans not only learn how to live and work
together but also how to take care of one another so for
the next 20 minutes or so we are going to enter into a period of silent meditation together in what soto-zen
which is my tradition i've studied in what we call silent illumination so to begin this
period of silent meditation i want to just briefly remind you about the points of your posture that
help support upright sitting you know first you find a comfortable and stable
position for your legs and your torso and then gently allow the energy of your
core body to move upward toward the top of your head like a spring that's bubbling up from
dry ground now let the muscles of your face your
shoulders your back and arms relax and like the water of the spring let the
tension just pour down over the surface of your entire body
allowing it to spread out and to nourish the space around you as far as your imagination can reach
allow your eyes to remain open with a soft focus on the wide space that's in
front of you take a couple of deep breaths through your mouth
and then return to your normal breathing through the nose
and now as we are instructed by the founder of our school of zen dogan zenji
think of not thinking how do you think of not thinking a
student asked non-thinking he says
this is the essential art of zazen
[Applause]
uh
welcome back from from wherever you might have been um perhaps with the parts of your body
or with some feeling maybe some sensory awareness or
thoughts about the past plans for the future most likely all of the above
so i probably probably should introduce myself to you who just joined expecting gail fransdale uh gill and
another close dharma friend paul haller are sharing for three weeks a teaching on
we call the harmony of zen and vipassana so we've all practiced in both of these
traditions well actually i haven't in the papasana but i have now listening
in on gil's teaching it's been quite wonderful um so our idea is to help us
here at sen center as well as inviting all of you who are most familiar with vipassana
teachings to have a taste of one another's style of practicing the dharma
so the buddha called the many parts of our lived experience the ten thousand things which basically
means reality itself in which a lot appears to be going on
and all the time so this we know so when we become aware of just how much
is going on as you experienced this morning it often helps to take a
bit of time and enough space to quiet ourselves to slow the many processes of our thinking and the
activities of moving around you know just long enough to take a look at ourselves
and that the internal clockwork that is driving our busy lives so given how
deeply we are conditioned not to stop moving except for dreamless sleep we're most
always busy both inside and outside
so the buddha met his own busyness by sitting down under a tree for many days on end something that all
of us do when we go on retreat either vipassana or zen sashin and even for
a brief time this morning as we sat together and as as we're doing now just stopping taking
a break resting a bit so the buddha didn't give us too many words about his experience
that morning of the eighth day of his silent sitting when he looked up at the star and then
he said wonderful wonderful i and all beings on
earth attain enlightenment at the same time i and all beings on earth attain
enlightenment at the same time so this statement has been talked about now for several millennia
and just what did he see and what did he mean by what he said
so one way of understanding what the buddha meant was that the star what he saw and the earth all things and
all beings all the objects of his awareness were not separate
were not outside of himself in other words that awareness and the
objects of our awareness are not two separate things and although we can reason how that is so that is not
how we normally think and that is not how we behave
so explaining the buddhist enlightenment experience in this way is called the teaching of
non-duality or of no two things and is a very important
understanding for us to have in order to know the deep meaning of what the buddha taught so one of the
things that we're endeavoring to learn on meditation retreats is how deeply ingrained
inside ourselves is this notion of existing separately from the world around us
we humans have even created languages that confirm that notion all day long
my home my children my friends my enemies my country
my job so we say in which all of these possessions belong
to me which then leaves me as separate singular and isolated
and in extreme cases causes great suffering there may in fact be none worse than the
belief that we are truly alone so along with the wisdom teachings the
other body of teachings that point directly at this type of suffering are the teachings of ethics or morality
ethics and precepts and moral guidelines have been given to us in order to
connect us to one another you know in order to bring harmony to humankind
through connecting practices such as generosity and patience and of course through
wisdom so as the buddha traveled through as buddhism and
the buddhist teaching traveled through many cultures and crystallized into these many forms and expressions
one of the expressions that i'm going to talk about with you this week is called the 16 bodhisattva precepts
which are in truth one precept the precept of how i over here
promise to take care of you over there as an enactment of the buddha's awakened
vision that i and you are in truth not in any way separate at all
so we are interdependent and we are free there's two sides of the same coin as
the buddha declared at that moment of his awakening i and all beings awakening at the same
time one whole being one whole life one whole precept
for embodying just how that is so so the one whole precept when it's
broken into many parts that make up our complex human life sound like this beginning with what are called
the three refuges i take refuge in buddha as the enlightened teacher
i take refuge in dharma as the enlightened teaching i take refuge in sangha as the
enlightened life and then there are the three pure precepts
i vow to embrace and sustain right conduct i vow to embrace and sustain all good
i vow to embrace and sustain all beings and then finally there's a
more detailed recitation of those actions that we take against others that cause the greatest harm
and we can read about these every day in the newspaper breaking the bond of our shared humanity
these are the 10 grave precepts or promises that i make to each of you i vow not to kill you
to steal from you to sexualize you or lie to you i vow not to poison your
body or mind with intoxicants i vow not to slander you praise myself
at your expense withhold my possessions or my knowledge from you
harbor ill will toward you and as a kind of summary vow i vow not
to disparage the three treasures the teaching the teacher of awakening the buddha the teaching of
awakening the dharma or the community of those who are devoted to awakening you know
this sangha that's us so studying the buddhist precepts is
studying the clockwork of our actions in the world and the consequences of those actions
wherein saying and doing are the primary elements through which each of us
together creates either a world of bondage or a world of freedom saying
and doing both arise from how we think which is why one of perhaps the best
known of the buddhist teachings is from an ancient collection of verses called the dhammapada
the footsteps of the truth what we are today comes from our
thoughts of yesterday and our present thoughts build our life of tomorrow
our life is a creation of our mind if a person speaks or acts with an
impure mind suffering follows them like the wheel of the cart follows the beast that draws
the cart if a person speaks or acts with a pure mind
joy follows them as their own shadow he beat me she hurt me they defeated me
he robbed me those who think such thoughts will not be free from hate she insulted me
he cheated me they defeated me he beat me those who think not such thoughts will
be free from hate hate is not conquered by hate hate is
conquered by not hating this is the eternal law
many do not know that we are here in this world to live in harmony with one another those who know this do
not fight against each other so not fighting against each other is
the main effort that we are all making as teachers and as students of the buddhadharma
and the teacher who inspired my understanding of the dharma was a japanese zen master shinrio suzuki roshi who came
to america in 1959 to share with us his own unique inspired vision of the
buddhist teaching you know he came looking for us so many of you are undoubtedly familiar
with zenmind beginner's mind published over 50 years ago now and among the many things suzuki roshi
said some of them were directly about the 16 bodhisattva precepts also known in the zen tradition as the
blood vein of the buddhas and the ancestors receiving the precepts is a way of
understanding what it means to just sit the integration of precepts and
meditation is the foundation for all of the practices and activities of our daily life
so this identity of meditation with precepts is also one by my own teacher attention anderson
called his book on the precepts being upright being upright
and one image for helping us to understand the function of these precepts as teachers have said is as a map of the
buddha's world taking the bodhisattva precepts begins by orienting
ourselves to the buddha's example and enlightened vision the buddha's awakening as someone
recently said even taking a single step is sufficient if you are headed in the right direction
so tomorrow and for the next three days i'm going to be sharing more of the stories and teachings about the precepts
that underlie our sitting practice the first of those being taking refuge in which another of our
founding sound ancestors dogen zenji said the essence of transmission of bodhisattva precepts is
taking refuge meaning that when we follow the map the teaching of nonduality and enter the
buddha's world we are taking refuge in clearly seeing reality itself
vipassana with all of its dents and illusions mistakes stories and
release taking refuge in buddha is another name for intimacy with all the
things that we are or rather all the things that we seem to be
another name for turning toward the world the buddha taught that the root of all
evil is ignorance or turning away from the world a fuzzy thrilling unreliable ungraspable
creation where the self cannot abide as separate
when sitting upright in the fuzzy ungraspable world with whatever seems to be happening
we come to realize that something we are used to seeing is missing and that something
would be me me in the form of my old habits of thought
my preferences my self-centeredness my fears and isolation and most of all my fantasies
so it's at times like this that the me tries to take control of the elements of existence for its own
safety and benefit and although the shields go up again and again
they are not holding so the precepts are a different kind of armor the armor of taking vows of making
promises and that's what i'll share with you in these next few days so to end for this morning here is a
brief teaching on precepts by the founder of the zen center miyu suzuki roshi from a collection of
his talks in a book called not always so so in the full lotus position
we cross the right leg over the left and the left leg over the right symbolically the right is activity and
the left is the opposite calmness of mind if the left is wisdom
the right is practice and when we cross our legs we don't know which is which
so even though we have two symbolically we also have one our posture is vertical without
leaning right or left backward or forward this is an expression of perfect understanding of the teaching that is
beyond duality when we extend this we naturally have precepts
and the study of how to observe our precepts this posture of zazen is not just a kind
of training but is the actual way of transmitting buddha's teaching to us
words by themselves are not good enough to actualize his teaching so it is transmitted through activity or
through human relationships well thank you very much
we're just about a time kevin offered very kindly to relay any questions you have so if you
do i'd be happy to respond uh so i think we've just got one
question here from uh leslie she asked what translation of the dharmapatha is that
yeah that's good i know it's an old one that i've had for many years um it is penguin classic
juan mascaro and i think this was translated
one of the first books i think i got 1973.
i know there are many different versions i happen to like this one i like the poetry of it
okay well um then we'll end i just want to thank you all who have come i'm sorry i can't see you
um but here we are so uh i'll be back tomorrow
and i'll be talking about the refuges and offering some more meditation kind of like content
or tone from zen teachings that have been meaningful for me and uh
and then we'll sit together and have another discussion so again thank you very much
phu we also had actually another question come in um from paul i said what do we do with our eyes
while meditating yeah well i noticed that gil gives
people the options so absurd i would never say that you don't have the option of course you do um and then we say to keep the eyes open
and partly the understanding being with the eyes closed it's much easier to enter into dreams
and to fantasies and so by having your eyes open it's a little hard to escape the reality of
that whatever is sitting in front of you so it's a way of connecting us to the present and where we're sitting
at this time so you can try both i've i've certainly tried them both and i find leaving my eyes opens more
supportive uh for my meditation
thank you very much foo thank you kevin thank you everyone have a nice day please stay safe