so warm greetings everyone
and we're continuing this process of
this exploration of samadhi and often in buddhism in
english buddhist buddhisms often enough the deepening levels of samadhi are
sometimes called absorptions to be absorbed
and in some ways it's an apt uh description of them the um
if we liken it to the idea of uh being absorbed in a good book or absorbed and listening to music or
um absorbed in some hot craft that we're doing that absorbed in a movie that uh
to absorb just to be fully uh attentive to it where kind of all our
senses are either focused on what we're doing or the senses kind of have receded from
receded from getting much attention from us so if you're absorbed in a book you
might not be listening so much to what's going around you someone might even talk to you and you don't hear them
because you're really absorbed and but not in meditation it's not a
it's an absorb that kind of absorption is one of great interest or usually there's a kind of sense of
goodness or wholesomeness and people usually part of the joy of being absorbed in a book or something is the
absorption itself and so same thing with samadhi it's a
very nice state of absorption it's not a turning off of the world but rather it's letting the
world around us fall away as we enter into a very wholesome healthy
state a healthy kind of and all the you know steps of anapanasati these
steps of deepening meditation are steps that are opening up and
evoking healthier and healthier states of being inside and of course it's not always going to
be that way and it's a process to get there but to know that we're looking for the inner health
we're looking to recognize where nourishment is what's wholesome is here and so we do that in the very beginning
trying to can we approach meditation in a healthy
wholesome way without greed or contraction or conceit or pouncing on things or
strong aversion trying to escape and push things away can we have a spirit of generosity
of kindness a warmth of good will and ease as we start engaging
our attentional capacities our ability to bring attention and then we begin finding where as we
pay attention how to evoke and spread and develop good feelings in the body partly because
we're starting to relax this process of relaxation is such a healthy thing to do
and and so as as a meditation deepens at some point the inner
health the inner goodness the nourishment the wholesomeness feels so great that it becomes easier
and easier to be absorbed in that to feel connected to it to be really there and
so to be absorbed and i also delight in the idea that that
of using the metaphor of a sponge a sponge absorbs water and the same way
there's a we absorb the sensations we absorb this experience of breathing
we allow it to just kind of like the whole body is the sponge and um and we just kind of like are
there to receive and be take in the whole experience of the present moment
in a receptive way in an open way and and the sponges i don't think force the
world to force the itself to absorb water just that's what it is
sponges do they just absorb so this absorption that absorbs the absorption
that really let's allows there to be a kind of a intimacy and a receptivity in a
to our experience to our breathing to be absorbed in the breathing
so assuming a meditation posture
and perhaps sitting in such a way meditating such a posture where the chest is a little bit more
open open to be receptive and sometimes when the chest is a little
more open it's a little bit more useful than or
capable to relax the belly so softness throughout the front of our
body soft front and sometimes it said that in meditation
we have a soft front and a strong back
and so to feel this especially if you're sitting upright to feel a little bit of strength
in the back stability
maybe adjusting the vertebrae a little bit so the spine is a little bit more aligned
centered and instead of strength
maybe some of you prefer the word stability
stability strength of the back and the softness and openness in the front
and to gently close your eyes and to take a few long slow deep breaths
kind of a ritual procedure for adjusting your state of mind
your state of body your attitude
into one that can begin to be absorbed in this practice of meditation
that is put aside temporarily its concerns of the past and the future or other
places other times it is prepared preparing itself
to settle in here and now
and then letting your breathing return to normal
to continue this process of softening the front of our body by as you exhale softening the face
face is where we present to the world so much but in meditation we don't need to
activate the face we can let it rest
on the exhale softening the shoulders
releasing to the pull of gravity the weight of the shoulders
adjusting your arms so that they can be loose and relaxed
softening in the chest
and relaxing the belly
and wherever you feel you're breathing the predominant place the common place
for experiencing the body breathing imagine that location
is a sponge for the sensations
of breathing so it's not so much that you're in the control tower
thinking looking down at breathing it's more like you
are that sponge in the body especially the inhale absorbing
the sensations of the inhale
and if those sensations are like water then in the exhale spreading
the goodness of that water throughout the body
absorbing the inhale and releasing it all on the exhale
throughout the body
and can you adjust your mind a little bit
so your mind is more like doing tai chi mental tai chi of receiving and flowing
moving along with the breathing
maybe as if the mind becomes more and more like water flowing
with and over and through the breathing
or as if the mind also gets absorbed into the body the body sponge
and abiding in the body breathing
abiding in intimacy will you turn yourself over to your
breathing entrusting yourself to your breathing
absorbed in the goodness of breathing
and whenever you exhale and you need to remember to let go of whatever takes you
away from your breathing let the breathing be the center of it
all the foundation of everything
the beginning of it all the end of it all just breathing
being absorbed in breathing not as a rejection of anything else
but in a way let everything else recede to the background
where your interest your involvement
your life energy
is intimately involved connected to
breathing
perhaps it's easier to be absorbed in the breathing if you make a small half smile with your
lips just turn up the corners of your lips just a little bit
it maybe shifts the mood just enough then it's easier to flow with the
breathing
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to bring forth whatever
good will tenderness love that might live in your heart
that lives within you in whatever way that that caring
loving part of you can come forth as we sit here
and breathe with that
let that be absorbed into the bodies the sponge as you breathe in
and may that spread through your body as you exhale
like water being absorbed and then dispersed
the water of love and kindness compassion good will
and without any responsibility to act on your love your goodwill
to simply sit here open to it
feel it and see if you can
sit quietly for a few moments more gazing kindly with kind eyes
on the people of your life those you know well those you barely
know
strangers and perhaps and thinking about
maybe some of the people you will encounter today without needing to do anything with them
at all this while you're sitting here see can you gaze upon them kindly
can you hold them in the warmth of your heart
and taking a few moments to do this he expresses our a wish
that our meditation practice supports us
in bringing helpful healthy attitudes to this world
around us that meditation is not just for ourselves
but it's also for how we see and relate to others
and maybe we unders discover more and more how that's the case
may it be that we meditate for the welfare and happiness of all beings
ourself included may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
you