good evening welcome
welcome so of course you guys can't see what I'm seeing here but we're starting
to get ready for being in person so things are set up here a little bit
differently looking forward to when we can practice together and not to worry
we'll continue with the YouTube recordings and offerings
also but I know some of you are local and might like to come to
IMC but a warm welcome to everybody whether you're local or far
away and whether you're listening to this now or sometime in the
future a warm
welcome so we'll start with a little lightly guided meditation
taking our
seat and just feeling into what does it feel like right
now to be sitting
There maybe globally there's a sense of relief like oh okay I'm just going to be
sitting here for the next little
while or maybe there's some restlessness like really am I really going to sit
here for the next little while whatever our experience might be
it's all welcome it's all welcome it doesn't have to be one particular way
can be helpful to connect with whatever it is we're sitting
on cushion bench
chair couch
bed just feeling the pressure against the body
and then when we sit and start to settle down a little
bit perhaps the breathing becomes noticeable
possible this body breathes of course it
does can we in a kind gentle
way rest our attention on the sensations of breathing
feeling the inhales in the chest or the
abdomen per or perhaps feeling the air going in and out of the
nose
feeling the expansion the stretching with the
inhales for the coolness of the air
then of course the inhales are interspersed with
exhales how do they feel
you can focus on just one area if you'd like the chest the abdomen or the
nose feeling the opposite of expansion a little bit
of deflation maybe even though that doesn't sound very
inviting but the air being exchanged and then going
out and just feeling this rhythm inhale exhale
and when the mind wanders which it naturally will
do just very simply begin again we don't have to make it a problem we don't have
to make a story out of it it doesn't have to mean anything in particular it
just means we were lost in thought and then we begin again
nothing in particular needs to be
happening we're just noticing the experiences of
breathing and just allowing the mind to come back when it gets lost in thought
and you might notice that there is an
uncomfortable experience uncomfortable
sensation and a relaxed next easy way can
we distinguish can we tease
apart is there a bodily physical
aspect to the uncomfortable situation and is there a mental aspect
that is maybe there's a sharp sensation in the
knee and the mind is starting to think
like make up stories i'll never be able to meditate
with this sensation i'll never be able to go on retreat where they sit longer how do
those people sit longer they must be abnormal or have done it since they were
young and when I was young we didn't sit in a way that was very flexible but
there was that person that was in third grade that was so flexible i remember she used to play on the monkey bars all
the time and be doing all these things wow do they still have those at schools these days what would it be like to go
play on them i hope they do kids should play outside right here we go so there's
kind of like the mental aspect and the physical
aspect can we notice that sometimes the mental aspect leads us
off where I just let us was off into a fantasy but sometimes it might be a I'm
damaging my knee i better shift my posture
i can't believe this is terrible i'll never be able to do it this is so hard
and we're saying things to ourselves that just exacerbating or amplifying the
uncomfortableness and to be sure we need to use wisdom and not sit through pain
if we feel like we're harming ourselves that is not what this practice is about
but when there is some uncomfortableness can we tease apart can we separate can
we distinguish the bodily experience from
the mental
experience and then as best we can to place our awareness on the bodily
experience it's a little bit more
steady so moving slower than the
thoughts bodily experience is staying here this moment
maybe the uncomfortable experience is some aversion oh I really don't want
this why is this happening
can we tease apart can we distinguish the
aversion and often we have aversion to the aversion so our reaction to the
experience can we tease those
apart and interrupt the aversion train
can we just be with the one version of a
version of course you have aversion to aversion it's a natural human response
but we don't have to amplify it
making this distinction between bodily experiences
and mental experiences
and making the distinction between our reactions and our
experiences enables us to see more clearly what is actually
happening teasing apart some of the different elements and this way we
can have some more choices about what to do have some more clarity about what
might be the helpful the skillful thing to do going
forward so that it might support us and we're also having the ability to
tease apart different elements to see more clearly to distinguish to discern
also helps us to help others so that we don't get lost
in experiences that some kind sometimes can be
overwhelming but instead to maybe pull out the
pieces or where we actually have some control or some
choices so that in this way our practice of discerning
distinguishing can be for the benefit not only for ourselves but for
others so may our practice be for the benefit of all beings everywhere
[Music]
good evening welcome welcome
so tonight I'd like to first extend a really warm welcome to
everybody and to continue on the series that I've been doing on the
Paramese in the earlier talks I didn't say that much about the parameies in
particular and I'll just say a little bit now pammy often gets translated as
perfections i like to translate them as perfections of the heart to emphasize that they're
not just one more list of things to memorize and they're not just gaining
more and more knowledge but to bring all aspects of ourselves including our
hearts so p me can means also can mean something that's of really high value
like something that has a maybe like a type of wealth an inner type of wealth
that we all have but these parameies can be cultivated and be
developed and there's a list of 10 of them and interestingly that in this list
of 10 there isn't a meditation in particular instead these are things to
do in our everyday day lives so it's not just a meditative
experiences although that's included but it's um qualities that we bring to all aspects of our
lives so the list of 10 is generosity ethical behavior
renunciation wisdom so the fourth one wisdom is what I'd like to talk about tonight
and then energy patience truth resolve
loving kindness and equinimity i think we can all agree that these are good
qualities to have in our lives whether it's part of your spiritual practice or just part of being a human being a good
parent a good friend a good worker whatever it might be
so I'd like to just say a little bit about wisdom which as I mentioned is the fourth part of me wisdom is um how often
this word pa gets translated also some other translations
for pa are insight or discernment and I was thinking about
this idea of wise and we often have the I don't know where this comes from
exactly but we have this um owls are portrayed as
wise and when We think about well why are owls you know like historically or
why might we say that owls are wise and it's because they have such big
eyes like their eyes are like a dominant feature of
owls and I think this is really appropriate because wisdom in kind of in the Buddhist sense and the way that
we're going to talk about it and explore it and develop is not about just gaining
knowledge not about getting those advanced degrees or reading those books or knowing the all the lists it's not
about that wisdom is about seeing seeing
clearly this is why the connection with owls with the big eyes it's about seeing
clearly and to say that wisdom is the fourth part of me that it follows after
renunciation and just at a really high level there's a few ways that we can understand
renunciation but one is a simplification like simplifying get rid
of the extraneous distractions things that we
don't need that are getting in the way getting in the way of our living our
best life so one way to think about renunciation is to simplify and to let go of what's
not needed another way to think about renunciation as
non-addiction joseph Goldstein says this and I kind of like it nonaddiction so that is to notice what
are our habits our habitual behaviors that we're just falling
into without thought just because it's what we've always been doing we might
have inherited these habits and in particular the Buddha
points to to notice our habit of always chasing after sensual pleasures things that taste good that sound good that
feel good and somehow kind of insisting that our experience be filled with sensual
pleasures and our annoyance when it isn't so renunciation about simplifying
and noticing what habits we have and letting go of those habits that aren't so helpful
and we could see then why how renunciation leads to wisdom is that as
we start to remove some of the extra that which isn't essential then it
be we are able to see more clearly see more clearly our
lives see more clearly the direction we're going see more clearly our values
what's important to us and see more clearly how all of our
experiences are made up of different elements and that gets us to wisdom
so one way there's a number of ways we can talk about wisdom and one is the
capacity the ability the activity of discerning or distinguishing or making
um distinctions you know to kind of like tease things
apart so for example we might have the experience of of thinking that well it's
time to meditate or thinking we should meditate but then also having the idea I feel so
antsy like I there's no way I can meditate so but antsy this word is kind of a
vague description and we can might be able to
get a little bit quieter or pay a little bit of attention and to see oh yeah this
word antsy restless has different elements to
it might have this bodily sensation maybe there's this
uh sense of fidgeting fidgeting a lot or there's a sense of like the body i know
sometimes when I'm feeling restless or antsy I just find myself standing up like if I'm sitting down or even if I'm
get at my desk intending to focus on the task at hand I just find myself standing
up and going to do something else or so there's this like this uh energy
in the body perhaps kind of like this movement of wanting to move or if not standing up maybe it's felt as uh just
um like ping pongs bouncing around so that might be the physical experience
but then of course there's these mental elements maybe there's a sense of just
being really distracted that is not being able to land on one particular thought or or one particular
experience for example the sensations of breathing and then we find ourselves
like starting something and then doing this or that and not finishing and going to do that bouncing all over the
place either in meditation or in daily
life but then if we can pay a little bit more attention even so after the kind of
like separating the physical and the mental is there something else that we
can see see a little bit more clearly then we can see oh yeah there's
a sense of worried feeling worried about something and that's what's fueling that
feeling antsy so when we notice and name the different
elements that are happening or that are comprising our experience there can be a sense of relief a sense of like oh okay
I'm worried of course I'm worried i have to give this big
presentation tomorrow or my loved one is not feeling well or whatever it might be
but just being able to tease apart some of the different elements to name them can start to bring
some clarity and and start to make it feel a little bit more manageable this is so much about mindfulness practice i
think probably many of you already know this but this is we consider as kind of
wisdom is this ability to pull things apart and see more
clearly because the greater the distinctions we make about what's going
Excuse me here
so the greater the distinctions we make about what's going on the more choices we have about how we're going to relate
to our experience an example I just gave
being worried once we notice we're worried like "Oh okay of course I'm
worried." And somehow it takes some of the pressure off that things should be
different and then there's something else to distinguish and that is between our experiences with all of its
components being antsy and our reaction to that
experience our response to it every moment there's two things
happening there's what's happening and then there's our response to what's happening and to be able to tease those
apart also is one way we might think about wisdom and so there might be something
uncomfortable happening and then in in relationship to that uncomfortable
experience there might be some fear might be some aversion some blame some
anger and as long as we're focused on the actual experience we might not be
seeing the fear the blame the anger that's happening and to recognize
that the experience and the relationship to the experience are two separate
things and as I mentioned in the guided meditation it's not uncommon to have
aversion to things that are uncomfortable but then to have aversion
to the aversion and then to have the aversion that we have aversion to
aversion so wherever we can disrupt that momentum is
helpful so just keeping in mind that can we sometimes it's helpful to pay
attention to our reaction to the our response to our experience not only our
experience so and then that aables enables us to make different choices
we're not just being um carried along by the tumbling along by the momentum of
what's happening so this ability to make some distinctions to simplify tease things
apart is one function of wisdom and it's not only just so that we can see more
clearly but to see more clearly allows us to make new choices to respond in
different ways and to respond in ways that are
helpful and supportive
but then there's also another way there's a number of different ways we might understand wisdom what I just
described is maybe um the garden variety that um is in our everyday lives
whether we're on the cushion or not but the Buddha's teaching is unique
amongst the great religions of the world and that it emphasizes wisdom
there's a real emphasis on wisdom in this tradition because the Buddha points to
ignorance as the deepest root of human
suffering whenever there's suffering underneath is ignorance it might be way
the ignorance might be really deep in there but underlying all of suffering is ignorance
and of course liberation is ultimately dependent on having some wisdom because
wisdom counteracts that ignorance so this personal insight into
the fundamental truth of things is the opposite of
ignorance it's another type of wisdom this personal insight this direct
experience it's not um it's not a knowledge about something though having
knowledge can help and can be a support and make it more likely that we will appreciate or help
create conditions when insights do arise but the wisdom as one way we might
think about it is knowledge and vision of things as they are it's commonly um stated that in the sutas and it's this
having this direct insight into the characteristics of phenomena the
qualities of all our experiences
but we normally assume that uh we understand things as they are i mean
what else is there more to see i'm here and there's these objects in front of me and I'm aware of the uh experience and
my reactions to the experience i'm aware of my bodily experience and my mental experience what else is there
so we normally assume or or believe that we know how things are but the say but
Buddhism says that the knowledge that we normally pride ourselves in but knowing
how things are is usually conceptual knowledge and or practical technical
knowhow different than direct experience different type of like really knowing
something i think probably all of us in our lives we
understand that people die that pets die but it's not until a loved one dies
that you really understand what that means that it takes on a whole different
experience whole different meaning so that's what the Buddha is pointing to
here is like the experiential
knowledge because for Buddhism this true wisdom true wisdom like the deepest
wisdom maybe I should use that word the deepest or don't want to say that some
wisdom is untrue but the deepest wisdom is the absence of greed and
craving the deepest wisdom Wisdom is the absence of hatred and
anger the absence of pride and conceit or the the deepest wisdom is
filled with love and compassion and it's filled with
simplicity and contentment and shows up as humility and
selflessness so for Buddhism that's kind of the expression of the deepest
wisdom and so the Buddhist texts some sometimes describe ignorance as being
like a like a mist that clouds over our clear seeing or something that covers or
dampens our spiritual lives or makes us see things in distorted ways
so ignorance is not um a terrible
um it's it's just it's like a covering something that's um obfuscating so that
we can't see clearly but with wisdom it's not that we
see these great mysterious esoteric uh
secrets instead we see the realities of our own lives the reality of our own
experience here and now and in fact uh some meditators might
think that okay the more mysterious and esoteric their meditative experiences
the better and sometimes are led down the wrong path chasing after some
meditative experiences but instead that with wisdom
we see the real nature of just our own experience the world of day-to-day
experiences that usually we aren't seeing
um because they not because that they're so difficult to see but because we
generally don't want to see them we are constantly um trying to hide
them from our view in some way or we're just intentionally not
looking at them and so what the part of this of
course is what you can imagine for those of you who are familiar with Buddhist teachings i'm talking about the three
characteristics of experience the three marks of of experience of all
phenomena so the first mark of experience that we can understand with wisdom with this penetrative insight is
impermanence ana and pi the second is
unsatisfactoriness which is duca in poly and then the third
one not self there's a number sometimes people say nonself no self not self i'll
use not self anata is the poly
word so I've talking a little bit about these three characteristics that impermanence
is the listed first usually it's the gateway it's the door to the other
characteristics partly because it's the most evident it's the most obvious you ask anybody on the street do things
change do they last forever and everybody's going to say "Of course
things change things don't last forever." You might think that some
things last forever but they'll recognize that things change we all know this
but with um there can be some meditative experiences where there's this understanding of not only that things
change and end but that they're inconstant that there's kind of like
this flickering this fluttering that they're not as stable they're not as
solid as we take them to be they're not as stable they're not as
solid they're not as steady as we want them to be so we are kind of like
projecting onto them some steadiness because we all want to have
this sense of there's a place which can be safe and secure a safe harbor a place
where we might rest a place where there's everything is like we have it
all figured out in some kind of way and we can just rest
there but with reflection we understand that everything
that is impermanent cannot be a source of lasting
happiness of course things that are changing might be a source of fleeting
happiness but they can be a source of lasting happiness therefore they're not
really as satisfying as we would like them to be they aren't like a safe landing pad
landing spot so whatever is impermanent whatever is changing whatever is not
constant is necessarily
unsatisfactory and just a little bit not quite right or maybe we might sense it's
flawed in some way or it's defective in some
way and whether it's in a subtle way or a gross way it's tangled up with
suffering it's bound up with suffering suffering or dissatisfaction
two different words we might use for this poly word duka
and then when we recognize that all these things that are changing and permanent and are bound up with
unsatisfactoriness then we realize they're not worth clinging to they're not worth holding on to
because they're not going to be a source of lasting happiness so it's just natural that it
just happens that we no longer cling like there's a letting
go and then we just we are there's a releasing of the attachment we have to
the objects or experiences but there is one subtle
attachment that's really subtle that is difficult to let
go and that is this clinging to the experiences of body or mind and
identifying with them as this is mine this is me this is
myself so this is one attachment that's definitely more subtle and doesn't
readily get let go of we're always trying to establish some
personal permanent identity within ourselves something that we can say "Oh this is my true self this
is me i'm like this i'm not like that."
But Buddhism says that this uh idea of a self is the lynchpin is the
crux of all the defilements it's kind of what keeps them all in
place this idea of mind that gives rise to craving it gives rise
to greed selfishness harm
this idea of me that gives rise to conceit and pride and always having to
bolster it up and protect it and make it look
good but the culmination of this of practice like the greatest
wisdom is this insight into the selflessness of all experiences the
selflessness of all all experiences
so this idea of a self I'm talking about selflessness we might say just a little
bit what do we this idea of a self we might consider it as maybe similar to an
idea of like an ego or a soul and we might we conceive of it as
something that's unique and constant and autonomous you know
independent but what's in addition we conceive of the self as being vulnerable and so
we're always having to protect it and bolster it and then so often when we
hear about these teachings about not not self our initial reactions are mixed or
ambivalent because it seems so counter to our experience and it seems counter
to common sense and our our gut feeling says well of course there's a self I'm
here so maybe we have this puzzlement or disbelief or discounting whatever it is
or discounting any teacher that happens to mention this like what are they talking
about maybe we just think it's just
ridiculous but this journey this practice asks for open-mindedness and
humility and maintaining this openness this uh this spirit of
inquiry this wisdom I'm talking about is kind of like this uh teasing apart
having this discernment distinguishing so like seeing clearly maybe we can
tease apart some of the different elements of um our experience and our idea about the
experience the experience and the concept and the label that we're putting on top of it can we distinguish
those and and watch for those moments when we categorize what is happening by
saying "Oh this is me or that's mine." Or that we succumb to this me
versus the world or us versus them
thinking but this being able to distinguish the the sense of self and to
to distinguish between the an experience and the way that we're labeling it the
self is subtle it's very subtle and it might take a meditative state before we
can see it but wisdom the greatest wisdom is to see
that see things clearly not just on the surface layer
and not just what um is obvious and
easiest and the most comfortable but to
investigate and to ask ourselves is what what is there something underneath
This is there something underneath that's uh promoting the
suffering so that our wisdom can maybe shine the light onto
some ignorance something that we're not seeing so that the suffering can be
released the suffering can go away so
wisdom wisdom as the fourth part of me there's so much we could say about
wisdom and I'd like to offer today that it's about seeing clearly those things that are obvious as well as
investigating with an open mind some of those things that are underneath what's so
obvious so that with wisdom we might find our way with things that are
difficult in our lives and in the lives of others so that our practice can be a
support for all beings everywhere thank you