so hello everyone welcome
and i read recently that the buddha
likened the eightfold path to a guest house
a guesthouse that all people were invited to come
and rest in the house but the nature of the guesthouse as a faithful path is that somehow
it um brought out the best in people
brought out the best in the person that was wholesome
so here we sit and when we meditate we are
a guest house where we invite everything
not so much to invite everything but we are a guest house that
welcomes everything that comes we don't go looking for things but if it
comes we welcome it here and there's something about
that welcome that ability to be mindful in an open generous way
without being for or against anything inviting all people all
states of mind all experiences that transforms
us into the best of ourselves and come forth
so the beginning of that is this ability to
receive equanimously openly a certain kind of impartiality or
all that all our experience and this ability to know to be aware to
be receptive without being for against without judging without closing the door
is transformative it brings out the best in us eventually
not immediately so taking a comfortable
alert posture and
lowering your gaze relaxing your gaze
and if it's comfortable gently closing your eyelids
and then lower yourself into your body
feel that the three-dimensional body that you are
the fullness the global body sitting here
your legs your torso your arms your
head make room for it to relax
to settle in
the more the tension in the body the more the less we are an open
welcoming guest house the more we operate from our
our preferences and our fears and our desires and our aversions
the more relaxed we are the more we become a guest house for all
things
and to help that process in a leisurely way like you have all the
time in the world breathe as deeply as is comfortable for
you
breathe deep breathe in deeply in the top of the in-breath hold the breath for a moment
just long enough that you feel the gentle urge to exhale
and give in to that urge to exhale
breathe in deeply exhale fully at the end of the exhale
pause for a moment a fraction of a moment
until you feel the body's urge to inhale and when you do
allow for that to happen
breathing in breathing out and as you exhale relax the body more
relaxation together with alertness with clarity of
attention is profound
and letting your breathing return to normal on the exhale
relax the muscles of the face
the forehead
around the eyes temple
the nose and the cheek
the jaws and the lips
as you exhale relax the shoulders
the area around the shoulder blades
and also soften the belly
and then instead of inviting
the body breathing inviting it to awareness
welcome it when it comes when the inhale comes
a simple welcoming awareness a guest house that receives the
experience
as if it comes out in from the cold or from being away
welcome it into the guest house of awareness
without any prejudice or judgments about what's there
and the exhale when it occurs welcome it allow it to
exhale
and if anything takes you away from breathing even if it's thinking
don't invite it but when it occurs have a welcoming attitude towards it
not to indulge in it but so it feels safe and
there's space and awareness awareness is the guest house
that receives everything equally
allowing each thing to be itself
and perhaps you'll see as you do that it's a simple welcoming awareness
that the best in you begins to
peek through
in the guest house everything is welcomed
and left alone
to find its own way to where it can rest
you
and near the end of the sitting can you be the keeper of the guest house
everything is welcomed not so that you engage in it or do
anything with it but so you don't judge it or need it to be different
but clearly recognize what's here in the guest house
allow it to rest to rest house for travelers
welcome and allow them to take their rest
and as we come to the end of the sitting
is there anything that the metaphor of the guest house being a guest house that is open to all
things that come welcoming but also doesn't
interfere with people's business allows all beings to come and rest and
be themselves without judgments without wanting something from them
and can you become a guest house for the people you encounter today
or the experiences you have or those you communicate with
they don't have to know that you're a guest house but in your heart you welcome them as
they are so they can maybe have a little experience
of being respected as they are allowed to be as they are
where they don't have to be worried about your judgments your needs your desires
your aversions that first and foremost you're there to
welcome them in your guest house of your
presence your awareness and may it be on this day
that your ability to hold all beings in your heart
with your heart as a guest house that you support others to feel happier
you support others to feel safe you support others to be peaceful
and you support others to be free
may we contribute to the happiness safety
peace peace and freedom of all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy and safe and peaceful
and free
so
[Music]
um
so
we continue today in the talks about mindfulness of mind also could be called
mindfulness of attitude or in the purity of it the mindfulness
of recognition and that's the theme for this from tuesdays
is recognition and recognition is a
powerful factor if it can be simple
if we can simplify our recognition of all the baggage all
the associations that it comes along with it so for example if you
maybe look around wherever you are sitting and can you find something to look at
where you can recognize what it is but that it's very neutral this doesn't evoke any
ideas of for and against i want that i don't want that it's just there in a simple very very
simple way and um so for my eyes now are landing on from the far
wall there's an electrical cord to a clock and i see the electrical cord and
it's just there i don't have any reactivity to it or preference around it or
for against it it's just there and then if i look turn my eyes up now
and look at something that i find that i like there's a statue of buddha statue
on the other house near near the electrical wire and now i find that there's a kind of a
liking and wondering and engagement with it where that's not more
not just recognizing it but now there's appreciating remembering history where it came from who gave it to us all
kinds of things and then i look down and there's some
tape on the floor here at imc and i have a little bit of a
issue about the tape on the floor because it's a long
piece of tape to mark a spot on the floor but it's crooked it wasn't laid down straight
and so i thought oh i should should i change it and can i use the same tape do i have to
throw it away and so suddenly my involvement is much more much more complicated
and i look at the electrical wire again and it's just very simple just a wire
so if you could look around in your space and you could see the different ways that you can recognize something
there how simple can it be just recognizing it and how much is it are coming with
preferences coming with judgments coming with for and against
coming with commentary it's in meditation in other times
the movement is towards becoming cleaner and cleaner simpler and simpler with recognition
so that we can see things as they are not as we want them or not through the
lens of what we don't want there simply there is a time there is a place
for preferences for desires for things we don't want there's definitely a time and place for that this is not doing
away with that forever but it's there's also a time and place to
learn the art a very simple recognition
and um and so simple that we're not it's not this recognition is
not distracted by our desires and our thoughts our commentary it just we recognize so simple just
there there's an in-breath it's just an in-breath and um
the uh it you know so simple that the in-breath has doesn't isn't tied to connected to
notions of time oh if i need to get concentrated i need
to stay here so that in the future i can be concerned so that i
don't so so that i'm present for the next exhale which is coming in the future
uh i lost it i lost my attention to the breath a few minutes ago a moment ago a few breaths ago
i can't have that happen again i have to kind of be able to stay with the breath
all those ideas are complicating the simple act of recognition
for this moment i'm able to recognize this inhale
as if there's no before and no after it's that simple
and if you mind wonders off in between and at some point you come
back to the next inhale the past is gone
just this inhale just that recognition and um
and at some point as the simplicity of recognition is there just this breath this step
this chewing my food this sitting in a chair
this walking down a hallway in the simplest possible way
then at some point what we recognize is recognition itself
we recognize that recognition as we're recognizing
we see that recognition is simple we see that recognition is free
of associations commentary preferences desires
and and then wow there's this thing called recognition there's this thing this experience this movement of recognition
of knowing of being aware and it becomes its own kind of object of
awareness and it starts being kind of special wow
there's this clarity there's this openness it's kind of like awareness now becomes
a guest house that all travelers are welcome to come into the
guest house but the guest housekeeper is very gracious and allows each people
everything to have its room and so it can rest
so it can be left alone so be accepted as it is nothing's needed
no judgments no nothing so this idea of recognizing recognition
aware of awareness knowing that we're knowing can seem like a hard thing to do
challenging you know and even nonsensical to some people but
one of the ways we come to that is that we begin recognizing
as a guest keeper welcome we started recognizing that
we are seldom aware simply
there's all kinds of things we bring along with the recognition we recognize something and we recognize
that we don't like it we do like it we want it to be a little bit different it should be sitting over there not
there can i have that we go into a room of people
and we start recognizing what's there but it's not just simple recognition
is who is it nice to sit next to who should i not sit right next to is it safe here where is the
where's the the good snacks and i think i'll you know that's what i want
and so there's all these preferences and agendas going on that and our awareness our recognition is
being used by our agenda it's being driven by it
now of course this is normal and healthy to do that in many circumstances it has to be that way
but the meditation practice and mindfulness one of the potential it has
is to start recognizing how we complicate or engage
awareness use awareness in the service of our agendas our preferences
and sometimes it's wise choices we make what we pay attention to when we're driving pay attention to the
road but sometimes our attention is hijacked
by things that we don't really if you thought about it you would say i don't want to do that
um focus on that again i've i've had the same complaint about
my neighbor down the street now it's probably a thousand times i've had that thought
and i feel lousy after i have it doesn't feel good to have it and it kind of hijacks my attention
and whenever i drive down the street and see that neighbor or see that house
you know i get contracted my attention i feel my awareness looking and i pull
away from the house so all kinds of ways we see how awareness
is being used and hijacked and influenced
as it's being used when we do that in mindfulness meditation sitting in meditation
welcome it all don't add judgment on top of judgments
but there's an r to welcoming it allowing it to be there which is paradoxically
a movement towards simplicity of recognition when we're not for or against things
then it can just be itself and there's room for us to recognize it as it actually is
and then as i've said this a kind of very special time comes
when we start recognizing recognition itself in and of itself
that recognition is this jewel is this amazing capacity
and this ability to recognize or to be aware or to know depending on
how that attentional faculty is showing itself at any given time
can become its own strong presence its own strong kind of entity not or i don't know what
the right language is to don't uh feeling of strength its own
territory it's it feels like a guest house feels like it has a room for things
and it's okay for things to arise and you know the idea of welcoming is
too much i just allow them to be there why do this
it seems like maybe then you're just victims of the circumstances things come and happen
because when we can keep our attention very simple just recognize
just recognize the thing that's happening including just recognizing how
we complicate recognition how i have desires and aversions we just keep doing the simple
recognition being the guest house allowing it to be there
then the best in us begins to come forth that which needs to rest that which
needs to relax that's which has a chance to relax it's not being fed it's not being egged on or encouraged on
and as in in this as as the simplicity of recognition if awareness starts
happening then um it's almost like there's space then for us to hear ourselves
there's space to know ourselves in a deeper way there's space to start recognizing
that there is goodness here there is wholesomeness here there is
space begins to be cracks in our in our in our in our crack center
maybe our hearts so that we can see where there's kindness and love and care generosity
goodness that resides the simplicity of recognition the
simplicity of awareness is a key to recognizing our own inner beauty
because we just welcome all the inner ugliness it's okay come
i'm a guest house for all of you and it's in the guest house in the space it makes in the allowing
that there is this welcome this generosity this goodness
that allows something to settle and relax and i suspect you'll be surprised by how
much goodness exists within you through this simple act of recognition
so all along in mindfulness practice we're practicing recognition of the breath of the body of emotions of
thoughts and everything i've been teaching before still applies
but at some point as we continue this practice at some point
it's appropriate to start recognizing recognition itself and recognizing that the way we are
aware of breath body emotions and thoughts is not
neutral it's not welcome it there's an agenda there's
complications we bring to it and so this turning around and being mindful of the mind mindfulness of
awareness of attitude is begins to free awareness from all
this extra baggage all this extra stuff that we add to it and
and goodness has a chance to grow
so thank you and uh may um
may you did for this day may you practice being a guest house
for all things that come along and maybe look for you know remind
yourself look particular appropriate places where try being receptive and welcoming
instead of maybe the usual habits of mind of how to be with things
so thank you very much
you