so good morning everyone we've had a
very exciting time
trying to welcome you uh this morning so
i'm sorry we're going to be
a little short on our meditation um i'll
be
having us basically sit for about seven
minutes
so i just want to ask you all to find a
comfortable place for your body
and
i think most of you are familiar with
the program that we're doing
for these three weeks there's an
intensive with gil
bronsdale myself and paul heller we've
called the harmony of zen
and vipassana so during this week we've
been taking turns
talking about the different elements of
our practice and how they differ how
they're the same
the roots are shared it all starts with
the buddhist enlightened vision
under the tree so as dharma comrades
we've been
really enjoying looking at the first
week we looked at samadhi
practices meditation the second week at
prajna
wisdom practices and this week we're
looking at sheila or the practices of
right conduct
so when the buddha was sitting under the
tree he was really giving us this
visible instruction
of how to meet our life you know
literally face to face and
how to meet the myriad things that are
continuously
coming forth to greet us like we had
this morning with all this
electronic uh efforts to come together
so right posture expresses not only our
integrity
and our dignity but in the best of
moments our kindness
and our innate curiosity about the world
around us
so like the buddha under the tree we sit
on the ground whether it's
on a cushion or on the grass or in a
chair and we find a stable
position for our lower body
as i hope you've already done this
morning
and then we lengthen the spine from the
base slowly
extending upward to the head balancing
your head on top of your
shoulders relaxing the neck
softening your eyes
and then inviting whatever tension there
is in your body to flow
back downward back down
into the earth from which we came so
very very very long ago
so finding your seed is a very long and
intimate process
as one monk said after years of sitting
the greatest pilgrimage of my life has
been my body
so take the time you need to explore all
the parts of your body lengthening the
torso
opening your chest relax your belly
and then let your skin hang loose i was
thinking about that this morning you
know kind of like a soft
silk dress on a hanger in a dark closet
take two deep breaths fully inhaling
through your mouth
and follow the flow of the air as it
enters your body that cool air
and how it becomes warm as it goes out
again
so a couple of times deep inhalation see
the mouth
filling the belly the chest and then
slowly exhaling
after that we just breathe naturally
and like
if you like uh helps you to concentrate
you can count your breaths on the
inhalation on the impulse to inhale
which i
locate myself in my
abdomen pulse to
breathe count one
and on the next impulse to inhale
two and so on to ten
and then from there back to one you know
it's not
always so easy to do this it takes some
time some practice to get to ten
so without discouraging yourself or
thinking you're doing it wrong
just start over at one whenever you
notice you've gone off
into dreams dreams of the past
plans for the future and just come on on
back to your body
your wonderful body which is always in
the present it's a great thing about our
bodies they are
always right here right now
like a good dog waiting for us to return
so i wanted to read you a little portion
of a poem written by
a chinese zen master who founded our
school uh sotozen his name is dongshan
and in japanese tozan ryokai
and the poem he wrote about meditation
about life
about awakening is called the song of
the
dual mirror samadhi
the teaching of vastness has been
intimately communicated by buddhas and
ancestors
so keep it well filling a silver bowl
with snow
hiding a heron in the moonlight taking a
similar they are not the same
when you mix them you know where they
are the meaning is not in the words
yet it responds to the inquiring impulse
move and you are trapped miss and you
fall
into doubt and vacillation turning away
and touching are both wrong
for it is like a massive fire just to
depict it
in literary form is to stain it with
defilement
it is bright just at midnight it doesn't
appear
at dawn it acts as a guide for beings
its use removes all pains
although it is not fabricated it is not
without speech
it is like facing a dual mirror
form and image behold each other
you are not it in truth it is you
uh
i'm so sorry we didn't have longer to
sit together this morning but i hope
you'll find time later today
or this evening to sit a little bit
yourselves
so good morning again for those of you
who might just be tuning in
um i'm foo schrader i'm the abbess at
green gulch farm
zen center in marin county california
and as i mentioned uh we are in the
middle or toward the end actually
of what's been a wonderful three-week
intensive with gil fransdale
myself and paul haller also from the zen
center
and so we've been offering these
perspectives uh from our two traditions
vipassana and zen
on many things you know what difference
what's the same
about our meditation about our
wisdom teachings and also about right
conduct which is what we're focusing on
this week so i've been discussing
in this morning session the 16
bodhisattva precepts yesterday i talked
about the practice of confession
and repentance which is preliminary to
receiving the precepts
you know acknowledging oh yeah i did
that i did that
and i i really don't want to do that
anymore you know really knowing within
our own hearts
what things we've done that we would
really like to change you know
and how to do that so precepts are one
of the kind of guidance systems for
making changes that we'd like to make
in our lives so the first of the three
bodhisattva precepts
are called the refuges the three refuges
and refuges are taken in what's called
the triple treasure the buddha
the dharma and the sangha community
so i want to begin with the koan from
the book of serenity
which is a collection of teaching
stories that
started to be gathered together right
about the time that zen arrived in china
over 1300 years ago this one is called
the world honored one points to the
ground the world honored one is the
buddha
as soon as a single mode of dust arises
the whole earth is contained
therein with a single horse and a single
lance
the land is extended who is this person
who can be master in any place
and meet the source in everything so
here's the story
as the world honored one the buddha was
walking with a congregation
he pointed to the ground with his finger
and said this spot
is good to build a sanctuary
indra the emperor of the gods took a
blade of grass
stuck it in the ground and said the
sanctuary is built
the world honored one smiled
so for me it's the buddhist smile that
has carried this ancient
tradition from its home in far away
india
over those thousands of miles and
hundreds of centuries
in order to shine brightly on us here
today taking refuge building sanctuaries
in the warmth of that smile is the
beginning of a well-marked path
to our own well-being and happiness and
for the benefit
of this terribly suffering world i take
refuge in buddha as the perfect teacher
i take refuge in dharma as the perfect
teaching
i take refuge in sangha as the perfect
life
so these are very powerful words that we
chant just about every morning
excuse me at the zen center
and although each of us may have this
unique feeling about what these words
mean
i think it's useful for us to look at
words carefully
and wonder about what they how they hit
us deeply inside
and what role they play and our own
understanding of buddhist practice
in our near perfect lives
so long long ago when the buddha the
perfect teacher
had set in motion the wheel of the law
there was a moment
in time where or so i can imagine
there was kind of near perfect stillness
you know like when someone shouts into a
canyon and then
waits for that familiar voice to echo
in reply hello
so in the case of the buddha the
response came from kondana
meaning the one who knows declaring his
understanding
and requesting the full admission as the
buddha's first disciple
hello kundana says i'm here
i hear you lord buddha
and then he says to the buddha i wish to
go forth under the blessed one and to
receive the full admission
the buddha replies come your
understanding of the dharma is well
proclaimed
live the holy life for the complete end
of suffering
and with that request the triple
treasure
was manifest in this world we have the
buddha
and the dharma the teaching and now
there's a sangha
giver the receiver and the gift
so at that moment as it says in the pali
canon at that instant
the news traveled right up to the brahma
world and this ten thousand-fold
world element shook and quaked and
trembled while a great measureless light
surpassing the splendor of the gods
appeared
in the world
so this request by kundana to take
refuge
in the buddha and the dharma was in the
form of a call and response
you know like the echo in the valley
this is a very familiar form of dialogue
that we practice
both in the zen and the vipassana
traditions right to this very day
and it's called by a number of names we
call it sometimes question and answer
uh or practice discussion or doksan
doksan means
a private consultation with a teacher
so with the buddha and his teachings
without them without these teachings and
without these people who came to study
with him
there wouldn't be any buddhism for us
right now there'd be no refuge
no blade of grass with which to build
the sanctuary
so taking refuge in the triple treasure
as suzuki roshi said
i mentioned this the other day by taking
refuge
you adore the buddha and the dharma and
the sangha
and that for you taking refuge is an act
of adoration
so before declaring your adoration for
the triple treasure if you
haven't already it might be good to
consider what each of these three
treasures means to you now first there's
the buddha
a word that means awake when the buddha
was approached by a wanderer on the road
shortly after his enlightenment the
wanderers said
are you a god would have said no are you
a water spirit
buddha said no are you a demon no
are you a human being buddha said no
he said and then the wanderer said well
dear sir what might you be
and buddha said i am awake.
so lots of things that can be said about
the buddha in fact we use this word all
the time
we bow to images of the buddha we offer
fragrance and sweet tea
and flowers and food we dress like him
we endeavor to act like him and we spend
a lot of time listening
to the words of the buddha and of his
descendants
all of which sound like adoration you
know at least the form of it
so one understanding that we in the zen
school have about what it means to take
refuge in buddha is to take refuge in
who we really are you know and that who
we really are
is already buddha is already this
quality
awake so the word refuge
literally means to fly back to fly back
in other words we fly back to our true
self our whole self
our limitless ungraspable and
inconceivable
existence so therefore
it's not something that we can change we
can't produce it we can't destroy it and
we can't bring it about
by any kind of effort there's nothing to
add
and there's nothing to be taken away and
as frustrating
as that might be it's something that no
doubt we've all noticed
about reality it always wins
so the shortest term for that reality of
who we really are in zen we say the word
thus thus the buddha is called the thus
come one just like the body always in
the present
or as zen master dongshan said as he
crossed a river
and saw the reflection of his own face
in the water
this is the moment of his awakening and
he said
just this person he was quite surprised
just this person and as the buddha said
showed by uh to the assembly by holding
up a flower you know just this flower
you know look just this person just this
moment
of awakening so being a buddha being
awake means being unattached to your
ideas about who you are whether you
think you are
rotten or you think you are absolutely
great
that not grasping those thoughts is
buddha and ironically
being a person who has such thoughts is
a prerequisite
for being buddha for awakening so step
number one
this very mind is buddha step number two
no mind no buddha so in either case
imagining that you can run away from who
you really are is
simply a delusion and what kind of
delusion
it's the delusion of running away seeing
that
is an insight it's called returning to
buddha you know taking refuge
return to who we really are including
all of our delusions
is to take refuge in buddha in the truth
of reality
the truth of our human life not one and
not two
and that's true sentient beings and
buddhas
are not separate in his book being
upright
tension anderson says this about taking
refuge in buddha
trusting that your buddha does not mean
that you identify with being buddha
it's not something special about you
that makes you buddha
it's simply you being you that is buddha
and it's not that you're so virtuous
that your buddha
but that you being you is virtue
to take refuge in buddha means to give
up running away
from home it means to recognize our
responsibility
to live in accord with our buddhahood in
other words to assume
you are buddha and now to act like it
the second of the triple treasures is
taking refuge in the dharma
what the buddha taught and here's what
he said to ananda at the very time of
his death
it's from the polycanada ananda you may
think the word of the teacher is a thing
of the past
now you have no more teacher but you
should not regard it so
the dharma and the discipline taught by
me are your teacher after i'm gone
the law i have taught has no secret
version there is no
teacher's closed fist about the good
things here
now i am old ananda my years have turned
80.
just as an old cart is made to carry on
with the help of makeshifts
so too it seems to me the blessed one's
body is made to carry on
with the help of makeshift so ananda
each of you should make of yourself an
island with no other refuge
each of you should make the law their
island and no
other refuge either now or when i'm gone
it is those whoever they may be who make
themselves and the law
their islands and no other refuge who
will be the foremost among my disciples
of those that is who want to train
how could it be ananda that what is born
come into being formed and bound to fall
should not fall that is not possible
then the blessed one addressed the
beaches thus
indeed beaches i declare this to you it
is in the nature of all formations
to dissolve attain perfection through
diligence
this was the perfect one's last
utterance
so part of our understanding of these
teachings is that the buddha was not
the person but the teaching itself which
has continued right up into this day
and in this way i think we're quite
fortunate not to bear the problems of
deification
although we do get carried away
sometimes
especially here at green country with
all the bells and whistles
so i think if we continue to appreciate
that these statues and offerings
that we're making in our homes and in
our temples are truly
gestures of gratitude being made by
those of us
alive today you know the living
buddhists
and without that there can't be any
ancestors if we don't remember and honor
them and there can't be the teaching
of the buddha unless you know we like
the honey ants carry it within our own
bodies
i don't know if you know about honey
ants but they're really amazing which is
why i think of them
as a good metaphor for the work that
we're also doing
together in our temples honey ants have
these
abdomens that fill up with honey and
then they hang
the ants hang from the ceilings of their
nests serving as storage units for the
benefit
of their communities and for the same
reason the students of the buddhist
teaching have been called the vessels of
the dharma
the honey ants of the dharma and so
what's the dharma
well that's a good question with either
a very long
or a very short answer in the prajnapar
mita literature which is the basis for
our
zen tradition prajnaparamita means
wisdom beyond wisdom
there are two versions that have been
written extreme examples
one version is a hundred thousand lines
it's a very large text and on the other
end
is the letter a so basically the dharma
is the truth
and it's really up to each of us to find
the truth
and to live within the circle of what
our eye of practice can see
and as for the sangha it is this very
wide and wonderful
community of friends who have been
gathering in a world around
to listen to the teachings of the gentle
buddhas and those teachings
being the greatest gift to us all
so thank you for your kind attention
this morning and i hope you have a
lovely day
and please take care of yourselves and
stay safe
hey thank you foo you're welcome kevin
food did you want to take some times to
uh take some questions or
sure if anyone has um a question i'm
happy to
probably spend a few minutes i don't
know kevin what the outer limits are but
i have a few minutes
yeah great um so we'll take questions
and chat if you want to put some
questions in there and
we'll um i'll i'll read them off to you
fool
you can take as many as you want so
okay
the echo down the canyon
hi patricia yeah well we will be putting
the
video recording on youtube and um we'll
be looking into
seeing if we can get a transcript
available so patricia also said that uh
this was an amazing talk oh thank you
patricia
i'm glad you loved it uh michelle has a
question
she says uh when we take the buddha vows
do we need to be in the presence of
someone appointed to be a witness
yeah it's called warm hand to warm hand
in our tradition the way we
practice those celebrations really and
so usually you have a preceptor
someone who has received transmission or
dharma transmission we call it meaning
they have permission from their teacher
to offer precepts
so that's really the only thing you're
granted
by receiving dharma transmission is this
authority
to give others the precepts so that's
um a wonderful relationship that you
have very intimate with someone you talk
to
as a mentor as a teacher and then at
some point when you finish
sowing your robes we sew we sew our own
robes i'm wearing one of them right now
it's
called a rock suit it's a miniature of
the larger robes that
i think you've all seen that the monks
wear i have one of those too
um we wear during meditation so we sew
our robes
it's one of the traditions that we
continue to practice at the zen center
uh it takes a while which is good and
with each stitch
you say i take refuge in buddha
thousands of stitches it's it's
fantastic practice it's very
if you like to meditate it's a great way
to meditate with this
cloth and thread and usually sitting
with other friends
in silence so once you've finished your
robes then we schedule a ceremony and
often there's more than one person
usually there's quite a few
and um it's a very beautiful ceremony
families come
friends come the community comes and
then we have a
a party after cookies and tea that's our
that's our favorite party so yes it's
it's quite a
uh it's quite an intimate part of
our community life is receiving the
precepts
so thank you for that question do you
want to take one more
foo or sure okay uh chris asks can you
give your interpretation of
be an island unto yourself
yeah well you know what comes to mind i
mean thank you for that question
right away what comes to mind is a
familiar teaching for me
is like when the buddha said
i and all beings together enlightened at
the same time
so the island unto yourself would be
yourself
as the entirety of existence that you're
this is a representative of all of it
right all of us are representatives of
the whole thing
we are the universe in this form
so an island unto itself is kind of like
the universe
it's a pretty big island and then all of
us are
you know kind of uh
we're all i i came up with this image
the other day of
after meditation you walk outside and it
feels like this womb of light
you've just walked into the womb of
light and i think as as
little babies we're born you know from
our mother's belly the dark
into this womb of light you know this uh
being alive in this world of light and
color and amazement sound so you know
we're kind of roommates that's what we
all are we're roommates
and that's for me is the island it's the
great island
jambudvipa it's called in sanskrit
the center of the universe where we live
so that's that's the island
okay well thank you everyone for coming
uh thank you for joining us through and
being flexible with our uh
kind of technical challenges we had
today well kevin
thank you so much for all your effort
and i'll see you tomorrow morning
yes thank you everybody see you tomorrow
bye