so
the 11th step of mindfulness of
breathing
is breathing in one concentrates
breathing out one concentrates
concentrates the mind
and so this relates to the whole topic
of samadhi
in buddhism words often translated as
concentration
and and we're
spending more days on this step
because uh the samadhi
is such an important foundation for the
final steps of
mindfulness of breathing and we don't
want to rush through this
ideally you're kind of coming along a
little bit
following just enough getting a sense or
feel for what we're
what these steps are about that you have
some inner reference point for what
we're doing as we continue going on even
though the next steps are getting to
very kind of more classically are
describing deeper and deeper states of
meditation
the these 16 steps are also relevant
um on well short of deep states of
meditation you
think we kind of can go through them
even in relatively ordinary states
and recognize kind of little shifts that
represent these different states so
i'm hoping there's enough by going slow
enough that uh
that um you know you're you can follow
enough so we're spending more time with
samadhi
and so
i've already said some of this that the
the word in this 16 stages for
concentrate has also been translated as
steady
and i like to translate it as unify
unific to unify the mind
or or steady the mind or
stabilize the mind the word is
uh and the
the verb adati means to um
to play something so it's like placing
the placing the mind placing awareness
on the object that we're
focusing on so placing it on the
breathing
i love the expression landing just
landing on it
and just kind of gently landing like a
like little
helicopter held a drone or something or
like a bird that comes in and just kind
of
i guess it flies in almost stops in in
the air
inch or so above the ground and then
just
lands on the ground so we come right in
there we land
and um and settle place ourselves
the i'm very fond of uh
using the word compose composure
as this we're composing ourselves on the
breathing
and that samadhi is an act of composing
ourselves
because of the word pose also means to
place or to stand
someplace so we're taking a stand and
resting in there
and um and um
to settle to study are all these words
associated with samadhi
and um now samadhi itself is often
translated as concentration but it
more generally means meditation or a
state
that we're in a state of mind that we're
in that
can be many different states where we're
quite settled and steady
and peaceful and and i wanted to read
you
very early uh commentary the from the
um very early commentary
where it lists it kind of defines
samadhi
and that's a wonderful definition a
whole series of little definitions
samadhi means embracing
samadhi means completion
samadhi means single pointed
samadhi means unconfused
samadhi means unscattered samadhi means
undisturbed samadhi means unperturbed
samadhi means liberation
and the next one is particularly nice
next series
samadhi is seeking harmony
is acquiring harmony
samadhi is receiving harmony
samadhi is grasping harmony
taking hold of it samadhi is entering
harmony samadhi is going along
in harmony samadhi
is a light
lightening up in harmony
samadhi is being lit up in harmony
samadhi is harmony welfare and happiness
so um it's like thing's a wonderful list
this idea of harmony
um or evenness or balance
the word is sama s-a-m-a
and um and so you get a very different
feeling
for samadhi from these kinds of
descriptions
than you would if you just told that
tamari is one pointedness of mind
and when you talk about when you talk
about these absorption states jhana
which sometimes the way that they're
talked about they have the intensity and
a kind of laser idea and people
really try hard to get into it not
really realizing a big part of this
samadhi is letting go relaxing
settling deeper and deeper and deeper
and then uh but for these uh
jhanas these absorption absorption
states
the verbs related to them are entering
the states
and abiding in them and this idea of
entering
is a i think is a beautiful image that
we're not looking to zero in we're not
looking to
force ourselves to be a state but rather
we're kind of
entering into and i like to think of
entering into a sacred
uh area a sacred piece of land or a
temple
where we enter into with some reverence
and respect and care
and how we are how we enter
is important part of the entering and
then
we the two verbs are to enter and to
abide
it means that we take time just to
linger in those states to reside
in those states and
in whatever kind of samadhi states or
good states or nourishing states there
are
we abide in them so that we can be
conditioned by them
there's a reconditioning process that
happens through meditation
that um we're allowing ourselves
to um you know life that as we go
through can condition us in all kinds of
negative ways
and meditation is to undo that the
conditioning that comes from greed
hatred and delusion
is very different the condition that
comes from generosity and love and
and wisdom and so some people have even
said that samadhi is kind of a
re-parenting if parenting didn't go so
well
as for us growing growing up it has a
very deep and profound impact on us too
if we allow ourselves
to be nourished by it which requires
abiding
let abiding in it dwelling in it so that
we really
can let the goodness of these states
really
seep in and affect us and if we're in a
hurry to get more and more concentrated
we're not going to get allow the
nourishment to really recondition us and
open us and soften us in a way that's
useful on the path of liberation
and i thought i would also read to you
the
a list of the things that buddha talks
about that people that encourage people
to abide in
so he's not just saying you know in
modern
united states there's often discussion
about a
being rather than doing and meditation
is a chance just to be
i don't think the buddha would quite say
it that way
rather than being he talks about abiding
maybe very
closely related just abide but he's
always talking about
abiding in something in something that's
wholesome and good
not just being angry you know or fuming
if you just abide in that
maybe that maybe has a negative impact
if that fuming and
resentment anger just kind of simmering
along and
in some way so that's a whole different
topic about
you know how to be wise with things like
anger but
um with the buddha it's abiding so
here's these states of abiding the
buddha talks about
abiding in safety
abiding in fearlessness
abiding in a mind free from the
hindrances
abiding in equanimity
abiding in contentment
abiding in pleasure
inviting in happiness and gladness
abiding in happiness without moving the
body
or uttering a word
abiding in lovingkindness
abiding in compassion
abiding in a mind like space
abiding in the dharma abiding
observing impermanence
abiding in stillness
devoted to a pleasant abiding here and
now
samadhi states are buddha often
describes as a pleasant
abiding here and now
and then abiding in the four foundations
of mindfulness
and now it's very significant that the
word is abiding in the four foundations
it doesn't say practice the four
foundations of mindfulness it says abide
in them
abiding in bliss
abiding in emptiness
abiding in peaceful liberations
abiding in the supreme goal
so to abide one has to be patient
i think of abiding as being very closely
akin to being in a
receptive state so we abide we're
patient we're not in a hurry
and we receptive state to feel the
goodness of all these states all these
ways of being
that can happen and so one of so we're
talking here now about
the the 11th step of anapanasati
so of course when we sit down to
meditate there are times when
these are not available and we are angry
we are
agitated and to sit down and say just
sit there and abide in these good
feelings
just simply doesn't work and
but so we learned to practice with the
first steps of unempathy that really
support us
in the challenging states of being that
we can have in daily life
in our ex but as we meditation proceeds
then at some point that what i'm calling
today the goodness the nourishing
feelings
the beneficial feelings sensations that
are here
the buddha encourages us to abide in
them
and that when they come arise in samadhi
in these states of harmony
subtleness steadiness unification
that we really kind of now we're really
here in the present moment and really
feel that in the present there's a kind
of
harmony and joy and well-being
gladness to all these possible
different flavors of the goodness that
might be there
whatever the flavor is of the day
there's also a very important place to
abide in it
to receive it to let it nourish you and
fill you
and and let it kind of penetrate and
permeate yourself in some way
and um
so to dwell in these states
is not to be thinking about them
it's uh not be seeking and planning and
expecting and wanting
and holding on to things it's just
simply abiding just allowing them to be
there
and just kind of basking in it or
enjoying it and
breathing with it breathing through it
now this mindfulness of breathing is all
with reference point is always breathing
breathing
in and breathing out so we're always
kind of using that as a
support as a guide as a grounding as a
as a pointer as a as a way of staying
in these different steps and so now
we're staying breathing abiding in these
states abiding in
in the present moment you know in the
pleasant
state here and now so
uh the word in pali is
it comes related to the word vihara
meaning a monastery a place where people
amongst the nuns reside
and so you might for the next rest of
the day next 24 hours
have this word abide or abiding
viharati vihara as a
something you keep close by maybe you
write it on a sticky note and
and have it with you or have it posted
some places
and uh and see when
in the day you it's beneficial for you
to pause
and abide with what's happening and
especially when there's a goodness or
something nourishing and you
abide really take it in learn to abide
and learn to unbe nourished by your
abiding states
so thank you and i will continue with
the samadhi for a few more days and
until we get to the 12th step with is
liberating the mind
so um and
that's you know only the 12th the 16th
so thank you all very much