there so so uh and also yes thank you neil for
posting information about uh the google groups
in uh in uh in chat so so
so let's see one last thing i need to do in order to set up the
settings okay so so i'll start with the theme and also one thing to share with you
is that um given that we've had
some zoom bombers visiting us after the the uh
little dharmet from now on um diane and i will
lock the room and i will share this with you so that if you want to come
and be part of the zoom uh gathering please come in earlier
otherwise we will be locking the room so that latecomers will not be getting in so that you know we can have
um and protect the space so
so with that i would like to [Music]
share a few words about the practice for tonight and the practice for tonight the
invitation for today's practice is um
meta and care for ourselves how can we care
for ourselves how can we care for ourselves and this being
a friday and and for summer will be already a saturday joining from different time zones
and uh beginning of a weekend how can we take care of ourselves
how can we take quiet time how can we take some downtime
um [Music] how can we take care of ourselves
by taking care of this body take care of this
this mind take care taking care of this heart what are some wholesome ways we can take
care of your ourselves and care for ourselves is it through
sleeping some more just a simple way of caring for this body
the basic the basic um you know the i think of the food
pyramid you know there's the care pyramid and the care pyramid i think of the first layer the most important layer
being sleep maybe it's sleep sleeping and taking care of this body if it's
tired if it's been working hard is it
through [Music] going into nature is it into is it is it through
being silent being quiet and not engaging so much with
with the world with stuff um is it
is it through could it be through um
perhaps listening to a dharma talk connecting with goodness connecting with
the dharma in wholesome ways what what are some ways for us
to take care of ourselves to take care of ourselves and meta meta
is also a way to take care of ourselves kindness goodness
entering into silence connecting with ourselves
so with that as the invitation i'd like to invite us to
the practice together to enter the space of silence together
and um to um yeah to practice together so
so [Music] yeah let us begin let us begin
by entering into a space of practice
landing landing landing deeply
landing into our seats
landing into this body
connecting connecting
connecting with this body
connecting with a moment of silence quiet taking refuge
how can we how can we connect how can we deeply connect
the space of quiet the space of quiet within
connecting to the breath
to our feet connected to the earth
receiving receiving the breath
receiving the breath
taking a moment of refuge
and silence enter silence as a moment of care
how can we care how can we care for ourselves
how can we care
how can we care for ourselves
so
relaxing the body receiving the breath releasing
whatever is not wholesome whatever is not helpful in this moment
may i be safe may i be safe
from inner and outer
may i be safe from inner and outer home
may i be happy and joyful
may i be healthy and strong
and may my life unfold with ease
tuning tuning into the inner peace inner silence
as a source of healing as a source of care
it's a source of nourishment
knowing trusting that connecting with silence
connecting with the inner silence
as an expression of care for ourselves
soothing and healing nourishing
each breath inviting ourselves
to connect
with the inner stillness the inner quiet
as an expression of care goodwill for ourselves and others
may this being who is me
feel nourished heart body and mind
with the grace of connection connection to silence
to peace to stillness
to care
may i be safe from inner and utter harm
may i be happy and joyful
may this body be healthy and strong
and may this life of mine made unfold with ease as much ease as
possible
may i be nourished healed calmed through silence
through the grace of peace in my heart
may i offer this goodness and peace to myself and to
others
may i know and taste for myself
the peace of the buddha
yeah i know a taste for myself
the peace of the buddha to serve to serve
this being who's me in this shape and form in this life
and to serve others in goodness
may all beings everywhere no peace
may all beings everywhere be free
thank you all thank you for your practice
so so we have time for questions
four comments and jane i see your hand is raised is that correct no
so yes we have time i see gabriel's hand is raised is that
correct gabriel yes yes
please hello nikki thank you very
so every question that popped up in my mind
during the session it was about the teachings on meta and on anatom that
self i was curious hear you say a few words about how we can work with the both of
these and if they can help each other yeah there is so much i can say about
this so um but without going into our long drama talk
tell me how this is coming up for you how it's showing up this question for you so i know what to say that might be
helpful to where you are in your practice right now with this uh yes so
um i'm working my practice on
some inside practice and just to see how the cell is concentrate and i'm wondering to see all the say
that again the selfish contract is constructed sorry yes it's built by the mind
and at the same time so this can sometimes feel a bit dry you
know but and at the same time there is the meta practice that uh
and i don't i don't know my uh it's just
it's not clear still in my mind how they can how they work together i know that they do but i'm not sure i'm not i don't
know yet how precisely got it great okay so
the the way i hear your question the way this is arising for you is that you're working
with inside practices and anata saying how self is
constructed how the self that is constructed from our thoughts and ways of seeing and
being and in some ways it feels kind of dry and
and you have this intuition that that meta care love has something to do
with this practice but don't quite know how it fits in yet did i hear you
correctly and you can keep yourself unmuted if you like when you do the back and forth yeah so and to be more
specific just it may be interesting i'm working with this in relation to my music practice because i try to see uh
when i play it's there is no me in there it's just happening by itself and it feels very rich to explore those ideas
and that's why i'm working with that got it okay well that's very helpful that's beautiful to hear that you're
yeah this is a sense of co-creation there's so much in creativity that
it feels like it moves through you it moves through you it's and and of course part of it is your
volition part of it is your will and and and also all the causes and conditions
so so to yeah i'm so glad you brought music especially because seeing the
uh seeing um love meta in that
um so so let me say let me say this um
the teaching of course as you know is not that there is no self there is a self for conventional reasons it's very
helpful yes there is and and yet from the particular way of
seeing from a particular perspective we can see how it's all constructed it's it is
constructed and in that construction in that
it doesn't mean that things become meaningless or that there is lack of love and care
or beauty in fact with what you bring in with music in fact you can see the
beauty you can see the grace there is this this this beauty that moves through
there is there's the uh there is this impersonal love and beauty and grace
that's not yours it's above and beyond you
and and yet it is you and you are a part of it
so this this this love beauty grace music just all of this
this can infuse the the impersonality
it's not just you see does that make sense yeah it does
[Music] and instead of it becoming dry actually
it becomes more graceful wow this beauty this um because as a musician you know
this it's amazing right when as a jazz musician
when it clicks it's like it's this is bigger than me it's not me there's some
this is wow you know when you get uh you know when you just get goosebumps
like this is bigger than this is not this is me and not me yes i am creating
this music and yet this is bigger than me so it's that is where the sense of meta love grace that
that's where it can come in play with that invite it thank you thank you very much thank you
so much for this question this was great really appreciate it yeah beautiful
maybe we have time for one more reflection before we turn into
practicing with small groups
okay so how about we turn
to small groups of roughly size three and start with maybe 15 seconds of
silence um and our theme has been peace and silence
and see how you can care for yourself care for others in the space of silence
meta care and then share as much or as little as you like
take care of yourselves take care of each other
this is a sacred space it's both you and not about you
i really appreciate gabriel bringing that in see how you can make beautiful music
of meta with with people in your small group
the rooms are created and here we go i'm going to open them up
open them now okay welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed everybody's back and we have a couple minutes for any
reflections questions comments what you noticed
anything it's part of your gift to the sangha from your
practice i see bill's hands fred and abraham okay
all right bill hey um
i just i i find the silence i mean the the the peace
appealing but of course my mind wants to go off and find entertainment somewhere else you know and it's it's always bad
so anyway it's always it's always that you said or it's always bad i didn't always that you know it's always that
yeah yeah and you know what it's um
i'm glad you're noticing this bill and this what you're reporting is not unusual at all
um it's a matter of seeing the delight and the joy of peace because we're not
used to that we are so not used to that um and there is so i'll give you a little
example you know when i was younger um i loved um you know ice cream that
had all kinds of stuff in it rocky road and marshmallows and nuts and chocolate and i couldn't understand why people
liked vanilla it seemed so plain and yet when i've gotten older it's like wow vanilla is so
sophisticated it's so subtle it's sublime right
but i needed to train my taste buds to appreciate the
subtle so of course and think of your mind that way yeah the mind kind of likes the
and it but it's a matter of training your mind to appreciate the the subtleness
thank you thank you and and and that's completely normal completely normal part of this
path thanks bill fred please
uh thank you nikki i was just starting to say this in our group um
how appreciative i am for this practice uh as as today i was sitting
in the att office after several hours of trying to
unravel a bureaucratic snafu and i as i was sitting there in silence in
fact i could picture myself at another time
enraged cynical uh impatient and i was a little of all
those things but i wasn't flaring to make it worse
and everybody around me was being as helpful as they could be and it was a drag for them too
and we all by behaving better together
got a resolution um with minimal you know with no damage really and i
and i thank you and sanka and this practice um for being helpful
in that kind of everyday way thank you
thank you fred thank you so much for this practice report this report from the field yay
my heart and i see lots of other hearts have lit up thank you
thanks for your practice and sharing it with so many others at the at t store
abraham please and this will be the last comment please
yeah i just wanted to thank you for that invitation at the beginning of the hour that
if all we needed was maybe some little quiet time and
maybe sometimes we just need rest uh i really appreciated that that he hit
a chord but it was so nice to be in a room with a bunch of guys who had spent the day sending love out into
the world and it was it was nice and the same thing in all these other rooms
i see here too sweet thank you abraham thank you so
much for that so we let this be the last comment and claire i'm happy to stay a couple of
minutes extra as the time is ending and i also wanted
to say speaking of the importance of rest i'm going to be taking a little
trip for about 10 days so there's some wonderful
guest teachers who will be holding happy hour sangha and diana will be here
too so just wanted to let you know and please continue to come support each other support
the teachers who will be supporting you and i look forward to seeing you in a couple of weeks
may you be well may you be safe may you be happy may all beings
be well including ourselves
thank you