so good morning and welcome to
the first meditation session of the retreat that some of you are doing and for those
of you on youtube good morning and good day and
welcome to this monday morning meditation
and for this morning's meditation i would
like to emphasize the word awareness
sometimes i like to think of the word awareness as a synonym or for mindfulness or
and i'll talk more about that but what's interesting about awareness
is we talk about being aware we don't talk about doing aware
someone doesn't say i'm a wearing they say i am aware
and i associate being aware or awareness
to something like hearing versus listening hearing
is something that we can just hear those of us who have the ability to hear we can hear
something without intending to hear it the sound arises in the ear maybe a loud
sound nearby and we hear it if we're curious about it
then we turn our attention to it and we listen to it and listening
being the active and the intentional quality of what we do with our capacity to hear
and um i am so so i am aware
is equivalent to the hearing we can be aware without intending to be
aware we can be aware without directing the
attention with our interest in our intentionality
and when we practice mindfulness we're bridging the world bridging these
two aspects the non-intentional and the intentional the directed
and the non-directed the doing and then not doing and the word
awareness gives a little bit more emphasis on the
on just allowing awareness to operate
so rather than doing awareness we
are being aware
and as such awareness is closer to
a state of mind than it is to an activity of mind
a particular mental action
as important as mental actions can be
are just a subset of what awareness can be aware of
and so with this anapanasati mindfulness of breathing
as it develops as we settle in
we're getting closer to the state of awareness than we are to
moments of knowing moments of what sometimes is called mindfulness
so taking a meditation posture
and finding a posture
adjusting your body to a posture that is suitable for you
to be aware in a calm and relaxed way
for this purpose it's helpful if the posture is relatively comfortable
relatively relaxed
and then it's helpful to
settle into your body and one of the ways of doing that
is to take a few long slow deep breaths at the beginning of the sitting
and the deep inhales are maybe three quarters full three-quarters of a full in-breath
nothing that would tire you out or strain you but something that would allow you
to feel your body more fully breathing in and that
full breath not only feels your body
but little bit energizes it in a good way
and then taking letting your breath return to normal
and feeling
your body letting your awareness your attention
roam around your body maybe in its own way
to the places where there are some tensions or holdings
and as you exhale relax soften the places of holding
perhaps it's a little bit in the muscles of the
belly softening the belly
maybe there's some softening around the front of the chest
softening in the shoulders
and softening in the face
perhaps also there's a some possibility on the exhale to relax the thinking mind
maybe around where the brain is
or are there places in the body where thinking has its tentacles and as you
exhale to quiet the thinking mind
allow the thinking mind maybe to think slower
there's no hurry here in meditation
there's no requirement to think of anything else besides the meditation
and if you're thinking about what the meditation maybe you can do so quietly
calmly slowly
in ways that are clearly supportive of the meditation
so maybe the thinking is kind thoughts about now turning the attention to the
breathing thoughts about experiencing
being present for how the body experiences breathing
simple thoughts of receiving the inhale
thoughts are being present for the inhale just as it begins
and letting there be a receptive quality where the the body's ability to be aware
to sense and to feel receives the inhale
maybe receives it as an upwelling feeling of energy of movement
of sensations
and then as you exhale to release with the exhale
there is a letting go in the exhale allow yourself to exhale
allowing the release
inhaling and receiving the inhale
in awareness
allowing the exhale
to release within awareness
so not so much focusing on the breathing
but more allowing breathing to focus itself in the middle of awareness
as if breathing
is received it's like the waves received by the beach
in which the beach then releases or allows to wash back
roll back back into the ocean
across the beach of awareness comes the waves of in inhaling and exhaling
and regardless now of what you're thinking about what you're thinking about is less
important than noticing the
it as activity of the mind
whatever the activity the actions the energy
energetics of the mind are see if you can let that relax
as the activities of the mind relax into a calmness of the mind
set a place of subtleness
a calm body a calm mind
and then we are always aware we're we're always conscious
there's always some degree of awareness going on
see if you can allow for a state of being aware or state of awareness
is more naturally there
it doesn't require a doing
but more an allowing to be aware
allowing awareness is close to being in a receptive state
receiving experiences as they occur in the present
and with breathing at the center of it
all a receptive awareness that
also receives breathing
receives the experience of inhaling and
exhaling
breathing is a rhythm
that reminds us
to be receptive in the awareness
not to fixate on anything or get caught in thought
the rhythm of breathing received an awareness
in a sense a rhythm that keeps awareness open and
receptive
so we stay closer to a place of quiet receptivity
a state not dominated by thinking a state more characterized
by receptive awareness of what is
a state of awareness
that we repeatedly allow for
repeatedly return to resting
in receptive awareness
there is a way of being aware where awareness not doing
but more being more a state that we're in a state of awareness
and within that state we can register be aware of many
different things that occur but those things can occur
without intentionality from us without desire without
making something happen
and to relax allow for that form of the state of awareness
allow yourself to be aware
in that allowing allow the experience of breathing
to remind you to stay receptive
to be allowing of what is
if we can recognize awareness as a state state of awareness
like a state of mind or state of being
that allows us to
be content in that state or to be to rest in that state
to allow ourselves to be receptive in that state of awareness
perhaps a state of awareness where we're not actively involved with what we know
we're not for things or against things
we're not trying to fix things or get away from anything
that there's a willingness to just be aware of whatever is happening
a state of awareness
that's receptive and open
and with a state of awareness resting in it content in it
you might bring to mind or include in that awareness now
some of the people that will be part of your life today
the community of people on the retreat or those are not on the retreat
in whatever communities you might be in today
whether personally or on some form of communication technology
and for a few moments to allow for a sensitivity of awareness
of those people
that's only possible if we rest in awareness allow them to exist in
awareness while we rest in the awareness
or remain receptive in that awareness
where we can be we can be aware of people without doing anything or
needing to respond act just aware
and that being staying close to this way of being receptively aware of others
just being aware of them
not paying attention to them but being aware simple awareness
that perhaps there in that awareness you can now tap into your good will
for others or your wish for their welfare your well-wishing of others
and to let that well-wishing radiate from you glow from you
flow from you may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
so good morning and welcome to the beginning of the week and a new theme
for these morning teachings and the theme is the seven factors of
awakening and it's following
the practice and the teaching of experiencing the mind
experiencing the mind state the mind state or the mind being
a broader experience of our inner interiority our inner life than noticing
the particular activities of mind that are operating for example thinking or particular emotions going on
and the state of mind is kind of like the mood or the atmosphere or the
general state of way we are our b state of being almost
and and so as we become experience a state of mind more fully
we start becoming aware that there are different states of mind that we can experience or
different qualities different characteristics features
of the state of mind and these seven factors of awakening can be seen as both as particular
practices we do and also as a state's
qualities or characteristics of the state of mind or the state of awareness that as that
state of awareness state of mind becomes more highlighted and becomes more noticed and something
we can rest in and feel then we can start noticing
these qualities of awareness these qualities of our state of mind state of awareness and
the um so there are seven of them and the first is usually in english
translated as mindfulness the second in english usually is investigation
then effort joy tranquility samadhi
usually translated as concentration and equanimity and these are considered the crown
jewels of buddhism they are sometimes actually likened apparently in ancient india
a a monarch had seven jewels that kind of were the represented the monarchy
and uh and may and so in buddhism those seven jewels are the seven factors of awakening
uh kind of a curious metaphor that's found in the ancient texts is that
the um it's like this a monarch that uh has seven special sets of
clothes suits to wear at different occasions and and so in the same way that
a monarch has a special maybe affluent sets of clothes to wear
so buddhist practitioners as they develop in practice have these seven factors of awakening
as their suit it's a kind of strange metaphor but i think that
maybe what's suggested by it is a suit is something you wear for a while instead of clothes
you wear it for a while and so these different factors of awakening at different times different ones of
them represent the state of mind we are in and we kind of wear that state for a
while so there can be a time when mindfulness involves a great sense
of clear awareness and the clear sense of awareness stands out and
that's the state of that's the primary characteristics of our state of mind
other times it might be that there's a great sense of tranquility or a great
sense of joy or great sense of unification or samadhi or a great state
of equanimity that uh stands out of the sec
seven-factor awakening each one can stand out and be the primary characteristic
or it's possible to be aware of all seven um kind of imbalance kind of all kind of
working together in a certain way and we can recognize them together and and
or maybe see how we need to bring them into balance and um many years ago when i sat a long
retreat at some point in the practice these seven factors awakening stood out in
highlight and which they can and when the mind is really settled in a peace
then these become some of the primary characteristics of what we notice in mindfulness because
everything else is kind of abated and gotten quiet and still and peaceful and these seven factors are what remains
and i found myself that i was kind of balanced i was actually instructed to balance them bring them into balance and at some
point the teacher said i've noticed that when you talk about bringing these
seven factors of awakening into balance you never talk about equanimity it seems like
you're always tinkering with them and uh and then i realized yes i was
always kind of thinking i had to fix them and get them just right and i had no equanimity around whatever
state i was in and that helped me kind of to settle back and become more economists
so the first of these seven factors of awakening is sati is the is the ancient pali word for
it sati and translated a number of different ways and
mindfulness is the most common in english and but the way that
mindfulness practices come to the west there are many things that are called
mindfulness all of them may be appropriately so but sometimes what mindfulness is is referred to as a
clear recognition of what's happening so it's a cognitive act act of recognizing hearing if you're
hearing my voice right now or or recognizing there's pressure on your
butt if you're sitting on a chair or that the recognition oh
my hand is cold but my torso is warm and so there's the clear recognition of
things and sometimes that's represented by using mental notes where that
recognition is a little bit more highlighted and and and focused with the mental noting
sometimes what's called mindfulness is um is feeling experiencing sensing
experiences and some teachers really emphasize not uh these languages of feeling feel your
your breathing sense your breathing experience what's going on and and so
it's set more sensory and so we're kind of resting in the sensory capacity of the body to be
to be mindful to be aware and sometimes what's uh emphasizes the
power of observation
just simply observe what's happening and but don't interfere with it and all
those three uh recognition feeling and observing
are emphasized by the buddha as practices that we can do
but it's but it's not necessarily what he calls sati or mindfulness he calls these other
words for those activities and and but what those other activities
are they're part of mindfulness practice because they're the practices
that lead to sati lead to a state of awareness and what we're
looking for is we practice these things clearly recognizing what's happening focusing on the breathing feeling the
experience more fully the experience as it's happening is what
we're moving towards is a state of awareness and
the sometimes it's been translated when it becomes a state big body sometimes uh use the
translation of lucid awareness and uh there's a sense of lucidity a
clarity an openness a luminosity it's all these metaphors that
people try to use to describe the state of mindfulness
and it's not easy to be there it's not easy to rest in that state or be with it and that's why in the process of
anapanasati deepening practice that with time we get a sense of
of this the state of mind we can also then become aware there's a state of awareness that's
almost coterminous with the state of mind it's almost almost the same thing or occurs within
the same domain and so sati mindfulness as a state
that we allow for and so i think that the word english word awareness is my preferred way of then translating
sati and we can and we are aware as we say i am aware and um
and uh so to kind of paraphrase descartes i i am aware therefore i am
and um and that and the word i am uh almost applies kind of almost an
identity like this is this this kind of defines me so this
i am aware kind of suggests this broad kind of way of being or just existing in a certain way
existing in awareness not easy to rest in or be with
but it is possible and one of the ways to get to that is to begin
living at the speed of mindfulness and this is a particularly
valuable to do while on a retreat where you know nothing really has to be done there's no hurry to do anything
hopefully and and where there's more time to take it easy and just kind of do things maybe at a slower pace than
usual and so to practice at the speed of mindfulness means to uh or say it differently to
practice at the speed of awareness and what i mean by that is to
do things whatever you're going to do do them at the speed that keeps you close closely aware
of being aware that that you're cognizant of yourself being aware as you
do it uh in whatever way awareness is for you in a particular time through
the recognition of what you're doing as you're doing it by sensing and feeling it as you do it
or simply observing it quietly from the kind of in the back of the mind or something that um
you um you sense it and feel it so so um the um
um so you so you the speed of mindfulness speed of awareness is to stay close you know you're doing
it you know you're part of it you're allowing something to register in the present moment around the experience as opposed to
doing things so quickly that you're ahead of yourself you're into the next thing you're more thinking
about the next thing and then just really beating for each thing you do
and so it doesn't necessarily mean you have to do things slowly i i was a fast order cook after i came
back from three years in a zen monastery and i learned to be very aware
spinning around and doing many things at once in the kitchen working fast in some ways i found it
easier to be aware there because i would just let go of all my distractions just be in
the dance of the kitchen so it doesn't necessarily have to be fast a slow
but generally especially on retreat generally for most people that's the kind of beginning the access point for
that to happen so the mindfulness
the first factor of awakening and sometimes seen as a particular activity of mind practice we do and sometimes as
a state of mind and hopefully the activity of doing it the practice leads to this lucidity of awareness this
state of mind a state of being mindful state of being aware and that you'll feel the goodness
of that and the freedom of it and the benefits of doing that
so thank you and and we'll continue
these morning talks with the factors awakening tomorrow