so
we're beginning now with the ninth step
of anapanasati mindfulness of breathing
in and mindfulness of breathing out
and the ninth step really
builds on what fault what was earlier
some teachers who teach anapanasati this
practice of 16 steps
will insist that you should always begin
with step one
and systematically work your way through
all the steps as far as you
you've gone so far you know and
and there's some advantages to that some
people's minds really like having
order and having a real clear definitive
steps the mind gets organized it gets
focused it gets concentrated
knowing what it's doing step by step
other people find that it it ties them
in knots to do that that kind of trip
over themselves it's too much trying
too much expectation and some people
find that
that it's good to be familiar with all
the steps
and then as we sit and meditate i
discover where we are
where the where the salient step is
and sometimes we can start on step five
or start on step
you know even step eight or even step
nine any any of these steps
because we sit down and we're that's
what's kind of available
in a kind of way and
then sometimes we move through up and
down in the course of meditation
so these steps are can be done linearly
linearly for those who
find this beneficial and they can be
more
a resource for those people who want to
track themselves and understand
kind of the domain the territory of
what's happening in their meditation any
any one time what the emphasis
is and um but we get
uh to then to the ninth step and one way
of
appreciating this though is that um one
way or the other
it's helpful that the earlier steps have
been been familiar
been developed in some degree and that's
because
the more we're grounded in our body and
the body is relaxed
the more we begin opening up in a
holistic way
to our experience and we begin kind of
working through some of the knots some
of the entanglements and
tightnesses and tensions that we have
and then and then to go to the second
tetrad
five to eight is to begin to fix
feeling sensing
the emotional tone of the body
and if you're quite relaxed and focused
it's a contentment and well-being
and then with that it's easier to begin
trusting it's okay to relax the mental
activity
we don't have to be so actively involved
in fixing solving
remembering planning criticizing
whatever the mind is doing
and the activity the mind can bring to
rest and this also this resting this
releasing
bringing making the mental activity
calmer continues this process of
becoming more holistic being more
inclusive
more open to our experience and then
based on that the experience of the mind
becomes easier to experience
so step nine is breathing in one
experiences the mind breathing out one
experiences the mind
and i love this word experience uh that
could the pali word could be translated
as to feel
the mind feel the the you know feel the
mind
and um and so it's not thinking about
the mind
it's not having ideas about the mind but
it's something that is more
holistic more broad and using a kind of
the
the range of sensory apparatus we have
to take in our inner life the but the
mind is not the details of the inner
life not the particular activities
as i've said the mind is just a sum
total
of its mental activities but it's the
way that we
can somehow take in the totality of that
whatever way our mind and i want to
emphasize
arm on your mind experiences
the mood the mental state
the overall overall configuration or the
kind of balance of it all
that's what we call mind and i say that
because
there's a lot of people who would like
to have the mind
be something in particular to define it
to know what the mind is
and i don't think that that's really the
emphasis in this buddhist practice is to
know in some abstract way what the mind
is
and that's a topic for some other
occasions some other purpose than
meditation
in meditation we're only interested in
how each of us experiences our mind
and for some people the word heart is a
better translation
for cheetah c-i-t-t-a
some people even translate it as heart
mind
and the
but it's the kind of the it's the it's
the
the um so the state of the heart the
state of the mind the quality of our
inner life
it's the mood the atmosphere it's kind
of the sum total of how
all this works and sometimes there's a
predominant mood
of the mind so the predominant mood can
be one of desire or lust or
strong wanting and
and everything is kind of seen through
the filter of the strong
wanting and the there's almost like the
mind has a force
overall force like give me that and um
it's quite something we have a cat at
home and it's i kind of delight somehow
and amazed to see
the cat definitely has desires and it
seems like everything
and the whole katniss is focused on
getting what it wants
and it's clear that the desire is there
and and so the mood of desire
this disposition maybe mind is kind of
like the overall disposition that we
have
and um and sometimes it's not
desire you can feel the difference
between a general mood
characterized by this desired design and
one which is not
sometimes it's aversion hostility ill
will
and that's kind of you can kind of see
it sometimes in people that
there's like almost a cloud of anger or
hostility around them
and you know that atmosphere i'm sure is
being experienced or could be
experienced in the inside as well
or there can be the absence of ill will
there could be love and then there can
be confusion
that characterizes it all and mind is
jumping around not knowing what it wants
to do and doesn't understand
kind of a lost feeling that's a kind of
a general tone
of the mind or the absence of confusion
maybe there's clarity wisdom
the overall mood of the mind mind state
can be one of
destructibility around scatteredness
or it could be one of um being present
and
undistracted and then one of the great
ones that the tradition talks about
is one can know the mind is being
expansive or large
or one can know the mind is not being
expensive not being large
and this points to how as we become as
we develop this mindfulness and as we
develop
a reflexive awareness of awareness
itself
of the mind itself that seems to change
the mind that seems to change the kind
of it's harder than to focus
on on only the things that we're
thinking about or
things we're aware of something begins
happening when we're aware of awareness
aware of the mind that knows or then
where the mind state
it's kind of like if someone points out
to you how dirty the windshield is in a
car
then now you drive and you're now you're
aware of the windshield you can't
you're not focusing on it but you can't
not see it anymore
so to become aware of the mind uh it
changes the mind
because the mind is not a physical thing
the mind is the one way of understanding
it's a
kind of this kind of the sum total of
the mental activities that are operating
and one of the key mental activities
is the knowing of itself if the mind is
known if we bring attention to the mind
and the attention is a uh
not for or against the tension is not
with
expectations with demands with criticism
it just kind of relaxed equanimous
allowing awareness of the mind that's a
mental activity in itself
that then feeds back into the formation
of the mind as a whole
and so we're shaping our mind all the
time
maybe the brain doesn't change that much
the mind is very flexible
the buddha emphasized the mind is very
very changeable
and it changes with all our moods and
activities and what's going on and so
mindfulness itself meditation itself
does have an effect on how we experience
the mind
and as we and here the instructions are
know the mind or experience the mind
breathing in and breathing out
as we do that um because everything we
do
has with the mind hasn't
feeds back onto shaping the mind the
experience of the mind we have
and so now we're in this kind of can you
start being in this kind of
loop this kind of cycle this kind of
where
as the meditation deepens we're bringing
more and more equanimity more openness
more and more receptivity
to whatever our experience is including
that of the mind
and that has
creates some of the ver brings those
qualities to the mind itself
so one of the reasons why in meditation
practice we're trying to develop
an equanimous mindfulness that's not for
or against experience
it's good in and of itself but as that
gets stronger
it feeds back to
reshape or reform the disposition of the
mind the quality of the mind the state
of the mind
so the mind itself begins feeling more
receptive
soft expansive
and um and all kinds of wonderful things
we'll talk more about
so it might be that it's difficult to uh
some of you to follow what i'm saying
but um
but maybe you think about it as mood
your the your mood that you're in or
the feeling tone the emotional tone of
your inner life of your mind your heart
and um and you can certainly be aware of
it anytime at all
but to be aware of it after having
meditated for some time
for example the more or less the first
eight steps
kind of prepares the ground for
mindfulness of the mind to have this
wonderful feedback loop
to continue to condition or
open the mind in a more deeper and
deeper way
that will allow for concentration to
develop
so i'll talk more about these this mind
thing over the next couple of days
so in the meantime what you might do
is as you go about some of your daily
tasks maybe some of the common things
you do
something that you maybe do regularly
through the day maybe
washing up or cooking or driving or just
going for you know whatever you do
why don't you start noticing the mood
with which you do it
and then really know the mood and don't
just check it off oh
you know i'm annoyed at the exercise
and don't just don't just check it off
really
experience the mood take time to
and one way to make sure you give enough
time to experience the mood
is to breathe with the mood take time
just breathe
with it for a while and get to know it
and start recognizing your mood
and start recognizing also how your mood
shifts
as it is known as you experience it
as you breathe with it and in daily life
as you go through the day
um don't overlook
the windshield by looking through it on
to what's on the other side
so thank you all very much
and and i'll say it a few times so this
week we're meeting at seven o'clock
and and then next week we'll meet next
monday
i'll start again at 6 45 for that week
and
um and because i'll be on retreat again
and uh so it works really well from
connecting the two
for the retreat practice and the what
we're doing here on youtube
so thank you very very much and i look
forward to tomorrow