so just a comment before i start that when i just sat down now the
my youtube screen for this my laptop here had frozen so i had to
refresh it and yesterday i noticed that there were a few like three or four or five maybe
comments about kind of in a row of people who were um i guess their screen has frozen too and
needed to be reset but mostly not and it seemed to go fine after that so i just want to say last week we had a
big problem with this and i finally got it to work by
switching our service provider we have two here at imc so if this should happen again today and
it becomes a big deal then just i will switch the service provider
probably take me a minute or so or two to make the change and and so hopefully uh you'll come back if
that's you know what's going on
so good morning and uh welcome to the meditation
and uh this week i'm going through the basic sequence the sequence of the basic
instructions for mindfulness practice that we i teach here at imc
where we focus on breathing the first and then the body and then emotions
thinking and then something interesting on the final day and and so here today is the day on
emotions and certainly emotions are an important part of life
and but i think it's useful to consider that emotions are probably not
what you think they are and they're probably more important in
ways that you can't imagine or don't really know at the same time as being less important
than maybe you realize for people who maybe have very little contact with their
emotions maybe for some of them that
they're probably more important than they realize and for people who are very much touched in contact with their emotions
there's a way in which maybe they're less important than you realize and either direction is a
is a corrective in the direction of becoming free
kind of freedom to emote to freedom of emotions in a particular buddhist way
so in the teachings of this mindfulness practice there are four
dimensions or four aspects of mindfulness of emotions
and these can happen all at once in some kind of holistic way or they can happen to each
distinctly as is appropriate as is useful as whichever one is the most freeing
in the moment and that begs the question of what does freeing mean
but so the one is to simply recognize to clearly recognize an
emotion which is there is powerful to recognize that we're happy here to recognize we're sad or grieving
to recognize we're angry discouraged inspired there's something that happens
in their recognition that if the recognition is very simple just the recognition that uh there's
something freeing in that just allows it to be there makes almost like making space for something
the second aspect is allowing and whatever the emotion is to allow it
and meditation practice whatever your posture is whether it's sitting or even walking meditation standing
meditation there's something about that's very special about the posture that we settle into or or or intentionally
place ourselves in when we meditate that becomes a posture that's meant to be able to hold and make
room for anything that we're feeling inside in daily life it might not be possible to
allow all our emotions their freedom just flow through us we might make a mistake what we say and do
we have to care for people in ways that sometimes our emotions wouldn't if we
just let them be expressed but in meditation it's meant to be a place of real no
shame no embarrassment and no blame no needing to run away from no need to
collapse lean forward and grab just sitting upright
and allowing it to course through us and and stay present stay aware
so once we recognize it we can allow the third is to feel
and the fields is a to really experience the
physicality of the emotion the physical expression of it manifestation of it
and almost all emotions that we feel have some kind of physical manifestation
that lets us know that we're having an emotion and and so you know it could be that the
chest is tight and compressed it could be the jaws are clenched it could be the stomach as
has butterflies in it it could be there's a warmth that kind of that kind of radiates from the heart
that feels so good or the hands feel delightfully tingly or there's a wonderful thrill that runs
through the body and when there's joy or something and so to feel it and to trust the body's
experience and one of the reasons it's so useful to feel the physicality of emotions it's a
it's a way of stepping away from the story making mind the stories the ideas the projections
the planning the reactivity of the thinking mind which has a way of fueling and
continuing the emotion it's a little bit like someone who reaches down to grab a beach ball on the
ground and as they do so their foot kicks the ball further and so they walk
up to the ball reach them to pick it up and they kick it then they're never able to pick it up because they keep
kicking it forward so the same way with our emotions there's a way in which our story making mind or
ruminations about there's what's going on keeps kicking the emotion forward and so
we're never quite able to get a clear view of it or a clear stepping back and holding it in a
loving compassionate way or wise way liberated way and so feeling is not the same thing as
story so it's a way of allowing the body to process the emotion and the fourth is something that's a
little more complicated which means teasing apart and that's meant to be
something very very simple but to begin distinguishing between
things have been different aspects of the emotion this for example the physical manifestation versus the
story making mind the difference between our attitude
towards the emotion and the emotion itself and so these very simple distinctions
that makes kind of breathing room to be present so it's easier to be there with it without having these knotted up with
each other when our reactivity and attitude is knotted up with the emotion uh it
can be very difficult and in some ways we keep kicking the ball forward
so those these four recognize allow feel and tease apart
makes up the acronym raft and with this raft we can float
on the wonderful current of our emotions rather than drown in them
so assuming a meditative posture
and gently closing your eyes
or keeping them open if that's your practice
and with your eyes with your sitting just like you are
just check in with yourself and how are you feeling right now
what's your mood your emotional state how is it
and i have a few moments of clearly recognizing it
and seeing if that recognition can be very very simple
just the recognition oh it's like this and if you it's very vague how you're
feeling then you can just recognize that you're having a feeling just that's all you
have to name it more specific than that
or if there's no feelings or emotions or mood states then recognize the absence
and however you are feeling what was it me what does it mean
for you to allow it now give room for it
not assume it should be different
in a sense giving permission for however you're feeling to be there
unconditioned unconditional
permission maybe as if your emotional state has
never had permission to be out in the sun it's the sun of awareness
and finally it's allowed to just exist and be felt the known
and then feel it in your body what parts of your body are most active
or alive or with sensations associated with
how you're feeling and it could be anywhere
the face the hands the belly the chest
the head the back the feet
and then to tease apart to notice tease apart distinguish
between your thinking your reactions your judgments
about what you're feeling and the simplicity of the feeling itself
tease apart the stories you telling yourself about it
from the embodied experience itself
and with this kind of beginning of recognizing how you are
taking a few long slow deep breaths three quarters full the inhale
may be inhaling and into the body that's feeling
and the long exhale softening and relaxing the body
around how you're feeling
long exhale and settling in to your body here
and then letting your breathing return to normal and with a breath and breathing kind of
itself on the exhale relaxing the muscles of
your face letting those muscles fall away from the
bone muscles of the face do so much work
throughout the day and now sitting here you can let it rest
and then maybe on the exhale to soften the shoulders
release the shoulders
no no need to carry the weight of the world for these minutes you're here
and softening your belly
and then within your body as part of your bodily experience
become aware of how the body
experiences breathing
and when you're exhaling perhaps from time to time you can let go
of your thinking
or quiet your thinking
so you can better ride along in the rhythm breathing in
and breathing out
so
and then quietly calmly
without disturbing things too much or at all how are you feeling now
what's the emotion emotional tenor mood that's present for you
calm or agitated content or discontent
happy or sad
irritated or
friendly
whatever it might be for you
recognize it for what it is
without being too concerned with how accurate the recognition is
like it has to be the exact word maybe it's a silent recognition an
acknowledgement
and in that recognition is there some freedom some
non-entanglement like stepping back and
non-involvement
and make room for how you're feeling allow it to be there
and in that allowing is there a kind of freedom
non-entanglement
and then gently how does the body experience
your emotion how's it felt in the body
perhaps trusting the body's experience
and then teasing apart the simplicity of your emotion your
state your mood in any kind of way that you define
yourself by it or judge yourself by it or
identify yourself by what you're feeling
those are two different things the emotion that can be independent
of any conclusion you make about what it says about you yourself
those conclusions are tease them apart and maybe the conclusions
can drift away
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting the respect the care that we give to
our emotional life
the ability to be physically sensitive
heightened sensitivity to the manifestation the arising of emotions
is the sensitivity that also makes room
for compassion and kindness
love and good will
and a sense of care and caring
a tenderness of heart
a tenderness that has room for
a sympathetic resonance with others
in the coming to the end of the sitting perhaps with whatever sensitivity you
have tenderness warmth
to now bring into your mind and heart the people of your life
people around you and your neighborhood and your communities
people that you're maybe communicate with or in your extended family
or strangers that you're liable to run into today
and to regard them kindly
to kindly gaze or kindly consider these people
and perhaps consider how wonderful would be if some of them could be happy
if some of them can be could be peaceful and
contentedly inspired in their life
and to wish that that was so to let you yourself have some good will towards
them may it be so may these people i know or meet
may they be happy
may these people that i maybe meet today may they be safe
may the people that i meet today think about today or communicate with today
or learn about today may they be peaceful
and may they all be free
and finally in ways that are appropriate and inspiring
for me may i
contribute to this possibility for
others for each of us in ways that are
right for us inspiring for us not an obligation but an inspiration
may we live this day for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
so emotions are probably not what
we think they are and maybe more often than not
thinking about emotions the way we think about them and conceive them maybe there's some way that keep us from
being liberated and free maybe even keep our emotions from being
have a certain kind of freedom i'm very fond of the idea that in
english the latin root for the word emotion motion means motion movement
and the e part prefix means out so moving out and i'd like to interpret
that that all emotions are processes so there are activities they're movements
and they all want to move out they all want to kind of spread
or process themselves and and our inner life has an amazing
capacity to process emotions to let them unfold or dissolve or
unfold the way that there's some wisdom to doing
and we often interfere with that wisdom we interfere with the natural process
i i love this
i love this way of thinking that i can cut my you know cutting vegetables
in the kitchen i might cut my my thing my finger and my bleed and
i have a responsibility or opportunity to take care of it by maybe washing the wound and putting a
bandaid on it to protect it and but the actual healing
i can't do it's a physiologically much more complicated event that i could ever possibly
engineer and understand figure out send the right antibodies and proteins and
hormones or whatever it goes it's involved into the right combination of things and
make the whole thing heal again what i do is keep the wound
clean and safe and protected so the body knows has the wisdom to heal
the wound usually and the same thing with our emotional life
our hearts our inner life knows something that if we get out of the way can allow
it to unfold and to move to some resolution or some solution or
some unfolding or some place depending on the emotion that's there
and and many times we don't allow that because we're so involved in either the
emotion reacting to it or something or we are
spinning the story even more uh spinning the story so like they say that one of the leading causes
for depression and not the only cause i don't want to get to give that impression but one of
the leading causes is rumination one of the things that makes grief a lot more
difficult than it needs to be is rumination is thinking and rehearsing and
remembering and and keep feeling guilt and blame and all kinds of things and
that get in gets in the way of really trusting and respecting the grief
and and so this uh um uh you know so it's like the beach ball
you know that we are constantly kicking up before we can pick it up and hold it gently and in the palm in the palms of
our mindfulness and and so instead of you know keep the
momentum going all the time in mindfulness practice we're learning how to kind of get out of the way
with the deep respect for emotions and i like very much the word respect as
kind of a synonym for mindfulness or phrabipasana because uh respect it comes from the
latin of prefect again and spec like spectator or spectacles to see
so to look again to respect our emotional life is to take us give it a second look and
really kind of what is this and then see it clearly and
allowing it to unfold and be there and whether that's useful in all
circumstances in life i don't know but it is very powerful and effective to do
in certain circumstances of life and meditation is one of them sometimes when
i have strong emotions that are difficult for me i will go for a walk in the mountains and go for a long walk and
the walking i find very useful because there's something about the movement of walking that allows
that keeps me from getting locked into the emotion and the thoughts and i can let all of it just flow and uh
and do what it needs to do uh sometimes when i've had strong
emotions uh difficult emotions uh i'll sit in meditation
and i don't try to stop anything i don't even try to stop my thinking mind per se but i'll constantly come back and
compost the strong emotions in my body just let them which means for me that i keep
returning to feel what's happening emotionally in my body like mixed space and really feel it
and when i do that i'm stepping a little bit away from the thoughts that are spinning um and if i
only thought i'd probably get into all kinds of trouble and go crazy but i step away from it but not to stop
it but to kind of change the context and really feel what's there as if the body knows how to process it
and unfold it and um and then i'll do it again and again as i compost
what i'm feeling so there are some emotions that are clearly a byproduct of what we
think and i've sat in meditation and i had a perfectly lovely peaceful time
and then for reasons that i have no idea why i'll think about
some conversation i had with someone 20 30 40 years ago now getting to be almost 50
years some of them so um and then just somehow that comes through the mind
this thought and with that thought boom i get angry or irritated or afraid or something
and um and uh and then you know i can see you know as i keep telling the story
she said i said um i should have said why didn't i say i could feel the emotions and the heat
kind of operating and it was clear that the thinking the thoughts seemed to be really central to keeping
this thing going and and then i've had times when i've learned to kind of
quiet the thinking mind and just be with the feelings and the emotions and it's really clear that i'm not no
longer feeding it i'm not like pouring pouring gasoline on the fire and uh and then something different begins to
happening something's cool and quiet and subtle and rather than solving our
emotional problems sometimes they dissolve sometimes what happens is that the you
know some emotions that we i feel many of us feel have nothing to do with
our external life but maybe it's has you know to do with physiology
and uh and so uh it's not a matter of what we're thinking a lot
but it's a feeling in the body and not identifying with it not making a
story out of it and a story about oh for me i'm bad or i'm wrong that i should feel this way
and and making a lot of space for it so that their mood or the emotion that
we have is not a filter through which we see ourselves and see life
and that ability to not let it be a filter that sees what's going on has a lot to do with this ability to
really stop and look and respect what's happening here and
and acknowledge it recognize it really feel it and know it and to um
um uh maybe tease it apart and just let it be simple
for itself and then that's a kind of liberation that's where freedom can happen
where we're no longer entangled and caught up in all this and we can just allow everything in its
uniqueness to be there for itself and this is a beautiful kind of generous thing
to grant to give all the particularities of our life its
freedom to let an emotion give its freedom to emote to be there in the quiet and the safety
of just being present for it to allow you know our reactions and
identifications with it to let that be free meaning we don't kind of get involved
and keep thinking it and you know scratching the itching scratching the scab
we just let it kind of okay you're there and okay you're free but you're free in a sense
that you're not casting a light back on me and i'm not defining myself by it
so this wonderful part of mindfulness practice in a rich part is uh bringing mindfulness to
real careful respectful attention to the fullness to the richness of our emotional life
and but not to be involved with them and not to celebrate them and not to denigrate them
but you just allow them to be there in their simplicity and what happens with that at some point
we start seeing that there are two classes of emotional
in the emotional life do classes of kind of emotions or attitudes that we can have one of the ones that
one side they're the ones that are clearly involved arise out of our reactivity
arise out of our contraction and resistance and pushing and wanting and
not wanting and the ways at which we build ideas of self
me myself and mine or attitude towards others and they're a little bit more compulsive
it's a little more automatic and they involve what in buddhism early buddhism might be called some to
some level of craving or drivenness lack of freedom
there's a whole other class of emotions that come when there's no reactivity but rather
it's the free and unfettered response of our psychophysical system some people
might say of our hearts and those feelings and emotions
seem to grow and expand the more we're present for them rather
than dissolving because we're not feeding them anymore with our attention and our stories and all
the illumination things like compassion kindness
warmth generosity love these are
wonderful states that can be pure and simple and spread out
throughout our body seemingly throughout the whole world spreading from us in their
simplicity that somehow learning to get out of the way and not being entangled with them and
shoulds and shouldn'ts and defining ourselves by them and trying to do something with them
just relaxing and and just allowing the simplicity of these good states and this
good sensitivity to be there this beautiful capacities for heart
centered emotions can grow and develop
so to develop a heightened respect sensitivity care
attention to our emotional life is one of the great benefits of the pasta practice it's one
of the great gifts to and life seems so much richer with a
this uh liberated emotional life
so thank you for today and um i'll continue tomorrow with the
mindfulness of thinking and they're also thinking is not what
you think it is thank you