okay so hello hello and welcome everyone
to this friday or saturday if you're in australia and other places or if you're
listening on audiodharma later anytime it might be good more good welcome to this moment of
practice together so so [Music]
for today's practice i'd like to invite us to to um
work with metta cultivating metal heart cultivating good will
cultivating uh meta and compassion as well as
um vicarious joy which becomes gratitude when we practice for
ourselves so as well as a little bit of equanimity all of these four brahmaviharas
practice all of those for ourselves with the support of
our metta mentor so today the theme is
cultivation with the support of a meta mentor okay so
so this meta mentor of ours is
someone it could be our inner buddha for some of you might be in your inner buddha that that you whip out comes out
and ah yes looks at you with eyes of care and love and just seize all of your
beauty all of your goodness all of your quirks all of the ways you struggle
and loves you completely completely so your meta mentor could be a buddha it
could be kuan yin for some of you you have a connection with kuan yin the embodiment of of compassion so so she
might be the one oh yes holding you for some of you might be a friend a dear
friend or a mentor or a coach or
or your fairy godmother you can imagine or
um a parent or or an angel an angelic being who is
full of goodness so whatever whoever whoever this meta
mentor just take a moment perhaps and conjure up for yourself and you can
switch later it's not good to switch too many times but if if one doesn't work later in the meditation you can switch
and choose another but but conjure up this being this being
whether imagined someone archetypal or being from your
life alive or disease doesn't matter as long as the deceased doesn't bring off
grief and sadness someone or maybe again is imaginary being who
sees you completely sees you and loves you unconditionally
this is your your quote-unquote flaws your challenges your
goodness your intention and just wants the best for you what's the best
for you seize your goodness so this will be your meta mentor
your meta mentor and come on this is imaginary right so
how hard is it to imagine someone of course it could be challenging i don't want to belittle this this this
challenge also that some of us might have but but really conjuring up someone yeah and
again if it's hard to think of a personal meta mentor think
of kuan yin think of the buddha maybe jesus maybe the being of light whoever
you connect with it's it's okay for this practice it's perfectly okay
so so with that let's begin our practice
and i'll have invitations throughout
ah so as always we land we land in our bodies
we land in this moment
connecting with the breath
the felt sense of the body connected to the earth with each breath
and i'd like to invite you to connect with your meta mentor
as described inviting this being this compassionate being
to your heart into your mind's eye into your space
this being either from your life or
this archetypal being your inner buddha
kuan yin being of light jesus mother mary
her friend or a coach very friendly
fairy
or metta fairy godmother conjuring up whoever
works for you inviting them inviting them and letting yourself be held
in their gaze taking some time to stabilize
still connecting with the breath and the body
letting yourself be held
letting yourself be held with compassion with love with care
the loving eyes of this metta mentor
this compassionate being
and if there are challenges right now there are any challenges in your body and your heart in your mind
bringing them up and sharing them with this loving being
with this caring being they know you they understand you
they don't judge you because you're having difficulty
they see you just as you are they know your entire history
all the challenges you've had they know your goodness
they hold you they hold the challenge the heartbreak the body pain
whatever it might be the disappointment with you for you compassionately
they understand we understand
allowing yourself to just receive receive
receive the care the love of compassion
being soothed
deep
circumstances may not be ideal in your heart
in your life in your mind your body
may not be what you wish for
or you would have chosen this moment in time
now this being this being understands understands the challenges
you don't have to explain they get it
they hold it with care with tenderness
without judgment
maybe you feel that their care
their understanding [Music] the unconditionality
of their good will is healing soothing
comforting gives you more
resources more resilience
and now as you were feeling care compassion of
this being
held in their care with this difficulty whatever it is
this challenge
see if you can ask them a question
if they have [Music]
some wisdom words of wisdom with care and love they have for you
that can support you through this difficulty
if you're putting your question gently offering putting it on the altar
asking is there something
i'm just listening there might be something there might be nothing
and the answer might just come in the form of
care warmth meta compassion maybe that's all that's needed
no words
let your body your heart be soft
challenge the sorrow being held with care
with care for you
with your particularities who you are the way you show up
in this world
and now invite this being
is being to whisper to you to whisper to you the resources you have
the blessings you have
for you to receive [Music] so hearing a song you already know
[Music] but hearing they
sing it to you your song of blessings of resources
letting yourself take delight be gladdened by these resources
these blessings that you are reminded of
and now letting this meta
friend meta mentor being meta being
i invite you to see your life the challenges you're having right now
the goodness in your life
the context and the bigger context of the entire arc of your life
the bird's eye view which they have access to
and through them you can have a glimpse
ah and witness the arc of your life how this current
moment fits in with spaciousness and equanimity
and warmth and care which they have for you
for you to have for yourself
and together with this being
of meta of compassion holding the entire
arc of your life with meta yourself with metta in the
midst of it as much as possible
in this moment
may i be safe from inner and outer harm
may i be happy and joyful
may i be healthy and strong
may i meet my life with ease
the entire arc of my life in this moment as it arises
with as much ease as possible
holding this period of practice however it was
with meta for yourself whether it was distracted sleepy however
it was saying it together with your metal mentor with the
gaze of metta and appreciation letting go of judgment you showed up you
tried offering the goodness
to all beings everywhere including yourself may all beings
all beings know their own goodness may all beings be free
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so we have time for reflections questions
comments you can type them in chat if you like if
sent to everyone i will read your name if it's just sent to me
i will not read your name and um
you're also welcome to raise your zoom hand
if you wish
what was this like for you to bring up your meta mentor
see yourself and did any of you also ask
for support for feedback for advice wisdom that's how we put it how i put it
words of wisdom the forest says
kept falling asleep but it was still wonderful to sit in the company of the buddha oh that's lovely beautiful
thank you for that first allison says i am so filled with gratitude for this
sacred space thank you to you all for being here oh
thank you allison for acknowledging the sacred space that we co-create together
nicholas please
um yeah i i appreciated the the meta mentor
because being held in compassion
from the meta mentor helped me see
i don't see compassion as mine but i do see presence or absence of compassion as
my responsibility and so you know when compassion is not
available there's a certain attitude of failure that this needs to be fixed
and i think i hadn't i hadn't noticed that clearly and so this sit was very tender um
[Music] because it was very tender to sit in that space of compassion doesn't isn't
really felt in this moment and what does it mean that that's not my
fault that was a very tender place for me to sit
hmm i feel so moved nicholas
i feel so moved with what you named sitting in this tender place
yes it is not my fault if there is if compassion is not arising in this moment it is the challenge in
this moment and for it to be seen with eyes of compassion oh
i am moved yes thank you thank you
what a beautiful opening thank you [Music]
mark shares that was quite a special meditation thank you thank you mark thank you for your
practice and if you'd like to say more if you
like to expand you are welcome too raise your hand but don't fail
i don't want to put you on the spot yes let's see i'm gonna ask you to unmute
yourself there
i was recently told that my final remaining
beautiful sweet seven-year-old golden retriever
has one to three months to live and will bleed out from a cancer
in an awful way and i was sitting with
with asking my
mentor as it were why this heartbreak and how to
to handle this heartbreak
and mom what what came
was love is always the answer
[Music]
thank you mark thank you so much for sharing that
love is always the answer isn't it
i feel soothed as you say this as you share the the wisdom of your meta mentor
in this situation i feel soothed yes love is always the
answer no matter what thank you for the blessing
you shared thank you all for the blessing of your
practice of this sangha
let us turn to practice in small groups size three
roughly and sharing with each other well always as always we'll start with 15 seconds of
silent meta and there's so much that we can gain from each other
from um what came up for us from our meta mentor
words of wisdom or the challenges that we sat with with
tenderness it's all invited it's all invited
so taking the first 15 seconds with silence for yourself or
others with meta with compassion and then sharing as little or as much as
you wish so here are the rooms they are created and take care of
yourselves take care of each other
great welcome back everyone
oops i'm going to mute the the phone zoom has a
problem when we come back from from groups the the those who are on um
phone don't get uh muted anyway welcome back
we have a few minutes for reflections questions comments so please
don't be shy especially if you haven't spoken for a while i'd love to hear from you
what did you discover any part of it and no one has commented
on on the part with equanimity yet or with the
with gratitude richard please
am i unmuted now yes you are uh i mentioned this to my group is that
uh i've done this sort of thing before and i imagine the the loving
presence smiling down at me and when that happens i sort of automatically you
know return the smile and um that really sort of lifts my spirits
that kind of creating a real feedback loop of
happiness nice i love that the receiving of the love
that we're seeing of the meta makes you light up you smile back it feels like a
virtuous cycle instead of a vicious cycle becomes a virtuous cycle of smiling giving and
receiving this smile thank you i love that and you're smiling now richard yes
that's great sorry exactly it's the virtual cycle that's
right and so is so many other people in the sangha a sangha i see in their videos it's very sweet
thanks richard melanie says just want to say thank you to my small group for being so
supportive oh that is so sweet that's so sweet oh
so dear ones we have come to the end of yet another happy hour practice together
an hour of cultivating meta compassion gratitude
and equanimity so thank you all thank you for the gift of your practice thank you
for cultivating your heart showing up for the sake of yourself and all beings everywhere
may all beings be well may all beings be happy
[Music] thank you
and now