hello and formally welcome to this edition of happy hour
so for today's practice
my invitation is to explore
letting go letting go as a way to make space
to make space for more peace for more love for more space within
letting go of what is not necessary in the moment what is extra and there is so
much extra often both internally and externally and
internally often many thoughts many [Music]
judgments criticisms you should do this you shouldn't do that just all extra so much reactivity is
just extra extra it's not needed what is extra can it be ah just put down
so for that we need to notice it with mindfulness with awareness and
simply putting it down and by putting it down then we can
notice oh there's more space for silence for peace
for goodness for love for care for nurturing for nourishment
so making space for love making space for love by letting go
and before we start i'd like to share a quote by john cemeto
and the quote is is longish one and a funny one
and i'll paste cut and paste the resource it's
here we go and later uh this especially for neil who's going to
be thank you neil for sharing for finding it later and sharing it with the sangha in the google
groups but here we go so here's the quote so ah john sumato
who's a monastic in the theravada tradition in the ajancha forest
[Music] forest practice so
he says the practice of letting go is very effective for minds obsessed
by compulsive thinking you simplify your meditation practice
down to just two words letting go rather than try to develop
this practice and then develop that and achieve this and go into that and
understand this and read the suttas and study the abi dhamma and then learn pali and sanskrit
then the madhyamika get ordination in the hinayana mahayana
vajrayana write books become a world renowned authority on buddhism
instead of becoming the world's expert on buddhism and being invited to great international
buddhist conferences just let go let go let go
i did nothing but this for about two years every time i tried to understand or
figure things out i'd say let go let go until the desire
would fade out so i'm making it very simple for you to save you from
getting caught in incredible amounts of suffering there is nothing more sorrowful than
having to attend international buddhist conferences some of you might have the desire to become
the buddha of the age maitreya radiating love through the world but
instead i suggest just being an earthworm letting go of the desire to radiate love
throughout the world just be an earthworm who knows only two
words let go let go let go you see ours is the lesser vehicle the hinayana
so we only have these simple poverty stricken practices so
[Laughter] it definitely has a sense of humor so
so let go so we'll practice a simple practice of letting go making space
making space for peace ease love letting go of whatever is extra
keeping it simple tonight so with that
ah i'd like to invite you to get into meditation
posture whatever it is comfortable supportive nourishing for you in this
moment sitting or lying down
ah and letting go letting go
whatever is extra whatever is not needed
letting go of any tension you're holding
in your head and your forehead
your face
behind the eyes
letting go of any tension in your jaw
muscles of the face releasing
what is extra what's not needed
letting go
inviting to be let go of any tension in your chest
okay let's go back to neck and shoulders yes neck and shoulders
ah releasing releasing the arms the hands [Music]
letting go of their weight
letting gravity support pull down
the arms and hands
releasing any tension in the chest
inviting your heart to relax heart center
the proverbial space of emotions
releasing any tension ah tightness in the belly
lower abdomen sit bones releasing tightness
letting go
any holding in the upper legs knees lower legs and feet
letting gravity support entire weight of the legs
the sub bounce
letting the body be breathed naturally on its own
with each breath
letting go of whatever is extra in this moment the tension in the body tightness
any muscles
extra not needed
the natural state
this human body heart and mind is of profound peace clarity
and if thoughts preoccupations
anything that comes up that's not needed in this moment is giving as you give yourself wholeheartedly to
this practice
notice what's there isn't this is needed right now
is this really needed right now
this is needed at all simply let go
then notice what opens up what happens when
letting go when something is let go of then turn your awareness
to the space and the heart and mind and body that opens up
notice if there's more peace more freedom more ease more space
to love to be to care to be still [Music]
self-care self-love in the stillness
mindfully notice what's extra
let go and notice what opens up mindfully
what is here when what is extra not needed is let go of very simple practice
foundation for more peace self-care
and love
and if hindrances arise of restlessness
or boredom
or sensual desire oral will
or doubt can they simply be noticed
as extra heavy not needed can they be simply be let go
and returning to the body and the breath
letting go of what's neat what's not needed what's extra
letting go again and again
patiently joyfully gladly
simply lovingly
not throwing anything with hatred or will but releasing releasing
releasing letting it fly away
feeling lighter upon the release
as if you're opening a door a window letting a bird fly away that was
previously inside thrashing about confined
in your mind and your heart open the door the window release let it go
ah
okay
and as we approach the end of this practice
session together
if any judgments any thoughts
arise of self-criticism
mindfully see them clearly
they are not needed they are extra they are really extra bumping
inside
open the door window let them fly away they're not needed thank you
you showed up you've done your best
may we all taste the peace the ease the freedom of letting go may all beings
everywhere be free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
what a lovely practice to let go what's extra what's not needed
so much we realize is extra not needed
so i will change the settings now in the chat
you're welcome to type in chat your reflections your questions your discoveries share
them with the sangha if you share them with me alone i won't
read your name it'll be private if it's the sangha i'll read your name you can also raise your
zoom hand your physical hand i may not see
yeah marie christine says simple and yet so powerful yeah powerful
indeed would you like to say more murray christine
yes or no you can shake your hand i'm seeing you yes that's it yes i think okay i'll ask
you to unmute yourself
okay you can unmute yourself if you wish i suppose powerful in the sense of um
the impact it can have on one's well-being with a physical and mental so something that seems so little can be
so transformative yes yes exactly absolutely right right it's a little
practice that could
and um yeah it's um and as you say this i want to
emphasize and really appreciate highlight what you're saying regarding the power of this seemingly
simple practice of letting go because it is a liberative practice it's
a practice of that leads to freedom to letting go and
[Music] um see what can i say without getting too
technical um it seems a very simple practice
it oh yeah it seems like a beginner's practice and almost but and yet there are
stages in practice very very um deep meditative
i'll say advanced state stages of insight practice where actually the
technique of letting go is what unbinds it unbinds the um
the the just the remaining attachments and leads to a profound opening this state of
freedom it's the very movement of the mind i hope that makes sense yeah
it feels like it undo it undoes me or you from the addictive behavior from the
addiction in a way yeah of doing things in a particular way and thinking in a particular way yeah yeah exactly it's so powerful
it makes so much space for what's good and wholesome yeah yeah
thanks for underlying that it's simple yet so powerful thank you mark christine
ah the other reflections observations
do you notice complaints questions
anything hello yes hi hi i i well what i have
heard is um we can't let go it's like um
we think we are in control of that but i think if we just set intention
uh you know a good intention or aspiration to let go that it goes on its own
so if if we are if we are in control it is
you know a couple steps removed or quite a few steps
you never tried to go let go let go the more you try try try the farther you
are from actually doing it yeah yeah thanks for raising that so there
are a couple of different things here actually so um and i appreciate you raising that
because when i teach i bring up both so there is this idea of setting the intention to
let go and yet there is this movement of the mind that does let go and yet there are times
that that some things are so so so the letting go is actually practice
for the simple movements of the mind and yet sometimes there are things for
example resentments say or say
yeah you want to forgive and you don't want to have the resentment or the upset it's better or the anger and
letting go if you try to let go in that way sometimes actually you get yourself kind
of tied up even more and more so there is a wisdom to know the
difference between the two so as i johnson mega points out in this simple yet powerful
practice there is a wisdom in not just setting the intention but actually practicing letting go in the
way of because the mind can't let go we can't just say oh we can't let go and just it's not possible so
so there my some movements in the mind that you can actually feel it it's subtle but
you can see it and feel it um that oh yeah this this thing that was heavy
you you it's let go of you set the intention oh it just let go of there's
lightness brightness and and ease and yet there are times when you set the
intention you try to let go you offer the the the practice as in the words of virgin tomato let go let
go and and yet it's tied in place so instead of beating yourself
up realizing those times that it is not so much
a doing but it's a non-doing so the practice can feel a little
quizzical or or perhaps non-dual in some ways you're both doing the letting go and
you're both not doing the letting go so i think both aspects of those are
of the practice are important to be held not to say it's just one or the other
so stephanie my stephanie says hello all i
was trying to let go of stories around strong physical sensations and to just be with the powerful
sensations lovely lovely that is beautiful yeah letting go
of the stories and just being with the sensations nice great yeah
beautiful i want i'd love to hear more from you stephanie and i do see anthony's hand
and i also realized hi so let's hold those two comments for when we come back from
small groups because i want to make sure we have enough time for those so so let's practice
let go of being in the big community in the big room and move to smaller
groups where we will practice together
in groups of three or four and let's start with 15 seconds of
silent meta for one another and then share as little or as much as you'd like to share
about this practice and how it was for you so i will open the rooms now and we'll come
back with some time at the end for reflections okay here we go welcome back welcome back
so um we have a few minutes and yes anthony had
his hand up and it'd be nice to hear more from stephanie if she's she'd like to if she wants to
share more it's okay if not so anthony please
yes thank you nikki uh i'm actually gonna change what i'm gonna say uh from the group meeting uh one of the
crew members mentioned something that really connected with me about how she had some uh i think she
said aches in her upper back or something like that and uh
and then she let go but and then that that just brought up to me that wow that's so
amazing that that's a i literally thought that's the best way to connect with letting go is our bodies
you know because we're usually we have some kind of tension going on somewhere you know contraction
and uh it's easy to connect with the body and to let go you know i just wanted to bring that up yeah
fantastic yeah thank you thanks for bringing that up great and um
and stephanie if you like to share you are welcome to and if not that's okay too
we'll open it up for you hi okay hi hi um yeah so
in the group we kind of continued on that theme a little bit and how when you drop
what you're thinking you are left with body that's it and sometimes it's really
intense um and that that's pretty much
it i'm not yeah that's it yeah yeah that's that's great that's a
great observation when you let go of the busyness of the mind you
come actually that's very profound you come to the body that oh oh sweet dear body i've forsaken you
you're you're exhausted you're tired you're i i've been so busy in my thoughts that
i even haven't noticed to care for you yeah yeah exactly yeah so common thanks for
bringing that in such excellent points really such beautiful points in practice
so dear ones we have come to the end of our time together
thank you so much for your practice for coming to happy hour
to cultivate your heart for your own sake and the sake of
everyone whom you meet so may all beings be happy may all beings
be free including ourselves
thank you