warm greetings from imc in redwood city and
in continuing with this series on this week on mindfulness of breathing
the if you if one is sitting still
being still not moving the body but then was going to notice
the largest movements that are still happening
chances are you become aware of the movements of breathing even if the rest of the body is still
not moving the movements of the chest the diaphragm the belly the shoulders the back ribcage
all the parts of the body that come into play with breathing are still moving and
they're as they're supposed to and so if we're sitting still
and attentive to the body one of the things that we will start
noticing is the breathing the breathing will make itself known
and this idea of what makes itself known is a very interesting idea
because often we are directing our attention we are have an agenda for what we want what we're looking for what
we're concerned with and there might be a lot of will a lot of
directedness in our attention and there's another whole way of
in terms of meditation or the way of being in life even and that's fascinating
and and kind of deepening for the purpose of meditation is what is it that is known what is it
that makes itself known and um and so
the breathing can make itself known and there's a play here a little bit between
uh our directing our attention to the breathing and all and are kind of receiving the
breathing it's maybe a little bit like we intentionally open a window
and then we can feel the breeze coming in so we open the window of attention to
the breathing and then we start feeling that experience that experience becomes
known and so it's a little bit less at some point of directing the mind on the breathing
as it is repeatedly opening the window
to receive the sensations of breathing and then those sensations become known
and or felt and one of the first things we can do is we can feel the breathing feel the
sensations and the feeling of the sensations is one of
the ways to develop concentration is to stay close to the sensate the
sensory experience so one of those is the movements of the breathing
another is the as you breathe in maybe the expansion the pressure
top of the in breath there might be a tautness as we reach near the limit there
and on the exhale there's a release relaxing a smoothness
maybe and sometimes that's breathing in and breathing out feels like a smooth feeling and sometimes it
feels choppy kind of like little segments that are going in and going out
and whatever it was to feel it and to feel it where in the body it's most compelling where the experience of
breathing is easiest and that sometimes called the home base
for some people it's the it's the um a particular spot
sometimes people really love feeling it in the lower belly just below the navel some people feel it in the chest around
the solar plexus diaphragm area some people will feel it at the at the nose the sensations of the air going in
and out through the nose and tip of the nose the top of the lip some people find it very nice to just
feel the whole experience of the body so it's kind of a holistic sense
censoring of it all as we get concentrated
there's a subtle shift that can begin happening and now in addition to sensing and feeling it
there's a very quiet relaxed knowing that can we can engage in we know that
that is moving movement we know that is pressure and release of pressure
we know that that is a sense of expansion and contraction we start
kind of recognizing knowing that what those sensations actually are
and then to go further down as we gets quieter the knowing begins to fade away or not
as important and it becomes a quiet observing
where there's not much recognition just observing and the intimacy of the feeling at the
beginning is replaced by an intimacy of the observing the observing has a clarity to
it and a beauty to it at the right time as as it gets more and more settled
so um so to
assume a meditation posture and
and adjusting the posture to make it a little easier for your
lungs to breathe your diaphragm to move and for some people that's letting the
chest be a little bit more open
sometimes sitting a little bit straighter so that we're not we're not collapsing in the front of our body
can make it easier to breathe and gently closing the eyes
and relaxing
seeing where in the body you can relax maybe relaxing around the belly
and as if you relax a lot in the belly you might want to readjust your posture
slightly so that the weight of your
body through your spine feels just right
and relaxing your shoulders
and there too maybe some subtle shifts in how your hands are
can feel good in the shoulders let them relax more
and softening in the face maybe letting there be a soft little
opening in the mouth
relaxing around the eyes
and then to allow the breathing to be known almost as the breathing
comes into awareness more fully gently take a few two or three deeper
breaths receiving the full experience and sense sensory
experience of breathing in and breathing out
and letting your breathing return to normal
and don't be too concerned what normal is if you find yourself controlling the breath or the bath a
little bit held in check
it's okay for the purpose of mindfulness it's just to feel it how it is
without any need really to for it to be different it's okay the way it is
the task is to feel it as it is
what is the body's experience of breathing
where's the predominant place where you feel the body breathing
the belly the chest the nose
or the whole body in a certain way the whole torso
and the more you allow yourself to feel the sensations of breathing
the less the the energy of attention goes into thinking about other things
now's not the time to be thinking about other things so
at least to put those things into the background of the mind
in the foreground
receive the sensations of breathing
like the window is open and the rhythm of breathing in and
breathing out is like a gentle breeze or gentle waves lapping up on the shore
to feel the experience of breathing is to be intimate
mindfulness is never in a hurry mindfulness is as an attitude of as
that you have all the time in the world
to sense and feel what's happening
as a gentle way of staying connected to your breathing
there's a very subtle way of thinking alternative thinking to being distracted
is to very gently with all the time in the world
recognize some of the sensations that come into play as you breathe
kind of kind of like you're stroking the sensations or
like you're putting a gentle hand on them too just acknowledge their presence
it can be as simple as recognition of movement
tingling warmth coolness
pleasure if anything of breathing is pleasant
or unpleasant if anything is unpleasant
pressure tightness looseness
sometimes there's a little pulling with the exhale
or releasing
jagged or smooth
the gentle little recognition that keeps you gently tethered
to your breathing
saying it in such a quiet voice
that that act of recognition is quieting for the distracted mind
stay close to the sensations of breathing feeling the breath
it has a gentle contact
gentle holding of those sensations
recognize them with a little word or act of recognition for what they are
not all of them not straining whatever is obvious
and easy in such a way that their recognition
support you to be intimate with the sensations
where the act of recognition is not a final decision at what's there
but rather it's more like opening the window
almost like a question mark so that you feel it more fully
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
is there any way that your breathing has become more useful
little more fluid or relaxed in the course of the meditation
and to feel that sense of ease or an easeful breath
and if it hasn't that's okay
it's also very important to recognize a no well
a breathing which is not useful
in both ways can be a reference for appreciating
other people understanding that they and their breathing
is sometimes difficult sometimes labored and tense
held and that all beings have the potential
of an easy breath open relaxed easeful breath
and it's not an incidental thing to do to have an easeful breath
because the breathing is connected to our psychology our minds our hearts
to breathe easy is to be relaxed in other ways too
to be at ease in this world
and may it be that as we end the sitting then we can wish
that others also have the experience of having enough ease and safety and
well-being that they can breathe easily
it's one of the great luxuries of life relaxed easy
to have breathing room for our breathing
and through that easeful breath may beings be nourished and supported
may it teach them about their potential for being being at peace and happy
contented
may all beings be at ease in their breathing
may they have the safety to breathe easily
may they have peace
so they breathe openly
may all beings have their breathing free free breath
and may we live in such a way that supports others
to be at ease in their breathing at ease in themselves
may the many of us gather together here this morning live our days
contributing to the greater peace well-being and happiness of others
may all beings be well
so i have been
i was introduced to a meditation on breathing
probably almost 50 years ago and if someone had told me 50 years ago
when i was still a teenager that
i'd still be practicing mindfulness or breathing 50 years later and those 50 years would
have spent a lot of time tuning into my breathing i probably would have
i don't know it probably would not have been a welcomed idea
but in fact it's been a wonderful thing that um these years and
in meditation it just feels like it just keeps deepening and opening and a great and great appreciation for meditation
for being present for attention and to do it through the the vehicle of breathing and i spent a lot of time
paying attention to my breathing in fact um my my attention to breathing
is kind of with me most of the time if i'm doing things talking reading
being on the computer it's kind of almost like i have become a second nature
to also be with my breathing at the same time it's like my breathing accompanies me with everything
and it doesn't interfere with my ability to do whatever i'm going to do but it um
it supports me it guides me i recognize right away or not quickly
enough sometimes sometimes right away when i get tense when i get tight
holding concerned when i'm pushing and trying too hard it all gets translated into how my
breathing operates and i lose the easeful relaxed breath and sometimes that's completely
appropriate to have the breathing change if i go for a run or you know hike
up the hill or have some real fun with some friends playing or something that the breathing does change in ways but
it's qualitatively feels wonderful if it's in for a good purpose that the
but sometimes you know there's there's uh you know i'm trying too hard or i'm tense or
you know trying to figure out my computer and you know i feel my whole chest kind of tighten up and affects the breathing
it's held and so they're constantly be aware of it kind of supports guides or supports me
and having a much more easeful peaceful kind of life as i go through my days
and i love my breathing his intimacy with it is almost like an intimacy with life and
keeps me intimate and connected in a wonderful way so the theme for today is recognizing
yesterday was relaxing and we can relax too much and become kind of a just a
you know collapse in some way but uh most people they relax deeply deeply to have meditation be a place of
releasing releasing the holding intention is one of the great purposes of meditation
but it's not the only purpose and if we over we can overemphasize in such a way that we kind of
slump a lot or collapse or just get kind of dull
and some of the sharpness of meditation comes from the factor of recognition
and this is kind of the heart of what mindfulness is usually taught that there's a recognizing quality to it
and and different teachers will emphasize different aspects of this
mindfulness of recognition because many people in the west tend to be thinking thinkers think a lot get
lost in their thought and up in the control tower some teachers like to really emphasize
language of feeling sensing feeling your breathing sensing your breathing
placing your attention in the middle of your the physic physicality of breathing is and just to really sense and feel it
um but there are kind of three major forms of recognition that come into play with
mindfulness practice and they different times different ones of them are relevant
and and knowing these three can be very helpful because sometimes we're trying one when the
other one is actually more appropriate it's more useful for the whole system and
sometimes one of them is more helpful to work through some kind of difficulty than others so knowing these threes can
be very helpful so one is this emphasis on feeling sensing
the direct physical sensation experience of breathing and that's one of the means of getting concentrated
because you find some place where the breathing occurs in the body where there's a sensation
and you kind of ride the sensation closely maybe you kind of imagine yourself
sitting in the middle of the sensation and being carried by it or focused on it or just really kind of
attuned very closely attuned so the mind doesn't wander off very easily just the
sensing becomes the grounding the stabilizing force the steadying force for the mind to quiet down and get
focused and stable and concentrated and um
people who do the nostrils will have their sensations on their nostrils uh their breath kind of very they get very
precise and acute and very sensitive and it's amazing how how cute the sensations
can get and very compelling very pleasant sometimes the feeling in the chest little movement it might be
the whole chest that it might be as we get concentrated at just a little round
spot maybe around the solar plexus or higher up somewhere in the midline and just a
feeling just right there feeling it and if it's uh in the belly it might be
there's a classic places of the hara this place is about two inches below the navel maybe kind of like one inch into
the body and like the attention is right there feeling the sensations and there you're feeling the movements often the
sensation movements the flow back and forth and
so it can be very effective to get us out of our head sometimes that way other times and for some people
what's more helpful is the what's really the heart of the recognition factor
which is to know what the sensations are to know what the experience is while it's happening
so to recognize it's an inhale when we're breathing in to recognize and exhale with the exhale
and the recognition is a little bit cognitive it could be all with a single word
we use mental notes sometimes or almost as if there's a mental note like we imagine we're saying saying the note
like um inhaling or in out or it might be that there's a movement
expansion and we recognize that we break now that's expansion with like expansions
happening that's known expansion is known there is release as we exhale those
knowing the release or there might be a whole slew of sensations that come into play maybe too
fast to kind of name them all but there's kind of a silent recognition or an acknowledgement of what these
sensations are so in a sense after an inhale you might uh remember in a sense that
there were because you recognized it well if you were there that there was a subtle release as the inhale began
and then there was a gentle push in the part of the chest perhaps and then an expansion is spreading
and then at the top of the inhale there was um some sense of tautness like some
resistance to breathing in any more and then um and then maybe a pause and
then a release as the exhale begin so there's a uh and the recognition if it's done too
effortfully like you're doing a checklist approach it just makes the mind busy it kind of
uses a coarser active part of the mind the idea is to be it very simple and
natural and easy almost like a wonderful expression is the cognitive functioning of
emptiness the mind left to its own very its mind is very relaxed and very present it will know
it'll it knowing just happens on its own it's not so much a willful effort
but initially there might be a little bit of effort to know but it's kind of like not so willful it's just just a way
of helping to stay present it's a tether it's an anchor to the present it's a way of having a little
more clarity about what's going on and as meditation deepens the clarity becomes stronger
and there's less of the filter or the cloudiness of that happens when we're
distracted a lot caught up in our thoughts and our feelings and so
there's more and more ease ease and just recognizing and some people will go
through this pattern of starting with feeling the breathing and then as the things settle down and
get quiet and concentrated it just feels natural then to
brighten things up to sharpen the clarity of the mind by having a gentle soft recognition knowing cognitive knowing
of what is actually happening here and it turns out that in deeper meditation
there's something very deepening about this cognitive knowing just very simple
natural cognitive functioning of emptiness at some point that cognitive functioning
might seem like it's too much and and at some point it shifts just to
observing very simple observing of the experience it doesn't
have the same kind of direct contact and intimacy of feeling it doesn't necessarily have the same
kind of clarity as as recognition of cognitive knowing but observing can be very spacious very
it's meant to be kind of one of the deeper places we come to we settle back and we're not entangled
not identified not involved trying to fix anything that's going on we're just there
peacefully just watching it it's almost like we get out of our own
way when there's observation there's observing but no observer kind
of thing and so these are kind of three of the main kind of
forms of mindfulness and different times different ones are relative
useful um and it's i kind of talked about them as being deepening but sometimes when the mind is
kind of very active some people find it's better to just settle back and observe
rather than feel sometimes the intimacy of feeling gets hooks us into being kind of caught and
more engaged so and sometimes the cognitive knowing
is can be so beautiful it's like um it's like in the knowing the cognitive
knowing is where this freedom is it's almost like you say to yourself oh
it's just an inhale it's just a tight breath it's just a
control breath and that recognition is like oh that's all it is and let it be
and um the so um
so the recognition factor and so we begin with some relaxation so we're not tense in doing all this
and then we practice recognition in three forms and you can experiment and there's feeling sensing
then there's cognitive knowing and then there is just observing simple
observation and um and this is uh
and uh for people who are real beginners i'd recommend just the feeling and sensing
and then stay with the sensations the best you can and and then as it shifts you know these
other ones as well and so thank you
and i look forward to continuing this topic of breathing tomorrow