this weekend i learned that in a south african
country in south africa language that the word for hello
is i see you and the
african person who told me this speaks the language i said that i see you has a kind of opening
impact this kind of a different way of connecting to people than saying hello and and then this idea to be seen
and it is little you know a little bit odd to i can't see any of you that i'm i'm speaking to but i do see the
chats and i so much appreciate the greetings and the connection and i sit down here and
delighted to begin the mornings this way
so maybe in a figurative way i see you and offer you my greetings and
so in important ways
the breathing how we breathe the experience of breathing is a reflection of what's happening in
the mind the mind is tense the breathing is tense
certain emotions in the mind or in the heart stimulate the breathing in one way and
other emotions do it a different way it's also to some degree true of the body as a whole there's something about
when we sit down to meditate some way in which we experience the body which does in fact
express or mirrors what's happening in the mind and it's kind of a profound thing to
appreciate this or to actually see how this works it's not obvious maybe in on the surface but then the
it works in the other direction that as the breathing changes it changes the mind as
the mind as the body somehow changes it changes the mind and i say this as we
begin as we often do with relaxing the body as a way of entering into meditation
and but relaxing the body and adjusting the breathing
are not just done for the sake of physically settling in and being here it also is a kind of a
an influence a healthy good influence on the mind or the heart
so for example as we relax the body perhaps that has a maybe we feel a
little bit safer maybe we feel a sense of safety or at least less fear or less anxiety
or less tension less preoccu and if as feeling less tension
in the body allow that to translate or to waft or
influence the mind feeling less tense as well and so the relaxing the body is
part of also preparing the mind for meditation and i'll talk more about
this during the talk so to take a to assume a meditation
posture and gently close your eyes
and with your eyes closed to spend a little bit of time rocking back and forth swaying back and
forth to see if you can find just kind of stretch and kind of awaken your body a little
bit and have a sense of your body in space and then maybe feel the contact with
your sitting bones if you're sitting against your cushion or chair
and then come to center looking for a way of sitting that feels like your weight of your body is
balanced in some way if you're sitting upright that the weight of your body is centered
over the sitting bones you're not leaning forward or or not
you know your center of gravity is not behind you but because you're leaning backwards
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
not only to feel your body more fully but to establish the connection between
the mind and the body more consciously
kind of create open the channels the communication between the mind and
the body
feeling the rib cage stretch and expand as you breathe and feeling the same rib cage maybe
collapse or contract as you settle in when you exhale
and then as you exhale long deep exhale see if you can relax and soften
your body
shoulders belly and as you take a long exhale
and relax the body let that have an influence on the mind quieting of the
mind relaxing of the mind
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and see that if we also do some more relaxing and see if there's some way maybe subtle
way that relaxing the body
has an influence on relaxing the mind as well
so beginning by on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
as you exhale softening the shoulders releasing them to the pull of gravity
maybe the weight of the arms encourages the shoulders to release a
little bit
perhaps relaxing your hands any tightening in the fingers
and as if the mind participates in the relaxation
relax the chest the center of your chest your heart
center
softening the belly
and as it softens the softening in the
mind
softening in the lower waist and lower back
and relaxing the thighs
and then to feel your body in some global way
and then as you exhale to relax the whole body
easing up in any way in which you're bracing yourself against life
and then bringing your attention to your forehead
behind your forehead and the area of the brain
feeling any tension or holding pressure that might be there
agitation and as you exhale
relax
the thinking muscle relax the tensions and pressure associated with thinking
associated with worrying
associated with wanting
and then once again feel the global body in whatever way that's easy for you
to the degree to which it's easy perhaps you feel a subtleness
or a tingling or aliveness
warmth some energy coursing through your body
maybe even you can notice some feelings of contentment
or peacefulness in your body
and within the body is part of the bodily experience become aware of breathing
and gently maybe slightly at the end of the exhale
relaxing the breathings maybe you breathe
exhale a little longer
at the top of the inhale a subtle relaxation releasing
maybe the inhale continues a little more
and then can you make some small adjustments to the breathing so breathing is more
pleasant more enjoyable not dramatically but just a little bit more
breathing a little slower a little faster a little longer or shorter
looking for whatever subtle pleasure there is
in your breathing
and quieting the thinking mind
so there can be more intimacy with the experience of breathing
and if there could be if there is any coziness
contentment it's just being here in your body
or satisfaction
being connected to your bodily experience directly
even if it's uncomfortable
maybe you can allow the mind and heart
to share with some of that contentment or coziness or satisfaction
content just to sit here breathing in this living pulsing body
there is an intimacy and deep connection between the mind and the
body that functions more deeply or more
clearly when the thinking mind is quieter
gently letting go of your thoughts
appreciating the ways in which the mind can be quieter stiller so
there's a richer connection awareness of the body breathing
in the goodness of breathing or the relaxation of the body
can have a nice influence on the mind
so
perhaps there's a way you can soften your belly more relax it
to settle your breathing further
and to reassure the mind and heart
breathing in and breathing out
and then when we breathe
we breathe together with all breathing life
we share it with all of everyone else who's breathing
it's our common humanity that we all require breathing
to not only to live but for their whole inner life to be
functioning well
and while we might wish at the end of the sitting for all beings to be well and happy and free
we could also wish them to have an easeful breath
for their breathing to be easeful and comfortable
relaxed open breathing
because this way of breathing is deeply connected to being happy and
safe and free
may all beings have an easeful breath
may all beings breathe with reassurance and safety
may all beings feel delight
with their breathing as they breathe
and may it be that we live together with other people
so that we do not we're not the cause and condition
for their breathing to be tense
shallow tight may we be a condition and a cause
to support others to breathe at ease happily and peacefully
and perhaps we can coexist with an easeful breath
and the best in all of us has a chance to come forth may all beings
breathe peacefully [Music]
you