so a warm welcome everyone wherever you are in the world
in this moment of time coming together to practice so today's practice the
the title i want to give it um is the joy of metta the joy of
metta it's this practice of metta wishing well
cultivating cultivating goodness
kindness for ourselves for other beings for all beings is a happy making
it's a happy making endeavor it's not a grim like okay may you be well very happy very well
you know that'll be kind of antithetical to the whole idea of cultivating good will
it brings up joy it brings up joy um and a couple of ideas i want to bring
in tonight um as we explore one is no matter how grumpy
you might be given the cause and conditions of something happening in your day your body um
[Music] or or challenging the day might be um
and i've tried this that the days that the mind and heart have been challenged and just if i
went for a walk for example just wishing well just wishing well for
all the passerbys or if i couldn't go for a walk i would be just wishing well as if i'm giving gifts
to others just giving gifts of kindness give gifts of kindness gifts of kindness to myself and to
others and sure enough i find that oh i become happier there is the joy there's a happiness of
gift-giving it's like christmas but you don't have to go shopping for gifts you're just giving all these
gifts from your heart gifts of goodness gift so may you be safe may you be happy may you
be well me it's just there's a sense of abundance and the heart really wakes up to
to the joy to the to the abundance of itself and it nourishes us it supports
especially if we're going through a hard time if we're not going through hard times we're already happy yay becomes a party
of of happiness and especially if we're going through a hard time if there is a challenge
it supports well-being supports goodness so that we can be be be with what is difficult support
ourselves and support others so that's one thing i wanted to bring in for exploration
today with this thing and also the joy of meta another inspiration for tonight is
there are some emails on the google groups the past few days past couple of days
some folks sharing um how the practice of the brahmavihara's
metta has transformed them how they have been changed and this i think was based on inspired by an
invitation that diana gave maybe it was yesterday so maybe it wasn't two days ago maybe it's just been
a day time is elastic anyway so so for me reading reading those a few of you had
shared how um stories of how this practice of meta has has
transformed you has shifted the way you feel you show up in the world the way you feel about
others the way you feel safer happier and it made me so happy it made me so
happy the joy of metta it brought me so much joy to read uh those accounts i i'm
actually getting goosebumps remembering what i've read and also feeling into what i know of
many practitioners that i have worked with over the years myself included i've worked with myself
knowing how transformative these practices can be
um and i'll just offer one thing to you i was thinking there's so many
ways that i have changed the way i feel it will be a long drama talk which i don't want to give
right now but just one thing that came up for me is i noticed the way i talk to myself
has changed i think when i was younger before i started this practice i don't know how i referred to myself but i
certainly didn't call myself sweetie and darling and that's how i talk to myself now which is quite sweet like how
you doing darling what do you need sweetie it's just it's become a part of the way i relate to myself
so and i didn't relate to myself that that way years ago so i just wanted to
share that with you as as one of the ways one of the very very many ways
that this practice has transformed me and my life and the way i show up for myself and
and others so so with that dear ones let's practice together
let's land ah let's land let's land in our bodies
let's land in this moment letting go of all the words
that came before
and just landing feeling our feet our legs
our sit bones
connected to the earth
and landing landing landing
each out breath letting go some more of what is not needed right now
as if your mind your body is a snow globe
and perhaps up to this moment was shaken [Music] lots of flurry of bright
little thoughts agitations in the body and mind
ah setting down
the snow globe letting all the little shiny objects of the mind the body
settle with the breath with the sensations of the body
connecting connecting with each breath
calming soothing breath the entirety of the breath
the abdomen
chest throughout the body
the peace the peace nourishment of the seclusion of the mind
just here just right now
the peace the joy of seclusion of the mind
just this breath within the sensations of the body
what a gift
to be able to sit and practice
turning the gaze of awareness
internally to connect with ourselves
what a gift
this breath this amazing moment
of consciousness
and now i'd like to invite you to bring to mind
someone who's dear to you an easy person when you think of them
you feel safe maybe a smile shows up
now imagine you're giving this this being this person or this child or this pet
even a gift of care a gift of your
affection wishes or well-being as if you're giving him a gift of
goodness a care package
which is exactly right for them
a gift of goodness
feel free to use your imagination whatever works for you it could be a care package you're giving
them some undisclosed contents
just know this is right for them it's just a gift may you be safe may you be happy may you be
healthy may you have ease
feel free to imagine whatever works for you it could just be that you're blessing
them flashing the blessing or maybe
this blessing is in the form of a blanket it's cold you're giving them a warm safety comfortable blanket
wrapping them in your love just whatever
works for you be creative inviting your imagination
it could just be a beam of light you have this magic wand
a magic wand
and you bless them may you be well dear one may you be well may you have the gift of
goodness then inviting in this practice
inviting others
sharing this gift of goodness this magic wand
another being may you be safe
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you have ease
taking a couple of minutes with this being so starting
first with people who are near to you you know [Music] care about and then we'll expand
take your own time wishing well
sharing gifts of menta and connecting really connecting
with each being you bring to your hearts and mind's eye
same way that when you give someone a gift you look into their eyes
you look at them you behold them when you share a gift of goodness
in your mind's eye look into their eyes wish them well
another being
to share the gift of mentor
prince family
for this practice today spending a couple of minutes with each person
we usually spend long time with each being but today
we're giving gifts to lots of people connecting with them looking into their eyes
but inviting lots of people and sharing gifts of mentor with them
in this gift-giving party where you're giving gifts of metta feel free to invite an image of yourself
as if you're looking to your own eyes wishing yourself well just as you're
wishing well for others
giving a gift of good will care kindness
may you be safe
may you be happy may you be healthy
may you have ease
lingering with this person who is you
as if a beloved other
and now expanding a circle further inviting more
beings to this party people you don't know so well
neighbors people you might have seen at the
grocery store cashiers
etc
giving them gifts of goodness wishes of well-being for these human
beings just like you
as they want to be happy may they be happy
as you wish to be safe maybe be safe
etc
giving gifts magic wand confetti whatever image works for you
more beings
it's okay to connect with just a few seconds with with each being connecting with their
humanity wishing them well wishing them happiness
and goodness health safety ease
being you might have seen earlier today virtually or in person
or the days before
as you invite more and more beings to your mind's eye sharing gifts
of goodness blessings notice if your heart your heart mind is feeling
uplifted more joyous more abundant
even if slightly more so
and feel free to expand
if it feels accessible and easy don't push it
and expand this well-wishing to some people who are a little
challenging not the most challenging perhaps just a little challenging
if you wish and don't push it you're welcome to stay with the easy
category or the neutral beings just sharing goodness
with more and more beings so many beings
connecting with each being as you wish them well
with their common humanity just like me
connecting with yourself again as if a beloved other
wishing well for all these beings including yourself
may all beings everywhere including this being it is ourselves
be safe happy healthy have ease
may all beings be well may all beings be
free [Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
ah so
we have time for reflections and you are welcome to type your
reflections and chat if it's to me then i'll only
read the reflection not your name and if it's to everyone then i will read
your name and the reflection and if you haven't shared in a while you are welcome to raise
your zoom hand and um yeah and share your reflection what came
up with you what did you discover in this practice
what did you discover
what was it like for you
and your your reflections are a gift to the sangha it's always
enlightening to hear what other questions you know what worked what didn't work
it's all supportive it's all supportive it's all good
please claire thank you uh thank you so much i just wanted to to
emphasize something that you shared at the beginning uh one of the loveliest things that's
happened to me during coven was that right before i got myself a little pomeranian not eating not knowing
we were going to be shut down but i had to go out to walk her and all the dog walkers in new york were talking
to each other and we were i have met so many people in my neighborhood
i didn't know before and it's been such a gift of you know you're talking about the joy
of passing kindness onto others and we were doing that through the whole fan we were all the
only happy people in the whole neighborhood that is sweet i love it i i love what
you're describing this neighborliness right it's just basically that's metta you're
right when you're meeting your neighbor's dog philadelphia like hi how are you how's it going like
that's menta by any name rose by any name that's metta
that's lovely and how happy making that has been for you thank you claire that makes me happy to
hear how happy making that has been some night i'll bring dolly to the meditation please
[Laughter] that's lovely thanks claire
it's lovely other reflections please questions comments complaints it's all
welcome ah one more reflection thank you for
your tip about mitta and how you talk to yourself nikki i will try it i think inner speech is
related to right speech oh yes yes you are so welcome
and so happy to to share that with you and inspire you to try it out it's i think for me it just happened
kind of naturally i became dearer to myself and everybody has become dear
so it's yeah i encourage you to try it on for size and
see actually what happens it's this um you know the expression
fake it till you make it but actually i think more appropriately is fake it or do it
until you become it so you keep doing it you call yourself by sweet names and one day it's like yeah actually
sweetheart yeah darling what do you need are you okay oh so thank you for that reflection
other reflections please
questions comments
anything you discovered from this practice yes please carol
hi nikki hi i i just love how there's different things
we say we say them a lot like may may you be healthy
um you know may you be at ease and it's like it's so interesting how how those things
mean different things on different days in some in some ways like sometimes it's almost like a mantra
you're just repeating and then some days it just really sort of pierces down to a deeper place
where you i don't i don't know it's just for me today when you said at one point like maybe
healthy i had to go to the doctor today and it was it was not that eventful but i was i went through
a period of several years where i was chronically ill so it's like i just still have these like
just remnants of like ptsd from that i feel like where i'm just like it's like everything there's part of me
that goes into this like oh no what if i lose everything again in my life and so just that like you saying like
maybe be healthy maybe at ease it was just like really like helped me connect to this
uh different part of myself that has developed since then in you know the 10 years since then that
is uh more loving and and is at ease so i just wanted to say thanks for that and
also just love our beautiful practice and how it is always different every day
thank you thank you carol for your practice and and it is isn't it always
different every day it's this gift of impermanence keeps it interesting every day and just
as you said these different um wishes they land differently oh yes
may you be happy oh sweetheart may you have ease oh yes yes lance differently
the different level layer practice is like an onion i like to
think it's sweet on you know different layers being peeled absolutely
what a beautiful insight yeah yeah thank you carol thanks thanks for being
here thank you
sweet so oh yes one more reflection i've been
trying to observe more closely how i speak with myself as an extension to right speech practice
and the way you nikki speak has been very inspiring thank you ah thank you for that reflection thank
you so much and it's inspiring to me that you're inspired we inspire each other it's it's we keep giving these gifts to
each other and yes the way we speak to ourselves definitely our inner speech
as um as an extension of right speech sometimes we we may speak to ourselves the way we
will never speak to others good heavens you know it so what if we treated ourselves as a
beloved other as this being whom we are entrusted
whose care we are entrusted with it was a complicated construction this beloved other whom we are entrusted
with his or her or their care okay maybe that made more sense anyway so dear ones
let's turn our practic our our attention um into practicing in small groups and
here's the invitation for tonight um you're welcome to well let's start with 15 seconds of silent meta
as as always for ourselves and each other and then um
let's if if you like to you can share a story of how your how you have changed something
about you the way you show up for yourself or others something something has
shifted and changed into some situation that was really difficult or people were difficult perhaps now
through a practice of meta something has shifted for you so um inspired by these
sharings on the on the um google groups the notes you can share that if you wish
and or not you can share about the practice tonight how the practice tonight was for you and
what you discovered well there was joyous for me it was really joyous i felt so happy
so um so so these are the invitations
and um how fun what how lovely to have
fellow practitioners to speak with take care of yourselves take care of each other the rooms are open
okay welcome back welcome back everyone the rooms are closed
everyone's back so we have a few minutes for any
reflections anything that you might have realized oh any insights that came up from
discussing in community so again if you haven't shared especially recently
you're welcome to raise your hand or you can type in chat either to everyone or
to me alone so
anthony please thank you nikki um yeah just something
that came up in the small groups is we were talking about how we uh noticed our
progress you know through the practice and uh one thing that i noticed about myself
and it's similar to what the other two were saying is that uh it's hard to pinpoint you know the
actual we just see the growth and i kind of thought came into my mind it's kind of
like uh you know getting doing a goal for weight loss or
maybe a musical instrument you know you don't see the actual the growth you know it's because it's such a long process
but uh you you do feel it you know you do feel it yeah yeah exactly it's it's
like any other practice you know practicing musical instrument it's like yes over time it doesn't
happen overnight but over time definitely progress progress happens and
in some ways you don't evaluate your practice like the stock market like one day okay you
might you know might not be feeling well or grumpy it's like oh i'm a failure i can't practice there are
always you know yeah months years of menta no no no look at it over the long term
over the long term so yes that's very wise exactly
um thank you anthony thank you for that reflection
[Laughter] one reflection comes in and we need a before and after picture
after pictures yes before and after pictures i love that that's exactly right
before meta after method i love it so dear ones it is
7 p.m pacific time we've come to the end of our time together and i thank you all for showing up for
practicing for cultivating your heart for your own sake in the sake of all beings whose lives
you touch either directly or indirectly may all beings including ourselves be
happy may all beings including ourselves be free
thank you