greetings global sangha greetings from virtua imc i'm in
mountain view california on seated oloniland and i am delighted to be here supporting
um sangha today with the last uh practice the sixth practice
of the body section in the sati bhattanasutra
um while gail travels to southern california to
visit his dad today so
so [Music] the sixth practice of the body
of the body in the satipatana sutta in many ways the previous practices
build up to this one really prepare us for this one and this is how all the practices in the
sati pratana sutta both the four main categories they build
from the more they build for the their foundations for one another as
well as in each subsection in each of the four subsections the body they build up um
for each other so this last one which really has to do
with appreciating our body appreciating our body as nature that this body is nature the
body that we take it to be me and mine is really a piece of nature
and is subjected to all the laws of nature
the previous couple of practices that we've done actually all of them but especially the
one yesterday that gil led with the elements with the
four elements the elemental nature
yes this body is the elements is is elements
inside nature inside nature outside as well as the one the day before with
the 32 parts of the body no as if this body was a bag of beans
as a so if we take those two practices and put them um on
wheels basically put them on steroids they put them on a time lapse put them on a time lapse oh what
happens with nature what happens with nature ah with that time lapse
with with the truth of impermanence then we arrive at this last practice
so so in order to um invite us for our reflection
for our um practice for our meditation today and i'll say a lot more about the
teaching of the suta specifically at the end in the dharma but just to
motivate our practice what i like to do
is to um flash a few images of nature
of of gardens and and outside there's as they say
picture is worth a million a thousand i don't know however many uh words so
um and then we'll start our guided meditation so this will just be a few seconds
to motivate that so so here we go
okay let's see here on zoom let's see driving
zoom sharing screen here we go okay so we'll start with the image
ah we'll start where gil left off yesterday so with the suggestion with the
invitation of seeing yourself as a garden
so you can use in the guided meditation also just an image of a garden a
vegetable garden you can use this one or your own favorite one
then perhaps an image of a forest redwoods lying down
watching the sky feeling a part of nature
again you can use this image or an image from your own mind later
and then the forest floor being a part of nature feeling that
nature inside nature outside all the elements earth water
fire and wind and fire being this this capacity of
nature to change and shift and and be transformed through sunlight through
heat and perhaps a log that has become a
nurse lock a nurse that has fought a log that has fallen
and has become a nurse log for other growth in the forest
and other images from the forest floor as we imagine ourselves as part of nature changing shifting growing
and of course decaying it's part of nature to grow
and shift and change we are not so different this body
is nature this body is nature
this body is not so different this body is nature
and so too just like nature this body is nature this body is not so different
it will decay
so so let's begin let's begin our practice
our formal practice by settling in by settling in into the fell
sense of this body in this moment
inspired and using the foundation of the previous
a days teachings
on the body
noticing the breath
moving in and out
noticing the contact points
the earth element the connection with the earth
as if we were earth sitting on earth this body as earth
sitting lying resting on earth
i like to invite you to imagine you're sitting or lying down
in a lush garden feeling this body
surrounded by nature
by fruits vegetables all parts of nature
this body alive and breathing is to
nature
perhaps as if you were lying down [Music] looking at the sky
at the trees around you vegetation around you
earth element to earth on earth feeling solidity contact points of this
body in this moment an expansion watching the sky
the clouds
the trees around part of the forest part of the forest
floor
relaxing softening inviting the body
to know to trust that it is part of nature
it's not separate it is not separate
to feel the peace
of nature peace to feel the peace of wild things
as in the poem by wendell berry
this body alive breathing is a part of nature
not so different from an apple
that falls from a tree
the forest floor and decays
not so different because body is nature this is the truth of how things are
the intimacy of being nature
seeing this body just as the apple
decaying the composting
going back into nature
this natural process
the mind can become quite calm and absorbed but the freedom
with the ease that this contemplation brings see for yourself
this body is nature
this body too is of the same nature
and it will be like that
like an apple
decaying the composing
it's not exempt from that fate this body is nature this body's nature
this body's nature
this body is nature
it's not separate from nature nature inside nature outside
nature inside nature outside
it is subject to laws of nature
this body will go back into nature someday
and for the last moments of this practice
if there has been any self-criticism or judgment coming up
about about your practice i couldn't do this my mind was
distracted whatever has come up let's compost it
let's offer it back into nature
no need to hang on offer it back to nature
and knowing that the natural being natural this body
being nature is true for us for this being
and this seat as well as all beings all beings
everywhere all beings everywhere are part of nature
they're not separate from nature all human beings all animals
we're all nature
offering our hearts while we are alive while this body is alive
blessed with the miracle of aliveness
offering our love our care our goodness
to ourselves and to all of nature
this incredible mysterious thing called life
it's too brief not to love
it's too brief
may all beings everywhere including us
know their true nature
and be free
thank you all for your practice
for the generosity of your practice practices generosity for ourselves and
others
so the topic the topic of the sixth body
contemplation in the sati patana sato
so it is called the nine journal ground contemplations
and as i mentioned at the beginning the previous practices especially the 32
body parts considering body as a bag of beans and the elements which you did yesterday
elements of earth water fire and air his body is nature nature inside nature
outside so in the practice that we did
we envisioned we brought to our attention to our contemplation to our
mind to our imagination that this body is not so separate from other
bodies other i actually did apple today just to be
more gentle with with entering into this practice
uh with an image that i also showed at the beginning and a uh an apple decaying on
the forest floor we are not different we are this body is not different this body is
nature this body is ours and yet it's not ours
we weren't given a choice menu before we were born were you i want this
feature i want to be this tall we didn't really choose this body this body is
nature this is a deep and beautiful contemplation
that helps us that supports us not to take this body so
personally so every every wrinkle every this every that
this body is nature and it will go back into nature it can't be any other
way we know this of course we know this and yet we we try to
but well the society especially the western society keeps it as a hidden secret almost
and our going back into nature is so sterilized is is
hidden is taken away from view um and this practice really tries to
bring it into our consciousness that yes this body is nature
it will go back into ground it will just it will decompose all the sinews the
flesh the bones the all the elements inside will go back to nature it's it's
natural the these this practice
is laid out step by step by step um actually when in quite a lot of
detail and when i teach longer day longs or retreats
i think it would be more appropriate but for today as it's brief you know not going through the
nine stages because it takes some preparation but i will read them from the suta
so that you know what is in the sutta
and and then i'll talk a little more about what some of the effects of this practice could
be perhaps but of course you explore for yourself to see what what it does for you
so here is here is the section of the nine charnel ground meditations
contemplations from the satipatana sutta
again practitioners as though one were to see a corpse
thrown aside in eternal ground and just to say the charnel ground in
the times of the buddha was an over um
over the ground place where bodies were left to decompose
and decay so not underground but overground and there was a
[Music] practice a very active practice of the monks going to journal ground to do
this practice specifically to actually witness bodies
left to decompose in different stages different stages and that's what the
nine stages are that this body is is yes it's alive and it's nature it
will go through these nine stages so so please humor me as i will read
these stages for you so as though one were to see a corpse
thrown aside in eternal ground one two or three days dead loaded livid
with oozing matter which is what happens with every dead material including this body
so that's one stage one second stage being devoured by crows hawks vultures
dogs jackals and various kinds of worms again it's part of nature nature is very efficient very efficient
i showed a an image of a nurse log a log in the forest that has fallen
becomes food for other for other beings for other forms of life uh
in nurse long so we become a nurse log in in this way food for earthworms
next stage a skeleton with flesh and blood held together with senus
a fleshless skeleton smeared with blood held together with sinews again clearly they observed very a lot of
detail what happens skeleton without flesh and blood held
together with sinews next stage disconnected bones scattered scattered in
all directions next stage bones bleached white the color of shells next stage
bones heaped up more than a year old next stage bones rotten and crumbling to
dust so all the nine stages is the invitation in this practice in detail one compares
this same body with it thus this body too is of the same nature
it will be like that it is not exempt from that fate
so this practice this contemplation practice is one to
bring to mind either being able to be in the journal ground or imagining in
one's imagination to imagine yes this body as if lying in the forest floor is not so different
from the apple decaying or anything else decaying this body is nature this body is nature
and one impact one impact that this practice can have
is again actually multiple impacts i'll speak about one first is to to loosen
to loosen our attachment to to this body this art or rather i should
say our over preoccupation we're preoccupied but over occupied this body is nature
and it doesn't mean that we don't treat it then with respect where we don't take care of it
no not at all we take care of it as this amazing incredible piece of nature
that somehow is us or has been entrusted to us to take care of without
taking it so personally oh my skin my hair my my as if it's our it's as
or my stomach is gurgling or my the as if we have per you know it's our
personal responsibility to make it all uh act exactly it acts according to the
laws of nature the hair might be frizzy according to the laws of nature it's it's humid or
or we get we get sick according to laws of nature so so it really brings a different
healthier more free again not a careless but more free
a different ways of relating to this body not taking it personally and yet
loving it caring for it as this amazing incredible piece of nature
another impact it can have is to again bring awe for this piece of
nature that's alive it will be dead when a liveliness when this this aliveness
when we take our last breath and aliveness is no longer part of this
body it will die it will decay very quickly in fact
within minutes there is research that internally um gases
and and compounds and chemicals in the body start to to decay i read was it 20 minutes
40 minutes i forget now after we take our last breath so so that this piece of nature is alive
all these cells are alive and functioning and we're thinking and going about our lives
and have agency wow this piece of nature is alive it's it's just amazing
it fills us with a sense of awe that we want to drop to our knees
and kiss the ground in awe that this body is alive in
this brief moment and the mind can let go of so many
preoccupations that are not healthy or not are extra are not needed
so may we all find freedom find
freedom in embracing our impermanence not hiding it but
embracing the impermanence of this body and may be a cause for
freedom and ease for all of us oh one last thing
i invite you in the next few days to bring attention to bring awareness
to um maybe if you do composting you know if
there is piece of fruit or food that's that's ah that's decaying oh nature nature this
body is not so separate so bring it into your consciousness instead of pushing it away and letting
it be sterile in a way not seen bring the fact that this is nature
bring it into your consciousness this is nature
so and one thing that i want to invite you for those who may want to actually take this
uh practice if they feel if you feel ready this morning to take this practice to the next
level what i'll do is that i'll formally close this morning and then
i will share and the link for um
for the zoom link that i'm on right now and there are few more images of this
practice that i can offer that for those who want to
to see them um you're welcome to enter the zoom blink and see
that there's a few more slides to the presentation uh that again if you if you like to see
them you can get on the zoom link otherwise continuing to practice um
[Music] yeah in a natural way so thank you all
for your practice deep bows deep vows for your generosity
for your practice may you be well may you be free
you