so here you are
you're all each of you is there and you're here here spot your spot for
being here and i think we should never
overlook the hereness of this moment the hereness of where we
are and where we're going to meditate to be here
not as a coincidence not as something to overlook not as something that is insignificant
but rather here is the most important place for this
moment for this meditation and so to assume a posture
for being here
to be rooted to this place and to this time
and to feel the connection of your body to this location
the way your the weight of your body is received by whatever
body that's that in a sense stops the pull of
gravity that keeps you in this location
and to adjust the body a bit especially it's nice to adjust it so the
breathing can be a freer more relaxed more open without
getting tense and without straining but maybe it's something you can do with
a spine that frees up the front of the torso so
the breathing can be more easeful maybe sitting up a little
straighter in the spine
and then to
see if you can take some deeper breaths that are enjoyable for you to take
so maybe for you it's to do just a little bit deeper than
what you're already doing or maybe doing it slowly
maybe the feeling of depth or fullness of breathing is done more in the belly or more in the
top of the chest or middle of the chest
or maybe the sense of enjoyable fuller deeper breathing
is a more subtle expansion of the back rib gauge or maybe there's something
pleasant about in a deep full breath the gentle pressure downward
as you breathe in the diaphragm pushes down and
pushes down the intestines and innards there and perhaps
that pushing down a gentle pushing down is a grounding here to this spot
and as you exhale is there any place in your body that would be
kind of pleasant or enjoyable to relax or soften
instead of maybe pleasant or enjoyable any place in your body as you exhale
it would be nice to relax
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and take a few breaths to familiarize yourself with your breathing
noticing the places in your body that move the most as you breathe
and where there's movement in the breathing but the movement is just light
and then once again to take a few deeper breaths gently
quietly not too much
if if it happens to be that you feel some resistance or holding
back at the top of the in-breath
see if you can relax around that place of holding resistance not ambitiously
but more as a expression of kindness to yourself and
a willingness to relax there
and at the end of the exhale is there also some holding back
and if so can you relax and release the end of the exhale
maybe the exhale is a little bit longer
and then again letting the breathing return to normal
and feel your breathing now perhaps by letting the thinking mind
become quieter it allows you to have more attention
when feeling the body breathing
and then ever so gently maybe just very slightly
within the range of what could be considered normal breathing see if there's some simple
ways to adjust your breathing to make it more pleasant
a little bit slower a little bit faster
a little fuller
a little bit more shallow and a smaller breath
maybe you find it a little bit more pleasant to breathe more fully into the belly
or more fully into the chest
or to really focus on the sensations of air going in and out through the
nostrils and notice
if if there is any feelings of pleasure or pleasantness in the breathing
that it's pleasant to breathe maybe not so much your effort to breathe
but the sensations are in the body of breathing
is there anything about them that feels pleasant enjoyable or comforting
it can be very slight
any small ways you can adjust around your breathing
maybe by being aware of a smaller little spot in your body where it's most pleasant
or maybe it's a broad awareness of the body breathing over a larger spot or the whole
torso and then as you exhale
relax your body more and in order to settle into your breathing
settling in to be with your breathing
for these minutes we're together
and if your mind wanders off in thought when you begin again with your breathing
spend a few breaths re-establishing
an enjoyable breath the pleasant breathing
even if it's just one little piece of the cycle of breathing
or maybe just reestablish a breathing which is a
little bit feels a little bit better than what you were doing
every time the mind wanders off spend a little bit of time
reconnecting to whatever is good about breathing in and breathing out
let the thinking mind become quieter so you can be in your body more
feeling the embodied experience of
breathing
can you relax your belly as you breathe
maybe it's more present pleasant to breathe to breathe a little bit further behind
to feel the area just little bits in the back of where you feel breathing
not so much exactly in the center of your breathing area
but kind of like the little bit in the back of it
just behind it or in the backside of it so that maybe there's a little bit less sense of
control or there's a lighter [Music]
more delicate feeling of breathing
and while you're focusing on breathing so your central vision central awareness
is on breathing peripherally see if you can allow the
to have the body be allowing receptive
the body is open willing to experience
the influence of breathing
it's kind of like breathing
is a gentle wind
that spreads its influence across the
body or a light that's been turned on that
glows outwards
letting the body be receptive allowing for whatever
influence the focus on breathing might have
not looking for something particular just available
with breathing at the center
um quietly receiving the bodies breathing
and perhaps breathing within within whatever larger
context of pleasure or joy or contentment there might be
whatever larger feeling of wholeness
calmness so breathing is at the center of a wider field
of goodness wholeness settledness
pleasure joy happiness
the thinking mind becomes quieter so attention can better
feel and sense the fullness of the
the way breathing spreads its influence out into the
goodness around it
the wholeness around it
and there might be ways that you do not feel calm or do not feel pleasure
that you're uncomfortable it's okay but there might also be in
addition to that around it underneath it in the middle of
it somewhere the opposite feelings
a wholeness a calmness that holds it all
lorry can accept it all
an ability to you stay gently aware of the breathing the rhythm of breathing so you're not
preoccupied by the discomfort it can be there but let it be just a
piece of the picture in the background you just breathing
and then sitting here quietly at the end of this meditation
is there anything that feels
more settled for you calmer for you having done this
meditation in some way or other do you feel
better than you were when you started the meditation
and if you do
if you if you would like you could offer
the goodness of your meditation how you're calmer more settled
maybe even a little happier peaceful offer that
for the welfare and happiness of others or dedicate it
let it be dedicated in some way or other that you use that
that it's the basis for benefiting the world out into the
world may it be a force may it be a avenue
support for bringing greater comfort and peace calm joy
love into the world
may we do that a little bit actively not just as a wish
but as an inspiration for being
concerned for the welfare of others
may it be [Music]
that this meditation is dedicated to the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings
be free may all beings be peaceful
and may our love and our care support that possibility
[Music]
you