so good evening
tonight's topic is joy
and you might first consider what you
feel
when you hear that word for some people
joy is almost the aim of the path
there's a sense of maybe seeking bliss
or something like that
for other people there might even be a
slight
negative connotation joy really
i don't know it feels a little bit
fluffy maybe denial
there's so much so many problems in the
world surely joy is a little bit
surface level lightweight something like
that
so whatever whatever your response is
to that idea i encourage you to
consider for tonight the possibility
that joy has some significant depth to
it
it's it's not lightweight actually and
neither is it solely
concerned with bliss and ease
it actually it's it has some substance
it's not an escape
from meeting suffering and
i'm gonna talk a bit about how it plays
an essential role
on the path to liberation we need joy
actually
it's important on our path
so joy is a very beautiful quality of
heart
it points toward in an essential way it
points toward abundance
and so we're going to talk about
several different kinds of joy tonight
i'm going to offer kind of an abundance
or a bouquet
of different experiences of joy that
come
on the path so just as an overview
there's appreciative joy or empathetic
joy that we can feel
for the success of others
there's meditative joy that comes
when the mind becomes stiller and more
free of the hindrances
and there can be joy in the past
in the practice in the dharma itself
there's even other kinds of joy than
that perhaps but
that's what we'll try to cover tonight
as a as i said kind of a bouquet
of different types
so let's start with this experience of
joy at the success or happiness
of others this is a kind of joy that's
also called mudita it's one of the four
brahmaviharas or heart qualities that we
cultivate on the path
the others you might be more familiar
with meta
loving kindness karuna compassion
and upekka equanimity those three
along with mudita appreciative joy
are the four brahmaviharas or divine
abodes
so these are relational qualities
and they acknowledge that we live in a
world
that does include happiness
we see people
getting what they like we see them
succeeding
we see them achieving goals and gaining
praise and one
quality of having a mature heart
is the ability to celebrate the joy of
others
in a simple happy natural way
the dalai lama said if i am happy
when good things happen to other people
billions more chances to be happy
so really this is a wonderful thing all
the time in the world there's
actually a lot of good things going on
there are acts of generosity
and kindness being done at every moment
somewhere in the world
and we can tap into that now if this is
sounding a little bit difficult
often one way that we can touch into
appreciative joy immediately is through
animals
like a dog dogs are excited about so
many things
and you can you can catch the excitement
of the dog
or watching a a kitten playing with a
leaf
in the wind that it's gotten attracted
to
something you know we don't want to
project too many things onto
animals but i think it's pretty easy to
tell when there's a sense of
of joy or excitement in an animal and we
can catch that
[Music]
we can catch that feeling i read a study
by the way that
cute cat videos have been shown to
reduce stress
so there you go um
one good thing as we're connecting with
joy in this
simple way is to start to feel
what joy feels like in our body you know
what is it like to have that
sense of uplift and just simple uplift
at someone else's joy
start to feel where that is in the body
how the energy moves
so that we can be familiar with it
and so we can experience it more often
it has a feeling in the mind too
a lightness of openness of warmth in a
certain way
so we can get familiar with that and
then we can
cultivate it for people also of course
and you know one way that we do this is
to say phrases
the common phrase for mutita
is uh may your happiness and good
fortune
continue your happiness and good fortune
continue so we wish well for the success
and happiness of others
when we do that we can also feel the joy
in our body
and maybe imagine an image of the person
being happy or joyful
and allow that feeling to mature
in us to cook in us if you will
another form of joy practice is to
evoke somehow that feeling of mudita
through an image or a phrase
and then um kind of drop the object that
we were thinking of and actually just
radiate that feeling from our heart
concentrate it into the heart center and
just
feel it like a light shining from inside
it's a wonderful way to cultivate medita
so it's natural of course that as we try
to cultivate
appreciative or empathetic joy we will
run into what gets in the way of that
and that's this is normal it doesn't
mean the practice isn't working
and you can imagine that the what's
called the far enemy or the thing that
really opposes our ability to feel
mutita
is envy so somebody else
gets some success or gains something and
we think
well why did they get that they didn't
deserve that
or we think i should have gotten that
how come i didn't get that instead or
also
and so there's a you know a turning
toward the self or somehow some
envy and so um
it's helpful just to notice that this
blocks our appreciative joy
one thing that fuels envy and that
the reason that we might have such
feelings
is there can be an idea that in order to
be happy
we have to get something and so
seeing somebody else get something we
would feel like
i didn't get something and so but if we
can learn to
feel this joy for others receiving
we feel a great amount of relief we can
realize
oh actually i can be happy
without getting something there is a
kind of happiness that doesn't come
from that and so this is actually quite
a wonderful discovery
for us like the dalai lama says it
greatly increases our chances of
happiness in the world
now we don't of course have to feel joy
at somebody else's joy
it may be that they're feeling joy about
something that's a little bit
unwholesome or that we
suspect is not going to be good for them
in the long run so it's not like you
have to have to experience joy if
someone else is feeling joyful
you know maybe if we see that it's not
leading in a good direction compassion
would be a better response so
just so you're aware of that there is
also what's called a near
enemy of mutita of appreciative joy
and that is um called
giddiness it's not a word we use very
often but the
you can get the sense of it it's like a
sort of over-the-top
uh excitement about something and
getting caught up in somebody else's uh
pleasure and joy such that we lose our
own balance
you know we fall into it and we're no
longer
aware present centered in in ourselves
um so our own heart
so you can feel you can feel when that's
happening
we've probably all experienced that
tumbling
feeling of of giddiness and so that's
just be aware that's not really
that's not really mudita um
so overall mudita is of course a great
way to reduce our self-focus
like all the brahmaviharas are all of
the heart qualities are
so we um undermine you know this belief
that we have sometimes subtly that
we need to be receiving and getting and
you know being praised and bolstered all
the time in order to feel happy
we don't actually there are many other
forms of of happiness available and it's
an expansive feeling of heart to be able
to tap into mudita
so much recommended as a cultivation
now in addition um there's a whole other
flavor of joy that comes from
meditation and this is something that
the mind starts to feel when it has less
of the
hindrances and less caught up in sense
pleasures
and sort of our usual pursuits
so this comes again through sitting
practice it's called
pt p-i-t-i and i'll get to
to it in a moment often when people
start sitting there's not a lot of joy
in the sitting and that can be because
we're busy dealing with body pain or
we've somehow taken on sitting as an
obligation or a chore and we're just
trying to
be with the breath or bring the mind
back all the time
it's a sort of work where's the joy
where's the joy in that
but there is an accessible way into
meditative joy
we practiced it during the meditation
which is that
even being mindful has a slight amount
of pleasure to it
you know it's not our usual kind of
sense pleasure like
eating chocolate or something but
being present as opposed to being lost
or caught up in something
is actually slightly pleasant it's a
very subtle kind of joy
being there being present and we can tap
into that
as i said in the meditation even when
what we're mindful of
is something unpleasant or a little
painful or
something the fact that we're present
for it we can start to appreciate
that that's better than being lost and
so that's an easy accessible way to
to start and so every time you get lost
which we do all the time in meditation
when the mind comes back we wake up oh
right
meditation mindful we notice at that
moment ah it feels better
there's a clarity it isn't there when we
were
lost and that clarity is slightly
pleasant then we tune into that
that the mind wants to be present a
little bit more often
so that's our first little taste of
meditative joy actually
just being present and then
it's also um just fine as we did in the
sitting to
as we start to feel some degree of ease
or
peace or softening in the body
um slowing down of the mind anything
that's
that's some direction toward well-being
it's totally fine to
notice that and appreciate it we don't
need to grab
onto it and try to make it bigger and
try to hold on to it
that will only cause more difficulty but
you can appreciate
those good feelings that start to come
in meditation and just let them be
nourished
by our attention to them let them
be naturally present that's also a nice
way to
slowly cultivate meditative joy
and then we will eventually at some
point
start to feel some genuine sense of
well-being
emerging from meditation you know we
know that it's coming because we're
sitting there
with some seclusion
of the body some seclusion of the mind
we start to feel an internal sense of
well-being
and it's often felt most strongly in the
body we may even feel
some kinds of pt meditative joy
feel almost like tingling or energy in
the body
sometimes the hair stands on end it's
kind of um
delightful these little feelings that we
have and then it can also settle a
little bit more and be more pervasive
but this is um this is a wonderful
development when it starts to come in
meditation and maybe you'll have it once
and then
not for a while it's not like it comes
and then stays forever
but just start to notice when this these
feelings come
um one way that we can know that what
we're having is meditative joy is that
full balanced pt leads to
tranquility now this is not our usual
mode with
joy right it's not your usual kind of
excitement which tends to agitate the
mind
meditative joy is pleasant in and of
itself
and it leads to tranquility it's almost
like there's a little
core of tranquility with this joy
wrapped around it and we touch the joy
first and as we settle into it and
deepen
into it we then touch the tranquility
that's at its heart
so that's um you might reflect for a
moment do you
know anything of this kind of joy even a
little bit a sense of settledness and
well-being that can come
through the meditation so mostly
meditative joy
comes as the mind softens and becomes
more continuously mindful
we don't have to try to cultivate it in
fact that's
sometimes counterproductive it emerges
from a mind that is soft and
more or less continually mindful so
here's a nice simile from the sutas that
i wanted to read
about this
just like a lake with spring water
welling up from within having no inflow
from the east west north or south and
with the skies
not supplying rain so that the cool
fountain of water
welling up from the lake would permeate
and
pervade suffuse and fill it with cool
waters
there being no part of the lake
unpervaded by the cool waters
even so the meditator permeates
this very body with the rapture and
pleasure
born of concentration or of composure
so there's a sense like okay lost in all
the words
a sense of a lake with a a well
within it that is bringing something up
it's coming from
meditation itself so what is the value
of this
joy there are a number of benefits of
course but the the main one is
this deep sense of well-being that
starts to train the mind
that something besides sense pleasures
and thinking
and our usual ways of trying to get
pleasure
there's something deeper than that
that's actually more satisfying
this is from the damopada tasting the
flavor
of solitude and peace one becomes
free of distress and evil drinking the
flavor
of dharma joy
so it starts out as talking about a
concentration the settling of mind that
leads to this joy
the solitude and peace who gives the
clue to that
but then this last line drinking the
flavor of dharma joy
that's going to lead us into the next
section i want to
talk now turn now to the kind of joy
that can come from the practice itself
of joy in the practice and the path in
the dharma
and there isn't just one word for this
like mudita or
pt it comes from a whole bunch of
different places so now we really get to
expand our
bouquet of different kinds of joy
i'll go through some ways that the
practice itself
generates joy so it's great i love this
third kind
of joy that we're talking about so one
one way
that it can come is through ethical
conduct
um this isn't anything complicated or
heavy
or rigid it's that when we've generally
behaved well
you know we've said and done things that
were
wholesome enough uh we've get to the end
of the day and we feel good
about how that went as sort of a sense
of joy it's actually called the bliss of
blamelessness
we don't need to absolutize that or make
it you know
blamelessness sounds a little bit too
idealistic to me
but essentially we can get to the end of
the day and feel like it went okay
that's actually very precious feeling
it nourishes us to realize that we've
generally said and done and even thought
things that were
good throughout the day
it also comes from having confidence or
faith if you will in the past so when we
have a moment where we realize that
we're confident that what we're doing is
the right thing you know
i have times when i realize i'm just
grateful that i have a path you know i'm
grateful that i have some way of
managing the things that come up during
the day and my mind and my body
that's right i have a path and when i
reflect on that
i feel a certain kind of joy just
emerges naturally kind of a delight
oh yeah good there's there's support
there's a way to deal with
life interestingly
joy can also come from renunciation
now renunciation is not usually our
favorite word
but it really just means letting go and
in this case
it might it could mean uh we don't have
so much conventional focus on
stuff and wealth and prestige and
identity
it's like we're not so wrapped up in
those usual kinds of pursuits
that the advertisements and marketers
tell us will make us happy
when we realize not really that's not
really the path to happiness
we can start to feel a subtle kind of
joy just in
the simplicity of living a more balanced
way the mind gets clearer so
the buddha describes a certain kind of
joy that arises from
if you will the wisdom of renunciation
i'll read a little bit about that
so seeing things as they are
so he says when by knowing the
impermanence
change fading away and cessation
of safe forms could be any of the five
sense objects but
material things and one sees
as it actually is with proper wisdom
that
forms are all impermanent and subject to
change
joy arises such joy as this
is called the joy based on renunciation
that's interesting so it's a little
subtle
but it means that you know if i if i'm
using this cup
and you know it's a nice cup
holds water but i know at the same time
that i'm looking at it that it's subject
to breakage
it will not it's not a permanent source
of happiness for me
uh i like it right now but this
wouldn't be wise to place all of my
happiness in this cup
there's certain subtle joy that comes
from knowing that
you know there's some wisdom there and
maybe a cup is somewhat trivial example
but
we can think about how the path and the
practice allow us to
realize not take the bait of things in
the world
quite so easily of course we still do
sometimes but
there can be a certain joy in having
that strength knowing
okay i know that all things change
they're going to pass
i shouldn't rely on this completely
so if you do feel that if you have some
sense of that in some areas of your life
take joy in that not everyone knows that
it's a kind of wisdom and kind of joy
so
we should get also to a question that
people sometimes
ask at this point which is why
or how can we be joyful in a world with
pain you know in the face of pain why be
joyful
so first off let me ask
why not seriously why not
so i do encounter people who think it's
some kind of a betrayal
to be happy or joyful or peaceful or
light
when there is so much suffering in the
world
or in a difficult situation you know why
why wouldn't you just fall into that and
get agitated and worried like everybody
else to show that you care
but i would again ask a little question
betrayal
of what trail of what so the buddhist
teachings
point us toward a happiness that is
unconditioned what does that mean that's
a word we don't use very often either
but it means a kind of happiness that is
not subject to
the conditions of the world so not
dependent on things being a certain way
you can be happy if they're this way or
that way or this other way
and it doesn't mean that at every moment
we're skipping down the aisles and
laughing that wouldn't be appropriate in
every situation
but there's a way in which we have a
certain happiness of heart
that can be present with anything
in various ways uh appropriate to that
situation
so we can look for that in our heart we
can look for ways that
we can find joy at the very least we
have the joy of presence
if we're present for suffering yeah we
may feel compassion
for the suffering concern
wishing to help and in that in that deep
presence or that wisdom of being there
for something
there is actually a little bit of joy
there's still that
that joy of presence subtle but it's
there
so jack cornfield says it this way in
joy we are not afraid of pleasure we do
not mistakenly believe
it is disloyal to the suffering of the
world
to honor the happiness we have been
given
so if we have some happiness in our life
we're not being disloyal
to appreciate and enjoy that
or this from archbishop
desmond tutu wonderful minister
from south africa it helps
no one if you sacrifice your joy
because others are suffering we
people who care must be filled with joy
so that others recognize that caring
helping and being generous are not a
burden
they are a joy how about that
we people who care we people who care
must be filled with joy so that others
recognize
caring is a joy it's so valuable
to see radiant joyful
helpers of the world and
so inspiring and necessary you know
uplifting
offer some hope some vision
even in the face of suffering
my friend spent some time in south
africa
and she was fortunate enough to be
working at an art museum
where archbishop tutu came
for some event that was being held there
and
somehow she managed to be standing just
about six feet away from him
and she said he lit up the room
he was made of pure joy so
there's just something so valuable
in this quality and so many ways that we
can
touch into it in our practice
there's the medita the appreciative joy
for others
there's the meditative joy that can come
from settling the mind there's the joy
and the path
practice the dharma itself that
can fuel us through times in our
practice that are difficult
or through meeting the world and its
difficulties
and in the end um
joy is one of the factors of awakening
there are seven factors of awakening
one of them is right in the middle
is joy and it
is a necessary component for awakening
so that we have a mind with some degree
of lightness
some happiness that is coming from the
heart
from the path itself and when the mind
is in a state like that
as well as possessing a number of other
wholesome factors
that's when it can awaken so i encourage
you to
touch into this very beautiful quality
that's accessible in a number of ways
through seeing other people
through the presence of mindfulness
through reflection through the settling
of the mind
and through wisdom through ethics almost
everything can be a door to joy
if we are looking for it and are open to
that
so to whatever degree
you're able to touch into that whether
it's just a little bit or whether you
feel the
opening of the heart happens to be
tonight
i encourage you to really appreciate
that and let it fill your being
so that we can help others with that so
may your practice and your path and your
heart
joyful
well