hello dear sangha hello and welcome to happy hour hi
good to be with you and if you can hear me okay if the audio's alright give me a thumbs up
yes yes fantastic terrific so so let's get informally started with
our hellos and welcoming each other and ourselves to this space
i'm nikki i'm in mountain view california unseated oloneyland welcome who's here
hello patricia who says hello to everyone lovely to be here joining us
from cork ireland hi neil from nashua new hampshire who else wants to say hi
different time zones we have hi bill from dallas texas
and you can also oh wait i'm going to change the settings so you can also unmute yourselves and say your hellos
verbally if you like put your voice in the room hi eileen from honolulu good afternoon
to you hi phillip from walnut creek hi we're mari christine from sydney in lockdown
oh good afternoon to you hi
and claire hi claire from new york city hi stan from corvallis oregon oh sweet great
welcome welcome uh hi mark from swim the swim contingent
hilary in seattle and sharon i see you're unmuted you want to say hi
from charleston south carolina hi welcome great
hi carly from norfolk virginia virginia norfolk i can say that in virginia um
lovely special a special welcome to those for whom this is the first time
this is your first happy hour so special welcome to the first timers
i see some new new names from pakistan welcome
[Music] and hi uh richard from midwest joining us
on youtube folks and hi violet from san francisco nice to have you oh sweet
my heart is warmed always with all these hellos and welcomes from different places in the world
different venues time zones zoom youtube
hello everyone who will be listening to us in the future on audio dharma or recordings
hi what what a nice way to to come together and connect
in this moment in time and hi amber from ohio so let's get started formally
and at this time thank you neil neil as always comes through
posting information about happy hour google groups which is a forum we have
um for the sangha where information is shared um
quotes and resources and and also members can connect offline
so at this time i change the chat settings so that chats will only come to
me on zoom the host if there's anything urgent like my sound drops off or
something otherwise we'll keep that quiet also and i also turn on recording now which
will zoom will ask you for confirmation this is for the sake of audio dharma here we
go okay
so hello and welcome everyone wonderful to be with you and see you
so for today's practice i'd like to invite us to
engage with the practice of compassion today compassion for the world compassion for
others especially what with what has been happening on the world stage
um the past few days ah with the catastrophes internationally
just to name a few of course there's afghanistan um
and there is haiti also with not just the
earthquake but also the weather now there the storm so
just a heavy heart so much suffering so much suffering around the world
and with the practice of compassion the practice of compassion especially in the
way that i like to invite us to engage with tonight
compassion supports us to meet suffering to be with suffering whether it's ours
or others to meet it not to
drown in it not to drown in the heartache that
is not compassion that's [Music] basically overwhelm that's grief
empathic distress is another word for it whereas compassion is where we meet
suffering ours or others with care with with
kindness with sense of stability with an equanimity that's
loving that's caring so we can hold presence we cannot be present
can hold presence for what might be painful difficult something that we cannot change and yet
we don't turn our face away that oh yes somebody else's problem
but we stay we hold presence we hold we are present
with with the suffering whether it's ours or others without pushing it under
the proverbial carpet and it brings a sense of
strength strength in the heart strength in the heart
and compassion is different from empathy
empathy is only read the resonance resonating
with suffering so in some in one way we can think of it if we think of the
paradigm the say the neuroscience paradigm it's just the mirror neurons resonating and it
turns out that so that is really the aspect of when you feel empathic oh yes somebody hurts and
you feel pain with them and their studies their research studies that actually when you see someone suffering
oh the same areas in your brain that that experience physical pain light up
so empathy alone is not compassion
what is compassion is empathy plus meta plus loving kindness plus care plus this
feeling of warmth that i care i am present for you with you breathing with you
um holding so it's both it's not just empathy alone and it'll become more
clear in the guided meditation as i will invite you and at any point if you find
yourself in empathic distress know that empathy alone just feeling the
pain without meta to balance it can fall into empathic distress so my invitation will
be at that point to stop and bring compassion bring care to yourself
because in that moment you're the one who's suffering so again
if at any point you find your empathic distress and overwhelm in grief
stop compassion for others turn compassion compassionate gaze to
yourself so that you have enough stability
and at that point you can turn back out or maybe just stay with yourself so so
know what is best for you what is best for you so the particular practice
actually you know i won't say anymore i'll just lead you into whatever you need to know and whether this is your
first time or a hundredth time uh in happy hour whatever you need to know will be shared with you
during this guided meditation okay so trust trust yourself trust the practice and
again if at any point it becomes painful and general challenging turn compassion
to yourself just remember that okay all right so with that let's begin
let's begin our practice formally
landing landing in this body
landing in this moment
as always we begin we begin by just arriving
letting go of any thoughts stories expectations
and just landing landing in this body in this moment in time
inviting awareness to connect
with the sensations of your feet
connected to the earth of your sit bones
your bottom connected to the earth
with each breath
ah landing landing connecting more deeply
feeling your feet
your lower legs you're sitting on the cushion your bottom
the contact points all the contact points feeling them
more and more to feel solidly connected embodied
well rooted to the earth
feeling your hands
feeling your lower abdomen
expanding and contracting with each breath
on its own
each breath breathed each breath breathed on its own
the breath has been breathing itself breathing you for all this time so don't make it effortful
let it flow just as it has been flowing all this time
just simply notice
the movement
of the abdomen the breath received
as if the body becomes more and more
alive more present
more settled more relaxed
through each breath
i'd like to invite you to imagine the breath as if the breath
is being received naturally on its own through the middle of your chest
the peripheral heart center
middle of the chest as if the breath was entered and with
each breath received this capacity of care
of warm-heartedness friendliness kindness
is breathed into enlivened
again not so much that you are doing it but i know
there is friendliness here already
as if the breath is bellowing bellowing
on the embers on the fire making it bigger
it's just happening on its own
as much as it's available right now just witnessing
letting the breath be received gently
might be a little tiny fire and that's okay
few more minutes allowing the breath
to be received from the art center bellowing throughout your whole body
calming settling letting go of whatever is not needed
whatever is not necessary
if thoughts are not necessary right now letting them go thank you
not needed right now please come back later
me
coming back here just here
and now
imagining imagining that your heart center
middle of your chest
is this holy fire
holy fire of love of care of compassion
that is both yours and is not yours it's not personal
it's holy fire of universal compassion [Music]
burning brightly beautifully
in your heart
as if it were a gift a gift from the beyond the gift of grace
ah it's not mine it's just here
it's part of being human breathing breathing with
breathing with holy fire this holy fire of compassion
and imagine that with each out breath
each out breath breathed out of your heart center
each out breath carries
this goodness good will of compassion
shining shining the light
onto the entire world yourself
and all beings who are suffering
and the out breath brings them comfort soothes
brings the message of good will of care from you
and now imagine
that the sorrow the sadness
the suffering naturally as it gets breathed in
into this incinerator this holy fire in your heart
it gets transformed it's not yours this transformation
it's not yours to do it's not yours to keep
suffering as if it's smoke as if it's
a dark cloud
it's breathed in on its own it gets transformed incinerated
transformed in this holy fire of compassion good will
to care
into goodwill into a self soothing and breathed out
breathed out
delivering your care
your compassion
to all who are suffering which may include yourself
and as this transformation continues
as dukkha as suffering is breathed and transformed
in your heart breathed out
bringing comfort and ease
there's a sense of courage heart
and fringe in your heart there's a sense of courage more and more courage
to not turn away at first it could be just a tiny little
bit of courage not to turn away to hold witness
to breathe with all these beings all these humans
who are just like you just like me
just like me they want to be safe
may they be safe
just like me they want to be happy
may they be happy
just like me
they want to be healthy
may they be healthy and strong
and just like me they want
ease in their lives
may they have ease
just as i don't want to suffer may they be free from suffering
me
you
at any point if you feel more empathic distressed
you can turn the compassion care love meta to yourself
you can also lean more into the care to the warmth
to the good will for others instead of leaning into the suffering
lean more into the good will to balance
i care i care for your suffering i care
may you be well may you be free
may there be ease
may there be peace
to breathe with to breathe with the times
when there is nothing else within
our ability or power to do to forget to hold witness and breathe
with
to breathe to breathe with those who are suffering which can include ourselves
breathing with the pain
letting the sorrow be breathing out care compassion
for the last moments of this practice period
connecting with the compassion the care for yourself
and all beings whatever this period of practice was
like whether it was distracted sleepy
whether there was falling into empathic distress sadness
grief it's all okay it's all okay it's all okay you tried you showed up
you did your best to align
your actions the training of your mind with your
intentions and now letting go letting go of the rest
letting go of what you cannot control given all the causes and conditions that
have come before
may all beings be well
may all beings be free from suffering including ourselves
[Music]
thank you all for your practice
so the practice today was
the practice of tongue length compassion as it's practiced in the way of tongue length to
the practice in tibetan buddhism
breathing in sorrow letting it be transformed breathing it out it's a
different way of doing compassion than we tend to usually do and also i try to bring in
and and to say that tonglen can often be a very challenging practice
so however it was for you whether it was challenging it's okay it's okay it's
okay you showed up you tried i also in this practice i brought a
little bit of equanimity practice which is being with holding witness when
when causes and conditions are above and beyond our control to acknowledge that and acknowledge the
being with holding presence and trying to have a bird's-eye view
so so
you are welcome now you're invited to share your reflections if you like
questions comments um and you can type them in chat if they're
typed just to me i will not read your name if they're typed to everyone i will read your name
you can also raise your zoom hand if you like to share your reflections
like to hear from you what was the practice like for you what did you discover
what did you learn it could be a question it could be what
was challenging what was a discovery
and know that when you offer an insight a question
you're offering it for the community for everyone's practice so not just for
yourself
especially if you're new to happy hour i'd like to invite you not to feel
that you're in the hot seat but if you like to share please sharon [Music]
so today especially reflecting on afghanistan
i've also really taken into my heart today um i'm sure you're familiar with
john halifax and she has a brilliant beautiful
teaching of strong back soft front and your holy fire went beautifully with my
reflections today thank you so much thank you sharon and thank you for
bringing in naming afghanistan
again as as it is in the space of course the common humanity just like us we're
human beings we could be born as them and to bring in the beautiful practice of joan halifax this the strong back
soft front was a strong back did i get lovely beautiful and a holy fire in the
heart beautiful thank you chef beautiful pair of reflections
thank you for that yeah strong back soft run yeah
yeah yeah
thank you for that reflection
now i don't know how to put my hand down i will do it for you dear okay thank you
thank you and others please you are welcome
what did you discover
philip says i knew your voice is quite soothing i didn't realize you were guiding using tongue length quite nice
was helpful to my nervous system namaste you are welcome phillip and you're also
welcome if you like not to feel on the spot but if you wanted to raise your hand you could say more but not need it
nothing for anyone else got another moment another
reflection here i appreciate your reminder to turn toward pain instead of
turning away yeah thank you for that reflection that was sent to me
it's important it is important yeah
it's been quite i have to say as a wait another beat for any reflections that
might come from you dear sangha oh here's um
here's another reflection from richard on youtube i had distraction due to physical pain
and difficulty tending towards pain the realization came towards the end of practice your invitation that it was all
welcome blossomed a bod of compassion oh thank you richard for sharing
this beautiful bud of compassion of your practice
to welcome it all turning towards one more reflection the breathing out
compassion was interesting it felt forced at first but it went well
after tuning into into to it somehow beautiful great i
appreciate that reflect the reflection that yes
it um if it feels forced then
then bring in this reflection of this holy fire that the breathing it happens on its own this this holy fire of
compassion in some ways it is yours and in some ways not so letting it just as if you're witnessing as if you're
witnessing something so i'm delighted to hear that that happened one more reflection i discovered
how to have compassion for myself beautiful thank you for that and neil i
see your hand please first of all i really appreciated this
it was great timing how do you remember that you know in particular in afghanistan that you know
despite all the terrors that are happening there are people deserving of your love on both sides of that
yeah absolutely um
i'm so glad you brought this up um
i'll share something with you from my own practice that came up for me tonight because as as i was practicing for the
terror of so many people who are scared so many people who are scared right now
and once i i was also seeing the other side i was seeing the other side
these fighters as children because at some point they were children
and in some ways they are they there's a particular way they see the world
and that is causing so much suffering to others and to themselves
so and i'm reminded of the in buddhism the root the root of all
suffering all all ills in the world are great hatred and
confusion or translated as delusion and in fact delusion is the root of greed and hatred
delusion really isn't anything but also translated as ignorance but it's
not an ignorance of of of not knowing but it's like a not
seeing clearly not seeing your true nature not seeing not knowing how particular ways of being
causes harm to yourself and causes harm to others it's similar to
the um to the prayer of jesus forgive them
father for for the harm they cause i'm paraphrasing as they do not know what
they do they do not know what they do so there's a sense of oh they they don't know what they do they
saw clearly if they saw without dust in their eyes how the way
of being is is causing pain for people for
for women children etc it's so in that way my heart can be open to compassion
to all sides forgive the father as they do not know what they do
so [Music] this is what comes up for me neil and i offer it
as a reflection to you thank you thank you
so so dear ones time has come for
us in this sangha in this community to turn to practice in small groups which
is what we do at this time holding ourselves holding each other especially tenderly tonight
and we will
oops let's restart we will practice we will practice in
small groups of size three or four and holding each other and ourselves
first in 15 seconds of silence aside for 15 seconds of
of silent meta and compassion for ourselves for each other
and then after the 15 seconds of silent compassion for ourselves and each other
we'll share however much or how every little you like to share about your practice
uh and again hold yourselves hold each other with care with tenderness take
care of yourselves it's about supporting each other not about impressing each other at all so
so the rooms are created and and um
again take care of yourselves take care of each other here you go
so
and the rooms are all closed now and everybody's back welcome back
everyone so we have just about a minute if anybody would like to share
a reflection um something that you learned or came up
for you came up for you in the practice and diana please
it's just a question i have a problem with the image of fire holy fire i find it kind of
menacing i've been trying to think of an another word to substitute that and i haven't come up with anything yet
but if you have one for that lovely fire it's a purifying thing
it is a purifying thing another i'll tell you another if you know the fire um one other image you can have is
an orb of light it's just an orb of light so it gets come in it gets
transformed through this orb of light okay all right thank you you are so welcome diana thank you so
much for that question yeah get ready it's all good i'll do it for you okay
so thank you all thank you so much for your practice for showing up for
cultivating your heart your mind for the benefit of yourself and all beings whose lives you touch
may all beings be free from suffering may all beings be well
[Music]
thank you and i will stay a few minutes extra today
on soon so what i will