so good day everyone and welcome to this meditation session
and one of the functions of buddhist meditation
is to place ourselves
squarely fully into the vibrant
and dynamic pulsing [Music]
experience of life of being alive that um
all the sensations that you experience whatever they might be pleasant or
unpleasant they come and they go they're dynamic they vibrate they
are flashing in and out of existence moment by moment
that all the experiences sensations that you have you have because you're alive once
you're dead your body is no longer energized or
animated with the whatever the life force is within us
there are no sensations whatsoever and um and the sensations we experience
are proof of the living livingness in us the dynamic and active
quality of the natural world the energies of the natural world that how they flow through us and manifest in
us and so to sit in the middle of our body and with
anapanasati and uh to be able to be centered unified collected
um liberated from distractions and really here be here to feel and
sense and be intimate with the dynamism
of change dynamism of the the coming and going appearing and
disappearing of phenomena everything to be called experience
in a certain way what it doesn't change are concepts platonic concepts of
things which their ideas of them which stay constant ideas of self ideas of others
ideas of what has happened to us and even some kind of funny way what will happen to us
these ideas give the semblance that things are continuous maybe in some things are in
certain kind of way but to drop into the flow of experience
to the direct direct immediate perception knowing experiencing
of life as it flows in that little window little kind of
where they vast past and vast future of you know coming and going
we have this idea i think in in english sometimes that we're moving into the future and i think
in ancient india they had the idea more the idea that the future was coming towards us
and this river of you know just time just flows and when it and we know the future
only in the experience as it becomes the present and as we know it it already vanishes
there's something about the immediacy it already vanishes here
so assuming a meditation posture a posture to
embody inhabit the lived experience of the moment
and perhaps to close your eyes in order to
be inside to sense and feel inside your life
your body sometimes with the eyes open we're looking at things externally and pulled into the external
world the eyes close the idea is to
come into this intimate world of our physical embodied experience
in the immediacy of here
and to gently maybe lovingly kindly slowly take some deeper breaths
maybe three quarters full
taking deeper breaths so slow and careful enough that you almost like you're savoring and enjoying
this the feelings in your body of the chest expanding the belly expanding
and then a longer exhale than usual not so much maybe that you're forcing
the air out but you let go you release
the muscles around your diaphragm your chest so that the exhale extends itself
as you have these long exhales also relax other parts of your body
relaxing into your body
and then again lovingly gently
allow your breathing to return to normal without the need for any
clear idea of what normal is just allow your breathing to breathe
itself
and also continue this relaxing softening the face
softening the shoulders
releasing the belly
and somehow maybe even releasing all the holding the global holding of the body
holding it all together no need to in meditation
to relax release
releasing into this body to feel and sense
the immediacy of our lived life
the experience of sensations
and then kindly gently maybe even tenderly
and determinedly center yourself on the experience of
breathing
breathing is often taken as a sign of being alive
and the inconstant shifting changing sensations of breathing
sensations of breathing in are different than breathing out
sensations of breathing in disappear so that sensations of exhale can begin
and vice versa
regardless of how pleasant or unpleasant your breathing is to feel it
and experience it to center yourself in it
is to enter into the intimacy and of being really here with our lived life
and then as you're with your breathing and maybe that's mostly what you do
to feel the inconstancy of all the sensations that flow through that appear and disappear
and perhaps as you do so you relax and open all everything around
the breathing and perhaps as they get more and more
intimate there will be some experience that everything
is shifting changing arising disappearing
in the immediacy of how they are felt and experienced
if we recede into thoughts and ideas of things
we begin projecting ideas of constancy and
permanence but as a thinking mind gets quieter
we just feel and sense experience
breathing in and breathing out
with all the inconstancy of things coming and going
so the experience of thinking
if we intimate with the actual experience thoughts are also inconstant they come
and they go rather than being involved in thoughts
to settle further in and just see thoughts as
arising and passing coming and going
individual words or images that appear come and they go
in the intimacy of the moment everything
is part of a field of appearing and disappearing phenomenon
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
there's something about being at rest
in the middle of change settling back as if we're sitting in an
easy chair allowing everything to
move and change and appear and disappear
freely without us interfering with them
feeling safe and comfortable just letting the things everything come
and go everything
it can be uncomfortable to do this but it also can open up
the barriers to feeling tender love and kindness
to feel compassion care
for this changing buzzing flowing world
because what gets in the way of our love is something we're holding on to
something that we are that blocks or covers over
but when everything is buzzing and changing and but we're at rest with awareness
there can be a greater capacity for compassion for all
this
to be still and gaze upon everything kindly
to be still in the middle of all the
change and to feel compassion for
the challenges that everyone has in this changing world
to feel the joy buddhita that because things change things also
get better for people
and because we're not holding on to anything there can be kindness
may all beings be free of suffering
may all beings celebrate
their capacity for freedom
may all beings live in a world of kindness and friendliness
may all beings be the kind and friendly ones
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings contribute to the peacefulness of this world
may all beings be free and may all beings
support the freedom of others
may we all share in love and kindness and friendliness
in living this buzzing changing
impermanent life that we find ourselves in
this