good evening welcome welcome it's nice to be here with you
all yeah so here we are practicing on Memorial Day so happy Memorial
Day what um a beautiful thing it is to bring to
mind all those who have served served us served this
country to open our hearts and to
acknowledge that we are not completely selfmade here right that uh that uh
we're a big part of a community lots of people making big sacrifices lots of
families making big sacrifices so happy memori all
day if there's some tenderness or sadness in this day
for you may you hold it with care and
warmth so we'll start with a guided meditation
taking our meditation
posture seated ight and feeling the
uprightness like how the body is oriented in space
uprightness as well as some ease some dignity as well as some
relaxation finding this posture can be a practice in
itself that reflects both both Our intention to pay
attention but without some straining without striving without
grasping but with ease
so to sit and know you're sitting feeling the
pressure of the chair or cushion couch
bed whatever you might be sitting on and whether you're sitting literally or
metaphorically but feel whatever the body is contacting feeling the pressure against
the body you're here now
and then to notice that the body is breathing and tuning into the movement
of the chest the movement of the abdomen or maybe the feeling of air going in and
out of the nose
and just noticing the sensations of breathing
nothing in particular needs to be happening
we're just noticing the sensations of
breathing and when the mind wanders which it is likely to
do we just very simply gently begin to again
can we let go of any idea that the breath needs to be
controlled the body knows how to
breathe can we just allow it to breathe the way that is comfortable
feels natural not constrained contrived
can we let go of any idea that things have to be
different than how they are right
now can we allow them to be how they are they actually are the way they
are can we align ourselves with the reality of the
moment
for e
when we do mindfulness of breathing and we find ourselves lost in
thought we don't have to make it a problem
emem we let go of the
thoughts and turn towards the breathing
again in a way that has a generous attitude towards
ourselves of course we're thinking chances are you've been
thinking all day and there's this
momentum what would it be like to have a generous attitude towards
yourself and your
practice e
can we have an attitude of
generosity towards ourselves towards our
experience the spirit of giving away rather than hold holding
on tightly clinging rather than demanding this is
mine it has to be this way can we hold things
slightly allowing the experiences to come and
go
e
for
e e
having this attitude of
generosity towards ourselves when
meditating of course can come Al alive or be expressed
when we're not meditating as generosity not only
towards ourselves but towards others that is giving the benefit of the
doubt letting go of insisting that things be a particular
way and being openhearted and
open-minded so in this way generosity can support our mindfulness
practice if we allow the inner critic to
quiet and instead we have a generous attitude towards
ourselves and also support our intention to be generous towards
others so that our meditation practice benefits not only ourselves but
everyone that we come in contact with so that we might have the benefit
give them the benefit of the doubt and be openhearted so in this
practice I'm sorry in this way may our practice be for the benefit of all
beings everywhere
[Music]
good evening good evening welcome
welcome I want to say it's nice to see you all but of course I don't actually see you all but I'm
imagining that uh we're all practicing together it's very nice for me to be
practicing with others even if we're not physically in the same
room so a number of years ago I was at the Asian Art Museum just here in in San
Francisco and I saw this beautiful statue of the
Buddha and I read the inscription that was underneath the statue
and I had to like it had a piece of scripture that I had never seen before
never heard about and I was like quite confused by it and this beautiful statue was maybe
the same size as this one and is in the same position as this one that is with
the right hand down and the left hand in their lap so I was a little bit curious what
is this this Museum I thought of course the
curator must be mistaken because never heard of this this was a number quite a
few years ago and I didn't know all the sutas or all the stories but never heard
that story that was associated with it well since then I have discovered
this story and I'd like to share it with you of about the Buddha that's in this
position it's a common one that we see with the I forgot what it is buis I
forgot the name in uh poly or Sanskrit of the mudra the the gesture of the
hands but with one hand pointing down and the other hand in the lap
and it has to do with the night of the Buddha's Awakening and the Buddha before he
became the Buddha was called the bodh satva and I think probably all of you
know there the story is that after a childhood of these
princely uh pleasures and comfort that he had some
disillusionment and he fled home and did six years of meditation and
aesthetic practices including nearly starving himself to death and then he abandoned his
aesthetic practices started to eat again and then sat down underneath the booty
tree vowing that he wasn't going to get up until he achieved
Awakening so I just said there in one or two minutes you know which often is a
really long complicated beautiful story and then what happens next there's a
bunch of different versions of the story and I like to think of it as just like
every good story there's gets retold and retold and different tellings have
different emphases or maybe different interpretations different embellishments
or so here's one version that we find in the
nadana which is not uh commonly read um
it's in the Canon but uh not it's the introduction to the jica tales but
that's just a little aside so the story is that Mara who is
that personification of obstacles that's one when one way that we could
understand this character Mara that when he realized that the bodh
satva was sitting underneath the tree and was determined to become
awakened and Mara likes to keep people not awakened in
what we would call samura because Mara can influence individuals beings who are
here in samsara who are in this realm of existence unawakened maybe that's one
way that we translate some Sor that are unawakened and and Mara is perfectly
happy if everybody's having a wonderful time and even practice diligently Mara
just doesn't want them to become awakened so when he realized that the
bodh satva was really determined to become awakened he's wanted to put a stop to
it so he approached the Buddha and he was writing on this big giant elephant
there's a description of how big this elephant is you can imagine at that time
in Ancient India right the elephant is probably one of the biggest most powerful things that's known
right they of course they don't have any Motors or anything like this so an elephant is the most powerful thing and
this is a big elephant so not only is Mara riding on
this elephant but he has this giant army that's accompanying
him and and the intention is to get the bodh
SATA to move and disrupt his concentration or disrupt his vow to get
awake or whatever they can do so they have this rain this delu on
the bodhisatta and the rain of different objects and maybe some of you know this story so at first Mara raised a
tornado and then the had these winds that and the the story is that would
have shattered mountain peaks right these are some incredible winds but then um the text goes but by
the virtue and Majesty of the bodh satva the winds lost their force and on
reaching him they were not able to shake even the Hem of His
robe so it's quite something right to go from shaking Mountain Toops to not even
rustling one's clothing so in the same way Mara causes this downpour of rain actual
rain and this great flood came because of the the rain was so much and the flood like was submerging entire Forest
but then when it gets to the bodhisatta it um doesn't even dampen his
robes as much as a DW drop would so I kind of love these greatly exaggerated
stories but you get a sense of the power and the the power of
Mara and the power of the bodh SATA and Mara is trying to do whatever
he can to get the body SATA to get up and there's a a total of 10 different
things that get rained on spewed upon the bodh SATA so a shower of
rocks and uh weapons coals hot ashes
sandstorms mud all these things Gloom this darkness and all these later things
when they that is the weapons and the coals and the lashes Etc when they are
uh thrown towards the bodh satva they all turn into flowers or garlands or
perfume or you know these beautiful things so pretty soon that bodh SATA has
all these flowers surrounding him and still he
sits determined to become an awakened and then Mara demanded that the
bodh Safa leave his seat claiming it as his own he says rise
sedor from that seat it is not meant for you it goes to
me a little twist to the story that Mara is saying well if anybody's going to become awaken it's going to be me not
you and sortha that's the name of the bodh SATA the give a name in this version of the
story and he replies Mara this seat is not meant for you I alone have the right
to it claiming his right to sit there in that
seat and then he goes on and this part is what is kind of interesting is often a part of the story that we don't hear
about so then the bodh SATA says Mara who will testify to your having
been generous I can imagine maybe Mar is
scratching his head a little bit but then he replies by he stretches out his arms and looks to uh all the armies that
he has all these beings that are with him and he
says all of these are my Witnesses so Dortha who will testify for
you being generous right the bis SAA is sitting there by himself underneath the
tree and sedara responds by saying for your
generosity you have sentient Witnesses but I have no sentient
Witnesses looking around there's nobody else there it's just Mara and his
armies and then the body SATA says this solid
earth though not sentient Bears witness he took his right hand from
under his robe and extended it towards the great Earth as we see
here saying in my life as ventara I made the great gift of the
700s do you bear witness to that or not so he's talking to the Earth and the
Earth responds and Roars I was your witness
yes and then Mara with his on his elephants Mara's elephant kneels before
the bodh satva and then Mara and all of his army
turn around and run away so it's this recollection of his
generosity that bodhisatwa he remembers he brings to mind some generosity that he had done
there's a whole story around that we won't go into that now but it's it's quite something this is what made Mara
the elephant Neil and Mara to run away might be a little bit surprised right we
might expect some magnificent insights or some knowledge or some supernormal
Feats or something like this but it's his recalling his
generosity that created the conditions that caused Mara to leave obstacles to
leave and then he becomes awaken and becomes the Buddha the awakened
one so the sign he's calling to Earth his witness as his generosity as and this is one of the
favorite subjects in Buddhist art it's as you can see here is common for um statues but also in all kinds of Art and
throughout southeast Asia why generosity of all the topics that uh
could have been talked about then or some great wisdom or something why
generosity well we could say that generosity is foundational to Buddhist
practice in so many ways it's really foundational it's out of generosity so
many things flower and Blossom that are support for practice and are
practice and one is generosity is a type of letting go
it's a type of giving and in a way all of our practices
come down to Letting Go letting go we let go of our
attachments we let go of clinging we let go of our underlying
compulsion to cling to our desires to cling to our opinions instead we have
some open-heartedness and open-mindedness
we allow things to be as they are doesn't as well as putting effort to
make things to work towards making things wholesome and abandoning the UNH
wholesome but we don't do that by clinging and grabbing we doing it by letting
go we also let go of a sense of self that is this idea that there's a me
this all important me that's at the Center of everything we let go of
that this often doesn't really make sense until people have that experience
it's definely an experience rather than just a logical or logical idea or a belief you
have to adopt instead it's more of an experience of noticing when there isn't a strong
sense of self maybe like when there's a sense of flow when you're doing one of your
favorite activ activities dancing Hobbies playing music listening to music
these are often times when there isn't a strong sense of self it's kind of a pointer towards
that so letting go so this practice is about letting go it's not about
acquiring getting I'm I'm kind of like grabbing my
fingers it's not about uh grasping
but so we can let go of an actual object or the grasping of that
object because this practice isn't that we have to let go of everything we just let go of those
things that aren't helpful unskillful UNH wholesome and those things that are
skillful and wholesome we just let go of the clinging to them but we still hold
them so maybe just do this right that Gil does this which is so helpful right
that it's not we can still hold things with a outstretched Palm as opposed to
clinging holding on to them but it's one thing to talk about it
to hear about it but to have the confidence and the trust to open the palm of the
hand this is a practice to gain this confidence this
trust to know that the way forward is to is that movement is that gesture of
opening the hand and generosity generosity is the
practice powerful practice that can really help us
to feel the beauty to feel the freedom but it's implicit whenever
there's this opening of the hands the opening of the heart and generosity by
definition is a letting go is an opening so that's one way in which
generosity is foundational to a Buddhist practice is that it really supports a
sense of Letting Go whether we're actually giving
objects material things money gifts objects or whether we're giving our
Attention our maybe our expertise our energy giving
the benefit of the doubt whatever whatever it might be this way generosity
is a type of way that helps cultivate
and and develop just this movement this gesture
of letting go but
generosity also has the op opposite
um the opposite impact and that it connects
us so it connects us to other people recognizing that we can't walk
this path all by ourselves sometimes we might wish to and there might be seasons
of our practice in which we spend a lot of time practicing on our own meditating but there will also need to be seasons
in which we practice with others are supported by practice with
others and I have the wisdom of others to guide us and to support us and maybe
help us find our way so we might be giving our time and
our attention so again it's not only things but sometimes it's giving feels a
little bit awkward or we don't really know how to be generous in that
way um and I'm inspired by this writing by David White he's a poet and
essayist and here's an excerpt from an essay that he wrote that it's not
exactly about generosity but um you'll see how it's uh connected to generosity I'll say that
when I heard this I felt inspired to be
generous and that's part of what this practice is also is to be connected to
what is inspiring what inspires us to be the best versions of ourselves okay so here's this passage
from David White it's an essay but you can tell he's a poet a little bit by the his
writing it may be that the ability to know the necessity for help to know how
to look for that help and then most importantly how to ask for it is one of
the primary transformative dynamics that allows us to emancipate ourselves into
each new Epoch of our lives without the understanding that we
need a particular form of Aid at every crucial threshold in our lives and
without the robust vulnerability and asking for that help
we cannot pass through the door that bars us from the next dispensation of
Our Lives Liv we cannot birth ourselves every transformation has at
its heart the need to ask for the right kind of
generosity every transformation has at its heart the need to ask for the right
kind of generosity so David White is writing
from the perspective of asking for generosity but just hearing this it
feels like oh yes giving generosity giving help so that we
can assist be part of support these
Transformations he writes with the next Epoch in our lives and to emancipate
ourselves into each new Epoch of Our Lives
and I think every crucial threshold in our lives requires some help and for us
to ask for that help and the vulnerability of asking for that help what a privilege it is to help
others what a beautiful meaningful thing it is to be generous so that we can help
others with their Transformations whatever that might be wherever they are in their life whether
it's a young person an older person and in between AG
person whether this transformation is going from singlehood to being married
from maybe being married back to single again
maybe from becoming a I don't know there's so many different
Transformations we do in our lives right and some of them are just very gentle um
slide in and some of them are really uh abrupt and there's diagnosis deaths in
the family these types of things so one way to frame
generosity is to help others but help others help themselves not because we
have all the answers or because um
they that we somehow are uh Superior in some kind of way but
just to whatever way that we can to help these Transformations that all of us go
through they're not easy so that's one part of generosity is
to connect us with others and to help others when they need it in a way that's
appropriate but also also generosity supports our relationships in other ways
too and the Buddha noticed this and he knew this and here's a quote from one of the
sutas generosity kind words doing a good turn
for others and treating all people alike these means of sustaining a
favorable relationship are like the Lynch pin of a rolling
Chariot I'll read it again generosity kind words doing a good turn
for others and treating all people alike these means of sustaining a
favorable relationship are like the Lynch pin of a rolling Chariot so they're
vital they if we don't have the this Lynch pin then the wheel gets disconnected from The Chariot and off it
goes and the charot doesn't go anywhere right
generosity kind words doing a good turn for others that is you
know helping them out is a way that can really support our relationship so
generosity and thinking about others what would be helpful for them what would they like not in a way that we
abandon ourselves and not in the way that we allow boundaries to be crossed
or barriers to be crossed that are inappropriate but just to
recognize that how generosity can really be a support for
relationships in whatever way it is one time I was on a walk with a friend of mine who
was a another Buddhist practitioner and it's lovely to walk in the neighborhood right
and see some of the people have beautiful landscaping and sometimes there's roses
and we we were walking and there's this beautiful rose
bush you just really in beautiful that you wanted to stop and admire and smell
the roses of course right but then I felt really touched when my walking partner said
here I'd like to offer this Rose to you without picking the rose or anything
like this but just just uh kind of like the generous Spirit it was so great cuz
that Rose I I felt so happy that it stayed on the bush where it could be fresh for longer and other people
walking by could see it so sometimes generosity just has a simple gesture
like that but it made me feel realize oh this person really cares about me it was
a very tender lovely
gesture so generosity connects us also because it
supports our relationships and then also generosity
is related to the Brahma viharas that is these four qualities of the
heart probably all of you are familiar with them but at the moment of giving at
the moment when we're being generous we're letting go we're letting go of desire and
grasping and we're also letting go of ill will letting go of aversion and that
moment when we're giving whether it's a material object or
not there's these beautiful qualities of the heart that are
present and so there might be some loving kindness might feel some Goodwill
towards the person who is receiving our generosity we might feel a connection
with them rather than some alienation or we there's a our being
generous is an expression of we want them to be happy so loving kindness and generosity
generosity and compassion we wish the person to be free from suffering maybe
that's why we are helping to help them with some difficulty and we also when there's
compassion there's a certain tenderness there's a openness of the heart and generosity often has that too right
this sharing this tenderness in the
heart and compassion also I'm sorry and generosity also is
associated with sympathetic Joy the third Brahma vihara that is that we
Delight in their happiness their happiness in receiving whatever it is
we're being generous about this is why it's so so wonderful to go to birthday parties right to see people uh receive
gifts and to see how the recipient is happy and we like to make people happy
in that way and to see their happiness for us to be happy in their Happyness
and receiving and we want their happiness to increase this is why we're giving them a
gift and generosity is also associated with Quin imity that is that means that
we have an object that we're willing to let go of or maybe it's not an object it's a a view or a stance that we're not
holding too tightly we're willing to let go of that is we have a balanced
relationship with it and that we are willing we're capable to be without it
and we're allowing others to be with it if necessary so in this way
generosity also connects us to others through the Brahma vajar through
helping and just supports our relationships and then as I started to
say that generosity is also about letting go this kind of movement of letting
go so in some ways we could see how generosity why the Buddha right before
his Awakening and what kind of frightens Mara and has him run away
even though he's so powerful with these big armies powerful armies is
generosity it's foundational to so many practices and anybody can do
it it doesn't require a meditation practice it doesn't require that you know with some Buddhist
teachings we can be generous in our daily life we can be
generous towards ourselves and the attitude we have towards ourselves or the way that we show up in the
world so my invitation is when you have this inclination to be generous when it
the thought arises in your mind to be generous go ahead and be generous don't hesitate don't maybe talk yourself out
of it or or rationalize it away I heard Joseph
Goldstein one of the kind of the senior members of our
Community talk about how he had this as a practice to always be generous and I
figured well if it's good enough for Joseph Goldstein it's good enough for me and I have to say I have never regretted
it when I've been generous and I have regretted those times when I thought oh
it'll be a little bit awkward I'm not sure if I want to give this to this person I've always regretted that I
didn't so generosity supports letting go and also supports
connecting to others so may your generosity be a support for your practice and be a
support for others around you so that all beings without exception can be free
from suffering thank you