so hello everyone and welcome to our meditation together
and um one of the
remarkable aspects of being human
is the ability to be conscious the ability to be aware
and in that awareness being conscious has many facets the different times different facets are emphasized
and one of those is the ability to recognize what's happening
to be aware and to recognize but the recognition is
there's different kinds of recognition this morning
i woke up uh fairly early about an hour before i
usually do and uh felt quite quite awake and refreshed
and i thought wow this is an hour before i usually do my morning meditation so um
you know i could probably do some things i have a long to do list and maybe i'll do some things and have less
to do during the day and and then i said no i can also meditate
longer so i sat down to meditate and still with thoughts that i should be
doing things and and as soon as i sat into my meditation posture
and kind of settled in i realized that
my my my thought my thinking about what should i do here is early in the morning should
i do some some of my to-do list or should i meditate that that was all kind of um
uh was um a lot of thinking
and the recognition there was a deeper recognition that was happened when i sat down to meditate
when i sat down and got into my posture that
immediately there was this knowing in my body that i was home it would mean there's a
knowing of oh this is good this this is subtle this is the place to
be and that recognition was not in the same discursive thoughts that i had when i
was considering what to do with my time this was a deeper knowing deeper
cognition that felt much more embodied oh the body knows oh yes this is the
place to be this is right and and so then i
you know i settled in i felt uh affirmed in my decision to meditate
and um and this way of being connected to the body and
letting the body be an informant let the body what how does
the body cognize how does the body know what does the body know
and sometimes the body knows before the mind thinks about something
if we're uncomfortable in our body the discomfort occurs before
the cognitive intellectual labeling of that oh i'm uncomfortable
it might happen seemingly at the same time but there's a little gap between them
and a gap that is noticed when it's possible to sit quietly in meditation
and the body there's a knowing that things are uncomfortable but there's no thinking about it there's
no reaction to it there's no higher cognition in the knowing of it they just
it's almost like a silent knowing and this knowing that i was you know in
the right place meditating this is good to sit here there was a silent knowing in the sense that it
wasn't really the mind talking or thinking or imagining
just the body speaking so
to our ability to be aware of the body is such a powerful thing so helpful
not always easy the body's challenging a lot of pain a lot of discomfort can
exist but below the level of
thinking about it reacting to it what happens what does the body know how
does the body settle in how do we really become attuned
to our bodily experience so
assuming a posture and mindfulness begins
uh can begin for meditation with mindfulness of the posture
taking some time to maybe sway back and forth
or maybe rock back and forth a little bit and and kind of to
become a little more embodied but also to find a nice
midpoint in which to sit or lay
in a good balanced posture
and then to gently close your eyes
and without much else to do what are you aware of in your body now
if you attune yourself to your body
familiarize yourself with the body
maybe almost as like you're listening to the body
then as a gentle way to expand the sensations of your body
the range of what you sense and feel in your body
take a few long slow deep breaths
three quarters full
and gently exhale long relaxed exhale
and then being attuned to your body following kind of a pace sorry
that feels relaxed for the body return to uh normal breathing
and as you exhale in a relaxed way no hurry
relax any parts of your body where there's holding
where it's easy to relax
relaxing around the face
let the area of your lips be relaxed so the lips are not pressing against each other
some people find a little bit relaxing to have the tongue gently touching
the upper palate the roof of the mouth
relaxing the shoulders
can you relax a bit your upper back
maybe if you do so it feels like you should adjust your back a little bit
and on the exhale softening the belly
sometimes if the belly relaxes and hangs forward down
might also feel appropriate to adjust the posture a little bit
to adjust the spine
relax the fingers
and then center yourself on the body's experience of breathing
then maybe the emphasis can be to allow the body to have its own
experience of breathing
the body can have its own knowing
the movements the sensations of breathing
and knowing that's deeper than the skin
the body's knowing
that is not the same thing as thinking about the body
in fact as you exhale see if you can let go of thinking
or let go with your interest in thinking so your interest
can be in the body's experience
as it breathes in and breathes out
letting the thinking mind become quieter so you're better able to
feel and sense the body knowing itself
so
the more we can feel our body
and let the aware in the body's awareness of itself
become fuller the more the body's own process of
healing of making whole
has a chance to unfold the settling the calming of the body the
opening of the body the awakening of the body
allows for all kinds of wonderful
healing and
processes understanding processes deeper understanding of our life
and as and it gives a different character
to our capacity to care for compassion
for love for friendliness
when it's embodied and relaxed healed body when it's relaxed and open
when it seems to vibrate or resonate from the body
and as we come to the end of the sitting to
turn this body awareness out into the world
and the art is to say centered in the body
and simply to become aware of the world around us in
some kind of intuitive way the people in your communities
people you'll encounter people you'll learn about and communicate with today
and may you stay in your body
in your contact with others stay in your body
and let that be a place from which friendliness and care can
flow not from your thoughts so much not from
the mental shoulds and shouldn'ts but from a sweetness
within and with whatever sweetness tenderness
gentleness beauty that we have within
may we wish well on the world maybe maybe wish for the
welfare and happiness of others
may it be that we contribute to the happiness of others
may it be that we contribute to the safety of others
may it be that we contribute to peace for others
it may be that we contribute to the freedom of others
and that as we do so we do so
so it grows our own happiness and safety and
peace and freedom
may all beings be happy
[Music]
so this week we're talking about mindfulness of the body
and i think it can be one of the wonderful
results of doing mindfulness practice is to become more embodied
and uh many years ago i read ancient mahayana buddhist text
that insisted that we don't get enlightened through the mind we get enlightened through the body
and whether that's literally true or not it's kind of an inspiring idea
that certainly as we practice mindfulness slowly slowly perhaps for some of us
certainly for me the body wakes up awakening of the body
and we have more and more access to sensing and feeling the body
there are people who for all kinds of reasons you know important reasons significant things
happen to them difficult things that it's very difficult to be in their
body the body is not a safe place to be it's it
feels like you tap into fear or or tear or even sometimes to really drop in
and feel the body so to emphasize the wonderfulness of being in the body
is a kind of a careful thing to do because of how difficult it is some people live
kind of from their neck up or from their waist up and feel really disconnected
from parts of their body and so for today the emphasis is recognition
as an aspect of mindfulness practice in these five days of the week it's relax relaxation recognition
respect restoration
and release and today's recognition and um
in the re the again part of recognition is kind of to reconnect to the body to
spend time getting to know it and to learn to do it in a way
that is not frightening or not distressing but to do it with the kind of gentleness
and care and for some people to do it in in uh in um
you know in very short periods of time spend a little bit touching in and then pull out
and just as long as it's safe and i know for some people i've given them the instructions when there's been
really difficult things in the body that um to imagine awareness is like a
soft cotton ball that we gently uh reach down and touch the place that's
difficult and just like touch it with that softness of the cotton ball and then pull back and let it be just so
it's known and felt and maybe note a little bit and then pull back
and slowly over time the different ways the body reveals itself to us
sometimes and it can be through discomfort as the mind gets quieter as the body
settles down we go through the layers of where the body is held and where there's tension
and there's layers of tension we have that we're not aware of because the coarser tension holds it in place
or kind of hides it or covers it kind of and so when the coarser tension uh
relaxes then we're aware of deeper tension deeper tension and um and slowly there's a greater
connection to the body and and but it's not just the connection to
the body as if the body is something separate from you um there's a body has its own
awareness its own uh and often we call it sensing uh sensing and sensations
uh belong to the body and uh the place where we uh like if we touch if i touch my hand
uh the i have sensations of warmth and pressure against upon my hand
now and then um and that's those sensations of warmth and pressure
occur in the location where the other hand is pushing against the
the left hand here for me so sensing that raw immediate sensing
occurs in the body in the place where the sensations occur and i like to say that sensing and
sensations are non-dual they're not really two different things and
and that and then separate from that um i know the body knows it's warm when i
touch and knows the pressure and separate from that i can have the cognitive thought
where i had put the english word a warmth pressure on it
and if i speak a different language i would use a different sound to represent that just sounds that
we use to represent things these words that we have and um
and so um and so we use different sounds to represent it
the if um but the body is already sensed it the
bodies feels it and so this sensing body starts to wake up as we do
mindfulness and and the parts that are numb or been disconnected get reconnected
and so this recognition is also a remembering
putting the members of the body back together again that have been disconnected and there starts to slowly over time to
be a flow kind of of harmony a flow of the body the whole body kind of just
hums in a very nice way but the path to that is
is to appreciate this deeper recognition so mindfulness practice uses the
recognition part of mindfulness is actually extremely significant in mindfulness practice
and there are different and so to works in different ways but it's always simple
it's not a story it's not not an explanation of why it's there it's not
a review of everything it almost like recognition doesn't have
it's almost like rec they're what we recognize doesn't have a history it's just recognizing in the moment
what's here and uh so if i recognize my the chest expanding as i breathe in
it's just the expansion just feeling and sensing the expansion feeling the movement
and then in addition we can have the mental aspect and the mental part of mindfulness practice
is sometimes to use a mental note and that mental note a label
a sound is just
is a um using a sound a word that recognizes
what it is we just uh we're experiencing so expansion of the chest movement that i feel
so breathing in and and but that's two different forms of
recognition happening it's the the immediacy of what's happening in the chest
and then it's very quiet kind of maybe in the background almost there's a mental recognition movement
expansion that's happening or uh if there's a pain in the knee
pain is happening um but that's very it's like five percent of what the mind is doing is a
label it's not like we're uh you know pounding that lay the mental note into
the experience it's more like a gentle brushing of it now this recognition both the mental
noting and the feeling of it to really be part of that and enter into this recognition mode
is an alternative to discursive thought it's an alternative to wandering off
flowing along with a storyline or a commentary line or
explanation or a prediction of what's going to happen all the ways we can kind of get involved
in discursive thought and the idea is that the recognition
begins to cut through that sometimes i think of it as the sword
that cuts through the gordian knot that you know our mental world of discursive
thoughts can be so complicated so many ideas that we live in and complicated
histories and stories and then we cut through it by just oh just breathing
that's an in-breath that's an out breath that there's a sound
listening now there's an itch now i'm back with the breathing the
stomach is tight relaxing the belly and
and it's just it's just coming back to that simplicity and so using the simple simple act of
recognition to help us be engaged nicely in the present moment
without being hijacked or pulled into the world of thinking
we don't have to struggle against thoughts in a few weeks i'll talk about mindfulness of thinking but for now the idea is to kind of cut
through it to keep it really simple the meditation mindfulness of thinking and the role of
thinking it comes later but for right now the simplest we use the simplest
kind of thinking to help us stay present and that's a very simple uh one word
cognition of things pressure warmth expansion
if it's more than a word it probably is not simple recognition and um
but don't but uh and so use the mental noting very gentle soft
or something that's uh close to it if your mind is able to really stay close to that simple
recognition without a mental note you don't have to use the mental noting but mental noting is a kind of way of
staying honest really knowing that you're not wondering often thought and
and just kind of steadily steady pace breathe in out expansion
hearing discomfort
pleasure whatever it might be we're feeling and sensing and um
and uh and then so whether it's cognition of a mental note or the cognition of the
body's own knowing the knowing that's much more silent whichever helps you to cut through
uh the thinking mind and connect you to something that's living alive
because it's a miracle to be conscious this wonderful thing that i started off with but human
awareness that um it's a it's an amazing thing
and to stay close to the living moment the living experience of life where cognition
consciousness awareness mindfulness keeps us in our animated body
keeps us in our living body the lived experience and the more we can recognize and open
up and be present for this eventually we start feeling and allowing for the
healing potential healing power of this body that we have
healing not necessarily from physical illness and and
injury and things like that but it's kind of a deeper um kind of healing a spiritual healing
a healing of awareness that uh this hum that moves through the whole
body and becomes whole so i hope that made sense and
and to really get to know the body well is such a blessing
so i'd encourage you uh through the day today the next 24 hours for those of you in a different time
zone to um to get to know your body better
listen to it maybe even uh have a timer on that goes on every few minutes you know 10 minutes
or something and then check in with your body check in with your body every time you go through a door frame every time that you
change your posture from sitting to walking to whatever you do standing
whenever you pick up a new utensil cooking or eating
check what do you have find different things to just check in check in what's happening in the body what is the body
showing if i listen to my body now what do i learn recognize the body
so thank you