okay so so hello and welcome everyone to this
rendition this edition of happy hour so
so for today's happier um it's interesting because i was sitting
earlier and and thinking about what to share for today's
practice different thoughts came up and and um
and then so i i prepared a little darmette on a different topic which i'll
present another day and then something else happened what happened was just before
i opened the room i was sitting in meditation i became really really aware
of my own mortality that time is very very short
and as many of you know mindfulness of mortality befriending
mortality is is a topic that i practice a lot and
teach a lot so guess what when one practices this a lot it shows up in
moments on its own very important ways so
with respect to meta then the question that came up was
how do i want to show up how do i want to be and the feeling was so strong just
before you came on that i decided no i feel like this is the topic that i'm called to present tonight this is
it see it feels like this is what's moving through um and often my
my uh invocation my intention prayer is
let the dharma move through me whatever needs to be presented in this moment let that come through it's not so much about
so much about me in the middle but whatever needs to come through and so this is the topic that wants to come
through tonight especially it might be relevant i
realize because as we are entering yet a new phase of
of the coronavirus and the delta variant and the various
[Music] shutdowns around the world and and challenging and
um and not just with with some so many cases so many caseloads increasing and
life feeling really precarious our lives and others lives that's one aspect to
really have this this contemplation love in the time of
of uh corona um
giving a nod to this famous uh book by
gabriel garcia marquez love in the time of cholera love in the time of corona so
love how how do we love how do we love when really
whether we are vaccinated or not or or or um
or whether we have some underlying health conditions for us and our loved ones life seems precarious
um and without having fear about it in the sense of
life is always precarious right it's always precarious you anything can happen at any moment it
really can anything can happen at any moment
especially feels more more more juicy perhaps more
prominent and also another way that this reflection can be quite
supportive is for many of us perhaps
life is feeling not for everyone but really for many might it might feel like
the movie groundhog's day that we're at home again and again
every day is the same shape or form maybe we have some zoom meetings we sit in the same chairs eat the same food
same it's it is groundhog's day i definitely do feel that especially with
the air having been particularly um air quality having been bad from the smokes
and fires here so being at home not going out indoors and yet and yet with
that sense of groundhogs like gosh oh this life is gonna end
it is not infinite it might feel like again okay same same thing but anything
can happen at any moment it's it's gonna shift it's gonna change
and unbeknownst without without any planning who knows so
but one thing that we know is that we have limited time we know we have limited time we live as if we're gonna
live forever we go through our groundhog's day day as if it's gonna last forever
this show this show are called our life but it doesn't so so how do we want to show up for
ourselves for others in the midst of what's happening with all the issues all the relationships
we're having in our lives with that knowledge with that
stark realization that time is short it's limited it's going to come to
an end how do we love how do we love
how do we love how do we let go
how do we let go how do we love
so with that as the introduction
let's begin our practice together dear sangha
i invite you to settle to rest
to arrive in your seat in this body
in this mortal body mortal frame [Music]
which is alive for this period for this limited period of time
connecting with each breath as if it were or last
with ease with ease with the freshness of spring
in breath bringing life
out breath goodbye relax soften
and if thoughts arise it's okay it's all right be kind to your mind
it's used to thinking that's what it likes to do
as if you've noticed
a young child wandering off come come sweetie it's okay
come back come back to the breath to the body
to your mind settle rest take refuge
and the freedom that impermanence provides
just connecting with this moment with this fleeting evanescent moment in
time
this breath is in breath come and gone this out
breath calm and gone
not hanging on
just this breath just this in breath
noticing aliveness at the end breath
with the out breath leaning into relaxing letting go
embodied
and if this were if this were this moment in time right
now unbeknownst to you
if this were your last days last week last month
feel free to chew the time frame that doesn't bring too much anxiety but but
brings a sense of limitedness of time time is short it's not guaranteed to run
forever definitely not
how would you want to show up
first of all how would you want to show up
for the people with whom you're close
if you knew this was let's say your last month
how would you want to show up
choose one person so as to not to get overwhelmed
choose one person in your life who's dear to you an easy person let's start with the easy category
someone who's easy
where your relationship isn't complicated to meta kindness flows with ease
could be a child could be a pet and how would your kindness
your love how would it express itself
your good will towards this being
you're well wishing knowing that time is short
can you allow your meta your good will your kindness to flow to this being
since person from this place of generosity knowing
time is short
no matter truly how much time you have left with
each other it is still short and whether
you have a month left or not right now there will be a time
when you only have a month left with each other and you would only have known that
in the rearview mirror so so trying it on for size
now this practice this experiment
of good will cultivating kindness good wealth feeling into your goodwill kindness
for this being important in your life from this perspective of time being
short
you're welcome to bring other beings or beings who are near and dear
to you easy category if you wish or just stay with this one but spend some time with
each one not jumping too quickly from one to the next which can unsettle the mind
the true phrases that come up for me this practice
from the perspective of time being short unreliable
life's impermanence with respect to dear beings
the two phrases that come up with the in-breath and out-breath for me are
thank you thank you
i love you
thank you
i love you see what comes up for you
it's an expression of meta from this perspective
or you can borrow mine
and now invite invite into your mind's eye maybe
someone with you with whom you have a bit of a complicated relationship just a little bit
not the most complicated one yet but just a tiny bit
and if it feels okay inviting them
to your mind's eye from this perspective of time is short
it's very short you have no idea how short it might be
notice what might come up in the way of
things being let go of on their own meta-rising goodwill
for both of your humanities the way you've been entangled
if it gets complicated it's okay let it go if you're not with the mind the heart
isn't ready for this
come back to an easy being
if not then stay
stay with the slightly challenging category
time is short time is short time is always running out
we all must die all of us all of us earthlings
the dharmapada the buddhism
all of us all
all those earthlings we must not those who realize for
those who realize this truth
quarrel's end for those who realize
emphasize really realize this truth of common humanity that we
all must die all quarrels end
now i'd like to invite you
to turn your gaze upon yourself
this being who is you
as if you were gazing upon a beloved other who has limited time
with this truth realizing this truth how does your relationship shift
how would you treat this being who is you
this earthling was limited time
this real fling being yourself how do you want to show up how do you want to be
the stories the stories that we tell ourselves about ourselves
would some of them not be needed or get loosened the ones that are not helpful
not productive
hold us back from living
our limited time according or according to our values
do we get freed from entanglements of
our heart that are not helpful entanglements
time is limited do we really want to spend time
with ill will
do we really want to spend time with lack of generosity of the heart
how do we want to show up for ourselves and others
if you knew your time was limited which it is
how would you want your heart to love to shine
upon yourself and others
loving and living our days as if it were our last
because one day it will be
and for the final fleeting moments of this practice period together
letting go of however this practice period was
letting go no need for judgment
but to just love and appreciate yourself
thank you for showing up just the way you could just the way you
did do your best thank you
i love you
[Music]
thank you all for joining
for this practice
i felt like i wanted to sit longer but it had already been 30 minutes so
such a rich reflection practice to bring in
mindfulness of our mortality together with the practice of metta
of love cultivating love loving kindness
profound practice which i vow to bring to do more often
here at happy hour
yes i see thumbs up for that so
so we have time we have time for reflections
for comments for questions for complaints for whatever you like to share dear sangha
the gems of your insights your humanity
the gifts you offer to one another by sharing of yourselves
you're welcome to type your reflections in chat you're welcome to raise your hand please
love to hear from you bring your voices in
one reflection coming in [Music] that was truly gay great thank you you
are welcome you're most welcome
yeah remind me christine says the reminder we are only here for a short time brought
up panic and anxiety that can happen as a part of mindfulness
of mortality practice also it can definitely happen so
the invitation i have for this is to titrate is to titrate go into it a
little bit and then come back out into mindfulness of body
mindfulness of of breath to calm yourself and then let it in a little bit a little more because
that way your capacity for it will get expanded
but that's a very good point and one can work with it one can we can
absolutely bring it in and support it in this practice and work with it aura says thank you so much for
this i recognize that even when i don't know i'm striving i'm striving
beautiful forrest says i missed the intro but this practice helps me get out of a negative
mind state metta is such a beautiful way to leave this world yes
absolutely another reflection this one sent to me only so i read the reflection not the
name that's our common practice here
the next reflection thank you that was very powerful tears
came to me thank you and mercy christine says thanks thank you
mark christine for raising that very important
nav says sharing a carl sagan quote it's a long one i'll read it the world is so
exquisite with so much love and moral depth that there is no reason to deceive
ourselves with petty stories for which there is little good evidence far better it seems to me in our
vulnerability is to look death in the eye and to be grateful every day for the
brief but magnificent opportunity that life provides beautiful thank you love
yes exactly exactly
eileen says thank you for this it helps not to feel alone with this awareness of mortality yes we're not
alone one more reflection my dear 80 year old mother-in-law was present with
me oh her cancer has metastasized and she continues to live in joy and service a
great teacher beautiful oh inspiring thank you for sharing that
another reflection sadness came up i the thought was if my life ended next month i should
probably be kinder and more generous to myself than i am being right now how i'm living right now is not how i
would like to treat myself if my time were very limited fantastic that is wholesome sadness that
is wholesome sadness when you realize that you're when you really recognize and connect
with your true values intentions and you realize
the the little misalignment when you realize there's a misalignment problem which many of us
have um beautiful i am so delighted to hear that
this came up of course because our time is always limited and wonderful to remember that to be kinder and more
generous to yourself to ourselves jerry says focusing on the brevity of
our lives and of the time as species made me appreciate the gift
of my life and of all yeah yes
what do i mean by misalignment says murray christine misalignment so this idea of what our values are and how we
actually act and spend our time is called the misalignment problem
so so what the person was reflecting was oh i want to be kinder more generous to
myself but i realize i'm not so that is the misalignment or if you realize that you really want to
serve the world but let's say you're in a career that's not really serving at all
so the oh misalignment between the way you're spending your life and your values so misalignment problem
on youtube patricia says a sense of urgency came up in waves for me very profound
indeed i found that mindfulness of the breath was very supportive thank you yeah thank
you and the sense of urgency is very common with this practice of mindfulness and mortality it's actually
with respect to practice it's called some vega some vega s-a-m
v-v-e-g-a some vega there might be an h in there somewhere with the transliteration from
poly to english but um the idea of spiritual urgency their
sense of spiritual urgency comes up with this practice which different ones of you are talking about
in different ways and more reflection my daughter is my role model she died
five years ago oh while fighting her cancer she lived her
life more fully became involved in a new spiritual tradition and got married oh
that is so beautiful oh thank you for
sharing the beautiful beautiful life of this beautiful being your child
hmm
ah thank you all thank you for sharing your goodness and beauty
this limited flash of time that we have like
stars in the sky we're crossing each other we're crossing
so yeah one last reflection before we go into
groups hearing your words at the beginning describing the groundhog's day sense
many of us are having coupled with the current seeming or immediacy of death was initially confronting but as i went into
the practice i found peace and love for myself and others over the weekend i was very ill
following the wallop of the second shingles vaccine oh i had the experience of feeling super
ill not even wanting to speak with friends on the phone yet at the same time knowing it was only my body
building immunity being that sick took me to an unexpectedly happy place without much to
be anxious about as i often am when i'm physically well and thinking about the
world life and my own little problems yes yes thank you deborah
profound practice to practice when we are ill
is profound practice it simplifies so many things let's go over because we don't have the
energy the usual around our energy to get tangled in fact i think some weeks ago i
did this practice maybe months ago practicing as if you are ill practicing
as if you are ill so that's an audio dharma so dear ones we have come to the time
when we hold each other these mortal beings that we are and we meet each other
in small groups and connect with each other and support each other
so let us join each other in small groups
with starting with 15 seconds of of meta
as always mettak or karuna compassion for ourselves for each other and then share
as little or as much as you like with each other about this practice so
the rooms are created i will open them now here we go take care of yourselves take care of each
other welcome back everyone actually note we have five more seconds
okay now welcome back everyone the rooms are closed
and uh by the way sorry uh i think in a couple rooms there was a truck someone
joined late so sorry jerry i moved you around by mistake you got to meet more people that's the gift
you got to talk with more people so welcome back everyone we have just a
minute any reflections if if any of you would like to raise your hand or share anything
[Music] briefly the floors open
so many rich reflections before we went into groups yes
going once going twice fred please
oops there
try again
whoops oh my god okay i just this time i accidentally muted you okay
check my clothes okay there okay well all i was going to say was it
that's it's very touching to be with one another as we're
contemplating or we're at the edge of thinking about our own deaths and the deaths of people we love
and it even in the small group for very few moments that i can feel it bringing us
close in this really lovely way so thank you
thank you thank you fred and thank you to every single one of you
for showing up and practicing this way yeah
jerry says joy of being alive with being able to be able to to be of
service with bits of kindness joy of being alive with being able to be of service with
bits of kindness indeed indeed so
so let's bring this practice to a close so thank you all thank you for showing
up for practicing for cultivating your heart
and kindness and goodness thank you for your practice may
all beings be free may all beings
be well including ourselves
thanks everyone take good care of yourselves