great so hello hello and welcome everyone wherever you are in the world
however the weather is externally internally it's lovely to be with you
so as we are continuing to practice go through uh the categories
for compassion practice together we've been going through them one by one
we've now made it through the category of
what's called a neutral person's neutral being so
i know diana did that yesterday and i'm gonna going to continue with one more session
of cultivating compassion for someone
whom we don't know very well someone who's a stand-in for all of humanity we don't really have
a history with them we neither like them nor dislike them very strongly
due to someone there's another human being so this neutral being category
is so important is so important because yes you know there are
categories where ourselves we know ourselves pretty well we spend a lot of time with this being
that is us so cultivating compassion yes that's familiar um our beloveds our people we care about
our friends and benefactors yes compassion for them many times comes easily because we care for them if
they're hurting uh we hold their care we hold their their hurt their sorrow with care
and compassion or um yet yet this category of the neutral person
person whom we don't really know um why is it such an important category
it's many reasons but just to keep my comments brief before we actually
practice together one reason is that when we practice with
this neutral person after a while our hearts open up and we care for this
person who we don't even really know and our hearts learn that whom we care for and who is a
stranger and who's a friend who's a beloved person it's so arbitrary it feels so arbitrary
our heart as a human being has amazing unfathomable capacity
to care to to express its compassion for people whom
we don't even know and many times um
especially if you've sat or retreat or if you've practiced with the neutral person for a while you realize that they
don't remain neutral you start to develop care for them oh dear person oh dear dear human being
so it shifts it it changes you start to care for them as if they were your best friend since childhood these
transitions can happen very illuminating
to to feel that and another perspective
to consider is that being able to cultivate
and have a sense of care and compassion for a neutral person the standard for all of humanity
you know in a theistic context it could be thought of having a god-like
consciousness where a god-like consciousness is is one of care compassion
love indiscriminately regardless of your history or knowing
someone having care compassion for any being
so this god-like consciousness or divine consciousness is something that
actually we have as human beings we can experience it's accessible
and when we practice in this way sometimes there feels like there's access to this divine
indiscriminate care love compassion for other beings god-like divine
being filled with beauty and grace and that is such a beautiful aspiration not just
aspiration but something actually we can feel into now and then the potential of our own hearts and mind
which may be beyond what we give credit to for to ourselves uh and we
even fathom that we're capable of but this practice opens us to that little by little so
don't have to take my word for it just practice and see what happens maybe not today
maybe in the next session or the one after that or the one after that
ah being open to possibilities so
so let's practice together it's the perfect time to transition into your sitting posture
ah if you need to shift and move
and as always we start by landing landing in our bodies
landing in our breath
letting go of thoughts letting go of all the words that just came before and
just landing ah arriving in the simplicity of this
moment just taking refuge for a few minutes and
breathing sitting and breathing that's all nothing fancy
just being simple one birth at a time in this body
inviting your awareness to intimately connect be intertwined
with the breath in the abdomen
for the entire length of the in-breath
and the outbreak
and if their thoughts arising in this moment
are they really necessary in this moment or can you tell the thoughts
thank you for visiting not now please come back later
with gentleness kindness and yet a sense of empowered
awareness thank you not now
and intimately reconnecting with the breath in this moment taking refuge
ah safety trusting this moment
and now bringing to mind
someone you don't know very well they don't have to be absolutely neutral
but as long as you don't have much of a history with them
it could be a neighbor someone at a store where you shop
etc etc
choosing someone bringing them to your mind's eye clear visuals
trying to picture them as clearly as you can or having you felt sense of them maybe
it's a neighbor you walk by when you go for walks
having a felt sense of this fellow human being
but they look like what they feel like as much as possible may not be too much
available
connecting with them with this fellow human
who are just like you just wants to be happy this fellow human
being just like me does not want to suffer
it's not one to experience pain just like i don't
and they do have a body
so they experience pain discomfort illness sickness
just as i have
they've experienced disappointment
sadness loss grief
which has been painful for them just like i have it's been painful for me
this this person is an object of affection
of others they are cared for they're loved they're
appreciated they're a friend
a child to someone maybe a parent to someone a sibling of
someone a partner to someone
and they care for others
they have hopes and dreams they delight and laugh
they cherish their loved ones their happiness
they've experienced both joy love gladness
delight and sadness and sorrow pain and disappointment
just like you have
their inner life is just as complex and compelling
as yours is to you
they want to be seen respected loved cared for happy and not suffering
they are not so different from you
feeling the sense of connection to this
person a heart connection
maybe there are things similar about the two of you you don't know
maybe they like the same vegetable you like or the same fruit or flavor of ice cream
imagine both of you discovering that your imagination
and sharing relishing [Music] this favorite food together
and for the purpose of this practice it's okay to use our imagination
it's a skillful means to use our
imagination to perhaps imagine
[Music] some difficulty some sadness some
challenge in their life which you know which you have
experienced firsthand
and you know how difficult it is it could be an illness
or grief or loss relationship challenge financial
work whatever it might be it's okay
knowing that they have challenges just like you and just a sense
have a sense of connection
what if it happened that their sorrow happened to be one way they've
had suffering experience suffering similar to yours who knows
or you can imagine some other form of challenge or sorrow
difficulty you know they have it we all do as human beings
and feeling just as you would how painful it would be for you to
experience this challenge this loss this illness the sorrow
and feeling your connection this common humanity
just as i want to be free from sorrow and pain
i wish you i wish you freedom
from the sorrow from this pain from this challenge
whatever it is you're experiencing
just as i wish to have ease
and freedom in the midst of my challenge
i wish you ease in the midst of yours
it's okay to use your imagination to connect
this person just like you pain sorrow difficulty
emotional or physical difficulty
you connect with
and wishing the meas
in the midst of it from it may you have peace may you have ease
may you be free from this suffering
sorrow
as if each out breath that you breathe out brings them solace and comfort
you can connect with your breath and the
phrases if you wish of compassion for this person
may you be free
may you have peace
may you be free from pain
you have ease
noticing as one that as you expand
your heart and care compassion [Music] for this neutral person
there can be a sense of soothing and calm [Music]
grace and beauty shining through your own heart
sense of peace and ease
and this cultivation of compassion
that you experience
and for the last moments of this practice period
holding yourself in compassion for whatever arose or did not arise
maybe the opposite arose or nothing arose it's okay it's okay hold yourself with care
compassion and love you tried you showed up you did your
best
and whatever happened distraction sleepiness whatever else
it's not entirely up to you so appreciate yourself
for having showed up or having tried or having explored
planting planting seeds trust you have planted seeds
that will flower later when you least expect them
thank you thank you for your practice everyone
so this can be both a lovely practice
practicing compassion cultivating our hearts and compassion for a neutral person
it can also be complicated can also be flat it can be so many different
things so whatever came up for you is okay trust that you're exploring you're
learning and would love to hear from you if you'd like to raise your hand
your physical hand i'm sorry not physical and if you do that i won't see your zoom hand if you go to reactions
under reactions there's ray's hand or you can type your reflections in chat
happy to take what came up for you what this was like
and their questions comments complaints confusions
it's all welcome
and as you share your reflection your question with the community know that you're supporting you're
supporting others by sharing your question or your wisdom
or what happened for you
especially if you haven't shared in a while would love to hear from you
wherever
anika please or if i'm saying your name right yeah
annika monica hi um yeah haven't shared ever so let's try
it um um what came up for me actually was uh
i was going with the visualization for like a third of the meditation maybe and
then um there was just a wave of anxiety
um manifesting physically which has just been something
[Music] that's been around in my body for a few weeks now
um and so you know i was changing around positions and everything and um
[Music] yeah i actually ended up sort of just being barely there
with the meditation um [Music] yeah i felt like that might be worth
sharing yeah yeah absolutely i'm glad you shared that uh anika
and here's an invitation if that arises again and
it sounds like the anxiety the restlessness is something that you said has been coming up for a
while so um oh
yes i just opened chat i forgot to do that um um so it sounds like it's been something
that's been coming up and of course when your mind right now settles and there's quiet
then that pattern that's been present for a while it shows up again oh
here you are here you are dear friend anxiety restlessness i see you
i see you so it's quite normal uh if it's been going on for a
while for it to come up in this way so what i suggest is to then
turn the compassion to yourself because you're the one in that moment
who's suffering and having a challenge of anxiety and restlessness it's not pleasant right
so turn the compassion even though the guidance supposedly is with the with the
um uh person with the neutral person feel free to turn it turn it
to where it's needed in this moment oh i'm the one suffering right now so the practice can become
self-compassion great practice self-compassion fantastic
so you and everybody else absolutely has license in fact you're invited to do
that you're encouraged to do that incident no i'm not supposed to have compassion for myself i'm supposed to have it for
this other person like it's okay just turn it as long as you're practicing compassion
mental loving kindness you're at the right place you're in perfect company so i
appreciate you bringing this question up and i see appreciation
in chat many actually some people have sent the appreciations to you to me direct message to me but know that there
have been multiple appreciations for you raising that so does that make sense annika
yeah do you actually um put anxiety under the category of like restlessness and worry
as far as like hindrances yeah okay yeah that does make sense
thank you yeah you're welcome and again always feel free you and everyone else you can
just turn it and hold it oh this is hard sweetie this is hard this is challenging right
now it's okay it's okay may you be free may you have peace in the midst of this
restlessness worry this anxiety may you have ease with it yeah
great thank you
and i had uh let's see chris die like to raise your
hand but you but somehow it's not working for you i'm going to ask you to unmute yourself there you go
thank you actually i'm not sure where it's at um yeah i find that the
[Music] compassion practice can often be quite emotional for me and today was
another example of that uh if i if i really kind of connect with
the practice i kind of feel it in my chest and sometimes i can become quite tearful
as well and today i think i think it's when i i i realize
that sometimes i really don't show compassion for other people
whose lives i don't have much insight into you know and and then when i realized
that i've once that i've done that you know i yeah it really it's incredibly
eye-opening um so it's both a positive thing because i'm like oh yeah okay i recognize that
i'm doing that and hopefully i can i can use that in my day-to-day life but also you know
a little bit of shame that that happened um yeah that i that i forgot well
i didn't forget i think it's easy to say oh we don't know what people are going through everyone's got a lot on
but to like truly believe that and connect with that and treat people as such i think is a
is a whole other step so yeah it's it's a good practice but i definitely get emotional sometimes
yeah thank you for sharing that i'm gonna many things you raised i'm gonna comment
on a couple of them because i think it's very important one is as you're saying can be an emotional
practice for you it's okay tears are fine it's perfectly fine in fact when um
i teach um uh retreats on compassion and unloving kindness specifically
and um and people come say oh i'm just crying in the hall and i'm practicing and crying and and what i
and other teachers say it's okay it's this is the place for it let it move through these are the tear
tears of healing tears of healing they need to be expressed so holding them back in fact
being able to cry is beautiful it's lovely this tenderness of heart so don't
shy away from it it's okay befriend befriend the tears
there's strength in the the tears and the tenderness there's a lot of strength
and there's so many people who say oh i wish i could cry i wish i could feel the tenderness so enjoy that
appreciate the tenderness of your heart krista it's not a problem and and then as you were saying oh wow
that's connecting with this um sense of other people
their challenges and really being able to connect with that again lovely beautiful and when self-judgment
comes in through shame like you should be able to do this better
it's like oh right it's it's it's it's the pattern of self-judgment
showing up in different ways in different areas like no this is a cultivation here i am i'm
cultivating it it's and it's hard for me to i and then have compassion for your dear self
you're overwhelmed with your own life and so here you are here you are you've
shown up to cultivate this beautiful gift to share with others so thank you so much
thank you yeah so so let's
practice i like to invite us in small groups and and tonight i think it'll be quite
special because you can also be each other's neutral people
you you know you all have challenges in each other's life so holding each other
with a sense of care and and meta and compassion
these dear beings from across the world who are holding you and you're holding
them in in challenge so maybe start with 30 seconds of just wordless wordless meta 30 second
of wordless compassion for each other just holding each other's presence knowing that you all have challenges and
then if you like to share for a few words you might be shorter tonight because we had more comments so um i'll create the
rooms and i hope you stay to participate it's such an important part of our
humanity to connect in this way in these small supportive groups and practice together
so here we go rooms are open okay everyone the rooms are closed we're
back and maybe we'll just take one quick reflection
about how the practice was in groups for you anybody would like to
quickly share and chat or raise your hand just take one reflection
what was it like
lisa i see you're reaching for did i say that right no okay
any takers comforting thank you jerry comforting nice and we have emily
okay emily here you go and just to share that it felt
comforting and kind of validating to talk about just how time both feels just this
feeling of oh another friday and the last year and how weird time feels right now and it was just
nice to hear that everyone else could relate to that it's like okay i'm not crazy this is really weird
so yeah yep yes you said it just like me just like
me it's this this common humanity just like me this this is weird
yeah yeah and here we are for each other thank you for sharing that i really appreciate it and thank you all
for showing up and practicing both for your own sake and the sake of
all those whose lives you touch including the people in this zoo room may all beings be
safe happy healthy and have ease may all beings be free including
[Music] ourselves thank you all thank you so so much