so welcome
welcome a really warm welcome to
everybody
wherever you might be and
whatever situation you might find
yourself in as you're listening to this
or watching it just the case may be
so i want to mention that a
book just came out just got published
called
be the refuge the subtitle
raising the voices of asian american
buddhists
it's written by the amazingly talented
chenzing han
and i know trenzying and i know
a lot of work went into writing this
book and pulling it all together
and on sunday afternoon february 28th
imc is sponsoring an event to discuss
the book
so everybody's invited to that and this
book is a part
memoir from chenzing
as well as it's a result of her research
and to the experience of asian american
buddhists and it's
quite touching so i can recommend this
book
and of course with the title of be the
refuge
um she discusses this or you know in
this
in the book and without giving away the
details of the book i'll say that
a person in the book
describes how they were to turn their
practice
toward being a refuge for others
there such a beautiful idea i think this
this kind of this act of generosity this
act of
recognizing the impact that we have on
others and this wish
to be a refuge for others
in some ways maybe that kind of
summarizes the buddhist practice
is to find a way in which we can be a
support for everybody
in some kind of way but in the book this
individual talks about creating a
space where people feel calm and
positive in a way that they are
taking care of each other rather than
creating
agitation sometimes
there's this um bonding through
mutual outrage i think uh kim allen i
heard her say that
and i recognized that there certainly
have been times in my life
when you know my friends were like yeah
and can you believe this
also and that oh my gosh and not only
that this and then we just kind of
rattle ourselves up more and more
but what is it to create a space where
people feel calm
and positive not by being pollyanna and
not
by denying what's happening
but to recognize that tremendous value
is there by
not creating conditions that makes
people more
agitated or more feeling
ill at ease or more worried or
anxious or whatever it might be
but to be a refuge in a way that to
create a space either
literal or metaphorically create a space
where people can feel
some well-being some calm and
positivity
and then in chenzine's book
this individual also talks about one way
to
be a refuge is to create communities
that are refuges for others
where people can find comfort and
well-being
and sometimes that's through affinity
groups
people coming together that maybe look
similar
or have similar beliefs or have
similar backgrounds similar ethnicities
similar experiences
similar preferences whatever it might be
similar ages so affinity groups
is one way we can help create a refuge
to help be a refuge is to either
create communities that perhaps don't
exist or if they do exist to show up in
a way
and that we can convert them into a
place that is a refuge
and of course it's not only affinity
groups there's all kinds of
kalianamita groups good spiritual
friends
and people that live in this similar
geographical area that before covid
would meet in person
to talk about the drama i'm imagining
many of them
are meeting online now
and for some of these programs we have
at imc we
kind of try to facilitate a little bit
uh the creation of home
groups which are kind of like this
kaliana meta groups these ideas
small community where people can
practice together and
discuss and explore different topics
and of course there's even these when
we're on the
zoom meetings i know for some teachings
that we do here at imc
with some of the programs that are on
zoom
we break people up into breakout groups
you know maybe
two three four five six people and those
of course are also
kind of a little bit of a community
and what would it be like if we had this
idea that
kind of to be a refuge is to help
create a community wherever we might
find ourselves
where people can feel safe they can feel
some comfort and some ease
for us to have this movement of the
heart
to be inclusive and to be generous
with our attention and our time
so chenzinghan she describes this in her
book
be the refuge raising the voices of
asian american buddhists
there's all kinds of great stuff in that
book that's
but also we can look to see what do the
suit does have to say
what does it mean to be a refuge
for others we often associate this word
refuge with taking refuge
take refuge in the buddha dharma and the
sangha
not so much this idea of be a refuge
and there's a suta that's uh in the poly
canon
and it has a parallel that was also
preserved in chinese
and it talks about this idea of being a
refuge and
as is often the case or maybe even
always the case
that when there's a suta that's in the
poly canon and there's a parallel that's
got preserved in chinese
that there's differences between them
and so i'll be focusing on what
the part that's the same uh between
these two sutas
so in this suta the buddha says
to a brahmana it is
here brahman that you should bathe
to make yourself a refuge for all
beings it is here brahman that you
should bathe
to make yourself a refuge for all beings
so maybe we can unpack this a little bit
what is the buddha talking about
about bathing and making oneself a
refuge
so maybe i'll i'm start by saying this
expression make yourself a refuge
if um we look at the poly i can't read
chinese so i'm not sure exactly what it
says in the chinese but
for a look at the pali the translation
maybe more literally would be make
yourself
a place of safety or
make yourself make a sanctuary or
something like that
it's not the same word refuge
saurona that we um when we take refuge
in the buddha dharma sangha
but a number of english translators have
used this word
refuge and i rather like it so
this idea of
making yourself a refuge for all beings
so this idea of bathing comes
from the context of the suta as you
might imagine
so in the suta the buddha is with some
monastics and he sees in the distance
that there's a brahman
so a brahmin at this time and in this
setting
and this is um we could think of as a
priest
for the dominant religious tradition
at that time in ancient india so
somebody who was a
not only a practitioner but somebody who
was
um an upholder maybe we could say of the
tradition of the dominant religious
tradition at that time
which we might call brahmanism
and so the buddha
is with some monastics and he sees this
brahman
in the distance that's approaching him
and knowing that the brahman will
overhear
what the buddha is about to say the
buddha begins his talk
directed to his monastics but also kind
of directed towards this brahman
and he says that there are these
16 different types of impurities or
defilements in the mind
we can think of this impurities or
defilements we could think of this as
um one way that i is uh
i find helpful to think about that or
things that are extra like we don't need
them
they're not helpful and so for me that's
one way i like to think about it
defilement and impurity sometimes has
this
feeling of this puritanical
way of tightness or something like that
to some of the
associations we might have with these
words
i don't know if that was the
associations that were
um with these words in ancient india
but i like this idea of things that are
extra and that we don't need them
and that gives these 16
i'll go through this list don't worry
i'm not going to unpack them all or
anything like this but just to give you
a sense
what are these uh this list
covetousness and unrighteous greed
it will anger resentment
offensiveness contempt envy
stinginess deceit fraud
obstinacy aggression conceit
arrogance vanity and negligence
so we might um
summarize perhaps this uh list of 16
as maybe greediness of self selfishness
or
i want more or i need more
or maybe it's aversion a will
hostility kind of like get away from me
or get this away from me
or maybe also um this self-assertion or
a conceit
you might also think of it like don't
you know who i am
kind of thinking and i would say with
the exception maybe that last one
negligence
negligence is just maybe not
applying ourselves or not being
careful or attentive or something like
this so maybe the first
15 we might summarize
and you might recognize this idea of i
want more i need more
or get this away from me or
don't you know who i am
and these are manifestations of greed
hatred and delusion
some of the core foundational
defilements
but the way that um the buddha is using
these
the words that he's using right he's not
talking about you know just the core
fundamental ones
with uh some of these words of
aggression
or stinginess or envy or
arrogance vanity using some of these
words
there are some of the ones that are um
maybe we might think well these are just
minor manifestations
of some of these deeper
things that are extra defilements
impurities
but um i appreciate what niapanica tara
who is a who was
a an elder in this tradition like his
book the heart of buddhist meditation
was one of the first and pretty
foundational books
written in english came out in the mid
60s
about vapasana practice
and he writes how much more pleasant
and harmonious will be human
relations individual and communal
if there is less pettiness and
peevishness and fewer vanities and
jealousies and
less self-assertiveness and words and
deeds
so that was kind of one his way when
he's looked at this list of 16 thinking
like
it would just be so much easier to get
along with other people
whether it's just one other people or
whether we're in a group
if there's less of these things these um
16 different qualities and we also might
consider
that there is a connection between these
qualities and
the deeper roots of greed hatred and
delusion
and so to work with where they show up
and maybe what we might consider
minor or we might consider surface level
to work with them and how they
get expressed in our daily lives is
really a way
in which to work with the the deeper
ones
the the foundational the root
defilements
so in the buddha in the suta he can he
can
um he continues after talking about this
list of 16 defilements he says if you
know it's a defilement abandon it
seems so straightforward right makes it
sound easy
of course it's not easy but this is why
we have a meditation practice
and why we have a buddhist practice not
just meditation but all of them
all of the elements of the eightfold
path or the gradual training
that is to recognize if you know it's a
defilement if you know
that this is something that's extra
that's not
helpful that doesn't lead to greater
freedom but instead
leads to less freedom and to some
suffering
abandon it so what are some ways in
which we can
lessen the attachment the clinging the
stickiness
of some of these expressions
of these of greed hatred and delusion
so if you know it's a defilement
sometimes we don't know
sometimes these are habits of mine
sometimes we're so used to thinking
well of course i'm
filled with arrogance because everybody
else is
an idiot what do they know or i don't
know maybe that's an exaggeration but
are there some ways that maybe we
weren't quite considering that
they were impediments to greater freedom
and greater ease
and then the buddha in the suta
continues and
he goes with a describing brahma vahreh
practice
probably many of you if not all of you
are familiar with this practice it
begins with
imbuing the mind with loving kindness
this is good will respect
benevolence care friendliness
love for others
and oneself not just others and oneself
and the way
love and kindness practice is described
in the suit does which is a little bit
different than
how we practice it like when i do happy
hour
i'm relying more on the way
living kindness practice is described in
the commentaries so a little bit
after the time of the suit does but in
the suit does is to
imbue the mind with loving kindness this
warm-heartedness if you will
and then to pervade it in ten directions
four directions we can think of as the
cardinal north south east west
and then four directions are the
intermediate
northwest southwest northeast southeast
and then the two directions above and
below
all directions
so to imbue the mind with loving
kindness
and then pervade ten directions
with this warm-heartedness
and then with a mind that is boundless
exalted
immeasurable and well-developed
i find myself smiling when i'm talking
about this because
sometimes right if we have this loving
kindness practice and
we're able to really
feel fill the heart and mind with this
good will
and to be sending it out and
including ourselves with it
that is such a way in which we can have
in which we are not expressing
aggression or stinginess or deceit or
contempt or resentment
all these other things that are lit in
this list of 16.
so in the suit that's not clear if the
buddha is saying first
abandon these 16 defilements and then
practice the brahma vaharas
or its and practice the brahma viharas
or maybe we might even understand it
that practicing the brahma vaharas
is a way in which we can help us to
abandon
some of these sixteen qualities
so many of you know the brahma vahrehs i
first started talking about
loving-kindness
but it also includes compassion
sympathetic joy and equanimity
there's those four movements of the
heart
we might say i won't go into detail
about what that is
but this just a recognition that
it's a sense in which there's
um maybe a sense of fullness
or a sense of um maybe some safety and
some
that itself can be a refuge
so then this uh then the
buddha and the brahmana start discussing
bathing and purification
so the buddha says
brahman so now he's directing his
attention to the brahm and maybe by this
time the
brahmana has walked there and has sat
down that's not explicit but that's
what's happening in my mind
is that now the brahmana is
sitting with the monastics and is
listening to what the buddha has to say
and the buddha says brahman this is what
is called
bathing the inner mind instead of
bathing the outer body so the
buddha is making a real distinction to
purify cleanse remove what's extra
from the mind making that's really
different
than purifying cleansing removing what's
extra on the body
the external body and the bon
the brahman replies by saying go to mam
you should go to the bahuka river to
bathe
because one who bathes in the bahuka
river becomes purified
and eliminates all evil
so we can we learn that this brahmana
was a person who
their practice their spiritual practice
was to bathe
in particular rivers and sacred rivers
with the belief
that that didn't matter so much what
actions you did
as long as you included the action of
bathing in the river and then
all the all the bad
or inappropriate unskillful unwholesome
everything that you had done
would just be washed away
that may be as a as a little aside i'll
say
there's a nether suta it's um
from the terry gata some of you might be
familiar this
is the verses from the nuns
and there's um some there's a nun
right now her name escapes me i think
it's puneka
who um also encounters a brahman who has
this
practice that just um
as long as you bathe in the right rivers
you can do whatever you want
and i'm i'm chuckling because uh the nun
says to the brahmin
something like this i'm paraphrasing
well if that were true
then wouldn't all the turtles and the
fish and
the crocodiles and serpents wouldn't
they
all be perfectly pure and if that were
true
wouldn't all your good deeds also be
washed away so i appreciate very much
that this
nun wasn't speaking truth to power here
this brahman but getting back to this
suta
where um the buddha is speaking to this
brahmana about
there's to do with this inner cleansing
this inner
bathing if you will rather than outer
and then the buddha says to
inverse
for the pure in heart and i looked at
the poly it's
it's this word is heart as opposed to
mind
which is um i don't know it's a
beautiful thing actually
to think about having this pure of heart
maybe with the
loving-kindness practice as a way that
helps us to have this
purity of heart or the brahma of our
practice
for the pure in heart it's always the
spring
festival or the sabbath so the buddha is
saying
we don't have to wait for special days
that we go bathe in the river to be
cleansed of
things that wrong doing if we are
pure of heart then every day is a
special day
for the pure in heart and clean of deed
their vows will
always be fulfilled we don't have to go
bathe in the river and then
that buddha says it is here brahman
that you should bathe to make yourself a
refuge
for all beings it is here
that is abandoning those defilements and
practicing loving-kindness
which maybe isn't a surprise for any of
us
the part of the buddhist practice is
these two
movements of the heart to movements of
the mind
that allow us to show up for others
to create safety for others to be a
sanctuary for others
also points to this idea that behaving
ethically is
much more than just following the
precepts
but also to notice any contempt or
domineering or arrogance that we might
have
and for us to think about that what are
some ways we might create
safe spaces for others
create safe communities or if we find
ourselves
as part of a community how can we
support
the that community to be a place that's
inclusive
that honors and recognizes and respects
everybody from whatever background
they have however they're showing up
and then maybe i'll close with this
um last
an excerpt from yet one more suta
that's this verse where the buddha says
one whose mind all day and night takes
delight in harmlessness who has loving
kindness for all beings
for them there is no there is antigone
antagonism with none
i'll say that again one whose mind all
day and night takes delight
in harmlessness who has loving kindness
for all beings
for them there is antagonism
with none that is
we can be a refuge for others
thank you