um welcome everyone i'm joining you from south
africa my name is nolita to be specific i'm joining you from johannesburg
and it is evening here so good morning good day good evening
wherever you're joining us from i really appreciate your presence here
gives me an opportunity to reflect on this practice and these
teachings aimed for our liberation
so we starting with a guided practice so you can find
the posture that best supports you
i'm just taking your time to find that posture
the intention is to be a lot awake and yet relaxed
bringing the attention to the body noticing how the body is
welcoming this body as it is
noticing the solidity of the body on the chair the cushion
spine is straight neck is long
the head is balanced at the top of the neck it's helpful
to tilt your chin towards the chest
it allows for an opening where the top of the neck meets with a
skull that allows for easy flow of energy
the hands rest on the left
if you move your lower back just a little bit towards the belly
you will notice the lifting of the upper body
opening of the chest area
and shoulders easily relax without movement of the lower back
moving towards the belly
softening the face dropping the jaw
allows for release of tension enhancing a sense of relaxation
away of the whole body release the body weight into the chair
of the cushion and noticing the pressure
where the part meets with the chair or the cushion
if you are on a chair notice the sensations in the soles of your feet
where your feet meet with earth
noticing the movement of the breath
resting your attention with the breath
taking your time to find a good posture
upright and yet relaxed awake and alert
can be helpful at the beginning of your seating to take a few long deep breaths in
we're allowing the breath to return to its normal review
we will use the breath as a place of anchoring our attention
whenever the mind goes away gets lost in thought
when we're not as that we bring back the attention to rest on the breathing
you
noticing where the breath is most felt
could be other nostrils as you breathe in the coolness of the air
as you breathe out warm air
is experienced
or it could be with the expansion of the chest
and the contraction of the chest as you breathe in
and breathing out oh it's the rise and the fall of the
belly just take your time and see
of those three places where is breath most experienced
then let your attention pressed three
mind will go away past or to the future
we don't make a problem out of that this practice is about returning
bring back the attention to the body
resting the attention and the breathing
can be helpful to make a soft mental note
that goes breathing in breathing out
putting in
bringing out
as the mind settles here with a breath we can release
the mental motive
we continue to up the rest of this setting to bring the mind back
allow the mind to rest the breathing
noticing how the breath is
maybe long maybe short
maybe smooth it is staggered
whichever way it is that's just fine
as the mind settles
we open our awareness to any predominant experience
that is there [Music]
maybe sounds maybe sensations
quotes and notice
what is here
one can always return the attention to rest the breathing
in a moment i'm going to add another dimension
to this kind of practice
where we reflect on the theme of good will
generosity
aim is enhancement for well-being
when we cultivate goodwill cultivation verizon
so i invite you to remember how it has felt like
for someone to be generous to you
someone may have supported you in a way that just clicks in a positive
way for you
i'm just allowing the mind to linger on the actual feelings
how it has felt
to receive generosity from another
taking your time to be with the thought experience
staying with how it shows
allowing the body to relax with these
feelings to support this experience i invite you to bring
to mind someone who gladdens your heart
someone you're grateful to maybe respect
but her sense of respect brings joy to the heart
getting the feel of that cut feeling
joyful glad because of this person
adding to this experience i invite you to bring an image
of a good friend or a beloved pet
imagine this person or this pet giving you
full attention
get a sense of how it falls to be in a space like that
maybe there's a feeling of warmth
welcoming space a friendly space
carrying space
allowing yourself to be with these
feelings
now invite you to imagine opening up the space
and sharing it with other people
notice how it falls to open the space of warm space of
friendliness space that's welcoming
to as many people as you can imagine
i'm just noticing how it feels to do this
now you can release the images and focus
by bringing attention on how the body is just now
attentive to the body
away with the body at ease maybe
relaxed refreshed
so
six
as we come towards the end of our seating practices
i like to invite you to pause
and think about what is here now that you can appreciate that wasn't
there the beginning of our seating
and just know to round
[Music]
you