so i want to share with you some of my
reflections from this weekend and maybe
you'll permit me not to
give a dharma talk but maybe a dharma
chat
since um maybe they're not so well
formulated
but the topic is an important one and
one that
is i think seldom talked about
and maybe even there's some reluctance
to
teach it here in the united states
because that
the topic is um is easily something that
is off-putting for people or can come
across as something which is
maybe even dangerous
and uh that is the topic of strength
uh that the developing uh
inner strength and inner power even
through this practice of ours
that that is part of what we're doing
here in this practice
and i think much of the
way that the inside meditation practice
is taught in the modern west
maybe that's implicit but
it's explicitly more language of
acceptance
more language of just being with your
experience
not trying to fix your experience
the idea of personal agency that you
have some
control some power some uh
in urex practice is not really get
emphasized
and i think that sometimes maybe it's a
shortcoming that we don't do that and
that
really developing becoming strong people
is actually one of the benefits of
developing and practice
becoming a strong person that develops
strong inner
core or capacity of various kinds
and it's important because certainly we
wanted to have enough strength
to not succumb to our defilements not
succumb to greed hate and delusion
not to come to uh
unwholesome unhealthy fear
and one of the things that people are
can be afraid of
is they can be afraid of themselves
and uh and so certainly be afraid of
things out in the world
but they can be afraid of themselves
afraid of what they're going to say
what they're going to do what they're
going to think and what they're going to
feel
and so there's a kind of an avoidance of
really connecting here
because of this self fear that that can
exist
now uh but that and that self-fear then
also
what it does it can easily dampen uh
personal strength and in fact some
people are afraid of their strength
they're afraid that if they are strong
that they will
harm someone that they will
cause trouble for other people other
people be uncomfortable
that somehow they'll be seen as
conceited or seen as being
somehow assertive too much
in a way that's maybe considered
unacceptable in the scenes the situation
we're in
and uh and and then also sometimes this
fear of one's own strength can be
related to a fear
an idea that we don't really
have a full right to exist or we're not
really
worthy enough to be strong that somehow
we're diminished we're less than others
or
we should really what what's you know we
should really kind of
keep uh small stay small or stay
unnoticed or stay in the back row and
somehow diminish ourselves because to
not diminish ourselves
sometimes is socially disruptive for the
scene that we're in
and sometimes in some families and even
some cultures
that there's a preference for somehow
not being a little bit
self-effacing a little bit not assertive
and certainly that can be quite valuable
and at times of quite healthy and
appropriate
but it can lend itself for support
go along with a tendency for people to
be afraid of their own strength or
reluctant to embody it or engage it or
not to realize or appreciate that can be
developed
and grow some people are kind of looking
for
something that's going to fix them some
insight some experience something
that's going to be their savior from
their difficulties they have
and so they're kind of a little bit
looking outside of themselves
for a solution and and one of the things
about strength is strength and practice
develops
there's something that grows from the
inside out
that is a little bit has the effect of
of not solving problems not
providing an answer per se but we grow
in such a way
that like the snake that grows the skin
gets shed
the old skin gets shed and there's
something about cultivating developing
a strong inner strength or sense
of power or powers or strengths maybe in
the plural
that makes us grow and all things
just get shed they fall fall off us
rather than needing to be solved so to
spend too much time
trying to solve problems sometimes as a
dead end
solve our inner turmoils and challenges
sometimes it's actually more useful to
develop a strength
so for example a strength in mindfulness
a strength and concentration
as strength and ethics integrity a
strength in
um in patience and strength in telling
the truth and being truthful to oneself
or maybe to others
as really a strength of presence really
to
and sometimes that can be done
physically in fact
so much of what can be developed in
practice develops
uh stronger develops more more more
effectively
if there's a kind of embodied
association or embodied
connection to actually doing this
embodied mindfulness embodied
presence in body truth
so clearly the buddha wanted people to
be strong
and buddhist practice develops inner
strength
and as i said ideally we become stronger
than our defilements
so we don't cause problems in the world
or problems for ourselves
and some of the language that buddha
used in his teachings
are words that i associate with strength
the words like ardency
with practice in an ardent way to
um the word that's often translated as
effort
which kind of the word effort is a fine
word
but it's kind of a neutral neutral word
just effort it doesn't carry any
strength in it and the word that's often
translated as effort is viria
and viria probably more appropriately
should be translated as something like
courageous effort that the word vira
that viri is part of
is a word for hero i've been told that
in modern india
it's the word for a soldier and so
a heroic effort i think is sometimes the
way it's translated in uh
maybe in tibetan buddhism where they use
the word hero that
in related terms so
the idea of courageous effort and
and then also the word power itself that
is used and um
and as people develop in freedom in
buddhism
greater freedom including a freedom from
conceit
they are frequently depicted as becoming
powerful
language and symbolism of mature
practitioners is often with
represented by images of power
so for example there's a delightful suta
where someone who develops
some degree of freedom initial degree of
freedom
together with the seven five seven
powers of awakening seven factors of
awakening
is described as be having a great self
a large self and um it's a little bit
surprising to hear this language of self
use in such a definitive way
a great self a large self and that great
self enlarged self
is uh represented or is the
analogy for it is a kind of a great
mythic being
that develops that grows in the great
himalayan mountains
that's a it's kind of a river spirit a
river serpent
and uh and so it's called the naga
and in this case naga means many things
but one of the things these river spirit
serpents and that a person a person
develops some initial
taste of freedom becomes one of these
great
nagas of with uh who are
of a great self and a large self
expansive self is one translation
the um and uh one of the also delightful
uh expressions of the power the strength
that a
practitioner can have is in what's
called the lion's roar
it was something that the people the
time of the buddha the buddha did this
and other people did it as well they
would declare
their full awakening when someone came
and told the buddha that they had
then now they were fully awakened
that was referred to their lions roar
and i don't know if you've ever been
close to a lion that roared
but i have fortunately it for me
at the zoo maybe not fortunately for the
lion
but i was probably only standing only
four or five feet away from the lion
and with bars between us
and the roar that it uh directed in my
direction
was one that commanded a tremendous
amount of respect
it had felt i had a primordial feeling
that the like the whole bowels of the
earth were kind of roaring at me and
and uh i thought the only respectful the
only proper thing to do with
that roar was to walk away
so the lions roar not that we're
supposed to walk away from in lines
enlightened people but it's a it's a
expression that conveys
great confidence and great strength
so so one of the things that
are called powers in buddhism and here
we see the powers are not meant to be
powers that we on other people
but rather inner capacities that we have
the five powers are the five faculties
when they're strong
and these are faith or confidence to
have a
conf the power of confidence of faith
uh the power of this courageous effort
that the courageous effort has now
become something a real strength that we
carry with us
the power of mindfulness the power of
samadhi
usually translate as concentration and
the power of wisdom
what a great power to have ways to be
wise in a way that has a real strength
that we carry with us
another place we seek i associate with
powers what's called the
four resolves and uh
the holy word is aditana which is a
means could almost more literally try to
be translated
in english as taking a stand
the etymology of the word and but
usually as resolves
and and so what we have resolved for is
what there's a power there's a strength
behind us in doing it
and um and so these are also interesting
lists
um again it's not power over others
so it's um the first one
resolve is not neglecting wisdom
the second one is um
is um
preserving protecting the truth
the third is cultivating the capacity to
let go
to relinquish and the fourth is to
train in peace train peacefully train to
become more peaceful
to so to develop a strength of being
peaceful
sometimes we don't associate i think
power and peacefulness together it's
almost like peacefulness is is an
alternative to being powerful but the
power the resolve of
being peaceful so
living in a confident committed and
dignified
fashion is are some of the associations
with this developing this power this
capacity to be
and so there's not in itself if there's
not a there's a there's
it doesn't look from the outside like
some developed practitioner is
self-effacing
at least not in how they carry and hold
themselves
but it is in terms of not having any
conceit or arrogance
letting go of being self-centered at the
same time as being
strongly centered
no egotistical center but a strong
centered in our lived vital experience
of being
here and present
one of the ways we might understand this
is to live in a manner where there's no
need to apologize for ourselves
i think there's a strong tendency in in
the united states for
some people to constantly want to say
they're sorry to apologize to
to kind of diminish themselves for
exerting themselves or being even being
and i think that to live in a way that
we don't have to apologize
not regularly of course not regularly
not as a policy not as a
second nature thing to always feel sorry
or apologize
and the way to do that in buddhism is to
live
what the buddha called the blameless
life a
life the blamelessness that is meant to
bring a certain kind of joy
the strength of a blameless life and
this is to live a life
that adheres to the precepts to not
harm people not intentionally be
involved in causing hurt or harm through
killing and stealing and sexual
misconduct and lying and
and using intoxicants and to
really have confidence that one is
living this way
um the end
we end up living a life we don't
apologize for ourselves
to be blameless and i don't think it's
second nature for many of the people
here in this country
but it's uh but if you can live that way
then you're encouraged to feel the joy
of that
the joy and the power of a blameless
life an unapologetic life
in the dhammapada there's
wonderful descriptions of of strong
people
that they don't use the word strong but
i think we can substitute it
reasonably enough and there's a whole
chapter called the brahman
the brahmanas were kind of the priests
of the brahmanical religion
they're also a hereditary role so there
were families that were brahmanical
families
and they thought of themselves as being
the top
class in society and uh
the dominant class and often they were
had a lot of authority sometimes and
owned a lot of land had a lot of wealth
and uh they're responsible for the
religious rituals of the brahmanical
religion
and there was often a kind of not just
in buddhism but in
other areas of india as well a kind of
jockeying for
position or um you know
but who was it really should be dominant
or kind of kind of critique of the
dominance of the brahmanas
and the buddha he did this by
redefining what it means to be a
brahmana
and he defined a brahman as someone who
has some degree of spiritual awakening
and so so here are some examples of
these
ways which he says this this is a verse
from the dhammapada
who has no clinging who has
nothing i call the brahmana
so at first no clinging having nothing
and that doesn't really seem
like a situation of power or strength or
you know important class of people in
society or someone someone to revere or
something who has no clinging who has
nothing
i call the brahmana whoever
is most excellent a bull
a hero a great sage a
conqueror free of craving cleansed
awakened i call a brahmana so here now
that's all these are all synonyms for
the same person all kind of describing
the same kind of person
hey or they're talking about excellence
a bull which is a powerful
uh animal and a hero which has
strength to it and a conqueror
now this can be quite off-putting for
many people in the west to have these
kind of masculine
seeming words or concepts associated
with it
but but there is clearly a show
associated with
non-clinging freedom from craving inner
cleanliness
it's not an assertiveness or a dominance
the idea of conquering being a conqueror
is really becoming conqueror of
one's own defilements one's own inner
attachments and clinging one conquers
oneself in a sense
not others so we get this
clear example in other verses
that this power strength of a
practitioner is not meant to be
over other people it's really over
themselves in these verses
having given up violence towards beings
both
timid and strong whoever neither kills
or causes others to kill i call
a brahmana i call i say
is strong whoever is not adversarial
among those who are
peaceful among those who are violent not
clinging among those who cling
i call a brahmana whoever lets passion
hostility conceit and hypocrisy fall
away
like a mustard seed from the tip of an
all
i call a brahmana who speaks
what is true informative and not harsh
who gives offenses offense to no one
i call a brahmana
so for me in in these
these verses all this emphasis on
non-harming
is presented in a way that prevents a
real strength of people there's a
dedication a community this definitively
this is what a person is this idea of a
blameless life that doesn't cause harm
in any kind of way
to do that with strength and be able to
stand up and
in a dignified to be a dignified
confident way
to carry oneself in the world with
confidence
to no one sells well enough to know all
the forces of fear
self-belittlement self-fear
the ways that we self-criticize ourself
or
and and kind of become less than who we
are
and to learn to shed those to learn to
not have them
diminish us us so that our native
strength we don't we're not it's not
assertive strength
it's not like puffing ourselves up in
some arrogant macho way
but rather the native strength of who we
are
can be there in a simple natural
full way it's not we don't
we don't diminish it we don't
apologize for it we don't you know
hide it or hide from it that somehow
we're allowed to be
strong we're allowed to be present fully
embodied in here in a clear definitive
way we are worthy of that
in fact one of the the meaning for our
heart someone is fully awakened
literally means a worthy one and uh
i i kind of like to translate to
interpret that i mean
they're worthy of really being present
to being here and alive and full
so that one of the goals of buddhist
practice is to become fearless
and and part of that is to stop
undermining ourselves through fear
and the fear that i wanted to emphasize
today in this chat is
self fear how we are afraid of ourselves
and therefore diminish ourselves and
and kind of undermine our strength
so to do this it helps to take stock of
our fear
of how we're afraid of ourselves
including
our fear of being strong
this then allows us to address these
fears
and develop growing confidence in our
capacity to live intentionally without
harming
anyone including ourselves
so i hope that
these ideas that i've presented here
uh are meaningful enough for you for you
to reflect and consider
a little bit how it is that um
as a pro in what appropriate way
can you step up
and uh and allow for yourself
to have a native power native strength
of someone who metaphorically
stands their ground
speaks speaks freely and confidently
what they feel like they have to say can
talk honestly
can doesn't diminish themselves but just
as they're
allowed to be present and fully there
and
have a voice and show up and um
and that that is i think one of the
great
benefits from doing mindfulness practice
the mindfulness practice that helps us
to
let go of any force within us
that diminishes us that undermines our
native natural strength that's here
and in doing so um we might
end up looking like strong people
in the eyes of others but in our
in our own inner sense we won't
necessarily
feel that we are now strong
the inner sense is feeling now we're
free
and uh but to be free from the outside
will look as if we become strong
so i hope that you will think about
this and reflect on it and so hopefully
there's something of what i said today
that
will be useful for you and
i would love to meet each of you in your
strength
so thank you all very much