so hello on this monday morning welcome
and
this week we'll continue this series that are more based on the introduction
to mindfulness course that i teach and add something which um
for a week something that i ca on occasion i've added to the intro to meditation course
as one of the foundations of mindfulness one of the basic areas
and it has to do with can be called mindfulness of mind
or mindfulness of attitude and i'll talk more about that during the
dharma talk at the end of now but i would like to again use an analogy for the practice
this morning and that is um
if uh your technology your computer or something is
not working properly and you need to have it work or it's important for you that it works
it's possible to get tense trying to figure everything out and trying to make it work and
and and so the less it works the more more you
can't succeed the more tense it is perhaps and then you start feeling kind of lousy
feeling tense kind of miserable and headachy and then one reasonable or not
reasonable but maybe one common strategy at that point is to blame the technology for how
you're feeling and maybe then storm off to repair shop or
put the technology in the wastebasket and go get buy a new one or you know something but blame the technology for
how lousy you feel another strategy is to appreciate
that the tension that's building up in the shoulders the back the eyes the neck
is not inherent in the in the technology but in their relationship we have to it
whereas maybe we can't solve the technology problem we have
a lot of capacity to solve the tension problem
so if we're blinded by the technology and trying to solve it or fix it or how bad it is
we might not notice the tension and we might even blame the technology for how we're feeling
but the pathways of suffering goes through our reactivity our
relationship how we respond to something and that's
in the pathways of our lives that's where meditation sits it sits there
where we are relating responding reacting to what's happening
and and if we notice that oh the tension there's physical tension here
the tension is not in the technology it's not i don't know somewhere else it's just here and my shoulders and my jaws and my
eyes then we can take a moment maybe to close our eyes take a deep breath and relax and
soften we can take responsibility for how we're feeling the tension
the technology the computer is not going to take responsibility for that
the only person who can do that is yourself so part of meditation is to
place ourselves or stay close to that place that location where we can take
responsibility for our reaction our response
and not be not have the reaction the response the tension
somehow color how we what we're thinking about what we're focusing on
even if that is the meditation itself it's possible to get tense over how
meditation is going
so it's this morning it's about relaxing it's a very profound topic it can seem
superficial so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and maybe rocking back and forth a little bit forward and backwards side to side
partly a ritual of embodiment the rocking kind of you feel your body a
little bit more in certain places perhaps a little beginning of relaxing
and also helping you find center where your sitting bones are centered
where you're lined up your weight is balanced
and continuing the process of embodiment to take a few long slow deep breaths
and use that time to feel the body
the wide global awareness of body as you breathe in and as you breathe out
and letting your breathing return to normal and as you inhale
feel some part of your body that there's likely to be tension
and if there is then on the exhale relax that part of your body
relax in a relaxed way
breathing in breathing out relaxing
softening releasing
and then settling into your breathing just
feeling the inhales the exhales
and with kind of a feather touch very lightly
very gently without any ambition
as you breathe gently relax the exhales
gently relax around the inhales
almost like you're softening relaxing around the edges of where your body feels itself breathing
and if anything takes you away from your breathing thoughts feelings body sensations
see if what what you can relax
what will soften
and what might relax also is your attitude towards it
every opportunity for whatever you're aware of
gently feel your way into what can be softened
and relaxed feel your way to where the tension is
and relax in a relaxed way relaxed about not being able to
just holding the tension
and if there's no attention no pressure or tightness
return to the breathing breathing gently softly
what can be relaxed as you're sitting here
in the face chest belly in the mind
the hands the thighs what can be relaxed and softened
okay
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to see if you can relax some more what can soften in you
what can be released
what are you tightening around what are you holding on to
that for a few moments here you can put down let go of
and then to stay as relaxed as you can to turn your attention now
to the world of people around you that you might encounter today
and notice if any tension returns and if it does
can you relax again
in particular relaxing the heart
into from your heart to wish others well
to wish their day well their life
a few moments of well-wishing that continues the practice of relaxing
opening
removing barriers to our care and our attention to others
and as we go through the day may we keep these
wishes close by
may others be happy
may others be safe
may others be peaceful
may others be free
and may i avoid getting tense
and if i do let me relax
and with those wishes close by for this day
may your day go well
[Music]
uh
thank you so then i'll start over again
so um so today we start the week on
mindfulness of the mind and it's a continuation of these last four weeks
where we kind of explored the basic instructions in for mindfulness meditation that we teach
here at imc kind of exploring the territory first week was mindfulness of breathing
then mindfulness of of um body then emotions and thoughts
with each of those areas it's easy to have
get focused on those things so we're breathing and we're focusing on the breathing and the breathing seems like
what's most important or if there's pain especially we're focused on the pain in the body and that
seems the most important or for emotions the emotion seems really you know central key
juicy and so the attention is focusing on the emotion or on thinking
whatever it might be and that's part of what mindfulness is but in doing so
what's also important is the focus itself is the attention that's brought
how are we with the attention what attitude comes with the attention
and it's a little bit like driving a car with a windshield has been cleaned
and maybe to go on a long road trip on the freeway and ever so slowly
the windshield gets uh dirty and it happens very slowly
and now you don't see it building up and after a while you don't really realize that
still restraining to look out the windshield and it's a little hard and
and then maybe you stop to get gas and you clean your windshield and lo and behold wow
is it clear again and you realize that some of the tension that was building up was the difficulty of seeing
and but you hadn't realized it was difficult it happens to me sometimes with my
glasses when i wear them that they get dirty without me knowing it but i don't really notice sometimes
that things aren't quite right with trying to see because the focus is so much on the
driving and getting and being safely other cars we don't notice the seeing itself and how that's changed
or something like that so so the art of this is to be able to
step back or turn the attention around 180 degrees and notice the quality
of the attention we're bringing the the um the quality of the how we
practice and so there's always two things i like to say it's kind of
there's only two things there's what's happening and our relationship to what's happening
and so here we're going into the domain of how we're relating to whatever is happening whether it's within us or
around us and starting to notice um today
because today's the day we focus on relaxation is um are we tense
are we contracted are we tight are we pushing are we forceful are we resisting in a tense way
and and it's easy to justify that tension and tightness
because there are challenges the world brings and um
the um and so you know it's easy to see the
problems out there the problems with that thing that i'm focusing on and we have to fix that or do something
with it or get away from it not noticing that there is this tension that's building up
and uh and not wanting maybe even take responsibility for that tension
when we do mindfulness practice when we're focusing on the dharma
the way that we relate to what's happening is crucial essential the way that we the attitude we have the
the reaction we have to it the way in which we bring attention to bear on whatever we're doing
that is really part of the pathway of suffering and it's a part of the pathway where we
can take the most have the most
regular and ongoing responsibility or make the biggest difference
maybe it would be a little bit like um
well they'll say the analogy i used before that um if uh
we'll say it this way that if someone's angry with you say it's uh not
on a scale of one to ten it's not ten maybe it's a 5 or 4 or something
but it's still what they're angry about seems to you
not right and so you get upset and part of being upset is being tense
now the person who is angry you could perhaps
ask them politely to stop being angry you could perhaps insist that they have
to stop or you walk away or you could ask them let's talk about it
or you could uh shake them upside down and try to shake the anger out of them
all kinds of things your options you have and sometimes most of those might work
but sometimes they don't and so then the irritation the frustration can build and the tension
builds as well the we might say that person is making
me tense and that's you know in some kind of way there's there's a
there's a relationship between that person's anger and the tension you have but the tension is your contribution to
the situation uh that that goes into the anger goes into
your mind and maybe you have uh associations to what anger is a
frightening thing or anger before there's been injustice to you and hears you're getting the
person's angry and it reminds you of all the injustices you've had to suffer or or maybe there's fear
and the person's anger happens to angry happens to remind you of an angry bully when you're young
and so so all these reasons why the tension and the reactivity might arise
but that belongs to our inner world or in our life our preferences our
experience our memories our our our judgments our desire to protect ourselves all these
things come into play so there's pathways there's a loud angry
voice coming to us we receive it we hear it we hear it and we process it
we process it and we feel afraid we tense a certain way we process it and feel angry in return and it tends up in
a different way and so that's the pathway and then we react and we maybe get angry
back or we say something but if we can sit in that place where there's
a choice whether to be relaxed or tense whether to go with attention or allow it
or to relax then we're getting close to where the dharma is that we're taking that now
we're focusing on our contribution to our suffering
and that is one of the key things that mindfulness practice can do or the dharma does
is it we we're very keen to take responsibility to our own contribution to whatever is difficult
it doesn't deny that things need to be changed or fixed in the world but it um but at least we can always
look at what our contribution is to our suffering and the place that i'd like to recommend
today is how you've become tense how you've gotten contracted tight
pulled in the ways in which you kind of feel that compulsion to push and to do and
we're kind of restless and and and and so that
can maybe maybe be relaxed not relaxed and softened so the real
world issues are denied if there are real world issues but relax
so that we can come to them with the most wisdom and the most care and the from the best place that we know
the more tense we become most people don't respond with a lot of wisdom
don't respond with a lot of care and sometimes respond in ways that
actually detrimental there's a lot of justification kind of
unconscious for being tense there's a lot of justification or feeling that the
blame is in the other person or the situation and so that keeps the focus out there
in mindfulness of the mind we're turning the mind attention back to see what is
happening in our attitude our relationship and with ourselves and that we train ourselves to do that
keep looking there and see where the tension is see where the and then relax
and to get be given the instructions that to relax might seem superficial not
very profound not very you know spiritually
you know ultimate or valuable but it's uh
relax is a kind of a simplistic way
of referring to the deep letting go the deep opening up that spirituality buddhist spirituality
kind of moves to and so relaxing is part and parcel of this movement
towards deep freedom and so to take seriously the way we
become tense is bringing us into the territory of the world
where we contribute to our suffering and where we can contribute to our freedom from our suffering
so don't overlook your attention don't justify being tense
maybe occasionally it's okay but the opportunity in this practice
is to turn around take an honest look at it and see what can relax
and then once you're kind of relaxed then you can turn your attention around again to what needs to be
addressed so may uh the
bliss of relaxation the blessings of relaxation
be something that you study and work with today as you go through the day it's not a simplistic thing
it's a it has this is a deep root in so many profound areas of our life
and hopefully you'll enjoy it may your shoulders your belly your face your eyes your hands your heart and your
mind find more relaxation today thank you