so so hello and welcome everyone dear sangha
makes me happy to see you how nice what a lovely ritual we have to come together
from different parts of the world and practice together
so so for today's practice um
i'd like to invite us to consider the frame of reference of our practice
[Music] and there could be many frames in in our
study and practice and there's not a wrong frame
or a right frame just different frames to consider and
the frame i'd like to to invite for us to consider is the frame of
of our practice of our life as art
this open-ended co-creation arising in each moment
this sense of sense of beauty sense of grace
which happens to be the um frame of reference yes
turns out to be the domain of art art is often where beauty is is explored
so what if we consider our practice our exploration not so much
with a or this should happen etc etc but as with with the sense of art in the
making the sense of appreciating the beauty of our
dedication our practice even if there is fatigue even if there is pain
even if there is distractions in the mind what if we treated all of this as part
of this art this this this beautiful creation
and with this frame of reference of art if you would imagine for a moment
with music if you're a music if you are if there's a type of music that you like
um how you listen how you listen to the favorite music that you like
with your heart opening your heart opening your mind opening all your
senses to be impacted to listen with all your senses not just with your
ears but with your heart in the same way if you were looking at
a painting or a photograph or visual art really receiving paying attention
letting yourself be impacted this sense of beauty because the art isn't just what's on the wall or just the music
that you hear it's co-created in the moment with your
perception with your way of attending with your way with your openness
it's almost like the sound in the forest if a t a tree
falls if there's no one there to hear it did it make a sound
did it fall so here the sense of this art this art of your practice opening
your heart to what is arising the breath the body
awareness knowing wow
the most beautiful and profound instrument ever
that we take for granted this co-creation of knowing with various
stimuli that arise in the mind and the heart and the senses
our thoughts all of this so so if you are wondering especially if
you're new wondering okay what does that mean what what are the instructions what
am i going to do what the heck is what does she read it'll become clear
and i also say don't worry don't worry this practice
that i will guide and introduce for us to explore is a practice of deep listening it's
just the practice of deep listening you know how to do this you know how to do this
it's not new we've done it a million times it's a practice of listening it's a
practice of deep listening listening with your heart listening your fear with your heart and
if if cognitively like what it what does it mean to listen with my heart don't think
about it too much drop into the body don't think about it you you you know
what to do trust trust that you know what to do
i'll say one more thing before we start this practice and then to say that
this practice is particularly um appropriate this way of deep listening
to ourselves deep listening listening with our heart listening with our hearts
as if our minds our our awareness
our thoughts our bodies it's the beautiful symphonies this piece of art in the
making this way of listening with our hearts is a
particularly lovely practice to to bring in when
you're tired at the end of the day when maybe conjuring up say metta may you be safe
may you be happy or maybe when you wake up in the middle of the night sometimes
and it feels like the mind is tired but the heart is awake so listen just deeply
listen to the crickets to the sound of rain to the sound of silence
to the to whatever is arising listen with your heart so these are the simple instructions
listen with your heart and let's begin by settling in with the body
so let's arrive and settle
landing in this body
letting go for now just because we want to land and arrive
first to stabilize first
letting go
of memories of thought of thinking and just being simple in the body with
the breath
connecting let your heart connect with the breath
relaxing relaxing into the body nothing to do
this is not a doing practice just receive receive the breath
as if you're listening to the breath with your heart
listening to the sensations of the breath with your heart
not just the sound but the sensations deep listening
opening your heart sweet dear body what do you need right
now
asking the body and listening with your heart it's care in your heart
what is needed what do you need right now
just receiving the breath receiving the sensations
and if thoughts arise not listening with your head but
listening with your heart what is needed
dear thought i wonder why you're coming up in this moment let your heart listen
and if doubt arises or the various hindrances
maybe your heart maybe your heart smiles says oh dear is that so
is that really so [Music] like a caring
mother listening deep listening
your heart listening
your body to your breath
and with each breath
that is heard by your heart ah relaxing more
into your chair into your sit bones
at first we primarily listen right now to the breath and the body
just to arrive and to settle later we'll open up some more
listening to the symphony this music
that is my life in this moment unfolding my breath
these sensations this awareness this instrument of
knowing
both knowing and being known
your heart knowing
this instrument of perception
notice of dropping into your body opening the heart
listening listening to the body the breath and now opening up to the sounds
opening up to the sounds listening with your heart
is there a slightly different quality to listen with the heart
and with the head
don't think about it feel into the heart
sounds noises
they sound different when you hear when you listen with your heart
opening your heart with ease
don't try too hard
drop in let it flow through you
you know you know how to do this this listening with your heart
if the question arises am i doing this right what am i supposed to do yes
the answer is yes you are doing this right just listen just listen
that's all just listen
relax and listen with all your senses with your heart
listening 360 degrees all around
staying with all your senses within an open
open heart
the heart that cares listens
what is needed right now maybe nothing
maybe something just listen with your heart
like art let it be open-ended nothing needs to happen
the beauty the grace this moment just
opening our hearts and listening
and whatever is needed for you right now is the right thing
no right no wrong
opening opening to this magnificent spacious unfolding
with presence and heart
and your thoughts memories emotions
fairy's colors are arise listen with your heart
listen deeply with your heart what is needed right now
to be cared for to be listened to with your heart
do the sounds even noises back in the background do they sound different
transform somehow when you listen with your heart
not with your head
receiving the symphony of perceptions knowings
with care
are even judgments transformed if you listen with your heart
coming back listening to your body your breath
the sensations is your heart
what care is needed for this body this breath in this moment
and for the last moments can you imagine
with our hearts more than our minds in this moment
we can listen and listen to the sounds of the universe
this magnificent unfolding of life
that we are a part of not separate
not an island completely interconnected
listening with our hearts to these amazing notes
of interconnection and causes and conditions
that we're a part of receiving giving
may our hearts be open to listen
to what is needed
for ourselves and others to serve as best as we can
thank you for your practice dear sangha
so changing the settings now so you are
welcome to share in chat if you wish your observations
questions what's arising for you
you noticed or the benefit of all beings you can also raise your hand your zoom
hand your physical hand i may not see because i privacy only i see a
small strip and only my image goes to youtube richard
you could hear him yes oh since you started with music and
beauty i wanted to offer this suggest this comparison of
our small group discussions to jazz and improvisation
where you have one soloist establish a theme and everyone else building up on the prior
people prior musicians doing their variations on a thing
i love that yes yes the co-creation of the small group practice
yes may you make beautiful music together
today as you go into small groups and it's all beautiful it's all beautiful there is
sorrow suffering it's all part of the the sacredness of being part of this
life so it's all beautiful not to shy away and just try to share the good
barbra see your hand is up please
i also appreciated uh suggesting art and
feeling the senses uh before joining the sangha i
went out on the beach and it was a vision of of
gray tones it was it was no color it was raining and the clouds
were low and you couldn't see the lights across the bay it was just gray on gray
with little white birds skittering along the shore
and so it was wonderful to get out of the hat my head
and suddenly it was like oh that was it's our first rain how wonderful and it
was wonderful to observe it coming down [Music]
i feel moistened my heart feels moist and as you talk about these images and
the moistening thank you barbara it's lovely yeah getting out of our heads that's
that was the intention one invitation for this for this practice yeah
and maury christine says focusing on listening made my tinnitus louder
ah and fred says strangely it dampened mine
i love the the art of all these different experiences
right it's it's not one way and and you're welcome to raise your hand if anybody wants to talk more about that
uh yeah so interesting so so what i would and neil says yay for you fred
yay i second that yeah and and mario christine i'm sorry to hear that and what what i would recommend what i would
invite with uh the if you wanted to try this practice
is you know i was using listening as a metaphor um obviously and and maybe
what what to something to try if you wanted would be to bring
more actually more awareness to the heart center here as if you're really listening from
your heart from your heart center um and and try that and see if if you
know we might make a difference or maybe this is not the appropriate invitation for you it's
all good thank you for sharing that thank you appreciate hearing that
mark also says that was wonderful meditation thank you thank you i will
sit with it many times yeah sweet uh thank you merry christine
yeah and neil says he put me in a non-reactive place very equanimous
yeah thank you for that yeah it's lovely to hear that i feel a lot more
spacious and i realize actually my rate of speech is turned down just speaking a lot more
slowly just their sense of oh and one other thing i wanted to share with you guys it was interesting
noticing like the sounds the ambient sounds i don't know there was
uh you know maybe a truck driving and the sounds just felt or or there was a co
yeah there was a a motorbike racing by and and my heart opened up to
oh wow somebody's having the thrill of being on a motorbike it was not like oh somebody's making noise being on a motor
was like oh somebody's going to get through so just it was a very different way of of
listening and hearing he says thank you nikki the sangha is a trained building
community of truth and trust and now making music together a song of communal love
and abraham please
uh okay thanks um as you know some of you people know i'm very very deaf and my hearing aids
lately screwed up and i have to bring my hearing aids into my audio center to get them fixed up so i'm not sure i even
heard it i was just trying to be economist um but it seemed like you were talking
about us opening up and so i just opened up and
what was there was just my tremendous love of music when i was a child how much i loved playing music
and that i i don't do that anymore and i don't sing and uh
then i i thought well this is a real could be a real pity trip and i don't want to do that and i
remembered my high school music teacher who inspired me to music and
how much we all loved him he was like a hero in our town and then later i heard that he was very
disappointed that he didn't get the position that he was supposed to get or wanted to get as a conductor and
maybe even got into some alcohol and so i started sending him loving-kindness and i thought you would
say something about be open for something that you don't expect or has never been there
and i've never sent him any loving kindness and it was just beautiful for me to
to love him for what he gave me thanks thanks folks
thanks abraham that's lovely thank you it's i'm delighted
the practice opening up your heart opening up exactly as in as it needs it to be tonight and hearing
the the um you know the instructions exactly as they needed to be heard
in exactly as they needed to be heard yay beautiful it's making art it's making
art right it's this is our life is is art
and our practice is art it's what comes up it's what what we hear i mean i say
so many things and and i trust many of you and from me too when i listen to guided
meditation there are only a few things i really hear and listen and it's amazing to hear the whole thing but but and and
you know with that it's just whatever needs to arise our practice is art so thank you all beautiful
so such a privilege to to practice with you all all of it included all the beauties and
all the sorrows the ten thousand joys and the ten thousand sorrows all of it
supporting art so so the time has come for us to turn into
making music in small groups uh
making um what was it uh earlier um
[Music] jazz yes making jazz so so um
so i'm going to create the breakout rooms now and as always take care of yourselves take
care of each other start with um 15 seconds of silent meta for yourself
or each other and then as much or as little as you wish to share
um so the rooms are now created they are open
actually wait not open yet i'm gonna shift something around there okay
open enjoy okay welcome back everyone welcome back
and we have a couple minutes love to hear about
any anything that might have come up you're making music together sangha music
so feel free to raise your hand especially if you haven't shared for a while
or you can type in chat you think about your practice in sangha or or
the uh this listening with the heart anything you noticed different
any thoughts about practice as art art as practice claire
hi there uh very quickly it was so funny that you brought this topic up tonight because i
was talking to somebody else about it this morning and what i was saying i didn't involve
the whole go into the whole story but ever since i've started working with you all my listening skills have increased
exponentially i can't tell you how much i'm it's coming to me from the universe and
what i'm hearing internally it's changed a lot of my behaviors it's so increasing
um and that's that's not honest truth and i was talking to
somebody else today you know what a difference that is doing
and then you bring it bring it up tonight i thought boy this is really weird
that's beautiful thank you claire the sound is coming and going in your sound a little tonight but what i heard
you say is that ever since you've started to to practice with the sangha and training in this way that there's a
sense of uh you're you're here you're you're um you're you're listening
and and also some kind of sense of intuition like listening to messages from the universe and from within
yeah i'm sorry i use earbuds when you're speaking because i can't cause i can hear better right but it blocks my
speaking i always forget to take them out it's all good
heard you loud and clear yeah there's something and now that you bring that up and and i'll say this and before closing
um i'll share with you that for me also there's this this listening this listening for
me also with my meditation and my path i feel like i i'm more much more intuitive
i listen much more about both with people and with sense of you know intuition it just it's
again i don't want to make it sound woo-woo but there's so much to this world it's just listening when we really
listen there's so much that we can pick up in conversations with others with just what what is what is offered so
yeah listening we can listen with our hearts thank you claire thanks for bringing that in
and we'll give the last word to nav who says just appreciating the beauty of endless possibility
yay love the poetry of that thank you enough appreciating the beauty of endless
possibility indeed so thank you all i appreciate the beauty
of the endless possibility of you showing up and practicing and cultivating and
all the ripple effects all the ripples of our practice together may all beings
be well may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music] thanks everyone thank you