good evening welcome welcome
wherever you might be whomever you might be a warm welcome
so we'll do a little bit of a guided meditation
coming into our meditation posture
in a relaxed easy manner
not forcing some stiffness but not being cavalier or casual
in terms of half-heartedness maybe is the better word
and can we sit whether that's literal or metaphorical
can we sit and know that we're sitting
what does this body sitting feel like right now
think about the body in just a general sense noticing the posture
noticing the pressure of whatever it is we're sitting on pressure
against the body
and maybe noticing a general
mood of the body
we could think of this in terms of energy does it feel like there's too much energy restlessness want to go
want to do anything except sit here not enough energy getting tired and
drowsy or maybe we're like goldilocks there's there's enough it's just
right just enough energy
and we can also tune into the more specifics about the body
and for this guided meditation
we'll take a particular approach
that is we'll do a scan of the body
just noticing where are their pleasant sensations
the pleasantness might be very subtle
maybe the hands are touching something smooth
maybe it feels good to be grounded rooted connected to whatever it is
you're sitting on
maybe it feels nice to have this spine upright
i'm kind of jumping all around the body sometimes it's helpful to do a scan
from the top of the head down to the feet
just noticing the pleasant sensations
sometimes it's helpful to use a little label pleasant
you don't have to do that if it feels too cumbersome but it can be helpful
feeling the smoothness of the breath perhaps as being pleasant
maybe there's a little bit of a pleasant sensation with the stretching that happens with breathing
and we can do the same type of scan except this time
noticing the unpleasant sensations
maybe there's a knee that's a little uncomfortable
we can scan from the top of the head taking our time
not in any hurry and going down noticing
what's a little bit unpleasant or maybe greatly unpleasant
can we do this in a relaxed easy manner we don't have to
fix anything we don't have to make anything happen we're just categorizing
the different sensations experiences
can we keep it simple just unpleasant
no need to go into the story about how you have to fix it or why it's
unpleasant just unpleasant
and then can we do this exercise of a body scan one more time
noticing what is neither pleasant nor unpleasant
what is neutral
these sensations might be very quiet
sometimes we might a little bit lost what do you mean neutral
earlobes most often are neutral unless they were recently pierced or
elbows
the back of the arms in general without
straining without pushing
just noticing neutral sensations
and then just open it up to noticing whatever
sensations there are and noticing whether
they're pleasant unpleasant or neither pleasant nor unpleasant
neutral
you might feel that as we
gently label our experience sensations pleasant unpleasant or
neutral it really simplifies
our experience kind of disrupts the momentum of story
making or the proliferation of thoughts
just by saying oh this is unpleasant
supports the ending of this feeling that it has to be different
no it's just unpleasant
this simplifying might create some spaciousness
in our experience less busyness
in our experience
simplifying our experience
just noticing pleasant unpleasant neutral sensations
can be a way in which we can kind of settle down it takes a little
bit of attention a little bit of quietness to
notice the sensations the affective the hedonic quality of the
sensations and that way can simplify and
make more spacious our experience
and that way our capacity to be with difficult experiences increases as we learn this skill of
simplifying them found just too pleasant unpleasant or
neutral and this way of increasing our capacity
helps us help others so that we might be available
[Music] either in the midst of our own difficulties or
more general difficulties that societal difficulties or
maybe we could be available for them also for others in this way our practice
supports not only ourselves but others so may our practice be for the benefit
of all beings everywhere
[Music]
good evening good evening
and a warm welcome i'm happy to be here to be practicing with you all
so tonight i'd like to continue on this topic that i started last week this idea of vadena this polyword
that sometimes gets translated as feeling but really you know we tend to think of
feeling as emotions doesn't mean emotions it means
the hedonic quality it's not a word that i usually use in my
vocabulary hedonic but essentially is it
how is it related to pleasure is it pleasant is it unpleasant or is it neither
pleasant nor unpleasant i think that i think the word hedonia
maybe comes from the greek but hedonism right we often think about so vedana
this pauli word probably the the best translation is hedonic tone
that translation is the best um descriptor but there's something
clunky and hedonic tone in my ear it sounds a little bit too much like demonic
and i don't want to be talking about demonic tone so vedana
vedana this is maybe it's best left untranslated sometimes
it's translated also as feeling tone i think that's a little bit better than feeling
just because so much in english we start to think sad lonely happy but that's not what
vedina is pointing to and last week i talked about how
practicing with vader as a way that can really help simplify our experiences
and also about um i talked a little bit about pleasant experiences and how
we are often kind of chasing or uh maybe chasing us the right word after
pleasant experiences thinking that there will be sources of lasting happiness
and of course they aren't and the disappointment that arises with that
so some of you may know so i'd like to build on that and maybe flesh out some of the things
that i talked about last week so some of you may know that vedana actually shows up quite a number of
places in the buddhist teachings but we don't teach about it like those of us that sit
in the dharma seat tend not to teach about it that much i'm not exactly sure why
except that i will say that i don't know it just uh there isn't as much material in this
who does resent as much stories
around vedana but i'd like to spend a little time here
to talk some more about it some of you might know that i think i mentioned this last week also
that vedana is one of the four foundations of mindfulness in the sati patana suta so the discourse
that is most associated with the mindfulness practice that we do today
talks about establishing mindfulness in four different arenas
the first one is the body the in which we often are teaching about the breath and
the body the second one is vedana feeling tone hedonic tone the third one is the mind
mindfulness of mind and the fourth one is dharmas and
that gets translated different ways phenomenon or something like this
so we have these four ways in which mindfulness is established or four arenas in which mindfulness might be
established and as it happens that both in the spirit rock
and ims and irc imc all of these meditation centers when we
teach mindfulness we often teach mindfulness in four areas
breath body emotions and thoughts so it would be easy to think four
foundations of mindfulness in the discourses four areas of mindfulness being taught at
these retreat centers by a lot of different dharma teachers but they're not exactly the same
right because uh the in the foundations of mindfulness we have vedana but over here we have emotions
by saying over here i mean what the dharma teachers are often talking about
vedana is non-emotions emotions probably would is that just the
in the time of the buddha they categorized their experiences differently and they didn't really have
emotions the way that we understand of course they had emotions but they the way they talked about them
and understood them as different than how we do now
so i know plenty of people that have been confused about this thinking well there's these four areas in these four foundations but
they're not equivalent i'll say that vedina is also
in the 12 lengths of dependent or rising this is also an area in which we don't
teach that much about there's a number of reasons for this
i'll say for myself personally one is because 12 is a big number
to do in a dharma talk to list through 12 things seems you know that's a it's a great
endeavor and it's just i don't think would be helpful or fruitful to go through 12 things
but what is helpful is just the principle of dependent arising as opposed to the 12 links
of dependent arising and the principle of dependent arising this not won't be
surprising to anybody here when one thing arises it causes
something else to arise when a arises b arises
when a goes away b goes away so the principle of dependent arising we teach but not so much the 12 links
and also vedina is one of the aggregates another topic that we don't teach that
much about maybe this will be a dharma talk that's only about what we don't teach
and i won't actually teach you anything i'll just list all the things that we don't teach about
i'll just say and the aggregates is which is a clunky translation but
um is one way that we might understand our all of our experiences different
components of our experiences so that's just a kind of introduction to
say like vedana even though it's really important and
can be a really a powerful practice and really supportive for lots of
freedom and i'll talk a little bit more about this today despite that it's often not talked about
in dharma talks so i talked a little bit about how
vedana is not emotions and it's often
we could think about it as hedonic tone but i will say that it arises in
response to sense contact what that means is
whenever the eye sees a sight when an ear hears a sound that tongue
tastes a flavor something like this so sense contact is when the senses have
contact with some object whenever that occurs
and the next beat is vedana whenever the eye sees something the next
beat is is it pleasant unpleasant or neutral
some people will say that neutral takes up like the most the majority of our experiences that we
don't notice there's so many things that are just details that we're not paying attention to
but this um it maybe i should say i'm talking about sense contact eyes in
sight but also mental events
some of you know that in the buddhist tradition that that mind is also a sense sensed or
so every any mental event also can be pleasant unpleasant or neutral
and veda vedina arises it's just completely natural we can't stop it it's
something that just happens and i would say that it's a combination
of some physiological and psychological aspects or whether we
ex assign the label pleasant unpleasant or neither to an experience
that is it's if we injure ourselves i think probably biologically
physiologically that's unpleasant smelling rotting food is unpleasant
that's kind of like a biological response being hungry these types of things
but there's also a psychological aspect in terms of what mood we're in or what else is happening
maybe one i'll um say that those that know me know that i just am
committed to my coffee practice in the morning if we can call it that there's something about
a cup of coffee in the morning that i find very pleasant i just yeah i just really enjoy having a
cup of coffee in the morning i like the taste i like the temperature i kind of like the ritual of making
coffee it's a pleasant experience probably that little bit of caffeine too
has a as a role there and i often will have a second cup of
decaf coffee not long after the first cup sometimes you know it's just nice to
have a cup of something warm in the mornings even in the summer
but a third cup of coffee the coffee tastes bitter it
just doesn't i don't know it's not as pleasant it's the same sense experience right my
tongue is having this tasting the same flavors but it's no longer as pleasant it's a little
bit unpleasant that third cup of coffee just doesn't i don't know why exactly but so i would
say that's kind of pointing towards some of the psychological elements too to vedana
so it's not entirely our biological response like you know amoebas of course they move
towards pleasant we could say that word pleasant things you know that are nourishing and
supportive and away from toxic things i would say that's more biological but
we also have this element that we add to it
and teasing apart what part is psychological in one part is physiological probably isn't
important but what is important is to notice that the the pleasantness or the
unpleasantness or the neutrality does not lie within the coffee
it lies within the experiencer it's not inherent to the coffee
it's inherent to one who is having that experience to the sensation
or maybe i shouldn't say inherent it's associated with
sometimes we think that um some things are just always bad they're always unpleasant but
recognizing that you know maybe other people in other conditions
might think that they're fine food is a great example different cultures right uh different
things with food different what those people who were not raised in america my experience has been
do not like peanut butter but those of us who grew up in america love peanut
butter i don't know if we love it but you know for me it's associated with childhood and some goodness of some sort
so vedana is this the pleasant unpleasant neutral to
experiences but i think it's important to recognize that whether something is pleasant or unpleasant does not
belong to what were to the object out there it belongs to the experiencer the
subject here and so one other way that we might think
about veda is because it happens right after a sense contact in the next
beat is a way in which what the body is experiencing
whether that's a sight or the tactile sensation as i rub my hands
together for example it's a little bit warm and pleasant
and then in the next beat is the vedina pleasant unpleasant neutral
that's a mental event the pleasant unpleasant neutral so vedana in some way is this link
between what the body is doing what the body is experiencing
and the mental experience it's not the only link but it's a big
part of it so in some ways vedana is the intermediary of how the body and the mind are
connected and all of us know this right when we're
certainly when um there's an unpleasant experience in the
body that the mind might start like speeding up and trying to find a solution or
something like this or when there's a unpleasant thought in the mind then the
body might um we might have a facial expression that's a frown or
a foreign of the brow or something like this so vedana is often the the link
maybe if i could use that word i said intermediary kind of like the medium the way in which body and
mind are connected and so this can be
a key way to understand how if we're going to make this distinction between body and mind
like how they really are connected also
and so one reason why we might think that the mind likes to do this like that veid in a
pleasant unpleasant neutral is because it's a way to categorize our experience
it's a way to maybe make sense of and all these things that are arising
that we're experiencing at once and of course we only pay attention to a subset of them
but the mind uses it vaden as kind of a filtration device not so much paying attention to
neutral we know that there's a negativity bias paying more attention to what's unpleasant
because that might be harmful and then paying attention to what's pleasant
so it's one of the like initial filtration devices that the mind does
and it's perfectly normal it's like beneath consciousness this uh labeling it's not
something that we're actively doing and so the goal of practice
is not to stop it from happening not to [Music] make it be different but just to notice
that things are pleasant unpleasant and neutral to use this as a place where we can bring some mindfulness
and i'll unpack this a little bit more here in a moment but i do want to say that when we do
notice them there's some things obviously that we'll notice
and the buddha talked about them in this passage in the discourses where the burrito says
suppose there was a guest house people come from the east the west the
north and the south and lodged there aristocrats brahmans merchants and
workers lodged there in the same way various feeling tones arise in this body
pleasant he's painful we could use that as a other
translation and neutral so just in the same way checking in and out of a hotel we could
see there's just people coming from all these different ways they check in they check out these types of people that type of
people tall people short people people wearing red shirts people wearing blue shirts or whatever it might be right
there's different ways we can categorize them so another way we might think of vedana as a way to the mind uses to
help make sense or help prioritize our experiences but importantly
they come and go they come and go of course they do
just like people checking in and out of the hotel we can't control them and there's
different types and they come and go so in some ways recognizing when we are
noticing vedana will notice that they are arising and
passing away and noticing the impermanence of them
can really affect our relationship to them because they are ephemeral not only are
they coming and going but they're insubstantial they're likened to um bubbles on their
on the surface of water when it's raining like in a body of water of course we don't like grab bubbles
expecting them to be there vade in us the same way
so noticing that they are impermanent coming and going
noticing that they're insubstantial there's they're not really tangible there's nothing really there to
grab onto just like a bubble then we stop trying to get all tangled
up with them we just naturally we don't have to make this happen it just naturally happens that we
disengage in some kind of way maybe we're still a little bit engaged but not as much we're not as entangled
and it might be that we completely disengage from them so being mindful of them is a way that
we can become a little bit less entangled and why would we want to do that because
in these 12 lengths of dependent arising and probably you know this from your own
experience without my having to tell you vadena
conditions craving that is pleasant vedana
creates the conditions in which there's this leaning forward i want more
unpleasant faith in others is pushing away i don't want which is kind of the same
right a version is just the slip the flip side of desire a version is desiring something
different and then neutral vedana
often leads to some boredom or you know not really connecting
and then there's often either this boredom which is a form of a version really
so in some ways we could think of that as being a type of craving but boredom also kind of um
the mind often slips off and wants to go find something entertaining so then it kind of slips into craving so
in this way vedana conditions craving so some of you
might know the craving that um the pali word is tanha which is also understood as thirst so
this type of demanding this type of expectation or i kind of like this word
demanding that things be different i want more i want less something like this is
push and pull with our experience
and the teachings tell us and our experience shows us
that this connection between something that's pleasant and full-blown craving or even
mild craving is a place where we can practice why would we want to practice why would
we want to get rid of craving maybe you all know this craving leads to
dukkha leads to suffering right craving is this maybe suffering is too strong a
word sometimes it is but maybe it's just this general dissatisfaction
and some i might even go so far as to say craving itself is a certain amount of duca it's a kind
of a contraction of i want something just having that feeling
is the opposite of a contentment of an ease
so a sense contact whether that's what the eye sees or a sound that the ear
hears naturally gives rights to vedana pleasant unpleasant neutral
veidenai gives rise to craving craving gives rise to dukkha suffering
and we can interrupt this momentum this movement with paying attention with
vedana this is the place which if we're aware of it
we can simplify it and it doesn't lead into craving and i played around with this not too
long ago when i had an unfortunate amount of dental work
recently and i remember uh thinking to myself this is unpleasant
yeah this is unpleasant that'd be being a big fan of a dental work i don't
know anybody that is but but just that saying this is unpleasant
kind of like calmed down this feeling of i have to get out of here what's happening you know there's this
when something is really unpleasant there often it can just grow and grow but just to say
this is unpleasant there's a way which could you kind of like let things calm down
quiet down and disrupt that movement that momentum to having this feeling like things
have to be different get me out of here or whatever it might be whatever it might be
it's striking how powerfully conditioned it is that when something is unpleasant
to have some of this naturally to have some aversion to want to push it away
but it is a habit and it that we can train ourselves
to not have it to be as strong and probably all of you have experienced
this with a meditation practice that as the mind quiets as the mind gets
settled that our capacity to be with things that are either
really pleasant some of the joy and happiness that can arise in meditation or some of the what i call body duka
some uncomfortableness in the body that might arise our capacity to just hold that
and not have it lead into a storyline i got to get out of here i want more of
this whatever it might be our capacity to do
that increases with practice with meditation
as we practice with being noticing a vedana
and noticing the subtle vedana and simplifying down to pleasant unpleasant neutral
makes it so much easier to be with whatever's arising and then we don't get so tangled up and
when we're less tangled up then the intensity of whatever it is that we're
experiencing calms down goes a little bit down
and it ends up it can be a very helpful cycle which when the less
reactive we are the less
um i want to use like it the less it promotes whatever that's the less pleasant or
less less the problem-ness maybe i could say out of the experience drains out and in fact
that vaden i could switch what's unpleasant can become pleasant when the mind is
quiet what's unpleasant can also become pleasant we could play around with this
i know on some retreats i've had some plenty of experiences when the mind is
quiet i'm just sitting and i remember so clearly this one time having this
thought like wow if i weren't meditating this would be painful
but instead it just was kind of fascinating experience and just this recognition that
it's not painful now it's just a sensation but if i weren't
meditating it would a different vedan i would get associated with it
and therefore different craving so vedana this can be this really
powerful place to practice a because it simplifies things and as part of this simplification
it interrupts this momentum towards dukkha this momentum
towards unsatisfactoriness so i don't know how many times i said
the word vedana quite a few times as opposed to feeling
tone or hedonic tone but consider this as a place to practice and
in the guided meditation we could do this we could practice just with the bodily experience
just noticing is it pleasant unpleasant or neutral and just giving a little
label a quick little label and this way we can
bring the problem-ness out of our experiences we can simplify it down
pleasant unpleasant or neutral and may this be a support for your
practice so it can be a support for all beings
everywhere thank you