good morning dharma friends so it is good morning on the west coast of the united states
my name is tara malay and i am actually coming to you from the town of
northampton massachusetts on the east coast of the united states which is the land of the nonotuck
here and i'm very pleased to be with you i teach uh at the
local retreat center which is a insight meditation society about an hour
away from where i am and then across the east coast and i lived for quite some time in the bay
area over 20 years and was pleased to also teach at insight meditation center in redwood
city when i was there and i'm pleased to be in connection with the sangha
with the the uh members and teachers so looking forward to practicing with
you today so let's rest into our mindfulness practice
we'll practice until 10 o'clock pacific time
and so finding our posture that balance
of ease and comfort in the body
as well as alertness and uprightness in the posture
and bringing in a sense of dignity also to the posture
calling to mind the nobility of this practice to infuse the body and the mind with a
sense of dignity practice is noble because it's onward
leading towards the development of more compassion
and wisdom and when we have this sense of dignity
in the posture it supports confidence in our ability to meet
whatever may arise even if it's difficult
even if it's unpleasant
so balancing that dignity with a sense of relaxation
noticing any areas of tightness
and inviting in a letting go
inviting ease into any areas of holding in the body
it can be helpful to begin with an awareness of the whole body
that shifting and changing field of sensations we call the body
and within that whole field of shifting and changing sensations
there are the sensations that we call the breath
a wave of ever-changing
physical sensations in any moment there might be tingling or softness
or tightness or expansion or movement and this
ever-changing way we call the breath we can simply rest into an awareness
that experience whether we're noticing the breath in the
whole body or in an area where we sense it quite
clearly
it can be helpful to keep some of the attention well the whole body and
really just notice the breath within that larger
frame [Music] of awareness of the body
and we bring attention to however the breath is presenting itself in this moment
and in this moment and in this moment
and whenever the mind wanders and mindfulness arises again
we can simply notice that mindfulness has arisen again that moment happens outside of our control seated by
previous causes and conditions previous moments of mindfulness
and here we are aware again of what's happening right here and right
now and we can notice what mindfulness
arises in relationship to whether it's an experience of the mind or the body
thinking or an emotion [Music] or a sound or a physical sensation
experience at these six sense stores the five physical senses we're familiar
with and the sixth sense door of the mind
where thoughts and images and emotions and moods arise
we can rest our mindfulness there
whenever that experience is not drawing it drawing our attention so strongly simply
gently return to the anchor of the breath
confusing our mindful awareness with kindness
be very supportive and strengthening of the practice
knowing that we are sensitive beings
arising at these sense doors unbidden without our
outside of our control are pleasant unpleasant and neither experiences
and as sentient beings
this is this experience of ever changing mental and physical phenomena
that's what we much less must meet and over time learn to meet
with mindfulness more and more
as a way of relating to our experience
that will diminish suffering and harm
so each moment of mindfulness allowing for the knowing of what's
arising to be infused with care
for our sensitive minds hearts and bodies
if we ever find ourselves struggling or in confusion or judgment in the
practice you know those thoughts so i should be being mindful
and not being mindful in the right way or simply confused how to do the
practice you can remember the simplicity of
mindfulness the simplicity of the instructions not easy but simple simply
to be aware of what's happening right here right now in the body
and in the mind without pushing it away or trying to
cling to it so just accepting and allowing what is
arising right here and now in the mind of the body
and knowing its presence so if it's frustration or judging that's
here we can simply now frustration feels like this right now
it's here it feels like this or judgment judging
feels like this right now it's here
it feels like this
this is the same invitation or instruction
or any experience of the body or the mind
if it's an experience of the body tingling tingling is here and it feels like this
right now pressure is here and it feels like this
so remembering and recalling the simplicity of mindfulness
whenever there is any struggle letting go into awareness
with non-contention of what's happening right here
and right now
uh
well thank you for joining us today tara
i just introduced tara tara malay is a practitioner of insight meditation since 2003 and has
undertaken intensive practice periods in the united states and bmr she's a graduate of the 2017
2021 ims irc teacher training in 2016 she co-founded the san francisco
people of color insight sangha and in 2020 to 2021 she served as the
interim guiding teacher for the insight meditation community of western massachusetts
her dharma offerings stem from the lineage of mahasi seyada tara combines a deep love of
classical teravata and early buddhist teachings with a focus on bringing the practice alive
in modern daily life thank you tara
thanks so much kevin and thank you all for practicing with me today
i would like to talk about um an approach or a phrase that to me
really encapsulates this actually holistic
integrated practice that we are doing
part of which is our mindfulness practice the holistic practice i'm referring to of course is the noble
eightfold path and for me personally
it's helpful to remind myself that it is a whole path
of eight factors and
when i recommit myself when there are moments and times of recommitment
there is this framework or approach that really for me embodies or
encapsulates that remembering and recommitment and it is a simple um and it is
caring enough to truly live that's sort of what it feels like to me and
also i found that i can sort of map all of the factors
onto this particular phrase of caring enough to truly live so i want to share that with you that
approach and perhaps it will seed some inspiration and perhaps free commitment for you as
well so i'm going to go briefly through each
of the factors and talk about how this approach of caring enough to truly live
how that plays out for me or how that is enlivening for me
and but first i want to just point to how it also describes for me a way that we
feel when we do make that recommitment it describes a sort of a sense of the motivation that often
propels us to practice and you know there are these choice
points that we sometimes have these inflection points um where perhaps our hearts are
calling us to practice to dive a little deeper into practice
so for example to practice more intensively or more regularly or perhaps
to take up a new type of practice that our hearts are really drawn to
that we've learned a little about and that would really seem to be supportive or a skillful means for us such as
a brahmavihara practice or the five daily recollections or a concentration practice there are so
many so many uh ways in which the buddha taught that would support
our whole practice of engaging with the noble eightfold path um but you know we we reach these times
in our practice and we can choose to really commit and follow our heart
and dive into that practice or sometimes we um falter or become more inconsistent
but what i have found that's helpful to recognize is that when there is this
act of diving in deeper or recommitting what i feel in my heart is that i'm
really caring enough to truly live this life that there is an aspect of caring and an ex aspect
of the commitment to life and to truth and so you know just to illustrate
i want to describe one of those choice points for myself
you know um this is going back quite a few years and i had been practicing for quite a
while in my daily life and um over time i had
started to go on short retreats and there was a time where i really did
falter in the practice and i came um came to a quite a commitment in the sense that
the practice was really what i needed to focus on and that it began with a health
crisis i had you might call it a health crisis or an episode i actually uh it involved
having to have surgery on my foot to um actually there was a bone deformity in
my foot and that needed to be corrected and in the period leading up to that
and after that in a very long recovery there was quite a time period there where
i couldn't walk unaided and i i needed to walk with crutches and many people experience these kinds
of difficulties health challenges in life with mobility
i was younger and i didn't practice well enough and i was in i suffered a lot because of
it i was you know wanting things to be different than the way they were quite a lot of the time and so very much
in contention with experience and there was a time where i i just really realized
remembering how the practice had supported me in the past in the past that i needed to
really turn back to that practice and try to meet my experience with it
and then um i did that i i began to go on longer retreats and to
practice much more um in daily life and to reach out more to sangha and practice more with sangha
but there wasn't even a much starker experience that i had of of really
um reaching one of those choice points and committing to the to where my heart was drawing me um in
practice and that was um sometime after i recovered i
actually found myself being very my heart being really drawn to intensive practice
and i decided to take a one month retreat the first one month retreat that i had done and i had the particular conditions uh
the privileges in my life that allowed me to to do that to carve out a month from my
uh at my workplace a month of vacation and i i went on you know arranged my life
and did all kinds of things to be able to do this one month retreat uh and as that
time approached i did though start to feel some trepidations and nervousness and even
some just kind of questioning why am i doing this what am i doing
and that intensified as i came closer and closer to the date at
the beginning of the retreat and you know i was worried about missing my family my
my partner my wife my dog and i um
nevertheless drove up to the retreat and i had some extra time and i
stopped at a grocery store and still my heart and my mind were filled with these thoughts and worries and i was already missing my
family i stopped at this grocery store i went in i came out
and i decided that i had a little bit of time
left before i just stay registration started so i would just rest in my car i got into the driver's seat and
um i reached down and i uh just climbed the seat back
uh a bit and you know an inclining back i looked up at the ceiling of my car
and there right before my eyes were all of these crutch marks on the ceiling all of these
marks that had been made inadvertently unknowingly when i had been pulling my crutches into my car over and over again
during that time period and at that moment all doubt all thoughts
why am i doing this what am i doing went out the window went out the door i absolutely knew
i saw the crutch marks on the ceiling i remembered the way in which i had gone through that
stage without mindfulness not really practicing consistently
not really knowing doing what i knew in my heart i needed to do to meet difficult experience and
i was completely committed i saw the crutch marks on the ceiling i said to myself that's why i'm doing this and you know
encapsulated in that was this knowing of the unreliability of our experience the
unreliability of our bodies the impermanence the dissatisfactoriness
of life the fact that we we do have pleasant unpleasant experiences
and um you know we can't control that we do we can't hold on to the pleasant uh
can't make the conditions the way we want them to the conditions are coming towards us and ungovernable
and that's so that not self aspect of experience so there was this knowing at that time
and i absolutely never i didn't have another doubt uh thought they flew out of my mind and i
went to that retreat and um the practice continued to flourish from there i was able to
move forward and i in that moment there was a caring enough to truly live
there was that energy that motivation to um practice in a way
that i knew when my heart would be onward leading for me and for
others you know not just for me to alleviate my own suffering but in that time period
and my frustration and anger and not practicing well
through the experience that i had with you know having difficulty with mobility
and recovery from surgery i wasn't able to be the kind of person i wanted to be
in relation to the rest of the world also in my relationships um i my energy was
channeled towards frustration and and um was not able to be there
and serve my community and also just relate in a way that was was really
um ideal in life because my energy was taken up
and in you know being caught in cycles of suffering so i cared enough in in that moment that
that well spring of caring enough to truly live to truly follow that um
my heart's called towards the dharma you know welled up as i remember that and you know there
are poly words for these kinds of mind states that support our that kind of propel us
that have bring an urgency to the practice and support a confidence in moving
towards it and so there was there was that in those time in that time period for me um
the words are some vega which is often translated as spiritual urgency
and pasada which is kind of a confirmed faith in the practice
or confirmed confidence in the practice and sandega is that knowing that knowing that we
have where we realize there is some the way we've been relating to experience has been
just causing us more suffering and is not the way through is the way we've been
relating with trying to maximize the pleasant you know those habits that we have as human beings
responding to the the truth of dukkha the experience of unsatisfactoriness in
life by trying to maximize the pleasant or diminish or get away uh um the the unpleasant push it away
or just not being aware in our daily lives that response
we start to realize that response is not the way that's actually going to bring us
freedom or peace and that experience of that knowing
is called some vega and then when it's balanced with posada which is some confirmed confidence some confidence in
the practice that that in fact the way to
um to experience that greater freedom and that greater peace
is is to practice the dharma is to practice mindfulness in the
context of of the rest of the past factors that combination is very potent and powerful
and my experience of that is this caring enough to truly live
life to truly follow my heart's desire to understand the truth
and to engage with this practice so um now i want to just talk a little bit
about this caring enough to truly live and
how i see it as as mapping onto and relating to our holistic practice of the noble
eightfold path so caring i see you know the first two factors of the noble eightfold path
are often referred to as the first basket and they're often referred to as the wisdom basket
and so i actually feel that this basket really points me towards
this wellspring of caring and so that may seem a little unusual because oftentimes
people sort of contrast wisdom and compassion or wisdom and caring that quite different but when we
really look at these um first two factors of the noble eightfold path
for me they really point towards the flourishing of caring in our in in our lives
uh they they point us towards really beginning with with caring and that that's wives so the
first factor is wise view wise view and that is
usually mostly described as understanding the four
noble truths that's the wise view it's understanding the four noble truths so when we look at this the buddha is
one of the first of the buddhist teachings before noble truths and it is based
in his own compassion for his own experience of suffering and then his teaching of the the formidable truth
out of compassion for us that of compassion for other beings that they could also
understand suffering that they were experiencing and understand that there was this accessibility
of cessation of suffering of peace and ease so the four noble truths in a nutshell
are there is dissatisfactoriness stress unreliability in life because our experiences
are ephemeral and we don't control them for example that is part of our experience
it's the first noble truth and that's to be understood and then the second noble truth
is that there is a cause or an origin for that dissatisfactoriness that suffering that
dukkha in pali d dkha that there is a cause in its craving
craving for example for sense pleasure is craving for becoming over and over trying to solidify our experience
craving also for non-becoming to really push away at the unpleasant
rejected and this is the second noble truth and then
the third is that there actually is a um a cessation of that suffering
and it's the letting go of that same craving and the fourth is the noble is actually the noble eightfold path
that that is the path to the cessation of suffering so this practice has this beautiful
non-linearity to it this cyclical nature and um
so this understanding you can see you know of wise view that that the four noble truths are
rooted in an experience an expression of compassion by the buddha himself
and as we practice them they are also an expression of compassion for ourselves
because we are addressing um we are recognizing and addressing and training our minds and our hearts
we're recognizing addressing the suffering and then training our minds and hearts towards greater ease and peace
and towards the cessation of that suffering there could be nothing more sort of caring than really really making that
commitment to actually understand what causes our suffering and respond to it
and and so that's that to me is caring and the second factor of the noble april
path is really directly about about um carrying mind states
and cultivating them so this is wise intention or wise resolve and there are three wise
intentions that this factor of the noble eightfold path calls on us to cultivate the first is
renunciation or simplicity so that means letting go of our greed
impulses that cause us suffering in the world also so renunciation or simplicity and that
intention is the first and the second two are the intentions of loving kindness and harmlessness so loving kindness
that simple wish for well-being for ourselves and others and harmlessness really relating
dropping that intention of non-harm moment by moment and what could be more caring for
ourselves in the world than to cultivate these kinds of intentions um
in in relationship to our own experience and not of others so this is caring in the in the first
basket it is a caring that's infused with wisdom it's based in wisdom
it's based in this understanding of the of the four noble truths but it is
infused with caring um also so caring enough caring enough well
to me the enough points to the second basket of the noble eightfold path
which is you know um acting on this caring acting on these
intentions following through and so the second basket is called the basket
of ethics or virtue it is really a
three factors a combination of three factors which point to um non-harming conduct
you know so bringing the non-harming intentions and the caring into our lives and infusing our daily
uh relation our relationship to the world our relationship to others our relationship to ourselves
interestingly to into you know bringing that
really acting on those intentions so the factors the three factors of this
second basket are why speech wise action and wise
livelihood why speech referring to speech truthful speech so abstaining
from false speech all of these are really framed in the abstaining as we drop our habits of harm our lives become to
begin to be infused by not harm and caring so abstaining from false speech
abstaining from harsh speech abstaining from divisive speech even abstaining from idol chatter where
we are more likely to fall into perhaps us habits
that are harming and why is action really pointing to um some of the
other uh precepts the typical five ethical training
precepts for lay people that many people are familiar with but those are abstaining from
killing harming other beings abstaining from taking that which is not freely
offered so abstaining from stealing and abstaining from sexual misconduct
right and then wise livelihood to not make a living in a way that is based on
harm or deceit so this basket is is this that
action of caring enough to infuse and imbue your life with
non-harming conduct and one of the most beautiful things i think about the teachings
is that this practice of ethics of virtue is one that the
buddha taught so that we would experience joy it was about non-harming for ourselves
just as much as others because there's a recognition that when we do engage in harm and
conduct there is an impact on our hearts and minds that we feel a remorse even if it's
underneath the surface it's even if it's sort of subconscious
we there are ripple effects of of a sense of dis-ease in our hearts and
our minds so this this particular basket is caring enough for ourselves and
others really and i just want to quote a couple of lines from the dhammapada because i i
like to really bring home this teaching this truth that the buddha taught
non-harming conduct for our joy so these are a few lines from the dhammapada
the buddha said live the dharma a life of good conduct one who lives the dharma is happy in
this world and the next so he equated in this line living the dharma is
equated with a life of good conduct and it brings happiness
you know what it brings is non-remorse he also said one who makes merit rejoices in this
life rejoices in the next rejoices in both worlds
seeing one's own pure acts brings joy and delight it brings joy and delight so this is
caring enough and caring enough to truly live so that
brings us to the third basket of the noble eightfold path the last three factors
and and mindfulness is here in this basket and to truly live is to truly be aware actually of what it
is to be a human being what is happening and arising in our experience moment to
moment so there's this way in which when when we're not mindful we're not practicing this
meditative cultivation and we're not practicing you know really
cultivating awareness more and more this is a way in which we don't quite feel alive right we know we're separated from
our experience we know we're we're not really living it and we're not really
understanding the truth uh when mindfulness is not it's not it
when we're not actively cultivating that mindfulness that awareness that we fall back into habits of non-awareness
so my so caring enough to truly live this third basket of truly living uh
is referred to as the either the concentration or the meditation basket it has three factors
it's wise effort wise mindfulness and wise concentration
and all of them involve this cultivation of the mind so that
we begin to understand what it is to live the life
of a human being what is the experience of life
and how it is that we can cultivate how it is that we
can cultivate our minds train our minds so that we experience
less suffering more peace more ease
and so how it is that we can truly live the our you know our hearts intention of
living a life um that is one in which we can really
meet our experience with that caring we can really meet our experience with that caring and that understanding it's a wise
effort this is getting to know
our wholesome and unwholesome mind states and getting to know and beginning to
understand how we can uh abandon the una wholesome which means those kind of mind states
that harm us those that's what's uh that's what's unwholesome so for example um afflictive mind states
like impatience afflictive mind states like really rage or there's
you know fear that gets in the way that limits our potential
so those nine states we can feel the the harm of those in the moment so this wise effort is
beginning to understand how to recognize abandon those those more and
more over time by seeing how they show up in our lives
and beginning to understand how we can abandon them and when they do arise just to um
overcome them and also this wise effort involves
you know uh recognizing bringing bringing forward wholesome mind states
so those that are non-harming um that loving kindness i talked about earlier for example
gratitude joy these kinds of non-harming mind states
understanding over time developing the skillful means to cultivate those more and more and have
them arise more and more in our lives and then wise mindfulness where many of us are very familiar with
you know mindfulness and this is again about really understanding our experience and
and truly living in the sense of truly being there for our lives more truly being aware um
and not only that this mindfulness allows us to understand the truth of the way
things are deeply and more intuitively over time as we practice more and more with being
aware of what's happening moment to moment and not pushing it away
and not trying to cling to pleasant experiences the more we see the actual ephemerality
of experience the deep the more and more deeply and intuitively we can understand impermanence and that deep
understanding then allows the heart to let go of its habitual entanglement
and suffering and reactivity to that impermanent experience
so this is truly living the sense of truly beginning to understand the mind's capacity for freedom
you know the mind's capacity to understand more deeply the truth and to let go
and you know bringing us back to the beginning of the noble evil path to understand more and more the four
noble truths including the third one of letting go of that craving that keeps us on that wheel of some
you know and that some sorry suffering and finally wise concentration um
so that is really this gathering collectedness of the mind that supports supports all of the
factors really that supports mindfulness and and wise effort it's it's
just this um collectedness just coming back again and again and again um oftentimes
experienced through a continuity of mindfulness it's the unification of the mind the collective the gatherness it brings
stillness to the mind in fact um some people are of the view that this
word that is often translated as concentration samadhi is
mistranslated as concentration and should be concentrated it should be translated as stillness
so you can think of it as the growing stillness of the mind as we practice wise concentration
so in this last meditative basket of the noble eightfold path
of wise effort why is mindfulness and wise concentration
i see the potential for all of us to really truly live and truly live a
life that is not harming towards ourselves and others and that
is not harming because we begin to really have a deep understanding
of a deep understanding of the truth of the way things are and that living in alignment with that
truth and truth of impermanence of not self of the unreliability of our experience
that that is what brings great happiness and also brings us in alignment with our
care for the world for other beings and infused with that our care for
ourselves so friends uh dharma friends i hope that
this framework might have been of some inspiration to you caring enough to truly live as a way of
thinking about or pondering the noble eightfold path and i wish you a wonderful rest of the
day of practice