so good day everyone and welcome to our sunday morning meditation
and um meditation practice is supported or helped
by our contributions to it instead of just sitting quietly and
expecting just to reap the benefits of quiet sitting it might be helpful to think of
a few things that we contribute to allow the meditation to unfold
and so we contribute non-hostility and non
aversion to what's happening to our experience we contribute a non-greed
the absence of greedy expectation or desire for something or
we contribute to we contribute non-delusion not getting caught up in
delusions of grandeur or fantasies or or all kinds of
abstract removed thinking that has nothing to do with the simplicity of the immediacy of right here
and so we make we contribute something and and non-hostility
is comparable to was related to offering
some degree of simple ordinary kindness goodwill friendliness
non-greed is offering associated with offering some very
simple ordinary
generosity being generous to what the experience is
and non-delusion is associated with the field of wisdom
to bring forth whatever wise understanding we have that supports us to or encourages us to
stay right here be here
so we make simple contributions
so assuming a meditation posture where you are upright
either literally or metaphorically in a posture that supports you to be
both comfortable and alert
closing your eyes that's comfortable for you
and then settling into your posture kind of becoming aware of your body
and if there's ways that you can relax and settle your body
soften ease into this human form that we have
perhaps taking a few long slow deep breaths
in the exhale stretching the torso to the edges of how
big this torso can become
perhaps a stretching
and letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale scan through your body relaxing those parts of the body
where there might be holding in tension
and then settling down into your body and is there some place in your body
that you associate with non-greed
the absence of any strong driven desire
may be a place of generosity here openness
and if there is such a place in your body breathe with it for a few moments
breathe through it connecting yourself to non-greed
is there any place in your body that you associate with non-ill will
the absence of hostility a place of peace of good will
maybe of contentment and to breathe with this part of your
body breathe through it grounding yourself in
non-ill will
and is there a place in your body that you associate with non-delusion
someplace in your body that feels at rest or relaxed when there is wisdom
understanding
and perhaps as we sit this meditation
in a gentle easy simple way maybe non-greed non-ill will
non-delusion can be a soft gentle
support and inspiration
for your present moment mindfulness for staying alert and present
moment by moment here breathing in and breathing out
um
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
what might how might you be at the end of a
meditation that supports non-greed
non-ill will non-delusion
how might you be at the end of meditation that feels like almost like a natural support
not complicated and not a lot of thinking is there something about simplicity of
being or being calm settled
being more mindful that supports
being alive without being caught in greed or ill will delusion
and may it be that how we meditate that the practice that we do that the
fruits of that this practice may it be that it's something we can share with
the world share in intentional and unintentional
ways knowing and unknowing ways share it not because we proselytize for
sure but share it just by the way we are in the world
may we live in the world with generosity and love and wisdom
and in doing so contributing to the good conditions that support other
people to be happy and free and peaceful
and safe may this meditation practice that we do
help someone today for the next 24 hours
to feel safe safer to feel more peaceful or at ease
to feel happier
and to feel like they can live with breathing more freely
their heart beating more freely their mind
freed from contractions constrictions preoccupation
may all beings be happy and peaceful and safe and free
and may we support that possibility
[Music]
so good day everyone and
welcome to ours time together sunday and this dharma talk
before i give the talk a couple of announcements one is that next sunday after the talk
so this uh i'll have a will offer a community
meeting here on zoom right afterwards and it's more of a community meeting for
the local people who are normally might come in person to imc
but everyone's welcome to come to the meeting and the topic of it will be the opening of
imc the time to open our doors and have programs again
is on the horizon is on in sight and uh maybe in august and so
i want to just talk a little bit about the opening and the plans and hear concerns hear
questions desires that people have in the more local community and
and and if you're not local you're certainly very welcome to come and you're you're
part of this community regardless and and might be interesting for you to know
uh some of the plans here and we will um certainly giving a lot of thought to how
to support the the widespread community of people who
have been participating this last year on zoom and youtube and it's on our minds
the other thing is that in a few weeks i think around the 10th of uh maybe 10th and
11th of july friday saturday and sunday
there's a dharma teacher a wonderful vipassana teacher gregory kramer who is one of the more
innovative and brilliant teacher innovating a lot of the application of
the dharma application of mindfulness into the rest of our life outside of
meditation he developed a whole practice called insight dialogue
to bring mindfulness into talking
in our conversations with people and he's written a book now called i think the whole path the whole life
the whole life whole life practice or the whole life dharma forget exactly the title but but he has a term the whole life and
uh he explores the eightfold path in this book uh addressing very well many of the
issues how to live the dharma in our whole life and uh
he's offered to come down come down he's offered on zoom for our community to offer uh
kind of a creative teaching and uh kind of a retreat over this
weekend at least that weekend in july where he'll offer teachings and
and practices on his whole life dharma approach and with lots of time
during the day to go about your life your daily life and to um practice with it and then
he'll have offer support through the day and i think the main meetings are in the morning in the late afternoon
um and then practicing on your life in your life with it so i feel very fortunate to have him
coming and i encourage many of you to come if you're interested and there's more information about it on
imc website and i believe the easiest place to find it is on the what's new
section on the bottom right of the home page but also if you look under programs
it's listed there as well and you have to register for it
so gregory kramer the whole life
path or the whole life dharma so something like that is this uh book
so yeah i see it in the chat there were several
happy father's day wishes to spend out and certainly
to all the fathers and a few weeks ago had mothers and
all the parents who listening to us may you be um
may you be honored and respected and appreciated for all that you do and have done
also this weekend many of us in the united
states are celebrating this new holiday we now have juneteenth day the 19th of june and
i think it's been already become my favorite holiday in the united states
i i kind of liked in principle the idea of fourth of july for being an independence day it seemed like
closely related to the buddhist idea of freedom but liberation but juntinte is much more
closely related in my mind to this and maybe this can be a holiday that we buddhists united
states might want to particularly cherish um it's not it's not it's interesting
it's not really the celebration of the of the particular day that the
immense immense emancipation proclamation when slaves were in a sense liberated united
states but rather represents today that um in texas in a particular town in texas i
think galveston where many months after the proclamation was declared the slaves
there learned that they were free in other words the locals didn't want to tell them that they were free and
it took that long to discover and so it's the kind of the last
of the slaves who discovered that they were actually liberated and and so to celebrate this
very important milestone in this in this country it seems like a celebrate to appreciate to honor to
remember seems like a very important thing to do and the fact that the liberation from slavery is a much
bigger liberation than from uh political control of england the united states where lots of the
people who were so-called received their independence from england
had a lot of freedom that this lots of freedom compared to what slaves had but to have this liberation from slavery
it's a you know much bigger one in and and to appreciate how important it is
and to feel the poignancy or the the pain the fact that the delayed notification of some slaves and how
difficult you know the freedom from slavery actually was and and how even being freed from slave
there was still kind of the remnants of that oppression uh
continues continues to this day in the united states the repercussions
of all that so that leads to the topic for today
which is um has a little bit to do with the buddhist teachings on karma
but i think rather than particularly focus on buddhism so much it's like actually i think a
wide ranging teaching in many religions that sometimes summarize with a little
phrase you you reap what you sow
and in that or say differently that um
what we do plant seeds that will come to fruition
and and those seeds the quality or the characteristics of those seeds affects the plant that grows
and the fruit that comes and so seeds or activities the actions
that we do that are unwholesome will produce unwholesome fruit those which
are wholesome produce wholesome fruit and the
the um and in this in plenty of places including in buddhism
it seemed to be kind of a fundamental law that this is how things work in this world and whether it's that fundamental
and works all the way all the time this way it works a lot of times this way and we see
result we see this over and over and over and over again and in some ways the tremendous
unwholesomeness of slavery which um
you know it says that it used the word on wholesome here just seems almost i don't know just
you know just seems like it's belittling it almost but the almost the evil of slavery
is um um the actions of the people you know 200
years ago 150 years ago however long it was that all these centuries of slavery in this
on this continent that a tremendous unwholesomeness
set in motion a whole series of fruits whole series of conditions whole
series of things that are rippling through our societies to this day that uh we are the recipients
of this bitter fruit that was been pla of seeds that were planted in this
soil you know for centuries with slavery and we're still contending with it and
dealing with it in so many different ways so we have a very clear example of this
and it doesn't necessarily mean that all the fruits that are produced by the
seeds that we do are limited to affecting ourselves sometimes in the buddhist karma teaching
the idea is that you will you will reap the fruit of the seeds that you plant
but i think that i find it very helpful to separate out you know it from being so personal because the
effect of what we do spreads out beyond us and sometimes the impact around us is bigger than
the maybe the impact we experience in ourselves but to be the caretakers of the seeds
that we plant to be very careful with the what we do
so that what we do is not planting not planting unwholesome seeds
but rather planting wholesome seeds and it's presented in almost like as a law that if you do
something unwholesome it will produce unwholesome fruit
if you do something wholesome it will produce wholesome fruit
psychologically we can see that in ourselves that sometimes we can see that very clearly and the
if we do unwholesome things that certainly it set up sets up conditions
that supports more on wholesomeness sometimes if we spend a lot of time
being mean angry critical hostile to others
they start to act and behave around us in a way that starts being uncomfortable for us
and that discomfort that social discomfort that maybe being ignored or not addressed or something
is painful and some of this unwholesomeness that people
live within the world is a result of the pain they feel
the so much so that sometimes i've heard this kind of karma kind of principle be that if you
act out of pain it produces more pain if you act out of out of non-pain or out
of happiness you produce more happiness and so to some you know and so when the
cycles there's cycles of unwholesomeness where unwholesomeness produces more wholesome conditions and those unhelpful
conditions are make it easier to act on wholesomely and that produces more conditions and so
this is this cycle of self-perpetuating unwholesomeness that can go on
not only for an individual for a lifetime but also gets passed on to generation
generation of people that uh where there's a tremendous
sometimes hostility anger even violence and families and people kids growing up
now they learn that that's what you do and that's the kind of learned behavior and they grow up to be adults and they
continue it and they pass it on to their children and and you see we see it that both in
oneself that the causing suffering in the world is a causes conditions for further
distress further pain further discomfort and pain is a primary condition why
people do things in unwholesome way unskillful way
and so buddhist practice is a practice to interrupt the cycles of
unwholesomeness to not perpetuate that
and it's remarkable that what meditation can how meditation functions in that
to sit down and meditate and be still and be quiet and just focus on your breath
is a not such a simple passive practice when the mind stream
has all this momentum of uh thinking certain ways attitude certain
ways of of anger hostility greed uh
um delusion and um and just kind of
you can feel the power of that's the cycles of that kind of thinking sometimes and there's attitudes those desires
when we sit down to meditate and then simply just come back to the breathing is an interruption in that mindstream
and maybe it's an interruption that lasts only a millisecond before we have to do it again and again
we get pulled away but we're beginning to interrupt the cycles to stop the cycles getting off
the wheel of this unwholesome unwholesome actions
produce the conditions for further unwholesome conditions
and um the um the um
and so we interrupt it but we can do better than just interrupting and stopping it
it's also possible to plant the seeds of the wholesome to plant seeds for happiness for
well-being for health and things that are done
in a healthy way produce more health usually if we plant seeds for happiness
it produces more happiness that the actions that we do
whether it's actions of thought actions of speech or actions of our body
that there's a way in which they can produce more of the same so unwholesomeness produces more
unwholesomeness wholesomeness produces more wholesomeness
and and the challenge here or what's fascinating i think is
sometimes we find ourselves that it's easier to do the unwholesome
than it is to do the wholesome it's easier sometimes to be angry than to figure out how to address a
situation um in in a way that's peaceful or kind
that's still effective easier to be short-sighted
about the impact we have right now and anger sometimes is to stop something
that we see that we want to you know you know push something away or have an impact right now on something
that this oftentimes the unwholesome behavior is short-sighted more often than not i would suggest
whereas the doing the wholesome can feel like a lot more effort and work is
needed it takes a little bit more reflection and thinking and
ending the mindstreams of unwholesomeness and and so if you're lazy it's just something easier just to go ahead and do
the unwholesome if we want to get immediate results
on wholesomeness maybe it can do that but the to do the wholesome routes
takes a little bit more effort initially it might take more effort to look for kind of delayed
gratification understanding how to be wise in a wholesome way in a
kind supportive way and non-greed non-hatred
but as we practice and we start being in touch with
non-greed and non-hatred and non-delusion inside of us as a kind of a almost like a place or a
clarity or a purity or an openness or a peacefulness
then it becomes easier and easier to be that way and we start seeing that to act with
unwholesomeness is a kind of instant karma where the unwholesome itself
is hurts ouch whereas to act on the wholesome it feels
good it's an ah so here's the principle in very simple
language if we do something that has an ouch in it
it's going to produce more ouch if we do something it has an ah in it chances are it'll produce more
ah and so even though it might take more
work initially to do the wholesome the healthy that which comes from the best part of who we are
it's a training we're doing we're beginning to open the door that might be rusted shut the hinges are rusted and
tight and we're beginning to open it and discovering and opening the store and the heart
so that the the wholesomeness begins becomes second nature or becomes a place
that we act on and live on from the world and we start feeling that this is what's easy to do the
unwholesome is actually more stressful more difficult in its own way
and um and so we choose the easy route to live a
wholesome ways so initially it seems like the unwholesome can be easier
but over time the wholesome becomes easier and and the advantage of the
of the wholesome uh it doesn't uh produce the same
levels of difficulty in a life the after effect of wholesomeness
there's no cleanup that has to be done there's no retribution there's no people being
angry back at us and perpetuating the cycles whereas if we do unwholesome
we have to explain ourselves we have to apologize we have to defend ourselves we have to escape we have to shut down
we have to ignore we it's all this kind of secondary tertiary behavior
that comes out of the unwholesome that doesn't come out of the wholesome
so to live a simpler life a cleaner life by tuning into what is wholesome
so this distinction between wholesome and unwholesome is really key to the whole buddhist
practice and to begin understanding what this means and more importantly how to recognize it
in ourselves how to recognize the healthy feeling
of the wholesome and the unhealthy feeling of the unwholesome how to recognize
uh that we're planting seeds and we want to be careful with the seeds that we plant
and we plant the seeds through our actions and the quality of our actions if as the
has is the particular plant that we're planting
so we want to be careful with our actions and careful means
[Music] bring use your capacity for choice
to choose what you should do don't live a life that doesn't use this
tremendous gift that we're given that we can choose between we can choose
what we do and what we say don't live a life that doesn't have the simplest self-reflection
of being wise and aware of what we're going to say and do before we do
the and this is one of the uh
reasons to practice mindfulness that the more mindfulness we have the more
there is space in the mind the more there's almost like a pause in which we can see
where the moment of choice is and if we can see that moment of choice
to choose the wholesome and if we don't know what the wholesome thing is to do
then it's all it's generally quite wholesome to avoid the unwholesome that's enough
sometimes you don't have to make it more complicated than that or it's wholesome to say
pause and say you know i need to think about that or can we kind of just kind of let it
sit for a while as i reflect on this and can we take a time out so i can just be with myself a little bit
before i respond to this difficult conversation we're having that there are unwholesome response
there are there are wholesome responses that don't mean we understand how to be
kind or generous or loving but we know something else maybe the choice is to be more mindful
to be more present and really listen more deeply to ourselves and to what's going on around us
but mindfulness as mindfulness begins to take hold of our life we begin to have that space
where we can see there's more and more choice and if you see your choice then
you begin exercising your freedom the freedom to live wholesomely
and you certainly you have a certain freedom to live in unhealth life however if you live unwholesomely
you're actually in bondage you're actually caught in the grip of things like greed and
hatred and delusion and unholsum un-wholesome is not the place of freedom it's the opposite
and so to see the place of choice and see where the freedom is to do the
wholesome this is the path of the dharma this
so you might want to carry with you this little nugget of wisdom little phrase
that what you do
everything you do is planting a seed for a plant that will come to fruition
so if you act in ways if the if in acting there's an
ouch chances are you'll produce more ouch if the way you act has an eye in it that
feels healthy and good you probably have an ah plant and the
fruit of it will be uh somewhere in the world maybe for you or maybe for others
so may this practice that we do in this weekend of the first juneteenth holiday national holiday
may this practice that we do uh help our whole society
to interrupt these century-long cycles of violence
and hostility and racism that keeps going on may it may it stop
with our generation and in doing so may the wholesome
flower may we plant gardens and gardens and gardens filled with wholesome seeds that
supports all of us our whole society so thank you all very much