so warm hello to everyone and welcome
and one of the
simplest ways of talking about
the path of buddhism buddhist practice meditation buddhist meditation
the direction that buddhism is going is to avoid
causing harm everything about buddhism is somehow
encapsulated in this intention and it's a little bit unsatisfying and that would be nice to
have some grand positive statement but uh it's phenomenal
to live a life that doesn't cause harm
and in meditation that is not this means primarily
or not causing either not causing harm to oneself
or not having any thoughts that could be considered harmful for others
if they knew what you were thinking they would feel hurt
and and then in meditation part of the advantage of it it allows us
to see is that when we have thoughts that are hurtful harmful for others if they
knew what we were thinking or if we enacted them the very having those
thoughts chances are that they're also harming ourselves
and when we harm ourselves we set up the conditions the stresses the tensions within us
where it's easier than to harm others
so it's a quite a profound thing it's kind of like the and if you don't think it's enough for
you then think of it as the entry entry door to what is
greater or more profound it's the foundation not causing harm
so here we are and maybe this can be on the back of your mind the front of
your mind this beautiful thing this wonderful marvelous thing
that may be to sit here and be attentive enough to track your thoughts track what you're
doing to see if you can meditate for these minutes
uh putting aside any letting go of any ways in which you are
causing harm even the subtlest kind of harm with thoughts
as you meditate there could be subtle aversion towards hostility towards
your thoughts or your feelings or even a kind of uh certain kinds of
impatience a certain kind of uh tensing up around
something certain kind of tensing up around thoughts even
or a compulsion or pressure to think there's a kind of subtle subtle kind of
harming going on in attachment to what we're thinking about
so you don't have to be ahead of yourself but as you become sensitive to ways in which you're adding stress
suffering pain harm to yourself and meditation see if you can let go of it
stop doing that and if you can't do that which sometimes is difficult to let go
of it can you then hold that and hold yourself in compassion
it with care and kindness with a deep appreciation of how difficult it is to
human life and in that sense of appreciation of difficulty that to hold yourself kindly
breathe with it so to take a comfortable
meditation posture
and in your comfortable posture to
adjust yourself so that your body can feel a little bit more alert
maybe a little lengthening of the spine
maybe as there's a way of opening the chest a bit
maybe your hands can be in a position that supports confidence
being present here confidently
gently closing your eyes
and then taking a few gentle but deeper breaths three quarters full
and as you exhale release tensions and holdings
tightening in your body that might be easy to relax
and then letting your breathing return to normal
part of the value of relaxing the muscles the body as you begin meditating
is to support a condition where you're
sensitive to the subtle ways in which we think and
feel and want which cause subtle harm to ourselves
subtle even subtle stress while we meditate
as you exhale perhaps relaxing the muscles of the face
muscles that maybe get overused in the course of everyday
life they have a chance to soften and relax
no need to try so much
softening relaxing the shoulders
and maybe even the area of your shoulder blades can soften a bit
relaxing softening in the chest
and softening in the belly
and then to awaken awareness of breathing
as if you could awaken within the body within your breathing
without force force
without expectation that leads to disappointment
without even the need to succeed which can also lead to disappointment
but rather than a need to succeed perhaps
a dedication to engage to be present
to the best that you can whatever that might be
so you're generous to yourself and your capacity to be present
when the mind wanders off
not to do the subtlest harm to oneself towards being discouraged or upset or
disappointed or critical
instead of old any of those things just begin again
simple open relaxed begin again and again and again
perhaps even enjoying or loving
the exploration of what it means what it is like to be aware of breathing
entering into the world of the body breathing the sensations in the nose or in the
chest or in the belly as you breathe
letting that be the center of your universe just here with breathing
being sensitive to the slightest ways in which there is harm being made or stress being
added tension being created
and even the most subtle and slightest you might feel
see if you can let go of it to relax it
see if you can trust that way of being
that needs no stress
imagine just imagine what your inner landscape would be like
if there was no harm ever
coming out of it no tendency no movement of harm
stress criticalness
no unwholesome harmful thoughts about others
imagine what it would be like in your own mind and heart
imagine perhaps the simplicity or the clarity the peacefulness
if we can rest in a place within
that doesn't cause harm resting confidently that this is a good
place
and then coming to the end of this sitting
turning your attention out into the world
and may you offer may each of us offer
non-harming to the world around us
whatever ways in which this meditation has supported us
do not get pulled into tendencies of harm-making
may that be expressed in a wish
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
may how we live our lives contribute to that possibility for others
may we live for the welfare and happiness of this world
uh
so this is the third talk now on living a dharmic life
so if you want to receive some of the benefits that could come from becoming a monastic
living in a retreat center being on retreat a lot where the whole life is kind of
dedicated to the dharma to practicing if you want those benefits
without doing those things just to continue with your ordinary everyday life
so i'm offering different ways that you can maybe get quite a bit of this benefit
and a lot of it depends on how much you dedicate yourself to these simple practices i'm teaching
but simple doesn't mean they're not profound or or phenomenally impactful
so for this one for today i'd like to offer something that maybe
is the only thing you really have to know about buddhism if you really live this idea
live this practice live in this approach to life if you do it well and thoroughly that
all of buddhism kind of comes along and follows all the insights all the ways of growing spiritually and
personally follow and that is
to be dedicated to causing no harm that's it
if you keep that with you if you you know if you had a ring made that was engraved and
no harm so you re you remember it all the time you know that this is really the heart
of it the center of it and um you know and that's all you did
was to live by that and become more and more refined in how you live that that life more more subtle and no harm
in any direction to towards oneself to other people to the planet to the environment
to not cause any harm and if uh it seems like too high a
challenge and maybe impossible um then not causing any intentional harm
uh you know willful harm and um and at least start there
the um so i'm just not making this up for myself that
there's an ancient teaching that uh the primary characteristic
of the dharma is in fact non-harming and the
in such a strong association with the dharma this idea of not causing harm and the teachings we i
did gave in the last few weeks on wholesomeness and unwholesomeness could be understood as
non-harming and harm that what's unwholesome is in some way or other defined by what
causes vexation suffering stress um on our system and onto the world
and what is wholesome is that which does the opposite doesn't cause harm it doesn't cause a cause of fixation and
distress and stress and
and the advantage of this one simple little thing causing no harm to use that as a
even if you not can't live up to it completely to use that as a reference point as a
gauge to really see much more clearly than ever before perhaps
that all the ways that you do cause harm now not to harm yourself even more
the way we live and dedicate ourselves to non-harming we do it in a way that's not harming it
doesn't work to dedicate oneself to non-harming and do it in a way that's you know we
set up to harm ourselves even more so but to but to use this gauge this
reference point of non-harming so we can see much more clearly
you know what we're going off and going wrong i suspect because on on freeways they have all these uh
lines for the lanes on the freeway that um those lines help us
navigate and keep straight on the freeway and but if there were no lines i think we'd be you know
swerving a little bit more moving back and forth further than we do and uh so the same way the this idea
principle of non-harming is kind of like the lines that uh for our
life so in our lane and we notice much more uh carefully then when we're liable to
kind of swerve too far in the direction of harming or
and i want to underscore again both to ourselves and to others and
um the uh so part of the function of this principle of non-harming is becomes a
mirror so we see ourselves better and then if we see ourselves really honestly
uh uh to have the self-honesty and see ourselves what um
that we were causing harm then what then what do we do then
and i suspect that seeing this clearly
will naturally change what you'll want to do how you want to live your life how you want to
talk or do what you what you want to do it's when we don't see it so clearly
that we tend to go ahead and cause harm so for example with speech which is mean
speech which is maybe spiteful or critical of someone angry at someone
you we might even know that we're doing it but we might justify it you know they deserve it or this is the way i'm trying to get my way
or something but if we remember that the principle is non-harming
and then well then we can have a explorer this in what way is my
statement what i'm going to make to my friend where's the harm here what kind of harm
am i causing am i harming myself am i harming our friendship my friend is this something that
i've been doing regularly and what's the impact of it and maybe is there another alternative to
take care of myself i think that's what i'm doing can i figure out some way to take care of myself without saying
this harmful thing this spiteful thing or something and so that kind of reflection a
reflective life is part of a dharmic life it's not only about just showing up and being
mindful and to in all situations it's also being reflective
and contemplating considering and some of those considerations sometimes are debates
within ourselves and going back and forth but if you have the the referee the or the principle of
non-harming as a reference point for those conversations in yourself and the
questioning and wondering um then maybe also you'll come up with a question
what's the alternative to doing something harmful is there some way that i benefit more
some way that others benefit more if um if i
say this in a different way and now what does it take to say it differently maybe
i need to learn new skills skills and you know a simple thing to point to these days is for some people
is non-violent communication techniques but there's a whole slew of ways of speaking that
that are not making statements about other people so for example that simple principle of
making i statements rather than use your statements talking about what we're feeling
which doesn't mean saying i feel that you're wrong it means when you say x i feel hurt or
feel afraid and and so to find new ways of being in
the world that are maybe more intelligent more creative more innovative
um than uh the ancient primitive simplistic way reptilian way
maybe of um of being aggressive or causing harm again towards oneself and others
and then as we live by this one simple principle not causing harm to begin to appreciate
what begins to bubble up into surface to appreciate
the peace that comes the ease that comes the calm that comes the confidence that comes
with not causing harm the way we start feeling better for ourselves
and start appreciating that there is this i think i would think that in most people
there is a strong instinct to not cause harm that's almost an instinct like you know
pulling the hand off the hot stove if if we're quiet
mindful enough to really be sensitive to where that instinct lives in us and
we're not so sensitive when the unjusta mind that's spinning and angry and afraid
and desirous greedy if that gets the upper hand and we're claustrophobic with
these thoughts and ideas and and preoccupations that um
that then there's no space to feel this wonderful place that's i think in
most people this wonderful place that really doesn't want to cause harm
and now one of the reference points for this idea also is is the idea that if you have
you know for many of us if you have a young child or grandchild or niece or nephew or
neighbor or something who's quite young maybe still a baby how much we don't want to cause harm how
much care we would do and to not cause any harm there and to
people we love and and if we have it there
the idea in buddhist practice is to begin universalizing it is to spread it out to all beings that
we see that not exactly that they're family but as if they're family we don't want to cause
harm for them and one of the important family members for this whole enterprise
is yourself and i can't underscore how important it is not to cause harm to oneself and
so if someone comes and criticizes you for anything at all watch yourself carefully there see what
your inner response is and see if there's some way in which you respond
that you're actually causing self-harm to yourself if you're too quick to apologize if
you're too quick to be critical of yourself and to uh diminish yourself and and and kind of
confess you know like oh how about a terrible person i am um the um uh if i if
that's not done wisely and carefully we end up hurting ourselves and sometimes we do it intentionally
because um if we show other people that we're hurting ourselves and feeling really bad
and then we more likely think that they believe us or that they see that they're having an
impact that they want to have on us which is actually to make sure that to put us us in our place but
what exactly does it mean to cause harm to oneself and is it necessary can there be a confession of fault
can there be admission of yes i did something wrong where we don't diminish ourselves we
don't belittle ourselves we don't harm ourselves and in fact maybe
we can learn how to confidently say yes i apologize when
necessary fully and clearly with with certain kind of strength
say i made a mistake and i'm not going to i'm going to try my best not to do that again i'm so sorry
how can i make amends what can i do for you or but do it from a place where we're not
diminished or harming ourselves so in all directions non-harm
and i'll repeat what i said at the beginning because i feel it's such an important point that i kind of
i believe that if this if you hold on to this one principle
this idea you really don't have to believe anything else that buddhism teaches
you don't have to hold on to anything you don't have to learn all kinds of complicated practices but you but to
really become refined and subtle with it and if you do that in a nice
easy chair and close your eyes you'll then begin going through layers and layers of
discovering how the you know there's subtle movements of harm in the mind
itself quietly within and begin releasing them and releasing them releasing them
and even to the point where the word harm is not quite the right word anymore
maybe but rather the word is stress that we're also learning to not add any
stress and in deep meditation practice and we see
the subtle you know in ordinary life insignificant but in meditation quite significant
ways in which we self-harm and that are really we see as forms of stress tension and
just we can let go of them let go of them let go of them to that place of safety that place of
peace that place where we can live breathing
safe and free from all tendencies to harm
so thank you