so hello everyone and on this last day of
2021 and
in a maybe in an interesting way the future is silent
at this point and we're going into the silence
so in in the teachings of the buddha there's a
concept called noble silence and it's uh
in the modern world in our retreats we call noble silence the practice of
being silent during the tweet not being not having conversations during the retreat but in the
in the buddhist teaching noble silence is the kind of the rich golden silence
that can occur in deep meditation
and i think this warm silence the silence of a warm spring
wind that brings about the flowering of the cherry blossoms
in china and japan sometimes it's called the golden wind
so maybe today the interesting way of meditating
would be to discover what it's like to experience
yourself in meditation in silence what's available
when the mind is silent how do you experience breathing
if you're silent in your awareness of it
if there's a continuity of awareness in the silence
what happens if you're aware of your body silently without any thoughts
and there might be difficult to do but there might be gaps
in your thinking pauses in your thoughts the end of the out breath there might be
a time for your thoughts to go quiet or it could be that the thoughts become
quiet enough and calm enough that you're aware of the silence around them
it's possible to have enough silence to if silence like in the
worldly silence can be so silent the place you're at that you still can hear someone speak
but you hear them in this vast field of silence so the same thing we're thinking in our
own mind to be aware of that silently your thinking silently
so what happens to you what unfolds for you if you stay close to the silence of the
mind if you if you stay close to the silence of awareness itself
independent free of thoughts and thinking
and what's that what happens what's if that's the emphasis if that's the priority you give to this meditation
then in those moments when the mind is silent really notice what's happening
and there's probably more moments of silence available to you than you
avail yourself of there's probably more points of silence
and it might be easier to tap into silence than you realize
and uh so you might want to um
you know tap into it or settle open to it allow for it
however brief it might be and see what happens in the silence of the mind
okay
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
there's an art to receiving the world
receiving the future that comes into the present with the silent mind
the kind of silence that doesn't have expectations or demands assumptions
judgments about what comes from the future into the present
this is particularly nice when it's a friend who's or coming stranger who comes
and to be able to receive anyone with a healthy silence of the mind
is a gift we give them so that we're there to receive them
closer to how they are than to how we
think things should be here with the projections of our assumptions
and judgments ideas and history and
expectations to be able to receive the people who
come into our lives with an initial silence
maybe they don't know we're being silent but inside we're there to
receive what is coming as it is
before the noise before the thoughts before the judgments and assumptions and
expectations it's a generous thing to do
and perhaps that can be the case for this new year as well
who knows what the new year will bring but perhaps we can meet it first and
foremost with the silence of the mind
that allows give space for us to be wise informed clear about what
is happening may whatever benefit that comes from our
meditative capacity ability
be used for the welfare and happiness of others
may we be clear and fresh and wise
in how we meet others and support others may we be free from our judgments and
our bias and our projections our assumptions expectations
may we not burden people with our demands
but may we be upright and strong confident in ourselves
confident take care of ourselves
and in the silence of our mind learn to be loving and kind and wise
of how we do respond may it be
that our practice supports all beings to be happy
all beings to be safe all beings
to be peaceful and all beings to be free
[Music] uh
[Music]
so what i would like to do this morning is rather than having me speak
um to read perhaps some of the questions you
might have about the practice about the teachings about the dharma and i'll try to respond if you can if
you're able to write it in the chat i'll read them the questions that come and while you're taking your time maybe
to formulate a question or two and the
um couple of announcements so one is that tonight for the new year's eve imc
has a new year's eve event that you can participate on zoom and it includes some nice kind of new
year's eve kind of things that are appropriate for meditators and now including
meditating silently into the new year and the way that you know this online
offerings work if some of you might find actually it's a nicer time to celebrate new year's eve
if you're on the east coast and and get to go to bed earlier
and uh so you can find information about that on the imc website both under the in the
calendar and also in the what's new section on the home page the other is that
i've said this a few times now but so starting monday i'll start a series on the sati patana sutta so last year we
did the anapanasati sutta the instructions of mindfulness of breathing and this time it's the instructions on
mindfulness of of
you know the mindfulness of life as a whole mindfulness of these four different domains of practice
body feelings mind states and dharmas and this is the foundational text for
this mindfulness tradition so we'll go through that slowly over a few weeks
so let's see the questions you know so let me see how i can if i can what i can do to
yeah so let's see
so there i don't see any questions yet it's a little hard to track on the youtube but let's see
and uh
how to let go of how to let fear go cultivate trust
yeah not let fear grow cultivate trust you can cultivate trust
by learning to be confident that it's okay to address fear to develop a willingness and wisdom
about how to be with fear so rather than thinking that we're not supposed to be afraid we can first focus
on how to how to bring mindfulness to fear how to
be present for it and and
but to do that it usually takes some it helps to have some ability to have inner stability
and so one of the reasons to practice mindfulness or breathing for example or any kind of meditation practice that
calms the mind down settles us down is we have some some degree of stability
so we can turn our attention to the fear without being triggered by the fear if we keep being triggered by the fear
of getting more afraid then probably it's not the right time to bring attention to fear and then the
confidence can come with knowing that i think the best thing for me to do now
is to um find another way to step away from the fear um if it's a real world fear something's
happening that is dangerous maybe i have confidence you can leave it
find make yourself safe if it's something in your imagination your thoughts or you know your anxiety
then maybe even sometimes distracting yourselves uh exercising doing something that pulls
you out of it so you're not caught in the fear of tr of the trap of fear can be useful
and then um but your practice with fear is a wonderful thing to do and one of the ways to do it is to
have the ability to stable attention to bring attention to your fear feel it in your body feel where it is
and have this attitude of helping the fear feel safe now sometimes our reactivity to fear is
we're trying to get rid of it or we're afraid of the fear but to meet the fear with this kind of gentleness and
kindness so the fear itself feels like it's held in a field of safety this is so
helpful
i feel like greed hatred and delusion are all born out of fear what are the teachings about fear there's a second
question about fear so yeah i think it's quite wise to see how
much greed hating delusion is born out of fear and so what another reason why really to
get a handle on fear and to work through it there is a discourse where the buddha
talks about working with his own fear before he was enlightened and
and what he did was uh whatever posture he was in while he was meditating walking sitting lying down that the fear
arose he continued doing what he was doing but then he would just be present with the fear until it had passed
so that doesn't involve a lot of insight into the fear or you know the kind of detailed
mindfulness instructions we often give around fear but it is a uh
instructions to give it its due its time from a mind that's stable
then mind that doesn't get pulled into its orbit pulled into its gravitational pull but then not be troubled by it and let
it pass on its own but you know fear is a big important topic and at some point in the pandemic
i think i did a whole week on fear so you can go back and see what i had to say then
and uh or you know an audio dharma there's talks on fear and and there's a lot lots lots it's a
really great topic and for practice
and what are what is cons
what is consciousness and how does it fit with karma
yeah that's one of the what is consciousness is such a great question and
you know i kind of suspect no one really knows and
though everybody's a lot of people try to know it and there's a lot of claims people know what it is
it's possible that uh consciousness is not really minimal to
a thing it's a process and as a process it's not a one thing it's not an entity but it's kind of like
um a uh the sum of the total of many different
mental processes that come together and there's some kind of way and um and what that way is it might just be
an image and the consciousness might be a a secondary sense of the overall
functioning of the mind who knows what it is in buddhism consciousness is
more the cognizing function of the mind the mind that knows the simplest kind of knowing
knowing hot as hot cold as cold knowing
you know color as color just the simplest kind of knowing but that's not very satisfying for many
people in the west who have very strong association what consciousness is and
part of the reason is so powerful this question of consciousness is many people
have very strongly identified themselves with consciousness and so i'm conscious therefore i am
and this strong identification of consciousness itself is reinforced by some religious teachings outside of buddhism
maybe in buddhism even but this identification makes it very very tricky to kind of work with it
but what's the connection to consciousness and karma there's kind of two answers to that one
is that consciousness itself is an activity like all activities and so in a sense it's
it's it's uh it creates karma perhaps and it is the recipient of karmic consequences
just like anything else the second answer is often um has to do with the theory of rebirth whereas uh
some people have this idea that it's consciousness which goes from one lifetime to another and so what's the connection to the
karmic uh momentum over time over multiple lives and um that's like what the question is
about it's a good question but i'm not really qualified or able to give a coherent
answer on that topic
so i'm trying to follow them in the order in which they were spoken
how to work with narcissistic people
i i don't know about that narcissistic people it's a little bit hard to work with them do we have to work with them
how do we relate to them maybe
and it's a little hard because i think of narcissism as a kind of a very strong
delusion that people are caught in and don't know they're caught in it and a very strong delusion about self
and self-importance and strong self-orientation and
you could have compassion for them i think it was a lot of suffering and being narcissistic
and um gave them some space um
not space to allow them to you know override you but kind of sometimes just
you know just don't participate in the narcissistic ideations they have but be kind
do you have suggestions on how to silence thoughts
well thoughts are connected to so many other things they're connected
there's a lot of thinking connected to physical tension physical pressure they're connected to
our emotional lives and so to relax the body and relax our emotions
to relax the mind are all ways of quieting the thinking mind
and then um and then the other thing is to do another thing way to do it is to
some people do is to practice concentration practice to really give a little emphasis on
staying with a breath not missing one in-breath one out breath just really staying maybe counting the breath
counting one to ten or counting one to one if that's easier and then start over again at one and
just really count and that's sometimes like counting and really staying with the breath can a little bit over time
remove the energy the fuel that goes into the thinking and begins to redirect the focus of the
mind to not be thinking anymore but to be present to kind of like
exhaust the thinking mind of its fuel and things get quiet
and then also you can turn your attention um and look thinking right in the eye say i see you and sometimes what
you really can be silently aware of thinking it's enough to quiet it down
so there's a lot to be said about the great question but this this context that's what i'll say
what came first a thought or awareness what a great
question maybe that's for you to discover and maybe
it's going to be discovered moment by moment it's never like a final answer to the question um
sometimes what comes first a body sensation or a thought and sometimes you'll see the body sensation arises
first and then a thought follows and sometimes a thought comes first and a body sensation follows
how do you not grade yourself and how effective you are being with meditation sessions
yeah that could be difficult so what comes to mind at this moment is um
uh start counting how many times you do it and keep tab you're going to keep a record of how often you do it
and at some point when you get to 323 you might kind of give up this is
ridiculous there's enough of this or you'll be humored wow here i am again
can you talk about heart space and how it shows up in everyday life heart space
yeah i think that the question maybe would be
not how heart space shows up in everyday life but how everyday life shows up in heart
space to sit and for example to meditate and have your heart space opened up
then that that stay there and let your life come to
come into your heart rather than you going to meet the world keep the heart space just keep expanding
it make it as spacious and open as possible making your heart as wide as the world
and then let the world occur you know do its thing within the heart space
how to set interpersonal boundaries without feeling that you are being selfish
yeah one of the ways is to tell people what your needs are uh tell them to tell people that uh you
know it's uh that you have you have need for a little bit more
time to process things and so you need to have a little more space
between people or you need physical distance between people just so you can kind of stay in
touch with yourself that when there's people cross your boundaries too much you lose touch with yourself you don't
understand yourself well enough you don't know how to be wise and respond kindly and so because you have that need
could you please step back a little bit can you please give me a little bit space and and um so you're talking about
your own needs so you're not telling someone they're doing something wrong you're you're saying with the impact
they have on you and that impact is not so helpful in that you're asking their help to
to create more space and if they don't want to help you then then then you know that there's a bigger issue going on
that if they don't take you into account and care about how you are than your needs
how does one let go oops
oh i'm sorry it kind of oh yeah how does
one let go when one wants to but keeps circling the same ground
[Music] well that's uh one of the things i find useful then is to discover what are the
underlying emotions that are keeping me clinging or keeping me uh
hesitant to let go the emotions have such a big uh are such a big effect on us
and so there are earlier questions about fear is there something you're afraid of and that's why you're clinging or is
something you're afraid of that's why you're not willing to let go of or is it anger or resentment or is it
anticipation and expectation what's the emotion that's uh under
underpinning it all and if you can identify that then we want to do uh
the um mindfulness of the emotion until it's passed or loosened up enough and
then you might find that the clinging is not so tight and it might be easier to let go of it or have a wiser
relationship to it
can you speak it to the distinction between buddhist and psychological depth
when releasing oneself from an area of stickiness
yeah i don't know if it's so useful to make a strong distinction about it
but
and it's a little dangerous you know to make any statement limiting any one of these buddhism or psychology to some simple
idea of what one is there's so much overlap
and but i've seen sometimes in the world of psychology psychotherapy
i've seen people refer to depth as being understanding your biography really deeply and well
going through the layers of what happened to us in life and the influences on us and the impact on us
and then and sometimes understanding that really well helps people to get unstuck
in buddhism the focus is less on our biography and more to go through the layers
of what's what's operating in the present moment and it might go through some of the same
stuff but it's a different angle towards it buddhism is always about the present moment
and so but the present moment has all those our past history the karma of our what's happened to us
exists in the present moment kind of layers so buddhism tends not to be so retrospective
in the depth but rather more into the layers of the mind something like that
i lost some of what you said in answer to your question well this has been recorded so you can go listen to it
again can you speak about moving through grief
it's such an important topic grief should be respected it's a grief is not a mistake
but see it as something that's really important and and maybe even a valuable part of life in
spite of being extremely painful and difficult but
we want to try to avoid grieving poorly
it isn't that we don't want to grieve but grieving poorly what i mean by that is resisting grief
uh being angry at grief trying to fix grief trying to get over grief uh taking antidepressants because of our
grief anything or alcohol because of it or blaming ourselves for grieving or
feeling that we should be over it by now all that i call poor grieving poorly
grieving richly is to find a quality time
and quality heart space to use a language earlier comment
in which to allow the grief its time and allow ourselves to really feel the grief from the waves of grief and
respect it deep respect for grief if we get out of the way of our grief
our heart our grief tends to know how to process itself and work through and even grief which seems impossible to get
through our hearts are amazingly resilient if we get out of the way
but when we grieve poorly we're kind of like interfering with the natural process and so those are some brief comments
about it i hope that gives you a little bit to to go with
and silence feels like loneliness how to
embrace the silence in these pandemic days oh yes um you know sometimes i think we need a
dictionary of silence that silence is so many different things and it communicates so much
and some people have been silenced and it's been very painful and some people
getting the silent treatment means that they're kind of dismissed or
their existence is denied and that people do horrible things to others to each other uh with the silent treatment
with silencing people and so the emphasis on silence sometimes in meditation or meditation retreats
it can be very hard for some people have this very strong history and associations with the silence
and um and so spending a lot of time with silently alone like a pandemic and and
having it mixed up with being loneliness can kind of kind of cast a certain perspective on silence
which is not so useful and how to embrace the silence of these
pandemic days i think that if silence is if loneliness is an issue during the pandemic days
then you know it's certainly for someone who's doing meditation loneliness is a
quite a a worthwhile focus for the mindfulness to sit quietly and really
turn your attention to the loneliness in a deep penetrating way loneliness is an activity of the mind
loneliness is not a you know it's not inherent
some there's operations and thoughts ideas processing of the mind that produces the
sensations feelings belief of loneliness and that's good news
because it's possible to quiet it down it's possible to free oneself of it
and to do that through mindfulness we turn our attention towards it and really feel it and sense it in some deep way
and learn to see it in such a way that the seeing of my of loneliness is stronger
than loneliness um and then there's also a kind of ordinary things to do
sometimes try to reach out to people if you can at all find ways to maybe if you can not be so
lonely and um even uh you know putting on a mask and going
walk in a public park where there's some other people around the three-dimensional people
might be you know kind of a good medicine so that we're not so alone in our house
by ourselves too much it's going to be very very hard and things but this pandemic's been you know
so unfortunate how difficult it has been for so many people so it's almost time i think we've
stopped so thank you for the questions i appreciate them very much it's wonderful for me to get the
sense of you know what you're working with and your concerns and
and be able to have this exchange i hope it's nice for you and um
and uh i look i'm sorry for those of you who i couldn't answer your questions because there were so many but
um i believe questions are always good whether they're answered or not it's it's always good to be questioning and
having questions and maybe questions you asked or questions you you can then now try to answer for
yourself if i didn't answer them or if i did
so i look forward to seeing you on monday and being with you and um
and i hope you wish you a good new year's eve and first day of 2022
and thank you all