good morning or wherever you might be maybe it's
afternoon maybe it's some really early in the
morning
for those of you who don't know me i'm diana clark i'm
sitting in for gail this morning just so he can have a day off
this morning and so for those of you on youtube
they will be back tomorrow at uh 7 am
for those of you on zoom you know who i am so uh warm welcome
warm welcome
as a little introduction i um heard this from gil
some time ago and i liked this uh idea that
when we're practicing with anapanasati when we're practicing with the breath
we might think of it as in the same way that we go for a walk we might go on a
pilgrimage and we keep walking one step after
another we keep walking whether we are going
whether we are there's things to notice there's
landscape there's buildings there's other people but
because we're on a pilgrimage we just keep
walking doesn't mean that we're not noticing other things but we keep walking
maybe sometimes with a little bit more emphasis on noticing the way we're walking and sometimes
the attention shifts a little bit to the way that we are noticing whatever there is
to be noticed so in the same way with
anapanasati practice that is mindfulness of breathing practice we stay with the breath
just like we might keep walking
and we might notice things the landscape of our experience if you
will and but we keep with the breath we keep
noticing sometimes it's in the foreground sometimes it's in the background but we keep noticing the
experience of breathing
and then to take this analogy a little bit further we might say that when we're walking we
might encounter stray dogs and some of them are so cute and we stop
and we pet the dog maybe for weeks we completely forget that we're walking on
a pilgrimage maybe there are barking dogs that
we ignore they they don't really seem to be a problem so we
don't give them any attention we just keep walking
maybe there are some barking dogs that we meet and we open our hand we show them our hand
to show that we're safe that we're okay we're safe for them
they don't have to be worried about us
maybe there are some dogs that come up to us and we clearly say to them no
go home
so through all these different dogs that might visit we just keep walking
so that's what i'd gil offered this initially and i kind of like this idea
there might be different experiences that arise but maybe there's some way that we can
just stay with the sensations of breathing
okay so before our guided meditation
just taking alert posture
posture that expresses our intention to practice
as well as some warmth some care kindness
so some uprightness but that doesn't have some coldness or
or hardness to it
and to connect with the experience of breathing
feeling the breaths
noticing the quality of the breath
are they smooth are they rough
maybe the breaths are long maybe they're a little more short
maybe the quality is maybe some deep breaths or maybe they feel a little more shallow
for just noticing
feeling the rhythm of the breath
an in-breath and then an out breath
and then is there a way that we can stretch our awareness
expand our awareness to include the whole physical body
this expanding stretching of the awareness helps us to
not get lost into our experience
or contracted around something
it might be helpful to imagine sometimes with the exhales a
little bit of blowing up the awareness just like we might blow up a balloon in a relaxed
easy manner
having the body be the arena of our attention
again nothing in particular needs to be happening we're being with
sensations of the breathing and with the body
can we offer our attention to different parts of the body
the face
the shoulders
the chest
the belly
it might be that bringing our attention to these
different areas allow a certain amount of softening
relaxing letting go of the tension
maybe not also we don't have to make it a problem if
there's still some tension some holdings
but is there a way that we can let go of some of the holding patterns in the
body maybe with the exhale there's a little
bit of release very subtle
this relaxing calming is more associated with allowing
letting go than with any doing
we might check in and see if we're creating any new tension by
expectations we might have
we can't notice any pleasant sensations that are associated
with breathing
this can be very subtle but maybe there's a little feeling of
smoothness
maybe there's a little feeling of letting go with the exhale
that has some pleasure with it
maybe there's some pleasant sensations associated with the
just being intimate with our breathing
maybe there's a feeling of contentment
a vague feeling of okay-ness
this may not be our dominant experience it may be just a corner
of our experience
can we tune into this aspect of our experience any sense
of okayness contentment pleasantness
and allow this to be a support
being settled in the body feeling the sensations of breathing
you can now turn towards the mental
experience a gentle inquiry are there any thoughts
some mental activity that takes us away from the present moment experience
and just like we did with the body and with the breath we can notice
the experience of this mental activity
rather than trying to make it go away
perhaps they have a lot of energy associated with them
or maybe not so much energy with this mental activity
are the thoughts more discursive writing novels so to speak
are they very simple descriptive just a single sentence
somewhere in between
just noticing the quality not so much the content
there might be a sense of constriction or tightness around
the breath i'm sorry around the breath but also around the
mental activity maybe there's a sense of ease
spaciousness openness can feel into that associated with the
thoughts the mental activity is there a tightening or
opening
maybe there's a sense of pushing or pulling not liking liking this movement of
wanting we can notice that also
maybe there's a sense of looking for something searching
how does that feel what is that experience
letting the content of the thought take care of itself
more being with the experience
of having these thoughts
maybe we're identified with the thoughts this is me this is
mine
no matter which way we are experiencing the thoughts
as we breathe in as we breathe out can we
relax soften these mental activities
letting the activities of the mind come to rest
maybe the breaths themselves are can reassure the mind in
some kind of way that the mind doesn't need to be so
active
not getting involved with the thinking but trusting the breath
not all mental activity needs to stop
we're just allowing a calming a softening of whatever is
happening in the mind
we can do this by being aware of mental activity without getting involved getting tangled up in
all the while breathing in
and breathing out
staying with the sensations of breathing
allows the settling of the mind and the body
the calming
so that we aren't pushed around
by this mental activities or
sensations in the body so that we don't spend all our
energy reacting to
responding to trying to take care of trying to make different our experience
and instead we can be with our experience
sometimes that includes being with others
if we have a certain amount of calmness then we're more apt to really be able to deeply listen
to what others are saying to us really be present for others
as well as for ourselves in a way that perhaps
we might be a refuge for others if we're not agitated we're not busy
with ourselves
so may our practice be a support for us
and for those around us
may all beings find ease and happiness
may all beings know peace
good morning again
and for those of you on youtube who
weren't there at 6 45 this morning i'm diana clark and gil will be back tomorrow at seven
california time he's spending some time with his family this morning
so just say a few words about anapanasati practice mindfulness of
breathing that gill has been doing on these mornings
and as many of you know there are 16 steps and gil has been through the first half
the first eight and there's a number of ways in which we might understand
all these steps and the organization of them
one way is that this is a progression of getting to know one aspect of our
experience the body the mind
and then after becoming familiar with it and being with it then there's some
letting go some releasing of that aspect of experience
when the time is right doesn't have to be in a hurry we just take our time
allowing the experience perhaps to melt or soften
as best we can so we started with noticing the physical
aspect of our experience breathing and this breathing accompanies
us through all the other explorations
just in the same way that when we're on a pilgrimage we just keep walking
one step after another one breath after another
then after breathing then there's expanding to include the whole body
the bodily sensations of course breath is occurring within a body
so to expand the awareness to include the body
and in this we also include any sense of contentment any sense of okayness any pleasure
pleasant sensations associated with this bodily experience
and allowing those to be a support
as we continue on our pilgrimage so to speak
i mean then we turn towards the mental aspect of our experience
including the physical sensations that are associated with
thinking or whatever mental activity we might be having
sometimes that's really subtle the physical aspect of the mental experience so without getting
tangled up and trying to
figure it out maybe just kind of being with the experience without being
identified or lost in the experience in some ways it's
a little bit of a pulling back from our thinking and of course
noticing how our judging our evaluation of our experience is yet one more mental
activity we might feel feel how that feels the judging the pushing the pulling
wanting not wanting this is desirable not desirable
so this to help support this experiencing mental activity is it can
be a stepping back of some sort so kind of a pulling back a little bit and knowing what is taking place rather
than being fully immersed into it
and mental activity deserves our attention sometimes we might have the idea that we just have to get rid of it
but it deserves our attention because when unattended it often is running our lives
without our even knowing it
so then there can be after becoming familiar with mental activity there can be a calming
as softening or relaxing of that mental activity
and notice that i'm not saying we have to eliminate eradicate exterminate something like this
the mental activity we're just allowing it to quiet
maybe i'll say a few words about what can be some supports for this
one is that the earlier steps in anapanasati the breath being with the bodily
sensations allowing some ease or relaxation of the bodily sensations
can be a tremendous support for calming the mental activity
so if we find ourselves really caught up and busy with thinking can just
incline the mind towards the physical experience including the physical experience of
thinking so that's one way is to ground
our awareness in the present moment in the embodied presence that we have right now
and this also includes being aware of some of the pleasant sensations
we might be having there might be some ease with the breath some
smoothness of the breath there also might be some vague diffuse
experiences of just some contentment or okayness
maybe we can incline the mind that direction that also can be a support for the
calming of the mental activities is to if there's some aspect of ease
to tune into that aspect of ease
and maybe we can rather than feeling like we have to get
rid of our thoughts or make them slow down or go away or whatever ideas we might have
maybe we can have this emphasis on a gentle inquiry is this
helpful or is it unhelpful
is it helpful in promoting a sense of ease and freedom
peace and or am i learning something here is this valuable
or or is there a feeling i'm just stuck and i'm just going around and around and
around there is no sense of potential potential learning or
potential freedom or ease
so that might be one another way to kind of work with mental activity is to shift away from it has to be
different to shift towards well is this helpful and sometimes the answer to that can
bring a different reaction response to our mental activity which might allow that mental activity to
unfold in a way that is helpful
another thing that we might do is to just do a gentle inquiry of what's fueling this thinking
there might be an emotion and just like at the beginning of this
um before the guided meditation i talked about when we're on a pilgrimage there
might be some parking dogs and one way to be with them is just to
like show them our open hands and show them that we're safe for them so is there a way in which
we can be safe for our emotions to be expressed to show up
can we maybe in some way listen deeply to ourselves and
allow the emotion to arise without getting tangled up and thinking
that it has to be otherwise or has to be different
can we just create the space for our emotional experience
and that might also kind of soften some of the mental activity
as we soften the fuel what's supporting that mental activity
and then maybe one other thing that i will say is
sometimes it can be skillful to replace unhelpful thoughts with other mental
activities that are more helpful
so to intentionally do something an example might be to do some
loving-kindness practice if we feel that we're filled with rage and ill-will and thoughts of
harming hostility in a way that is not helpful or healthy or
we just feel like we're lost in it
so we can do some loving kindness practice in whichever way it's easiest
we're not necessarily towards the object through which we have hostility but just
incline the mind towards where it's easy with a lovable
being allowing the mind to kind of like calm down and settle with this loving
kindness so it might bring in to like replace
thoughts and comfortable thoughts with some or unhelpful thoughts with some other
thoughts another way might be to use our imagination
sometimes we do this in guided meditations maybe you do it yourself
the wings of a bird flapping
or maybe ice skaters that they skate skate skate and then glide and feeling into the glide
or maybe the imagination of taking off this itchy scratchy sweater
and instead putting on your favorite t-shirt
so there might be some skillful ways in which we can replace some of our thinking
and can we do this while being aware of the breath all the while allowing the breath to
accompany us that may be the last thing i'll say
is there might be also an opportunity to say for some thoughts some mental activity no
i'll work with this later after meditation right now i'm going to be with the
sensations of breathing
so i offer these as some tools that might be helpful as we're practicing
meditation and as tools if they're not helpful we don't use them
so with a sincere wish
that you are being with the sensations of breathing with your practice your meditations
maybe they be a source of support of ease and peace and freedom in your life
and in the lives of others thank you
you