so hello again and formally welcome to happier
i like our soft beginning at the um at the start where we just say hello
and and basically it's a way of um
welcoming ourselves welcoming each other it's it's meta in action it's meta in action
um and i love that part it always warms my heart that when folks say hello and
sometimes they share a weather report very sweet so
and i find that part which does not get recorded on
for audio dharma in some ways for me to be the the landing the landing into the meta space
because we've already started our practice of meta when we arrive in this space in this community
by saying hello and and um sharing greetings so
so so for the theme for this evening uh evenings practice
um in some ways continuing with the theme from earlier
this week from monday is the theme of you know at this time it's such a busy
time of the year for many it's also it can be a challenging time of the year
it could be a challenging time of the year so so metta as a refuge metta as a refuge
as a coming home metta as a coming home as a refuge so
so that is the theme that i'd like uh to continue to practice with today the
sense of coming home and um [Music]
yeah let me see if there's more i want to say maybe i'll just say one more thing
before we start and that is um you know there are um
so many ways that meta can be practiced and
and for for this session for this practice
to come home this feeling of coming home coming home being nourished being cared
for and when we come home to our hearts with a sense of care the sense of
nourishing sense of love and warm-heartedness for ourselves
we are more available we are more stable we are more
um [Music] equanimous we're more present
to be available with care for others
especially during this time of um [Music] yeah of busyness
both for the holidays and also what's happening in the world so much happening in our planet right now and with
omicron the famous oh affecting so many people
on this planet so so
maybe that's enough let's just practice together let's just enter the space of
practice together so i'd like to invite you to land in
your seat in your chair whatever is most comfortable for you
may be sitting you may also be lying down
if that is more comfortable
so landing
arriving
here
home
home in this bodies
arriving home arriving home
letting your breath
find home find your body
the abdomen
home and it's in this moment of sitting
if you find the mind is particularly active
it might be helpful to just put put a hand on your belly
in your lower abdomen home
connecting connecting with your body with your breath
the movements
you
home with age breath continuing to connect
with the body to arrive home
connecting connecting with the feet
on the floor letting them relax
give their weight to the earth
you
home
and the thoughts are rising stories it's okay
noticing noticing what's arising with kindness
let yourself be at home here in the body
home no need to leave your seat
this nourishing place of the heart
home home
breath nourishing calming soothing [Music]
soothing as if a gentle breeze
sweeping refreshingly through [Music]
your home your body home
you
now if you wish imagining
there is this fuzzy comfortable blanket
nor blanket
blanket of care safety
just feeling cozy warm cared for
maybe there was such a blanket when you were growing up when you were a kid maybe
and when you were sick you were bundled in maybe not it's okay can always re-parent
ourselves imagine this gift this blanket of mental
cozy comfortable at home at home in our bodies
wrapping wrapping ourselves with care with kindness
sweetie you're home sweetie you're safe
it's okay may you be safe
addressing yourself may you be
happy may you be healthy
you have ease
and maybe this bright blanket this imaginary blanket
this imaginary magical blanket
as these messages of meta of care goodwill
feeling held warm comfortable loved
using as many felt senses
if you're visually imagining yourself wrapped in the blanket
maybe this felt sense of the warmth ah cozy cared for
your auditory maybe hearing phrases of meta saying them for yourself
or maybe the blanket is saying them for you may you be safe
may you be happy i hold you in safety
happiness health and ease
whatever works for you it's okay to be creative
in this part of the practice it's a cultivation practice
home home
home in your body home in your heart
you are welcome to experiment if you wish with putting maybe hand
the center of your chest your heart center maybe another hand on your belly
this can be a really supportive posture for many just feeling at home
holding your heart your heart center and your belly home
connecting with yourself home
give it a try especially if you haven't in the past or even if you have
see what might open up from this visceral felt sense of touch
let yourself be surprised
you
meta loving kindness
you're coming home coming home
you
feel like you can stay with metta for yourself
sense of refuge taking refuge
and kindness good will home at home in your heart and your body
or if you wish inspired by this quote from ryokan
said oh if my monk's robes were wide enough
if my monks robes were wide enough
for the entire world for the entire humanity for all beings
oh if your bra blanket of metta is wide enough
to include to cover with kindness with good will of your heart
all the suffering beings of this world
maybe in your mind whatever imagery works for you
maybe you imagine yourself perhaps
as a little fairy metta fairy
rapping various beings around the world people you know people you don't know
covering them and blankets of meta of care
may you be safe may you be well
may you be free from challenges suffering
whatever image works for you in this practice to share to spread
a sense of goodwill is gift freely freely from your heart
you're welcome to stay as long as you wish with any being
in your mind's eye
maybe there are those you know people you care about close dear to you or suffering
wrap them in the mid to blanket
[Music]
maybe you cover yourself and another being sharing your blanket
with another being may both of us be safe happy healthy and well
and have ease or may both of us be free from suffering
[Music] whatever is appropriate for you in this
practice tonight
remember to stay home in your body as you spread meta
home in your body home
if it gets too overwhelming just come home
just be in the body with matter
you
and for last minute or two of this practice
coming home again coming home to the body
to your heart being wrapped
blanket of meta in a blanket of goodwill care
here home home
living this human life is heroic enough heroic enough
for each and every single one of us with its ups and downs
especially during a global pandemic heroic enough
take a moment to come home [Music] to the body
in this heart take a refuge
and wrap yourself with care kindness it's okay it's okay
you are doing your best
may all beings everywhere be wrapped
in blankets of care meta goodwill
may all beings everywhere including ourselves
be happy well and free
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
now i don't know about you but i had a very long
pretty intense day today coming home and being wrapped
in a blanket of meta felt really
[Music] nourishing supportive place of refuge for this heart to then
be more available for others so
so what did you notice what came up for you
you're welcome to raise your zoom hand you're welcome to
share in chat wayne i see your hand please
that that was just so beautiful um thank you very much
thank you wayne thanks for your practice
other reflections please you can type them in chat if you type them
privately to me i'll just read the reflection on your name if it's to
everyone i will read both clark i see your hand please
yeah i was just gonna say i feel like uh doing meta for all beings often feels
kind of hard because the phrases sometimes feel sort of artificial and i don't have a concrete
being to imagine it's sort of like i'm not sure what i'm connecting to
i it wasn't it was fun imagining i i imagined that my blanket just like
went on forever and as it encountered people like wrapped
over them which sounds kind of scary but it sounds lovely it sounds really
lovely monster but yeah there was something really tender about the idea of like wrapping a blanket around
somebody right like so that it helped bring that tenderness alive so
it wasn't just sort of like a you know sometimes you just feel like a meta robot like you're just repeating
their phrases sort of by wrote i really like that image so thanks
that is so lovely clark thanks so much for sharing that i'm just loving the generosity of that image your blanket
expanding and covering everyone it it comes in contact with it's just such a lovely fun playful image right a way of
practicing meta instead of as you were saying being a uh meta robot sometimes which
can feel pretty uh yeah not connecting but yay what whatever works the way to
to connect with the practice so yeah the meta blanket is always available to you
for yourself and others um jane
says thank you nikki love the soft warm blanket whispering meta and then opening
up to include others ah makes me happy just to think of it oh that's lovely thank you jane
on youtube sharing her practice very sweet
yeah so any other reflections before we go into
uh into uh small groups and practice
together i see dave's hand please
oh yeah that was that was really delightful i noticed on the drive home i was at the
far end of whidbey island it's about 45 miles south when i looked after in the distance
the world seemed more all of the piece instead of taken apart by the critical mind
i don't know how to describe it really but it looked like it did when i was a kid
before i learned to take it apart and judge and well that's this place and that's they're no
good there and and so when i came to this and you're inviting us to come home
i really do feel like a kid again so that was very
very apt thank you beautiful wow
profound what you shared is so profound because the way often we
see the world as children these fresh eyes non-judgmental eyes and what a
blessing i i feel so moved in my heart what a blessing to be able to get that
perspective back right to look at the world and see it with those fresh
beginners eyes how beautiful i'm getting chills actually they feeling into what you just
shared ah beautiful maybe we'll make that the theme of our practice at some point
lovely thank you dave it's lovely yeah i see so many smiles yeah
so dear ones there are no other reflections now let's turn
into small groups small community connection with
such a great way to connect with other human beings share your blanket with
each other in these small groups of three and then we come back and we'll have a
little more time and space for um for reflection so i'm going to
create the rooms now let me take a moment to do that
okay so all right the rooms are created i'm going to open them
please take care of yourselves and each other with the meta blankets coming home
here we go
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed and we have a few minutes for any
reflections anything especially that might have come up while you were
in groups together sharing your meta blanket with other practitioners i see some of you actually wrapped in literal
blankets right now it's very sweet so
so any reflections any thoughts you like to share
you can raise your hand type in chat
i see jerry's hand usually i don't see people's hands because i see very few of you but oh jerry can you raise your
uh zoom hand it'll be so much easier to ask you to unmute that well here here we go there
so i was in our group we were reflecting about how this practice
both for some of us on the east coast it's
near 10 but for all of us we were reflecting on how
um just a little it's it's it's like
analogy that i said was like if someone cracks a joke um
and it's inappropriate and good in good spirit the next person you see no matter what's
going on in your life is a little lighter so you're smiling and they may
not know why you're smiling and it just sort of lifts things a bit so
i i was reflecting that this work that both of you and diana are doing
it just takes the edge off uh some of the things in life and allows you to
not get lost in the weeds not to go deep down and sort of reflect and and
frankly be a bit nicer to people whoever they are as you re as you go through life and
with you don't do it you can get deep into the weeds faster than you
would like so that's the thought that was coming up that's lovely thank you
beautiful yeah not getting into the weeds and coming up a little faster and
i like the you know happy hour is like a good joke that keeps he keeps your spirits up or maybe keeps
your heart warmed uh and and that's actually that's similar to a comment someone else made which i
had missed earlier on on youtube who said thank you for always reminding me
of what's important and how to be and that's similar you know a reminder just a little reminder to our hearts of how
to be how to be just touching into that yeah thank you jerry that is lovely yeah
so meaningful so such a beautiful reflection reflections
to bring us to the end of the hour so let us
close this hour of practice practicing good will kindness
cultivating it for ourselves and others dedicating the merit the goodness
as a part of our service this cultivation is a gift it's not
something we keep for ourselves with a tight fist but we share with all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere be free may they be reminded of their own goodness may all beings everywhere be
happy including ourselves [Music]
thank you all