good evening good evening
a really warm welcome really warm
welcome i'm hoping you can hear me now right let's see here i think have all the
buttons going in the right direction
so okay good thank you getting a little that the sound is okay
thank you so settling into this moment for a
little bit of a guided meditation
and just feeling into what it feels like at this
moment that is what are the bodily sensations
what are the sounds
can we just notice them not so much thinking about them but
feeling them being with the sensations
as we're feeling the sensations in the body of course we'll notice the
pressure against the body wherever we're sitting
on the buttocks the top of the legs or the top portion of the legs
perhaps the feet
and the movements associated with breathing
the expansion [Music] and contraction
but as part of the body breathing
we're just noticing the sensations like from the inside
not so much thinking philosophize or
anything like this but just being with the experience of breathing
maybe we feel it in the chest or the abdomen
or maybe the feeling of air going in and out of the nose
feeling the rhythm of the breath
we don't have to control it we're just noticing
can you notice the difference between like really being with the experience
feeling sensing whatever is arising
as opposed to more thinking about the breath thinking about
whatever's arising can you notice the difference between
the sensations and the thinking
about whatever the sensations are
and whether it's a sensation that we find pleasant
or unpleasant or neutral
can we just notice it feels like this
this is the experience
and as best we can not getting tangled up
with the experience
nothing in particular needs to be happening
we're just being with our experience and perhaps primarily with the experience of
breathing feeling the contraction and expansion
the stretching tautness
and the ease
hey
so this practice is about being with our experience
mindfulness is imagine being present for what's
happening as opposed to lost in thought and story making fantasies memories
it seems straightforward turns out not to be so easy to stay with our experience
but doing this is allows us to be present with what actually is
to be in accordance with what's actually happening with the reality of the moment
and in this way we can respond in a way that's supportive and
appropriate hopefully with what's actually happening
so that our practice can be a support for ourselves and not only ourselves but
for others sometimes maybe our just being present for what actually is and not spinning
out can be a tremendous benefit for others who are maybe spinning out
into stories or blaming or memories or whatever it might be
so just to simply be with what is
it's a benefit for ourselves and for others and this way
our practice can ripple out and may be for the benefit of old beings
everywhere
[Music]
so welcome welcome welcome everybody
it's nice to be here and a way that we're connected you know
in some kind of way through our screens but connected nevertheless
so a really warm welcome
so tonight i want to start with a story that's in the sutas and the story is
about this woman the nanjani and
she's a brahmana which means that she's from she's a from the what was the dominant religion at the time of the
buddha and apparently there's a meal happening
and she stumbles or she trips and as she recovers herself
she says homage to the blessed one referring to the buddha
and so it's a little bit surprising that amongst a meeting right of one religious tradition
that she's saying homage to a different at that time it wasn't really a religion
but a different um teacher religious teacher
and one of the people there the story is that it's her
brother-in-law says what what are you doing i'm paraphrasing
obviously what are you doing why are you saying blessed to homage to the blessed one
and she says well if you knew if you knew his ethics and his wisdom that is the
way that he is in the world maybe you would be doing this as well
so sangarava the person who is asking about this says okay well
the next time this buddha person is in town let me know
so the next time the buddha is in town he was you know a traveling
mendicant we don't know how much later it is how much longer it is
tells him and he goes to see the buddha and
he asks the buddha when he sees them about he says well there are and i'm paraphrasing here
there are some recluses in brahman so that is there are some teachers religious teachers there are some
teachers who proclaim the fundamentals of the religious life
after finding a final and ultimate insight into this life
and how do you stand among them how do you mr gotema stand among them
and the buddha responds he says that there is a difference
not everybody responds this not all teachers are proclaiming the fundamentals of the religious life the
holy life in the same way and in fact there are three different types and then the buddha says that the
first is the traditionalists that is those
who are upholding the tradition and at that time the dominant tradition
were the brahmins who were well versed in the vedas and the vedas were these
ancient scriptures but i'm using this word scripture it's not really the right word because they weren't written down
they were just passed down orally from generation to generation i believe that that's still like today
and they have these amazing memories like this amazing capacity to remember
so they're memorized and passed down from one generation to the next for thousands of years
so the buddha says well there's one set of religious teachers that are the traditionalists or those who are
um memorizing the teachings that have been passed down
and they consider these um sacred texts to be revealed in some ways that you know that the sages
of the past had received these sacred teachings and
they've just been preserved through these years one thing that's interesting about this is that they
believed that it wasn't really necessary to go find new knowledge it wasn't really necessary to go figure
things out everything that you needed was already known
and it was in these vedas so you just had to find it in the vedas
so not as so much of an emphasis on finding things new or figuring things out but of learning
this emphasis of learning what was already known so that was one type of teacher that the
buddha talked about and the second type were the reasoners and the logicians and we might
say the philosophers those are the they did that um they didn't entirely like discard the
scriptures but they considered it more of a secondary source of wisdom but they
believed that knowledge of reality was or a knowledge about how to live a good
life was more found by reasoning and speculating
and working with inference so this included ideas about what happened after death or
primarily about this so that you could use a logic or philosophy or
speculation to know about that so this was a second type of teacher
and then the buddha said that there is a third type of teacher what we might call
the experientialists those that place an emphasis on what can
be empirically known what can we know for ourselves
not only from learning not only from philosophizing reasoning using logic but
what can we actually experience and the buddha put himself in this third
category the experiencers and to be sure
all three of these types of gaining knowledge we might say
have value and have a place right we might remember that when we were beginning meditators
that it was helpful to learn from others it was helpful to perhaps
even here at imc do an introduction to meditation class these days listening to an app reading
to a book there's so many recordings you can listen to so all these ways in which
we might learn from others and the knowledge that we have
and there might also be this way in which it's helpful to read uh the suttas some of the
scriptures that were before and or it might be helpful to really contemplate
and think about some of these teachings that we hear in dermatalks is this true does this make sense is
this consistent with my experience so not relying solely on what was heard
so not giving complete authority to what some teacher has said whether that teacher is
in a book or on a podcast or a dormitog but giving some authority to our
thinking mind our capacity to figure things out
but especially with meditation we can see this or maybe i could use the analogy of a mango
we can read about mangoes we can see pictures of mangoes we can hear or read about a description
of mangoes but of course it's not until we actually
hold and feel the mango how they feel the shape the heaviness of them
maybe cutting into them ourselves and seeing smelling
seeing the juicing juiciness of them the tasting of the mango
right the experience is different of course we know this
and so the buddha he's pointing to this also he's pointing to the importance of
experience and this idea that we want to have
not only think about the teachings but to see them in our own lives and to
experience them and the buddha on his night of awakening
he says the dhamma that i have attained is profound hard to see and hard to
understand peaceful sublime unattainable
by mere reasoning subtle to be experienced
by the wise so this dharma that he teaches this
drama that was part of his awakening experience that he realized he's saying that we can't just reason it
it has to be experienced and of course as we would expect sometimes in the suttas we hear him
saying with regard to things unheard before that is that hasn't been
passed down through the oral tradition with regard to things unheard before there arose in me vision
knowledge wisdom true knowledge and light so making this distinction between what
has been learned from others and what has been actually experienced
but we need all three we need all the to be able to
have learned from others to think about things and to experience things
and part of what we this third category of experiencing is
part of where insight arises and ajan omaro this um
delightful monk in the thai forest tradition writes
all that is required is to know understand digest practice and embody
this and through the triple gem the buddha dharma and sangha liberation will be
realized this is all we need to know
not much simply what is here in this small package
i'm imagining that he's like saying here and this self
but then here's what he says kind of like this trick maybe is but it needs to be fully
internalized fully actualized made real brought to life
through our practice during the course of the day so john omarou is pointing to the same
thing that the buddha was pointing to this idea that we have to
make them our own make the teachings our own we have to let them
not only like bounce around in the mind maybe but also to kind of like drop down
into our experience of the day and so one way that we might think about
this is this is where insights come from is from our experiences
and some of the key insights that the buddha points to are the insights of anicha duka and anata
insights of impermanence unsatisfactoriness and not self
anicha dukkha and i appreciate that
that uh john omaro he's pointing to that we don't have to
take these um something that were as belief we don't have to take these as
articles of faith but instead we can use them as tools to explore our experience
so and in each of this change and uncertainty or dukkha this
unsatisfactoriness or anata this inherent emptiness of self or what belongs to a
self or we can use these as tools to ask ourselves
with my experience is this changing or is it permanent
is there some portion is there some aspect of it that's completely steady that will never
change or is it changing is there some inconstancy is there some
little bit of adjustment or movement is this experience completely
satisfactory or
am i identified with this experience thinking that it somehow defines me
or that somehow it's mine maybe i'll unpack these just a little
bit these three different insights or sometimes we call these the characteristics of
experience and we can use this expression insights
and the way that we um notice them when we're looking at our experience but
omaro is also saying there can be tools to help us be with our experience
so exploring this anitra this one is kind of the most obvious one
this exploring the way that things change this inconstancy we see change everywhere
we look around the way that the audio equipment was changed
here i pushed this button it's a toggle switch and i thought i was toggling it on not
knowing that it had been left on and i was toggling it off
right so many of these things we've seasons change the weathers change our
bodies change our internal experiences about our thoughts our moods
these change too you certainly don't need to be a meditator to recognize that things
change but maybe we can explore this idea of
dukkha this idea of unsatisfactoriness a little bit more because
even if we have this really wonderful this perfectly delightful experience you might ask well
where's the dukkha in that is it true that everything has this
unsatisfactoriness this dukkha quality to it and using
dukkha as maybe a way as a tool to examine our experience maybe as a
way of looking a way of seeing things when if we really explore we can see
that even the most fantastic experience we have the most glorious
experience we have has this quality of unsatisfactoriness to it
partly because it cannot make us completely and
permanently happy maybe it brings some happiness but that
happiness arises and passes away right to that impermanence thing
so each experience might have some
might to help support the conditions for some happiness to arise but it also
we can notice that the happiness is fleeting it's not permanent
and not only that it might make us feel that subsequent or maybe even past
experiences somehow become inferior they pale in comparison
or even when we're having this experiences we might be worrying about how we can
prolong it or or we experience it i certainly have noticed this
sometimes when um i cook a meal oh this is delicious
or i'm eating a meal that somebody else has cooked i'm not necessarily the greatest cook but so if
somebody else has i'm often thinking like oh how can i make this again now what are
the ingredients what was it that made it special so there's this little niggling
sense of like oh i want it again how can i make it again
this little sense of grabbing holding on this which isn't quite happiness
the sense of wanting more a little sense of dissatisfaction at that moment
so the second i'm sorry the third anata
this principle of not self so again this isn't a belief we're not
trying to make ourselves believe that we don't have a self but it's a lens
through which we can explore this experience of
what is this sense of me-ness this sense of i it's the sense
of mind sense of mindness what is it that feels as if there is
a me that's listening to this talk for example
what is it that feels like there's this mind that's having these experiences
that um we look at we are encouraging us to look at during our the meditation or at this
moment that what are these experiences that we're having what is it that owns these experiences
and if we consider that to own something means that you can control it
is there an owner to these experiences
how does any being really own anything
you know really like in a substantial absolute real way
can there really be such a thing as owning that is controlling complete control
when we explore we discover that this sense of i is really
made up of a process of identifying this is me this is what i do
but that's a thought i like this i'm going there
those are thoughts too i want it to be this way i don't want it
to be this way these are thoughts it's in
created the sense of self is created entirely by thoughts but
what are thoughts they don't have any substance
they're arising and passing away just maybe one thought after another and
the only way that we can effectively maintain this illusion of a having a self is to do a lot of
thinking thinking and planning and projects and programs and if we just
keep them coming and one after the other and quickly pace them all together
we have this sense that we might be able to make something solid but if we look
we'll see that it's just thoughts
and when the mind starts to quiet down and this might be in the setting of
retreat practice when the mind has a really an opportunity to really quiet down and we investigate this whole
structure of the sense of me the sense of the way that we identify
this and structure begins to slip
it starts to seem not so solid in fact
and if we're not so caught up in
each experience identifying with it and instead we can simplify and see that
each moment is really just seeing hearing
smelling sensing tasting thinking
and all of these are without a self
so in this way this this exploration
impermanence unsatisfactoriness not self this active looking and exploring
we could say is inside practice this part of what vipassana is about
mindfulness is just about being with them with the experience of what's actually
arising and it can be with just simple mindfulness there are these insights can arise
but part of vipassana experience is to include some of these investigations
maybe just occasionally maybe only on retreat not to do maybe during daily life maybe
during meditation but i appreciate that ajahn amaroo kind of
describes that when we see oh yeah all of our experiences
not not the concepts but the experiences kind of like this third
group of teachers teachings that the buddha talked about so not just what we've heard
not just what we're thinking about philosophizing rationalizing using logic about but what we're experiencing
when we see them and we see oh yeah they're a nietzsche
we might see one of those three we might see all three often they see when you see one they kind of go together and
often it starts with anita impermanence
describes that insight as a change of heart an opening a realization an expansion of
vision a clear scene and seeing the world in a radically different way
like seeing like oh right how could there be an owner of this
experience how could there be an owner of this sensation it's just an experience
and the experiences are fleeting they're not sources of lasting happiness
and there's not a self and part of the beauty
of this practice of this teaching is that we can learn from every experience
whether it's pleasant it's unpleasant whether it's neither pleasant nor
unpleasant these explorations these inquiries can occur with any experience any sensation
we don't need to be having a pleasant experience on a meditation retreat
we could be filled with aversion and restlessness but the mind that notices that aversion the mind that
notices that restlessness that mind is not tangled up
instead that mind has some mindfulness and is noticing the experiences
and that's the same mind we could say
that notices that things are impermanent
unsatisfactory and not a permanent self
so we don't have to tie ourselves up in knots thinking about oh these are pleasant experiences these are
unpleasant experiences i'm never going to get anywhere i'm having all these unpleasant experiences my meditation is
terrible i'm a terrible meditator all these story making that we might be doing
instead all of our experiences whether they're the ones that we're
wishing for the ones that we don't want
all of them we can just investigate we can be with we can be mindful of them
and do this exploration is it permanent
is it really a source of lasting happiness and this third one
not self is often a little trickier often this one in particular does help to see a
more quiet mind but we're not asking you to adopt some belief just to
take on these teachings but instead the encouragement is to experience
whatever is happening right now
and then seeing these three characteristics are also the doorways to greater freedom
the doorway to greater ease the doorway to nebana
so that whatever experiences you're having may they be an opportunity for you to
deepen your practice have some insight
and may they be maybe supported with some of the learning and some of your own thinking
and your experiences putting them all together so that they might be a benefit not only
for you but for others so you can show up in your life in the world
with freedom with ease thank you