so good morning everyone good day hello everywhere
and
i offer you my warm welcome and and i feel very warm
sitting here with you again after being away for a week and um
happy to be back so um
one of the interesting variations for doing mindfulness
practice is to keep a focus on the breathing
but whatever clearly takes your attention away from the breathing
or clearly makes it difficult to be with the breathing then
turn towards it and acknowledge it briefly maybe all it can be needs to be
is okay i see you or okay there it is
or maybe it's a particular name you know thinking
aching sound whatever it might be but does it do do a moment or two of acknowledgement
and don't rush off after that acknowledgment kind of like like the acknowledgement is like dropping a
pebble in a pond and just be there for a moment to watch the ripple out just be there for a moment and allow yourself to
register the experience more fully and then beginning going to begin again on the breathing
and it doesn't matter how often you acknowledge something different than the
breathing it only matters that you do it and then you begin again with your breathing just always begin again
and don't linger with anything and this exercise uh you might go back to it again and
again the same thing but don't linger don't like study it investigate it just acknowledge it
give it its time for a few moments and then begin again on the breathing begin again in the breathing always on the
breathing but without denying or pushing away or ignoring
what's making it difficult to be with the breath or what takes you away from breathing
acknowledge it and come back and one of the interesting things about this exercise
is you start getting a sense of what it is that takes you away from the breathing where does your mind go
what are the concerns and preoccupations and you don't have to think about it or do
anything about it in meditation but it's just interesting to see that and come back
and maybe it doesn't need any more attention than that it's enough just to come back to your breathing over and
over again so assuming a upright posture
either literally or metaphorically a posture in which it may be a little
bit easier for you to attend to your breathing
accompany your breathing the body breathing
sometimes it's a posture which is a little more open in the chest so there's more space in the chest to breathe
or a little bit more relaxed in the belly
so there's room in the belly to relax hang forward
and then lowering your gaze about 45 degrees to the floor
not looking at anything in particular and when you're ready
you can close your eyes
and then taking a few long slow deep breaths
breathing in and breathing out
re-familiarizing yourself with the experience of breathing deep deep breath
long exhale here now
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale relax more
on the exhale relax the muscles of the face
release the shoulders
and soften the belly
on the inhale feel your body broadly globally
and on the exhale release your body globally
widely let go soften in your body
and then settling in to the body's experience of breathing
maybe like an airplane coming into land and
everything gets very
still and focused and quiet coming into land in your breathing
feeling the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
and letting breathing be the center of your world
but if anything takes you away from that center take a few moments to relaxedly clearly
acknowledge it it could be as simple as a
imaginary nod in the head or
i see you or okay and then begin again with your breathing
no need to linger with anything that takes you away from the breathing
just acknowledge it register it
and begin again with your breathing relaxing into your breathing
foreign
so
whatever takes you away from your breathing you can
acknowledge it kindly acknowledge it peacefully
even if it's a surprising new thing receive it peacefully
and they're learning the art
of turning the attention to what is happening so that
it's a peaceful meeting between our awareness and what's happening
in this way of meeting the world
allows for what's good in the world to show itself more clearly
and may it be that this meditation practice supports us
to see what is good in the world what is good in others
and may we value it and appreciate it
in this seeing the good in the world and appreciating it
is one of the ways of living for the welfare and happiness
of others
when what is good is appreciated it has a chance to grow it's not ignored
may this community of ours that meditates together these weekday mornings
may the benefit of our collective practice be for the welfare and happiness of the
world may it spread out from us with our ability to see and appreciate
what is good in others even when they can't see it may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
so
so we have a guest on the altar for this week it's kuan yin kannon abu lokata
different names and um
and i left it there uh yesterday morning for the sunday morning talk because i wanted to give a talk for the new year
the coming new year and so i gave a talk i called it the calling this the year of care
and so talked about care and compassion so i wanted kuan yin to be there
and now she's there left her there and i thought of giving the same talk
spread it out over five days these mornings but this morning i woke up with a different idea
so um
it begins with a story in the monastery
there was a hallway and a door
that went outdoors into the garden and
but there are all kinds of other places that offshoots other passageways that went
off from that hallway but when you went straight down the hallway you came to the door big door big wooden door
but it was a kind of a special door maybe a magical door and
the only way to visit this special garden was to go through that door and many of the monks and nuns the
monastics wanted to see this garden that heard rumors by how wonderful it was and peaceful it was
and they really wanted to see it and some of them were depressed or angry or upset somehow
disturbed and they wanted to go someplace away from everyone where they could be safe and that's what they really wanted to do and some just wanted
to see beauty and some wanted to get away from the work of the monastery
and many many of the monastics stood in front of that door and tried to open it and it wouldn't
open it wouldn't open and um this door only opened under very
particular circumstances for each for the monastics to discover how does it how to open this
door and and because they really wanted to go to see this garden or they want to get
away from what they were doing and how do you open this door
and and because the door didn't open some of them ended up going down the side
hallways and into the labyrinth of the different places in the large monastery and
some of them forgot about the door or took a long time before they came back to that door
but every once in a while some people would stand in front of the door long enough
that they would and try all the different things to open the door
that they would just stand there and and not have any more wish for the door to
open stand there without any desire
and when that happened then the door opens
the door only opens for people who have no craving no clinging
who are not caught in the grip of desire where
then the door opens so this little story is
you know represents a huge possibility for us that a door that's always standing in
front of us ready to be opened when we meet it
meet reality without projecting and asserting our desires
our craving the strongest desire that buddhism talks about is craving
and craving is a desire which has the better of us
kind of it it directs us it's it's compulsive
and we can't put it down easily some desires are a dime a dozen they come easily and
easily let go of there's no big deal but the cravings are the ones that we can't put down that kind of a force
within us like i have to have this and as long as that force is there
there's a door that won't open door to reality door to our heart door to our minds there's a
door that won't open then only opens when we put down our craving and we stop
desiring for a few moments at least
now it's a hard thing to do because desires are
some people identify with desires i desire therefore i am
desire is me if i have a desire it's my desire it's part of me it's an important part of me
and to deny my desires to deny myself in some way and of course there's some truth to that
not all desires are a problem but the desires of craving the desires of god
that are compulsive the desires that that uh have the best take the better of us
those are the desires buddhism is learning to we're learning to address and um
and when we identify them strongly and we follow them and go into them
and try to understand our life through them sometimes it's uh the metaphor for it is
that of a ball of a tang big tangled ball of string
and it's like where it's like more than it's a two-dimensional labyrinth or maze it's a three-dimensional maze
labyrinth that you know it's very hard to find find your way out once you go into the
world of desires and wants and not wants and cravings and aversions
and try to understand and find your way and navigate and understand it and find the right one and
it's kind of like can be a a labyrinth you never come out of all these side hallways and trips you take for a
long time and then there's the uh
the gordy and the sword that cuts through that that gordian knot the big knot of the entangled desires
and it's a very simple thing it's to put very very hard both to do
but maybe even harder to appreciate the value of it
and that is to crave nothing in a sense to be present
in a sense without any compulsive desire whatsoever maybe with no desire just here
just present when what opens then
and what then we just stand if the door opens we just stand there some people don't like to have no
desires because then they feel like they don't do anything but then there's a next instruction
and in the monastery if the door finally opens for you there's a rake
just the other side of the door and begin raking the garden
cleaning it it works to have no craving
if it doesn't work we have no craving if we're couch potatoes
but no craving no compulsion nothing
no desires driving us and then
take you know start raking sweep the kitchen floor
when's the last time you clean the shower clean the refrigerator
take out the trash
go say hello to the neighbors call a friend
start doing the simple things of life but the ones that are kind of in front
of you and obvious but don't do nothing have no craving
and start caring for this world in the simplest possible ways
and then that grows and develops and can become the whole world
the danger that challenges how to engage
with the raking the caring for the world without then succumbing back into the
world of craving into the world of desire and one of the ways to do that to avoid
that is to meditate every day to find a way to be present
that allows you to shed put down the
burdens of desire the weight of craving and aversion and
the force the contraction in meditation to discover
or get close to a way of being when you put down
desires put down craving even healthy ones and good ones that are good to pick up again after
meditation but to kind of come to a kind of place of
diminished quiet calm diminished desires and have that as a reference point then
to understand what are the healthy desires to act on
when we come out if we come out of the door if we stand in front of the
door and we have no desires and we just stand there
very quickly that becomes a desire it's a natural thing follow the natural
pull into the garden the rake is there starts raking the leaves
when i was um a zen monk i um
there's a very formal way of eating in the meditation hall um we have these three bowls they're
nestled inside each other one is you know so the big one middle one a small one and uh usually the rice will go in the
big one the soup would go in the middle wine and some salad or vegetables go in the small one
and um and i thought well i just eat the most efficient way there is i don't have any desires for anything i just i'll
just eat everything from the first bowl then everything in the second bowl everything in the third bowl and they'll
be done but i was eating in the meditation hall where we ate in silence
next to the abbot and at some point he saw what i was doing and he told me gil
just eat naturally uh and then i noticed that if i hadn't if i kind of stopped my kind of
drive to eat efficiently simply because i was not supposed to have any desires
i noticed that i would take a few bites of the rice i'd put it down i would naturally pick up the soup and perhaps i
would put it down you know i'd go back and forth and kind of you know and it was almost almost as
if there was no desire which is kind of this natural thing to do to go through and eat
at different from different bowls at different times
what is your natural inclination when you have no craving when you have
no desires and maybe it's to clean the kitchen
floor the refrigerator or the bathroom or go visit a neighbor or
it's all kinds of things this world calls us calls on us to do
and so to have no desires
that'll to be desirelessness desireless in a certain kind of way cravingless
in a way that allows us to care for the world
and then do please do engage but be careful you don't get
caught up then back in the world of craving so that's my thoughts for today and
thank you very much