welcome to our meditation and um
one of the closer one of the faculties or
capacities we have that's closely related to mindfulness is truthfulness
that in a sense [Music]
being honest out loud it's just mindfulness out loud in a
sense practicing mindfulness is being honest to oneself
is to really recognize what's happening for us and perhaps
with a an honesty or a clarity or a
that maybe is not often done in daily life not because we're necessarily dishonest
but rather we don't acknowledge fully what is here
and so closely related to mindfulness is truthfulness
and our honesty and also to truth in the sense that we
are aiming in mindfulness to sit in the truth
or to become the truth the word dharma could sometimes be
translated as truth and to sit in the dharma to sit with what is true
what is most true and and the path of vipassana the path of
mindfulness is the path of discovering what is really true here
and sometimes it's useful to put a question mark behind what we're
understanding about ourselves or experience and say is this really true is it is this an interpretation
that i'm doing is this a projection of my own ideas
what if i get really quiet what if there's no projections no
bias no even no memory really to influence how we experience the
moment what's most true about now
and then to find our ability to be at ease in that truth to find a way of being at peace
to find a way to wake up and find have no conflict
no struggle with what is most true about life
in fact find the opposite find that it frees us
so to sit up or to assume a meditation posture
that may be a posture you would assume if someone came along and was sat you
down to really tell you the truth what's really true
someone who's kind compassionate is concerned with your welfare and
well-being and gently lovingly wants to tell you about this
life of ours and tell you what's really true it's really valuable
and you sit down and maybe sit up straight maybe you're
attentive you're really present like this and you get quiet
to really hear what this person has to say
and surprisingly the person says the first thing the person points to
about what's true is that is your very attentiveness
that the search for truth maybe begins in seeing the truth the value the
freedom in a certain kind of attentiveness
to the present moment
and if we don't have this attentiveness to the present moment then we're in our thoughts wandering off
in the past and the future telling stories
reacting to what's happening
but to really discover the truth
we first discover the truthfulness the truth of
attention attentiveness
and with your attentiveness really attentive really care for caringly attentive
to yourself to your experience to take a few long slow deep breaths
breathing in deeply and lovingly for yourself exhaling
maybe with care for yourself to inhale
and letting your breathing return to normal
attentively this wonderful capacity for attention
there is no spiritual life without attention
attentiveness
becoming attentive to your breathing to your body breathing
an attentiveness that is is also embodied awareness
the awareness that the body has of the body breathing
and as you exhale to release the body relax
the body
as you exhale to let go into the pull of gravity
so the whole body settles a bit
settles into the place of contact against your seat your bed the floor
and then gathering yourself around your breathing this simple breathing
in in the dedication to truth to truthfulness
it doesn't have to be complicated or elaborate it can begin by the simple truth
of the body breathing
and the truth of our attentiveness our attention to the breathing
and the attentiveness we're looking for is one that is quiet
this has a stillness to it that maybe is a little bit like the
quiet still surface of a very calm
mountain lake
unruffled
with attention resting in the experience of breathing
with attention riding
on the experience of breathing in and breathing out
here now with the truth of breathing
uh
so
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
we sit we sit and meditate so that our thinking our feelings
our actions our body have no clinging as part of them
that we don't grasp or close down or
turn off from the world without clinging without grasping
without resistance with the strength of the truth
as our foundation we can become aware of the profound
heart connection we can feel or have with other people and other beings
and one of the times to feel that is the end of a meditation session when perhaps a lot of
the dust and clouds of the mind are settled and we can see in a different way
different eyes and to see look upon the other world
with kind eyes caring eyes
and perhaps discover we have within us a capacity for well wishing
for others capacity to care for the welfare and happiness of others
a simple care and so at the end of a sitting it's a
profound thing to give voice to our care for the world
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we in however small ways we can or big ways
may we contribute to this
[Music]
continuing to share the stories
that exist in the ancient discourses and one of the more famous stories that
involves the buddha is the buddha's encounter with anguli mala
and gulimala is a was a mass murderer at the time of the buddha
and this encounter [Music] raises all kinds of important questions
about karma and retribution and
punishment and the possibility for reform kind of people can be reformed
um how much people can leave their past behind and their terrible
actions behind and start life new in a new way
uh how much can people be transformed and changed
and so the story of angulimala
begins with a description of him that he was
a murderous bloody man who took to blows
and striking people and killing people and that he would kill you know whole
villages and devastate whole territories
10 20 40 men would go out after him and he would slaughter them all he was
amazing surprisingly strong and athletic and
fast and
so one day uh the buddha went into town for his arms to receive food for the day
he finished and had his meal and put everything away and then he
started going into the forest where angulimala was
and and villagers the people in the road said no
don't go in there there's a terrible murderer on gulimala
don't go in there he'll kill you and the buddha
said nothing was silent but just kept walking three times people said that no no don't
go in there angulimal was there and the buddha silently continued walking into the forest where angulimala was
the word angulimala is a nickname and anguli means finger
and mala is a kind of like a necklace like a rosary kind of thing a necklace
and he was called that because he had a necklace made of the fingers of his victims
and so the buddha goes into the forest and he's walking along the road and
angulimala sees the buddha and he says wow
i am you know really strong and murderous and capable and no matter how many men they send
after me i kill them all and here comes a solitary
monk he doesn't recognize the monk as the buddha he just recognized solitary
monk with no weapon and walking undefended and all this is going to be easy for me
and so he goes after the buddha to kill him and um and now the buddha just continues
to walk calmly down the road and aniga limala can't catch up to him
okay mala starts to run while the buddha just calmly walks slow
meditative way perhaps and anika mala who says he can you know he can
run faster than any chariot and horse and elephants and jesus you know very
athletic and he just can't catch up to the buddha just walking quietly it's kind of like a little bit of a
supernatural event so angulimala finally yells out stop
stop to the buddha the buddha
keeps walking but the buddha replies to angulimala
you should stop i have already stopped
and and angalimala says these recluses these monks they never
lie they always speak the truth so what does he mean and he says i have
stopped you should stop and and so he said he asked the buddha what
do you mean by this and the buddha says i have stopped
fully harming any living being but you have no restraint and you go on
just killing and this simple statement by the buddha
in the context of this little supernatural thing that's going on that he can't catch the buddha
he understands that the buddha is talking figuratively then the buddha has is not you know talking
about literally stopping that he stopped walking he stopped the killing of
the harming and um and this gets the attention of angulimala this sees maybe the light
he sees a different way he realizes maybe that he that the life he's been living is a life
that is not worth living anymore something happens to him and so
he requests from the buddha he renounces his evil ways he throws away his weapons
and asks the buddha for ordination as a monk and back in those days it was quite
simple ordination just simply meant the way it was ordinary one was ordained then buddha simply said
um come monk you know so come now you're a monk so that's all
and um and uh and so anu limala became a monk and went to
live with the buddha in a little forest place where the buddha and the monks lived
and so that's nice so you know he's been converted so simply it's you know it's almost like a fairy tale
that it should be that simple someone who's so murderous but the story goes on
and um the story goes on and one of the next things that happens is that
now as a monk angulimala goes out for alms and he comes across a house where a
woman is giving birth but the birth is not coming the baby is breach or something
and he hears the screams and the struggles are going on and he goes back to the buddha and tells
him what he saw and the buddha said go back to the woman and make a statement of truth
and and the baby will be born and in ancient india in india there's
this idea that certain statements of truth have impact on the
on the natural world and they're so powerful saying the truth and so um
so buddha says go tell go tell this woman the truth and tell tell her give her a statement
of truth and say this never end of my life have i harmed anyone
and gullible are surprised by this and he says but i can't say that it's not true
and the buddha says no say it everest in your uh ever since you
entered your life were born in your life as a monastic you have not killed anyone so this kind
of radical change that is so radical that he can actually take a stand of truth
on the fact that now he doesn't harm anyone he hasn't harmed anyone in maybe just a few days and
and so he goes back and he makes a statement in the presence of the woman and the baby gets born and
and i lived on the farm in tennessee kind of
a large hippie commune that was famous for its midwives and they have a book called the spiritual midwifery and
so we got a lot of stories there from the midwives about the births they attended and sometimes
they would tell stories about how the baby wouldn't be born until the couple who had tension between them worked out
the tension between them they spoke the truth and cleared the air and then the baby could come so you know
so anyway so the story of angulimala making this true statement made a difference for the woman
but it's kind of a whole thing as kind of a fairy tale and it's a literary work and what's
happening here in a rhetorical way is that there's a contrast between
angulimala who kills people
and then angulimala who supports or helps the birth of a new life
and angular mala who kills um uh cannot stop
there's this idea of not not being able to stop the baby's birth is stopped
and anigurly mala in his new new life as a monastic he now
is able to support and help the birth of life so it's kind of this i think it's a
rhetorical play going on in the text this contrasting of these two things
um so the story goes on a little bit and uh at some point angoliamala goes
into the town a town where people knew about him and and maybe were even impacted by him
by his murders and family members and all that he goes in for alms as a monk and
understandably people are pretty angry with him upset and so they're throwing rocks at him and
uh yelling at him and and some of these rocks hit his head and he's gashed head and he's bleeding and
he comes back to the buddha and and buddha sees him bleeding and and the
buddha simply says to him you have to endure this this kind of uh
pain this kind of attack that you're receiving you have to just endure it bear it if it uh if you had not become a
monk and uh and changed your life radically in this way
your punishment would have been you would have ended up for eons and eons living in the worst of the possible
hills just a little uh cut in your head is not really such a
big deal and but you have to endure it you can't don't defend yourself don't justify
yourself this is just your karma in a sense for what all the things you've done and it this is and
this is a surprising teaching for people to hear this idea that there's no retribution and
he's not punished he doesn't go to jail uh the worst that can happen is he has some cuts on his
bloody head and uh is this really okay is this right and shouldn't there
be some kind of justice that requires more punishment or more impact on angulimalam
in any case at some point goes into the forest to engage on a retreat
and to practice meditation and and he becomes fully awakened
and and as he's fully awakened he he he gives a poem
his awakening poem and one of the interesting things about the poem is he mentions that before he got the
nickname angulimala his given name was ahimsa
means harmlessness non-violence
so uh he ended his life living up to his birth name so angulimala so it's a
story that's rich in associate interpretations rich in
challenges rich in in maybe as a mirror to look at our own
values and beliefs and our reactions to all these stories and you know this fairy tale story perhaps
but still and many many people study the story and write about it
interpret it and find it very very valuable story and in england there is or maybe it was
until rece a non-profit organization called angulimala
that was buddhist chaplains who'd go into the prisons to minister to people in prisons in england
i think the idea being that every human being has the capacity for to be reformed
every human being has capacity for a radical change of heart and and perhaps we can give them
the opportunity to do so so angulimalam ahimsam
finger necklace or non-harming may all of us
find the tremendous truth and value and impact on the world that a life of non-harming has thank you