welcome everyone and uh thank you for the greetings that are in
the chat youtube chat and thank you all for being here
and thank you those of you who have come been coming regularly for some of you well over a year now and
i think all this has added inspiration momentum to me and i think many of us
for the practice and engagement with the teachings
so uh today's guided meditation is based on a little bit of what's going
to be said during the darmette following here and i want to do a little
uh caveat first and that is that what i'm gonna teach might not be
suitable for everyone and uh for for wonderful important
reasons so what i'm offering is not supposed to be like this is a better way or the right way for anyone and that
there might be good reasons for you to not to have other other approaches other ways are practicing mindfulness which
is more appropriate for many circumstances including what you're working on these days in
terms of developing your practice so please you know use some discernment
of whether to go along with what i'm saying or you're
welcome to if it seems like it's going in the wrong direction to tune me out turn off the sound maybe and
and then just kind of sit quietly in your way and uh
so that the the topic is um strength
to bring a sense of strength be a power
to engaging in mindfulness practice and i would uh like to
suggest that it's not so much a matter of
overriding how we are to be powerful or strong in the practice but rather to um realize a certain kind
of inner strength and power that is being channeled or which is uh engaging
our capacity to be mindful and this uh you know personal power kind
of inner power strength maybe a vitality
i associate with things like confidence nothing to sit with
really strong confidence gives a kind of strength to people
to uh sit with courage sometimes sometimes it's what we are working with is quite
difficult and what we have to be present for is challenging and to sit with um
a certain kind of courage and again not the courage that uh is bypassing how we are but that it
rises from deep inside and moves through and supports and engages all of who we are so that we're
not limited by anything or held back or held in check and so there's a fullness that can come
a certain kind of fullness and so the art of this
is to discover just that how uh we can use our
um a kind of a native strength you know something that's in
here almost inherent within us in our whole psycho physical system a capacity for
letting the energetic engagement feel like it's not even us doing it but
rather allowing the systems to express a kind of wonderful
yes hey yes i'm here yes i'm going to be present in a full
way and when there's that kind of energy of strength or power
that it's very easy for that to be channeled into thinking into agitation in the mind
and so the art of it is to learn how to in a certain way be have a kind of a
cognitive quiet or calm that is
almost like because we're not thinking a lot or caught up in thought that
it's like there's more room for a physical almost a physical embodied
strength to support us here to be really here and that would be the the kind of goal
of tapping into our personal strength is a strength for being present
a strength for just be being really here like embodied yes to yes here i'm going to
this whole system is going to be here in a clear engaged open
energetic way that is a balance creates kind of a partnership
with a certain kind of vitality and a stillness so
if this doesn't make sense for you um you know plea please don't uh hold it
up as being you know a better way or the right way to practice mindfulness and
but uh if it makes sense you might experiment with it this time
so to assume a posture and if it's possible to
have a posture that expresses some degree of confidence
and you might adjust your posture maybe very slightly to have a feeling of confidence
in the posture you might not tap into some innate confidence
but to assume a posture which is an expression of posture of confidence like if you were an actor
what would you you know if you were going to show a confidence dance
not not not too dramatically like an actor but just very subtly
and gently close your eyes
and without do breathing deeply different than you ever you do other times begin by breathing
deeply and recognize in the deeper inhales and longer exhales there is a
some degree of confidence strength
that's being manifested
and as you may maybe a longer exhale appreciating that energy of confidence or strength
allow yours allow yourself to also relax
all the physical must the muscles which are being held and tense
almost as if those muscle tense muscles are interfering with
a inner confidence
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and again with a little bit of confidence as you exhale
relax the parts of your body maybe with the word yes
that expresses that confidence and relaxing to be present
exhaling and relaxing the face
softening exhaling and relaxing the shoulders
and then with a yes as you exhale softening the belly
and then scan through your body and see if there's any location in your
body where it seems to be the
clearest location for you to have confidence
or courage or a sense of strength
either because you know from previous experience that that's the place or you feel it now
and it could be anywhere it could be this kind of strength in your belly
a fire kind of it could be in the chest where the word
courage comes from the word heart in french
it could be in a sense of strength in the spine
or maybe it lives in the hands legs and the feet
and if you can as you exhale
relax into that location in your body
almost like you're letting go of your thoughts and letting go into whatever feeling of strength or
confidence that you have in your body
and any feeling of vitality or strength in your body is present
moment experience it's not a memory or a
plan for the future the experience the feelings the sensations of
vitality energy confidence
strength his present moment
here in the present allowing that to support
or enable mindfulness maybe an
embodied sense of awareness body fullness
keeping you grounded or rooted
in the present moment body experience
and perhaps whatever sense of confidence or strength you can feel
maybe you can let it spread and be global enough
to include the body breathing
as if it animates or supports or
is channeled with through the breathing
so a confidence of being here with each breath
and if the energy seems to be building too strongly remember to relax as you exhale
soften so the energy doesn't get
concentrated in any one place in the body but a global soft
open feeling of confidence and courage
letting the thinking mind become quiet
and letting this strength or confidence
cooperate with whatever feeling of peacefulness
calm that might be here as you practice
a calm confidence a peaceful strength
not letting the strength or energy override the peacefulness and calm
if it does then maybe let go of the strength and the confidence
to settle in deeper
you
and now shift your attention
just a little bit from the sense of inner strength or confidence to whatever sense of
inner peace or calm there might be no matter how small or
background it might be feel
relax the thinking mind and settle into that
feeling of calm and peace so that
present moment peacefulness or calmness
is a little bit more what carries your mindfulness your awareness
so the sense of gentle yes gentle tender
mindfulness can be infused
with a peacefulness and calmness
you
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to appreciate the capacity of human beings of others
and yourself to live a life
which when where our life energy does not feel held in check by
fear or attachments within or by the social conditions around us
where confidence and courage is not channeled through
an aggressiveness that then limits or intimidates others
but is a kind of freedom of a wonderful yes
and a feeling that we're not we're able we're confident that we're able to make a difference in the world
we have the ability and the capacity
to make this world a better place
even if it's quite small even if it's very local in our own lives
people immediately around us
and to turn that your heart inside out
to gaze upon the world kindly compassionately tenderly
and to wish both for happiness and well-being and freedom for
others and to wish that you have within you
the appropriate yes
that you would like to support this possibility
yes may all beings be happy
yes may others feel safe
yes may i contribute to a peaceful world
yes may we all together
find ways to work for freedom
for liberation of all beings
yes may we live for the welfare and happiness of the whole world
so today i'm offering the fourth talk on on the
topic of ill will hatred hostility and the talk is not meant to
be standing as a stand-alone talk certainly it's meant to kind of be a continuation of the first three talks
that set the ground for today but also it's kind of meant to be a
continuation of a long period of time focusing on
mindfulness practice buddhist practice and it's meant for people who have
a strong grounding in mindfulness
and most specifically it's uh this talk is kind of meant for
um it's kind of little bit if i may i don't usually use this kind of language a little bit we think of it as an
advanced practice in the sense that it's really i'm really
offering it either as a possibility in the future
for some of you or those of you who have already cultivated a good sense of how to
practice mindfulness because
it builds on the capacity to be non-reactive with our experience
to be in a certain way to get out to get out of the way and to um
um allow what's within us to be there without being involved
without picking it up without getting caught in it without fueling it
and without trying to get rid of it or resisting it or trying to fix it and
and this is to learn this capacity and how to do it wisely so that we don't cause harm in the world
or harm to ourselves i think of meditation practice as a wonderful laboratory for it a wonderful
place because the topic is ill will hostility hatred
that's overlaps but it's not synonymous always with anger sometimes with fury
and and when we sit in meditation we're kind of committed for the duration
of the meditation practice to not act on any of these impulses to
sit with a body that's quiet and still and we're also kind of committed to not
intentionally and actively to be involved in the stories the ideas
the planning that are connected to these intense feelings of
ill will that might exist in us and what the practice is today in which
every thursday for these three weeks is composting these difficult states
or these intensities these things which in buddhism are considered poisons so rather than
condemning them learning how to be present for them so that they can be transformed
but not transformed because we're in there tinkering with them but the composting of them the way the
whole psychophysical system can has them has the capacity to move
them to greater health hostility hatred
is a form of illness inside it because it illness in the sense that it's self-harming and uh and can become kind
of a buddhist tradition of poison but rather than condemning it
there's a we allow the inner system to heal it to transform it to compost it
in a certain kind of way by allowing it so and this is sometimes it's
most useful when um when there's no you know kind of no other choice because it's so strong
the anger the hostility and so um if we have the ability to kind of be
present for it without getting entangled or caught by it and just allow it something different
can happen than if we're trying to fix it or if the self
identifies with it or pushes it away or somehow the self is in relationship
to it um so one of the advantages of this and one of
the is that our sense of personal strength even power a real vitality that
moves through us in a wonderful way
is overlaps or is connected to hostility and anger these are very
powerful states there's a lot of energy in them and rather than feeling that rather if
we kind of squash or push away or deny these powerful feelings of
we might also in some ways inadvertently kind of suppress the vitality the energy the strength the
confidence that can exist in us as well the suppression of anger the suppression
of hostility uh creates kind of a bottleneck or kind of a pressure cooker or unhealthy ways in
which this life vitality can then explode later on or
can fester within and and so one of the advantages of
connecting with uh mindfully practicing really careful careful mindfulness
with these strong kind of negative energies harmful energies is to um
one of the advantages is it also connects us to this inner strength and it's possible as we compost it and
transform this negative energy in a sense negative expression of this energy
it can be the energy can be retained or be made available for
positive things for healthy things for wholesome phenomena and
because i think in buddhist practice in a way over time the idea is to become
strong human beings to not have our inner strength or confidence or even courage
be somehow stifled but to actually be able to show up in the world
not aggressively assertively but you know with with a clear sense of stable upright
energy presence so composting hostility in meditation
and so we have to first learn the capacity to be present non-reactively to be present without
being for or against the sense of mindfulness becomes strong enough that it feels like it can open even
to be present here for this and when anger hostility is strong it's i think
it's best to look upon this as not you know just be able to do this continuously um used
to open and just kind of uh but rather that um it's uh
uh uh uh sequential it's a moment by moment that um
so it's like um like for we we might recognize oh there's anger here hostility here
and and then for a moment open up and feel in your body the what it feels like in the body like
let the body feel it um and uh and as soon as you're in your
body the body is in the present moment and the body is kind of a processing center
it's a way in which things can move and and and transform make space like we're
giving things breathing room for it to kind of relax open up sometimes it needs to get stronger
and and then the thoughts are there and you know we don't we're not to fighting
the thinking and and think we have to make that the
bl and end all to let go of the story and all that when we're practicing this composting
it's um it's moment by moment um opening to what's here oh this is what's happening
and in those few moments that we can open that's where the non-reactivity is that's where the freedom is
and then we have to do it again and again and sometimes we um and we just kind of
trust got opening again and again and what we're doing there and that constantly okay here
feel this feel be present for this is we are stepping away
from being entangled fueling identifying with feeding
the anger the hostility the hatred but to really give it room to as
if it could take care of itself it could transform itself
and so there's no need for shame there's no need for hostility towards our hostility and and
you know i don't know if i want to say no need for fear there's healthy fear
definitely around hostility and anger fear of causing harm but there's also
kind of no need to kind of um i don't know how to say this
um be somehow caught in the fear of it there's just
here here and um and sometimes it takes a while
for things to settle down open up transform and on the way we might realize that the
hostility the anger as i said yesterday is a symptom it's a messenger almost for
something deeper inside of us and by making room for it something in
the cracks of the of the of the ill will can show that
there's things like fear or hurt underneath it or and then if we open to that then
that itself begins to show that there's something deeper still and underneath it there's a sense of
maybe of care or compassion a sense of good will
or tenderness there's a whole other world deep inside waiting for us here that uh
sometimes is the uh is the uh is the very thing that's been
um challenged or overlooked or uh we're closed down around which
the very closeness to our tenderness our peacefulness our love our compassion
is part of what gives the some of the negative power to hostility and to be able to discover
this reservoir of peace of compassion and care of tenderness within and then that's where the energy
that's where the strength can us flow through and be here for and uh and then the energy of our life
um is not squashed or diminished but it can flow now through
good will instead of through ill will and a good will and a compassion that
maybe in circumstances needs to address the situations in the world
that are the conditions for anger or hostility there is injustice in the world there is
you know is that there is a injustice and harm that's being caused
in the world and to ourselves and so how to respond to that or how to
protect ourselves from that how to address that um with
with this sense of confidence and courage and uprightness of this deeper vitality
that you know that somehow gets skewed or becomes more dangerous
if that energy is channeled through hostility and anger but it this is not to do this practice
of composting and transforming is not meant to be an avoidance of
addressing the issues of our life and around us but rather to do so from a
a different place where we're rooted in the wholesome
treasures a wholesome you know roots of roots inside of us we're
rooted in generosity and love and compassion and wisdom but
in a way that people feel oh that's that there's strength there there's a real kind of chance to meet someone and
be with someone who is has um you know is uh is confident here
and is not is not diminishing themselves or
so um so i think that i feel a little bit uh you know cautious
in what i've offered here you know that it needs this what i'm
saying today needs to be done with great care and and certainly compassion and
gentleness and very careful monitoring of it so that this allowing and being present for
things like hatred and hostility and ill will uh very careful so that doesn't get
stronger than we then we can somehow manage and the the standard for knowing when is
stronger than we can manage is that um the it takes over so that
when we take open our eyes and take a deep breath we can't just feel grounded again or
can't feel kind of stable and and one of the ways of practicing this composting
is periodically in the meditation to pull ourselves out of it look around
take a deep breath somehow shake it off and then dip down again if it seems
appropriate but we don't want to let that pressure build and build and build because we're supposed to just kind of stick
through through it to the end of the meditation that's usually not so useful it's useful
this standard is just do it just well enough just good enough and trust
that over time the composting will happen not insist that it has to happen in one
sitting but rather it could do it just good enough and when you feel like it's getting the upper hand a little bit
then take a deep breath open your eyes maybe even get up and go for a walk and then come back
it is very important to kind of feel that you have some strength in not being pulled into it
just too much so composting transforming
and so we have one more talk tomorrow that's related to the liberation the liberation
from and of um ill will hatred so thank you all very much and
and i look forward to our time tomorrow