so good morning a good day and welcome to
the insight meditation center as a location that is spread around the globe
and so i'm wonderful to be here
and
one of the wonderful wonderous experiences that some of us can have is
have the occasion to be in a natural environment that brings us a sense of wonder
sometimes it's looking into the night sky and the stars and maybe the full moon and maybe it's
looking at a sunset or a sunrise if we're up early maybe it's a particular tree that uh
maybe it's leafed out in springtime and it just seems so wondrous and fresh and alive
maybe it's the weather that's something about it even sometimes
with great storms it's a kind of a wondrous show of the natural world
and it's easy to be distracted from that it's easy to
to be involved in our preoccupations our concerns and some of them are quite important and
of course we're concerned and i saw on the chat i forget the exact
name i apologize for someone who said their son is in surgery and janelle
and i wish your son well and you well and of course you're concerned about your son
and in some ways uh it's as natural as the weather and the sunset the sunrise and
leafing out of a tree and of course this is what a parent would thoughts and concerns and
heart would be about in a situation like that and it itself is a natural phenomenon
but we get sometimes kind of pulled into it and maybe naturally so
that as well but then we don't necessarily see the naturalness of it
the the amazing working of the natural world that um has been going on for
you know long before there are human beings on this planet and to you know most of you know most of
what we who we are is the product of amazing uh shaping of the by the environment and
um of this planet that as it evolved as well
all amazing and to sit in this amazement or this wonder
or to sit in a sense of the naturalness of it all that rather than seeing things as good
or bad or pure impure or
you know or special versus everything else which is not special conceit of me being better and worse
than anything there's something about sitting in meditation and appreciating the naturalness of it
all naturalness of our thoughts and our feelings our body
breathing that can be quite profound and quite liberating just here
and so there's a tendency there's a orientation in buddhist early buddhist meditation and to this
day to really see this body as a natural phenomenon
and to see below the layers that we tend to be preoccupied by
the layers of our hair you know and how many of us can write a biography
autobiography of our hair all the different ways our hair has been over a lifetime and concerns with it
and expenses that we spent around here and you know and
and um concerns with it or our skin
such a painful and kind of consuming concern of human beings unfortunately in
beauty and thing all kinds of things racism the teeth and the eyes and all kinds of
you know things that make us self-conscious
but then to see the naturalness of it dropping deeper deeper into the body and greater
intimacy here in this body and the more intimate we become
the more we tend to not be not see it or feel it so much in terms of me myself and mine and
self-conscious ways but perhaps it becomes more of a place of naturalness
where there's a freedom from the limited view of self and me and
what's in it for me or how it is but rather this naturalness that we are a continuation
of unfolding and evolution of all this
millions of years on this planet so to sit this way part of mindfulness
of the body this kind of intimacy so to
maybe with the naturalness of this wonderful connection between the mind
and the body with our mind we can enter the body with attention
and make adjustments in the posture to make our body more suitable
for being present and here alert
amazing that this connection between the mind and the body is here
an amazing natural thing that we can awaken awareness in the body we can
direct awareness into the body and to do so and appreciate this body
that's breathing a rhythm of breathing that's as natural
as the rhythm of the waves lapping up and down across the sandy shore
and to be aware of this rhythm of breathing
a rhythm we we share with so many breathing animals
it's just a naturalness of it all
and if you are self-conscious it's possible to step away from
it and recognize that too is a natural thing
we're built to have this capacity and the environment sometimes
evokes it but still stepping back and
appreciating the simplicity and naturalness of it all
taking a few long slow deep breaths
and those deep inhales feeling and sensing intimacy with
more of your body here now
and letting the breathing return to normal and perhaps there's a way that the
experience of the body breathing
can pull you into an intimacy with the naturalness of this body
intimacy where we trust the body itself to breathe
for the heart to beat for the blood to flow
relaxing into this body relaxing the face the shoulders and
belly
and becoming aware of how the body experiences itself
then wherever it feels most grounding and settling for you into the body maybe supports a quieting
of the mind let your intimacy of attention be in that part of the body
and breathe maybe with that part of the body through that part
and perhaps the naturalness of the body of breathing sensing through the body
can support you and help you to let go of thinking or quiet your thinking
so there's more space and allowance and trusting
of the body's awareness of itself the body's awareness of breathing
deep appreciation the naturalness
we are one more expression of the vast world of nature that we live
in we're part of
as we come to the end of this meditation
it's possible to consider that in this body of ours
flows our life flows our lived life
flows what animates us and motivates us
and that at any given moment this river of life within us
can take one of three tributaries or one of three different forks in the
in the river and if we flow through life blindly
then we take the fork maybe that has the strongest current
but if we are attentive and aware see
perhaps we can naturally easily of course
take the river that's most beneficial
most nourishing or supportive
one river is that that
has in it
degrees of hostility or greed conversion clinging
and now there is one that's just neutral about everything
no greed no hostility no aversion no attachment just okay everything's
just kind of allowed to go in uninterested way
and the third stream natural stream lives in us as well
is that of good will love kindness
a simple ordinary natural caringness for the welfare and happiness
of ourselves and of others a tenderness of
caring and if you can see these three streams
inside of you maybe you don't have to be pulled by the
strongest current
but you can allow yourself to float in the current
of kindness and love and care generosity
the wholesome current
and if that is at all available as the end of the sitting even as a hint intimation of that
wholesome river you might end this sitting with words of
dedication words of aspiration
that this meditation
supports the wholesome and the desire to for the welfare and
happiness of all beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere be free
thank you
um
so continuing with the discussion of the
exercises or the practices related to mindfulness of the body
as discussed in the discourse sometimes called the discourse on the four foundations of
mindfulness this for establishments of mindfulness and the next one is um
has a uh analogy or a simile for it or a um
an example of something that is evocative of what were what we're practicing here and
orientation for a particular practice on mindfulness of the body
and um and so i'm going to read you that
simile example that one practices what we're going to
talk about later just as though there was a bag
with an opening on both ends i don't know what that means but you know certainly
makes me think of the human body which has these two openings things come in and things come out these two openings
so i don't know if it's evocative of that or whether it's just a kind of bag that they used to have in the
ancient world just as though there were a bag with an
opening in both ends full of many sorts of grain
such as hill rice red rice beans peas millet and white rice
a person with good eyes were to open it and review it thus look upon it in this
way this is hill rice this is red rice
these are beans these are peas this is millet and this is white rice
so i've seen bags and bowls of mixed beans and
you know red beans and pinto beans and white beans and all kinds of beautiful beans
and there's a kind of dry beans usually and there's a kind of beauty to it or
kind of simplicity to it and it's kind of a delight and sometimes i've been put my hands through them and
kind of just let the hand and they just walk kind of roll off my hands and just appreciating
and sometimes that each different kind of being stands out and highlight you know if you look at it you can see
it each distinctly and you can also see the collection and all the different modelly
of colors and shapes that are there so this uh
image here of this bag full of different kinds of rice different colored rice different kinds of beans
millet all these things there's clarity you can see each one but there's a a collection of
different things that we're seeing there and kind of a kind of a specialness and seeing of it all and
and maybe also kind of an amazement that this natural world produces this wide
range of different seeds that that become human food and and that they dry nicely
and store and and are available to cook at a later time and to
feed us and and um and uh and people who are you know close
to the land working land farmers um you know see the seeds also as seeds that can be planted for next
year's crop and then amazement of you know built into these seeds is
or kind of is this sense of this a capacity to um to sprout and grow and develop
into plants into flowers into more seeds and this cycle that continues
naturally and easily and probably for most of us if we looked
at this bag of different things you know you might have our preferences of which to eat but uh maybe you know just seeing it it
doesn't lend itself to um you know too much of a greed or
attachment or an aversion to any particular seed um the um unless maybe we're allergic to
some of it but but um you know it's just um there's a kind of
marvel and naturalness and ease a beauty of sorts there but it also is not something we easily
get attached to or the seeing of it then
and it isn't that we start looking at the different seeds and say well that one's a
that one's really a superior seed that's a more beautiful seed oh that's a terrible seed you know how
could nature make a seed with that kind of that kind of shape and color and
and but it was kind of like everything is kind of seen in this natural way this is how it is
and there's a kind of maybe an appreciation maybe a kind of marvel and at it but
also not a lot of pull to be attached or a lot of pull to to be aversive to it in any kind of way
so the naturalness of it but the you know so that's how i see this simile that uh
when the text says just as this and then the exercise itself is to
rev the translation is to review it can mean to visualize for oneself
or to bring to mind for oneself as maybe sitting in meditation
uh 31 parts of the body and this 31 parts of the body that
sometimes there's 32 if we add another piece
the brain is not included so some people add the brain and have 32 parts is a classic and still to this day a
regular meditation practice taught in in in southeast asian buddhism and
theravadan buddhism i've known people that when they get ordained as a monastic this is the first meditation practice
they're taught and so it takes memorizing these 31 32
parts of the body and so just the fact that you're memorized and can recite them and
and then review them visualize them for yourself requires concentration and focus
that um that maybe it's a kind of an exercise of memorization and focus
that's easier than something like breathing where you don't have to memorize that you're breathing and it doesn't require
this higher order attention or functioning of the mind to stay focused as memorization does and so it's a way
of training the mind to be present and it's present for them for something that's very important for human beings
and central to who we are our body and um and to be aware of these
different parts of the body with the same naturalness and and i
don't know if detachment non-attachment is the right language but the
absence of attachment absence of aversion but a marvel and just watching the
naturalness of these beings and seeds same thing just being with the body that way
and this for some of us human beings is a radically different way to relate to our body
uh human beings maybe because of social conditioning maybe because it's built into our almost our dna to
do this are very concerned about our attractiveness and our non-attractiveness and and
we spend an ordinary amount of time some people with caring for that and some people spend a lot of money uh
concerned with their physicality and how they look some people spend an ordinary amount of time being
critical embarrassed or shamed for some part of their body and how they are and there's a kind of a higher order
self-consciousness and evaluation that a lot of it's learned from our society
you know there are trends social trends and what kind of body types are
considered attractive or appropriate or not appropriate or something like that and then we buy into these social
constructs and ideas and and there's a tremendous amount of pain that goes along with it
and and distress around you know this completely natural thing like we don't
see the beans being upset about being a certain kind of seed certain kind of shape is different shape they're just
they're they're allowed to be who they are the trees around have all kinds of same species
tree kind of all kinds of different shapes and generally we don't look and say you know that's a not appropriate shape to have
that brand shouldn't be coming out in that angle it's just like all part of the natural world so
so how to shift our attention from this more complicated socially conditioned
way to be concerned our body kind of from a kind of an image based
you know external image and how would we project ourselves into others to a very different way of being with a
body i think it's uh where we're not inclined to look at ourselves or
others as in physical terms as being better or worse than anyone uh there's
no hierarchy no uh judgments of people just oh this is also you see it in a kind of
naturalness and ease of all the different ways it can be
and so this exercise begins with the four or five of the external things that
we human beings tend to be most concerned with and maybe when they start getting a teenager
or you know that's when this self-consciousness around looks becomes more and more market sometimes earlier sometimes later
depending on the social situations we're in and what is valued and
all this and so so the text goes like this
a practitioner reviews or visualizes considers this body
from the soles of the feet a body up from the soles of the feet
down to the down from the here the top of the hair so anyway considers his whole body in both
directions kind of reviews it visualizes it
in this way in this body there are head ears body hairs
nails teeth and skin how many of you have been preoccupied
with those things maybe you've been spending a lot of money to adjust them and fix them so they're this way or that way or
or upset and embarrassed or ashamed or shy about you know this and you know our society
creates a tremendous amount of suffering and imposes it we project concerns like just this skin color for example i mean it's
heartbreaking what we do around this
and but here just being reviewed visualized considered like we would look
at this bag of beans just not negative not positive but
but maybe a dry bag of seeds the seeds themselves
because they're dried are unappetizing and so
not not ready for us they're just there but they have their value and importance
so it starts with these external then it gets more and more deeper inside maybe the first two places which we're
kind of neutral about um imagine the ancient world people didn't have a really clear sense of what
these organs were these things were so then it goes on
flesh sinews bones bone marrow kidneys
heart liver diaphragm spleen lungs intestines mesentery
so these are all you know if any of you have ever had a chance to look inside of the human body
i've done that going to cadaver labs and there can be kind of an amazing
beauty to it all or but also it's not a beauty that's exactly attractive or or aversive it's kind of like just
wow it's like looking into the grand canyon and wow that's quite something it's a
natural marvel to see it then it goes on to things that maybe
some of us you know would consider a little bit unclean unattractive maybe a little bit repulsive repulsed
even so it goes from what we would maybe be attracted to or maybe to what we may be most
commonly repulsed by some of us the contents of the stomach feces
bile phlegm pus blood sweat fat tears
grease spittle snot oil of the joints and urine
so in some ways what what way can we look at all these different parts of the
body equally what stands what approach can we
visualize get focused review step by step to get concentrated have the mind become still and they free
the mind from its reactivity for or against these different parts of the body
to the degree to which the body is a preoccupation our own body other people's bodies our preoccupation
for lust and whatever we might have is there some way the appropriate and
freeing way beneficial way to see all these different parts of the body
the ones that we're attracted to the ones were repulsed by or not
and to find a a an equality to dwell a place of maybe i
don't know if neutrality is the right word it seems maybe too passive but um maybe a kind of
appreciation with no attachment and no aversion
just oh it's the naturalness of it that frees us from the social conditioning
frees us from the self-consciousness frees us from the preoccupation settles us and allows us to be settled
and intimately connected to this amazing naturalness this natural wonder marvel
of who we are and physically free of attachment and aversion
if we go inside and feel our body from the inside out that's what the body really appreciates
i think our body appreciates that best just being allowed to be the body
without the overlay of all the projections and
values and and ideas that the mind lays on top of it
to allow the naturalness and maybe the natural beauty of who we are be that which radiates from the inside
out freeing ourselves from the particular
constructs of a particular society and times that we're part of
and that way our body our hearts from the inside out will sing
we'll just sing and be it's play it song of its own naturalness and be free
so um thank you and then we'll continue this series
tomorrow thank you very much