okay good morning so we'll go ahead and get started now
with the meditation just settling
in to where you are
perhaps closing the eyes if that's comfortable for you
having a sense of taking your place finding the spot where you're going to
sit or stand or lie down
and feeling into how it is for the body
to be in that posture right now just an overall sense of the body
then bringing attention to the place where you're sitting the place that's supporting you
chair or the cushion or maybe the couch or bed
and just feeling the balance of the body against that surface
and letting it support you letting go of it
to be supported
by your seat and ultimately by the earth
finding some balance sometimes i rock back and forth a little bit or forward
and back just to find that middle point
or something close close enough
so that it doesn't take so much effort to be upright
and perhaps taking a breath that's a little deeper than usual
and then on the exhale letting the body soften
maybe imagining it expanding a little bit
softening the face and the eyes
even softening the thinking muscle in the brain if you can imagine that
and down through the throat and the shoulders
down into the chest area and the torso it can help to imagine the spine as
a support and everything else relaxing around that
softening down through the belly
into the legs letting go of any sense of bracing
and on out to include the feet and the hands
if we've been busy up in our head thinking or
reading something on the screen or talking
we may want to imagine bringing the energy down into the body
letting the energy of the mind spread out through the body
softly
perhaps sensing how there's an aspect of the body that is an extension of the mind
if we have an emotion or a mood or a predominant thought we've been
caught up in there may be some echo of that in the body
and we just noticed that just have mindfulness of that
you don't need to change anything
so intending to use the body as the main object of mindfulness for this sitting
and if at any time that becomes uncomfortable or difficult
it's possible to remember the ground where you're sitting feel that connection
or to open the eyes
what if you can staying with the simple energies of the body
the various sensations it has coming and going it's a very rich area of
practice just to be with that
perhaps using the natural physical sensations of breathing as a gentle rhythm in the background
flowing through the body
so
exploring if the space of the body
and the general stillness of the body can begin to
calm the mind even just a little bit
even if the body is not a very comfortable place today
there's a way in which its steadiness can support the mind
often the body is moving a little slower than the mind and that can be useful in meditation
as we continue to settle into the body soften
the muscles we may sense a kind of energy in the
body
not always but maybe kind of a subtle sense
of vibration or flow
warmth sensations a bit below the
more surface level sensations of muscles and skin
and just including that in the mindfulness
foreign
uh
and it may be that as we tune into
the energy of the body and we sometimes encounter
tight spots or knots
or areas that feel constricted or like a wall
any of those these are normal
and one way to include them in the meditation is
to create some space around such a spot
allow the attention to be broader than that
and not get drawn into the tight area
and just let it be in that broader attention
that may be enough for it may be possible to gently pass the
breath energy through such a spot
but just generally giving it space seeing how that is
yes
so
foreign
as we continue
bringing in widening the mind to include
the heart so bringing in a sense of care
of love for this body
softening this connection between the mind and the
body to a sense of compassion
the body holds quite a bit
and as the body supports the mind the mind supports the body
so touching in with the breath breathing in and out
perhaps smiling a bit in the mind
feeling the mutual friendliness between mind and body
if there's been any sense of ease or peace
or appreciation emerging through today's sit allowing
that to pervade the mind and the body even if it's just a little bit
i'm moving toward a unification [Music]
a wholeness
as we gently begin to bring the mind out of meditation
you can imagine bringing our whole body and mind
out into our life today
remembering the way that we can bring space around
areas that are tight remembering that there are layers below
the surface going on
and if this is true for us it's true for others
so we can bring our wholeness and our gentleness
and our understanding of how it is to be human into our interactions today
perhaps with a sense of just like me
just like me others have these layers
and others have a wholeness we're connected in this
mind and body of being human
so we turn toward how we can help how we can be supportive
how we can love those around us
how we can be at ease in all the ups and downs of the world
may our body carry us through the day
in a way that's useful and helpful
offers some degree of peace to this world
in whatever way we can
may all beings be at ease
so [Music] this series is called the the depth of the body
and we talked yesterday about how the body is a place to feel many of the energies of life
the very process of life is occurring here
many mind states impact the body in various ways and we
can get a lot of information through mindfulness of the body very much helps us to be
less reactive and to have more wisdom in the moment
but it it can be that as we do more mindfulness of the body practice
we will start to encounter sensations in the body that seem to be longer lasting
and that may not be about something that seems to be immediately happening in the
present moment so we can encounter what are called
bodily knots where the energy is frequently restricted in a similar way
you know it's [Music] we always have a particular tight spot you know we sit down to meditate and
after five or ten minutes we feel a sense of hardness in the shoulder for example
these things are very normal i want to first of all normalize them
and so in this case we have the body informing the mind you know we have something going on
in the body um that's quite normal this isn't very many people encounter this
and in the sutures there is a teaching about four kinds of bodily knots
and it's an interesting list not so frequently taught so i thought we could have a look at that today
at least as a start so here's vikibody's translation of this
suta there are these four knots what for the bodily knot of covetousness
the bodily knot of ill will the bodily knot of distorted grasp of
rules and vows and the bodily knot of adherence to dogmatic assertion of truth
don't worry we're going to unpack those into clearer language
and then it goes on to say that the eightfold path what we practice in this
tradition is the way to understand and develop [Music]
the mind to overcome these particular knots so let's let's talk about these
i think the first two are fairly easy to understand so the first nod of is
covetousness or envious desire so my dictionary said it means inordinate
desire often for the possessions of others and the suta is saying that covetousness
creates a bodily knot so if we're fixated on wanting something
that we don't have it can create a tight spot in our body
in the language i'm using here that would be in the energetics of our body so this you know this might make some
intuitive sense as if we're grasping for something there would be a an impact in the body and we can also experience this
um and then the the second knot is kind of the converse of that so the bodily knot
of ill will so if we feel aversion towards something or someone and
energetically we may be pushing it away or resisting it in some way and so then
again there's some contraction when we do that constriction and this is also you know maybe quite
sensible and so i encourage you to explore this you're in your own experience if you're feeling
aversive or uncomfortable or have some
ill will toward a person is there an impact in the body you know in the sense of some tightness and if we
carry that for a long time it may turn into one of these knots it's
a little bit longer lasting if you will so then the third one is said to be the
distorted grasp of rules and vows which gill would translate as practices and
precepts so this is um actually not an unusual idea in buddhist teachings the buddha
knew very well that people can get hung up on conceptual understandings of
ethics or of rules such that they become inflexible and that's the problem is
when they become inflexible we can have uh rigid thinking around
various spiritual practices that we do and even sometimes about the precepts
and if we have this kind of rigid thinking that's that's what can bind us up internally
a friend of mine was on the three-year retreat that is sometimes done in tibetan practice
and they one of the things they do on this type of retreat as they learn
various rituals and then you know go through the process of learning them and he got fixated on one of them and he
really wanted to perfect it some kind of an offering ceremony and he
started correcting everybody else about what they were doing wrong and he practiced again and again with kind of
furrowed brow to get it just right and the other retreatments were getting irritated by this behavior
and so but he didn't realize he had gotten so fixated on it and the the spell was broken when one of the other
yogi's threw a vase at him luckily it missed but the the point was
made and he realized that he was really kind of grasping onto that so if we're holding on to
fixed ideas about our practice or even about the precepts we can create a
knot around that holding it's interesting and then um
so then we come to the fourth one and then i'll talk a little more generally so that is getting stuck on a view of
what is true so the teachings say that a person with this kind of knot
will assert only this is true everything else is false
and so it's easy to go to extreme examples of that places where people have really gotten stuck on just
one idea of what's true but you know we hold all kinds of things like
there is only one right way to load the dishwasher
all other ways are wrong or any other such thing around the house
have you ever gotten into a conflict with someone about these things so i don't know if the thing about the
dishwasher would bring about a bodily knot but it might be that our our political or
philosophical views could do that if we're clinging to them quite tightly
so it's interesting isn't it that attachment to a view can show up as
tightness in the body and i encourage you to explore this if this makes sense
so in some ways we can't hide uh rigidity of the mind it will appear in the body maybe it wouldn't be visible to
others but we will we will come to feel it so
i think this this list of four bodily knots has the potential to evoke
compassion uh we all have these knots to varying degrees because we're not free of these
things and we've created them by thinking that such movements of mind are going to
bring us safety in some way maybe it feels like grasping after
things or pushing them away or having fixed views about things
will provide some kind of certainty or security for us which is what we you
know some part of the heart really just wants wants it to be certain safe secure
but if we do that in the wrong way it can lead to a constriction so it was
sort of a good idea but it was held in the wrong way and a lot of practice is
about untangling some of that that we've done with our mind so i don't think we need to analyze
every knot that we have in great detail i think maybe the top level point of
this teaching is to show us what we're up against in a certain way
these are deep habits of the mind and they get stored deeply in our energetic system
but by touching into them gently we can start to unravel these knots not
so much by analyzing them and figuring out why is this there and what caused that and what in my past led to this i
don't i don't know that that is so useful sometimes sometimes but not every time
um meditation practice offers us the possibility of unraveling these a little bit in a
deeper way than language might get to um
so of course there's you know some care is needed in doing this we would want to approach
these knots um somewhat gently and that was why i suggested staying
connected to the ground or opening the eyes definitely
we don't want to use covetousness and ill will in our approach to working with
bodily tension no covetousness being i'm gonna get in there and
really make it um go away you know kind of wanting to get it to be a certain way
and ill will is i'm gonna push it away or make it you know destroy it in some
way these are movements of mind that are not supportive or you know probably only
make the knots tighter so we have to learn how to hold them with space
how to touch into them not um for a long time maybe just
touching briefly and then go back to the breath or do some other practice
but slowly over time i hope to impart the idea that we can unravel these knots because they
of course represent issues in the mind the very issues that meditation addresses
and for some people it's useful to work in the realm of the body so if this is useful i i offer that
but we we might also make one additional point which is that the suta is not saying that
every knot we have has to correspond to one of these four difficulties it's very
important that we don't just start trying to map like that these are four possibilities and of
course there are other possibilities one time joseph goldstein was practicing
with upandita and he reported that his meditation was
generally going well with lots of smooth pleasant energy flow in the body
except that he was experiencing a block in his neck so you know like the word not that i've
been talking about today and upon data looked at him and said block
that is a judgment you are experiencing tightness so we also have to remember that the
word not might be a bit of a prejudgment in some cases so um we can feel tightness for a
variety of sources it's worth looking at these four because the buddha identified
them as the most common ones so covetousness ill-will wanting and pushing away
and then also two ways of attaching to certain kinds of views or ideas one of
them being ideas of how to do practice and what is you know
practices and precepts as it's called and the other being views of what's true or what's right or what's correct
those are areas where we get stuck but you know it might be that we have um
something physical going on or it might be that what we need to work with that particular tight area is not
to judge it as something that's bad or needs to be gotten rid of in any way and
just hold it as tightness just be mindful of that very neutrally so there are a number of so many different ways
to work with these but if we use it you know wisely this understanding of tension in the body we
can really expand and broaden our practice
so i wanted to bring this in as a kind of a method or an understanding that is at least for me
has been very very fruitful to try to find ways to work with tight
spots in the energy system so if it's of use to you also i hope
you'll explore and have some confidence that with care and with compassion
there are ways to slowly over time loosen these knots just a little bit
and even if some of them just become a little bit loosened then the body starts to open up and
kind of in the space that opens there can be room for more well-being
even a very deep sense of well-being so tomorrow we will
continue our exploration of the depth of the body by by using the body as a support
for concentration practice or for gathering the mind into this deep sense of
well-being so one more dimension of the body that we can explore
so i wish you very well for the day or the evening and
please take care of your body be well