greetings greetings friends wherever you are in
the world what a privilege it is
to be able to practice together i know the marvel it is really
is that we get to sit together we get to practice together this global
amazing sangha my name is nikki murgaforie and i'm delighted to be with you this
week practicing together and supporting you and supporting you while he's taking
your vacation and backpacking in nature so
so practice the deliciousness of
practice so for today
and for this week i'd like to invite us to explore
some ways to calm settle invite the mind to be
more available more available for calming settling for
what's called samadhi or translated as concentration
of course i'll say much more about it later but the invitation for today for the theme
of our practice is to to put down to put down what is not
necessary to put down what is not necessary what is when drag and image
i would like you to consider is if you were riding a bicycle
if you imagine for example the professional bikers in tour de france reducing
wind drag reducing wind drag is so important putting down what is not necessary what
sticks out so that one can be in the flow
be in the flow of movement in this case movement of the breath on
upon the sati movement of this moment the movement putting down what's wind drag
what's wind drag for us is whatever is not necessary
ill will judgment i can't do this i'm terrible at this wind drag when drag
put it down put it down not necessary putting down what is not needed coming
back with a sense of intention resoluteness just here
just this just this thinking about plans future past
regrets in this moment not necessary wind drag ah releasing
just sit just be in this moment giving our hearts our hearts to this
practice being alive in this body in this moment
for the benefit of ourselves others and the world
so let's begin let's begin with that frame
let's begin adjusting our posture to whatever
is called for in this moment whatever is necessary
listening to the body what does the body need does it need to sit up a little more
straight with integrity
spine [Music] aligned vertebrae
sense of alignment as if there was
a vertical a vertical point of reference
internally
sitting nor lying down or standing with integrity
and then inviting the body to relax all the soft tissue
all the soft tissue to relax
this elephant
setting the intention
with wholeheartedness
to give to give ourselves to give our hearts our minds
fully completely
to this simply sitting being here
in this moment
filling our hearts
our bodies our minds
with the goodness the sacredness
of renunciation of what is extra what is wind drag
settling
into the sit bones
letting our weight drop internally
held by the earth
letting go of the weight of the legs
and feet offering it to the earth
ah softening relaxing no need to hold on for it to be tight
dividing the abdomen the lower abdomen
to release
any tightness or holding
for the chest
to soften for the heart the proverbial heart center
center of the chest place of emotions
letting it be safe feel safe for whatever is present right now
softening around it breathing around it
inviting the neck and shoulders the arms the hands
ah to put down to relax
to release the weight their weight
similarly for the forehead
for it to soften
any tightness any holding in the forehead is wind drag
not needed
inviting the eyes their socket to rest
the jaw the chin all the muscles
behind the face they can relax
inviting the breath
to breathe you just as it has been doing for all these
minutes and years just naturally
simply being aware intimately intimately connecting
with the flow with the flow
and the abdomen lower part of the body to settle
and if judgments arise
i can't do this my mind is distracted when drag not needed
put down the self-criticism
i don't like this
this is not good etc etc wind drag wind drag
relinquishing relinquishing putting it down
giving your heart
to itself not to these strangers
any type of conflict with reality
extra
and if thoughts arise lots of entanglement in thinking
past future present
there isn't a problem in thinking per se
and yet giving our hearts to this practice of
simplicity in this moment relinquishing
putting them down for just this not
needed in this moment later later
seclusion of the mind resolving ourselves and seclusion of the mind
and for the last moments of this practice
if there are any criticisms externally internally
judgments self-judgments
arose during this period
oh my mind was distracted etc it's too noisy around
whatever no need it's all extra it's all extra wind drag
wind drag for the mind for the heart
and with resolve putting them down bowing to them
with gentleness with kindness putting them down thank you you're not needed
and appreciating that we have showed up
we've done our best for the benefit
of self others
and the world that is enough
dedicating our goodness our shared goodness freely generously
with all beings everywhere even if we may judge our practice to be
shoddy trusting there is goodness
trusting there is goodness generated
may all beings be well
may all beings everywhere including this being that is me be free
thank you thank you for your practice
so greetings everyone greetings friends friends in the dharma
hmm how nice to sit together dispersed in space and maybe
time so powerful so powerful
to realize to consider for a moment really the beauty the grace
the wonder of us sitting together in this moment in time
all around the world this profoundly touches me
so if it may be of support for your practice
i'd like to share some reflections about calming
quieting settling the mind and heart settling [Music]
landing the mind and heart chitta translated as mind heart
because when our minds settle it's really our hearts that settle also
mind hearts also our body settles true they're all related the body is unsettled the mind
is unsettled and the mind is unsettled mind heart the body is unsettled so settling settling calming
calm abiding unifying arriving so many different words
we can use for the same concept another word that's used often
is the word concentration to concentrate the mind
though that brings this translation of the word samadhi the practice of
samatha brings some tightness
concentration i feel like whenever i hear that word i remember doing math problems i want to concentrate and my
forehead gets tight which by the way i've seen for many practitioners
therefore it gets tight as if they're trying to concentrate whereas ah actually somebody
collecting landing settling is more of a relaxed endeavor which
we'll talk more about tomorrow relaxation so the theme for this week is settling
the mind the word samadhi
derived from the pali prefix sum which means together and the root
da which means to put to place
which is related to the verb
date so basically samadhi means to put
together to bring together to concentrate concentrate in that way to bring
together so it entails unifying the mind
steadying the mind with undistracted awareness
many other words as i mentioned used for this idea
composure gathering collectedness non-distractedness stabilizing
calming i especially like calming steady malleable
are some of the other words used stillness that's another word also use
stillness where hindrances and distractions are at bay and the mind is protected
so samadhi
can support us this settling of the mind this calming of the mind
this undistractedness of the mind can be so supportive through
our practice the path of practice for insight for seeing things clearly
in about ourselves about others inside the rising and also it's
tremendously helpful in life in our daily life
for example having a mind that can become settled unified composed undistracted
still is very helpful when you want to go to sleep
and we know that in terms of health impact sleep has number one health impact more
than anything else um that we can do for ourselves
for example researches is is more and more research is is showing
that sleep is really number one numero uno and have you noticed at night if your
mind is distracted here and there and everywhere [Music]
it's hard to settle it's hard to sleep it's hard to be nourished so developing developing your mind
that's undistracted that can settle that can calm learns how to knows how to
do that has been trained how to do that is a huge gift
that can that we can give to ourselves again not just for practice
but for our daily lives for sleeping for for doing what is needed to be done etc
and for practice um i once did the survey and looked at machi manikaya
and um the number one number one and two
words that were repeated the most was buddha and dharma and number three
there were few there were few words tied for for the third uh position um the third one
in that position was [Music] states of jhana absorption samadhi
so states of mind being calm and undistracted so
it is so important for this practice for us to know for us to learn for our heart
minds to learn how to settle be unified be undistracted
there are many different ways many different tools that are
supportive that help this distractibility of the
mind as we'll discuss together this week
the first one i'd like to discuss today as actually we've been practicing with
is sense resolve is a sense of resolve for seclusion resolve for
non-distractedness or what i called when drag to put down to put down what
is not needed in this moment put down what's not needed
and often when we think of seclusion or if we think of
relinquishment we think oh relinquishment sounds
so heavy and oh relinquishing what's good and sounds pretty bare whereas it's actually
the other way around we're relinquishing giving up we're renouncing
renunciation of what is extra what is too much what
is distracting what is not wholesome
and renunciation this relinquishment
is it requires right intention it requires a sense of resolve
so that when the mind says goes off in thought and and worry or self-judgment
or ill will you name your top 10 list
the heart mind doesn't revel in it like oh yeah juicy fun more ill will
more self-judgment no there is a right intention there is a resolve
no no come back i've done this so many times not helpful this is not helpful
dear mind beloved mind come back come back again with loving kindness
with gentleness and yet with a sense of resolve knowing that this is not helpful for your benefit
for others and the world
and the buddha talks about this um and i'd like to share briefly quickly
from majamalikaya 19.
as i remained thus hateful ardent and resolute thinking imbued
with ill will arose in me i discern that thinking imbued with ill will has arisen in me
this is the buddha talking of course and that leads to my own affliction
or to the affliction of others or to the affliction of both it obstructs discernment
promotes vexation and does not lead to unbinding
and as i notice that it leads to my own affliction it subsided as i noticed that it leads
to the affliction of others to the affliction of both it obstructs discernment
promotes fixation and does not lead to unbinding and binding being freedom nibana
it subsided whenever thinking imbued with ill will had arisen
i simply abandoned it dispelled it wiped it out of existence now
that is pretty um
direct that's very direct guidance noticing noticing
what is what is not helpful what is not helpful what the where the
mind has gone before and with hatefulness ardent
urgency and resolution abandoning abandoning
so my invitation for today is to notice in your daily life what is extra
what is wind drag what doesn't lead to benefit for yourself
for others and the world and in fact the other way it leads to your own affliction affliction of others
or both as the buddha says what needs to be put down and just doing
what you're doing if you're washing the dishes just wash the dishes donate the extra
wind drag donate the extra afflictions just be just simple undistracted
wishing you all the best sangha and may our practice be of benefit to ourselves
others and the world may you be well
take good care