good evening good evening warm welcome a really warm welcome
wherever you might be and whenever you're listening to this
so we'll begin with a guided meditation
just a simple bringing the awareness to the sensations
of the body in a global way
sensing into what does it feel like right now
to have a body to be embodied
we might notice some general feelings of
energy restlessness or maybe the opposite of restlessness some
weariness maybe the mind is busy
can't quite connect with the body whatever is happening can we
welcome it in after all it is happening
so instead of trying to get rid of it can we just acknowledge it
and sometimes that's sufficient to
create the conditions for a different unfolding
but it's different if we acknowledge our experience
with an agenda that we're acknowledging it in order for it to go away or to be
different
can we acknowledge it simply because that's what's happening right now
been noticing the breathing the body is breathing
in a simple uncomplicated way noticing the inhales
and the exhales
letting the mind settle on the sensations of breathing
when we find ourselves lost in thought just very simply begin again
part of meditation practice
is to align ourselves with the truth of the moment
it's one way we could frame it that is to see clearly what is actually
happening what is our actual experience in this moment
in some ways we might say that so much of buddhist practice
is about seeing the truth of the moment if we can use that word truth
how is it now without all the extra story making
that we often add on top
we might gently inquire
what's actually happening right now
not in a way that we have to dig and find it
but in a way in which we open to it
what are the experiences that are being experienced right now
sometimes this word truth can feel
weighty but what if we just consider that
it's what's actually happening it's the reality of the moment
and with our meditation practice we can
become attuned to sensitive to aware of what's actually
happening as opposed to our ideas our fears our
concerns and this way
we can bring a certain amount of ease that happens when we are aligned
with what's actually happening and not lost in our thoughts
or stories even if what's happening is doesn't match our preferences it's very
difficult there can be some
delight in like well at least i'm facing it at least i'm turning towards it
and can see what how things really are and have a sense of perhaps what to do next
so so much about our benetation of practice is to help us see
what's actually happening the truth of the moment we might say
and we do this not only for ourselves but for others
so that we don't get swept along and the stories
the untruths perhaps so that we can have some steadiness some
groundedness for ourselves
and for others so that we might support them just as the truth supports us
you
so good evening good evening welcome welcome
so today i'd like to continue on my i don't know if we could say the word
journey but uh i'm talking about the pyramids these list of ten
perfections sometimes they're translated these ten qualities
that help a person in this movement towards greater and greater freedom
and one thing that's noteworthy about these is that they're not entirely about meditation
so much of the practice that in this tradition that we emphasize is about meditation but the
pyramids are about what we might do outside of meditation in our daily
lives so this list of 10 is generosity ethical behavior
renunciation wisdom energy patience
truth which is what we're going to talk about tonight resolve love and kindness and equanimity it's a
long list of ten run number seven truth
we can say that truth is you know to not lie it's the opposite of lying and
we might as well how do we define line and a kind of a modern day a
contemporary definition that i like is
that to lie is to intentionally mislead others when they expect honest communication
and that is to lie so that others will form beliefs that aren't true
so that they won't be aligned with reality but in fact they will be having some untruths in their minds
and sometimes we might have this idea that the truth is or you know to not lie or to speak the
truth is somehow like quaint or some charming
uh moral or ethical uh behavior or
something like this i know that um when i've given talks on the truth in the past there's a lot of protests a lot of
people yeah but what about this and what about that and they like to think about them all the exceptions what if the
nazis come to the door and they're asking for the jews shouldn't we lie then this is often something that we
hear the short answer is yes i think we should lie then
right to protect others there's different um
uh maybe degrees of harm until i in that case uh i would say that
degree of harm is much less than what might happen but one thing to think about what lying
is i like to think about like do these thought experiments and to think about the opposite
what would our world be like if there were no lying
imagine what if all the politicians told the truth all the time how things might be different would be
different imagine if manufacturers advertisers told the absolute truth about their
products at all times or what if we imagine the opposite
that is sometimes we just assume that the uh excuse me
that's the i'm gonna take a drink of water
okay so to return to this imagine if politicians always told the truth or if
manufacturers and advertisers always told the truth
it's almost mind-boggling to think about this right to think about how much we have structured our society in this way
because people don't tell the truth but not all the time
because we could do these thought experiments in the other in the opposite direction
that is that when there is a prescription when our doctor writes us a
prescription we believe the pharmacist when they say yes we put 30 tablets of
whatever it was that uh your doctor with a prescription for
and if the medication doesn't work in the way that you and your doctor were anticipating
you probably never wonder well maybe you didn't actually take the drug that was
prescribed can you imagine what would it be like if in fact we didn't trust pharmacists
we thought pharmacists lie and put different things in our pill bottles
what if we have this idea that the buddha lied
and then we would have to figure out which is true and which is a lie and
so sometimes we it's helpful to like take things to their extremes
to help us to appreciate them at least that's the case for me so this idea of
lying or this to not lie to really take this to heart like if we
want the world to be a little bit different then how might we behave what is the
role that lying has in some of the problems in our lives or
in the world and maybe not lying is a direction a movement in that
direction towards a better life a better world we don't want to naively think that
telling the truth is going to solve all the problems but we could say
that addictions that we have
really the addictions can't blow up and to be the biggest problems often that they are
unless there is some lying involved often some of the our vices
go hand in hand with lying what if betrayals and fraud and
corruption these things also go with lying
you can't do them without lying so just this movement towards the direction
of a a better world and a better life
but why do we lie besides maybe because we want to do betrayal or fraud or corruption
or because we have an addiction but really people lie for a number of
reasons but one of the primary reasons is to
project a false image of themselves that is to avoid embarrassment
or to exaggerate their accomplishments they want people to think something about themselves
which isn't entirely accurate so it's about the the liar or the one who's lying having a
view of themselves that they want others to have even if they themselves don't believe it
but they want to convince others maybe or
let them not know the truth so because the liar has a sense of self
that they are trying to protect or maybe they're trying to defend they have this sense of self i'm the one who
always meditates and when you ask me i'm going to say yeah yeah i meditate daily
during that guided meditation i didn't get up and go to the refrigerator or
any of these other things we might do when we are refrig when we are meditating from home
so to defend oneself is another reason why we might lie to disguise a wrongdoing or
to conceal something that might have been harmful
to others or but to lie is um mostly about protecting
a strong sense of self as much as maybe a product also is uh related to a sense
of self you want to have some benefit or something i think the buddha recognizes he doesn't say so explicitly but
he recognized that the harmfulness of lying can do
many of you will know that um it's the one of the precepts it's the fourth precept is to refrain from false speech
so the buddha made it to a precept which is not the exact same
thing as a rule that everyone is compelled to follow otherwise there'll be some
terrible outcome instead these precepts are commitments that people make
when they have chosen to follow the buddhist path and the buddha
said for all practitioners to have at least five of these precepts and the fourth one is to refrain from false
speech so if we want to move along the buddhist
path which includes this movement towards uprooting greed hatred and delusion this
movement towards seeing clearly less delusion
not being obfuscated by a greed and hatred
whereas we might say that lying is intentionally either
making so others can't see clearly or if we lie to ourselves making it so that we can't see clearly
and it's lying is has a root of greed hatred or delusion probably greed
or hatred underneath it this kind of is fueling it
so that in this way the buddha made a connection between truthfulness and
personal integrity this recognition that speaking the truth
comes from a practice of truthfulness comes from a commitment to truthfulness
and a commitment to one's spiritual practice this movement towards greater
and greater clarity we might say and we see this uh this buddha making
this connection between our personal integrity and whether we're teaching
truthfulness or speaking truthfulness in a teaching that he gave to his young son
rahula the tradition holds that rahula was seven years old at this time
and and he um and rahula had just um ordained so he was a novice of his
monastic and shortly after he had ordained the buddha
called rahula to his presence and when the buddha was speaking there
was a pot of water nearby we just had a little bit of water in it
and the buddha picked it up and showed it to rahula and said just so little is the spiritual worth of
a person who is not ashamed to tell a deliberate lie
so little is this spiritual worth i'm using this language spiritual worth um i
heard to be kabody when he was describing the suta passage use this expression
and the suta it's now i don't remember the exact poly
but we could also translate it as you know the monks uh
practice or they're we'll just use that word the monks practice so spiritual worth
so the buddha shows see how there's just this little bit of water
in this pot here just in the same way the person that
would tell um who is not ashamed to tell a dipper deliberate lie so little is their spiritual worth but
then the buddha goes on he throws out the water
and he says so a person who is not ashamed to tell a deliberate lie throws away whatever
little spiritual virtue they have been cultivating so if you've been
cultivating and you've been developing along the buddhist path whether it's
your meditation practice or wisdom or sila
ethical behavior when you lie you throw it out pretty strong statement
but the buddha continues he takes the pot and he turns it over
now that it's empty he turns it over and he says so a person who is not
ashamed to tell a deliberate lie turns their whole inner being upside down
right if we have this movement towards non-greed on hatred on delusion
this movement towards the truth seeing things clearly
when we start lying is we're going the opposite direction and it's a discordant with this movement
of wanting to have a greater and greater clarity
and then the buddha goes even further he says he
turns that pot right back upside and shows it to his son and he says see how
this pot is vacant and hollow and rahula responds yes
that's how vacant and hollow the spiritual value is in one who is not ashamed to tell a deliberate lie
then he ends the discourse by saying when one is not ashamed to tell a deliberate lie
there's no evil that one would not do thus rahula you should train yourself
i will not tell a deliberate lie even in jest
are pretty strong words i appreciate very much that the buddha is teaching a young person and he's
using something tangible you know this pot of water throwing it out it's like throwing out
your whatever you've been cultivating looking inside and seeing that it's hollow
strong words so as i mentioned earlier often people protest but you know maybe we should
there's like a little white lies and to address this i'm inspired by this
little book it's called lying that addresses this very topic it's
written by sam harris and
sam harris writes that when we say white lies to our friends presumably because we
want to not hurt their feelings
when we say white lies it compromises our connection to them
it compromises our relationship with them for a number of
reasons a number of ways and he says that well one is that we
deny them access to reality we deny them access to the truth
so their resulting ignorance often harms them in ways that we don't anticipate
do i look okay in this dress you know maybe
the dress is a little bit too revealing and they're going to
something and they don't realize it for whatever reason
yes yes that dress looks great you're going to do fine but maybe as it happens they're seeing a
future employer or maybe they're going to a job interview or something like this
so maybe they're not knowing that their address is a little bit too revealing or maybe they're going to a monastery where
there's some monastics where there's an encouragement to for women to
cover their shoulders and their chest areas in a way that is supportive
for these monastics so
if we don't let them know what they don't know maybe we're doing them a disservice
but rather than saying a truth that may be hurtful
can we say to the septext if it's appropriate what is the subtext
does this dress look okay on me honey
i love you no matter what you wear honey i think you're beautiful
even when you're in your pjs whatever it might be so
maybe the way to answer the question is to address what's the question underneath that's being
asked which requires us to be sensitive and to be on our toes
and then sam harris continues and he says that somehow if we are telling white lies to our friends or family
members or partners it somehow seems a failure of friendship
that in some circumstances some circumstances false encouragement can be costly to another person
yeah that was great when in fact it maybe it was good but there were some
ways in which they could do better and maybe they're not encouraged to
do a little bit better because they think that they did great but if they had some feedback it would
make a difference yeah and this art of giving feedback is
so it's a real skill and it's sometimes uncomfortable to
receive it it's uncomfortable to give it but if we're a friend we will find the
right time and in the right way
time might be one of the key components here maybe when they're
specifically asking for feedback or maybe in the context of
something else and maybe it could be said maybe they gave a talk that didn't
go so well we can you know start the conversation i i don't know exactly how to do this but it could be well what do
you think went well or i really appreciated this but i admit that i got a little lost when
you were doing that or i i i felt um it was a
different uh feeling a different mood the mood shifted when you did this or i don't know
i'm just making this up but this idea that not telling the truth is a failure of friendship
so that also might be a way in which we can understand that to
receive feedback can be a way in which friends are taking care of us even if it does sting a
little bit and this goes to something else that if
we don't say something to our friend and instead we are offering
insincere praise sam harris states that it's more like to treat others like children
it's to treat them in such that they can't handle it or that they
won't be able to make some adjustments or won't be able to
understand and see like oh okay yeah that that's a good point actually i didn't realize that
and wouldn't we rather hear this things that are
maybe could use a little polishing or some little
tweaking why don't i use this word wouldn't we rather hear that from our friends
when we know that it comes from because they care about us and that they want the best for us
so this idea of not telling the truth sometimes is a
failure of friendship and then just this recognition also that trust is eroded when we don't tell the
truth if others find out then these tiny erosions of trust they
add up and they can be insidious because they often are never remedied they are
just a little and that chips away at the relationship
and so when there's these failures of integrity people remember that
and even if we never talk about it they remember it so this the importance
of truthfulness in our relationships so the buddha was pointing to
the importance of it for our integrity
but in addition we know that it's important for relationships and we know that the buddha often is
talking about the importance of kaliana mitta so is there a way
that we can speak the truth that is kind
beneficial and timely not the truth just for the truth's sake
but can we say it in such a way that is supportive
we can see where this is a par me this is a practice in our daily life that is that's
it's in our interactions with others and as well as with ourselves when we're on
the cushion are we seeing things clearly are we seeing things
are we telling the the truth to ourselves
are we seeing the way that greed hatred or delusion might be showing up maybe not
so some of the benefits of course maybe it's obvious but
if we have this commitment to truthful speech it also has this has a sense of
responsibility this commitment to this truthful representation of what we know
and this emphasis on a truthful representation of what we know supports our own quest
our own journey our own path for truth for seeing things clearly
and one way that we can preserve the truth is the buddha
is in another suta there's a story where a brahmana which is the priest of the
dominant religious tradition of the time he says to the buddha this priest says to the buddha
with regard to the ancient brahmanic hymns so those are their sacred scriptures
with regard to the ancient brahmanic hymns that have come down through oral transmission that is they've been
memorized through the years this was happening even before buddhism
that have come down through oral transmission preserved in the collections the brahmins have come to the definite conclusion
only this is true anything else is wrong
and then the buddha responds by asking him well do you know this to be true have you
seen this to be true no as your teacher no one didn't seen this to be true no
as your teacher's teacher as your teacher's teacher has the people who created the hymns
do they know this to be true and the answer is no so then the buddha
says well you are saying this out of faith and then the buddha says
there are five things that can turn out to be turn out in two ways true or false
and these five things are things that are held out of faith things that are held out of preference
things that are held because of an oral tradition this is what we've always done for example
or for reasoned contemplation considering often philosophers are doing
this or acceptance of a view after consideration maybe you've heard something and you thought
well okay yeah i believe that to be true so all five of these may be true
but they may not be true also the buddha points out that even though
you have full faith in something it may be false just in the same way even if
you don't have full face faith in something it may be true
even though we have a strong preference for something it may be false and if we don't have a preference it may
be true and he goes through this with the other five so then he says we preserve the truth
when we say that under these conditions a wise person to preserve the truth
would not come to the definite conclusion just saying only this is true anything else is wrong but they would
preserve the truth by saying my faith is thus
and then say whatever they want to say my preference is thus
and say whatever they want to say i believe this because the tradition has
it or i believe this reasoned contemplation i've thought about this and this is my
current thinking so this idea of to preserve the truth to
maybe let people know our authority or why we believe it or what's underneath
supporting those so then we can let people know
yes i believe this because i read it in this newspaper i heard it from this person i'm not sure but this sounds true
to me and this way this we can in our speech we can really
emphasize this commitment to truth and not trying to mislead people or but
instead to let them know what our current thinking is
let them know what we're imagining to be true or let them know
what our hypotheses are or what we have faith in as opposed to saying
only this is true and anything else is wrong
truthfulness the seventh parame this shows up in so many different ways
in our lives i've talked about a few of them truthfulness and speech
i like wanting to see clearly in our meditation practice
helping our friends what are some other ways
which you might have see how truth or the commitment to truth might show up in our lives and might support not only
our lives but the lives of others in which we can be part of this movement towards
truth and greater peace and greater freedom
for the benefit of all beings everywhere
thank you