so good morning everyone and welcome
and um so we're here uh
to meditate and perhaps to use the word meditation
is too broad perhaps
another way of saying it is we're here to deeply appreciate
our capacity to be aware to deeply
use that awareness to discover what the lived life is
at this moment not the lived life we'll have tomorrow
or we had yesterday but the live life of the moment
that is the place where there's it's almost like three dimensions if the past
the future is two-dimensional
the present moment is three-dimensional has depth to it in a different kind of way
so to assume a posture
that can help you really be here to appreciate this moment
but not appreciate it only from the mind from the controlled torah watching or thinking about it
but one that a posture of embodiment
a posture that you arrange your body in such a way that there's an intentional
intentionality to being embodied
for some people that means to sit up a little straighter
perhaps without puffing up the chest there's a gentle art of opening the chest as we sit
maybe by gently pulling in the spine between the shoulder blades
and sometimes you can no sound
um the um
and sometimes you can get a little bit more sense of engaged presence
by pulling back your head slightly
and tipping your head gently forward
opening up the space between the last vertebrae and the skull
and then gently closing the eyes if it's comfortable for you
and this closing the eyes is a way of concentrating our attention
in the body
kind of dropping into your lived experience of your body
feeling sensing your body
so much of the lived experience of the moment is mediated through the body
including the things that we don't think of as the body our emotions our thoughts our attitudes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
so you can feel the fullness of this embodied life
expansion of the chest lifting of the shoulders
swelling of the belly perhaps as you breathe in deeply
and then letting your breathing return to normal and with a normal breath
on the exhale relax your body
and relax into an awareness of embodiment of being in a
body having a body
and relaxing the muscles of the face
on the exhale relaxing the belly
and on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
and then within the body as part of your embodied experience
become aware of how the body experiences breathing
as if awareness lives in your body not in your control tower not in up in
the thoughts see if you can rest into
the body's experience of itself
the body's experience of breathing
and ever so gently as a whisper in the mind
say the word in as you breathe in and out as you breathe out
and let that word not be so important
for its own sake but rather as a gentle pointing
of staying with the embodied experience of inhale and the embodied experience of exhaling
so the mind doesn't wander off when it does wander off just gently
begin again returning to the embodied experience of breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to realize that the more centered we are in ourselves
the more we have to offer others
the more centered we are here that can be the genesis of our
kindness our friendliness our care
our love take a moment to center yourself the
best you can here in this body
and turning your attention outwards out into the world either generally towards everyone or
towards the people that you'll encounter today
and imagine yourself maybe in the presence of some people where you're
centered and balanced and relaxed unthreatened
everything's okay and there's lots of room for your
love your care your good will your well wishing
and in that situation with that situation in mind
extend your good will in the following way maybe repeating after me
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may i have the kindness and good will from which such quick such good will can
flow may i contribute to the welfare and happiness of this world
[Music]
so we come to the last talk on discomfort i hope you've been
usefully uncomfortable this week not anymore than usual
but that you've learned something about the value of mindfulness of discomfort
i think that well as i like to say that if buddhism focuses ultimately on a
certain kind of spiritual freedom inner freedom and if we become free only when we're
comfortable we're not really free the one of the tests for how free we are
is to discover if we're free while we're uncomfortable
and um uneasy and there will be i was always going to be discomfort in this world
so to fight it or feel like it's a mistake is going to be exhausting
and so we can develop a power the power of being comfortable with
discomfort discovering how to be free with discomfort
not free when discomfort has gone away and
and this kind of combination of learning how to be free with discomfort
is very extremely useful sometimes if people think that they have
to be comfortable to be free then we're never going to learn how
to be wisely with discomfort if we feel like if when we're uncomfortable we
have to react to it and and change it or fight it or hide from it or give into it
collapse around it or something then we'll never discover how to be free
but uh the combination of learning how to be comfortable with discomfort
so uh and to be learn how to center ourselves
or to be present for discomfort without reactivity
and and in the pla and be free enough that while we're uncomfortable
to be able to stand metaphorically stand tall or upright
metaphorically be able to look reality directly at look directly at reality
discomfort is maybe always a message and the question is
what is the message is it a message to heed or is it a message to
not not give into the ability to be present for discomfort
and being able to look reality in the eye really see what's happening here
sometimes we need to look at ourselves what's happening and sometimes it's it's a call to look
at what's happening around us and to take discomfort as a message
for greater attention something here needs attention
and and then to look at it directly what's really going on here this is beginning to exercise our
freedom to look at what's happening as opposed to giving in to the reactions about
what's happening and so this ability to then be able to stand
comfortably in discomfort also gives us the ability when it's appropriate
to be allow ourselves to be uncomfortable and do what has to be done the discomfort doesn't interfere
doesn't distract us from what has to happen it can be very uncomfortable
to to have to take a neighbor
to a er to the hospital when the hospital is full and long lines outside
and and covet is there very uncomfortable and the ability to but this has to
happen i have to help the neighbor i know how to be uncomfortable this is the time to be uncomfortable and not be
caught by it but keep that keep focused on the task of helping the neighbor
the the um
and so to have the strength to have this capacity
to have this maybe dedication to have the ability
to stay present to investigate to see what's going on and take care of what
needs to be taken care of without being sidetracked by the discomfort
now sometimes what's needed is the task at hand is to investigate
the discomfort itself and that investigation it works a lot better
if we are not living in the reactivity with discomfort if we learned how to be comfortable
with discomfort because then we don't have filters over our eyes to see what's happening we're
more able to be honest and see more clearly and deeply what's happening if we're looking at ourselves
same thing if we're looking outwardly this is uncomfortable social situation
i think it's important to take a good look and see what's going on here and to be able to
again not give into this comfort not be be distracted by it
but to really take but not ignoring it either but being able to use our capacity to
look and investigate what's really going on here so i see this uh i see this
as a capacity to do two things at once the capacity to know or three things to
know we're uncomfortable to be okay with that
enough so that we either look and see more deeply what's happening
or we dedicate ourselves to the tasks at hand we do what needs to be done
even if we're uncomfortable so for example giving a public speech for some people is very uncomfortable
but to learn to be comfortable with discomfort might mean yes i'm uncomfortable and i'm not going to hold
back i'm not going to go up there to the stage i'm going to go up there and just stand there and i'm going to do it and
not going to be held back by the discomfort i'm not going to be inhibited by the discomfort but i'll
know it's uncomfortable so this ability to look and hold all
this i think is one of the great skills that we can learn from this practice of
mindfulness and it requires a little bit or lot it takes
not don't be discouraged or upset
or avoidant of discomfort that occurs while you're meditating
don't hold up a standard that meditation is only supposed to be relaxing and calm and blissful or whatever it might you
might think it is sometimes the greatest growth in
inner growth can happen when we're willing to practice with our discomfort
when meditation is uncomfortable don't go make yourself uncomfortable for this lesson
but when discomfort comes don't shy away from it don't feel like oh this is not the day
to meditate this might be the ideal day to meditate you might learn more about freedom more
about yourself more about your reactivity and more about how to not give in to to discomfort
if you sit with it upright clear present and really
practice mindfulness of it it might feel how it is in the body feel how it is in your attitudes your
reactions so this week has been a call
for all of us me myself as well to
understand the value of practicing with discomfort
as i said yesterday sometimes when we give in to discomfort
we actually shortchange uh some of the most beautiful parts of what's possible in our life
we might be uncomfortable with love we might be uncomfortable with receiving gen generosity from others
we might be uncomfortable uh with honesty we might be uncomfortable all kinds of
things that interferes with rich social interactions
and to learn to be comfortable with the discomfort so that our love our generosity our care
our receptivity from others generosity other people's love can flow freely
is one of the advantages of being comfortable with discomfort
so thank you for this and um
i hope this has been useful for you and and i hope it does lead you to a greater
comfort in this life including a comfort with discomfort
so a couple of announcements so next week i'm off teaching a retreat
again at the retreat center the second in-person retreat and
we will have a wonderful teacher coming
ying chen she's been teaching here at imc for some time and
and i'm very very happy and delighted that she's going to be able to be here for the 7 a.m teaching
and then um also uh next sunday on the 4th of december 4th
and the 11th december we're having another round of something we did back in may or june
which is a mindfulness circle for people who are identified as black so
black identified practitioners people and two wonderful black teachers will be
leading it and
and it will be on zoom it's at i think at nine o'clock in the morning on on saturday that week from saturday week
from tomorrow and the following week so if you're black or if you know a black practitioner might
value having um being in a mindfulness circle with some teaching some discussion some practice
you can find more information about it on the imc website uh easiest place to find it is
either in the what's new section the bottom right hand corner or on the calendar it's also under programs and
other places so um thank you and i look forward to being
back in you know in 10 days or so and continuing here
you