so hello and welcome good morning good afternoon good evening wherever you
are so um the topic for today's meditation is
self-compassion we've been working our way to through the concentric circles
the different categ worries and compassion and we've come to self-compassion and we're going to linger here um for a few sessions
because you can can't have enough self-compassion um filling one's own cup
with one's own care especially holding one's own
suffering with care love
affection instead of self recomendation or self-
judgment or trying to whip yourself into shape like here you
are you're being a crybaby calling yourself names ouch ouch it's adding
more insult to injury it's more adding more insult to injury and it doesn't
really work actually it doesn't really work to get us to do what we want to do
in the world it just makes us more depressed uh this empowers us makes us
feel bad um plenty of studies um connecting Lack of self
self-compassion and self flagellation with um depressive mind
states self-criticism self-judgment with depressive mind States and of course it
makes sense because if you keep hitting yourself keep demeaning yourself of
course ouch ouch it doesn't support you but it makes
you feel worse so instead of actually supporting you to to
be stronger in the world it actually diminishes you so
self-compassion is also very different from self aggrandisement um
from um uh self um being self-obsessed
it's none of those it's none of those it's a healthy self-care
self-regard for this for oneself basically the way you would treat
someone you care about you can think of a young one and
we did this in the meditation couple of weeks ago if you imagine a little little
child who's having a hard time uh you wouldn't kick
them and say oh come on get it together but ouch we we tend to do that when we
have a hard time we kick ourselves in the shin get it together instead of oh sweetie this is hard this is
hard so the first step in compassion
especially in self-compassion is acknowledging
that this is hard simply acknowledging that this is hard what you're going through right now this is hard just that
simple acknowledgement that we often miss and I know that I've missed that
many many times in my life having had a chronic illness the first few years the
first few months of it I would be tired exhausted and I would berid myself come
on there all these emails waiting for you get it together it's like oh and then it took me a while to realize wait
sweetie you're tired you're you're not being lazy you're this is there's something going on in this
body and learning to actually be to to be
more affectionate to be more understanding to realize that it was
challenging it was the starting point of knowing of learning how to work with it
so that awareness bringing awareness to seeing that this is
challenging can open our heart to care and can open our minds to wisdom to
actually open up to ways to wisely work with it instead of continuing to kick
ourselves and get into a vicious cycle
so so with
that let's start practicing
together let's get into our meditation
posture and Landing
Landing Landing in your body
Landing with whatever is showing up in this moment in this body in this heart in this
mind taking a temperature of what is
present and whatever is present as you become aware relaxing around
it it's an emotion thought pain in the body
and I will spend a few minutes as always at the beginning just to
rest just to arrive with the
breath in the body one breath at a time
relaxing softening the soft
tissue as much as possible letting go
receiving receiving each breath in this moment in the abdomen in the lower
body you know what to
do
for for
taking refuge in this moment Simplicity letting your heart settle and
relax putting down thoughts concerns
just this
moment
for
e e
and if thoughts arise in this moment becoming
aware noticing ah thinking is happening right now and is it necessary to have
these thoughts right now is it really and smilingly with a sense of
humor bowing to them putting them down thank you come back
later
e
e e
I'd like to invite you to bring to mind something that has been challenging
for you it doesn't have to be the first the most challenging aspect of your life
right now but something that has been challenging and perhaps
you haven't been recognizing it as difficult you've been berating yourself
and judging
yourself for not doing better handling it better etc
etc bring this aspect to mind your
heart realizing that given all the causes and
conditions and your life unique to you this is a challenging
situation it's hard this is hard
and if anyone else given your
genetics your uping gang your family your background all the experiences of your
life was faced with this challenge right now with this situation right
now it would be difficult for them
so it's not so
personal this is a challenging
situation for
anyone and letting yourself feel emotion
feel this is hard this has been hard this was hard
this is challenging sweetie we're simply
ouch ouch letting yourself feel the
difficulty get in touch with the pain sorrow the suffering
of this situation
this is hard sweetie this is hard it's not easy
this would be hard for
anyone oh dear one this is hard is
challenging inserting whatever word works for you this is painful difficult
hard using your own language
and now as if you were a younger version of
yourself a miniature version of yourself feeling this pain this sorrow this challenging
situation this loneliness
sadness confusion
exasperation whatever it might be
frustration imagine this younger version of
you is experiencing this or if it's more accessible for you
a younger version a young version of someone in your family you really care
about if it's not as accessible to see
yourself either way see what works best for you to really feel
into of a younger
being experiencing the same situation similar situation
how would your heart
respond would you judge them kick
them be at them or would you try to comfort them support
them care for
them with affection Love and help them through
it you know what to do
trust your heart you know how to respond
and if you're visual you can use a visual image of the
situation your reaction or felt sends or sounds words see what works
best for you you to really feel into a sense
of wise compassionate
response to this challenge to this
pain to this sorrow
maybe you invite the little child
to sit on your lap and be
comforted whatever way you show your care that you care you
understand you listen to them you hear
them you're
open and you believe them you don't dismiss them
how can you make them feel safe and supported with
you with this
challenge
e
e for
it's okay sweetie it's okay I'm here for
you I understand I love and support
you I know this is hard it's okay it's okay
swee
e
e e
and now realizing this young version of your self or
this young child is not so different from you
and as if they were in your own
heart feeling your own pain your own challenge holding yourself with
care how hard it is for you in your body in your heart in your
mind this challenge acknowledging this is hard
this has been
hard holding your own heart your own self
with [Music] understanding love care
compassion and if you wish experiment with putting the palm of your hand in
your heart center the middle of your chest physically connecting with
yourself as if this little younger version of you was in your heart center
connecting with them oh sweetie
heart connecting with this dear being that is
you e
I'm here for you sweetie you're doing your best you're doing the best you can
I care for you
this is hard this is
hard for
and for the last few minutes of this
practice extending our Circle of Care and
compassion for all the beings are practicing with us in this
moment knowing that all of us have challenges it's part of this Human
Condition it's not that we're doing it wrong we're living wrong it's part of the human condition
[Music] challenges suffering sorrow
difficulty it's a mark of existence extending our
care we're all as humans dealing with our own challenges
in our lives wishing all of us ease may we all
have ease with our challenges with our difficulties or sorrow or
pain may we all meet our difficulties with care with
love with compassion
may we hold ourselves
dear holding each other
dear [Music] extending our Compassion or care to all
beings everywhere those we know those we don't
all beings may all beings everywhere have
ease with their challenge with their sorrow suffering may they appear free from their
pain may they all hold themselves and be held in kindness and compassion
may all beings be
safe feel safe be
happy be healthy and have ease
[Music]
thank you all thanks for your
practice so there are so many different ways to practice self-compassion
so many paths to the temple there is not one path we explore some ways here there
are other ways keep exploring keep experimenting and see what works for you
see what works for you and let yourself be surprised if there are ways that have
worked for you in the past try something else try something
new let yourself be surprised and can practice
self-compassion with words with the phrases or without
words there different ways to enter it holding ourselves our younger verion
holding ourselves as an adult receiving care love from a compassionate being
there's so many different flavors and ways to do it and we'll explore many of them so can love write a love letter
compassionate comp compassion letter to yourself so we'll explore another way on
Monday and yeah I would love to hear what you
discovered in this way in this exploration today and you are welcome to
type it in chat to everyone or just to me and if it's just to me I won't say
your name um can also raise your hand to
unmute yourself and and share your Discovery your wisdom your question
which is very important especially if you haven't shared in a while I'd like
to invite you to speak up or if you're new to this s your contribution is important
so so what did you discover it's all
welcome and by sharing what works or didn't questions you're supporting each
other you know this already by making yourself vulnerable and sharing of
yourself you're supporting others
let me start by asking ah so we have a um Reflection
from Jerry it was very helpful to think of my friends relatives and if they were in my position how difficult that they
also would feel great yeah yeah that's a helpful
perspective sometimes we think we are superhuman and we should be able to deal
with this whatever this is and and realizing and and as Jerry
brought in thinking of your friends relatives somebody else in this
situation especially someone with the same as I was offering with the same causes and conditions especially with
the same background genes and upbringing and all the challenges that you've
had so this is not unique to you this situation would be challenging for
anyone and of course with the combination of conditions that you have
so so this is hard so realizing that can be the first and most important step
yeah thank you Jerry for sharing that very important
did that realization support others or imagining
yourself Emily please so um I think something that was hard
for me just like in the actual experience of trying to practice tonight
was it being the end of the week and you know I'm a freelancer like I run my own
life and business and just kind of feeling this feeling of dissatisfaction with what I accomplished today and this
week and it was really hard for me to let go and I noticed with the like at a
certain point like I even turned the zoom on but I was like but I'm going to work on my taxes at the same time and
then I was like that feels crazy and I kind of felt like I was
um like wanted to be done with working and kind of drained and you know didn't
really want to do more but because I didn't feel as productive as I want you know that it
was like hard to let the weekend begin and I think for me there's a
challenge around like what my behavior is versus The Compassion like it can
feel like I should have done a better job and so I if I feel compassion then I'm gonna like not take care of my life
yeah so those are just some some thoughts I yeah yeah I'm glad you brought this in
Emily because it's um what you said is so typical so typical that oh and and I
was trying to refer to it at the beginning that oh if you feel compassion then you
won't get anything done and you'll become a couch potato and you'll just be compassionate to yourself all like oh I
won't get anything done if I'm compassionate which is the wrong perspective and studies show that in
fact when we are more compassionate we take more responsibility for our actions
um and it's in fact the other way around when we self flatulate it's like Oh I'm
a failure I didn't get enough done I'm terrible then we're just beating
ourselves up and we're throwing perfectly good moments after maybe what
hasn't been accomplished and we're beating ourselves we're making ourselves small and then we get depressed and then we don't feel like doing anything it
becomes a vicious cycle so I want to say trust me and trust the
research but at the same time don't trust me try it try it just see take
that step that step step of trust if you with what you just described and and
being a freelancer this is so familiar because you're on your boss and you're pushing yourself and you have so many
hats and you're doing so many things and yet it's hard it's really hard to say oh
sweetie this is hard for all Freelancers this I can tell you this is hard this is
hard it's an ongoing if there was a forum of Freelancers just should be number one didn't accomplish enough
whereas if you actually went through your day you did this you did that you did like oh so oh sweetie this is hard it's hard to
be a freelancer it's hard to work on your own it's hard not to have a network
it's hard to set your own schedule it's hard to set to motivate yourself it's
it's hard sweetie it's hard isn't as I say this I see you're
nodding all I know all of the so sweetie this is
hard and I love you and I know this is hard you're doing your best and it's okay so many things are not done so I'm
inviting you to trust this try it for a week if you become a couch potato CH
please send me an email let's chat but try it what do you have to lose you've tried the other way right and and as you
were saying there's a sense of like I don't want to do my taxes but that's crazy like you've done this right so try
it for a week and let's check in is that okay Emily can we make a little contract
okay great fantastic oh want to read a couple more
Reflections um one reflection is my hand and my heart feels incredibly tender I
often looked for this compassion outside of myself it is such a realization that
I can give myself this compassion and love beautiful thank you for that reflection another reflection I had a
right chest and the Deep uh and the deep breathing and your words loosening the I
had the tight chest I think you meant to say I had the tight chest and the deep breathing and your words loosen the
tightness lovely compassion often does that and last
reflection um I'm surprised at realizing how hard I have been on myself since
childhood and this awareness and realization is helping me to build a self-compassion practice thank you for
guiding this meditation with such gentleness and kindness you are so welcome that is such an important
realization that we've been hard on ourselves and it can be transformatory
just transformational for ourselves and for all those whose lives we touch so
thank you for your practice dear one and all of you who are
practiced together so the invitation I have for our practice different kind of
practice is where practice meets the the rubber meets the road and again if you
have to go it's okay but if you um if
you can stay please stretch yourselves please stretch yourselves to practiceing
community I invite you to please just stretch yourself a little bit and the invitation is again as we go
into groups spend a minute of compassion
care for others that you see with your eyes open and let them receive you this
can be so powerful in healing so powerful in healing we don't do this
enough and so connecting on Zoom so connecting of our common Humanity across
the world and then you can share what every little or as much as you like to
share making sure everybody has a time to say anything if they wish to holding
each other as the these little these young versions of yourselves who are having challenges in the world and we
all have challenges anybody not have challenges come on we're all humans of course so
with that I like us i' like to invite us to practice together and hold each other
with care and tenderness and compassion hold ourselves
and others so I'm going to create the rooms now and they're open and here we
go okay all the rooms are closed and welcome back welcome back everyone so um
just have a couple minutes for for um comments and
um it looks like Forest had a comment but Forest uh um I see Susan has her
hand up first if you still have a comment please raise your your um hand not physical one because I can see you
but the zoom hand so I'm going to ask uh let's
see um Susan yes go
ahead um thanks everybody and Nikki thank you so much
um I uh just want to name well first I I really am glad we're doing this and I
hope we extend it because I think it's so important um and so hard sometimes it's
less hard right now so I guess what I want to name is just how triggering it can be um to touch into the memories of
childhood and I'm grateful to be doing that with with yall yeah thank you thank you thank you
for naming that um yeah and it's it's it
can be very challenging and it's also nice to have community support and
you're courageous to be gently gently going there gently gently touching into
into into the sorrow and the pain of the memories and holding them with
compassion holding them with compassion slowly slowly gently gently
so thank you for your deep practice Susan yeah and we will stay with
self-compassion um um little longer Ariana
please I just have to uh give public acknowledgement to the people in my
group because they were so incredibly supportive when I shared um kind of the
tough stuff that came up in my set I'm really grateful for
that oh it touches my heart just to hear what magic happens in in these small
groups when you come when you all of you come together it's a privilege that unfortunately being the moderator I
can't have with the zoom and all that and and yet it brings so much joy so
much mudita vicarious joy for me hearing what is created by all of you uh for
each other together it's it's really um heartwarming and G says it is quite
amazing and I'm deeply grateful that it is possible to connect so deeply in the few minutes of
breakout yeah yes it is amazing it's beautiful so beautiful and Jerry said
likewise for my group very supportive thanks so much everyone Thanks so very much yeah
beautiful so dear ones and Forest I didn't see your Zoom hand raised so
um so we'll leave that um if you wanted to
type it in chat and okay well let's
let's dedicate the Merit of our practice together
so so may may the goodness generated from our attempting to meet
ourselves with compassion serve ourselves and serve the
world and meeting the world others with passion may all beings
be free and happy including
ourselves thank you