warm hellos from redwood city
and uh i appreciate all the good mornings and the warmth that it comes kind of
radiating out of the chat here so thank you for those who are making the greetings and and
thanks to all those of you who have those kinds of greetings in your heart
so we're continuing with mindfulness of breathing and one of the functions one of the
wonderful functions or potentials of mindfulness of breathing
is a combination of doing both mindfulness and concentration practice
that we are both developing a steadiness of mind to stay on the breath to really rest in the breathing or
stay kind of immersed in the world of breathing without being pulled into extraneous
thoughts and ideas and feelings and it can be a real delight to
simplify the mind even our life in a certain way and be absorbed in one thing in this
case the breathing and it's not necessarily the breathing is so wonderful and as it is the absorption the really
kind of intimacy with it that intimacy and connection continuity opens up a whole different inner world
of possibility and one of those possibilities is to observe
carefully the experience of breathing which is really where the passana practice practice of insight
begins opening up and to distinguish to highlight what observing means
we can distinguish between
looking seeing and observing looking is an active function
we if we look at if we say look look look at look for look for the needle and the haystack
then um there's a kind of staring that might go on you might kind of really
actively engage the eyes to see and try to find the thing that we've been asked to look
for and so it's an and it might be very active engaged
and um and even the head might go forward and the eyes may be you know more fixated as
it kind of really searches the terrain uh to see uh in the more
passive sense of the word or there's less active senses of the word
it's just the i see there doesn't have to be an intention to see determination to see any effort to find
anything or look anything particular there's just seeing happens and we might
not even choose what we see it's just new things come in and you just see that for now
and it's more receptive quality than the active quality of looking and observing has a little bit
of both qualities observing has
the the receptive quality of just seeing not interfering not trying so hard not
staring at anything fixating on something but it is also a little bit
intentional gentle loving determination intentionality to be intimate with the
experience to really get closer and really feel and sense and experience it in a
more precise way and a little bit like you're still seeing
within that kind of receptive mode but you've placed a magnifying glass
or you're still seeing but you've gotten really close so i've had a history of being
nearsighted and that's a little bit changing now with cataract surgery in one eye
but uh still my right eye is nearsighted and if i keep my eye my hand you know
three feet away from my myself i see that i have a hand but i don't see many details at all
it's a little bit fuzzy but as i bring it closer i can see really all the lines and the
fingerprints and i can see the details of my hand very nicely and and so i can still just seeing
but there's a things get highlighted and clear and clear so it's a little bit like that
the observing that we're building or finding discovering
that comes with being settled and immersed in the world of breathing is to now begin seeing this the subtlety
or the details the fingerprints almost of each little in-breath and out-breath
each little experience of breathing and so the observing has a little bit more of a little bit more maybe kind of
intimacy than just seeing might have but not the active kind of looking
forward and reaching for out that that looking would have
so to observe so that's kind of the so to take a comfortable meditation
posture and gently close your eyes
and relax let go soften your body
tune into your body see your body feel your body
and then within this body take a few long slow deep breaths
the purpose of which is to remind yourself now you're going to be
with your breathing that you're offering to accompany your
breathing and your breathing and ascent is going to accompany you
hand in hand you will go
and here you are you're saying hello to your breathing with these big breaths
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as a way of settling into your breathing more you might
relax your shoulders and as you relax your shoulders almost as if you're relaxing into the
body breathing
easing up some of the muscles and that are surrounding
the body's engagement and breathing
and the same thing with a belly to relax the belly as you breathe
so that there's a greater connection to breathing and freedom to breathing
and maybe there's also a softening in the chest the solar plexus area
and as you relax the chest it's almost like you're able to settle in more to the experience of the body
breathing if you experience the breathing mostly
in the nostrils maybe there's a way of softening relaxing your face
so that you settle more into the place where you feel the breathing
there as you exhale
to relax your thinking
calm your thinking a little bit
reassuring the mind that things are okay at this moment just for now here
as you exhale letting go of your thoughts
as you let go of your thoughts let go into your breathing
and in the beginning of this sitting keep returning to your breathing as
often as necessary but do so gently lovingly
do so in which in a way that the returning the beginning again
is pleasant the returning the beginning again itself
is done in a way that's calming relaxing
maybe a mental tai chi
where you flow awareness back into your
breathing
and then stay intimate with their inhales with the exhales
as if there's a wonderful tai chi dance between breathing and your
awareness why the breathe the awareness mirrors
the breathing follows the breathing
rides the breathing
and relaxing the mind's ability to be aware
so that the awareness of breathing is more receptive
than active but a receptivity that
is committed to the intimacy between awareness
and breathing
[Music] hmm
do
and then with a little bit more intimacy
awareness getting really close to the inhales and the exhales
begin to experience the details of sensations that come into play
as you breathe in that come into play as you breathe out
breathing in breathing out intimately
letting things letting the sensations that are connected to breathing begin to
stand out and highlight in the clarity
of awareness that's not swept away in thinking and thoughts
but becomes more like a soft relaxed magnifying glass that just
feels and senses intimately
the beginning the middle the end of the inhale
the beginning the middle and the end of the exhale
observing
observing the particular detail of your breathing
particular detail of all the sensations that come into play as you breathe
and that is those sensations are changing
no need to look at the details in any a different way
but begin observing the relaxed receptive way
how every sensation that comes into play as you breathe
changes by fading away or turning into something
else
maybe the way that waves washing up on a shore are constantly changing
as they wash up and roll back on the sand
immerse yourself in that changing landscape of breathing
observing in a relaxed but careful way
not only noticing how the sensations change
notice that some appear and disappear
an ongoing sequence of sensations that appear and disappear throughout the inhale
throughout the exhale no need to think about it or be involved
with them but allow those sensations to be known
as coming and going
as we observe the breathing allowing the sensations to come and go
on their own there is a giving of freedom to those sensations
there's allowing each of them to be its own self as it arises as it passes
and this way in which observing grants freedom
from our involvement our entanglement our fixing and wanting is a wonderful
lesson for how to be with others
to allow others to be as they are
to have the ability to be present and maybe even a certain intimacy or
closeness or attentiveness
we allow others to be who they are where others become free
of our desires our needs our expectations our fixing our wanting our bias
and interpretations
and to allow to let the deep capacity to observe this way
be registered deeply in the mind and the heart
and to stay close to it so we begin to find wise ways
of offering this freedom to others the freedom from what our minds does
and may it be that this meditation practice that we do
offers a lot of freedom
for others to be as they are
they might not recognize that you're granting them freedom because it's really a freedom that
within which how they are seen and received in ourselves
and it's a freedom that then also makes more room for the hearts tenderness
kindness love for others to shine forth
in a way this freedom that the mind grants to others
allows for space for more love care
and may it be that what we learn here
can be expressed in the words may others be happy
may others be safe
may others be peaceful
may others be free
and may others be included in my circle of care
a care that is characterized by
freedom the giving of freedom
to others so they can be be themselves in some deep way
may all beings everywhere be free and safe
you