so good day greetings and here we are beginning of our
meditation session and there are two things i want to
bring forth at the beginning of this meditation where the overall context is
or focus now on this practice of mindfulness of breathing
is samadhi the unification of mind the
serenity of mind the concentration of mind and um a very strong association with
the deeper concentration in buddhism in the early buddhism is the idea of
assurance some people some translators translated self assurance or
confidence and so that uh we're kind of looking for or we're
evoking or we're resting on some where we're um beginning to prioritize or
recognize in us and providing in us
is um a deep sense of internal assurance
internal confidence that comes along with somebody with this unification
but also supports it so certainly for many of us something
deep inside in our hearts probably it could use a lot of assurance
the world is in big change and a lot of challenges and
and to be able to discover a place of deep assurance so that
we can let go of our thoughts our concerns our everyday preoccupations really let go
and discover us the tremendous goodness that resides within us and have that
goodness be a resource for how we live our life so that's one thing assurance the other
is that one of the primary one of the great analogies or similes buddha uses for a particular state of
concentration is that of a of a mountain lake
that is not being fed by any water any rain or any rivers feeding into it
but the only feeding of the lake the nourishment of the lake replenishment of the lake is an
underwater spring maybe right and smack in the middle of the lake underwater spring with an underwater
fountain of water that gets sprayed up and out and fills the lake with a new water
fresh water clean water and so the idea of there being a found
a source within us a spring within us that really is a little bit peacefully
wonderfully uh flowing moving dynamic this sense of flow a vibration of it
aliveness of vitality of of a joy of assurance
that we are opening to allow for and so these two things assurance and
this inner flow of goodness of warmth of of energy of vitality
requires something of us requires of us to create the conditions for to allow it to
fill us to allow it to live in us and one of the requirements
is not being preoccupied by things not being off run running off to the races and
thinking about things and worried about things certainly it's difficult not to put down
it's difficult to put down our everyday concerns and emotions and feelings so i acknowledge that but
it's also possible to begin orienting oneself in in the kind of level of receptivity
and softness and kindness that generosity inner generosity
that begins making it possible to invite or to sense or feel or receive
a kind of assurance and a kind of vitality and aliveness that samadhi is
so not samadhi is not this narrow laser focus that we all get tight and contracted but
rather it's an opening and letting go into the bottom of the bowl
into really being centered here in that center maybe somewhere there you
feel more alive and vital it's flow of goodness maybe very subtle
so assurance and receptivity a willingness to receive and be here
a willingness to be here to allow all to invite all things to come in and be unified be
gathered collected here so taking a meditation posture
that maybe for you will somehow some simple way
in some simple way that will
invite goodness invite nourishment invite
what's that what's really good in you reassuring in you to be here
a posture of assurance and to gently close your eyes
and allow yourself to relax in your body
so that with some assurance your inhale begins
and the exhale is allowed
the inhale has characteristics of this inner
this the inner the spring and in her leg something that arises and flows
and moves and expands through the body
and to allow the beginning of the in-breath
to allow the all the sensations of breathing in
to be received and felt
and then to as you exhale allow yourself to relax the body
relaxing the face the shoulders the belly a kind of relaxation that becomes
an invitation for your body to self-organize
the body to become whole
and as you exhale allowing the mind the thinking mind to relax
and soften
adjusting the mind a little bit so the attitude the way of thinking the way you are in
the mind is
is kind enough for pleasant enough friendly enough soft enough
that the mind gathers together everything in the mind is welcomed to come into a hole
and as you exhale again to settle in
let go with the exhale deep inside of you
to a place maybe where there's some assurance confidence
some place of peace or tranquility
allowing the body whole body to be receptive
to the vitality of itself the physical vitality of life
flowing and moving through you
relaxing into that opening
and then at the center of it all steady yourself on your breathing
breathing in breathing out a gentle steadiness
with a mind that's softening quieting
breathing with inner
assurance
breathing with whatever inner wholesomeness there is or maybe in some people's language
whatever inner goodness that's here not that you're thinking about it
but a felt sense
a vitality aliveness of goodness
of which the movements of breathing are part of
and then instead of counting the breaths today maybe at every exhale
there's some there's a similar thing you can do a single word
to place you into the experience in a receptive soft assured way
and maybe you don't say the word with your inner mind your inner voice
but you do it so quietly that it's you imagine you're saying it
and every time you exhale imagine saying yes
just yes to your experience to being here to breathing
to steadying yourself quieting yourself
on the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
the breathing that occurs within the vitality aliveness
of your lake
yes on the exhale
yes and letting go of your thoughts
hey yes that comes with a small subtle smile
barely perceptible turning up the corners of your lips
yes of delight
so
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to find within you
a place of assurance
confidence
even if it's quite small find the place where there is
located within you embodied expression of
confidence assurance and breathe with that
maybe as you exhale letting go into that assurance that confidence
a confidence and assurance which the buddhist tradition associates with a
peacefulness
and as you're sitting here meditating
maybe with some assurance and peacefulness confidence
and without needing to say or do anything for anyone here in the privacy of your own
meditation open your heart and mind
to the people around you in the town you live county
province you live in the people maybe you'll interact with on
through technology or people you're likely to think about
and just settle back in your assurance and gaze upon these people kindly
relax back safely in your place of assurance
and gaze out imagine everyone engaging upon them with good will
maybe even imagining what some of their faces would look like
if they were happy smiles they would have
maybe a little sparkle in their eyes
and imagine how good it would be if they could be happy this way
and let there be inside of you if you'd like an attitude and thoughts of good will
and well-wishing for these people may they be happy
may they be safe
may they be peaceful
and may they be free
and may you carry with you through the day this private place within
whether you have enough assurance and confidence that privately you can gaze
upon others consider think about others with good will and well-wishing
for their happiness and whether you act on it or not is a
secondary thing
to allow to bring at least your inner life
to have love or care or goodwill for the people around you they don't
have to know
[Music]
you