hello everyone and uh thank you for being here
and as we begin this meditation
i would like to mention that one
i think useful slogan for insight meditation
is attention to detail sometimes if we
take in our lives in generalities it's hard to understand where we are
attached or where we could benefit from what's happening but as we begin distinguishing
some of the details of what's happening we can see and recognize what is useful
and and beneficial to rest their attention in
and what it's uh most useful to not avoid like not have it
but avoid giving it a ten a lot of attention avoid giving it our interest
interest can be a little bit like food for some of the ways in which we are
and so if that food is a precious commodity you want to be careful what you give it
to and so attention to detail
and so sometimes we'll say that you know we say we feel a certain way i
feel great i feel lousy that might be definitely the case
but it's a very general the details are missing and what are the details of feeling
great what are the details of feeling lousy and what are the different component
parts and where is it useful to place the attention
and where is it useful to not place our interest so much
so for example if um if i feel lousy or i feel great
and and my interest is somehow evaluating myself because of that
i'm feeling great therefore i am great i'm feeling lousy therefore i am lousy
and then to put interest in this eye that's feeling this way
it might feed a kind of self concern which
is not in the long term very helpful and maybe not even very accurate
and um and but if instead we give our attention
to the details of how it feels to be feeling great or lousy
what it feels like in the body where in the body does that felt in expressed
and if you feel it in the body the body knows how to deal with it
the body knows the process by which it goes if we make room for the
body to feel it we might find it more interesting to be with the breathing
to breathe through how we're feeling to breathe with it so that we don't add or fall into
evaluating ourselves because of it and it can be quite a relief to just be
present for what's here without relating it to me myself and mine
just it's here and i don't have to be either interested or disinterested
i just have to kind of let it be and just breathe with it recognize it breathe through it and it's useful to
stay with the breath the breath is a balancer is a mediator is a
is a harmonizing force within us
and see what where the breathing takes you so i'll talk more about this in the talk
but attention to detail so assuming a
meditative posture
relaxing the eyes
and gently closing the eyes
and then in a calm way as if you have all the time in the world
take some deeper breaths
as if the you're getting a massage from the inside feel the expansion of the torso
in the in-breath and the settling back of the torso on
the exhale
breathing in and breathing out
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and again calmly as if you have all the time in the world as you exhale
relax your face
if there's pressure against the eyelids maybe that can soften a bit
against the teeth maybe the teeth can part a little bit
and if there's pressure against the lips maybe soften it
if there's tightness in your shoulders perhaps you can
release the tightness
if the belly is pulled in perhaps you can let it fall out
soft belly
and then noticing how you're feeling now what's your
general mood or state of mind emotional state
and is there any way in which you're experiencing that through your body
with your body any parts of your body that are
activated because of how you're feeling
is there any way in which you're
putting your interest in how you're feeling beyond just
recognizing it are you investing anything in it
being for it or against it
how simple can you be with how you're feeling
and then to return to your breathing
and either just stay with your breath as it is
or you might try breathing with how you're feeling
breathing through it
where your primary interest is in breathing but allowing the breathing to accompany
how you feel as if you have all the time in the world
you can do it calmly
where's your interest going if it's going into your thoughts
what is the emotion underneath those thoughts
how are they how do those emotions feel in your body
and then return to breathing breathing through that place in your
body
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
a gentle attention to detail is also helpful when with other people
sometimes we can get tripped up for anxious
irritated by the generalities or the big picture
but to slow down and take in another person the people you're with attention to
detail may be ascertaining how they feel and
what's happening for them
and to use your ability to be present mindful
to offer that mindful presence to someone else
you don't have to notice you're doing it that could be awkward
but you're taking in the people taking time to
feel them reflect about them consider them
so that you're in a better position to be friendly to be kind
to be generous
and kindness and generosity and friendliness which is not so much an addition
but is an expression of the simplicity of being present and aware
to consider how you can bring this practice into your daily
life to be present for others in a way that supports them
cares for them is friendly may this practice that we do
may it support us in promoting
goodwill friendliness and kindness
through our communities
may we do this practice for the welfare and happiness of
ourselves and for all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
so this is the second taught talk on mindfulness of emotions
and the focus of today's
approach to mindfulness is recognition to recognize what's happening is really
a central feature of mindfulness of the kind of careful attention that
we're providing to the world to ourselves
and um the um
um so recognition and uh maybe some of you had the experience
of something being named like uh and then things just get relaxed
or let go or settled when they're named so for example someone might notice
you're running around kind of frantic to doing something and someone just mentions to you oh you're tense
and you say oh yes oh yes i am tense and then only then do you stop and relax
and shake it off a little bit or you're in a difficult uh social situation with a number of people
and um and everyone's kind of in the full swing of the social storm
and and then someone says you know there's a lot of tension in the room right now
and somehow naming that tension something makes everyone makes space everyone stops everyone oh yes that's
what's going on and there's a chance to take that in and adjust accordingly
the naming of something the recognizing of something is can be phenomenally useful
and uh mindfulness practice builds on the power of recognition
oh that's what's happening even something so simple as recognizing the inhale and the exhale
or recognizing the mind is drifting off into thought oh thinking
and there's something happen just oh that's what's happening i'm thinking i'm no longer with my breath oh now i am with my breath this is good
so the recognition of our experience
the so in terms of emotions it's helpful to think of emotions as
not single unitary things but rather as composites as made up of
different elements because if we just have a general overview of you know how we're feeling
what the emotion is it's hard to see where it is that we
attention the recognition is most useful to be to be placed or it's hard to see if there's
attachment or clinging or resistance some complication in how we're relating to it the emotion it's hard to see
if we just see the general state but if we notice some of the detailed aspects of the emotion they say oh
that's the part i'm attached to that's the where the the resistance might be
and so what are some of the different uh com components of
emotions one of the things is that i find
particularly useful to notice is the physical aspect of it
that emotions pretty much always are expressed or felt
somewhere energetically emotionally sensation-wise in the body someplace
some some of those sensations are agitated ones some of them are peaceful subtle depends on the nature of the
emotion and if you don't feel it in your body
someday you will as the mindfulness gets more and more settled and you become more more sensitive and
embodied then you start noticing oh look there it is
the there's tension in my hands whenever i get anxious oh that's where the tension is in my hands my fingers are
ever so slightly pulled in you know it could be all kinds of places in the body
so a physical manifestation is one the second one is there might be
a story connected to it and the story might be what's fueling it
we're telling ourselves reviewing what happened in the past and as we keep repeating it um
we're triggering and fueling the emotion so if it's a
history in the past that you're you're angry about something that happened
you might be sitting peacefully and very peacefully and meditating or something and then you
remember this anger evoking experience long time ago and you can feel now you get angry
and and you weren't angry a few moments ago and now there is anger and the anger
arose with the story there's something about the story that triggers the anger so the story is a
part of it and even in the moment when it's not a story but a living experience of the moment
the mind is little bit making stories about it is interpreting in ways often
for us to have the emotions we have so the interpretation the signing of
meaning the story that goes along with it is um is goes a long ways part of the
emotion and part of the value of feeling the physicality of the emotion
is the body is not a story and and so it's a way of stepping out of the story
which is fueling the emotion keeps it going into a place where the emotion
can be processed in the body can't be processed so well by just repeating the story
some emotions have motivation as part of it something that we want we want something to be
different we want something to have more of something we want to have something we want to
push something away there's approach motivations and there's
pushing away emotions or pulling away pulling away so is it um
is it a what's the motivation what's the relationship that we have
that is being expressed to this emotion so again if it's angry it's something
like we want to push something away or we want to you know
assert something and make our point to some someone so as a motivation as part of it
if there is something seemingly quite beautiful it could be love and but the love maybe has a desire it's
a longing a wish and that's the motivation that's part of it
the um and then there's the something a little bit more amorphous maybe the
emotion itself which is a little bit the overall feeling tone of the emotion
and that has different details as well uh some of it just might be is it pleasant or unpleasant
some emotions are pleasant and some are unpleasant and sometimes the hook
to how we get attached or involved or resisting or entangled with the
emotion sometimes it's nothing more or less than that we're reacting to it being pleasant or
unpleasant comfortable or uncomfortable so um
so there and then the other thing you know part of the kind of the
elements of emotion that to be interested to look at is what is
the relationship of you to the emotion what relationship are you having
and one of them is are you defining yourself through the emotion somewhere evaluating yourself
so if you're angry are you now consider yourself a kind of a bad person because you're angry you
shouldn't be angry or and you should be different you should be loving and all these reference back to how i
should be and how i shouldn't be or we justify why we're feeling some way
because we want to be justified we want to be someone who's right or doing the right thing or know we're
doing the right thing so all this me and myself concerned in relationship to it
and um you know if someone is if he's walking down the street and crosses across the street another
sidewalk you see someone who's um clearly angry maybe they're talking into
their phone and they're angry uh you know you might look at it and wonder what it's about or
find it interesting and um in a little bit that person's angry and talking loudly and
but you don't uh it's across the street and a person doesn't see you and it has no bearing on you
and you're still there that's interesting a person's angry can you do the same thing with yourself
can you allow there to be anger without relating it to yourself almost as if
it's someone else's of course it's yours but we add this extra component part
so all these things come together the physicality of it the energy the sensations of it
the stories and the thoughts the judgments the interpretations that we have
around it the ideas we have around it ideas of what should and shouldn't be
our values there's also um the motivation that's connected to it what we want to see
happen and there's the way that we uh define ourselves by it or get hooked by it or
want more of it our preferences and there's also the pleasant and unpleasant aspect of it so these are
some of the component parts that all get rolled up together into one big ball of the emotion
and so if you say you know that you're feeling grief
that it could be a very accurate statement to make but then attention to detail
what are the different component parts to it and you go through the list of everything
and you find out that partly why it's so difficult is the discomfort that comes
and the discomfort seems to be as you seem to interpret is that something is wrong if i'm uncomfortable
it's not okay to be uncomfortable and that's where the complication is so the grief is not just kind of simple
clean grief but now it's complicated with this judgment it should be different i should be uncomfortable
or perhaps uh the grief is you know genuine in many ways but uh there's a
story connected to it and the story might be now i'll never and you fill in the blank now i'll never
x y z and um and maybe it's accurate enough sometimes
when something will never happen again that's why we grieve but um but when we recognize oh that's what i'm
grieving i'm grieving um um
futures that will never come and you know so you know and then what that's what it is so that's kind of a
fascinating kind of perspective on grief that's grieving future futures that will never
come so uh or it could be that um
we're telling ourselves a lot of stories and it's the repetitive stories
rumination that is somehow driving the emotion we have and keeping it going and keeping us entangled with it
so maybe what i'm saying this today is not so you know as articulate as i wish i could
be it's such an important topic and something to respect a lot for each of us our relationship to our emotional life
but i hope the principle that i'm pointing out is useful that the principle is emotions are not
unitary events they're made up of uh of different elements
they're composites there's components to them and as we settle into our mindfulness
it's helpful to look around and see what are these different elements
how is it in the body how is it in the feeling tones pleasant unpleasant
what's the quality and mood of the mind as i have this emotion is it contracted
or is it more spacious are there hindrances in relationship to it
is there identification in relationship to it what's the motivation connected to it
and as you kind of begin kind of looking around then you might ask yourself
is there one of those places that i'm caught where i'm entangled
and if it is maybe it doesn't not denying the emotion or
getting rid of it but it might make it a lot easier to be with an emotion
if that one place where we're caught up and entangled is no longer entangled
then there can be a cleaner relationship and there can be a clean emotion clean anger clean grief
clean clean joy clean even desire in a certain way
so um
so so you might look do that over the next
uh before we meet again tomorrow you might spend some time
and maybe with even paper and pencil trying to map out or understand
the different component parts of your emotions what are all the different streams that come into play
that build to this singular thing of emotion that you have and you might even do it with a friend
it might be interesting to brainstorm together what are all the different pieces and elements of your
emotional life that contribute to the whole and then
to see where where do you get tripped up the most which of those components is a place where you most often get caught
recognition through recognizing our emotions carefully attention to detail
thank you very much