so hello everyone and
nice to be together with you all this way and um
so one of the wonderful supports for mindfulness
meditation when it is available is
metta is loving kindness or good will
and when it's available it makes it a lot easier to be present for
whatever is here it's it means we're more comfortable being present
more comfortable with ourselves if we have meta if we have kindness love as we sit and whatever
arises in meditation whatever happens in meditation occurs then within the atmosphere within
the context of some good will good will for ourselves good will to what's happening
sometimes the inner experiences can be difficult and to meet them with good will with
kindness with friendliness makes a world of difference rather than
meeting with them with with aversion or fear or um
you know it's intense desire for something else metta makes a kind of a relaxed state
for it hold everything and so what allows us to sit with metta with
loving-kindness being calm helps and being gentle
and these two things gentleness and calm the opposite of them don't whatever the
opposite are is and maybe there's a range of things they don't make room
for this quiet thing this little shy thing called love or kindness
friendliness to exist it gets crowded out
and so one of the whereas mehta supports mindfulness
mindfulness supports meta when it helps us to calm down
when it helps us to shift from being so the opposite of gentle to something like
being gentle the opposite of being harsh is maybe
being gentle the opposite of being hostile is to be gentle the opposite of being a poking and and
attacking our experience and wanting it to go away is not necessarily to want it to be
there at all but to be gentle gentle with what is so perhaps for this
meditation maybe we can sit with um with an orientation towards calmness and
gentleness and a a kind of a
orientation a kind of reference of that even if you don't feel that it's
difficult to feel calm difficult to feel gentle maybe there's something inside of you
maybe deep down or in the corners of your heart your mind that knows little bit what those things
are and just knowing them is a lifeline to not getting swept away in their
opposites so assuming a meditation posture
that is supportive for you in being alert
but also a posture that will help you to be somewhat calm and gentle
but not collapsing and relaxing too much sinking into a couch and
but somehow a posture of that allows you to hold some alertness
together with calm
together with being gentle
and then gently calmly taking a few long slow deep
in-breaths
breathing in and breathing out and as you exhale a few long slow
exhales letting go
releasing the body relaxing as deep into the body as you
can
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and being easy with your breathing
being easy with how things are right now at ease
even if things are difficult breathing with that easily calmly
and part of common meditation is as if you have all the time in the world
to offer attention to our experience
to get to know it as if you're calmly listening to a troubled friend
and you sit there as if you have all the time in the world to hear hear them out
and to be gentle is not to intrude or push yourself force yourself assert
yourself in on what's happening but to allow your inner life to allow
your body space to show itself to be itself
here and now
softening the belly
and calmly settling into your body breathing
calmly
orienting yourself to experience the in-breaths and the
out-breaths in the body
with the exhale allowing yourself to become calm
slowly a little calmer more relaxed
calming the thinking mind as you exhale
in small incremental steps
if you're inclined you can very calmly say the word calm as you exhale
and see if there can be a gentleness in how you receive the inhale
breathing in and breathing out
calm and gentle in a way that supports you to be present
for what is
one thing that supports calmness
is recognizing the calm that's here
[Music]
recognizing gentleness that's here
supports the growth of gentle
settling into the present moment
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps you can recognize whatever way that you are more settled
calmer than you were at the beginning maybe even gentler
and in being calmer or gentler more settled
does it give more room inside for for your heart
for your warm-heartedness or kind-heartedness
or a simple maybe very ordinary
caring caringness
kindness and love and maybe not carrying that love or
kindness with you into the world so much as carrying the calmness
and gentleness that has room for the heart
room for heart qualities
and then as we come to the end of the sitting perhaps you can open up this
calm gentle space kind-heartedness
to the people in your life neighbors and friends and family and
members of your community people that you might learn about
through media and dedicate
the benefit and merit of this sitting here for the welfare and happiness of others
the kind of welfare and happiness that might allow them to go into the world
warm-heartedly may all beings
be happy and peaceful safe and free
so that their best qualities of heart may be shared with others
maybe may we all share the goodness of our hearts with each other
you
um
so so for this week i'd like to
focus on meta loving kindness but in a particular way
on friday i heard my friend paul heller who spoke here a few weeks ago for the 7 a.m for a week he gave a wonderful
talk where he divided up the discourse on loving-kindness into four parts
it was very nice to hear him and i was inspired by this four part division
and so i thought i would do that for this week is to um take a look at the
the the kind of the fun foundational teachings attributed to the
buddha on loving kindness that's a particular uh poem that
that then it can be divided into four parts that's kind of the poem uh on loving kindness and
um and if you want to uh read my translation which is what i'll
use um you'll find it in the what's new uh in the home page of imc's website
under reflections from gil you also find it um the part we're going
to talk about today in uh in a little description of
the on youtube description on the on the of what's happening here in the
underneath the photograph underneath the video if you do show more uh i put this section that we're going to talk about
but please don't read it now and get distracted we'll go through it and that paul's talk
is not recorded so for for public use
so um um
so we find in the ancient teachings of the buddha
that loving-kindness gets emphasized a lot of the four brahmaviharas the four kinds of love that
were championed in the ancient world lovingkindness gets the most most attention and it encompasses
quite quite a bit uh but encompasses uh the desire to be friendly and all the
good qualities of uh that comes flows out of friendliness helping people when they're in trouble
our friends in trouble supporting people when things are going well caring for them
being kind but the fundamental way of seeing it is a good will what comes out of our good will and
the good will is a nice translation some because the opposite of
loving kindness is sometimes seen to be ill will and a certain kind of hostility towards
others and so in this discourse on
loving-kindness it's divided into four parts or can be divided into four parts
and the first part is not really about loving-kindness itself but can be seen as the the uh
the support for it the way of being in the world and being with ourselves that uh makes
room for makes uh the ability to have good will grow in us and develop and some people
will refer to this section as being ethical kind of
kind of kind of an uh ethical teaching but so
many of what's talked about is not ethical in the sense of how we relate to other people but how we are in ourselves
and um so maybe the word integrity has integrity and ethics sometimes are
considered near synonyms of each other and so maybe this is a qualities of
integrity that this involves i like to think of it as different things that makes room for the
heart qualities to come and if we want to have more metta more
kindness in our life more friendliness then it's not just a matter of of kind
of just drumming it up like if we can just call on it evoke it automatically
but rather create the conditions for where it's more likely to flow out of us more likely to be here for us
so it's a little bit of indirect way of cultivating loving-kindness not to do it directly but to prepare the
ground for it and many things that are important to do in life we prepare for it we adjust ourselves
accordingly and so we're ready for the situation that we're going to do and um so i'm going to put
in the in the chat um the the section of it
and it's not quite formatted very well this way but uh so this i told you different places you can do
it you do it or you can just listen to me as like i go read it so i'll read it first and then we'll i'll discuss it
so the discourse on lovingkindness to reach the state of peace though skilled in the
good should be capable and upright straight forward and easy to speak to
gentle and not proud contented and easily supported
living lightly with few duties wise and with senses calmed
not arrogant and without greed for supporters and they should not do the least thing
that the wise would criticize so here the explicit discussion here is
not about loving kindness but to reach the state of peace and a more more kind of close reading of
the metasuta it's uh it's can be understood as being um utilizing or
being supported by loving kindness uh on the path to liberation and freedom
so rather than loving kindness being an adjunct or something you know different from the path of freedom liberation it's actually
very much on it and the cultivation of this form of love supports the movement towards liberation
and those skilled and the good and there's a lot of a lot of words in the
suttas that are related this word good my favorite is the word beautiful kaliana
skilled in what's beautiful skilled and what is beneficial skilled
and what is wholesome uh which is the topic for the last week
uh so there's a skill again this is the word skill is related to the word wholesome uh you know kusala there is skilled
in the good and and what follows is some of the
skills that we can develop and i like it think of it as skills um because
it doesn't we don't listen to this and think where you'd automatically be this way there's an ideal and therefore you
should be this way but rather these are things to cultivate to develop these are things to work towards
these are valuable states that shouldn't be overlooked and and if we want to live a purposeful
life uh this uh cultivating these are phenomenally supportive so being capable and upright
so i think the word capable here means able to apply oneself that's at least
how i understand it not so much that we're capable in doing a lot of different things
but rather we're capable of engaging in the practice and cultivating skills
cultivating yourself in ways and upright i think this is a in the ancient world
this idea being upright like sometimes it is in in english has a meaning of being having
certain kind of integrity and uh an integrity that allows a person
to stand upright uh without feeling uh diminished or feeling
belittled belittling themselves or feeling shy or feeling somehow less than or something because of who
they are but the kind of integrity allows in a very simple way uh to be upright
hold oneself straight and certain confidence straightforward means to be
direct in how we speak not go round about just say things as they are in a kind of simple straight way
easy to speak to means that it means that if someone needs to give us
feedback about something that's difficult we're easy to receive that we're not
automatically defensive we don't go into the attack mode but if someone has to say something to us we're there to listen and be there
uh without automatically defending ourselves not automatically agreeing or being
pushed over by the other people but uh it's easy for people come to us and say by the way i need to talk to you
i want to talk to you about something and that was difficult for me gentle
and not proud so upright but not proud and proud here uh sometimes in modern
english the word pride has very positive connotations so what proud here means is to be puffed up a certain
kind of conceit and gentle and
which was kind of the topic for the meditation we had a certain kind of gentleness and i like
the reference point for gentle for me is to understand it better is to appreciate
the opposite of it that to not be gentle makes the heart and mind kind of crowded
usually to be harsh to be mean to be
rough with people there's a kind of engagement and involvement that that doesn't make room for freedom
for love for kindness for the kind of inner cultivation of the
heart that the path of freedom involves so in gentleness
and contented and easily supported so these are values that are a little
bit more focused on monastics easily but it can be for anyone monastics are supposed to be very
contented with having just a few things just enough to be comfortable and through the eyes of modern world
the monastic life can be seen as ascetic but in time of the buddha it was clearly not to be ascetic there are people who
are much more seriously ascetic than the buddhists rather the buddhist monastics to have just
enough to be comfortable just enough clothes just enough housing just enough food
and just enough medicine but not more than what's needed contented with what's what keeps us the basics comfortable
and that's kind of a fascinating reference point um content with just enough to keep us
alive healthily and easily supported for monastic not to be want a lot from
other people and you know the supporters and and trying to acquire more and more from the donors that
support them similarly living lightly and with few duties not being so busy because having a lot
to do and lots of responsibilities doesn't make space in time that this these heart qualities
need in order to flower um wise and with senses calmed and
the senses come so the eyes are calm we see the world in a calm way we're not always
darting about looking the ears are calm so that the taste buds are calm we don't
you know want more and more food something like that not arrogant and without greed for
supporters and they should not do the least thing that the wise would criticize
so for the people who in your life who you really respect and and value for being being wise people
to not do something that they would be critical of um mostly it means don't be unethical don't
be mean don't be don't have ill will but
to use the reference points of those who are wise uh to how to care for yourself and also
how to relate to yourself don't do the least things that the wise would kind of that's not quite right
um and uh so it's a tall order but it's kind of a
call to be careful also with how you are when you're alone in the privacy of your own life
are you also there living in a way that those who you respect would not be
critical of and so your life is transparent or harmonious whether you're alone or not uh
ready to bring these qualities all these qualities uh to your life when you're living alone
and quietly from your privacy of your for your own situation or when you're
in the world public with others that you would be capable and upright
straightforward and easy to speak to gentle and not proud contented and
easily supported living lightly and with few duties wise
and with senses calmed not arrogant and without greed for supporters
and not the least not doing the least thing that the wise would criticize so this sets the stage
then for an attitude a orientation towards others
that can be said to be that of kindness or friendliness good will metta and that will be the topic for the
next section of the matasuta tomorrow so thank you
and if you're at all inclined you might want to memorize today this
section some people find tremendous benefit from memorizing the metasuta
and this this version is not the one we usually use here at imc we use the monastic one that
comes out of the monastery abbaya gary or amaravati in england because that's a
nice kind of chanting kind of quality but either one and
and so thank you