go so okay hello and welcome formally to everyone
to this happy hour so so the theme for our practice
today is what i like to call nourished
so these practices of the heart that we engage in meta gratitude
uh generosity etc etc they're they're a way to support ourselves and
others oh sound went out i hear from kim can you still hear me
give me thumbs up if you can still hear me you can still hear me so maybe the sound went out for a moment okay all right okay thanks for for that heads
up kim but seems like it came back let me make sure my settings i'm going to
change something to the settings here just in case this is causing problems
here we go that might make it better so okay so where was i uh yes so
so uh and and we often engage with this practice uh with with people with human beings
and and then in the categories of of meta and the brahmaviharas as we
expand expand further we the last category is all beings may all
beings
humans
i got logged out well but that seems okay it's still
recording wow that was impressive that had never happened before wow i love it you're all still here i'm
back okay so all right so i think the
being logged out and logged in i think all the issues of being frozen up should have uh should be fixed
now all right things are as they are let's continue let's continue it is what it is it is
what it is such as life right such is life so
so uh so yes nourished by nature nourished by nature so um so with the category of of
all beings um yeah and it's nice to actually
intentionally include nature leaves living beings
trees flowers in that and um i'll tell you personally
the the um inspiration the inspiration for tonight came when i
went for a little walk earlier and just looking up again it's an urban
area but there are trees there are some you know there's foliage around there's some greenery and just looking
up i felt so nourished by all the green i started to see and then
i started to see more and more because i was tuned to green just being nourished by the green by the
sky and then i imagined what if this wasn't here it was just asphalt and roads and my heart sank so
there was so much gratitude so much gratitude for all the green
for all the nature that surrounds us supports us our hearts
and i want to share actually one image with you also another uh
motivation for me so when i was on retreat um a
few weeks ago i went on a solo hike
um in a forest in a redwood forest and lay down in the forest and
just lay down there and looked up and this is for those familiar or not
familiar with redwoods this is a grove of redwoods there's usually a mother tree
and the mother tree spawns a whole circle of baby trees who grow up so i was
lying in this circle in this circle of of um these
beautiful giant tall still rhett was feeling held just lying
there meditating for 45 minutes and just took a photo as a memento to remind myself of the
beauty and peace and i want to bring that bring that to this guided meditation to
be to feel held whatever your version of the grove is of the redwood grove is
to be held to just be hell looking up at the sky and hearing the sound of birds just held
lovingly held dear we're here if you're safe here you are
we're holding you we're supporting you you can be nourished you can be nurtured in this moment your heart can
be still so you can borrow my image or have your own image
of being supported by by nourished by nature so
so with that as the setup let's start our practice together
so invite you to get into your meditation posture
landing landing in this body
as always we start with arriving in the body with the
breath inviting inviting stillness
letting awareness sense sense the breath
in the abdomen being pulled in naturally in and out by itself
you don't have to do anything breath is breathing you let it be natural
let it be effortless
let awareness receive the sensations of the breath
the lower abdomen expanding contracting settling
with each breath
connecting connecting you connecting you to clear sit bones
connected to the cushion or the chair
there are stand-ins for mother earth as if you are connected to the earth
your feet
connected to the earth the touch points
so you're sitting on the cushion your entire underside
rooted to the earth
noticing the breath moving through the abdomen and through
the lower body ah expanding
relaxing connecting sit bones lower legs and feet to the earth
as if your entire lower body is breathing
the same way that trees all the leaves breathe
the entire lower body breathing
letting the breath be sensed
in your abdomen your chest expanding
making more space around your heart whatever is happening right now
holding spaciously holding emotions
let the space show up freely in your shoulders and
neck the breath moving
through your arms and hands relaxing softening the hands
let them drop
the breath soothing ah as if opening
any contractions
the face and the head relaxing the forehead
the eyes resting in their socket
the cheeks the chin
muscles be behind your eyes your jaw inside your head
relaxing
let the breath be filled
it's movement it's life-giving [Music]
enlivening relaxing
natural movement throughout the body
wherever there's any contraction or tightening
with the out breath it's released
and if thoughts are arising it's okay it's not a problem
that's what minds do they think no need to problematize what's natural simply
notice ah spaciously the thinking has arisen
and gently ever so lovingly just for the benefit of this moment's
practice not that there's anything wrong with thinking
but but to settle the mind to take refuge in quietness
the next out breath ah gently releasing thanking the thought saying if it's
if you're important enough please come back later after meditation i'll be waiting for you
just here just now
feeling nourished by the natural breath
and now if you wish
i'd like to invite you to bring to mind a plant a flower
a bush something green that has brought you
delight has brought you joy
the recent times maybe to flower your smelt
or a tree that you sat in the shade of
this living being that you had a moment of a personal connection with
this plant this flower
a baby's flower someone gave you a bouquet or you gave someone
made you happy made them happy some time
ago bright colors
letting yourself connect connect with that moment of relishing
feeling nourished feeling nourished by nature
this plant this tree this flower
noticing sense of appreciation and
gratitude
for this particular instant
with each breath as you breathe in as if you're breathing in the nourishment
of this plant this flower that moment of
connection thanking thanking this plant
this tree flower the grove in your heart thank you
letting yourself expand from this instant from this instantiation
more expansively feeling held all around feeling held by nature
could be a favorite garden of yours somewhere you've been
or a hike you've been on
or if you like to borrow the image i offered
and settle in in the middle of the redwoods
the grove of tall redwoods
held ah held in safety and care
letting your heart settle and relax
be nourished be held know where to go nothing to do
but to just be held
by nature
the green vibrancy of nature can be so healing
let yourself receive it without getting in your own way
imagine it's freely offered
receiving it with appreciation with love maybe with a bow in your heart
not taking for granted what's around you what's about you
and noticing just as your heart can receive
be nourished
by nature could also beam care love appreciation
for nature for the trees about you the green
so giving and receiving receiving and giving with each breath
as if you were a tree
receiving with each breath giving with each breath
spreading your care and love appreciation
gratitude
for nature for trees for flowers for greenery about you
either physically where you are or in this image in this vision that you have
in the garden or in the grove
and for the last few minutes what if what if you were a tree this being
the tree if you the image of the grove a tree in the
grove with mother trees or a flower or a bush
connected through your roots to the other trees and bushes
sharing resources sharing nutrients sharing information
as we know we know now with other trees other
growth the garden in the forest
part of the family
receiving and giving receiving and giving
and nourishing human beings who might come
might walk through the garden
with shay with shade with care
beautiful tree well rooted tall
still part part of nature
nourished by nature part of nature
nature inside nature outside it's all nature it's all nature
may we all wake up to our nature
our true nature may all beings be happy
may all beings all beings
be free
thank you all for your practice
so change the settings for your reflections you can raise your
zoom hand or type in chat if you type to me privately i won't say your name
if it's to everyone i'll say your name ally please
so this was just so powerful for me um i'm on a solo camping trip right now
and i'm in idlewild in southern california and i was here last year around this
time and at that time i was having this
really profound spiritual awakening and so there was just this real magical quality to it and
when i got here last night it was so hot and the place i'm staying is so much
different it's not what i wanted and i just had all these expectations
russian um and then this morning i you know i got to this place where i could say this prayer of like can i
can i see what's beautiful here can i be with what's happening right now and
i was just so blown away today by all the beauty um that i saw
and what just kept coming to me in that meditation was like nature
you know nature is never static it's never the same um just like we're never the same and
can i bring presents to myself um even when it's not
you know the the climate or the the conditions aren't aren't preferable
so anyways it was just really um fitting and um
just wanted to share that thank you thank you ali thank you so much for sharing that i
i'm so grateful that you dialed in from your cafeteria i see you on your camping
chair that's great i love it i'm so grateful yeah that you you um tuned in and dialed in and joined
us because this is it's so fresh i am so touched i am so moved here you are in
the middle of of nature i'm actually getting goosebumps with with doing this practice and yes the
conditions it's too hot you're right it's too hot outside sometimes it's too hot inside the
temperature the you know emotional temperatures too can i be with this changing nature can i
be can i appreciate what is nature inside me outside peter thank you so much for bringing that in it's lovely
of course we pl we planned this right ally you and i [Laughter]
just kidding thank you
yeah other reflections please person on the phone
hey nikki it's michael michael i had huge mudita when you talked about
your retreat just you going on my retreat warmed my heart and then sharing under the redwoods and
then prior to that you talked about your walk and seeing green and green and nature are so healing and
i just really appreciate you bringing that up and um i loved
the guy i had very pleasant feelings through the meditation because i love
nature it's such a wonderful dharma teacher so deep bowels and i'm so grateful that
it's taped and i do have a question for you yeah please where were you on your retreat or would
you like to share or not yeah i was uh i was in scots valley
in close to santa cruz so close to the redwoods close to the ocean yeah and thank you for your modita i
feel it michael it goes back and forth it feels you know
my joy brings joy for you and then i feel joy that you feel joyful by joy so it's an infinite
echoing and mirroring is the virtual cycle and i so appreciate you speaking because if i remember correctly
part of what you do part of the work that you do is is um supporting nature
in some way i forget the details but the non-profit that you work that you lead right do i get that
right well um i'm a huge gardener
surfer slash plant-based vegan sustainable wait
that's great but i'm fairly like retired
i'm in the last chapter but um yeah i mean that's right guessed you
were at medicine buddha because they have a magical forest there that's just delightful
but um again deep vows thank you michael yes that's right i
remember naya you're a big surfer i remember your special connection with nature thanks for bringing that in nicholas
please nice yeah um
i just remembered the just how nice it is to be in a forest
and hear the rustling of the leaves and the creaking of the branches and the wind and the shade shifting and
bringing that same kind of attitude to all the shifting sensations inside and
all of the creaking inside and all of the wrestling inside and just kind of something about the image
it really helped just kind of settle back into the flow of it all the pleasant and the unpleasant and this and
that and just it's it's so natural for me to be in the flow of the shifting sensations kind of
externally of the forest and somehow that was very supportive of settling in and just kind of being with
the flow of sensations internally in the body nice nice great beautiful
beautiful is this is inside that alright it's the yeah how the wrestling the nature
outside like oh yeah it's nature it's okay it's just wrestling and inside oh yeah this is just rustling
i can be with this it's not a problem lovely beautiful synchronicity synergy thanks for sharing
that that beautiful inside synergy is just what came up thank you nicholas and
oh yes thank you mark have a great local sangha mark says goodbye to us
so dear ones let's turn our attention and practice in a small grove of three
small grove you're maybe you're a redwood you're showing up with two other redwoods in this small
grove and sharing your love for the other redwoods who support you and you
support them with each breath and we'll start with 30 seconds of um silent meta
for each other and then share as much or as little as you wish about your practice about whatever is
coming up so i will create the rooms here thank you all and
[Music] let's try this again okay here we go the rooms are created and i'm going to open
them now here okay so we have time for reflections
what what came up for you what did you notice i would love to hear from especially if
you haven't spoken for a while or if you're or if you're new
let's see am i saying any oh you see carol okay hold on one sec let's see
there you go carol i'm going to uh there yeah
hi hi um i got cut off in the group but i i was just commenting on what somebody
else had said in the group about how nature everything fits in in nature and
um how i i think that that's a really beautiful idea and i i i often feel like when i'm in
nature all of the kind of um you know just like ego based random
self-deprecating thoughts negativity all that stuff kind of falls away and i can sometimes really tap into me being part
of that and i think that's one thing that i personally find really
healing um being in nature and i really appreciated um the other person anthony in our group
pointing that out because i really i really think it's awesome
that's absolutely awesome thanks to both of you for bringing that in yeah absolutely yeah it's interesting
as i've been guiding this meditation i realized oh i wouldn't i want to go for a hike this weekend i want to be in nature now this weekend i
have a desire for it and and also at the same time um both you know there's that desire to be immersed
and what i did want to point out with this guided meditation i often point out
is there's nature outside and there's nature inside we can always bring the nature we can feel as if we're immersed like this
guided meditation that we are in nature and that sense of oh ease that nicholas was talking about oh
yeah there's rustling in the trees oh there's a little rustling inside that's okay i can chill with that
there's a set there's so we can bring it in too so yeah and and i love what you've
brought in carol and anthony yeah so yeah profound profound ah
thank you other reflections you're welcome to raise your hand or
or uh type in chat
maybe something quick
okay well maybe we only have time to dedicate the merit and close which would be perfect
so so thank you all for your practice thank you for showing up for yourselves
for each other and for all beings whose lives you touch directly and indirectly
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
thank you