good day to you all greetings and uh
nice to be here so um
an expression from the ancient language pali that it's translated as here and now
sometimes here and now literally the literal words are um
the the seen dharma the dharma that is seen
and sometimes those two words are reversed rather than ditty dhamma it says
which is the the um that uh seeing the dharma
so the dharma that seeing or seeing the dharma and this points to the experiential
quality of this practice here and now refers to really seeing the truth seeing
the dharma seeing phenomena experience directly here
whether it's through the eyesight for those who can see through hearing those who can hear
through smelling through tasting through the tactile sensations of the body
it's this direct contact direct seeing correct experiencing that that is where
the dharma unfolds that's where we see the dharma it's not complicated
it's not in a sense it's not found in books or in dharma talks it's found in the direct
perception direct experience that we have if we can make that direct experience
direct in a sense unmediated by the projections
we put on top of it uh so that we see experience
and it's kind of kind of in its rawness without identifying with it or
being for or against it or interpreting in all kinds of ways just a raw basic sense experience
there's something powerful about finding ourselves at peace in our direct experience
so that's partly what we're here to do and be passed in our practice is to
settle in become centered and grounded here
in our direct experience
so to begin by taking a meditative posture a posture
that maybe supports your ability to be
aware at all at your scent stores
the heightened awareness
and even though we use this language of seeing a lot it's the inner mind's eye
and so we sometimes close the eyes
to simplify our experience
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
where the exhale is particularly useful
for returning here where you are
long slow steady exhale where you consciously center yourself
in your body in this place where you are
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and to continue the centering grounding settling into here and now
as you exhale might relax the muscles of the face
softening around the eyes sometimes there's a strong habit to be
always looking even when the eyes are closed searching
wanting fearing and to allow the eyes to soften
sometimes softens the wanting
the fear
and as you exhale to soften the shoulders
let them relax and
shoulders can feel the gentle pull of gravity
maybe in feeling the weight of your shoulders
and then softening your belly maybe his belly relaxes maybe the whole
belly area can settle and down into you so your center of gravity
gets it goes lower in your torso
that is seen the experience that's experienced
the sensations that are sensed
an interpretation not a story
not being involved in a prediction or fear what will happen
not lingering with what has happened thinking about it
but seeing if your body and mind
can be ready moment by moment to be fresh
almost like renewed as if there is no past just this moment
to experience and to know the direct experience here and now
free of past and future
experiencing the experience of the moment
feeling the feelings that are here
breathing with the breathing that is happening
sensing the experience of breathing
one breath at a time
you
staying close to the experiences that are direct immediate the experiences that are
intimate with your five senses
and with the present moment unfolding
of your life your inner life and mind
the river of life that's seen
in the present moment
you
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to turn your
inner eye sight on the world around you
people in your home or in your neighborhood your communities
friends family strangers the people that you're aware of through
the news or other means
and they become
the dharma that is seen the seen dharma and to gaze
upon others with soft and kind and easeful eyes
to gaze upon others without fear or anxiety without desires or aversion
so that some of the best qualities of your heart
have space to come forth and meet those people as you
consider them
may it be that this practice we've done together
benefits the lives of people we encounter this week
may the practice of mindfulness help us the best qualities friendliness
of kindness love compassion respect
flow out of us in our connection with other people
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe
may all beings be free
and thereby may all beings also be filled with happiness
may we delight in the shared happiness
that we might experience as a result may all beings be free
thank you
so before i begin with the dharma talk a few announcements so when we finish
this talk at 10 30 or so
those of you who like will switch over to a zoom meeting and it's going
to be a community meeting for imc and everyone of course is welcome but
the topic is the reopening of imc uh being able to come here in person and
practice together and of course that has some effect on the people who are far away who are
participating through youtube or zoom but the topic mostly is about beginning to
open here in august and maybe take questions hear about concerns
people have and some of the plans we have for that and anything else so um
the the the zoom link is in a few places it's on the imc
account calendar i think you have to cut and paste it from there it's also
on the imc what's new page on the home page of imc
and uh if you can't just click on it you might have to uh you know again cut and paste uh copy and
paste the uh the zoom link and um if you
if you need to use a password to get in the password is mehta m-e-t-t-a it's a
poly word for loving-kindness and um and also i'm going to put it here in the chat now it's at the top of the chat as
well and it'll be at the chat um
when we finished today i'll put it at the end of the chat as well so just so easy to find and i don't i think you can
click on it from the chat and um so um
the other announcement is that in a couple of weeks maybe three weeks um the
this very innovative and creative dharma teacher named gregory
kramer who will be teaching for us on zoom kind of a modified or a
kind of a kind of creative way of having a weekend retreat where there's a lot of time for practicing in daily life
and and gregory is very focused on relational
practice how we practice in our lives in relationship to each other and he has this a wonderful new book on
the whole the whole life path which is um
uh taking the eightfold path and applying it to our whole life not just meditation or some
segment of our life and it's a nice very nice book and and so he's gonna present on that in a creative way and
and support you through a weekend of practice and reflection and information about that is
also in the what's new uh on imc's homepage and also on the
on the account on the calendar you have to register for it so i think part of the creativity is that
uh in the times during the weekend when you're not not actually on zoom which is not all
time he's going to periodically send people text messages
with some dharma teaching or practice or something so to kind of keep us practicing and
engaged outside of the zoom session itself
so
as many of you know the word vipassana is the word that
the pali word the ancient world word for the that's used for our meditation practice
sometimes which we say we do the passana practice
and now what i want to highlight is that vipassana the root of the word pasana
means to see and the v is an emphatic prefix so it's kind of
like to see in some special way or an important way and so some of us like to translate it
as clear seeing and then as you know it's often translated
almost like the brand uh that you know the our brand of buddhism uh insight
um translates insight so insight meditation and it has the word you know sight or
seeing in it and this ability to see is uh
and here we're not talking about that only the physical seeing some people can't see but uh it's the
kind of the ability to perceive through any of the senses or to be able to see through the mind's
eye the wisdom eye the dharma eye which is the the place in the mind where
we are really present for what's happening and there's a wisdom about it there's a
penetrating understanding about what is happening here
and in fact uh the experience of it's a real
penetration of what's happening in our lives uh in the dharma as we mature
is called opening the dharma eye uh and uh so opening the dharma eye
the um and so the idea of seeing clearly is also
when we open the dharma eye we see the dharma
the dharma which is visible here and now is clearly seen
the and then sometimes they even talk about it with a dharma eye open there's knowledge
and vision and for those of you know a little bit about hinduism or some of the yoga traditions in the um
the word for uh vision is dasana which in sanskrit is darshan darshana and which is a very
powerful word and darshan is often used for sitting in the presence of a
of a guru where you the guru is in sight as if seeing the teacher is really
powerful and here in this tradition is seeing the truth seeing the real dharma the
experience directly is very powerful so knowledge and the
seeing this vision is over and over again emphasizing this tradition
so imagine that you leave town on a hike and leave
city you're living in a maybe metropolitan area but there's a mountain on the edges of it and you go for a nice
long hike up in the mountains higher and higher and higher and and if you don't like to hike maybe
there's a a gondola that carries you up to the
heights but you're up to the top and uh there's a kind of a
get to get near the top and there's a tunnel that goes in and you go through you go through or
there's a there's a big kind of say that you get close to the top and there's a big
door two doors double doors and uh you open these double doors
and you step forward onto this little bit wide ledge on the other side of the mountain and
there on that ledge is this vast panorama of mountain
after mountain after mountain mountain ranges
rivers forests birds flying eagles flying around
hawks um clouds you know that you're up and tie
up in the mouth and so it's a vast sky that is so clear and broad and wide
and it can be take your breath away it's so beautiful this natural world and
maybe in a healthy wonderful way you feel very small or you feel like
you're part of this amazing natural world that we live in
and uh but you're on this ledge looking out at it and it's just a sense of awe
but this isn't that you want anything you're not like leaning forward try to i
want that i want that mountain on that mountain and it isn't that you're identifying yourself with the scenery there the
rivers and the forests and the trees and say well that's mine or that's how i want to be or it's just
like it's just almost like the sense of self and self concern drop away in a way that back in the city
when you knew people and they were concerned all kinds of social concerns are operating and
but here in this ledge looking out at this amazing scene um self-concern drops away and in fact
it was kind of self-forgetting and we look across the scene and some of this what we see seems
dangerous some of the mountaintops indifference there's a storm brewing and there's snow up there and
you're glad you're not there because that looks like it could be quite dangerous to be caught in that storm but it's far away or you see these
rushing rivers and of course it's pastoral and wonderful from a distance but you know if you were
to come across that river we treacherous to cross it it's roaring
down and um and so you can see that some of the paths on the
side of the cliff going down to the valley below are treacherous little thin little paths and
it'd be dangerous to walk down there but you're not going down there so the danger
has no fear for you and it's like wow this the beauty the pastoral nature of it the
peacefulness setting the danger that's there standing on a ledge and looking out
and just taking it all in in a peaceful open comfortable way feeling secure on
the ledge not being for or against anything just at ease
taking it all in then you turn around to go back and
when you turn around you find out that you're actually on another ledge that's facing the city
and you look down the city and some of it is quite inspiring and beautiful and some of it
is um these beautiful buildings tall buildings and some of it clearly is treacherous and
dangerous and um there's a smog and fires in places in the in the city there
are clearly uh poor places that people are in squalor and places of excessive
wealth and and um and then you know but there's also the edges of the city
and beyond the edges there's this vast uh green plains uh grasslands
and beyond that other mountains and oceans and rivers and then the city is just part of this wider
big circle and you see it all but you're high on this ledge
and again you are there's right now there's no inclination
to be judging it to be for or against it it just all seems to be in the context of this
vastness of the natural unfolding of this universe and you sitting on the ledge just watching it
and again even though you go back down to it defining yourself by it being caught by
desires and this and that doesn't exist you just kind of take in this wide
field and there's a stillness and a quiet within you as you gaze out
upon the scene so maybe this this analogy
is pointing to the ability to be gazing out of the ledge of your eyes if you can
see uh physically see you know there's kind of like that's your mountain top
on your head and and the ledge is your is your you know maybe the bottom rim of
your eye socket and you're looking out and how do you look when you look out into the world do you
look with an agenda does your looking sir
serve as the servant of your fear and anxiety darting around
looking how to make yourself safe does your looking is it a servant of
your desires looking what you can get to the next thing and next things i think that some of us you know we
sometimes get pulled into web surfing and there's the eyes are looking and looking and getting and
going to the next thing and they're busy they're not at rest and at ease just looking at the scene
or do they is a seeing in the surface of what's wrong the aversion we have or is the seeing
you know how does how is that seeing or is it just like settling on that
ledge in the mountain looking out on a scene a natural scene that we don't have to identify with
we don't have to judge we don't have to have any agendas with we just gaze peacefully with a calm eyes
with the relaxed eyes soft eyes taking it all in without it in a nice
way when i first went to practice in thailand
i practiced in a small monastery meditation center outside of bangkok and
there was an interesting place with a variety of things but there was a man there a monk
who it was explained that he was an extremely mature practitioner and a deep deep
meditator in fact i was told that he could um he had attained something called
niroda samapati that he could sit in a state of suspended
animation a certain kind of state of cessation unmoving for seven days
he can just drop into this deep deep state and and so i don't know about he could
actually do that but that's what i was told but uh so so that i met him and i talked to him
and the thing that was so remarkable about him was looking into his eyes
and it wasn't like his eyes were deeply receded exactly like physically receded but there was
something about looking in his eyes they felt like looking into this amazing
depths kind of like being on that ledge in the mountains looking out at this huge natural scene
or looking out at the night sky and just so deep and vast there was something about looking at his
eyes that i thought wow this man is deep there's depth there or spaciousness there
and some of it was that his eyes were not darting around
his eyes were kind of at rest and at ease and it wasn't like he was staring at me
but he wasn't not looking at me his eyes were not bulging out his eyes
were not pulling back he was just there and it kind of there was a feeling inside i had that this man's
mind is not really it's not agitated it's at ease and in that ease he's just
looking and uh kind of like looking and there's no one i mean
one thing then one way it's talked about sometimes in terrible buddhism which some of you might not like this kind of
description but is is that all the lights were on he was
fully conscious and awake it was like a house where all the lights were on but no one's home so everything was
firing everything was clearly there and but there was no place of self no center
he was holding on to no contraction around self me myself and mine it was kind of this vast emptiness
that they experienced so to see to be able to see
and become free is a phenomenal thing because as we begin practicing as we
practice and we start seeing understanding feeling
that our the way we see is uh all these things are
sticky things are kind of stuck themselves onto the seeing and we don't just see clearly
we see with desire we see with fear we see with judgment
we see with interpretations we see with bias
we see with bias about who we are we see about projections and ideas and
identities i'm this way i'm not the way i have to do this i'm supposed to do that
and all these ideas are sticky and they stick onto
the eyesight or the perception that we have and uh and sometimes it's really clear
that they're agitating and with an agenda the mind is the eyes or the perception the hearing whatever
it is is darting around and moving and wanting and but when there's no another sticky
stuff then there's just seeing
and it's kind of like if the smog clears and the or the fog clears
and we see after a long time not seeing it how clear the ear is and we see the
mountains in the distance we don't normally see it isn't so much that we're seeing
anything but the absence of smog we see the clarity
is clarity a thing it's not exactly a thing but the clarity is there the same thing
can happen with the mind the mind can become clear and uh
and there's no self-preoccupation self-assertion there's no
self-criticism or self-belittling we don't have to know self-apology
the self is not in the seeing and the perception
and the same thing we turn inward we stand on the ledge of the eyes and we look inside
and we see all kinds of things in there as we go along in practice and sometimes it said that
self-knowledge is seldom good news because some of what we see is we see our bias and our projections and our
fears and our interpretations and our shortcomings and all kinds of things operating in there
and they can be that can be a source of agitation that can be fuel for continued
identification ideas interpretations of ourselves i'm a bad person i'm wrong because i'm doing
this and i'm an embarrassment to the buddhist world because i had an attachment
and but to be able to sit on the metaphoric ledge of our
eyesight and look back into ourselves just like we would look out into the
natural world with this unmoving mind with this peaceful
eyesight not darting around not wanting and not wanting not
interpreting just looking and of course some of the things that you might see is
maybe not not your best qualities but maybe you don't have to identify with it
or do anything with it and in fact if you do nothing just see it maybe
something inside will be slightly amused or slightly kind of liberated
oh it's just it's just a natural phenomenon
and so we're seeing what's there and this ability to see
with a kind of unmoving mind or the mind that's at peace and at rest that clearly sees but it's not darting around
not straining trying no strain no trying to understand
no searching j no stickiness of self me myself and mine
no self in the seeing just seeing
and there's something about the eyesight maybe that can maybe a hearing as well where in the seeing and in the hearing
that itself there's no added we don't the seeing itself doesn't
add so much but so we can see at some point all the stuff that we add
the judgments the interpretations and the desires we have those are all extra and to see them as
extra but to see with this quiet still
soft easy eyesight to see
the dharma eye that is opened that the buddhism talks about the buddha talk about
opening the dharma eye happens when there's a clear seeing
undisturbed seeing when the mind the heart the eyesight or the
inner eye is not agitated it's at peace we just we can just quietly gaze out
on the world to quietly gaze on what's inside to see the direct experience as things
are and we start seeing how things arise and disappear how they come and go
how experiences are transient and they move and flux and change
and there's something about seeing in this still peaceful clear seeing
how things are in flux and changing that frees us from
the identifications the attachments the stickiness of all these ideas and night desires and feelings that go along with
seeing there's a kind of just allowing this the flow the stream of things
experiences to happen through and to appreciate how they everything is just coming and
going and in the going of it
allowing things to come and go and the going of it then there also is this freedom from
attachments from clinging there also is this clarity and simplicity
of clear seeing of just being at rest at ease
on a ledge overlooking a vast natural world on an edge
ledge looking at the vast natural world that includes all the things that humans
create and are part of it and maybe be inspired maybe be free
maybe have compassion maybe have the heartbreak at some of the
things we see but there's only seeing
or say it maybe a little bit more accurately there is clear seeing without
self caught up in the seeing
and that clear seeing makes room and space for the heart for all other things to
operate in a kind of natural way
so both literally you might be mindful of your eyes and seeing
and see if you how much how you use your physical eyes do you use how often do you strain how
often are they darting around how often are they at rest how often are they just gazing quietly and peacefully
like you're watching a river sitting on the back of a river watching the river go down or looking at the sky at the clouds
floating just kind of very relaxed and open peaceful and how much are they agitated
and the service of desires and fears and aversions
and and and then also more deeply in the mind
is there stuff your mind does that is sticky that sticks itself onto your site and so
your site is not so clear it's
and what experience have you had of clear seeing
can this can this idea of an unmoving mind
in a certain kind of way an unmoving eyes that just sees
without getting agitated by anything be a reference point for you to
understand and to gaze upon the inner world
of how we do get caught and how we do get sticky and then in all these complicated ways
that you see when you look inward can you discover how to look upon it
with also with an unagitated mind with unagitated sight it's all nature
it's all natural phenomena coming and going
and to switch the paradigm of how we see from we see through the lens of
me myself and mine and self and i and identity to the other paradigm
where we just see it as nature as natural phenomena coming and
going certainly things that we respond to and care for and we take care of when it's appropriate
but without this huge heavy filter of self gazing upon the world inward and outward
with mine with eyes that are cool not feverish
eyes that are peaceful not agitated eyes that are caring and not hostile
may your dharma eye open and it
so thank you