so warm greetings
and welcome to our meditation together
and um
those of you who come regularly know that i often begin i usually almost always begin the meditation
a guided meditation with spending some time relaxing the body
and some people might think of this as kind of a beginner's meditation kind of
before we get into something more profound and in similar veins some people think
it's just that meditation done for stress
reduction is is also not very profound it's just stress reductions
there's great religious things to experience profundities to discover maybe that's true
but what's also true is that what we learn in relaxing
with the the activity of relaxing is just what gets more and more thorough
more bigger as we go along in the path of buddhism and until we come to
awakening or release or nirvana which is the big relaxation
um it's a big letting go of the holding the tension the grasping the the stress
and so i think rather than looking at relaxing at the beginning as as a
beginning practice or just before we get into something more serious it's really the it's uh beginning to
lubricate or practicing or getting familiar letting the body become familiar with
something that is going to keep happening deeper and deeper and deeper this releasing relaxing letting go
and and what helps with that is that as you relax at the beginning
if you're able whatever degree you're able to relax even if it's just a teeny tiny bit that you feel the
the goodness of that or you feel the benefit of that you feel how that's nice
let it register allow yourself to feel it in other words feel the influence that
relaxation has on on your body your mind your heart
um and uh and as this goes along the relaxation will help you relax
um or uh what's deeper like a surface relaxation sets up the
condition for a deeper relaxation and deeper relaxation until we get down to the very core
of our being in a sense where something there can release and relax as well and then it's we're
free so um so we'll start now and do some of
this relaxation so one of the reasons to assume
a balanced aligned posture if you can to sit upright
but if you need if you're laying down to be careful with that posture as well
because it's a posture that um that allows for
relaxation if you're new to meditation sometimes you feel the
work of sitting upright but after a while the muscles get stronger and body adapts
to it and this sitting upright in a certain
kind of meditative way is a posture that allows for some of the deepest physical relaxation
that the body is able to do and they say the corpse posture laying
on your back is equal and how deep one can relax
and we can relax deeper if we're not hunched over and collapse in the chest
so gently closing the eyes
and as if your whole body is participating in a deep inhale
breathe in deeply so that your torso expands in all directions
ribcage in the front goes out the ribcage in the back expands a little bit the shoulders
maybe are lifted up a bit and if your stomach is relaxed as you
breathe in you might even feel a pushing down
i feel take deep breaths and feel the fullness of the whole torso
participating and then as you exhale long slow exhale
the whole torso relaxes settles back
taking a deep breath in
and then relaxing as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and then as you as you exhale normal exhale
relax the muscles of your face
around the eyes
the jaws the cheeks
exhale relaxing the shoulders and whatever relaxation you can
feel that the influence of that relaxation through your body
as you exhale relaxing or softening in the shoulders
maybe a releasing in the shoulders
as you relax as you exhale relaxing in the chest
around the heart
the solar plexus diaphragm
and relaxing the belly
and it's helpful if the whole body participates in this
so you might look and see if you can relax your arms and hands
maybe a subtle release of tension
holding
releasing relaxing legs
the muscles of the calves the thighs
and then perhaps there's a global relaxation you can do
for the whole body and as you release or soften
the body more broadly let that be felt deep inside
and also to relax wherever your center of thinking is
whatever tension contraction pressure that's associated with thinking
as you exhale relaxing the thinking
muscle
gently quieting the mind
and it's possible to go deeper inside within perhaps
if you feel and sense deep in the center of your being maybe there is a
holding or resistance attention
maybe a chronic one
take a few moments to breathe with it breathe through it
and as you exhale to relax and release the center of your being
and there may be a little bit of tension around breathing itself
don't worry about that tension make room for it breathe with it
as if it's okay
and maybe at the end of the exhale you can rela relax a bit of it
and if there's a pause at the end of the exhale even if it's infinitesimally short
see if you can be very relaxed so you can receive
the inhale allow it to
arise
and deeper in your mind than your thinking there can be a very subtle
pressure contraction coagulation
around self around the doer or the experiencer
around the one who's responsible or the one who's scared
perhaps you can allow whatever other relaxation you've done so far
be there to support and receive the deep relaxation
of this tension around self
you
chances are any ways in which your take going away from the present moment
in thought feelings
there's some tension related to that
if there is see if you can relax that tension
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
we relate to others in the world and to the world itself
very differently if we relate to it through our tension through the ways which
were contracted
than if we are relaxed and
loose expansive
imagine that sitting in front of you is a friend
someone you care for uncomplicated friend
and imagine yourself relaxed and peaceful
safe and contented where nothing needs to happen you don't
have to do anything or say anything particular maybe your friend is reading a book
peacefully you sit and you can sit then
together with your friend in your relaxed state
perhaps there's room there for your feelings or friendliness
your feelings of appreciation maybe feelings of love for kindness
relaxing deeply into and with
your feelings are friends friendship for your friend
perhaps it's fairly simple then
to relate to your friend more from kindness
than from hostility complaining resentment
more from good will then ill will
more from generosity than from greed
and then with the whatever feelings you have for your friend
maybe those can be extended outward in a simple way
out into the world
with goodwill for others
the deeper and fuller our relaxation is the more space there is
for friendliness and kindness care
tension makes us claustrophobic and fills the space of awareness relaxation
opens that space so that our wholesome feelings for
others can exist there may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free and may we
in whatever way that is easy for us appropriate contribute
to that possibility
continue the topic of also unwholesome a fundamental
concept for kind of the entire teachings of the
buddha and the focus today will be
on more on the unwholesome next week will
be more of the wholesome and the unwholesome
the is said to have three roots and the roots are greed
hatred and delusion and the the idea of roots
is very interesting a root is not something root of a plant is underground and you
can't see it but some plants if you chop them off at the surface level in the ground then the
roots are still alive and and those the plant will still sprout will grow again from the roots
and so and sometimes plants die back and they're not really at all seen visibly above the ground
but then spring comes and and maybe and the rainy season comes and
they start growing again and there they are sometimes greed hate and delusion as
as roots are called latent tendencies they may lay inside
of us latently ready to sprout whenever the conditions are right
for it some people might feel that they have no greed hatred and delusion
because they don't see it in themselves but then some point the conditions come together and like boy is it ever there
and um the um there's a story in the suttas of
of uh maybe i told you this i don't think i told you last week but
i was thinking of it of um of a woman
who was always kind but then someone said maybe this is not only kind of
surface deep and so someone challenged her in a simple way
and sure enough she got angry and and violent even
so this idea of the latent roots the roots inside and it could be in greed hatred and
delusion and teachers like me and a lot of terrible teachers will repeat this
phrase greed hate and delusion a lot and when i was a younger student i heard
it a lot and i think part of my brain just kind of checked out what i heard it i heard it
so often it was so repetitive so wrote and and so you know almost like i
didn't hear it anymore because it was emphasized so much and and um but the reason it's emphasized is
that the truth is that these these are the roots deep inside they give birth to all kinds
of unwholesome behavior i find it very compassionate to call it unwholesome
behavior as opposed to you know bad behavior or evil behavior
or wrong behavior there's a lot of judgments that around some of the ways we judge
we understand people's behavior but unwholesome
means that you can change it into something wholesome and wholesome is more the quality of the activity
and doesn't necessarily uh judge the person some behavior is unwholesome
and but they have these three roots and um and inside of ourselves like
there's a deeps inside unseen many times can be living inside of us a source
from which unhelpful unbeneficial behavior arises and in the simplest kind of way it's
related to tension to holding to places we feel hurt
places where we've coagulated or condensed around our pain or our sadness or conceit
all kinds of things we're holding on to and and that can be very deep and subliminal and and not even seen
feel like it's latent these tensions but they're ready to express themselves in all kinds of ways
and so part of this practice of the dharma is to really reach down into the roots of our very being not
just the places that we can see and know but uh and uh deep inside that from
which unwholesome behavior springs this deep holding patterns and tensions and
and uh inside and um and so for that the process of relaxing
and feeling safer and safer relaxing deeper and deeper uh releasing releasing until we touch
these places that are usually not seen but where the roots the the the deep inside
and so when we pull the root of a plant out of the ground then the plant doesn't sprout again
so we have these ideas of these three roots of creed hatred and delusion
and i think of these as umbrella terms for a whole family of
related motivations or feelings or attitudes and um in the ancient texts they have
synonyms or describe some of the words for some of the
other elements of that family so with greed that's related to
lust to relishing relishing is enjoying but holding on and
really wanting more getting the most squeezing the most out of it
longing attachment clinging and craving so these are all
in the family of greed and when we say greed we include all of these kind of included within it and
and where do those surface from where what's the root of those inside of you
when you feel agreed when you feel lust or there's deep longing or attachment or
clinging or craving to really respect these in a in a way that's
beneficial um to respect the power of them and the influence they have on us um
where what are their roots what are they arising out of what's the deeper disposition from which
they come what's a deeper feeling tone what's the deeper tension that we carry with us that seems
to be from where they arise hatred is uh
the synonyms for that is wanting to harm
anger hostility although you know anger is a little bit confusing that word
because not all anger is wanting to harm in uh but in this buddhist list it all
has to do with wanting to harm so so hostility or
wrath malice obstructing one word is irritation but
so the question is irritation how does that mean causing harm some kind of ill will is there as part
of it
delusion ignorance bewilderment foolishness interesting
not knowing oh not not really understanding suffering
if we don't understand our suffering some deep way and see how it arises how it seizes we don't really
understand it suffering not understood
is a source for delusion and that then gets expressed often in greed and hatred and ill-will
so the these have a wide influence on us and
uh what's interesting in the buddhist analysis of human behavior that all unwholesome behavior all
behavior which is harmful in some ways to ourselves or to others
has its root in these three forces inside of us these three
categories of things and if these are the roots then the task
is to is to somehow get sensitive enough still enough feel comfortable enough in oneself feel
a certain enough security in oneself to really be quiet and touch those roots
to really feel what is subliminal feel what's often latent and one of the
avenues to do that is physical is to feel the physical tension
with a very heightened sense of mindfulness to really tune in deeply deeply deeply
to the subtlest forms of tension that sometimes only are felt
if the surface tension is finally relaxed enough and it might even after a long period of
kind of peace and ease will we get a sense sense oh look at that
there's a little tightening a contraction a little kernel of tightness or pressure
or something and and then to help that soften and relax
let that release and even though it might be feel like a small little kernel subtle deep inside it's often the very
seed just like a seed of a redwood tree is quite small but the tree grows really big so uh
in the same way these little seeds deep inside of greed hate and delusion
they might seem inconsequential because they're so small but in deep quiet meditation
that's the place where sometimes we can touch those roots or those seeds and let them relax and release
and in that all wholesome behavior unwholesome behavior comes from these it becomes really useful to address them
to meet them to understand them and so one of the practices in buddhism
is to recognize greed hatred and delusion when it arises but not recognize
sometimes those words are so big words they seem like they represent you know big obvious movements of greed and hatred
that everyone can see but the tendency in buddhism is to see them even the very
subtle movements like one word for one synonym or a connection to hatred is irritation
and and attachment can be very very small very mild but but
any movement like that where there involves you can a kind of self-harm
or self-um tension any tension we have holding tightening
that's that's chronic is a kind of creates very unhelpful conditions for us
and as we relax that and soften that we create conditions for something that's very positive
um the opposite of greed hatred and delusion and those also can be roots and they
have the roots of non-greed non-hatred non-delusion be the source from which we operate is a
whole sea change in how some people can live their lives but and that also
is discovered by deeply relaxing they're waiting for us those seeds are waiting for us and
they also grow into big redwood trees and become strong
so greed hatred and delusion and one of the things to become sensitive to
so that we are not um pushed around by them caught in bondage
um to their their influence
so thank you and i offer these words and thoughts about
these deep roots inside of us with the tremendous respect for
your depth your roots care for it and really wishing that in that depth of
who you are that you can find peace well-being and love and freedom like something deep inside can
release and let go so thank you