so warm greetings everyone and welcome to our meditation time
and now one of the principles of mindfulness meditation
is or one of the potentials is to be equanimously mindful
of everything that no matter what the experience we're having it's possible to have a relaxed calm
clear recognition that this is happening and in relationship to mental activity
the topic of this week thinking uh mindfulness meditation is
not making an enemy of our thinking it's not uh condemning it to some place where
it's not supposed to exist at all and we're supposed to get rid of it it certainly can calm down thinking and
it's quite nice to have it become quieter and stiller sometimes there seems to be
thinking stops entirely and it can be very peaceful but that's not necessarily
the point the point of mindfulness meditation is to see clearly without being for or against
the experience being for and against that's uh
you know that that is a different capacity of the mind it's a different function of the mind
that sometimes has a role and sometimes doesn't but for mindfulness itself it's just a
simple being present for our experience so with that as an introduction
nist maybe just close your eyes as you are and think that the principle for
mindfulness meditation is that you're allowed to come as you
are to come as you are meditation and and so when you sit and close your
eyes one of the possibilities is begin first by just noticing how you are
without any effort to meditate just notice how you are right now
what's happening for you and your body what's happening for you
in your heart and what's happening for you in your mind
and to
particular for the purposes of today
without any idea to be any different notice your thinking
allow yourself to think whatever you have to be thinking but just to become aware of it be
curious a simple recognition of what you're
thinking
maybe a little bit as if you could step away step backward a few steps
and then turn around to look at yourself look at your mind
as if it's thinking
thinking in words thinking in images sometimes just that clear recognition
and allowance to think
the thinking quiets down or even stop sometimes it'll come back so just take your time
and notice how it is
and notice the energy of thinking the pull of it
is it strong is it weak
do you have an attitude about your thinking
are you do you relate to your thoughts as if they're
you know you relate to them in a friendly way in a hostile way
in different ways
and what it would be like to neither be friendly nor hostile
and certainly not indifferent just present and seeing
in the way that you would maybe look at walking down the street
you might look at a tree here look up in the sky and watch clouds
sail by
and is there any physical sensations connected to thinking
is there pressure or attention
contraction
is it the experience not what you're thinking about but the
experience of thinking in and of itself as an experience as something that
this has sensations or you can feel it in some way
is it pleasant or unpleasant
and now thinking of thinking of thoughts you're thinking imagine your
thinking are like bubbles thought bubbles
take a deep full breath as you exhale let those bubbles float
away
deep breath in relaxing the mental activity
relaxing the pressure and tension
and now continue thinking
as the mind wants to think but can you think in quieter ways
can you think with a quieter voice or calmer images
maybe you let the images recede a little bit further away from you
or they slow down the quieter thoughts
slower thoughts adjusting the volume and the speed of
your thinking
and then instead of letting yourself think whatever you wish to think about
choose what you think about and what i'd suggest is you choose to
think instructions for meditation
maybe i'll give you some now you can repeat them to yourself
in a quiet calm thinking or you might have variations
gently softly
take a few fuller breaths and as you exhale
relax your body
as you exhale softening the shoulders
releasing the shoulders
as you exhale softening the belly
letting your breathing return to normal
as you exhale soften the muscles of your face
around the eyes and the forehead
and soften what can be softened in the area of your brain
even if it's softening around the brain
and then to settle into the experience of the body breathing
and for these minutes you'll accompany your breathing
maybe imagining that your you and your breathing are walking along
holding hands so there's continuous contact between
awareness and the breathing breathing
and the awareness
and without leaving the attention to breathing if
while you're breathing mindfully you notice that it's easy to relax the
body more you might do so
if you notice that there's a feelings of well-being or contentment or joy
allow it to grow mix allow it give it space in your body
and if you notice it's possible to relax the mental activity the thinking muscle
without leaving your breathing maybe on the exhale relax the mental
activity but all along accompanying your
breathing awareness and breathing walking along
hand in hand
softening your thinking slowing your thinking down
quieting your thinking and with your thinking quieter
maybe it's easier to relax the mental activity
the drive the push the pressure
an image for relaxing the mental activity
is that of a flower bud that goes from being tightly closed
to opening up wide so the inside of the petals
open to the wide open sky in space so we relax the mind
and intuit or feel the vastness of quiet space
all around
and in that space we stay rooted in the breathing
relaxed and open receiving the experience of breathing
maybe you can assume that for these next minutes there's nothing that you need to think
about even though you might think there's no need to
no need to invest any importance in your thinking
and there might be a greater contentment available
by dropping into your body to feel what is more tender and soft and
open in your body
the quiet still place within
through which you could be breathing from which you can be breathing
thinking can be a powerful storm
howling wind and thinking can be a soft breeze
a soft refreshing breeze that lightly moves through us
and with the lightest softest
maybe almost insubstantial or imperceptible thoughts
have thoughts of good will for others
maybe thoughts of wishing them well wishing them happiness and peace
and see how softly is there from a still tender place
within that you can silently in your mind atone
evoke thoughts ideas wishes of goodwill
for others
maybe they're even just half thoughts
in a way that opens you up your heart opens you to a care
a tender care respect and valuing of others
and may a soft quiet tender
kind regard for others be something that you touch into
throughout the day today it doesn't have to be dramatic
it doesn't have to be obvious to others
from the quiet place within simple quiet thoughts of well wishing
for others and may it be that
the benefits of this 30 minutes together meditating
may those benefits be shared with others either directly or indirectly knowingly or
unknowingly
and may it be that this meditation supports the possibility of others being
happy may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
you