so
uh so warm greetings
and i hope this uh finds you well and and that you are
comfortable and safe and somewhat contented to be here now for
meditation time together it's a considered to be one of the really great
things in life to meditate and meditate in community knowing that
there are people throughout the world with youtube but also in other ways who
are involved in meditation and the dharma and people have been involved in it for
centuries and we continue in a lineage of practitioners and in a sense we are
the recipients standing on the shoulders of all the people who have practiced before
us and that our shoulders hopefully are broad enough and stable enough so that the meditators who
follow us will feel inspired and feel like they are part of a wonderful
lineage that uh traveled through us
so there's an ancient uh teaching that faith or confidence
is um or refuge maybe is like a magic stone
that if dropped into muddy waters it immediately clears the muddy water
the mud just settles out and in the same way the
faith in the dharma faith in the practice faith in oneself in the practice the confidence that
comes along with that when we evoke it or touch it or let it drop
really deep inside settles the places of doubt
worry distress settles the places where we feel like
we're lost or that the world doesn't make any sense or there's no way forward
and all these ways in which we kind of have this centrifugal force away from ourselves when we drop
faith into our hearts faith or confidence the dharma in then
something that is extra within us extra agitation um gets settled
gets reassured and one of the functions of refuge is a deep inner reassurance
to have a sense of assurance and wonderfully
the word for assurance can also in poly can also mean breathing
or breathing easily and so to really connect the sense of assurance
of faith of real sense of being settled in our confidence
with our breathing is kind of to the point to be able to come not to some abstract
idea of confidence or faith but a way of being that allows us to breathe easily at ease
so to begin this process of meditation and assuming a posture that
gives you both a sense of ease but also expresses confidence expresses
the body expresses a sense of assurance even if the rest of you doesn't feel
that and to then gently close your eyes
in a way that maybe for you is friendly caring loving
take some deeper breaths than usual
the life-living air oxygen comes in
filling your lungs and then as you exhale to relax your whole body
taking deep breath in maybe three quarters full and as you exhale
release the whole body in some way maybe as if all the edges of your body
are released outwards into space where the places where you touch your
chair or your cushion the floor you release yourself into the support
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and again as if you really can if you have doubts
lovingly with goodwill for yourself
on your exhale continue to continue to relax your body
softening the muscles of your face
releasing your face from all the work it has to do throughout the day of expressing itself
responding to the world
so the muscles of the face fall away from the bone
on the exhale softening around the shoulders
for some of us those shoulders work a lot and being tense and being held up
and to soften the belly perhaps one of the
ways of being deeply at ease in this world
is to have the belly be soft that in these few minutes of meditation
there's nothing we need to do to defend ourselves or protect ourselves or
push ourselves prove ourselves in ways that tighten up the muscles of
the butt of the belly
we can allow ourselves the opportunity to be at ease
and if you have some degree of confidence or faith or assurance
in this practice of meditation even if it's quite difficult for you
sometimes when it's difficult for people they're actually getting the most benefit from it
to have faith whatever your faith is see if you can drop it into
the waters of your heart
and as that stone of faith drops
see if there can be one more big feeling of release and relaxation here
now
and then as waves on the surface of that
body of water is your breathing
gentle waves that move across the water
and in a sense your body your mind your awareness floating on the waves of breathing up
and down expanding and contracting
trusting simplicity of floating on your breathing
entrusting yourself to breathing as if it's the only thing to do for now
as if it's the most valuable and protective and deepening way of being
is to rest in the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
maybe for the next three breaths you can relax your body further
release and release the grip of your
thinking soften in the mind
so
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting recalling the best that you can
the state of being deeply reassured
may be deeply trusting
with the feeling of being at ease safe may be contented
and maybe with the remembering the feel those feelings of a time such deep reassurance
to breathe with that we through it for two or three breaths
and then perhaps imagine that the people around you have the ability to also feel
deeply reassured in this life deep trusting sense of peace and
contentment to be able to breathe with ease
have breathing room and space and ease
and imagine how good it would be for others all around you throughout the world to breathe this way
to feel this way
and perhaps from the depth of your heart you can wish it were so an open-handed open-minded
wish without questioning it or doubting it or
it's just a simple wish may all beings be at ease
may all beings breathe easily
breathing room
may all beings feel safe and reassured
may all beings be peaceful and contented
may all beings be free
without oppression or
hostility
may all beings
be deeply reassured of their place here on this planet
harmonious peaceful contented
so they too may live for the benefit and welfare of
all beings may all beings be free
and may all beings live in mutual respect and care
[Music]
so allow me to make an announcement at the beginning of this talk
that as we continue these 7 a.m sittings
in weekdays that there will be a change for the next
three weeks starting on monday i'll i'll be here next week and
and then the following two weeks we have two wonderful zen teachers friends of mine who are going to teach
first paul howler we'll teach on the following week so the week of the
26th i think and then the following week um the abbess of the green gulch zen
center fou schrader will uh do this five five talks in the morning
and um and the reason uh for this what's happening is that um i was
invited or asked to teach um as a support for zen center i teach
what's called a zen intensive for three weeks and the three of us who are wonderful friends and have
wonderful dharma discussions among ourselves and wanted to share some of these dharma
discussions with other people and so we're doing what's called the zen intensive
with a schedule of sittings and teachings at san francisco zen center and since i'm doing these 7 a.m
teachings anyway i thought i would fold it in as part of the intensive
and the intensive is about the harmony of zen and vipassana that's the theme
and then once i thought of folding it in then i said well i should also ask my colleagues to participate in this as
well so i'm not sure what i'll be teaching next week but it'll be probably something something
basic about vipassana practice but perhaps presented in a way that is in harmony with zen
and then the following two weeks uh you'll certainly get some zen teachings uh zen approach to meditation um and other
things uh zen wisdom and things from my two friends so um
so um and uh so anyway so you can expect that change
and uh some of you might want to participate in the zen intensive uh the harmony of zen and
vipassana that san francisco zen center is offering and i think that today is the last day to sign up if you want to be part of
that and you can see there's a schedule there of
what's what's being offered and things like that it's all on zoom so
so thank you
so um
so this topic this week is refuge and um yesterday i talked about refuge
in the buddha dharma sangha it's called the triple refuge and now
one of the peculiar things if you study the ancient teachings of the buddha
he never actually actively suggests that people should go for refuge
a few times he speaks favorably about people doing so and and talks about the value of doing
so but there's never the instructions to go for refuge but he gives a go for the triple refuge
he does but he does give instructions for a different kind of refuge in the triple refuge
and and but to the background for this the triple refuge the idea of a triple
refuge is a term predated the buddha
it was a custom in ancient india to go for have the triple refuge in three
of the gods of the indian pantheon and and so ancient texts talk about this
triple refuge that people would do and going for refuge in the ancient gods so
there was already a custom in ancient india to people do something called the triple refuge and when
the buddha came along that language that ritual or that article a way of
expressing faith was then directed towards the buddha dharma and the sangha and that became
the new triple refuge and most literally it's an external refuge the literal
buddha the literal his teachings perhaps and then the community
and as i said yesterday can also be an internal refuge we can find the what corresponds to that
within ourselves now uh when the in the buddha gave
instructions for refuge he gave on one place it's a
very significant place right near the end of his life he knew he was dying so his teachings now became particularly
significant and he said i gave the instructions
make yourself uh dwell abide with yourself as an island with yourself
as a refuge with no other refuge with the dharma as an island with a
dharma as a refuge with no other refuge and the metaphor of an island
they uh the metaphor for an island is that of a place that's safe
from the floods and swirls of the world uh the floods of the floods
the strong currents the strong waves that the strong tides like i hear on the coast here you can't
really go swimming very many places in the ocean because of the strong rip currents that exist
so an island is a place from safety so make yourself a place of safety
make a refuge of yourself and then he goes on to say do the same thing
with a dharma with no other refuge and the only way to
kind of harmonize these two statements is that the self and the dharma are
somehow becoming the same the dharma isn't out there but the dharma is found
somehow in oneself with oneself and um and it's a very strong
affirmation of one's own personhood as a place of practice and a place of
religious value and to call this person that you are the place of the dharma the dharma itself is an
affirmation and that often is not captured so well
if we emphasize uh too much that buddha's teachings are not self
teachings on not self teaching and emptiness sometimes involve a kind of as profound as they
can be to overemphasize sometimes um dismisses
the ordinary phenological world that we live in the ordinary uh experiences of how we are and how we
live and and i've seen plenty of people dismissed the value of their emotions their intentions their
own safety sometimes and well-being their health by over emphasizing that this some idea
that there is no self or or everything is empty or something like that and
but here we have the buddha the end of his life saying make yourself a refuge make yourself
an island a place of safety and then he goes then he asks a
rhetorical question he says well how do you do this and then he explains he says you do it
by practicing the four foundations of mindfulness that one dwells observing
the body and the body ardent aware and clearly comprehending having
put aside greed and distress for the world
one abides observing feelings and feelings
ardent aware and clearly comprehending having put aside greed and distress for
the world one abides aware by
observing mind and the mind ardent aware clearly comprehending
having put aside greed and distress for the world one abides observing dharmas and dharmas
ardent aware clearly comprehending having put aside
greed and distress for the world so here the way to make oneself a refuge the way
to make the dharma the refuge is the practice of mindfulness there's
something about uh mindfulness is the real refuge
mindfulness is the place that we really find our safety and uh and part of the task of
mindfulness is to do it long enough dedicated enough sincerely enough
to discover how it provides a tremendous place of safety of assurance of value of wisdom
and a freedom and and so it isn't pointing even though the buddha is pointing to self
it isn't the conventional idea of self and what we identify as a self or self identity or
conceit but rather it's what opens up when we have this uh powerful form
of awareness and it isn't that awareness is the self but it's almost as if awareness
is the closest thing that just taking refuge in self taking refuge in the dharma
take refuge in your awareness but not awareness kind of in the abstract but awareness that
arises out of or is established in the body in our feelings
in our mind and mind states and in the dharma in the dharmas which here in this co
this context dharma means the mental processes of our inner life so there's a clear grounding a clear
connection to the specificity of our life the details that what's actually going on within us and
around us really be aware of that to be established in it so we're not distracted or reactive or
caught up in things but clearly aware to the point that we dwell
independent not clinging to anything in the world where the ability to be mindful
is not caught or dependent on anything at all but it's clearly established in this
world of ours this experience of ours here and this personhood that we are and
and not clinging to anything in the world so this is how we make ourselves a refuge
is by being aware and the word refuge sauron saruna s-a-r-a-n-a
is one of the most powerful expressions of faith of assurance of
trust of confidence that religious confidence religious
inspiration a kind of sense of religious enthusiasm
that i think that buddhism really honors and has a place for and have all
that kind of religious feeling if you will faith associated with awareness
and uh not to gods outside of us which was with the custom before the buddha there is not a
savior out there who's going to save us protect us but there's something here within
ourselves that is the protection that is the savior that is the place of safety and
and so we do that through practice it's not wishful thinking but by
practicing the four foundations of mindfulness the practice of mindfulness
and that includes anapanasati that we just finished going through
so this is another way in which the buddha talked about refuge and and then we'll continue with other
ideas of refuge this wonderful quality that supports our
practice we'll continue with that tomorrow so thank you