so good morning and welcome to our meditation monday
morning meditation beginning of a new theme for the week
and we're continuing kind of in the ongoing
series on the basic foundations for meditation and the way i we teach it here at imc
and this week it's going to be talking about or working with practicing with thinking
and i'd like to use an analogy that is somehow you received a gift
of an amazing thousand-year-old clock with all kinds of gears very very
precisely made and sophisticated that as gears that keeps the time for
nanoseconds and seconds and minutes and hours and days
the years including the leap years and the cycles of the moon
the seasons and light and dark through the year
centuries so it's amazingly precisely made and sophisticated math and arithmetic and
engineering to make it all work and all the gears and
it's a great present to see in awe of it but then it turns out after working
perfectly for a while one of the gears decides to
go faster than everything else and suddenly
the gears start getting confused and not working properly and and
we put under a lot of tension and and uh the whole clock doesn't seem to
work very well anymore it worked well for a thousand years but under your watch one of the gears started up to
go too fast so we as human beings are
even more sophisticated complex system then
such a complicated watch um amazing amount of
you know uh interconnected parts of the human being that all all have to work harmoniously for us
to stay alive even and uh it's kind of an amazing it's amazing
that we exist and all that it takes to keep us going all the interconnected
kind of complicated deep uh gear work of this biological systems
that we have and there's one system one of those
gears that if it works faster than the others it kind of begins messing it all up
and that is our capacity to become tense that anything that becomes tense
anything that begins working faster makes it difficult for everything else to go smoother
and if we can relax the tension then the whole system that we have begin
to operate much much more smoothly emotionally intellectually biologically physically
emotionally all these begin to kind of come into kind of a more of a harmony more working together
and um so relaxing in meditation is really good
it's possible to focus on it too much it's possible to in a sense get too relaxed
but in a sense then some some of those gears in the clock you know stop working if they get too too relaxed
but if there's identifiable tension in the system your in your body
it's really good to relax it it helps the whole thing so today we'll focus on relaxing the
body so that you prepare the ground so the mind can
relax the thinking mind and i use an expression called the thinking
muscle and this is the the activities of the mind that are
constructing and spinning out thoughts and
our brain is also a complicated neurological event and when there's tension there and
something's working too fast there that also kind of messes up the whole neurology of it all the mind
and that thinking muscle is uh you identify it by the physical
manifestation of thinking and if there's a lot of tense thinking
the jaw might be tight the eyes might be locked the forehead might be scrunched there might be a lot
of whirling and agitated energies in the skull and the area of the brain the brain itself might feel contracted and
tight it might be other parts in the body that get activated the muscles of the hands even or the
shoulders the belly and all those together i call the
the the thinking muscle especially the ones that are up in the head
so at some point to recognize the physicality of this and then relax so
so assuming a meditation a posture and
seeing if you take a posture that allows you to be alert but also to
be sensitive be aware of where there's tension in your body
and the upright cross-legged meditation posture
it's not required or needed for meditation but it has some advantages
and one is that it is a a posture that can reveal unnecessary tension
while not kind of relaxing and giving up or just or collapsing from it
to stay upright reveal where it's tense in a healthy way and begin to relax
lowering your gaze relaxing your focus
of your eyes enclosing your eyes
and to enter into this body body and mind that we're here with for this minutes
taking a few long slow calm deep breaths
as you breathe in deeply really feel the global body whatever is easy to feel
of your body the three dimensionality of the body
in a long slow exhale just letting go relaxing softening
wherever in your body your mind lands where you feel there's tension
let it soften
breathing in and feeling the body exhaling relaxing
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and continuing as you exhale to gently
without ambition relax your body
exhaling and softening the muscles of the face
sometimes feeling a coolness in the face can help relax the heat of
tension maybe the coolness of the air around the face
on the exhale to relax the shoulders
softening
sometimes feeling the weight of the shoulders can help relaxing
sometimes shifting where your hands are if moving the hand someplace allows the
shoulders to not be propped up
but we allow them to hang more
and as you exhale to soften the belly
and maybe in the belly if you feel the warmth there if there is
perhaps the warmth of the belly can give a kind of comfort to support some
kind of relaxation
and then take a few moments to notice your thinking
for these moments you have permission to think
and notice if your thinking is fast or slow
forceful or gentle
if your thinking is insistent or at ease
and if you think in images is there a location for where those images occur like on a screen
if you think in words or an inner voice
is there a location where that voice is coming from
there doesn't have to be a location but if there is
sometimes it's possible to notice if there's any tension
in that area that location
there might be a physical association or manifestation of thinking
tightening tension pushing pressure
contraction something that feels stressful in the
body connected to your thinking and as you exhale
see if you can relax the thinking muscle
relax the tension in your body that you associate with thinking
if there is a location for thinking let the location get larger spread out
maybe like the surface of a lake that the waves get quiet the surface spreads flat
out to the horizon
sometimes a thinking mind has been working so long
that it's tired weary of all the ongoing the ongoing thinking
often repetitive
to relax any ways in which you are investing in your thoughts
relax even the interest that keeps you glued
to thinking
allowing thinking become calmer and slower
and then returning now to breathing
wherever you feel be breathing most pronounced in your body
feel the inhales and the exhales
and gently on the exhale
either let go of your thoughts or relax around your thinking
relax your thinking mind
feel your inhale riding the exhale
relax the mind
so
on the exhale relaxing the thinking mind
softening either feeling comforting warmth
surrounding your thinking mind or maybe you can imagine or feel
coolness that relaxes an overheated mind
and for a minute or so can you allow your thinking mind to
become quiet the kind of quiet you would have in a
library or a cathedral or a sacred grove of trees
a quiet where you would listen
better let your mind thinking mind become quiet
so you can listen better to your breathing
here
and then as we come to the end of the sitting not only are
we individuals finely tuned biological system
with all these interlocking gears so we are socially as well societally
it turns out the society works best too if the individuals are relaxed
free of tension and stress
and to learn something new about being relaxed free of tension stress
from meditation and considering how you can bring it
into your social world
how can you not sacrifice your ease
how could you learn to recognize stress as it begins tension
and remember how important it is to relax
and in doing so it's our gift to our society
a gift at least that we don't contribute
to the ongoing momentum of stress and tension that's so
much part of many of our societies
but rather we contribute peace calmness
care love
respect may it be that as we
come out of this meditation may we aspire that this meditation
supports us in helping make this a better world for everyone
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
so
so so this is the beginning of uh the
five-week the five-day series on mindfulness of thinking
and we'll follow the pattern we followed over this last weeks of relaxation
recognition respect restoration and release
so there's a tendency in meditation circles to sometimes be frustrated
around our thinking or even worse to sometimes thinking uh thinking that thinking is our enemy
that it's a problem to think and if only if i didn't think then i could meditate
in mindfulness meditation we are
learning the art of bringing a
clear awareness clear attention to all aspects of our life
the inner life the outer life personal life social life and all that but in meditation
particularly all the different parts that are become clear in the present moment
in the present moment in our whole
you know psychophysical system that we are
and so one of the things that will stand out sooner or later for some of us sooner or later
is how much thinking there is some days there's a lot going on in life and we have a lot of concerns and the
mind can be going you know really fast spinning out sometimes it seems like the mind has a
mind of its own we're just like churning thoughts and thoughts and thoughts and there's no chance to stop it
and so rather than making an enemy what we can do in mindfulness meditation we turn
our attention to be mindful of thinking but the art of that
is to make sure that the mindfulness is not thoughtfulness it's not thinking
about thinking some people will confuse mindfulness with thinking
that we're kind of thinking what's about what's happening in the present moment and then i'll talk
a little bit more about that tomorrow but um we're not having discursive thoughts we're not having commentary
interpretations we're not um it's not like you're having a conversation with yourself about what
you how you're thinking what you're thinking about there's a kind of almost a silent awareness that we're using in
mindfulness that kind of silence that happens if you
have a dirty windshield in a car and you clean the windshield
the windshield now is clean and it's still silent it doesn't speak or say anything
but you see through it you see through that silence he threw that clarity to see clearly what's on
the other side so to the mind's ability to see or to sense
quietly um is the movement we're going and so to listen like you're listening
to your thoughts with a qui you're listening with a quiet mind even though your thinking mind is busy
um or you're feeling and some people find it very helpful with thinking to feel thinking
and in terms of relaxation this physical sensations that we can feel connected to thinking
can be really key sometimes it's difficult to see the physical connection between thinking and
the muscles and other times you can really feel it there are times when i'm particularly sensitive and quiet
that it feels like the mind is a puppeteer and it's all these strings
i'm the puppet kind of all these strings coming down from the thinking mind connected to all kinds of little muscles
in my body and they're all kind of like micro muscles are being pulled or tightened or released
as i think about different things some thoughts are really powerful
resentments that maybe i have at some point and i could feel my stomach pull up
or my shoulders go up or i think about the wonderful conversation i had with a friend
recently and something releases in the puppeteer as they relax the muscles and even though it was tense or holding but
in thinking about this nice conversation something ah that's good and i relax
and the more relaxed we become the more we can feel the
this micro muscle strings tugging and all the muscles that go on if we're really tense or really
preoccupied in our thoughts so we can't notice our body we haven't we won't have a clue what i'm talking about
uh chronic tension where there's no relaxation at all uh can become normal for people and they
just this is how it is as if you know this is the natural way to be um and there's no movement in the
chronic tension for anything to relax as people meditate most people find
slowly that the body relaxes um some of the surface tension that we
carry with us begins to soften and relax and the same thing with the mind
that there's maybe in the thinking doesn't stop but thinking calms down it gets slower
so uh i i was going to emphasize again that we're not making thinking the problem
but rather we're turning our attention when thinking is strong and when it kind of captivating
we calmly turn our attention to to be mindful of thinking itself
and the whole week will be spent talking about how we can be mindful of it in different ways
but what i want to emphasize today is uh we be mindful of
uh the tensions there the energetics of it the um
the stress the forcefulness the pressure the contraction the tightness
the insistence the hesitation the
closed down-ness the shutting down the dullness the numbness all these things can be associated with
thinking and and those things
need our care if we're distracted by the content of
our thoughts and thinking the content is what's most important we might miss
the underlying kind of tension that is much closer in actually to who
we really are it's kind of like a deeper layer that um a way to do our way into the
depth of who we are is not by thinking ourselves and remembering and figuring things out
their mind and and reinterpreting the past the way to really
have a doorway into the heart into the deep inner life is this ability to relax
so when there's thinking and we're really pulled in the world of thoughts
one of the things that be really helpful to learn to do when it takes time is to relax the interest in thoughts
to break the enchantment with the content of the thoughts
some of us have had similar thoughts over and over and over again for years
the amount of repetition that goes on in many people's minds is kind of astounding if people could hear any of
us how often we think the same thing they would wonder about you know our sanity or something
it's normal enough to be repetitive but it's also not necessary but what's interesting for a meditator
is to recognize that part of the reason is a lot of repetition part of the reason why there's
often oneself is a central character or centrally involved in their thoughts
is that we're there's an uh intense interest in
the content interest in self and me myself and mine and so that interest that investment
can be felt distinct from the content of what we're thinking about
sometimes i've had the feeling in my mind that i'm glued to my thinking and i could feel the glue or i could
feel the bungee cord pulling me in to it close by
uh and if it no matter what it doesn't matter what i'm thinking about i can feel the glue or the bungee cord or
something that's there and and then to feel that tension
and sometimes you can relax it but sometimes we can't relax the tension
the physical tension the mental tension and you can't relax it as a will as in
something we do but here's a real key to really long-term mindfulness meditation to
really find your way with it and that is it really helps if you have a willingness
to allow yourself to be tense allow yourself to feel the stress
the contraction the pressure as if it has permission to be there it's
okay but hold it in awareness and i have i love the image of two
cupped hands that come underneath where awareness and mindfulness is like two cupped hands that gently come along
and hold the tension hold the stress uh kindly supportedly
and and learn the patience you can do that forever because some of the tensions that we
carry within us are not really amenable to being directed or told to relax
or we in charge that's just one more time sometimes one more insult that we're in charge we're going to do
something to this whole wonderful system we have but if we can come with respect and care
and kindness and say okay here i am i'll be with you forever long
it takes and um and then uh and then
amazingly uh things begin to shift under that kind of attention
something maybe something unexpected begins to relax something unexpected softens
and um and our job is to bring bring that attention that is soft the attention that is kind and caring
and the attention that's slow the attention is not in a hurry or
insistent the attention that's not um forcing the issue or the attention which
is not tense so relax
learn about your attention become a student of your attention
maybe before you can relax you have to really recognize and get to know it and chances are that for most of us
there's more tension through the day than is necessary and so to study the unnecessary tension
and stress that's there in the body and the mind and so in the next 24 hours in
preparation for the teachings tomorrow you might think of yourself more of a
student of tension than a student of relaxation get to know it well
but if you feel like you know it and recognize taking time to know it then if it's easy to relax please do
and uh and maybe maybe this can be a fun day of uh
of studying and hanging out with tension and relaxation and
and see what happens if that's the subject of the day the theme of the day for you
and then we'll continue tomorrow and in some ways this series i'm doing
with starting with breath and body and emotions last week and now we're thinking each of
what proceeded is building up towards our capacity to really work with thoughts so work
mindfulness thinking is not meant for people for beginners but really have the foundation of these earlier types
and then what i'm going to talk about through the week is also builds on what proceeds proceed so the relaxation
is supports what i'm going to talk about tomorrow and so forth so
so i say all this with the idea that
um i'm not expecting you to be able to do all this suddenly like if you're a
brand new beginner but really it builds on the skills and the understandings that have been growing
by ongoing meditation practice so hopefully that's the case and
that this is supportive and i look forward to tomorrow thank you