so
the topic of for
this talk is the equanimity factor of
awakening
and uh it's the seventh of the seven
factors of awakening and
over the last week i've been talked to
her about the earlier factors
and and we're talking about these seven
factors of awakening in the context
of the practice of anapanasati
mindfulness of breathing
where we're mindful of the mind that we
experience starts
experiencing the mind as we breathe in
experiencing the mind as we breathe out
and so we've kind of taken our time
to understand some of the things we can
start experiencing
when we experience the mind the word
cheetah
the pali word for mine c-i-t-t-a
is
often translated as mind state
and it's not the mind as a thing
like the brain is kind of a physical
thing but rather it's the
way in which we experience our interior
life
our mental life as a whole
and rather than the particular details
of different activities of the mind
that goes on particular thoughts
feelings
impulses intentions it's the the whole
of the mind that kind of and how we
experience the whole
is personal and contextual and
depending on the different factors of
the mind that come together
and and it sounds a little bit strange
to say this but the state of the mind
how we experience a state of the mind it
depends on the state of the mind or
how we experience the shape of the mind
or how we experience this totality of
the mind
is based a little bit on the state of
mind or which mental factors are
strongest
and um but as we open to the mind and
feel it
it has different characteristics that we
can feel
now that takes a lot of stability and
really settled in the practice to start
feeling this whole mind
and the mood or the mind that that might
be there
but as this practice gets strong there
are seven
factors that quality qualities
characteristics
that become predominant in the state of
the mind that we can experience
different ones of them at different
times and sometimes kind of all of them
together
and these are the seven factors of
awakening mindfulness
investigation effort joy tranquility
samadhi and equanimity
and uh these all have different
functions they
work in different ways as a state of
mind
mindfulness creates real stability
and uh it's kind of like what there's
that would say differently if the mind
just doesn't waver
it's not agitated and jumping around
when mindfulness becomes a little bit
more
or awareness becomes a little more a
state that's present
rather than something that we have to
keep renewing but i keep making the
effort having the intention to be
mindful
so there's unwaveringness of
of attention uh investigation
or this ability to see clearly to look
up and see clearly
or intimately experience not by
analyzing it or
probing but by uh like tuning into the
frequency of the radio and not having
any more static
just really feeling it and sensing more
fully that
what's going on that's of that function
is pr
is really important for the process of
liberation they say that's the most
important
of the seven factors for liberation
because we have to get things really
into focus
and then um the effort factor that can
see the difference between wholesome and
wholesome is really key in not being
trapped
by the unwholesome by but finding
a certain kind of healthy escape or
stepping away
from into the wholesome
joy is provides a deep satisfaction a
deep contentment
a bodily and physically that
is really kind of feels good
and then the last three tranquility
and samadhi and equanimity
are particularly useful
and so the joy factor as well these are
all feelings of
pleasure well-being positive feelings
that we can have
that are tremendous support for practice
in helping free us from some of our
addictive patterns some of
our attachments attachments to pleasure
attachments to all kinds of things where
we
searching if we think we're searching
for happiness by having more money or
more status or more relationships or
more
something that's outside of us
and that drive can be addictive at times
and
and um or the strong ways in which fear
operates from us inside of us that
itself is compels us to act certain ways
and be
certain ways and anxiety
phobias and there's something about
being settled
in these positive factors these states
of mind of joy
tranquility samadhi and equanimity that
is so
nourishing feels so wholesome that feels
like so such a source of well-being
that it creates a reconditioning factor
it conditions us in new ways rather than
being conditioned by fear or
feeling of lack or feeling of being
deprived or
feeling unsafe for all kinds of ways
which life has kind of conditioned us to
be
we're starting to recondition ourselves
and then it becomes
easier to begin letting go of some of
the dysfunctional ways in which we might
be living
and so rather than only relying on
mindfulness seeing clearly recognizing
what's happening
to free us from some of our conditioning
which is very hard to only rely on
mindfulness
but to really have the mindfulness
support this process of settling and
stability and growth in the dharma to
begin
eventually and eventually is an
important word here so we don't get
impatient
start kind of getting nourished
by these wholesome qualities and way of
being
and the last of these is equanimity and
equanimity
um for many people who are unfamiliar
with this
idea and buddhism will think that
equanimity is kind of maybe aloof or
kind of dry
or kind of not really relevant for
having a good time in life and uh
and maybe even not relevant for making
ourselves safe in this world
if we're is equanimist how do we make
ourselves safe
the um
and um but
uh and i think when i was before i
became a buddhist practitioner
i don't think i had any i used the word
equanimity in any kind of way
in my vocabulary i probably knew what it
meant some somewhat
but it had no relevance for how i lived
my life or how i talked about thought
about myself
but certainly with practice and
meditation equanimity became
has become a more and more important
quality something that i recognize and
appreciate
it kind of as a state there's this kind
of feeling that courses through my whole
body
um a kind of stability and clarity and
openness and
and the kind of a freedom that comes
with equanimity
and it's considered to be one of the
most sublime
uh states of being that a person can
experience
it's um kind of kind of considered the
crown jewel of the seven factors of
awakening which themselves are the crown
jewels
so you know it's that that's
just letting you know that if you're
practicing
develops over time maybe you'll start
feeling how
special this equity manufacturer is and
the rich emotional aspect it's not
indifference or aloofness or dryness
and the equanimity factor
it worked it belongs to a family of
concepts and states that
is championed by buddhism and one of
them is this
equanimity which is upeka in
pali another one is a mouthful of
words that means literally something
like etymology of it
standing in the middle of it all
standing in the middle of this
and that's often seen as a sense of
balance and then there's a word
sama which maybe is cognitively related
to our word same
i'm not sure about this how these
languages
connect um they're distant relatives of
each other english and
and pali and some uh
can mean can mean something like even it
can mean also like light
like the same but even
balanced also but an evenness of mind
and it's related to some is related to
words samana
s-a-m-e-n-a which
means either impartiality or sometimes
it's
translated as justice so impartiality
that
uh like the impartial justice the
impartial judging of things
it's considered a really high ideal and
to treat people in a certain
impartiality doesn't mean indifference
it means that we treat everyone kind of
equally and it's kind of
the equal so it's some as equal or same
or sameness so an evenness of mind an
impartiality of mind
a balance of heart and mind balance of
body and mind
and equanimity and
for now i will just
say briefly a little bit about
equanimity and then pick up this topic
tomorrow
and um because it's so important
and the word for equanimity upeka
upe kkha
is the etymology of the word is actually
quite useful here
it literally means something to have it
like to have an overview
to have the bird's eye view of what's
happening
so it involves a kind of wisdom that
comes from seeing how things are
so it's a kind of a wisdom factor it's
not just something that
arises because the quality
of some kind of inner balance is strong
but rather it also comes from the
strength of mindfulness
investigation all these other factors
and then being able to
not be pulled for against things not
quickly become impartial not quickly be
reactive to experience but have a
stability
that allows us to have the overview and
wisdom operates
wisdom can see that oh that's being
pulled into things i don't need to do
that
that's my anger i don't have to get pick
it up and get involved
that's pain i've been i know about pain
i've
meditated with pain for a long time and
i know i'm better off
not getting pulled into its orbit and
preoccupied by it or
reactive to it and so there's a little
bit of wisdom operating with this
overview
having the big picture of how it works
and um
so um so it belongs to the
the uh aspect of mindfulness
where we can begin observing what's
going on it's a little bit like it's a
little bit like
you know stepping back and having the
big picture or being up in a
hilltop maybe looking down or the
experience that i had this wonderful
experience that was very
valuable for me many years ago was a
second year in college
first time i was living with the college
roommates and
little apartment and the little
apartment had a
deck out the living room and one day i
was out somehow i was out in the deck
with living room sliding door closed
and two of my roommates were having an
animated i think a friendly enough
animated conversation
in the living room and i couldn't hear
anything they were saying
but i could see the animated way they
were
and i could feel how i was kind of
delighted seeing them
but i could feel how i wasn't being
pulled around by what they were saying
and how they were i wasn't getting
pulled in
or reactive to it i was just kind of
sitting peacefully
delightfully just watching in a kind of
way of equanimity
so this ability to observe and watch and
maybe be delighted
maybe be compassionate maybe have a
response that's
situation appropriate because
of our ability to have the overview and
clear seeing of what's going on
equanimity factor of awakening so one
more talk on that tomorrow
and then we'll pick up the the pace of
uh
these 16 steps of anapanasati
so thank you all very much and
i do look forward to being together
again tomorrow