all right so hello and welcome again warm welcome wherever you are in the
world to this Friday edition of happy
hour so for the practice
today um I'd like to offer a um a practice of
of working with gratitude today and I'll tell you what The Inspirations are
multiple Inspirations for for today's practice one is that I'm going to try to
keep a give a lot of space a lot of spaciousness and a lot of Silence because I've noticed that for our Friday
evening or Saturday for the case of mar Christine in Australia um it's been nice
to have more space more silence at the end of a week just not too many words so
that's one idea I'm going to be bringing have keeping in mind for our uh practice
together now for the Gratitude uh the inspiration for this
practice um comes from having had a conversation with a student this past
week who's been working with this practice of be grateful to everyone
which is one of the loang practices so I wanted to flesh that out a little bit
and and support us all in exploring this beautiful practice which is just a wonderful practice for for everyone so
so this is just a couple of words about this so one
consideration is um know with a practice of gratitude generally we tend to be
grateful for what is easy what is good people that are benefactors in our lives
wonderful people we don't often think as people who push our buttons and
challenging people uh to be grateful for them and of course this practice really
opens us up and shifts our perspective to that and I wanted to share something
this is a commentary this paragraph is by PMA children and and just to say this
these um practices these L Jang uh practices are from Tibetan loang SC um
slogans there many of them many some of them seem more specific in the for the framework of Tibetan
practice but many of them are more General so so this is number 13 so this
is the commentary from Pema so she says others will always show you exactly
where you are stuck they say or do something and you automatically get hooked into a familiar
way of reacting shutting down speeding up or
getting all worked up when you react in a habitual way with anger greed and so
forth it gives you a chance to see your patterns and work with them honestly and
compassionately without others provoking you you remain ignorant of your painful
habits and cannot train in transforming them into the path of awak
so this is one way to have a sense of gratitude for everyone especially for
people who push our buttons because they they support us to wake up to see our habitual patterns because it's not
really about them our impatience our anger our whatever habitual pattern
comes up it's really about us so thank you dear person I'm having a challenge
with you are serving as a miror helping me wake up helping me uh see these
patterns loud and clear thank you thank you for being in my life thank you
otherwise I would think I'm awakened and you know just done and here thank you
you're showing me yes there is work to do to to to to cultivate my heart in
goodness and expand it in compassion so really just a sense of appreciation and gratitude that they are in your life
that they're helping you develop um in this way as and um so
having said that I want to say one more thing before getting into our meditation and that
is in order for this practice especially if we do it as a medit so you can take
this practice into your daily life in the next week or over the weekend if you like if the opportunity
arises being grateful for everyone and uh now for the practice for the
meditation practice on the cushion now what I suggest in order not to make it
busy and also to cultivate this hard space not thinking
space but just a settle space to land into a space of spaciousness calm quiet
and let instead of going out and thinking about people and things to be
grateful for which can get really busy I'm going to suggest a different
mode so listen carefully the mode is you sit in you sit
back into your seat with your breath your
body and you allow as whatever comes up when whether it's people in this case or
whatever comes up for it to be met in this space in an open heartedness of
gratitude kindness can I be grateful for this so it's a different kind of
practice it's a receptive practice and the answer might be no I can be grateful
for this right now is this pain in my knee it's okay don't push it just let it
be let there be kindness but we super receptive kind of practice which tills
the soil supports Us in more active in
the more going out practice okay does that make sense not if yes okay great
I'm think seeing a few Nots great all right so let's start practicing together
so I invite you to get comfortable however you need to get comfortable in
your cushion in your chair your sitting
posture and
Landing Landing in this body with this breath
whether the body is tired
heavy light
energized anxious or sleepy whatever is
happening can we land in this body with openness to
it to whatever is here right now
opening opening your
heart your mind the Mind heart and ply the word is
chitta translated as mind heart sometimes as
Consciousness opening it up to all the sensations of breathing in the body
all sounds in your
environment sense of expansiveness as if the heart the
Mind spacious are spacious and expanded
relaxed above and beyond the imagination in including and welcoming
it all whatever
Rises e
just settling for a few more minutes in
silence e
nowhere to go nothing to do but to just be and be breathed
spaciously at this
moment
e e
I like to invite you to imagine that you are
sitting a very very comfortable chair
maybe it's a recliner very comfortable relaxed your
body at peace in the middle of a house
with six doors and windows representing the six sense
stors the middle of the house this cozying comfortable recliner
chair sitting being breathed your
seat not leaving your
seat this house is spacious very
spacious plenty of room plenty of space
tall ceilings LS of
light of ease and rest
cozy and as you are in this house
expansive expansively
there might be visitors who come through each of the different sense
doors sounds you hear maybe the Mind door The Sixth Sense
door in Buddhist cosmology thoughts come up images come
up visitors these visit visitors show up at
the doors or Windows they peek in like little
animals little birds spaciousness as you're sitting in
your comfortably chair you see them you greet them and whatever they are can we feel
happy grateful that they're visiting in this moment thank you for visiting
without needing to get up and walk away with them
into whatever they're doing just from the comfort the ease
spaciousness they can come and visit thank
you there could be Sensations that come and visit
through the sense door of the body be unpleasant Sensations
pains
discomfort seeing these friends too who are visiting
hi thank you for visiting for whatever lesson you want to teach
me spaciousness and ease greeting all these impermanent visitors
as they come and
go greeting them with peace equinity with
gladness e
and if no visitors come to visit it's okay relishing the Peace aity of
just sitting being breathed on this comfortable recliner
chair e
as these visitors visit is there any
need for reactivity at
all can the visitors visit come and
go just as they
are is there any need for any
reaction we need to pick pick it up pick anything
up on our end making it about us about
me
myself
e
e e
you can continue to practice in this
way with visitors the different s sense
doors thoughts images Sensations
sounds Etc
smells if you like if you
like tying with the theme of being grateful for
everyone it's okay if you like to invite
allow different people to visit a different door
doors people who are friends [Music] benefactors people with whom you've had
some irritation and as you don't leave your
seat your seed of equinity your
embodiment can there be a sense of GRA itude
appreciation everyone who visits everything that
visits without getting up and walking away with them with stories and
thoughts but staying right where you
are
e
e e
see what your heart needs in this moment and simplify the practice if needed bear
bones
e
e e
the last few minutes of our practice together
what if the people who are visiting are those you've had some
entanglement with and you really feel grateful for
them don't know quite why what the reason
is what the lesson is how you grow through this interaction but just
feeling grateful for them let yourself be one of the visitors e
you are included in everyone to be grateful for
everyone including this being who is
you
e e
may all beings everywhere be happy may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you all for your practice
so I changed the setting so you're welcome to share with everyone or with just me or
reflection so I'll say a few words and um I'll start by saying that I
had never done this practice in this way and let it in this way and it was eye
opening for me was so beautiful it was similar but slightly different flavor from um
meta loving kindness for people with whom with have we have a challenge with
whom we have a challenge it was similar to that for me what I experienced but
slightly different actually it brought up nuances the sense of feeling grateful
not just feeling well may you be safe and happy person I'm having challenges with but oh I'm grateful for you I'm
grateful for you you I'm grateful for you and and as I was doing it these the
things that I'm truly grateful for in with they they really lit up with these
beings with these different people things in our history in our past just
really there was a lot of gratitude for them even for the difficulty just really
led up this practice not so much as a daily practice which is how the loang
slogans are often practiced but as a formal practice I had never done a formal silent practice of feeling
gratitude for these visitors of the heart uh we have challenges with so for me it was just really beautiful I loved
it and I appreciate the practitioner who brought this into my Consciousness this
past week so thank you and thank you all for practicing this together so would
love to hear what what it was like for you what did you discover um you can
type in chat privately to me I won't read your name or to everyone I will
read your name or raise your Zoom hand which would be either under reactions or
or somewhere else you probably know it by now and uh I'm ask you to unmute so
Mari Christine please for me the challenge was that
every time I opened the door I got carried away with the dialogue I couldn't just open the door
and be with it I had to talk in my head of course so it was it was it was
interesting but it was a bit challenging that we not to get carried away with the dialogue yeah yeah thank you for sharing
that thank you so what what I would suggest to kind of help with that would
be um don't leave your seat don't go to the door don't go open the door because
we have the habit of when we open the door like hey how are you you know this kind of like it's in our body in our Bon
the habit of talking and whereas um if you um um just you are in your seat they
come they visit they just hang out at the door or and you're silent you're silent then it can it can support that
Mario Christine how does that sound yeah yeah thank you thank you so much that's
lovely yeah yeah and G uh gurgel who's joining
us from IR I hope I'm saying your name right said these slight differences can really create openings for inner discoveries
yes yes beautiful exactly slightly different yes so uh your name says
iPhone suang I think it is suang I ask please unmute yourself yes I see your
hand
raised can you hear me yes loud and clear here okay Su Jang Su Jang Su Jang
great Su Jang hi I always enjoy your different um type of practice for meta I
appreciate you a lot and today um I just basically
sitting in the couch whatever it was and I stay in there just welcoming all those
people coming to six doors and I was so surprised as there are so many people coming in
especially uh the person I actually arguing with in the morning it wasn't really arguing but who does uh business
with me who I hire to do something and uh
basically he was actually saying that you know what this is not gonna work
because you know he was talking about all those like um you w to you are my
managing stuff which is true you know I mean to be honest I don't feel offended
about anything at all someone tell me what's my personality I'm just okay
you're right to be honest you know so he was saying that oh this is not gonna
work and blah blah blah but he actually was saying it in a really nice um from
his heart I could see it because he's been he's been great for me you know he helped me through through and stuff like
that he's very honest and all that and he was like so stood up so much in that
door and I was like oh my God I appreciate you so much
a I love it is it isn't it so interesting because like all day I spoke
with him the first conversation that I have it was him and I was like unsettled
all along all all day during my work whatsoever I'm like wow our last you
know wow oh my goodness I love it and now I hear this sense of gratitude Grace like
oh you're so grateful for him there's just a shift that I hear in your voice as you're talking s it's lovely thanks
for sharing that that's just oh yeah sure I'm not gonna go on and on and out but I'm gonna stop right there so people
can say that's great thank you all thanks for that and one more and we have
one reflection uh who sent to me so I won't say your name who says this is so
timely for me I'm a beginner to mindfulness and meditation and approaching it with gratitude makes a
lot of sense for me it just really clicked oh I don't know if I'm I'm
supposed to say your name I get uh okay oh great you're from the Bay Area okay
you can tell me if I'm if it's okay to say your name or not because you gave me the correct pronunciation so yay lovely
I'm so glad it worked for you lovely and and especially given that you're new to this practice and exploring this way
really clicked for you beautiful so any other quick Reflections before we
go or maybe we'll save some some time tell you what we'll save some time on the other end when we come back from
small groups to see what might have come up in small groups as we've practiced together
so dear ones um as always uh invitation is to practice
together in small groups and let's see
um here we go room size of three and we'll start with 30 maybe 15 seconds of
meta for each other and um and then share sharing
whatever you like to share as much or as little as you like to share so I'm about
to open the rooms and take care of yourselves take care of others kindness is what we're trying to cultivate in our
interactions with each other okay so here we go welcome back everyone we've got a few
minutes for um any Reflections you may have especially if you haven't spoken
yet today or if you haven't spoken for a while would love to hear from you either can raise your Zoom hand or type
in chat what did you discover in your practice especially together being
grateful for
everyone um we said we were grateful for these challenges these challenging
people because they helped us grow and um helped us see ourselves more clearly
nice yeah what a gift to see ourselves more clearly right yeah it it is a gift it's a
profound gift yeah we may not always like what we see yet it's so profound
the gift to see ourselves clearly so profound Priceless of course as long as
we we may not like what we see but as we see it with kindness and gentleness and
with aspiration for call cultivating and growing instead of
badgering ourselves with you're bad you're terrible you're you're awful of course not that but yeah yeah thank you
Janie thank you
yeah yeah it's great Zoom is thank Neil is thanking the zoom voice for letting us
know the meeting is being recorded yes otherwise I would forget to turn on recording as sometimes I do after we
come back from the practice from the small groups now you're feeling
Neil now you're feeling grateful for everyone even the zoom voice I love
it oh sweet any other Reflections we have time for one more
please hello yes I'd like I'd like to share a quote from Brother Brother David
steinle R he says we are not grateful we are not grateful because we are happy we
are happy because we are grateful yeah thank you for bringing that in yes he is
amazing he's a beautiful being and a beautiful teacher of gratitude and happiness thank you for bringing that in
yes exactly gratitude and happiness intertwined
[Music] so dear ones oh yes uh what was his name
says Marie Christine it's uh brother stendal Rost uh we'll send it we'll send
it in the Google Groups afterwards can yeah so dear ones thank you all for the
grace the gift of your practice coming together in this group cultivating your own heart both
for yourself and all beings whose lives you touch may all beings be happy may all
beings be free including
[Music] ourselves thanks everyone so good to be
with you