okay great so hello hello and welcome to all of you
wherever you are zooming in from all over the place and i missed
susan from santa cruz and uh awawas
thank you yes hello to all of you wherever you are zooming in from or
or youtubing from or or listening to this on audio dharma later so lovely to be with you so
so for today's practice um
this this practice is inspired by um a talk i was listening to by my friend
catherine mcgee who teaches uh in england and the title of the talk was
something like your attention can be beautiful um so and that's been swinging
and swinging in my mind so of course i'll offer my own version of that
related to happy or in practice of the heart so so
so to consider that you're always paying attention you are always paying attention
somehow to something and we're often focusing on the object
well actually most of the time we're not even aware that we're paying attention because it feels um as if we are
in autopilot and we just do things and our attention
wanders from one object to another to another so there isn't even a sense of awareness
that we're paying attention but often we might be aware that we are
paying attention and we might only be aware of the object we're paying attention to
say if you are on the computer sending an email you're sending you're
paying attention to the email you're sending or right now maybe you're paying attention to the
sound of my voice or maybe to the sensations in your body or to the colors on the screen etc
now just as important as to what we're paying attention to
is how we are paying attention what is the quality
is our attention tight are we tightening the body trying to
bear down say on the breath in order to get concentrated
yes perfectly good intention beautiful intention to to settle the mind etc and yet how
are we engaging what is the quality of the attention
is it tight is it way too lax is it
just wandering from one object to the next etc
is the quality that attention is imbued in
is it judgmental is it grabbing is it grasping is it
perhaps pushing away the object it's aware of
so becoming aware paying attention to how we are paying
attention [Music] and as relevant for our cultivation here
in happy hour is noticing
or perhaps seeding or cultivating whether the quality of our attention
[Music] is imbued
with friendliness
ah with openness with a gentle kind curiosity
this is this meta that can infuse this friendliness
this non-judgmental stance that awareness can be imbued and how are
we paying attention how are we meeting the breath
how is the attention needing the body how is the attention meeting thoughts
that are arising
perhaps one distinction that i was thinking earlier about a cartoon that could be
made in on one that with two images of a meditator who's a beginner and just
started to meditate and one who's an experienced meditator
practitioner and in one in on one side
the experience the inexperience the new practitioner meditator is the the thought bubble
is oh darn it i was thinking oh i was thinking again this is terrible
i i can't do this thing i can't do this meditation thing i'm a failure i'm a loser my mind keeps
wandering i must be defective everybody else they you know can just be clear and spacious
and i keep thinking okay that's on the right hand side and on the left hand side the thought bubble of the experienced
practitioner says ah thinking is arising
thinking is arising our thinking has arisen it's just like that so
how are we paying attention how are we aware of the thoughts that are coming up
is it with a sense of unfriendliness oh i'm a failure uh thoughts go away i'm just like oh
interesting thinking is has arisen has arisen and or is arising just
the sense of openness spaciousness this friendliness of meta where things
can arise and pass without becoming sticky
so so in the practice today i've said plenty to frame or practice
inviting us with meta with kindness with ease
to become aware of how we are paying attention and in that way
may our attention become beautiful may our attention become filled with
this ease of spaciousness this quality this quality this freeing quality of the
heart and mind itself so let's begin
let's begin let's settle into our
ah into our bodies into our breath
and then writing fighting
our attention to release to let go ever so gently
of thoughts of preoccupations
and to turn to turn inward turn inward towards the body
this whole body sitting and breathing
and from the outset noticing if the attention is tight if the body is tight
there is a sense of bearing down [Music] or can there be a sense of spaciousness
attention awareness
like a comfortable bed that we rest on
like the air that can infuse like the breath that goes through the
body is breathed in on its own
in on its own gently
and not getting too self-conscious at this point about wait how am i paying attention just let go
let go
we can turn off our awareness or attention just so let it be let it be just as it is
receiving whatever is arising and this
fear of awareness in this moment
letting each breath be received
and the lower body and the abdomen [Music]
the tension awareness connecting
intimately not tightly but intimately as if
as if attention is the water the breath is swimming in as if the breath was a swimmer
swimming coming in contact to contact with
awareness the entire body of the swimmer immersed in water
the entire body of the breath beginning middle and end
immersed touched gently soothed
caressed by awareness
and if and when thoughts arise
notice our thoughts are rising thoughts have arisen
and notice the quality with which
thinking is being noted
is the knowing the quality of knowing spacious friendly
or is it aversive
is it like a generous host ah this is what's
present right now where visitors come and go
or is the quality imbued with the resistance
calling them distractions
and notice how the attitude of the kind generous guest could be one of
oh hello visitor thank you
and this is not the best time to visit see how can that be how that can be very
spacious and easy lovingly firm
please come back another time thank you
no trace of ill will
the heart the mind the mind heart the chitta
kind generous as wide as the world
we're always paying attention
how how are we paying attention
can awareness attention be imbued with friendliness
with meta these qualities beautiful qualities of
the heart and mind
and now what if the sense of
the self self as the center of the world
it's the constant frame of reference
what if that was loosened with this quality of meta
be more easily accessible when there isn't so much me and mine
in my self-interest what i like or dislike
what does this say about me what if that was dropped
what are we attending to and how are we attending
can we notice tension and its quality with metta
and now can we expand instead of just being internal with our
awareness can we turn awareness to be external
as if aware of other beings around us with us
in space and time
awareness turned external
to humans non-humans
plants etc
the air the earth
and can there be a sense of benevolence kindness
meta-infused
with attention turned outward
any object it comes in contact with
sense of friendliness
can attention turning external and now internal both external and internal
whatever objects of the mind
thought internal external comes in contact with
be infused with goodwill friendliness
and matter
even if what we meet internally externally is challenging
can the stance of awareness be a friendly one curious open
patient
and for the last moments of this practice as we come to an end
and we gather ourselves up and perhaps an evaluation
[Music] attention to evaluation comes up
can we see can we attend
this evaluation if it's coming up with kindness
it's not judgment or friendliness no matter how
challenged or challenging sleepy [Music]
distracted this period of practice was
bringing appreciation that we showed up we showed up as best as we're able to
and appreciating with friendliness
and love thank you me thanks for showing up as best as you're able to planting seeds
that's the best we can hope for and do moment by moment thanking yourself for
showing up for yourself and all beings whose lives you touch
thanks everyone thank you for your
practice so we have a few minutes if you'd like
to share your reflections uh what you noticed what came up for you you're welcome to
raise your zoom hand or you can type it in chat either to me privately in which case i
wouldn't say your name or or um
to everyone in which case i'll say your name so yeah
so what did you notice any insights any or any questions as i wait
for you i'll share that noticing how we're paying attention turning awareness on awareness to
quality when we see that it can free something it can
something can let go something can release and more kindness more ease more
spaciousness more meta can come in through that process
did many of you have an experience of that even for a split second
yes mary please
hi thank you hi so i was very i was anxious
and my breath was anxious and then when you said can you let go of the self
at i i took my breath away i was like gasping for breath and then
i mean it brings tears i just i was so grateful to let go
of that busy anxious self thank you
thank you mary thank you so much for sharing that
profound right profound that that is possible
that is possible and it can it can happen just like that by
inclining by turning the attention the self dropping away so much space
there can be beautiful all you're doing yay or all your all your non-doing well all
none you're doing
thanks for sharing that mary beautiful
what any other reflections observations
questions complaints
i'll ask you a question that um [Music] with the invitation internal
external turning awareness internal external did you notice a shift there is there something
in the inside perhaps something that came up or different aspects
or as mary talked about ah the self dropping away or noticing thoughts arising kind of the
stance of friendliness arising and passing with the thoughts
gracious host
was there anything particularly challenging that didn't quite that was confusing instruction that
would be helpful to unpack
so how about we turn to practice in
small groups in sangha and there as you share and you listen to others i think
different reflections might come up there's so much to learn from each other
so the invitation is let's start with
30 seconds of silent meta for each other and then whatever
reflections you like to share with each other about the practice
so i'm going to open the rooms here we go enjoy meeting and practicing
together okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed
so what did you discover discussing in community sangha practice
love to hear something you've noticed please don't be shy especially if you don't tend to speak
in in group
trusting that your observations your insights your questions your confusion
is valuable to offer that if you wish
um hi it's michael um it was super sweet and there were four of us and we kind of
ran out of time meaning there was not enough time for the shares
and i hope the woman who wanted to share something but she
said she thought it would take four minutes we'll share whatever she's gonna share because i'm interested deep vows to you
all thank you michael
i second your invitation if that person is comfortable
diana are you raising your hand or giving thumbs up
so i'm the one oh great and i'll try to be fast but i was at
dinner tonight with a friend i'm three hours ahead of you so it's almost 10 o'clock
and um i wasn't feeling it but i practiced loving kindness anyway and i was in the previous um
retreat the one before i did it anyway i was really blah and negative and then
i was eating eating mindfully at dinner or attempting to and every now and then i would take
really serious breasts and just be with myself although i was listening
and both the internal and external came into play i was very much with him
and settled within myself and very much feeling her without boundaries and that
was our dinner it wasn't a perfect dinner but then as we were walking back
i something so struck me and i had it just came to me i
totally understood her profound profound fear she had this past year of the
coronavirus which i had been putting down and she was just always had been this
way and i'm not and we live in a city where it kind of gripped us
and i finally felt into something for the first time and then also during the course of
dinner uh the family i got to get a really clear sadness about something so i
processed that sadness is here i mean i sound like i'm this is this is dinner tonight my sadness is
here and i started to breathe again and i didn't analyze it i just said what is this i went through that
she's talking so by the time i got home tonight and set up everything i thought
what just happened so all these various experiences of meta self-compassion
just started playing that's my story it was like this
record of things playing one to another nice thank you thanks diana thanks for sharing i'm so
appreciating oh what you shared i'll reflect a couple of things back um as you were in the retreat uh the
meta and wisdom retreat a couple weeks ago so you're saying you've been practicing and and this is what i always
tell practitioners on retreats that your retreat isn't finished it's going to keep doing you and that's
what that's what i'm hearing that you know your dinner with this friend there's this sense of oh internal
external and the heart opening up to their fear to their worry like feeling into it really
connecting with it and um just the
the you know the retreat is continuing is doing you in so many ways internally externally with a sense of openness and
kindness and compassion internal external being in your experience opening up to sadness
and conversations that are pushing it away it's just it's all here it's all it can all be included lovely thank you
for sharing that it's beautiful a beautiful detailed observation of how practice can unfold
no great miracle during the retreat or afterwards it's just
these things coming along and um like almost out of nowhere not planned
although i'm practicing that's you planted seeds in diana you planted seeds and now the
seeds are being uh bearing fruit thank you yeah so any last quake reflections about
you know this paying attention quality of paying attention knowing how we're paying attention we're
always paying attention
all right so i let that be i will close the evening as i don't see any takers or any any uh
reflections in chat but just i will say as you can see it's michael i do have a
question yeah sure um your teacher friend in england is she tanzania style
no no no no okay you mean no yeah
no what what is she what flavor is she oh gosh lots of deep different
practices you look her up yeah okay i can't summarize i can't do her justice
you i will deep pause thank you michael so thank you all
thank you all for showing up for practicing for planting seeds
for your own sake and the sake of all beings everywhere we do this practice for
all beings seen unseen past present future this mysterious nature
of our lives so thank you for inclining your hearts and minds to kindness may all beings be happy
may all beings be free including
ourselves thank you