so good morning and welcome to the meditation session
one of the very supportive qualities for meditation and for the
buddhist path is contentment and the image of contentment is that of
a bird flying unburdened with its wings
so a bird doesn't really carry anything with it luggage and kitchen sinks and the idea of an
unburdened wings that we fly we move we
are free is the reference point for contentment
and there's nothing about renunciation in this classic teaching of contentment
but rather it's a teaching on being content with what one has
and uh to be content with the situation one has maybe
for this minute or for this hour and that it's not a moral imperative to
be content but rather it's a pointer
to a way of being that supports our ability to be present discontent
is a support for being not being present for wanting more or being anxious or thinking ahead or
hoping and all kinds of things and to avail ourselves of the contentment
that's here that's reasonable at this time to be content
with one circumstance to be content classically the buddha talks about content with the clothes one has the
robes and monastic has to be content with the food that one has
to be content with what to to look for where it's reasonable to be
content and if we combine that with the first
beginning of mindfulness or breathing which is very much body centered
then the contentment can be be an embodied contentment
a contentment which is not a thinking so much only thinking but a contentment
that is felt somatically is a contentment that feels that comes
along with the relaxation that
starts off this practice of anapanasati
and perhaps it's a contentment found in the relaxing even in the simplest muscles that relax
that there can be some feeling there of contentment or ease or well-being and to
be attuned to that and that's an antidote to being attuned
to our fears being attuned to our desires our thoughts our stories it's
shifting the paradigm of where we find our home
and finding our home here in this body breathing contentedly
being present so assuming a meditation posture
a posture which allows us to be to be alert but also
a posture that is just comfortable enough that there's space
for contentment so not collapsing or slouching in the
couch
it's hard to feel contentment if the body is in a lot of discomfort
gently closing the eyes and taking a few fuller breaths
breathing in and a long exhale
and maybe for three times to have a much longer exhale than
usually do maybe with a little maybe internally in
your mind when that wonderful mantra
the mantra of contentment
and then letting yourself breathe normally and to do a progressive relaxation of
the body but to do so each time you're able to
relax some part of the body to feel whatever
positive feelings that comes with that maybe it's contentment
maybe it's relief maybe it's ease or a feeling of goodness
or feeling of rightness
beginning with the muscles of the face
as you exhale relaxing the forehead
all the way around to the temples
relaxing around the eyes if the eyes are trying to see
see if you can let the eyes rest in their sockets with the eyes closed there's nothing to
see or to understand
relaxing the muscles of the cheeks and the jaw around the mouth
softening and around the shoulders
releasing the shoulders to the pull of gravity
maybe a softening around the shoulder blades
and softening around the chest
around the heart
and then what happens if you release your belly soften in the belly
sometimes softening the belly is complicated but perhaps there's also some feeling of
positive feeling in doing so
and it might also be possible to relax the whole body
to release the way that we're braced against life or contracted
a deeper settling
and to be here now with some contentment
there may be things in the world which
there's discontentment about maybe for the time being to put those
aside and appreciate what there is to be
content with right now here in the immediacy of this moment
within the experience of this body and mind
an embodied feeling of contentment
or of ease
which maybe comes along somehow with the
breathing
and to begin sensing the body breathing
and is there any point in the cycle of breathing in and out
that contains within it some more distinct feelings of
contentment of ease
where it feels okay just to go along with it to be satisfied with this moment of
breathing maybe it's during the exhale
content just follow along to ride the exhale
or maybe the inhale content to be carried and lifted
by the inhale
and then relaxing the mind
softening quieting the activities of mind thinking
so there might also be some contentment of mind
a contentment to just be here with the present moment
with what it whatever's in the present moment that
allows you to be content just to be alive just to breathe
putting aside your burdens they can be for later and for these
minutes content to just be present unburdened
maybe like a bird flying
your wings catch the updraft of the inhale
and glide on the exhale one breath after another
maybe to notice the contentment that's already here
maybe that's unnoticed it lives in the body
or maybe you recognize it more as calm or subtleness
some positive feeling of satisfaction or well-being and no matter how small it
might be let that support your breathing
maybe it comes along as you breathe or you breathe with it or through it
as a way of encouraging you to be more embodied in this practice
and then as we come to the end of this sitting take a few moments to feel more
whatever way that you feel more settled in your body
or that you feel more content or calm
if your knees ache or you feel need to readjust your posture
to feel more settled and content please do so
and feeling some ways in which you are more settled or content
now imagine that you're meeting with someone else
and you meet them without your need without impulse to interfe interrupt or
to speak over eagerly but that with your contentment and
subtleness you're more ready to listen
more inclined to really be present for someone
without asserting oneself on them
maybe also with not without closing down or pulling away
and it becomes a gift we can give others if some of these qualities of subtleness
calm and contentment that has happens in meditation
is shared with others and how we are present for them
and may it be a gift of our meditation
that we're able to create a safe place for people to be themselves
and we listen and we're present
may it be that we learn how to be a gift for our world
in offering presence and attention and safety to others
and in this way may some of the benefits and merit that
comes from our practice be for the welfare and happiness of
others may we practice so that
we we support the happiness of other beings
the safety of others
that others may experience peacefulness
that they may have room to be unburdened unlimited
by our presence so they have room to be free
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
peaceful and free may all beings everywhere be free
so
i think many of you have heard from me and maybe other buddhist teachers and
teachings the value of being embodied
so much so that i sometimes will with kind of imagine that it would have
been nice if we had translated sati not as mindfulness but as
uh body fullness it's such an important part of this practice
and in the two classic buddha teachings by the buddha on mindfulness
practice in the discourse the four foundations of mindfulness and the discourse on
mindfulness of breathing it begins with an emphasis on mindfulness of the body and
now one of the reasons for this is that the body the more present we are
for our body the more we're aware the more there's awareness that's alive and
and kind of available through the body the more the body becomes an instrument
for the growth of meditation practice it becomes the vehicle in space for some of the deeper feelings
some of the deeper qualities of meditation that begin to arise it's kind of like as the body
receives some of the benefits of meditation those benefits are augmented or or um
not augmented but those those benefits grow and fill out and we get the most out of them
so what i'm talking about here partly is that as the body becomes more alive
and more sensitive and more of an instrument of sensations and experiences and feelings
it's not just feeling the body itself but it's also start the body becomes the the sensor
for feeling some of the goodness that comes from meditation and i would use the word goodness in a
very abstract vague way like just like maybe like the word all the some of the positive feelings
that can come with meditation so um classically it's joy and happiness
but it could also be contentment i like the word ease quite a bit there can be
gladness there's deep feelings of equanimity deep feelings of
of confidence that can arise even feelings of being of inner
cleanliness and inner purity that really are embodied feelings that kind
of course through us so all these qualities are felt more fully
when they're felt throughout the whole body felt with the body if the body is not available then it
becomes a mental thing and sometimes that's quite wonderful and and
profound in its own way but it's really uh especially in the beginning stages of
meditation it's really a way of um being quite limited in the experience
and it gives us a different impression of what meditation is about um and different orientation which if
it's too much towards the mind it doesn't really help us
develop the wholeness the unification of all of ourselves
which is ideally what we're looking for in buddhist meditation
i think it's one of the meanings of samadhi is unification bringing it all together here present
so the so again the body is not just a you know a bunch of physical stuff that
we have to carry around with us the body is a is a significant
uh repository of nerve endings significant uh location for
uh the emotions the feelings the the goodness of meditation to course through us or to fill us
and be here um
the um the so to begin tuning in being relaxing the
body sitting in with the body feeling the body is uh one way in which we begin to
open up to this repository of goodness as i said classically what comes next
after the first four steps of anapanasati what comes next as a practice deepens is
some feelings of well-being joy or ease or gladness and something like and so
to know that that's coming to know that's part of meditation it can and then encourage us to be a
little bit more sensitive to when they start uh appearing the hints of them appear
and we start feeling a little bit the these good feelings that come sometimes it feels like pleasure in the
body or tingling at places a sense of lightness that comes and
it's not that we're trying to make it happen so much or or searching for it or striving for it
but when it begins to show show themselves a little bit there's an art to opening to them
to relaxing with them to include them so they go along with the breathing or the
breathing goes along with them so we're encourage us to become even
more embodied to feel these in our body and as we feel this goodness
to kind of breathe with it and open with it and continue this process of feeling and sensing and
developing as we go along and
so the contentment is part of this to feel contentment allows
it isn't like again a moral obligation to feel content but it allows for this filling out of
the practice and really being rooted and centered here in this body feeling more and more
the same thing with this idea of being in the present moment and not thinking about the past and
future it's not like a moral obligation we have to do that but when we're no longer caught up in
the past and future in thoughts it allows for possibility of filling out more into the wholeness of this moment
that includes so much more of us and it's kind of like a momentum a movement towards becoming
really whole and present with all of who we are and part of that comes along with
relaxation and and uh tranquility calmness is a
more and more space for uh delight a joy well-being a sense of pleasure
and just being alive and being here and i think of this joy of meditation as being a joy that has
no opposite it's just a joy that exists kind of in its own way if it had an
opposite then you know it's we can swing from one to the other but it has no opposite so
certainly we can not have it not be there but it isn't that it swings it's not part of a pendulum that goes from
one to the other so for example if your joy is dependent
on praise the opposite then is blame and then the pendulum can swing because
dependent on getting something or if your joy is dependent on
success then there can be failure if it's dependent on physical pleasure
it can be dependent on things being uncomfortable and so but the joy of meditation does not have
an opposite it just has this wonderful simple and clear quality of surfacing and
arising and being here without really in a sense not depending
on the things that come and go in the world so much but is a wellspring that flows within
the body and so the more we can kind of center ourselves in the body relax be
present the more we will be
you know starting to open up to our potential our capacity
for well-being for joy for happiness and um and that's a wonderful thing and
it turns out that meditative joy and happiness is a wonderful it continues this process
of unification of wholeness bringing more and more of ourselves into the picture so that we can
continue on a path to liberation