and we'd like to thank nalitha for joining joining us all the way from johannesburg south africa um
for those curious it's 8 p.m there now and as we're transitioning from the
winter to the spring here in california in south africa they're going from
summer to fall so it's a good time for a good transition period for everyone so
nolitha sengiwe is a guiding teacher at the
dharmagiri retreat retreat center in kwazulu-natal south africa she will be
completing a four-year teacher training under ims and irc in may of this year
nolitha is a student of kitasaro and tanisara who are students of ajahn chau
growing up in a culture underpinned by the principle of ubuntu which means i am
because we are and where the power of generosity is
greatly appreciated and being introduced to buddhism and living in a place where there aren't
many buddhists felt like coming home for her nolitha is also a single parent to a 23 year old
son in a culture where villages help to raise their children
so thank you very much for joining us molita
thank you kevin i'm delighted to be here
the theme i've chosen for reflection is generosity
so under the theme of generosity i'm going to talk about giving
sharing a key practice and buddhism
in all buddhist traditions called donna that's the pali word
for giving i'll also talk about training in
ethics buddha referred to training in precepts as the great
donor it's another form of giving
i'll also speak about relinquishment
letting go kali word for relinquishment is kaga
letting go is also a form of giving and lastly i will
talk about forgiveness forgiveness is a form of giving
where we give each other fearlessness
when we forgive
so the cultivation of generosity is really the foundation
for training of the mind
it is the foundation for mindfulness and wisdom for liberation
so i noticed the words i'm using
giving and sharing precepts relinquishment forgiveness
these words can bring up interesting experiences in the heart
can bring up discomfort i know for a
long time for me the words precepts and relinquishment
would bring a sense of terror to my heart
i don't know how it is like for you these words maybe you're well ahead in
this path these words bring joy to your heart
that's what they are aimed for actually to bring joy
so i'm going to start off with a story that for me highlights the beauty and
the grace of generosity
a friend of mine i teach with here in south africa moira shares a story about being in zambia
zambia in south africa share border so she says here she is in some village
in zambia driving on a dutch road
the car starts to give her problems
she drives on and suddenly notices that there's this homestead near the
roadside and there are scrap
cars old cars in the yard and she decides to stop here thinking
this would be the kind of place that can give her help in fixing her car
at the homestead she's welcomed by an old man
she notices children playing in the sand
and also notices signs of great poverty in this household
she mentions seeing a few chickens without any feathers so
she explains hannah hanid and um the old man organizes all the boys
they look at the car kai is fixed and then about to leave moira offers
this old man some money he says no
he then offers some fruits in the car he says no and she says but it's for the
children he says no and then he says
if we can't help each other that would be really sad if we just cannot
just give how
for moira this was a new experience
and receiving this experience foreign is white person old man is black
and i'm mentioning the race here because i'm joining you from south africa
and uh issues of race uh are still a big issue
moira shares that from this experience she felt deeply connected
and she also mentions that she felt like she didn't deserve that connection
so acts of generosity allows for these benevolent connections
with each other
hmm
generosity acts of kindness giving sharing this is what the buddha
has to say about sharing
if beings knew as i know the results of giving and sharing
they would not eat without having given nor would the stain of selfishness
overcome their minds even if it were their lust bites
their last mouth full they would not eat without having shared
if there was someone to receive their gift
so when growing up practice of generosity was truly a way of life
i remember that growing up in a more rural countryside part of
south africa always there would be an extra plate of
food set aside in case there's a visitor
or someone passing by who can be offered a meal
i also remember that there was no time that we ever were a nuclear family
only our home was always a home to many cousins aunts
uncles sometimes i didn't i wouldn't even know how we are related to that
person who was there to share our home for as much time as she needed or he
needed to be there
my parents were doing what their own parents did so i don't know a lot about this kind of
giving i must admit though moving to the city
getting ebonized plus less and less of this kind of generosity
so i know generosity personally but i also know generosity
at a country level
the world often wonders how did south africa manage a bloodless transition
from apartheid south africa to a black led government
many think it was because of nelson mandela
rightly so he did play a critical role
in um what the world thought of as the miracle
a miracle that gave hope to the whole world
to us it wasn't a miracle to what to us it was this was
so because the african culture is underpinned by the principle
of ubuntu i am because we are
if i cause you harm i'm causing harm to
myself steve biko was the leader was the leader
of black consciousness movement a hero a struggle hero who died in the
hands of apartheid south africa
is speaking to this principle when he says our contribution to the world would not
be in technology our contribution in africa to the world
will be to give the world a humane face
the face of humanness
so to be fully human is about being generous giving sharing and forgiving
so in the country i also noticed that we're really great at coming together at times of crisis
and this has been the case during this crisis of covet 19.
i have a few stories to share with you about these acts of kindness shown
by people not only here but really everywhere this is what people have done
they've remembered what it is to be fully human by giving support in any way that they
can we know medical care and related
professions would even risk their lives to save lives so i have a friend who's
an academic so she had a task of collating these
stories local stories of kindness during this period of covet and
she's actually in the process of compiling a book titled archives of kindness so i am going to
read to you two of these stories actually what she did was to ask a number of us to
choose your five top stories so this is this is the two of the five
that i'm going to read to you
candace in cape town in french mooc rights
i've been living in friendship now for 12 years we are a small village but as with most
places in south africa we have a polarized society
of the wealthy and the poor some of whom live in the township
setting for a small village we also have a hugely
successful and vibrant hospitality sector which means we have many hardworking
people in all levels of an industry that with some of the hardest hits
during this lockdown over the years i've been amazed at how many people have done
extraordinary things in their private capacity because it's the right thing to do like
building schools and sports centers for poorer communities
but during this crisis we reached a whole new level so many people contributed and did
awesome things coordinating relief turning restaurants into food kitchens checking it out that
everyone was okay in all different parts of the town
a lady from the township dip club here in johannesburg right
my lane lady is an angel she has given us a free stay for two months all
five of her tenants she's unemployed and depends on her rant
but she's seen how we're all struggling in the yard she says we will share
whatever food we find she is now trying to find someone to donate nepalese for my son
i'm embarrassed she's an old lady during this time she has the strength
i'm lacking she is my hero and a mom to all of us
may god give me strength to pay it forward one day these are joyful stories
this is what happens to the heart when there is generosity
so the buddha in teaching when teaching to new people to the
practices he would always or mostly start off by teaching about generosity
he would then proceed and teach about precepts
only then when he has the sense that these teachings of generosity and training in ethics
have landed will he then introduce meditation
ajahn chah and shah teacher of my teachers the thai forest
master when this theme says with virtue as a basis for everything you do your mind
will become kind clear and quiet meditation will
grow easily in this environment
so through the practice of generosity virtue we can recover the connection with ourselves with each other
and with mother nature through generosity we recover the
heart's potential for sensitivity
the parts potential for opening
lava mendez who lives in zimbabwe also zimbabwe shares a border with south
africa baba is known as an international
peacemaker he is a guardian to our center here
founded by kitsaran tamizara zamagiri
when they speak about baba kittisara and tenisera talk of him as a contemporary of agent
chair baba says
we have been disconnected to ourselves disconnected from each other because we
are disconnected from nature
and because we are disconnected from nature
we take whatever
we want from nature without giving back
as the world we are in an ecological crisis because we do not see ourselves as part
of nature we abuse nature for our greed
and our great is endless
through this we lose this heart sensitivity the intuitive intelligence
it is said that we are the only species that destroys its own habitat
with lost connection with the goodness of the heart
and i think we're paying a price for this
disconnected from each other disconnects it from ourselves we feel separate
we create us and them [Music] in mutton bubba's language
we create i it relationships it is through the cultivation of these
practices of generosity that we can recover what
matin bubba calls the i and thou relationship the i and we
relationship with the we identity we can remember the
truth that we all suffer and we all want happiness
our sense of conscience and concern can be reawakened
i'm going to talk about generosity as relinquishment
relinquishment is a form of letting go in letting go
we let go of greed craving which the buddha
has identified as the cause of our suffering the second noble truth that we suffer
because of craving and the task in this path of freedom for liberation
is to let go of the craving as practices of giving
can support us help us to let go
craving has no end it feeds itself
it is true understanding it is through these practices
that we can release craving
what underpins cravings ignorance confusion
see how we can look for what is this heart's longing in wrong places
when we follow sense objects to satisfy our craving that has no
end desire feeds itself will look for fulfillment
and sense experience since experience changes
what is pleasant becomes unpleasant
there's a story i delight at in buddhism about this
confusion of looking for fulfillment in the wrong places
it's the story of nasruddin nasruddin is a sufi mystic
he's sitting outside in a ruby and spice shop and he's eating these hot chilies
his eyes a watering a friend comes by and says what are you doing
eating these hotels with your eyes watering and you're sweating
astradin says i'm looking for the sweet one
this is what we do you and i right
we look for the freedom which is the longing of the heart
heart lungs
freedom freedom from creates hatred and delusion
lastly i'm going to talk about
forgiveness as a form of giving
how is forgiveness a form of giving when we forgive we
give fearlessness
when people know that we hold no grudges we hold no ill will when we have been
the victims it gives relief it gives happiness
i know personally about this kind of relief that comes from
one who i have harmed holds no ill will
towards him
i can't remember what year it was but it was the year that uh nelson mandela died i'm not sure
whether that was 2011.
i leave home and i notice the feeling of anxiety
and between leaving home and um
maybe it kind of mean even 10 minutes after i left home
my phone rings i'm driving and i answered the phone within no time
between that moment of answering the phone whilst driving
i drove into a biker
get out of the car in shock
and this man is on the floor
he's on the ground
i can tell he's in great pain
i go near him he is screaming at me
you wear it on your phone
and then in no time you know other people
who stopped to check what was going on
and i remember just at one point i had a feeling that was running across
my heart of fear in that moment i was thinking oh this is
going to become ratio i look around people here
are black it's me and the security guard
i offer to take the man to the hospital he refuses he's still screaming at me
an older white couple decides to take him to the nearest hospital
i wait for the police
wait and wait then i'll be so i decide to go to the
hospital i get to casualty
he's with medical staff
i sit across him he's laying down on a bed i take a chain and sit right across him
when i maintain eye contact ignores me and then at some point he
says you don't need to be here you can go where you need to go
my response to him is i want to be here and i'm really
sorry um so i continue to just sit here
and then at some point i decide i have to go and report this to the police
as i'm about to leave he says to me tell them that you own a cell phone
i'm thinking oh interesting i go and report the case i come back to
the hospital and he has been discharged
and apparently he suffered really serious injuries a broken collar bone and a crushed ankle
now what do i do i decide to go to a grocery store
i buy food i buy flowers i buy bottle of red wine
i organize a script for strong pain killers go to the pharmacy
i get the medication oh only at that point that i realized oh
i must have decided that i'm going to visit him at his house he had given me an idea
where he lives so i drive there and then i get to the boom gates
and um
they call him lolita is here
allows me in and as i'm parking my car he comes out
one of his arms is on a sling
and with his free um he hugs me and places a kiss on my cheek and then i
smile at me now say are we good he smiles
people come and visit and he introduces me as the one who drove into him people are not sure how
to respond to this cut lord long story short
about two weeks after that incident it was mr mandela's funeral
so i i invited him i've been checking on him daily just to find out how he
is most of that first week he was in terrible pain
couldn't even work and this is a man who works for himself
so with mr mandela's funeral and uh we're watching it um i'm watching
it with him from my home over a meal we talk about south africa
we talk about racism
and from that experience
i had an experience of what is it to
be forgiven i know what it is to be offered
fearlessness at a country level we know the power of
forgiveness through the truth and reconciliation
commission where
people would committed serious atrocities of harm
[Music] police soldiers
the law enforcement officials had during the
period just before the first elections in south africa 1994
[Music]
post the elections trc was instituted and
those perpetrators
were brought together with their victims
had to tell the victims
all they had done under the apartheid government
intense intense experience
where the victim and the perpetrator are given an opportunity to find
each other through forgiveness
i think that particular practices gave hope not only
to us as south africans but to the world
i mean our problems are not over as a country by any long short much as we are led by
black government we are stuck in material structures
of white supremacy
the poor in south africa has a black face
and there is corruption ongoing corruption
but i know myself africans we do come together during times of
crisis
so generosity is a foundation for practice of mindfulness and wisdom
for liberation i think we all have opportunities
especially in these times the world is on fire
in many ways we have opportunity to cultivate generosity
i'm going to end this um reflection with words from arjun shah
on virtue and mortality virtue and morality morality are the
mother and father of the dharma growing within us
they provide it with the proper nourishment
and guidance
so sustaining deepening our cultivation of generosity
is the way that we can ourselves each other
in this quest for freedom freeing the heart
from hate creed and delusion
thank you grateful for this opportunity
to see these beautiful [Music] teachings of the buddha
so uh kevin and mark i am happy to take some questions
based on this reflection on generosity
so if anyone has anything that they'd like to ask novita you can either raise your
hand in zoom or post your question in chat and
nolita maybe about 10 minutes of q a okay okay jerry you can go ahead and
unmute yourself um hi um
jerry quigan in toronto uh a bit away from south africa but uh a country i do want
to visit so thank you very much and i guess uh i was interested in your
last words about virtue and morality and the interrelationship with that with
generosity so recently
i was in a situation where
i'm a physician here and the group that was negotiating a lease with the landlord
some of them had their income had gone down and they wanted and another problem was one of the people
were leaving and of course there's a covet epidemic uh going on here as there is in the
world and it's difficult to find replacements so they proceeded to write a letter to the
landlord initially in a general way wanting to um get a reduction in the rent
and um asking the landlord you know out of generosity and the landlord wrote
back uh saying that well because they had said that the one person isn't renewing and
they're going to find it difficult to find a replacement for them and that
people were working at home albeit at a reduced capacity well some it applied to but it really didn't apply
to others and it resented because i was signing the letter that i didn't speak out that it didn't apply to
everyone so i felt that misrepresented to some degree what had been said and then the landlord wrote back and
said well tell me how bad it is and give me a global estimate so the letter never got to be written
but i was then pressured to uh indicate that uh
you know they said well we'll put the specific numbers in about how much people had increases or decreases
and they then proposed a letter which was not uh accurate and i said look i can't
participate in this letter go ahead and send the letter on your own and then they will
they called me said listen uh you know and i was
disgusted that they hadn't uh indicated the specific amounts having said that they would about how
incomes went up and down in the letter and so uh i had just listened to a dharma talk
here in fact at uh uh at redwood city and california via the wonders of the of
the internet and um the person had said you know sometime why do we do mindfulness we do
mindfulness to uh uh develop an ethic so that uh we will speak the truth and
avoid the defilements of greed um and uh delusion
and hate and uh so anyway they wanted to speak with me
and they started the conversation after some niceties saying look uh
you know about the letter and i i said look i said i didn't want to participate
and then they said come on you don't we can put the specific amounts but you actually have to put this amount and then i said
listen you've lost your moral compass this is disgust me and it uh
is uh um the letter as originally composed was uh
dissembling and uh so this of course i was speaking the truth but i guess in
retrospect uh the letter never did get written and the group disbanded and were moving
apart to with the peoples that were there's a group of six and now
there's four and two which is fine but i guess i wondered whether i should have
related it more toward in a generous way look i feel uh that it's um
i would be immoral to sign the letter i feel that this is dissembling instead i projected it on to the other
person and i just wondered whether or not that is uh would have been a more generous
approach so i realize it's very specific and detailed but it's the issue about
um in trying to be generous and also at the same time trying to be moral
getting caught in the approach that one might take to try to be generous
kind but also hardened and courageous when you feel that
a group is going awry
sorry for the launch what's the actual question summarize it for me make it specific so
the specific question would be would you just speak to yourself and not sell someone else that you've lost your
moral compass even though you feel that they did
are you saying is the feeling that you acted in ways that were not ethical
i felt that they did oh they did
by not representing what they said they would by putting the specific amounts in the letter and then calling me to now
ask me to sign the letter which i said i wouldn't and then i i basically very specifically
named them i said this you've lost your moral compass this letter is dissembling and uh
i'm disgusted with you so another way that can help me to understand your
question how does it relate to this buddhist teachings
on training in morality well in the sense that the mindfulness
helps you identify not getting caught up in greed
and so i did it i felt that this was greed
misrepresenting results that would of course not be helpful for them to say that well one person's income went up
i don't have a wise response to this
because it is not necessarily about your own experience of
acting unethically so i'm not sure i'm a bit lost i i
really don't have a wise wise answer to you because i'm not even sure
that i'm understanding the question well i guess the question i'm trying to ask is should you just direct it to
yourself or when you see an ethical behavior in a group should you identify that unethical
behavior and not and and name it or just say listen for me to participate in this it's unethical
rather than tell them that they are unethical to proceed with this approach
even if you believe it socially do you appreciate that in the buddhist teachings
this is training so it is it is not about
shoots or shouldn't sin that way it's not very helpful
so if it's training it means all of us are going to fail
and we do fail to act ethically and yes you are right the practice of
mindfulness allows you to see that it's hard to
not see with a trained mind when you act in ways that are not
ethical and also in this
practice you can only start again it's not about punishment
it is about developing it is about
training so let's leave it there let's leave it to that jewelry
thank you very much but it's helpful thank you thank you okay okay so i guess we have time for
one more so i think miriam is next so miriam if you want to go ahead and unmute yourself
kevin is okay i see there are two if oh okay okay yeah okay okay here i am you're next so
go ahead oh okay um i am i'm rooted now yes okay well um
so nolita i want to thank you for your generosity for sharing all that um i'm from the
congo and i live in california but um i'm really emotional because this is the first time
for me to hear someone from africa doing buddhist teaching so i
don't feel like alone but um and for me my struggle about generosity
sometimes i feel like i'm not kind to myself when i'm not generous to other person like when
i'm specifically like i'm um like i know some people like who are gay
in my community but i know in african culture that's not acceptable and i really feel um sometimes not
generous when other people have strong idea like against that but i don't accept
them not being open-minded and that's the struggle that i have
um yeah and i don't know how to deal with that
what is great miriam is that you see what is going on that you are
struggling so the encouragement would be
to turn towards that experience of pain with kindness
with an attitude of openness and allowing
because this practice of mindfulness is exactly about that it is also about opening the heart
towards ourselves and what we struggle with
that is what i would encourage you to do
because rightly so we are products of our cultures
some of these beliefs are part of our psychology
what mindfulness can help us is to see which of these beliefs
are beneficial and wholesome and which are of these
that are harmful not only to others but also to ourselves
i would encourage you to really be gentle and kind to yourself in meeting with that pain
okay next is jill uh joe you can go ahead and
unmute yourself um thank you very much for taking the
question um i i need to share that that for a very long time uh the concept
of forgiveness there seems to be a very strong divine element to it something
something outside of just myself and that if i had the power to forgive
someone for a great harm that it seems very very bold and outside of
my own entity so my question is can am i misunderstanding the definition
of this word forgiveness or what do you think might be coming from my
sense that it's the ability to forgive is outside of my power
jill when you say it's outside of your power what does that mean
that it when true harm is done i i would not understand the motivation
of that other person or the deep reasons that it it is beyond my
um not capacity but that and perhaps this is just because it's
it's a leftover from training of another religion which was very rooted in the concepts of guilt and only
god has power to do things so maybe that's a part of it but even in my best of buddhist
moments and my best efforts to feel generosity i know i can change my feelings in my
heart about this person who has caused great harm but i feel
that the the true washing away or something so maybe it is
a leftover religious thing belongs to a power greater than mine
so it sounds like you've answered your question then
so i'd encourage you to notice the experience of unforgiveness
and open to that allow that
be with the actual experience of unforgiveness [Music]
not making it right or wrong but just meeting it
with openness
with the sensations of the experience not so much the thoughts the stories
stay with the false sense of unforgiveness
so that's what i would advise as a practice and really being gentle with yourself with
that as well very helpful thank you okay okay
thank you thank you no letha there's a question in chat i don't know if you have time for one more
oh okay yeah let me take it kevin yeah so uh cindy asks nolitha how do you practice
generosity in an environment of racism white supremacy it has been present in this country the
u.s since its beginning and it is very difficult and it is a very difficult thing to forgive and understand
just notice that
in a moment it isn't um
wisdom that's present for me in responding to that
but the fact that um this person is is thinking about forgiveness and
just not knowing how is already a generous place
to be that there is
a desire or a curiosity to what forgiveness might look like in that
situation
stay with the idea of being with
the desire to forgive