so i find that one of the inspiring
topics
in the teachings of the buddha
is the teachings around cheetah so
ci tta which
is often translated in english as mind
or sometimes it
may be in context is also translated as
state of mind
and maybe there's no difference between
mind and state of mind
um the mind here as i said yesterday is
not a thing
it's not like we can see the mind in
some clear
like take a microscope in the brain and
discover where the mind is the mind is
more of a gestalt it's more of a
the sum total of
our mentality of how the mind works
and so it's not a thing and so because
of that
maybe because of that the buddha never
talks about
letting go of the mind he talks about
letting go
of a form of
feelings of perceptions of
mental activities and he also talks
about letting go of
something that we've come to understand
in the west as consciousness
the pali word is vinyana and
it's possible that vinyana it should not
be translated as consciousness
there's a whole history of about maybe
three four hundred years or so three
hundred years maybe of
uh the western use of the word
consciousness
it's kind of a coined in just you know
in relatively
recent times and but it's uh
it's kind of entered into our languages
word consciousness and the idea of it
probably
in a deeper deeper way in the last
hundred years or so
and we take it now as many of us as kind
of second nature's obvious what it is
and and it's often held up in religious
circles spiritual circles meditation
circles as something really ultimate
and there's ideas of cosmic
consciousness ultimate consciousness
different states of consciousness
altered consciousness
and so it gets really there's a lot of
it gets that word consciousness gets a
lot of uh
association a lot of power a lot of
projection a lot of
a lot of expectations and hopes around
this word
and and a lot of people will feel that
somehow
a broad state of consciousness is
ultimate and really profound
and i certainly don't want to diminish
the ultimate feeling of it the
profundity of
of states of consciousness states of
awareness
but what's fascinating is that for the
buddha whatever
that is
if it's vinyana this word that he we
translate his consciousness
he says let go of that let go of that
and um and sometimes he even treats it
as a kind of a problem
clearly it's problematic this vinyana
what we translate as consciousness
and um and
but he never says that about cheetah
about
mind maybe mind should be translated as
consciousness
but consciousness also has a sense in
english of something that knows
and the state of mind i'm not sure
exactly if it's
something that knows but it's a
broad a tone or mood or
feeling or sense of the mind
and sometimes that state of mind can
feel fragile it can feel sluggish it can
feel
agitated contracted and
certainly sometimes the state of mind
doesn't feel good
and in fact some of the some of the
sufferings the dukkha
that this buddhist practice is meant to
alleviate
is experienced as kind of a vice-like
experience of the mind or the heart
where it's really tight irritated
mind is like rough sandpaper perhaps or
um you know the mind you know just feels
just so miserable in our minds
oppressed by it so sometimes the mind
can feel that way
but the mind can also feel the opposite
of that i'm experienced
and um the word cheetah is a very
fascinating word that this is what used
to
to translate his mind because the word
has many
other meanings or homonyms
same sounding words word we would spell
the same way
and but the dictionary for cheetah also
has the word for brightness as a
definition for
cheetah also wondrous or wonderful
and so there's maybe a little kind of
idea that the mind is something really
not exactly in itself
but has it's related to something
wondrous and bright
sometimes the mind is called a luminous
in buddhism teachings of the buddha or
clear
or clean the mind it becomes clean
and not that the mind is inherently any
of these things
because the mind is not a thing that can
be inherent to anything
maybe it's a little bit more like a
hologram or
you know or yeah something that
doesn't quite exist by itself and you
could put your hand right through the
mind if you ever see it
it's not quite not there but it's
it's still a mood feeling a
sense that is can be very powerful very
significant for us
and so significant that as i said
uh often when the mind is suffering it's
really oppressive
when the mind is happy or peaceful or
clear the mind feels quite wondrous
quite bright and open
so um so the uh
and much of the buddhist
path of practice is really is
is done in terms of the mind and that's
sometimes it's done so instead of
personal terms
instead of saying i'm training myself
it's we're training the mind
we're we're developing the mind and
we're liberating the mind and this is i
find fascinating that
plenty of times the buddha doesn't say
that a person gets liberated
rather the mind gets liberated
and some of you might find a little bit
disappointing that find out that you
will never get liberated
and that's not the name of the game
but your mind will get liberated and
your job whatever you
are whatever the you is a job is to help
the mind
experience liberation to be free to
bring it to some kind of
beauty and this this idea that the mind
has the potential for beauty for
luminosity
for brightness for cleanliness i find
phenomenally inspiring and
and but also that my other things even
more inspiring
is that the mind is not a thing because
it's not a thing
it's malleable it's shapeable it uh
it's uh we're never stuck with our mind
might be stuck with our brain
and um in whatever way the brain works
but to the mind we're not stuck with the
mind
it's uh it's the it's kind of the field
within which
our practice uh has its effect its
influence
that as we develop as we develop more
concentration more mindfulness
more letting go more equanimity more
wisdom more strength in the practice
in the mind that the mind begins to
to uh um whatever then we call the mind
to say the mind is
starts to have a wondrous feeling
wonderful
sense that we can experience
and um and one of the things i also find
wonderful about this word cheetah the
way it seems to be used in the suttas
is that it's very personal the
experience of it
so don't go looking at a buddhist text
or listening to a buddhist teacher like
myself
for a definitive definition or exp
or description of what how the mind is
experienced
and then try to make sure that you have
that experience too or feel bad because
you don't have it
the way it's described um
you're the your mind you are shaping
your mind you're
the this this thing that's being
constantly morphed and changed and
shifted
that's something that's arising within
you with all the cause and conditions of
how your
inner life works and how your attention
works and what you focus on
and what you're how you're thinking or
conceiving it's a dynamic thing
so um it's very personal so it's more
discovery of how you experience it
then you have you don't be concerned
about discovering what the right way to
experience the mind is
or what the right mind is or how the
mind is supposed to be
but you can as we feel the mind become
aware of a mind that
is has an ouch to it
and a mind that has an ah
and this very technical terms in gil
language
ouch and ah is meant to kind of give us
lots of room to not get caught up in the
details and
try to be right or wrong or it's a very
simple thing ah that
that's an ouch that the state of the
mind doesn't feel good that's not
doesn't that's
it's and now or this feels good
and the direction of buddhist practice
is in the direction of the ah
direction of the beautiful mind in
whatever way that you
define or experience or see beauty
luminous mind clear mind clean mind
spacious mind peaceful mind
so it takes a while
and i'm not still you don't have to kind
of be in a hurry to experience some of
the
wondrous ways the mind can be
experienced
but as the anapanasati develops and as
we become calmer and more settled
going through the steps especially after
step eight where we're pivoting
as mental activity relaxes it means
we're not so fixated on the what's what
we're thinking about and wanting and
but we're beginning to rest back into
the
into the easy chair of the mind resting
back
and just allowing and feeling and
sensing
the overall state of the mind and
breathing with that
breathing in experiencing the mind
breathing out experiencing the mind
so thank you and we'll continue tomorrow