so welcome to this meditation session
and a valuable perspective on mindfulness meditation
is that it is the enactment of freedom
where expressing in in mental action our capacity to be free
so when we decide to be mindful of something something as simple as mindful of the breathing we are making a choice
when the mind wanders off in thought and you're mindful enough to and
choose to be mindful rather than wandering off in thought when you're mindful enough to choose
beginning again with your breathing that's an expression of freedom to
choose what often happens is that
we will what comes along with that choice and which obscures the freedom is ideas
that i didn't do it well enough i need to do it better i should try harder i should
strain push make more effort all these other you know that i'm a
lousy meditator or someone else is doing it better than me or the real thing is something different
and all these ideas and all these get carried along and all these shoulds
get carried along and obscures the fact that for one little moment
there was an ex an enactment of freedom the freedom to of where our attention
can be focused and uh and we and so to appreciate that
moment that initial moment that moment that's independent and free of all the thoughts
agendas fears that we might have all the ideas of self
that kind of come along with it obscures the fact that we have just
enacted a small little moment of freedom
and if then we choose to investigate to explore to look
more closely at the experience there also
it's an enactment of freedom it's a freedom from our preoccupations
from all our judgments and reactivity
so to be first to be mindful is a little freedom from preoccupation from being
pulled into a world where we're trapped or not free
of thoughts ideas fantasies judgments just simple be mindful of this
that freedom is enacted a little bit more strongly in the initial moment we decide to look
more carefully and that's often obscured the freedom because
we think that we have to be successful there's it's a it's an exam and we're going to get it
tested if we you know how well we discover what we're going to what's there and there's some magic key that we have to
see and and i have to really strain now and look and analyze and
all these other ideas that obscure the simplicity of the moment of looking
more carefully looking what is this that's an enactment of
freedom and as we see more clearly the choices we make become
an enactment of freedom the choice not to strain as we look at our
breathing as we meditate on breathing the choice to
turn our attention from the breath to look at how we're being critical of ourselves
in the criticalness lost in that there's no freedom but in the moment of turning around to
look at it a choice to look at it rather than just going along with it is also an
enactment of freedom to see what is helpful and not helpful
healthy and not healthy and to choose the healthy is an enactment of freedom
and so to begin appreciating no the little hints the little hints of freedom
in mindfulness investigation in effort
and as we appreciate it we can that appreciation
is a pleasure that appreciation can be
can give rise to a contentment oh this is the path to freedom
i'm on a good i'm discovering something helpful here
they can give rise to joy the joy of freely
being aware of our experience
and then there can be even affection for the difficult things because we're
aware of them with our freedom
so as these seven factors of awakening develop first they develop as little hints
little as little intuitions of how they're there but as we do this meditation perhaps you
can sit here now with an intuition the hints a recognition
of how you enact freedom in choosing to be mindful investigate
make effort and the freedom that's found before all
the complexities we bring to those things in their simplicity
so to sit to assume your meditation posture
and some of you probably didn't recognize that in assuming your posture you were expressing your freedom
there is a choice free will choice to now adjust your posture
take a posture
and then to gently close your eyes
and as you're sitting here with the eyes closed
what is the simplest freest way that you can allow yourself to be aware
of your body
a choice a free will choice if you want to take it
to become aware of how your body is right now
before preferences before likes and dislikes
just aware
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
as you exhale relax into the posture
deep breath in exhale relax the whole body as if the posture
relaxing is a homecoming to this posture
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale softening the muscles of your forehead
and temple and if they don't soften or relax
maybe you can the awareness of it can be spacious and open
as you exhale softening around the eyes
the cheeks
the jaws
as you exhale maybe there can be a relaxation and
opening in this the back of your neck
the vertebrae just below the skull can they soften and relax
softening as you exhale around the
collarbones
and then releasing the shoulders
as you exhale relaxing the chest
the heart center
and then softening the belly
in the lower half of your torso
lower back the hip area hip joints
and down your legs
and then gently calmly
become mindful of your breathing
and can you as you're mindful of breathing
feel or perceive how the choice to do so
if it's your own is it small little enactment of freedom
freedom from the tyranny of thinking
just mindful for a moment
receptive to the inhalation receptive to the movements of the body
as you breathe in
and is there some way that that simple receptive awareness
have qualities of freedom independence
for a few moments maybe awareness free of being hijacked by thoughts and
ideas and judgments
simple awareness receptive to breathing
as you exhale allowing the exhale and allowing awareness
is there some freedom and awareness that is so simple it just allows the
experience to be there
even if you are thinking and judging
maybe part of the awareness of breathing can feel like there's freedom there
a silent freedom spacious open
and very gently exploring the experience of breathing
feeling it more fully more clearly not dramatically so just a little more
and in that choice to explore and feel it more fully
there's also an enactment of freedom
enactment to be aware rather than being pulled into thinking
and if you find yourself thinking and you choose to begin again with your
breathing
that's an enactment of effort which might also contain
some freedom freedom of choice freedom of where your effort is placed
if while you're inhaling you choose to be with the inhale
but then when you exhale the choice becomes to be with the exhale
it's a simple enactment of liberated
effort
into whatever degree however small
you can feel that your practice enacts
freedom even if you keep getting caught and
thought and preoccupied in it
even so is there some little corner of awareness
of effort will you feel your freedom
and to appreciate that to feel the pleasure of that
maybe even the joy of that
appreciating our freedom is also an enactment of freedom
feeling the joy
of liberated mindfulness
and then it doesn't matter so much what we're mindful of
because we delight in mindfulness itself
we delight in investigation there's a delight in this effort or
choice that has qualities of freedom in it
and there's freedom in enjoying
the joy of freedom as we practice mindfulness
no matter what we're mindful of there can be a delight
in that freedom
if you find yourself caught up in thought or caught up in anything
if you allow yourself to clearly know that that's the case
there is some quality of freedom in that clear knowing
see if you can build on that freedom expand that freedom
by doing it again and again
in the last 10 minutes of this sitting perhaps you can feel your way
to stay close to where you're free
the freedom which is closely related to simplicity of being
nothing complicated
recognizing the simple freedom in choosing to be
aware this simple freedom and seeing what's
happening the freedom to en to appreciate to enjoy
the simplicity of being that's related
to our freedom
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
imagine what it's like for what would be like for you
to be resting in the simplicity of being
resting in a freedom of being
where you're not caught up in your reactions your judgments your criticalness
not cut up in the shoulds and shouldn'ts sense of obligations and
just resting in simple freedom where you're allowed to be free you're
allowed to be simple and present
and in this way imagine that you encounter another person
who's also free a person who has no agendas and
has no needs at the moment
is not living in their judgments or preferences likes and dislikes
this person is also at rest at ease in their own simplicity of being
at ease in their freedom
and to sit with this person you and your freedom and they and their
freedom
freedom where it makes it safe to have good will love
care friendliness for the other
and perhaps you can open your heart safely fully
a meeting of hearts each of you independent and free
without any need from the other content and to sit with each other
appreciating each other
and how much can you open your heart your good will your friendliness and
this circumstance and now imagine that you can do that
with others who are not so free people who come with agendas and
preferences and needs imagine that you can rest in your
simplicity of being even then
and without them necessarily knowing
to continue with your good will your friendliness
choosing freely choosing
goodwill and may it be that we learn
through this practice to open our good will to all beings
equally while being rooted in our capacity for
freedom freedom that allows us to return to a
simplicity of being
so that we might genuinely feel and think may it be that all beings be happy
may it be that all beings be safe
may it be that all beings be peaceful
may it be that all beings be free
and may i in my capacity for freedom
help make this possible at least radiating for me
comes good will and safety for others
may all beings be happy
you