getting back into the swing of things after not having been here for a number of weeks it's great to be back
and maybe i'll say a few words about what we can expect going forward
excuse me that is oh hold on to second
okay so going forward starting next monday
gail franstall and i will be sharing this monday night at 7 30 time slot
and it will be open the meditation hall will be open
so it'll be a combination will be both on youtube and live in person
and how we're doing live in person right now is individuals sign up
so that to attend and just so that we have a control over the amount of people here
so that we can maintain some social distancing
and they ask that you upload a vaccination card and once that's done then you can sign
up for monday nights and sunday mornings i think they're the limit is about 25
people so i'm i'm looking around the room right now there's little uh
blue tape on the carpet where the individuals can sit and so that
there's plenty of space and maybe just to for those of you who have been here to
imc just to give you a little uh frame of reference 25 people
is a little bit less than half than if this room were filled so just to give
you a little sense of that so perhaps i'll be seeing some of you
in person but otherwise we'll still be here on youtube
okay okay
so a really warm welcome really warm welcome to everybody
what a pleasure it is to be here
yeah so we'll begin with a guided meditation
in general i don't like to have too many words during these meditations but just
an encouragement to maybe incline the mind a certain way
so taking an alert posture
a poster that reflects your intention to meditate
to be present
as well as having some ease as well as having some softness rather
than too much stiffness
and then checking in with the body what is it like to be
in this body at this moment
can we sit and know we're sitting
maybe the body is a little bit tired a little bit restless
however it might be can we make room can we allow
the experience as best we can
and allowing our attention to rest on the sensations of breathing
without pouncing on the breath without ignoring the breath
but with some gentle noticing
gentle in the sense that we're not grabbing on
but we are connecting with the breath
the movements of the body associated with breathing
connecting with feeling the expansion the contraction
of breathing
we can characterize our experience
of when we're not on the breath this may be either being pulled towards
something else that seems desirable
or being pushed away from something that's not desirable
this push and pull
it can be helpful to just acknowledge oh yes there's a pull
towards something i want
or i push away from something i don't want
sometimes just noticing that movement push or pull
can help weaken the pushing or pulling
make it a little bit easier to come back to the breath
we might notice but it's the habit to do a little more
pushing or a little bit more pulling
are we moving towards something we want or away from something we don't want
when we're no longer being mindful of the sensations of breathing
it can be empowering to notice our habits of mind
you don't have to make a big story
it's just a habit of mind
this idea of noticing
whether the mind is pulled towards something or pushed
away is just a tool to help us
understand our minds the habits of mind
a way for us to tune into the movements of the mind
so that we might understand ourselves better
but understand the way this particular mind works or
likes to work
so then we might be alert to some of the ways in which we might not
be seen clearly if we're always being pulled
towards something maybe that means we're
not noticing fully what's present here in the moment
there's this idea that something better is out there or if we do feel like we have to get
away from something is there a way we might look to see if
there is a sense of security or safety or stability already here
and whatever we discover is perfectly fine perfectly fine
the practice is to just notice
and as best we can do not have a big story about it
just notice this is the habits of this mind
so that we can have some more ease
and if we have more ease we can show up in the world
in a way that supports everybody ourselves
and those we come in contact with
so maybe this practice that we share this practice that we do
may it be for the benefit of all beings everywhere
[Music]
so welcome welcome it's nice to practice together
today i'm joined by my good friend who's here in the hall with me
the two of us we have this whole hall together and all of you there on the other side
of that camera
so with this practice you might have heard or sometimes um
i know that i've said in different settings that part of this practice the goal of
practice maybe we might say is to see things as they really are
yata buddha as they really are kind of like that the truth of the moment
not how we're wish that they were or that we're imagining how they might be but how they really are
and the tradition tells us that the way things really are
are impermanent unsatisfactory and without a self at the center of it all
aneecha
and then the idea is and the teachings are and certainly this has been my experience
that when there is this recognition of the truth of how things are
impermanent unsatisfactory without a steady self at the center of
everything then there's a just this natural letting go
that arises it just doesn't seem just doesn't make sense to hold on
it's less maybe a logic and more just uh recognition like yeah it just doesn't
make sense to hold on and so there's a letting go
and this letting go can bring greater freedom so we might ask well why is it if
there's the truth of impermanence not self and suffering why can't i see it all the time why do
we have to do all this meditation and dharma talks and study and all this work
well maybe i'll say a little bit more because we also have this idea of
the four noble truths maybe some different truths here
the truth is suffering but also the truth of its cause its cessation
and the way the path leading to this cessation and these have this title noble truth so
these feel like really important truths and certainly they are foundational to the buddhist teachings and buddhist
practice and these truths overlap with
some of those other truths about anita anata dukkha
impermanence not self suffering
so we might begin to think that okay this idea about truth is an integral part is an important part of practice
and recently i've heard in a number of different settings also this um
story i'll say or that the tradition holds that you know the buddha had
countless lives past lives before he became a
buddha and he's reborn and all these different venues or settings
and it is said that despite these hundreds thousands untold number i don't know how many i don't know if maybe the
nobody knows that uh the buddha never told a lie throughout all these rebirths
because truth is so important that even though he might have
done some other transgressions he didn't tell a lie i've heard this a number of times
including just recently just as a little aside i'll say it's not
that itself is not actually true that there is a uh jataka story
that jataka jataka 3 42 that um
when the bodhisattva so before he was a buddha in that particular life he was a monkey
and uh he was just deceived a crocodile in that story so just as a little aside
uh it turns out that uh that buddha in one of his past lives according to these jadaka tales in fact
did lie but nevertheless the tradition believes and holds that it's so important
that they have this tradition that he didn't lie so we might be led to believe that this
practice is about getting to the truth and certainly that feels good right that
we want to know what the truth is we don't want to be following lies or something like this
and maybe we even have this idea it's the truth with a capital t
the truth but this type of thinking lends itself to the idea that there's a
truth that's out there somewhere and
that we have to discover it and find it and it's certainly the practice is about that but
one way that if we were to do this it can leave us feeling maybe
disconnected that there's some great truth out there there's me over here and
out over there is something that i'm supposed to discover
and this is a legitimate way to consider buddhist philosophy certainly but in this tradition we were
really highlighting practice
so the truth is naturally necessarily subjective
it's the truth of the things as we experience them so we can try to say how things are out
there quote unquote but when the mind always makes sense of
the world through perceptions and through the lenses of conditioning
so my experience at any moment is not going to be exactly the same as anybody else's experience
and in this early buddhism the buddha is not concerned with
the stat that we could say the ontological status of things that is to
say whether how things exist independent of any humans interacting
with them instead this practice really focuses on
the truth of our experience the truth of the moment in fact we might even say that
mindfulness practice it was really a practice to help us tune into and align with
this moment the truth of this moment the reality of this moment
so instead of approaching this idea of truth from this idea that it's something to be had out
there somewhere but instead turn it around
think about it's more as the truth
as an antidote to
the self-delusion as a way to help us see our experience clearly
help us see ourselves clearly
we might say that the practice is really just a commitment to look deeply
into whatever is arising and i appreciate very much matthew brent
silver sometime last year he gave this talk about this idea and
he highlighted that when we first begin the question or when we're beginning practice
we could say the question is what is it like to be human
what is it actually like not what do we think it should be or how we
imagine it by might be or how we have been told it should be but what is
it what is the truth of this human's experience
and in this way practice is to like stop fooling ourselves or wishing that things were different but to really see
that truth truthfully about our own minds and we can ask ourselves are we really
seeing ourselves truthfully
instead of trying to go find the truth out there are we really seeing ourselves clearly
and this is what practice is about
so when we look in this way we might discover
perhaps to our that we're doing a lot of rationalizing
rationalizing our habits rationalizing our preferences
maybe this is one of the humbling aspects of practice is to see how much of our lives our rationalizations of our
conditions and our preferences was it until matthew kind of highlighted
this i that i really saw it but i think i have to agree
of course through our conditioning we have certain ways in which we
like to be seen or experiences we like to have we have preferences
and often we're just kind of maybe not like noticing some of those maybe
unflattering things that we might see in ourselves instead we might rationalize oh yeah but
i'm just that way because we have some we have a reason of course
we have a reason but there might be a way in which we
don't really see all that's going on in our minds maybe we have this idea that we're like scientists
and that scientists have a hypothesis like i wonder what's in the mind and
then they conduct experiments to see and they conduct these experiments not
necessarily knowing what they're going to find they
set up something like a clinical trial or something like this right
and then when the experiment is finished they look to see what the results are
so many of us might think that we're doing this with our own minds our own experience
but i kind of chuckled when i heard matthew say they said that what happens is that many of us instead
of being scientists or more like lawyers in the sense that lawyers have a
conclusion that they need to have and then they find the data to support
it so we all have as conclusions about ourselves
this ideas that we think about ourselves i'm a good person i'm a bad person i'm a
kind person i'm not so kind i'm generous i'm selfish
whatever these ideas that we have they're all about kind of like this self
and our ideas about ourselves and so often of course when we look in
our minds when we look in our experience we are
seeing data that supports the way that we think
about ourselves whether that way we think about it is flattering or unflattering
so we're not maybe seeing the truth of our selves
the entirety of ourselves perhaps and maybe we would say
specifically we often don't see our the expression of some of these unwholesome roots or defilements
not so keen on this word defilements it sounds uh pejorative and and to be sure
that unwholesome roots are not fantastic i should say but it is part of
what it means to be human is to have these
these unwholesome roots these unskillful roots and the buddha recognized this
and he gave this simile of the cloth as one way to describe it and it goes
like this suppose a cloth were defiled and stained
and a dyer someone who was with some that would die things
and a dyer dipped it in some dye or other whether blue or yellow or red or
carmine it would look poorly dyed and impure in color
why is that because of the impurity of the cloth
so too when the mind is defiled soiled we might say
an unhappy outcome might be expected so the buddha is pointing out that as
long as we have these in our minds then you know the outcome is not going to be
as if it weren't there of course and so to maybe um
speak a little bit more specifically the buddha gives this long list of these
unwholesome roots or you can say imperfections that stain the mind
and i've looked at a number of different translators looking at this long list
and it's fun to see how different they all are on some of these words because they're not so common and
maybe we don't quite know how to translate them into english so to hold these loosely but to give you
a sense of what's being pointed out here
so this list of 16 we could maybe say calaises
defilements and wholesome states unbalanced greed
anger resentment contempt spite
envy meanness deceit treachery
stubbornness rivalry conceit arrogance
vanity longing and carelessness
sometimes if we were to see something like this in our minds this can be this
dance between revelation and denial oh i see oh i see i have this quality no i
don't or you know it can be a sense of a flash
or a flicker i see this although i don't see it maybe i do have this maybe i don't
it can also be the opposite right where we can see that we have some of these states and then we just
grab on to it and take on a new identity i'm the one
who is filled with envy i'm the one who has
rivalry whatever it might be
so many of you know that we can simplify this list to three
greed hatred and delusion peace unhols the roots of all other of
the defilements and
maybe we can say that delusion is a way in which kind of
helps us not see our greed and our hatred and all the different forms that it takes
so truth like this practice of working with truth can be an antidote to
self-delusion there's a way in which we can really
understand ourselves better not so that we can beat ourselves up better
not so that we can finally find that data that proves that we're a bad person or something like
this just so that we can wash this cloth
that has some stains on it
and so i've one way that we could say that maybe we
could play with this analogy that there's some uh pre-treatments before we
do some of this washing like um i used there used to be this
product i'm not sure if it still exists called like spray and wash right you could like put it on the cloth before
you put the cloth into the into the laundry into the wash
so some things that might help with some pre-treatment of if we find some of these states in
our minds loving kindness practice because it takes a lot of warmth
care and compassion not to mention courage
but warmth care and compassion to do this work this mindfulness
and to really see how things are that sometimes we do have flickers of anger or flickers of
conceit it doesn't make us a bad person it makes us human
and part of this practice is just to help you know loosen up some of these
stains some of the ways in which the beauty of the heart and mind might have
a little bit of specks some soil on them so loving kindness practice
compassion practice any of the hard practices fabulous pre-treatment to help these
come out another one concentration practice
and i don't know how this works exactly but if the mind has an opportunity to
settle and we have an opportunity to feel some
well-being to feel some happiness to feel some
contentment even if it's just a little bit that's a way in which helps
these everything else to come out in the wash so to speak
so one way to work with these kalashas these defilements these
unwholesome roots is with loving-kindness practice concentration practice as well as
mindfulness practice and it can be helpful to work with just
one at a time instead of feeling like oh my gosh i see everything there that whole list
of 16 i've maybe at times have seen it or maybe not too right
but maybe just to choose one i'm gonna notice rivalry
just when does that show up for me is it a habit of mind
maybe it says something that i learned long ago and is no longer helpful just doesn't make sense anymore
so maybe to just choose one if you notice it and just notice how it shows up in your daily
life it shows up in meditation with
a warm heart right this is so key this is so key
right this practice is not about beating ourselves up it's not about
making ourselves feel bad but freedom
getting this cloth clean is freedom complete freedom
and it is possible so we can just work with these a little
bit as we see them in a warm-hearted way
in the same way that we're looking at some of these defilements we might we should and can
also ask are we acknowledging what is wholesome we also acknowledging what is wholesome
right the practice is to be what is it like to be a human
humans have wholesome qualities too so sometimes we might just
not be seeing the unwholesome sometimes we might not be seeing the wholesome
so just to acknowledge that there's both sides and the practice is to see maybe the breadth
of our experiences
and to keep compassion as a companion in this investigation
and i'd like to share this poem by rosemary trauma i appreciate rosemary trauma very much
her poetry his touching is beautiful
in a way that i and i appreciate maybe not for everybody but this is a poem that she wrote on january
24th 2021 less than a year ago and it's called choosing truth
and it goes like this and
if i find i'd rather not meet the truth
then i can notice the little girl in me the one who hides in the closet when she
is afraid the one who plays dead the one who ends all her stories with
happily ever after and i can choose to love her
i don't need to drag her out or force her to look or to tell her that sometimes the villain wins in the end
instead i can remind the rest of me how alive i feel
when i meet it all when i choose to enter the day eyes open
ears open hands open and let the world in
that is how on this day when i know the truth of how cruel
we humans can be i can lean into that pain
at the same time i watch the sky turn pink
behind the white aspen and feel the cold air kiss my cheeks
my breath rising in visible prayer meeting difficult truths
i walk right through
this is practice i think this is a beautiful way to describe practice
you discover things that are uncomfortable difficult about ourselves about others about life
and we don't beat ourselves up i appreciate very much that rosemary
trauma writes instead i can remind the rest of me how alive i
feel when i meet it all there's a way in which if we're not
telling the truth or seeing the truth or holding the truth intentionally there's a way in which
there's a secret somewhere that we're trying to keep away from others keep away from
ourselves and when we hold secrets there's a
little bit of a dead name maybe something that we're trying to
lose contact with but rosemary right rosemary trauma
writes i don't need to drag her out or force her to look or tell her that sometimes the villain wins
in the end instead i can remind the rest of me how
alive i feel when i meet it all when i choose to enter the day
eyes open ears open hands open
and let the world in
if i find i'd rather not meet the truth then i can notice the little girl in me
the one who hides in the closet when she is afraid the one who plays dead the one who ends
all her stories with happily ever after and i can choose to love her
so truth as an antidote to self-delusion
maybe love is another antidote to self-delusion
maybe if we have love and compassion it's a way in which there can be an opening
to see that which might be difficult to see to hold what might be difficult to hold
so we might have all these different ideas about truth and we might have this idea that we want to see or find
the truth with a capital t and this belief that we're going to find it somewhere and it's going to make us
happy we may not know what truth with a capital t is
but we do know what honesty is and that's what this practice is asking
of us to be with our experience
to see the truth of our experience and to be as honest as we can
bathed in care bathed in love bathed in compassion
bathed in warmth to increase the capacity to see
everything and use a little pre-treatment on any cloth that has a stain that needs to be
cleaned so in this way we can show up for our
lives we can show up for others we can show up in this world that is
benefit and support for all beings
everywhere thank you