so good day
and it's a happy occasion to be here with you all and
have the opportunity to meditate together and for me to teach it's a privilege and
i appreciate the opportunity thank you and um we have this
wondrous wonderful mind chitta ci tta
that begins to stand out and highlight the calmer the the mind becomes
so when the mind is agitated it means it's caught up in its concerns its preoccupations its
agitation it's um and uh often then it's the more agitated
the mind is the more it's swirling around in its thoughts ideas
feelings and it's the subset it's a particular aspects of the mind that the
mind is focusing on thinking for example or emotions
ideas memories and what we're doing as we switch to being mindful of the mind is to
no longer have the preferential attention to
particular corners of the mind particular activities of the mind
and so as the activities of the mind get quieter and calmer
what's available then in highlight and over time as meditation deepens it
becomes stronger and stronger is there's becomes a felt sense
of the mind as a whole and exactly what that is is not so you know so important
what's important is your own way of experiencing it some people might prefer to use the word
awareness to represent the mind as a whole the the total gestalt of how things are
operating the the the sum
the total is greater than the sum of the parts so there's something that
marvelous that happens as we open up more widely and fully to the mind
and in this early tradition there's sometimes sometimes his mind stands out so much in
highlight that it's anthropomorphized and thermopromorphism sometimes seen as
a person as if a person can talk to their mind or work with the mind
train the mind it's never seen as the self and this movement of selfing of
positing feelings sensing itself and this early tradition is seen as just another form of mental activity
that can also be calmed down put to rest and as it does so that also frees up the
space for feeling the mind as a whole
or sometimes it's called the state of the mind or the mood inner mood the general mood of in our
mentality or the heart mind and it begins to shift
the orientation of how we live our life and rather than focusing on the
particular concerns we have it gives us the opportunity to care for and i love this word care
compassionately care for lovingly care for the quality of the mind or the quality
of the heart the quality of this inner life that we have that's what's the gestalt the totality of it
that here in the tradition is called chitta mind and we can
begin settling the mind opening the mind
pleasing the mind bringing joy happiness to the mind
and liberating the mind and it's such a phenomenally satisfying thing to switch
from the details and concerns of our life to the present moment experience of mind
and caring for that so with that as an introduction
i will take a assume a meditation posture
and gently close your eyes
and with the eyes closed and feeling your
body from the inside out taking a few long slow deep breaths
deep deep breaths really as if you haven't breathed for a while and finally you get to really fill yourself
with oxygen and then exhale a delightful long
exhale ah here you are
here you are breathing in and breathing out
and then letting your breathing return to normal for a few minutes few moments and just
sit here and feel your body maybe those deep breaths have had a
influence effect on your body
maybe its body is a little more there's more sensations to feel
maybe you want to adjust your posture a little bit more
and then we'll do a little breathing exercise
that maybe will help the deeper relaxation maybe at relaxation deep inside
the heart the mind the cheetah
so it involves taking a deeper breath but only about three
quarters full but only as far as as comfortable
and then when you get to the top of that that particular in-breath hold the in-breath a little bit don't
exhale right away and hold it for as long as it's comfortable
and then as you release it as you begin the exhale see if that occasion can be one of a
deep relaxation letting go it's almost like the holding
of the breath heightens the awareness of your body your insides
that there's more available to relax as you exhale
so taking a three-quarters comfortable deep in-breath holding it as long as
it's comfortable and then exhaling with a deep relaxation
and it might be that the exhales can be longer than usual
maybe as you exhale you also relax the mind itself
softening opening expanding the mind
and even if you can't relax the mind
as you exhale feel whatever softness that's in the mind
feel whatever transparent boundaries
there is to the mind
and if it's comfortable continue a little bit longer and now at the end of the exhale
pause a bit just as long as it's comfortable before you inhale
so there's a rhythm of inhaling pausing exhaling
pausing that brings a heightened awareness to
your body and mind and a greater ability to relax
settle in
and then let your breathing now return to normal no special effort to pause or hold
and take a few moments to feel and sense your body again
and if there you are some memory areas of your body you can easily relax
so softening around the face
releasing the shoulders softening the
belly
and if the relaxing you've done settling in you've done brings any sensations of pleasure
or well-being breathe with a pleasure breathe with a
sense of well-being the tingling the warmth
the glow the
dancing energy
and allow the thinking mind to become quieter
letting go of thoughts so you can have more energy more attention to feel
the body breathing with the well-being
that might be here however small it might be
and you might become aware of how the mind attention is predisposed
to focus on particular things concerns preoccupations
and if so then you're experiencing a limited aspect of your whole
wondrous mind
without necessarily letting go of your concerns can you expand your awareness to include
more of your interior life more of your quality of inner life your mind your
heart this state of your mind state of your inner being
something that inclusive because everything that happens happens
within the mind
and then breathe with the mind breathe through it
almost as if each inhale fills the mind with the sensations of
inhale each exhale relaxes
and expands the mind settles it
becoming aware of the global mind the global sense of in the
state of mind mood of the mind
the quality of the mind over all
it could include the space of the mind
the space that the mind fills
so you're not focusing on any particular part of the mind
[Music]
a state which has no
boundaries
and if it has a location this mind of yours
chances are that there's a little feeling of contraction or gathering together
that gives that feeling
as you exhale relax that gathering together
soften let the mind rest
out into the vast space all around
mind with no walls no boundaries
mind that involves no conscious effort
that is just there here
um
if there is suffering suffering has a
location the mind
includes all that is beyond the edges of that suffering
that's wider bigger
and to relax outward beyond the
suffering that whatever suffering there is
is held in this wide field
of open mind open awareness that has no
edges
breathing in outward breathing
that goes outwards towards the edges beyond the edges
all inclusive
wide broad open
resting into the open space
and as we come to the end of the sitting
with whatever way that you can rest in open space
without the mind getting quickly fixated or preoccupied on any particular thing
just open and receptive allowing things just to flow
through you nothing stops nothing is held onto
and staying that way the best you can bring to mind
some person that you might encounter today
personally or through some medium of communication phone or computer
and imagine that you are quietly allowing that person to exist
as they are without you fixating on it and anything
as if they too can be held in the vast open mind
in that way providing them to get providing them with a gift
that they can be just the way they are without any interference from you with
your desires aversions agendas
reactions allowing someone to be themselves
in the vast open space of your mind
and in doing so imagining that you're doing so does that give you a different
reference point for good will for love
friendliness care even respect for this other person
and if it does no maybe wish them well
may this person be happy
may this person be safe
may this person be peaceful at ease
may this person be free certainly free of my attachments
and may it be that other people that you encounter and other people that you have
some contact with or think about today that they also benefit
from this meditation practice you've done today
may all beings be happy may all beings be at ease
may all beings be free
and may we contribute to that
uh
you