so good morning everyone and on this thanksgiving day thank you all
for being here and participating in this um
daily meditation we've been doing many of you have been coming for a long time and i'm
grateful for that and grateful that we've been able to have this
time together and share the dharma together and and the practice and
and uh certainly i felt very much the large sense of
community of people participating and i hope that all of you also will feel some sense of that you're actually
participating in a in a maybe a loose community but a definitely
a dharma community sharing something wonderful and perhaps
also together bringing a good influence into our world
so
one of the characteristics of being free freedom is
being one of the goals of buddhism is to not be
limited in an unhealthy way that our life force our
ability to be present our ability to love to
be with others be with ourselves is not limited by
having embracing ourselves life or closing down or withdrawing
or identifying too strongly with whatever is happening including our
discomfort including our comfort and identifying strongly with our
desires and our aversions our preferences
so that something inside can feel open and unlimited
and one of the things we're exploring in meditation whether it's consciously or
unconsciously is how to be have a sense of
no limitations nothing that defines us nothing
restricts us nothing diminishes us including any desire or wish to be
unlimited to become and identify with being unlimited
and to prefer that so it's a little bit you know
so there is a little protection from overdoing this stuff and this delightful thing of being being
not limited not restricted so
to be able to sit here and breathe with what is
is symbolic or represents just being with what is
but breathing through it breathing with it being mindful of it
where the mindfulness itself and maybe that may be the breathing
is not defined by whatever comfort or discomfort is
happening so assuming a
a posture which will support you
confidently
in being open not collapsing
not diminishing yourself in any way but not puffing yourself up a posture
that maybe has some stability and strength
as if the posture
can manage fine with whatever happens the posture has a as if the posture has
a capacity to hold whatever goes on for us
without us collapsing to it
in lowering your gaze softening your focus
and perhaps gently closing the eyes
and to then gently
maybe slowly as it's as it's comfortable take a few long slow deep breaths
one of the functions of the deep inhales is to stretch up against and
through maybe places of tension and holding
in the body places where we are kept limited
gently almost as if you enjoy it take a deep breath stretching into the
chest the shoulders especially places that are still
held or tight
and then on the exhale to relax
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and with a normal breathing whatever that is for you right now
imagine that your breathing
moves freely through whatever way you feel uncomfortable or
any way that you feel contracted or
tense agitated in your body or your mind
imagine that your breathing can just move through that gently
like a self that soothes whatever is there
perhaps relaxing as you exhale
and then settling down to just breathing experiencing how the body
feeling how the body experiences breathing
and letting breathing be at the middle of everything
as if maybe you're doing some very your person is doing very fine work
even even with the lots of activity in the room around you
you get completely absorbed in the work you're doing something that's delicate and careful it
needs to be carefully done watch repair or
surgery
and let yourself imagine that the breathing is the delicate work
that you give yourself over to
partly so you're not defined or reactive to anything else
leave everything else alone
let everything else take care of itself and for these minutes
breathe mindfully that's the work
at hand for now and if other things arise that are strong
stay with your breathing that's where the work is
but breathe through or breathe with this other thing
after these minutes of meditating is there some
better quality capacity you have for being simply present for yourself
and search around inside for the your capacity for simple presence
open available to experience
not asserting yourself and not distracted
but here in this with a simple
attentiveness
maybe an attention that's embodied embodied
mindfulness
and how might you call upon this capacity
today how about you let it
come to the forefront so that you are not limited
by circumstances
and as we come to the end of the sitting may our capacity for simple presence
simple attention embodied attentiveness
allow us to listen deeply to others
to receive others in our hearts
to make room for our friendliness our good will
it may it be that this day and all days
and we spend time actively
expressing good will and well-wishing for others and for the world
and to do so in a way that it's at the same time
a good thing for our own hearts
that it's medicine for ourselves as well so it's not a duty to have good will
it's more like a
a healthy momentum arising from ourselves
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
and may our capacity for simple attentiveness
unrestricted unlimited attentiveness
contribute to these things
happening may we be a force
of goodness in this world
[Music]
to learn how to be wise about discomfort
one of the interesting questions around discomfort
is to consider what is the function of discomfort what's the message certainly as we asked
yesterday but what is the what is the function how does it what does it do for us
and is a function healthy for us or not healthy supportive or not supportive
and certainly there are times when we feel uneasy about something that we should feel uneasy about it feels like
it's not a healthy thing or ethical thing or something or safe thing
and so the function of our discomfort is to let us know sometimes before we're consciously aware
that oh there's something here to to be careful for but sometimes the function of discomfort
is to have us hold back have us
restrict ourselves or limit ourselves or close down not because there's any real danger out
there but because we're uncut we are uncomfortable and easy about
things which are good things that are healthy that somehow we assume there's
threats where there is no threat or we project
uh we bring along with us a concept definition of who we are
and who we need to be that maybe it's not necessary but it's the definition the self-concept
which is we feel oh it's going to be threatened here or there's a discomfort because we
for what we want or what we don't want or we don't want to be we want to be seen by others in a
certain way and we're you know so there's there's ways in which then
when we're uncomfortable we hold ourselves in check
and in times when we actually
limit ourselves unnecessarily where it's actually we don't avail ourselves of the goodness
the wonderfulness the potential that's here
and one of the ways that's kind of dramatic is when we feel uncomfortable about
love uncomfortable about warm feelings and warm-heartedness that we might have
or that others have uh we might feel like you know threatened
by people's warm-heartedness or feel like we're obligated to return it or do people favor or
or we just we're uncomfortable with intimacy uncomfortable with kindness sometimes some people are
or we're uncomfortable with expressing kindness expressing love expressing care and some people feel very uncomfortable
with expressing gratitude even though it's thanksgiving
saying thank you to others or expressing our appreciation of others
and sometimes we're uncomfortable simply stay to stay present without saying anything without actively expressing
love or friendliness or or gratitude but we're afraid of
just staying fully present aware receiving whatever is happening in the room
when what's happening is good people are being happy and celebrating and
maybe people are appreciating you and so then we don't feel that
we don't allow ourselves to to to be with it
so one of the interesting issues around the word comfort and
discomfort is that the word comfort comes from the
french word for strength with fault
with with uh it's related to the english word force but we're not talking about a force here
which maybe seems aggressive but rather a strength with strength
uh with power and so discomfort is can be seen as a way in which we
limit we hold back we killed and check our own strength to be comfortable is not to be have a
pleasant abiding and have a wonderfully comfortable couch to to live in
but rather in the dharma uh comfort is to have a delightful
peaceful but strong kind of inner strength in our attentiveness in our presence
in our posture in our ability to be with what is
and this turns the concept of comfort and discomfort around a little bit
and um and uh so that um the idea of not letting
discomfort limit us not let discomfort allow some natural
life force to blossom and bloom and be present
in a peaceful way maybe even a gentle way because when we're with people
uh sometimes when we want to be careful that we're not asserting our will
on them asserting our power on them our strength but in the dharma
this practice we do the movement is in fact to becoming
strong buddhism is often associated with being peaceful and calm
and that seems to go against the grain for being strong kind of goes a grand
against the grain it doesn't seem like the two are compatible but they are and that's kind of the
wonderful thing that it's possible to be have strength in calmness
strength in peacefulness and uh and uh
and one way to have that is we're not diminishing ourselves when we're peaceful and calm there's a
embodied attentiveness so we're there and present for what goes on
uh we don't need to go to the back of the room and pretend we don't count we don't need to
be in the middle of the room and be the one who has all the attention but we could be fully in the room
in some balanced way that is uh with our with a kind of peaceful strength peaceful confidence
that here i am um and the advantage of that
is that when we are present in a in a confident way and a strong way where strength is there we actually have
more to offer other people our love for others our kindness for
others our friendliness for others is um is uh it kind of
has more i want to say embodiment has more strength has more fullness to it
um you know if i'm kind of slumped in the couch completely slumped and half asleep
and and uh and kind of look over to someone and say oh yeah you know
you know i think you're great you know and then i fall asleep you know it's there's no strength to it
but if i'm standing with someone i walk up to them in an unthreatening way and just really there in a strong way and
say i really appreciate you that appreciation has so much more value
than uh than you know slumping in the couch is kind of mumbling something before i fall fall asleep
so it may be a dramatic contrast but but
today in other times when be careful with how you restrict yourself or limit
yourself with your discomfort this uh discomfort one of the functions
is to limit us is to protect us when it's necessary
but we often succumb to it when it's not really necessary
and so what we learn in meditation to happy have a simple embodied
attentiveness and really be here for our experience without holding back or collapsing or
cowering or just fully here and not asserting ourselves not insisting on who we are
but just here in a full way is something that
we can learn to do if we learn how to be wise about our discomfort
how to recognize when it's there how to recognize how we
how it causes reactivity the hindrances come up and we and they take over not rather than
discomfort and how we might limit ourselves and define
ourselves through the discomfort we can learn how to stay grounded and
present in the midst of this discomfort to breathe through it to
it know it's there but not let it limit us to be able to uh
to tell someone how much you care for them or how much you appreciate them or how wonderful they are or something in
an appropriate way it might be uncomfortable to do it maybe you're shy or something
but it doesn't have to be the discomfort of the shyness doesn't have to limit us
and so this is what we're learning and meditation to breathe with things and and uh breathe through things and to
allow things to be there but still to stay present for the breathing then we can learn to stay present for
what the task at hand is without being limited or defined by
some of the inner voices or inner feelings that might keep us limited
so sometimes we can we can relax and let go of our discomfort
sometimes we can not let it limit us and do what's wonderful to do in spite
of it and the advantage of really recognizing the discomfort
is we get to maybe look get the messages from it we can pay attention to it enough to know whether it's
we want to have it limit us or we want to use our skills
to be present in spite of it and offer ourselves
so it may be comfort we can translate now
into english as something like with our life force
and discomfort is without our life force and perhaps our life force when it's
most healthy most free is a peaceful force
one that has a lot of space and room for warmth and kindness and friendliness
generosity and respect appreciation for others
so on this day please
use these lessons as a way to live comfortably with your own life
force whether you're doing that alone or with other people that
it's a wonderful any day is a wonderful day to let your peaceful life force
arrive and offer you as confidence bring confidence
and strength and presence to your life
and if you have time today to meditate a little bit
even for 10 minutes you might see if that supports this way of being
so thank you very much and
may this day be a nice day for you and and i look forward to coming back here
tomorrow and and for the last day of the week
thank you