good evening good evening welcome welcome
such a wonderful thing to be able to practice together
it makes a difference chances are i wouldn't come here
to this room and uh just meditate by myself if i didn't know
that um there's a whole community of us whether you're listening to this live
or sometime later probably not before but later or there's something
kind of wonderful about the reaching across space and time together
so we'll start with a guided meditation
and just finding some balance in our seat
maybe that requires a little bit of rocking a little bit of adjustment
it's worthwhile to spend some time finding a place where there can be some
a brightness with some balance
and allowing the spine to be upright if you're sitting
for a lying down might consider this energetically but is there a way
in which we might imagine we were just very very gently
pulled up in a way that
is not stiff or contrived
but a way that introduces a little bit of space
and i want to use this word uprightness
maybe there's a better word but
the opposite of being collapsed
allowing the shoulders and arms to just
hang and then just feeling the body as a
whole the posture the geometric
shape we are in type of pyramid
we're sitting and knowing that we're sitting
and then we might feel the body breathing this
movements of the chest or the belly or
maybe feeling the air going in and out of the nose
can rest our awareness on those sensations
associated with breathing
feeling the in-breaths the out breaths and the transitions
between the breaths
it might be that while we are resting our attention
on the sensations of breathing
but there are some compelling bodily sensations
it's not uncommon in fact it's quite common
for there to be a little bit of uncomfortableness in the body in general
that's why we shift postures put on sweaters take off sweaters
we can rather than getting all tangled up with the uncomfortable sensation in
the body you can use a simple label unpleasant
unpleasant
it turns out it makes a difference the tone
that we use when we make this label
that is whether it's evenly
or comes from a balanced even-mindedness unpleasant
or with it comes laced with a lot of aversion or hatred or
dang it get out of here go away type of a tone
can we label this much ease as is available to us
with this unpleasant sensation
it might not affect the unpleasantness
our labeling
but it can disrupt the momentum of all that might happen this aversion
to aversion to aversion to aversion this buildup of
repulsiveness or type of hatred
we can undermine that with a simple label unpleasant
without worrying about how it got there
what we're going to do next to make sure it never arises again
can we nip it in the bond all the thinking and planning and story making
by just noticing unpleasant
if it feels overwhelming or it's too unpleasant by all means there's no need to stay
there with that practice it can be
really helpful to notice a neutral part of the body
the top part of the right leg maybe
near the left elbow maybe that's a neutral place
place with neutral sensations
uh
we're only labeling as a support
if it feels too much effort burdensome there's no need to do it
but it can be a way to work with some of the discomfort that arises in the body
and this way if we can label unpleasant bodily sensations as
unpleasant we might disrupt the momentum
of this unpleasantness that might lead to
ill-will or anger or all kinds of different expressions of
aversion which might cause harm for ourselves
and for others so in this way learning to
work with or be with unpleasant sensations not only supports our path to greater
freedom and greater ease but also helps protect others
from our angry our anger our
ill will or whatever might arise as a consequence of this unpleasant experience
so may all beings be happy and free
good evening welcome welcome good evening welcome morning good afternoon whatever
time of day it might be for you
so today i'd like to continue on this series of i've done this will be the third talk
and then two earlier talks on vedana often translated as feeling but
it's not really feeling because so often we associate emotions with feelings which
is perfectly natural thing to do but vedana is not about emotions
instead it's about the hedonic tone of our experience that is is it pleasant
is it unpleasant or neither pleasant nor unpleasant so these three options
pleasant unpleasant neutral so it's just this um the
feeling tone or the some people kind of say the flavor of
our experience chocolate vanilla strawberry pleasant unpleasant neutral
invading arises in response to physical experiences as well as mental
experiences so every single experience that we have every single sensation that we have has
this hedonic tone associated with it for example there might be
vedana of the body if we stub our toe there's some physical pain
and the vedana is unpleasant but there's also vedana in the mind
that is if somebody says something unpleasant about us the ear
is not in pain but the mind is so this is a mental vedanta that kind of like that
little bit of an ouch and in the satipatana which is the
discourse from the buddha or attributed to the buddha at least that is on establishing mindfulness and
there's these four sometimes called the four foundations of mindfulness the four
establishings of mindfulness and being mindful being mindful of
vedana is the second one body vedana mind and then dhammas phenomena we could
say and so in the satipatana suta this
discourse on the establishments of mindfulness the instructions aren't to practice with
noticing whether all the sensations are pleasant unpleasant or neutral
and then to notice whether they are worldly or unworldly
that is pleasant worldly and unworldly unpleasant worldly and unworldly and
neutral worldly and unworldly so what does this
mean worldly and unworldly it's a little bit unwieldy to say
unworldly repeatedly but so in pali these words
are samisa and niramisa and i think literally they would be
translated as of the flesh and not of the flesh so that is is it associated with the
body or not but that's not quite right it's not quite um accurate because
there can be mental sensations that are worldly so
of the flesh not of the flesh carnal versus spiritual as i've seen that way
translated or sometimes related to the senses or related to renunciation
leading to craving versus leading to freedom so these are all these different ways in which we might understand
this expression worldly or unworldly and an example might be that might be a
pleasant sensation from eating cookies i love eating cookies there's a this
pleasantness about the cookies and there's also this pleasantness of my
time from reading or hearing some of the verses in the tarikata that is these liberation poems
from these women at the time of the buddha when they had some awakening experience they
are some verses that are attributed to them in which they describe their awakening
beautiful beautiful verses and really inspiring and touching
from thousands of years ago these beautiful verses those are pleasant also
so eating cookies hearing these verses from the buddhist nuns about their liberating
experiences are both pleasant but they're not exactly the same
and part of being mindful evade and not paying attention to vedana is to discover and to learn
how are they different how do they feel similar they're both pleasant but
maybe a little bit different they lead in different directions
eating cookies might lead to eating more cookies and then some revulsion oh why
did i eat all those cookies whereas reflecting on or hearing these
poems from these early buddhist women in the tarikata can be inspiring and uplifting and
might support us to practice okay like rededicate ourselves to our meditation practice to
our buddhist practice or maybe we'll be encouraged to read a little bit more another poem
and feel like um there's an opening of our understanding and for me
often there's a softening of my heart and mind when i
read some of these verses so eating cookies goes in one direction
not so agreeable whereas reading these poems of the terry gotta goes in another direction more agreeable more supportive
for finding more and more freedom
and when we reflect on the experience these like the difference of
these experiences cookie eating inspiring poem reading we start to
notice and as i said get a little bit more familiarity with the how it feels and if we
contemplate or allow the mind to rest in the terrigata the poem readings
the mind becomes more familiar becomes more accustomed to that type of
pleasantness that type of pleasantness that leads to more freedom and supports our practice
and becoming more familiar with that it recognizes that
we can start to recognize when this sensation arises earlier and earlier in our experience
rather than it being full-blown experience so that is right at the very beginning of the
sensation the vedana is there the hedonic tone is there
and the more familiar we are with the pleasantness associated with cookie eating
versus pleasantness associated with inspiring reading
then the mind and the body can respond accordingly like oh i know that it's
more fulfilling more satisfying to be with inspiring poems
cookie eating not so satisfying in the the big picture right turns out not to
be such a great thing but the more the mind and the body just
become really familiar with just that that first
taste of the hedonic tone then we can work with it while it's still
weak it hasn't been like a full-blown it's not after we've eaten 10 cookies or it's not after
we've been reading poems for hours and perhaps we should
have been doing something else or but we can more familiar we are with it the more we can recognize it at
earlier stance and then we can respond in a way that supports our practice
and of course it's not just pleasant vedana that's worldly and unworldly
but also unpleasant vedana that's worldly and unworthy and it can be
really helpful to be able to recognize when that's happening and to
when we notice that there's unpleasant vedana that's worldly that is this
maidana that's associated with a version or this um something that's
unhelpful then we can stop
going cultivating that or going that direction because that can only lead to something
that's not wholesome and we know about kusala akusala
wholesome unwholesome skillful and skillful and a big part of practice is to
cultivate the arising of the skillful and the diminishment of the unskillful so this is one way in
which we can do that is practicing at the level of vedana
and so part of the way in how this works or what's associated with
the hedonic tone are these underlying tendencies you might have
heard of these greed hatred and delusion these underlying tendencies because
they're we're not conscious of them it's not something that we are actively choosing to do
but it's a tendency to react with sensations a particular way it won't be surprising
that pleasant vedana
often activates the underlying tendency of greed desire lust those types of thing
unpleasant vadena activates aversion repulsion hatred
and neutral vedana activates ignorance or delusion and for me what's
interesting about this is also what so they get activated when
we have pleasant unpleasant neutral sensations
if we're not paying attention they just lead right into these underlying tendencies get manifest
as some forms of greed hatred or delusion but for me what's interesting also is
that whether there's greed hatred or delusion in the mind
makes it more likely that the the reaction that we will have to whatever
sensation we're having will be greed hatred or delusion that is if there's a lot of greed in the mind
than something that's just mildly pleasant we're more apt to have some strong greed associated
with it so there's this feedback loop that goes and it can build and build and build
so just being aware oh yeah this is unpleasant this is pleasant can kind of
undermine or subvert this building of this snowball of greed hatred or delusion
so just being aware of these underlying tendencies even after the fact if we aren't aware at
that moment it can be helpful just because as i had said a number of times it interrupts
this momentum and this making of the big this big snowball
because sometimes we do unskillful things all of us and we are very good
at explaining to ourselves and everybody else why we had to do it and these big deep
reasons behind what we did but actually what pushes us to do
unskillful things is vedana the vedanan does the initial pushing and
then there's the rationalization that happens afterwards often we don't see that it
happens so quickly there's this unpleasantness and then we just say no to this or
no to that and then we come up with all these reasons why
but if we can notice that some of the vedana the
tone the feeling tone pleasant unpleasant or neutral then it can make it less
likely that we will just fall under this way of greed hatred
and delusion desire repulsion ignorance
an example is that we might say oh i i didn't i didn't get angry because she we might
realize oh i see i didn't get it wasn't so much that i was angry about what this person said i was
actually angry because i was having unpleasant bodily sensations and there was just all this aversion
and then i just reacted in a particular way and i blamed it on what they said but it
wasn't i realized yeah if i was feeling more comfortable i wouldn't have had the same reaction
i think most of us are familiar with this this idea of being angry hungry and angry uncomfortable in
the body leads to our being angry and just recognize this recognizing this
can be sobering it can be see how important it is for us to be
aware of the feeling tone that's happening in our moment-to-moment experience
because it ends up affecting so much so as part of the benefits of
why we would practice with vedana is to aid to under mine or stop the momentum of these
snowballs to gain greater clarity into some of the actions why we want to do this
it's also an easy way to disentangle any complexity that we might have especially in daily
life when we don't have this maybe the
focus or the awareness on exactly what's happening so we might be able to say oh yeah this is
unpleasant but i i've mentioned this and it's
the earlier two talks but i'd also like to add this um quote from nyanaponakatera
who's one of the the i don't know what word to use
one of the ancestors that doesn't sound quite right one of the founders somebody a
predominant person that's kind of at the beginning of this the mindfulness practice in tervada in
the west and he writes if we permit the three
roots of greed hatred and delusion to take firm hold in our hearts then their outgrowths will
spread far and wide like a jungle creeper like there's a plants that just grow
and like a jungle creeper suffocating much healthy and noble growth all around
it creates the conditions for unethical behavior it creates the conditions for us to say
and do things that might cause harm to ourselves or to others
so if we can be aware of the vedin as a way in which we can prevent that from happening
and another benefit for practicing with vedina is because
this phenomenon which psychologists called my side bias
i learned about this from pico anglio this my side bias which means that we always
assume that our views are correct and others views are wrong and any information that comes
in i manipulate in such a way that it confirms that my views are right and
anybody who disagrees with me their views are wrong and the underlying cause for this
actually is because there's a pleasant sensation
associated that i'm right and everybody's wrong it's a little bit of this pleasantness
of i'm right and people hold on to that pleasantness and hold on to their views and get
pretty dogged in their views and we all know this suffering
that can happen when there's a this real clinging to views and even though there's all kinds of information that
comes in that says these views or are not accurate unable people are unable to let go of
them it comes back down to vedana this pleasant feeling tone this feeling of
i have it right everybody else has it wrong
and so working with vedina gives us the tools in which we can learn to have views hold views
without clinging to them without holding on to them in a way that is unskillful and unhelpful and causes harm
to others
and as i mentioned in some of the earlier talks of course working with vedina um also just in general it helps that
there's more freedom vedana and the dependent arising is associated with um
craving and then craving it leads to dukkha
so i want to talk just a little bit how might one work with vedana i had
been mentioning just noticing in our pleasant sorry in our present moment experience
is it pleasant unpleasant or neutral but it's really helpful to have some familiarity
with this so that it becomes really quick in the mind so one way to do this is to do a body
scan and to initially just scan from top to bottom
looking for pleasant sensations just noticing the pleasant ones
and then noticing the unpleasant ones and then noticing the neutral ones
the ones that aren't pleasant or unpleasant and then do a body scan in which each
sensation just labeling it pleasant unpleasant or neutral after you have some more familiarity
after having done it then there's this more recognition or sensitivity to it
so that's four different body scans and then opening it up so
to any feeling whether or not it's felt in the body so including sounds or thoughts
and then maybe i'll mention that we don't have to always be labeling it pleasant unpleasant neutral that might be helpful
in the beginning in the first few body scans or maybe when we're just starting this practice
but then just you using labeling just feels tiring and burdensome
so instead there can just be this recognition this flash in the mind ah yes pleasant
neutral unpleasant without actually using the words
so this hedonic tone vedana is always present
i'm getting present and pleasant is always present it's not always pleasant it is
always present though and the point is to be able to readily recognize it
so a natural question that comes up well what about this neutral vedana this
neutral feeling tone how do we work with it what is it i think most of us
probably recognize pleasant and unpleasant but i'd like to talk a little bit more about neutral
i would say that due to their bland nature they are the most difficult to
notice to pay attention to to contemplate to be aware of
but to notice them can be really supportive of our practice one
is we might notice how we tend to dramatize or
exaggerate um neutral feelings i don't know if it exaggerates the right
word dramatize we tend to make it into something other than neutral
just so that it's easier to be with and or so that it satisfies
this need to be entertained or
need to be engaged in some way when there's this blandness often the mind just
starts to dart wherever it can to find something that's more interesting and exciting
so we want to quickly shift to something and we want to overlay our likes and
dislikes so this is good that's not good but when something's neutral we don't
have that this habit of liking or unliking we don't get to express it
but to learn how we are often dramatizing our experiences
and that it's completely unnecessary we don't need to do that in fact a lot of harm can happen from it
it can be really powerful just to see this this natural inclination it's a
perfectly human thing to do but if we can not do that
and allow there to be bland experiences
and that to be okay then we can say that our life can unfold
with less drama less problems more ease more spaciousness if we allow ourselves
to linger and notice with the blandness
and as i was pointing to neutral experiences don't really support our sense of self
that is the sense of like oh i like this or i don't like this
mutual experiences don't you know we're not for them or against them so they don't really do anything for us so they
don't bolster our sense of self i'm the person who doesn't like this or i'm the person who needs that
but it can be really helpful the more
experience we have with there not being a strong sense of self i like this i don't like
this as a obvious way a sense of self gets expressed
the more familiarity the more comfort we have with not propping up this sense of self
the easier it is to find freedom
because freedom is when there's not a sense of self the highest freedom the greatest freedom is when there is
not a sense of self so any softening any moving in that
direction is a movement towards freedom
and so the more that we can gain familiarity with that or rest in that or and by abide
in just the blandness without any drama i'm using the word
drama there might be some better words without trying to make it more exciting
trying to make it more relevant to ourselves and our stories
can be really supportive and then neutral experiences if we
don't pay attention to them then we might have this mistaken idea that there's this
neutral bland experience that's the background to everything else
and this neutral bland thing is permanent while pleasant and unpleasant
are impermanent so if we don't pay attention to the neutral
experiences they might kind of like all merge into this background
this stage and then we might start to feel like oh yeah there's this
permanentness in which pleasant and unpleasant are arising and
passing away but everything's impermanent everything
and so our noticing neutral experiences and practicing with them we
might start we might start to see oh yeah a neutral and maybe it shades into unpleasant
so it's no longer neutral or maybe it shades into pleasant or maybe it just goes away
so to notice the impermanence of neutral experiences
mutual vedina can be really powerful can help create the conditions
for us to see impermanence more thoroughly which creates the conditions for us to
let go more thoroughly which creates the conditions for more freedom peace and ease
so in this way working with vedina in so many ways can help lead to more
freedom by interrupting this kind of snowball effect of unpleasantness leads us to
fill our mind with uh aversion repulsion um hatred which then
can feed on itself and that we might do unskillful things or harmful things
which is duca of course right so if we can nip that in the bud earlier then we can find more and more
freedom so working with vade in a pleasant
unpleasant neutral something we don't often talk about but
is immensely powerful it can help simplify our experience and
can help bring greater ease to all our experiences
so may you find freedom amidst pleasant experiences unpleasant
experiences and neutral experiences thank you