good morning
as we explore punjab price you know wisdom you know
we let awareness illuminate
and it reveals everything from the workings of mind and heart
to the subtle perceptions through which we construct reality
and each time we sit we start over
there's an initiation and as i was saying yesterday we can
initiate in a deliberate way
we hold the notion that this is engaging with unbiased
attention and then that unbiased detention
reveals all the influences all the biases
that arise all these assumptions
and there's a delicate art between attending to experience
and not trying to manufacture experience
and maybe let's start with a demonstration of that so i'm going to
ring the bell and just listen to the sound
and then can you continue to listen as the sound of the bell diminishes
and hearing engages whatever else is happening
in the realm of sound
[Music] [Applause]
so [Music]
the quality of noticing the quality of a consciousness of
noticing of experiencing
each time we start to sit to rediscover that quality of attention
starting in a global way without any agenda
what's happening now
experiencing what's happening rather than manufacturing what's
happening and yet bringing attention to god
[Music] attending
and receiving
and then with that delicate attending and receiving experience to
attend to the sensations in the body
attending to the the qualities
of body that support awakening
kind of uprightness
in in the body that you are how does uprightness express itself
the spine rising connection to the cushion or seat
rising the whole way up through the hips the spine
lifting up supporting the chest
allowing the shoulders to widen and open across the front and across the back
coming up through the neck
an enlivening quality of uprightness
and in complement to that uprightness letting the body settle
any place where there's tension are holding it up
letting it soften
letting the eyes and the muscles of the face soften
[Music]
maybe noticing any subtle ways the face
is holding and letting it soften
letting the chest soften and the shoulders
and letting the abdomen soften
[Music]
and letting the arms and the hands soften
as if to assure the body
that in this attentiveness it will be taken care of
this is an engagement that will support
the life of being the body of being
and with the quality of attention and deliberateness
we're not in a hurry to get anywhere each detail is given the time it needs
when we do that it's always a reassuring quality to it
and then bringing attention to the breath with that reassurance
exhale in a way that might help you to open and
enliven the breath to extend the exhale
but can you extend the exhale without tightening the chest or the abdomen
or the face
and at the end of the exhale can you just pause for one or two or three seconds
and then allow the inhale
and quite deliberately study the influences
of breathing in that way
how does it feel in the body
can it invite a subtler kind of release
after breathing out and pausing for a few seconds
can you feel the body's impulse to inhale
how the inhale has a quality of allowing what is
to come forth
the exhale can have a quality of releasing
letting something that's being held go
in the inhale equality of
receiving opening
and just for a few breaths almost in a leisurely fashion in a
deliberate fashion extend the exhale
pause and allow the inhale
attending in a way that's discovering the subtle teachings of the yoga
of breath
a deliberate extension of the exhale the pause that
quality of allowing receiving the inhale
and then deliberately attentively shifting
and resuming a natural rhythm of breath for your body but as you do that
attending just as carefully just as detailed
just as deliberate as you were when the breath was being related to in a
extending and opening way now how is the breath being experienced
each time we set an invitation to discover
the subtler details of the yoga of body and breath
how it can be both enlivening
and in a way soothing or reassuring or tapping into something
very fundamental
[Music] yes the mind and the heart [Music]
a lot of passion
but this being body and being breath
adds a marvelous quality of attention in the midst of the passion of mind and
body
in the deliberateness of attending to body and breath
inviting kind of a dwelling
dwelling here in simply being
and just as listening to the bell the sound of the bell opens
not just to the side of the bell but to all songs
dwelling in the body breath opening to experiencing it
opens to dwelling in all the workings of being
it's not a corruption of attention it's the expression of being alive
this delicate play between the simplicity of being
and the complexity that it dwells within
with the support of body breath opening
noticing acknowledging all that arises
exploring what is it to bring an unbiased simple attention
to what arises
noticing the quality of permission
to just let it be
so
and as the thoughts happen is it possible
to dwell in unbiased attention
or do they conjure up
an intrigue
that dictates what happens
so beard that's part of being
notice and acknowledge
okay can they're in the midst of noticing and
acknowledging can there be an opening to that too
just as the sound of the bowel opened to all sides
still just sounds
even though they're labeled signed of a passing car signed of a bird
signed up something in the room
the thoughts are inclined to conjure up a version of
reality notice acknowledge
let it interplay with unbiased attention
and if unbiased attention disappears
so be it just deliberately leisurely
start over
this is the nature of consciousness
oh
and when there's a noticing that the mind has conjured up a reality
soak it up experience it
what's its dominant quality is it an image is it a feeling
is it the urgency of its creation
invited into awareness
in a moment i'll ring the bell
this time three times
let the sound wash over your being
and listen as the sound becomes all sounds that are present
[Music]
sometimes it seems so simple
just noticing and not grasping
and having a feeling of liberation no just in that moment
wow that experience
illustrating and instructing us
on the wisdom of liberation
the compassion of liberation and how both are
intertwined with how consciousness is being attended to
the great gift of having a meditation practice
is that each meditation session will invite us
to rediscover to dwell
in that practice of unbiased awareness and to see what comes forth
it creates a version of reality
and it creates a version of reality
that's initiated by or conditioned version of reality
maybe if we wanted to be smart we could say it's an unconditioned
response to a conditioned experience
but usually in the process of practice
it's more helpful to be naive
and then there's a saying that says not knowing
creates the intimate experience the intimacy
and yet for us simply not knowing
can leave us with like some way of connecting of acknowledging
of allowing it to be to register
once when i was a monk i went to visit another monk and in his
little hut his kuti as it's called in thailand he had on the wall a picture of a baby
and i i was a little surprised in that setting to see a picture of a
baby and he said to me i want
that mind that's that's the mind that i aspire to i don't think he said i
want i think more aspirational
we come into this world with the capacity to pay attention
and one of the enchanting things to my mind and heart about babies is
they engage it completely each experience they give themselves to
it completely
but we all grow up we all create
a much more complex version of reality
and noticing and acknowledging
the the ingenuity of it is
that it can shift the noticing and acknowledging can shift dependent upon the state of
consciousness the circumstances the stimulation
like when we ask what's happening now it's like what's the dominant experience now
is it is it a quality of mind that's turbulent or quality of mind
that's deeply settled
is it a version of reality that has great authority
within our being
we said can we invite any and every experience that happens for us
into a state of awareness that sees it for what it is
in some ways we could say the process
is panya this is prajna the very process
of unbiased seeing of the biases of being
unconditioned response to conditioned being every process is wisdom
and then we could say what's illuminated by the process
all the particular details and ways that consciousness takes shape
and then the way me the the unique expression
of those biases that arise in our individual being
and the inquiry of how to learn how to work with
our own being in a way that will enable that unbiased attention
and out of that the many practices that arise
the practice of compassion the practice of patience practice of
accepting what is the disciplines of
not corrupting or undermining the capacity for awareness
my experience of zen practices that staying close to this
unbiased attention to the biases of being
staying close to that exploring that
is an important aspect of our practice it's like listening to the bell ring
and as we listen to it the sound of the bell opens to all sounds
so we attend to with precision to the experience of unbiased awareness
and as we do it it opens up to everything
all the ways we be
and often in our dedication the complexity of being
is deemed to be inappropriate
it shouldn't be like this it should be a different way
but what if we think of this moment as a momentary culmination
of not just our life but of our parents lives too and their parents and their
parents and their parents
what if we think this is not just opening to the experience of me
this is opening to the experience of this vast web of being
and here we are dipping our finger in the ocean of being
with this momentary awareness and in doing so
appreciating the uniqueness of the moment
and in an utterly mysterious way connecting to well-being
how do we do that is there still a singular self
in that experience
so this dance between acknowledging okay in this moment
this thought is present and it describes it implicates it has
inferred within it a version of reality me
my life this place this time
and yet it touches all being
so in the language of zen we say
this is the great mysterious inquiry in the being this is the coin
of being alive
like it dislike it love it hate it
be grateful for it despise it you know feel deeply connected
feel isolated yeah
can we sit down in the middle of that
and then can we stand up and open to all of it
the deliberateness of practice can steady our heart and our mind
and not just support us to enter into all of it but also
invite a kind of joy in doing so
now what to please enjoy yourselves
thank you