good evening good evening welcome
it's nice to be here to be practicing together and whether you're listening to
this live or in the future it's nice that to practice with others
so i'll do a little bit of a guided meditation here
settling into our seat
maybe feeling both the pressure of the chair or cushion
maybe like the gravity pulling us down as well as the uprightness kind of
pulling us up to both both movements
in balance
and feeling the body breathing
that is the movement of the abdomen the chest
or the air going in and out of the nose
just noticing how it feels to have an in-breath
and how it feels to have an out-breath
nothing in particular needs to be
happening we're just noticing the sensations of
breathing
and when the mind wanders and just very
simply gently begin again
so again and again returning to the sensations of breathing
it turns out there is absolutely no limit none to how many times
we can return to the sensations of
breathing
and when we find that it's not so easy to stay with the
sensations of breathing or something compelling
maybe an emotional state
can be really helpful to just simply recognize what's happening
to name it
oh here's restlessness
here's drowsiness
here's impatience whatever it might be
so to just recognize what the experience is at this moment
and then as best we can to allow the experience to be there
after all it is there so to align ourselves with reality
can we allow whatever this experience is to be there
without trying to shove it away
or grab on tightly
one support for allowing a compelling
experience is to feel it in the body
feel the maybe energetic buzzing feeling with restlessness
or maybe there's feeling in the legs like wanting to jump up and run away
maybe drowsiness has some heaviness on the shoulders
the head
maybe frustration it's a furrowed brow and maybe collapsed shoulders
clap's chest whatever it might be for you to feel
the experience in the body
the body is more tangible it's easier for the mind to rest on
physical sensations
another support for allowing the experience to be there
is to tease apart the experience from our reaction to the
experience
we feel restless and then we have aversion to the restlessness
and then do we have aversion to the aversion to the restlessness
and then do we have aversion to the aversion to the aversion to the restlessness
it doesn't matter how many iterations
can you tease apart a sensation and experience from the
reaction to it
all of these approaches to recognize allow
feel in the body tease apart the experience from the
response reaction to the experience are ways to help the experience
move through us arise and pass away
take some of the compelling nature out of it
recognize allow feel in the body tease
apart the experience from the reaction to the experience
we can use the tools of recognize allow
feel in the body tease apart the react
the experience from the reaction
and just like all tools we only use them if it's helpful
if it's beneficial we don't carry around a crescent wrench
and try to use it on everything we use it when it's useful
recognize allow feel tease
r a f t
raft
doesn't have to be used in that order or all four elements
but having a mnemonic
so we can bring so we can use this tool when it's needed
sometimes when it feels like we might be overwhelmed by an
experience or an experience is really compelling
it's difficult to not be caught up in it
it can be useful to use what skills with tools we have
available
as a way to lessen the compelling nature make it less strong
of the experience
so that then we are available we have the freedom the space
to be available for what else is happening
and to be available for others
so that we might be a support for others and so that we might not be
stuck and narrowed in on just one thing
r-a-f-t raft may it be for the benefit
of all beings everywhere
and i'm looking for the striker for the
bell [Music]
thank you
welcome welcome good evening
so in this tradition sometimes we talk about this idea of crossing the
flood perhaps you've heard that and it's not an uncommon idea and
i might say that floods represent that which keeps us submerged and suffering perhaps or
not able to rise up to a secure stable place
which we could say is nibana's awakening is the most secure we wouldn't call it a place but it's the
opposite of being submerged and overwhelmed
and classically i'm not going to talk about these i'll just mention them that classically um
there are said to be four floods in this in the theravada tradition in the pali
canon or maybe it's even in the commentaries i'm not sure
the flood of sensuality the flood of existence the flood of views and the
flood of ignorance so these four experiences are things
that if we grab on to them can really be overwhelming and
we can feel like we're submerged in them and not on steady ground but instead getting
swept away or pushed around or this can be terribly frightening of
course to be in the midst of a i'm thinking in my
mind a raging river or perhaps a flood
and a john suchito he writes about this um the whole metaphor of uh
crossing the flood in this tradition and he writes an interest in deep change
gets triggered by the feeling of being swept along by events by the sense of being
overwhelmed by and even going under a tide of worries duties and
pressures so that's the floods worries duties and pressures
and just in our daily lives may just feel like oh this is too much and there's like no end or they
just keep on coming and we can feel them and then john suchito
continues he writes and crossing them the floods is about
coming through all that to find some firm ground it takes some work
some skill but we can do it so some encouragement that we can cross
over these floods and that's part of what the practice of buddhism is about
is to get out to the other side
i remember a number of years ago i saw a movie
i think it was called into the wild but i'm not certain i don't remember a lot of the
particulars of this movie but my memory of it is that there's this
scene where the protagonist this young man who had gone into alaska
to live off the land be kind of like a survivalist i guess
and when he first went out into the wilderness
into the wild i guess he crossed a river
and then when he became sick and he wanted to go back now the river river was flooding
or was raging maybe and he couldn't cross so he couldn't go back and just that
scene has stayed in my mind this idea of okay you can see where you need to go
but that you can't get there this it's like maybe certain death
if you were to go into the water and
so maybe we don't in our daily lives don't have experiences like that
i do have to say sometimes i am struck by how effortlessly in my car
or even walking that um just to cross over bodies of water or
ravines or valleys or something like this
like how often we have uh we've solved this problem of
crossing an expanse of water in modern times but of course that
wasn't the case in ancient india especially when the buddha was
in the gangetic plains near the ganges river
it flooded right during the monsoon season so this idea to cross the flood was a real
issue even though we might today not be able to relate to it as much i
was thinking that you know for them and this time of ancient india this would have been a
real concern it might it might have even been okay we can only cross
certain times of the year we just simply can't cross on other times of the year
so with this is kind of a setting there's uh i'd like to talk a little bit
about the simile of the raft probably most of you are familiar with this
this um i'll read uh here here's a little bit
different translation but it goes like this the simile of the raft
and this is the buddha speaking as part of his teaching imagine a person in the course of a
journey arrives at a great expanse of water whose near bank is dangerous and whose
far bank offers safety but there is no fairy boat or bridge to
take them across the water so the person thinks what if i collected
grass twigs branches and leaves and bound them together as a raft
and supported by the raft and by paddling with my hands and feet i should then be able to get
to the far bank the person does this and succeeds in getting across
on arriving at the far bank it might occur to this person this raft has been very helpful indeed
what if i were to hoist it on my head or load it on to my shoulders and proceed on my journey you know just
put it up on here and to carry and just keep on going so the buddha continues and he says the
buddha says now what do you think by carrying the raft with them would that person be doing what should
be done with a raft no sir replied his audience
so what should the person do with a raft having arrived at the far bank the
person might think yes this raft has been very useful but now i should just haul it onto dry
land or release it and set it adrift in the water
and then go wherever i want
those of us that often are familiar with this uh maybe i should just speak for myself
when i heard this simile of the raft i thought oh okay so it's all about just dropping those
things that aren't useful because we're not going to carry a raft around
on dry land unless of course we need to portage because we know there's another large expense of water or
maybe we don't know what's next and we think it might be useful but for the purpose of this simile the
emphasis is on putting down the raft but i'd like to unpack this a little bit
more because i think the there's some real richness here and sometimes it's easier to
at least for me i think for many of us it's easier to remember things to feel inspired by them
if they're kind of fleshed out and part of a story in some kind of way
so the story of this for this simile of the raft is that a person is on a bank
on the bank of a large expense of water which we're assuming is like a flood
or it could be a river maybe it's a large lake i actually don't
know but and this the wanting to get to the other
side because this side is not safe there's dukkha here
so the simile begins with noticing dukkha
and for so many of us this is the beginning of our spiritual practice our buddhist practice
and certainly it's the first noble truth there is dukkha
so just noticing that oh where i am here is not safe
i don't need to i need to go somewhere else and what's in front that is the flood that's
not safe either it's going too fast maybe it's a trench
torrent maybe it's raging rapids we don't know but for some reason they
can't just wade across or swim across so sometimes we feel like this
here's not safe there's not safe this feeling of what am i going to do in fact it's
probably not until we feel this feeling stuck
in some kind of way that we're really able to maybe try something new or do something
different and so maybe i'll say that that the buddha he spent a lot of his teachings talking
about this actually about kind of the about dukkha in general but in
particular pointing to the dukkha of sensual pleasures not because they are inherently bad but
because we are often turning to them to try to
find maybe a little confused about pleasure and happiness and we're trying to find happiness and instead going we're going
for pleasure and then we discover again and again and again that things that are pleasurable are not
lasting sources of happiness
and some and the buddha he gave quite a few similes
talking about some of the dangers of sensual pleasure and maybe i'll just offer one here
so the buddha says suppose a person took a blazing grass torch and went against the wind so that
is you know holding something that is a flame
now in modern times we just get a flashlight if it's dark and we want to see right
and there aren't dangers usually associated with with using a flashlight
but in ancient times right of course they don't have flashlights if you need to see at night you have a
torch and if there aren't trees around or something it might be a grass torch
so suppose a person took a blazing grass torch and went against the wind what do you
think if that person does not quickly let go of that blazing grass torch wouldn't that
bleazing grass torch burn their hand or their arm or some other part of their body
so that they might incur death or deadly suffering because of it i think it will relate to that if you're
holding something that's a flame and the wind comes towards you you're going to drop it it's just a
natural thing to do so of course he asks wouldn't they drop
it and they say yes venerable sir and then he continues the buddha continues so too
a noble disciple considers thus sensual pleasures have been compared to a grass torch by
the blessed one sensual pleasures provide great disappointment great trouble and
the danger in them is still greater so in the same way there are some things
that for us that can be really useful helpful enjoyable i'm using the simile of using a
flashlight but there's so many different things that
even though they may be helpful they uh lead to trouble it can be a slippery
slope using a flashlight isn't one of them but maybe
watching all kinds of tv or youtube videos or something like this can feel how it
kind of accepts your energy or kind of warps your influences your mind
maybe in a way that isn't the best thing for your mind or maybe gossiping
saying something not so helpful about another person
some of these things the buddha is using the word sensual pleasures
maybe i could just use the word distractions or things that we do for entertainment
turn out to not be so helpful and it so sometimes the duke is really obvious
we have a terrible diagnosis or some really untenable situation
or maybe it's not so obvious watching too many youtube videos
but this idea that there is dukkha all around on this shore and in the water
so we want to go the other side and so part of the practice is also to
notice that there is another side there is an alternative
there is a place that has some safety
and this of course is the third noble truth the cessation of dukkha
can consider it as nibana's awakening but even if it's not a complete sensation of
all dukkha think of it as a diminishment of whatever duca we're having it's safer
even if it's not completely safe we can also think of the other shore as being safer
so this encouragement for us to notice okay when is it experiences that are
neutral where are experiences that feel like can be a foundation
a ground for a source of lasting happiness something that's we can build on or
create a firm foundation with
and then so in this simile of the raft the person is standing there on the near shore sees
dukkha all around sees that there isn't duca on the other side and then
in the assembly of the raft they weave together a raft using grass twigs
branches and leaves that is they just look what's there what's
available right there and they work with what's there to make a raft
this is how i'm interpreting it they just are using things that are in nature
and one might find in the expanse of a river or something like this and i like this word that they get woven
together to make the raft so we might consider
that sila samadhi panya are things that we could weave together
to make a raft that is the teachings and practices of ethics
mental development meditation and wisdom these three practices we can
weave together it's just part of our daily life
the grass twigs leaves and branches are part of our daily life and we can
approach them and engage in it in a way that has ethics mental development and wisdom
so we create a wrath with our practice with the teachings with what's what we encounter
in our life and this of course is the fourth noble
truth about the eightfold path see the samadhi and panya
and then so once the raft is created in the assembly of the raft says the um
the person paddles with their hands and feet to get conveyed across to the other bank
so they don't just create the raft and then just sit on it
no they build it and then they use it as a support but of course they
have to do some of the effort they have to do some of the paddling they still have to engage with the water
they still have to maybe navigate or steer or just
using i think it says literally in this using their hands and feet so using parts of their body
doing some effort so there's a plenty of teachings also about using the
right kind of effort of course that's even one of the elements in the eightfold path
that is essentially to cultivate the wholesome and not to cultivate the unwholesome
but also is specifically about this idea of crossing a flood here's a another excerpt from the buddha
and where somebody asks him how dear sir did you cross the flood
so again using this uh metaphor of crossing the flood in this setting and then the buddha
responds how he crossed the flood by not halting and by not straining
i crossed the flood but how is it that by not halting and by not
straining you crossed the flood when i came to a standstill i sank
when i struggled i got swept away it is in this way by not halting and not straining
i crossed the flood so not only does it need to be some
effort but maybe a kind that doesn't have too much struggle or straining or by complete stopping but this
recognition that that there's maybe there's building the raft
and allowing what we created to support us but to find our way with wholesome and
unwholesome and to convey us in the direction that we want to go
so then the assembly of the raft continues that when they get to the other side
is this inquiry like wow this raft has been really helpful suppose i hoist it on my head or load it
onto my shoulders in some cases as i said maybe that makes
sense to portage a raft across some dry land if we know that we're going to go to some water elsewhere but also
there was this uh um this when the buddha was saying well
what should a person do with the raft is this inquiry to say
well rather than just hoisting it on one's head there should be an inquiry should i hold
it onto dry land or should i set it adrift in the water
hold it on to dry land maybe we need it later
set it at drift on the water just release just let go
so then once one has the simile continues once one has hold
it on to joyland or to let it go the simile says then the person can
go wherever they want have complete freedom no obstructions no
limits so with this foundation this raft that
we've created and some effort got to the other side to a place where there's even greater
freedom and whether we understand the other
shore as nibbana as awakening or just as a place that has more safety
than where we currently are this idea of release letting go
is part of this path so one way maybe taking the bird's eye
view of the simile of the raft and we might even say the ark of uh somebody's buddhist practice
could be first noticing noticing that there is suffering there's difficulty there's
dukkha there's unsatisfactoriness here and when i look over there like
all kinds of places and to also notice it seems that there's more safety on the
other bank further over there
if this isn't a perfect uh simile but just to notice that there are places of dukkha and
places without dukkha maybe that's the first step to notice
the dangers on this the dangers on this shore the floods and the safety on the other shore and
then there's some doing there's some cultivation some
development this building the rafts uh paddling and maybe heaving the raft up onto the
dry land and even having this inquiry is this helpful
this instead of saying oh this raft has been helpful therefore i have to carry it to have the inquiry is this helpful
and then to release happens the raft is left behind
so that the person has the freedom to go where they want
and it's important maybe to say that this release is natural it just when you realize
oh there's no more water i'm safe here there's no obstructions you don't have to
convince yourself to release the raft this isn't a perfect simile
because well there's different ways we could say what is this this it's not saying that we
should release ethics and mental development and wisdom so facility isn't perfect
if we're considering that the raft is the eightfold path we don't completely release the
eightfold path when we get to the other war there's it's more that we release practicing it for an awakened
person the eightfold path is just how they are in the world they show up
with right view right intention right speech right action right livelihood
effort mindfulness and concentration
so the simile of the raft
is somehow it can help us in particular moments is it we can think is it helpful to
notice where is there suffering and to help but to also notice where is there less suffering
and then just using what we have with us branches twigs leaves
and grass whatever our daily life is offering us
we can weave them together in the same way that we weave ethics meditation and
wisdom to support us to get to the other side and
when we get there then we can embody the eightfold path in some kind of way not
that we have to carry it but we just embody it
and that to recognize that releasing happens naturally this letting go and it's an integral
part of the path it's not just accumulating and building and
cultivating creating there's also a lot of letting go that happens
so in some ways maybe there's this simile of the raft works in small situations
as well as it might be the whole arc of practice
so i'm wishing you that you might find different ways all kinds of different ways in which we
might build a raft including with bubble gum and
toothpicks and i pick it up macgyver right whatever this tv character used to solve problems
with uh whatever they found so may you whatever difficulties you may
find yourself in may you also be able to build a raft so that you may cross over
the flood and be able to let go of those things that aren't helpful
maybe you build the raft and you help others across the flood
maybe you vary back and forth helping others
this way may our practice be for the benefit of all beings everywhere
thank you