hello everyone and warm greetings very happy to be back here after being
away for a week and um
someone hears loud no hum not buzzing
so i'm also hearing buzzing
i'm better now it's the silence audio fine here okay so hopefully it's all okay well enough i'm
sorry for the people with the buzz i'm not sure what to do the
the heater is on so i don't know if they were picking up the sound of the heater here it's um
so
good morning
there's a kind of a rule of the road
kind of for rules the right word but it's um that when you're driving a car
you vary the distance between yourself and the car in front of you depending on the speed in which you're
driving so if you're driving um slow you might
keep your you know one car's distance from the other car
but then uh as you go faster maybe at 50 miles an hour you want to keep at least five cars distance from
the car in front of you so there's enough time to slow down and stop if something else something happens
and it's certainly done with a tailgate and so the same thing with our life
the faster our life goes the more space you want to have
between your thoughts that maybe if you're just sitting
quietly and just ruminating and thinking nicely that it's fine just let your thoughts do
the speed with which they go but when the thoughts start tailgating
thoughts start kind of one after the other without any pause whatsoever
and if especially if the thoughts are going fast then
there's not much room for a deeper awareness of what's happening
there's not much room to stop and really see and consider and be wise
about what is going on so the idea the possibility of
slowing our thinking down or maybe not slowing it down exactly but
giving space for thoughts the space between our thinking our thoughts
and not to have the thoughts kind of run through our minds one after the
other is a one of the wonderful ways of develop tapping into our own wisdom
and also our own safety we become safe safer
if we're not tailgating our thoughts because then we don't see enough they come so fast we don't really
see what's happening so does so so with that as a background for this
meditation
assuming a meditation posture in which you can sit in an alert way
if you take a really deep deep full breath and let your chest feel and
with air and then that sense of openness in the chest
as you exhale don't lose all of it sit with a posture that allows a chest
to be a little bit open a little bit expanded
sometimes if you take a very deep deep breath at the beginning so much so that you feel you're
pulling on your shoulders as the rib cages that expand upward
then when you exhale let your shoulders relax
and same thing if you take a very deep full breath and let your
the diaphragm when you breathe in pushes down if you're relaxed
and expands the belly to take a deep breath and relax and let
the belly expand as fully as you can
and then as you exhale let the weight of the belly settle
and then if your eyes are still open you can lower your gaze
if it's comfortable you can close your eyes
and then breathing normally
on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
on the exhale
softening the shoulders
on the exhale relaxing the belly
on the exhale relaxing your arms and hands
and if it feels right you can adjust the posture of your hands
and on the exhale relax your brain
as if the brain is a muscle
and then notice kind of the speed by which you're
thinking are your thoughts fast and tailgating each other
and if they are on the exhale can you soften and slow
down your thinking
maybe at the end of the exhale let there be a brief pause in your
breathing breathe breathe in a brief pause in your
thinking
so you begin getting a feel for there being space between thoughts
and then begin settling down into the body's experience of breathing
relaxing your thinking mind as you exhale
letting there be a simple pause in your thinking
at the end of the exhale
and maybe with that pause
you can receive more fully the beginning of the inhale
noticing the speed in which you're thinking
can you calm your speed calm your thinking down
slow your thinking and with the slowest thinking that's
available direct your thinking
to think about your breathing
with the simplest shortest thoughts you can thoughts of recognition
of the experience of breathing here and now
and as you're sitting here
if there's any degree of calm
align yourself with that calmness
allow yourself to feel the calmness the subtleness
letting the thinking mind enjoy the calmness
and as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps you can consider that when you have a traffic jam of
thoughts there's not much space in the mind to
take in other people to really
see them hear them feel them recognize what's happening with them in
some fuller way
but when the thinking becomes quieter slower
it's possible to gaze upon others to look upon them
to see them
more fully
and that ability to be present for others
can be a gift can be a form of generosity
of care of kindness friendliness
may it be that the calmness and subtleness that might come from this
meditation today whether you know it or not
may it be that it somehow comes with us into our
life in the world
so that we're more present for people listening better hearing better
seeing better without the distraction
of a lot of thinking preoccupations
may it be that this meditation that we do serves for the welfare and happiness of
others may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
so good morning everyone and welcome to this monday morning talk
and this morning or this week i'd like the theme
to be calmness and to discuss five different areas or
aspects of calmness and meditation is often associated with
calmness but not for its own sake though it can be quite nice for its own
sake but because calmness allows for greater wisdom to operate
it allows us to a greater capacity to see what's happening
and also sets up the conditions where it's easier to let go
of things which are healthy like to let go of there's more space in the mind or
softness in the mind where a clinging begins to loosen its grip
so to talk about calmness and
so the the
i when i think about this topic i think about it in relationship also to a distracted mind
a mind that is caught up in his thoughts and preoccupations that um
the faster the thinking is the more preoccupied the mind is the more uh chances are that the mind
and maybe even the body is not tranquil does not calm
um and what happens when we're when there's a you know incessant chatter in the mind thinking
fast thinking one thought follows the other thoughts are tailgating each other
is that uh where our ability to un to perceive to understand
to um be creative to be um
is is diminished because the uh the busy thoughts
fill the bandwidth they fill the space and so other forms of intelligence as we
have other forms of ways of of perceiving and of reflecting
uh don't have a chance to operate but when we when thinking when we're not
distracted then we're also not distracted from
our deeper wisdom our deeper understanding we're not distracted from taking the
time to really see what's here the uh recently i heard someone say that
the more urgency he feels the slower he goes
but that was a wonderful principle because when things are urgent
it's probably a time when we have to really use all our mental capacities to
problem solve to figure out to understand what's happening to do things well to not be impulsive and make mistakes
because we didn't take time to learn what happened and so to um to
to learn the art of calming ourselves learning the art of not being swept away
in destructive thoughts and agitated mind
is one of the most useful things that one of the great useful things we can learn from meditation and for
mindfulness but it's easier to learn it if we begin to appreciate
the value of calmness they uh and maybe we can begin by understanding
the uh they appreciate the calmness of a calm mind or more specifically
calm thinking it's hard to uh
well the buddha talked about the calmness and calming speech
so if you find yourself speaking very fast and sometimes when we get agitated we
speak faster speech how we speak and the speed by
which we speak we have some control over
some it's easier to control when we speak and how fast we speak
than it is to control our thoughts and our thinking because we have to engage more
physically with the act of speaking to begin experimenting and getting a feel for
speaking in ways that are not hurried begins giving you a feeling a sense
of what it's like for the thinking mind to also be unhurried
and then to begin slowing the thinking mind down especially
when you're distracted when you're distracted by your thoughts and your thoughts and concerns
and so to um slow down calm down the thinking mind
like you would come down speaking so the advantage of this is is not
saying stop thinking let go of your thoughts which might be too tall of an order for
anyone to you know do effectively in daily life but
but maybe it's possible to begin slowing down your thoughts
to have a little more space around them or a little more calmness associated with them
and um and so how do we do that one of the ways is to do it
relax the body chances are that if you're thinking in a fast
distracted way that something in your physical system is tense this tight this
pushing or leaning forward or or kind of holding on to some some feeling
holding on so to relax relax the belly relax the shoulders
and that's the advantage of some of this relaxation is they can be done without anybody else knowing that you're doing
it you can do it at meetings you can do it sitting in traffic you can do it you
know standing in line at the store you can take a little bit of time to relax
if you feel like you don't have the time to relax when you're standing in a line
cashier line check check in line at a store then you're probably
caught up in some kind of distraction something that is limiting
the depths of your wisdom the depths of your clarity of really seeing what's happening
so be very careful by the insistent voice in the mind or the sense of authority that distracted thoughts can
have like it's really important to think about this i have to think about it's so important this concern
and the kind of fear and sometimes desperation that goes in or the desire or the greed
that might even go in to thinking it has an insistence in it
when when that happens and you can't standing in a checkout line can't stand on your boat both feet and relax and
just um you know just relax your body for a few
minutes for a few moments then i then there's not much chances are
that your innate natural wisdom and clarity of thinking is not going to be available
because you're caught in that insistence that push to think so you might
take go as you go through the day look for opportunities maybe secret
opportunities no one needs to know you're relaxing your belly or your shoulders or
your face or whatever your hands but look for opportunities to relax
and see in that relaxing or that intention to relax if there starts to be a tug of war with
your thinking mind thinking minds kind of doing somehow in some form or other saying no
no we don't have time for this it's so important to be
thinking fast and furiously or so important to be caught up in thinking about this concern
and maybe that's not the case maybe
if you really have an important concern that something that really needs to be thought about
maybe you think about it more effectively
better when you're calm when you're relaxed um when you slow down
when the thinking mind becomes slow enough that you can be attuned to what it feels like how you know that you're
in your body you feel embodied we thinking mind slows down enough there's a space to be aware of your
emotions and feelings kind of the deeper emotional connection to what's happening not the surface emotions of fear or
desire but slowed out enough to kind of those are kind of often symptoms of something deeper
and if you can slow down and calm down enough to fill in the picture with more of how you are who you are how
you are with more space for undistracted thoughts
calm relaxed thoughts that somehow arise from a deeper place of understanding a
deeper place of creativity within us uh often we can we
can find our way better with our challenges in our life than if we are have an agitated mind
so to uh practice to have an unagitated mind
is the same thing as a calm mind and and one of the vehicles for doing that
is a calmness of body a relaxation of body and this wonderful interplay and
mutuality between mind and body in terms of helping us be calmer
if some of you don't like the word calm there's other words tranquility
serenity peace ease all these words are kind of like in the
same family and if you don't like any of those words and you think it's too high bar or
somehow not not appealing then perhaps
an unagitated mind an unagitated body
because when you're agitated we can't be so wise
and we can't be kind it's harder to be kind it's hard to be generous from a place of depth and one of the
wonderful things about becoming calm and unagitated our care for others our friendliness to
others or attention to others they'll feel that it comes from a different place
in us it's bigger it's more richer it's more connected
if we connect to others with a calm place rather than a distracted place or an agitated place
or this fast pace that some people some of us can be in sometimes where
there's not really enough space let it known for ourselves really in a deep way
but let not enough space for others as well
so calmness and maybe this week's theme will be useful
for you especially as we're getting ready for this
winter season and holiday season may you become a student of calmness
this week thank you