you know there's always preliminaries in every practice especially in the tibetan tradition there are a lot of
preliminaries before you actually get to sit and meditate so these are our preliminaries
settling here we are okay so so hello and welcome a warm welcome
wherever in the world you are and for our practice today together
we've been practicing um this past week with a practice of
appreciative joy vicarious joy uh in pali it's mudita m-u-d-i-t-a which is
basically happiness for others happiness
happiness begetting happiness sense of um generosity of heart feeling happy
when others have good fortune which could be us ourselves happiness for our
own good fortune which gets expressed as gratitude
and we spent a few sessions with the practice of vicarious joy
appreciative joy for a neutral person just anyone in the world which is
such an expansive practice in in expanding our heart and um and as many of you comment in the
previous sessions this is such a an expansive a hard expansive it's such
a happy making practice um to really turn our minds
to good fortune with appreciation whether it's ours or other peoples and just
celebrating celebrating goodness celebrating happiness in the world
yay as if it were our own yay sense of delight celebrating i'm so
happy that you're happy so as we work through these concentric
circles in this practice and we start where it's easy and then we expand
our heart more and more and more and then we might get into areas that
are a little challenging and we work with them and we expand our heart further so for today
we are going to both work with the neutral being and a little bit
ourselves and then dip our toes expand into the next category which is someone we're having
some challenge with someone we're having some challenge with and um
really feeling that they too are a human being just like us
and can we also celebrate their good fortune not condoning everything all the other
complications that we might have but saying hey can
my heart be expanded to just feel happy for their happiness and
see wow how that can be transformative how transformative that can be
in the in the way we see our own capacity to relate to others
we can actually really surprise ourselves in how we can celebrate the good fortune
of others even even if we're having some entanglement
can really surprise us and really get us to see dimensions of our humanity
that maybe we were not even privy to so so that's the invitation for tonight
and we'll get into it slowly slowly slowly especially if this this seems a little intimidating what
what are we gonna do don't worry we'll slowly slowly as usual we'll get it to also the
end if any challenges come up i always want to say this if any challenging emotions come up
turn with kindness with meta with loving kindness to the challenging emotions so
if upset anger disappointment pain whatever comes up then hold that
with metta with care oh sweetie this is hard it's okay it's okay it's okay then it becomes a practice of
compassion which is okay whatever comes up
as long as you turn to it with kindness good fortune of another person comes up kindness yeah i'm happy for your
happiness your own pain oh it's okay meeting
the pain with kindness so as long as you're meeting whatever arises with kindness you're doing this practice
perfectly so it doesn't matter if i'm giving invitations instructions for one thing
but something else is coming up for you that you need to attend okay so
let's get started so i invite you to sit
in whatever posture or lie down in whatever posture
ah most supportive to you in this moment what supports you the
most in this human body
ah landing landing in this body this moment
softening softening softening
the muscles
of your feet your legs
your sit bones softening your abdomen
your chest your heart
your neck and shoulders
arms your hands
feeling the softness of the flesh of your fingers your hands
the tenderness softness
softening your face
your jaw your eyes in their socket
letting them rest your forehead
letting your breath as it is received as your breath is received in your body
your abdomen expanding contracting
and with each out breath
letting go and landing into your body some more
letting go of any holding tightness anywhere in your body that calls to you
if thoughts thoughts arise it's okay
turn your awareness to them with kindness hello thoughts plans memories fears
ah softening relaxing letting go of tension in your body that might have arisen
with the thought so bowing to the thought and letting it
go for now thank you not now
releasing releasing releasing thoughts freeing them up
as you release any tightness or tension in the body
reconnecting with the breath in the body calming soothing
in this moment right here
and this moment of aliveness
never to be repeated fresh and new
diving as if into a pool of this moment right here
with the breath
right here this breath
do i really need to think this thought right now
smilingly releasing letting go
i like to invite you to bring to mind
some blessing in your life that you are happy about
turning your mind from your awareness to something there's always something in
your life that is good
i'll let your heart feel relish
sense of happiness gladness
letting your heart feel expansive celebrating delighting
this goodness this blessing this gift
notice how naturally when celebrating and turning our minds to goodness
in our own life thankfulness gratitude might arise on
its own intertwined
happiness for your own happiness for your own good fortune
with each breath connecting with this goodness
letting your heart expand celebrate dance
be grateful if it wants to
and if the mind sometimes jumps into the future fear what if it goes away
smiling we bring the mind back to the present come back sweetie stay in the present moment
not helpful to look at the future or past with worry and fear stay right here right here celebrating
inhabiting this moment right here
this is what can be known fully it's what here what is here right now
let your heart be expands celebrating this goodness
it's in your life right now right here right now
now i'd like to invite you to consider someone you don't know well
as a neutral person you don't have much history with them
it's okay to have some feeling about them not 100 neutral but you don't really know
them maybe they're a neighbor you see walking by
or maybe someone at a store where you shop
or a delivery person
bringing this person this human being a stand-in for all of humanity
this person to mind appreciating this person
just like you just like me they have challenges
this human being this person connecting with them this human being
just like me have hopes and dreams
they have a complex inner life
that is just as complex as mine and their life is just this dear to them
just as compelling just as i want to be happy they want to
be happy just as they have likes dislikes
things they hope for or aspire to
so do i we're similar
in our humanity and just like me as i appreciate the blessings in my life
this person too has blessings in their life
and it's okay to imagine some blessing in their life for the purpose of this practice
something they're grateful for something they're happy about a good
fortune whatever it is maybe they wake up
feeling healthy without pain that that's a blessing maybe they have a
special relationship in their life a loved one a child
whom they love a parent a friend it's a blessing in their life
can imagine their happiness for their good fortune
maybe they just got some good news about something they care about
maybe they just recovered from an illness
and they are so happy to be healthy again
and let your heart celebrate with them happy for their happiness
sharing the generosity of your heart
may your happiness good fortune may it continue
may it increase never may it never wane
can recite silently if you wish or simply i'm happy for your good fortune
i'm happy for your happiness
or maybe wordless just feeling your gladness for their happiness
their well-being are gladness
and now just as you [Music] and this person
you have so many similarities in your humanity bring to mind
someone with whom you have some minor entanglement
not the biggest entanglement in your life you have some entanglement a little bit
of challenge as you bring them to mind
seeing that just like you just like this other human being they too want to
be happy have hopes and dreams
and their life is dear to them just as yours is to you
and just as you celebrate are happy for good things that happen to you ah
they their heart celebrates they feel happy
for blessings in their life and they suffer just like you do with challenges in
their lives you're not so different
and as if you were them as if you were this person living their life
for a moment imagine yourself as them
their challenges with their good fortune
ah
just as as you look out through their eyes and you feel the
challenges they have in their life and bring them sorrow and also the good
fortune the blessings that
make them happy bring them joy
and with generosity generosity and of heart
flooding our heart too
be glad for this good fortune for this happiness for this blessing
as if it were yours as if it were yours as if you were
experiencing this blessing ah what a relief imagine
they recovered from an illness and they are relieved happy
ah as if it were your own happiness feeling relief
this shared human condition
may your happiness by your good fortune continue
made increase may never wait
i'm happy for your happiness
see see how it may be possible to step out of the contraction
of the heart not condoning the harm or the hurt
the poor behavior not condoning any of that but it's also possible to step
out of the limited view of me and you and them i just
feel happy for happiness for good fortune
for good fortune in the world as if you're stepping out of yourself
because if you're a little fairy with wings a little angel that is you this feeling
happy for happiness in the world including this person
letting your heart feel expansive in its own gladness and generosity
so much more expansive and glorious
capacity of our heart that we give ourselves credit for
and as you may see yourself as this little fairy with expansive heart
sharing feeling gladness the gladness of
this person you are entangled with also you're neutral this neutral person
as well as yourself seeing yourself from perhaps an external perspective
may all your happinesses all three of you
all three your good fortune continue
made increase may it never end i am happy for your happiness
may there be more gladness joy in the
world
bringing each being close one by one and feeling into their
blessings expansion of your heart for them
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your
practice so we have some time for reflections questions
reports from the field the field of your heart
what did you notice what worked what was challenging it's all welcome
everything you share is supportive of others
nancy please um i have sort of
repeated problems with this issue of um jealousy that arises when i'm trying
to wish somebody that i clearly uh care deeply about um
but uh i'm struggling with it yeah yeah thank you for sharing
so just to say this is very common uh with this practice as i've
said before um it's considered um since this is a purification practice
it will bring up it will bring up the feelings that we have so is it okay if i ask you and you don't
have to answer if you don't want to but you can unmute yourself
does it come up in the sense of you feeling happy for this area of their life and you want that
thing they have or can you say just a little more what's how if you feel comfortable i would like
to have what they have and i would also like um to share that with them
say more i if you would what do you mean um
[Music] having a partnership with them in that certain area
okay to share it to share it with them i see a love relationship but a partnership
a creative process partnership yeah yeah i see so this is something that
they have you feel happy for them it's a blessing in their life that they have partnership creative partnership with
others and and you're so happy they have that and you want that in your life
too um and you want to have it with them oh oh so so that's where the tightness
though i want this and they're suffering oh i really want this yeah um but it's clearly
um a beautiful and very um um rich uh
fruitful part of their life right now yeah yeah yeah so a couple of couple of
suggestions i have nancy both for you and and everyone will be many of us
experiencing this because as an aspect of this so one thing you can do is to um
start perhaps with feeling um practicing uh
mudita practicing vicarious your appreciative joy first for an area of their life
that is not also what you want just kind of start where it's easier right start where it's
easier and then make your way towards something that you also want so that could be uh
one way to work with it that's one idea and then another idea is actually
um what i was suggesting towards the end of the guided meditation is for you to uh what if you stepped
out of yourself and you were this little fairy right and you were saying nancy oh nancy
oh dear nancy she wants that too i have compassion for her oh and then this friend of of hers has this
has this great partnership oh can be so so basically what i'm suggesting to
not personalize it because when we are in our selfing we're not then it feels like me
i want this for me it's like but if you try to remove yourself
even if for a moment you tap into that like oh wow this is possible
this is possible i can open something new up yeah i'm really stuck there
then try the first one and try the first one yeah yeah great thank you nancy
yeah appreciation for you asking the question mothers
so any other reflections or questions you like to share before we
move on
ah william please hi
i had a similar situation to nancy and what came up um
was the wish like what i could what i could access and i don't know if this is bypassing
was a wish for their happiness um
that was free from conditions so like a happiness free from dependency on conditions
um rather than wishing them more of the thing that i wanted um so i don't know if that's equanimity
or if that's bypassing yeah no it's not so what what basically
you did what i appreciate in how you tried to work with it is you went to metta
which is may you be happy may you be well may you be safe so basically uh
generally wishing them well without focusing on that thing that
you also want so i think that's what you did ram is very skillful yay and that i consider
what you did also a bridge a bridge to then doing with beta for
them because mudita is you know happiness for someone
who has what you want especially if they're challenging person it's kind of it's like expanding expanding and we
want to start where it's easier and then make our way for it so what you did is lovely fantastic it's not a spiritual
bypass at all it's going to matter cultivating just goodwill may you have
plenty and then later when there is more stability in the heart and mind more expansiveness more practice than
then i do suggest expanding it a little bit how does that sound
doable doable is good great fantastic
um
jerry asks is it helpful to see others accomplishments as something to admire rather than be jealous of them um
i appreciate that that suggestion that that's another way to see how actually what they have can can
inspire you can be inspiring instead of contractive
how it can be inspiring so um that's great also building bridges these
are all creative ways to work with our hearts and minds when they get contractive
to see oh how can i work for it to be more open you know either you little fairy or you
start with meta or you you uh feel inspired like oh wow
what they have is lovely it's fantastic oh i'm so inspired by that that's that's a great idea too so this is a
creative practice everyone this is a creative practice so so let's
practice in a small come in in little groups so my invitation
is tonight as we get into small groups first um let's
just start with sharing one thing you're grateful for or one blessing in your life let's do
one round of that one round of that all around and then you can share anything you like
about anything you wish about your practice something that was challenging something that was
inspiring something creative that you work through so um that's the invitation so
let me make the rooms and here we go
[Music] okay i'm opening here we go
the rooms are closed so we've got a couple of minutes we'd love to hear what you discovered in
um practicing together and and discussing so especially if you haven't shared
please if you'd like to raise your hand or type in chat i'll wait a minute and
actually while i'm waiting for you to raise your hand i'll say that this is not an easy practice
because of exactly these um challenging emotions that come up
wanting some especially with respect to what we did tonight someone we have
entanglements with this is it's a challenging practice and yet and yet we work towards it so if you if
you found it challenging great you're discovering the
purification power of this practice so hang in here hang in here hang in
here it's very very very common for this to come up and i remember years ago um for me also when i was a
beginner practitioner these are the things that would come up and there's a lot of purification what happened
so this is part of it this is part of it don't feel like you're failing or you're not doing it right
you're doing it exactly right this is what's supposed to happen on the way to to purification of
emotions and wanting and the contraction so it's all good so and really appreciate nancy for
bringing it up yes enough hey good morning nikki oh morning now
talking about uh entanglements um i'm wondering about the relationship of this
practice with expectation so you know the idea that you know an expectation can be a contract with
ourselves to be unhappy until we get what we want so um are we really ultimately working
with um our expectation of the other in this practice
so so um what i heard you say is or what i
understood you say was is all the maybe one thing that's making this practice challenging is that
this idea that we have this understanding that until we get what we want we won't be
happy and oh other people have what we want and also there's the scarcity mentality perhaps that could be a part of that oh
they have what what we want and we want that too so and and uh
happiness without conditions we can be happy um this this my my
one of my favorite quotes happiness is a choice you make it's not about what you have which is
part of this path it's really so um it's about realizing that the even if you had what
you think would make you happy there's still more to want so
it's it's yeah this this can this is a huge teaching
both in terms of selfing just being happy for your own happiness and wanting what you want
uh and and also as you brought up beautifully this expectation that what you want will make
you happy and that person is happy because they have what you want it's just all these implications that
you're pointing to um yeah thank you enough anything else you want to add if i missed
what you were trying to bring up yeah i'd love for you to just touch a little bit on generosity
and kind of cultivating that quality of fullness i mean i think um you know the that base
in which all action springs from um i wonder if like that's the base quality that
really needs to be cultivated in order to kind of have this right view yeah yeah it is and and it's
you know it's interesting because um there are so many different ways that this practice works there's so many
different ways that it works so um for some people it does work with
this sense of abundance and generosity of spirit and this concept that i've brought into
into this meeting a lot uh through this sense of generosity of
spirit um and for example the example of the little fairy that i was bringing up
for you to try on is this sense of generosity of spirit this little fairy
who's not attached to an ego or herself is just generous just generous
so that could be one way that works for some people for some people that doesn't work it might the need might be to go through
the pain of wanting oh i really want this and i don't have it and ouch that's painful
really working through the emotions of contraction and wanting and selfing so
there are many many different paths to the temple uh nav and what you're bringing up is
one path a beautiful path and there's it's it's very individual it's not one size fits all
yeah thank you thanks for bringing that up yeah good to see you so
um [Music] one quick question from bill
purification implies that these negative states lessen over time correct yes correct
that is a correct bill so the time has come for us to bring this session to an
end so thank you all thank you for your practice for your generosity of heart to show up
for yourself and all those whose lives you touch may you all be well may you be safe
happy and free [Music]
thank you