hello everyone and
here on this friday we come to the end of the series on faith
and i'll probably say this later as well but um
there's so much to say about faith and i've over there over the these
months on youtube i think i've talked about it a few times including the topic of refuge
so there's a lot to say but i prefer and maybe it's the truth
not to know what faith really is there's something to me quite marvelous
about not knowing but trusting or allowing or
feeling something here and
you know i think i'm a fairly rational person who
reasons and thoughtful and and i also uh tremendously value the way
that then mindfulness we do know we don't know we don't we know that this
we know the particulars of this moment the the we know our experience as it's
unfolding in the moment for itself and there's a clarity that arises with
mindfulness that we really know and the deeper we go and mindfulness practice the positive
practice the greater the knowing quality is and at the same time
the process the unfolding the larger picture of what all this is this
human life of ours you know there's so much that i don't know and
and uh mindfulness has placed me in the middle of all of it with a deep trust
a deep confidence a deep faith that
is heartfelt that that is a kind of close to a kind of love or warmth storm
a sense of um you know maybe in kind of an in a
language that's not becoming popular a sense of this is a belonging here
of being at home here and
in one of the definitions of belonging that i'm fond of is the idea that belonging is the
capacity to give care
and to receive care the capacity to give and receive care
so rather than belonging being a passive thing rather than faith trust or place here in
this world is passive uh it does involve the capacity to give
and receive care and so that capacity what is that
how can we center ourselves in the present moment and expand this capacity
and one way is to expand our capacity to just know this
the more we can know this and trust this have faith in this have confidence in our ability to be present
for this the greater become becomes our capacity to care
so the simple word i'd like to offer today for this practice
is the word this t-h-i-s and perhaps uh
that little introduction i just gave can add some uh some
greater dimensions to the simple maybe humble word this
that this is really a doorway to a greater capacity to belong to be at
home in this universe and but not at home in a way that is
passive but awakens our hearts capacity to care in a deep way
to give and receive care so that's what i recommend today is if
you'd like you might try as you meditate here to use the word this
and maybe the richness of that word word or what it points to can awaken in your heart
so to begin to
belong to the place in which you're sitting
there's a long tradition in buddhism to take the particular place you happen to be
meditating in the physical location of where you're that which receives the weight of your
body as being
you're the spot of awakening this spot this location
and so to feel the weight of your body being held by whatever that supports it
and maybe appreciate the support and that contact
and to relax and soften the gaze of your eyes
so you're not really looking at anything staring at anything
letting the eyes relax in the eye sockets
and if it's comfortable for you you're welcome to close your eyes
and as you exhale to release the holdings of your body
perhaps through your not relaxing your muscles releasing
your heart your mind from your concerns
not to abandon them but to let them be put aside for these few minutes
it's okay to allow yourself to be here in this
experience
relaxing deeply
and taking a few moments to feel your global body whatever way is easy
for you to be aware of your body a particular area of your body
or the whole body whatever comes easy to you
there's a tradition in buddhism to take your body as the meditation center the meditation hall
and to breathe in within this body
experiencing how the body experience knowing how the body experiences breathing
maybe as broadly as you can become aware of
the impact breathing has on the body
as you exhale relaxing the tensions contractions
tightness of the mind
the pressure that might be associated with thinking
perhaps by stepping away from your concerns
and instead appreciating
the totality of our minds all that it does for us
stepping away from our concerns so there can be a greater appreciation
of this here
and then settling into your breathing maybe using the word this
when you breathe in this in breath
gently saying this as you exhale this exhale
or if you find yourself thinking you might say this this too was included in awareness
this is a marvel it's a wonder
a sound body sensation this
that opens the door to not to a
rejection of anything but this too is where we find belonging
care the ability to receive and give care
to be in your present moment experience
and to recognize it as this
this which welcomes everything including
yourself into being
into belonging here now
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to appreciate that we have the capacity to
give and to receive care and then when we meditate
we're doing both giving care to ourselves and receiving
care from the meditation from the dharma
and to feel degree of gratitude or appreciation
for the circle of care
that happens in meditation
and then at the end of the meditation to expand that circle of care
out into the world we receive so much from the world
the air we breathe the water we drink the food the farmers provide
so many people in the world are doing services that sustain our life
our lifestyle and it is a kind of care
that we receive and then we can return that care
and live in a circle of giving and receiving care
and this is what it means to belong one meaning of belonging
and so at the end of the sitting to consider whatever benefit we receive
from this practice known or unknown
immediate or benefit that comes over time
may that be somehow
transformed or inspire us
to share those benefits with others to extend ourselves
to serve and care for the world around us
may we contribute to the welfare and happiness
of others may the benefits of our practice
spread from us out into the world and
providing peace compassion care generosity
love good will out into the world
so that all beings may one day experience
happiness and peace and freedom and safety
may this practice we do benefit the world
[Music]
so before i begin this talk a couple of announcements
at the end of the talk i'll open a zoom room and we can have a community meeting
and on zoom and now the zoom link is um right now it's posted at the right near the second
to the top chat in the chat uh here and i'll post it again at some point
at the bottom near the bottom of the chat and i'll just i'll tell you when at the after the talk
and it's also um on the youtube page if you look probably underneath below the
the video picture that's going on where it says inside meditation center and some details there
it also has the zoom link there you might have to copy and paste it
and finally it's also on on the what's new
section of imc's home page and the bottom right hand corner there's a set little section called what's new
and they're one of the top things there is a link to the
you click on the click on the heading and then it takes you to the link for this um our meeting here
and it might be in the calendar i don't know if it made it there the imc calendar
and um so hopefully all those with the areas work and if you uh and then the second is
that um today and then again on sunday is a day that all the
donations which aren't specified clearly for other purposes all the donations that are coming into imc
uh we'll turn around and and give them to partners in health it's a wonderful
non-profit that does work in haiti and they're kind of on the ground working
with uh some 5 000 or so local health care providers people working in villages
nurses and doctors in the rural countryside all over um and where they're partnering with
people there to provide the kind of care that both the haitian government is not doing
and and many people don't have access to help so many people there who are suffering from the earthquake from
poverty from storms from uh now now a dysfunctional government
and so to support people there and i think it's a wonderful thing and these neighbors of ours
or can we say are our fellow citizens on our north american
kind of continent here and um
so it'd be lovely to see our youtube community we've never done this before kind of come together and as a group
kind of care for to offer you know we talk about benefiting the world the end of our sitting and here's a chance maybe to do
it more as a community so um
so thank you so for the talk today
um the general topic maybe the title can be service
faith as service and then and the idea of service um
is uh to offer care and but to offer care in that when we combine the idea of faith
uh it's maybe it's associated a little bit with devotion a little bit with trust a little bit with generosity
that faith is uh can also involve not only what we receive if what we trust
and kind of just allow for it's also something deeper in that it's also a wellspring of what we offer
that it's an action of expression of our love an expression of our faith expression of
where we place our hearts what uh what inspires us in some deep way
and and so faith is not we're only recipients in having faith we're
actually givers and to really have faith i think it really
helps to also to if there is a feeling or recognition
inside that there's a desire for action to do something
and many times it's its desire to serve um
whatever the source is for the faith to support it to help it out to benefit
it but it could be faith can this kind of the service aspect of faith
doesn't have to be to some particular the source of the faith your religion
for example or your community religious community or practice community but it could be
faith can elicit this desire to out of love or a care compassion out of
a fullness of heart to uh serve oh people anywhere in the world maybe
haiti maybe other places maybe your neighbors maybe more fully in your own family
and this idea of service to serve is a beautiful thing of the heart
it's a there's um it's kind of a wonderful rich multifaceted quality of generosity
of love of care and there's something about caring that's really uh
part of freedom non-clinging which i talked about yesterday as we don't cling to anything there's
much more room in the heart than the mind to be responsive to the world around us
responsive to the suffering and the joys of the world and to respond in a way that feels like uh we're expanding
um the the faith or expanding our freedom expanding our love out into the world in
some wonderful way and so to serve out of faith
is not to want anything in return but rather it's just a clear clean
expression of generosity of serving something that's valuable to
serve and uh and this language that i use in the meditation that
the circles of giving and receiving and to have those circles be to flow and
move and and turn freely not to be clogged up or stopped or not have the brakes on or
um you know if a wheel if you take the you know half of the wheel away
it's not a wheel anymore it won't roll you need the whole wheel to roll and so the wheel of giving and receiving
giving and receiving that arises not out of a should not out of obligation
but from being settled in some deep way in our hearts in a way that
something here we trust here we have a devotion to here we have
confidence in yesterday i talked about the confidence and non-clinging and to rest in that confidence is not a
passive thing but it it's kind of like the soil
the nutrients for then responding to the world
a response which again i want to emphasize is not an obligation but it feels like the most natural thing in the
world it's just what flows out of it the liberated heart
the heart and the heart that's filled with this kind of dharma faith that heart that goes for refuge
is not a passive heart it's one that has an orientation and a motivation and inspiration
to act in a new way to live a new way and uh and one of the ways of
understanding this is to live with care to uh to offer care
to care for [Music] you know it's in some ways it's natural
to care for um i think i you know say it a little differently um one of the wonderful
things to do is to care for the place in which you're practicing
that's part of the practice is the care for the place you practice part of
practice is to care for the world in which you practice
and that world spreads out beyond any walls beyond any boundaries and
open-ended and so to do that with it as a sense of
the kind of service that is almost like a devotional service or
an expression of love or good will so i've talked about all these different
qualities characteristics of faith this week and there's many more faith is a rich rich capacity
thing and and as i said in meditation i think that
i actually prefer not to have not to believe that i know exactly what faith is
i can talk about different aspects of it but it feels much more in harmony with
faith with this deep trust not to know fully what it is and not knowing
to open myself to like trust it or appreciate something
larger and bigger than anything i could know anything that i could um
have control over or possess or or
and so there's a kind of a wonderful feeling of of this willingness
to be open that doesn't have to know but is ready to serve ready to care
ready to participate in this world as if i belong here we belong here
we're belonging is this wonderful circle of giving and receiving care
and maybe in the end this practice that we do
is a practice that
transforms us into free beings
that are deeply connected to our communities and our world in this mutuality of giving and
receiving care this so service
is an element of faith so thank you