warm greetings from imce in redwood city california
and we're here
maybe also to enjoy the light show that will happen in this time of year as the sun goes up we have these very big
windows here and there's a this time of year that for a few minutes the
sun gets very intense through that windows and so uh right now that's clear and a
little while maybe it'll be a little bit too strong and then it'll get
changed keeps changing the light show so um so changes our minds
and uh probably our minds can be sometimes more changeable than
the changing patterns of the sunlight on the wall and and uh and maybe you can marvel like
your own mind and all the if you marvel at the changing nature of the mind and
the amazing things and thoughts and impulses that arise in the mind and
kind of be amazed that you even have a mind as opposed to getting caught by what's
in the mind or preoccupied what's in the mind
one of the descriptions of a mind that is imbued
fully imbued with metta with loving-kindness is that it becomes unlimited
boundless and what this means in part is that the mind is not caught or
trapped in anything so if we are fully preoccupied with
something we might not notice anything else
we go about even looking for something in our home that's lost
we might not notice other things just we're just looking for that particular thing or we're preoccupied with some task and
we don't hear that don't notice the other people
around or their needs or their situation and and the same thing we notice in meditation that the mind can be
preoccupied with things with thoughts with desires with aversions
and everything gets kind of narrow constricted kind of organized the mind around that
particular thing and then in the buddhist language the mind then has been limited by that
has been bounded by that concern that
preoccupation and the idea is to begin to free the
mind from its narrowness from its uh limitations from his preoccupations
and start experiencing something in the mind that feels more unlimited more expansive and open and um
and a little bit paradoxically that it's possible to uh to get involved with mindfulness or
breathing in such a way that the breathing we become preoccupied with the breathing and we're limited by it
constricted by it some people who find that mindfulness of breathing doesn't work for them is because
the only way they know maybe how to focus on it is in a way that limits them or constricts the mind or
or it ties us up in some way the um but the idea is that as we use the ma
the breathing as a way to free the mind from all its limitations all its preoccupations
not add another preoccupation so to find a way to engage in the mind that
in the breathing that has a softness to it openness to it a receptivity to it
it's kind of like welcoming the breathing into the openness of the mind rather than constricting the mind to
zero in on the breathing and as we do that the world might get reduced to just
breathing it can be a real pleasure this way absorbing the breathing breathing in a mind that feels unlimited
but is not caught up in all the things of the world around it
and the so to have an unlimited mind or
unlimited awareness that's not caught by anything is the one of the conditions that
supports uh some of the wholesome qualities of our
hearts and minds and one of those is is kindness is good will is friendliness
that sometimes seems to just flow out of that unlimited quality of mind
so to take a assume and meditation posture
and to spend a little bit of time adjusting your spine adjusting your
chest adjusting whatever you can your torso
and your position of your neck and your head so that your body
begins to feel like maybe it feels a little bit larger than usual or more
ready to be expensive not contracted not crunched in itself or collapsed
then to gently close your eyes
and taking a few deep slow breaths at the beginning
can be seen as the beginning of this movement towards expansion now kind of an expanded body is the
torso expands filling with air
and then the exhale had time to let go of thoughts preoccupations
activities just being here
expanding on the inhale
making room for the expansion by clearing the mind
releasing the limitations of the mind as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and there's such a intimate relationship between the body and the mind that
it plays out also in the tensions in the body the way the body is
held in some ways it's an expression of tension in the mind
so as you exhale softening relaxing the shoulders
releasing the shoulders sometimes can feel like it begins a process of relaxing the mind
maybe releasing as you exhale the center of the chest
relaxing the chest
and to relax your belly
soften and as you whatever softening you can do in your belly
maybe allow it to be a softening of the mind as well
and then also a relaxing softening of the face
and in the softening of the muscles of the face maybe it sends a reassuring signal
to the mind that it doesn't have to work it doesn't have to do so much
it's okay to put down concerns preoccupations
doings
and then before now before settling in and breathing
check in with yourself and see if there is any
see if there is any preoccupations in the mind
that can be felt as a limitation as a narrowing of the mind or
or being pulled into something particular
thoughts fantasies ideas
that limit your connection to an openness and a res wider receptivity
and then perhaps you can relax the thinking mind
relax the thinking muscle
and then settling into your breathing
settled on your breathing not fixated on your breathing
as you exhale
to let go of your thoughts and let go of any kind of tight
contracted effort
as you inhale perhaps using that as an occasion to have the
awareness be receptive open
wide in the open wideness of awareness
to receive the inhale
and when you find yourself wandering off in thought notice that in a wholesome way
but notice whatever way it limits you limits the field of attention
or involves a narrowing or a
or a preoccupation
and if you can let go of it see if you can let go of it into a more open
receptive state quiet peaceful
into which you can allow the experience of breathing
relaxing the constrictions of the mind in the heart
and then in that relaxation you receive the inhale
relax with the exhale
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
perhaps you can consider these last few minutes of the meditation
as kind of a private time and that what you do in this privacy of
your own meditation only you need to know
so with that sense of maybe kind of privacy maybe it's easier to open your awareness
open your heart to make room for all beings
to make room for others to come into your awareness
meaning that you're not preoccupied by something or fixated on some aspect of the
relationship to others or some some fear or annoyance
some defensiveness but for these minutes to open up wide
and make lots of room infinite room for others to be in your awareness
in your regard and nothing more is asked of you from
this moment than just simply making room at the end of the meditation you can let
them go and not hold them anymore in your mind or your heart if you want
and perhaps in this kind of open receptive mode
including people in your heart and your mind perhaps in your privacy of your mind you
can also
have good will for them
a kind regard
a generosity of spirit that wishes them well
imagines themselves them well and wishing it for them
and perhaps
coming out of the meditation perhaps you can in that openness
goodness of the heart aspire
that your meditation practice in whatever way known or not or unknown intentional or
unintentional
has benefit for the world around you that it's one of the ways that
we live for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
and may the open expansiveness of our hearts and minds
contribute to that possibility
so then this is the fourth talk
on the meta sutta the discourse on loving-kindness and
the first talk i said there was dividing into four parts and maybe maybe we are but uh it's also
i'll do five talks so the next section of it
is about the cultivation of lovingkindness so first is kind of the the
the the wholesome qualities of heart and mind that we cultivate on the
path to liberation and then it's the wish having this wish
the wish doesn't have to be with these words but wish that for all beings to be happy and safe
and then to really get to the bottom to work with our aversion our anger
our resentments because these limit us these are a narrowing of the scope of
the mind and awareness it involves a preoccupation to be angry and resentful
and when they're preoccupied there's not room for really taking in the world taking in
others in an open-hearted open-minded way
and then with that as a foundation then the practice of this of this
discourse on loving-kindness goes on to emphasize the cultivating
uh a boundless heart cultivating and developing with loving-kindness cultivating an
unlimited heart or mind and um so it's not just simply having
wishes and simply having the you're saying phrases over and over again it's not really the point of loving
kindness but the phrases are there to support and help if we do them if they help to create
this uh open awareness this openness of heart this ability to be wide
to include others into our awareness without contracting or narrowing or
resisting without getting caught up in desires and aversions and fears
a very simple state of mind that's there that's open and available to really absorb or take in or receive
the experience but so open so boundless in a sense
that uh it doesn't stick with us it doesn't the others don't kind of
almost like more transparent and things just go right through us not because we're dismissing them but
because it's the limitations of the mind the way that we uh uh contract and and
get preoccupied that are sticky and we get caught in the the world of
other people in our world of our reactions and moving to the mind that's free
is a mind that is not has no stickiness in it so things just kind of are fully
experienced but they also in a sense go through or don't stick anywhere
so this is called an unlimited mind or heart a boundless heart and mind
and so this next section then goes like this and uh on youtube you'll see it in the
description of this episode that's on the underneath the video if you click on show more you scroll
down and you'll see this fourth part of the metasuta
as a mother would risk her life
to protect her child her only child so towards all beings should one
cultivate a boundless heart with loving kindness for the whole world
should one cultivate a boundless heart above below and all around without
obstructions without hate and without ill will so for some people it's a
touching metaphor this idea of a mother with a single child going to the extent of protecting the
child um at the risk of her own life uh
you know that it involves a kind of non-self-preoccupation and when i was a
parent of young children especially it felt was much more acute than where uh it just i didn't feel so
important i was willing to put aside all kinds of personal needs because it just seemed like the
importance of this child this little baby couldn't take care of itself was so much more important and there was
this uh wonderful feeling a healthy feeling uh most of the time in this kind of just
giving myself over giving myself you know up in a certain kind of way for the welfare of this other person and
um and uh in some ways i when it was done well i felt that you know
it wasn't because i was trying to benefit myself but i could feel this was really good
when i did it uh in a ways that were unhealthy then it would come back and bite me and
it would you know didn't really work but this idea of a parent protecting
their child now it isn't that we're supposed to risk our lives protect
all other beings in this text at least but rather it's that kind of letting go of self
this boundless this is lots of space for doing the inclusive of others in our
hearts that that we're cultivating
in doing loving-kindness practice we're developing not only through loving-kindness but i think through
the path of liberation is a path that we're in the mind the heart is no longer as
i've been saying today limited contracted preoccupied um resistant shut down closed off
it's just completely open and receptive and and like a open window the wind can wind
can just go right through or the kids baseball that they're playing outside won't break the
glass because it just goes right through and so
to cultivate that and cultivate as a very powerful word because it doesn't mean that we're
supposed to do it automatically and that you're bad if you don't it means that there's practice you practice
it you practice and practice and practice this is what we're working towards and
and it's not and more we practice the more we're moving in this direction
if the practice has a quality to it or parts of it is
this openness is this relaxing this receptivity this not getting tight and not getting forceful
not getting all kinds of unwholesome movements of needing and wanting and expecting and
pushing away but rather it really has a quality that as we do the practice
something is opening something is releasing something's making more room there's more and more room for things
when people become mature in buddhist practice their mind has lots of room
for things infinite room and sometimes you can feel that spaciousness in others because their
mind doesn't move as much you don't you don't find them you don't see the mind jumping around or you
don't see the agitation or the restlessness or the or the deflecting or the turning away
there's an openness and a quiet a willing just be there in a kind of open stillness
in that maturity with loving kindness for the whole world
should one cultivate a boundless heart so this is the you know the upper reaches of
real loving kindness certainly in the privacy of our meditation
alone it's easy to love everyone or relatively easy to love everyone and to
feel like universal love is a great thing but it's when we really run into people and are working with
people and and engaging in people and sharing lives with people that the idea of loving all beings
sometimes just gets lost and it gets you know recedes from importance because of the drama and the
preoccupations and the importance and the irritation and the injustice of whatever
is happening in the moment with
and so the idea of cultivating a boundless heart
with loving kindness for the whole world is the direction we're going
but to do that is not only learning how to let go a lot but it's also learning how to be wise
and have street smarts about how that is expressed and how to live in this world that's so complicated and difficult
and how to live it and live it in a safe way in a wise way and in a so
that we can have this boundless loving kindness um we don't want to do boundless loving
kindness and be naive in a certain kind of way easily
victimized by what goes on around us cultivate a boundless heart with loving
kindness for the whole world should one cultivate a boundless heart above
below and all around without obstruction without hate and without the ill will so this
obstructions ways and mind is limited the the two that are really
big in relationship to our capacity for love is hate and ill will big words
but they have a very they can have very subtle manifestations and sometimes it's the
subtlest manifestations that are really the cutting edge the growing edge of our practice
so even the subtle ways we don't overlook we don't um say doesn't matter
and you know or you know just easier just to go ahead and do it and and but you know even the subtlest forms
of hate and ill will to find out how to live without those obstructions without
those limitations so cultivating a boundless heart above below and all around
uh uh some people experience this as a kind of irradiance
a glow a warmth some people has a sense of light that's not really light but that's the
closest the clarity the openness that feels like it's a radiating light and
and this idea of radiance loving kindness is based on the idea of
an intention but that intention doesn't have to be a mental exercise we keep saying words of
may all beings be happy the words are can be useful but uh as a practice as the
heart gets more and more boundless it becomes more of a glow more of a
clarity more of a openness that we can feel that goes out in all directions 360
degrees all around is the attention it's not focused narrowly on something and
only that but it's opened up 360 degrees with the kindness with the goodwill with
the friendliness with the radiance this glow of kindness above below and all around
it's phenomenal the human capacity to dwell in love to dwell in
good will to dwell in kindness and friendliness it's
phenomenal that we can kind of have that be the predominant mood the predominant field of attention
the predominant flow of concern that we have
and and to be integrated and harmonized and all of us kind of all of us kind of centered in
in meta is a phenomenal capacity that we should be
born this way to have this capacity is just fantastic and it's a capacity we can cultivate and
develop and grow and sometimes it's done intentionally doing
meta practice and sometimes it's a byproduct of just doing mindfulness practice
as a mindfulness frees us from the limitations of the mind we can begin to recognize
that in fact living in our hearts waiting for us has been love has been
good will and then it's a matter of making more space for it
just as you make space for more people in your heart you make more space in your heart
for your love so thank you and then we also have one more talk on
this tomorrow