good evening welcome welcome
nice to see you all and how is the volume does it sound okay
is it okay yeah yeah okay i'm not sure if we're live on youtube
but if we are welcome to everybody out there also
i had a little bit of technical difficulties earlier but what is it like okay great
maybe before i turn on the recording i'll just mention that um
there are conversations about with the omicron variant whether imc should
consider closing again no decisions have been made and right now we're the plan is to stay open
but i just want to let you know that that might change in the next week or two or something like this so
just a heads up about that okay
so really warm welcome it's nice it's nice to practice together
while we were sitting you know sometimes we hear the rustle of somebody shifting their posture and somehow it just made
me happy there's you know human bodies here individuals here together you know
practicing it was so thank you
so tonight i want to talk a little bit about something that seems so obvious
like it seems like we shouldn't even have to talk about it and yet there's a way that there can be
a depth about it and there can be some real awakening or some new understanding when we really
look at it we kind of unpack it or explore it in some kind of way
and that is this idea that that actions we take whether they are of body speech or mind
so whether they're thoughts i'm i'm putting thoughts in there with this uh category of uh actions
actions have consequences there's a cause and effect
and this is not anything new to anybody in this room
in fact i think there's even like a physics law about this right for every action
there's an equal and opposite reaction right it's so fundamental that even the physicists are
have talked about it and so
we know this that if we are dishonest with a friend and
our friend discovers this or even if they don't discover it but it there it affects our relationships
if we spend a lot of time being angry at the news
then our minds get filled with being with angry thoughts
and we tend to just be have a lot of tension
and anger inside of us and of course there's this teaching that
that which one ponders becomes the inclination of the mind
right so we're kind of like priming the the mind to just be more readily angry
if we're just fueling it all the time so to be sure some things have little
impact on our lives that we experience maybe
there's not a big impact that we have to wait in line a little bit longer at the grocery store for example
some things have large impact if we find ourselves behaving unethically this
could unfold in a way that has large impact if we do a lot of meditation that can be
a way that also there's a big impact so some of the impacts some of the
consequences are small it might even be dismissive and some are large
but there is nothing that doesn't have any impact and part of the buddhist practice is to
just thoroughly recognize this and to thoroughly understand this
that of course things have consequences and this simple idea
which now is so commonplace for all of us wasn't so obvious at the time of the buddha
in fact there's um another teacher a non-buddhist that the
gets described in a number of different places in the sutas and a little excerpt of what this other
teacher would say makali gosala he would say there is no cause or
condition for the corruption of beings there is no cause or condition for the
purification of beings all beings all living creatures all
sentient beings that control power and energy instead they are molded by destiny
by circumstance by nature so this idea that something out there
was responsible for whatever happened to a person
so it didn't matter what a person did there was something out there and it wasn't ever
for this particular teacher wasn't clearly described what that was
but this idea then that people doesn't matter what we do doesn't matter
no consequences
we might say but the buddha's teaching on the four noble truths
is the opposite there are consequences
there's a number of different ways in which we can approach the formal truths we can emphasize different parts and
we can translate some of the words a little bit differently but one way to look at this is
that there is dukkha right the first noble truth there is dukkha
we can translate dukkha as just this dissatisfaction like just things are not
quite right and maybe we can't even like necessarily put our finger on it
it just feels dissatisfying or just not not
not perfect all the way to dukkha being the suffering of
tremendous physical pain that humans can do experience
tremendous emotional pain that humans can experience so this dukkha from
just the something not quite being right to great pain
first normal truth there is dukkha and then the second noble truth there is a cause
for dukkha is a consequence of something else
there's a reason that it's there it doesn't mean that we know it it doesn't mean that it's obvious to us but it does mean that
it's not like magic or you know sometimes or somehow it's uh
have been happening from some other reason that has nothing to do with
humans or i guess it might be right i mean weather and these types of things that
happen but i'll unpack this a little bit more about what i mean by dukkha
so the second noble truth there's a cause third there is a cessation of dukkha and fourth there's a way leading
to this cessation so practicing this path
requires that we recognize that there are actions that bring us dukkha
and there's actions that bring us non-duka we might say freedom peace ease
and so much about this practice is just recognizing okay
is this going towards dukkha or no is it going towards freedom and we could interpret the four noble
truths this way and without this understanding of course it's really difficult to have our lives
unfold in a particular way that everything has consequences and we can consider whether
those constant consequences are more duca or less duca
maybe what i've been saying it's like okay okay diana we know this isn't our
first dharma talk we've heard about the formidable truths we've heard about dukkha
but something that i appreciate so much about the dharma is how it's there's this depth and this breath
when we really explore we can find something that
meets us wherever we are we hear about teachings we read suitas we practice
again and again and then sometimes our understandings start to shift our
the way it touches us starts to shift and we start to even though we might have seen it so many times we might see
it in a new way and understand something differently and that we didn't understand before
and i'd like to suggest that our understanding of dukkha shifts
as we practice probably many of you have this experience
i know that i remember this so clearly that um a dharma teacher
i was having a practice discussion and a dharma teacher said something to me about
suffering and i said i don't have any suffering
you know i had just quit my job at that time and i was feeling you know pretty great like wow i had attributed like all
my difficulties with you know having this job but
not realizing that this is our meditation
practice starts to grow and we start to experience more and more calm
as we start to experience more and more peace then our definition of dukkha kind of shifts along with that
and we start to notice oh yeah there are more and more subtle
experiences and expressions of dukkha
so we can start to become that it starts to become that which is less calm
that which is less open
that which is less quiet so dukkha can be understood as
this tightening as this constriction which can be really subtle
and maybe it shows up primarily in our meditation practice or maybe it shows up in really obvious gross ways in our
daily life as well but we can explore this world of actions
and consequences by looking at duka
because for some people they're suffering their difficulties their why things aren't going the way that they
wish it's a little bit of a mystery to them why isn't my life the way that i
thought it was going to be or why is i why is there this suffering why is there this sense of dissatisfaction and often
we look in the wrong places for the cause
it's a habit that many of us have it's a human habit to blame
somebody else did something wrong this has to be fixed somebody better fix it
this is not right with we might blame ourselves
if i only i were a better meditator if only i were a better this better that it would uh
then this uh suffering wouldn't be here often people are looking outside
themselves okay i have to fix this out there i have to engineer manipulate can
manufacture you know somehow create some different conditions in order to see for the dukkha
or sometimes people just are complaining not even having some clear idea of what is the source of dukkha
we can bring attention bring care to this dukkha
without self-pity without blame but to look at it and to see the action
that is underlying that is fueling that is the cause for
this uh constriction that is dukkha
very often that action is attachment or clinging and
so much about practice can be loosening the constructions kind of be about
loosening this uh the tightening that happens around
that causes stuka
so this clinging this attachment can be really subtle and when we find ourselves experiencing
duca we can just ask okay what is where is there any sense of tightness any sense of holding on
any sense of clinging it's likely that we will discover that
this clinging this tightness that's holding on this contraction
is related to having a sense of self stuff that we want to be a particular
way or we want to not be a particular way
and there's a particularly strong sense of self when there is blame
there's this often a sense of self-righteousness that arises like don't they know who i am what what are
they thinking or when we make a mistake or something goes wrong we most
often are turning towards blame and there's this exaggerated and flexible sense of me or you
and the kind of he said she said i said i don't think that happens often we're
blaming ourselves or blaming others and then these negative self views or
these negative views of others they tend to like fuel themselves or fuel each
other creating this vicious duka cycle
so i would like to propose or suggest there's a way in which we can find our
way out of this that we can uh interrupt these dukkha
cycles and one way is to
re-look at re-analyze and experience experience in which we're having dukkha
and look at it again maybe it's on the cushion or outside of the cushion as a way to understand
what are the conditions that came together that are supported this experience of
difficulty this experience of dukkha
is there a way that we can look at that from a different angle with maybe a heart of compassion
and with it in the service of compassion to recognize that there are so many different
conditions that come together so many like countless conditions that
come together and whenever is happening right something is the consequence of all
kinds of different things us being here together as a consequence
of this building being built and
things on the internet that's on the calendar and however transportation you use to get
here right it's countless things that come together so to illustrate this i'd like to share
a story this story is from rob verbaea and
it gives an example of how one might do this
so imagine that you're or perhaps this actually happened
you were with a friend and your friend is telling you some difficulty she is going through
and you're listening as attentively or sympathetically as you can but at the same time
you're also aware of some disquiet within yourself and
you're vaguely worried that maybe you should have a little more empathy or you should have some more compassion
for your friend some but they're telling you this story about difficulty somehow you feel
unmoved not really touched by what this is saying and
later when you reflect on this it bothers you and you wonder is there
something wrong with me why wasn't i able to connect with my friend
and maybe you have this idea well i've been doing all this practice
and am i just a cold-hearted person after all how come i couldn't uh connect with
this person that i care about but that way of considering
that particular activity or that particular um experience
is where you're focusing on yourself and holding only yourself responsible for how things went
fails to see it fails to take into account a whole range of other factors
that contributed that's contributed to limiting the connection you felt with your friend for
example it could be something really basic
maybe you had a headache and you weren't quite feeling your
the best version of yourself a little bit feeling a little bit off maybe you were tired
we shouldn't underestimate right how human beings are not the best versions of themselves when they are tired
and when we are often sometimes when we are putting pressure on ourselves to feel something different
than what we're actually feeling we have this idea i should really be more sympathetic or
empathetic or compassionate towards my friend and yet i'm not when we are putting pressure on
ourselves to feel something that we're not then often we feel disconnected from
ourselves and disconnected from other people around us so maybe even just having that idea i
should be different kind of created the conditions for things to unfold a little bit in a different way
so maybe that's one thing that was happening but maybe that's something a little bit
more complex maybe there was some slight tension between you
and your friend that was left unresolved the last time you met and something
small that at the time seemed insignificant but now is affecting you
maybe it's enough that it affects maybe your openness maybe you're feeling a little bit more guarded
or maybe there was something in the way that your friend herself the way that she was uh telling the story
like maybe she was telling the story that she was exaggerating in a way that felt a little
bit off like she herself was disconnected from the story
or maybe she felt like she was holding back or she was uh hamming it up being
dismissive whatever it meant whatever it was there might be a way in which she was behaving
so it's not that we definitely would now like blame our friend oh i felt i couldn't feel connected because she was
behaving in some particular way because right there's all these conditions of why she was behaving this way
the point here is that there are different types of
conditions that come together for every moment every one of our experiences and they
all have an impact on our experiences
so sometimes when we blame ourselves or we blame others
we're not taking into into account
these other conditions so one way we might do this to re-consider
review re-analyze an experience we had in which we feel like there's a lot of
blame either for ourselves or for others or that we feel constricted about or any time in which there's a lot of duca
for example is um and there are some tools that can be helpful it can be feel cumbersome
also so i offer these just so that they might be helpful i myself i find i do this when i get
stuck when i feel like i'm blaming myself or blaming others about some difficulty
i sometimes use these different tools as a way to help
kind of kind of help like flesh out everything that happened so for example
what are some of the present inner conditions that happened at the time so what do i mean by that
what was the mind state that you had what was the what was the
emotional state what were beliefs or perceptions that were really active at
that time and the example that i gave tiredness
would uh be an example what are at the present outer conditions
for the story that i told it was the way in which your friend was relaying the story when she was telling it maybe
there was something that wasn't quite right or didn't feel quite right
so in the present moment what was happening in the inside your inner experience and what was happening in the
environment but then of course what were some of the conditions in the past
that related to this maybe there's habits of mind or
some um inner states that are affecting us and in the story i told
that would be that maybe there was something unresolved between you and your friend maybe there was some slight tension maybe you felt just a
little bit offended by something she said or you know and the time passed and so now
you're showing up just a little bit differently
or maybe there's these past uh outer conditions these impressions or influences we have from
our friends for or from our history so we can look at these different
categories as a way to help us see oh there's so many different
conditions that led to this consequence
of not feeling connected with my friend in this story
so rather than there's a having to blame or rather than saying okay i'm at fault or my friend is
at fault or or something like this instead we can just soften that whole idea of blame
soften the idea of that there's a self at the center of everything and recognize that there are so many
different things that come together and came together for that particular
experience and that has now gone away those
conditions are no longer there it doesn't mean that there still isn't some maybe some harm or some
feelings about it but now there can be some moving forward often when there's we're stuck in a
sense of blame there's a real stuckness we can't find our way forward
so this and i'm not saying that we don't um
accept responsibilities for our actions either and just say oh it's just conditions there's a no responsibility
this is so much about practice as recognizing yes there's these conditions that come together and we have
responsibilities to accept the consequences of our
actions and this is a big part about what it
means to be a mature practitioner too right is to recognize that some of the
consequences of our actions are uncomfortable dukkha
and then we practice with patients we practice with forbearance we practice with equanimity
we learn from these things so that we can in the future
perhaps not have as much difficulty
but this idea of looking at actions and consequences
that they can and rather than there being a self
which is often associated with blame not always but often it doesn't have to be at the center it
doesn't have to be like this stuckness there instead just to see oh all these things came together i had a part there
was these other parts and those they've gone away now and there's these
further consequences but just feel the
freedom that is available there when we don't have to make ourselves or
somebody else at the center and taking responsibility for everything
and so this part of practice is to recognize we take responsibility for our actions and
we recognize that lots of conditions come together including clinging
and often the clinging is so a sense of self so if we can soften the sense of self if we can soften the clinging
there'll be less duca and often this clinging is taken the form of blame not always not always but
often so in that way we might take this
idea of that actions have consequences a humdrum everyday thing that we know
and just more thoroughly apply it to everything everything in our life
and to help us kind of find our way with more ease
and less dukkha less dissatisfaction less suffering
so thank you
so i'll end there and um if you'd like you're welcome to
come up and and talk to me or i don't know if i yeah let's because i
already turned off the recording i was gonna say maybe i can do some q a in the whole if if somebody has a question that
they'd like to ask but yeah we don't have a microphone so
i don't know if anybody does
how do we use meditation to prevent future suffering i'm sorry i didn't tell you the first
part how do we use or how do we continue practicing or how does meditation essentially help us to prevent future
suffering yeah thank you that's a good question so i uh hinted at this at the beginning
as the mind and the body settle as we start to get more quiet with our
meditation we start to notice these movements of the heart these
movements of the mind that uh are more towards construction that are more towards a clinging
and so we start to just notice oh yeah when there's this movement towards letting go there's more ease and when
there's this movement towards clinging there's less ease and just that recognition that you have
to see ten times a hundred times a thousand times ten thousand times before we really start to see oh yeah
this movement of letting go is where the freedom is so in our regular ordinary life we often
don't see these subtle movements of constriction and and selfing because so
much of society really supports us to have a strong sense of self and
us versus them right there's so much of that out there but that's not the way towards
greater freedom and less dukkha was that helpful
yes bill
the longer i'm in buddhism
the more i start to get the feeling that even the slightest
little um pursing of the lips or knitting of the eyebrow
or maybe you know or clenching of the jaw just the slightest little facial movements
or maybe leaning forwards or leaning backwards in social situations
um have these or can have these subtle
effects or consequences that you mentioned
and so
and uh so i i think that's i think that's a good thing uh
to notice and to um try to
come back to just like mountain pose as we go through life or especially in social situations and
be relaxed i find when i'm in front of someone who is really relaxed around me
something in me just relaxes too so um
so i'm trying to pay attention to these subtle little things i do um uh what do you think is that sound good
i think that's fantastic bill and you're highlighting also kind of like the link between the body and the mind you know
of course but so often we're not we don't really know what's
going on there might be some tension but we don't know it until we notice something happening with our mind
i know for me this was a big impact years ago i found myself standing there with my hand on my hip like this
and i realized like oh i guess i'm feeling indictment you know i didn't even know i was right and
you know or tapping my foot you know this like feeling impatient or something like this but
absolutely and right we wouldn't maybe even notice this unless we really know what it's like to be
calm and settled then these little ways in which agitation gets expressed
really gets uh highlighted yeah thank you bill uh just just to add
it's it's been helpful for me to realize that people's antennae are very
sensitive they pick up all this stuff they may not fully
be aware that they're picking it up but maybe it's just part of evolutionary
biology but but i think we we do notice almost everything that goes on between
people yeah thank you i i would agree yeah we communicate so much right by our
body language in subtle ways yeah yeah thank you
anybody else ever have a comment
thank you for your talk uh one of the things that caught my attention i think one of the areas
that i struggle with the most is when you were talking about taking responsibility
because sometimes i think i rarely
consciously take on responsibility it see it always seems and maybe this is
wrong that the responsibility is laid on me from the outside
and so um i don't know if you've ever had that
experience but i was wondering how how do we work with
the dukkha that arises in not meeting
responsibility the duka that arises with not meeting
our responsibility yes or the i don't know if it's dukkha or just the
you know kind of seeing the con the consequences that come from not meeting responsibility
so but those are the consequences of so you're asking how to deal with the consequences of not taking consequence
or not taking responsibility and how would that be different than any
other consequence
maybe i'm not understanding the question yeah well i probably don't understand the
question either excellent that's great we'll find our way
otherwise it would probably be clearer to me but for example at work i you know i've
been assigned certain tasks to do and i just find
a resistance or you know it's just it's almost like i know yes that's my
responsibility and i'm pretty sure i'm not going to meet it
you know and so maybe that's the census i don't know if it's just the sense of self like i want to think of myself as a responsible
person so there may be some selfing involved in it some of it may be sloth and torpor that
i just don't have the energy to do it some of it is just there's some like
internal resistance of you know you know some sort of passive resistance
of being told what to do yeah so that that's that's kind of where i'm
it's the fuzzy edge of practice for me yeah i think that microphone maybe went
out
so what happened what would it look like if you were to do what i'm just suggesting here to look
at the different conditions that are coming together what are the
conditions inside of you in the present moment when you receive that email or your boss tells you you
have to do x y and z and you there's resistance what's that present moment experience and you maybe there's
times in which you get some responsibilities and you're okay with it and this time you're not or maybe you're
always not okay and what are some of the um
outer ones maybe it's the way you get asked or or you know something like this
and then there's the past also past inner ones like well i have this experience every time i do this it
doesn't it does it doesn't turn out in a way that makes me happy or something like this i'm making these up jim you
you would know for yourself but there's these are a way in which we can unpack it and
and so that some of the dukkha flows away and then there's a way in which uh
we can start to see oh yeah i see how i have this habit of showing up in these
situations in a particular way and then maybe we can work with that this one particular habit instead of
something that's a little bit bigger and complicated with lots of these different aspects playing together
does that make sense
thank you jim thank you
okay okay so with a deep bow of appreciation really
for your practice it's a it's lovely to practice together to
share this practice so thank you and if i don't see you before then i'm
wishing you all a happy new year and uh wishing you to take care and stay safe
thank you