okay all right so let's let's formally begin let's formally begin thank you
neil for posting information about the happy hour google groups where folks can
join and receive information quotes references
and share information with one another and
and i also change the settings at this time for for unmuting and the chat and last but
not least i will turn on the recording for the sake of audio dharma here we go
okay all right everyone so hello hello and welcome
to happy hour lovely to be with you to see you to feel you
ah whether you're joining in real time um on zoom or youtube or you'll be
listening later joining the sangha leader on um
uh on audiodharma or on youtube so so for for today's
practice um i'd like to bring up the theme of
transitions it seems like with with uh those of us
well either in northern or southern hemisphere if you're in the northern hemisphere um if the fall is coming and and
the colors on the trees in california we're finally having rain yay there's a transition there's a
transition in the air and if you're in southern hemisphere like mari christine
or dear sangha member different transitions yes spring spring
is springing right now i i trust and and so this sense of
transitions transitions um and
and transitions change change is a part of life is a
part of life we know this of course we know this uh yes change happens and yet how do we
feel how do we approach change how do we hold change as it arises for ourselves for others
and can we bring both menta to the wisdom of being with change
can we be can we bring equanimity can we bring a
sense of care warm-heartedness friendliness to change and again change somehow the
word change sometimes brings up this sense of fear like oh change goodness
change whereas sometimes change is positive change is good
changes yay rain um so change change how do we so so the
invitation tonight in our practice would be to open our hearts and our senses can we be
with with change whatever you know the waves of the ocean will always be here can we
be with them can we surf them with with warm-heartedness with metta
with equanimity which is one of the four brahmaviharas one of the four heavenly
abodes so so transitions change however they're
showing up for us um and drinking more awareness
um yeah that is basically the theme and we will explore it more in our um
[Music] yeah in our practice tonight so let's let's check it out let's try
let's start let's start by sitting let's start by landing
let's start by landing in our seat
hmm
can we arrive can we arrive transition can we embrace this transition
can we embrace the transition from busyness
can we transition busyness
to stillness
to being here
just here
can we just arrive and embrace this transition
what does this transition entail for us
landing settling arriving with the breath
with each breath each breath
and each breath each breath itself is a transition
each breath itself is the transition
constant movement
constant change
can we settle in open up to this constant sea of change
with each breath each in-breath each out-breath the
entirety staying staying steady
staying warm-heartedly steady with all the transitions
the in-breath the pause between the in-breath and out-breath
the out-breath and the pause again
each moment change
present present to change
with each breath relaxing into the change
embracing opening up our hearts and our awareness to the change
with each breath in each breath
and can we open up to all the changes in the body happening all the sensations
coming and going
there is a stillness of sitting and yet all the inner movements
the breath the sensations of breathing
all the sensations shifting
moving vibrations
can we receive them smilingly yes this is to be alive
transition change is part of being alive
can our awareness be steady steady and warm
steady and warm with the transitions
not turning away and not falling into
as our minds might wander away into thoughts and
memories of planets like little puppies running around it's okay it's all right
it's okay notice the transition away from the breath away from the body
to thought to memory yes yes movement transitions
can you not frown upon it to smile yes here it is that's what minds do
smilingly invite invite awareness
to transition back to settle
with the body with the breath steady with these transitions in the
body transitions also in the sound escape
sounds in the environment sound of my voice
noises they're not a problem nothing is a problem
all these transitions
from silence to sound from sound to silence from one note to another
can we embrace them wholeheartedly aware of them awareness unmoving
awareness kind wholehearted
it's warm-hearted
and notice that the mind can become very still the heart can become still
with the awareness of change
the mind the heart can become quite steady noticing change
how interesting
if you notice again your mind moving to a thought memory
coming back it's all change it's all change be
open and spacious with all these transitions
no need for judgment and for you to chastise yourself
noticing change aware of change with kindness
and wisdom
maybe you're sitting comfortably and then maybe part of your body starts to feel uncomfortable and painful ah
bring your awareness to change with kindness oh here is change
hello change hello transition
so not focusing on the content and oh yes akina but the process the process of
transition it wasn't here a moment ago now it's here
can i be warm-hearted open kind to the transition
or maybe you were sleepy and now you feel more awake or feel more relaxed more spacious more calm
yes you can receive the content let's say the calmness more calmness more peace
with appreciation
but instead of just the content see the process the transition from less
peace to more peace this transition this change
can we open our heart to change
not turn away receive it with kindness
with curiosity with stability steadiness
equanimity
relaxing interchange
with each breath change
notice how relaxing interchange with the breath
brings non-reactivity
stability of the heart and mind
transition from thinking into stillness stillness into thinking
stability with all the transitions
me
bringing an attitude of meta open-heartedness
to our awareness of change every moment every breath
sounds etc
can bring a sense of steadiness stability peace and joy
not the fear of change but the joy of change
the interest
the energy zest of change
if you notice your mind is thinking just notice the transition ah
interesting transition from peace to thinking ah interesting
noticing change no need for self-flagellation
notice change notice transitions
and maybe the transition back into stillness
the breath and body non-thinking
change is the nature
of the force of life of the life force
in us and others in life in general in the universe
aliveness entails change transitions
it's not to be dreaded or feared
it is the nature of the life force
change
nature of life force the nature of nature all around us
nature outside nature inside this body nature
this body as nature
embracing opening up to change transitions wholeheartedly
it is the dharma the unfolding love the universe
change to embrace it wholeheartedly
is to step into the stream
and to be carried by it not fighting
may we all embrace change
with wisdom and an open heart
maybe may we be free in the midst of change
may all beings be free and happy in the midst of change
[Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so embracing change embracing change
with openness warm-heartedness care
so in this practice tonight as a practice of for those of you might
have noticed this was a practice of bringing in wisdom practices together with metta
meta and wisdom meta and wisdom together so the meta aspect is the
openheartedness the warm-heartedness like yes here it is yes
and the wisdom aspect is guess what change transitions is another
word for an nietzsche impermanence so we've been practicing with one of the
three characteristics of wisdom teaching so bringing a warm
open-hearted awareness to change in this way in this unusual way can really help
us befriend change because instead of being afraid of change so it's the way
of the universe it's the dharma it's the unfolding law
of the universe change you can't stop it so might as well
embrace it so i'd like to invite you all for
reflections for questions for comments what did you note especially if you
haven't uh shared in a while i would like to ask you to share
to raise your zoom hand and also you can share in chat
you just send it to me i will read your share not your name if it's sent to
everyone then i will also say your name so take
it away what did you notice did you notice that okay i'll ask a question did any of you
notice that your mind actually became quite steady quite stable
noticing change noticing the breath changing sounds changing yes i see
one at least one thumbs up from neil yes so noticing oh
yeah and some people yeah i see notice the total opposite mario christine says
great i love all the variety of experiences coming up so so i'm going to
ask you actually if you'd like to comment so i'll ask neil you first if you want to say anything about it then
mario christine so you can just both if you like you don't have to you're
welcome to yes you're unmuted yeah sure um
i just found it you know very calm you know in many ways it felt like a
continuation of wednesday's practice you know
you know i mean things just change and so they just move on
you know and as long as i don't get hung up in them being the way they are it's okay
right it's the grasping that you know and that seems to be the problem
right right exactly it's grasping to the content of oh this chain thing's changed
and it's this way now and why is it this way why is it it's like oh yeah it just changed it's just like pump
uh buffing of one level yeah yeah right many of the changes are from pleasant to
less pleasant yeah right which is a bummer i guess but
you know it's the way it is yeah exactly so if you stay not with the
content but with the process oh yeah this transition no that's interesting there's a
the mind has spaciousness there's more spaciousness that comes
and you notice that yeah great that's one thing i wanted to
for uh hopefully to get across and if it didn't get across no problem there are plenty of other opportunities to
practice with this this is a significant insight this is this can be
a significant insight on the path of practice seeing change and how the mind can
stabilize actually seeing change not the content the from pleasant unpleasant and
back but actually oh yeah there's change there's change so
thanks neil larry i do see your hand up i wanted to invite murray christine if she wanted to to share anything in you
don't have to worry christine yes no yes you would like to yes so
please for me it was interesting i was trying to observe i've got a bit of body pain i
wanted to observe as opposed to get absorbed by the content yeah but as all the pain as
every pain a symptom kept coming up in my body it meant that my my monkeys were just moving around a
lot because my monkey mine was literally trying to stay with the change the ongoing change but and that then it
didn't settle my mind it was the opposite became super active [Music]
but right right it does make sense absolutely yes so so what i'm hearing you say is that there was so much going on in the body
and and not and and what you were trying it wasn't to be with the content of the
pain but to notice the transitions but it seemed like there was so much movement that it was just like whoa this
is this is too much yeah and that sometimes when there's so many transitions like and that can
happen exactly it's like wait too many transitions like i can't keep up with these there's like too many right great
i'm so appreciative that you brought up that i went back to my phrases what would you advise
yeah yeah great um so so one thing you could do we could go back to the phrases that's lovely that's great that's
something that kind of anchors you and stabilizes another thing is if you if you wanted to still dip your toe with
this uh transition is to to invite it back to be with the breath because the breath has simpler transitions right it
has simpler like clips [Music] and like afterwards the mind the mind is
like a lullaby yeah right it calms down and then you could open up to the to the body sensations
again you know the body transitions again with the mind that went back backwards thank you mario christine
that's lovely thank you so larry i see your hand please
um i really appreciated the guidance um
watching change sort of the ever-changing existence at times it it does really calm me
and i can get very still and what i felt this time was i would get still
and then i would move to the future i was like do i listen to should i listen to this
talk again and then i'll be in the same place or how do i stay in this place and as soon
as i went to the future i could feel the clinch of you know the self coming right back
and then i could see that and then i could go back to the still place again so it was that
watching that watching that watching that it felt very useful nice
what a wonderful insight that came out of this with noticing that yes when the mind went to the future that's when the
clenching the self came in the selfie me am i going to be in this place like whoa whoa wait just
beautiful wonderful thanks for sharing that insight how how important yeah
that's great thank you see a couple of shares and then we'll transition into
the group bill says thinking became more stable but not completely stable that's fine
that's all good is this more focusing on awareness than on what is noticed
ah kind of kind of it's it's um
we're not focusing we're not aware of the content but we're aware of the transition so we're not actually aware
of awareness itself it's not that and we're not aware of the cut we're not uh
focusing on the content either it's kind of in the middle where it's it's the
transition we're aware of it's like the derivative or for those of you who like
mathematics it's the that that's what we're paying attention to so yes i hope that makes sense bill
r says i feel like i need to practice this more to really drop in it felt like
open awareness practice and my mind kept trying to decide what to focus on ah right right so what the invitation i i
have is to stay with the breath to stay with the transitions of the breath that is
your anchor here so usually our anchor is the breath itself the content of the breath
the sensations of the breath here i was suggesting for the anchor
to be the transitions the from the in on the breath in breath out
breath all those transitions so so that could serve as the uh as the anchor here
or if you wanted to try this again so that's what i would invite you excellent questions beautiful
reflections everyone so touched with your practice everything that's coming up for you so juicy
everyone thank you so much so so let us transition now let us transition
uh to um practicing in small groups and and
bringing a theme from wednesday listening with our hearts listening with our hearts
sharing with our hearts and whatever transitions we would like to share or not it's all good and let's start
with 15 seconds of of silent meta
for one another before we engage uh and i've created the rooms the rooms are
made take care of yourselves take care of each other
here we go okay welcome back everyone
um we have just about a minute left for any reflections
that might have come up um [Music] either during or before so i'd love to
hear from you especially if you haven't shared for a while don't be shy go for it
yes jerry i do see your hand please uh anyway i can talk and talk a lot but
try not to like i learn more when i listen but anyhow just add i joined late but it really helped when
you said that the essential of life is change and a reflection came up in the group
and they said you know so often in our lives we we don't well
we either want something to change now which it will eventually or we don't want to lose what we have and
so we get sad thinking of the loss or loss aversion and so i was thinking about that that
happiness or content might be more contentment which i think is the greatest wealth as they say in
buddhism that it's to embrace change that it's inevitable
is essential of life actually makes the enjoyment of the moment that we're
here for such a short time so rewarding so thank you
thank you jerry well said well said thank you thank you for that and and larry quickly
asks uh or i'll quickly answer why do we need an anchor
uh is we are watching everything change if not is wait um
i think there was a typo there but i think i get the gist of the question why do we need an anchor if everything is changing or something like that the idea
is that um so that our awareness can can be stable otherwise it becomes overwhelming other
because it just it you know it's like if you're looking through binoculars it just if it's
shifting and moving too much like it right you can't really look through so but you want to look through the
binoculars so that they're stable so you can see everything that's shifting really
clearly so that's the idea that's the reason for that and thank you thank you for all your
practice showing up your beautiful reflections and and that was a lovely
point to end on jerry love that thanks for that reflection and everyone thank
you for coming to happier practicing cultivating your heart your minds
for yourselves and the sake of all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all being be safe
[Music] okay