hello again and welcome a warm welcome wherever you are in the world whatever time zone
so for today's practice um we are going to turn our hearts turn our
attention to the practice of equanimity for all beings
we've been working our way just to give a little bit of context and again if you're new it's all good
you can jump in wherever you arrive everything you need to know will be shared with you
during this guided meditation and also just to share the context both
for those who are new and also have been coming we've been going through the brahmaviharas one by one
meta loving-kindness compassion karuna mudita vicarious joy and
upeka which is equanimity crown jewel of buddhist practice to have a sense of
equipoise equanimity peace ease with whatever arises and passes
and those cultivation practices are done in concentric circles as we go through them
where it's easiest we extend our heart extend extent so we have made our way to the fourth
realm of ihara which is equanimity and the category of all beings
all beings and this is actually a very i mean all of
them are rich i don't think a single one is not rich in exploration and in ways that we can
cultivate our heart so here in this practice today
again whether this is your first session or your practice really the
invitation is we'll start as always we start with the breath and the
body to just settle for the first 10 minutes of our time together to arrive
breath body settling arriving calming the mind
inviting the mind to settle and then the idea of all beings
all beings everywhere they have ups and downs in their life just as we do so well by
the way we are included in the all beings practice let's remember that as we practice together
all of us every single one of us has ups and downs we may not know
sometimes we have the sense of oh everybody has it easy everybody has an easy life it's just me
who has challenges guess what
challenges stress suffering dukkha whatever name you give it um
are part of our mark of existence our part of being alive part of being human part of
being animal just part of being alive on this on this realm so we bring to our hearts a sense of oh
all beings have challenges including me and can there be a sense of equipoise
developing tapping the sense of peace and ease to be with whatever arises and passes
just as it is without falling into it without grieving attaching wanting
things to be different which which is also turning away pushing it away resisting but just being
withholding caring presence it's like this right now it's like this right now may i be
present with what what it is like right now and with all beings too may
all beings have spaciousness of equipoise so it says this can be a
very expansive practice actually equanimity for all beings can be very spacious
so that's what we try to to kind of tap into and whatever arises in this practice as long as you turn
into it with care and hold it with care you're doing it right so whatever arises
for you allow yourself a sense of safety for
whatever comes up to be held the sense of care and ease it's okay
if resistance comes up it's okay whatever comes up so it's that's
a sense of cultivation the practice of cultivation of art so enough words
let's dive in together let's practice in community so i'd like to invite you now ah
to land to land in your meditation posture
if you need to shift and move lie down that's okay
ah see what your body needs in this moment whether you need to stretch a
little bit find your sit bones find your center of gravity
say hello to your body hello buddy ah how have you been all day i've been
in my head so arriving arriving in the body landing
letting the body be soft relaxed
inviting dividing the breath
to move through this body soften and relax
to energize whatever needs to be energized
to soften whatever needs to be softened
as if you're turning away from all the preoccupations
thoughts gently in the friendly way
saying not now closing the door and going to the inner sanctum
taking refuge in the inner sanctum of your heart in this body
letting yourself be breathed with tenderness
letting yourself be breathed
with gentle care
gentle care presence with the feet on the floor
your legs soft
relaxed
gentle soothing hair said bones
the abdomen
gentle loving care
toward the entire lower body
embracing the upper body chest neck and shoulders just be
as they are ah hands softened
facial muscles jaw i didn't go from the inside
all can be held just as it is
if there's any tightness tension discomfort pain anywhere it's okay
gently breathed into with care
the thoughts are arising it's okay
for the benefit of taking refuge in this moment
gently saying not now it's okay if you're important enough please come back
later
right now i'm taking refuge with the breath the body the moment of
quiet thank you come come back again later
now allowing the breath as it moves through the body
on its own and breath and out breath through the whole body
feet legs abdomen chest
arms neck face
as the breath moves through the body softening relaxing expanding
allow yourself to feel allow there to be a sense that
the edge of the body is just a little beyond
the conventional edge of the body so the breath
is more expensive filling
this expands a little beyond your body
not effortfully breathing to do that but just noticing oh
there's a sense of spaciousness spaciousness
awareness can expand with the breath
just beyond the edge of the body
just as naturally you're being breathed again not making it effortful just noticing that
there's there can be a sense of more spaciousness even wider
as if as if your breath was feeling
the whole space around you the whole room [Music]
again don't need to breathe any harder or more energetically it's worth
noticing their sense of spaciousness
that can be there
as much as it's available
sense that your awareness
can be expansive can be relaxed and expansive
unbounded space
all around you
as if you were sitting on top of a mountain [Music]
360 degrees all around
a sense of expansiveness you can land and to relax
into
just relaxing into spaciousness
your body relaxing into spaces
with each breath
now this sense of relaxing into spaciousness with each
breath
a sense of being open
receptive
uh unmoved not toppled over but there's so much space so
much space
for birds to fly come and go in the space
clouds clouds of the mind to come and go weather patterns
to come and go so much space
for the comings and goings
and just as the buddha says
[Music]
the same way that if you took paint you couldn't paint space
air you couldn't paint it just wouldn't work it wouldn't stick colors
colors are presenting attitudes want not want good
bad push away grab grasp space
cannot be painted on a sense of spaciousness
it can hold everything it can hold everything
it can make space for everything in a caring way can all be held
it doesn't turn its attention away its care away can all be held
without sticking
so just as space can have presence available
holding it all
without falling into turning away so can be this
space of equanimity equipoise
upeka
the space of our hearts our minds spacious
all things being just as they are
just as they are held with care
present to them just as they are
spaciously this top of the mountain as you're
sitting perhaps with a sense of all beings
all around 360 degrees
birds that fly human beings other animals beings
all with the conditions of their lives including yourself
all the comings and goings of circumstances the ups and downs of life
as if those were color all the comings and goings all the
sadnesses and challenges all the happiness and joys all of them held
in the space but the same way that you can't color space
same way all the comings and goings
held in equanimity
may i be at peace
with all the comings and goings all the unfoldings of events for myself
and all beings everywhere
whether i understand it or not
all events for all beings
are unfolding according to the lawful
nature
or the traditional metaphase
all beings traditional equanimity phrase all beings are owners
of their actions heirs to their actions
their actions are the womb out of which they take birth
and they give birth to their actions
their happiness and unhappiness depends on their actions
not my wishes for them
all beings are owners of their actions actions of
thought speech and body
heirs to their actions their actions are the womb from which
they are born and they give birth to their actions
their happiness and unhappiness depend on their actions not my wishes for them
or simply may i may we
have peace with things as they are
our things are the way they are right now or simply it is what it is
it is what it is
see what version of a phrase works better for you or maybe without phrases just tapping in
the sense of spaciousness
caringly holding risings and passings
beyond foldings
all beings have their own journey whether i understand it or not
and for the last minute of this practice period allowing there to be
this spaciousness expansiveness
caring expansiveness with which this practice period was held
whatever rose or did not arise
can just be as it is
no judging no fixing no regret no pushing away
no attaching and grabbing could just be as it was as it is
ah sense of ease and freedom in the heart
can be just as it is
so much space so much freedom
may all beings everywhere including ourselves
be at peace
and their hearts and minds be free [Music] spaciously free
[Music]
so thanks everyone for your practice
equanimity practice
can feel very spacious calming soothing um balancing
the sense of freedom in the heart sense of equanimity actually the sense of peace can arise
in the heart and the mind through this practice so much more i can say but oh one other
thing i want to say before i invite reflections and comments
is that the phrases i was offering many um i
sent through nils and longer lists of various phrases to uh
the google groups so if you aren't already part of google groups you can get on the google groups and see
the brown these uh equanimity phrases and play around with them and see what works better for you
and if you're already on then you probably have already received and seen these phrases so so
we have some time for reflections for comments for questions
for complaints what did you notice what came up for you
[Music] okay susan
thanks i mean i'm over here i swear thank you everybody it's
um it's really great practicing with you all and um i what's been on my mind lately
and i was thinking about this i have to admit well i was supposed to be meditating
um is how important equanimity is to be a good listener
to develop equanimity is so important if one wants to be a good listener and um
i think did i mention to you guys that there was this andre no no in there's you know unrenewing
this author i have this quote by him i want to read it
can i real quick okay here i go okay when we honestly
ask ourselves which person in our lives means the most to us we often find that
find that is that it is those who instead of giving advice solutions or
cures have chosen rather to share our pain and touch our wounds with a warm and
tender hand the friend who can be silent with us in a moment of despair
or confusion who can stay with us in a hour of grief and bereavement who can
tolerate not knowing not curing not healing and face with us the reality of our
powerlessness that is a friend who cares
beautiful that's the spirit of equanimity in listening beautiful yeah thanks susan
and i appreciate this this quote really eloquently brings up what
we were discussing i think was it yesterday already seems like so long ago or thursday wednesday in this sense of
um you know if you're sitting at the deathbed of someone who's dying that's where equanimity sense of
care you care so you hold presence you're holding care you're present
and really that is the spirit of equanimity and if you wanted to share that quote
actually in the google groups with folks i trust they would appreciate it because
that really epitomizes the difference between being you know aloof which is the near
enemy like uh things are as they are things are as they are whereas that's that's not equanimity
that's aloofness uh whereas equanimity cares it's present stays and yet doesn't
meddle it just holds space so beautiful thank you so
neil you have your hand up yeah so there was one of the quotes was
something about people being responsible for their own happiness right based on their actions
so how does that work i mean there are external factors that impact people fairly dramatically
yeah so how do you like you know rectify that
yeah yeah that's a that's a really good question um
yeah it's i think there are um because absolutely i mean they're
external circumstances and that that effect
that affect people in um and defect different people differently
et cetera so yeah so it's not to condone external circumstances at all i think what
what this phrase with this equanimity phrase is trying to get to is not
to to close that off and say that is not the case um but of course acknowledging that and
yet there's a sense of um and and you know there are some cases that that
maybe that traditional phrase doesn't work and actually there's some people who don't use the traditional phrase at all
so don't use it if it brings up a lot of um uh mental like wait this doesn't make
sense maybe the sentence that actually works a little better in is that that people have their own journey people
have their own journey so yes of course they're impacted but it really taps into the sense of
your care it becomes more relational instead of um positing about the world
so you see the difference when this cultivation or what i'm trying to point out here i
understand all the other phrases but the one i asked about but that's okay i could just dump it yeah yeah that's that's what i'm
suggesting i'm suggesting that it's okay to to not use that and if you
insisted to really really explore that then um maybe
relate to it not as positive this is how it is in the world positing
uh you know as if you're accounting for all circumstances in the world but in a way of your understanding of
relational but i can also see that as i'm saying that i can see that that can also fall
fat so you know if it doesn't work just drop it there are many people who don't like that phrase and it's perfectly fine if
it gets in the way of cultivating equanimity then just yeah just drop it yeah thank you
a couple of reflections uh far says when you invited us to imagine
filling the whole room i realized that my breath is literally creating little air currents that circulate around the whole
room which was a delightful image oh i love that forest thanks for sharing that i'm going to have that delightful image too
it's true a little currents everywhere throughout the whole room i love it yeah
bill asks when you say spaciousness does this mean not having reactivity
it can mean a lot of different things bill so you can explore so there can there can
be not having reactivity that can be one meaning one way to relate to it but sense of spaciousness it can also be
the sense of feeling into the space element the spaciousness around like landing into ah
it's there are various studies you know when when you're um when you go
into a space a place that's really spacious your mindset changes from one that's
limited to one that is open to a lot of possibilities so there's so many different ways
to relate to spaciousness either literally as spaciousness or or non-reactively so i invite you to not
limit yourself to one sense and be open to so many different ways and the ones that
you haven't even explored yet so you are welcome bill
so um so dear ones so as we turn our practice now
in this brief short time into practicing in small groups we'll
start with 30 seconds of meta for each other kindness and then holding
this space of equanimity for ourselves and others with care just listening with care just
listening not trying to fix it change it just with care listening um
[Music] so that would that's the invitation and this is such
precious and important practice that you can take to your loved ones in your families and friends and
colleagues to to be to to listen with equanimity
so after 30 seconds of uh silent meta so i'm going to create the
rooms they're created and they are now open
take care of your hearts and each other okay welcome back everyone
so we have a couple of minutes for reflections for any reflections that might have come
up from your practice from your conversations and groups so especially if you're new or
usually don't share this is an invitation we'd love to hear from you what did you notice
for yourself
you can either raise your hand or you can type in chat
what was it like to listen with equanimity to yourself and others with care and equanimity with that in
the space but anybody would like to comment on that
or anything else
yes please so we we had a conversation about picking
up on the last question we um somebody asked about the last uh one of the last phrases
and how we recognized how overwhelming it can be when you're not in a spot of your
meditation journey perhaps where you can hold these things or even let go i remember personally
being quite angry when somebody told me oh you know just you're responsible for
your own happiness because just biologically you can be so overwhelmed by external external circumstances but it's a huge
challenge so then to switch into
loving kindness perhaps and uh and even just physical basic grounding techniques or
frankly walking away from people who are telling you this even if it's you yourself telling it to you and um and so i could
totally relate and we could both totally relate to to to that comment and uh i wanted to just acknowledge that
uh but this can't be because often this is what brings people to the practice to be in that spot where you're not able
to be kind to yourself and you're not able you intellectually know that you could be responsible for
this but just don't know how to do it that can be a huge challenge yeah yeah yeah i really appreciate you
bringing that up and verbalizing that guitar um
it's yeah it i think the more we're having this
conversation i think i'm realizing that there's something that's not quite captured in a way
in this translation of this traditional phrase it's it's not so much about
that we're all fully responsible for everything that happens to us because that is that is kind of um
[Music] um that's kind of mad in in some ways
right it's so i think that translation isn't quite appropriate it's especially you know
when it comes to it's like oh it's all my responsibility like really whereas it's more i think what
it's trying opportunity possibility no not exactly i think what it's trying to get to
so this is the intention so so that's the intention that i was trying to communicate in the guided meditation and
then i offered you know this traditional translation but the intention is to acknowledge the causes
and conditions and there's so many causes and conditions that are beyond your control
part of them are within your control but so much of it is beyond your control and this translation i realized
even though it's traditional it doesn't quite capture that so i'm not going to use it from now on i need to come up
with my own translation that really captures that so i really appreciate you and others
and and neil for bringing that up because yeah i think it's kind of it's falling
short to the meaning to the spirit of this practice which is acknowledging wow there's so many causes and
conditions it's not just me what i do but my genetics my upbringing but but like historically what has happened
and this it's just there's so many causes and conditions that are causing this and for me to take responsibility that
it's mine to fix it's like wow there's so inviting ourselves to have peace with that
if possible to have peace of life this is this is such this is so complicated this mess of
being human and being on this planet like wow may i just hold
the enormity of the the mystery of all that's going on it's not awful
it's not great and it's it's it's just it is what it is
this so that's where that's why the phrase of well it is what it is this is what this has all come to can i be
can i be with a sense of care with with what this has come to so that's the
spirit of equanimity practice and this phrase let's ditch it until i come up with a better
translation now but just because it's a traditional translation it doesn't mean that it's a good one
there's so many awkward translations of so many things that i don't like so thank you all this has been a
very very interesting and helpful fruitful discussion and i hope it helps oh yes
and a couple of things i want to say one is maybe i'll say this from now on that um
when we go into groups i think it is it's uh everyone is asked please turn on your
video and your audio because it's part of being a share sharing is the spirit of
of being in the group the etiquette of really showing up um so so let's
let's offer ourselves up as people other people are offering to support us in this way
another quick thing i wanted to say is as you've noticed um for the first uh well
um as uh has been announced i should say um that uh diana is off for the whole
month of march on retreat so i i taught the first two weeks of march every night
as you've noticed maybe and for the next week i'm teaching a retreat for the entire next week seven days so
i'm not teaching and neither is diana so we have wonderful substitute teachers
next week and then i will be back the week after that and teaching monday wednesday
friday and we have substitute teachers tuesdays thursday so anyway all that so thank you all for
your practice for showing up for your fullness for supporting yourself and each other
may all beings everywhere be free happy peaceful
thank you all thank you so much