good day good beginning of the week
just a minute
and
so it's probably a little confusing for some of you that we've switched now
back to meeting at 7 00 am for the meditation and i think it was over many of us it
was quite wonderful to be starting at 6 45 last week and have the 45 minutes sitting
and the plan is to do that again next week starting on monday
and then we can assess for one week and then we can assess whether to
continue this way somehow or other do it once a month or not do it at all
and
so the in terms of the
16 steps of mindfulness of breathing we've gone through the first eight and
today is to introduce the ninth and that is to become aware of the mind
knowing the mind breathing in one knows the mind breathing out one knows the mind
and what exactly the mind is is a fascinating topic
and maybe there's no final
decision to be made about what the mind is some people call it the mind heart some people call it the heart the pali
word is chitta and i'll talk more about later but for
now i want to say that using an analogy that if
you're driving maybe on a long trip with a car and you still notice that slowly the
windshield is getting dirty it slowly slowly builds up over time and driving is so important you're very
focused on the traffic the road the driving itself
and so you're focusing on what's beyond the windshield and so you don't really notice the
windshield but the windshield is getting more and more dirty and what you also don't notice then is
the strain to have to look more carefully through the dirt
so this is an example of how if um we might not know recognize the filter
through which uh we are aware of things because we're often focusing on
something in particular just like we're often when we think we think about something
so our awareness is usually about something we're aware of but how we're aware is not really so
easily seen or prioritized and then with the driving if you could
stop at a gas station and wash your window and then get in the car and you go wow
now it's clean that is impressive and and you realize how much easier and more
relaxing it is to drive without straining through the dirty window so
so this is what the topic is for today is mindfulness of the mind and take a while
to kind of really explain what it is but with that introduction
please begin in your meditation posture
and and uh if your mind's gonna be about
something thinking about something aware of something
be aware for a few moments of your posture and to really become even more aware
you might kind of sway back and forth rock back and forth and re-establish
your posture maybe making smaller movements as you kind of really get settled
and kind of whatever you know make a small adjustments really feel
where the posture is comfortable not comfortable aligned not
aligned in a way that works for you maybe there can be small adjustments
and then letting the body become still and now the focus of attention can be
maybe the stillness of the body
just what it's like to have the body still not moving
and if in feeling the still body there feels like more adjustments are needed
herb would be good please do
and the next focus of attention can be
the breathing of the body wherever breathing is most easy for you
to experience in the belly the movements of the chest
movements of the air going in and out through the nostrils
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
three quarters full and for as long as it's comfortable for
you a long slow exhale
long slow exhale when you get to the end of the exhale
briefly maybe then just barely perceptibly pause
before you inhale pause so the inhale
really feels like it wants to start itself and allow it to start
and then letting your breathing return to normal and now bring your attention
to focus on the parts of the body that might be easy to relax
maybe the muscles of the face the eyes
almost like the muscles of the face can be spread wide to the side maybe
where they can sink down sliding down the bones of the skull
perhaps as you exhale the softening of the shoulders releasing of the tension
and then softening the belly
if it's difficult to soften relax the belly be content to do it in very small
degrees maybe relaxing around the place of most
tension
and then let your attention receive the experience of the body
breathing in the belly the chest the nostrils
or globally all of that in some easy way
maybe letting there be
a little pause at the end of the exhale
maybe just barely perceptible a relaxed pause
and then allow the inhale to start itself receive the inhale
receiving the inhale and awareness
riding the release of the exhale
releasing yourself with the release of the exhale
releasing your thoughts as you exhale
and as the thoughts release maybe there's more space in the
awareness to feel the fullness of breathing in and
breathing out
and then also notice if there's any tension or pressure agitation in the mind
and as you exhale perhaps you can soften the mind
release the tension of the mind
soften the thinking muscle
maybe where the sense of the mind becomes more open expansive
mind has mind has more room
lots of room in which breathing in and breathing out
is known
and then become aware as you're following your breathing
become aware of how you're aware what's the attitude or mood
that comes along with being aware
what's the mental atmosphere
is the general mood or atmosphere attitude of the mind
is it pleasant or is it unpleasant
is it more on the side of contentment or of discontentment
is the quality of the mind field does the mind feel more small
located in a particular place or does it feel more large
expansive may be difficult to locate in any one
place
the general quality of your mind your inner life
your mind heart
what's the emotional tone not of particular thoughts or impulses
but the background tone or the
atmosphere of it all
and without any kind of judgment of how it is
what happens to you as you gently honestly
recognize something about the quality of the mind
the mood the attitude the atmosphere
not to be thinking about this with more feeling or sensing
a quiet awareness
of the mood of your mind state the state of the mind
and then whatever state of mind you have if you're aware of it breathe with it
as if breathing accompanies it breathes through it
or whether or like the state of the mind accompanies the breathing
breathing in knowing the state of your mind
breathing out knowing the state of your
mind
in the way that you might experience humidity in the air
or the warmth of the sun standing in the sun
see if you can experience the state of the mind
the overall mood overall gestalt
of the inner mental life
let's say characterized by a wanting
characterized by an aversion pushing away
is it characterized by confusion
is it characterized by stability and presence or by distraction and
jumping around it's all okay just experience it as it is for you
breathe with it
and if it's possible to relax the mind or expand the mind
so the boundaries of whatever mind is are soft boundaries open boundaries
no boundaries and resting into that
expansive mind settling into the open mind
and breathing through it breathing with it
breathing at the center of it
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
maybe you can discern that or know the difference between
a mind that is small and closed and
involved in itself and the mind or heart which is open
open to receive and feel the world around it
maybe the difference can be like trying to talk and see someone through a
closed glass door and then having the door open
and then seeing them and talking being with them
to open the mind to open the heart for it to be expansive and wide and
the mood and atmosphere the state of mind receptive and available
and in this mode either doing so or imagining it so
be take in the people of your life
people you might see today or talk to today or
think about today people on the street in your
neighborhood and in your communities
and to let them be received or known with a heart the mind wide open
at least for these minutes or two we're sitting here at the end of meditation
a time and place where it's safe to be open-hearted
and then see if there's a greater sensitivity a greater
tenderness heartfeltness
in considering these people when the heart the mind is open
and then taking the idea of whatever benefit that's come from this meditation
practice let it be offered up
and be offered for the welfare and benefit of others
whatever calm or centeredness or peacefulness
may it be transformed into kindness for the world
care for the world all beings be happy
may all beings be saved
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
[Music] you