good morning good day everyone
one of the directions that this practice goes in
is to a simplicity of being
where anything that is extra
anything that's really not needed to be happy peaceful
has kind of fallen and fallen away kind of taken a vacation
so that we give ourselves permission we are given permission
where just to be alive is enough breathing sensing feeling
knowing thinking whatever is happening
in a kind of simplicity of being that highlights
what we're doing that's extra how we get involved and pick up thoughts
pick up concerns react push away want fixate on certain thoughts and ideas
that the simplicity of being kind of shows us that you know this is extra
there's something really good happening here something really nice in this simplicity
just being alive is enough nothing to prove nothing to defend nothing to
for a few minutes a radical
vacation a radical pause in the incessant movement of doing and
wanting and thinking and we have permission to do this
just to be alive is enough for these minutes while meditating
and trust the process keep coming back to being simple
with what is happening simple meaning not getting involved not fixing not
pushing away just being just allowing what's there
and as the mind knows what's happening
let that be simple just to know there's a wonderful expression the
cognitive functioning of emptiness
the knowing functioning
of radical simplicity
where knowing has no weight awareness has no weight
no shape no color
no boundaries no walls
awareness our capacity to know
is porous transparent just is
and one of the things that falls away with the simplicity of being is all forms of self-preoccupation
self-concern not because we're not important and we want to care for ourselves we don't we
do want to care for ourselves but one of the greatest ways to care for ourselves
is to trust that just being alive is enough just allowing the simplicity of being
where there is no self-concern because in this simplicity
it's not needed so assuming a meditation posture
and to begin a process of simplification simplify your eyesight your looking
maybe let your eyes gaze look down at the floor
relax your focus so you're not really looking at anything in particular
and as you exhale closing your eyes
and then feeling your body globally so you're not
landing and standing on any one place in the body
but a global open awareness that maybe roams around the body but it
doesn't take a stand anywhere just doesn't get focused on any particular
thing for now just global feeling of being in a
body as you exhale relaxing
the belly
softening the lower path of the body
including the legs and the thighs and the feet
relaxing in the solar plexus area
the chest
releasing
releasing the shoulders
always going in the direction of being simpler less work less activity less
tension just being here
softening the muscles of the face
if the lips are pressed or the teeth are pressed together release the pressure
if the jaws are clenched release the holding
maybe by dropping the jaws open a little bit
softening around the eyes and the forehead
and on the exhale softening in the mind
quieting your thinking
turning whatever thinking you have to gently and quietly
think about being here in this body
at this time
let your concerns
simplify to just what's happening here in your body
and feel your body breathing
the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
becoming simpler with the breathing as simple as it's easy to do
not trying to do anything with your breathing or not trying to get concentrated or
anything simple being
simple just breathing
allowing for a self-forgetting as you enter into the world of the body
breathing
and if it helps you be simpler as you exhale
gently softly let go of everything
or let go of anything that appears anything that's more complicated
than simply the body breathing
and just maybe at the end of the out breath
you can even let go of yourself self-concern self-referencing
the end of the up breath before the in-breath
the simplicity of no weight no color no shape
no body no feelings no thoughts
no mind no self
none of that needs to be a concern
you're allowed the simplicity of being
just to be alive is enough
so
let go as you exhale
for these minutes trust letting go
let go of anything and everything the mind is involved in
until the last thing to let go of is letting go itself
as we come to the end of the sitting
whatever way you can appreciate your simplicity of being
just being alive is enough nothing to prove nothing to defend
it's enough just sitting here breathing peacefully because all other
demands and needs and ways of being have receded for now
just enough to be alive in that way
it might be possible to have a particular respect even
reverence for others
they too they too you can allow to be
just as they are the simplicity of being
you can see them as someone
with whom you don't need to add desires and needs and demands
just as you see yourself that way for these few moments
so you can also see them that way
free of your needs your judgments your desires your fears
freeing them from projections and demands
and it gives birth to a kind of respect a kind of reverence for others
seeing past whatever behavior they have good or bad
past whatever history they have
to just allowing them to be who they are for a few moments
and having a reverence for the life that's there
another human being is as wondrous as
looking out across the ocean at the beach or
the vista from a mountaintop or the beauty of a flower
not to deny all the things that we should notice but not be limited by it
deep respect deep reverence for every life
and with that respect to care for their welfare and happiness
may all beings happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we contribute that by freeing others
from all the projections and needs and demands
that we carry allowing each person each being
to be itself
[Music]
thank you
so mindfulness of mind mindfulness of awareness
awareness has in the simplicity of it has no weight no color no shape
awareness in itself has no history and no future
and to free awareness
from all the ways in which we burden it
with our desires and wishes and fears and projections and
so that awareness becomes simple is one of the great possibilities
in this practice of mindfulness and
awareness is released awareness is set free
and even of ourselves and this is one of the more radical things about this practice
the way in which it can freer free ourselves from ourselves
and um so if you engage in mindfulness practice in meditation practice
and you're able to kind of really give yourself over to just being here just being mindful in the
in the current of the present moment the current of breathing since sensing feeling whatever's going on
and then uh it's
we get at some point we get absorbed this becomes all we're doing and in the other all we're doing
absorption and just being present self-concerned self-preoccupation
uh falls away we're still here in a fully full way
but i like to for some reason i like to liken this to basketball players
that it's if you watch someone playing basketball professionally or something
and you know there's no time to wonder about how is that fan thinking
about me is my shirt tucked in properly the did i
you know did i do well did i snap my fingers right at that last
shot i mean all kinds of preoccupations and thoughts there's no time for it and there's a kind of complete
losing was giving oneself over to what they're doing and not most of us are not basketball
players but it could be uh cooking or playing music or reading a
book or you know there's activities that we do that we kind of forget ourselves we lose
ourselves in a healthy way in the activity some people say that time stops
as they when we lose ourselves in the activity we don't really lose ourselves because
there's but we um there's a a wonderful self-forgetting
or stepping out of this the closed of self that we wear
and and to have this wonderful uh getting out of our own way and being
free from self-concern self-preoccupation referencing everything to self
also begins to free awareness it frees our presence
our ability to attend to what's here there's a freedom there's a likeness there's an ease in that
and so then as that we continue the practice there's more and more of this kind of
self-forgetting or more and more this shedding of anything that's extra
and and there's a kind of a sensitivity that arises to what's extra
so sitting quietly being with the breath being with something
and um and then you have the thought you know what that breath wasn't as good as the previous breath
but rather than believing it or getting involved in that thought it's so clear that that's extra that
thought the goodness of the moment doesn't need it
and so we we don't get involved in that thought we don't pick it up and we just kind of stay with the flow
the activity of here and here and
and uh and so then awareness gets simpler and simpler we get simpler and simpler or
maybe we don't get simpler anymore we've receded from the picture and awareness gets simpler and simpler and simpler
and at some point awareness
releases itself awareness just like there's a
self-forgetting there is an awareness for getting awareness forgets itself
and um and what is that like when it gets that simple that free
that's safe that settle that
just being alive is enough just here and even awareness
doesn't have to do anything doesn't have to accomplish anything it's not directed anywhere or
and there's a self forgetting in the awareness too just awareness is so smooth and operating so simply
it just kind of forgets itself sometimes it's called a dropping away
sometimes it's called a a ceasing the ending of something
and then it comes back but to have that experience of
awareness for getting itself awareness getting out of its own way
is uh teaches something very profound about
clinging and the possibility of non-clinging
so the final step for this week about awareness is the release not only the
release in awareness but the release of awareness itself both of those
so we respect our minds our awareness we begin by just relaxing that was the
first day and then there's recognition a huge part of awareness is its capacity to recognize
and we're building on that capacity so the recognition becomes simpler and simpler and simpler less baggage less
associations just the simple knowing just
in breath just a thought just hearing just being
and um and then there's this uh deep respect for this whole process of
being aware of being present respect for ourselves i think this dharma practice is kind of
founded on a very deep respect that borders is a kind of reverence
for all this and so of course we want to be present and attentive and and
and find a way to be with everything that the being with is simple just there
with it we don't interfere with anything and then there's a kind of restoration of
a wonderful kind of freedom of mind that can just know whatever's happening freely openly like
like there's no barriers no boundaries to anything just it's just known it's free
everything is known simply nothing sticks and then as we continue this process of
deepening the awareness and just kind of getting the flow of awareness just relaxing in the simplicity of being
there is this a greater and greater process of simplification and that might be a nicer word for some
of people to hear rather than letting go releasing because letting go can seem
like we are dismissing things or we're abandoning things or we're you know
we're going to be without anything but this simplification is simplifying into the most
the part of ourselves the part of life that is most reverent most respectful deepest
most sacred and um
and to trust it so deeply and so well that um there's a self-forgetting
and then an awareness forgetting
and then you'll know something new something different about this life and
you probably never believe that clinging
is important again you might you're probably still cling but you will no longer believe in it
and now that that's what's important
and so the buddha talked about awareness use the word cheetah so maybe mine but
awareness liberated
through non-clinging so
and then you get yourself in the simplest most beautiful and
profound way that you can be that paradoxically wonderfully
wondrously also involves a self-forgetting
so it might seem like you're not going to be there to appreciate this wonder
but maybe part of you is not there the part that's extra
so thank you for this uh opportunity to teach this stuff
and i appreciate our time together and so as i said yesterday uh next week i'm
teaching retreat and we're very fortunate to have matthew brent silver uh teaching the 7 a.m and he'll do that
together with some other things he does for the week so if you want to get a deeper immersion in the practice
and the teachings and with matthew check out the what a house described on the imc website
and on the calendar and includes the saturday saturday day long next saturday
and then on wednesday next wednesday evening the 17th of november
a few of the senior practitioners teacher trainees here at imc both have done chaplaincy training
spiritual caregiving training involved with that very very intimately are going to offer a
grief circle it's sometimes we've done sometimes the end of the year to
to kind of honor respect commemorate engage in the losses of the year
and there's been a lot now because of um you know all kinds of losses with the the
pandemic and kovid and and um and so um
it'll be on zoom and uh they'll have a protocol and zoom you should read the description because
you need to come with something uh for the the ceremony the ritual they'll do
and um so that's this with this uh coming wednesday
with ying yang chen and don neal so thank you all and um
i'll see you i guess in a couple of weeks thank you