[Music]
so good day and i offer this greeting as partly as a sound check and let's see if
a few of you could say do you hear me
um
wonderful it's wonderful to be here with all of you and
to share this time and
so the general topic for last week and this week is
the general topic for this week and next week is um
uh
kusala it's a poly word and um often translate into english as wholesome
and for this meditation i want to use that translation the other one is
skillful and and that mindfulness is
understood to be a wholesome practice and
and it's sometimes said that mindfulness of the buddhism mindfulness of the body brings with it or includes within it all
the wholesome qualities of mind and heart that a person could have and that's
quite a powerful statement about the value of mindfulness of the body that
it just seems to be all good in some certain kind of way or promotes what's really good the um
so meditation practice is meant to be wholesome healthy conducive to health and
nourishment and when we sit down to meditate we bring with us our minds
and our minds uh are variable quite you know it's very variable and
and contains a lot of different things in it and some of it is
some of it is
you know not so wholesome not so beneficial for us or for the world
around us and and that you know
that's the way it is sometimes but the practice of meditation the practice
of mindfulness is different than the
momentum the tendencies the variability of what lives in there in the mind our mind the
idea is that mindfulness is wholesome or we
and the simple act of being present and it is to bring this wholesome
engagement with even what's unwholesome that's our job is to bring the wholesome
or be wholesome in the engagement we have and one of the simplest ways for to do this
that doesn't require us dredging up good qualities or being wholesome in some kind of even some kind of
artificial way or some forced way is a very simple
practice of mindfulness no matter how it's practiced to have this clear mindfulness of the
moment just oh that's what's happening that's what's happening but in particular mindfulness of
breathing i think of mindfulness is the breathing as being a place where things begin
working themselves out a place where we begin
finding or adjusting or relaxing into having a wholesome
attitude wholesome approach to the meditation practice
just like just settling in with the breathing and then we begin being able to meet all the different
parts of the mind including the parts of the mind which are not so exemplary or which have a lot of
suffering in them or struggle or conflict in them and hold them in a attention which is
kind which is supportive which is wholesome so as we do this meditation don't worry
too much about any unwholesome tendencies you have any painful
trains of thought you have and um any negative self-judgments you have
don't just simply don't try to be involved in them but don't try to stop them either
there can be simple letting go but just keep coming back to mindfulness of
breathing and finding how to have this wholesome awareness of everything including of
what is unwholesome so
entering into a supportive meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and slowly
gently taking a few long deep breaths
breathing in deeply and relaxing as you exhale
breathing in
and softening on the exhale
letting your breathing return to normal
and going through your body and relaxing on the exhale
relaxing letting go as you
softening in the face
as you exhale softening in the shoulders
as you exhale softening the belly
sometimes a good softening of the belly will also soften
the shoulders
softening the belly can also involved softening of the whole lower torso
relaxing into the seat if you're sitting
and then gently calmly letting your awareness
meet the body's experience of breathing
and as we continue this meditation
gently relaxedly see if you can have a wholesome
attitude in being mindful of breathing
wholesome in that it maybe has a quality of
caring
or acceptance
gentleness
perhaps it's not so ambitious greedy for
it to be a certain way expectations but an attitude which is
more generous to how it is a willingness to trust the simplicity of
breathing in and breathing out allowing the breathing
to be the pathway to a more settled wholesome state of
mind that comes as we settle relax into
just breathing not being so troubled by the variability
of the mind just beginning again and again with your
breathing trusting
mindfulness of breathing
[Music]
in what way would trusting breathing trusting mindfulness of
breathing shift things for you in a more wholesome
direction
and wholesome means partly it means nourishing
if you feel the nourishing quality of meditation
might that help you to stay present
[Music]
you
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
an expression of a wholesome state of mind heart
are things like generosity and care compassion
kindness and concern and care for the welfare of
others and then there's this wonderful movement
called dedication of merit where on one hand we dedicate all the
benefits that we've received from our meditation practice
for the welfare and happiness of others but because this is an act of generosity
and care it generates more merit great merit
or to say it differently if we dedicate the benefit of this meditation for the sake of
others we benefit as well
we don't end up with less benefit we end up with more
so may it be that this meditation practically done on this
first day of the week may it spread benefit out into the world
for the rest of the week wherever we go whoever we talk to
whoever we think about may we do so with greater care
and concern for their welfare may this practice we've done today
support us in spreading kindness
welfare and happiness out into the world may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
so the topic continues to be on wholesomeness skillfulness
there's a single poly word that we we use we translate into english in
both these ways the pali word is kusala k-u-s-a-l-a
and um probably is seen as a maybe an ancient ancient
buddhist world had a singular meaning in that time but it just happens to be that
in english it seems like the two primary meanings that are translations that we've come to
settled on now is wholesomeness wholesome and skillful
and then the opposite is unwholesome and unskillful
um some of it depends on the context of um
in which the term is being used it seems that and things that have an interpersonal
relationship interpersonal nature relation relating to other people for example or
maybe relating to ourselves as if we're another person then wholesome seems to be
the better translation but when it has to do with uh personal spiritual development uh
personal meditation development to make meditation want meditation practice
then it seems like a better translation is skill and the
and so wholesomeness has the idea in english
of uh something which is nourishing something which is healthy the
dictionary definition that i've seen is promoting health and well-being of mind spirit and body whereas
skillfulness has to do with proficiency at the one's ability to do something well
and the wholesomeness can imply the goodness of
something in and of itself just doing it is its own reward because just feels so good to
do whereas skillful has a little bit more sense that um
there's you're doing it for something for a purpose and it supports a purpose it might support the growth of wholesome
qualities growth of what's good but still it's skillful for a purpose so and so you say you know
this is skillful you can ask for what purpose or in what way
and so these these distinctions are not so absolute but there's a tendency to be kind of divide
these two different uh translations one is has to do with
interpersonal and the other real personal development and one has to do with um
with promoting health and well-being in a direct way for oneself
with wholesome qualities to acting on the wholesome and acting on the ways that benefit other people
uh if it's done wholesomely it's nourishing supportive form here
according to this translation um conducive promoting moral
promoting health or well-being of mind spirit and body
it's interesting that another definition of wholesomeness in dictionary is conducive to or promoting
moral well-being and so this particularly has to do with the how kusala sometimes refers this
interpersonal relationship in fact the word kusala is probably the closest
match for the english word moral or ethics but rather than having
some kind of authoritarian feeling or moral obligation feeling around the word
the concept it has this kind of warm i for me this warm internal feeling of
upswilling upswelling of what is nourishing supportive this good within us so it has an inner
source for ethics rather than external source of right and wrong should and shouldn't
and all that and so to keep using this wholesome inner experience
to be connected to that to know it in a way that can be uh eclipsed
if we're too much caught up in the cognitive ideas of um the you know the abstract ideas of
what is and isn't ethical what we should and shouldn't do what is right and wrong coming from our
society or from religious textbooks or of all kinds of sources that are very different than
this welling up of a reference point inside of what really feels
nourishing healthy that's different than using the
experience of pleasure as a reference point if it's simply what we enjoy what brings pleasure then we might go ask you might
go astray a little bit but if we use what's wholesome i think the buddhist ideas
that's a really reliable reference point for ensuring that we act well in the world
generously in the world so staying for a moment with a little bit with this translation of wholesome
um and that it has to do with the interpersonal world probably the most common reference to
this wholesome quality in terms of our relationship to other people in this
in the teachings of the buddha have to do with a list of 10 ethical guidelines
that are called the 10 courses 10 practices of
wholesome action and the opposite are the 10 courses of unwholesome action and
uh and there were action here is karma so of wholesome karma and unwholesome karma
and um and uh and because the word kusala wholesome is
there these 10 kind of looks like precepts maybe shouldn't be seen as maybe as
precepts in some of the associations we have the word they are more like the 10
wellsprings of wholesome actions that we can that we can act on and live live by
so these ten in in uh there's a longer description of each one in the suttas
but uh for now i'll say the ten are not killing not stealing not taking what
is not given not engaging in sexual misconduct not lying not speaking maliciously
not speaking harshly not speaking frivolously not having
not being avaricious and not having ill will
and and having a right view the skillful view and
understanding and one of the skillful views is to distinguish primordus wholesome and
unwholesome one of the skillful views and understandings is to understand how to come from
what is wholesome as we engage in our life and so these they're mostly
talking about what not to do but it turns out that not doing killing stealing sexual
misconduct lying and so forth um just clears the decks in a sense
for what's in there the wholesome to come out it also provides a tremendous sense of
safety and room for other people to thrive and to do well
in the way in a way that if we kill and steal and hurt people through our sexuality
doesn't allow the best in other people to come out as well violence against others
and and hostility against other meanness to others can clamp close people down or
cause challenges for people in a community for you know really for centuries it was
very touching to read about the survivors of the tulsa massacre who went to congress recently
today is the 100th anniversary of that massacre and uh so if someone who's 107 years old
coming and speaking about the legacy of what happened a hundred years ago that
violence and how every day of her life every night of her life she relives and is you know troubled by
what happened to her for 100 years that's a long time and so the impact of our negative
actions are huge and but what we're trying to do is to
live a wholesome life and i for me that's a very different feeling than living an ethical life
a wholesome life just feels like it's um um you know just you know wholesome it's
just it feels good it's relaxing it's softening it's warm warm
warm heartening for ourselves and so this um idea of
wholesome examples of what's most wholesome are these ten
wholesome actions and they have um there's as i said there's a long
description by paragraph long description of each one and i'll give you an example of the
first one you get a sense of it's actually relatively short compared to the others
abandoning killing of living beings one abstains from killing living beings
with weapons laid aside gentle and kindly one abides
compassionate to all living beings so here we have uh it's not just a
matter of avoiding killing there's also this
positive wholesome qualities that are being encouraged here and and being allowed to
develop and grow and so it's not just simply a a prohibition for something it's because
it's focusing on what's wholesome it says yes and these beautiful qualities as well
let's live by them as well with weapons laid aside a gentle and
kindly one abides compassionate to all living beings the um uh
in abstaining from militia speech one reunites those divided
and promotes friendship and unites those who are not yet united in avoiding her speech
speech one speaks gently and courteously
in abstaining from frivolous speech one speaks by what is factual
and useful and abstaining from ill will when
one wishes others that they be free of affliction
so this these these ten wholesome qualities and these get listed talked about over
and over again the suit as much more as my impression than the five precepts and it seems that
in the suttas in the teachings of the buddha these ten skillful actions while they overlap with the five precepts
they're richer and more heartfelt in in nature in terms of these positive
qualities and but more importantly they're presented also
as important stepping stones in the path to liberation
whereas the five precepts have a lot of benefit but they're not so directly tied to the
purposes for liberation the purposes are to create a better society and help the other people feel safe and not
create bad karma for ourselves things like that and and so um
and so um
the um so the ten courses of
wholesome action that lead to both liberation but also the growth
of wholesomeness in ourselves and what a wonderful thing to do what a wonderful thing to
do with one's life is to develop wholesome qualities that support others and protect others
and for the benefit of others and um
and right on the path to liberation what a nice thing that these two things coincide
so um that is um uh so the ten courses of skillful
or wholesome actions are found repeatedly in the pseudos and the in the middle length discourses
i see there's a note asking the source it may be relatively easy place to find
if those you have the have access to it the middle length discourses in discourse 9 has a
has a list of them but i don't know if it's a full list the full description the full
description might be in something like um
um in the middle length discourse 39 or 40 something like that so
so um thank you and uh may your day be wholesome
you