hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour hi
so i'm nikki and i'm in mountain view california one seated oloneyland and the weather is
actually sunny it was rainy before but it turned out sunny and cool
crisp crisp spring day who's here who wants to say hi
neil from new hampshire hi neil how's the weather out there we have 60s for the first time today 60s
wow warmer than california it wasn't three weeks ago though
yeah sure welcome bill from dallas well welcome murray
christine from down under who says warm humid and stuffy in sydney
summer in sydney oh sweet welcome who else wants to say hi
linda from utah where it's been snowing all afternoon
oh wow cool cool marie christine would probably like
to trade places with me if she's nodding yes wildly i love it
[Laughter] send you my background [Laughter]
yes neil sends you his wonderful snowy background yeah yeah humility humidity is
challenging he's a killer says marie christine yeah
ah so let's get started why not let's get started together
whether it's cold or hot wherever you are whatever the time zone let's get into
the field of practice together so it's a time when i change the
settings so one cannot so that unmuting will go
away and great i waited for neil just long enough to post information about happier google
groups before i change the settings so the chats will just come to me if there's anything urgent so there's
some more quiet in silence during the practice session and no accidental muting
unmuting rather and preliminary is recording
to this computer for audio dharma great so welcome everyone
welcome to happier so so for today's practice we're continuing
to expand in the ever-expanding circles of um equanimity practicing with upeka
the fourth brahmavihara and as many of you commented yesterday a
more nuanced practice more nuanced than meta vicari or a meta or compassion
or or sympathetic joy and equanimity the sense of equipoise
caring saying staying connected to the being that we practice equanimity with and yet
with the sense of spaciousness a bird's-eye view of all the causes and conditions that
have come and contributed to what is arising so a sense of peace and ease holding whatever is
happening in their life in our life depending on whom we're practicing with
and we've worked our way through the concentric circles and for today's practice we have
found our way to the category of someone we have some challenge with
so practicing equanimity with someone we have some challenge with
this is an interesting practice and we might find ourselves surprised as to what may
arise so the idea here is to establish a sense of
connection first well actually first during the guided meditation we'll spend you know
about 10 minutes just settling in the body with the breath as we usually do
and then after we tell the soil of awareness settling the mind calming the mind
then we turn we open up to this being
with whom we have some entanglement with whom we have some entanglement
and then feeling into the per the humanity of this person
connecting with with how they too want to be happy just just like me they're not so
different and then withholding them with equanimity whatever is arising
in their life and then for this uh variation we'll also work with
equanimity for this entanglement that we have with the two of us which is another way
and another way that connemity practice can work with with the person we have challenges with
there's so many different possibilities but this is what we'll try and see what
happens cultivating cultivating okay so ready shall we try it
yes yes let's so
i like to invite us all to get into our meditation posture shift and move
ah settle in this body
landing arriving
in this moment in time
and this body connected to the earth feeling your feet relaxing into our sit
bones relaxing our hands
ah shoulders neck
face muscles of the jaw
the internal muscles of the face
letting the entire body relax ah dropping dropping
holding tightness
softening relaxing and letting the breath be received
intimately by the awareness touched
by the awareness in the lower body in the abdomen
as if the abdomen is an organ of perception an organ of perception perceiving
receiving the breath the in-breath of the opera
if you know this if you notice thoughts arising
smilingly i wonder if this thought is necessary right now
and whether it can come back later if it's important enough it will
and without any judgment letting go
as if opening your hand letting go of this helium balloon of
thought ah feeling lighter coming back to the
breath organ of perception the abdomen receiving sensing the breath
intimately
here right here
here and now nudging
nudging lovingly nudging
awareness to stay close here now
now i would like to invite it to bring to mind
while we stay connected to the body to our breath in the body the
physicality the groundedness of the body bring to mind someone we have some
entanglement with relationally
not the toughest hardest one but some maybe lower on the throngs of
complications entanglements bringing bringing this
person to mind
allowing ourselves to feel into first and foremost their humanity
not condoning the harm the challenge but that just like us just like me
this human being this person wants to wants to be happy
they don't want to suffer just like me just as i want to be happy
and i have hopes and dreams aspirations
they too have aspirations just as i experience
joy and laughter happiness just as i experience sadness
just as i suffer this person too
feels happy at times feel feel sad at times they've experienced
sorrow and loss pain just like me
their inner life is just as compelling and just as complex as mine is
just as i have a full inner life full world
internally so does this person and their life is very dear to them
as my life is dear to me my happiness and well-being
we are not so different in this respect this person tonight
bringing to mind for a moment the entanglement we've had
and saying if this entanglement in this moment could be held with spaciousness with a
lot of equanimity instead of pointing fingers blaming it's
their fault they're this way my fault i should have done this just for this moment seeing if there can
be a perspective of just spaciousness seeing all the causes and conditions
so many of them out of our control that have led have led to this
entitlement as if we had a bird's eye view and saw all the causes and conditions
so many things predating us even historical
familial cultural art jeans or upbringing everything that brought us
that brought us to that moment
of this two beings me and them being entangled in this way
as if you were sitting on the proverbial top of a mountain you could see all the causes and conditions
past present and all the people
all the cause and conditions holding this entanglement within the context
in a bigger context of both of your journeys in life
and offering the equanimity phrases allow for a few see which one works for
you
whether i understand it or not things are unfolding according to a
lawful nature
staying connected with your body with your breath
with each offering of this phrase as if you're breathing this phrase
phrase of equanimity
may we accept things as they are may i may you accept things as they are
or may we may i may you be undisturbed
by the comings and goings of things
may i may you may we hold this entanglement with spaciousness
equipoise equanimity
or the traditional equanimity phrase all beings are owners all beings are
owners other actions heirs to their actions
their happiness and unhappiness depends on their actions
not my wishes for them
this
um
all beings have their own journey
whether you understand it or not
and for the last couple of minutes of this practice period
allowing whatever rose or didn't arise whatever arose in past
during this practice period this 30-minute set
let there be equanimity equipoise
okayness with whatever happened or didn't happen
not resisting not pushing away not attaching clinging
to having a spaciousness freedom of heart it was like this
it was like this may i accept things just as they were as
they are ah releasing letting go sense of freedom in
the heart of the conditions in this moment with respect to this practice
right here right now may all beings everywhere
have peace may all beings everywhere
have freedom of non-clinging
spaciousness in their heart
may all beings be happy including
ourselves [Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your
practice so i'm changing the settings
so if you like to chat with your reflections questions when you noticed you can
either send them to everyone in which case i'll read out
your name or you can just send them to me in which case i won't say your name but
read the question the reflection you can also raise your hand to
share your reflections what came up for you what did you notice how what was this like for you
this practice of equanimity in this way or form the person we have some
entanglement with
something that i notice sometimes with the practice of equanimity
sometimes there can be a lot of quiet and silence there's too much
like not no desire to even talk because the heart can feel settled and peaceful and kind of equinimity like ah
i don't have to say that i've noticed that in myself i have to say that it's interesting
equanimity kind of gets into the space of [Music]
our thoughts of course and murray christine says the person i have a major entanglement kept popping up so it was
really hard for me yeah it can be even though of course the invitation is to start where it's
easier and not a major entanglement but with a minor one but of
course the major one it can be and i do wonder i do wonder actually uh mark christine
as challenging as it was whether actually that is as you're it could be the edge of your practice
can i have equanimity can i hold this with peace can i have a sense
can i hold this comings and goings of this entanglement with just spaciousness things are like this right now it is
what it is it is oh yeah yeah thanks for adding that it felt so weepy
do you want to say it is it okay you don't have to but if you want to say more about the challenge you're welcome to and if not it's okay too
but yeah it can be challenging and maybe also having equanimity oh yeah i see
you're unmuted yourself so please yeah it was difficult because i was trying to just um
focus on the person with a very very small entanglement but the other one came popping up and
unfortunately as the other one kept popping up the pain and the hurt kept coming up coming up and i was a real struggle and
it made me feel at one point i thought i'm gonna switch everything off and start crying and i thought no no keep with the practice um
so it's brought up a lot of hurt for me yeah a lot of hurt and i miss emotional hurt
from the second with the major entanglement exactly i was trying to focus on the one that was really easy but it triggered the other
one and i wasn't able to contain it yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah thank you for
sharing that yeah yeah
yeah and in that case it becomes a practice of compassion for yourself self-compassion no sweetie this is hard
right now this is hard this is good i should have done that yeah this is hard right now and it's
okay it's never too late marie christine so i'm so glad you're bringing this up uh both for
yourself and for others because whenever new chat work hurting challenge comes up
please please feel free to turn the practice to taking care of your own heart with
kindness and compassion and then if there is enough stability then you can turn back to whatever the guidance is or not stay
with self-compassion for this for the entire practice this is what's called for great
let it be that's what's needed because it sounds like there's a lot of hurt in this this entanglement so maybe
that's what's called for uh to practice with self-compassion right now
thank you for your pills of wisdom ah thank you mark christine for your pearls of wisdom for being here
and practicing and sharing sharing yeah thank you
nikki do we have time for one more share we do please oh hi my name is dorothy and
this is the first time i've shared at group level but i wanted to say thank you so much for the reminder
that um the person that comes to our mind um that their actions is really what's the
cause and effect of how their life stands out and it's not our wishes for them because
i have a very very dear friend that i have a wonderful relationship but there are some entanglements and there's some wishes i
have for him just even a basic thing like he's able to be in the age range to get the shot
right now but he chooses not to and much bigger and deeper things that i wish for him
but that my risk wishes really have no um effect on
his life because it's his own choices so i want to just thank you so much for the reminder of that
yeah yeah thank you so much dorothy for bringing this up and sharing
in in community and really fleshing out how important this reminder this um
equanimity phrase really this this teaching equanimity that and that is the traditional phrase that i offered
how important that is that yes um people's happiness and their
unhappiness is dependent on their actions and not what they choose their actions their karma that's the
same word really it's it's what it's their their their actions in the world and no matter how much we wish for them
to be well it's part of the biggest bigger cause and condition so we can still
care for them we can still hold them with with care and dearness and
not take it on as our responsibility um but but
yes it's it we must fix it it allows us to stick to stay in
relationship with them with care without toppling into it or or um yeah
letting them have the space they need on their journey so thank you so much dorothy
thank you yeah great
yeah great we do have time for maybe one more
reflection if anyone has any before we go into to turn turn into group practice
nicholas please
oh there we go um yeah there there is a sense of happiness maybe kind of some some guilt
or i should have done something differently and considering the small entanglement
and it's just interesting that the impulse is to try to lighten the load but with equanimity there's a
sense of just having a more solid foundation that can carry the load underneath it instead yeah
nice beautiful well said equanimity really providing this
stability where this load can be carried without it kind of needing to be lightened up or analyzed
it's like oh it can be carried it can be just as it was in this moment and be held beautiful thank you nicholas
really appreciate your reflection yeah
great so dear ones let's turn our hearts to each other
and take this practice into small containers of
small sangha small group practice so the invitation is for the first
30 seconds to share meta just kindness for the other people
in the group in silence may you be well fellow human being just
like me have entanglements and you suffer we all do and feeling their meta for you
and then share as little or as much as you wish about your practice and support each other and what you
um again respectfully and what i mean by support is not to give each other advice that's not what i mean at all
you support each other by sharing from your own first person experience when you share this is what happened for
me that is the way you show up and you support each other um and when you just listen without
judgment without trying to fix it fix the other person or make it better for them but you just
listen you offer your ear with equanimity and care
then you're supporting each other so supporting each other in just showing up showing with meta showing with
equanimity with for each other which is profound practice really profound practice not trying to
get in there metal and just and that is the practice of equanimity so i'm inviting you to practice
equanimity for each other relationally with care
and just listening just listening just listening not trying to fix it
not turning away by jumping into just listening with care okay and as you'll
see this is profound practice it might push your edge you may want to offer something if the person says they were hurt
but stay on the edge and see if you can just hold it with equanimity and then you can
take it to your friends and relatives and just offer care without entanglement getting entangled into
what's happening for them so so let us practice in this profound way
together and i hope you don't hop off and
here we go i'll create the rooms and they are
open now here we go
hi everyone welcome back so how was that what did you notice
i'd love to hear from you your reflections this way of practicing holding space with equanimity
and experiencing with equanimity and care space being held for you
emily says it's always amazing to me how much connection can happen in five
minutes yeah yeah thanks emily
i see nods and hearts
of you are welcome to un unmute yourself bill says talking to others seems to be
its own type of therapy for me [Laughter] yeah there's nothing like practicing in
sangha it's so powerful so powerful
so powerful that's why in buddhism it's one of the three jewels the three the third jewel
is sangha is community so profound so important
anybody else wants to share today
nice to hear somebody else's voice pelosi says very grateful for this
community [Music] maybe someone who usually doesn't speak
so much or hasn't shared in a long time would love to hear your voice how how
did you find it how was it anything what did you find about your practice
be lovely to have you share of yourself if you would
susan says mammals need to connect i had an embodied moment where i realized any glimpse of
equanimity proceeds my having let go of something ah
nice thank you susan thank you for sharing that insight beautiful
glimpse of equanimity proceeds my heavy letting go let go of something
and i also wonder whether it can happen the other way around too whether
equanimity can precede letting go or something so bring that up
as an inquiry
happening both ways yeah so dear ones we have come to the end
of the hour of practice together always grateful so grateful for you showing up
for practicing for your own sake for the sake of all the beings whose
lives yours touches may all beings be happy may all beings
be free including ourselves and thank you again so much for being
here and practicing [Music]
thank you and may you all be well in every way so