so
so the topic much of this week is
step nine of mindfulness of breathing
and this is the step where we're
experiencing the mind
and i hope that the way i'm presenting
the mind is something
that's not not trying to define it in
ways that you have to fit your
yourself into the definition but rather
that it's um
i think it's uh pointing to how you
experience
the mind the mental state mind state
heart state that there's a lot of room
here
for you to find your own way to this
and um but one of the ways to appreciate
it
is that um we're moving into
the the
the the the sum total
of how we experience the mind
the pasta practice often has a big
emphasis on particularity
really seeing the particularity of the
in-breath the out-breath of sensations
that they occur
my you know the particular particular
activities of the mind as they come in
to go
and and
uh and uh but there's also some way that
part of the particular is also the
harmonious working of all this together
or the kind of the awareness or the
knowing that knows it all
and exactly whether mind and awareness
are the same
knowing is the same or not you know it's
very hard to kind of pin
down these things to know exactly what
the mind is or
consciousness or all these kinds of
things that are belong to this rather
i don't know if amorphous is the right
word
but uh difficult to define uh
qualities or experiences of our
interiority of
inner life and
and you'll see now in a moment maybe why
it's difficult to kind of
put words on it and define it exactly is
that
the concepts that we live with the ideas
that we have
about our experience actually shapes our
experience
we are not innocent bystanders of our
that whatever happens to us whatever
experience we're having
that it's only happening to us
we're also contributing to some degree
to that experience
that certainly there are clear things
that happen to us
so to choose something relatively
innocent perhaps
if i go out um
well i'll give you the example i've
taught many times and i was thinking
about it
today when i was biking down here it was
cold biking down here this morning
is um kind of a revelation from you many
many years ago was living in
central california and going to college
at a
college called davis and um
and it was um that is fog early morning
fog
thule fog and in the winter time the
cold fog was really cold
and and i didn't have any gloves and i
would bike to school
and the first five ten minutes of being
in class i couldn't actually use my pen
because my hand was still frozen and so
you know so
it was so cold so i used to uh
for a while i was biking to school this
way and kind of feeling miserable
sorry for myself and it was so terrible
this cold that i felt and
and then at one point i kind of had a
memory
that exactly the same feeling of cold
that i was having biking to school was
as far best of my memory
exactly the same feeling of cold i had
in my fingers
as a kid when i used to go skiing and
and that skiing it was exhilarating it
was fun it was fantastic it was part of
the
richness of the whole experience and i
realized that
that how i was experiencing the same
sensation
vary depending on the interpretation i
had it the context i put on it the ideas
i had about it
and after that biking didn't become so
difficult anymore
i realized that i was adding something
to the experience of cold
i was adding self-pity and this is going
to be tough and hard and i don't know
what i was adding exactly
and then it became just a matter of fact
and simple to have the cold
it was still cold and a little bit
painful but i didn't complicate it so
much with all the
ideas that were kind of subconscious
almost i didn't really realize how much
i was doing
i thought it was just the cold the cold
was the cold was painful was bad
but we contribute to the experience we
have interpretations
meaning making predictions of what it
means
we have self-referential feelings about
it this means that
i you know if maybe have self-pity about
things are difficult or
self-congratulations for things that are
good
and these inner movements of the mind
may be very subtle we don't necessarily
see them
but they are kind of helping to shape
our experience
and give kind of the totality the
gestalt of it
as we practice mindfulness we can start
teasing apart
the different component elements that
are all glum together
we can see that self-pity is self-pity
it's different than the cold
we can see that the the way that we're
worried about the future
that comes pulls into the my experience
of cold for example
is just my thoughts about the future and
we begin kind of teasing apart all this
the component elements
and and as we do that we begin actually
freeing the mind
we begin rather than glomming on or
focusing on it
then we begin to free it because not
only is our experience
you know like for example of me of the
cold partly shaped by my relationship to
it
but it's also shaping how i might
experience the mind
the mind gets contracted it gets tight
it gets small
the mind gets hot agitated and you can
the inner mood the state of mind that we
have
shifts and changes also depending on
what we're focusing on and how we're
focusing on it in relationship to things
so we're also in a sense shaping how we
experience the mind or how
the mind can be felt whether that's the
mind itself who knows what the mind is
but how we experience the mind is what
we're really working with
in this practice here and so the mind is
also being shaped
and and the language of the early
tradition
is that the concepts we are focusing on
fixating on creates limits
creates a boundary to the mind an edge
to the mind
but as we stop focusing so much on the
things and our preoccupations and
all this activities of the mind the
activities of the mind get quieter and
quieter
the shape the way which we kind of shape
the feeling of the mind the sense of the
mind
begins to lose its edges its its
coagulation
its contraction its its gathering
together
and it becomes more open more spacious
and
after a while you can almost feel like
there's no boundaries to
the mind or no boundaries to awareness
or
no boundary uh boundaries to the state
that we're in
and to use a little bit dangerous word
from what i said earlier
no boundaries to consciousness
and and it isn't so much again important
what
all these words point to
the wonderful thing is the experience of
no more edges no more boundaries
and the mind starts feeling
large great expansive
wide and and this is one of the things
that
can be experienced as we deepen this
meditation practice
is the mind becomes expansive becomes
wide
in zen they called it a big mind
and uh as opposed to the small mind
and the expansive mind rather than the
contracted mind
the and the the more expensive it gets
the calmer it becomes the less agitated
it is
in the similar that the space empty
space
you know kind of has no agitation and
they say that um
it's um you know that mind becomes
similar to space
so less and less agitation and calm it
also helps make the mind more malleable
and shapeable
because when we're really fixated on
something the mind becomes
hard maybe even brittle and kind of
fixated also and
if you do the same habit of mind over
and over and over again for decades
the mind gets kind of locked into being
a particular way it's hard to
soften it but with meditation enough
time it begins to soften and relax and
it becomes malleable and shapeable and
one of the ways the mind can be
and then more what happens when the mind
becomes more shapeable or malleable
or soft and is it's easier and easier to
train the mind
it's easier and easier to get the mind
focused and
centered settled and
and that allows for some of the more
beautiful qualities of the mind to shine
the mind that's fixated and bounded and
limited by its agitation and
preoccupation
doesn't really allow for the luminosity
of the mind to show itself
the clarity of the mind the cl
the mind feel that feels clean the mind
that feels
bright
so
this gestalt this wide sense of
the attitude of mind the state of mind
the mood of mind the quality of
awareness
that is so wide that it includes
all things and it includes our suffering
not to deny it but to give it a very
different context
than if our relationship is is like a
locked on
to our suffering and it's possible to
suffer
of different kinds and
and not lock on and to feel that
the suffering being held or existing in
this much
wider broader context has certain kind
of ease or calm
that also allows to have compassion for
suffering
there's space for friendliness and care
for it
as a that's maybe more difficult when
we're locked into it
so there's a lot of benefits to
discovering
the this mindfulness of the mind
and for an anapanasati the mindfulness
of breathing practice
we train ourselves to breathe with the
mind
breathing in one breathes with one
experiences the mind breathing out one
experiences the mind
and as always with anapanasati this
rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
is meant to keep us from getting fixated
on anything
including fixated on the mind so they're
just a fluid and relaxed
with the breathing breathing in with the
mind breathing out with the mind
so um how about taking care of one's
body by getting mittens
or wool socks over hands these days i
drive i bike down
with mittens on my hands on with gloves
i just was not smart enough when i was a
college student
for that even to occur to me i didn't
have gloves and never
never passed my mind so some of us um
you know it takes a while to become wise
about how to take care of ourselves
but in the meantime i got a very good
lesson from my story with uh
with the um you know my cold hands
so thank you very much
you