thank you for uh being with us everybody um and thank you to ere for joining us today uh sitting with our
sangha uh so tuarius salah is a guiding teacher at the seattle meditation society and she's
the founding teacher of the capitol hill meditation group she's a retired prosecuting attorney who
has practiced the possible meditation for over 30 years tuareg believes that urban meditation is
the foundation for today's practitioner's path to liberation she's inspired by
bringing the dharma to non-traditional places and is a strong advocate for practitioners living with high stress
past trauma and difficulty sitting still tuareg has been teaching since 2010 and
will be completing the four-year teacher training program through the insight meditation society
uh this may thank you terry thank you kevin
kind of strange coming here giving this talk to you when it's some
in some respects i've been at the center so many times through the teacher training process so i feel at
home and then it's there's also this uniqueness that i don't really know
most of you you may have seen me on a retreat or something but i don't really know most of you so there's a trust here
that happens in the dhamma that is very very touching to me
and so i i think that's what it is that i want to talk a little bit about i want to talk a little bit about as
practitioners how why it's so
important that we practice taking the time to come to this present
moment here and now why do we even bother with all this meditation
i mean we can do all kinds of things to settle ourselves down some of us run some of us do you know
martial arts some of us do crafts like the woodworking and
uh reading and all kinds of things that we do to kind of settle ourselves down so
why why the meditation why what is it that we're trying to do
here with meditation and from my perspective what are urban practitioners trying to
do with meditation you know we can look at monastics and think oh they're they're headed right towards enlightenment
and awakening and but not us right we're just meditating um for some
other reason and i'd like to share a little bit about why i think
we should meditate and why we should take it um treated with respect
and a level of sincerity because of what it can ultimately help
us see and maybe i'll introduce myself a little
bit to you so you know a little bit about where i've come from so i grew up
in the uh where a housing project in seattle and
i did not grow up in a buddhist content context at all my parents were
conservative christians and very strict one might even go so far as to
point out all the abuse that i went through when i was a child with that strictness but um
it was just a very dysfunctional family but my parents were very rigid on
education and so i went all the way to law school
and it was in law school after law school really that i failed the bar twice when i
failed it the first time i thought there was something wrong with the bar but when i felt it the second
time i thought there was something wrong with me and i did not
have that as abusive or dysfunction as our lives can be when we're growing up
you don't know that dysfunctionality exists so i did not
know of the dysfunction until i felt that bar the second time
somehow the whole world dropped out somehow um everything i thought i was
walking towards uh got disrupted
and i found the dhamma well i should say i think the dhamma found me because i think it was probably looking for me
for a while and i finally connected
to this nine kind of nagging thing in the back of my mind
was it cannot just be about this there's got to be something more than just
this this working hard striving striving getting to one thing we talk about this
all the time but no matter how much we talk about it it still seems like we are still
doing and living in the same pattern even though we talk about it a lot
and what i've come to understand over the years i mean finding the dhamma i did ultimately pass
the bar became a prosecutor spent my life as a prosecutor
but over the years of practice
i i cannot tell you that my practice ultimately came to where i was pointing
it towards because i didn't point it this way that it ultimately came but there's a
way in which practice is doing something to us and that's what
i really want to point to is what is it that it's doing to us what is it that it's
allowing in us that if we give way to it we um
allow the practice to do what the practice is intended to do
you know how our bodies are intended to eat food and digest food
so we could eat cardboard and it would digest the cardboard but it wouldn't
really get the point babies don't know the difference between
food and non-food so it just eats anything and so you we sort of have to learn what
food is but when you learn what food is you can eat bad food you can eat good food you can eat
healthy food unhealthy food i know plenty of people that are old folks in my family
that they know i don't think they ate any vegetables but or if they did eat vegetables had so
much meat in it that you know i don't know if you could call it vegetable you might have to call it a
vegetable meat mix but even with that they can live long long
time and then some people can eat very healthy food and then they don't live very long at all
there's a way in which our bodies does what it does because it is the nature of
the body to do what it does and it doesn't have anything to do with you or me
and there is a thing that's happening with meditation that if we allow it to happen
um we can really see some uh we can see
a flock of blackbirds taking a wide turn
and be astonished by it so here's a couple of things
just a framing we live in a we live in a closed circuit
mind we don't live in a mind that's wide open and fluid we live in a closed circuit
mine so we live in a mind that's pretty much guarded by our grasping
mind that says this is right and this is wrong this is good and this is bad this is
pleasant this is unpleasant it has very strict rules and associations and things come together in our mind and
everything makes sense and we feel comfortable because actually the stability that we feel in
life isn't coming from life it's coming from habit it's coming from our habitual way
of doing so i feel still because i wake up in my own house and i have the habit of
seeing that door that wall that kitchen everything looks the same
so i feel solid and secure and steady it's the habit of it and then as soon as
something outside of that habit happens i've lost
my stability which is why this pandemic was so unnerving
i remember when it first happened i didn't really believe i was going to be stuck in the house for
a year okay a few weeks okay okay i can do a month
i can tell i can't believe a couple of months i realize it's gonna take a little bit
longer for this to clear out but then you know a couple of months and then months after months after
months and now i have found i have the habit
of staying here so now their mind is like well i don't know if i want to go out so
much i don't i mean i want to go out but there's all this apprehension
about going out even if i could go out because we
we have a mind that is built on habit and that habit becomes our stability
but that habit is not real it is
how do i say it it is built on sand
it's like i like that the buddha would use examples of how
insubstantial it is so he said like bubbles that rise when
water is falling the bubbles in the pond a puddle that we don't think of those bubbles as
being i'm gonna put my faith in those bubbles holding true it's insubstantial it makes sense
or foam that comes off of the ocean i've never seen that foam before
the example that he uses this seafoam i've never seen that kind of foam before
but once when we were at irc the first time and went down to the beach area
i saw this phone and i really did think it was substantial until you get up on
it and then it's nothing it's it disappears you can see that it's insubstantial
a mirage on a hot road you can see you know it's not real
that's not really water or a magician we kind of know these
things but yet we believe in our habit as if it is substantial
as if this is reality and this is the truth
it's very difficult if not impossible
to see this to see this insubstantiation to see how untrue it is
it takes a steady mind it takes
a level of curiosity and interest and it takes a soft heart
you know the non-judging acceptance soft heart steadiness
and this um interest
that's what you're cultivating when we meditate that's what we're cultivating when we
meditate we're cultivating a level
of seed that allows us to steady the gaze
that allows us to soften into a level of kindness
and that creates an interest in whatever is happening so in l less of the doing to
fix the meditation and more of a watching
and i i i probably i'm gonna take a stab at this but i'm
pretty much i'm pretty sure that all of us on this call in hearing this talk
could say oftentimes when you're sitting there i
don't know what i'm doing i don't know what i'm looking at i don't know what it is because we're
we're taking a mind that is used to setting its understanding in habit
that's used to having labels and associations and knowing things as it knows and we are
exposing it to a vast constantly moving dharma
the dhamma is moving and our grasping mind
is permanent so the world is impermanent it's moving all the time and we're
taking us a mind that's used to labeling things and knowing
things and we're putting it in a place where we want things to just move and
flow it's not going to make any sense
well i should say it's not going to make any sense to the grasping part of our mind but it makes
total sense to the embodied part of our mind because the embodied
part of our mind is present it's in the present moment it
knows things are in stem it knows things are insubstantial it knows and understands the three characteristics
of impermanence subject to change which is gonna bring dig duga and that's not personal it
knows this so we are spending time
learning how to let go of that grasping mind
and relax into get to know begin to trust this more
intuitive embodied mind and the intuitive embodied mind
allows us to see things like the black birds turning
just a little bit more here
it's not easy to tap into this intuitive mind you know this because when we sit
the grasping mind pretty much gets in the way with all of its talking and talking
and talking and rehearsing and planning and thinking thinking thinking it's got
plenty of stuff to say and it waits until we're still to say it
all of it
so in order for us to access this intuitive mind
we need to be kind to the grasping mind i used to have this so so because i grew
up with a lot of trauma i also grew up with a lot of dysfunction and a lot of i had a very i would say aggressive
angry mind it was pretty anxious this whole meditation
thing and it's way too fluid for for my mind i grew up in a
house full of chaos so it wanted everything to be non-chaotic and of course sitting in
meditation can raise a lot of chaos in the beginning
so i used to have this habit of being nice to my
sort of uh dysfunctional what i would call my
trauma mind because it was always thinking this is the end this is the
end this is the end and so i would the way that i would help soothe it is
the way it would help soothe my kids and i would thank it for whatever it said i would just say
thank you and then i would ask into the moment again so i began to use
what i would call uh asking questions like there are all kinds of practices that
you know you can learn to do this professionally i mean or or
you can get trained in it i just made this up for myself but it does do wonders
i would pick something that seems hard to see
like soft it's hard to see soft when you have a
mind that is pretty rigid it really doesn't believe soft is around maybe some pillow but it
has even complaints about the pillow softness level
so i would ask my mind where soft
and it would say you know there's no soft we meet so often here because it's just
too hard but there's no soft and i would say thank you and i'd ask again where's up in seattle
inside rodney smith my teacher used to do this in little discussion groups and so i started doing
it with myself where is it and i just say thank you and then ask it again
but i learned something from doing this that has helped my practice immensely
if you if you if you if you begin to consider that what we're trying to see in this
awakening what we're trying to see in the idea of seeing that if you're trying to see the four noble truths
that that there is suffering that there is a cause for that suffering and that
there is a cause to the way leading out of that suffering
and the eightfold path itself all of these list things that we've
learned they're all very difficult to see to experience because we have a mind
that's set in habit and set in stone of the way it thinks
so when i would start asking a question some theoretical rhetorical
you know there's no real answer to it i'd ask and and began to have the mind
stumble over trying to find that a hardened answer
i learned something that if our grasping mind the part of us
that needs to know if it is not
shoved pushed if you're kind to it
but you keep asking a question eventually it will ask
the intuitive mind the answer
this is a strange phenomenon which is why i think some practices have you with these
asking pointed questions over and over and over because what ends up happening is i
this is the best way i can describe it so when we're sitting in meditation
and if you in your kindness keep coming back to the same anchor
not forcing the mind to come back but just in a kind way like thank you
for that planning but we're going to come back to this moment thank you for that
come back i think what the mind this
i'm gonna tell you what i think is happening i think the mind is going
in the back to the intuitive body and saying hey what is going on there
what is she asking for what do they want i keep telling them there's no soft
around why did you keep asking me do you know what soft is
because if you keep asking what is saw is there software is it
and you don't you don't get mad at what the mind says
just say thank you and you ask again what you end up experiencing
is the felt sense of soft and all of a sudden you feel softness
everywhere because softness is not something you can intellectually
know it's something that we feel so a lot of the dhamma that we are
talking about is a felt sense experience not an intellectual concept
and if you try to force your mind to understand it it doesn't make any sense
it will keep trying to create an image of what it is that you want
in your mind like when we're trying to get still and we we've been still before so we're
trying to get to that and the mind will try to recreate it but it'll constantly tell you
well we can't get still because you need to solve that problem you need to fix this if you would get this done then we could
get still and it's constantly planning preparing rehearsing doing all these
things in service of one day we are going to get to that moment when
you were still and that's what it's trying to get to but you got all this mess in the way
so instead you're trying to question into is stillness here
now and you say no it's not here look we got to get through this oh thank you for all that is stillness here
now no it's not i'm saying i'm not still okay i'll say it again
there is stillness here
the best example i can give this for those of us that are older is karate
kid what mr miyagi did with karate kid is what we're doing with the mind
it's the best example so if you haven't seen karate kid or if it's been a long time you gotta
look at it and you get a it's a dollar talk this is not some hollywood movie just ignore all the you
know kerfuffle but what what you are learning to do
is to embody the moment not kind of
know what's going on you don't need to know and over the years of my practice i've
learned to shift my awareness from this kind of knowing where i'm
at controlling what i see knowing knowing knowing to this
more intuitive knowing that is much more trusting
so even though the mind didn't understand the pandemic when i
came into it and doesn't understand what we're going to do now that it's
we're gonna start having vaccinations and am i really gonna leave and what does that mean am i gonna go back to
flying what does that mean airplane i don't even know really
even though all of that's happening inside is kind
it's still and it's curious about the whole thing all of it
it's not that i to where i am like that i still have the trauma mind from my
childhood but i just have a relationship
with the intuitive body i was born with and that aspect of me is very strong
very kind and very um
it's just interested curious about everything
it's in all of us it's not like it's in me because i got some special gift if i had some special gift i missed
it when i was growing up it's not that it's in all of us but what
we're doing is we have to sit and learn to access it because we have a grasping
mind that is hell bent on running the show
and so gradually gradually gradually we keep introducing the grasping mind
to this intuitive knowing my intuitive embodied mind
and that mind is stronger more courageous it's not afraid of
mystery you know take on anything what mystery in fact it probably is less interested
in the same old same old same old it's like come on let's go do something different let's go see
let's notice sounds that we've never heard before
so i'm gonna end here on a poem another one
um to show you uh i think where
i think this poem um
it points to how we do this how we live with both this grasping mind that set in
stone that controls everything and this what uh buddha dasa would call
dhamma wisdom donald mine that's very uh open and vast and can see
and penetrate through
this is how we do it this is called the second music by annie
lightheart and he says now i
understand that there are two melodies playing one below the other one
easier to hear the other lower steady perhaps more faithful for being
less heard yet always present when all other things seem lively and real
this one fades yet the notes of it touch as gently as fingertips
as the sound of the names laid over each child at birth i want to stay in
that music without striving cover
if the truth of our lives is what it is playing the telling is so soft that this
mortal time this irrevocable change becomes beautiful i
stop and stop again to hear the second music i hear the children in the yard a train
bin birds all this is in it and will be gone i set my ear to it
as i would to a heart
so let's just sit quietly for a moment
[Music]
thank you so much for your practice and your
of patience you're all on zoom and you're all muted so you seem so quiet but
so we'll take a little time for some questions in case people have some
okay so if you have a question and uh you can go ahead and use the reactions button to raise your hand and we'll
call on you or you can post your question in chat
i'm getting all these thank yous
hi laura
so i see one question here
um capitol hill's in seattle washington so it's just capitol hill
meditation group if you look online and then i see carrie has her henna but
i'm going to answer this one question here how do i stay consistent with practice
that's a great question because um it might seem like
uh that i think the question might be asking how do i stay
consistent with sitting on the cushion that kind of practice but one way i've learned to stay
consistent with practice is i think practice is constant i'm never
not practicing so if i am cooking dinner i'm always using that
as a meditation i tell people on retreat and it works really well on these online
retreats is everything you do is a meditation so i just put the word meditation if i'm
going to the grocery store i'm doing my going to the grocery store meditation i learned that at retreats because
the only difference between going on a residential retreat and coming uh being in your house
before we actually started meditating in the house was that when you would go on a residential retreat all the work you did
were called yogi jobs i mean you're still really just chopping vegetables or cleaning toilets but yet
it had some kind of honorable integrity to it because on a retreat it's a yoga job so
when i would come home that's when i started calling everything i did like a yogi job and
somehow as an urban practitioner we have to
bring practice into our everyday existence because
something that you can note is when when we go on retreat for those of
you that have gone on residential retreats on the land you're kind of tucked in you get tucked
into this little cocoon and it takes a couple of days to get the mind to let go
of the flow of your life and then you're tucked into this safe space and you can
cultivate this really really strong kind of internal
connection with this intuitive this kind of embodied mind that's where that samadhi is
that sense of groundedness we get and then we take that and we go out in the world
and basically we let it get spent out until we can't take it anymore we come
back to a retreat we generate some kind of a samadhi again and we go
we use that to go out in the world and i i like that i mean we definitely need to come tucked in and cultivate that
samadhi i'll be so glad we can go back to going on the land and get that sense of tucked away
experience but as urban practitioners
we got to bring that tucked in experience into our everyday
world and probably the greatest thing that's happened to western practice is this pandemic
where we all had to have these retreats online if you have not done a retreat online you got to do one
you got to know how easy it is to begin to actually allow
your household to be a sanctuary for practice
when that happens you're practicing all the time so it's not let me get this done so i
can do something else you can begin to feel the sense of
curiosity kindness and this um steady of mind no matter what you're
doing all the time that's how i have consistent practice
is i stopped thinking that i was only practicing when i'm sitting on the cushion and
something happened when the grasping mind learns that it's okay
to stand at the sink and wash dishes and you're practicing it also won't mind doing it when you sit
on the cushion in fact it will want to sit on the cushion let's sit on the cushion and try
this well we don't have to do anything so my sitting on the cushion
increased because i was willing to get still all over the house doing whatever i was
doing so don't limit your practice to just sitting on the cushion
trust that if i bring this stillness this willingness to have a steadiness of
mind to the here and now a level of kindness about whatever's arising
and this curiosity in it then i am going to
i'm that that sitting on the cushion part is going to come
our our problem is that we keep losing it because we only think we're practicing
on the cushion and if you have dishwashers there is no better meditation than
standing at the sink and washing dishes we gotta let that dishwasher go and you gotta take some time
to wash the dishes and do nothing else but stand there and wash the shoes maybe it's the warm water i don't know
what it is but there's something about the sound or the the simplicity of washing
dishes so you can that can be your meditation that
ultimately you are creating like in retreat where we cultivate
continuity between the sitting the walking the getting up in between that and the
eating and going to bed we create this continuity
you're doing the same thing when you create that kind of continuity at home
so i thought carrie had her hand up but i don't see it now so let's see there's a couple
of questions from youtube tourey so so one of them comes from paul
he said how best to access that second music
this is what i was pointing to about the karate kid movie so you gotta watch the movie so you can see
that the what mr miyagi was showing this kid is that he already
had access to this karate wisdom
we already have access to that music it's already there we have to learn to turn towards it and
notice it and so take into consideration that the grasping mind
doesn't isn't necessarily going to trust it so i used the
repeated questions rhetorical questions to look for it so even if you like the
poem the second music you could ask because you know what is the second music that's just a phrase
that the poet wrote right so you could ask where is my second music where is that of course
your grasping mind's gonna say it's it's i don't know i can't access it's not here
because there's too much stuff going on right now you just thank the mind for that and ask
again where is that second music listen forward where is it and eventually your mind will ask your
intuitive mind where is it i don't understand where is it and that's when you begin to access
it so that you're accessing it not from the grasping mind
you actually have to give the second music layer permission to show itself or
reveal itself and that permission has to be granted almost by the grasping mind that's why
you have to be kind to this grasping mind so that it doesn't overpower
your wisdom and that's what we do on retreats we learn how to give permission for that
intuitive mind to be present so you're doing this in in your
everyday urban life just have patience with it just be very nice very kind
sort of like uh nilla reba once said there's a quote by
miller but let me see if i can remember it be more like a lion
than a dog chasing after your thoughts right because dogs
chase after sticks sticks he says soaked into the effect so one
only throws a stick and a lion once it's like you're not gonna be
throwing a stick at it so that if you treat your mind
like a lion you're gonna approach it with a level of kindness and care you're not gonna just be like
treating it like go get it go get it so that's what it's pointing to is to treat the mind with care but
thank it and ask again keep asking and you'll find that second reason
what's the other question uh so there's a couple people asking about like the names and authors of the two poems
you read today oh it was uh
blackbirds by julie cadwadler c-a-d-w-a-l-l-a
d-e-r her last name is staubs s-t-a-u-b
and the other one is the second music by annie lightheart l-i-g-h-t-h-a-r-t
and uh eric our last question he said uh what helps you to calm the
judgments we have of ourselves and others yeah there's a couple of um there's a
couple of things here about busy mind and and it's along the same line so this is
this is this is what i'm pointing to this is the crust of what i'm pointing to
judgment is part of grasping mind everybody on this call has a grasping
mind comparing is part of the grasping mind everybody here that this is the mind that we have um
the busyness the overwhelm all of that energy is part of a grasping line
it's the same anxiety i had for so long all of that is part of that mind that's
trying to control everything and keep things safe and protected
that aspect of mind is not designed to harm us it's actually designed to
help us to remember when things hurt us and keep it in line to remember what's good and
remember what's bad and keep it keep it tight know where to go know how to do it
it's based on surety and the sense of control and and it's it's not very mysterious at
all it knows the problem is that we live in that mind we live in that mind
as if that is the mind that's gonna keep us safe and we're very much afraid of the intuitive
spontaneous kind of mysterious i don't know what's gonna go on let's just take it as we take it
but that is the nature of the world we live in we live in a world that's very
fluid and mysterious with a mind that's set in stone and that is where
our conflict lies so we can't just dish this this a
judging comparing like rigid fixing mind
we think more of it's not getting rid of that mind it's adding
in the other mind that we do have an aspect of us that's
just aligned with the way things are it's trusting its nature is to be intuitive
its nature is to live in mystery that aspect of us is existing simultaneously
so what we're learning to do is how do i not disrespect this mind
as uh in the hood we'd say throw shade on this mind in order
to say i'm in this my hook because we won't stay very long we'll be in it and
then you know this might all mess it all up so instead we want to give respect and honor to
this mind but know that there is a completely
different world a different way of existing in the moment and we are
going to learn how to touch into that you do it at home you do it when you're sitting you do it
when you go retreat you just do it as often as you can you listen for the second music you listen
for the intuitive mind in any given moment and you never
disrespect or get mean to this grasping mind because it's not designed to see it
it's designed to keep us steady and safe but that other mind is there
and gradually i think enlightened beings walk around in the world knowing both of
those minds and their intuitive mind is far superior
instead of its flip for us our grasping mind is more superior and so we're just learning to balance
this out so that it's steadier
all right well do you have time for one more question yeah uh so carrie i think who had her
hand raised oh yes she did uh so she asked have you experienced a shift in the trauma mind
over time yes this is what i'm pointing to trauma mind
grasping mine it did not know how to manage the world that i was
living in when i was a kid so it came up with all these structures and systems and thoughts and mechanisms
to try to help me and i lived through that and when i failed the bar what i thought
was a perfect understanding of the world came crashing in on me because it didn't work so i mean i had
to do 20 years of therapy to get rid of trauma mind don't get it twisted
adama is not therapy it's not gonna it's not gonna do the therapeutic thing
because it's not at one respect dumber doesn't care if there's trauma in the space
it's more like do you know there's trauma in the space but most of us when we get trauma we get
triggered in trauma we don't even know we're in that trigger so this is more about do you know
where dhamma helps in trauma assuming that you have worked through
the the the the therapeutic side of it it's like a
psychological side of it where trauma really helped where duma helps
is it is the aspect that allows us to bring a degree of softening and
kindness and curiosity around whatever's happening
so what i found was i became less and less uh
panicky about the anxiety or the fact that i just got triggered or i
just had more capacity to be with unpleasantness to be with anxiety and see it for more
what it is and i the grasping mind cannot do that it cannot be with anxiety with any
degree of trust because it's too um it's too judgmental basically anxiety is
bad there's just no way around it nobody wants it but we have an intuitive side of us
that knows anxiety is here it's not caught in the anxiety and it can steady us and say well this
is this oh what's that white weight not actually having a heart attack
nobody's actually hitting us hold on just a moment that aspect is an
intuitive mind and so practice is about learning how
to rest in that intuitive mind and not letting our grasping mind basically
tell us what to do that's why when you're there sitting you're going to feel
unpleasantness practice being with that unpleasantness a little bit what it may be
wait only gonna sit here for five minutes can i just be with this unpleasantness
the mind is all talking talking talking not gonna try to get rid of that just
wait just okay do what you gotta do talk talk talk let me just see if i can settle in
the body and notice that i'm doing all that talking and not caught up in it that is
something we learn how to do it's not something that just happens so you're going to practice and
sometimes you're not going to be able to get out of the the uh i couldn't get out of that anxiety
you know violent kind of thinking and i just have to get up but sometimes i could like oh wait i see
something and then it's all gone again and then you know back i'm stuck in it
our practice sangha is really what helps us just keep doing it just keep trying and
keep trying and keep trying and over time you don't have to fix it
the mind will do it on its own
i see one more hand here gary jerry let me go ahead and sorry unmute
him um first of all thank you very much uh for uh
an excellent uh talk i really appreciate it so um i just wondered in terms of uh
i'm a psychiatrist and i help try to help a lot of people in toronto and of course a lot of people are
frightened about covid and so anyhow you spoke about the grasping mind about keeping us safe and the intuitive
mind so i i might take am i to take that both are necessary but perhaps in our
society that the intuitive mind has been unnecessarily suppressed and that it needs to be brought into balance with
the grasping minor do i get that's what i think that's the right thing i'm going to give you an example i gave
to my thursday night capitol hill group this is the perfect the best way i could explain it so
um i have a outlet in my house that uh was connected to uh a fan
and i didn't think it worked i mean that's how i bought the house and it didn't work and so we took it off the
price and so it didn't work 20 years i've been in this apartment never used that stupid outlet so so that somebody asked
me well why don't we put a i've always wanted an outlet over there but i don't have one because you know it doesn't work so my friend
who does electro like you know electric things said why don't we put an outlet there i said
it doesn't work guess what i mean it doesn't have wires
it's like oh yeah but it doesn't work it goes well can we see it opens it up and of course
it works like i had it 20 years ago okay it works so he puts an outlet there
and plugs in an extension cord not even anything of power just an extension cord
to show me it work i'm like oh it works
and then maybe i don't know maybe about an hour later the power goes
off and it goes off in the house and of course i think i should have never did that outlet
that's what did it it was the outlet he goes to work there's nothing plugged in it would've if it were too much power it
would have happened immediately like no it was it was me and then i went to the door and i looked
down the hall and i'm like oh i'm taking out the power of the whole block
and then it turns out i've been my whole neighborhood the power's out
all because of me the grasping mind it
it associates this is what you would know jerry it's like it associates things and connects things
together and it creates stories based on that the intuitive mind
is much more connected to just what is arising in this moment
so the biggest problem with code was and is our fears is what we think
is going to happen it's the the extrapolated stories that get
drawn out and dhamma is about here and now this moment this
moment this moment and the more we learn to acknowledge
that this moment even though the story as much dumb as i had i still had this mind that was growing
ever big of trauma that was about to happen and what saved me was a friend of mine
sent me an email that said oh did you are you stuck in a power outage i heard
capitol hill had this uh you know some the snow it was snow at the time the snow broke
some power line and are you stuck in you know no electricity and i was like
oh that's where it comes from but you can see that how easily the grasping mind
it doesn't it didn't have anything to do with me it's what i'm saying the mind just envelops and goes on its own
and we kind of go with it unless you have some ability to kind of stay so the old me
would have pretty much panicked i would have shut down i would have been in anxiety i wouldn't
even have been able to hear if someone did tell me that it was from a power line i would have insisted
that this is what it was from me i would have closed that outlet off and i would never use it again
but this uh what what what dhamma has taught me is to be in the hearing now and in the
here and now i can tell oh that is a trauma mind that is not reality reality it happens
it comes it doesn't have to rock me forever you know i don't have to shut
off that whole side of the house sort of like i did in the beginning or it doesn't work i
can actually allow the present moment to have influence on you you see that that
that is what it is that i think damma can help people
begin to do what you could consider a double check you can double check the
present moment to see if it's in line or in keeping with the mind's story it's creating
and double checking that story against reality it begins to help us
learn to see the difference between the stories that our minds are creating and the truth of what's actually going
on so what could have been a really long lasting problem ended up only
lasting about an hour see the difference yes that's very helpful thank you so
much i really appreciate that thank you yeah too area actually dunder actually
had a question i don't know if you still have time okay take that so he asks or they ask where do these two minds
come from grasping mind and the intuitive mind and then he has a follow-up is there an evolutionary background for these two
minds i don't think that there are i don't think of it as i don't know about the it's it's
evolutionary nature of it i guess what i would say is the two
minds i'm speaking of is like digestion it's like uh
our respiratory system it comes with the package so grasping that
i guess you could call it reptilian brain but i think i've heard from a couple of uh uh
dhamma teachers that are scientists also that it doesn't really line up with the reptilian brain like we try to say it
but there is an aspect of mind that compares and judges
it's the name and form aspect of uh the link on the dependent origination so
this mind just automatically does this there's an aspect of mind that automatically labels
things as pleasant unpleasant and neither so that part of mind is what we tend to
live in in our urban society there is still an intuitive mind you
know it because something as simple as you can walk into a room where two people were
arguing they're not arguing now but you know something went on you don't know what happened but you know something went on
or you can look at two people and say oh they like each other oh i can see you just have this intuitive sense so we
do have an intuitive capacity consciousness of knowing and penetrating
through mostly we don't come to that knowing until we go into a retreat where we have
shaved away all of the other distractions and we can point our mind towards it
and what we're learning in practicing in urban life you're learning how to
be and cultivate that intuitive mind in the midst of a lot of distractions
so it's harder but it still can be done
all right great i think we've probably used up all our time now yes thank you very much okay good thank
you so much for having me i appreciate it you know i hope to see you again
bye thank you thank you bye