so hello and welcome everyone it's good to see you here at happy hour dear
sangha so so for today's practice um
i was having a tough time deciding between two practices so maybe i'll do one to today and another one next time
so or on friday so
the practice for today i'd like to invite us to consider is um
is what's considered tilling the soil or till or preparing the soil
for forgiveness so we are human beings we all go through
life and [Music] there might have been situations where
you know there's still a little bit of you know uh not quite clarity being
completely clear with somebody in our lives and we may may or may not be ready
to forgive them or maybe we have forgiven them to some extent so anywhere there or there has been some
kind of um maybe challenge or rub or
uh entanglement say with someone in our lives where we have pushed their buttons
they have pushed our buttons it happens we're human beings we get entangled right is there a single one of us who
hasn't had an entanglement and so in order to till the soil in order to
prepare the soil for gratitude you know we may not be ready i'm sorry
not gratitude that's what we'll do on friday that's the other practice i was thinking of doing a different way of
doing it i guess that's the preview okay come for gratitude on friday
but um to tell the soil to really prepare our hearts for forgiveness even if we're not ready quite for forgiveness
because forgiveness is something that can't be pushed can't be rushed um
and um or also maybe as i said we've forgiven this person
quite to to a large extent but maybe there's still a little little rub there and of course this idea of forgiveness
etc doesn't mean that we bring them back into our lives but just that there's clarity in our heart
so the way we till the soil with the way we prepare our hearts to be ready
for forgiveness is to consider their common humanities to consider
their good qualities to consider the good maybe some of the
good deeds they have done for us maybe some of the in the past maybe we've been friends and just recollecting
bringing to our heart um not as a not with forcing and pushing but to
really glad in our heart or there's this other human being who has some good qualities and
and um maybe they are really supporting some
other people in in some ways through their work through their
uh family life and just so bringing these good qualities and
again we're not trying to rush into forgiveness and tonight it's
just in in some ways maybe this could be another way i could frame this is a meta
for someone we have had challenges with or meta for someone we have a challenge with but with kind of our ear out or our
eye out like oh yeah when we do this when we consider their goodness
the heart gets ready the soil gets tilled for forgiveness at some point
whenever the heart is ready so so that is the framing that is the
context and i hope i've been clear enough maybe i'll just say one more thing about it
which is um what i'm inviting us to explore tonight
is considering in our hearts the good qualities of someone we've had
an entanglement with and it's a it's similar but slightly
different from doing metaphor them as you will see similar but a little different and it's definitely not
forgiveness yet right so it's not it's not forgiveness organism might arise tonight it's like oh naturally great if
it comes up have fun with it but we're just recollecting goodness it's a
recollection of goodness that's that's that's how i'm framing the practice
tonight let's explore let's see what happens different things might come up always
trust your experience and if at any point it gets challenging or difficult
um go to self-care go to self-compassion self-meta taking care of your own heart
if challenges from the past like really bubble up and you find yourself in anger and remorse or whatever just go back to
self-compassion all right dear it's okay it's all right okay so as long as you bring kindness
to whatever comes up you are doing the practice right
let me say that again as long as you turn
with kindness and hold with kindness whatever is coming up
even if it's remorse or anger whatever it is if you're kind with it just holding it with patience and
kindness you're doing this practice perfectly right it's all about meta so
plenty of words to set the frame let's start let's formally start our practice
together so let's
as always land in our bodies
start with mindfulness of the body
mindfulness of the breath
aware aware of the body
aware
of the heaviness of this body letting the body be heavy
offering offering the weight of all the muscles
starting from the feet through your legs
sit bones abdomen chest
arms hands neck shoulders head
ah the entire body offering the entire body's weight
to the earth
inviting all the muscles to soften
ah the next exhale
letting go some more letting go into the chair into the cushion into mother earth
into your feet
so nice just to sit just to sit and
be breathed breath breathing you
breath knowing what to do just resting
taking refuge for a moment
from the stream the busyness of our lives just this breath
and breath apron
my
let the awareness be receptive receiving the breath
with ease
receiving the breath in the abdomen the lower abdomen
this
and your thoughts arise it's okay
it's all right noticing what thought has arisen
and as if it's an old trend hi smilingly greeted
say thank you but not now can you visit come another time please
i'll wait for you then but right now i'm giving my whole heart
wholeheartedly i'm giving myself to this practice just being quiet
settling connecting with kindness
to this body to this moment
letting letting yourself enjoy the breath
the simplicity of just sitting and breathing
so much richness in just this moment
richness and the simplicity
this
and while feeling embodied feeling your breath
in the abdomen feeling your feet on the floor
your hands on your lap
your sit bones and the chair on the cushion
and if you're sitting on the floor your entire
bottom of your legs contacting the earth feeling a body feeling the body
breathing
uh
now i'd like to invite you continuing to feel embodied
so the center of gravity is low low low [Music]
in the body in your abdomen not in your head and as i give invitations if and when
you notice you're thinking the center of gravity is moved up
ever so gently drop back in drop in into your chair your cushion
so i'd like to invite you to bring to your heart first so we
prime prime our heart bring someone who's easy you care for
someone with whom you have a good
easy relationship could be a child could be a pet could be
an adult
as you bring this being to your heart
feeling what it feels like to consider them
in your body
maybe you notice a sense of peace and ease or a smile shows up just notice
maybe a sense of friendliness good will that this person has for you and you
have for them care love
and with each breath so that it feels embodied not
[Music] thinking with your breath maybe not with each breath let there be
a recollection a sense of something you appreciate
about them when you stay for a few breaths with it
something you appreciate about this being is breathe with it
maybe maybe you've been friends this is a human being you've been friends for a long time maybe
letting their various things letting the various things arise
feeling with them with the breath maybe you appreciate that they're happy when they see you
this could be particularly true if you've chosen a pet
let each of these recollections brighten your heart brighten your heart glad in
your heart
as if you're soaking in them
taking them in with each breath take your time
with the different qualities or it may be things they have done for
you or they do for you maybe they call you
or have called you when you're not feeling well
really really let yourself breathe and then take it in
brightening your heart we all have this capacity
let your heart be gladdened made brighter with these recollections
recollecting dimensions aspects of their buddhahood their inner beauty their goodness
their buddha nature
now with our heart primed and recollecting of goodness
now i'd like to invite you
to choose someone you've had some entanglement not the toughest one on the list not number one
not the most challenging but someone that maybe you have
already worked some things through or in your heart at least you've offered some forgiveness it's not too big it's just a
little a little entangled just a little entitled
not over the top entangled choosing this being bringing them to
your heart and similarly noticing that they too
have a buddha nature not condoning the harm that was done but
they too are a human being can you bring
bring to heart some of their good qualities
some of the ways maybe they supported you in the past
or that their kind loving giving
to others or that their work supports others their gifts in this world
if you need to keep some separation not really bringing them close to your heart but just having some kind of separation
it's okay too for this practice they don't need to be right up close but as long as you feel into their goodness
again if even that them at a distance it feels too much then go back to your dear
being your easy being and when there's more stability you can
come back to this person i think there's been some challenge maybe keep them at a bit of a distance
maybe they're sitting in the other side of the room but you still see their goodness
you let yourself see their goodness
they're not all bad
maybe there are some things that come to them naturally which you appreciate
maybe even let yourself see some of their vulnerability
the feeling of good will comes up naturally you can offer it and if not
that's okay respect where you are
we all have challenges in this life every single one of us
has challenges and vulnerabilities
and if natural forgiveness arises as much as it arises partial you can
offer it and if not it's okay don't push it
we're collecting good wholesome qualities and acts of goodness
this
for the last minutes of this practice period
recollecting your own good quality for showing up and practicing
doing the best you could given the causes and conditions and letting go
letting go of any judgment
anything that it was challenging or difficult
you've done your best offering forgiveness to yourself
goodness to yourself and the wishing world for all beings everywhere
may all beings know the blessings of their own heart their own goodness
their own but in nature may all beings be free
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
[Music] so
[Music] it is said that
forgiveness is for the curve the courageous
and by building by recollecting goodness the
goodness of people who've had some entanglement with we build more courage in this way
so so
i'd love to invite you to share questions comments observations
what came up for you what did you notice you can type them in chat and if in chat
if you write them to me alone i will only read your comment not your
reflection i mean not your name only your reflection let me try that again if you write it to
me privately i only read your reflection not your name if you write it public to the chat is to everyone then they'll
acknowledge you your name and you can also raise your hand especially if you haven't spoken for a while would love to
hear from you what did you discover with this practice
i'll share something with you as i was doing the practice i i found myself smiling when i was
bringing up i was smiling of course at the beginning when i was bringing up the recollecting the good
qualities of of a person dear or just my heart was sliding up
and and i also found myself recollecting the good qualities of someone i've had some entanglement with
that also made me smile it made me light up and my mind wanted to just consider
and remember and recollect more and more of the good qualities of this person
that i had forgotten it just it and having meta for them seeing their
vulnerabilities and offering even more forgiveness it just became natural just
flowed like you know as the buddha says the water the stream water just flows
downhill naturally it just all these started to flow naturally of course your mileage might
vary i'm just sharing my own practice report a little bit as support as
inspiration but it's all good maybe it was challenging maybe it was very difficult for you it's
all good bring it on
one reflection from someone uh i was just thinking about how i still
feel angry towards my ex even though i think i have found forgiveness
if anger is still present does that mean i still have further forgiveness to give
this was very emotional for me yeah thank you for sharing this
if there is still anger yes i respect your inner wisdom knowing that
you know yourself that there is still further forgiveness to work through to offer and yeah
thank you for that reflection i appreciate this practice can be
emotional and can't be rushed or pushed
other reflections please
questions complaints discoveries
dawn says i smiled too thinking of others i also thought of the anger that
i caused in others needed to forgive myself yeah beautiful
yeah thank you for that reflection how this can go deep and seeing
and offering forgiveness to ourselves yeah beautiful yes please carol
hi nikki hi um i uh thanks for the nice
guided meditation i had a hard time focusing um the whole time because i'm
i'm in a really intense period at work and wrapping up a three-year construction project this week so
but i kind of focused on um i mean i i work in a very like male
dominated field and there's a lot of misogyny sexism is still kind of a
stronghold there so i kind of focused on that versus an individual and there's
lots of kind of micro moments that happen with people that i really like to work
with it's just kind of part of society and socially like where we are
still so it was kind of nice because i was like half distracted
um and just trying to really like like uh undo some of the like
wound up quality in my uh system um but then also kind of being
able to hold some of the challenges that i face that other women face in the industry and sort of see that as
part of the experience and part of what can be really frustrating about the experience and work in general
and so i really enjoyed it i kind of took your intention and
crafted it to exactly what i'm going through and it was really it was actually really nice and i felt like it
it felt like a nice uh thing for me to do as an intention to kind of close out a big uh thing that
i've worked on for several years so thank you so much thank you carol it's beautiful i so
appreciate hearing of course you know as you're i love your words wound up you're
going through a very intense period so there's a lot of energy and
you figured how to make this practice uh work for you tonight how do i make this
work like oh yes there's a lot of challenges and you know misogyny coming
and how can i work in just general me maybe and and maybe the sense i get uh
you didn't say this but i wonder you're welcome to admit yourself if not it's a sense of maybe seeing some of the good
and some of the people that you said i like to work with so i like these people and yet there's these uh
challenging yeah challenges yeah yeah i mean you can't there's so much of it that happens so
frequently you know when you're kind of working in an industry when you're where you're an outsider still
you can't really stay in anger all the time but you can sort of take it as sort of like oh these other people are also a
product of our own conditioning and society and so like they're good people
who are intending ill will it's just they're like there's unconsciousness and sort of like a
larger collective social thing that happens um and when you de-personalize it in
that way it makes it a lot easier especially for yourself like for your own experience right you can
de-personalize it in this way where you're like oh i'm just part of this bigger thing and you know i can work
to change that by being positive and bringing a different kind of consciousness to it but in that you
still have to acknowledge the frustration and the pain
of being subjected to that you know yes kind of balancing both exactly
so well put carol thank you so to of course to acknowledge the the hurt the
frustration the the harm that has caused all of that and
and it's a both end all of that acknowledged and as you said one can't
stay in anger to see they know their intention they have good intention it's it's
and yet it's out of ignorance it's really ignorance causing
harm not to condone the harm and hurt and yet seeing their humanity in that way supporting yourself
to not stay in anger beautiful so much wisdom here thank you carol
thank you beautiful so dear once i see more reflections in chat i like to acknowledge them and
it's it the time has come we tend to so let's transition to the uh small groups practice and
community because especially this has been such a can be such a rich topic and it's important for us to to make space
for holding each other and um and then when we come back i'd like to acknowledge the
the uh the more reflections given time so i am creating the rooms right now
and um let me uh yes so the yes the rooms are
created and i'm about to open them take care of yourselves take care of each other here we go
so um we have a couple of minutes and i wanted to make space if there's a comment
anybody wants to make after having been in groups if it's brief um
oh my connection is unstable let me fix that here
the group if not i will acknowledge the one
while i wait for your hand to raise okay so i'll acknowledge a couple of reflections before i went into
um into group and eileen had um shared that you know i may have the
intention to forgive but there are still freeings of anger and hurt and so that's why we are doing this practice because a
lot of times we have the intention to
all right i got logged out and i came right back on hi everyone
that was quick so so um
yes let's see where were we yes i don't know how much of that you heard but i was saying basically that sometimes you can have
the intention but uh there's still more work to do which is why it was inviting us in this
practice to till the soil to till the soil to gently gently think of the positive quality so that the heart
you'll kind of loosen it will loosen the and it will allow for natural forgiveness to come through
and appreciate jeremy's reflection about the intention to pay to allowing
yourself to be happy and for your happiness to shine through yes it's a gift to the world
and and jerry's reflection on yes it helps to think about people's causes and conditions and you know that they might
have had a challenging history and background and childhood which
might be part of their their upbringing and and their costs and conditions
uh to see their humanity in that way so that contributes to their present behavior says jerry very wisely and dear
ones it is seven o'clock we have come to the end of yet another happy hour and
it's such a privilege and pleasure to practice with all of you so i thank you all for your
practice for showing up for doing this practice for yourself and all beings everywhere may all beings be
happy may all beings be free
thank you