so good day and welcome to the arising of this
meditation session together and it'll now that it's in the process of
appearing it will persist for some minutes and
then it'll come to an end and this insight this appreciation
deep appreciation for the inconstancy of experience
is one of the specialties of insight meditation and to really begin to appreciate and
value and be attuned to how things are
how experiences how we experience things is a transient phenomenon
that the particularities of what we are aware of in the moment come and they go and
so some of the thoughts that you're already having now listening to what i'm saying but didn't
exist 10 minutes ago and then a few minutes ago then that they have appeared
and i'm sure someday they'll disappear as a current active thoughts that you have
and and there's something about observing or recognizing this transient
of experience that supports
a movement towards freedom freedom from being entangled in the transient
experiences freedom from the searching and looking and wanting to hold on to something
just letting go and and so there's many ways to experience
constancy you can be aware of how things arise that something new appears it was
unexpected unplanned and there's a sound there's a thought there's a feeling we could be aware that
things have passed things that were there now are gone and sometimes it can be a surprise where did
it go i've had physical pain in meditation
and then i don't know some point i was aware it was no longer there and i didn't see it pass away but i
certainly know now it's passed away and wow where did it go and
the and uh and it's not just uh you know the
experience that's you know things that we experience that arise in past but it's also the way in which we
experience them the fickle way in which attention and thoughts kind of focus on things
that we might be focused on the breathing and hang stay there pretty well but then there's
a loud sound and we say what's that and the sound has just arisen the thought what's that has just arisen
the thought i better find a quieter place to meditate has just arisen and then we're aware that that's passed
for a moment it's just a thought and because we don't lean into it and hold on to it we don't add another thought i should
find a better place to meditate i wonder what's a better place to meditate we take the time to recognize the first
thought it arose it was there a little bit and then it passed and
and if what i'm talking about you don't understand that you have the thought that doesn't understand that thought arose and then
maybe persists and then it passes and so it doesn't say that all things
are supposed to be quickly transient and constant the buddha talked about things arise
they persist and they pass away but there's something about being attuned to how they arise
when they arise that they arise and that they pass is really the art of this and
and and part of it what's also interesting is that maybe we're not there to notice when
something has arisen but maybe we notice that our awareness of it
has now arisen we weren't exactly aware of it but oh i'm aware of it now and that
awareness has arisen and then at some point we it hasn't
passed away it persists but we've been focusing on something else we've gotten involved in a fantasy
and then we're aware that oh the awareness of that has ceased for a while and so there's
all these ways in which we see we're not supposed to search for seeing
arising and passing a phenomena as much as settle back and observe it
appreciate it be attuned to it in the way that it helps us to keep letting go keep
relaxing keep not getting involved with things and searching and wanting and making
things happen just settle back and the arising and passing of phenomena in all the ways
that can be experienced happens without our involvement without our making it so
and so to settle back and just observe and watch and watch
so taking a uh i would say maybe say differently
beginning with a new beginning of bringing attention to your posture
and adjusting your posture and be aware that as you do so there's
something new that keeps arising new sensations in the body new feelings
and then settling into this body
and if your eyes are still open there's the occurrence of closing your
eyes a new beginning or an
ending of the eyes being open
and the breathing itself is one of the great teachers for
inconstancy all the sensations that come and go with breathing
are coming and going arising and passing
and in some ways the constancy continuity of the inconstancy of breathing
is also a wonderful reference point for seeing the
inconstancy of the mind's ability to stay focused and present
the arising of new thoughts through persistence of them the changing nature of thoughts
thoughts themselves are not one constant hum but new thoughts ideas
images are constantly streaming through and to be attuned to the inconstancy of the
details of thinking as a way of
not clinging so much holding on
as you exhale relaxing the belly
softening the belly and being aware of changing sensations that come and go as you do so
as you exhale relaxing the chest
as you exhale softening the shoulders
some things pass if the tension relaxes and do things arise in the shoulders
softening the muscles of the face your dear face
softening relaxing giving it a break
and then gently maybe lovingly to relax your thinking mind
maybe on the exhale softening the brain or the forehead
the holding the contraction the searching the wanting
exhale and soften relax the whole body
and then taking that thinking mind of yours
and letting it rest settle back as if it's settling back against a
comfortable tree on a comfortable day
ready to observe the river flowing by
the flow of arising and passing a phenomenon
sometimes we're aware of sensations coming and going sometimes aware of our attention coming
and going our thoughts coming and going
one way or the other something new is always arising
it's one way or the other something is always ceasing and passing away
and you can do all of this seeing all of this in the breathing
settling into your breathing maybe your breathing is the tree you're
leaning against resting in the breathing
floating on this river of change
in the body as you experience breathing changing sensations of breathing
so
foreign
there's a way that the arising appearing of new
something new in awareness supports not clinging to anything
there's a way in which the ceasing of things the passing of things
supports not clinging not holding on
if you stay close to how things are appearing and disappearing moment by
moment it can be a little bit like a massage for
the mind the mind's tendency to want and search for and
create think
just let go let go let go with the inconstant
the flow of inconstancy
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
one of the descriptions of mindfulness practice could be that it's being available
for the way in which life is ever renewing
ever-changing to be available for what arises that's
new by not lingering and holding on and
living with what has passed
it's a wonderful gift to give to others to be available for them as if they are
new as if they are renewed as if you don't know them
but they're appearing fresh without your
old news your old ideas about who they are and what
they've done and your expectations of how they should be
but to be available to see how people are ever new and
freed of their past
to be available
for the ever-renewing aspects of this life so that we can love and care and
be tenderized by what is happening moment by moment
so we can be sensitive to the depth of the present moment
sensitive to the depth of our contact with others
how they live in our lives
and this ability not to linger in the past or hold on to things
to be fresh is a wonderful basis upon which to care
for others and may it be that this practice of ours
helps us to care deeply because we feel deeply
into the newness of each moment
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
you