greetings and welcome to our meditation time
together and into our reflections on the dharma
and one of the primary purposes of the dharma and reflecting on the dharma
is so that what is beneficial in us what is
wholesome can grow and
so for this meditation i would like to suggest something um maybe a maybe a kind of a thought
exercise but it's very much at the heart of the kind of teachings the buddha taught i
think and that is put aside
any idea you have of being good or bad
any thoughts you have about doing things right or doing things wrong
any thoughts you might have about that there is
you're supposed to get something or reach some place in meditation
and and instead stay in your in the present moment the
best you can and simply
avoid doing those things that feel like they
hurt you diminish you darken you
obscure your vision and uh and um
and and continue doing those things or do those things that uh it just seemed to to uplift you
or to bring out the best in you or to just feels like there's an inner
goodness to them continue doing those
but particular avoid doing anything that is has an ouch to it
and but sit still so to sit still
let your body be as still and quiet
and if you find that there's any movement of the mind
that seems somehow
it doesn't feel good for you it doesn't feels detrimental so there could be
fantasies that you go into that might feel pleasant but to really be attuned to them you can
feel us not so healthy to keep thinking that way
it's not wrong you're not bad to do that but simply oh this is not
there's an ouch to this there's a kind of diminishment to it and so so the criteria for the
meditation is to move towards the wholesome and away from the unwholesome
and and just very very simply and
it means that if you don't do this exercise well
if there's an ouch and saying that to yourself don't bother with that judgment that idea
if you find that you're thinking a lot you're probably there's some way in
which that has a little ouch and a little bit of a you know not quite the best for you
so if this exercise doesn't make much sense it's okay then you don't have to do it but
the idea is to stay very pragmatic to move towards that which is beneficial
brings happiness and well-being and to not do the activities of mind
that clearly are bringing more suffering
so to take this posture meditation posture
and to gently close your eyes and maybe you want to sway a little bit
side to side rock back and forth and and then to find a
midpoint to balance where you feel grounded
in your sitting posture [Music] where you feel connected to the chair
the floor
and then let your body come to stillness
not a forced stillness but maybe if there is a stillness that feels
nurturing or relieving or even enjoyable
take a few moments to feel that maybe subtle well-being
of allowing yourself to be the body to be still
maybe a relief of not having to do a lot
relief of how the body can begin to unwind or relax
taking a few long slow deep breaths
and perhaps it feels good to then on the exhale to release and relax the body
perhaps as you relax parts of your body you can feel that the way you were tense
holding parts of your body well it wasn't a problem it doesn't have
the same wholesomeness or healthiness
of relaxing
and letting your breathing return to normal
and continue relaxing on the exhale
perhaps starting with relaxing softening the face
and if you're able to relax the muscles of your face maybe the idea of tightening them up
again doesn't feel
so wholesome or healthy or pleasant
but keeping it relaxed does
then to
soften relax your shoulders
maybe there's a really relaxing of the belly
sometimes a relaxed belly can feel a little uncomfortable
but maybe it's the kind of discomfort that leads in the right direction
there is a kind of goodness in some forms of discomfort
and then settling the attention on your breathing
gently maybe even lovingly steadying your attention on the
breathing
and then as you sit and meditate here be attentive to any
self-critical thoughts of do you think you're doing it right
whether you're doing it wrong being good or being bad
and those are not needed but rather notice the simple way
that some movements of the mind and some thoughts
can feel unhealthy or unwholesome
they don't lift you up
and other ways of being meditating on the breathing
are more
wholesome or healthy
as we meditate cultivate and nourish
that which is wholesome the kind of wholesomeness that supports
the mind to get quiet and settled
here in the present moment with your breathing
letting go of what is unwholesome
probably all unwholesome activities
go in the opposite direction to being settled and peaceful here
now
when the mind wanders off in thought
see if you can avoid any unwholesome judgments about that
maybe rather substitute it with wholesome ideas
of goodwill compassion wisdom
so that the way that you begin again with your breathing
that beginning again itself feels wholesome feels healthy
so
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to consider
that when you act and speak and think
from the sources inside of you that are wholesome and healthy
they're the very top very same time that you are doing so for yourself
it is also wholesome and healthy for others
when we're interacting with them when we're come into contact with people
that's a wonderful
i want to say coincidence a wonderful coming together
that this movement towards wholesomeness
the benefits go inward and outward probably at the same time or sooner or
later the both directions
to the degree to which you this half an hour meditation
has calmed you or settled you or connected to you to
some maybe a way of being that feels
healthier or more wholesome or more connected than you were before
how is it that that way of being can also benefit others
how is it that as you go about your day if you stay close to this way you are
now if you stay close to being guided by what is wholesome
that you'll have wholesome relationships with others
and having wholesome relationships to others is a way of
growing the wholesomeness that's within within us
may we come to a deep understanding
of how we grow in wholesomeness
we benefit others and as we engage in wholesome ways
with others we benefit personally
so that when we wish well for others
it does benefit us
so at this end of this sitting may whatever benefit that's come from
this practice be dedicated
be inspired offering to contribute to the welfare and
happiness of others may all beings
be healthy in body mind and heart
may all beings experience the wholesome
in body mind and heart
may all beings find peace in recognizing
the goodness that's within them may all beings be happy
may all beings be free
[Music]
so continuing on this topic of wholesome
and unwholesome
and it's such a central
orientation in the teachings of the buddha so much so that one of the
short pithy sayings from the early tradition
to kind of encapsulate the teachings of the buddha it goes like this
avoid doing what's harmful
cultivate what is wholesome purify the mind this
is the teachings of the buddha and it could be this they were for
harming it's translated many ways in english it could be wicked sometimes it's
translated as evil but it has to do with causing harm in the world
and it could be just said to be abandon what is unwholesome
don't do what's unwholesome cultivate the wholesome and purify the mind this is the
teachings of the buddha so this idea that that at the heart of
the buddhist practice is this distinction and dichotomy some people say duality
between two different directions to go and to make it pragmatic which it is
we could say what works and what doesn't work and if something works even if it
partially works in the right direction great let's do it and if it if it
doesn't work in the direction we want to go then don't do it and to be able to distinguish between
what works and what doesn't work what's helpful and what's not helpful is at the center of this you know
what mindfulness is about mindfulness is meant to place us in the center of our experience
so that we can make these pragmatic choices in this direction to illustrate a little
bit more um how important this is in the buddha's teachings
i'm going to paraphrase now so my examples are not going to be quite as i said in the text but
that um um it's the buddha
as someone said to come to come to the buddha and say
do you teach that we should avoid all pleasure
and the buddha would answer no i teach that we should avoid pleasure which is
unwholesome but we should cultivate pleasure which is wholesome
do you say that we should always speak the truth no i say that we should speak the truth
when it's wholesome and beneficial to do so not when it's unwholesome and harmful to
do so do you say that we should always be
x why believe in this or that is it always one way and the buddha keeps
coming back and says no if it's wholesome we do it if it's not wholesome we don't do it
so this essentializing and absolutizing behavior beliefs ideas seems to be
something the buddha was very reluctant to do in fact there's a whole discourse in the
middle length discourses where the whole discourse is based on idea what should
be cultivated and what should not be cultivated and and they go through all these different
categories of what should be cultivated through actions through speech through mind and different categories
and and the answer always is we cultivate what is wholesome we abandon what is unwholesome
and the um and in discussing the wholesome
the buddha says that these are qualities that lead to a sense of abundance they grow we thrive
there's a thriving with them there's a we want to take the wholesome and make them abundant and thriving and
increase them to grow very kind of dramatic language emphasizing the value and importance of
what is wholesome now i think in my early years of buddhist practice
especially when i was doing zen practice this kind of message was i think not
something that i understood or picked up from the teachings that i heard and was engaged
in in fact i kind of got the opposite not quite the opposite
but more like any attempt to try to cultivate intentionally or orient towards what
wholesome was somehow missing the boat that what we should do is just sit
in emptiness sit in as if we are buddha without trying to do
anything or make something happen and i kind of sat that way in zen and it
was very beneficial for me it's there's a whole zen thermology or
approach to life that where that's coherent and if you understand it it works really well
but i also felt that that's as time went along that it was also limiting if that was
all i did but rather sit meditate that way when it's
wholesome but not when it's unwholesome and so in this the in this making this
distinction between whole sun and wholesome we become our own teacher
uh and it isn't that we're supposed to go into the books to the manual and what should i do what
should i not do but where but we're using our own inner antenna our own
psychosomatic um apparatus for sensing and feeling and
knowing our own wisdom to recognize the impact
that our behavior has behavior and body speech and mind and if it is healthy
wholesome if it brings a sense of goodness if it brings joy and happiness well-being
um then yes do it develop that you're allowed to
develop that if it does the opposite abandon it avoid it
now another criticism that i would have had in my early years for this is it lends itself to selfishness it
lends itself to kind of pursuit of hedonic uh to uh you know just pleasure and
um and hedonism kind of i think that it doesn't when what we're
doing is practicing real mindfulness real careful attention really sensing and feeling what's
happening in here and what we'll feel what will recognize that if it's selfish uh if it's
hedonistic that that itself is unwholesome unhealthy and we can feel that we can feel the
impact it has that it actually debilitates it actually
deflates and undermines us it's uh not such a good thing to do
and so part of what this practice is about is starting to become a connoisseur of
the impact or of our behavior not whether it's good or bad in some
abstract way not that it's um right or wrong in some abstract way
but what we know from the inside out what we learned to recognize directly in almost like we feel the wholesomeness
neon wholesomeness we feel that the out should we feel the ah that's going in a good way
and the importance of doing that for oneself being one's own teacher this way is that there is no um the
divine authority in buddhism that's judging us there is no external source
for what is right and wrong it's all mediated here this
in our own psychophysical being can we really find
you know the wisdom the deep understanding for exactly how this works
and in this way early buddhism is a tremendous trust in the human being's capacity provided
they are have a heightened mindfulness heightened sensitivity maybe even a
heightened ability to be still and peaceful so we can really tune in to what happens
so when you do that you start feeling like when we're have hostility that
we're hurting ourselves when we're greedy we're hurting ourselves
when we're caught in delusion there's that very tightness and
contraction and being lost in delusion is a kind of feels also like something's
being lost here and the obscuring going on or
confusion and and to feel that oh look at that there it is and
sometimes the early warning sign that we're going in the wrong direction does not come from our
abstract ideas but rather from our body and in the felt sense the movement
of what's oh that's now it's um it looks like what's happened just now i feel
diminished contracted i feel drained a little bit i feel like there's a there's a tension building up
and um and so when we look more closely is this wholesome or unwholesome healthy and unhealthy in terms of the
unwholesome the buddha described the unwholesome as
something which harms the very thing that is producing the unwholesome so and the
analogy he used was that of a some kind of reed some kind of plant nature in india
in india that when the fruit ripens the it takes all the nutrients from the
plant the rest of the plant and the plant dies and so the unwholesome is like that
that it takes the energy from the person in some kind of a way of being and
something gets diminished something even at times can even die if the unwholesome
thing we do is really dramatic um like we really harm someone in terrible ways
and so so in this way there's a possibility to
not get caught up in old ideas that we've inherited from our society our religions and all that about that
we're good or that we're bad that we're right or we're wrong rather
we just kind of lovingly care caringly evaluate look consider is this wholesome
or is it unwholesome is it helpful or not helpful does it lead to growth of wholesomeness
or diminishment of our wholesome qualities and what we're looking for in the path
to liberation is a growth in our wholesome qualities and we'll talk more about those over
these next couple of weeks and the diminishment of the unwholesome ones
and because on the path of liberation the unwholesome qualities agitate the mind obscure the mind and
heart it makes it very hard to be on the path of liberation the cultivation of the wholesome
qualities looking for what's more and more wholesome leads to a deep sense of
well-being and subtleness and peace that allows us to move into freedom
into liberation freedom from all unwholesomeness
so um so tomorrow i'll talk a little bit more specifically about the unwholesome
because in a sense we're supposed to become a connoisseur of the unwholesome
so we can recognize it and not be caught by it and so
in the meantime please study yourself and see what you know what you recognize
how you recognize this distinction between healthy and
unhealthy wholesome and unwholesome and what it means for you right now and maybe over these next
days you will maybe come to a more refined understanding of what
these concepts are so thank you