so
warm greetings to all of you as i begin
this talk
there is a renowned verse
from the dhammapada
ancient anthology of buddhist poetry
verse and it goes something like this
hate
is not overcome by hate
but by love alone is hate overcome
this is an ancient truth
so hate is not overcome by hate
by love alone is it overcome
and it's possible that translating the
ancient world
word is love doesn't really capture the
full richness of this verse and i'll
talk about that a little later
but i want to evoke this very
you know well-known verse
that it's really a central idea
in buddhism that we cannot
pacify hate by adding more hate to the
fire
hate is considered to be a
that burns the one who's hating that
harms the one who's hating
so to respond to hate with hate
means that there's two people now
who are burning and suffering who are
wounding each other
wounding themselves both
and this is such an important topic in
the climate of
the world really i don't know if there's
more or less hatred in the world
than there's ever been before
but we're certainly becoming
acutely aware of it here in the united
states
and perhaps
perhaps we're coming into an era of this
country
where there is the possibility of
beginning to recognize
the tremendous harm that hate has
that maybe it was difficult to see
before when
the hate was expressed
with you know so
you know violently that people are
mostly spending their time
protecting themselves from lynching and
riots and all kinds of things
and hate was certainly present back then
but maybe it was not what was being
addressed directly
but now we come to a time where there's
a real heightened sensitivity to
what hatred looks like how hatred speaks
how it spreads as a kind of poison to
our society
and i speak about this because of in the
wake of the
the rising hate crime against asian
americans
here in california just a month ago
there was a arson and
vandalism of a buddhist asian buddhist
temple
in in los angeles
a japanese buddhist temple the pure land
tradition of buddhism
a very peaceful peace-loving of buddhism
and and the temple was partly destroyed
not dramatically but enough to be quite
disturbing
and
and you know these are this is a
tradition of buddhism where uh it's been
in this country for well over 100 years
it's possible that membership of their
temple has or at least of that form of
buddhism
their members have been here in the
united states for
six seven it's possible even eight
generations by now
and and to
be the recipients of hate as if they
don't
belong in this country is quite painful
for all of us
in this family that we hope to be and in
this country
and so in some of these images we've
seen of
elderly asian americans being attacked
on streets
right here in san francisco as one of
them
and it's not like over there that this
kind of violence happens but it's
close in and it's uh
it didn't start then but it certainly
raised people's
worry a year ago when there started to
be
hateful things said to people of asian
descent especially chinese descent here
and locally in the peninsula
because of the coronavirus
and somehow
spreading of animosity towards people of
any kind of
asian descent because of a virus
like this so there's ease in which uh
sometimes people hate this
part of the issue here in this country
and and certainly there's a need to
stand in solidarity with the people who
are the recipients of hate and
certainly to send solidarity with the
asian americans who are
struggling with this and with fear and
worry and
about what it means to be out in public
even or
not in public at night and we know
what's coming
and um and to offer our protection and
to create places of sanctuary where
it feels safe to come and not just
welcome to come but
feeling like it's home like they belong
and it's a little bit hard here at imc
to be maybe teaching here
all alone these
this last year but you know it's i want
this place to be a home
for all people and for everyone to come
here to feel like they belong and
even not just welcome not just belonging
but
feel like it's their place where they
can really
engage fully and bring themselves
completely here
so um
you know certainly i'm concerned for the
membership of imc that are asian
american the membership of imc
that are black and all the people who
are been
the recipients of hate crimes here in
the united states
the word hate crime is an interesting
term
because the definition of hate in this
regard
is different very certainly very
different than some of the other
meanings of hate and
that we use we use the word hate uh when
people say that
you know they hate spinach it's uh
it's a very different connotations very
different
meaning of the word that when we say we
hate
an ethnic group or we hate one of the
you know i think i think the the highest
number of hate crimes in the united
states is
against african-americans and
one of those other really high numbers
is
lgbtq
and
so the um the
um to be a res so when there's a hate
crime it's not just you know that
an intent you know a dislike of someone
but one distinction
some people make also between like anger
and hate
i hate hate as a hate crime is that
anger
is for a particular behavior a
particular event particular situation
whereas uh
racial hate or gender hate or
ethnic hate or something it's hate
towards a whole category of
the whole person not the behavior of the
person what they say or do
but the whole being of the person
and and their family and their community
and so it's not just a singular emotion
but it's an attitude a disposition a
way of seeing it's an interpretation
that's
overlaid on the totality of who a person
is
and that's why hate crimes and
expressions of this kind of
ethnic and category crimes is so total
why it's so
difficult for people and so painful is
because it's a diminishing
diminishment a contempt of who they are
as a
as a human being and to have that
repeatedly
to be recipient that you as a human
being
are somehow worthy of my
hate is quite difficult
and then to know that that's a lingering
disposition a lingering attitude
it stays means that you know it's not
just
a mistake of the moment or an incident
of the moment
passion in the moment but it's something
that
stays and will be here and continue and
continue
and to be the recipient of the victim of
hate crimes it's not just individuals
who suffers but also
the families in the community because
it's known that it's
it's in some ways related to all those
together so it's really a fabric
a tear in the fabric of society
it's a rupture in our ability to be
together
cooperatively harmoniously as
as fellow citizens fellow
companions in our humanity
it's also kind of a diminishment
of people's humanity and
and this is one of the great tasks i
think of our society and for ourselves
and our times
is to learn how to see the humanity of
other people
and how to share our humanity with other
people
there was i i saw an interview recently
of um
between um i think an imam the
religious leader of a mosque and the
neighbor
of the mosque a man who had been high on
drugs
uh heard about some
violence i think it was the paris
shooting
a massacre where all these people died
in paris
uh by some uh
isis kind of followers and he came home
high on cocaine and uh
and we're just you know angry at muslims
they're all
his idea was that they were he he said
he had been listening to a lot of social
media
and so he thought all muslims were
somehow violent and terrorists and
terrible people
and um so he shot up the building next
door the mosque
and no one was hurt but uh still he shot
it at it
so he was arrested and went to jail and
um for the for what he did and he
apologized for what he did and
you know he i think when he was no
longer high he understood what he had
done and the mistake
huge mistake he had made and when he
apologized the
people in the mosque the religious
leaders of the mosque
forgave him and apparently brought him
food and little gifts in the prison and
when he was released because he lived
next door
they invited him over to the mosque and
and uh and they were able to tell them a
little bit about
the what their form of islam was and
and he was shocked he found these people
to be fantastic wonderful people
and peace loving people and
and who had forgiven him and as then he
brought his friends over
and to see them and they were all kind
of discovering the humanity of each
other sharing each other's humanity
getting to know each other
which is not so easy not possible when
there's hate
not possible when there's that
categorical
idea that someone is somehow
contemptible
and so how do we respond to hate
as individuals in society
and from a buddhist point of view we
don't respond with more hate
and so to take a lot of care it's hard
to avoid doing it's hard not to be upset
with
them those people who are doing it of
course there should be
of course they shouldn't be of course we
should take a strong stand
against the acts of violence against
these acts of
this level of hate and uh
and hopefully stand up and help protect
our fellow humans who are
struggling with this kind of situation
it affects all of us
but we shouldn't hate and so
in this dhammapada verse it says hate is
not overcome by hate
and common translation is by love alone
is hate overcome but the actual
language of the original language of the
of the line
it literally says by non-hate
is hate overcome and so non-hate
is a larger category larger points to a
wider range
of responses than love
love maybe is too hard too difficult to
draw up love and expect we're always
supposed to be loving and
and maybe it's not even appropriate as
as the first response
or as the response and situations of
hate
and so the question is what is non-la
what does non-hate
mean and most literally it means
not to hate and so
the idea of loving i think is a great
one
and and and the motivation to love
it can arise out of deep meditation
practice
in meditation practice we let go we
quiet all the fevers of great hate and
delusion
we settle discover a deep level of peace
and well-being
within a settled peaceful contented
reassured heart
we discover that there there is a way of
living a way of being
that becomes more important like one of
the most precious things that
live there can be a feeling of kind to
kindness
love friendliness compassion that
radiates from within
and with this is this feels like home
this is the this has integrity this is
the
place of of um value
of how to live this life and then to
feel a commitment
that that this is how i want to be
and so what can what can exist rather
than being loving
there can be the wish to be loving
we can't always love but maybe we can
always have the aspiration to love
and sometimes that aspiration to love
means that the best we can do it today
is not to give into our hate our
hostility
maybe not giving in to hate maybe the
wish to love
commits us to pausing sacred pause
to hold in check
any movement we have to hate ours to
hate
we we hold and check our tongue we don't
speak
words of hostility we hold our our hands
in check to not express
any uh physical expressions of of
hostility
that uh this learning to to hold
ourselves back
because we want to love it's not a kind
of repression
but rather it's a kind of expression
of something that's deeper that wants to
come out
something deeper that's that's saying
wait
hold it there's something more important
here
don't lose yourself don't give in to
something which
adds to fragmentation alienation
don't give in to something that is going
to burn yourself
that's some of the dramatic images of
hate and
metaphors for hate and buddhism is that
of a poisonous snake which is biting
itself
or that of a fire that is burning itself
when it burns
so hate we the fire of hate burns the
person who's hating
the poison of hate poisons the person
who hates
and one of the one of the dynamics of
hate
is that for sometimes hate is a
person's response to their own pain
their own hurt and it's often said that
that hate that hurt
can evoke hate
a kind of blaming others and trying to
avoid the pain we feel ourselves by
attacking other people and blaming other
people
and and turning the attention outward
so hurt can evoke
or hate but then hate
in return evokes
hurt and there you see there comes a
vicious cycle
one leads to the other and round and
round and gets stronger and stronger
hate evokes alienation
and alienation is a condition that
promotes more hate
that when we end up hating we're
separating ourselves from the humanity
of other people
and then we're more alone unless we then
find
companionship in other people of hate
and we think we're connected then
the mutual cause of hate what we're
hating
but it's not really a very deep
connection it's a shallow connection
and to get somehow supported or feel
enlivened
by hate is a kind of self-alienation
and the more we're alienated from others
and alienating from ourselves
then the more um
the more that drives further hate
hate brings alienation and
alienation promotes even more hate
in buddhist language buddhist ideas
hate is a form of bondage
and to be uh to be free
to to freely um
you know do the wishes of our jail
keepers or jailers
is not real freedom so to feel have the
freedom to express the hate and feel to
be free and wonderful to express it
freely is really doing the work of our
jailers
they're just enslaving us or jailing us
more and more in bondage
that people who are hating are in fact
caught and diminishing themselves and
jailing themselves in these very strong
feelings
to find freedom is to find freedom from
hate to find the ability to allow
something that's deeper than hate
to come forth and move through us
and so for those of us who are
practitioners one of the great
possibilities for us
is not to diminish ourselves because we
might feel hate
or we might feel animosity or we might
feel
we have prejudice and bias
but rather to turn the light of
awareness on that
to really be honest about that learn to
see it and recognize it
in whatever form it takes our anger
hostility even to anything
to keep turning back 180 degrees
away from the object of our hostility
our prejudice our bias to
what it's like for us to have the bias
the prejudice the
hostility or even the intense hatred
that occasionally can exist
and really be honest about it and see it
and if we want to love ourselves
then we want to have the sacred pause
and don't give into it but look at it
deeper and deeper and deeper
what's going on here and
and then to see find by and and bring
with that
the awareness that's calming the
awareness that is peace
peacemaking the awareness is not
hating or in conflict non-contentious
awareness
so we can start relaxing and settling
the fires relaxing the hurt
the alienation relaxing the way in which
we recoil from pain
feel our own pain deeper and deeper
until we find where the healing is
where the where there is peace
where there's wholeness maybe where
there is love
and we discover that when we respond to
hate in the world with non-hate
that maybe it takes the form of
generosity
sending presence meals to someone in
prison who
hated us maybe takes a form of
forgiveness
the imam who was talking about forgiving
the man who shot their mosque
said it makes sense it made sense to
forgive him because
he had apologized and so
to discover the ability to forgive
to forgot discover the ability to
be friendly we don't have to be
to love someone to be friendly and in
these all these expressions maybe we do
discover how to bring more love into the
world
how we bring more of a peaceful settling
pacifying presence into this world to
benefit this world that's so challenging
here
so i think one of the great tasks
these days in the united states and
perhaps
many countries in the world one of the
great noble tasks the
important tasks is for us to
stand in solidarity with everyone
who is a recipient of hate and hate
crimes
the black people in the united states
the indigenous people the hispanics
the lgbtq the asian americans
and the list goes on and on and also but
to really
more than just stand in solidarity and
support
to be actively involved in making this
world a better place and a safer place
for all
and understand as deeply as we can the
roots of hate in ourselves
how this works and to learn to develop
the strength and the courage and the
confidence
to always wish
always want to be loving
it doesn't mean you have to be loving
it's a it's a difficult task
but we can always want to do it and in
wanting to do it
maybe we pause sacred pause to avoid
causing more harm and
we at least don't
express actively our hostility
to anyone and maybe then slowly we can
begin learning
how really to meet the challenges of
this world
with expressions ways of being and
loving and
caring and and standing up
and speaking up in ways that are
[Music]
going to heal the great divides of our
society
let's discover the common humanity of
all of us
so that we don't live fractured
but we live together as a community a
fellow a family a society
that cares for each other they all of us
care for
everyone we encounter thank you