hello everybody greetings
greetings from los atos
california so i'm going to do a sound check again before we begin
hello hello i'm seeing greetings uh in the chat
nice to be with you all again here
thank you everyone yeah so for those who um
wish to just settle in and arrive just take a few generous moments to do
that i will begin momentarily
hello everyone welcome welcome to our
sitting practicing together
i invite you to all arrive arrive here
the sense i'm having right now it's active we're all settling into a quiet
meditation hall
maybe a little bit of a gentleness and care is offered
as we settle in
arriving here gently softly
not joking ourselves around not forcing anything to happen
quietly settling in into a sitting posture
or whatever the posture you're taking for this next 45 minutes or so
arriving may be a process for most of us
take some moments to arrive
allow the body really sit down
maybe with some intentionality being deliberate
taking a sitting posture
now we make ourselves available
to however the body is sitting
making contact with the floor the chairs
when the arrival becomes full maybe we also feel
the support of the ground
and landing here and now
present experience
and our awareness is already here knowing
that we're here in this body this mind
receiving sound
sensations in the body
fleeting thoughts
may be ripples of emotions
we are available to this
not wishing something else to happen
being pulled by our preferences
available to this
from a stable ground we align
align our body heart and mind with our aspirations
values integrity
virtual inner virtual
we align with a wholesale skillful
and beneficial to ourselves and others
and sometimes the alignment is about as some kind of ease in the
body maybe in the heart
a heart is unburdened
whenever you're ready
open your awareness to receive the felt sense of earth element
the hardness of the bones
weight settling down
sort of a strange holding this body up
the bones are holding this body up
maybe a hint of stillness coming [Music]
along with the earth element
earth element is grounding
and relatively speaking unmoving
relatively speaking not totally unmoving
allows earthy body resting on earth
with the steadiness and stillness of the earth element
maybe you already are aware of the air element
movements of the breath
vibration bubbly sensations
in the body
there is a stillness in the earth element and there is a movement
in the air element
still moving body
water element may avail itself
feeling into the water element
moisture in the mouth
moisture around the eyes sockets and eyes
maybe you feel some sense of fluidity inside of the body
more than 70 percent of our body is water
the water element may settle along with the earth element
there may be a sense of sitting in the still pond of water
there may be waves in the pose on the surface
thoughts emotions
yet they can be held by stillness
quiet
my
letting go of any momentum trying to figure it out
matching some ideas we may have
in our head to let the body
speaks for itself
we are available to the without sense of the body
however it manifests itself
now if you wish maybe you can follow along
i'm becoming available to the fire element in the body
maybe there's some warmth in your palm
coolness and some part of the skin in the body
warmth of the out breath
maybe coolness everything
foreign
this body experiences different temperatures
you may even feel some heat in the belly or the chest
the coolness of the face the skin with the face
certain emotions may have an embodied fire element
in us
anger and frustration may be felt
as some kind of heat inside the torso
without trying to push them away
or wishing them to go away resting
in the knowing of the fire element embodied
experience just as is
being kind and truthful to this experience
from here we make our awareness wide open
receiving whatever
is available to us
stay true to whatever arises
and passes away
the stillness of the earth element may be prominent
where the movement of the air element
is obvious or the heat
where the coolness is clear
however it is receiving
receiving the blessing of this life
okay
[Music]
i feel quite fortunate to be able to spend this morning sitting with you and
practicing dharma and explore drama
so today we'll continue continue our discussion around sila
and we're going to speak about the fourth precept
which is uh to undertake training of abstaining
from a false speech
i wanted to expand this a little bit because clearly in our modern day societies
this speech has kind of broadened out a lot more right with many different
modalities um with internet social media
emails you know lots of different devices that we use and
it's not the same as you know 2500 years ago where
a verbal exchange is mostly the only way to explore
the aspect of a communication and to now
we have so many modalities that we're engaging in communicating exchanging
information and so this preset in
our day and life now i would
i would expand that to include all of this modalities
so we undertaking the training to abstain from
false communication or lying through all these different
ways or miss um are
uh propagate misinformation miscommunicate communication
and this is under uh this training perceptive for our day in life here as well
and so again i wanted to explore this from the dimensions of
awareness and abstinence and alignment
and that's a triple a framework we've been talking about
all right instead of speaking about lies or lying
and today i wanted to start with truth
staying true dedicating ourselves ourselves to truth
in our guided meditation um i
guided briefly and for us to tune in
to the truth of our experience as we cultivate mindful awareness
we can become sensitive unto our own heart and mind and body
and we can begin to notice what is true what is the foul sense of truth within
us and what what is the felt sense of not being truthful
and so for me and the felt sense of the truth has some sense of
alignment in my body heart and mind that there are
um my body heart and mind are in harmony
with each other and not like a you know one wants to go one direction the other one goes to
another direction and cultivating clear awareness is very
important for us to begin to know what's true and what is untrue
without cultivation of a clear awareness often the state of a delusion
might cover cover up what might be true
so for me um i'm kind of very aware of a certain conditioning i
have um i'm an asian american and sometimes i would notice that
when i'm in a group with other people with people with other kind
of cultures and that i'm not familiar with and
if i'm the only person who's not in that kind of uh a culture dominant culture in the group
um when people say things and that it feels like everybody else knows what they're
saying they're laughing they're nodding and but here i am i don't know i have no
clue what they're talking about because i don't grow up with this kind of culture or
that the group is expressing and so there are moments that i would
notice but would i not as if i know um
or not and so for me this is a learning i learned that
when i actually not pretending that i know
there's something off inside of me something not aligned inside of me
and so i learned in situations like this
to not give in to the tendency of simply following
along um pretending or maybe feeling embarrassed if you know i don't
know something that everybody on everybody else seems to know
and so there can be all this little kind of self thing going on
that pull us out of um staying
true to what we know and what we don't know
and so for me i learned and that it's okay to say i don't know
and in fact many times the people are very happy to tell me
what they know and i learned something new and so rather than caring
and the burden of misalignment in our heart and mind and
our bodies when we really tune in to our inner being
in situations and begin to discern this kind of
alignment in this we can become clear
and we can practice this precept with a lot of lightness in our bodies
and heart and i i don't know if i i you notice
that this if you observe little kids um
especially for some uh maybe when they're quite young
if they tell deliberate lies sometimes you see that something is kind of off in
them they're not quite themselves and in the same way
and that may be true for adults as well
and so this cultivation of awareness is to begin to get to know this a felt
sense of truth truthfulness and a felt sense of untrue
dishonest and we when we can stay connected
with that sense of the truth we can then trust more and more what flows out of that place
our words and our actions and there is a teaching
in the maja manikaya sutra mn61
and that again is another suta that the buddha taught his son rahula
and this is the one rahula was about seven year old a very young monk
apparently had um had um made a deliberate lie
and so the buddha decided to give him a teaching and
i'm not going to go through the entire teaching here but the buddha ended
a section of the teaching to rahula by saying this and he said
rahula when one is not ashamed to tell a deliberate lie
there is no evil i say that one would not do therefore rahula
you should train thus i will not utter a falsehood
even as a joke that's quite a strong statement to a
young kid right so for me i kind of
you know made me pause just to reflect oh what is buddha
pointing at here what does it mean to tell a deliberate
lie without feeling ashamed of
so if it just kind of take a few moments to pass just right there
what might this be pointing towards and for me there was a vivid image of
piling mud on top of thick mud it's kind of layers of the dilutions
pining up and the the first thick layer of mud is the
deliberate lies and then not having moral
conscience it's kind of like a piling another thick layer on top
now the truth is really far away a hard to get access to
and so i wanted to just say a few words about this having um
conscience and to know oh you know then you know i may have
an engaged in the action that wasn't wholesome
and this having a moral conscience in the classic teachings is said to be
the guardians of our heart and mind so we can reflect
about the consequence of unskillful actions and speech
communications and then we can begin to have a choice moving forward
from this point on without this moral conscience
without something that we feel in our heart that isn't aligned
it's pretty hopeless right imagine that
can you imagine in the world where
people will behave and and um behave in unh harmful ways but there's
no protection of some form of moral conscience
i have a hard time imagining living in a world like that
and so this um having the moral conscience uh to know
and let this moral conscience also have a dimension of care and wisdom in it
annoying whoa this wasn't skillful
and now i'm going to make a different choice now and so now we have an opportunity to
train our heart and mind in a different orientation
and so i also wanted to kind of go back to the importance of
staying true because lies break trust amongst human beings
lies break our own inner integrity
and so we human beings live our lives we depend on trusting some levels
trusting of each other of each other right
so when we can really have that deep trust for our own actions and speech and our
activities and we can trust others
there is so much safety in us so much well-being that can come from it
and so because of this it's important to undertake this training precept
to abstain from false speech and false communication
and then we align we align ourselves with the truth
and we cultivate wise skillful speech that are kind unifying beneficial
conducive for creating safety and trust
and so i'll end by coating again this mangala sutra
suitor for blessings and it has this few lines
speaking to this he says education and the craft
discipline and training and well-spoken speech
this is the highest blessing may we all continue our journey of a
practice may our practice benefit all beings
and thank you all for being here today and i'll see you tomorrow
have a wonderful rest rest of the day wherever you are