so welcome once again everyone to this edition of happy hour
um practicing cultivating our heart
so for today um i was thinking today being friday or
saturday morning whatever the time zone you might be in it's been a pretty intense week on the
international stage is a pretty intense week
all all around and [Music]
this being the the quota unquote end of the week
sometimes what's nice is to just sit and practice mostly silence coming
together you know when when you're tired you just want to come sometimes come together with your friends you just want
to sit you don't want a loud party you want to just sit with your friends and maybe not even talk much
but know that you're with people with good people and and just sitting with
your body with your heart with your mind just holding presence
with each other it's almost like holding a vigil sitting sitting holding
a vigil as if each of us was holding a candle with our meta
as if each of us was a candle was a candle
of light onto unto this world
and trusting that each of us each of us are are a light
even if we judge ourselves criticize ourselves it's tough it's difficult at times
and yet there is this inner goodness this inner light
and especially when we come together in
this container for cultivating meta for cultivating
compassion trusting that our light is shining our light is
shining even brighter
the light shining to dispel
greed hatred and confusion
both for ourselves and for everyone in the world as we cultivate
our heart and kindness and good will towards ourselves and towards others
so with this frame will be more of a quiet
practice session tonight but with really feeling into the sense of
interconnection as if we were sitting all of us in a room together
in some ways we are sitting on a room in a room together
zoom room youtube room but this sense of sitting with people sitting holding
space holding a candle so that's a lie that's an image i like to invoke for us
with this practice so so let's formally begin enough words
ah let's land let's land in our bodies together
both separately and together as a community
separated in space
and maybe time here
here coming here
connecting with the body breathing
with your heart with whatever is arising in this moment
and asking yourself asking your heart
this dear being who is you sweetheart
what do you need what do you need in this moment
my dear
and answer my top come up or maybe silence is what comes up it's all okay
by just asking the question simply asking the question kindly from
ourselves we're extending
[Music]
kindness first to ourselves
to the light that is us
simply letting awareness connect with the body and the breath settling settling
with care with gentleness
now bringing pure awareness again [Music] that you are sitting
with others
so if we're all together holding vigil each holding a
candle
the candle of our heart's flame
of menta together
holding a vigil holding these candles
of light of light together
holding the light together
as the light shines it shares the wishes of well-being
for ourselves for everyone it shines upon
and beyond all beings may all beings
be safe fully knowing that it may not be
possible and yet holding the candle
holding this light
holding this light of goodness for the sake of humanity
may all beings be happy
may all beings be healthy
may all beings have ease
if phrases of compassion feel more appropriate you can share those may all
beings including myself including all of us
be free from suffering have ease have peace
may all beings be free
remember to connect with your body and the breath especially as you hold the candle
together
and if thoughts stories arise
the mind goes off
it's okay simply notice that this is not helpful right now
ever so gently smilingly free it let it go
ah connecting with your body with the breath
connecting with your light shining upon yourself and others
wherever it's needed in this moment the most
your body heart and mind or suffering
it's okay
to really notice the light of your candle shining upon
yourself
also know that it can shine on many beings at the same time it is possible
it's not either or
letting your light shine letting your light shine
just as if you were holding a candle individual together
for humanity sharing meta just as
the candles flame doesn't belong to you
it's just a flame the candle might be yours
in some way but not the flame trusting trusting this flame trusting
this light
that is yours and not yours
you are the guardian of you're the guardian of this light this
goodness this flame for a limited time in this life
to support it's flourishing it's shining
it's getting stronger trust it is here already
let it shine brightly for the benefit of all beings may all
beings everywhere including ourselves
be well be free
for the benefit of all beings
i offer my light of menta
to the world
notice the difference between doubting
this light doubting that there is a light this flame
scandal of goodness shining meta notice the difference between doubting
just trying to believe trust trusting with
confidence as contrast that it is here ah
good will kindness meta
shining shared for the benefit of yourself and all beings landing in it
landing with it holding it with humility
holding it with others
what happens if you trust it if you trust this goodness
trust there is goodness that you're holding holding up
cultivating letting it shine
for the last minutes of this practice period
having confidence in the goodness
we're coming together practicing together
this vigil of meta and offering the goodness
the merit generated the goodness generated offering it generously
may it be [Music] the cause and condition
for freedom for awakening for goodness in the whole world
may all beings be well may all beings be free
thank you for your practice everyone
hmm so we have time for reflections for questions for comments
what did you notice what was this like for you and know that when you offer your
insights your challenges it's a gift to others it's a gift to others
so you can type them in chat if typed publicly to everyone i'll read your name
and the reflection if just typed to me in the chat i will only read the reflection not your name
you can also raise your zoom hand to share
especially if you haven't shared in a while i'd love to hear from you
and as i wait for your reflections to come in what
i'll share about my practice today is
this image this image of us holding candles of meta these candles of light
as if a vigil all of his coming together the sense of connection
was really sweet for me really sweet for me a sense of connection with all of you
practicing either here together on zoom and youtube or
separately later on on audiodharma
and those who will be listening later on youtube just the sense of coming together even if separated in time and
space coming together and this idea of holding this light
this candle again it's yours and not yours because sometimes if
it's ours like oh it's our meta we're pushing it out it becomes too effortful
so this idea of well it's yours and it's the the flame isn't yours nobody owns a
flame it's not to be owned a flame right so that idea conjuring up conjuring that
up is to really get us not to take ownership so much of
of this meta of this cultivation it is ours and not ours the duality is
important to keep so so what did you discover what what
worked for you ah a reflection comes in
thank you nikki i feel less alone thank you for that reflection
appreciate it yeah yeah
there's power in acknowledging our coming together we're coming together
one more reflection quite a bit of sadness but hold up tonight for me the meta candle image was very supportive
beautiful thank you for that reflection
another reflection on youtube it's nice to think that we can embrace all creation with our inner
light and that creation can in turn embrace us beautiful beautiful thank you henry
thank you for that reflection indeed indeed
as ramada said we're all just walking each other home all of us all of us
serving each other
any other reflections anything that was notable or different or challenging or
with these invitations
it was a pretty quiet set relatively there's a lot of silence so
it's also possible that we're feeling pretty quiet which i do actually i feel pretty quiet
it felt nice to sit together in silence so tell you what
let's hold our candles in small vigils
of small groups of roughly size three or maybe four
and hold light for each other and for ourselves and see what it feels like if
you go with this kind of intention into a zoom room and it could be silent you
could just be sitting together silently tonight in the zoom room if you wanted to in the
breakout rooms just see what it's like not to feel alone with three other people not feeling
compelled to say anything maybe you just actually start with just silence just holding your
light and then whoever feels compelled to say anything at any point they may
or they may not so so let us
hold the candles our light with each other
and practice together in this way to me so i'm creating the rooms
the rooms are created and i'm going to open them up
and here we go take care of yourselves take care of each other
welcome back everyone the rooms are closed so we have a few minutes
if any reflections have come up any thoughts especially as you practice together in
small groups can really bring up more insight
when we sit together how were the small vigils small breakout
rooms holding your candle love to hear some reports if you're willing to share please
allison please hi nikki um
it was really interesting to uh to see that it's
for me i was having a lot of trouble staying present and um kind of nodding off and it was it was
just very quiet for me and i didn't have a whole lot to share and it seemed like other people had that experience too so
it's um yeah it was interesting that you know just that um [Music]
it was the same for others yeah yeah great
thank you for sharing that it's um [Music] it was a pretty
quiet sit so so that can be you know when there's it's a quiet set then the
mind can also get kind of quiet um and which is nice and there's not a desire
to really talk much which great you know that's the observation really that is the insight that you're
sharing that's one insight and the other one is that well sometimes when also the
the mind gets very quiet and one is tired oh sleepiness arises oh yes it's
born of causes and conditions oh yeah okay so that's a very interesting insight to have thank you
for sharing that yeah barbara
please oops let's see here hold on one sec having
okay here we go okay um i also noticed that it was very
gentle and quiet uh as contrasted to wednesday when we had
our magic hose and was spraying everybody with and i've been busy spraying
with mata ever since i mean there's so much need so anyway i just wanted to say
uh wednesday was much more active and and and since i did that a lot as a kid
spraying people with hoses i could really get into uh my magicos
and spraying with meta i love it barbara i love it i love you
bringing the contrast so the two different ways and the you know one is very active and kind of joyful
and it's like okay a different way of practicing meta and this is very quiet it's it's a vigil
we're holding candles letting it shine absolutely thank you for bringing that counterpoint
in absolutely and and they're all wonderful different ways for different times for
yeah great beautiful thank you barbara i appreciate that contrast
i had forgotten about all all the the hoes and you know all that on wednesday
it's like you're still doing it i love it it's great yeah
that's it's lovely and and uh yeah and patricia sharing an appreciation sitting
together in silence with kim larry and sharon oh very sweet
any other thoughts and the other reflections you like to share
oh actually i say it's seven o'clock we have come to the end of our time together
so ah it's been so sweet nourishing really to sit with all of you
um today feels very special all of it the the
wednesday the hose all the different ways we practice method together and
today the silent this meta vigil for the world that come together so
so thank you all for your practice for rolling with it whatever offers invitations are given thank you so much
for your practice may all beings be well may all beings be free
thank you