okay now we go
i was teaching at um excuse me
i was teaching at our uh retreat center this last week uh insight retreat center teaching our
first in-person retreat in uh since the pandemic started
and that was wonderful and the mute button for the
speaker system there is the opposite uh direction for the button then the one here so i'd
used um
so i got confused with the up and down on the button for the mute
so wonderful to be here and
so the topic uh this week will be something that i believe is
important and i hope that you'll either understand it is important or come to understand its importance
it's multifaceted touches all kinds of parts of our life and that is developing the
ability to be comfortable with discomfort to develop the ability to be
non-reactive to be available to be present wisely present attentive to situations
where we're uncomfortable and so we'll see over the course of the week that
you know the different different areas where this plays out not just when it's uncomfortable and it's you
know something unfortunate tapping happening but sometimes we're uncomfortable with fortunate things happening
uncomfortable with love and comfortable with people helping us uncomfortable with um
peace even or calm all kinds of things so we'll explore this topic
so for now to meditate uh assume a meditation posture
and
and what i'll emphasize for this meditation posture is whatever discomfort you might have
recognize it but don't give it a lot of attention
stay connected to your breathing like you would be if you were on a rocky
rowboat in the waves and you were able to stand you had to stand and you stood in the
middle of the boat where it's most stable with your feet
planted wide and it wasn't dangerously rocking but you had to pay attention
and you had to give a lot of attention to navigating the rocking of the boat and
adjusting your weight and just really stay there and you might be aware of other things
you might even be having a conversation with a friend who's sitting in the boat and but part of your attention important
part of your attention is on the standing there and keeping your balance
so in that kind of way stay balanced stay connected to your
breathing for the sitting and i'll talk you through it a bit so
gently close your eyes
and as you inhale become aware of some part of your body
where there's some tension or holding and on the exhale
let go of it so let your attention roam on the inhale
to discover where the tension might be the holding
so first you might do this with a few long deep breaths
three quarters full inhale but as you inhale
feel where your body your body there's some holding and tension
and on the exhale can you soften it and relax it
you might come back to the same place repeatedly
you might allow your attention to wander around to find new places
and then letting your breathing return to normal and continue this process for a few more
minutes of on the inhale feeling tension or holding tightness in your body
on the exhale release it relax
and if it doesn't relax soften around it
and as you exhale and relax let there be an ever so slight pause at
the end of the exhale to see if in that pause you can relax
some more release some more
okay
releasing relaxing on the exhale with an extra
attention to relaxing when the exhale finishes
and now bring your attention just to the breathing
not to places of holding or tension in the body
but maybe now on the exhale at the end of the exhale
there can be a little relaxing or more releasing of the exhale
relaxing around the place where you feel breathing
and look almost like a little pause at the end of the exhale
so so that the beginning of the inhale is highlighted
and gently maybe imagine that the
inhales and exhales are like the gentle rocking of a boat
to keep your balance you stay there connected
embodied awareness the rocking and rolling and swaying
moving the body breathing
and for now trust that trust attention to breathing
more than you trust your thinking for these minutes
stay in with an embodied connection
to the rhythm of breathing
if things are uncomfortable as you do this
try not to give any attention to the discomfort let it recede in the background
and in the foreground of attention let there be the breathing
not ignoring discomfort but also not giving it primary attention
primary attention goes to breathing to protect you from being reactive
protect you from thinking about it
and maybe you breathe with it the discomfort breathe through it
[Music]
and then as i as we come to the end of the sitting
to imagine that on your exhale
you can send wishes of goodwill to the world
to send your wish for the well-being of those who are close to you
those are your neighbors and members of your community and out into the world
may all beings
be peaceful may all beings
be safe may all beings be happy
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music] uh
fifty
um
so good morning good day and so the topic for today is
this this week is discomfort and with the hope that you can be
uncomfortable in better ways it isn't necessarily
always good to alleviate discomfort discomfort is a
part of human life and sometimes discomfort is what keeps us
from being living our life fully keeps us from being connected to others or
keeps us from being honest or keeps us from being free
so if we react every time we're uncomfortable by pulling away from that
we might be shortchanging our life dramatically
also the things that make us uncomfortable that are there at times not always of
course but there are times where that's a window into some deeper understanding of
ourselves to understand what is it that's been triggered that we feel uncomfortable
is it necessary to be uncomfortable is it discomfort that
that we're reacting to is it the discomfort of the situation or is the discomfort of our reaction to
the situation but regardless of what
the discomfort is the um today i just want to emphasize
the willingness to be uncomfortable
not so that you suffer more but rather so that you are not being pushed around by the discomfort
so that you are not reacting running away
grabbing something to distract you reaching for some
alcohol or something because you're so uncomfortable but
but start learning how to be skillfully
uncomfortable so one of the things that really helps
is um is this thing to understand that it's valuable to be uncomfortable
that but when you're uncomfortable don't go make yourself uncomfortable
isn't that valuable but if you're uncomfortable learning to
realize it's valuable to train yourself to hang out with the discomfort hang out
and be kind of non-reactive to be present in a way that you're
you're balanced and so the analogy i gave before
is you can be uncomfortable in a row boat
and the rowboat that's in the waves and swaying back and forth
and but if you can and if you have to stand in the robot for whatever reason
you find a place in the mid-point lowest center of gravity in the boat and now you put your legs kind of wide
and firm and you stay in touch with the slightest
movements of the boat so you can adjust your weight and um
and uh shift and change as you don't just stand stuck still but you get fluid like that like fluid
kind of almost like you're swaying with the waves um when the boat lives up on the
on the right side maybe you lean in that direction and bend the right knee and then when it goes the other direction
you do the opposite then and so you're attuned and maybe it's uncomfortable
but uh if you react to the discomfort or get afraid in the discomfort or
you know then um you're not going to have the fluidity you're not going to have the balance with ill
so you have to be willing to feel where you're at and be with what you're at to find your bearings in it
and so how can we do that in daily life there's a few things one of the things that um
is breathing there's something a very
can for some people very effective about staying in touch with the rhythm of their breathing
to the degree to which your attention is grounded in the breathing that attention is not going to the
reactivity to the discomfort and and so and the breathing also tends to
be relaxing tends to be grounding or stabilizing and so to find yourself in an
uncomfortable situation and breathe and you know that's a common psychological
uh technique is if you're anxious in some situation to breathe deeply
if you're angry breathe deeply breathe all kinds of things you know you breathe
in order to kind of come back into balance breathe so you're not pulled into the
world of the reactivity the fears the anxieties the the angers the
uh you might feel in relationship to what's uncomfortable it doesn't mean that
we have to for now it's not doesn't mean that you have to live forever with the discomfort
but you want to have um you want to learn the skill
of not being pulled into the reactivity
and breathing is one of the places to learn that skill eventually as we learn to be balanced
and present for discomfort without the reaction then it's a time that we can learn
what's wise to do with it if the discomfort is is uh unnecessary
or unfortunate maybe there's things you can do to change it if the discomfort is a
is limiting you from doing something which is wonderful then perhaps the balance with the
discomfort that you find non-reactivity that allows you to go forward into this wonderful thing that
you're going to do so to use the breathing
to be with discomfort to use your mindfulness of your body the
body is such a fantastic place to rest to be established in
and to use mindfulness of the body to stay present in the body
in the uncomfortable situation if it's a social situation for example
have some of a fair amount of your attention rooted in your body find a comfort in your body
breathe with your body find a kind of safety
if you can with your body so that you're not automatically being pulled and reacting to what's being said
and what's being done the um
and then sometimes in terms of feeling in your body is to feel more precisely
where the discomfort is felt physically because sometimes
recognizing the actual place of discomfort gives it a kind of um
simplicity that's not there if we don't really recognize and feel
where the discomfort is it's kind of i'm thinking a little bit like the wizard of oz
that when they finally make it to the emerald city and they find that the wizard is this great big voice and the
wall or something and and then they pull the curtain and behind the curtain there's this little
guy who's the wizard and suddenly he's not this big domineering
imaginary presence so uh sometimes discomfort if we're
vaguely feeling uncomfortable or more in our reactivity of the discomfort it can loom and seem much bigger than it
needs to be but to drop into the body and find where particularly am i uncomfortable
am i comfortable my belly and my shoulders and my chest is it swirling in my mind
and sometimes by locating that and then breathing with that on the inhale feeling it on the exhale
maybe softening and relaxing um makes it kind of like
it protects us from the imagination it protects us from the general idea that oh this is bigger than
it actually is oh it's just tightness in my belly i can be with this
my shoulders are collect you know my chest is collapsing oh that's what it is
and so learn to breathe with discomfort learn
to recognize it in your body and then an interesting thing to do with discomfort in some
situations is to notice your posture
and notice if your posture is collapsed or your posture is pulling away or
reacting or how's your posture in relationship to the discomfort
and can you take a posture of strength a posture of confidence
a posture that feels both confident and calm
if you only take a posture it's calm you might settle back and become a couch potato and there's a kind of collapse
that might happen but to have a confident posture
and cost you a posture that itself expresses confidence and maybe may be
calm maybe if your finger you're tapping your fingers a lot or playing with your fingers maybe stop doing that
now you don't have to feel confident you don't have to feel calm but
assume a posture that expresses that
and then breathe with the discomfort then feel it in your body
then then kind of just be with the experience in a fuller way
so one of the purposes of advantages or possibilities in meditation is to let that this be a
as a laboratory for discomfort and that the situation is so simple when
you meditate uh hopefully that you don't have to solve any social
problems you don't have to um you know do a lot of things
it's just a simple you know you're feeling uncomfortable and then in the meditation
learn to breathe with it learn to connect to your breathing and find balance
in the meditation find a way to feel grounded in your body
and then locate where the discomfort is in the body in the meditation you can rely on a
posture which is confident and calm and then don't physically give in to the reactivity to discomfort
and so in meditation then you're beginning to discover yourself
about how you are with world of discomfort what are the tricks of the mind what are the reactions of the mind
what are the beliefs that come into play um and you're not giving into it but you're
studying it you get to know it and in this way you become a student of
discomfort not to be discomfort more uncomfortable
but rather to learn all the unnecessary reactions
responses fears beliefs that come into play that sometimes hijack your attention hijack
your wisdom and hijack your ability to be with the situation in a wise way
so sometimes in the out in the world it's hard to
you know to really assess all this and really know what needs to happen and some situations are uncomfortable and we
don't have not the time in place to check in with our discomfort it's really the time to get out of there
but and so we don't have a chance there to study it but find situations in your life where it's
appropriate it's okay to hang out and hang out with your discomfort
not to suffer more but to become wiser to understand more what's going on be
curious breathe with it feel it in the body feel location
assume a posture that allows you to
have a greater capacity to just stand there and feel the discomfort
so it's maybe an unfortunate instruction for this
day but i do instruct encourage you to look for opportunities in the next 24
hours when you are uncomfortable and become a student of your discomfort
in this way that i'm talking about and this will set a foundation for what we'll talk about this week as we go
along so this is not just so you can do it for today but so that you can
build on build on that as we go forward so becomes for today become a student of
discomfort thank you