so good morning everyone and good day
and
i think most every time i sit down to meditate i feel lucky
i feel fortunate to be able to enter into this very
rich world of um
maybe i can say of health that
meditation is often associated with calm and peace but part of the function of relaxing and
becoming calm is not for the purpose of calm but it has other purposes
and one of the purposes is to allow our psychophysical system our body and mind
our hearts to
reorganize and to come into a kind of
health healthiness a kind of wholeness
a kind of harmonious working when it's not being interfered with
by our attachments our fears our projections our fantasies
and to come to this very sim kind of a radical simplicity of mind
where we're learning to leave our system alone in a wise way
and what makes it wise is a number of things but one is we
really understand well how we interfere how we get entangled
caught up and and it's a phenomenal process
because even if a person is physically sick and maybe even dying
there's a way in which to get out to have learned how to get out of one's own way
there can be a radical feeling of healthiness wholeness or harmony
that gathers together that settles here that is independent in a certain way of
being sick or even dying i have known people who are been phenomenally
spiritually psychologically as they die but they did not were not healed from
the illness that that they were dying with
so this idea of sitting then to get out of the way but also to allow
this rich valuable thing that this system we have to make space for it to
allow for it to you know move through us to
settle to reorganize come to all the puzzle pieces of our life can come together click together
and make a whole puzzle that can't be if we're spinning and juggling all the puzzle pieces
and uh and
so to stop spinning stop juggling stop running stop
pulling away and just to be here and make room for this
self-organizing self-healing self hole-making
hey w-h-o-l making that
that meditation can become so to
assume a um
upright
meditation posture and upright is very subjective so each of you even if you're
laying down to to be there in a way that feels
psychologically upright like here i am
and sometimes before letting go of attachments and
before relaxing it's good to when we sit down and assume the posture
to do so definitively to do so in clearly inhabiting
the space in which we're in even if it's just the space that the body fills
as if we have a right to be here as if there is a dignity and worthiness
self-respect a definitive feeling of yes i am here
and it's okay to be here without any movement of diminishing
oneself devaluing oneself and to begin with this definitiveness
here and that can be done with this posture taking a upright posture
and to begin a process of relaxing and
harmonizing with yourself you might begin by
taking a lowering your gaze
if you're looking at the screen maybe no longer looking at the screen but
rather letting your eyes go down 45 degrees
so the gaze is soft relaxed maybe unfocused
with nothing in particular you're looking at
and then gently closing your eyes
and sometimes taking these three or four deeper breaths at the beginning
can also be a kind of definitiveness that yes here i am and it's appropriate i'm here
it's okay this is my place to inhabit this life
no diminishment of our value breathing in deeply
and as you exhale to let go into this kind of self-respect
definitiveness of being here
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale relax your body
not a giving up but is settling into being completely
here in this body bringing things into harmony or
allowing the puzzle pieces to come together
relaxing the belly
relaxing the chest
relaxing the shoulders
and as you're exhaling softening the face
the face that carries so much of our emotions
so much of our concerns and our responses to the world
giving it a chance to rest to relax
and then in the mind relaxing any tension or pressure
contraction in the thinking muscle
that's associated with thinking
allowing your thinking to become quieter softer gentler
maybe even slower
and then to settle into the body breathing
and when you begin to exhale a little
small attitude of allowing
the exhale to unfold
as you beg inhale begins allow it
to appear allow the inhale to
get bigger
and it's not so much that you're you are directing here
it isn't so much that you're directing your attention
to the breathing as it is that you're allowing
the breathing to arrive into awareness
you're allowing breathing to occur
and if it's possible maybe that feeling of allowing
can be from the whole the body body allows for the inhale and
the exhale
the whole body allows the inhale the sensations of inhaling they can move
throughout the torso freely
the whole body allows for the exhale
and staying connected to breathing letting the breathing stay connected to
you in this generous open allowing
for whatever wants to reorganize or heal
come together
the allowing is a kind of getting out of the way
so the self-organizing self-healing capacity within us
can slowly unfold and find its way
so
letting go of your thoughts so there's space for your body and heart and mind
to come into harmony
or at least to begin that process
letting go of your thoughts and allowing breathing
allowing the body to be allowing the heart to be
so
and coming to the end of this sitting
to once again feel yourself here in this body
definitively without apology without
diminishing yourself without puffing yourself up for
without conceit but really here definitively present
alive breathing so there can be clarity
that here is a person who can offer good will to others
here there's someone substantial caring
you can turn their attention outward into the world
and be present definitively
with kindness generosity
compassion love so that the good will the love the care
the generosity itself becomes more definitive
more embodied it's clear that it's here
and to consider how coming out of meditation
you might be able to meet the world with greater good will
greater friendliness and for the people that you'll encounter
in the next 24 hours
may you meet them with a generosity of heart
good will
spreading your good will out into the world
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free and may we contribute to that
possibility
so [Music]
continuing on the theme of breathing mindfulness of breathing for this week
it's a remarkable experience to be at the birth of some mammal animal or human
being and to witness the first breath
and the first time i saw that was the birth of a calf
and and i don't know what was going on with a
calf but it certainly didn't look alive when it came when it was born came out
but at some point it took a breath and the eyes opened and there was life
and uh sometimes uh life is marked by the first
breath and marked by the other end of the marked by the last breath the last
exhale and in between we have a lifetime of breathing but each breath is a kind of in-breath
is kind of the beginning each out-breath is kind of a something comes to an end
and in that rhythm there's a kind of renewal there's kind of rebirth that goes on
and one of the aspects of mindfulness of breathing is how this this kind of rebirth or this
restoring that goes on and the theme for today is restoring
and um as people settle into meditation and settle into just being with the breath
and are no longer scattered distracted preoccupied
no longer caught up in their whatever dramas going on in their life
not to disrespect the drama but no longer scattered by it or disconnected from it but the whole psychophysical
system begins to get organized healed the jigsaw puzzles come back together and get settled
there's a restoration of health uh spiritual health or kind of psychological health that
to call it psychological maybe implies a little bit too much just the mind but it's very embodied
a sense of embodied health and that could happen even when uh the parts of the body are sick
and now it's a different kind of health than what we usually think of as physical health
and um
let's see someone just walked in little bit distracted
and so um
[Music] so this physical health and this
psychological health or spiritual help and it can feel like um
this is this is what's healthy this is what's
normal this is uh and when we settle into meditation some people and i've had this experience
where this feels like the most healthy appropriate nice way of being
and uh whereas the um the uh
the ordinary daily life can feel that's what feels extraordinary
that's what feels like an altered state compared to what's the healthy state or
the feels the really normal state uh the healthy normal said oh this is really what life
can be about and uh it's kind of like if you've been
exhausted from working a lot then you take a nap or sleep and you wake up and you feel ah i'm restored
and so in the same way as we allow ourselves to settle into meditation and and
the ordinary concerns of life fall away and we're just here focused simply on
the breath but not focused on a way that's tight or constricted or or greedy for something but it's more
this sense of allowing respecting making room for our
experience almost like getting out of the way but not getting out of the way so that
we are no longer connected and attentive
really attentive to the breathing to our experience allowing it to wash over us allow the
breathing to kind of occur so the breathing can restore itself the breathing can find its way into some
kind of healthy and healing so that um
and with the breathing because the breathing is so interconnected to our emotions our body our thoughts our
psychology our intentions the whole uh phenomena of it it feels like
like it moves to health it moves to wholeness to harmony
to and and one of the wonderful feelings is to feel the sense now this is normal
this is what the ordinary is like and stress stressful mind that with people
ordinarily living under that's not the ordinary that's extraordinary that's
losing touch with the normal the healthy and so this um so there's a restoration
that goes on and that is not a restoration that is only about letting go of things
but it's also about allowing something to grow allows me to cultivate something to spread and develop and kind of be
here for us and the um
so the uh i call it the restoration and uh and it's a restoration where
uh independent of buddhist ideas of deep letting go
independent of ideas of not-self or independent ideas of emptiness or
kind of disappearing somehow in in awareness that all kinds of things that that can happen
um if those things are overemphasized then um
sometimes it feels like we're subtly or maybe not so subtly diminishing the
definitiveness the clarity the value of being a human being
and the restoration process of meditation uh is uh
is uh def is an important part of this process that we're allowing yourself to
become whole harmonious allowing things to settle to drop away
so that there can be this emerging of a kind of inner confidence and inner
strength and inner definitiveness that
feels like everything is in harmony and peaceful in such a way that if there is conceit
if there is a diminishing ourselves or a kind of a denying part of ourselves you can feel how that
the effect of that is is is stressful is off it's not quite right because it it's
a loss of the harmony it's fragmenting again and so we can't get too caught up in we
can't have conceit but we also can't have devaluing there's a kind of a
embodied restoration of wholeness that can happen and maybe this language i'm
using is too strong to implies maybe it has to have kind of
you know you know some strong way of being it's kind of uh gentle also
it's kind of uh sneaks up on us it's not something you can force or insist on or spend a lot of
time looking for but uh as we just stay with the breath and let go of our thoughts let go of the
ways we diminish ourselves or fragment ourselves and and just settle in and allow allow
allow the breath to breathe itself allow the breath to breathe through the body allow the body to breathe allow the
whole experience everything to come into awareness uh you might find that there's a shift
and a settling and a movement towards healing and wholeness and fullness that happens
and to start getting a sense of that can give a lot of confidence that we
a lot of confidence in the value of not prioritizing
our neurosis not prioritizing our suffering not prioritizing our
challenges and our difficulties and saying it that way not prioritizing
it that it's not meant to deny that these things exist or to push
them away or say that they're not worthy of attention they are worthy of the whole they are
worthy of being recognized but there's a strong tendency to over prioritize those to limit ourselves and
to narrow our life to our neurosis to our fears to our our
you know to our suffering our challenges and this process of
just settling into breathing being with a breath kind of begins to shift those priorities
so that something can restore something can re-emerge something can
can become whole so um
i hope that made sense so monday was relax tuesday was recognition
yesterday was respect today is restore and tomorrow uh will be release that is
often more closely related to you know identified as part of buddhist practice
and um but uh all with all the first four processes
set the stage for kind of a healthy release and um that's the topic for tomorrow
so thank you all very much and i look forward to meeting tomorrow