wow nice to see you here and um jamie and jane on youtube
thank you for your note glad you're with us
um so um i've been
contemplating uh the living a reflective life right a
dharmic life and uh
oh yeah yeah please so i've been contemplating what it means
to live a reflective life a dharmic life and
you know in simple terms right it's uh it's not
dharma to cause harm and it it is dharma to refrain from causing harm
and the discourse
advice to rahula and majima nikaya 61 is a a really great
set of instructions for living a reflective life
so i'm going to talk some about that and i'm also going to talk about how
much sila ethics non-harming are a part of that and
and how maybe some ways that we can
engage with reflection that on some layers that maybe we don't normally
do um and some of the personal like and uh biopsychos
bio psychological aspects of our minds and beings that can impact
and complicate our connection with our experience and our reflection process
so um
yeah so you know um
you know the dharma is a manifestation of non-harming it's the embodiment of non-harming right and this becomes
possible as we live a life that's reflective
and you know sila and our ethical actions and this
non-harming is incredibly important aspect of that but also
is deeply connected to how well we can settle how we can be mindful and
concentrate and and that leads to our capacity to connect with wisdom
so they're separate but deeply intertwined and connected
so in the discourse on advice to rahula
the way the buddha teaches it is often kind of considered just a foundational
kind of teaching for how to live a dharmic life right
and so rahula is the buddhist son and
the buddha is said to have left his home the night that his son was born
to go and and to seek happiness a different way of living
and he came back to his village when rahula was about seven
and um one of the ways i've heard the story is that um
his mom probably wasn't so happy with the buddha for his splitting
leaving her and his son told her son to go find the buddha and
to tell his father that he was there to
collect his inheritance his birthright and to ask for it
and so rahula comes to meet the buddha and
relays this message and what the buddha does is uh instructs
sarah putta to welcome rahula into the monastic tradition to become a monk
samana and training not probably what he expected nor his mom expected right but um
so he was about seven and this teaching is the first teaching
there were three teachings that are that i'm really aware of that are big teachings to rahula in the sutras and
this was the first of the three and i don't know how old exactly rahula was
i've heard seven i've heard nine um but young
and um so you know the setting is that rahul has
you know been meditating in his little spot and he sees that the buddha's so he prepares a seat for the buddha and gets
water for his feet so the buddha can wash his feet when he arrives and
comes and you know the buddha comes and sits down and uh
talks to rahula and
kind of the sounds like sort of the first thing he says to him is that those who are not embarrassed and
knowingly telling a lie have thrown away their life as a samara
so it's implied it's not said in the story that rahula lied but it's a
pretty clear implication and buddha takes the bowl of water for
washing his feet and says something like see how little water there is in here is like throwing this water out and
wasting it and then it's like whatever little water is here turning the bowl upside down and wasting
it and then um and then he goes on
and he says to the rahul he says what is the purpose of a mirror
and when his son answers he says for reflection
and then the buddha proceeds to give him teachings on how he is to use his
actions as a mirror for reflecting on the consequences of
what he does and the pali word for reflection has the
same dual meaning as it does in english right so it can refer to the reflection in the
mirror as well as when we're reflecting in our mind when we're contemplating when reflecting on
things giving it time yeah the consequences so both
are here right watching what what we do seeing that seeing the consequences of that and
contemplating in advance and afterwards
so in this lesson he is
you know speaking to rahula about reflecting on all actions body speech and mind
so our thoughts included and not just
on our actions but their consequences on ourselves
on others and both self and other
and to help him and guide him on what he should reflect
on to help him with this task the buddha instructs rahula to consider three
questions so
if he is anticipating whatever this action is will cause harm
he should not initiate it he should stop not proceed
so that's before right during an action
so we assume let's say he thinks it's not going to cause a problem but if he's reflecting and he notices harm
is occurring while in the middle of an action he should stop
sounds really simple doesn't it is it always this simple i don't think
so right it's not always sometimes it's so clear but you know
yeah and um and then afterwards
if rahula realizes that the activity has led to harm of any kind
that he should first tell this to his teacher or to a wise spiritual companion
and then practice restraint in the future
now if rahula understands his actions are wholesome
skillful not causing harm and leading to happy consequences
he can engage in them freely says the buddha yeah
so he also
kind of talks about um these these there's this three pairing in here harm and non-harming
wholesome and unwholesome which also could be thought of as skillful and unskillful and suffering and happiness dukkha and
sukkah so we have reflecting before during and after
and we have reflecting on the impact for self other and both
and then we have reflecting on these three potential ways to evaluate
what's been what we're contemplating doing or have done
so the buddha gives him this guidance and it he doesn't say okay
don't do these things he says reflect right so this is so much about the practice
the art of our practice is you know we it's
no it's impossible for us to have it be about just what we do and
don't do right it's a complicated life complicated relationships
so many possibilities of things that can and can happen it's so interesting how
much the buddha pointed not to these you know mandates but rather to staying aware staying present
and connected and and reflective about what's happening what's
happening and in this in these instructions [Music]
you know he is really really enforcing reinforcing the idea of impact
over intention so often we get caught right if we've done something
maybe i should just speak for myself if i've done something and my intention was not consciously to cause
harm but i have you know some some way
triggered something in somebody or caused some harm it's uh
can be a little bit automatic to want to respond by clarifying what my intention
was instead of just staying with what the impact was
just really honoring that because that's the consequence right and it may not be that i did anything
horrible but if the consequence of an interaction is to cause some distress
i want to attend to that first right not not try and protect my ego or
my my goodness right my my image or whatever it is
but it gets tricky it can be sticky in this space right
so i really appreciate this focus on noticing the impact having that feedback
be what we pay attention to that we honor that more than
what we were thinking we were doing or trying to do i also think it's incredibly inclusive
to really spell out that we don't want to harm ourselves we don't want to harm anybody else
and we don't want to harm both right so it's not like um
well i can i can harm myself but not harm you right or harm you but not myself it's like no
no no we don't want to harm anybody
the other thing that um really stands out to me that seems quite um
i don't know really important and social you know it's uh relational is that the
buddha tells us to go talk to somebody when we reflect and we've seen that what
we've done is causing harm he encourages us to to to share it
to not keep it quiet and hidden
to make amends potentially even right to make it to bring it into the world and not not just let it
sort of be quiet inside so
all of this says to me you know we're living a life of caring
to care we need to care about what our experience has been what things
have been going on and um and to do that
means we need to to look to listen to re-look
and i think that for me another area that
where this is uh invites a deepening is you know how do we really know when
we're causing harm or not causing harm
how often you know are we actually paying attention to the subtle suffering
that we're experiencing or asking others around us if we've
harmed them in some way how often are we just sort of assuming
that what we're doing is the norm and it's fine or whatever right there's it would be
impossible to do this constantly but um but it's also
well maybe it's not impossible right but it's a challenge
and um again this is where i come back to sort
of the incredibly important part of being connected with our direct experience and sila
to me uh i think this zela points to experiential
very much experiential and what's happening in our bodies and our
hearts and our minds and noticing contraction you know noticing
dukkha reactivity in our lives
and noticing also the opposite right when we feel ease at ease and we feel happy and
we feel like we've been skillful i was uh reflecting
i you know had this question huh did i avoid causing harm today
do you know did you can you think of anything this is just an invitation for reflection
but can you think about a moment in your day where you avoided causing harm
i was kind of thinking well you know some some days i will accidentally kill an insect
like i didn't that didn't happen today that i know of right and i don't often sit there and
think at the end of the day i might think about it if i killed an insect right
well that will come up for me but i don't often just say oh well did i
avoid causing harm today i think so
i think so um
and then was there a time today where you reflected before
you were choosing to act was there a time today where you
thought about what you were going to do and decided yeah i can do this this is this is wholesome this is skillful
you know this will bring happiness
did you stop an activity because you noticed that it wasn't
continue because you noticed it still was did you reflect afterwards
so one of the reasons i think that it can be a little
tricky or that we might be able to look a little bit more deeply
is that we actually have
there's you know the felt sense of our experience right we have a nervous
system and we have something called interiorception and exteriorception
and so we have all these processes happening that are kind of
hap you know taking in interior what are the sensations happening in my body
inside what am i receiving from the world what's the external sensations that are
coming in and and then we have a mind that is
based on per you know it predicts it's a prediction organ
and it predicts based on past experience
so you know that's means that when we're experiencing something
internally or externally and the brain is associating with what past experiences
it may or may not be getting it right right it may or may not be getting it
right so this idea again of how important it is
to continually reflect right because the brain will catch up things will
catch up as our experience continues to unfold we will be taking in more data
right we'll be getting more feedback if we're open to it and continuing to attend
but it requires this sort of a constant attunement and re-attunement
so there's that process happening there's the vedna response right the
sen the sort of feeling tone of our experience i've had people um
say to me that they they think that they're feeling anxiety and then later upon further reflection
they realize they're actually excited right so this is an example of when they think
it's anxiety they have a it's an unpleasant response
when they recognize its excitement then it feels more like a a pleasant
response either one of those interpretations
creates a different behavioral movement
right so if something feels good then we're tending to be more open and
to follow it if something doesn't feel good we tend to pull back and shut down from it
but sometimes the information the somatic information and the story or the
historical data don't all match up so
in one of the ways that um one of the ways one of the strengths
that the dharma speaks about is uh these we have this something called hirian of
tapa shame and remorse and they're said to be the guardians of the world right
and and what is the treasure of conscience there is the case where a disciple of
the noble one feels shame at the thought of engaging in bodily misconduct verbal
misconduct mental misconduct this is called the treasure of conscience
but i know for me that shame right
is complicated this is an example of sort of historical
you know the brain's history of experience with shame that how
you know i can see in my own mind that that um
there are times when i can feel that little nudge of shame like oh no this is
probably not a good action to take and i feel like there are times that i don't i just don't want to feel
like it feels there's something about not wanting to feel shame i don't want to feel the sense of shame so i think that
there's this way that we can especially when we've been really shamed and humiliated or
feel a lot of just we just generally tend that way
i think we can shut ourselves off from some of our inner wisdom right if we're we're aren't clearly
noticing our reactivity to something like the more pure form maybe of shame which
might be and i think about the western perspective of shame brene brown who's a
shame researcher she says shame is i'm bad
guilt is i've done something bad right and that's an identification i am right
and from a buddhist perspective we have the opportunity to really say okay i'm not my actions right
so if if i can if i can make that shift and not identify
i think we don't have to have shame become toxic we can actually use it to support ourselves
so there's some interesting research you know around shame um
that uh it's there's some people who hypothesize it is our primary social emotion
you know it's an interesting thought um it's shame informs us right of an
internal state of inadequacy and unworthiness dishonor regret or disconnection
is another person's view another way to say it is shame is a clear signal that our positive feelings
have been interrupted that's kind of a simple simple way with less reactivity in it
right sort of oh there's something here the positivity the flow has kind of halted here
and you know when i'm thinking about trying to live a life where i'm not causing
harm and i uh if i get too caught up in trying to
never cause harm it's uh i can make myself feel very you know
unworthy and bad but i really uh have to think and focus that it's not
really about being perfect that it's much more about staying connected that it's never too late to
reflect that we can reflect before during after and after and after and after
right that we don't it's never over we don't have to you know in a way if we
if we uh think it's done we cut ourselves off from the opportunity for kind of letting
something free itself i guess is the way i put it
and one of the things i found when i was looking into all this research on shame
i got kind of fascinated with it in japan
in the the teaching and the teaching style from what i read in the research is actually to utilize mistakes as
for learning in the classroom so they actually are students are directed to find their own way through difficult problems
and then the teachers lead discussions about the common errors and why they might seem plausible
and so in this way they're they're really bringing
sort of uh that opportunity to struggle and to make a mistake
into the environment as a place for sharing and learning
whereas in america the students are you know taught how to avoid making stakes
mistakes that's the real emphasis and the teaching in general from the research i was reading
and so students are rewarded and praised when they don't make mistakes right
and in general here if we make mistakes they equate to some sense of failure
and hence shame there's a great quote from [Music]
eleanor roosevelt it's learn from the mistakes of others you
can't live long enough to make them all yourself right i love that it's so great
so you know dharma practices uh
you know it's not an escape right it's an intimate meeting with the discomfort of reactivity which is stress and
suffering the first noble truth and it's incredibly important to turn
toward that when it happens so
one of the this is just a very small example
of my personal experience but i picked my daughter up from the airport last night
and i had dropped my son off at 4 am and i was picking her up at 10 pm
last night and i had sent her a text during the day just letting you know i'd been up since
four so i was just you know hoping i'd be there to pick her up and when she got in the car
she made this comment about um it was kind of this sarcastic karma
comment about you know oh i'm glad you know thanks for going
through all the trouble to come and pick me up right and there's just this like
little edge in her sassy voice and and i just you know i was like
i reacted i i definitely reacted and i
um instead of kind of looking at the impact i was
there defending my intent no i said i'd pick you up i'm just letting you know i'd been up and
um and so it was kind of this like you know my
charlie brown sounds um and and then this morning
right um i was reflecting on it had a little bit of sleep and i thought about and i thought you know i kind of i think
i hurt her feelings and that's i i think you know i think that i didn't i couldn't see that or say
that because i was reacting and so i just sent her a text this morning and saying you know i'm sorry if i hurt your
feelings yesterday you know and she didn't respond to that text but
she did to several others right so i knew that it was okay right
and uh so that's an example for me of you know
reflecting afterwards right and not just right after the right after but the next morning after and maybe even after i had
come up a few times for me in my mind it had come up
there's this there's this really beautiful inspiring idea and attachment
therapy and theory which is that you know there's rupture and repair
and we don't need to avoid rupture it's just we just need to pair it with
repair so here's a quote from bonnie badenock who wrote a book called the
heart of trauma healing the embodied brain in the context of relationships and
she says when we experience a break in connection followed by repeated attempts at repair
until the bond is restored we build implicit pathways of resilience
right so when we have a break in connection followed by
restoring that bond right we build an implicit pathway of resilience bouncing
back and we come to know in a visceral way and so this is coming back to that idea
of the body the somatic knowing that when things break down
interpersonally someone will return to help us come back into relationship
and this wired in optimism and expectation makes it much more likely that we will form lasting relationships
that have this quality as we accept and then rejoice in our humanness and we offer this vital gift
of rupture and repair to those around us and i think this teaching that the buddha offers is
isn't is you know sort of supporting our ability to repair
if we don't think it's too late and we think you know don't expect ourselves to
have to be perfect maybe the perfection is in recognition and reconnection
yeah so
this other part of connection around this teaching of going and telling your teacher right if you've
done something that you think caused harm gill says he wrote confessing to someone
else and exercising restraint in the future are characterized as growth
in the path right this is you know it's if you make a mistake you harm somebody
and you go and you talk to your spiritual friend it's not considered that you've regressed
it's actually considered growth right
yeah and um back to the well let's see here yeah
um so well speaking of gil so um i'll say
you know one one of the things that happened a couple things happened for me when i was early
and my relationship with gil one was that i was
helping pack boxes to book book boxes to ship off to the prisons
and i was in this room and there's this beautiful table this conference room table
and uh i had this big heavy tape gun very heavy tape gun and i pulled it off the package and you
know how they have those ridge ends so i break the tape and boom
take a big chunk out of the table right i was just mortified and he wasn't there at the time right
and i just remember being like oh my god oh my god oh my god what am i going to say i felt so you
know non-mindful and you know talk about shame and wow well i couldn't you know and i'm like i
gotta tell him right so i tell him and he was so kind right he was so kind
and there was another situation where i was managing in that bell i hit the bell
so loud everybody jumped at the end of the meditation right it was just like oh my god
and uh you know one of the things that he said i don't know both times one of the times was you know there are no
mistakes here there are no mistakes here like it's all okay it's all included
so this to me this is such an important balancing point to um our intention to
practice a harmless harmless life right is to really hold all of this and we
don't have to be perfect right we just need to stay connected we need to stay aware and open
um and mistakes you know like we learn a lot from them
most people i talk to have learned more from their mistakes if they're willing to open up and and
sort of process them and share them not keep them in secrecy
most people feel like they've learned a lot more from those things than just a simple success mostly probably because
we didn't have to try so hard when something's successful right
so here's another another quote on
mistakes failures are not just inevitable
excuse me failures are not just inevitable but are a necessary part of the process
a good mother is not one whose baby never cries but one who knows how to respond and
soothe her crying baby and we learned that to be part of the
solution we must be willing to be experienced as part of the problem
so
i think i'll just one more quote and i'll i'll wrap up and if anybody has any
comments anything they want to share i'd be delighted to hear anything at all from
you but this is a quote by sue johnson who
does a lot of attachment and couples work she says love is a constant process of tuning in
connecting missing and misreading cues
disconnecting repairing and finding deeper connection
it's a dance of meeting and partying and finding each other again
minute to minute and day to day
so any any responses to these reflections
should they connect with you in some way and feel relevant to the
teachings that buddha gave to rahula or how you engage
let's um bill get him the microphone
no i don't think you need to stop tanya during your um
talk i was got me to thinking about something i i like to think of my body as an early
warning system yeah so if i'm about to say or do something yeah harmful
you know the anger results in all kinds of
events in the body contractions you know yeah in heart or stomach or
quench jaw clench fingers quench hand yeah and then i what i got to
what i thought for understood for the first time is if if you're about to do
a physical harm those early warning systems in your body
are real obvious like you know like you know let's just say a raised fist boy
that's obvious that's easy to notice yeah comparatively yeah
speech
it's harder to notice the early warning systems the chain of events
is so fast you get ticked off and then
it's really i mean they're there and then i like to think that
um if you meditate a lot time kind of slows down and you have more time
it seems like to notice all that stuff and to maybe oh i won't go there
and then if you're having thoughts that are harmful those go by
too fast yeah yeah so um i mean my example with my
daughter is a great example of speech that you know not like i said anything horrible i didn't swear i didn't say
anything mean but the reactivity was there right and i think we just start to try and tune more and
more into just that that reactivity that feeling right there's still a feeling in the
body of clenching or tightening or you know for me it often feels like
a pulling back like there's something that feels like it's pulling back so
i agree it's harder and that the practice you know the more we slow down
and also there's you know mindful listening practices right where we can really
pay attention purposefully pay attention to our body as we're speaking
purposefully slow our speech down
and these things help you know i don't think i've done that
practice it sounds like it sounds great thank you yeah thank you bill i appreciate your sharing
i am found this very timely coming after a
a holiday that usually is spent with many family members
and um we had a little family drama
as many people do i guess around these holidays and so i was reflecting a lot about what you
were saying um in regard to those circumstances
itself and trying to re remain out of the fray and not get activated and
um wildly failing at that
and trying to recoup but what bill was saying about you know using your body as
an early warning system i don't know if it is
not sure what it is but it seems the more i've practiced that when
i get activated or when i do something where i feel like i've caused harm
is i actually feel the pain of it more and i don't know if it's because i'm
finally noticing it how badly it feels or because i've become more sensitized
to it i'm not sure what that is but um maybe both yeah yeah anyway it's a great subject
for timely yeah and let me just say um i think
another complicating factor is um if we're really tuned in to that
uh oh i'm you know feeling harm and there's some degree of that
slight shame response i'll call it a clean chain response a non-toxic response
this the the nervous system is still likely moving into actually shame
physiology which means that our capacity to think and reflect
uh diminish are diminished and we move more into a frozen state
so it makes it harder it makes it harder to like
to have access to full access right to our capacity to
connect and relax and all of that so i think it's just it's just it's a challenge
because we're dealing with a physiology that wants us to do the opposite of what we're going to try and do
i also just wanted to say the trains are unbelievably active tonight nice to hear
him again [Laughter] thank you all so much for being here and
may the time together be of benefit to you and all those you meet and everybody and the
whole world all beings so be well thank you