warm greetings to our meditation time together
and as a way of introducing this meditation
i want to use as an analogy something i witnessed
some days ago at a local park there were some people who were flying
remote control airplanes little airplanes in the field
but one of them was a helicopter a little drone helicopter with four
propellers and i was just kind of it was zipping through the air and
flipping around and doing all kinds of things and it was actually kind of hard to follow its
jagged path and it's kind of following it looking around and i felt a little bit discombobulated
trying to find it and looking for there it is now it's gone and it was zipping around and then at some
point it started to return back to
you know back where the person was who was controlling it and uh there was a clear spot on the
ground a little three four inch little disc
that it was going to land on and so it started coming in and it was easy to follow it and it kind of zipped back and forth a
little bit over around that disc kind of oh like then it was easy for me to watch and
stay with it and it's and then at some point it came
right above the disc slow slow down slow down came right above the disc and it hovered above the disc right
above it and it was kind of delight to kind of feel the delight and joyful to
just see it hovering there and it was so much more relaxing for my attention not to be searching for it in the sky
and i was just there just watching it hovers like my mind hovered and it was kind of like a little bit of a thrill to
see it just a few inches above the ground and then it just went straight down on
top of that disc and rested on the ground and something in my mind just
rested ah and the kind of thrill a little kind of excitement just having it hover vanished my mind
and i just my mind kind of settled it's almost like my my mind got grounded
oh
so i just see that the zoom folks didn't
uh weren't hearing me because i had them to mute on so so those of you
on youtube hopefully you'll be patient with me and i tell this little story
again and then we'll start going going going again
so everyone welcome to the meditation
and i'd like to begin by a little analogy of what happened a
few days ago in a park where there was a people flying
remote control little airplanes over the field and there was one drone helicopter with
four propellers there was zipping around in the sky and it was a curiosity thing for me to see
it but it was very hard to follow was see it for a moment it would zip away and
very jagged trajectory and path and so i was kind of busy my mom was kind of
active busy looking searching it was a lot of work at some point it
started the helicopter started coming back to where it was going to land and then i
could start seeing it again very easily without having to search for it
and then it clearly was a spot in the ground where it was going to land a little around disk
and and i um
um and then it was kind of like went back
and forth a little bit looking to be close to that spot above it and it's easy to watch it kind of glide and slide
back and forth it was kind of nice to see it little gentle movements and then it came
to a place just a few inches above the disc and it was completely still
hovering in the air and it was such a pleasure to watch it hovers like
it was a little bit of a thrill like just kind of defying gravity just being really still just right there and i felt a certain
kind of joy and delight and my mind got really still like oh what's happening here
just kind of being still with that hovering and then the
the um the helicopter just kind of landed on the ground and just was
atlantic got still subtle on the ground and i could feel my mind just get still
and the little bit of thrill or kind of the hovering feeling in my mind which was a little bit of energy rested
and my mind kind of something in my mind ah and it rested there
so this is an analogy for samadhi for the development of this wonderful thing
called samadhi sometimes called concentration some translators
translated as serenity and and it's you know if you're if your
mind is a helicopter then sometimes your mind is zipping
around and it's hard to even find it wherever the mind goes it's trajectory is not so clear it jumps around
and so you know for a mindfulness practitioner it can be a lot of work kind of like where'd it go now and
finding it and keeping up with it and remembering to look for it and be
present but then as as we start getting settled
more subtle than meditation the mind doesn't flit around so much
doesn't jump around so much and it begins to kind of still not quite in the present moment
here but maybe it's with the breathing some it's kind of in the territory and it's kind of a little bit moving back and forth
getting close in and out and sometimes there times i'm not but it doesn't go very far and
you kind of know where the mind is but it's just kind of looking for its landing spot
and then at some point it's really there in the present moment here in our experience in our body maybe
with our breathing and it just kind of a little bit hovering and it
just feels so good to kind of to have a certain kind of stillness but also to have a certain kind of
well maybe i don't know if weightless feeling or hovering feeling of just there but it's
kind of a bit of a thrill and it's so nice a little bit wonderful and delightful
and then it's it doesn't go anywhere except it settles further down onto the
landing spot and for the mind to land here in the present moment a
landing spot on the ground where it's still peaceful
unmoving and then our mind just comes to our deep rest it just rests there it's not searching
for anything it's not chasing for anything it's not bouncing around
and even the even the delight of finally just kind of being in a spot hovering is ah that settles as it comes
down and just up just here stillness quiet
peacefulness and settled here
and one of the descriptions of samadhi is a settledness of mind the mind is
settled and the deeper the subtleness is the stiller the mind comes
and a stillness that's not just a stillness of a particular spot within us
but as if everything is still because the awareness has become still
so assuming a meditation posture
that can be both your landing spot here in this body
and your helicopter your mind here
and if your mind is
dashing about after this thought and that thought just know that
you also have the remote control
to direct it back to its landing spot
gently lovingly still letting the mind know come back come back home
be here this is where rest is this is where safety
is don't need to flit around so much
and maybe one of the remote control signals for the mind to
settle down is taking a few long slow deep breaths
a deep breath about three quarters full without without any strain in the
in-breath and then an exhale that's maybe twice as
long as usual again without any strain
and exhale where there's more letting go at the end of the exhale
more release at the end of the exhale
and then letting your breathing settle down quiet down as if the breathing now can
begin landing here in your body
as you exhale softening and relaxing the body
and part of the relaxing of the muscles is to help the body come to a greater
stillness
as we soften the muscles of the face relax them
it's letting go of the activity of tension and holding
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders and if the shoulders are being held up
it's activity and action
that interferes with a deep settling into stillness
and the same thing with a belly softening relaxing the belly
and sometimes there you can feel the greater stillness sometimes not if it's difficult to be
relaxed
perhaps or some way to bring the entire body to stillness to relax let go
in the hands the arms the chest the legs
and then to begin bringing the mind the awareness
home to the landing spot of the body breathing
and you might not quite be there yet might be close by you might fly by and come back and
circle around close to the breath but not quite there that's okay
that's that might be needed to kind of locate the place to land
maybe you're with the breathing for a few breaths or half a breath off you go again
and rather than being discouraged be encouraged that this is part of the
process of coming to landing and you are getting closer
maybe less off in the distant sky flitting around coming here
to your breathing
and maybe for a while you hover over the breath
almost as if the in-breath is a dr upward draft that you catch and
kind of hovering in gliding on
and the exhale is kind of a
provide support to glide along slide along on the exhale
and for the mind to really land in the breathing
the mind needs to become stiller
mind needs to be quieter which might be held by relaxing the
thinking mind relaxing any muscular tension
associated with thinking worrying and wanting
tension that might be in the forehead or behind it around the eyes or jaws
in a slight leaning forward or pulling being pulled or like pulling back
a more subtle relaxation of the body that corresponds to the settling of the
mind it allows the mind to settle and get
quieter
and feeling more in the breathing the body breathing
and what would it be like for you to be right there with a breathing
hovering over it gently quietly
putting in just enough energy for your mind your attention
to hover over the in-breaths and out-breaths
so the mind is not wandering off and into thought so much but right there
breathing in and breathing out
and not so much like there's a laser focus like you're in the control tower looking
at the breathing but more like the whole body is
gently vibrating hovering over the breathing or with the breathing
right there breathing in and breathing out
they're kind of hovering where there's a stillness and a tranquility not a lot of movement
and then to let the mind
land in the breathing to land in the present moment
so that the engine can go off and
has deep stillness groundedness
safety having landed secure and stable here on the ground of
the body breathing
around the earth
wide and expansive and quiet earth
where the mind can feel secured enough to be still quiet
resting on the body breathing
whenever the mind is wandered off lot come back to first hovering with the
breath with breathing and then with a relaxation letting go
land on the breath land inside of it
come to a stillness of mind in the middle of the moving experience
of breathing
do
finding a place that of stillness within
and allowing the mind to become still
quiet even unmoving
together with the inner stillness
so
and then coming to the end of this sitting
and thinking about how samadhi operates in our interpersonal
relationships it is not a concentrated focus
on others but rather it's a deep
settledness in ourselves
to be deeply settled without any fear
agendas without any leaning forward or pulling
back without being pushed by desires or
pulled by aversion just a deep subtleness
and to be with others in this settled way
so settled that of course you'll be aware of the other person
you don't need to intently focus of course you're open and available and
aware of the other and from this subtle place may be of
peaceful place
here there can be a kind of deep love and
positive regard and offering of good will of safety
a deep respect of others because you're not interfering with them
or needing them to be different you're simply settled with them
settled on yourself
and this settled samadhi factor
can give a wonderful perspective
for how to be with people with care with love with friendliness with good
will that is not so much work or an obligation
or a transaction
it just is
and may it be that our ability to be still in meditation
may it also be for the for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be settled in them on themselves
may all beings be nourished by an inner stillness and safety
may all beings know inner peace
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so the topic of today is the samadhi factor of awakening
and tomorrow's topic monday will be
equanimity and we are one day behind because of the technological glitch that happened on
tuesday and we will
um and then for the youtube we'll be back meeting
again at 7 00 am california time tomorrow
so samadhi is commonly translated as concentration in english the
the prolific translator tenisero tunisirobiku american who lives in san
diego he translates it as serenity
and so it's a very different feeling between concentration and serenity
when it's translated as serenity it then raises the question how is that
different than tranquility the factor of awakening that's listed just before
samadhi and i see that
that samadhi is characterized by stillness
serenity for me is characterized so i don't know if the english english word serenity and tranquility
are maybe almost complete synonyms of each other but if you look at the pali words the
ancient language words that pasadi the word for
tranquility i think has more of a connotations of brightness
of um of a kind of a bright quality a soft quality a very light
feeling the body can feel very light and soft when there's tranquility whereas in samadhi the
the the when the primary characteristic could be more a stillness than samadhi
there's a very sense of deep stillness things have gotten very still the greater the samadhi the more
stillness there is and um and also with with somebody it's a very
clear the stillness of it this sometimes can feel very strong there's a strength can be a strength to it at
times and the mind has is not distractible mind won't wander away at all just
it's like the mind is kind of sometimes there's a feeling people describe as being locked in
in somebody it's so strong and the stillness was boom we're locked in and then the mind's not
going to move anywhere into anything whereas in tranquility the mind very tranquil and peaceful but it's not
really 100 still maybe i associate
tranquility as i did mentioned yesterday about with a quiet very peaceful morning lake
completely placid and still not a ripple of wind on it and um and the morning you know morning
light is just very clear and bright and still very stillness in the air the birds haven't come out yet
and um and so this but this body of water it's very flat
and um and so so tranquility
is you know it's kind of like a body of water and i associate it with much more with a body than the mind
somehow and then um in samadhi
um at least for me it is it's uh it can be very embodied feeling
that comes with it but um it's much more like the stillness of the mind there
it's not like a body of water but it's more like the stillness of space
and um then where there's you know everything is still in in space
space in and of itself is stillness uh kind of and uh and there's but
there's space like if you look up at the scott knight at the sky you know space has no boundaries it goes
on forever it's you can you don't you can say that space is soft i guess
but you know it's not a quality that has softness or lightness as part of it
it's more porous or just it's the openness or something so the my
and i associate samadhi a little bit more with the mind becoming still and porous open has no boundaries to it
and but you know definitely it's landed it's here
and then it landed here and then sometimes the place sense of a landing place disappears
it's just here but with this openness kind of an openness and it's not exactly
embodied body sometimes disappears in deep samadhi
so the primary function of samadhi one of the primary functions of
tranquility here is to support samadhi and so when the body
is tranquil it really supports the mind to become stiller it's kind of like if
you try to land that you know drone on top of a moving train
that's going along fast it's you know it's a little hard but if the train stops then you can land it on the roof of the
train perhaps it's so the same thing if you try to land in a body that's all agitated
it's hard for the mind to land and be here so that tranquility supports it creates
a nice home and nourishment and support for this uh to be settled to be
settled on our experience more than being focused on our experience
the idea of of focus in samadhi uh sometimes this idea of one pointedness
maybe that's a good metaphor a good good for some people that really works today
okay i'm really going to be focused one pointed on something but i think of it this this so-called
one-pointedness as a gathering together so all of ourselves are all of us is centered on something
it's being centered on the breathing and so rather than being one pointed
with the mind it's coming to rest at the center point of the concentric circles of our life
and we're just really right here so with the breath completely with a breath for example if the
focus is the breath but there's more feeling of being centered on it than it is being
focused on it at least that's how it is for me the buddha said that the nourishment
for samadhi is serenity and the word there now is
samatha so it's not the same word as samadhi but samata in particular has that i
in my rudimentary understanding of poly etymology is that it's um
even closer to the city of stillness of landings stan taking a stand where we're
really still and quiet so it so it's a kind of serenity of stillness not the serenity of us
of um of softness and lightness
and um so the nourishment of samadhi is
is stillness and that means that uh to be nourish yourself with stillness
so to notice the places where the you are still where there is stillness
and um and perhaps that's within um there's a woman nearby
local woman who wrote a composed this uh she's a mindfulness teacher um and she
did a little cd for children called the still quiet place within i love that
little title the still quiet place within and so to uh to recognize and find a place of
stillness but not that we're being held still or kind of a trapped being still but
something that actually feels nourishing it feels wholesome and if you're able to touch into that
inner place of nourishing stillness allow yourself to be nourished by it
and this is one of the wonderful characteristics of these teachings of the buddha around meditation
it's not just kind of this dreary dry you know focus on the breath and
stay with the breath and count the breath just you know zero in on the breath and and like a little technique of
you know of i don't know of mental focus
it's uh it's a it's a it's a settling into allowing and
touching into all kinds of ways in which we feel nourished wholesome feel the
wholesomeness of something feels a nourishment of something feel the goodness of something allow
ourselves to we're allowed to feel joy we're allowed to feel happiness
and one of the characteristics of the the buddhist community in the time of
the buddha that apparently was a little bit unusual for the religious circles of his time
was that the buddhist disciples were smiling a lot always kind of kind of a
joyful group so it's not like it meant to be a grim practice this meditation
don't take meditation too seriously meditation is much too important to take
seriously because if you take it too seriously i think you kind of like squeeze some of
the life out of it and makes it harder to feel the nourishment and the and the wholesomeness and the joy the
pleasure of it all not to indulge in those things and not
to hold on to them and expect them and huff and puff for it
but in the very even in the smallest ways in the course of a day or in the course
of meditation you're allowed to tap in and discover the places that feel wholesome
places field where there's inner goodness nourishment each of the seven factors has a
nourishment for it and so um
so what how would it what how does samadhi come about if that's the orientation not this one
pointed focus but rather imbibing
the nourishment that's here even if it's just like if one percent of yourself
feels has this good nourishing quality um then um
maybe that's worth a lot more than the five percent of your of who you are that's neurotic but if
you give a hundred percent of your attention to your five percent that's neurotic
then you're not going to be nourished but if you give a hundred percent of your attention to
the one percent that's wholesome then you can be nourished by that and
then things begin to relax and open and something like that i don't know
what percentage you are of all these things but uh chances are that if you're a regular
human being that you probably give more attention to what's not
nourishing than to what is nourishing and so sit down meditate in the
nourishing stillness the nourishing awareness the nourishing
tranquility the nourishing joy the nourishing mindfulness
so samadhi the samadhi factor of awakening and when that it becomes well developed
meaning they're well nourished by it supported by it to feel the goodness of it that creates the wonderful conditions
for the mind to have equanimity to develop equanimity so it's not enforced equanimity where
you hold yourself still but it's an equanimi that comes because there's a feeling of being really
settled and at ease and in this nourishing place of stillness
so the so the samadhi factor of awakening so until we do equanimity tomorrow
those of you coming back for that you might
spend some extra time today seeing if you can become more familiar
with whatever capacity whatever ability you have to discover
a nourishing inner stillness quiet
unwaveringness unagitatedness within and see what it's like to
let yourself enjoy it and be nourished
may samadhi be a delight for you thank you