warm greetings from insight meditation center here in redwood city
and uh greetings to all of you from all the different corners of the world
where you're listening and watching in
so one of the things to become wise about in
meditation is the nature of our thinking
and people struggle with thinking and in meditation sometimes
the struggle is unnecessary however at the same time it's important to
overcome the tendency to get lost in thought and or be preoccupied in their thinking
and so one way to uh to overcome that without struggling with it
excuse me is to become wiser about our thinking
and take some time to understand something of it and for this meditation
if you do find yourself thinking during the meditation i suggest you notice
whether you're thinking about something other than what has to do with here and now
if you're thinking about something different than the meditation itself what's happening for you as you meditate
if you're thinking about work or home life or conversations with
friends or relatives or companions or strangers if you're planning vacations or if
you're remembering something in the past whatever if the mind is involved in something
that's other than here and now recognize that clearly and the way to recognize it clearly
is to rather than noting it or being aware of it as thinking
maybe just say the word other that's short for thinking about other
things and then to really take stock and understand how much the
mind is thinking about other things that that are not about here
it becomes a little bit of an alienation or a little bit of a abandonment of oneself
here and now it's choosing to go into a realm
of thought that limits your ability to
really delve into deeply your lived experience in the moment to
settle in it to wake up in it to really be
intimate with this time right here so say the word other
and then
if you say the word other i just didn't recognize when that's the case and then
come back to here come back to here
and do so gently if you find yourself thinking about the meditation
maybe continue to do that maybe even use the word here for that
but see if you can adjust how you think so it's only friendly and kind and
supportive calm settled at ease
just kind of like as a gentle friend gentle supporters accompanying the experience
recognizing the experience being with the experience where that thinking about here
becomes less important there's not a strong pull into it but it's you're not letting go of it
entirely just calmly maybe almost like a whisper in the mind
kind of adjusting it to support you to be here be here
so as so
entering into a meditation posture
maybe from the inside out feel yourself adjusting yourself into
the posture if you're sitting upright is there some way that from the inside
out you can sit up a little straighter or sit with a little bit more open chest
relaxed way with the shoulders a little bit
rolling backwards
and then
relaxing your gaze and if it's comfortable to close your
eyes
and then gently relaxedly
as a way of beginning to attune your attention
to your lived experience take some long slow deep breaths
maybe three quarters full just full enough that you don't get winded or stressed
stressed by it
and this continuing as a way of attuning your attention to your lived experience in your body
breathe out a little bit more fully than usual but make sure that your attention is
accompanying it you follow along with the exhale
deep inhale and follow along with your attention
long exhale and have your attention accompany the exhale
as you exhale with the release and letting go
let's see if you can relax any tension in your attention
any pushing or striving or tightness
and attention that accompanies your breathing
and if you're a little bit too complacent or hesitant or
resistant to meditation attention
as you inhale awaken
in attunement to breathing a being
connected
perhaps even a little bit of diligence
in your accompaniment of breathing
and then continue to accompany your breathing let your breathing return to normal
and on the periphery of your awareness with the center being with your
breathing as you exhale relax your body
forever can soften or release
and then settling into your breathing
and as you're settling and focusing on breathing on your present moment experience
if you find yourself thinking a lot preoccupied in thought
recognize whether you're thinking about the meditation
here and now your present moment experience or anything other
and if it is other name it as other recognize it as oh this is involved in
other things not here
and then come back to the intimacy and the
realness of here and now
and if you're thinking about meditation
see if you can calm your thinking down
think calmly about it
and if thinking is in the background and you're not preoccupied with it
it doesn't interfere with your being with your breathing then no need to concern yourself with
your think thinking just continue with the meditation
recognizing other when you're thinking about other things
and then recognizing it maybe notice
the way that it is a disconnection
with the experience here and now
say other to yourself and then reconnect
to the embodied experience of the present moment breathing
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
there's a way in which a lot of thinking about other things and other places other people
limits our ability to
love or to care to be kind
and there's a way in which being centered in ourselves intimate
calm gives us access
to love to care to kindness as the situation
calls on it
and with whatever ways in which we're centered in ourselves at ease in ourselves
that we can in fact then
not so much think about others
but have our hearts open and directed towards others
to care about others coming from being centered
here not toppling over
with a lot of head concerns thoughts and stories
to center ourselves deeply and well here and then find ourselves being turned
inside out so that we
our hearts now can touch and be touched by the world
and may it be that our ability to be centered and grounded and intimate with our direct
experience becomes the source from which
we care for this world and live in some way
for the benefit and welfare of others may from this meditation practice we've
done today may the goodness of the practice spread
outwards from here out into the world may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free and may we
contribute to that
[Music]
so again good day and before i give this talk
i want to mention my gratitude for all of you who donated
to our haiti fund efforts to support the people of haiti
passing on the donation to partners in health and to me it was phenomenal
how much was able to be raised this way as a
community we raised last count i heard thirty thousand dollars
and that that was a count a week ago i think there's something still coming in that's designated for that purpose
and we had the full accounting uh some beginning of the month but uh all the money that was donated
for that purpose will go to um partners in health so thank you very much it was inspiring
that that's enough money to i believe to make a big difference for some people
in the country of haiti and partners of health goes into the countryside and all kinds of places
where often people are forgotten and works with local medical care people and
so very locally focused so
thank you so today's topic on patients has to do
with patients under insult
and so this is any circumstance where
the tendency is to get angry or agitated or maybe
so afraid that we become impatient in a hurry
but especially in the tradition in buddhist tradition it has to do with situations where we get angry annoyed
irritated furious and it could be with other people
it could also be have to do with events in the world it could be that you are angry with your
computer because it's not behaving right or or it could be the weather is irritating
because it's not what you planned it for plan planned it to be
and um and so here uh the word patience
patience under insult patients under assault
is might be interpreted as a kind of tolerance
tolerance of people being unkind saying mean things doing things which are provoking
tolerance with all kinds of things but tolerance is not really the
orientation because intolerance is a focus outwards to the other to the thing
out there buddhist practice kind of the beginning point not the end but where it kind of
more often begins is not the other but here with us what's going on here
and so rather than tolerating insult patients under insult means that
maybe even a kind of intolerance an intolerance for us
inside diminishing us or causing suffering to
ourselves harming ourselves and
and so to kind of an intolerance no i don't want to harm myself and the particular way that the
tradition emphasizes that is through being angry so rather than tolerating
injustice in the world that's a whole other topic of what a relationship is to injustice things that
are wrong things that make us angry upset that's an important topic but but the
the core aspect of the patients under insult is that we don't allow ourselves
to succumb to anger and a particular kind of anger because
in english sometimes the word anger covers a wider span than what
classically in buddhism is considered to be angry the anger in buddhism is always
connected to hostility malice
there's always a so if you can have it be angry but there's no hostility then
it isn't what buddhists call angry anger so you have to kind of understand you know translate between
languages here when you hear buddhists talk about anger it's always implies that there's some
hostility involved in the motivation in the in the fury and the fire
but hostility that we have towards others always hurts the hustle always
hurts us it harms us and it's hard to see that when
the focus is on the other excuse me for a minute
so it's hard to see that when the focus is on others it can actually be a kind of pleasure even sometimes to be really
focused and angry and directed you know one pointedly on the on someplace else
if he can feel very alive or feel energizing it can feel some people feel so powerful that way
and they enjoy the power so but when but when we can stop
focusing on the other and what it feels like to be othering and directing
and feel the in intimately what's happening for us come back and being centered here
then hostility always harms ourselves and we don't want to harm ourselves and
buddhist practice as i say kind of always begins with ourselves it doesn't end there it ends with caring
for the world but we have more to if we can care for ourselves properly we have more to offer
the world we're safer for the world we're not going to make so he liable to make quick
mistakes in what we do and so um so there so sometimes we talk
about this patience under insult as a practice of restraint
uh not giving in to the anger and um and that's maybe the first kind
of line of uh action here so you know so if
buddhism likes to divide human activities into body speech and mind
with the understanding and maybe you don't share this understanding that the coarsest is what we do physically
with our body and that we have more we can see it it's visible and we can have a little bit
more control over it and so to be restrained
in harming people with our bodies and that can be with glares that can be
with um you know gestures and then um
and then the second which is a little bit harder maybe a lot harder mindful speech is harder is to be restrained
from causing harm through uh speech
and so if we feel angry start becoming very very careful with speech and don't
cross the line to speak in ways that then is expressed as hostility
wait if you can if it's appropriate to wait to calm down
don't necessarily leave the situation and don't address what's going on but
hold back until you feel you can do so without hostility you'll be much wiser that way and more
effective uh in the especially in the long term hostility is effective in the short term
because it frightens people and people pull away or they stop what they're doing and so there's a kind of reward into
being hostile but the long-term consequences in human relationships is not good
and that can actually be more harmful for you socially in the long term than
in the short term so to be restrained in speech and then the more subtle but the more
important area for buddhist practice practice is to be really careful with your
thoughts and if your thoughts are mean thoughts are hostile be very careful with that
and hold back restrain yourself from giving into those don't succumb to them
and this act of restraint is an act of strength it's not an act of repression
but it is an act of protecting yourself
from yourself the impact of actions that harm others
the impact of speech that our mothers on oneself is actually quite big
and the buddhist tradition kind of suggests that we don't really recognize how big it is because it has this karmic
impact it affects deeper conditioning the deeper subconscious workings of the mind the memories how things are
remembered how things are uh return in the future time in a way that's unexpected
and so but it's huge so
how to be restrained how to hold back in a way that is not repression
is not but really is for our own good and one of them is by really recognizing
the difference of othering having the mind concerns being directed towards others
others have to be different others have to do things certain way others have have wronged me
and of course it's accurate sometimes that kind of thinking but to be
preoccupied with that and caught in that is an alienation is a loss to ourselves
and as we're not grounded on ourselves and focusing externally that's when hostility can slip out
because we're not in we're not following ourselves mindful and careful what's going on here
and so to learn in meditation to not spend a lot of time thinking
other than thoughts recognizing it as othering and become skilled at not going down those channels
and coming back here is a training for in life to be patient under insult
to learn to recognize what's happening here and focusing him being careful attentive
and being so attentive that you're there with yourself at those choice moments
about what you're going to do with your body what you're going to do with your voice
and even what you're going to do with your trains of thought you're right there and that's where you
relax that's where you let go that's where you settle back
and if necessary so you don't cause harm that's where you practice restraint
maybe just you know clamp your mouth shut if it necessary you know
bite your tongue so you don't say something that you later regret and
restraint is the right action when the alternative is worse
and but through practice we can do better than restraint we can let go we can stay
close to that place where we're free we're not caught in these movements we have
we might still feel angry we might feel hostile but there's no tendency to pick it up no
tendency to go with it to do anything it has no power over us even though it might bubble up
and where the power is is in ourselves in our ability to be mindful attentive centered
and have choice about how we work with all the inner impulses that come along
and as we live that way then we start having wisdom and clarity
about how to interact with others how to have the difficult conversations
how to show up in ways that um don't frighten others but also
don't lead to retaliation or or difficult dynamics where you know
anger is meeting anger and it flares up even more
and um and then finally maybe i shouldn't say this as a
punctuation for this talk but just so you don't take
i want you to take what i said seriously but maybe you know not not to hold it up too idealistically
and that is that sometimes
you know the way to irritate someone who is being hostile to you or irritates someone as being a
problem for you is um not returning irritation and kind and
not getting angry in return staying calm staying non-reactive
staying kind of uh un concerned with what's coming or something staying free
and um and sometimes that little reward knowing oh i got to that person the person you
know is frustrated now irritated maybe it's not the healthiest thing to do but
maybe it kind of can inspire you to find your way to healthy patients under insult
so thank you very much and and if you have opportunities the next
24 hours where you feel frustrated irritated angry
you might use that as an occasion to see if some of the things i've said today
how they play out in you how they're working inside of you and um and maybe you'll have more wisdom and
more options of how to live in a with your own frustration and anger
so thank you