so hello hello and welcome hello and welcome to happy hour
lovely to be with you in this moment in time
so as we've been continuing to cultivate to go through the categories with metta with a cultivation of
kindness good will arose by any name can translate to metta
in so many different ways good will kindness love warmth
friendliness so we've come to the category of all beings
and diana uh shared meditation on that uh yesterday and i did it on wednesday
so let's linger with it a little more because this can be um it can be a fun and joyous category
of just spreading good will wishing wishing beings well
and i'm going to use some imagery today to kind of loosen us from our usual conception
of of well-wishing so my invitation to you is to be playful
with this not have a sense of should i should be
able to wish well for all beings and everywhere and i'm failing and have a
playful attitude with it really have a playful attitude
these practices if we have fun with them then they take hold a lot more
deeply than if we do them as a grim duty especially wishing well for for all
beings it's just kind of an easy thing like yeah and see where you're
you're fine your heart finds connection where your heart feels drawn to
um what categories in what ways
yeah and and one other thing i want to say is um this i i find this particular
practice the well-wishing for all beings to be
and well it can be expressed in so many different ways it can be heavy it can be light it can be very joyful you
really can't be light it can be happy making especially if you're feeling kind of heavy and and more rose
it's like okay spend some time wishing well for others and all beings people you don't know you can just imagine them you
can just pull them out of a hat like a magician and wish them well whatever works for you and
and and a practical aspect of this is if you're walking around say if you have you've had a tough day
and if you go for a walk start wishing well for whomever you come across
when you're walking the path just wish them well and find you'll soon find you're lighter you're smiling you
happy you're happier i've done this practice in this way and it's just like oh wow i i feel like i'm walking on clouds now
it's just your whole perception gets um can can get shifted so don't
fight don't judge yourself like oh it's not working it's not uh just plan c's just
you're giving these offerings as if you're giving these offerings offerings to all to these beings you're
just you're spreading petals of flowers you're just without any expectations you just do it
you just or plant seeds or whatever imagery we're gonna play around with imagery tonight so
so that i would like to invite you to get into your meditation posture and
ah and settle i have to say neil was he your backer it
looks like you're sitting in snow on your porch in the middle of snow this is so funny oh my god may you be well
may you be warm [Laughter] i love the humor of it this is great
and forest looks nice and cozy and warm in his blanket i love this okay great
so yes let's get into our meditation posture
landing landing in this body
ah how nice how nice to just land and sit
in this body here in this moment
this moment of being alive right here right now just as
it is and just letting yourself be breathed being aware
of the breath of the sensations of the body
and just settling
one breath at a time
me
hey
this moment of refuge
to honor and cherish
just as it is
not needing it to be any different but relaxing into
this body this breath
not fighting not resisting
fully embracing
however it's showing up
me
hmm
um
and if thoughts preoccupations come up
be gentle let them be seen
to be released
to be released in the current
holding on no fighting no resistance just release
and be aware
me
okay
hey
me as you receive the breath
i'm gonna invite you now i'd like to invite you to imagine as if the breath is being
received the middle of your chest in your heart center
and with each breath entering your heart your heart center and leaving your heart center
you find that your care your good will your
friendliness
is awakened more and more it becomes more vitalized
more awakened
you're welcome to use whatever image works for you maybe
it's a light shines brightly in with each breath
it simply becomes brighter and brighter it's not so much that you are making it brighter it's
becoming brighter on its own check this out interesting
there's the image of the sacred holy fire works for you maybe each breath is
bellowing the fire is becoming warmer
bigger
and more beautiful
me
whatever image works for you in this moment then you can change later it's okay
allow this a sense of good well to shine
to radiate it's not so much that you are doing it
just all you quote unquote do is not to get in its way
let the inner goodness the inner kindness that we all
have and we often get in its way
we're shy or scared to express it just let it shine on its own
a sense of goodwill touching shining on people you care about maybe see that
first your benefactor your dear friend
it touches them and brings them your good wishes my friendliness goodwill wishing them
well may you be well may you be happy
a simplified version of metaphrases what are the four phrases may you be
safe happy
healthy and have ease
seeing the brightness the good will shining brightly
upwards downwards
to your life to your right to your left
behind you in front of you all around you
this light of goodwill shining touching you too
as it radiates out of your heart center in the middle of your chest it touches you with good will ah
and maybe you relax and melt a little bit as the light touches you first
ah may i be well friendliness goodness may i be well
this light can lie like a nice warm blanket
[Music] embracing you
and shining shining all around you
any being it comes in contact with
wishes them well brings them happiness goodness in your
mind your wish
oh goodness
maybe imagine that you're a human being walking
walking in this earth ah and anyone this light comes in
contact with as you're walking in your neighborhood
with words or without the words of meta just this radiance
is an offering of goodwill
me
maybe you imagine you're a fish swimming in the ocean
with this light shining from your fishy heart center
and every being in the ocean
comes in contact either directly or indirectly
ah he's touched by this wish of goodness
[Music] well-being
without attachment to outcome have fun with it
imagining sharks
being touched by this well-wishes colorful fish
sea horses shrimp eels
spreading meta to all beings and swim
and all the oceans all the waters
again let yourself have joy with this maybe you're a dolphin
jumping in and out of the water with this orb bright orb of meta
shining good wishes joyfully
swimming and dancing in the water spreading
goodwill
i feel like you can imagine you're a bird in the sky
spreading your let your body be relaxed
may all beings that fly may all beings that fly be well
me
okay feel free to explore whatever imagery
works for you
you can be the rain that washes all over the world all the
beings it touches it brings them wishes of well-being
may you be safe may you be happy
may you be healthy may you have ease
soaking all beings with friendliness good will
see what works for you
hey
here if you are having challenging time right
now it's okay for you to be the recipient of the rain yourself
both be the reign and the recipient ah let your body
soak in the goodness the good will the care
okay
eat
you can't do this practice wrong
as long as you meet whatever comes up with gentleness and kindness you're planting
seeds of kindness it's all good
hey
feel free to use any of the imageries that have worked for you in this practice and just stay
with them until the end
me
yes
thoughts arise and you happen to think about anyone just wish them well
share some mental and goodwill with this being who's come up in your mind's eye
hey
me
if there's if there are any judgmental thoughts coming up i can't do this it's not working
can you meet the thoughts with kindness with a smile with friendliness oh sweetie
don't fight no resistance just kindness and love
radiating kindness and love whatever comes up that's all
yes
just radiating kindness and love
with age breath that's all
may we radiate kindness and love
with each breath as we live
that's all [Music]
thank you for your practice
radiating kindness and love
with whatever that arises
beings people thoughts ourselves just radiating radiating kindness and
love it's all that matters anyway in this
life
so love to invite you invite your
reflections what came up for you reflections questions
what worked what didn't work it's all welcome you can type them in chat for everyone
to see or just privately to me which case i'll read them out loud without saying your
name or you can raise your your um hand by either going to participants or
going to reactions on zoom doing raise hand and especially if you haven't shared
for a while or if you're new would love to hear your reflections your wisdom is is important
it's a gift you offer to the to the sangha so
hello good to see you too have a greeting in chat
what what else tell me what's coming up for you what what worked oh yes we have linda
please
i think i realized during this meditation that something i've been
doing every day when i walk my dog is is like a loving kindness for all
beings and i think that's why i've been enjoying it so much
and i started it kind of when covet started and i started making eye contact with
every driver and just i just beam
at them because honestly i'm happy to see a person and
i swear now people like look for me and they wave enthusiastically and you know big
semi truck drivers wave and i just i just got that feeling when
you were talking and then being the dolphin in the sea and i was like oh no wonder i look
forward to it it's beautiful it's beautiful for me but i i and i get so much enjoyment out of it
watching their reactions so anyway that's enough
it's love that's that's lovely just lovely linda thank you so much for sharing that
i feel mudita vicarious joy as you describe your metal walks you it it is a practice
of meta you are just that's meta it's not like it's not complicated you're just smiling at
people friendliness you're waving at it which is so sweet you're establishing eye contact i see you that's lovely thank you so
much for sharing that it makes me happy yay sweet let's see i
see lisa your hand is up please hi thank you so much nikki um
i was imagining like the moonlight um as the like radiating the metal practice
um and remembering it's a full moon tonight so that was really i was able to really
connect with that lovely beautiful i love the idea of the moon especially in
in buddhism and uh zen especially the full moon is a symbol of a fully
awakened being so when you talk about that i love the symbolism of the fully awakened heart
shining its light of love onto beings i get chills thank you lisa for sharing that makes me
happy jesse oops your hand disappeared
okay i'm gonna take a moment i'll read the reflections and if you want to raise your hand again
it's all good neil says i was like tinkerbell sprinkling sprinkling fairy dust of meta
everywhere i flew oh my god that's so sweet
oh it's fine it's fine um bill says what if my meditation isn't just visual but
verbal i have fragment of a song that seems to work for me is this bad no it's not bad
it's some people are auditory you might be uh some people are visual some just whatever works for you some it
might be fragrant you might be giving fragrant roses to everyone it's all
good or uh it's great so it's a song fantastic go with it go with it bill
it's a cultivation practice lovely jerry says i love the expression
radiating kindness and love with each breath that's all especially that's all
yes thank you jerry yeah it feels that way that's all
and another reflection here my back was hurting for the first 20 to 30 minutes
and it took my body a while to physically let go i felt very tense no problem
no problem um and i i'm delighted to hear that you stayed
with it you stayed with it and it opened up and you didn't give up after like okay i'm done with this oh
just staying gently staying with it gently staying with it gently staying with it
um and and my invitation is if this happens again and if i'm giving instructions about
flowers and i don't know fishes then then direct the meta to your hurting back to your hurting
back and just invite it to relax it's okay it's loved it's loved it's loved it's all okay can be as tense
and it could be as tight as it wants to don't judge it just love it that's my invitation if this happens for you
uh your practitioner or anybody else and jesse your hand back up again okay so this is last reflection we're going
to take go ahead hi thanks for the some great meditation
um yeah for the loving kindness of all beings
um it just seems it seems a little bit more open-ended than the other categories and
um do you sort of do you wait for you know and i i pictured you know the
occasional animal would come to mind but did do you just wait for them to come or do you try and think about just
any being um yeah yeah yeah
that's an excellent question um it can be either way and there there's no right or wrong way
to practice this um and sometimes it might make sense i think i did that on wednesday to kind of
went through the categories you know all the beings that are hop and swim and you're like kind of bringing
categories and thinking about all the beings in that category and some other times it could just be kind of like open
and you know north south east west whatever beings who show up oh people who live in
middle east just showed up oh may you be well you know uh all the birds in africa just showed up
well maybe so so either way either way and you can choose and and you might find your heart in
some sessions is drawn to one versus another way but there's no right or wrong it's all cultivation
practices yeah okay is that okay jesse yeah great and
question last question uh jerry asks does the bee does the being need to be sentient um
um yes and no i think in in buddhist practice we go with sentient it's like may all sentient
beings be well all the beings that have consciousness and then i think sometimes it's okay to
to extend that and and extend it to plants and on mother earth
and there's a sense of embracing gaia this life energy life force that that moves through
all living beings so it so it doesn't have to be sentient in my
opinion but you can practice either way so
so dear ones let's practice together in in communities spreading our good
will and and the invitation so the invitation as you as we go into groups is the first minute
actually for the free don't hop off just yet practice check this out for the first minute actually don't say
anything just with each breath radiate meta for the other couple of people who are in
the practice group with you and see what happens if you radiate meta for them and receive
you're meant to see what what gets transformed stay in your body stay in your body
and then after the first minute just share as little or as much as you
wish to share supporting each other with your wisdom with your with the community wisdom so
i'm going to create the breakout rooms and here we go let's see
okay and i'm about to open them here we go
enjoy each other's meta so uh we have a couple of minutes i
would love to hear your reflections about the practice being in the groups whatever you like to share um spreading
love and wisdom in the world so especially if you haven't shared before if you're new would really love to invite you oh
and if you haven't shared in a while so pulling back pulling forward especially
if you're shy like i don't know i want to talk if you're shy then would really love to hear from you i see someone who's like when i said shy
their their head is yeah yeah i'm shy so i invite you to speak
jesse says all the best to my group we got cut off at the end but appreciate being with you all and thank
you for sharing oh sweet thank you jesse
other reflections oh that's nice yeah
emily and ben bensen smileys those are happy faces anybody wants to share
oh my god that's sweet
all kinds of fun uh fun tech chats are coming of
appreciation and cute emoticons and smileys and and you discovered you have
a friend in common two of you in the group oh my god this is sweet so any last comments before we end
especially from the shy ones please you can raise your hand uh you're here um
oh and and we have a reflection also from you too uh when sending out love when winning
when sending love out required energy i switched to receiving love from those
that love me and then without effort love went back out from my heart it became circular
receiving and sending out lovely lovely holly thank you so much for sharing that beautiful
yes indeed um this natural naturalness of giving and receiving
beautiful yes anyone any last comments before we end going once
i think you're fantastic thank you so much for um for the space that you've created
really thank you thank you sarah thank you for being part
of it coming and practicing being part of the sangha the sangha belongs to you you're part of the sangha we co-create
this together thank you and susan also says holly that is so lovely so holly
appreciation for your share that's that's beautiful so dear ones we have come to the end of
this happy hour together practicing and and cultivating breathing sharing
love and good will with each breath that being all may you all be well may
you all share spread cultivate your love unto the world
in any way that you can serve may you all be safe happy healthy and
well in all beings everywhere [Music]
thank you