for today's topic for practice together um
let's continue let's continue one more session with the practice of mudita with the
practice of vicarious joy
um sympathetic joy empathetic choice many different ways is translated
because it's such a profound and beautiful practice to feel happy for
happiness for good fortune for goodness in the world this way we notice goodness more
and of course this time of the pandemic especially there might be lots of
challenges both for us personally and people we care about and it's wholesome it's wholesome to
intend to train our mind to also notice the good
notice the blessings notice what's good in the world and feel happy for it um
and um and as i was saying last night
[Music] us human beings we have the genes of the human beings who were more
anxious and worried and as they were walking on the savannah
they were more concerned about the dangers about the african mammoth not the woolly mammoth one of you
you've pointed out there was no holy mamas on on the savannah yes the african mammoth
they were more concerned about dangers in the environment instead of instead of the positive the
positive in the environment so that the ones who are more tuned to
more positiveness in the environment they they were hunted out they didn't live
long enough to pass down their genes the the ancestors who passed out their
genes were the ones who were anxious who were looking out for all all the negative and
difficulty in the environment so so what we feel if you've noticed that oh
when somebody gives you a compliment it just rolls off but if somebody gives you a challenging
feedback ah you think about it over and over and over and over again
so you can just see this this um tendency in yourself and everybody else
you know we're it's it's also said that our minds are
like teflon for good experiences they don't stick good experiences just roll off whereas
their our minds are like velcro for challenging and difficult experiences it
just sticks so different ways to think about this natural tendency
that us human beings happen to have evolutionarily so this practice
of turning our minds to um intentionally to notice the good to
notice the blessings to notice what's good both for in our lives and other
people's lives and celebrating feeling happy for happiness
um is a wholesome way to train ourselves in gladness to train ourselves our heart
in in happiness which is wholesome it's not avoidant
it's not avoidant in that we build more capacity more resilience
to be what is difficult it's not about avoiding the difficulty but to build
more capacity through joy have you noticed if
you're in a good mood if somebody gives you bad news ah it's easier to be with it
then if you're already depressed somebody gives you bad news and oh you're just shattered so in the first
scenario you're more resilient so in this way we're building more
resilience to be able to support ourselves and others so so many different ways to
think about this beautiful practice of modita so without further ado let's do it
let's practice together so this is a perfect time to get into
your meditation posture if you would like to move shift
sit up straighter yeah or maybe relax
soften even lie down if that's what your body is asking you to do
ah and landing landing
landing in this body
at this precious moment however it is
embracing opening up to the moment with every cell of your body
every chamber of your heart
fighting your body to land
to soften to relax
for the awareness to connect intimately with each breath
and the lower abdomen
cherishing celebrating
embracing hugging as if the attention is hugging
warmly lovingly embracing the breath in
the lower abdomen
and if thinking arises gently kindly ask yourself
if it's necessary to be thinking this thought right now
and smilingly playfully
telling the thought not now not now
giving my whole heart my whole body
of this practice this moment this present moment of being alive
precious mysterious
[Music] profound
just this breath just this in-breath just this out breath
intimately connecting
the relaxed body
settling arriving tilling the soil of
awareness
letting the goodness of this breath
life-giving enliveling enlivening energizing
soothing living the goodness of this breath
right here this one
this in-breath write this out breath right here
letting the goodness of it be
appreciated
opening your awareness to something something in your body right now that's
comfortable maybe it's that you're sitting
relatively comfortably and the chair or the cushion
not standing in line somewhere but relatively comfortable
that your body is warm the right temperature
appreciating the goodness
letting your heart relish
the goodness of this comfort sensation
not taking it for granted
inviting yourself to notice
some blessing some other blessing in your environment
in this moment noticing the good
and you have a roof over your head maybe
the lighting is good or wow that you have a computer or
a phone or tablet some means that you are connecting you are connecting
right now to this practice
appreciating the goodness this blessing simple blessing often taken for granted
of course sometimes the mind can veer off into all those who don't have these blessings and
feel guilty ashamed etc
we're training our mind to attend we're training yes
there are many challenges in the world that we have and others have
we're not avoiding them we'll practice with them bring them to
mind with compassion and action in this moment we're training
our mind we're intending to train our heart and mind to attend to the good
so reconnect with your intention
the power of intention
noticing what's good right now
the blessings in your life as we start this practice
letting your heart open to them and celebrate them it's okay unabashedly
celebrating your own goodness
and opening up now someone who's dear to you
bringing to mind something that's good
in their life something they are happy about
they celebrate could be something as simple as they were sick and now they're
healthy and they're happy about that
or they didn't have a job and now they're doing something they love
and you're so happy for them celebrating their happiness as if
as if it were your own i'm happy for your happiness
or maybe they have a relationship they cherish whatever the blessing the good fortune
is
something that makes them happy can not every aspect of their life needs to
be hunky-dory and happy but this this aspect
this blessing
really connecting with their happiness with their gladness how they celebrate
how happy they are and let your heart feel their gladness
feel the connection to their joy
i'm happy for your happiness
may your good fortune continue made increase may it never
end if we choose to recite the sentence full
fully well knowing there is impermanence and yet we share
the sentiment as a generosity as a statement of
generosity of our heart not attached to outcome that this will
continue forever it may not but we wish we wish it with generosity
celebrating their happiness without attachment
i'm happy for your happiness or maybe simply war wordless with data
celebrating their good fortune
and now bringing to mind someone you don't know very well
maybe a neighbor whom you have met but don't really know or someone
working at a store you've interacted briefly with or a delivery person
somewhat of a neutral somewhat of a neutral person
as a stand-in for all of humanity to bring this person this human being to
mind that just like you
they want to be happy just like you they have a complex inner
life that's compelling to them
just like you they have sorrows just like you they have joys they have blessings things they're
happy about in this category it's okay
to use your creativity so maybe as a way in it's okay to imagine
something you are grateful for you celebrate
maybe it's a comfortable home maybe it's a friendship
maybe it's a relative a young one in your life
it was a blessing for you or a work or a connection
whatever it is maybe bringing that to light to mind
feeling your own gladness appreciation
and imagining oh they happen to have a similar blessing
in their life that they're so grateful for they celebrate
feeling into how cherished how happy making
this blessing is for you
and to consider the two of you are similar in this way
this blessing this goodness
be delighted feeling happy for their happiness
or maybe for both of your happinesses
celebrating may this happiness may this good fortune continue
may this gladness continue may it increase may it never end
maybe imagine the two of you you and the neutral person talking and discussing
how happy making this blessing is in your life is goodness
isn't it wonderful feeling shared joy
and now inviting someone you have a slight
challenge with
bringing bringing them to mind and noticing that just like you
and just like this neutral person this person also wants to be happy
they have challenges in their lives they have blessings too and again not condoning
the challenge the hurt the harm separating the actions in your mind
from the humanity
of this person see if your heart can connect
with something good in their life i was generosity being happy for them
being happy that they have this this goodness
allowing yourself to feel the generosity of your heart in this way in this beautiful way
i have i'm happy for your happiness
as if it were my own your happiness makes me happy
may you enjoy appreciate your happiness may it continue
made never cease
now for the last moment of this practice period
inviting inviting all beings yourself your dear being
a neutral being being you have challenges with
inviting them all and celebrating all the goodness
we all have challenges and we all have goodness in our lives
letting our heart letting your heart
open to celebrate feel brightened by
this goodness blessings
then inviting to your mind all the beings the zoom room
on youtube practicing with you and all the beings who listen to the audiodharma leader
feeling happy for all the happinesses all the blessings
large and small we all have may they continue
may they never end expanding further to all beings
everywhere
the generosity of heart may all the blessings everywhere all the goodnesses all the happiness
continue may they increase
may they never cease
so
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
i don't know about you but i feel happier compared to when we started i see smiles
so we have some time um for reflections
questions comments you're welcome to type them in chat if you type them directly to me i won't say your name
you type them to for to everyone and i will say your name out loud and
you can also raise your hand and and if you haven't shared in a while would love to hear
would love to hear your reflections what worked what didn't what did you notice
we had some lovely reflections last night and i forgot to say since diana is off for
this month i'm for the first two weeks of march i'm teaching
every night i'm teaching happier every night so tomorrow it's me again
surprise so so based on some feedback last night
um i think you remember jamie talk asking about how to connect how to better connect more easily
connect with the neutral being so i changed tonight's meditation guidance to
to support that and i hope that was supportive for you jamie and others i see you're nodding giving thumbs up
great so other questions comments it's all welcome it all helps supports everyone
in the community so
fred are you trying to raise your hand to speak i am yes okay yeah the the race hand
button is right underneath that um this is the clap but it's good
so i can i can hear you yes please um i i found your suggestion
to use our imagination uh very effective and i was having the same trouble as was
being discussed last night of trying to grasp the happiness of someone i knew
almost nothing about but knowing that my imagining of the
person's details of their life and their inner life were probably
invariably wrong uh you know i'm i'm mostly wrong about people i know
well so why would i get you know a stranger right and that was just fine it felt like
we could move closer in a way that was very gratifying great lovely thank you for sharing that
reflection i'm delighted to hear that that that imagination surprisingly it
does work with this practice yay especially with the neutral person with creating the sense of connection
because this practice of metta mudita these brahmaviharas are skillful means
our ways that we use imagination we use different um abilities different
tools to conjure up a connection to create a connection with people um so lovely thank you for
sharing that fred nice
other reflections any questions comments complaints what worked what didn't what
surprised you
and please know whatever you choose to share of your practice with the community is helpful for the community
something was surprising if you noticed yeah i'll pause
yeah so i have a question maybe before we go into practice into small groups together and
using the reactions the reactions button um they're the green the yes
if you notice you feel or at any point you felt happier this really tuning connecting
with goodness in the world give a check mark give a yes i'm curious this is
an informal survey and i'm going to count the yeses
yeah so i see it a dozen yeses
roughly the number keeps changing i think it it times out after a while
and if it's a no do the x so which is fine too great i think it keeps timing out i
think the number is yeah it keeps increasing decreasing that's so funny all right i'm getting about 15 or so
right now something like that okay great nice well thank you for voting it's it's
nice to get a sense so
so thank you all for i'm getting thumbs up on youtube too that's sweet um so
so for our practicing community as again yesterday we did an informal
survey it will start with 30 seconds of silence silent modita gladness for other
people's glams and if at this point you usually hop off notice what happens if you stay in order
to support others as a gift of generosity to others to see it that way if if you have to go
it's all good but if you can stay see what happens if you stay out of generosity to others
for the practice so i will create the practice groups the small groups
and oh yes and after um the uh after 30 seconds of silent mudita for
each other happiness for each other's happiness then um let's go one round and
sharing something you're happy about something you're grateful for in your life and you can practice real
time with detail for each other and then you can share anything you want to share
about your practice so let's see
here we go okay i'm going to open the breakout rooms and
here we go enjoy okay everyone welcome back the rooms are
closed and we have a few minutes left for any reflections you like to share which
became clear after discussing with others and or how was it to practice with others in
this way you can type it in chat or you can raise your hand it would be lovely to hear
your your reflections
um i thought it was really heartwarming listening to one of the shares and
about mudita i just felt mudita listening to the share it was really sweet so deep bounce
nice thank you thank you for sharing michael and nicholas says laughter is such a joy
yes yes it is yeah laughter begets laughter hence laughter
yoga tom please
it was it was i really enjoyed hearing what other people were joyful about and
we finished um by agreeing that uh either singing or listening to a choir was
it was was a great joy for us nice nice that's great i love it
i love it shared joy sweet and the other reflections before we
close our joyous togetherness this evening or morning
or afternoon depending on your time zone
i see trevor's hand what's up trevor
yeah i just uh i i when i i kind of leaned towards leaving um
for for that part not for really any particular reason but just was thinking more along the lines
of sila before i left and just practicing um some some
thoughtful speech in some in some way you know so using that time it felt really good
stuff yeah nice thank you for sharing that what a beautiful intention
um to stay intentionally to practice
wholeheartedness virtue kindness you know ethical
wise speech right speech so many different names just to relate from from a place of
integrity and kindness and wisdom through wise speech in in this little sandbox of interaction
what a beautiful intention to bring in i love it yay and i'm highlighting it because i
think that's a lovely intention for all of us i see hot net heads nodding it's it's a
beautiful intention for all of us in this way to um practice and in the past when i
used to the first year i would say a lot setting up the groups about intention when you
go into small groups and now i don't do that anymore and your your share is a beautiful reminder trevor
that i think every time it's important as we enter this sacred space of a small group to really show up in
this way oh this is a sandbox how can i show up with integrity kindness wisdom for myself and
for others how can i show up differently and model this for myself and others
to take it into my daily life so thank you for that trevor so we have
come to the end of another happy hour together everyone thank you all for your practice
may you be safe happy healthy and well in every way
and may all beings everywhere be happy and free
[Music]
thank you all