good evening or maybe it's not evening where you are
good morning good afternoon a warm welcome
so as usual i'll begin with a guided meditation
so allowing ourselves to
take our meditation seat our meditation posture
and just arriving here in this moment in this location
for now there's nowhere else to be and
nothing else to do except to be here
with this experience of beginning a meditation session
so feeling the the body the pressure of the chair
cushion bench bed couch whatever it might be against the body
and then noticing that the body is breathing
of course it's breathing
noticing the in-breaths
the stretching the pulling the expansion of the chest area perhaps
or the belly
and noticing the out breaths the exhales
what does it feel like to have an exhale
just in a gentle relaxed manner
and noticing the transitions between the inhales and the exhales
nothing in particular needs to be happening
just resting the attention on the sensations of breathing
and when the mind wanders we don't have to make it be a problem
we just very simply gently begin again
we're practicing with a sense of warmth and openness
not a tight constricted striving kind of way
but with ease and
sincerity
and then we might notice that there is a compelling
bodily sensation
we can let go of the breath so to speak
and invite in this compelling bodily sensation
this to this too can be incorporated folded into
our meditation practice
and when it's no longer compelling
just very simply return to the breath
there is something that occurs when we turn towards
a compelling or difficult or uncomfortable sensation
and are able to be with it even if it is just for a fraction of a second
but rather than reflexively jumping away
but to recognize yes this is uncomfortable this is compelling
to turn towards and invite in instead of push away
there's a type of confidence that grows
as we recognize yes i can be with some difficult
uncomfortable
sensations
this confidence grows as we recognize our capacity
to be with difficulties is increasing
maybe only by a small amount
that's okay
maybe our confidence also grows
as we recognize that we can direct the mind a little bit
we can turn toward things towards the breath towards a bodily
sensation
our capacity for directing or inclining the mind
is increasing
sometimes it's helpful to just recognize acknowledge
our confidence is just naturally shifting the more we practice
shifting to be a little bit bigger
a little bit steadier
and as we practice we have more and more experiences
some of them have been uncomfortable
and then recognizing okay i can be uncomfortable
i don't have to make it more difficult than it is
and as our confidence increases there are less things that we have to
avoid shy away from
less people i need to avoid and shy away from
and with this confidence allows us to
maybe be the one that's steady when others are feeling out of balance
unsteady perhaps we increase our capacity that we
can support and comfort others
just by noticing that our capacity is increasing
every time that there's a difficult uncomfortable moment in our meditation and
we're able to however slightly however short of a time we're able to just be
with it be with it and in this way
our meditation can be a support not only for us but for others
and can ripple out from us to others
so that our practice can be for the benefit of all beings
[Music]
everywhere
good evening again good morning good afternoon whenever it is you're
listening and a warm welcome
so today i'd like to talk about a topic is something that um maybe for some of us
isn't our favorite topic let's say this i know it certainly wasn't my favorite topic
before i actually kind of shied away and felt uncomfortable with it and
maybe even a little bit angry about it in some kind of way
and that is to maybe build a little bit on with this on the guided meditation this idea of
confidence that comes as we the more we practice it grows and really can be a support for us
but that's not what was making me angry or people shy away from
but sometimes the word faith is used rather than the word confidence
sometimes we might also use the word trust or conviction
but i thought i would unpack this a little bit for us and explore and examine and tease apart
some of these different parts or these different elements of faith
trust confidence conviction
and specifically to say that the topic of faith can be difficult for some people because
it's associated with mindless belief perhaps with this idea that we
have to proclaim allegiance to a particular doctrine or creed or something
and not only do we have to proclaim an allegiance but then we will be judged by this
judge ourselves or maybe we're judged by others by one's degree of
compliance or one's degree of belief or something like this
so when we use faith in a buddhist context it's very different from this very different
but it's natural of course that we might have some different associations with
this word with the whole concept the whole idea of faith
but faith is a part of buddhist practice it's just not this kind of faith where that's we have
to pledge an allegiance to a doctrine or something like that
but um maybe i'll start with this little a quote of bef that the buddha
gave before he was a buddha so he talks about faith here but clearly
it can't be faith in buddhism or faith in
him or something like this because he's not a buddha yet when he's saying this and
where it's in the context of the commenting how the buddha wished
everyone a better life he wanted people to have a good life
and it was summarized in this verse faith morality learning intelligence
restraint and justice much good else wealth possessions partners and children
flocks kin friends colleagues health beauty and happiness
these things he wished for others that they might keep and never lose
so faith is here at this beginning of this long list of all these desirable things that
people might have in their life and he was wishing that everyone might have this
so clearly faith here isn't um isn't maybe what we're thinking it might
be instead it's uh goes with the possessions partners and children
and health beauty and happiness so what what is faith and the way that
it's here and how might we consider it in the buddhist practice
well i'd like to suggest that uh faith has different aspects maybe you won't be
surprised to hear that and we can consider some of these different aspects
in one aspect is that it has a relational practical
cognitive value to it that is it provides motivation to do
something that it's underlying like activity or action it's like a readiness to do something
with the belief with the confidence that this thing that you're going to do
will lead to um go in a particular direction that you'd like to go
so one aspect of faith is kind of a mobilizing force it's a way to
stir up the energy maybe to do something because you have a belief
that what you're about to do will be supportive for you in your practice
and we can see that in in one particular quote from the dhammapada
where faith is associated with diligence and it's uh um
it's contrasted with laziness and sluggishness
so this um two little verses here in the dhammapada says whoever lives focused on the
pleasant senses unguarded and moderate with food lazy and sluggish
will be overpowered by mara as a weak tree is bent in the wind so overpowered by
mara mara we can understand is this personification of things that get in
the way of awakening so being focused on the pleasant senses
unguarded and moderate with food lazy and sluggish these are help or help create the
conditions in which things will hinder will be an obstacle to greater freedom and then the
next verse says the opposite whoever lives focused on the unpleasant
so we're not saying that we have to focus on the unpleasant all the time it's just uh countering focused on the
pleasant so it's this recognition that there's pleasant and unpleasant and neutral in our
experience but sometimes we're always only focused on the pleasant
whoever lives focused on the unpleasant senses guarded that means to not always
be if we know that it's the equivalent of
if you know you don't want to eat a lot of cookies not going down the cookie aisle in the grocery store
if you know that you really need to sleep more it's not starting that movie at
a midnight that you're going to watch or something like this
whoever lives focused on the unpleasant senses guarded moderate with food faithful
and diligent will not be overpowered overpowered by mara as a stone mountain
is unmoved by the wind so in this verse faithful and diligent
counters in the earlier verse lazy and sluggish so it's this way in which we can
consider faith as a way that provides some motivation some
inspiration to act to do something it's a
it's maybe it's a um aligned maybe with an inspiration has a
heartfeltness so it's not just an action because um we feel like we have to do
something to make something unpleasant go away but it's more of a feeling like yeah
this this is the direction to go this is the direction for greater freedom greater peace
greater well-being so the practical volitional
cognitive aspect of faith and then another aspect of faith might
be this heartfelt this emotional affective aspect of faith
that is maybe this feeling of reverence devotion love esteem
this more of a heartfelt this um
yeah what is how what is a way to describe devotion but not devotion with
a sense of zealots or um or that's blinded or something like this
but with a real commitment maybe a warm commitment something like this
maybe this feelings of confidence that's coupled with an attitude of devotion and
commitment and it's maybe this is like we can think
of a belief in something so this
heartfelt confidence a warmth a warm confidence
and we can find um a short little verse that also talks about this
aspect of faith and this verse takes place in the
context there's a number of brahmins so these are non-buddhist they aren't the followers of the buddha
instead they're priests of the dominant religion at the time
and they go to the buddha and they ask him questions and after the buddha answered all their questions they
were so inspired and touched by what the buddha had to say that they became his followers
and one of the brahmanas pingia he returned from after seeing the buddha
and he told some of the other brahmanas how wonderful the buddha is and one of
these other brahmins said to him but why don't you spend all your time your
every moment with this person gotama gautama's clan name of the buddha
and pingia responds this way my faith joy mind
and mindfulness do not go away from the teaching of gotama whatever direction the one of great
wisdom goes to there is the place i incline
so pointing to how his heart and his mind are in inclined towards this direction of
the buddha even though he's not there all the time with him like physically there but
as this connection this commitment we might say this word devotion
so that's another aspect of faith it's not a devotion that asks us to
get rid of our intellect or our rational thinking or unre reasonableness it's not a devotion
that asks us to give up our autonomy but it's a warm
hearted commitment that's born out of a recognition that there's
something special here something that's worthwhile
and then how do we know that or how do we tune into that is maybe the third aspect of faith
which is more the intellectual cognitive mental aspect of faith
and this way we might define faith as provisional knowledge that is
we have this belief that so maybe it's not so much belief in but belief
that it makes like this belief that this is true it makes sense to me it's consistent
with my experience it's consistent with my understanding but i don't know it first hand myself
right now so it's a kind of provisional knowledge a provisional
understanding that implies a willingness to accept on trust
certain teaching certain propositions that we can't experience for ourselves
directly at this time or we haven't yet so this willingness to accept on trust
so it might lack adequate it might lack adequate evidence at this time
but it isn't irrational it's not necessarily inconsistent with
our experience we could see how perhaps there could be experience that
leads that direction and through practice we
a big part of practice is where we make this transition from belief into knowledge maybe you had this
certain belief that meditation practice would be helpful and would be a support and
use initiated started meditation practice through some before you had the first
experience there was something that supported you encouraged you
and then you did some meditation practice and and said yes there is something here
that's valuable and continued so maybe your confidence
in the practice grew maybe your trust and the confidence grew
so there's three different aspects of faith one is you could use this word practical
but it's kind of supports action the second one is an emotional maybe a
heartfelt commitment or confidence the third is intellectual like a
provisional knowledge a belief that something seems reasonable but i don't have direct
experience yet and when we think about it in fact there's so many things that we have this
provisional knowledge for right black holes for example like okay
it seems consistent that there might be this place and space where gravity pulls so
much that light can't escape but you know i i'm not a physicist i
don't know this for myself but i'm trusting that uh those people that are talking about it
know what they're talking about seems consistent with what i do understand about physics
so there's so many things like this right that we have this i'm using this expression
provisional knowledge but there's a little bit of trust we have trust or or this confidence that what
they're saying makes sense even though we don't have this direct experience
so i've been describing a little bit of some of these aspects about faith but another way that we can unpack
or examine or look at faith is well what function do we see it playing in
buddhist practice what role does it do how do people use it how is it supportive
rather than just describing what it is how is it show up in people's lives how does it
affect people so there's one way it's a little bit
about in the guide meditation is this recognition that this
confidence that we can gain through having more and more experiences
can provide encouragement inspiration dedication and not in a zealous way
not in an overt exaggerated way but in a way that helps us to feel a
certain amount of reassurance or a certain amount of contentment
yeah this is this makes sense to me this is a direction i want to go
my my heart is in here too it's not just my mind but my heart
so one way that faith shows up in the buddhist teachings is in a number
of lists some people are like oh no please not the lists
i'm one of those people i like the lists i kind of enjoy them
but one thing that i'll point out i'll share a few
uh lists uh with us and one of maybe is the obvious one is
um i did a list of the five faculties and of course faith is the first element
in that list faith energy mindfulness concentration and wisdom
you'll notice that faith is first and wisdom is last
so there's maybe two things i'd like to point out here faith is not standing by itself
it's with four other elements so when the buddha talks about to
cultivate and develop the faculties he doesn't say
cultivate and develop faith by itself it's with these other qualities
and in the beginning of this talk i give this long list of things that the buddha was wishing
for other people and faith was part of a collection of positive things
and that's the case this is how faith always shows up is part of a group of practices or
qualities or things that can be cultivated or developed it does not show up by itself
and very often i think actually every time it's the first element in the list
which suggests that it's a starting place so faith is not the end it's not the
goal of practice it's a support and it's a place to begin for our
practice so i'd like to introduce you to
some maybe some other lists that talk about faith the five
factors that support meditation it's also called the five factors for
exertion sometimes these get translated
these two different ways the first element is faith the second
element is health that's defined as being seldom ill or afflicted and having an
even digestion so faith health honesty honesty here is defined
as revealing themselves as they really are to their teachers and fellow
practitioners so really honestly knowing oneself
and being able to share that with others who are wanting to support you in your practice
so faith health honesty for this energy
we um are familiar with this it's a in a applying um
a little bit of effort towards abandoning those things that are unwholesome and cultivating those things that are wholesome
so a certain also maybe a steadfastness or perseverance
and then wisdom so here we are again wisdom is the last one and faith is the
first these five factors that support meditation
and faith is one of these elements and then here's another list don't worry
this the whole talk is not going to be just filled with list after list but i wanted to share one more is that
five qualities that allow a person to live happily
we all want to live happily and if those of us who have meditation practice we want to
have supports for meditation so five qualities that allow a person to live
happily it says in the sutta if a person has
certain qualities they will live happily without distress anguish or fever
i think they of course don't mean fever literally it's more metaphorically without getting agitated
and upset about things okay so what are these five qualities
faith is first conscientiousness prudence and then here's energy and
wisdom so this list these um
what i'd like to point out here is that faith is just a support for our practice
as different elements it's not the purpose of practice it's not instead of practice but instead it's a
way to help us find our way with um cultivating wholesome qualities
and abandoning unwholesome qualities our way with allowing
wisdom to rise and then maybe the last way
that i'll look at faith here so first we talked about there's these different aspects and then we talked about well what function
does it have and it functions with other qualities to be a support for our lives
and then we might ask well is it ever actually flat out defined anywhere and the question would
with the answer would be yes sometimes faith is defined
as a person is a person of faith a person of faith
is one who places faith in the enlightenment of the tatakita
places faith in the enlightenment of the tatakata
many of you know tattoogata is how the buddha speaks of himself this is faith in the boot and the
enlightenment of the buddha there's two different ways we can understand this
one that enlightenment is possible the enlightenment did happen
for gautama and made him to be the buddha or
we might have faith in the buddha's
enlightenment that what he is teaching is comes from a place of
awakening a place without greed without hatred and without delusion
so this faith that enlightenment exists or maybe faith in the buddha as a
teacher maybe each of us gets to find our own
way with us and maybe it changes at different stages in our practice or
different circumstances but i like to think about this sometimes
that how both are true the paulie supports interpreting it either way
faith that enlightenment exists and faith in the buddha as a teacher
this can be a support for us maybe it's some provisional knowledge maybe we see there's
it makes sense we can see how we have more and more freedom and ease with the more we practice maybe there's
some emotion some heartfeltness a commitment to
the buddha and his teachings maybe when we take refuge in the buddha dharma and sangha there's a
heartfeltness and maybe faith that enlightenment is
possible or even in the buddhist teachings supports us helps us to continue with meditation
practice continue with uh listening to dharma talks
so in this way faith i'll have to say maybe this is one thing that i love about
kind of studying and practicing together is there such a depth here there's so
many different ways or like a richness
it feels um a certain like juiciness if i'm allowed
to use that kind of language you know like an aliveness faith it's we're invited to explore
and examine and investigate these three different aspects of it how
faith might work with other qualities other factors to support awakening support our meditation
practice and to support living happily
and may our faith be a support for us so that we can be a support for others
of course we're not just practicing for ourselves but for others so that we might make our
communities and those we come in contact with a place where people can bring their
best versions of themselves so thank you