so good morning everyone and welcome to
insight meditation center it used to be that that was identified with
this building that i'm sitting in but now more and more over this course of this pandemic and doing these
youtube sittings i think of imc as something
much broader and wider and maybe even international and um maybe we should call
imc international meditation center so thank you for being here and for
expanding the the meaning and of what our sangha is
and being part of this
one of the really valuable
aspects of the discoveries of this practice is a way of being
the quality of mind a capacity of the mind to be
desirelessness to be desireless to be without the desire
and it's a probably pretty foreign idea to the way most minds work because
most minds are kind of going from one desire to another
and but to be without desire uh
is to be without any compulsion any attachment any kind of
need for something to happen and i know that this goes against
what's necessary for much of ordinary life
so not to think of it as this is how we're supposed to be the ideal way of being but rather
it's uh kind of like if you are been working in the garden and you're
dirty and grimy then it's good to be dirtless for a while to take off the dirt and
then refresh and then we can go back out into the world so to spend a few moments
without desire as a way of kind of refreshing a way of cleansing a way of opening to something
different as a way of tapping into another way of being in the world where there is a response where there is
there is a way there's wisdom and intelligence and uh that can operate but it seems to come
from a very different place than where kind of ordinary desires come from
and it's a place where we don't identify with our desires we don't make a self
out of desires or we don't tie the desires to self-fulfillment self-enhancement
self-protection all kinds of things so what would that look like for you to
sit and meditate without a desire and maybe it sounds like a very foreign
idea but maybe just assume that something in you knows what that is
and that it's something maybe also assume that it's something
precious something valuable something that is maybe once we tap into it deeply
inspiring so to assume a meditation posture
and maybe you can adjust your posture a little bit maybe sway back and forth sideways a bit
maybe move your shoulders in a circle or something and and kind of
loosen up a little bit in your body
and then taking a posture that supports being alert
and then hopefully the same posture is one that supports relaxation
and to gently close your eyes
and to take a few long slow easy going breaths
as if you have all the time in the world to exhale
and allow the exhale to extend itself as long as it's comfortable
sometimes by extending the exhale it's possible to soften and relax
parts of the body that otherwise wouldn't be
felt or known
to let your breathing now return to normal and as you continue now with a normal
breath in a comfortable way see if with the
exhale you can let the exhale continue
a little bit longer exhale at the end mostly by releasing and allowing
a fuller exhale without any special effort except letting go or allowing
and at the end of that exhale
may perhaps make a very short pause
not so much maybe making the pause but rather allowing a pause
or allowing yourself to wait a moment to
feel the urge to breathe in very simple urge and then allow
for that inhale
perhaps receive the inhale
and as you inhale see if you can attune yourself to the
fullness of that experience of breathing in
without strain but an attunement that's more and
allowing the experience of inhale to be
experienced
and at the end of the inhale see if you can have an allowing
releasing of the exhale allowing of
exhale
and taking a few moments
to more fully feel the what it's like to allow and receive
to allow the exhale to receive the inhale
without any other desire
almost as if it's a release of all desires and in the release of desires
there's an openness in awareness to the experience of
breathing in and breathing out
where desirelessness is closely related to allowing and
receiving
and if you notice there are desires or thoughts
desirelessness is more found in letting go of those
or letting them be
desirelessnesses and not picking anything up or getting involved
the kind of letting go that is not even letting go just letting be
closely related to receiving allowing
whatever happens in experience
in becoming attuned to that part of your experience
that is free of desires even if there are desires present as
well
don't prioritize the desires don't live in desire
see if you can live in the place that is content
open receptive
being with what is
not what we want
you
for a few minutes experiment to the best of your ability
being free of desire
being content to do so even if you're at the edges of it
being able to being content even if it's just an
intuition or feeling for what it's like to be that way
noticing what comes alive in you
when there's no desire that is obscured
by the presence of desires
you
desires often come with a lot of baggage associated with it beliefs we have
aversions we have ideas about who we are and what we need
and all this baggage can obscure something deeper
to allow ourselves a chance to be free of desire
can allow for the wellsprings of a warm caring heart
can allow for compassion and love
can allow for a simple warmth and good will
for others
a warmth and goodwill which has no resemblance to ordinary desires
because it's not tied to me myself and mine
it's deeper more intimate within
then thoughts ideas and feelings of self
and perhaps in these last minutes of the sitting maybe you can intuit or imagine or feel
a place within which is not governed by desire
but which is a source for warmth and care and love where in a sense
nothing needs to happen
but where we can allow for that warmth and love and care the tenderness
without complicating it with shoulds and shouldn'ts anxieties about caring for ourselves
in the last minutes of this sitting perhaps to if you can
sit quietly with a sense of warm heartedness
tenderness care for the world
that maybe in a certain way is free of desire to do anything
has also a momentum a motivation
a wish that all beings be well
that others be happy have the opportunity to feel safe
have the opportunity to be peace at peace and to be free
and then as we get ready to end this sitting now maybe is a time for desire
and maybe your desire can be to contribute to that possibility
may your lit may you live your life to make this a better world for others
for everyone you and others
may you contribute to the happiness and welfare of all beings
so welcome now to the fourth talk on greed and
today's talk is going to be about composting greed or letting it become transformed
and it's not an original idea with me
sometimes in buddhism where this kind of idea exists sometimes seen as kind of more
advanced practice and because it's best not
to do it in a way that we get all too easily the old habits of mind
and habits of self are kind of come along and gets entangled in this practice of composting
greed and that's why having a strong foundation in mindfulness practice the basic
practice is really important something i tried to do a little bit yesterday
and um and to learn to have this you know really strong clear recognition of of desire of greed
of wanting of anything where there's a little bit of freedom little bit of
distancing or opening or in relationship to what's going on and
this clear recognition when it's practiced with vipassana often involves a kind of clear and clear
recognition of the details of experience rather than lumping it all together in one big
maybe amorphous idea of what something is we start seeing the comp components of
it the components of the body the bodily expressions the emotional aspects of it the motivational
aspects of it the cognitive aspects of it as each of them becomes more
in highlight and seen as distinct then the kind of amorphous hole doesn't
grab us as much and we don't get so reactive to it or caught in it or greedy about it and uh and we start
seeing the underlying kind of conditionality of it the underlying uh
changing nature of it in a very powerful way and so this is a core aspect of the
apostle practice something is tremendously valuable something to be uh to love and to care for and to
it's so liberating and sometimes it's a little bit like you
take what you want to take a really good look and really recognize what a bicycle is
and so you look at the bicycle and you get your tools out and you begin taking apart all the
pieces of the bicycle and separating those unscrewing everything and laying everything out in the ground
and so you can really see what a bicycle is and all the parts of it
and that's fascinating to see that maybe and but when you do so
that thing that was the bicycle no longer rolls it no longer works as a bicycle
in order to really kind of let a bicycle be a bicycle you don't take it apart you have to let
all the pieces be together and work kind of in harmony and then allow it to roll
so sometimes that's true also with our inner life and with desires and greed
sometimes if we kind of do this deeper kind of look of vipassana or if we get deeply concentrated and
bypass kind of the the desires the greed itself
then the rolling of the bicycle of desire of greed has been interrupted and sometimes
that's like a tremendous safety to do that to be caught and involved in greed can cause
so much damage to ourselves and to others and it's very stressful it's very alienating
it's disconnecting it's sometimes lends itself to an
assertiveness and aggressiveness that objectifies others or doesn't really see others as human
and bulldozes over people because our greater desires are more important than even other people's welfare it's a
horrible what can happen in this world in the in the in the assault of people's
desires and greed but if we learn how to have this clear
recognition learn how not to be involved in the greed not to be entangled with it
then we have the opportunity to compost it and what i mean by that is to is to
not be caught in it but also not interrupt it not interfere with it not not to go
deeply analytical not get concentrated so that it kind of changes the inner kind of landscape so
dramatically it's not there but rather to let the greed be
allow it to be there but and one way to allow to be there that's safe that kind
of protects us from getting caught up in its uh thoughts ideas its goals
is to feel it in the body and now that's why i call it composting it in the body
and and doing to do it so i said before this is an advanced practice
but sometimes it's not necessarily for only kind of more well matured practitioners
it's also for people who have no other option because the greed is so strong
that you know it's going to take over if we don't do something and maybe there's no access to you know
this deeper mindfulness that i talked about yesterday and so instead
just coming back to the body feeling it in the body grounding in the body over and over again and letting it kind
of move through in an embodied way feel the momentum feel the move
feel the urges and by grounding in the body
it does a number of things one thing is that it takes us away from the thoughts the ideas the
as the the hopes that exist in the mind that are often kind of what's compelling it
uh they're feeding it it also takes it a little bit away from uh the emotions just in and of itself
it allows whatever emotions are connected to the greed to be grounded in the physical
body here it's kind of like has a root it's in the present moment the body is always present also we start feeling it in the
body feeling the sensations the impulses of greed in the body
the body is kind of like a large but the the as we when we meditate with our
body the body is in some ways bigger than what we think of over our body it's kind of like it's lots of space in the body
and so to allow the momentum of greed and desire to course through the body kind of keep
opening space to it allowing it to be there and and this what i'm talking about now
is best done in meditation where you're committed to not moving
not acting on it you sit there and just let the greed course through your body the
feeling sensations of it and when you get out of the way of it this way
but also don't enact it don't get involved in it then there's a composting there's a
transformer there's a change that goes on that is kind of akin to um
i think of it as akin to um the way the body can be self-healing at times
that uh you know if you sometimes when we get sick sometimes if we injure ourselves if we
allow for the right conditions keep a wound clean or have a if we break our arm have a cast
on and have it things the bones lined up again then the body has an amazing way to find its way to
health and to healing and um and so uh same thing with emotions and
desires and greed greed is a little bit like being sick an illness and the system knows how to move
to health if we create the right conditions for it now if we
and one of the right conditions is to not enact it not be compelled by it to do anything
but also not to push it away or to to not allow it to move through and course
through our body and then as we do so it's kind of like we get out of the way and allow it to be
here then something begins to shift and change sometimes it just simply settles
uh sometimes it changes into something a little bit different and uh and there's like layers in our
inner life then we go through those layers so for example greed itself
in some circumstances might be a symptom of something deeper that's going on
inside of us and so as we do this composting this transforming allowing it to be there
that deeper thing begins to show itself that deeper thing begins to kind of
bubble up as well and that's much more important so for example some greed for example
might be a symptom of fear that we're really afraid of something
and the and we really want something because we think that's going to make us safe
or we might have uh really strong lust even sexual lust but if we look
underneath it there's a deep loneliness and that deep loneliness is looking desperately for something
that we think is going to fill and take care of it that's really impactfully powerful and
kind of like real assurance that we're not alone that someone connects to us and and so sexual engagement sometimes
is the ticket we think and um and to feel that deep the fear that might be there or the
loneliness that might be underneath greed or the anger that might be underneath it
there's sometimes a strong anger that propels us to want to do something maybe something harmful even
and um or there might as we kind of go through we go through these layers and so for example if there's fear there
might be underneath that fear a sense of vulnerability or tenderness
there might be a sense of hurt that we have or a deeper kind of quieter
fear that is doesn't really have an object of the fear but just kind of
exists there more existentially and as we go through and transform and allow these and allow
these in laozis then the the the transformation the composting begins happening
the movement towards health but it you know it often requires going through these
layers and discovering here and this idea that greed is just a
surface manifestation of something a symptom in a sense
and so don't act on the symptom don't kill the symptom it's just a messenger
but to kind of sit quietly allow it so we can hear more deeply see more
deeply what's really going on inside of us so we can connect more deeply or
allow the more deeper movements and revelations what's really happening here
show itself and and so there's a composting going on a
transformation going on and occasionally that transformation like something like desire and greed
is that greed is a kind of wanting something just like compassion is in buddhism
faith is a kind of desire for freedom and so as we get deeper and deeper down
we start finding that part of the transformation might be the discovery of a of a of an
appropriate desire beautiful that healthy desires that are really there at the base but
we've never figured out how to express it or live it or trust it so quickly the self and uh
kind of the ego ego comes into play that selfishness comes into play or the or
the care of protecting ourselves or the anxiety around things or that all the cultural beliefs
we have around self and others come into play that obscures the deep
beautiful kind of desires that compassion is or the movement towards liberation might be
so to compost and and how i know to compost when things are
strong is just keep returning to the body and uh and when they're when like greed is
strong then um it might keep coming back it might have thoughts as part of it
we just allow all of it just to be there um but it's kind of like come back be here
with it and then be here with it and just keep coming back keep coming back it's like you're
turning over the compost pile so that it can keep burning properly come decomposing
you're turning yourself over just coming back feeling the body feeling the body feeling the body and if
you keep doing that that is a protection against getting involved and getting involved in the
thoughts the ideas getting involved in the desires just don't get involved stay here stay here and if what i said
today doesn't make sense to you or is confusing then maybe just ignore
what i said maybe this is a kind of i said it's a little bit of an advanced practice
and maybe it'll become clearer as you trust the basic practice of mindfulness it's so powerful so effective so
useful and meaningful trust it and when the time comes you might get some sense of what i'm talking about when i talk
about composting so thank you very much