so good morning and i think i have the technology set up a
little more complicated today
so
we're going to be working with the breathing that's what the anapanasati is where
the simple rhythm of breathing in and breathing out is used as the
through line as the thread that goes through uh all our experience it's kind of like
the the um the beat of the song that's always there or it's the
kind of like the ballast of a boat that keeps the boat steady it's a the breathing is a
the rhythm of breathing and the coming and going of breathing so can support the mind to both have
develop a stability and also not to hold on to anything
and in fact this part of the stability of the mind it comes maybe seems like a
paradox comes from not holding on to anything it's when holding on
to things being preoccupied being churning away ruminating on things that
the mind becomes more unstable because it has an unstable basis on the
unstable foundation and um and so the rhythm of breathing
coming and going it's a con there is continuity there there's a constancy there that supports
us it's always there for us and because the inhale disappears the exhale disappears
it's like a wave like coming and going it's you can't really hold on to the
breathing and so it both provides us with this constancy this stability
and a kind of massage or support to not get caught in anything we still might have thoughts there might
be sensations all kinds of things might happen and we can be aware of them but with the
breathing kind of at the center or the breathing as support as a foundation
it comes and goes they it's a little more difficult to mind get fixated
or caught on its preoccupations and whatever is going on the emotions that are happening
and so it can be very it can be a gentling effect it can be a nurturing effect it can have a
tranquilizing effect to do this and for this meditation i'd like to
offer you something a little bit extra to pay attention to with the breathing
particular quality of it and that is the transition between breathing out and breathing in
the transition between breathing in and breathing out
and this is a place where
um just a little extra attention to and
there's different things that might happen there and so this is where you can literally pay attention to how it is for you
and it might change over time that on the in that uh the end of the out uh
exhale there might be just a very s
automatic quick automatic transition between breathing out and
breathing in it's just just boom boom breathe out and then immediately the in-breath begins
and that can be noticed how it happens one happens immediately after the other
it might be a the transition might be not so quick it might feel more like
it's gradual the exhale gradually ends and the inhale gradually begins
or it might feel like there's a sense a pause between the exhale
and then the beginning of the inhale and each of these has its advantages each of
these is part of the you know you know part of what we can notice but there's something about
noticing that transition in a relaxed and open way without expectation
that completes the cycle of attention of breathing in and breathing out and so um
and so um we'll bring some careful a gentle attention to this as we go
through the breathing so to take a comfortable
alert posture and
gently close your eyes
and perhaps taking a few long slow deep breaths full breaths three quarters
full and then as you exhale a little longer
exhale than you would just on your own
breathing in deeply deeply and then relaxing on the exhale
releasing and letting go
letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale go through the little almost like a
ritual of relaxing the body
and as you relax see if you can feel
some quality of tranquility or peacefulness in the area that you
relaxed so as you exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
around the eyes
the cheeks jaw
and if it's you're able to relax those
muscles is there any evidence any little even partial sense of tranquility
as part of that
then as you exhale to soften the shoulders release the
shoulders
and as the shoulders relax in the shoulders is there any sense of
greater calmness or tranquility
as you exhale relaxing the chest
the area around your heart
and even if there's agitation in that part of your body if you're able to relax a little bit or
soften are there any even hints of tranquility calmness
and then on the exhale relaxing the
belly letting the belly hang forward or
settle down deeper into
sometimes when we exhale sometimes when we relax the belly
they can also support a relaxation of
other areas of the body and you might as you exhale both relax
the belly and see if you can relax at the same time
release the shoulders the hands
arms
release the whole body
and then feel is there any physical tranquility or calmness
that you can pick up in your body as a whole
even if you do feel some thing opposite to calmness
see if you can be attuned to that which does feel tranquil and calm
and as you exhale relax with that calmness
and then becoming more centered on the experience of breathing
and in relationship to breathing itself is there any tranquility or calmness
or maybe around the experience of breathing underneath it behind it
some feeling of calm or peace
that's there associated with the breathing
and as you breathe breathe with that calmness breathe with the tranquility
and very calmly without thinking about it too much
appreciate or notice how the physical experience of inhaling is different
than the experience of exhaling
and then letting go of noticing the difference between them
let the inhale just be the inhale allow the exhale to just be the exhale
as if it's the only thing that's here
and notice as you inhale the inhale inhale has an
end an end that fades away or an end which
comes abruptly and don't just notice and
feel the physical experience of that ending of the inhale
and then observe the transition to exhaling
maybe a little bit like you're
driving in a car and along a flat road and then there
comes a little hill a little bump that you gently lift up and then over the crest and you
go down kind of ride
the end of the inhale to the beginning of the exhale the
releasing
and then the same thing for the end of the exhale beginning of the inhale
maybe like driving along and there's a gentle dip in the road and the cars goes into
the dip and then slowly comes up
or maybe the transitions are sudden almost like a switch
that goes on and off switching from inhale to exhale exhale to inhale
both ways are fine gently observe how it is for you
perhaps in doing this careful sensing observing
maybe you can feel a quiet intimacy with the experience
of breathing
feeling whatever calmness or tranquility that's here
a tranquility that allows breathing to be as it is
comfortable or uncomfortable
but you just follow along in this rhythm
of breathing
seeing if you can feel any tranquility or calmness
associated with any part of the
breathing
and perhaps you can notice any calmness might be there in the transition between
breathing in and out between out and in
a calmness that's closely related to allowing
allowing that transition to do itself
with an intimacy with awareness breathing in breathing out
calmly receive the inhale
in the body
calmly release the exhale
and ride along in the transitions between these
a continuous intimacy tranquility
with your awareness of breathing
if you find yourself involved in thinking
what happens to your thinking when you place the rhythm of breathing
back in the middle of your experience
and for these few minutes we have together trust your breathing
more than you trust your thinking
center yourself on breathing in the body
releasing into tranquility as you exhale
receiving the inhale in your calmness as you breathe in
[Music]
so
and before bringing this to an end
scan through your body to notice what is it and where in your
body is there some tranquility calmness
even if there's places that are agitated notice the places that are calm or quiet
for a few minutes here breathe with that tranquility breathe through it
breathe along with
tranquility calmness
peacefulness
as if it's a gentle vapor that you can
blow through your body spread outwards throughout your whole
body as you breathe
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
perhaps in a world that's so agitated
our calmness
can be so that we don't fuel that agitation further
may it be that we don't add to people's anxiety
may it be that we don't contribute to restlessness
maybe that we don't reinforce
agitation of any kind
and may it be that whatever goodness benefit that we received from this
sitting may we dedicate it
to the benefit of others
may in our calmness may our benefits and merit
spread out across the lands so that all beings be happy
so that all beings might be safe
so that all beings might be peaceful
so that all beings might be free
may all being everywhere be free of all that oppresses
may all beings be happy
so
uh
in these 16 stages 16 steps of mindfulness of
breathing as i've said that they are organized in
groups of four called tetrads and that the last step in each tetrad
the instructions are has to do with something in the family of letting go
or of freedom or of release whatever your language that you like to think of
that is and uh in step four
it's uh calming the bodily formations
sometimes it's translated as tranquilizing and i love the word tranquil but
tranquilizing i associate with something you do with animals or something
so it doesn't really evoke a positive obviously positive response for me
and and but you know bringing about tranquility of
the body in the eighth step it's calming relaxing
tranquilizing the mental formations the mind we'll see in a while that in the
12th step it's um freedom release releasing the mind
freeing the mind and then in the final step of the 16 steps number 16
it's something called relinquishment which maybe it's a big word that doesn't really inspire so much
but it involves a real qualitative transformative experience of freedom of
liberation and so the movement towards greater and greater freedom
begins with this simple thing of relaxing the body and uh it's kind of beginning to learn
the lesson of freedom it's beginning to have a reference point for the goodness of what it's like to
not be tense not be caught and i think for many people it's a little bit more accessible this
physical relaxation than it is full-blown liberation but we're beginning to get a
little taste of it and it's embody taste of it and
most people don't associate you know just simple physical relaxation with buddhist liberation but maybe
there's um the liberation is kind of such a matter of fact thing it's uh it's not
once you the greater liberation we have the more it just seems seen as
i don't know if ordinary is the right word but not such a
unusual thing or not such a
otherworldly thing in a sense it's uh it's just a very profound experience of
what we're beginning to experience as we begin to relax the body as we begin to relax as we begin to
experience a physical tranquility so in so you know as you know those of you
following along that i give a lot of emphasis on relaxing at the beginning of the body
the beginning of the meditation and now relaxing
you know it's maybe a little bit too s limited in describing the sense of
tranquility that comes that can come as we continue deeper and deeper into this anapanasati
but looking for tranquility looking for the calmness or the serenity that can exist
in our practice is said to be the support for greater tranquility we're not making
calmness or tranquility the be-all and end-all but it's a wonderful foundation that
begins to soften the hard hardness of the heart
the hardnesses of the mind the word stuck and things don't move tranquility begins to create a sense of
safety inner safety where things begin to release more and more and we're not looking towards you know i
like the word tranquility more than calmness in my use of the words because calmness
can lend itself to the idea of becoming too calm so calm that you fall asleep and my vocabulary tranquility has an
alertness to it and the tranquility is not just calm
but it's also kind of a harmonious energy kind of energetics and so this calm kind of
aliveness a tranquil aliveness that can be here an embodied way
so i say all this as a way to encourage you to begin appreciating the in the influence that
relaxation has that in your daily life as you go about if there are times when you you notice
your shoulders relax your belly relaxes you sit down at the end of a long day
and you finally let down all your preoccupations and drive and
you know momentum that you have and you feel more relaxed
see if you can appreciate the the influence that has on you and see if you can maybe begin feel uh some
of the initial feelings of a certain kind of freedom if some kind of release
a certain kind of no longer being limited or bound or caught in something feel feel what it's like
physically begin to appreciate the small little movements of freedom that can be here and as you
get a hang of it you might find that there's actually a lot more little movements of freedom
little movements of not being caught that are happening all along and um and that may be often so easy to
overlook because we're it's not valued particularly other things getting something done is
might be more valuable but there might be a very a lot of little movements of of just kind of oh that's great you
might step out of your house after a rainstorm and the rain has passed the sun has come out
and something inside of you just kind of releases um in that feeling of just being in the
sun being outdoors in the fresh air and so what is that influence what's
that effect on you and the body to be there and and to appreciate it don't hang on to it
don't you know get too complicated around it but just kind of start feeling
the little movements of freedom little movements of release of relaxation of tranquility
of peacefulness that seems to emanate from the movements of relaxation of ease that
happen and the more we start recognizing this in daily life and
meditation in different places it reinforces that movement it
reinforces the value of not being tense it enforces the value of not being
caught up in preoccupations or driven or or or
bracing ourselves since things or closing down or trying to run away from things it reinforces it kind of kind of begins
to question those movements of mind those act ways in which we are which are the opposite of freedom and to do that
in the small areas of your life ordinary things
is a wonderful stepping stone that supports us finding it deeper and further further
along until the deeper areas of letting go of freedom that anapanasathi
is taking taking us to become more natural more accessible
more understandable because of what we've kind of
really taken in earlier on in the practice so not just simply in meditation to
experience this but in other times of the day as well begin you know if you really want this anapanasati to really
deepen deep deeper deep go deeper and deeper in it this movement towards freedom
can be called it can become a a a
an ongoing sensitivity and ongoing attention
that we have um and it's not being self-preoccupied to do this it's i hope
you don't think it's selfish because the freedom is kind of beginning to turn ourselves inside out
so that we're actually in the freedom we are i think kind of more easily naturally
going to be more sensitive more caring for the world around us
so tranquility letting go release relaxation
calmness all kind of or all ways they're connected to this
the family of experiences of movements
uh that's connected to liberation and um and to become a connoisseur of
this become a sensitive to it be informed by it to be inspired by it to be in touch
with it regularly maybe even so it becomes a little bit of a habit
so they can grow and develop in you and uh so that may this practice
that we do lead you to greater and greater experiences of freedom
and in doing so may it be for your delight so thank you so much for today and
we'll continue this tomorrow