so welcome welcome to your meditation and our meditation
together and um
as a beginning now one of the concepts that i think is a synonym
almost a synonym for mindfulness is honesty and that in particular it's
honesty with oneself and there's a kind of a categorical statement that i
like i think i don't prefer not having categorical statements but
one that i like is that it's never okay to lie to oneself and so when we sit in
meditation and being mindful of our experience it is an exercise in honestly
recognizing what is happening and whereas many other times the
experience is pretty mundane you know the comings and goings
of breathing uh it is a training and just recognizing honestly what's happening
now directly here now and there are times when
it's difficult to see what's inside and sometimes self-knowledge is not good
news and so to be honest about that so the mindfulness practice involves
being honest but then we want to do that in a wholesome way in a skillful way
always the analysis in buddhism is how to do something wholesomely or skillfully and in a way that's
beneficial and healthy and so it's not simply being honest but
to do so in a way that is generous that is caring that is non-afflictive doesn't cause any harm
whatsoever it doesn't debilitate us or hurt us that
we the self-criticism or something but something that's open and kind and aware and
generous in its presence oh this is how it is and so this combination of
sitting in honesty can be helpful idea because it might
help you to step back from the immediacy of what's happening in terms of you know what you're directly thinking is happening
to seeing a little bit the bigger picture of your relationship and your reactivity your context of
what's happening to you as you're with your breathing as you're with your your body or your emotions or
even your thoughts oh this is how it is for me and uh and it's equally important
how we have that honesty how we do the mindfulness it is as it is to be mindful
and so we try to do it wholesomely or skillfully so
to begin to assume a meditative posture and
and then gently close your eyes
and to
take a few long slow deep breaths
kind of breathing into the very center of your being
including it all from the center
outwards
breathing in and breathing out and as you exhale to relax
settling into what is here for you
and then to let your breathing return to normal and take a few moments to honestly
recognize what's here for you how are you right now and
and to do that recognition in a wholesome way neither being for or against the
experience neither being celebratory or
upset about what it is just a simple honest recognition this is how it is now
and as you exhale relaxing all the places in the body that's easy
to soften without losing
a posture that is alert
if you're sitting upright not giving up a posture which is energetic
relaxing the shoulders especially
relaxing the belly sometimes relaxing the belly if you do it kind of
a wide relaxation that allows relaxation
all over the lower torso
even the smaller the back
and then settling in with your breathing
this is
and perhaps sensing and feeling the inhales and exhales as if your
awareness is a soft feather that gently
brushes against the body that's breathing
so there's a care and a delicacy
sensing experiencing the body breathing
and softening relaxing the thinking mind
quieting your thinking with the idea that the simple
mindfulness simple recognition and honesty is meant to be simple it's meant to be
kind of an honesty and recognition with what is obvious
no need to go digging and searching
we allow things to show themselves more clearly over time
but a simple recognition of how we are
and within it all to be breathing and
perhaps the simplicity of breathing supports you and not getting entangled
or caught up in the experience so there can be a wholesome skillful
attention to what is simple light
soft quiet breathing in
and breathing out
you
all right
taking a moment or two to step back
and check in with yourself how are you
and if you were going to answer that question as honestly and deeply as you could
what would be what would be the honest answer
and i associate honesty with a recognition that is
freeing that is relaxing opening
the very simple direct recognition of how we are
and then with that recognition perhaps it's best to return to breathing
maybe breathing with how you are breathing through it
or maybe the recognition of how we are supports us to return to breathing
and a little bit more of a fuller
engaged way settled
you
and then coming to the end of the setting
to again recognize how you are
and is their way of doing that honestly where it's meaningful that it's an
honest recognition of how you are
that's connecting maybe settles you or maybe
opens you
maybe adds some embodiment to your sense of being a fullness
and perhaps awakens a little self-care
good will and kindness to yourself a willingness to see yourself
through the eyes of kindness love
and then turn turning the gaze outward out into the world
and to be quiet and still internally but gaze upon the world
kindly gaze upon the world
maybe with the imagination that others have the potential to be
happy and well and to wish that for them
and to dedicate the goodness the value the benefits from this
meditation for their sake
may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
so good morning everyone and good day and today we're continuing with
the theme of kusala the pali word for either translated usually is either
wholesome or skillful
and partly what's defined as wholesome and skillful
is that which is non-afflictive meaning not doesn't cause harm and
doesn't cause pain and that combination of neither harm nor pain because some things are painful you
know like i'm today i'm going to the dentist and i think it's going to be a little painful
but it's not harmful it's actually beneficial so the things that are beneficial and bring
happiness or those things which are wholesome and these things come together very nicely
in a in a teaching the buddha gave to his son
the buddha had one child a son named rahula and he was
apparently joined his father lived with his father from the time he was about seven onwards i don't know what living
with his father meant when his father was a monk but you know in the he lived in the
monastic world with his father and was a novice monk at the age of seven
and um and this particular story seems to be um um
seems to be when the son was a teenager a young teenager
so maybe 13 or 14. and no no actually i'm sorry i'm confusing two stories so
was uh when when the son was supposed to be quite young maybe soon after he was became a novice living with his father
seven eight years old and um and it seems that uh
uh he was caught telling a lie and uh the buddha then sat him down and
said uh something like the the religious life the monastic life of
someone who tells a deliberate lie is about as valuable as the amount of
water left in this bowl of mine my eating bowl it turns it upside down after having cleaned it and
all whatever water is left in there kind of drips out and it you know so it's a kind of a
maybe somewhat indirect way to say to a young child that what he did was not val you know was
counterproductive or not good and then and then at some point he goes
on and tells his son the criteria for how to know what to
do physically with the body what what to say and even what to think and it
involves a reflection and so he begins the buddha begins by saying to his son
and what's the purpose of a mirror and the sun says it's for reflection
and the same way this is how you should reflect on yourself so this is a way to be a mirror for
yourself to really see what's going on and so it helped you guide you in deciding what you're going to do
so here is an act of attention of mindfulness not just for the sake of mindfulness but
mindfulness for the purpose of knowing how to act in the world what to what to say and do and even to think
and uh so in some ways this teaching that he gives his son maybe could be seen as being
simple teachings for a seven eight year old but uh there's a tendency in many buddhists
teach some buddhist teachers i know to really including myself to see this as a
this simple teaching is kind of encapsulate very clearly the thrust of the buddhist teachings the
center of it this is what he had to say to his son in a very simple way that all the rest
of the buddha's teachings in buddhism can flow from this in a very important way
so zoe so this is how he tells his son to
consider his his actions an action with the body
should be done after repeated reflection
action by speech should be done after repeated reflection and action by mind should be done after
repeated reflection in this way rahula
when you wish to do an action with a body you should reflect upon the same bodily
action thus would this action that i wish to do with the
body lead to my own affliction or to the affliction of others
or to the affliction of both and i think the word affliction here could uh equally uh be harm
does it lead to your harm someone else's harm or to both of your arm is it an
unwholesome bodily action with painful consequences with painful results when
you reflect if you know this action that i wish to do with a body would lead to my own affliction or to
the affliction of others or to the affliction of both it is an unwholesome bodily action with painful consequences
with painful results then you definitively should not do such an
action with the body but when you reflect if you know this action
that i wish to do with the body would not lead to my affliction or to the affliction of others or to the
affliction of both it is a wholesome bodily action with happy consequences with happy results
then you may do such an action with the body and then he goes on to say the same
thing for acts of speech and also acts of the mind
so even how we think there's a movement to reflect how i'm thinking right now the attitude
i have the bias i have the the desires i have the is this
um afflictive is it harmful to me to someone else or to both of us
is it unwholesome unskillful and does it lead to
pain to suffering and if it doesn't if it leads to what's
beneficial if it leads to what's wholesome if it leads to what's uh to happiness then uh go ahead and do it
and so that's what he says what you should do before you do something so this before doing
something reflect on it best you can while you're doing it
you should reflect he goes on to say same thing but you should also reflect while you're doing it have some self-awareness as you're doing something
and while you're doing it if you find out that it's afflictive and unwholesome then stop doing it if it's not then keep
doing it and the value of checking in while we're doing something
is we get more information about the situation uh we don't always know ahead of time
the impact our words our actions are going to have and so um only in the middle of doing something
do we say oh wait a minute i didn't realize that situation is different than what i thought
and actually for me to say this or do this right now is harmful to me or harmful to others or
something like that so to continue the reflection while we're doing and the buddha then goes on to tell his
son when you finish doing something to also be reflective about it
and same way and is what i did
harmful unwholesome painful if it is and it's interesting here he
says if you have caused harm this way then you should go find a wise person
that you know and let them know what you did in other words be accountable for it
and now there's something about letting someone else know what you did i think that uh really is a
real wonderful step of honesty and it's a way of uh
kind of work through something or to acknowledge it fully and to really begin the movement of no
longer being behind that no longer easily slipping into doing that kind of behavior again
because now it's known by someone else and so it's a little bit more i think it's more
likely your own mind is going to be a little more attentive and careful to not do something that you don't want
to do but you have the support of someone else so here the buddha is teaching a
reflective life that so mindfulness here being in the
present moment seeing what's going on is a is support for living a considerate
life and um and sometimes it might seem that uh to do so is a lot of work um you know
adding this whole layer of self-reflection about it or or self-reflection kind of
can slide into being self-conscious and self-critical and negative ways but the that's why
that third category to pay attention to what you're doing in your mind is it
harmful is it unwholesome is it painful if it is stop doing it so we are there's
a self-corrective mechanism in mindfulness where the very way in which we're mindful or reflective or
tracking yourself what's going on the way we do it should be beneficial the way we do it
should hopefully bring some well-being and happiness so it needs to be a movement of reflection which
is not critical it's not heavy it's not stressful to do but one
that has a light touch is generous to ourselves is kind to
ourselves is it has a nice feeling kind of like we're our own best friend
who's uh supporting us and and helping us see ourselves in a better light and and
wants the best for us and so to have your own best friend inside
that wants the best for you that cares for you and supports you and
who in a certain kind of way is not you know it's always going to see you in a positive light
but not let you get away with doing things which are harmful or unwholesome or
painful or cause of suffering so here we see this uh you know
inaction the practice of working with what's skillful unskillful wholesome and unwholesome
and what's interesting here one thing i find interesting these are not uh um commandments
of what you should with the things you should and should not do
they are what you should investigate how you should investigate
principles for finding out for yourself what is appropriate not appropriate
not external kind of rules that of morality or something
so so we see as wholesome and unwholesome
skillful and unskillful as being a valuable part of this buddha's teachings and i see on the chat
there someone asks where this is from and it's uh again and also in the middle
length discourses and it's uh it teachings to rahula
and it's um i think it's uh discourse number 61 in there so thank you and
we have one more day tomorrow to talk about this topic and um i appreciate the opportunity
thank you