so
before we move into the talk
i would like to make a few announcements
and first
is that
that on friday i said i would post we
would post
some of the things that i read last week
the simile for the
jhanas for the states of absorption
samadhi
and also i posted the little passage
from the buddha's teachings
with the 16 steps of anapanasati
and the easy place to find that is at
on imc's homepage on the home page
there's a little
in the bottom right corner in what's new
section and in there there's a little
line for reflections from gil
and in there that's where you'll find
those
passages and
and the other is that next week so
starting from next monday
the plan is to have for one week have
these early morning sittings
be 45 minutes meditation be 45 minutes
rather than 30 minutes
and we'll start 15 minutes early so
we'll start at
you know whatever time your time zone is
15 minutes before the hour
in california at 6 45
and um you're welcome to join at 7 if
that early time doesn't work for you
just that you know you should probably
um
tiptoe into the meditation room when you
when you join us
and um and the reason for this
longer sitting is i think that it would
be after all this time of sitting some
of you've been sitting for months this
way with me in the morning
i feel like we're kind of deepening and
going further
and to be able to sit longer is one of
the ways to
experience more the benefits of this
path to kind of let it unfold more
deeply in the course of of the sitting
so we'll try it next week and maybe in a
few weeks we'll do it again
next time i do a retreat
so
so the uh the ana panasati practice
involves 16 steps of mindfulness of
breathing in and mindfulness of
breathing out
and the eighth step between the eighth
and ninth there's kind of a transition
that goes on and the transition is we go
into the ninth
we we're staying in the first eight aid
we're still staying very closely in
intimately involved
with our embodied experience
and and then that's always a foundation
for the
the second eighth but now we're in the
second eighth we're going to open up
more to the
uh realm of experience which maybe is
not so
directly related to the body it's a work
related to the mind
and and so we're still in this
body section um of the first half
and so in the first tetrad
it's about just learning to develop a
continuity
with the breathing and beginning to
experience and sense the body
and the and especially how the body is
activated by the mind
the tensions of the body and to learn to
relax that
as that relaxes it frees up a good kind
of energy in the body
and as the concentration deepens it also
awakens a kind of um
meditative joy and happiness well-being
that comes with calmness subtleness uh
contentment that comes just sitting here
and being here
and with that as a foundation certain
kind of meditative well-being
it's only then that this instructions
then
is opens up to becoming aware
of
becoming aware of
aspects of the mind and uh
so in the step seven the instructions
are breathing in
one experiences the
mental formation breathing out
one experiences the mental formation
so a few things about this the word
experience
the poly word for it as maybe the
english does
has a lot to do with the uh the physical
direct experience of the sensation
and it's almost like this word that's
translated as experience
could be translated as one senses
when senses for oneself
the sensations of the mind of the mental
formation
and here it's a singular the mental
so it's not necessarily going and
looking at the detail little detailed
aspects of
the mental formation but the whole
the whole thing somehow how it's
experienced
so the mental formation are
those experiences associated with the
mind mental activity
that we can sense and feel so it's the
mental activity
that has some impact
on the body that senses
i think of sensation as being very much
part of the body
and and so the sensations of the mind
also
so it could be for example something is
clearly physical
that if we're afraid our shoulders might
be up it may be tense and tight
and that's a physical formation but if
our
if we're if we're afraid and our mind
feels contracted
feels small or tight that's the mental
formations the mental
expression of the fear
of that activated state so it's feeling
the mental activity
so if particularly associated with
thinking
if we're thinking very intensely we
might feel it physically as
you know maybe the forehead is all
bunched up and
scrunched together and that would be the
bodily formation
but if you look kind of more deeply into
the area around where we're thinking
if we think in the area of the brain for
example you might feel that kind of
behind the forehead
in this in the area of the brain that's
not particularly associated with muscles
that are
tightened up there's still sensations
there's might be a feeling of
contraction there might be a headache
there might be
agitation there might be a sense of
pressure or pushing they might sometimes
i feel like there's a magnetic
pull gravitational pull
for me towards thinking or thinking
towards me
and there's something that feels like a
pull or
a tug going on that's
in relationship to the thoughts there's
a leaning in
in the mind sometimes the center of
gravity of my thinking
is a little bit ahead of my body
somehow i'm like i'm leaning forward
into the future a little bit
so it's possible to start feeling
something that
resembles or is sensation like
associated with the mental activity we
do
and that's those are the called mental
the mental formations
the mental activities that we can feel
and um and so then um
the um so what's interesting here
is a variety of things is certainly we
have a lot of mental activity let's look
at thinking for example
thinking is a mental activity and the
instructions here are to
feel that physical the kind of the
physical experience of thinking
and and it's only feeling the feeling it
it's not thinking better or
understanding what we're thinking or
analyzing what we're thinking
it's not about recognizing even what
we're thinking
it's simply recognizing the physicality
or the sensation level
of the thinking itself so
in the shorthand i like to think of this
as feeling the
the um the thinking muscle
and um and so the ways in which we feel
i'm thinking it feels uh energetic or
tight or constricted
or there's pressure or there's a hurry
or there's a kind of
low energy there's sometimes it feels
swampy in the mind it can't
lack of clarity there's um uh
so so a whole realm of things that are
how it feels for us as opposed to what
it's about
and partly this is a wonderful support
and aid
to not get caught up with permission
during meditation
to not have to fix our thoughts fix the
world
understand what's going on analyze
what's going on
we're here we're only asked to feel it
and feel an aspect of what the mind is
doing the mind is very important
but a particular aspect which is the
sensation level of it
so we're connected to it but we're not
being pulled into the storyline in a
sense
and so and and we're trying to do this
based on the foundation of the of
um step
five and six which is feeling this
sense of well-being so until we have
some feeling of well-being
then we don't really start actively
taking in
what is going on in the mind what the
mental activity is about
perhaps so that there's a container
there's a context of well-being
for looking at an area of our life which
is often quite difficult
and so we're not you know trying to do a
spiritual bypass we're not trying to
avoid
our inner suffering or challenges that
we have
but maybe we're touching it with um
a breath with an awareness with a
with emotions that are supportive
that have a goodness to them that have a
calmness or
kindness in them that have a kind of
generosity to them
some something like that it's on the
building on the foundation of what's
been done earlier
in these these steps of mindfulness of
breathing
and so the context for becoming now
aware of the mental activity
is one of kindness of goodwill
or even joy
it's one of the great maybe peridot
wonderful paradoxes
when i first discovered it that one can
exp one can experience
suffering in oneself and suffering in
the world
and at the same time have a lot of joy
and in fact my ability to go deeply into
the practice of vipassana
where there are times we experience a
lot of our personal suffering
was it was supported by having
cultivated meditative joy
that could hold that suffering so it
isn't one or the other
but it can be both there and all this
involves a disidentification from
being locked in or overly preoccupied
with what we're thinking and what we're
emoting and doing like that
so that we can just hold it and be
present for it in a different way than
we usually are
and that's one of the opportunities here
with uh
with with um
this anapanasati is mindfulness of
breathing
so breathing in one experiences
the mental formation one isn't even
trying to parse out the details of it
just the whole gestalt the global
feeling the sensations of what they're
going on in the mind
breathing out one experience of the
mental formation and and then because
we're breathing in and breathing out
this is again like a support for not
getting wrapped up in not being caught
by
as long as the breathing stays relaxed
and smooth we tend to have a more
open freer relationship to what we're
including
in that awareness to what we're
accompanying with the breathing
so i hope that makes sense uh and we'll
do more of this over the next few days
so if it didn't make full sense don't
worry about it too much and
and just maybe there's just enough that
when i go on for the next days and
become clearer
so so for now
maybe you can spend the day this next 24
hours
reflecting practicing this idea of
accompaniment
that we're accompanying things we're
accompanying ourselves
we're accompanying our hearts our minds
and we're accompanying other people
what does that mean to be a companion
that way
so thank you and i look forward to
tomorrow