so warm greetings everyone happy to have you all here and
um before the pandemic we used to broadcast these sunday morning talks on youtube but i never thought about the
people on youtube but now i do so now clearly
they're right there where the camera is
so thank you for those of you logging in today
so um the topic that i want to talk about today is time
it's been on my mind lately and uh
i want to tell you a story from my time at the monastery
i was the the kitchen manager i guess that
and uh so i was like the person most responsible for the production of the
food and the meals and there was a crew of
anywhere from maybe four to
sometimes ten depending on the time of the year that i supervised
and but during the retreat time we had three months of retreats
and at that time uh in zen things are highly choreographed
the schedule is really clear and set
uh it's kind of like time is one of the teachers in his end monastery because you have to kind of do things on time
and and also you have to stop on time one of the great challenges was
we'd have this 15-minute cleaning period breaking the grounds or sweeping or doing something
and when the bell rang to end it you couldn't just keep doing it to
finish the job when the time to end happened you were supposed to stop
and then it took a training people to learn it's okay to stop and next day you could do it some more
so anyways everything's choreographed on time and so one of the things that was uh was that it was meals
and meals basically had to be served up in the meditation hall
by them at the minute that it was supposed to be there because there was saw this ritual beforehand
and so the ritual people are chanting and bowing and doing all this stuff and then sitting there and sitting in
meditation hall you know just for the meal to come and so in order for all to go smoothly you know
the meal had to be there right on time so i don't i don't remember exactly when
lunch was but maybe we the food had to be ready and
at the door of the meditation hall it's something like 12 15 or 12 20.
and then we had us and it was kind of you know hectic to get everything ready
but then one of the rules of one of the practices of the monastery
when you worked in the kitchen at noon exactly at 12 o'clock everyone had this all the cooks had to stop what
they were doing go in front of the kitchen altar and chant the heart sutra chant this
text and uh i would regularly since i was
supervising you know like be aghast no
we're never gonna get done we have all the stuff to do and just like 15 minutes before supposed to be served up no
and uh but you had to do it so which had the heart suit drop and always when we finished chanting
there was more time to get it done without fail and we you know we always
the meal was always ready but somehow the the sense of time
for me was very much tied up in how busy my mind was how much my mind was concerned with all
the things and the desires and the complications and my mind was crowded
and somehow that crowded impulse of the mind the pressure of the mind
you know i had a very different feeling about time then after chanting my mind got calm and
settled and there was more space in my mind more calm in my mind
and they just seemed like oh yeah we have time and somehow i don't know if we worked naturally faster or just it was
all an illusion in my mind but but we always had time so
in the years since then there have been times when i feel like i'm running out of time i'm too hectic too much to do
what am i going to do and don't know which foot to stand on because there's so much to do and i learned that if that happens
i just do one more thing and uh that seems impossible right which
is sit down to meditate and i'll meditate for 10 minutes and then when i come up suddenly oh
there's time i'll do this now and i'm still here and i've survived
and um so it always works out it's remarkable to do this
but i had no one waiting for me so it wasn't like you know you know i took the 10 minutes when
people are already up in the car ready for me to come you know that wouldn't make sense
but so time the sense of time our relationship time uh as a is a fascinating topic an
important topic because a lot of suffering that people have is directly or indirectly connected to
the topic of time and if we consider a little bit the nature of time
and how we will how we live in time and and often in subconscious ways
unconscious ways we'll start seeing our life in a different way
some people are time poor impoverished in time
because time is constantly slipping away they're running out of time they didn't have enough time so they ran out of time
for whatever they had to do or their time has deadlines and things you know and so
to have to finish before a certain time and uh and people are struggling with
these notions about time and part of it is the nature of in the industrial society when things
became started getting regimented and organized that people started to have to show up at
these factories at a particular time and and had to
have teams of people had to kind of be organized shifts and all kinds of things
and then with the industrial form kind of idea of scheduled time
there arose the idea of school time my understanding is that school time was
kind of modeled on the kind of what happened in factories and so then school time became very regime
originated i guess people didn't go to a lot of people didn't go to school before that or education happened in a different way
there was not so time centric you know and um
i remember when in high school the bell rang and leave the classroom and it was just like
this sea of humanity in the hallway you know jostling for their way to the next classroom and
but if you left the classrooms to go somewhere during class it was really peaceful in the hallways but you know
this this rhythm of the temporal rhythm that we were living and then that was
and uh and i don't know you know nowadays zen monasteries japan and america that are
very time centric i don't know if that was always the case i don't know when that started
the in the ancient times in zen
they knew when to end the morning meditation when the person who could see the bell
could look at their palm and see the lines in their pawn so that's a kind of a different
different kind of time than waiting for the clock to you know
clock hands to be in a certain position so you know so we've kind of lived in
time and the other day i was reading about um you know parts of our society now
are are running on nanoseconds you know the partial nanoseconds are so
the gps devices we many of us use right because many of us kind of depend on gps
devices gps devices with these satellites that are 12 000 miles
above the earth there so every day there's a time correction
because this nanosecond difference between those satellites the satellites of the time and the satellites and the
time that we live in and is all it needs to be in order for their measurements all work
has to be exactly the same time um and so these you know nanoseconds
partial point 10 nanoseconds or something the def of time difference has to be
corrected for 100 nanoseconds
well let's come down it's come down to that yeah i don't think in the time of the buddha they he thought much about
nanoseconds he had to worry about it so it's kind of remarkable but it's also
remarkable that i think that just in my lifetime how much time has become more and more of a
pressing thing an issue and an event and
that we live by and so it's easy to imagine that we become time poor we don't have enough
fine time and we wish we had more time
and some of it is that uh there's so much available to us and there's a kind of hunger for it and expectation we
should be able to get to everything that's made available to us
i still remember fondly all kinds of you know times in my life when i was young
of um looking back at it now
there was no internet there was no cell phones what did i do
you know you know i just wouldn't you know i'd go the whole day without checking for a
message on my phone is that legal or possible you know so but you know i
remember i have happy memories now i didn't think about it then but now uh
these many years later i actually have a visceral memory of walking around san francisco
with lots of time and uh the streets being compared to other traffic now
being much more spacious the things that you know the whole feeling of the city has
changed and um and that was one of the great values of
the monastery that all the different monasteries and retreat centers i was at i've been at
is how the the relationship to chime time changes so erratically
so that there's no time pressure very little time pressure even though there's crooks have to be
had things on time anyway so there was also lots of space lots of time
and there wasn't so much to do you know you weren't supposed to you know you'd have to check the internet and news and
and uh my kids watch tv programs on their their
computer and i'm just amazed how many there seems to be
i mean it's like you could spend your life watching new tv programs and not get to them all
that would be a sad life wouldn't it if you didn't get to get to them all
so the point being that there's so much to do that he can do and we're available to us
in a way that hasn't been available for people for until recent times it's a phenomenal thing to live in this world
so it takes some care to learn and navigate the world of time
to learn to navigate the world of all these possibilities that exist for us
and today's topic is time how to be time rich if you want to be rich
be rich in time spacious time live in spacious time
not tight time contracted time
live in a kind of boundless time as opposed to a bounded time that's bounded by all the concerns and needs
and duties and responsibilities and uh
so one of the things i learned in the monastery was to live in time like this
schedule of things that had to be done at a certain time but do it within spacious time and so
the two don't have to be separate from each other there's a way to be relaxed calm and
fully engaged and you know it was working in the monastery sometimes it
was you know very engaging very active engaged work and there was a spacious time for it
sometimes time would kind of disappear because of the full engagement in what we're doing
so uh meditation
meditation is a wonderful reference point for discovering our relationship to time
and in many ways meditation is a time to do something very different than what we
usually do in our lives and then in that difference
i have the difference highlighted so if we're
always running around being busy and it's become second nature to do that
and then what's the problem that's what everyone else is doing too and then you sit down to meditate and
you feel the cost of that running around you feel the impact it has of a distracted mind a tense body
and uh and then in meditation because the contrast
then we can see the busyness in a way we couldn't do it when we're living in it to see it in a different way so
meditation is a reference point to understand ourselves and that's a different purpose than
thinking meditation is about becoming calm it's fine for it to be help you become calmer
but if that's the it's all about you're not going to become wise about how you
operate when you're not calm and if you use meditation little may start seeing the contrast the difference
to use it as a as a look a standard kind of to see really get to know yourself
better what's going on so when we first sit and meditate maybe not
first sooner or later most people will notice that their mind is
distracted and they they bring the mind back to their breath then they get distracted
again come back to the breath distracted
so to be to be distracted chances are you're living in time you're
caught up in time in some way so to ask yourself the question when
you're distracted from the present moment are you are you living are you thinking
about the past kind of living in the past thinking in the past
are you thinking about the future are you somehow actively distractingly
in thinking about the present maybe the present that's not here but someplace else
and uh or or you're thinking in kind of a mythic fictional time
you know fantasies can you know don't exist in time exactly they can just be a fantasy
um or you might be solving some wonderful problem that uh
or task or something writing the great great american novel in your head
and so that doesn't you know it's kind of like outside of time but so it's kind of i call it mythic time or fictional
time and which which is your tendency
which which is your default where do you tend to go in time when you get distracted
do you attend when you get distracted is it more often in the past is it more often in the future
is it more often about things happening in the present but not here and now is it more often do you get distracted
by what's actually happening here and now and
like you can sit here and meditate with a room full of people and just have your eyes closed you know you know
there are a lot of different kinds of masks that people are wearing right now i can't remember because my eyes are
closed let me see if i remember their color and their shape i wonder if someone had the ideal mask and i'll try
to remember which what that person had that kind of shape that's distracted thinking right but
it's about the present moment so where does your mind go what does it do
and if there's a pattern for you what does that tell you what does that say about you
if you're mostly thinking about the past what are the values what are the priorities what are
the desires what are the concerns that you have that keep bringing you back into the past
if it's mostly about the future what are their concerns what are the values what are the what is the
where's the what's the energy what is it about the future that keeps pulling you into the future
and so forth so forth for the other ones so to try to understand oneself deeper what's going on here
for the purpose of meditation uh knowing what it is that not just knowing
that you're thinking about that past future and so forth but to know you know oh my this is my
pattern and this is kind of what's driving the pattern
it helps you then to bring your mindfulness to something deeper than the distracted thought
if you're thinking about the past because you still feel hurt about what happened years ago
and you're trying to navigate and negotiate and figure out the hurt and who did what and who's to blame who's
responsible what you could have done and just reviewing it and reliving what happened a long time ago
maybe that hurt still festers and that hurt might need our attention
the hurt is always in the present moment and if we want to heal the hurt it's probably not going to be healed by
making a better past thinking about but rather to really meet the pain
and learn how to sit with that in present moment if we're thinking about the future
some people they think about the future because they're planning and they're you know anxious about the future
the anxiety is what needs our attention or maybe it's delightful anticipation i
know people who just seem to have a joy in anticipating things
and uh my son one of my sons was that way he would just like lay in bed and he'd be anticipating planning and it
seemed like that was like and what you know and sometimes he loved
like his little kid he loved like building a stage for play but the play would never happen
and that was besides the point it was just the building anticipating and that was that was so much fun and then he'd
build it and then he go on to do something else and uh so there's you know sometimes it's joy
that brings us into past and future and being distracted so that's nice
but if you if you bring your present moment attention into the joy and follow that back
to the source follow that back inside to what's going on that's a very different uh movement to
to arrive in the present moment then continually kind of batting away distracted thoughts and letting go and
coming back letting go and coming back because you're getting to the underlying source from which these distracted
thoughts are bubbling up from probably something that's close more intimate and more important and
closer to something value and you know really important about yourself
so that's one way meditation can be a reference point and and seeing understanding
what's going on with earth distracted thinking another thing about distracted thinking
is that um there's there's probably desires involved
in them that are time sensitive time concerns like and so what is that how does time
operate in the concern itself and uh
so for example being anxious and planning in the future it's because something is again time bounded and i
have to get it done in a certain time and so let me think about ahead of time so i can do it fast enough or efficient
enough so so time comes into play but as we settle down more in meditation
then and we're no longer so distracted but here and present time can still be an operating concern
it could be that yeah i'm present but they better ring the bell you know when is this meditation going
to be over yes i've been present but i've been present long enough
you know and so um you know so there's there's maybe restlessness coming up
and that that's a you know and something wanting something to come to an end
and uh or it could be that we're trying to get concentrated or calm or something
and so there's an attainment focus about attaining something in the future
hopefully in the next minute or something but still it's like leaning into the future and operating on the
assumption that you have time in the future time and that you can kind of
navigate and try to attain something in the future and uh
and so time is operating again so we're kind of being we're making kind of being
i don't know if it's too strong a language you said but we're being led around by time or caught up in time
what happens if we don't have a future in meditation what happens if it's just about the
present moment so we would we would then no longer be
attaining anything because attaining is always in the future and uh so it's a little bit of a
fantasy and sometimes we do attain things we do get calmer so sometimes we can practice in such a way that good
things happen to us so it's not like we it's illegal to do it and impossible to do it but it is operating in time
and as the mind gets quieter sooner or later you'll notice that any concern with
about the future is a bit of a drag for the mind any concern for the future means the
mind is activated with with a certain activity of thinking
and that i think that's time involved and what's fascinating about this is we
start discovering how much we are the time belongs to a conceptual world
that we create at least the time that we experience
the time that we live in is a is a is born in our minds in how
our minds operate and it's not like a time is not like a
the time that we live in the time that we're operating under is not doesn't is not cost free it's not
like you know the air that's just always here for us
and we can just breathe and not have to think about it there's sometimes idea that time just exists
there's a big debate in philosophy does time exist does it not exist how does it exist what is time
independent of those kinds of concerns meditators can learn
as their mind gets quiet that the very we're very conceiving of
things dependent on time takes mental energy tends meant takes a
kind of mental work and if the mind is quiet enough we'll see that work as being agitating
if you're super agitated to begin with the level of agitation about the future
is so subtle that it's in consequence it doesn't mean anything like you can't give me a break
but when the mind is really quiet we start seeing that the activity of even cons
being concerned about a future takes work it's agitating it's ripples it's uh you
know on the on the surface of the the mines lake thinking about the past same thing
so then if you want to settle more we let go of past and future
and the way we do it in mindfulness practice you can just let go of it of course but one way is again always turning towards what's going on
and you know where's that work where's that pressure yes it feels like there's agitation or
very subtle pressure or little piece of stress having to do with this past and future
where is it now can i hold it can i bring my attention to it
so not let go of this first chance you have but keep coming back and feeling it and sensing it and one of the advantages
of doing that it's kind of like trying to bring you moving you back to the source to use a
kind of buddhist language and you're kind of following the stream back to the source
and you know what is that source are you following it back back and then
as the mind gets quieter it's fascinating that
even concern for any kind of subtle subtle
concern is where like if you're following your breath in breath any idea that there's an end to the out
breath is extra any idea that you know the beginning of
the outbreak just happened is extra
there's what happens when you're just with experience or breathing without a past and a future
it can be very peaceful it can be very settled
no past no future just this moment of the breathing as if as if kind of like
it's forever but of course it isn't forever but it becomes something else and becomes something else
but every every new thing is just itself just that moment
just the experience and they some people will say that
the moment of experience and time have become no different from each other but just this time just this
and uh so you can see that for example there i
start seeing it and eating a meal if you're eating quietly not talking or
on your device but just eating lifting a fork up to your mouth
you know it's it's kind of goal-oriented right you you're trying to get it up into the mouth
in you know in a timely way but uh what if there's no you know you're living just without in the past
in the future there's like infinite time for bringing
that fork up to your mouth it's qualitatively a different way of
experiencing eating than if part of the mind is so you know a very subtle part of the mind is
concerned about the results of the action of getting it up there to the mouth so you know
you can you know put in the mouth and put another mouthful of food on the fork quickly
just to and start starts being sensitive walking down the steps
each step each stepping is not without the past and the future
that becomes a as that becomes available that sense of that you can never do it i don't know if you
could ever do it 100 perfectly but that's not the point is to do it
perfectly the point is to see use that as a reference point you get a
sense oh just too close to the present just this and then we see oh there's still a little bit of greed or desire operating
for something to be different in the next moment or a little bit pressure to get to the bottom of the steps
as opposed to just walking down the steps just walking when eating just eating
but i have so many things to do i can't you know i can't just to walk down the steps you know i have all this
stuff that has to be done and have to get there quickly and and if i don't the sky will fall down and
just walking just this but i have to be ready and
just walking and it's possible you'll discover that if you're walking someplace
and you just walk without future in the past just this this activity is the
thing of the moment when you come to the next activity you're actually in a better space
to meet it take care of it be present for it then if you were hurried and came out of breath and you have all
these things to do and okay now i'm here now i have to do this quickly and so i can move on to the next thing
i've there's been times when i've started one thing and as soon as i start that thing which
i've been thinking about for a while to get to i'm already thinking about the next thing i have to do
or the next two things or three things i have to do and uh it's this momentum
this uh of the mind this habit formation of the mind to live in time to live concerned about
doing and getting and getting to the next what's in the future what's in the future
you know it's rather unfortunate how strong i can operate in some people's minds
so as we meditate we get to see all this and that's hopefully one of the one of the opportunities in meditation is to
really see your mind clearly and how it's living in time its relationship to time and how much you
can put down the time and quiet the cons the conceptualization the conceiving of time that we do
and one of the fascinating feelings you can get from all this is the feeling that
time always begins in the present that's where time begins
the past begins in the present
because we conceive of the past
in a few minutes we'll leave here and this talk
will only exist for you in how you conceive of it how you remember it how your mind construct
reconstructs it being here what it's like and
so when you leave out the door got the door the talk only exists in some kind of way
in your memory that that when this talk becomes the
past that past was born
here the past is born in the present that's a
very different idea that the linear movement from the future i know you know into the future looks
like it's a line that passes behind us and the future is ahead of us some cultures have the
future coming towards us and and we leave so the
but anyway so the uh but what happens if we understand that
time future time past begins in the present
if that's the case the present is the source
for all time past and future in a certain kind of way
and uh and if that's the case how are we going to be responsible
how are we going to be intimate how are we going to care for ourselves at that
important juncture this present moment where time begins
are we are we creating time as a gift are we creating time as
something that's useful and healthy for us and for others we are the creators of time at least for
our own minds we are the creators of the past the creators of the future in a certain kind
of way so it gives us a phenomenal vantage point phenomenal
potential to live in the world a very different way around time
and so if you feel harried by time if you feel in a hurry in the world of time
you've constructed that time that's been born in your mind
is that how is that what you want to have produced in your mind for the world is that your gift to the world
a hurried mind a harried mind what happens if you construct a
different time is there a timeless time is there
spacious time is there a way of holding the events of your life past future and present
in a wide open time
and that i think is one of the gifts of meditation is that
because to the degree to which we can get calm in meditation it slows down the incessant
kind of rush of thoughts ideas constructions conceivings that the mind does
and one of those conceivings is the conceivings of around time and so you get a sense you get a feeling that time
is now opened up is more spacious and that
is a valuable place to take care it's a valuable place to
value to see it as important see it as a teacher
see it as reflecting on what is important to now and what and your role
in staying close to it and your role in losing it
and if you find yourself in a hurry
you've become attached to something there's no hurrying
without attachment but there can be
doing things fast without hurrying there can be doing things fast
without attachment but you can't hurry without there being attachment
so as we slow down in this becoming a more spacious time
we have then the opportunity to discover what these attachments are
and why do we live with these attachments why do we give them so much authority
why do we think that they're required and so necessary and so important
follow that back that idea back to the source where does that come from where does that arise from in you
what are the beliefs what are the deeper feelings and emotions
that give rise to the attachment that causes hurry
so there is time poverty
which i think has been growing for our modern society
more and more empowered people impoverished in time
and then there's being rich in time an abundance of time
that is only a moment away or you know we have to be faster these
days it's only a nanosecond away
abundance of time that's always here
so i hope that uh this gives you something to a little different than usual to
be curious about and consider and talk to your friends about and
and study your mind with may time become your friend
by you becoming friends time thank you
you