so my friends and welcome welcome to our meditation
session together and meditation
is a way that we care for ourselves and in doing so we care for others
we care for ourselves and that meditation is a time to to
heal to rest to open to discover kind of inner
harmony and health that comes when we're no longer in conflict with ourselves or no longer
chasing things and running away from things pushing things away and grabbing hold
and holding tight when all those things kind of bottle up
energy or limit us and tighten us
and to sit here and care for ourselves and allow all the conflicts and tensions to fall away and sit here
in a healthy present open way
then that disposes us to more likely to
meet people with in a way that cares for their humanity cares for their humanness cares for
their life and we're more likely to meet people without conflict and without
pushing away or holding on or without hostility or
or greed or something like that and so it's understood that this practice we do is really meant for
caring for self and for caring for others some people emphasize one more than the other some people are
inspired by the idea that meditation is a way to make us more more helpful for the world around
us in a way that's deeply uh helpful in the sense that
we know the best we know the healthiest we know that we know something what's possible
for happiness and some people do it for their own sake for their own hap well-being and
happiness but even though the choice might be for one or the other
you can't separate the two and the two come hand in hand as we benefit others this way we benefit
ourselves as we benefit ourselves this way we um we uh
we benefit others and so today as we sit uh perhaps uh
we sit here to benefit in all directions and we do so
by offering our care and our friendship our friendly attentiveness
to our breathing and that breathing
is a place where we offer our care offer
our kindness our compassion our it's a training ground for how we
can be present in a way that's clear and healthy and open and directed
it's not just a matter of learning how to stay with the breathing and be with the breathing a lot of it
has to do with learning how we can be with the breathing so as we sit here today
you might experiment and call upon your capacity for
kindness tenderness compassion truthfulness
clear unconflicted presence to really be here as a training ground
for a way of being with self and others that allows for this deep movement
towards spiritual and psychological health
so to us to adjust your body into a meditation
posture that is suitable for you to be both
alert and also to meet yourself be with yourself
as if you're going to be with a good friend you know maybe a little bit troubled and
needs the attention and care of of you
gently closing your eyes and feeling sensing being with yourself
checking in
without an agenda just check in with yourself your body your
mind your heart how are you
and then taking a few long slow deep breaths
and what you're offering as you take a deep breath is attentiveness
attentive to the body's experience of breathing
and the long exhale is a time to let go of the world of your thoughts and concerns
just for these minutes so you can be more fully here and
present for yourself
and letting your breathing return to normal and for a few of your your exhales
relax the different parts of your body
soften
as you exhale perhaps there can be a quieting gentling
of your mind
quieting of your thinking
a calming of the mind
and then to gather your attention around the body's experience of
breathing some people do some more in the belly moving
some people the chest some people more they are going in and
out through the nostrils and some kind of the global experience
that includes all of those areas but the body's experience of breathing
and rather the id rather than the idea that you're now going to focus and stay concentrate on the
breathing the focus is more on sustaining
a friendly kind attention on the breathing
as you would if you were being with someone who was troubled
or sick or somehow challenged a friend of yours and you were going to
stay and be present
so focus on that offering of your presence kind presence
to your body breathing
not interfering with the breathing not interfering with your friend
but there to accompany to be present with
with a friendly presence a kind presence a caring presence
that says here my friend i'm with you
gently quietly
attending to the breathing
with kindness or compassion or care with
gentleness but really do attend stay there
stay nurturing yourself
with a simple experience of breathing in and breathing out
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to turn your gaze outward
to the people of your life in your neighborhood your communities towns cities country
and to offer that and that gaze a kindness or friendliness
a gentle care caringness for all beings
and to consider how any benefits you received from today's
meditation anyways in which you feel calmer or better
how that can translate or be applied
to support the lives of others today
what can you do to make the lives of others a little better maybe some as simple as smiling or
small acts of kindness small words of appreciation
small words of thanks
well-wishing or bigger things
because of the mutual way in which caring for self and caring for others
reinforce each other then they benefit each other they grow together
if you care for yourself care for others may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere be free
and may we contribute to that
possibility
so so i'll offer today another story
from the jataka tales details from the former births lives of the buddha
that are as i say kind of fables and um but they're fables which carry
the values that uh indian buddhists of
ancient times uh had and wanted to convey to others and some of
the you get a very different feeling for buddhism from the these stories that are told the
values in them and how do people relate to each other and and the virtues that are emphasized
and you get a sense of how you know what buddhism
is emphasizing for how to live a life as opposed to what to believe or what to
um you know understand philosophically or metaphysically or something like that
and um and they belong to the values of another time another place and sometimes maybe so
some aspects of it a little hard for us in the modern world to appreciate but some of it seems universal and
and these wonderful fables so this one is about um a golden deer
and this is about a deer that was magnificent with the golden fur and
antlers of that were shining silver and eyes that were like kind of sparkling
radiant gems jewels
and because this uh and this deer was very wise
but because of its great beauty it was often searched for and hunters
wanted to have it and capture it as a trophy or something so it would go into deep woods and
hide in inaccessible places to be safe but it was content being there because
the deer liked to meditate and would sit there and meditate and become wiser and
and kinder in the process so there it was the deer in its hiding place and it happened to be the
thicket of woods where it hid was close to a river upriver at a city upriver
a wealthy merchant died and left his wealth to his son
and his son who was a bit of a
playboy and gambler and other things started to spend the money um quite
extravagantly for all kinds of things and uh pretty soon had spent up all the
money not only spent it up spent it but i had come into deep debt
and the creditors came after this wealthy this this uh this son to get their money back
and but not having any money or anything to offer uh the the uh
the son had a little trick up his sleeve he thought that he kind of made up on the spot maybe an ill thought
out plan and that was come i'll i have money
for you i have a treasure that's buried in the sand next to the river and we'll go down there we'll dig it up
and you'll have your money back and so this crowd of creditors
because there's a lot of debt he had and this young man were walking down the
river and up the river and and uh on a sand embankment right kind
of that goes down to the river kind of steep and um and
the young man pretended to slip and slipped intentionally in the sand
and fell into the river with a raging water and the plan was to be swept away by the
river in this raging water and so that the creditors thought he would
died in the river through an accident of slipping and falling and would no longer be chasing after him
for their money and in a sense that's what happened the boy kind of feigned the slipping and
slipped down into the river and got swept away but what it turned out was the river was
quite strong and um and there was no way to get back onto the shore there's just like
big wide river with raging water carrying him down and it carried him down the river a long
ways and as after a while he felt like this is serious i'm i can't get back to shore i'm going to
drown i'm cold things are difficult here and greater rapids downriver
so the young man started calling out for help and in his in his screams for help
the golden deer hurt heard the cries for help and the deer said well as long as i'm
alive i'm not going to allow anyone to die that i can help and save
and um and so he he dashed out of his thicket in the woods and to the river
and dived and jumped into the river and swam out to where the young man was and kind of ducked under
the water and came up underneath the the man and picked him up on his back and and
then swam back to the shore by this time the young man was quite
cold hypothermia set in was quite weak and and so the deer brought him into his
thicket secret little place he had and over the next couple of days i nursed him back to health to
well-being brought him fruits and nuts from the forest water kept him warm and
and then the young man revived and felt good and and so the young man
thank the deer and this is quite something and and anything i can do in return and the
deer said yes i'll bring you back i'll take you back out to the road to you can go back
to your city but um please i promise that you will will not tell
anyone where i am so so i can stay safe here and the young
man said yes i promise so the deer carried him out to through the tickets and thickets of
woods and forest and showed them where the road was through the city and the boy then returned to the city
and by now um no one recognized him or maybe it was a different city or something and the capital of the of uh
this country now it happened that uh after a while the the queen of the
country had a dream and she dreamt of a great golden deer with silver antlers
and gem-like eyes who uh in her dream was very very wise
and she was intrigued and and desirous of that wisdom to be a teet to be a student of this
wise wise deer that she had dreamt about
so she asked her ministers to please go find this there and bring it to her so she can learn its wisdom but no one knew where
their stare was and so um a proclamation was sent out with people throughout the town
announcing if anyone could find this golden deer or find out where it is for them to uh that
they would receive a big treasure chest of treasure and so this
uh young man heard this and he said oh well i know where the deer golden deer is and so he went
to the queen and said i know where it is and i can bring you there breaking his promise to the deer and uh
so then they the queen assembled her soldiers and people together and they went maybe a little bit afraid to
go into the woods and came with their spears and arrows and started to kind of circle around the place where the deer
was and making a lot of noise and the deer could see through the trees the spears and the arrows and the
soldiers and and said oh i'm here to be captured
so he what he did was he got up in a stately calm way walked right to the queen who was with
the peep everyone and the queen got a little bit scared had this big
deer walking right up against her she pulled out her bow and arrow and was going to
protect herself but there's something about the non-threatening nature in which this big
deer came walking up to her that she didn't let the arrow fly and the deer stopped and said what are you
doing here and uh and who brought you here how do you find me
and the deer and the queen said oh it's this man here who the young man who that showed us the
way and showed us where you were and and the deer said oh there's an ancient
saying better to save a log better to rescue a log from the river
than someone like you and um and the queen didn't understand
that you know what are you talking about not saving someone and oh the dear said this man
he was drowning in the river i plunged into the great river and fought the rapids and brought him back
to the shore and nursed him back to health and then he promised he would never tell anyone
where i was in my safety and the queen was horrified to hear this hear both about that to hear that this
person who had missed this animal that risked its life to save another human being had been betrayed and that the young man
had made a promise and and the promise was betrayed and so she
took her bow and arrow and she said you're you know you're a traitor you're betrayed and this is terrible what you
did and the deer said no don't shoot don't shoot you promised the young man
that you would give him a treasure if he brought him to you he brought you he brought you to me and
he should be given the treasure and and but maybe you can banish him from the from the queendom
and so that's what the queen did and uh the man left with his treasure but never to come back to that country
and then the queen said please come with me to the palace i'd like to learn from you and your teachings
but i'll offer you a wish that's my payment any wish you want and the dear said please
pass a law that no one is allowed to injure or hurt or kill any animal
in this queendom and the queen said okay i offered you a wish and that's what you
take that's that'll be the new law and they went back to the to the palace
and the deer taught both the queen and the ministers and many of the people of the capital the virtues of kindness and
friendliness and generosity and um and truthfulness
and and all the wonderful virtues
and that all went well except that the farmers who've been that the animals started
eating the crops of the of the farmers and farmers couldn't chase them away or couldn't injure them or kill them to stop them
so it became an uproar from everyone about the problems they had and so the great golden year went out to
into the into the world and and told everyone told all the animals
don't eat the people's food they need to they need to be able to grow their own food and support them they're not going to kill
you but don't you take their their plants and crops and um and the animals agreed and in
this way the kingdom became vegetarian and the animals were safe
so there's a lot of kind of interesting kind of little lessons in this story uh maybe a
you know kind of fantastical story and fable but certainly the value of uh helping
others and preserving life and saving life and dedicating oneself to even
at the risk of one's own life to help others it's a huge value of ancient buddhism that you see in many of these stories and the
tremendous importance of truthfulness to speak the truth and then adhere to the truth especially if you made a
promise and and the value of not harming
and and it's there seems to have been a trend in certain parts of ancient indian
buddhism of kind of emphasizing or pointing towards vegetarianism as a so that no animals
nothing gets killed and injured so that's a story for today and
and just like the deer stayed in this quiet secret place so it could cultivate
its great compassion and care and wisdom so may you go to your
secret place of meditation and and be a place where you can develop your own kindness and compassion
and truthfulness and and care for this world may you be the
great golden deer that is wise
so thank you