so
we come in this series of talks to the
consider the final step of anapanasati
the 16th step of mindfulness of
breathing
and the way it's worded
in english the most common translation
into english
is something like
observing
relinquishment one trains
i will breathe in observing
relinquishment
one trains i will breathe out
this word relinquishment
that translates a pali word
patini saga
s s p-a-t-i-n-i-s-s-a gga
that has a double meaning
it means a kind of letting go
relinquishment
and it also means generosity to give
and in some contexts in the
teachings of the buddha it clearly means
being generous
and now just that's so nice this passage
i'll read it to you
and
so a noble disciple
someone who has come now towards the to
the end of this 16 steps
noble disciples recollect
consider their own generosity like this
it is truly my good fortune
and gain that in a world of people
obsessed with greed
i dwell freely generous
open-handed
delighting in giving devoted to charity
delighting and giving and sharing
and the expression delighting in giving
the word giving is the same word as this
final step in anapanasati of
relinquishment
so there is a
letting go a deep letting go that's
almost an act of
choice if
now if you review these last four steps
of anapanasati
is that as we settle in having gotten
concentrated and quiet and still
then we come to a stage where
it just feels the best just to not be
working meditation anymore
we don't have to work and we just settle
back and just observe
we're observing we're kind of like in
the process of life
the flow of life and we're just
observing the transiency and the
changing nature of
moment-to-moment experience
and now there's a fading away of
clinging and greed and wanting
and that fading away happens up to the
point where
the greed and the hatred that we have
seizes and stops and wow
to have a qualitatively high experience
of the stopping of these unhealthy
movements of the mind
and heart and wow this is good this is
right this is health this is freedom
and inner psychological freedom and
and then knowing that seeing that having
wisdom about that
then saying i'm i would like to be done
with this
i no longer want to invest in these
kinds of ways of being i don't
no longer believe in them i no longer
stand behind
being greedy or hateful or resentful or
complaining
or jealous or
or you know having any kind of annoyance
or hostility that i'm keep getting
living in cynicism and
um and uh and not we don't do it
punitively it's not like we feel bad
about ourselves
but now we know something much better
and so we're letting go of what is
unwholesome
and and if you look carefully read
carefully the teachings of the buddha he
when he talks about what we let go of
it doesn't talk about letting go of
things so much
hardly at all or if at all like we don't
let go
of our material wealth or
let go of our friendships our
relationships what we're letting go of
what we're relinquishing
our inner psychological states
things inside of us and they're clearly
the ones
that harm us what the buddha calls
unwholesome or unskillful
and he says that explicitly in one place
he says um
if one if when one
gives away something
unwholesome mental qualities grow and
wholesome mental qualities
waste away then i say one should not
give away
in this way and the word giving away
here
is that word relinquishment so uh
so they would give captures the idea
that it's an act of generosity
and so i'll read it a different way if
one
relinquishes anything
and then unwholesome mental qualities
grow and wholesome mental qualities
waste away then i say
one should not relinquish in this way
but if one gives away if one
relinquishes
something and unwholesome mental
qualities
waste away and wholesome mental
qualities grow
then i say one should give away one
should relinquish
in this way so this is not blind
relinquishment it's not the blind
letting go of something just but
we hear they're supposed to let go let
go of everything
it's really we're letting go of that
which
interferes with our betterment
interferes with the best qualities we
have
we're letting go so that the better
qualities of who we are
can come forth and we have a much
clearer sense of what those are
and what gets in the way well the
obstructions
when we get quiet and peaceful
now one of the most wonderful meditation
instructions that i received
many years ago from this wonderful
english beku monk named arjan amaro
and he said something like
set yourself at ease
and then notice what takes you away from
that
and that was the instruction no 16
stages
that's so complicated so just recognize
set yourself at ease and i think i
understood that to be whatever modicum
of ease that's
accessible just if it's the simplest
kind of just
softening and relaxing but then the
important part the wisdom part
is to notice what takes you away from
that
and then consider is it really worth it
is it really for your betterment to
lose whatever the ease you have
it's through that then through then
deepening the ease pushing the ease
deepening that ease deepening these
coming to more ease and more ease
we get better and better recognition
of the goodness that's here within us to
be better recognition of
when there's an unwholesome direction
and when there's a wholesome direction
that we're going
when it's for our betterment or for the
opposite
and so we come to hear the lasting last
stage of anapanasati
there is a real real deep relinquishment
now
where something we're really ready
to put something down
and and be done with something enough of
this already
and even though we can't necessarily
stop
certain mental habits that we have or
tendencies we have
it's a powerful movement to have made an
inner choice
inner turning and say i no longer stand
behind this
i no longer believe in this kind of
behavior
and we can do that without any aversion
hostility
feeling better about ourselves we can do
it with joy
delighting in this word relinquishment
delighting in it
that now i'm going to move in a good
direction just no i know there's a
better direction
and to know that deeply is one of the
great gifts of this practice
great gifts of life and uh and to be
inspiring
so rather than seeing our for inner
foibles and
inner you know old habits coming back
and feeling
depressed or upset by it there can be a
stance a recognition oh here
it is again and now i get to practice
this is what this practice i know what
practice is about now
the practice i know i'm going to there's
a direction amount of direction
on a movement on a journey to really i
know what freedom is i know
what this is not where it's at and now i
have an opportunity to practice with
this
and that is a fortunate thing anyone who
has the practice
has good fortune anyone who has a
practice
is involved in a path of great goodness
and benefit
and so to celebrate and delight in the
fact you ever practice
more than being upset by the fact that
one more time you got angry or irritated
or
greedy or something just keep
turning it over to appreciating it and
looking for the generosity and the
goodness and the delight
in the possibility of on being on a path
of
liberation or freedom of letting go
and so no matter where you are on these
stages of anapanasati these 16 stages
each step in the way is good for itself
is good enough in fact the ancient
commentaries
said that each step of the 16 can be a
complete step in itself they
they contain within each step contains
within itself
the path to all 16 or
so if you stayed at the first step of
just breathing in long
knowing you're breathing in long the
other 15 steps kind of will follow along
as you really settle in and just do that
one get concentrated doing that
but it doesn't matter just the fact that
you're whatever your stage you're at
that's the right place for you that's a
good place
and that's where your delight and
pleasure and
joy can be that uh you're so fortunate
you have a path you this is your step
now this is
your movement your ability to practice
and the further you go the more you'll
understand what's wholesome
the more you understand what's wholesome
the more with generosity the lighting
and generosity
you can give away give up
the unwholesome and i use these words
like
the give up in the kind of original
apparently meaning of the word
which is to offer something up on an
altar
or the original meaning of sacrifice to
make sacred
or the original word of surrender
then the latin i think maybe in the
french as well the roots of the word
is to also to to give
something give up
so um so that's his
uh we've come now to the end of these 16
steps and
this the discourse on anapanasati has
further things to say about this and
what is most interesting for me about
the next
kind of instructions of this uh six
after the 16 steps
is how um the fruit of the practice the
liberation of the practice
becomes more and more the
the basis for the practice and how
liberation becomes a basis for practice
is the topic for next week so
so thank you for all this
and i can take a little bit of time
for taking some questions if you'd like
and
anything really but if you'd like to ask
me 16 steps or anything about this
i will try to do my best to track the
questions if they come
and
any additional
advice on how anapanasati can be
practiced in a relaxed
open way without turning it into a
linear checklist
i'm i'm turning this as i sit
great yeah i think that every meditation
practice we do
all these funny habits of the mind will
come in and
kind of take over and sometimes the
practice starts becoming mechanical
sometimes maybe a linear checklist where
am i
and don't be discouraged by this but
learn to recognize it
and then figure out a way to not do it
and sometimes i've done some
similar things like and i've just kind
of backed off
and i just gone back to the very
beginning or um
just just come back and just not try to
do the practice of anapanasati and
just open my awareness and
then my kind of my
my my one of my kind of
great default for practicing
when you know it seems like nothing's
really working
is uh to tell myself the word here
h-e-r-e
and just say here and it's uh not a
command like to a dog
it's just the recognition i'm here and i
say the word
and then i open my attention to just
recognize what is here
and sometimes what i recognize is my
mind is out of control and
spinning around oh here this is what it
feels like to have a spinning mind
here this is what it's like to be upset
here
this is what's like to be agitated
and it's a gen there's a generosity in
that here
in that and that opening oh this is what
it's like
nothing has to be any different it's
just a
clear recognition of this and i'll do
that for a while
and then at some point things settle
down or
if i got a mechanical or a checklist
approach to practice
then i can kind of i've stopped doing it
and then i can start fresh again
okay
it's a lot of thank yous i appreciate
them it's very nice
and
is it to be expected that grief would
come with disenchantment
ah no it's not to be expected
but it's pretty common and so i think we
should just
um that sometimes when we do this
practice we realize
that even when we let go of things we
know are unhealthy
there can be a grief too for the going
away of something that's been our
companion for a long time or
or there's a grief around what we lost
because we were caught up so long in
some unhealthy way of being and we have
to grieve first before we can really
move on
um there was a psychologist who did a
lot of this practice
and uh his his take on all this is that
the path to liberation is one continuous
process of grieving
so it might have been true for him it
hasn't been true for me and but
but grief is definitely can be an
important part of this whole process and
it's not to be
pushed away or feel like it's
unfortunate to have grieving
and i did give a talk last sunday on
grief sunday morning talk here so
i talked about liberating grief that
might intrigue you if you didn't hear
the talk
to hear it
the folds and the unfolding yeah
what is the source of the excerpt you
read about generosity today
it's um
it's a it's a
now my own translation so it's all i
have here is a reference it's from the
numerical discourses of the buddha
chapter 6 suita number 25.
this
it's very nice to read all these little
comments and thank yous and
and uh it's really a wonderful thing to
share this
path and this practice together with all
of us here
grief arises in unexpected times yeah
for sure
i think some some i've heard teachers
say that
if you don't uh if you haven't had a
good cry
you're probably not really on the path
to liberation
at some point or other it does not all
the time but
can you please clarify again the
relationship between 16 steps of our
practice of the cushion
as well as while meditating yeah well
that's a good question
i generally don't think about too much
about the 16 steps
in daily life i do i spend a lot of time
because i spent you know much of my
adult life meditating on my breathing
and
and it's kind of been the kind of the
foundation of my meditation practice
that um it uh it spills over into daily
life where i'm
frequently kind of attentive to my
breathing or
include my breathing whatever i'm doing
and awareness of it and
and so it's been a great gift in my
daily life to
track and watch my breathing when my
breathing gets held or tight or
constricted
and how it shifts and changes and
sometimes
it's the first indication i have that
i've gotten caught or stuck
or reactive or hot and something
and so uh just being familiar with the
breathing and
connected to it and then being able to
come back and
and uh relax their breath and have an
ease full breath as i go through my
daily life has been beneficial in many
many ways
and whether i'm on any particular step
of anapanasati in daily life
i don't really think about so much
it's the 16-step open awareness
some people might experience open
awareness with the 16 steps
but i wouldn't want to identify the two
together
because um letting go
the deepest letting go we do is just a
phenomenal absence
and to give it any kind of
description that it is something even
something like open awareness
just little bit diminishes it or misses
the point a little bit
oh what is the poly word you said at the
beginning meaning
generosity so the the word there's uh
there's a three different poly words
that mean both
letting go or relinquishment translators
often translate all three of them as
relinquishment
but also mean generosity and
and the one for that that's uh this
sixteenth step of panasati
is patini saga
n p-a-t-i-n-i s s a g h g g
a and then there's chaga c
long a g a and then there's vo saga v
o s s a g g a and so it's a wonderful
thing you see
this that this is the close association
in poly with
letting go and generosity
okay so this is wonderful so i need to
stop
and uh thank you all and and
we'll continue this
exploration of anapanasati in context of
liberation
next week and i look forward to it and
and also i maybe i mentioned this but uh
i'm teaching two retreats coming up that
are
not part of imc it might be interesting
for you
one is the they kind of actually kind of
at the same
time some of them so i'll be
moonlighting one to the other uh one is
um
the um with san francisco zen center
i'm doing a kind of a interesting
dialogue retreat it's not a full retreat
but it's um
like all day long but it's a you know a
couple hours few hours a day and on the
weeks a few days of the evenings and the
weekend
that's um that uh kind of a lot of this
dialogue between
uh two of the senior teachers at san
francisco zen center myself
on the harmony of vipassana and zen
and that starts on 19th of april and uh
it'll be folded into the 7 a.m sittings
so um i'll do the first week and
then paul heller and phu schrader will
do the
the other two weeks instead of me
teaching the 7 a.m
so you get a taste of the retreat just
by coming here at seven a.m
and the other is uh i'm teaching a
retreat at spirit rock
um online for
for six days uh starting um
april 25th and
and that should be a quite a lovely
retreat and i love these online retreats
so okay thank you