good morning everyone and good day welcome to our meditation
and as a few words of introduction um
i'd like to mention that one of the classic functions of
buddhist meditation is to quiet still calm
the inner fires and the idea of a blazing fire that
burns the wood that sustains it that fuels it
as a metaphor for the kind of inner fire that burns us that harms us and that
particularly these fires are the fires of greed hatred and delusion and
in all kinds of ways in which we are excessively agitated caught up spinning around
can be seen as fires and it is to calm these fires it may be
extinguished with extinguish the ones that are the most painful and
harmful and the water that in a sense the water that can
quiet calm quench these fires is mindfulness
if mindfulness contains qualities of peace qualities of non-assertion
non-um greed non-hatred non-delusion
and so the art of mindfulness practice is to find a way to be aware of our experience be aware
of our breathing be aware of our body be aware of our feelings emotions even our thoughts and what goes on in
the mind the how we're aware of it is so crucial
and how is it for you in the way that your awareness your mind works that
you can how is it that awareness itself can feel like
a calming influence on you in what way can you be aware of something as simple as the
breathing be aware of some of the inner fires that exists for you maybe agitations that exist that
the awareness itself is reassuring it's settling it's spacious
it begins to remove some of the fuel that keeps us agitated because we make
space for it's there or we bring calmness to what's there or reassurance to what's
there so each of us are probably going to find a little different way of being aware
um but the principle is how can we be aware in such a way that it's settling for us
it settles us into the present moment it settles us into a kind of being at peace with
this experience of life that we're sitting with so to experiment to look to search
inside of yourself how to be aware so the awareness itself
is not caught in analysis and judgments and shoulds and shouldn'ts
but it's a reassuring awareness a calming awareness
that encourage and supports a deep settling here
so entering into a meditation posture
one that hopefully will allow you to be both alert
and relaxed
and to see if there's simple ways you can adjust your attitude for awareness
the task of awareness so that you're a little bit more
the awareness is a little bit more stable and centered and
reassuring and with this awareness that
reassuring awareness
to take a few long slow breaths and begin to process of relaxing your
body deep relaxation
full relaxation
and letting your breaths return to normal
and then considering how awareness can be have some peaceful quality to it
let your awareness shine upon or settle upon your belly
and as you exhale to relax your belly soften
do
letting the light of awareness shine on your shoulders
and as you exhale relax your shoulders
soften
and also to soften your face
your temples around your eyes forehead
relaxing your face
and then breathing normally experiment a little bit to see
how you can be aware of breathing how you can know that you're breathing
as you breathe so that awareness
is peaceful
maybe he has a soft accepting quality to it
the awareness itself doesn't need the aware the breathing to be different than how it is
awareness is just there as a friend to accompany
your breathing
awareness free of greed free of hatred ill will
free of doubt and delusion
awareness that's there peacefully present
with the inhales and the exhales
and if something else arises as you meditate see if you can discover how to be aware
of that peacefully
a peaceful awareness that calms the fires inside of you
that cools the fever
that settles the agitation
a simple awareness that has a feeling of reassurance for all things
so that what is not reassured can begin to relax
relaxing here into the present moment
if your mind is wandering off in thought engage your awareness more fully
engage your awareness to be here
with your breathing your body
engage a peaceful quality of awareness
awareness that is non-contentious
an awareness which is reassuring settling
peaceful
so
and in the last minute or so of this sitting
is there some way you can adjust your awareness so awareness itself is a
peaceful influence on you a calming influence
just to be aware simple awareness spacious awareness
an awareness that maybe spreads through your body and heart
with a reassuring calm
reassuring inner peacefulness
and then to imagine that you can now open your awareness up out into the
world then light that your awareness your consideration of the world is like a
light that you shine and there's some way that you can hold
the world also in a calming
awareness in a peaceful awareness
maybe an awareness that's reassuring that there is a way
to calm the greed the fires of great hate and delusion
for everyone
and perhaps our ability to be peacefully aware can allow us to
look at the challenges and fires of this world
to look at them directly to not turn away or not get agitated
ourselves an honest awareness
of the challenges of this world
gazing and gazing upon all of it
as if our gaze is coming
stilling and may it be
that whatever we could do to offer to this world around us
he contributes to the happiness and welfare of everyone
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
it may be the way in which we're aware and present for this world
maybe may we be aware in a way that contributes to this well-being
may we know the world
in a way that brings peace
[Music]
so warm greetings to all of you as i begin this talk
there is a renowned verse from the dhammapada
the ancient anthology of buddhist poetry verse
and it goes something like this hate is not overcome by hate
but by love alone is hate overcome
this is an ancient truth
so hate is not overcome by hate by love alone is it overcome
and it's possible that translating the ancient world word as love doesn't really capture the
full richness of this verse and i'll talk about that a little later
but i want to evoke this very you know well-known verse
that it's really a central idea in buddhism that we cannot
pacify hate by adding more hate to the fire
hate is considered to be a
fire that burns the one who's hating that harms the one who's hating
so to respond to hate with hate means that there's two people now
who are burning and suffering who are wounding each other wounding themselves both
and this is such an important topic in the climate of the world really i don't know if there's
more or less hatred in the world than there's ever been before
but we're certainly becoming acutely aware of it here in the united
states and perhaps
perhaps we're coming into an era of this country where there is the possibility of
beginning to recognize the tremendous harm that hate has
that maybe it was difficult to see before when the hate was expressed
with you know so you know violently that people are
mostly spending their time protecting themselves from lynching and
riots and all kinds of things and hate was certainly present back then
but maybe it was not what was being addressed directly but now we come to a time where there's
a real heightened sensitivity to what hatred looks like how hatred speaks
how it spreads as a kind of poison through our society
and i speak about this because of in the wake of the the rising hate crime against asian
americans here in california just a month ago there was a arson and
um vandalism of a buddhist asian buddhist temple in in los angeles
a japanese buddhist temple the pure land tradition of buddhism a very peaceful peace-loving form of
buddhism and and the temple was partly destroyed
not dramatically but enough to be quite disturbing and
and you know these are this is a tradition of buddhism where has been in
this country for well over 100 years it's possible that membership of their
temple is or at least of that form of buddhism their members have been here in the
united states for six seven pep it's possible even eight
generations by now and um and to
be the recipients of hate as if they don't belong in this country is quite painful
for all of us in this family that we hope to be in in this country
and so in some of these images we've seen of elderly asian americans being attacked
on streets right here in san francisco is one of them and it's not like over there that this
kind of violence happens but it's close in and it's uh
it didn't start then but it certainly raised people's worry a year ago when there started to
be hateful things said to people of asian descent especially chinese descent here
and locally in the peninsula because of the coronavirus
and somehow
spreading of animosity towards people of any kind of asian descent because of a virus
like this so the ease in which sometimes people hate this part of the issue here in this country
and and certainly there's a need to stand in solidarity with
the people who are the recipients of hate and certainly to
send solidarity with the asian americans who are struggling with this and with fear and
worry and about what it means to be out in public even or
out in public at night and we know what's coming
and um and to offer our protection and to create places of sanctuary where it
feels safe to come and not just welcome to come but feeling like it's home like they belong and it's a
little bit hard here at imc to be maybe teaching here all alone
um these this last year but you know it's i want this place to be a
home for all people and for everyone to come here to feel like they belong and
even not just welcome not just belonging but feel like it's their place where they
can really engage fully and bring themselves completely here
so you know certainly i'm concerned for the
membership of imc that are asian american the membership of imc that are black
and all the people who are been the recipients of hate crimes here in the united states
the word hate crime is an interesting term because the definition of hate in this
regard is different very certainly very different than some of the other meanings of hate and
that we use we use the word hate uh when people say that um you know they hate spinach
it's uh it's a very different connotations very different meaning of the word than when we say we
hate an ethnic group or we hate one of the
you know i think i think the the highest number of hate crimes in united states is against african-americans
and um one of those other really high numbers is lgbtq
um and um
so the um the um to be a res so when there's a hate
crime it's not just you know that an intent you know a dislike of someone
but one distinction some people make also between like anger and hate i hate hate as a hate crime is that
anger is for a particular behavior a particular event particular situation
whereas racial hate or gender hate or
ethnic hate or something it's hate towards a whole category the whole
person uh not the behavior of the person what they say or do but the whole being of the person uh
and and their family and their and so it's not just a singular emotion
but it's an attitude a disposition a way of seeing it's an interpretation
that's overlaid on the totality of who a person is and that's why hate crimes
and expressions of this kind of ethnic and category crimes is so total why it's so difficult
for people and so painful is because it's a diminishing
contempt of who they are as a as a human being and to have that repeatedly to be
recipient that you as a human being are somehow worthy of my
hate is uh quite difficult and then to know that that's a lingering
disposition a lingering attitude it stays means that you know it's not just
a mistake of the moment or an incident of the moment passion in the moment but it's something
that stays and will be here and continue and continue
and to be the recipient of the victim of hate crimes it's not just individual who
suffers but also the families in the community because it's known that it's it's it's in some ways related to all
those together so it's a really a fabric a tear in the fabric of society
it's a rupture in our ability to be together
cooperatively harmoniously as fellow citizens fellow companions
in our humanity it's also kind of a this diminishment of people's humanity
and and this is one of the great tasks i think of our society and for ourselves and our times is to
learn how to see the humanity of other people and how to share our humanity with other
people there was i i saw an interview recently of um
between i think an imam the religious leader of a mosque and the
neighbor of the mosque a man who had been high on
drugs heard about some uh uh
violence i think it was the paris shooting uh massacre where all these people died
in paris by some isis
kind of followers and he came home high on cocaine and
and were just you know angry at muslims there all his idea was that they were he said he
had been listening to a lot of social media and so he thought all muslims were somehow violent and
terrorists and terrible people and so he shot up the building next door the
mosque and no one was hurt but still he shot it at it so he was arrested and went to jail and
um for the for what he did and he apologized for what he did and you know he i think when he was no
longer high he understood what he had done and the mistake he huge mistake he had made and when he
apologized the people in the mosque the religious leaders of the mosque forgave him and apparently brought him
food and little gifts in the prison and when he was released because he lived
next door they invited him over to the mosque and and uh and they were able to tell them a
little bit about the what their form of islam was and and he was shocked he found these people
to be fantastic wonderful people and peace loving people and and who had
forgiven him and as then he brought his friends over and to see them and they were all kind of discovering the
humanity of each other sharing each other's humanity getting to know each other which is not so easy not possible when
there's hate not possible when there's that categorical idea that someone is somehow
contemptible and so how do we
respond to hate as individuals and society and from a buddhist point of view we
don't respond with more hate and so to take a lot of care it's hard
to avoid doing that it's hard not to be upset with them those people who are doing it of
course there should be of course they shouldn't be of course we should take a strong stand
against the acts of violence against these acts of this level of hate and uh
and hopefully stand up and help protect our fellow humans who are struggling with this kind of situation
it affects all of us but we shouldn't hate and so in this
dhammapada verse it says hate is not overcome by hate and common translation is by love alone
is hate overcome but the actual uh language of the original language of the
of the line it literally says by non-hate is hate overcome and so non-hate
is a larger category larger points to a wider range of responses
than love love maybe is too hard too difficult to draw up love and expect
we're always supposed to be loving and and maybe it's not even appropriate as the as the first response or
as the response situations of hate and so the question is what is non-la
what does non-hate mean and most literally it means not to hate and so
the idea of loving i think is a great one and and and the motivation to love
it can arise out of deep meditation practice in meditation practice where we let go
we quiet all the fevers of great hate and delusion we settle and discover a deep level of
peace and well-being within a settled peaceful contented reassured heart
we discover that there there is a way of living a way of being
that becomes more important uh like one of the most precious things that i have to live there can be a feeling of
kind to kindness love friendliness compassion that radiates from within and with
this is this feels like home this is the this has integrity this is the place of
of um value of how to live this life and then to feel a commitment that that
this is how i want to be and so what kind of what can exist rather than being loving
there can be the wish to be loving we can't always love but maybe we can
always have the aspiration to love and sometimes that aspiration to
love means that the best we can do it today
is not to give in to our hate our hostility
maybe not giving in to hate maybe the wish to love commits us to pausing sacred pause
to hold in check any movement we have to hate us to hate
we we we hold and check our tongue we don't speak words of hostility we hold our our hands
in check to not express any physical expressions of of hostility
that this learning to to hold ourselves back
because we want to love is not a kind of repression but rather it's a kind of expression
of something that's deeper that wants to come out something deeper that's that's saying
wait hold it there's something more important here don't lose yourself don't give in to
something which adds to fragmentation alienation
don't give in to something that's going to burn yourself that some of the dramatic images of hate
and metaphors for hate and buddhism is that of a poisonous snake which is biting
itself or that of a fire that is burning itself when it burns
so hate we the fire of hate burns the person who's hating
uh the poison of hate poisons the person who hates
and one of the one of the dynamics of hate is that for sometimes hate is a
person's response to their own pain their own hurt and it's often said that
that hate that hurt
can evoke hate kind of blaming others and trying to
avoid the pain we feel ourselves by attacking other people and blaming other people and and turning the attention outward
so hurt can evoke or hate but then hate
in return evokes hurt and there you see there comes in a
vicious cycle one leads to the other and round and round and gets stronger and stronger
hate evokes alienation and alienation
is a condition that promotes more hate that when we end up hating uh we're
separating ourselves from the humanity of other people and then we're more alone unless we then
find companionship in other people of hate and we think we're connected then the mutual cause of hate what we're
hating but it's not really a very deep connection it's a shallow connection
and to get somehow supported or feel enlivened uh by hate is a kind of self-alienation
and the more we're alienated from others inhalating from ourselves then the more
the more that drives further hate hate brings alienation and
alienation promotes even more hate in buddhist language buddhist ideas
hate is a form of bondage and to be to be free
to to freely um you know uh do the wishes of our
jail keepers or jailers is not real freedom so to feel have the
freedom to express the hate and feel to be free and wonderful to express it freely is really doing the work of our
jailers it's just enslaving us or jailing us more and more in bondage
that people who are hating are in fact caught and diminishing themselves and jailing
themselves in these very strong feelings to find freedom is to find freedom
from hate to find the ability to allow something that's deeper than hate
to come forth and and move through us and so for those of us who are
practitioners one of the great possibilities for us is not to diminish ourselves because we
might feel hate or we might feel animosity or we might feel
we have prejudice and bias but rather to turn the light of
awareness on that to really be honest about that learn to see it and recognize it
in whatever form it takes our anger hostility even to anything
to keep turning back 180 degrees away from the object of our hostility
our prejudice our bias to what it's like for us to have the bias
the prejudice the hostility or even the intense hatred that occasionally can exist
and really be honest about it and see it and if we want to love ourselves
then we want to have the sacred pause and don't give into it but look at it
deeper and deeper and deeper what's going on here and um
and then to see find by and and bring with that the awareness that's calming the
awareness that is peace peacemaking the awareness is not hating or in
conflict non-contentious awareness so we can start relaxing and settling
the fires relaxing the hurt the alienation relaxing the way in which
we recoil from pain feel our own pain deeper and deeper
until we find where the healing is where the um where there is peace
where there's wholeness maybe where there is love and we discover that when we respond to
hate in the world with non-hate
that maybe it takes the form of generosity sending presents meals to someone in
prison who hated us maybe takes a form of forgiveness
the imam who was talking about forgiving the man who shot their mosque said it makes sense it made
sense to forgive him because he had apologized and so to discover the ability to
forgive to forgot discover the ability to
be friendly we don't have to be to love someone to be friendly and in
these all these expressions maybe we do discover how to bring more love into the world
how we bring more of a peaceful settling pacifying presence into this world to
benefit this world that's so challenging here
so i think one of the great tasks
these days in the united states and perhaps many countries in the world one of the
great noble tasks the important tasks is for us to
stand in solidarity with everyone who is a recipient of hate and hate
crimes the black people in the united states
the indigenous people the hispanics the lgbtq the asian americans
and the list goes on and on and also but to really more than just stand in solidarity and
support to be actively involved in making this world a better place and a safer place
for all and understand as deeply as we can the roots of hate in ourselves
how this works and to learn to develop the strength and the courage and the
confidence to always wish
always want to be loving it doesn't mean you have to be loving
it's a it's a difficult task but we can always want to do it and in
wanting to do it maybe we pause sacred pause to avoid
causing more harm and we at least don't
express actively our hostility to anyone and maybe then slowly we can
begin learning how really to meet the challenges of
this world with expressions ways of being and
loving and caring and and standing up
and speaking up in ways that are going to heal the great divides of our
society let's discover the common humanity of
all of us so that we don't live fractured
but we live together as a community a fellow a family a society
that cares for each other they all of us care for
everyone we encounter thank you