okay got it here so hi hi formerly hello
and welcome to happy hour everyone so so for the theme for
our practice tonight um i wanted to bring in something that i
have recently learned from this book i've been reading called
breath by james nester i think i mentioned it some
sessions ago and um interesting fascinating book
um and one thing that's interesting is some some study
some research that he cites about um exhale
exhale being very important and salutory so i want to bring this theme in
together with our practice and and merge them together so here we go
so so what i knew but discovered again from this this book
is that we can only speak when we're exhaling we can't speak or sing
when we're inhaling inhale then we talk and then we take another inhale and
and um it turns out that uh again according to to some studies
that exhaling fully exhaling completely and elongating the exhale
can calm settle quiet the mind and have some effects
on not just breathing but the parasympathetic nervous system um
and and so physiologically can be supportive and helpful now combine that
with a tradition of chanting i'm not a big chanter but the big tradition of chanting in
both in buddhism and christianity and there are many different traditions in the world
and and it turns out that apparently um
five and a half in-breaths and out-breaths
per minute is kind of the optimal cycle and also some people some studies
suggest having a quicker in-breath and a longer out breath
so it turns out that what he was suggesting is that if you take some of the
famous familiar buddhist chants and christian chants they are roughly the same length the
length that it takes to do the chant is about five and a half six seconds
which translates to this five and a half in breast and out breaths per minute so oh i thought wow that's an interesting
um discovery a coincidence so i've been exploring this the past few days and
i've been chanting and and elongating my exhale
um and exploring the you know the calming physiological
effect with the cultivation of meta cultivation of goodwill cultivation of
[Music] well-being in a way while being internally well-being internal
externally for the benefit of all beings so this is the theme i'd like to explore
um invite us to explore together tonight and or this morning whatever
your time zone may be and see how it goes so
so um and given that our practice here primarily is about meta let us
explore let us play around with the metaphases elongating them as
if we were chanting singing them and you're welcome in the space you are to
either say them out loud if you want at first or maybe
kind of hear them in your mind um in your mind's ear uh but be silent but
kind of make your exhale elongated so this this idea of of well-being internally good will
internally goodwill externally so you know in the past we've played
around just to put this in perspective um when especially when we did the series
on meta we've explored images we've explored different nuances
of the words we have explored radiating we have explored so many things and now here
we're going to explore the breath the duration of the breath together with
wishing well for ourselves for others so something new
in this exploration i'm excited i've been having fun exploring it and excited to share it
with you so so
let's begin let's settle let's settle into
ah let's settle into our bodies
arriving arriving
feeling the breath feeling the breath
the in-breath and the out breath
[Music]
nourishing this body
inviting the sit bones
ah to relax to give their weight
to the cushion to the chair to the earth
fighting our lower legs to offer their weight
to the earth and our feet
the entire lower body
so
i'm inviting
the inner abdomen as if
there were a line a vertical line
internally ah aligning our body
relaxing around that this vertical line is both having a
sense of integrity around it with our spine straight
and also relaxing around it
softening the chest neck shoulders
arms and hands
our face our jaw the eyes resting in their socket
letting the breath move through the body as it well letting
it be natural for now
in the practice of mindfulness we let the breath be natural receiving
it just as it is later in our cultivation practice
today with metta cultivating metta we will explore lengthening
the out breath with the metaphases but for now let the breath be natural
now if you would bringing i felt sense the image of someone you
care about someone who's easy for you you don't have a complicated
relationship with them when you think of them
sense of safety care warmth maybe a smile shows up
bringing them to your mind's eye
their felt senses alive as present as possible
now best to choose someone who's alive if possible if you know your way around
this practice and there's no longer grief it's okay to bring up someone deceased also
as long as they bring up joy and gladness
the sense of the felt sense of this being [Music]
this person this being could be a pet or a child
let's offer them the metaphases
you can say them out loud or just say them silently your mind's ear
hearing them elongating the exhale
experimenting i'll offer the long phrases for this
purpose
may you be safe from inner and outer harm dear one
may you be saved from inner and outer harm dear one
now the next race may you be happy and have joy
in your heart dear one
may you be happy and have joy in your heart dear one
may you be happy and have joy in your heart dear everyone
may you be happy have joy in your heart dear one
next phrase may you be healthy
and have strength in your body dear one
may you be healthy and have strength in your body dear one
may you have strength may you be healthy and have strength in your
body dear one may you be healthy and have strength in
your body dear one next phrase
may you have ease may your life unfold with ease dear one
in your home time experimenting with a longer exhale
and the inhale can be half inhale it doesn't need to be a full
inhale it turns out a half inhale is fine but exhaling fully
in your own time with the phrases as you wish whatever works for you
experimenting maybe slowing it down
may you be safe dear one
may you be happy
dear may you be healthy
dear one may you have ease dear one
may you be safe dear one
may you be happy dear one
may you be healthy dear one
may you have ease dear one
may you be safe
you be happy dear one
may you be healthy dear one
you have ease dear one
experimenting perhaps with saying the phrases out loud see what it feels like if you can
if you wish notice the calm that can come
the elongated breath when the feeling of air
lacking air that might come up it will kind of it will go away the sense of calm
stillness the air hunger will go away interestingly
may you be safe dear one
may you be happy dear one
may you be healthy dear one
may you have ease dear one
may you be safe dear one
may you be happy dear one
may you be healthy dear one
may you have ease dear one keeping the image of your loved one
may you be safe dear one
may you be happy dear one
may you be healthy you
may you have ease dear one
may you be safe dear one
may you be happy dear
may you be healthy dear one
may you have ease dear one
may you have eat may you be safe dear one
may you be happy dear one
may you be healthy hear what
may you have ease dear one notice the air hunger will go
away sense of calm synchronicity as if the breath becomes
synchronized with the wishes the images
sense of alignment arises after a while
after a sense of air hunger goes away
now bringing a felt sense of yourself an image of yourself together with your
dear being as if the two of you are sitting
together practicing together
directing the metaphrases to both of you and again let's experiment today
with saying them out loud extending the exhale
may we both be safe
dear one may we both be happy
dear one
may we both be healthy dear one letting go of the exhale at the
end may we both have ease dear one
may we both be safe dear one
may we both be happy
may we both be healthy dear one
may we both have ease dear keeping an image of both of you
may we both be safe dear one
may we both be happy dear one
may we both be healthy dear one
may we bow at ease dear one
may we both be safe dear one
may we both be happy dear one
may we both be healthy dear one
may we both have ease dear one imagining both of you and your
mind's eye receiving these blessings
may we both be safe dear one
may we both be happy dear one
may we both be healthy dear
may we both have ease
feeling the ease of the exhale letting go of the end of the breath
may we both be safe
may we both be happy dear one
may we both be healthy dear one
may we both have ease dear one noticing how saying the phrases out loud
has a different impact than reciting them silently
this
now switching to ourselves and if you wish you can put the palm
in your heart center in the middle of your chest to connect with yourself
and for this part if you have been saying them silently in the past so far
i do invite you to try saying them out loud now see how what how it goes what you notice
may this being who is me be safe receiving the blessing
may this being who is me be happy
may this being who knows me be healthy receiving the blessings
may this being knows me have ease in this moment
may this being knows me be safe letting go of the end of the
exhale may this being go as me
be happy and joyful
may this being who is me be healthy
may this being who is me i have ease in this moment
to continue to say it in this way or say i if you like
may i be safe
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i have ease
may i be saved
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i be we have ease
may i be safe
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i have ease in this moment
may i be safe
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i have ease at this moment
may i be safe
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i have ease
may i be safe
may i be happy
may i be healthy
may i have eggs
in your own time with your own rhythm
now turning the wishes or good will or menta radiating it outward to the entire world
from our heart our heart center touching ourselves first radiating out
touching all those who are near us near and dear
and far away may all beings everywhere be safe
may all beings everywhere be happy
may all beings everywhere be healthy
may all beings everywhere of ease
may all beings be saved
may all beings be happy relaxing letting go of the end of the
outbreak may all beings be healthy
may all beings have ease
may all beings be happy
may all beings be healthy
may all beings have ease
may all beings be safe
may all beings be happy
may all beings be healthy
may all beings have ease
as we bring this practice period to a close
offering the goodness of our practice to all beings everywhere
sharing the goodness generated even if we might consider or
judge our practice to have been shoddy trusting there is goodness here there's
goodness generated in this cultivation and aligning our actions with our
intentions of good will sharing this goodness together as a
sangha foreign wise
generosity and gratitude for this breath
letting go of the merits generously letting go of the outbreaths
may all beings everywhere be happy may all beings everywhere be free
thank you for your practice
so today we experimented
with the metaphrases saying them out loud actually and exploring
elongating the out breath as if we were chanting
not quite chanting but but as if we were chanting elongating the
out breath especially and the in-breath letting it be
as it was half-full and exploring exploring how the mind can
actually be more quiet become more quiet with this kind of breathing make more space
for the cultivation of meta because the mind is not going here and
there and everywhere in some ways you know i've explored i've
described the practice of menta as a three-ring circus whereas there is the image of the loved
one the deer being there is the feeling of metta and then there are the phrases here now
tonight we had the four rings here because we're juggling four balls and the fourth one
being the rhythm of our breath so what i noticed and would love to hear what you
discovered that as as i've been experimenting with
this breathing [Music] technique at first there's a sense of
air hunger that comes up when the out breath is elongated and in breath is half full and then there's a
sense of calm and peace the mind becomes more quiet and i
feel as if i've meditated for a long long time
right now even though it's been 30 minutes and i've been talking most of the time teaching so so
interesting so i'm curious what you explored what you discovered what worked what
didn't and you can type in chat if it's to everyone
i'll read your name as well as your reflection if it's just to me then i will only read
your question or your comment not your name you can also raise your zoom hand um
yes and bring your voice into the space so please don't be shy
especially if you haven't spoken shared in a while would love to hear from you what did you discover
this is new bleeding edge
neil please so i found saying the phrases aloud
made this complicated right there was like it felt like there was a lot going on
for me you know and you know i don't even always say the phrases
when i practice meta sometimes i will you know just say like the last word you know happy or something you know so
saying the whole sentences and saying even the longer versions to try to drag the breath out you know it yeah it made the meta less
accessible to me i think yeah yeah thank you for that observation
and and how are you feeling now afterwards given all the complications of the juggling of
these balls at the end of your practice well right i
mean there was a settling right i mean you talk about you know feeling settled
right i could say you know things started to be less bad at the end
right it's not quite the same thing as feeling settled um you know so so
so right so it left me you know you know wondering you know if i were to do this more and you know you know
get better at it you know perhaps you know perhaps yeah i don't know perhaps it won't be as bad i guess
yeah yeah yeah yeah interesting well it's it's an interesting exploration and
maybe some other things need to be explored so so let me mention something so i really
appreciate your reflection neil so um so
maybe something to explore is is elongating the breath but with reciting them silently maybe that
would make it less busy uh in the mind because saying is or maybe just
maybe it's too much to add in in one go so so that might be actually
something to explore and experiment with um and and
yeah getting another reflection here saying similar to you don't go away neil saying i had a similar experience my
mind was trying to keep up with the pacing of the phrases but it felt like i wanted to go slower so i muted the audio
so that i could try it on my own great okay so it seems like maybe the the phrases out loud and this
pacing um could seem could feel like too much
could feel like too many balls juggled so and i appreciate the person who sent me
the reflection so yeah trying to go out on your own pace trying to slow it down trying to go um and
yeah and and another thing that could actually maybe exploring this would be to try
just one phrase just try one phrase and that could be the repetition it could be that you know we're rotating or you know
going through the four phrases and the breath and it's just too much to keep in mind and i confused the phrases
at some point where i was too it's it is a lot to so so with the um what i was exploring actually um
um um what i was exploring earlier this week was was in another
uh chant which is actually mahayana chant is um which was mentioned in in this
book because the the meta chant again the metaphases can be more complicated so
so i'm just thinking about ways to explore so um [Music] uh omani padme om is what i was
[Music] exploring
and that has a rhythmicness or rhythmicity that can be helpful in maybe doing meta
to that so we can explore this is fun thanks for bringing this up neil we're exploring this together
uh stephanie says not sure if my camera is off or on uh i can't see you stephanie i'm not
sure uh so but but you say saying the phrases out loud felt so good
it felt energetic and i enjoyed my hearing my voice blending with yours nikki
visualizing my friend added energy as well thank you great thank you stephanie thank you for that
reflection also for adding that the energizing aspect
because that's also another thing that saying the phrases out loud can do kind of this energizing
we can't fall asleep because actually that's what chanting does usually on retreats we do chanting at
the end of the evening so that it brings up energy so you don't fall asleep so so so many
different you know we're exploring here together and figuring out what can work uh for ourselves so diana i see you
let's make this brief because we're running out of time for the groups so
at the beginning of the meditation i didn't feel right with the world at all at the end i had just much calm
and was really at peace i have a question about the in-breath what happened because i was trying to get enough going
and like sucking up and then how do you pace the in-breaths
yeah so thanks for that report and and and the question diana so so
according to this this these studies um the in-breath so it's um in-breath can be half-full and
this is kind of a practice so in-breath can be half-full it doesn't have to be full and the out
breath the exhale needs to be more uh more complete and in fact this method
is taught to athletes to to run or swim and kind of like in training to take a
half breath not fill the lungs fully but can a half breath and exhale uh extend exhale as
long as possible as a training so so that the body can take in more air and the calming effect i feel like
i'm running out of breath i know it feels like that but yeah but then
but it does then it kind of there's a sense of calm that overcomes the body when one gets used and again
we're exploring here we're being scientists of our own mind and body jerry says the extension of the
exploration over the inspiration was very calming yeah
yeah thank you jerry yeah it it tends to be very calming so so great thank you all for these
reflections very interesting what we discover how to tune it for ourselves how we figure
our own way through this these are just skillful means just skillful means of what might be
supportive for you so so let's turn and practice in small groups in
breakout groups of size of three and as always we start with um
15 seconds of silent um meta for one another and then share as
much a rest a little exploring this and um and here the rooms are created
with meta for yourself and meta for your fellow travelers okay have fun okay everyone welcome back
the rooms are closed so we have just a minute if there are any
reflections that you like to share from um
from what you discovered talking with each other please don't be shy go raise your hand type in chat
why did you discover
jerry says reinforce the calming effect being with others that's great
thanks jerry any other reflections
any thoughts any questions last chance on this practice so actually let's take
a little pool let me see if this is possible would you like to let's see how can i do
this poll quickly ah edit no i hm okay no this is not going to
work okay let's try this let's try let's try um
you can try your reactions so if you want to try this this practice again here in
different ways do a yes in your reactions choose choose a the green bar
if you don't want to try this ever again and happy hour do the red the x mark and if you click on reactions
i think you'll see the uh you can vote okay so we have 10 yeses
no no's okay all right so we had okay great so all right well we will try
it maybe we'll try it a little differently next time but yeah lots of yeses no no's so okay
we'll explore oh violet has her hand raised play what violet um it's 701 so i'll
formally close but i do want to hear from you i want to give the chance to people to leave but but i do want to hear from you so
is it quick or is it longer tell me
it's quick i just wanted to say i usually force myself to focus on the in-breath to stay awake so i liked the
permission to just do the out breath this time nice nice great thank you that was quick and
that was a lovely contribution so on that note the permission to
to really focus on the out breath which can be calming relaxing maybe we'll bring this again we'll
explore different ways of of uh practicing in this way and thank you all
thank you for your practice and exploring um yeah thank you all may all beings we
be well may all beings be happy including ourselves
thank you