so
good day hello
and perhaps this morning we are all both
welcomed by each other and we are the welcomers
and what a wonderful thing to be the welcomer and the welcomey
uh together and uh thank you for all being here and sharing this time
with the dharma with the meditation
and one of the words that i will use for myself
sometimes meditating especially when my mind is busy
it's hard a little bit to get centered in the present moment i'll tell myself in a gentle open
undemanding way i'll tell myself here h-e-r-e
and i see it as a reminder that i'm here and uh not where my thoughts are going
and not somewhere else and uh and it's um
and when i say hear then in the wake of that simple word
simple reminder i open all my in a sense i open all my senses up to experience what it's like
for this moment to be here and sometimes it's hearing sometimes it's sensing in my body sometimes it's
just knowing how active my thinking mind is
here isn't here in the present is a mind that's filled with thoughts
but i'm not involved in those thoughts it's kind of like i step back and i recognize oh this is what's happening
here and now and then in the wake of that that lasts for a
second or two or something before the thoughts take over or something and then i'll gently say it again here
here and it's not a command like you give to a dog it's more like an invitation or a
welcoming here into here and
it's quite special quite wonderful to be here but we want to be careful not to
uh evaluate here by the circumstances we're in
maybe you're in a wonderful circumstance maybe you're in a not so interesting place where you're meditating
but the wonderfulness of here is not the externals not just the
internal but rather the the way that awareness begins to grow
and flower in the middle of here and that enter the interaction the
mutuality of the place we're in the experiences we're having here in our
body and mind and the awareness that meets it that's the fully embodied here
and that is what can grow and develop and that and it's like we're developing
a capacity to be aware here and this capacity is what starts to
becoming very special and rich and wonderful and a marvel
and the capacity to be here in many capacities we're developing in buddhism
but one of them is to feel safe here and maybe where you're sitting and
meditating is a safe place just for these moments that you're here
and maybe there's a lot of danger in your life but here maybe for these minutes it's
safe and as the capacitive awareness grows we're also developing that capacity to
feel the present moment safety but it isn't just a safety that's around
us but also the safety that we bring with us as awareness grows
the awareness itself develops a capacity for
non-fear the capacity for awareness grows and develops here
and it's this interaction between our inner capacity for feeling safe or feeling having no
fear that meets the environment that makes it rich and valuable
and and at some point we realize that we have the ability to bring that non-fear to bring that
safety that's always here with us as we go into the world and go
into the places where it's even dangerous and so there's a different chemistry between the dangers in the
world and ourselves because we develop this capacity this ability to hold to have space for
the ability this inner strength to meet what's going on
so that's all to say that to say the word here simple relaxed as an invitation for you
to open to what is here
is a wonderful little practice it's so rich even though it's so simple the simpler
you do it the better so as we sit today we'll get started and do some of this basic usual
um you know getting settled and then at some point
you might want to uh on your own just in a nice rhythmic relaxed way
tell yourself the word hear a soft little whisper in the mind
in the wake of that say of saying that to be present for what's here
take in more fully and take in the breathing the body the
feelings the emotions whatever it is that shows itself that appears
in the wake of here so assuming a comfortable meditation
posture and
making sure that it's not only comfortable but also that the posture will express alertness
in some way a certain vitality
physical vitality that supports being here
present and if it's comfortable you can close your eyes
and gently take some deeper breaths maybe three quarters full
but deep enough so you have to do it consciously and that consciously deep breathing
deeper is a way of being more fully here
so that your mind is not so much drifting off in thought
and then a longer exhale than usual
not so you get winded or to strain but maybe a little bit at the end of the
exhale exhale more
at the end of the exhale pause ever so slightly
maybe saying the word hear and feel your experience in that
fraction of a moment of pausing
and then you take a deep breath in pause ever so slightly on the top of the
inhale here
in that pause
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and taking just a few moments to scan through your body to relax any holding tension in your
body the face the shoulders the belly
and then again attune yourself to the experience of the body breathing
and at the end of the exhale maybe have an ever so slight pause in
which you say gently softly the word here
and in this cycle of breathing in breathing out perhaps a
infinitesimal pause being here for your breathing
is there any point in the cycle where you feel safe
feel an assurance
or a lack of anxiety or fear
or the place in the cycle where there's at least fear
or the most sense of safety
and if there is such a place in the cycle or is such a
feeling in your body anywhere gently softly say here with it
hear and then feel it more fully
increasing your capacity to be here
without fear
you
um
remembering here
here being like a drop of water
landing in the middle of the pond the ripple of awareness
spreads through the about the pond
of our life silently openly
you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps to appreciate that as we develop our capacity
to be here that this recognize that this is an
inner capacity of awareness of of our
whole system psychophysical system being able to be present
for present moment experience
and that capacity is closely related to our capacity to
be without fear to feel safe
safe enough to feel or fear where that which is without fear
knows if we are afraid and the capacity to be fearless
to be without fear to feel safe is a profound form of trust
trusting that can be a gift that we provide others
that the more we know how to be feel safe
a safe safety we carry with us everywhere
the more we can offer that safety to others
we can be reassuring to others they have nothing to fear from us but
more than that they recognize
maybe they'll recognize that they are able to relax their fear
they can be more at ease and may it be that
this practice of mindfulness that we do that it develops our capacity
to share our absence of fear with others
that it shares our ability to be present
in a way where no one needs to be afraid of us
and may it be this practice spreads out into the world
a greater assurance reassurance for others that they too can begin to relax
be at ease may the extension or the
the influence of our practice spread out into the world in known and
unknown ways
to bring greater happiness and well-being
greater safety and peace and greater freedom
of heart to all beings everywhere
may all beings feel safe
may all beings be happy
so good morning and good day
continue today with a second talk on faith in buddhism buddhist practice
and so often that's the common translation of sadas s s-a-d-d-h-a
and um one word one translation i like for that poly word is trust
and uh it's a word where trust is the concept of trust is one that i feel
very feels very something very deep inside of me or very
rich and valuable and in some ways i feel more
connected to trust than i do through the word faith both words i love and
and um and i feel like the trust speaks a little bit more
to me to a capacity uh an inner kind of
quality of heart that uh we're evoking in practice that uh the word faith is a little bit
still residual association i have in english that it has a little to do with a belief
system that we have and maybe a little bit more intellectual than uh something that's more embodied
and more um you know connected maybe to uh our emotional life
and so trust and to be able to uh live and trust uh if we trust someone else or trust
something that i associate that with living without fear
this thing that i trust i don't have to be afraid of and and so
a faith a trust that is that is felt
as an as a deep sense of safety or an absence of fear at least
and kind of an assurance a deep assurance and some of this
is a capacity we can develop the capacity to be without fear
the capacity to feel safe and that's an important thing to appreciate because if we only know how to be safe
by rearranging the deck chairs on the titanic then you know it's not going to make us
so safe and some people feel like they have to just arrange everyone else and
arrange every thing and system and everything so everything's lined up so then they can
feel safe but the problem with that is it might work for a moment but things are always
shifting and changing and then we have to do it more again or the very the other thing that
sometimes happens the very effort to control other people or get other people to behave a certain way so
i can feel safe creates a kind of alienation a separation that can't do that that actually doesn't
really work when we can't really become safe when we're kind of forcing or requiring other people to be a certain
way for our sake and and maybe that's not the best way to
you know find safety in relationship and one of the one of the things we human beings are capable of
is developing and growing the inner feeling of trust the inner capacity for being without anxiety and fear
the inner capacity to not to be free
in a way that we're not as affected by the things of the world
maybe we're more porous and uh things don't hit
our identity or the what we're holding on to it as my egos me myself and mine
or maybe there's not the contraction of fear that world events
hits inside of us and and so we're not impacted as much by those in
some heart way so we developed a capacity of trust the capacity of safety inside
and and so some of that has to do with the buddhist idea of cultivation
a very important part of buddhism is to develop cultivate all kinds of inner strengths
one of those strengths is faith another is a strength of engagement of
practice of of efforting to be able to do and engage
the other is mindfulness itself can become a strength our ability for concentration for
stability for steadiness can become stronger and stronger and our capacity for wisdom for
discernment for seeing clearly what's going on can be developed and as these inner
strengths grow that that reinforces faith reinforces trust reinforces our capacity to feel
like we're capable of holding and being with what's there i love the word capacity
developing our capacity because it has two meanings in english for me
one is that it's in the inability to do something and some people they say that they have great capacity means they have
a great ability to do do certain things but another meaning of capacity
is that um it's like the capacity of a of a container
to hold liquid water a little teaspoon can hold a little bit of
water contain a little bit of water a cup holds can contain more water
a gallon jug contains more a lake will contain much more water and
an ocean contains even more so the capacity
to hold something can grow and develop and so our capacity for our awareness
our mind to our heart to be aware of things without
contracting without reacting without getting a fear afraid but to be able to hold it with some freedom or some
equanimity that can grow as these inner qualities develop and get stronger
and the advantage of that is that they would bring our safety with us because certainly there's dangers in the world
but we have this we've developed something powerful inside we we're less affected by it we're less
fragile what goes around goes on around us and some of that is faith developing
faith has a power that trust is a power that
that we have this deep reassurance that our life is
supported in a way that is is significant helpful valuable
so that when that it reassurance that trust means that we're not so caught up and
concerned with the details of what happens that
the recently
i lost something and now something that was kind of important it was i had hearing aids so i
thought i lost my hearing aids and i think years ago when i would lost something like this i would have gotten
quite anxious and afraid and now uh i lost them i looked for them
and um and uh i had this reassurance simple reassurance and trust that i can figure
out what to do from there i can find my way and um you know i have to have to i'll
get new ones i did find them eventually but um but so you know it's a simple maybe silly
example of developing a capacity uh to be able to deal with some
difficulty that in the past i wouldn't have been so easy but now i have this equanimity and peace around it
and so and so this faith the quality of this trust
is one of the really valuable things in buddhism is to trust the the practice
that the practice of mindfulness the practice of meditation the practice of
kindness compassion these practices are powerful and valuable
and there and to have enough experience of practicing with them to feel confident
these work but confident they work they support us in a in
many ways but one of the ways is that we know we had enough experiences with
them that we're confident even if i don't know what needs to happen here even if i don't know how to find my way
i have these practices that can keep me safe keep me without fear keep me
at ease it can support the situation to unfold in a healthy and good way
that somehow the situation will find itself the way forward and the way out of the
challenge that exists and so they have this this deep trust in the practice
and maybe eventually the trust and practice is greater than a trust in anything else
certainly greater than the trust that it says on the in the us dollar bills where in
god we trust you know how many of you to trust you know
money more than you know anything else but to trust yourself more than anything to trust the
practice i mean not yourself so much but to practice in fact
at some point there's a shift where the practice helps us not to be so caught in me myself and mine and we no
longer kind of we're no longer at the center of the play of our life the drama of our life
because now the practice is at the center and that's such a liberating thing to have happen
related to the practice is trusting the dharma not the dharma as teaching so much
but the that there's some something that's transpersonal operating here something that's not about me myself and
mine maybe it's within us but there's a inner wisdom an inner process and
unfolding a movement towards freedom that operates that is natural
and operates independent of the ego independent of my
self-preoccupation and self-concern in a certain way so some people might call it
transpersonal even though it's maybe within this psychophysical body
and so to begin having faith or trust in something which is within us
but it's not what you identify with as yourself this is a great freedom and to know that
and develop it gives a lot of assurance so faith as trust
and trust is a power that we carry with us and um and it's the power of being without fear
and certainly we wanted to be together with wisdom the power of wisdom
so we don't do foolish things without the absence of fear
but to feel safe to have this deep abiding feeling of safety that we carry with us
that's not easily threatened by what happens around us
allows us to then offer the gift of safety the gift of fearlessness to others
that they have nothing to fear from us and perhaps we can be reassuring presence in this world
and finally i'll say that the word for being for assurance for reassurance
in the ancient pali language uh is uh the literal meaning of it
is to breathe easily and so may we all find the ability
to trust in such a way to have faith in such a way that we can breathe easily
going through our lives thank you