so a
couple of words kind of to end this
meditation
before switching to the talk
because of the nature of these 16 steps
of anapanasati
you know there's more to teach as we go
along and
so maybe i'll be talking more guiding
more in meditation than
maybe than usual and
and what you might want to do and
consider
is to if it works for your life
is to meditate a second time during the
day
even if it's just 10 minutes 15 minutes
or another half an hour
and perhaps having a little more
practice with what we're doing in this
guided meditation
and or build with it or allow for more
of it to kind of percolate and develop
and
and then it might you might find that it
supports you more when you come so you
have
back to the guided meditation and also
you might
appreciate the time to have more silence
to explore this on your own
so continuing on the 16 steps of
breathing meditation that the buddha
taught
that does come from a variety of places
in the
discourses of the buddha the most common
one
place is a text called
discourse on mindfulness of breathing
and it's um in the what's a collection
called the middle length discourses
and there's been a variety of books that
are you know complex
explaining this or describing this the
descriptions are
16 steps are really just like cliff
notes just like brief sentences
and different meditation teachers will
have a little different take or
explanation of how these work or what
they are and which is appropriate
there's many techniques and
they're like you know these are just
kind of little placeholders for a whole
universe of
experience so we're coming into the
fifth
and sixth step of anapanasati
and it's the fifth one says
one trains in other words one practices
one like one practices the alphabet to
really learn it
one does it over and over again
one trains to
trains that as one is breathing in
one experiences
joy as one breathes one trains that as
one breathes out
one experiences joy and then this the
sixth
the sixth one is as breathing in
one experiences happiness
breathing out one experiences happiness
and um the um
so these words for joy and happiness
some people will translate uh like the
famous translator bekabodi which has
translated as a rapture
for joy and what i translate as
happiness he translates as pleasure
and and the difference between these two
is that uh whatever this uh the joy
factor is or
um is it's a it's something that's a
little bit energizing it's a little bit
it can be quite strong
but it's something that's a little bit
more
like a thrill in the body a delight
it's a flow of energy or flow of
pleasure
in the body that is kind of uplifting
and delightful and
and just has a lightening feeling
and and then the the next one that what
i call happiness
he calls pleasure is uh when the
energy energetics of joy quiet down
that that the pleasure of the joy the
happiness of the joy
remains something more subtle than
something has more
sense of contentment some people
um get quite attached to the energetics
of joy and
sometimes this feeling of ecstasy and
rapture and very strong
can course through our body wave
cascading waves of joy and
it's quite and it can be quite intense
and
but sooner or later people get a little
tired of the energetics of it
and then the energy the energetics the
upwelling energy of it
begins to settle and quiet
and now there's kind of a state shift
and and that uh
and uh and in retrospect we see that the
joy
has a kind of mental quality mental
energetics of it
that it settles and then we're more
subtle in the body
and then a more feeling of contentment
in the body
of well-being in the body tranquility in
the body
that for me feels like a very sublime
kind of
happiness but because it's more physical
some translators like to translate it as
pleasure
and because it doesn't have the mental
energy of it of it as well
and and so
uh and the operating word
verb is is one experiences
uh you could just as well translate the
pali language word here
as one feels when it allows when someone
really feels
what it's there elsewhere the buddha
says when this kind of pleasure or joy
begins to surface when it's allowed to
feel it in such a way
that one allows it to spread through the
body
and as i said yesterday the buddha said
this kind of pleasure or joy
is is not to be feared
and as not to be kind of dismissed or
belittled it's actually quite a healthy
thing to experience it
some people when they feel it finds very
healing
and it creates a context in the body and
the heart
in order to better kind of be present
for what is difficult it's not a denial
of what's difficult and painful in our
lives or
difficult emotions and what's happening
in the world around us
but it's easier to be present for it
with uh without uh falling victim of it
or being
oppressed by it or being you know
suffering ourselves
even more by it or feeling self-pity
but because we have this goodness we
have this joy happiness well-being
in which to hold um the challenges of
our lives
so um so uh there's something about
so this joy this well-being that comes
in this step
it comes a lot from really being uh
starting to be absorbed
or really intimate and continuous
with the experience of breathing it also
comes when there's more sense of
uh a wholeness everything is included
is being held at bay and so the earlier
steps
the steps of the body has to do with
really feeling the body and relaxing the
body
when the body is tense the body is in a
certain way not whole
so we're kind of cut off from parts of
it this kind of way
but as we feel the body and relax the
body there's feeling of wholeness of
gathering together
and that gathering together and becoming
whole is what contributes
to the joy arising it's kind of like
we're creating the channels we're
creating the
the openings for this well-being to be
there
that can come when we start becoming
really uh
um intimate or connected or continuous
in the attention and so the awareness
itself
gets gathered together to really be in
the present moment
with the breathing as opposed to the
thoughts jumping around here and there
and about what's for dinner and what i'm
doing tomorrow and what i did yesterday
or something
the the mind begins to the wholeness the
mind also begins to gather around
just this experience here the mind
itself now
centers itself on the experience of the
body just breathing
and this i this centering itself in the
body breathing
has the joy or the delight of we know
the the problems of our life the
preoccupations the agitations the
anxieties that are
um that are fed by thoughts and
perpetuate by thoughts
begin to quiet down and so just that is
a relief
to have and then we uh and then this
the combination of the
the mind's intimacy the awareness is
intimacy with the whole experience of
breathing in
and the wholeness of the body then it
tends to
start producing from the inside out a
sense of
goodness which is my kind of generic
name for a whole
whole class of things family of things
we might feel
joy delight satisfaction contentment
pleasure that
thrill wonderful feelings that come
and and they don't they come back for no
good reason
for what's outside in the world nothing
has to be better in the world in our
you know it just comes because of this
really this intimacy and gathering
together this harmony
harmonizing of our whole being that
can come when we're really present here
so the first four steps of anapanasati
which can take a long time to kind of
really do and have a lot to do with
really finding ourselves really present
here
in a whole way in an embodied way in an
inclusive way
so it's not a narrow tight little
concentration
but rather a centering on
everything's included and everything is
centered so the image i have for it is
a big bowl that if you take a
a marble and drop it into this big bowl
it'll go up and down and around and if
you
dip lean into the bowl and push the
marble
you can just keep it going it just keeps
spinning forever if you keep pushing it
but if we stop pushing it slowly slowly
it'll come to center at the bottom of
the bowl
with the whole bowl is there but
it's center it's resting at the center
so the same thing with our attention our
thoughts our
awareness that we keep spinning it uh
pushing the marbles in our mind with our
thoughts with our involvement with our
interest with our reactivity to things
and the mind just the thinking mind just
spins and goes and gets distracted
but as we leave it alone then
everything begins to settle gather
together and we support it with our
practice of intimacy and getting close
to
breathing and and
and then with time we find we get
centered at the bottom of the bowl
centered on the breathing and this can
starts becoming a very pleasant
experience
and uh very enjoyable and if
this uh the the joy factors begin
bubbling up within
and the buddha's description of this
is i think i said it recently is that of
an underwater spring
flowing up into a lake
and it just flows up from the inside and
spreads out
and so with a for example sometimes you
can feel that with the inhale
it's almost like there's an underwater
spring under deep in her torso
right down near the base of our body or
uh
base of our chest or something and
as we breathe in there's an upwelling
feeling
of this and then as we exhale perhaps
there's a feeling of it flowing all back
down again
and flowing out because flow and flow
happening
of this pleasure this energetics this
lightness
they can be quite subtle when it begins
happening
and it's good to recognize it and
realize oh this is actually a good thing
to pay attention to
don't look for it when it's not there
don't try to manufacture it
and don't feel like you have to have it
this fifth step
and sixth step of anapanasati
it's you know only only sometimes it
begins to come happening
the core practices the first four and
this is so beneficial just to stay in
the first four for a long time
in a sense the longer we stay with the
four the stronger foundation we
allow ourselves to have for what follows
but uh unless you learn about this
potential for
joy and pleasure as part of the
meditation practice
then you might not appreciate it when it
happens you might not recognize it when
it happens
and then you won't kind of include that
or become whole with that let that
spread and open and
receive it through your body and all
this requires some modicum of a quiet
mind
it doesn't have to be completely quiet
there can be some thoughts in the
background or
light thoughts so don't be at war with
your thoughts and think you have to not
think at all
that just produces tension but
there is a quieting that happens as we
practice
so
mindfulness of breathing and
i hope that you'll have some
opportunities through the day and
through meditation
to appreciate and value and enjoy
your self-breathing thank you very much