so hello and welcome to
this edition of happy hour practicing
mata and the brahmavihara is together [Music]
so so for our practice today
i'd like to invite us to um
to break to our mind and hearts today in our practice um
meta for our collaborators our collaborators past present
and future our co-creators people with whom
or beings with whom we have collaborated in the past personal projects
um work projects um
volunteer work because
none of us is an island and the work that we dedicate ourselves
to whatever it might be it's always a collaboration the
co-creation of some kind of some kind sometimes it's more
apparent more easily noted that it's supported by the work of others
sometimes it's it's a brainstorm and working together creating
so [Music] so
there are one reason why it's helpful it's important perhaps to practice with in this way you
know with with let's say with practice of meta kindness
good will we do this practice in concentric
circles as you know right we start with ourselves and go to benefactors and
friends neutral beings um and then to those we have difficulty
with and all beings and when we get to the all beings category all beings
one way that traditionally all beings practice is
taught because if you just think of all beings in a way the mind kind of goes a little numb like all beings it's
kind of hard to imagine all beings we divide it into lots of different
categories different you know categories of beings that are like this or beings that
are like that so just so that the mind can kind of grasp oh yeah these beings oh yeah then these beings so that
there's a sense of relatability right so one way to think of this practice as i'm introducing tonight for us to
consider people we've collaborated with or collab will collaborate with or just collaborators as a category is both as a
way to think of it oh yes as this unique category we usually don't think about of all beings so that we can kind of rock
it connect with this category and also it's a category that's kind of
spread perhaps over some of the other categories right amongst the collaborators could be
people that um are our benefactors our work are what we contribute to the world
really depends on their work depends on their goodness on their gifts to us some of them might be dear friends so
the category of dear friends like oh yeah we really like these collaborators they're just good friends
some of them might be in the category of neutral like we don't quite know them yet maybe we'll just we're thrown into a
project to work together in the past or present or future some of them might be in the category of
[Music] guess what those we have challenges with
that wonderful category of people who are our best teachers and really seeing
the areas of um of entanglement in our heart where our
heart has entanglement so so this category there's a has a lot
going for it has a lot going for it this collaborator category so i'm just
bringing this to life and again right now may not you know you may not be working you
might be retired but i trust you've had collaborators in your past the past again either work or family
groups maybe you've hosted a party together or you know a reunion and
you've had collaborators so just people you have co-created with so
that you're not alone you're not an island we're not an island and also in this way
humility comes in we don't do things on our own so many
causes and conditions and people [Music] support us and we support them to
co-create what is what is here in this world so it also brings up a sense of humility to not just all me me me we
come together so so i hope i have convinced you
that this is a juicy category um that has a lot of implications
and and uh and also to to invite you to be creative with it and don't say oh i'm
retired am i working right now but just be creative with this who are your collaborators now who have
been maybe in the past who knows what the future might bring so have fun with this see how you can
um inhabit uh fill in this category with all the gifts that it has with humility and
co-creation and seeing our parts and other people's parts and all of that so
it has a lot going for it there's a lot of good threads here so okay
i have set the topic up let's begin let's
let's land let's settle ah
let's arrive let's arrive
high in our bodies
as always we start by landing and arriving
in our body with our breath
landing
turning our awareness inviting our awareness to turn
to this body their breath
all the parts of this body collaborating with each other
all the systems
our lungs collaborating with the oxygen
collaborating with the blood carried through our body
collaborating with the heart with the central nervous system
in the brain the muscles
the digestive system
the bones the skin
gosh so many collaborations
within this body alone appreciating all this
orchestration coordination
where we seemingly don't have to do anything about it
or the beneficiary
uh
receiving the breath
in the abdomen
settling relaxing [Music] muscles with each out breath
me
this
and first i'd like to invite us as we continue to stay embodied with this
theme of collaboration [Music] to bring to bring to your heart to
yourself this being who is you
as a partner as a collaborator
in your projects in your life and this collaborator who's you
sometimes a benefactor
supports you loves you is caring is generous
supportive
some time
they serve but they show up as a dear friend as a good friend
patient
appreciating [Music] your good qualities as you
appreciate theirs what they bring to this collaboration sometimes
you show up for yourself as the person you're having challenges with
having patience gosh why couldn't this person do it do
it this better as part of this project i have some humor about this
invitation i'm bringing in seeing all the ways in which we our own our own collaborators and this
categories these categories show up for us
you can see if you can appreciate all these different ways that you show up for yourself
this collaboration that is your life your projects your work
the sense of humor appreciating the gifts
the goodness the talents
the idiosyncrasies the challenges the shortcomings
with humor with warm-heartedness
see if there can be some tenderness towards these very variations
especially towards the collaborator you're having challenges with now then
they're doing the best they can
may you be safe may i be safe your manner and out of harm
wishing you all for all these versions of yourself
may i be safe all these versions i offer myself my psychological safety
benefactor dear friend maybe even neutral sometimes and
especially to the version i sometimes have challenges with to the self i sometimes have challenges
with may i be safe
for myself may i be safe to myself
offering safety i offer safety
to all the ways i show up for myself
it's okay doing the best i'm able to given all the causes and conditions
of my birth my genetics my upbringing
all these collaborators different versions of me
may i be happy
may i be healthy
and may i have ease
may i meet the moments of my life
as i create co-create moments of my life with ease
as much ease as possible
may i be safe from
myself for myself
inner and outer arms
may i be happy and joyful as i co-create my life
may i co-create it with joy
as much as possible
may i be healthy may this body
that's the ease of well-being and health
may my life unfold with ease may i co-create my perception
ways of being ways of seeing that meet the conditions of life may i
co-create my life may i meet moments with as much ease as possible
now i'd like to invite you if you would bring
to your heart now some collaborators there are people you're
collaborating with now anything
work volunteering [Music] family
people you have collaborated with in the past
both just as good
letting there be open of heart appreciation for the gifts
for the goodness the talents for the challenges
for the streams of our energy coming together
to co-create something bigger than ourselves than each of us individually
appreciating with meta and care and warmth
thank you may you be well i wish you goodness i wish you ease
may you be safe
may be happy
may you have health may you have ease in your life
you can consider each individual one at a time
you've met it to them one at a time or as a group
all of you are all of us collaborators
see what works best for you in this moment what's needed
do
could be with the phrases of mentor as you wish them wish them
safety [Music] happiness health and ease
or without
make sure you include yourself
in the meta goodwill good wishes appreciation
may all of us collaborating co-creating together
for something greater than each of us alone could bring to this world
offer this world may all of us be safe
have a happy heart
of health and well-being
heavies
preaching that our son the sum of all of our efforts talents
devotions including challenges it's bigger bigger than each of us alone
appreciation gratitude
love and kindness for the grace of this
co-creation collaboration do we be bigger than me
for age persons talents and gifts
their values their goodness the complexity of their lives
they have just as rich an inner life in a world
as i do
wishing us all well
present or past
c if you start to think about the project
or people come back come back to the breath to the body
and just to the sense of good wealth just to the sense of goodwill
hmm
acknowledging that your collaboration with
these collaborators is impermanent it has arisen
and it will come to an end at some point if it already hasn't it's
all impermanent it's all impermanent and what is more
important to you in collaboration if it's ongoing right now
fostering goodwill care generosity
service
may all beings everywhere be free
thank you all thank you for your practice
so so i've just changed the settings you're
welcome to share your reflections questions comments observations and chat
and if they're just sent to me i will only read the reflection not your name
and if it's to everyone i'll read your name also you can raise your hand your zoom hand your physical hand i may not
see so what
what did you notice what was it like for you what did you discover
barbara please
oops you're still muted
oops still muted let's try that one more time
down here yes can hear you now uh as i was thinking over
my uh sort of a life time a career of working in different
ways with different people the
so many collaborators and i must say now that i'm retired my very best friends are former
collaborators from different jobs you know decades ago
and that the bonds formed by someone who's really a good collaborator
is just worth their weight in gold
yay that's a beautiful reflection yeah that there's so many friendships
have come from deep engagement beautiful engagement together yeah
very sweet thank you for sharing that
abraham please oops where did abraham go
uh oh there you are there we go hi hi
so um two thoughts one was that uh maybe because i'm a very opinionated
human being i there's a lot of collaborators that i have in my life
that we didn't necessarily call ourselves collaborators
more like competitive but you know that's that's the whetstone that
sharpens the knife you know the people that you rub up against really hard they teach you so much or they
i got learned a lot the other thing because i am older maybe or maybe a
young person would do this too but i have such a lifetime of people
uh it just was flooding me at times it was like as i was doing meta for this
one it would trigger me to go here and trigger me to go there it was it was quite uh
quite a flow of of ideas so i'm just interested in how that happened for
other people thank you abraham yeah
thanks for that share and also the invitation if others want to share and for me i'll share from my practice i
think for me what what called to me most today was to um have meta for for one project that
i'm currently working on with some collaborators just they lit up they really lit up just i just stayed with
them it was so yeah just their presence i appreciated their contribution their good will
their talents their skills and just taking their perspective it was just
so hard opening and brought in more humility and and appreciation for for
their being their roles all of that all of us together again as i was saying the streams coming together
so much bigger than any of us alone so that's that's the way it showed up for me neil
i see your hand please so
so i mean i i you know i found myself thinking about the people who come and pick up my trash
you know i mean you know that's not like a direct collaboration perhaps but but gosh they sure make my
life easier and you know i mean right and who who who who made
that truck that they pick it up in and mind thee or i mean you know right i mean you know i found
myself thinking about lots of people you know and who made the discoveries right i mean it went back you know it
went far back in time and wide across lots of areas you know
certainly you know my parents who gave me their dna um you know i mean
you know i mean i had reasonably competent parents but even if i had terrible ones they're still the ones who
gave me their dna um you know i mean you know even if even if that was the
end of their goodness i mean that was like a good deal um it was a pretty big collaboration for
to make a meal happen
maybe regrettable but i mean you know i just i mean there were just so many people who seemed involved
you know right right right you know the people who keep the lights on i mean
yeah lovely thank you neil i'm just delighted
hearing the way it showed up for you all the all the
millions i don't know how many uncountably many uncountably many collaborators through
your life and that's how this practice showed up for you tonight which is beautiful it makes me happy to know and
and to hear that just the variety the way he showed up for abraham and for me and for you just it's all different all
good whatever is needed whatever the heart is calling it's all beautiful these beautiful reflections there's no
right way to practice this these are just invitations so yay
delighted so speaking of that we will now
the invitation now is for us to engage in a collaboration a small collaboration of
a group of roughly three together collaborating in a small sangha
co-creating with each other and hearing as abraham invited like i wonder
what else showed up for people how did it show up for them you get the chance to hear and share with each other
so i will create the breakout rooms and again let's start with maybe 10-15
seconds of silent meta
and wishing each other well and then share as little or as much as you wish
by your practice have fun with your collaborators your co-creators
here you go okay welcome back everyone welcome back
the rooms are closed and we've got a couple minutes for any reflections questions
oh as you're coming out of rooms i heard folks say deep bows and hugs oh that
just warmed my heart that was so sweet to hear it was so sweet to hear so please don't
be shy especially if you haven't shared today in a while love to hear from you
what did you discover with this practice what did you discover
sharing your insights your wisdom your question your confusion for the benefit of all beings
it's all good
especially if you're shy you're invited you're hesitating like oh i don't know about this talking in public thing lisa
please hi thank you nikki this talking group
helped me remember so i had a class that i've been in for four months and today
and it was such a wonderfully supportive group with
the teachers and other students like definitely a collaboration and i was feeling really sad
like about the impermanence and then hearing my two
group mates like talk about other phases of the journey where they are in that process like of
starting a collaboration and what comes up with that or like being past one years later
and reflecting back and it just helped me remember and not be so stuck and focused on the
ending because i was really going down into that like pulled into that understandably but
so yeah so the dovetailing with the impermanence and like just being able to
see being reminded of like the fuller cycle yeah
so thank you to everyone thank you lisa yeah thank you for for
sharing that that's beautiful i love the juxtaposition of his appreciation and the sadness for this ending is like oh
yes it is impermanent and the cycle in the ear from all of that yeah beautiful thanks for
sharing that that's lovely katie i think it's katie
it's my first time in the sangha i'm very very thankful to be here um we were just in a breakout room with
marianne and uh barbara and i was the class to share so
the continuation of that was uh i really reflect
that on all the color collaborations i've had throughout my life and the culmination is the color advocacy
that i have now um
the past year or half year like i've just been in spaces where the right people like couldn't be more
perfect people for around me supporting and supporting each other and
supporting the same [Music] cause for a more peaceful loving world
and it's all in these like intimate
and beautiful thank you so much for sharing
yeah that just the synchronicity and and and the what a blessing good
collaborations can be that's what i'm getting from there's so much appreciation so much
heart there's so much gratitude oh my goodness all these collaborations wow i'm so blessed
yeah and and gratitude for that arising and here you are you're new at hour and
this is here's the new set of collaborators for you this is beautiful thank you and welcome it's lovely
thank you and we're at time and abraham i see your hands up is it quick
because you've already also spoken before earlier today so so actually tell you what i'm going to stay late and then i want to hear you abraham
but just to respect the time let's bring bring it to the end also given that you've spoken so so
let's bring it formally to an end it's 702 but i'll stay a few minutes extra how's that
so thank you all thank you for showing up thank you for your practice
for your collaboration your co-creation in this sangha may all beings be well
may all beings be happy [Music]
thank you