so
i think many of you have heard from me
and maybe
other buddhist teachers and teachings
the value of being embodied
so much so that i sometimes will
with kind of imagine that it would be
nice if we had translated
sati not as mindfulness but as
body fullness it's such an important
part of this practice
and in the two classic buddha
teachings by the buddha on mindfulness
practice
in the discourse the four foundations of
mindfulness and the discourse on
mindfulness of breathing it begins with
an emphasis
on mindfulness of the body and
now one of the reasons for this
is that the body the more present we are
for our body
the more we're aware the more there's
awareness that's alive and
and kind of available through the body
the more the body becomes an instrument
for the growth of meditation practice it
becomes the vehicle
in space for some of the deeper feelings
some of the deeper
qualities of meditation that begin to
arise it's kind of like as the body
receives some of the benefits of
meditation
those benefits are augmented or or
not augmented but those those benefits
grow and
fill out and we get the most out of them
so
what i'm talking about here partly is
that as the body becomes more alive and
more sensitive and more of
an instrument of sensations and
experiences and feelings
it's not just feeling the body itself
but it's also start the body becomes the
the sensor for feeling
some of the goodness that comes from
meditation and i would use the word
goodness
in a very abstract vague way like
just like maybe like the word all the
some of the positive feelings that can
come with meditation
so um classically it's joy and happiness
but it could also be contentment i like
the word ease
quite a bit um there can be
uh gladness there's
deep feelings of equanimity deep
feelings of
of confidence that can arise
even feelings of being of inner
cleanliness and inner
purity that really are embodied feelings
that
kind of course through us so all these
qualities
are felt more fully when they're felt
throughout the whole body
felt with the body if the body is not
available
then it becomes a mental thing and
sometimes that's quite
wonderful and profound in its own way
but it's really especially in the
beginning stages of meditation
it's really a way of being quite limited
in the experience and it gives us a
different impression of what meditation
is about
and different orientation which if it's
too
much towards the mind it doesn't really
help us
develop the wholeness
the unification of all of ourselves
which
is ideally what we're looking for in
buddhist meditation
i think it's one of the meanings of
samadhi is unification
bringing it all together here present
so the so again the body is not just a
you know a a bunch of physical stuff
that we have to carry around with us
the body is a is a significant
uh repository of nerve endings
significant uh location for
uh the emotions the feelings the the
goodness of meditation to course through
us or to fill us
and be here um
the um the
so to begin tuning in being relaxing the
body
sitting in with the body feeling the
is uh one way in which we begin to
um open up to this repository of
goodness as i said classically what
comes next
after the first four steps of
anapanasati what comes next as a
practice deepens
is some feelings of well-being joy or
ease or
gladness and something like and so
uh to know that that's coming to know
that's part of meditation
um it can then encourage us to be a
little bit more sensitive to when they
start
appearing hints of them appear and we
start feeling
a little bit these good feelings that
come
sometimes it feels like pleasure in the
body or tingling at places
a sense of lightness that comes and
it's not that we're trying to make it
happen so much or
or searching for it or striving for it
but when it begins to show show
themselves a little bit
there's an art to opening to them
to relaxing with them to include them so
they go along with the breathing or the
breathing goes along with them
so we encourage us to become even more
embodied
to feel these in our body and as we feel
this goodness
to kind of breathe with it and open with
it and continue this
process of feeling and sensing and
developing
as we go along and
so the contentment is part of this
to feel contentment allows
it isn't like again a moral obligation
to feel content
but it allows for this filling out of
the practice and really
being rooted and centered here in this
body feeling more and more
the same thing with this idea of being
in the present moment and not thinking
about the past and future
it's not like a moral obligation we have
to do that
but when we're no longer caught up in
the past and future in thoughts
it allows for possibility of filling out
more into the wholeness of this
moment that includes so much more of us
and it's kind of like a
momentum a movement towards becoming
really whole and present
with all of who we are and part of that
comes along with relaxation and and
tranquility calmness is a more and more
space for
delight and joy well-being a
sense of pleasure and just being alive
and being
here and i think of this joy of
meditation
as being a joy that has no opposite
it's just a joy that exists kind of in
its own way
if it had an opposite then you know it's
we can swing
from one to the other but it has no
opposite so
certainly we can not have it not be
there but it isn't that it swings it's
not part of a pendulum that goes from
one to the other
so for example if your joy is dependent
on
praise the opposite then is blame
and then the pendulum can swing because
it's dependent on
getting something or if your joy is
dependent on
success then there can be failure
if it's dependent on physical pleasure
it can be dependent on
things being uncomfortable and so
but the joy of meditation does not have
an opposite
it just has this wonderful simple
and clear quality of surfacing and
arising and being here
without really in a sense not depending
on the things that come and go in the
world so much
but is a wellspring that flows within
the body and so the more we can kind of
center ourselves in the body relax and
be present
the more
we will be
you know starting to open up to our
potential our capacity
for well-being for joy for happiness
and and that's a wonderful thing and
it turns out that meditative joy and
happiness
is a wonderful it continues this process
of unification of wholeness bringing
more and more of ourselves into the
picture
so that we can
continue on a path to liberation