good day good beginning of the week a minute
and um
so it's probably a little confusing for some of you that we've switched now back to
meeting at 7 00 am for the meditation and i think it was over many of us it
was quite wonderful to be starting at 6 45 last week and have the 45 minutes sitting
and the plan is to do that again next week starting on monday
and then we can assess for one week and then we can assess whether to
continue this way somehow or other or do it once a month or not do it at all
and so the in terms of the
16 steps of mindfulness of breathing we've gone through the first eight and
today is to introduce the ninth and that is to become aware
of the mind knowing the mind breathing in one knows the mind
breathing out one knows the mind and what exactly
the mind is is a fascinating topic and maybe there's no final
to be made about what the mind is some people call it the mind heart some people call it the heart the pali
word is chitta and i'll talk more about later but for
now i want to say that use an analogy
that if you're driving maybe on a long trip with the car and you just don't notice that slowly
the windshield is getting dirty it slowly slowly builds up over time
and driving is so important you're very focused on the traffic the road the driving itself
and so you're focusing on what's beyond the windshield and so you don't really notice the
windshield but the windshield's getting more and more dirty and what you also don't notice then is
the strain to have to look more carefully through the dirt
so this is an example of how if um we might not know recognize the filter
through which we are aware of things because we're often focusing on something in
particular just like we're often when we think we think about something
so our awareness is usually about something we're aware of but how we're aware is not really so
easily seen or prioritized and then with the driving if you could
stop at a gas station and wash your window and then get in the car and you go wow
now it's clean that is impressive and and you realize how much easier and more
relaxing it is to drive without straining through the dirty window so
so this is what uh the topic is for today is mindfulness of the mind and uh take a
while to kind of really explain what it is but with that introduction
uh please begin in your meditation posture
and and uh if your mind is going to be about
something thinking about something aware of something
be aware for a few moments of your posture and to really become even more aware
you might kind of sway back and forth rock back and forth
and re-establish your posture maybe making smaller movements as you
kind of really get settled and kind of whatever you know
make a small adjustments really feel where the posture is
comfortable not comfortable aligned not aligned in a way that works for you
maybe there can be small adjustments
and then letting the body become still and now the focus of attention can be
maybe the stillness of the body
just what it's like to have the body still not moving
and if in feeling the still body there feels like more adjustments are needed
herb would be good please do
and the next focus of attention can be
the breathing of the body wherever breathing is most easy for you
to experience in the belly the movements of the chest movements of
the air going in and out through the nostrils
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
three quarters full and for as long as it's comfortable for
you a long slow exhale
long slow exhale when you get to the end of the exhale
briefly maybe then just barely perceptibly pause
before you inhale pause so the inhale
really feels like it wants to start itself and allow it to start
and then letting your breathing return to normal and now bring your attention
to focus on the parts of the body that might be easy to relax
maybe the muscles of the face the eyes almost like the muscles of the
face can be spread wide to the side maybe
where they can sink down sliding down the bones of the skull
perhaps as you exhale the softening of the shoulders releasing of the tension
and then softening the belly
if it's difficult to soften relax the belly be content to do it in very small
degrees maybe relaxing around the place of most
tension
and then let your attention receive the experience of the body
breathing in the belly the chest the nostrils
or globally all of that in some easy way
maybe letting there be
a little pause at the end of the exhale
maybe just barely perceptible a relaxed pause
and then allow the inhale to start itself receive the inhale
receiving the inhale and awareness
riding the release of the exhale
releasing yourself with the release of the exhale
releasing your thoughts as you exhale
and as the thoughts release maybe there's more space in the
awareness to feel the fullness of breathing in and
breathing out
and then also notice if there's any tension or pressure agitation in the mind
and as you exhale perhaps you can soften the mind
release the tension of the mind
soften the thinking muscle
maybe where the sense of the mind becomes more open
expansive mind has mind has more room
lots of room in which breathing in and breathing out
is known
and then become aware as you're following your breathing
become aware of how you're aware what's the attitude or mood
that comes along with being aware
what's the mental atmosphere
is the general mood or atmosphere [Music] attitude of the mind
is it pleasant or is it unpleasant
is it more on the side of contentment or of discontentment
is the quality of the mind field does a mind feel more small
located in a particular place or does it feel more large
expansive may be difficult to locate in any one
place
the general quality of your mind your inner life
your mind heart
what's the emotional tone not of particular thoughts or impulses
but the background tone or the
atmosphere of it all
and without any kind of judgment of how it is
what happens to you as you gently honestly
recognize something about the quality of the mind
the mood the attitude the atmosphere
not to be thinking about this with more feeling or sensing
a quiet awareness
of the mood of your mind state the state of the mind
and then whatever state of mind you have if you're aware of it breathe
with it as if breathing accompanies it
breathes through it
or whether or like the state of the mind accompanies the breathing
breathing in knowing the state of your mind
breathing out knowing the state of your
mind
in the way that you might experience humidity in the air
or the warmth of the sun standing in the sun
see if you can experience the state of the mind
the overall mood overall gestalt
of the inner mental life
is a characterized by a wanting
characterized by an aversion pushing away
they characterized by confusion
is it characterized by stability and presence or by distraction and
jumping around it's all okay just experience it as it is for you
breathe with it
and if it's possible to relax the mind or expand the mind
so the boundaries of whatever mind is are soft boundaries open boundaries
no boundaries and resting into that
expansive mind settling into the open mind
and breathing through it breathing with it
breathing at the center of it
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
maybe you can discern that or know the difference between
a mind that is small and closed and
involved in itself and a mind or heart which is open
open to receive and feel the world around it
maybe the difference can be like trying to talk and see someone through a
closed class door and then having the door open
and then seeing them and talking being with them
to open the mind to open the heart for it to be expansive and wide and
the mood and atmosphere the state of mind receptive and available
and in this mode either doing so or imagining it so
be take in the people of your life
people you might see today or talk to today or
think about today people on the street in your
neighborhood in your communities
and to let them be received or known with a heart the mind wide open
at least for these minutes or two we're sitting here at the end of
meditation a time and place where it's safe to be
open-hearted
and then see if there's a greater sensitivity a greater
tenderness heartfeltness
in considering these people when the heart the mind is open
and then taking the idea of whatever that's come from this meditation practice
let it be offered up and be offered for the welfare and benefit
of others whatever calm or centeredness or
peacefulness may it be transformed into kindness for
the world care for the world may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so we're beginning now with the ninth step
of anapanasati mindfulness of breathing in and mindfulness of breathing out and
the ninth step really builds on what what was earlier some teachers who teach anapanasati this
practice of 16 steps will insist that you should always begin with step one
and systematically work your way through all the steps as far as you you've gone so far you know and
there's some advantages to that some people's minds really like having order and having a real clear definitive
steps the mind gets organized it gets focused it gets concentrated knowing what it's doing step by step
other people find that it ties them in knots to do that that kind of trip over themselves it's too much trying
too much expectation and some people find that that it's good to be familiar with all
the steps and then as we sit and meditate i discover where we are
where the where the salient step is and sometimes we can start on step five
or start on step you know even step eight or even step nine any any of these steps because we sit
down and we're that's what's kind of available in a kind of way
and then sometimes we move through diff up and down in the course of a meditation so these steps are
can be done linearly linearly for those who find this beneficial and they can be more a resource for
those people who want to track themselves and understand kind of the domain the territory of what's
happening in their meditation any any one time what the emphasis is and um
but we get uh to then to the ninth step and one way of appreciating this though is
that um one way or the other it's helpful that the earlier steps have been
been familiar been developed in some degree and that's because the more we're
grounded in our body and the body is relaxed the more we begin opening up in a holistic way
to our experience and we begin kind of working through some of the knots some of the tanglements and tightnesses and tensions
that we have and then and then to go to the second
tetrad five to eight is to begin to fix feeling sensing
the emotional tone of the body and if you're quite relaxed and focused
it's a contentment and well-being and then with that it's easier to begin
trusting it's okay to relax the mental activity we don't have to be so actively involved
in fixing solving remembering planning criticizing whatever the mind is doing
and the activity the mind can bring to rest and this also this resting is releasing
bringing making the mental activity calmer continues this process of becoming more holistic being more
inclusive more open to our experience and then based on that the experience of the mind
becomes easier to experience so step nine is breathing in one experiences the mind
breathing out one experiences the mind and i love this word experience that
could the poly word could be translated as to feel the mind feel the the you know
feel the mind and um and so it's not thinking about the mind it's not having
ideas about the mind but it's something that is more holistic more broad and using kind of the
the range of sensory apparatus we have to take in our inner life but the mind
is not the details of the inner life not the particular activities as i've said the mind is just a sum
total of its mental activities but it's the way that we
can somehow take in the totality of that whatever way our mind and i want to
emphasize our mind your mind experiences the mood the mental state
the overall overall configuration or the kind of balance of it all that's what we call mind
and i say that because there's a lot of people who would like to have the mind
be something in particular to define it to know what the mind is and i don't think that that's really the
emphasis in this buddhist practice is to know in some abstract way what the mind
is and that's a topic for some other occasions some other purpose than
meditation in meditation we're only interested in how each of us experiences our mind
and for some people the word heart is a better translation for cheetah c-i-t-t-a
some people even translate it as heart mind and uh the um
but it's the kind of the it's the it's the so the state of the heart the state of
the mind the quality of our inner life it's the mood the atmosphere it's kind
of the sum total of how all this works and sometimes there's a predominant
mood of the mind so the predominant mood can be one of desire or
lust or strong wanting and and everything is kind of seen through
the filter of the strong wanting and the there's almost like the mind has a force overall force like give me that and
it's quite something we have a cat at home and it's i kind of delight somehow and amazed to see the cat definitely has
desires and it seems like everything and the whole catness is focused on getting what it wants and it's clear
that it you know the desire is there and and so the mood of desire this
disposition maybe mind is kind of like the overall disposition that we have
and and sometimes it's not desire you can feel the difference
between a general mood characterized by this desired design and one which is not
sometimes it's aversion hostility ill will and that's kind of you can kind of see
it sometimes in people that there's like almost a cloud of anger or hostility around them
and you know that atmosphere i'm sure is being experienced or could be experienced in the inside as well
or there can be the absence of ill will there could be love and then there can
be confusion that characterizes it all and the mind is jumping around not knowing what it
wants to do and doesn't understand kind of a lost feeling that's kind of the general tone of the
mind or the absence of confusion maybe there's clarity wisdom
the overall mood of the mind mind state can be one of destructibility jumping around
scatteredness or it could be one of being present and
undistracted and then one of the great ones that the tradition talks about
is one can know the mind is being expansive or large
or one can know the mind is not being expensive not being large
and this points to how as we become as we develop this mindfulness and as we develop a reflexive
awareness of awareness itself of the mind itself that seems to change the mind
that seems to change the kind of it's harder than to focus on on only the things that we're
thinking about or things we're aware of something begins happening when we're aware of awareness
aware of the mind that knows or then where the mind state it's kind of like if someone points out to you how
dirty the windshield is in a car then now you drive and you're now you're aware of the windshield you can't
you're not focusing on it but you can't not see it anymore so to become aware of the mind
changes the mind because the mind is not a physical thing
the mind is the one way of understanding it's a kind of this kind of the sum total
of the mental activities that are operating and one of the key mental activities is
the knowing of itself if the mind is known if we bring attention to the mind
and the attention is a not for or against the attention is not
with expectations with demands with criticism it just kind of a relaxed equanimous
allowing awareness of the mind that's a mental activity in itself
that then feeds back into the formation of the mind as a whole
and so we're shaping our mind all the time maybe the brain doesn't change that much
the mind is very flexible the buddha emphasized the mind is very very changeable
and and it changes with all our moods and activities and what's going on and so
mindfulness itself meditation itself does have an effect on how we experience
the mind and as we and here the instructions are
know the mind or experience the mind breathing in and breathing out
as we do that um because everything we do has with the mind hasn't
feeds back onto shaping the mind the experience of the mind we have and so now we're in this kind of can you
start being in this kind of um loop this kind of cycle this kind of where as
the meditation deepens uh we're bringing more and more equanimity more more
openness more and more receptivity to whatever experience is including that
of the mind and that has
creates some of the ver brings those qualities to the mind itself
so one of the reasons why in meditation practice we're trying to develop an equanimous mindfulness that's not for
or against experience it's good in and of itself but as that gets stronger it
feeds back to reshape or reform the disposition of the mind the quality
of the mind the state of the mind so the mind itself begins feeling more receptive
soft expansive and and all kinds of wonderful things
we'll talk more about so it might be that it's difficult to uh
some of you to follow what i'm saying but um but uh maybe you think about it as a
mood you're the your mood that you're in or
the feeling tone the emotional tone of your inner life of your mind your heart and
and you can certainly be aware of it anytime at all but to be aware of it after having
meditated for some time for example the more or less the first eight steps
kind of prepares the ground for mindfulness of the mind to have this
wonderful feedback loop to continue to condition or
open the mind in a more deeper and deeper way that will allow for concentration to
develop so i'll talk more about these this mind thing over the next couple of days
so um in the meantime what you might do
is as you go about some of your daily tasks maybe some of the common things you do
something that you maybe do regularly through the day maybe washing up or cooking or driving or just
going for you know whatever you do why don't you start noticing the mood
with which you do it and then really know the mood and don't
just check it off oh you know i'm annoyed at the exercise
and don't just don't just check it off really experience the mood take time to
and one way to make sure you give enough time to experience the mood is to breathe with the mood take time
just breathe with it for a while and get to know it and start recognizing your mood
and start recognizing also how your mood shifts as it is known
as you experience it as you breathe with it and in daily life as you go through the
day don't overlook the windshield by looking
through it on to what's on the other side so um thank you all very much
and um and i'll say it a few times so this week we're meeting at seven o'clock
and um and then next week we'll meet next monday we'll start again at 6 45 for that week
and and because i'll be on retreat again and so it works really well from connecting
the two for the retreat practice and what we're doing here on youtube
so thank you very very much and i look forward to tomorrow