so good evening everyone and as we come here today
uh for me uh a few things that come to mind one is that it's been it was 20 years ago just about now that
we bought this building so it's kind of a little bit of an anniversary it's also the
first time for me to come back teach here with people here in uh
you know for a year and a half or more and before that almost 30 years i taught
almost every single monday so like that kind of was a big big big gap so it's kind of a big
wonderful to be back monday evening and i'm so happy to see some of you that
all of you that i know they're here thank you and those of you on youtube are watching
thank you for being here and i see the names in the chat and it's lovely to see the ones i know
so i'll say i'll do a little bit of beginning to the meditation and then we'll sit quietly
and then one of the ways of understanding meditation
is that initially it's preparing the ground so that we can see
in some clear way and so we're preparing ourselves to be able to have that clarity of insight
clarity of seeing and so we're kind of we're the variety of things we do at the
beginning are kind of settling in some people like the language of
settling in letting go and kind of doing less just being and some people like the language of
constructing like we're constructing our temple we're gathering together organizing ourselves in such a way
that we're kind of here in a qualitative at identifiable way like i'm really here
i'm not wandering off not thinking about the day anymore i'm really here
and uh and that and that ability the higher the greater the ability to really be here in
the present moment that opens the door to see in a new way
and i'll talk about that in the dharma talk so in a sense this meditation is a
preparation for the seeing that will be emphasized in the talk
so to let this body of yours
be the become the meditation hall
the real meditation hall is here in your body
and to take a few long slow deep breaths in order to begin
establishing yourself here
and letting your breathing return to normal
and for many people the beginning of this process of arriving here
is to relax and not just relaxing them up the
muscles and face shoulders and belly
but relax into this time and place now
settling into being here
and in a gentle loving way perhaps caring away
begin gathering yourself together so you
collecting yourself here in this time in this place and if the mind wanders off
gently lovingly unhurriedly
invited back bring it back collect the mind
bring it back here with the body in the present moment
bring the mind into the body so the mind is not wandering off in
thought just here
slowly steadily gathering yourself collecting yourself
here at this time at this place moment by moment
as we come to the end of the sitting
one of the descriptions of meditation practice
is collecting ourselves here into the present moment
and gathering together all of who we are
so it's all together here in a singular package
of presence of attention and one of the advantages or
opportunities with this is when we're gathered together and not scattered and
distracted disconnected from ourselves
there's more of us to meet others
there's more presence embodiment
more receptivity a greater capacity to listen
to attend there's more of us gather together to
care and to be kind respectful of others
there's more of us here to love
and it's a gift to give more of ourselves over to be with others
so others can feel met seen heard known
respected and cared for
may it be that this meditation we do this evening
supports us so that we can bring ourselves more into
a full human connection with others at a time when people many people still
feel very disconnected and isolated and
may we bring ourselves to greater
kindness and support for this world of ours may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
could you turn that one down that went down to one
so good evening again and i'm delighted to be meditating with people
in the same room and for the last year and a half i've delighted with sitting with people
who were on the other side of the camera and i appreciated also also we're going to
see their names and greetings and chat and that was quite lovely but it's also very nice to be here with you all thank
you for coming and uh it's the beginning of uh
you know hopefully beginning that we'll continue now to develop that we can open up and people start gathering together
as a community so the idea is to for us to
continue on mondays being open the way we are with people who are registered and signed up to come
and uh and then diana who's been teaching this holding down mondays throughout the pandemic
thank you diana and the idea for the next while is that
we'll also alternate uh teaching here so diana will be here next monday and i'll be the following
and so on for a while that's kind of the general plan
so thinking about a talk for today i thought that
this is kind of a new beginning here that i thought that a really good place
to begin is with the four noble truths they're considered kind of a core teachings of the buddha
and it seems pretty symbolic to start with that pretty
evocative for me to kind of start with as they say that all the
buddhist teachings can be subsumed or held within the
four noble truths the ancient analogy that they come from india just like of all the animals in
the forest their footprints can be held inside the footprint of an elephant
this is big enough to hold it all so the four noble truths are big enough to hold it all
and down through the ages there's been many understandings or interpretations of the
four noble truths and uh there isn't like a singular understanding in fact the buddha
suggested that he said there are innumerable explanations for these four noble truths
they're very rich and and evocative and and now rather than taking them as being a
singular thing that there's only one thing we learned the basic idea of it
and then we learned to apply it to ourselves into our lives and discover you know how it means for us
there's a mahayana buddhist teaching that in this universe of ours there's lots
and lots of uh kind of world systems with people who live on planets all over the uk cosmos
and all of them have the four noble truths and then they go through a long list of what those how they they talk
about the four noble jews and all these different world systems it's like a long long long text
and that's mostly just a list of all the different formulations of these four that could could exist
so this idea that there's many so i'll offer you you know one one of them which
is based on the early buddhist tradition and uh
and you'll see if it's nice for you and that's an introduction to it
um if
if you
say you rent an apartment someplace and you you day to move in and everything in
apartments all good except in the corner of the living room there's an old radio
that's uh that's really grimy someone must have spilled food on it long ago and
it's not very nice but but you know someone forgot it or left it curious you said what's that doing
here and uh the thing is it's on and it's on some
really kind of the kind of radio station you'd never want to listen to and it's on
and so you look at it and say wow this is not right and maybe you get angry at the people there
before or maybe you feel spread a self-righteous letter to the to the landlords and
and say you know this this radio was left here and it's a real problem or
maybe you should go out and buy a bigger radio to put in front of it to hide it or maybe you should uh
find another apartment or all these thoughts and that goes on for days and weeks you know trying to figure out what to do
about this radio that's on all the time and then one day you finally decide you realize
you know i could just turn the radio off and you know at least you don't have to hear that terrible radio station all the
time so it's possible to
have all see all kinds of things wrong in our world in our society
or with ourselves and miss that there's a little button
where certain things can be turned off and maybe that's a little bit too
dramatic of a story analogy but uh but maybe uh it's worth kind of
preparing for what i'm gonna say that what we're looking for in the four noble truths
we're looking for trying to understand ourselves to see what
what we can do to stop suffering to turn off the button
of our suffering and what and to do that we have to understand our contribution to it
what are we doing to attribute to the radio being on and where can we turn it off
and there's lots of things that are wrong with having the radio there and they left it there and it's dirty they didn't clean and
it's the wrong station and you know what was the landlord thinking and you paid a deposit and this is what you get
so you can do all those things but the radio still blares and you can turn it off
the fact that you weren't treated nicely or respectfully by the previous tenants or someone may be still true
not to be denied but if you want to sleep at night you want to turn the radio off
so the four noble truths are a means it's like a little four
four like a little uh description
of four steps or four areas by which we can understand our life
to help us understand what is our contribution to our suffering to our distress
what are we doing that's adding to it not to diminish you know necessarily taking care of
things in the world but what is our contribution and because your contribution to your
suffering that you have some ability to do something about
whether you can change the world around you is maybe you can maybe you can't
and some people will spend an ordinary amount of time trying to change the world around them
changing their family changing their work their boss their co-workers their
friends trying to get them all to behave just right and their neighbors or whatever
and sometimes the track record the success record of doing changing the world to accommodate
ourselves and make it all right is not so high and it isn't that it shouldn't be
done but if it overlooks where we can make a difference it's a
little bit sad and so the art of it all is to look where can i make a difference where can
i change something and this has to do what i call our contribution to our suffering
and so these the schema of the four are are offering perspectives to get us in
the territory so we can begin understanding what our contribution is
so the four are the first one is a very simple and uh it just says that
it's the noble truth of suffering that's how it's translated into english
the ancient language buddhist language the word suffering literally means painful
and so it's saying that there is there is what is painful there are painful things in this world
but it's uh what we're looking at now is where the suffering is so where is the emotional pain what's painful
emotionally where's the distress and now the second noble truth is stated
very simply it's the arising of this painful thing the rising of this suffering
the third is the cessation of it the ending of it and the fourth is uh that there is a way
to the ending of that suffering the middle two the arising and the
seizing are uh it's a very important to see
because this is where we understand that our suffering is not hardwired in
it's not like we're born with this suffering and therefore we're gonna they can't do anything about it
it's something that comes and goes it appears and disappears it might seem like it's constant
and seems like it's solid and unchanging but in fact in in its uh
his essence or something in its own nature it's actually something that's arising and passing and coming
and going and that's the good news because if it was solid and unchanging then
there's no hope but if it's something that comes and goes then we have some possibility to do
something about it we have some possibility to to find it another way
so the first noble truth is just an acknowledgement that there is things are painful
and all kinds of things are painful uh you know so let me and then the list
that the classic texts give are things like birth is painful
old age is painful sickness is painful separation from our loved ones is painful
non-separate not being separate from the you know people who are difficult is painful
there's all these things that are painful so there's acknowledgement yes there is this pain in the world
but the second noble truth says and then where what is the suffering
that is arising that appears in you
and that's the idea of your contribution where is the suffering that appears within you
that has its genesis in what you're doing or where you where you left the radio on
what is it what is that and it and then that the text points to
that it has to do with the suffering that you can do most about
is a suffering that is craving and the word is usually called it's
usually the classic the original word is uh thirst which is meant to kind of like a thirst
for power or something this drive or this compulsion
by which people are not free we're so driven by something that we have to have it
and this driveness that where we can't put something down
we can't stop what we're behaving is the genesis of what's this the
suffering that we can do something about that's where we contribute to our own
suffering so that's what we want to understand we want to understand
the craving the thirst the drive not only because it brings about
suffering but it is suffering it's painful to be caught in the grip
of these of this you know craving of thirst of
things you can't put down and i think meditators have developed a pretty good sense of this
because it's one thing to kind of just go about your day and feel like you can't put something down
but you sit and meditate and you see the mind just kind of churning away with its preoccupations concerns and drives
is i say wow this is powerful this is suffering sometimes the promise of getting what we
want the imagine and the imagination of imagination of it hides that it's that it's actually
distressing and uncomfortable to be under the under the the yoke of compulsion
of craving because but but it's hard to see it if you're focusing so much on the thing
you're going to get if i can get if i only win the california lottery i have to win the california lottery then everything's
going to be okay and i can just imagine i'm going to build a swimming pool if i get a california library it'll be so
great with three temperatures you know and it'd be so great but you don't see that that drive
maybe is a kind of uh desperation it's kind of comes out of maybe loneliness or even
fear and security all kinds of things that it comes with as we meditate we start seeing this
and at some point we see that it's not solid
it's not fixed it's something that it has is porous
something that's inconstant something that comes and goes but in order to see that we have to be
somewhat quiet and gathered and collected and have the ability to really
see and that's why i made it one of the functions of meditation
is not to sit down and right away just see what's going on and have insight in some deep way
but meditation is partly to settle us enough quiet us enough just enough not dramatically
but enough so we can really start seeing that the porousness of our suffering
the inconstancy of it the coming and going of it
and as we see that more and more we see that there is possible to be without it
it is possible to bring it to an end that it can cease
and uh because we we taste that very fleetingly perhaps but we say wow
i've had this this resentment for two years
and i thought it was solid it's like a mood that i carry around with me everywhere but now i see there's flickers of times
when it's not there wow it's not always there
and to the in the buddhist practice the idea is to appreciate those flickers appreciate those moments it's not there
and that's that can be hard to do because an absence like that doesn't count for much
and because the um the drive the craving the wanting the
ideas the stories we tell ourselves come so quickly
that they override the flickering moment of peace the flickering moment of their something
what got quiet and wasn't there though it's not like these waves that
come and they come and because they come so much we don't see the small little gaps small little
pieces go on but as we start this meditation practice that at some point
we start seeing there are gaps it's it's porous
it's not so solid it's not so constant as i thought
and it can give a lot of hope a tremendous amount of inspiration comes then
oh there's another way and at some point those little gaps the flickers
begin showing us that we can be at peace there's little peace here there's a little bit of ease here
even though it's only there a flicker it's there i know it's there i feel it
now the task is to begin to grow it to recognize it more
and the task for doing that with mindfulness meditation is to just do the same thing over again
just keep settling keep looking keeping present but know where to look
if you're still writing letters to the landlord about the radio you're looking in the wrong place
you won't see that the switch to turn it off if you are
so so you need to look and learn how to settle and turn the attention here to
yourself and i like to think of that as turning around to become intimate with yourself
get really close and intimate get to know yourself well feel yourself sense yourself
allow yourself to get collected and gather together it's like a wonderful thing to do for
yourself to feel yourself gathering together collecting unified
where the mind and body and the heart are all operating together at the same time in the same place
and primarily that's the task of the mind to come into the place where the body is
because the body is always in the present moment and so the mind is often not
and so it's a task of the mind to come back here be here and it's possible to do that
that job of mindfulness of gathering yourself together it's possible to do it with lots of love
lots of care lots of compassion lots of generosity to
oneself that each of us counts each of us is important
and so so much so important so valuable that it's worthwhile
being here for yourself gathering together collecting yourselves settling here
becoming more embodied more present more more yourself in a sense
in this process that begins quieting the mind and the gaps
become longer the porousness gets bigger and we start feeling more and then just
flip more than more of more than just flickers of peace of well-being
but becomes you know moments the moments become minutes the minutes become hours and they grow
so life is life is painful in all kinds of ways
turn the attention to understand where that painfulness is here in yourself
and you'll notice that craving attachments clinging is a whole slew of words that buddhism
uses that move those movements those activities are painful
and it's hard to appreciate that they're painful if we're too focused on what we're clinging to what we want or what
we don't want so the art of turning the attention 180 degrees around
to feel and sense hear be with yourself and feel like this is where
this is where my contribution is to my suffering this is what i'm adding
is that craving that thirst that resistance that hatred
and we said oh that's what it is and then we feel it
and then it's be with it breathe with it sends it embody it a certain way
let the mind get quieter with it and you start seeing its porous nature
it's flickering nature the gaps you see the rise you see that appears and disappears
and one of the great moments in this whole process is that
you're sitting around minding your own business and
maybe a thought of some intense something you're very attached to arises you can feel the attachment come along
with the thought but you didn't have it and now it comes
and you see it wait a minute you watched that happen oh wow
look at that it wasn't and now it's come into existence and you are wiser than it you've now
been watching it without identifying with it and being caught in it you see it arise there it is
and then you might also see that it disappeared and then if you're interested in that
process interested in extending those gaps discovering more and more about how to
bring this craving clinging to an end then you come to the fourth noble truth
and the fourth noble truth is the truth of the way to that cessation that we're not just
the small little gaps but a really you know qualitatively significant way
in which something really drops away and
and the classic description of that is the eightfold path
which is a a set of eight practices that are meant to encompass our whole life
all of our life because if you really want to make this four noble truths
really deep really thorough and complete so not just flickers or momentary
it should be something that relates to how you live your whole life so how you speak how you act
what kind of work you do how you live with your own mind how you pay attention
how you be focused what attitudes you have as you go through your life
and what understandings you have that through which you see
how to behave and how to live in this life so eightfold path is right view right
understanding right usually says right intention or right attitude
right speech right action right livelihood right effort
right mindfulness and right concentration and so to begin be it to be inspired
maybe only if you're inspired but inspired by this possibility of bringing the suffering to an end
right make these flickers last longer then it helps to create a bigger
foundation to gather yourself together to be collected and really show up for yourself and be here
and that's what the eightfold path is about to live that faithful path
so that freedom is not just a flicker but becomes uh you know
a um you know something that's more regular in fact that that's what becomes
constant at some point the sense of the freedom from clinging the freedom from this contribution we make
so a simple way of asking yourself this question is what am i attached to right now
so if you're suffering we ask where am i attached right now that's one of the questions that turns
the attention around 180 degrees and then not only what am i attached to
but where is the attachment where do i feel in my body and my mind
and my heart the contraction the clinging the tightness
that we can do something about and if you in the long term learning
to understand your contribution to your suffering and learning to end that contribution
is the most reliable thing you can do in the dharma and it'll it'll you'll learn it well and
you it's phenomenal how it changes one's life the confidence it gives the ease it
gives the peace it gives and the wisdom it gives for how to navigate and
and work to where this life and live this life
so we're interested in our contribution to our own suffering
and i think it's a very mature thing for human being to take that take up that interest and really study that and look
at it and not enough people do it too many people i think are looking outside of themselves
for how the world contributes to our suffering which is certainly a worthwhile thing to
do sometimes but if that's the only thing we do then we gonna live for a long long time
with that terrible radio station blurring and it's nice to turn it off
so those are my thoughts for this uh beginning and um
so there are other dharma talks to be given the four noble truths that are possible and other
interpretations other takes on them but that's what was here today
hopefully it was a fit for you to give you something to think about in orientation
so thank you very very much and uh i look forward to seeing you more and
i know all of you that are here so it's uh i've seen you before and
it's very nice to have you back and be together after all this time and thank you so much and
for those of you on youtube thank you very much for being part of this and
and i look forward to having this chance to do this with you
again thank you