so good day to everyone and good to be here with you
and the topic uh continues to be for this week samadhi
samadhi meaning usually translated as concentration
and one of the verbs associated with samadhi is abiding
to dwell or abide in these different good qualities of samadhi
and learning to abide is uh
you know is lingering is due is uh result residing in these states
as opposed to being in these states and striving or pushing or trying to have more
and the tremendous value of when we get settled have landed here in the present moment
and feel settled here to learn how to abide in those states
and the biting is not a passive thing exactly though there's very little doing and
it's very consequential which i'll talk about later so to abide also is to be receptive
to abide and allow the goodness of a particular state to nourish us to
penetrate into us so and a lot of samadhi has to do with
letting go and so we could understand it a little bit as
abiding in the goodness of letting go abiding in the nourishment
that happens when we let go so we'll start this meditation
and and we'll do this abiding and receiving of
this nourishment or goodness of letting go of relaxing
so to assume a beneficial meditation posture
with some care to take a posture that will allow you
kind of a maximum amount of relaxation without falling asleep a balance between
remaining alert but allowing for deep in a sense deep body work to happen
as meditation kind of begins penetrating into all the different corners of our muscles
and allowing for deeper and more thorough letting go
and to gently close your eyes and without breathing deeply this time
just simply sitting here i'll direct you to relax different parts
of your body and as those parts relax linger a bit
with whatever good feelings are there with having relaxed kind of let yourself
take in even if the good feeling is a real kind of relief a local relief
of not being tense or maybe there's a pleasure
allow yourself to abide and receive the good feelings that might come
with relaxing so on the exhale then
relaxing the shoulders
releasing the shoulders and
perhaps there's a way to also release and relax the arms and the hands
so from the shoulders all the way down to the fingers
relaxing releasing and then receiving whatever lingering good feelings are there with
that however mild or small
relaxing the muscles of the face
and even if there's also uncomfortable sensations for now receive the comfortable ones the
pleasant ones as you relax your face
as you exhale relax the belly
sometimes harder to feel good feelings with a relaxed belly but maybe there are
some that linger
also in the legs the thighs and the calves all the way
down to the feet these are some the muscles there be released
and feel some good some nice pleasant feeling of vitality or
relief and then bring your attention to your
breathing as you breathe as you exhale
see if you can relax your whole body on the exhale and feel whatever
goodness comes from that relaxing
an opening a softening a settling
perhaps more of a sense of flow and vibration in the body
and the exhale itself is a kind of letting go
allow for the full letting go of the exhale
and not always easy to feel but maybe you can feel some parts of the exhale
the release and letting go
as a nourishment as a good feeling
the exhale part of the goodness of the exhale
is letting go of thoughts as you exhale
letting go of thoughts and letting go into the body breathing
in whatever openness receptivity there might be there at the end of the
exhale receive the inhale
let go your thoughts your thinking as you exhale
and allow yourself to feel how that might be good feel good or
pleasant to not be caught up in your thoughts and
thinking and abide rest in
the quiet and openness and receptivity of awareness in your body
that remains when you let go of your
thoughts
and then as you inhale in the abiding with the breathing
there can be also a receptivity in allowing the inhale to arise
the inhale to arise in the vibrating
flowing tingling vibration of the body
to abide and receive here in this body
and whatever letting go or relaxing you do relax in the body relaxing the mind
releasing the exhale whatever settling in that happens
feel and sense and abide
in the good feelings that are associated
reside in us in the goodness of it
allow it to nourish you to spread through you
staying close to your breathing
with a letting go of the exhale and the allowing of the inhale
each within the abiding here in the goodness pleasantness
that is also here
letting go into receptive state receptive with your body to the
pulsing vibrating flowing dynamic sensations of the body
allowing them receiving them where part of the goodness
is the receptive state he is the simple abiding and receiving
and to feel the goodness of abiding receiving
this body this body breathing
letting the thinking mind become quieter
so you can more fully abide and receive
so
to abide in whatever goodness
pleasantness enjoyability there is here now
and breathe within that breathe with that
quietly receptively
with an inner quietude that is sensitive available
receptive simply to abide here and now
with whatever is here not trying to make anything happen
just abiding in whatever goodness is
available
so
and as we come to the end of this sitting
to abide here in the present moment
for these last minutes to abide
not to do anything or accomplish anything
but to be at rest or at ease in one own one's own skin and body
and whether you actually can do this well or not you might just imagine yourself
in a circumstance where you can just abide just be rather than do
some place where you feel comfortable and safe and settled
where you have all the time in the world and no pressure
and in this state in the privacy of your own mind and
heart let others the presence of others
abide also here with you
so that others are abiding around you or with you without requiring anything of you
needing anything of you
and in this way perhaps you can open up a kindness a care
maybe even a love good will that it's almost not a doing
but more how the heart vibrates when nothing is needed you feel safe
and you take in the humanity of another person
and without requiring anything that you do or say to the person to
people can you gaze upon them kindly
gaze upon them with goodwill
and may they and all beings be happy
may the people you think of and all others be safe and peaceful
may the people that you consider and all others be free
and may it be that the benefits of this meditation practice
in seeing in unseen ways intentional and unintentional ways
may those benefits spread out to benefit the people around you and the
world around you may the goodness of your meditation
be for the welfare and happiness of all beings yourself and all the rest
may it be their meditation changes the world for the better
[Music]
uh so the
11th step of mindfulness of breathing is breathing in one concentrates
breathing out one concentrates concentrates the mind
and so this relates to the whole topic of samadhi in buddhism words often translated as
concentration and and we're spending more days on this
step because uh the samadhi is such an important foundation for the
final steps of mindfulness of breathing and we don't want to rush through this
ideally you're kind of coming along a little bit following just enough getting a sense or
a feel for what we're what these steps are about that you have some inner reference point for what
we're doing as we continue going on even though the next steps are getting to
very kind of more classically are describing deeper and deeper states of
meditation these 16 steps are also relevant
on well short of deep states of meditation you think we kind of can go through them
even in relatively ordinary states and recognize kind of little shifts that
represent these different states so i'm hoping there's enough by going slow
enough that that you know you can follow enough so we're spending more time with samadhi
and um so um i've already said some of this that um
the the word in this 16 stages for concentrate has also been translated as
steady and i like to translate it as unify unific to unify the mind
or steady the mind or
stabilize the mind the word is uh samahadati and the
the verb adati means to um to play something so it's like placing
them placing the mind or placing awareness on the object that we're focusing on so
placing it on the breathing i love the expression landing just landing on it
and just kind of gently landing like a like little helicopter held a drone or something or
like a bird that comes in and just kind of i guess it flies in almost stops in in
the air inch or so above the ground and then just lands on the ground so we come right in
there we land and um and settle place ourselves
the i'm very fond of using the word compose composure as this
we're composing ourselves on the breathing and that samadhi is an act of composing ourselves
because of the word pose also means to place or to stand someplace so we're taking a stand and
resting in there and um and um
to settle to study are all these words associated with samadhi
and now samadhi itself is often translated as concentration but it
more generally means meditation or a state that we're in a state of mind that we're
in that can be many different states where we're quite settled and steady and peaceful and and i want i wanted to read
you very early uh commentary the from the um a very early commentary
where it lists it kind of defines samadhi and it's a wonderful definition
a whole series of little definitions samadhi means embracing
samadhi means completion samadhi means single pointed
samadhi means unconfused samadhi means unscattered
samadhi means undisturbed samadhi means unperturbed
samadhi means liberation and the next one is particularly nice
next series samadhi is seeking harmony
samadhi is acquiring harmony samadhi is receiving harmony
samadhi is grasping harmony taking hold of it samadhi is
entering harmony samadhi is going along in harmony
samadhi is a light lightening up in harmony
samadhi is being lit up in harmony samadhi is harmony welfare and happiness
so it's like i think it's a wonderful list this idea of harmony
or evenness or balance the word is sama s-a-m-a and um
and so you get a very different feeling for samadhi from these kinds of descriptions than
you would if you just told that samadhi is a one-pointedness of mind and when you talk about when you talk
about these absorption states jhana which sometimes the way that they're talked about they have the intensity and
a kind of laser idea and people really try hard to get into it not
really realizing a big part of this samadhi is letting go relaxing
settling deeper and deeper and deeper and then but for these
jhanas these absorption absorption states the verbs related to them are entering
the states and abiding in them and this idea of entering is a i think is a beautiful image that
we're not looking to zero in we're not looking to force ourselves to be a state but rather
we're kind of entering into and i like to think of entering into a sacred uh
area a sacred piece of land or a temple where we enter into with some reverence
and respect and care and how we are how we enter
is important part of the entering and then we the two verbs are to enter and to
abide it means that we take time just to linger in those states to reside in
those states and in whatever kind of samadhi states
or good states or nourishing states there are we abide in them so that we can be
conditioned by them there's a reconditioning process that happens through meditation
that we're allowing ourselves to um you know life as we go through can
condition us in all kinds of negative ways and meditation is to undo that the
conditioning that comes from great hatred and delusion is very different the condition that comes from generosity and love and
and wisdom and so uh some people have even said that samadhi is kind of a re-parenting
if parenting didn't go so well as for us growing up it has uh the very deep and profound
impact on us too if we allow ourselves to be nourished by it which requires abiding abiding in it
dwelling in it so that we really can let the goodness of these states really seep
in and affect us and if we're in a hurry to get more and more concentrated
we're not going to get allow the nourishment to really recondition us and open us and soften us in in a way that's
useful on the path of liberation and i thought i would also read to you
the a list of the things that buddha talks about that people that encourage people
to abide in so he's not just saying you know in modern
united states there's often discussion about a being rather than doing and meditation is a chance just to be i
don't think the buddha would quite say it that way rather than being he talks about abiding
maybe very closely related just abide but he's always talking about abiding in something in
something that's wholesome and good not just being angry you know or fuming
if you just abide in that maybe that maybe has a negative impact if that
fuming and resentment and anger just kind of simmering along and in some way
so that's a whole different topic about you know how to be wise with things like anger but with the buddha
it's abiding so here's these states of abiding the buddha talks about
abiding in safety abiding in fearlessness
abiding in a mind free from the hindrances abiding in
equanimity abiding in contentment
abiding in pleasure inviting in happiness and gladness
abiding in happiness without moving the body or uttering a word
abiding in loving kindness abiding in compassion
abiding in a mind like space
abiding in the dharma abiding observing impermanence
abiding in stillness devoted to a pleasant abiding here and
now samadhi states are buddha often describes as a pleasant
abiding here and now and then abiding in the four foundations
of mindfulness and it's very significant that the word is abiding in the four foundations
it doesn't say practice the four foundations of mindfulness it says abide in them
abiding in bliss abiding in emptiness abiding in peaceful
liberations abiding in the supreme goal
so to abide one has to be patient i think of abiding as being very closely
akin to being in a receptive state so we abide we're patient we're not in a hurry
and we receptive state to feel the goodness of all these states all these ways of being
that can happen and so one of so we're talking here now about the the 11th step of anapanasati
so of course when we sit down to meditate there are times when these are not available and we are angry
we are agitated and to sit down and say just sit there and abide in these good feelings
just simply doesn't work and but uh so we learned to practice with the first
steps of unempathy that really support us in the challenging states of being that
we can have in daily life in our ex but as we meditation proceeds
then at some point that what i'm calling today the goodness the nourishing feelings
the beneficial feelings sensations that are here the buddha encourages us to abide in
them and then when they come arise in samadhi in these states of harmony subtleness uh steadiness unification
that we really kind of now we're really here in the present moment and really feel that in the present there's a kind
of harmony and joy and well-being gladness to all these possible
different flavors of the goodness that might be there whatever the flavor is of the day
there's also a very important place to abide in it to receive it to let it nourish you and
fill you and and let it kind of penetrate and permeate yourself in some way
and um um so
to dwell in these states is not to be thinking about them
it's not be seeking and planning and expecting and wanting and holding on to things it's
just simply abiding just allowing them to be there and just kind of basking in it or enjoying it and
breathing with it breathing through it now this mindfulness of breathing is all
reference point is always breathing breathing in and breathing out so we're always kind of using that as a
support as a guide as a grounding as a as a pointer as a as a way of staying
in these different steps and so now we're staying breathing abiding in these states abiding in in
the present moment you know in the pleasant state here and now
so uh the word in pali is biharati it comes related to the word vihara
meaning a monastery a place where people amongst the nuns reside
and so you might for the next rest of the day next 24 hours have this word
abide or abiding viharati vihara as a
something you keep close by maybe you write it on a sticky note and and have it with you or have it posted
some places and uh and see when in the day you it's beneficial for you
to pause and abide with what's happening and especially when there's a goodness or
something nourishing and you abide and really take it in learn to abide
and learn to unbe nourished by your abiding states
so thank you and i will continue with this samadhi for a few more days and until we get to the 12th step with is
liberating the mind so um and
that's you know only the 12-16 so thank you all very much