okay so we'll go ahead and get started
um my name is kim allen and i've been
teaching at
imc for a while diana
is teaching a retreat this evening at
insight retreat center
so i'll be stepping in for her
so why don't we go ahead and begin as
usual with
a guided meditation
so allowing yourself to
settle in to
have a sense of arriving
maybe taking a long slow deep breath
just allowing the body and mind to
settle on the out breath
if you're comfortable doing so you can
close your eyes
just gently feeling the body
in the sitting posture
upright and also relaxed
so we allow the attention to come inward
you can begin to connect in with
the body
inviting ease through the body
so softening the muscles of the face
around the eyes around the mouth
relaxing the eyes and the eye sockets
releasing any tension in the jaw
down through the neck
letting the shoulders gently drop
relax soften
down into the chest area
the belly
letting the belly be round soft
all these places where we tend to hold
tension
letting go of any bracing in the legs
and extending awareness all the way into
the hands and the feet
inviting softness and ease
through the body
and then similarly we can invite ease in
the mind
so we bring in a gentle awareness
mindfulness of our experience
in a very simple way
even if parts of the body or the mind
are not at ease
we can be at ease with that
offering simple attention
often we will notice that there are
thoughts in the mind
thinking going on
it can be so easy to
wish that the thinking weren't there or
to
feel somehow that the thinking is
getting in the way
of meditation
if only my mind weren't thinking
then i could have a peaceful sitting
but this very wishing for it not to be
there
as a way of also being agitating for the
mind so
perhaps beginning this sit with the idea
that thinking
is not the enemy
actually thinking is very normal
that's what minds do
so perhaps seeing the thinking as a
natural
process when we notice it
ah there it is again
gently letting go
and knowing knowing the thought
it's enough to be mindful that there is
thinking
even a simple thought like thinking is
what minds do
or thinking is natural
it's a thought but it's a beneficial one
actually not all thought is unskillful
so continuing to rest the mind and the
body the breath
i'm seeing any thought that arises
simply as natural
it may be that simply having this
less aversive view of thought
already reduces its intensity
and even when the mind gets caught up
as soon as we realize that
just recognizing that thought is normal
perhaps adding a good thought about
the fact that we're sitting here
meditating
i'm returning to the breath of the body
no sense of diminishment of our
meditation
sitting with the normal flow of mind and
body
is meditation
you
as our connection to the breath and the
body
becomes even a little bit more
continuous
as we sit
it may become possible to
breathe through any thoughts
that arise in the mind
we sense the feelings of the breath
even while the thought is there
like wind blowing through
a cloth that's out on a line drying
thought is there and the breath just
passes through it in and out
another way of seeing it is to imagine
the breath
or the body in the foreground
and any thoughts
other such movements of mind to be in
the background
still somewhat there but just in the
background
just gently favoring the present moment
experience
and letting the thoughts ripple in the
background
from time to time
checking in again with the body
softening any tension that may have
built up
allowing the breath to flow
throughout the body
and even through the thoughts that arise
imagining that we could relax the
thinking muscle
and in the last five minutes of our
meditation together
i will offer a reflection
[Music]
question
the aim is not to
think about it
but more like when we drop a
stone down into a well
a sound will come back
and we just let that ripple through
the body the heart the mind
and then go back to the silence
so i'll ask the question
[Music]
let me just see what comes back listen
to it
but let it pass by and then i will ask
the question again
what about the dharma
touches my heart
perhaps the answer was
simple perhaps it was different first
and second time
perhaps it had no words and was just a
feeling
or a body sensation
these reflections are
a skillful use of the
thinking mind the mind with language
and once more
what about the dharma
touches my heart
you