so warm greetings everyone and
so certainly i'm happy to be here with you all and spend this time in the practice and
in the dharma and there is a
kind of a loose principle that
agitated thoughts attract more agitated thoughts
and that tranquil thoughts attract attract more tranquil thoughts
and one of the ways of understanding this is that that i understand it is that
just in the ordinary activities of daily life if we're a little bit busy doing things
and maybe a little bit busy and maybe feeling a little pressure about what we're doing
it's easy to do those things with a little bit of agitation or a little bit of pressure or tension as we do them
and that pressure tension agitation is kind of a magnet or an encouragement
or a catalyst for more agitated thoughts maybe on unrelated topics it's like it
predisposes us to be agitated tense anxious
and uh and this is one of the reasons why sitting down to meditate can sometimes feel like such a relief
because we're no longer having to do anything no longer having to
take care of the daily affairs of life or work or responsibilities or for these few
minutes all that can stop and and the relief of that stopping
then becomes a little bit of a magnet or a catalyst to begin shifting how
our thinking is so thinking becomes quieter becomes more tranquil and
tranquility attracts more tranquility so perhaps for some of you you will feel
that relief of being able to sit here and and not have to be doing and making and accomplishing and
just just to be here in a very simple way and all this practice and instructions
kind of sati can lend itself to the idea that there's a lot to do
and if we sit down with this kind of this agitated energy or this pressure energy
that can be carried over into how we do this practice but uh it's i think it's best to start
with a reminder that you don't have to do much
and in a big way meditation is an undoing it's allowing ourselves to
not be so busy and doing a lot and accomplishing a lot and starting off with a contentment and
just a relief of just being here where just being alive is enough
just breathing attentively without any other activity is maybe enough
and then on that foundation then the practice builds and uh i say that carefully the practice
builds rather than we build on that there's something about allowing something to evolve and develop
that's very important for this practice so assuming a meditation posture
and it's often good to have a posture that feels stable
because in that stability we can maybe shed
the busyness of life shed the agitation and concerns and
needs to do kind of like water just rolls down the
sides of a mountain so the agitations and concerns begin
just kind of rolling down off us
closing the eyes
and gently maybe slowly maybe not too much
taking some fuller a few fuller breaths
just so it's comfortable and nice to really take in more air
[Music] expand the ribcage
feel the body this more solidly more the substance of the
body in the movements of the body breathing more deeply
more fully
and perhaps letting the exhale last a little bit longer
longer than the inhale
to do something that's a little different that might get your mind's attention on the breath
you can exhale through a slightly open mouth
breathing in through the nose fully and then exhale gently slowly
prolonged breathing out the mouth
breathing out of the mouth and silently in your mind saying
ah and allowing the tensions of the
shoulders to drain off you
taking a rest from the holding of the belly
may be softening the arms especially the elbows
you might flap the elbows a teeny bit to make sure that they're loose
maybe releasing any tension in the hands
and then letting your breathing return to normal
breathing maybe through your nose in and
out
and bringing your attention to that part of your body where you most associate to thinking
where there might be some tension or pressure tightness associated with thinking
agitation someplace where it's energized
and as you exhale see if you can relax
soften
open
as you exhale releasing the hold on your thoughts
and resting in the space of the mind
that's wider bigger
then your thoughts and images that you have
maybe you can notice some quality of the mind
that has the ability to be receptive tranquil
calm even when you're agitated
maybe it's below the agitation or behind it
or in the cracks between it see if you can become attuned
to some quality of mental calm tranquility
peacefulness
and in as you exhale relaxing the mental activity
so it relaxes into dissolves into the calm
and then with a very relaxed way with very little energy expended
receive an awareness the experience of the body breathing
so that there's a very light touch between the body breathing and awareness
inviting the experience of breathing into whatever calm or tranquility that
might be here even if you're agitated in other ways
and for a few minutes if you can don't worry about anything
just trust entrust yourself to your breathing without measuring it
or needing it to be different or judging yourself for it
a very simple dedication trusting all you need to do
is to accompany your breathing
for a few minutes here with any without any concern with the quality
of your attention or just a dedication to breathing
and when you find yourself drifting off in thought rather than letting go of your thinking
see if what look around and see what you can relax that's associated with thinking
see what needs to be settled reassured
let the mind return to a little bit more
calmness in doing so you might find that
your the the strength of your thinking
decreases
the more settled we become in meditation
the more heightened awareness we have sensitivity to the mind thinking
noticing it sooner noticing the unsatisfactory
this of being involved caught up in thoughts
noticing the relief of not thinking so much
when you find yourself thinking see if you can feel or experience
the impact thinking has on your body your mind
and then relax the tension the agitation
soften the thinking mind quiet
whatever mental activity that your can be sensitive to that you can feel
see if you can relax it
calming the mind maybe as if the breathing
is washing a calming wave through your whole body
that includes the mind and the mind softens opens expands
beyond its concerns there's so much more
to relax into in the particular concerns and thoughts
that we have
waves of calmness breathing through the mind
so
and then coming to the end of the
sitting the mind has greater intelligence
the mind has greater creativity when there's not so much energy poured
into thinking
the less agitation the less force in the thinking mind
the more ease there is and the more space there is for
an intelligent wise contact consideration
of others
and to turn your attention now
to other people
families friends neighbors
people in your county your state your country
your province people that you encounter and through
the news or other ways
and begin by just relaxing around thinking about them quiet
soft mind
soft heart and without putting too much effort into
it can you evoke a simple
tender kindness good will
friendliness for these other people
kindness begets more kindness
love attracts more love to itself
all within our own hearts
and then to see if there's an aspiration a wish
for the welfare of these people may they be well and safe
may they be happy
and to imagine yourself in their presence
with some dedication and championing
of their happiness and well-being as their advocate for happiness
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
so the eighth step of anapanasati is one trains oneself
experience um one calms the mental activity
one relaxes the mental activity
you most english translations will use some language of a tranquilized which makes tranquil
the mental activity and and the mental activity here is you
should often translate as mental formations the formations the activity the
constructs the constructing aspect the doing aspect of the mind
so i think activity works relatively well that then we now begin to calm
the mental activity and this doesn't have to be a big
project if it's easy to relax and please by all means do but it's also
recognizing this is a natural process of settling that goes on and as we gets more and more settled in
meditation more focused on the breathing and and we start shedding a lot of the concerns of the day and we're just more
and more here uh their attention starts being a heightened sensitivity to
different aspects of our experience one of them is experiencing bodily tensions the way we
hold tensions in our body and of course there's a feeling that well enough the body itself wants to
relax and let go and there's almost a natural letting go and relaxation
just from knowing and recognizing what goes on but we can also be participate in that
if it's easy enough and we don't get busy we can help ourselves relax more
so as we begin having more well-being and more settled and in meditation at some point also then we
develop a kind of a special sensitivity or awareness of the mind thinking
of course we can know that earlier and we're letting go of our thoughts coming back to the breathing but it uh there's more and more
sensitivity as we go along to the unsatisfactory quality of thinking the way that we start noticing
that when we're involved in thinking it's almost like an alienation from ourselves
that's unimaginable for people who identify strongly where they're thinking like thinking is who they are and but we
realize that thinking is just in one aspect of our life that there's a fuller range
of who we are that really becomes apparent as we get settled and calm and more embodied and present here in
meditation we start seeing that thinking is just a piece of what we are
and if we get lost in thought we actually lose touch with the fullness the uh the fullness of who we are the
wholeness of who we are in a sense and there's a kind of alienation even if the thoughts are really great and exciting
or important so called and but we also become sensitive to the
in the impact that thinking has so one impact is the alienation another
impact is that unskillful and wholesome thoughts
attract more on wholesomeness so if we're thinking a lot of with agitated ways angry ways greedy
ways that those tend to kind of perpetuate themselves and attract more of the same
agitation and preoccupation and we also start feeling the impact it has on
very subtly sometimes on our musculature that i could go around all day long
somewhat calm and engaged in life but when i sit down to meditate i realize that my thinking has somehow
created a little bit of tension around my eyes and just behind the forehead that i'm too
busy kind of with life to really notice the subtlety of it but as we settled in meditation that
subtlety of where the whole tension and tightness becomes more and more apparent
and and the tension associated with thinking the pressure the agitation that's physical almost in nature
that's more closely connected to thinking uh rather than the surface muscles that
we often kind of we can relax um or actively or something i call that
the thinking muscle and part of meditation is to is to relax the thinking muscle
and and and so as we feel this is there's a
natural tendency for the system the psychophysical system to want to relax the more we are mindful of tension
more more we feel like almost in the tension itself is a momentum to relax but we can also
soften and relax ourselves softening the mind relaxing thinking
mind and and certainly this is very helpful because the more the mind is calm
the more it that attracts more calmness the more the mind is calm the less we're
likely to be so interested in being caught in our thoughts and wonder often thoughts it's easier to stay focused and continue
with this process of meditation but also there's a very important lessons that can come
about how our mind works as we get calmer and calmer and one of them is that there's a
certain wonderful intelligence creativity that can happen when the mind is
calm and settled that's much more difficult to happen when it's agitated
it's a little bit of a trap for some people because sometimes they start composing
you know the great world novel um by um you know they have some great idea
for something and the creativity and the intelligence of the mind is really kind of operating it just feels so good and
engaging and and right to be involved in some wonderful creative thoughts
and um so so but it's a dead end for the purpose of meditation it becomes
actually another way of being kind of self-alienated even though it feels so good and exciting and like finally i feel
fulfilled i'm doing something very important writing the greatest poetry that's ever been written
and uh and um so so to not get sidetracked by that but the process that got us there is
showing us that there's a natural intelligence or creativity or wisdom that can operate
when the mind is not so active that the in the principle that actually the um
the mind operates the best when there's no extra energy no unnecessary energy operating
and that's a great lesson and a difficult lesson to really take in that it's so it can be so compelling
to get to worry so compelling to feel like i i have to accomplish i have to fix something i have to do something and
i have to think my way to it and and we get agitated and pressured and sometimes we feel like
we have to if we're responsible we have to engage the mind and show ourselves and maybe even show other
people how serious we are in thinking and taking care of things and that if we allow the natural quiet
calm mind to operate then it looks like we don't care and looks like we know that we're just
being kind of letting things just go you know whatever way they go but what
i'd like to suggest is that our our love our care our responsibility even a sense that things
are really important to take care of even then they can be taken care of better
if the mind is is relaxed and calm and we don't build up this extra tension
in the mind of doing and accomplishing and fixing and thinking about things
and to learn this this um this shift of perspective to learn
how to trust a calm mind and have that combined be engaged responsibly take care of
things is a process of trust process of familiarity of experience
seeing oh this actually works i don't have to believe in the in the messages even from
society around us that i have to be anxious preoccupied angry
apologetic i have to kind of engage my mind in some way to please other people or please myself
it's possible to stay peaceful and love and intelligence and creativity and
responsibility all can operate when there's no extra energy going on
so unnecessary energy in the mind and so this learning to to relax and to
calm the mind it very much depends on our ability to recognize
how we're over efforting in the mind where the agitation in the mind is that tension in the mind is
the pressure in the mind the closing down of the mind that goes on and and so the seventh step
is to feel that and to feel what's going on and then this eighth step is to relax it
and this has a wonderful uh effect where some of our problems that
we have in our lives that we feel like we have to fix and care and take care of
maybe some of them don't have any solutions but rather than solving them we can dissolve
them so for example someone who wants to know the meaning of life
they might have a lot of agitation around this even some anxiety around what's the
meaning of life i need to know because i need to know where i fit in this universe and what's happening with me
and have a purpose and all this stuff and there's a lot of agitated thinking
around searching for the meaning of life but if they do this meditation process
and all the agitation and anxiety associated with this question
abates dissolves goes away then lo and behold they might discover
that it still might be an interesting question the meaning of life but there's no personal need or
investment or desperation around it it just becomes an abstract question and the existential
power that held our grip around it has dissolved without solving it it's no longer a
problem it just becomes and maybe an academic interesting question
that might not have been the best example but i'm hoping that you can just apply that to yourself that
think about what are you concerned with what are you preoccupied with that maybe doesn't need to be solved
maybe more valuable is to dissolve the underlying tension
fear anxiety pressure ambition greed that might be the very thing
that's keeping those thoughts pumping up and going and to relax
the mental activity trust softening the mind and
it's a wonderful thing so this is especially true in meditation so as meditation con continues to develop there comes a
stage where periodically it comes and goes where it's really clear
that the what's really good to do is to trust the calm mind and letting go of all the
unnecessary energy that's there so um thank you very much and
we'll continue this process of step seven and eight uh for another couple of days thank you