so hello and welcome everyone
give our practice space together
so for the theme of today's practice i'd like to um
[Music] pick up in this similar vein
where we're practicing on wednesday with the theme of putting down or letting go
and bring another nuance another consideration into it
and and this idea of letting go of what is not beneficial
what is not wholesome what is not needed in this moment in order to make space
for what is wholesome to make space for peace to make space for during our meditation
quiet silence as a way of also self-care as an expression of love
for ourselves taking care of ourselves and taking care of others when we're
more available when there is more care we care for ourselves with more stillness and love and
one quote that i like to bring in to inspire to inspire
to be served as an inspiration for our practice together
is a quote by thomas merton
who was a [Music] mystic writer priest
um and [Music] yeah beautiful being so
um here is the quote the rush and pressure of modern life and
mind you he wrote this i think he passed away in the 40s am i
right let me quickly check he passed away well anyway he passed away long before the age of the intern he he
passed away in 1968 so he definitely wrote this even before
the age of the internet so whatever he's saying about the busyness of modern life you
can put it on steroids and and imagine just how much more profound of course this applies to our situation so
uh yes he was a tapist monk that is he was a tapest monk theologian
mystic poet social activist and scholar so so he says the rush and pressure of
modern life are a form perhaps the most common form of its innate violence
to allow oneself to be carried away by a multitude of conflicting concerns to surrender
to too many demands to commit oneself to too many projects to want to help
everyone in everything is to succumb to violence the frenzy
of our activism the frenzy uh the frenzy of our activism
neutralizes our work for peace it destroys our own inner capacity for peace
it destroys the faith the fruitfulness of our work of our own work because it kills the
root of inner wisdom which makes work fruitful
so i'll reread a part of this again the russian pressure of modern life are
a form perhaps the most common form of its innate violence
to allow oneself to be carried away by a multitude of conflicting concerns
to surrender to too many demands to commit oneself to too many projects
to want to help everyone and everything is to come succumb to violence
so powerful words this busyness of our modern lives
to want to help everyone in everything to be carried away by a multitude of conflicting concerns
surrendering to too many demands it kills the inner peace it kills our inner peace which really is
the foundation for service
to care for ourselves and for others so with this as an
inspiration i'd like to lead us into a guided meditation especially this
friday and for some of you saturday or merry christina sydney australia stillness in a way to
let go to let go to put down to put down all the multitudes just to come back
just to come to our heart to this moment
so so i'd like to invite you to land
in your meditation posture
whatever is supportive for you in this body sitting lying down
and can we let go can we let go in this moment
our preoccupations not necessary in this moment
can we set our intention at the outset set our intention
with uprightness with a sense of integrity and dignity
can we set our hearts our intention to put down to let go
oh what is not necessary right now what is extra
preoccupations worries
as much as possible as much as it may be available
and having set our intention with wholesomeness letting go from putting down
ah can we release is it possible to invite
the tension in the body to be
softened released the tightness the holding can we bring our awareness
letting go of thoughts preoccupation stories can we put down the stories right now
release the stories no stories right now thank you stories
not needed in this moment and gently invite our awareness to the
body to the experience of breathing
being breathed
letting the bear the breath fill the abdomen the chest the whole body on
its own no work needed
with our end just noticing that it's already happening
simply being aware simply being aware
no extra effort is needed putting down the extra effort
this
can this putting down for what is not needed in this moment
is extra be seen as
care as meta as love for ourselves
this relinquishment it's a foundation of inner peace
it's a foundation make space for care and love
for ourselves and others and the world
can we let go release
this inner violence of our times
in the words of thomas merton
the inner preoccupation with all the demands we have taken up in this moment
relinquish push release favor of peace stability
space to be and not do non-doing
this
can we see the equivalence of relinquishment
and love
relinquishing what's not needed what's extra
what's burdensome to release into love and care for
ourselves stillness and in spaciousness
this
this can inner silence
be a place for loving oneself caring for oneself stilling the mind
feeling nourished
this
even if it's a mindstorm in this moment simply ask is it possible to put it down
in this moment is it possible just gently ask the question without
forcing without forcing
just gently ask the question and often with that question alone
things are let go of and if not it's okay
be patient giving it space a lot of space
it doesn't have to be center stage plenty of space
for stillness and silence
this
putting down again and again whatever is extra
doesn't serve needs to be put down again and again it's okay with patience
gentleness and ease
it's a way to nourish to care for yourself
as if you're a little tricky the comfortable nest
nurturing soothing nest of your heart letting go of whatever is
extra in the nest take space
resting resting in the nest of the heart
without clutter without what's extra
this
and for the last moments of this practice period as we
come to a close is any criticism self-judgment arises
or how it went or how it didn't go for you
it's extra it's extra
self-criticism doesn't need to be in the nest of the heart
letting go letting go relinquishing releasing
and appreciating that you showed up you tried as best as you were able to
given the causes and conditions in this
moment and letting go of whatever arose or did
not arise and meeting this moment this moment
fresh and a new
may all beings be free including us
thank you all thank you for your practice
ah so before we turn to practicing
in small groups in sangha and community i'd like to invite you if you like to
share any from your practice and the
observations you can type them in chat if it's to everyone i'll read your name
if it's just to me it'll be private i won't say your name out loud and i read the reflection you can also
raise your zoom hand especially if you haven't spoken for a while if you haven't shared
or if you're new would love to hear your reflections your questions your
comments your observations as a gift offered to the sangha
to yourself to be held witness and to others always of benefit all reflections and
questions so
as i wait for any reflections that might bubble up from you i'll share that for
me what i noticed with this practice
was a lot of inner stillness a lot of inner care and their stillness as if as
a way of nourishment and care um became more and more prevalent
and and yes putting things down preoccupations and thoughts over and over again
with patience is part of this practice just part of this practice when we've
gone through the whole day or whole week with lots of demands
especially given our modern lives it's natural to have to put down to gently incline
the mind to put down to put down and sometimes it's not possible and that's okay we set the intention
of but we're gentle with letting go not being
possible nicholas says the phrase
sowing seeds of presence came up as a kind response whenever the mind got swept up
oh that's lovely thank you nicholas for sharing that
sowing seeds of presents yeah lovely sowing seeds of presents what a
gentle what a beautifully gentle and wholesome image
love it sowing seeds of presence yeah beautiful
thank you for your appreciation person sent it to me that's
privately yeah and another one another reflection i love the little
bird in the nest just like our hearts yeah and i see nancy please
um i think you were saying something about uh extra it's extra
um i have too many fans going to have heard you uh the entire uh context of what you
were saying but in my meditation i was trying to let go of all of this stuff that was extra
and so i heard those words and um it was very helpful i hope you
actually said them and i didn't misunderstand you yes i did say that nancy you heard you
heard it just right given all the fads that's exactly right and delights maybe
yeah it got you and and and it sounds like it was helpful i'm delighted to hear that yeah
thank you noticing what is extra great beautiful thanks nancy and casey please
hi nikki thank you so much for a beautiful guide another beautiful guided meditation
um there are a lot of phrases tonight that really resonated with me
and i had a visceral response i think it was the part where you said putting down as well
as there's enough space for stillness and silence and my my body just kind of went like it
went like it felt like relaxed like ah and there's like this appreciation
um coming forward and it was interesting also when you talked about silence
and how um this past year and a half i've been really hypersensitive to sound
and i'm not sure if it's because i haven't been able to sleep very well but um
there's a lot of noise around me but i crave violence so i was wondering i have such because
i'm so hyper sensitive to sound i have like like i've developed i feel like dog ears where i'm just like i wish my hearing
wasn't so good it's never been this good but anyways i'm wondering if you have any advice or guidance because i have
such a version to um to sound to a lot of different sounds
because my nervous system is out of balance but i i really just want i really crave silence and i know that
people have mentioned you know like go in inner silence but i haven't able to master that so any tips
would be greatly appreciated yeah yeah thank you casey thank you for what you brought up
um and what you're sharing is not uncommon for the past year everything that has happened becoming
hyper vigilant and then their sense of ah sounds and you know here i am i don't know if you can hear
through the mic the sound of this the ambulance going yeah
um so what you're describing the uh the hypersensitivity to sound
and the wanting the craving for silence and really is coming through
is being co-created by what you mentioned which is the
um the aversion to sound which is the aversion so the aversion is what is making the
dog ears the hypersensitivity if there wasn't the aversion there the lens of a version i don't want
sound i want silence i once then like you you see you know if if i
all of a sudden told you uh color whatever red is terrible bad
then all you would see in your environment is color red like oh my god danger danger i don't want color red oh my gosh he's wearing red ah
right it just you become hypersensitive to it right so so basically the the clue
that the way to work with it is through the aversion really that is what hooking it in place
so and that so notice the aversion notice the aversion uh like i hate sound
i hate sound why it's just sound it's there's not it's not good it's not bad
it's just in the environment there's so it's it's this
affiliation the association that's bringing all the the suffering the way that
the mind is seeing it so bring the attention with kindness with
gentleness to the aversion like oh sweetie it's it's just a version it's just
a version it's okay make friends with the aversion then make friends with what's underneath
their vision which is the unpleasant vedana unpleasant feeling tone oh my mind just perceives it as pleasant
as unpleasant okay it's just unpleasant big deal and slowly it will lose its
its hold on you and there can be a lot of sound without the reactivity and then there
can be the nourishing enjoying the inner silence even though it could be a lot
of noise around but it's really i'm pointing to the aversion
which is on top of the reactivity to the unpleasantness so so when they're so when the
reactivity to the unpleasantness is met with ah it's just unpleasant okay
it's unpleasant big deal it's not gonna kill me it's just not but then you're not giving it power
otherwise you're giving power it's unpleasant it's like okay here take you know have power over me like every
did you see how it it happens you know unpleasantness so so that's what i would like to offer you
as a way to work with it and happen happy to reflect again later come back
and and you can share how it went okay great thank you casey
so dear once the time has come for us to turn to into small
practice groups or sangha to practice together so i'll create the small groups
and the invitation is to start with um 15 seconds
of silent meta for each other and then take care of
each other take care of yourselves really important to be uh sensitive to each other sensitive to
yourselves and let go of what is not needed
what is not needed just saying only what's what's needed and maybe you'll spend
time in silence and if there's awkwardness in silence
awkwardness is not needed let the awkwardness go from your mind see if you can be
in community with just care and ease so it can be profound practice put down
what is not needed put down what is not needed whether it's i want to sound impressive
not needed oh i don't have anything to say of value not needed just put it all down see what explore
experiment all right i'm opening the rooms and here we go all right everyone
welcome back welcome back the rooms are closed and we have we have about a minute for
reflections if you notice something in the practice meetings if you haven't
shared please would love to hear from you
neil please so i was in a room with three and and we
all found this to be um you know a very warm warm and sweet experience
um you know each each in a different sort of way um it was you know and i will tell you
while you were talking i'm like what is she doing this isn't meta but you know you know it was lovely
thank you thank you neil yeah i appreciate the report back from
the group it's um meta shows up in so many ways
without phrases and making space for meta making space for care and love in this
way is quite radical it's actually quite radical and i like to teach to share radical
teachings how's that [Laughter] so yes okay so uh
let's make this the last comment it's i forget since your your name says
iphone uh here please oops
oh wait we're having okay there you go one more time if you mute yourself oh
there perfect here it comes so um just just letting you know
that i just want to really practice letting go of everything and it feels like it's just
letting go of whole series it just like scares me off of like like
losing my power over something that i want to accomplish it just to keep like haunting my mind
so it caused not letting go
so i hope that i you can just give me some advice or maybe i'll just practice more
yeah so so the question you're asking is complicated enough and i need to ask you
more questions about what it is you mean so what this is what i'll do tell you what
um will will formally close
the and then i'm happy to stay a few minutes extra afterwards and and and uh ask a question then
jennifer says uh nikki as you responded to casey's question i really appreciate your
comment about how we co-create our experience you're welcome jennifer and this is very important and also yerba on
youtube appreciated both uh also the question that casey asked and the
response yes it's so much about co-creation then maybe maybe next time maybe on monday else
i'll talk more about how we co-create so much in our reality it's so important
so dear ones thank you so much for co-creating a beautiful reality of your
practice and showing up to cultivate this for for yourself and for all for all beings
everywhere may all beings be well may all beings
be free [Music]
thanks all take good care be well let go what's extra
see you next week