so
a warm hello to all of you and welcome to
our meditation together
one of the qualities that this whole series of
practices on anapanasati this mindfulness of breathing and probably all forms of buddhist practice
that one of the things one of the goals of practice
if i can speak about that way is to have confidence in the practice
and to have tremendous confidence in the practice that um it it's really worthwhile
to just settle in to do the meditation to do the mindfulness
to do the dharma practice in all its different forms that
and uh people who have practiced for a long time that confidence is said to become unshakable
and so to practice with confidence regardless of whether
particular meditation session that you're doing you feel like you've met never meditated before you're
a raw beginner or if you feel like wow i'm really
meditating well today that from the point of view of confidence it doesn't really matter
whether you're a beginner or an experienced practitioner or whether you feel stumbling along one day and cruising
along the next day what matters the most is that you have confidence in the practice and you
settle down and do it day in and day out through the ups and
the downs that there's real confidence that this is worthwhile this
is a kind of has great meaning and purpose and
homecoming or something so
to enter into a meditation posture
and to gently close your eyes
and to spend a little bit of time
exploring your body and your posture to see if you can make small adjustments
so the posture is a confident posture
even if you don't feel confident can you assume a confident posture for some people that's sitting
up a little bit straighter or feeling a little bit more grounded
maybe it's having the chest a little bit more open and expensive
and then as you exhale to relax your body
relax the muscles of your face
softening releasing the shoulders
maybe there's a release that can happen in the heart area
maybe there's a softening in the belly releasing of the holding any holding in
the belly
and then look around your body and see if you can find some part of your body
that you associate with confidence
maybe there's a feeling of confidence that's available now
or simply a place that if you were to be confident that's where it lives for you
maybe for some people it's the hands or the feet
some people in the belly or the chest some people just a broad feeling
throughout the torso where does confidence live in you
and perhaps in reference to this location for
confidence maybe in reference to whatever confidence you have
however small it might be to begin breathing together
with confidence breathing with your confidence
being confident with your breathing
perhaps having some confidence in the practice of mindfulness of
breathing
where the confidence is in the practice not in what you're experiencing
no need to look for validation or doing it right or
experiencing some particular state
what's important is the simple continuity of the practice
one breath after the other
no need to strain or push or with a
mindfulness being confident in an open-handed
mindfulness relaxed receptive awareness
with a confidence in it that you're ready always ready to begin
again with your breathing mindfulness of breathing
a confidence where it doesn't matter so much that you wandered off and thought it only matters that you begin again
and again
and a confidence
of hanging in there one breath after the other
that that's all you need to do now for this meditation
gently lovingly continuously
confident in the simplicity of practicing mindfulness
awareness of the body breathing
so
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to evoke again the idea of confidence
confidence can be a strength that we bring to the important things of
our life and one of the important things is our
care for the world around us
our generosity our good will our compassion our love
and to have enough confidence in these things
that we bring forth our care our compassion
her love even when it's difficult
enough confidence that we don't get distracted from it easily
thinking that other things are more important
to be confident in our capacity to look upon other the others and look upon
the world
with our kindness friendliness our good will
and perhaps there's a way that meditating clarifies what is important
so that we let go of some of the things that
are not so useful to have at the center of our preoccupation our concern
and so there's room for compassion and may it be that our practice of
meditation supports us in being able to walk
through this world be in this world confidently
confident in our kindness our care our compassion
confident in the value of friendliness
may it be that this practice we do supports the welfare and happiness of
all beings everywhere may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
so my friends we come to the end of this
series of talks on mindfulness of breathing
relying on the classic teachings on this practice given by the
buddha long time ago the heart of it is the 16 steps of
mindfulness of breathing and the instructions go on beyond those
16 steps to describe the process by which mindfulness of breathing
leads to full awakening and i had a teacher
in japan with a zen teacher i practiced with there who said that all of buddhism
can be revealed through mindfulness of breathing focusing on the breathing
and uh it's a uh when the buddha that they all the best
records we have of what meditation practice the buddha himself did
he explained he did mindfulness of breathing he would sometimes as a fully awakened being
he would go off into the forest for two weeks four weeks at a time
to to be on retreat and before he went or after he came back
he would explain that what he was doing was practicing mindfulness of breathing
so it isn't only a practice to bring us to awakening enlightenment it's also a practice to do after
enlightenment and uh and maybe the enlightenment is
just kind of a maybe it's not you know certainly
important but maybe that's not really the point maybe the point is to continue
practicing before awakening practice after awakening practice having
confidence some people there are some schools of buddhism where they say that enlightenment or awakening whatever it
might be in their at school they emphasize what it really is it's a
confirmation of the practice that now we really know this is what the practice is the
practice is good it works it's this is what you know this is uh so there's a very clear
confidence in the practice itself and certainly buddhist practice can be more than
mindfulness or breathing but um but uh
the to have confidence in the practice you do and and and that that is one of the
signs of maturing and developing in this meditation practice rather than measuring success by states
of meditation states of concentration states of calm or states of insight
whatever it might be i don't want to dismiss the value of those but more important
is this unshakable confidence that this practice is worth doing
really to trust it and one of the great gifts that mindfulness practice has given to me
that is that um uh is that um i have this kind of real trust
that uh in just being mindful in the practice of mindfulness practice of showing up and being aware
of what's happening now and there's certainly plenty of times that i run into difficult situations situations where i
don't quite know how to find my way through and understand what's happening but i trust even those situations that
to be mindful and there's a sense of direction and purpose and grounding and orientation and
and uh and um and a sense of safety where i don't get swept up in the drama
of the moment or the concerns anxieties of the situation perhaps
because i have this deep trust that things will work out when there's a strong mindfulness just
come back to it and practice now it doesn't mean it's only mindful but mindfulness then reveals
the way forward sooner or later and that i don't seem to go wrong by
pausing by stopping to look and be present and see what's really going on here and
what's happening in me what's happening outside and it i don't go wrong by coming back
and just breathing some of you have done yoga classes where the common instructions from the yoga teacher or
observation is is you know you're holding your breath you know don't hold your breath
or something that sometimes the straining of doing a posture so people hold their breath then
and the yoga teachers like you to keep it relaxed loose breath as you go and that's really good advice for all of
life and and so to one of the possibilities of mindfulness of
breathing practice is that it becomes second nature to be aware of
your breathing and how you're breathing and where the breathing is constricted or held and
uh and come back to a relaxed breath the fluid breathing
an easeful breath makes a huge difference because it kind of reorients
or resets the psychology the emotionality the mind itself
because when the mind is real when the breathing is relaxed it's actually harder to cling or grasp
or contract around things it's kind of a little bit protection i think i think of it as a lubricant
of the mind lubricant of the heart keeps it fluid and
moving and not rusted the um the um and then uh
you know there's a wonderful the rhythm of breathing in and out and that rhythm is a protection from getting caught up
and fixated on our preoccupations our concerns our fears and if we're not fixated we get often a
more realistic uh understanding a bigger better view of
what's going on than if we get caught up in the middle of our preoccupations
so mindfulness of breathing is always useful i think sometimes there's some people
who don't find it particularly like their their favorite or most effective practice for themselves and
there are other wonderful practices to do but these weeks that we've been doing this mindfulness of breathing
i want to emphasize that it is a wonderful practice for many many people
and that as we sink into it and develop it and grow in it that one of the primary qualities
eventually is a real confidence in it a real confidence in practice
where it's um the um we just do it in day in and day out
and i believe and that's my kind of reading of the classic instruction of 16 steps
that most of those steps has the expression um i
i will breathe in i will train training i will
breathe out in the midst of everything whatever is going on in the 16 steps i train to breathe in i train to breathe
out and this intentionality this dedication i'd like to say this love of just kind
of breathing in the middle of it no matter what no nothing is worth getting so caught up
in that we can't just stay on the floating on the river of breathing
we can't stay in the with the lubricant with the ease with the relaxation that mindfulness of breathing can
provide and it makes life so much easier and in the buddhist terminology it helps
it to be a life that's freer
uh freer more liberated more easeful more open and then available for more
wisdom to see more clearly what's here we have this amazing capacity for wisdom and insight
and seeing that can come in the wake of
relaxed open subtle experience with the breathing breathing in and breathing out
so i hope i think this is uh the 76
second maybe um session we've had on mindfulness of
breathing and we've done it since the beginning of the year it's a quite a journey i hope that this
has been meaningful for you supportive for you and kind of opened up or pointed to you some of the value and
richness that can come with mindfulness of breathing and some of the 16 steps or you know the
topics of the steps are relevant for other forms of meditation practice as well
and um and it's given you uh new perspectives on yourself and and maybe even pointed to
dimensions of your inner life that you haven't really thought about before or focused on or
seen before and and maybe it's uh has supported you and
developed you and and um so
thank you for letting me share all this these months but mindfulness of breathing it is i would say that it's uh my
primary practice and for meditation and going around daily life i've been doing mindfulness of breathing
since i was probably 20 years old and uh so for decades and i find it still to
this day a fantastic wonderful practice and so it's not the only practice i do
because mindfulness includes everything it's part of the beauty of mindfulness to be all-inclusive
but breathing is at the center of it all and it's a wonderful center
so um thank you and uh we'll continue on monday with a new
topic i haven't decided quite what we're going to do and there's a small chance that on monday
that i'll be in a different location and then here with the maybe with wi-fi
that's a little bit weak as i was told it was slow so we'll see how this goes if i'm there
i don't know it's 50 50 chance i'll be here or be in this other location and um and
but we'll do some topic next week that does feel a little bit like a follow-up maybe from this whole series
so i hope you have a wonderful weekend and and thank you for the opportunity to
give this series