so good day warm greetings
and here we are to continue on our adventure in
mindfulness of breathing and the last tetra at the end of this
whole sequence of settling in deeper and deeper
is to come to a place where we're able to
observe things in a
non-interfering way non-reactive way and whereas
observing by itself might not seem like a very interesting way of meditating perhaps or a little
bit detached it comes after [Music]
a process of calming relaxing the body and mind and liberating ourselves just enough
with our reactivity and our preoccupations and our busy mind
so that rather than letting go at this point we can let things be
and letting things be can be seen as a very generous thing
to not interfere to not assert the self and not assert one's preferences
and desires and aversions but to really just kind of have the peacefulness to
observe and some things we observe are difficult we might be anxious
we might be upset we might be you know agitated in some way but it is
possible to come to a place where we just observe that and we let it
be we don't have to let go of it because we can just let it be
um and uh and
and watch it see it and so the last tetrad is just observing
things coming and going and starting to become attuned to the fact that in some way or
many ways in profound ways our experience is constantly shifting and changing
and arising and passing and to now not be interested in the
content of our experience the content of our thoughts the content of our feelings
but rather to be interested in the process by which they arise in their past they come and they go
we're switching to process rather than content as a big shift for the human mind and to observe
to let be and in a sense we're learning to ease up on our
experience not to get rid of it but to be able to observe it in a peaceful way
so beginning with a meditation posture
that allows you to both have some alertness but also to feel at ease in yourself
some easiness
and to gently close your eyes
and to take a few long slow deep breaths
long slow deep breaths to feel yourself
fill yourself with awareness and to relax to settle in
and to settle in as you exhale to some place within that feels stable
a stability stable in your body
stable in your heart
maybe stable in your mind
not looking for great stability but rather
becoming a little more stable than you were stable here definitively
here and now in this place at this time
and then letting your breath return to normal and
perhaps as if there's waves of relaxation through your body
relaxing the muscles of your face
as you breathe the waves of breathing are like waves move washing through your face
softening relaxing
waves of relaxation through the shoulders
waves of relaxation through the belly softening on the exhale
and waves of relaxation through the whole body
and then letting yourself sit quietly here
and let yourself be easy be at ease in your body
or if your body feels it uneasy ease up on how it is
allow things to be but ease up around them it's okay
breathe with it ease up and just observe
experiences of your body
and set your heart at ease
maybe you can feel gentle tender soft
in the heart here and now at ease or if the heart is uneasy to ease up on
that it's okay and for you to observe this is
how it is as if a as if the observing is
accompanying the uneasiness you feel with care and compassion
and as you exhale setting your mind at ease it's okay to be here now
and if the mind is uneasy ease up on that
so you can maybe just observe
and be at ease in how you observe
no need to strain or be afraid as you open up to observe
phenomena
the observing itself is a place of safety
we begin approaching a place of non-reactivity non-harming
just observing phenomena
and one of the things you can observe
is how you lose your ease how you lose your calm
how you go in the opposite direction then easing up
be sure that you don't overlook the moments of
contraction and agitation
reactivity but when you see it when you know it meet it with relaxing
meet it with easing up
with observing this is how it is now
letting it be
but not being it letting it be but not becoming
the reactivity
and all along breathing in and breathing out
as if breathing is the rhythm of the universe
that washes through you through
everything
[Music]
um
[Music] ah
so
noticing ways that you've been caught that you get caught in thoughts and
feelings and experiences in the body
we're being caught or preoccupied or concerned
is going in a different direction than being at ease easing
up simply observing
with the help of breathing
let breathing help you not get so caught in things stay with the rhythm of breathing
so that you're in better position to simply observe the comings and goings of reactivity
preoccupations
contractions comings and goings of what you want and what you don't want
the coming goings of wanting and not
wanting
[Music]
um
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to appreciate the possibility of easing up
and one way this easing up is so helpful is to
help us recognize in inner safety
that as we sit and meditate we don't need to be talking to people or
interacting with them and be out in the world driving our cars on dangerous freeways
that for these few minutes of the meditation
you don't have to solve your problems or
engage in the difficulties of life it's a safe time just to be let be
and it's also somewhat private what goes on inside
so in the safety and privacy without anybody needing to know
can you open your heart tenderly caringly
to feel good will to have kindness love first for the people in your life
it's relatively easy to love and have good will
and allow you yourself the luxury of feeling that privately
without the any complications of it being done publicly or
overtly just feeling the simplicity of your care your kindness
your appreciation of others perhaps breathe with it breathe through
those feelings make room for it
and with this simple useful connection to your goodwill
perhaps it's easier now again in the privacy of meditation
to have thoughts of well-wishing for others
it would be quite wonderful if they could be happy and peaceful
safe and that they they could thrive and
have a good life
and then to give words to this good will this well-wishing
may they be happy
may they be safe
may they be peaceful
may they be free
and may our well-wishing extend outwards throughout the lands
and seas and in all directions how wonderful it would be if all beings
could be happy may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be safe
may all beings everywhere be free
and with the support of our meditation practice mindfulness practice
may we in our way in ways that we can
contribute to that being possible
[Music]
you