hello everyone and welcome
one of the states of being that are is often associated with meditation
is calmness and perhaps sometimes calmness is
misunderstood and therefore underappreciated
it isn't that calmness has to characterize all of ourselves that all
of us is come but rather it's more like the
the containers come it isn't that
everything in the room everyone in the room is calm but the somehow the size of the room
the emptiness of the room the clarity in the room something there's a calmness in the room that
holds or includes someone who is not calm so the same thing in ourselves
we could have a lot of energy good energy engaging energy and sometimes the calmer or more
peaceful we become in meditation it releases a kind of beautiful
kind of flow of energy or aliveness in us that very clearly is
held or supported by that calmness
so if we're looking for something very placid and peaceful everywhere we might miss the calmness
that's already here and some of that has to do with the
awareness the mindfulness that knows that holds
our experience and that can become
it's somewhat like someone who uh there's a lot going on a lot of busyness or
important things to happen but you watch this person you see that they're completely engaged in what
needs to be done but their eyes are calm their eyes seem
just settled and peaceful and engaged they're not there's not a constriction around the
eyes or our eyes are not darting around just they're calm and settled gazing
upon what needs to be done in a calm way while they work quickly and strongly
so sitting up or assuming a meditation
posture that allows you to be externally
still externally with a body so the body can be still
so that some part of your body offers calmness peacefulness even if there's a
lot of agitation in the body maybe there's something
about the stillness that the body is in it also is there together with the agitation
and gently closing the eyes and taking a few long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale see if that can be
an exercise in calming settling
an exercise of knowing recognizing something that's calming about the
exhale
settling
and as you breathe in fully deeply
in that whatever calmness that's there welcome the experience of breathing in
welcome the inhale
then letting your breathing return to normal and with a normal breathing is there in
your experience some reference point for calmness
peacefulness maybe not all of you maybe much of you is not calm or peaceful
but is there somewhere within or somewhere in your capacity for
mindfulness that supports you to gaze upon your
experience calmly peacefully
and not a calmness or peacefulness that pushes anything away
but rather something that allows what's there without getting caught in
it agitated by it
and then settling in further with your breathing
perhaps there's a way of continuing to relax the body
some of the tensions and holding in the body
on the exhale softening releasing whatever holding there might
be
and then settling into your breathing
and part of the function of focusing on breathing is not to deny anything or push anything
away but support us in not getting involved or entangled or reactive
to anything because the energy of attention
steadily calmly
moves with the breathing
and helps us to find the calm center
or the peaceful container
with which we can we can gaze upon whatever needs our attention
calmly without agitation
seeing clearly forever long that's useful
and then returning to the breathing
relaxing with the exhale
welcoming the inhale
is there accessible to you
a capacity for more calmness peacefulness
somewhere within or somewhere in the container of it all
some way that you can be mindful in a calm open
peaceful way
you
so then as we come to the end of this meditation
one of the benefits of recognizing calmness or peacefulness
is that it helps purify our love
imagine when we're caught in agitation and fear and anxiety and
hatred and greed the simplicity and purity of love
is hard to tap into but the calmness the peacefulness that
we can experience makes room for the simplicity
and the clarity of love of kindness
warmth loving kindness compassion
the whole range of caring emotions and caring motivations
that can well up within us
the simplicity of love that includes ourselves includes others includes the whole world
the buddha call love meta
has a form of wealth that we carry within us
and so as we come to the end of the sitting perhaps we can
extend our calm gaze onto the suffering of this world
anywhere that her eyes land our gaze
lands locally in our own family or local communities or around your country
or the world and the calmly allow your care
your good will your compassion
take in the suffering the world
and at the end of the sitting meditation it's good to evoke some motivation
that to have your meditation practice support you
in helping to alleviate that suffering in the world
even if it's in the smallest possible ways that's accessible and easy for you
may it be that this meditation practice we do supports us to live
for the welfare and happiness of this whole world
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
this week for the dharma talks
the theme will be um the second of the three
unwholesome roots second of the three poisons and that is hatred or hostility
and so the three are greed hatred and delusion and so last week we went through greed
and this week we'll go through hate and it's phenomenally important in the
buddhist course of practice to understand these three poisons greed hate and
delusion because these are the primary
conditions or sources or catalysts for human suffering
and to and to alleviate to to end suffering to decrease the amount of suffering in ourselves and the world
around us it makes a huge difference if we understand greed hate and delusion
and are able to decrease it and even eliminate it completely which is one of the purposes of buddhist
practice is to really bring it to an end a remarkable achievement it is possible
and so as i did last week for greed i'm not going to
start the first talk this today not by talking about hatred directly
but by talking about non-hate because this contextualizes the discussion about
hate so the word for hate is dosa a
d-o-s-a and non-hate in nepali
in the buddhist the discussion is a dosa a d-o-s-a so not hate
non-hate and now that's more than just the absence of
hate it's understood in the tradition that it's the presence of something wonderful that somehow the
absence of hate doesn't leave us neutral doesn't leave us empty in some kind of void uh impoverished way
that it's the opposite that the presence of hate is what's impoverishing for us
and that as we release it wonderful states arise and now the primary one that's
associated with this is love that is loving-kindness
and um it's also associated with patience with
calmness and with peace and um and there's a
wonderful verse that uh famous verse from the dhammapada it's
the third verse in the this anthology of buddhist poetry from the ancient times
and it goes something like this hate is never overcome by hate
by non-hate only is hate overcome this is the ancient truth
so the word non-hate as i said implies the positive corollaries to that
so some translators will actually translate it that way so they'll say hate is never overcome by hate by love
alone is hate overcome this is the ancient truth
and that particular verse was very impactful after
world war ii because in the early 1950s 51 52 i think there was a big international
conference in san francisco to decide on the fate of japan japan had lost the war
united states had occupied japan and was governing the country and many of the countries 40 countries i
think came who had been impacted by japanese aggression during world war ii came to san francisco to decide
on the fate of japan should japan be divided up into multiple countries should it be
different different countries take over parts of it you know what should happen to it and
there was kind of a stalemate at this conference until the foreign minister from sri
lanka came up and evoked the principle of of caring for everyone and
and and including for the japanese people and he recited that verse
and when he recited that verse the way the report goes everything settled down and the
conference then went ahead and decided to grant japan its independence
and the kind of expression of love and expression of good will
and maybe even a trust that there was another way possible after the aggression of the world war ii
and so um there's a plaque in tokyo uh it's commemorating this event
that has that verse um on its own on the stone
so um the so as we meditate or as we have other
means in our lives from time to time maybe we begin tapping into
a degree of calmness or peace a capacity for love and all the different manifestation
of what love might be a capacity for deep patience
and that uh that begins showing us something very
important and it shows us that when there's hatred
that it diminishes us it impoverishes us it it brings with it suffering
that hatred is a fire that burns the person that's
uh hostile that the one exit one
analogy is that picking up hatred is like picking up a hot piece of coal and of course uh not everyone who
hates or has hostility recognizes that partly because of the intense focus on
the object of hostility that that sometimes blinds us to the
impact that hate has on ourselves and also doesn't lead to very clear
thinking calmness on the other hand peacefulness love
tends to produce wiser trains of thought not necessarily always but it tends to
help us think more wisely and by including
what the impact our behavior has our feelings have our emotions have on ourselves and those
around us and um and uh and we can feel then
the diminishment of our own well-being so rather than talking about for this
week talking about hate uh in a in a critical way or in a way
that's uh condemns hate or is puritanically like we should just get rid of hate
because it's the wrong it's bad what i want to emphasize the perspective we have on hate when
we are really rooted in a place of peacefulness of calm or love
and in that kind of situation we can look upon hate not as an enemy not as something that we
need to judge in some negative way but rather almost like it's an illness
almost like it's a something that needs to be addressed but
we don't have to condemn ourselves or condemn other people for it but we do want to address
and find an alternative and find a way of settling and relaxing and and supporting ourselves and others
for the best qualities of heart to come forth and to meet the world if we want to try to help
support the world to suffer less human beings to suffer less we really need to figure out some way to
show that the suffering of hostility the suffering of hate and one way to do that is to really know
the opposite to really know this thing of non-hate to recognize and
even if it's in small halting ways at first to keep coming back and recognizing
where we can find in ourselves our capacity for calmness for peacefulness for
for uh for love for generosity and uh and not to make that help us
become passive because of that but maybe it's even empowering to step
forward in that way in that peace in that love
and to learn the wise ways of doing that and the engaged ways of doing that
and so as we go through this week and focus on hostility which you know is maybe not not necessarily a
pleasant thing to talk about or reflect on it is uh
something that if we if we remember that we're looking upon it and exploring
it from our capacity for peace love calmness that then we can kind of look
and see um in the the topic as something which
moves us into greater capacities for those things greater capacities for love for kindness
for goodwill for compassion we have a wide range of
of wonderful feelings inside of positive feelings connected to non-um
non-hatred so for the buddha or for the buddhist tradition the
quality the state of non-hate is refreshing or for or enlightening
like the full moon that comes or they're actually the expression from the ancient text is
pleasing like the moon full moon is pleasing so imagine the full moon on a clear night um
is his analogy for your non-hate in the clarity of an
unobstructed heart and mind it's uh this non-hostility is
characterized by the absence of violence
it's said to be gentle like a good friend and it's the cause of friendship so
rather than simply the absence of hate there's something here that supports friendship uh in this kind of this approach the
state of non-hate and it's said to be like a smell like
sandalwood sandalwood has a wonderful smell it's used for perfumes or different things but it uh sandalwood
normally doesn't harm anyone and so the same way that the non-hate
someone who lives in non-hate there's a kind of non-harming perfume or atmospheric mood
that somehow can waft from them that is palpable sometimes
they say that um when there's non-hate we never harm ourselves or harm others
not intentionally or knowingly and uh
in fact uh the opposite exists that we're interested in promoting welfare
for self and others that's one of the functions uh manifestations of
non-hate and finally a couple of other things about non-hate
the tradition says that it's a condition for youthfulness that the fire of hatred
speeds up the aging process and they talk about the ancient texts talking about when there's a lot of hatred that
there's a quicker gathering together of wrinkles and gray hair to be a little bit careful with
this kind of idea that don't assume just because someone has wrinkles or gray hair that
that there's hate there but the speeding up of that process is what the ancient texts say um
and that um having non-hate discovering non-hate is like having a
tight knot that's unraveled and set free
so may you come to appreciate your capacity for non-hate
as a untangling of the constrictions and knots in your heart
and your mind and to discover your capacity for peace and love so that
the way we gaze upon hatred is not hateful but rather brings the
medicine of goodwill and
and care so tomorrow we'll we'll talk more specifically about this
and there's the same plan as as last week to go through um the five
different aspects of this i'll i'll share that tomorrow again
that plan so thank you