great so welcome welcome everyone welcome to happy hour lovely to
be with you whether you're joining on zoom or on youtube
and um the theme for our practice today
is continuing to practice with um the fourth brahmavihara the
brahmaviharas are the practices of the heart heavenly abodes um first one being meta loving-kindness
second one being karuna compassion third one mutita vicarious joy and the fourth one
being up or equanimity and we've been going through all the brahmavihara since
the beginning of the year uh methodically and if this is your
first time at happy hour no problem whatever you need to know will be shared with you i'm
just giving some context here so the practice of equanimity or upeka
is a crown jewel of buddhist practice and it shows up on so many different
lists and as i was saying on friday there are ten different types of equanimity
and some of you might have been familiar with the seven factors of awakening
equanimity shows up there in a different way it shows up there supporting our awakening or
our being in the world and with brahma bihara as as these four fantastic
practices equanimity shows up as a way relationally it shows up relationally to
for us to practice with relation to ourselves in the relation to others
people we care about people we don't know all beings etc so it becomes a
relational practice in some way and um it's a beautiful practice it's um
the the near enemy of it as i mentioned and it's bear mentioning uh worth
mentioning again is aloofness or or indifference and
sometimes we might think of we might mistakenly think of equanimity
as not caring just uh being aloof indifferent but that's
the near enemy that's the masquerader it's what masquerades as equanimity
equanimity and again it's okay to fall into the near enemy or even the far enemy which
is the attachment and aversion that's the fire enemy so it's it's not a sin to for those things to
arise oh they arise you notice what's happening and you learn you learn from where the heart and the
mind is falling oh yeah i'm veering a little towards the right i'm veering towards the left
so yeah you learn by by actually you learn better about this practice by actually
falling into the near and far enemies and realize this doesn't quite feel like equanimity and
and seeing what is needed to to adjust your own practice so don't think like
you've made a mistake or it's a waste of time no it's whatever practice however it arises for you as as long as
you're aware and and you don't self-judge and you just kind of self
oh you're curious like oh what's happening here how do i work with this it's all good so one more thing to say
about equanimity before we start our practice together is that there is a sense of
care and equinimity there is a sense of care presence even warmth which holds
all holds everything that arises and passes with a sense of peace with a
sense of equipoise and stability so so we started on friday
with the neutral person traditionally that's where you start
this practice and then the second uh category that we extend to tonight
is ourselves so we're going to do equanimity for our own
condition in life and there are a lot of different potential phrases to use
i will offer a few today and um as many well many of you are
already on the google groups happy hour google groups and i asked neil to forward the phrases
to and i see nods you've seen many of you have seen them if you haven't it's in the google groups
waiting for you all those phrases you can read them and explore them and see what
works for you and i'll offer a few and you may have
your favorite from the list or from one that i will offer tonight so
all right enough words for framing the practice and whatever comes
up as long as you have caring equanimity with whatever comes up with this
practice you're doing it exactly right okay so let's do it let's practice together
dear sangha ah so
landing landing and settling
landing in our bodies
ah landing in this moment arriving
letting go of all the words and everything that has come before today
and anything that you expect to come later today
let it go meeting this moment fresh and new completely anew
freshly meeting this moment as if you were being born in this moment anew
taking birth in this body in this heart and mind and
new in this moment
taking birth in this body
sensing feeling
your feet your legs on the floor connected to the earth
your sit bones on the cushion
connected connected to the earth
receiving the breath
embodied grounded relaxed soft
settling and arriving for the first few minutes just with the body and the breath
if you notice that you take birth in the thought in the story
notice the self that has now taken birth
in worry and fantasy
and without any judgment of a gentleness smilingly
saying thank you not now
letting it go letting this
balloon helium balloon a thought of taking birth opening your hand let it
go ah coming back to the body to the breath
stable grounded settled
feeling your breath received the lower abdomen your sit bones
blending
with each out breath relaxing dropping any tightness
or contraction
in your belly the sit bones
feeling more connected rooted
softly to the earth
spending another few minutes to settle the breath in the body tilling the soil
of calm awareness before we proceed
to practicing with equanimity upeka just this breath just this moment
right here
feeling your feet your hands your sit bones feeling embodied with each breath
as the basis as the ground
of equanimity practice feeling embodied
feel your feet your legs your sit bones your abdomen
with each breath
now feeling your body
breathing
feeling yourself connected to the earth
sense of stability of uprightness
sitting tall what if you're lying down feeling your spine
turning your gaze inward
sense of earth on earth this body
sitting the same way that
the buddha statue
sits with integrity balance stability grounded
sitting on a stable platform rooted
feel yourself as if you were this graceful
stable grounded nice heavy
buddha kuan yin
statue a symbol of stability
strength
above and beyond what you give yourself credit for
opening up to the possibility of yes there is this possibility there is this
dimension of stability
calm
poise equipoise that's here
that's deep within
feeling your abdomen lower abdomen feeling your sit bones
connected to the earth your shoulders dropping your head tall
it's not so much that you have to try to be
it's more that you notice that it actually is it's a part of you it's a part of you
to be stable
grounded spacious as if your heart shining is shining with
resilience stability
equipoise
your body grounded connected to the earth rooted
in ways that might even surprise you
but your breath ah the out breath just relaxes
lets go of any tightness tension
gets you even more connected to mother earth
the more connected and rooted you feel
the taller you sit
the more you can contain
just as the buddha statue many of them have the mood rather
the gesture of the earth the earth touching mudra the buddha
touching the earth is earth be my witness
i am here i belong here
sense of stability groundedness
from this place of stability connection to the earth
not easily toppled over
from this place you can open up
from this stable platform of the body
opening up the comings and goings of your life
and not to be lost in thought still rooted in your body
feeling your feet your abdomen your sit bones
the contact points
and just as a well-rooted tree the winds can come and go
the leaves might ruffle but the tree is well rooted it's not
going to topple over so you can open up maybe to
one consideration in your life one comings and goings
not to be overwhelmed with too many just one
feeling your stability as you allow this consideration to be
held to be here
one challenge maybe not the biggest one yet
this can be here this consideration
like a wind that ruffles the leaves but there's stability in
the tree the trunk and the body
and with respect to this just as you feel your breath continuing
to connect with the breath reciting silently one of the phrases of
equanimity i'll offer a few options
may i accept
may i accept their rising and passing of things
with equanimity and balance
connecting this phrase to your breath in breath out breathe
may i accept the conditions of my life with ease
or whether i understand it or not
things are unfolding according to a lawful nature
may i be undisturbed may i have peace may i
accept the comings and goings of events
whichever version works best for you
or it could be worthless
with just a sense of holding
with care with presence
what cannot be controlled
there could be just a sense of equanimity and peace
spacious expansive beyond time and space
eternal
not so much ours
something we're sharing tapping into so in that way it is ours and not ours
the grace of equanimity
the bird's eye or a cosmic view of comings and goings
whether i understand it or not life is unfolding
[Music] according to a lawful nature
may i accept and be heartbeat harmony
and flow with the unfolding
of events
and for the last moment of this practice period
may i be at peace with whatever a rose or did not arise
during this practice period holding it with spacious equanimity not
resisting not attaching
it was like this right now it is like this right now
things are like this right now
may all beings everywhere have profound peace and ease
in the midst of the flow of life
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
ah so we have more folks joining us on youtube from different
time zones hello from iran superhero good morning and hello from
bangkok i don't know how to say good morning in thai hello so
i'd love to hear your reflections you can either type them in chat to me privately i won't say your name or to
the whole sangha if you like in which case i'll read it out loud and say your name or you can raise your hand
with questions comments observations about this practice
can be quite a profound practice this practice of equanimity
so what did you observe what would you like
to share for the benefit of ah community dawn says thank you nikki
the practice is a refuge for me thank you don for saying that for
putting it in those way in those words practice being a refuge for you with i'm touched
you're such a soul is such a beauty in connecting in this way
thanks for sharing that ah appreciation also for the practice on
youtube from clifton you're welcome clifton delighted you're practicing with us from
bangkok and kim please
uh i found that by the end of the practice i had a real
feeling of solidity in my lower body i would sort of tried out different
mediums but stone felt like stone and then my upper body was there's a
little bit of swaying and my breath sort of felt like
things moving through or creating a little bit of swaying so yeah i really appreciate the
practice thank you lovely thank you kim i'm loving the way you just describe it
and also seeing you and as i feel uh as you're describing the sense
of stone the stability and oh the sway with the breath which gives which doesn't you know there's no
resistance doesn't break it's like oh yeah there is the gentleness um
yeah beautiful beautiful thank you okay lovely
yeah yeah more reflections on youtube and
gratitude from uh venice ref hello from midwest
grateful for the meditation delighted you're here with us practicing anything else you notice you'd like to
share or ask holly says i like imagining
being the stable poised buddha statues because the qualities of them came into
my being oh beautiful yay that's lovely yeah this quality
nice of the buddha statue the poised ability and neil says deeply relaxing
calming and soothing lovely thank you neil for sharing that
ah great so
any other reflections questions challenges it's all good
the benefit of the community anything you like to share or ask
yeah so there can be such a sense of stability
and heart opening to be with what arises and the sense of universality what i was calling this
sense of you know this equanimity or equipoise
it's both yours and not yours in a way there's a sense of universality that
that can arise with this practice in a way similar to practice of meta this this loving
kindness tapping into this beauty and and graciousness of generosity so
so how about we practice in small groups and we'll reserve some time
at the end for for reflections that might come up that might the wheels might be greased as you
discuss in small groups with each other which is really precious heartful practice
so for the practice today in in community the invitation i have
is first start with 30 seconds of silent meta just 30 seconds of wishing each other
well wishing these um lawful sorry wishing these
buddha statues that the buddha nature the buddha-ness of each of you
both sharing your buddha-ness with each other and sharing each other well and then after
30 seconds you're welcome to to share whatever you like about what came up for you as little or
as much as you like um there could be silence and i see your question jamie i'll
address it when we come back out of the group so so um i will create the breakout groups and
yeah so much wisdom and connection that comes out of group practice so
[Music] here we go i'm going to
open the rooms now oh open they are enjoy okay
welcome back everyone so we have a few minutes
for reflections what came up um what do you notice oh and first actually
i'll respond to jamie's question who had
asked before we went right into before we went to the groups
can you comment on what you mean when you refer to things unfolding lawfully so this
is um the the the teaching of causes and conditions
cause and effect that there are laws of nature you can think of them both as
laws of physics laws of karma laws of you know for example in the simple way
if you if you are nice to someone the chances are they'll be nice to you if you're nasty to them if you
if you slap them well they won't be very happy so their lawful nature there are things
that life unfolds according uh unfolds according to lawful
uh according to a lawful nature both physics and and the physics of of how life
works basically so that's the lawful nature it's not as if you would plant say a seed of a mango tree and you
would get a fern tree it just there are things unfold according to a lawful
nature in this this world it's not random so that's what that refers to jamie so
so now your chance
thank you you're welcome thanks for asking and following up from
friday i think that came up before also
so any reflections questions please or or what came up in community practice
how was that
did you have an aha about anything aha
jerry says very supportive hmm nice
the people in my group uh all of us were just uh feeling very good about the
connection that we had with each other and with this group and that how much
we feel supported by it and how important it is to us and um and that was
pretty much the main thing sweet that delights me yeah and and
jamie especially i appreciate because now you become an old timer you've been coming so you're part of the sangha and
what you're sharing about how important this sangha has become to you in the way
of supporting you and practice that just delights me to no end it's it's such a gift for me to be supporting
you and this teaching that supports me so yay thanks for sharing that genie
and emily says i always feel shy when i first see the small group folks i don't know
but then it feels like we're fast friends oh that's so sweet
it's sweet fast friends any other reflections please
michael is that you i see you're unmuted on the phone
that might be might be me this is dorothy but i'm just listening ah hi dorothy all good hi nicky thank
you thank you this is great lovely so thank you all
for your practice this this day this evening this morning this
afternoon whatever your time zone is this moment in time thank you for
practicing for your own sake and for everybody
whose lives you touch so thank you for your practice may all
beings everywhere be happy may all beings everywhere be free including ourselves
thank you for your practice