so hello and welcome to happy hour everyone
and for the theme of our practice in this moment in time
i wanted to offer a contentment contentment as a theme
contentment as a theme [Music] for meta because meta kindness good will
friendliness friendliness with reality friendliness with how something how things are right now in
this moment a sense of ah contentment as the birthplace of
gladness happiness gratitude contentment and i want to start really seed
this practice today with a little poem
that is called enough so i read the poem and the poem is
from david white w-h-y-t-e
from where many rivers meet 1990 and here is the poem
he writes enough these few words are enough
if not these words this breath if not this breath this sitting here
this opening to the life we have refused again
and again until now until now
ah enough enough
what if this is just enough so that serves as the theme of our
practice together enough relaxing into enoughness
as always uh i'll start our guided meditation with a few minutes
of being with the breath and the body and maybe that will just be enough
for the rest of our time together so all right so i
invite you to get into your meditation posture
whatever is appropriate for you in this moment
moving lying down sitting up straighter whatever it needs to be
letting it be enough
opening up to however the body is in this moment
letting the body whatever
way it's showing up in this moment whether it's tired
whether it has a headache if it's excited
what if it's a key if it's light
it's bubbly with excitement or anxiety
if it's calm and settled
however this body is showing up
this heart and this mind
welcoming with arms
that say this is enough
enough
letting this breath
it moves through the body
however it's showing up offering it safety
friendliness this is enough this breath is enough
and if thoughts are rising
thank you thoughts hello thoughts and you know what's happening right here
just sitting just being with the breath is enough
this is enough i'm bowing to the thoughts
not now not now ever so gently
this is enough
nothing needs to be different
we don't make a problem out of it
it's just yes and whatever is in this moment right now
in this experience experience it's enough
taking refuge the simplicity of this moment
just sitting and breathing
i'll read the poem by david white one more time
and let it wash over you
enough these few words
are enough
if not these words this breath
if not this breath this sitting here
this opening to the life
we have refused
again and again
until now until now
if not these words this breath if not this breath is sitting here
this opening to life
enough
if we don't fight with reality if we don't push away what is
what's here right now with aversion
softening into this body this breath this moment
embracing embracing enough enoughness
an act of friendliness with ourselves [Music] and a radical shift
in our perception and our perspective
this moment just this moment not the last one not the future one just right
here right now this one is
this breath this lived life in this moment's experience
contentment
enough
this
it doesn't need to be more than what it is right now this is enough it's plenty
any different anymore any less
if there is any resistance of reality as it is can that too be included
in the friendliness to be enough
to offer that safety it's okay don't have to reject rejection see what
shifts if that's the case that's present
maybe this practice opening to enough
also supports seeing the ways in which
the mind interprets this not to be enough the ways that it's
critical this is not enough you're not enough and can that be seen with kindness and
care you are enough this is enough
what if what if we invite that perception
for the last few moments
you are enough i am enough this moment is enough
for the last minute
let's practice
what if we chose what if we inclined our intention
to contentment or whatever this period of practice showed up as
to be content that we showed up and we tried as best as we could to be content with that attempt not try
to change the past re-engineer the past
and to appreciate our gratitude be content with whatever arose
or did not arise
our wholehearted intention to sit
and come together in community has been
enough
[Music]
so enough contentment enoughness
so i notice that
i feel much calmer and soothed and settled
after this period of practice which was quite bare taking a line
from david white's poem
these few words are enough so we had few words tonight tonight
in the spirit of enoughness contentment more of a maybe zen style of
of um yeah
silence more silence so i'd love to invite you if you like to share any reflections
what was this like for you this turning the mind the heart
with friendliness as an expression of friendliness safety and meta
to enoughness what if this moment is enough enoughness of this breath
this body bill shares simple and calming
thank you thank you bill
you are welcome to share your reflections in chat
or raise your hand richard says tenderness ease thank you lovely
i see dawn please
thank you so much i really appreciated the quiet and also
the statement this is enough you're enough um because i was
thinking like oh i just need to be sit better and get in like the perfect
meditation posture and i'm thinking too much and i'm thinking about what i'm going to say
after the meditation and you know sort of all this stuff and anyway
i appreciate it this is enough thank you thank you don thank you for sharing
your reflections yeah great yeah it's so interesting it feels like
this is enough i'm enough can be like a little friendly pen that pops the balloon of of
proliferation of thoughts i should do this i should do that or i'm gonna oh this is enough simplicity
thanks for sharing that don another reflection sent directly to me
so i won't say the names escape from the madness of the world thank you i love that escape from the madness of
the world this practice another reflection refreshing and spacious
thank you oh thank you so appreciate your reflections any other
reflections any anything else you noticed
if you found it challenging too that's okay too you can share that as well it's all
welcome it's all enough whatever it is it's all enough it's all included
i love this other reflection a womb of enoughness i love it a womb of enoughness yes
great giving birth to gladness contentment ease
nice well maybe that has been enough reflections
for now so i don't see any any hands or reflections
popping up then i'll start our slow transition
[Music] to practice in sangha
and the invitation in these small groups for the few minutes is to start with the fume with 60
30 seconds of silent meta silent enoughness maybe silently as you're sitting feeling
i'm enough and you're enough as an expression of meta as an expression
of friendliness and see what that feels like in the interpersonal field and then you
can share right you practice say a few words or not maybe silence is enough just that's
lovely actually to cultivate the comfort to sit in silence with others or share words so see see whatever
feels right for you um you decide what what is best for you so
so with that i will yeah
i will create the rooms and let's see here
okay so some shuffling last minute always okay
the rooms are ready and they are open okay welcome back everyone
the rooms are closed so i wanted to share the poem with you
um in chat here it is the formatting is gone but the title is
on top the reference is on the bottom it's a short poem so
so we have a few minutes for reflections questions comments complaints it's
all welcome so welcome to raise your hand type it in
chat especially if you're newer if you're new
or you often don't speak you're welcome you're invited
richard please
so this is the first you hear me right yes hi richard how are you doing this is the
first time in as far as i can remember that i didn't feel like i was working
during meditation uh so should i feel guilty that i wasn't doing anything i wasn't
accomplishing anything yay i sc absolutely
celebrate this is absolutely fantastic that there was this sense of non-doing
their sense of ease that's fantastic richard
yay and it sounds like this is the first time in a long while or ever or the way you're putting it
same how did it feel i mean i i know your inner wisdom knows that wow this is good this is wow
this is easeful well i i always feel that i have
an agenda or something or a um you know so i have to use some method i
have to like concentrate or count my breasts or something or other
or pay attention to work to pay attention and this was just sort of accepting whatever you know
it's enough it was enough yeah yeah yeah
yeah it is enough and um i so appreciate you raising this
because this is such an important point and it's so subtle actually what you are bringing to the
fore to the light it's often so subtle
that we use the same mind that we use for everything else in our lives
the same mind we apply the same mind that wants to get wants to do wants to
be wants to accomplish wants to attain uh our profession in our profession
especially in the west we bring the same type of mind to our meditation
and this is what we do this is what we all do richard until we notice wait a minute that feels like
a lot of work and we get tight and knots and it's effortful and then we don't want to meditate because
it's too much work i'm not getting anywhere and yet the secret actually is the sense
of easing into relaxing into the sense of openness and friendliness
with reality the right effort wise effort because
wanting to do do do is too much efforting and sometimes if there's absolutely no
it's just you know our mind is just wandering all over the place you know that's too little effort but the sweet spot
after we've experienced the the two ends so it's okay to go you know we will never ever always get
it right on we will miss and it's perfectly fine that's how you tune a bow
and there's there's similes that the buddha teaches about effort that too tight is like tuning
a bowed instrument sometimes it's too tight sometimes it's too loose and that's a part of it so what you're
sharing is that oh your instrument your mind has been too tight wow it's been like like wow what is how
different it is how lovely how my words not yours lovely how easeful maybe how easeful it is that but no
guilt feeling because that sense of ease actually can open you to finding itself because meditation
shouldn't feel like too much effort this ease full feeling is a part of it
so please don't feel guilty celebrate as i celebrate for you this realizing that oh there is a
different way and this could be a turning point does that make sense does that how does
that land it's perfect hopefully thanks for thanks for coming
to happier richard great a couple more reflections i see
uh one is it was less stimulating and very helpful to quiet the mind
at the end of the week thank you for the reminder that being present here was enough
yay thank you for that beautiful reflection and one more reflection from
elizabeth love this metaphor of rivers coming together many of us as rivers coming together and
just an acceptance of each of us rivulets yes ah
all of us rivers of humanity riverlets of humanity coming together and
may all of our little rivulets coming together as we practice together again this is
another simile that the buddha uses that with practice when you practice
wholeheartedly there is no destination other than you
will end up in no place other than the ocean and the ocean here
is is a simile for freedom for liberation for peace and ease with
all the conditions of life as they come and go peace and ease in the heart
so that we can be more present more loving more accepting of ourselves
others and all beings everywhere so thank you all for your practice for
coming to happy hour to practice and may our practice serve and support ourselves others and
all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings enjoy the taste of the
ocean of lebanon
thanks everyone