so we're continuing now with the last
steps of
last of the 16 steps of mindfulness of
breathing
and we're coming now to the the 15th
step
and which is uh the polyword that it
represents that has been
being used is niroda
and in the 14th step the poly word is
v raga the rhoda is spelled
n-i-r-o-d-h-a
and um and it's sometimes it's nice to
just
use the pali words because in the
original context and in india
these words have really rich
connotations
in fact the these the
raga and eroda are sometimes
listed almost as as synonyms or almost
as synonyms
for liberation itself and so they have a
very very kind of almost sacred or
special
quality that the english word for viraga
which i've said sometimes translated as
fading away
and sometimes as dispassion it doesn't
really capture the richness of the
the the associations or the the way it
feels in pali to the raga
and then same thing with niroda such a
rich
world word that in the original context
i think that
it really felt like a heartwarming idea
that
you don't get from the english
translations
the most common translation for niurota
is
cessation and cessation just
end you know ending doesn't really
bring for most of us doesn't bring much
heartfelt feeling
inspiration delight joy just cessation
it's like
just seems like okay it's not the ending
of something
the word niroda comes from the
prefix knee which means without
not free from
and rhoda which means obstruction
so it's being without obstruction so
cessation is a very different feeling
than
free of obstruction and maybe the
cessation of obstructions
cessation of blockages or clinging or
contraction or
what gets in the way of freedom and so
the 13
the 14th step the fading away the
dispassion
is the involves the fading away in the
ceasing
the ending of uh
attachments of cravings of conceits of
the driveness compulsive ways we're
being that
heaven definitely a feeling of uh
stress and maybe even pain associated
with their drive with their
presence and that the the
the pain of those the stress of those
becomes more and more apparent
the more wonderfully and beautifully
quiet and still the mind becomes a
meditation
the more calm we are the more they stand
out and highlight as being wow this is
kind of
uncomfortable to feel this way that in
ordinary street consciousness we might
not feel and so i can even say what's
the big deal
it's okay to have a little bit of
irritation but in deep meditation a
little bit irritation it doesn't feel
like a little bit
it feels like a real disruption and more
importantly an obstruction
to deeper peace deeper freedom
so the 15th step is one trains
um
observing cessation
one will breathe in observing
cessation won't breathe out observing
non-obstruction
when we'll breathe in observing
non-obstruction one will
breathe out and and so
uh as we get deeper and deeper at some
point we observe
a sacred absence we observe the absence
of something
and the absence uh that was really
strong is really uh noteworthy it's like
um deeply inspiring
so with watching in constancy
in constancy we're watching things come
and go they arise and they pass
and this and being in the river the flow
of transiency
but as we do that we begin to
the attachment to reaching into that
river of change
begins to give up can still relax
and with that something ceases something
stops something is no longer there to
obstruct
the freedom and that
and that absence is not just a temporary
absence like
it fades and then comes back a second
later or
fades away and comes back a minute later
or something
but it there's a way in which the
cessation the ending of it the
absence of it is really
impactful for the mind and the heart
wow it's possible
to really be free of cynicism
wow this is right you know i've been
sitting cynical
for decades wow this is possible
or i've been always you know
preoccupied and self-preoccupied with
self
wow this preoccupation with me myself
and mine has fallen away
and it's not here i can look around
where is it it's not there
wow it's it's absent it's ceased
it there's a non-obstruction now that i
realize that self-preoccupation was a
kind of a
obstruction or wind drag or something
jealousy doubt
hatred resentment
all kinds of desires that sometimes are
there kind of in the structure of how
our mind works
so embedded fear
and wow this has ceased for now
it might come back the next day it might
come back at the end of the meditation
but there's something about the
thoroughness
of that absence which makes an
impression
and then of this i know is possible
i had no idea this was possible and
of course this is like coming home or
this is health or this is my birthright
or
this is worthwhile this you know it's
worth this is is fantastic
and any movement away from it any way of
picking up the compulsion
that's a diminishment that's not really
worth it anymore
and that's not the direction to go
that's not the way i want to live
this is how i want to live without this
obstructions this kind of stress of
these kinds of things
and when this sense of absence is really
impactful and strong enough when it's
really
a very very deep thorough absence then
a person will never be the same again
it's almost as if that absence is a
living
memory or presence or something that as
a guide
oh this is where freedom is this is
where peace says this is where truth is
not truth propositional truth but just
the true way of being a certain way
and and and then it becomes an
orientation
for how to live our life or to say it in
different way
the tradition what the tradition says
when then has entered into the current
the good current the current that takes
us to full freedom
so we're in the river of change the
river of intransicency
but we've now discovered that there's an
a place that's not in the eddies
that's not in the in the brambles that
are
growing into the side of the river but
where notice maybe in the center of the
river there's a beautiful current
that if we stay in that current it'll
carry us
to the tradition talks use this as
analogy
to the ocean of liberation and freedom
and so this so i call this the sacred
absence
the absence of and to recognize the
value of absence
and this is a hard thing for many people
to appreciate
that absence has importance
the uh in a sense you can watch the mind
and see as soon as there's a quiet
moment in the mind sometimes it seems
like a mind just reaches out for the
next thing to think about
or we have certain problems and as soon
as that problem is solved
the mind just goes on to the next thing
and the next thing and the next things
the mind is filling itself all the time
but but to appreciate absence
cessation this deep sacred
pause or stopping and
let it impact us wow it's true
so that it's possible to be free
so it's a little disappointing for
people who always want to
have something that's be reassuring
something that's a confirmation that
they're important they're valuable
that they're on the right track that
they can have the badge to tell their
friends look i
have this beautiful thing the spiritual
quality or something and
but and an absence is not a badge you
can put on
absence is not the presence of something
there might be our ability to be present
for things of the world
become stronger but freedom is not
something tangible it's not something
that
in a sense that the mind can focus on as
an
object of attention in a usual way that
things we can
see and touch and feel
and so it's very easy to overlook
absences
or to diminish their importance in fact
in
in the history of buddhism in the
ancient world
there were debates and big concerns
about
some people some great buddhist teachers
couldn't understand
how an absence could be
that the ultimate goal the ultimate
freedom of buddhism was somehow
represented by an absence
it had to be a thing it had to be some
something and
they posited a variety of different
kinds of transcen transcendent kind of
states and experiences
because it had to be a thing um so
whether that's true or not
uh is besides the point what i'm trying
to say now
in the 15 steps of mindfulness of
breathing
it becomes it's at observing absence
observing cessation observing a space of
non-obstruction
observing how with the fading away of
of these you know passion for
these lust for clinging for craving
that it uh at some point the stopping
the cessation is so
full and sometimes it happens like like
a
like a quantum shift wow and sometimes
it happens slowly or fading away
but something and
and it might be just one thing it might
be cynicism or it might be
doubt but something that's been plaguing
us for a long time
boom wow we notice
this is possible and it is possible
and the buddha made this great statement
if it was not possible if it's not
possible
to i'm kind of paraphrasing him if it's
not possible
to bring an end to our unwholesome
mental qualities
i wouldn't teach you to bring them to an
end
but it is possible to bring unwholesome
mental qualities
to an end to cessation
and so i teach you that this is possible
so this 15th step is an
encouragement to appreciate
absence to appreciate sacred absence
take time recognizing when a
preoccupation when
greed when anger when desire when lust
when anything like all these things that
the mind involved in mind contracting
the heart contracting
notice know it appreciate when it's not
there
and that appreciation will allow to grow
or
allow you to feel some confidence about
this and keep making space
in sacred space sacred openness of
attention
to be more present and more here that
supports this whole process
of of furthering along onward leading
aspect of this
path of practice
so um breathing in
cessation breathing out observing
cessation so
thank you all and may
you appreciate the all the
absences that occurred to you today that
will enliven you or say it maybe
or just uh
just delight you benefit you open you
free you and there's probably much more
absences
that are the door to step through today
than you realize
may you appreciate the sacred absence
today
thank you