so a warm hello to all of you and
those of you who are writing your names in the chat hello it's nice to see your names and those of
you who are not warm hello and it's so wonderful to
have this time together and uh i find that uh this
meditation practice mindfulness practice um a little bit of a miracle
and we're kind of a natural wonder wander in that
[Applause] in its essence it's very simple
and in some ways the simpler you can make it be the more wondrous it becomes the more
amazing and well maybe sometimes immediately miraculous becomes and this art of learning to be aware
but be aware in radical simplicity
in a sense just be aware and not to add anything to it not to
build stories around it or not hijack your
awareness with desires and aversions and of course we have stories and
desires and aversions and stuff but it isn't that we have to
be free of those but we include them in this radical
simplicity of awareness rather include them in the sense of knowing it
as opposed to having them somehow color take over influence how we're
aware so radical simplicity
and some of you have been doing these all these last 70 talks on mindfulness of breathing and
it was a lot of information a lot of ideas and and now as we're coming to the end you
know i want to evoke the idea that
there is a path through all these steps and the ideal path i think is
not to make much effort to do so but just to rely on the radical simplicity awareness
and then watch how these steps develop watch how practice unfolds
but without any expectations or demands or efforts to make it so
and finally this uh kind of a image that i've
learned from buddhist teachings that was very meaningful for me for this
simplicity is the idea of taking a backward step just stepping back and then watching and
looking stepping back and how far do we have to step back in the mind so we can just observe just be aware
in the simplest possible way and sometimes it's taking a step back
and turning around 380 degrees and just just looking at
how we're aware and appreciating how simple it can be
just aware in its essence awareness is very simple
and as some of you have heard me do before now you know if i gave the instructions for you to stop being aware
for many people when they hear that it's like then they can't like you they can't turn it off
you know unless you distract yourself somehow in fact the instructions to stop being
aware for some people heightens their awareness it's kind of always there in
some form in the simplest possible form of it just
here with this maybe here with um
with your breathing so
entering into a meditation posture
and maybe adjusting your posture some
part of the adjustment is just a reminder that you'll be here now
gently closing your eyes and then to
take a few gentle slow long breaths three quarters full
as a movement towards being here
in this body simplifying yourself from all the concerns of the day
yesterday and your life just simply here
in this body
breathing in and in a long gentle exhale
relaxing at the end of the exhale so maybe you release more
longer exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale to move through the body from the top to the bottom settling
yourself and relaxing as you do and the exhale relaxing the muscles of
the face around the eyes and the forehead
the jaws
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
small adjustment in your hands where they are in position might free up the shoulders a
little bit more
softening the belly releasing the belly
softening and releasing the legs the holding in the thighs or the calves
and then within the body as part of the body
becoming aware of your breathing
breathing in a simple ordinary way
but perhaps on the exhale for a few exhales
releasing relaxing at the end of the exhale
so that it's a little bit longer
and so there's a little pause before you inhale
very little pause
just long enough so you feel the body's natural urge
to breathe in
and allow for that urge to manifest as an in-breath
and then with the breathing
just the breathing how simple can you be aware of it
perhaps a simplicity
that allows the a fuller experience of breathing
to have space in awareness
it's not crowded out by other concerns and things
and then as we sit here today no matter what is happening for you as
you sit and meditate maybe there can be a refuge for you
in the simplicity of awareness the simplicity of just being aware just
mindful taking a backward step so you're less
involved and tangled simple recognition ah this is how it is
okay
a simplicity of awareness where nothing is a problem
just something to be aware of
whatever is happening to you it's all right to limit yourself to
simply knowing it simply being aware
taking a backward step to not be involved with it
just be aware
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
the simplicity of awareness can also teach us about the simplicity of love
sometimes when we are alone like in meditation it's kind of personal
situation where you don't have to speak to someone or interact with someone
where it's a little bit safe sometimes this is where we can discover
the simplicity of love the simplicity of kindness or goodwill
a caring quality of the heart may be a appreciative quality
way in which our heart is delights and appreciates and values someone
that doesn't require us to say anything or do anything
the person doesn't have to even know it and so it can be free we can be freer
to love freer from complications
and to discover the simplicity of love
can be a great lesson that supports us and how to care and love and have good will for people
when we are together
so as we sit and end this sitting perhaps you can touch into
the simplest form of goodwill and well-wishing or
or about our appreciation for of others
maybe it's a worthless appreciation with just a warmth or a softness
of the heart
maybe it can feel quite lovely to allow for that softness the warmth
the love to be there without needing to do anything about it it's just there
vibrating or glowing
and then as to whatever degree you can in fact feel some simplicity of care
love see if these words i speak
resonate with that place
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may that my love my good will my kindness my care
word wordlessly
flow out for me out into the world
and may whatever benefit that's come from this morning's meditation this day's meditation
may in fact be for the welfare and benefit of all beings everywhere
so having covered the 16 steps of mindfulness of breathing
the the buddha's instructions in this practice continues and to
first explaining how mindfulness breathing
comes along with the fulfillment powerful word
fulfillment of the four foundations of mindfulness
and and and as i said yesterday each of the four
parts the four tetrads are the 16 steps is directly connected to one of the four
foundations of mindfulness so if you do the first tetrad of just
connecting to the breathing and feeling the breath body relaxing the bodily
formations that to do that well fully to enter into that deeply
is also fulfills the first foundation of mindfulness the mindfulness of the body
and so forth what's interesting is then next the buddha says that practice
fulfilling the four foundations of mindfulness fulfills or brings about evokes the
seven factors of awakening and the way that uh it does that is is
that if you do fully the first tetrad it fulfills the first foundation of
mindfulness the full fulfillment of first foundation of mindfulness then awakens or brings along with it
the seven factors of awakening and the seven factors awakening then lead to awakening and
uh so the implication here is that each of the tetrads each of the four steps of of anapanasati
is can be complete in itself you don't have to go through the 16 steps one after the other
it's enough that your practice is just staying with any one of the four and i think for many
people just staying with the first step and so the first four steps
are not like elementary or remedial or something and you want to get to the higher steps
it's uh you're supposed to kind of you know guide yourself through them the the first four steps can take you
all the way to awakening just just doing that after the buddha
died there were commentaries early commentaries and they kind of went on a little bit the same
way to say that if you just do the first tetrad it
also fulfills the other 12 steps that somehow just kind of the simplicity
of just being present for breathing in the body and relaxing the body
uh calming in body and doing that fully um brings about all the other
benefits all the other movements of practice and to me this has a lot to do with the simplicity of all
this practice that the simpler we can be uh and the less entangled we are
and trying and wanting just being here in a very simple way it's onward leading it sets free
a a you know it sets the water begins flowing down
the river flowing down the mountainside you have to put up big boulders and blockages to stop it
and you can do that but but it's a lot of work but if you remove the obstacles
water will flow so this practice of anapanasati mindfulness breathing
is a practice becoming simpler and simpler in that all the obstacles are step we step away
from we release the obstacles and then something unfolds and moves and
deepens and and uh and so the meditator doesn't have
to be so concerned about that deepening just but go along for the ride
if we can really stay intimate and connected and trusting
of this mindfulness of breathing mindfulness of the being in the body and letting the body
relax and soften and around this breathing we do and not get caught up in other things
and just simpler and simpler just breathing just breathing
focused settled steady composed on the breathing and the idea is not to force that
but uh to know that a lot of that has to do with letting go it's just allowing yourself to become simpler and simpler
so that as the so then the buddha says with the with the with the fulfillment of the
first foundation of mindfulness then that fulfills the first
of the seven factors of awakening which is mindfulness itself when mindfulness is fulfilled that in
the language is very interesting it's a language is more like then it's natural or what flows out of
that what arises out of that as opposed to what we're supposed to do so continues this process of simplicity
we're just getting out of the way and something begins to bubble up and unfold this miracle of the
dharma so he says that when the mindfulness
has become well developed then what follows that is uh
investigation one looks more carefully with wisdom at what's happening when you know what
is if mindfulness is clear clarity uh investigation is really seeing more
more in more detail what is clear what is happening so just kind of a great amount of
clarity and investigation of discerning what's there for the buddha
the more we're discerned the more we see clearly what's here it gives rise to
energy gives rise to engagement it gives rise to interest and oh this is good partly because the
more we can investigate what we're investigating we're really discerning and seeing if we're really
mindful is how the the trail the path that opens
in front of us into what's where freedom is where what's wholesome what's beneficial
and we follow the choices that are in the wholesome direction and because
we know what's unwholesome we know that clinging and grasping and aversion doesn't really work
and so we choose not to go there we don't pick we don't stop having those feelings but we don't get
involved they don't pick up which to degree which is true there's choice
we choose what's wholesome and in the for meditators that the wholesome thing
can be as simple as just staying with the breathing being mindfully breathing considered to
phenomenally wholesome healthy thing to do and so then there's energy in that there's enthusiasm for
that and so there that arises and not that you have to be enthusiastic or interested
but it just flows out of this practice as it deepens
as we have this interested engagement then what flows out of that is joy and
delight happiness about this what flows out of that
is something deeper settles and relaxes feels reassured
uh it becomes calm tranquil a deeper tranquility or serenity
and that deeper serenity and tranquility leads to greater concentration or or more subtleness and more
steadiness more composure and and that deeper composure and
subtleness concentration then out of that flows equanimity a deep
non-reactivity of the mind and equanimity is like the pinnacle of simplicity
that's where things are so simple the awareness we're just aware and the awareness is not ruffled by any
wanting and not wanting so you know until we get to the stage of
equanimity awareness is not really completely simple so don't worry about it
don't try to have perfection but the movement is just be simple as you
as you can and so then we move through these seven beautiful factors that's kind of the miracle of practices too
that the simple awareness just staying in the simplicity of it can lead to these beautiful qualities of
mindfulness deeper discernment or investigation
energy or engagement effort joy
tranquility concentration and equanimity and
and part of the value of this deep equanimity is that um this simplicity
it's a radical simplicity where we're getting closer and closer to where the mind is not for or against anything
it's just there luminous clear present fully here without
wants and and aversions without building a cell for having itself
referential like you know it's a self-help project it just there's almost like the self self concern conceit
just falls away because things have gotten so simple and clear and that equanimity that is that way
then uh is uh because it's not doing anything or
wanting anything or trying to get anything at some point that awareness can discover
a kind of a rest a kind of a letting go a kind of release where
the any remnant any kind of way a structure uh
personality structure linguistic linguistic structure any ways in which the mind
is involved with things and thinking about things and just releases let's go and um and
there's an experience of freedom that it's such a nature or this freedom
that then people say well now i know what the practice is about
oh so this is what it's about this level this possibility of being free from any attachment any
clinging any agitation any contraction at all
wow this is possible and it's uh then i would call it the
ultimate fulfillment of simplicity and it's a simplicity which that rather
than being boring or being like we feel like we're missing out on the wonderful things of life
this is the wonderfulness this there's something of the peace and the clarity and the
happiness and the of of freedom is just you know one of the greatest things in this universe
and and so some people then to this is when then we
really know this is what practice can do this is what about this is what simple clear awareness is and then
um it said in the ancient world and this is not meant to be discouraging i
hope it's encouraging um the in the ancient kind of lore is
that then this is when dharma practice begins
the first real taste of freedom is because when we know what the practice is really about
we have no doubts about it anymore and now i can start practicing this is what
the practice is and there's this huge confidence that arises and uh and in the ancient language of
the buddha then a person at that point is called
a practitioner so it's you know of course we're practitioners before
that and wonderful practitioners and a lot of benefit before this kind of freedom
but um and then usually in english they translate the word
sika as a trainee now a person is ready to train now a person knows what
the practice is about so um but all from this simplicity
they don't have to make it complicated and and even the very first step of anapanasati
the commentary you say is enough just stay there be with that's enough to go all the way you'll be taken you'll be carried there
if you do it sincerely and fully and regularly and then
the text goes on to one more teaching for tomorrow and that's a teaching of what practice
looks like uh this looks like
after a person has when a person become a trainee when persons become a practitioner in the way i'm talking about
how do we practice after the first glimpse of awakening
so thank you very much and i'm looking forward to being here with
you again tomorrow