good evening good morning good afternoon
i'm happy that we're practicing together
so we'll begin with a guided meditation
we'll start by just coming into the body
recognizing that we're here at this moment
and maybe in a global way
i'll just check in how is the body
maybe it's feeling a little bit tired or maybe a little bit restless
or a little bit achy or a little bit spacious
or maybe you're not quite sure yet
however it may be it's all welcome and invited
doesn't mean it matches our preferences of course but
we don't need to exclude or push away
our experiences but to make room for them
and allow them to be here as best we can
and feeling connected grounded feeling the pressure of the chair the
cushion the bench the couch whatever you're sitting on
feeling the pressure against the body
and then checking in with the posture is there a sense of evenness a sense of
balance sometimes it's helpful to rock back and
forth a bit a little bit of an adjustment
we all know how uncomfortable it can be if the
if we're not sitting just right
then we find ourselves squirming or just simply getting up and abandoning
it but to feel the uprightness
and the balance in the posture
and then to allow the attention to rest on the sensations of breathing
and feeling the inhales feeling the exhales as the chest moves
the belly moves
enter every now and then just check in with the body in a global sense
just noticing the posture
are we leaning forward maybe we're slumping
maybe our chin is up
without making it a big project
but just feeling into the body maybe the body as a whole
seeing if there's a sense of balance
if you find that your shoulders are up or maybe you're leaning forward a little
bit we don't have to make it a problem we just very
simply bring our posture back into alignment
into balance
and if we notice that repeatedly we're leaning forward or our chin
is up we might just get a little curious
is there a mental state that's associated with this physical
expression this physical movement
some people sometimes when their chin is up they're doing planning
leaning forward it's a little bit of
striving getting slumped collapsed is
maybe lost in fantasy or lost in some kind of thought
maybe a feeling of dejection or disappointment sadness
being sensitive to our posture
can be another way in which we can be aware
of our experience our inner experience
maybe the mental state
maybe our emotional state
we might not be aware of it until we notice the shift in our posture
hey
so finding the balance in our posture in our body
can help us notice when we're a little bit out of balance
in the mind maybe there's a lot of wanting this leaning forward
maybe there's some collapsing mentally as well as physically
maybe there's a lot of planning and or striving
we don't have to make it a big problem or make a big project out of it we can just very gently
bring the body back into balance
allowing perhaps the mind follows
perhaps the mind is already there but using the body
and this idea of balance as a support
for our practice
help us not to be out of balance
so that we can take care of ourselves and take care of others in a way that's
appropriate
so in this way our practice is for the benefit of all beings
not just for ourselves for those we come in contact with and
whom they come in contact with they come in contact with etc etc
so may all beings be free from suffering
welcome welcome a really warm welcome for everybody
wherever you are whomever you are
sometimes when we listen to a dharma talk or give a dharma talk there's this tendency
to approach them with our cognitive minds i know that certainly is the case for me
sometimes been reflecting on this and for many of
us who have had a profession or just enjoy kind of like solving problems figuring
things out to acquiring knowledge understanding it and
creating models from the data that we get or i know that my years as a research
scientist i used to love that so much love that's when the to get the data and like wow okay now
what does this mean and put together the little pieces and there's so many different ways in
which we might uh do this whether we're actually doing experiments or not
and so of course of course we or sometimes will bring this type of
thinking or this type of way of being into the way we approach dharma talks
either giving the dharma talks or uh listening to them
trying to might be a way like if we're listening to them we might have this idea that okay just if i just take in enough
information if i understand it if i can make all the little pieces fit together
nice neat and tidy or maybe if i can the sense of okay if i
just have to get everything straight now how does this relate to that and what precisely is the definition of
that and this energy of um trying to figure it out and this feeling
this may be leaning into well if only i just added all the information
then i could do this buddhist practice thing i could do this meditation thing
of course it's easy for us to fall into that type of thinking when we have it probably in so many
other areas of our lives and in some ways and sometimes that type
of approach of figuring it out or acquiring information
is helpful with our buddhist practice is helpful with meditation
but it's not the only way and nor is it have to be the predominant
way there's so many different ways in which we might listen to a dharma talk or just approach
the dharma in general
so one way that also this cognitive uh really intellectualized approach
may also approach uh listening to dharma talks is not only trying to figure it out but
also there might be this little nuclean thought okay it's surely it's not really that
simple it must be more complicated so this always this thinking that there's like
there's got to be more here this idea of mindfulness just being with them our experience
surely that can't be enough pay attention to one's breath surely there's there's got to be more
that there that's doesn't seem snazzy enough
so there's this way in which we might be tempted to substitute knowledge for
practice they cannot require information or thinking they have to figure it out
but there's a way in which practice can be actually really simple really simple
one way we might think about it is maybe can be demonstrated with this simile perhaps some of you are
familiar with this simile that's uh in the suit does so we might and the buddha tells the
story as a way to make a point that suppose there's a crowd of people
who are watching a performance a really beguiling
uh interesting performance and their attention is there and maybe
there's a in my mind there's like an upbeat mood
maybe there's a yeah there's just like a a um in my mind it's kind of like you
know you know sometimes we see concerts rock and roll concerts or something like this
pop concerts so there's these people that are what happily watching a performance
and then you can imagine that you have been instructed to carry a bowl of oil
on your head and to walk through the crowd towards
the stage without dropping the oil
from the bowl and just to make it a little more interesting there's a person behind you
with a sword that will cut off your head if one any drop of oil falls
it's a little bit outrageous even to imagine this but the buddha is pointing to this is
one way we might consider mindfulness practice that is if you're going to walk with a
bowl of oil on your head that there and there's like some hustle
and bustle going around around you and people are paying attention to the performance not to you
that means you need to have some mindfulness you need to be aware and to be aware of your posture so that
you remain balanced but there also needs to be some flexibility and some agility and to be aware of
what's going around but around you maybe not so much that you like
returning your head to look and see everything but in a way in which maybe your
awareness is kind of broad
so it has to be like really embodied with a sense of agility or a sense of
flexibility and stability to walk through this crowd with a
bowl of oil on your head and then you might consider that
the sword the person with this sword and the that's gonna chop off your head it's more
pointing to the to be sustained to have this sustained
mindfulness so it's not to be upright with good posture and balanced
in a sense of agility once or twice but the entire time you're walking
towards this stage and i'm imagining i don't know but i'm
imagining in the buddha's time maybe um it wasn't so unusual to walk with a bowl of
or walk with anything on your head so maybe they it's not that doesn't have the same
degree of difficulty that it might for us but again pointing to this sense of
embodiment and awareness
so if this were to be a simile that points to practice we could say well
actually in some ways the practice is simple be aware and stay balanced
be aware and stay balanced
but we might also hear about some of this this person in the sword in the back of
us with a sword and we might consider there'd be some tension and some tightness about this
not flexibility or agility or something like this
so maybe to bring in another visual you know sometimes we can understand things
with a visual with similes and stories and even though buddhist buddhism
and buddhist practice certainly has a lot of lists there's also these stories and these visual things so that's a little bit
what i'd like to use today so here's a another visual
but there is a a monastic who is feeling really discouraged
it feels like they want to leave the monastery when they disrobe
and this person was in before they became a monastic would
play the loot we can think of the lutus proto guitar
it's in the guitar family perhaps and so when the buddha hears that this
person sona wants to leave the monastery in disrobe he goes to sona and
says so sona you're a loot player right yes venerable sir well when the string
was too loose did it sound good no venerable sir well what about
when the string was too tight did it sound good no venerable sir so
in the same way tune your level of effort so that it's just right
in the same way that you would tune the strings of a guitar so it has the right
sound like tune the level of effort that is
to not be too tight and striving and straining and not to be too laxadaisical
and one thing that's nice about the simile of the loot is if we think about the loots have more
than one string i don't know exactly how many but that's when we know with guitars that
when you tune one string then you tune other strings to that string
so that everything comes into harmony so you can pay attention particular to
one string and then everything else it becomes a little bit easier to tune all the others so to pay
attention to the amount of energy the amount of effort
and maybe one way that is an indicator for how much effort
one is applying is your reaction when the bell rings at the end of a meditation period
when the bell rings and there's a sense of
that's the sign that there's a little bit too much tightness it may be too much straining or a little bit too much
a sense of white knuckling it till the end of the period the meditation period
so we will need to tune our energy we need to have some agility but also maybe to emphasize this
sense of a little bit of movement here's a one other simile
i'm sorry this isn't a simile this is a little story
in which a deva this is a unembodied being comes to the buddha and
says dear sir how did you cross the flood
and we could use the word flood to represent all kinds of things
but without saying anything specific we know that floods are generally
undesirable that they kind of like destroy things in their path and our have a lot of power and
i mean you know the product of torrential rains or something
dear sir how did you cross the flood i crossed the flood by not halting
and not straining then the davis says but how by not
halting and by not straining did you cross the flood and the buddha
responds when i came to a standstill i sank
and when i struggled i got swept away
so to not do anything to sink but to put afford a lot of
effort a lot of energy struggling fighting is to get swept away
in this torrential flood to not find a way across
but to be susceptible to the energy of the flood itself
so there's these are some visuals in which we might understand practice way we can might really
simplify practice be aware and stay balanced
i heard this from another dharma teacher be aware and stay balanced
so what does this mean stay balanced i talked about this a little bit in the guided meditation one way is with
our posture whether we're sitting or walking
or whether we're moving i guess you don't worry about your posture so much when you're lying
down in terms of being balanced but it's really worthwhile to
spend some time learning which kind of seating equipment is best
and to really learn is our our ears over our shoulders and sometimes
having to tuck the chin a little bit so that it opens up a little space in the back of the neck
so that the spine has a real sense of uprightness and allows the arms to just hang
but as we are sitting we might notice during meditation if we have this intention to check our
posture we might notice that sometimes there's a certain amount of leaning
it can be leaning forward maybe maybe not so much literally but maybe
kind of like figuratively leaning backwards that's kind of like a push and a pull a sense of a push and a pull
that we feel in the body as well as we feel in the mind
but this leaning we can maybe if we notice that we're leaning might be an encouragement to to inquire well what
are we placing our attention on what are we aware of
because sometimes our minds fixate on what we want or what we don't want
and then this kind of um causes us to lean either literally or figuratively
this push or pull but mindfulness practice is to be aware
of this this preoccupation with what we want or with what we don't
want is of course it's a natural human impulse to be preoccupied preoccupied
with these things and trying to fix them but we can be aware of our mental state
rather than just letting them
continue like unchecked but to beware and stay balanced is to
notice when are we a little bit out of balance so to be leaning towards something to be
wanting something to have desire for something it's not inherently problematic
we we all have the desire to eat when we're hungry we have the desire to care for
and protect those people we love we have a desire for the world to be a
better place i have a desire for practice and to find
more freedom experience more freedom so desire by ourselves itself isn't
inherently problematic but this our practice is about becoming aware
and being able to distinguish between skillful and unskillful desire
the desire that leads to more and more freedom or the desire that lends to getting
tangled up and leading to less freedom
so practice isn't about getting rid of all desire even though sometimes i have heard some
buddhist teachings that made me think that perhaps it was but this recognition of what's skillful and
what's unskillful sometimes we can notice that by whether
we feel out of balance or not and if we notice that we're a little bit of out of balance with our desire
one thing we can do is to take a careful look at the object of our desire
the actual thing or the situation and
to just do this gentle inquiry are we seeing it accurately
chances are when we have a lot of desire we're just seeing all the beautiful aspects all the attractive
aspects but everything has you know it's not
the chances are that something is a hundred percent beautiful
is not high so can we see the fullness can we see some of the unattractive aspects of whatever we're
desiring and can we take a
and imagine well this really fulfill these expectations that i have
and ask in that question ask us well what are our expectations
that we have for whatever it is that we're desiring
and then that kind of brings us back to our own experience so there's the object with it is it
really as beautiful and perfect as we're imagining and what is my experience both what are
my expectations and how does it feel to be desiring
how does it feel to be like leaning this
pulling being pulled towards something and it might be really subtle
this way that we're maybe a little bit off balance in a subtle way
so to simplify the practice to be aware and stay balanced one way that we might be out of balance
is because we're filled with desire and of course the flip side of that is
aversion this mild or maybe even really strong dislike or really
sense of i don't want this and just like with desire there are healthy forms of
aversion and in some ways it might even be a kindness to turn away
from some things that are painful and there are times also when we're just
for so many different reasons not quite ready to work with some particular
difficulties or have that particular difficult conversation
so we feel like okay it's the time isn't quite right and that's perfectly natural
so not every single time that there's an aversion there's a turning way doesn't mean that it's bad
and again practice is about learning to discern when is it helpful and when isn't it helpful
but aversion also can be mixed in with a little bit of hostility
and have some ill will that of course is not helpful and it's been more a little bit out of balance
so this kind of a push maybe like a really strong pushing away
so to work with this can we just be with this aversion or ill will without
trying to fix it can we just notice oh yeah that's what's
happening right now i'm aware this is what's happening i'm aware i'm a little bit
out of balance and then sometimes when we're just
bringing awareness some open-hearted awareness we come back into balance
also similar to desire when we're the invitation is to
look really closely at the object and to see is this really going to satisfy our
expectations maybe when there's some aversion maybe to do a little bit of an imagination
how would you feel if you acted out your aversion
your ill will maybe there'd be some regret maybe there'd be some remorse or maybe
there's a sense of oh yeah okay the wise thing to do here
is not to get tangled up with that but to come back here to center
so to just check in and to use our imagination
about a it's the objects as well as be how we feel and just to notice also
how does it feel to have a version there's often a real sense of tightness
and constriction and a sense of
maybe collapsing or it's not it's the opposite of open and
spacious and then also we don't want to have
aversion towards a version because that just perpetuates a version so
is there a way and that we can just recognize and allow ah yes here's a version
i'm a little bit off balance here because i have some aversion
so that's one way that kind of this leaning maybe that literally or metaphorically
might be one way we're a little bit out of balance but another way it might be kind of like energetically
that is there might be this like a lot of restlessness there might be a sense of we want to
jump up and run away or maybe there's a sense of
ping-pong balls inside that are bouncing around so this agitation or maybe a real
scatteredness in the mind can't really settle anywhere
where there are also this kind of there can be a really subtle way
in which the mind is like quietly searching for something more interesting
so rather than kind of like landing on the object like the breath
instead there's this kind of like this probing this looking this looking for
what's next what's next maybe a type of foraging or something like this
it can be a really subtle type of
restlessness which maybe it feels i don't know if i would use the word out of balance
because it's very subtle but it is out of balance when you compare it to
the experience of just really being here like completely here with
our experience and so when we have this restlessness we
might again use our imagination to work within
one thing that sometimes i like to do is to imagine stepping into a cathedral
i was in rome
this is now quite some a long time ago but i remember that sense of awe
of stepping into this magnificent cathedral these really
high ceilings and the just the sense of space so it's not that the restlessness
has to go away but now that same energetic feeling but in a
big space it's a way that kind of like is a sense
of calming can be a sense of settling like there's
room for the restlessness to be
so that's one way to work with restlessness another way it
might be to kind of like zoom in and how does it feel in the body and to just really get
curious about the the jaggedy feeling that goes with the restlessness
and then of course energetics the opposite of restlessness is a sense of
dullness in the mind and the body a sense of maybe collapsed energy
sense of just not enough energy and maybe conflict literally or figuratively
collapsing not enough energy to sit up not enough energy to really be
with the objects but instead just kind of a foggy
detached way so this like maybe so maybe there might
like an absence of vitality as a way to describe it
and it might show up in our mind is just kind of retreating a little bit
from what we're wanting to pay attention to rather than arousing just enough energy
to pay attention and when we find ourselves in this i
might call it sloth and torpor we find ourselves with this we might
investigate what's underlying it often there's there's been a
not quite paying attention that there's been some discontent a little bit of aversion
some boredom which is also a little bit of a version
maybe there's also just some physical tiredness from the body not being have enough
sleep or maybe sometimes there might be some of this shutting down or lack of vitality
when there's some really difficult emotions that we don't quite feel ready or capable
to be with and so there can be this collapsing
so we can really simplify our practice without having to use exclusively kind of thinking about
it but to use imagery and use experiences in the body to be aware and stay balanced
and we might use this idea of balance and our posture as a way to point when we're a
little bit off balance and we can discover ways to come back
into balance but first is to just recognize oh yeah i'm leaning
or i'm bouncing or i'm collapsing i kind of like use the kinesthetic
somatic experience as a way to point to when we're a little bit out of
balance and of course the more we are in balance
the more we can respond appropriately not only to what's actually happening to us
but what's happening to others so that we may be able to support others and
help them so in this way our practice can be a
benefit not only for ourselves but for others thank you