so continuing these
talks on anapanasati
mindfulness of breathing
um
we've entered into the domain
of mental activity and the
pali word is
chitta sankara so it's
usually translated as mind and sankara
is formations or calling it to this week
activities of the mind
and so
it turns out that the mind is not the
container
for activities or the organ for
activities like
the brain that's maybe the organ for
you know what many of us the modern
world think of as mental activities
the cheetah is itself an activity
or it's the sum total of all the
activities
of the of what we might call the mind
it's the um or the cheetah is
all the activities of the mind as we
experience them
as we can know them
and so this idea that the mind itself is
an activity
is an encouragement not to take the mind
as a particular thing
not to kind of reify it or
treat it as a almost like a foreign
object
but rather all we have as human beings
really in the in the buddhist point of
view
is the activities that
are all operating together
to to make make us alive is when the
activities of life
are no longer here that we're no longer
alive
and one of those activities is the
activities of the mind
the mental activities and to start
becoming aware
of the mind appreciating it
uh is the task now in the middle stages
of anapanasati and it's very important
to appreciate it that it's um
it's uh it's kind of in the middle here
so that there's been a lot of emphasis
on breathing for sure
embodied breathing and but also being
rooted in the body
really feeling the whole body and then
also starting feeling a real sense of
well-being
a contentment in the body joy in the
body
and and spreading that contentment
throughout the body
and so there's a movement towards
becoming whole
or the classic language is becoming
unified
where everything's included and
and and so as we move through panasati
it's not so much that we're now starting
to
emphasize more the mind but
we're opening up wider and wider to more
and more inclusive
of this whole but if we're very s
quiet and still centered and in the body
the body begins to because it's taken
care of so well
because it's no longer a challenging
place to be
in deeper meditation that
the body begins to recede from
the central focus of awareness the
breathing tends to change its quality
and it's fascinating to watch as we go
through meditation
the different stages that breathing will
take and sometimes breathing will go
very quiet and subtle and still
sometimes it's so quiet the breathing it
seems like we've stopped breathing
the first time that happened to me in
meditation i was very
content and a lot of well-being and just
sitting there very still
and nope no trouble at all and then a
note i noticed i hadn't breathed for a
while
and i immediately gasped for breath with
fear
and i had this thought i'm going to die
and um
but you know there was no danger of that
to just that i'd never
you know you're not you're supposed to
be breathing all the time
and uh so this idea that the breathing
had seemingly seemingly stopped
was you know a little bit jarring for me
and then eventually i learned that
it seems like there's plenty enough
oxygen getting into the bloodstream
some way or other even when seemingly
the experience of breathing has gotten
so still that it's kind of stopped
and so the body and the breathing
sometimes recede
and so then this sense of wholeness and
inclusion
begins to include the mental activity
the mind itself
and and one of the things we begin
appreciating in this path this journey
is at some point it's possible to
understand
that the body itself
not the physical body but the body that
we
experience how we experience the body
is a byproduct or contingent upon
the mental activities we have so
if the mind is
really quiet and still
the construction of the body the the
making of the body experiences
and interpreting the body and focusing
the body begins to
recede as well and the experienced body
begins to become more porous
more transparent more translucent
until it also sometimes kind of
disappears
so this activity of the mind is part of
this
his incense all in
some forms of buddhism they say them
it's all we have
all there is consciousness is all there
is they're saying
but i don't think that the buddha would
say that
but he would say that most of what we
experience the
experience of life is very much
conditioned and affected
by the quality and the activity and the
of the mind itself of this cheetah so
this cheetah activity the activity of
the mind
is actually a very important part of our
hugely important part of our life
and it's how we construct ourselves
construct our world in the way that we
live in it and experience it
so to start becoming aware not of this
complicated idea that we're
constructing our own experience in some
way we're influencing it
greatly but to begin appreciating that
as the
that we can it's actually possible to
quiet the mind
still the mind soften the mind
not so much by necessarily doing it too
intentionally
but it tends to happen as we start
getting more settled and unified
less in conflict with things thus in
conflict with the mind or the heart or
the world
and there's kind of a less being for and
against things
the mind tends to become quieter
and the activity slows down and
and but slowing down doesn't mean it
doesn't mean we could be
we become slow-witted um it
it's like i said the last few days um
the mind actually
operates so much better clear more
creatively more intelligently more
wisely
when the less active energy or less
applied energy goes into our thinking
into the mental activity and the mental
activity is kind of like it's
begins coasting or it comes into a
harmony
where there's no resistance to anything
there's no
and so it just kind of begins to operate
in a very
harmonious deep way and almost
effortlessly
so this movement of quieting the mental
activity
so part of this is then to
recognize what it feels like
the mental activity the experience of it
and and that's how we can start becoming
aware
of how energetic it is how tense it is
how much pressure there's in it
contraction how much resistance there is
how much
agitation there is in the mental
activity
and then to hold that in awareness
breathe with that just be aware of that
and then when it's easy to relax
calm the mental activities not to do
that
too much not to make it a big project in
fact
the bigger project than calming the
mental activities
is just to get to know it step seven
we can't under i can't underestimate how
important it is for people who do the
pasta practice
to really just learn the art of just
knowing the experience
really well and knowing how to be with
it
without being for and against it without
being actively engaged
trying to do something with it and when
that's learned well
then it's a really good time to
actively quiet and soften the mind
the mental activity to let go of our
thoughts
to let go of our preoccupations too
and but not to do it because we have to
but because it's wise to do it not that
and not do it because we're expecting to
be successful
but just because you know
we're quiet and peaceful and calm enough
that why not
why not let the mind become even stiller
and quieter
and so appreciating the mind
as an activity activities
and and relaxing and calming it
and then also beginning to appreciate
and recognize
the ways in which the mental activity
has become calm
has become quieter and that's a relative
degree
if you're super agitated it's really
good
to appreciate that you've now you're
half agitated
and before you're 100 agitated rather
than feeling upset about the 50
agitation celebrate it
any movement in the right direction in
meditation
just be celebrated rather than to be
give yourself more material for why
you're not far enough along and
not doing better
and but then to appreciate the calmness
of the mind the tranquility of the mind
and for the buddha tranquility
begets tranquility extreme quick
tranquility you
actually use the word food tranquility
is the food or the nourishment
for more tranquility so as we
relax calm the mind as the mind becomes
calmer
nourish yourself with that calm
take it in enjoy it
let it spread let it let it be more part
of who you are
and appreciate it i've had situations
where i got calm enough
but the authority of my thoughts and my
things i my sense of responsibility were
strong enough
that i felt like i had to think about
things and not sit and appreciate the
calm
but tranquility is the food
for more tranquility so you're allowed
to
take in that food you're allowed to be
nourished by it
when it's there when it comes
so step seven is breathing in
one experiences mental activity
breathing out one experiences mental
activity
step eight is breathing in
one calms the mental activity
breathing out one calms the mental
activity
and so i hope that you enjoy that
and and also i hope that you don't set
up
an excited mind in opposition to a calm
mind
because there are times in life where
it's quite wonderful to be excited and
engaged in things
and and um and to be able to be fluid
and relaxed and
fluid and just going back and forth
between happily excited minds and
and happily combines is one of the joys
of practice
so enjoy your day thank you