so hello and welcome to happy hour
wherever you are on this planet of ours in whatever condition in this moment
for your body for your heart for your mind
so for today's practice the theme i'd like to invite us to explore together
is the theme of um practicing compassion practicing care
holding suffering with love both giving and receiving
happy everywhere in the past we have explored many times we have explored giving and
receiving of meta loving kindness friendliness where we share our good will and care for
people we care about and we also receive from others
we receive or for ourselves the sense of goodness
good wishes friendliness well-being kindness care so many different
translations of the word metta similarly there is the practice of
compassion which is very similar to meta but met when met metta
holds suffering when meta meets suffering and friendliness kindness holds
suffering it gets expressed as compassion so [Music]
many many times in your life i have no doubt i have no doubt that you
have been there for someone for some being maybe a child maybe a pet an adult a
friend who has been in a challenging situation
either physically maybe they've been hurt or emotionally they were going through a hard time and you were
you were there for them maybe it was just simply holding presents and listening
just making them not feel alone in the world
and i also fully trust that each of us each of us in our humanity
have had times where something someone has been there for us
has supported us it's given us inspiration support care
maybe with just their presence being there could have been a teacher a coach a parent a relative
a friend or sometimes a stranger just being there for us supporting us
so this idea of giving and receiving giving compassion holding others in
compassion when we have the resources when we have the
stability of mind and heart to support others through a rough time
whatever it might be and many other times in our lives when
we are in need when we appreciate a holding hand a supportive ear a patient ear to listen
to us maybe a friend on the phone just listening just letting us share
being there for us feeling cared for so we have both received compassion
care where we have been suffering and our suffering has been met with kindness by another
by patience by listening by presence and when somebody else is
suffering we have held we have met it with our kindness with our patience just with our presence
so in this practice today we will bring we'll bring we'll tap
into this felt sense memory in our body of
just one time doesn't have to be a whole panoply of of situations just
one situation is enough if you want to bring more you're welcome
to where someone has been there for us
when we're suffering and also tapping into this felt memory
felt sense of the memory of when we've been there for someone else giving compassion even if we didn't
think much of it like oh yeah it's not that big of it it's like but yeah it's like this giving compassion is very simple
maybe it's just being on the phone with someone with a friend who's going through a hard time being
there for them just as simply as that as helen keller
says to sweeten someone's pain your life is not in vain
to sweeten someone's pain your life is not in vain
so let's practice together i'd like to invite you
to land to land in your body
as always we start with
this body
this moment this breath just connecting right here right now
relaxing the body [Music]
landing in this moment
each breath
calming soothing the entirety of the in-breath
the entirety of the out-breath
with each breath landing into the body more feeling the contact points
to feed the sit bones with the earth the cushion
hands on your lap the contact points
feeling embodied more and more with each breath
here just here
the moment of refuge just this breath
my
another minute or two just to arrive just to tell the soil
of the mind to be settled here available present
to plant the seeds of our practice
and i'd like to invite you
to bring to mind a time maybe in the recent time even the past
days weeks maybe today maybe yesterday maybe some
time ago a time in your life whatever memory is most easily
accessible of a time when someone offered you
compassionate presence care warmth when you were having a hard time
when you're having some kind of difficulty
maybe it was physical illness you're having a hard time
let compassion be cared for you are having a difficulty
in any area of your life
he listened to you maybe or in any way in any way you felt
supported in any way you felt that your suffering
your challenge your pain your anguish
your sadness was met with care you felt cared for
you felt cared for you felt seen
held
let yourself feel that felt sense memory in your body
of being held in compassion
held in care
you may not give it the name compassion met with care when you're having a hard
time is enough
letting yourself be held receiving the care
to meet suffering
in your body what does it feel like in your heart and your mind
receiving the soothing salve of care
the soothing self
healing nourishing supporting the hurt
now i'd like to invite you
to bow to this being this person [Music]
and bring to mind the situation the recent times when
someone else can it could be recent or sometime in the past
the failed sense memory is accessible when someone some being
suffering physically emotionally and you were there for them
bringing up the scenario not just in your head in your thoughts but in your found sense of your body what does it
feel to care to care for someone who's going through a challenging time
offering them your love your tension your time
your help
your compassion
any names you want to give it
the rose is sweet by any name
feeling speeding this person's sorrow suffering the hurt
ah does it feel like does it felt did it feel like
is there a sweetness
to be there for them to connect with them
serve them be available for them
is there a sweetness supporting them through the sorrow
is there sweetness in expressing your love your care
for this being connecting with your care with your love
is your affection for this being
really in touch with your care with your love for them
and holding their sorrow not turning away from it but holding it with love and care
letting them have their tears
not pushing it away but being there
present
not falling in with overwhelm but just present with love
with support
now bowing bowing to this image to this
person i'd like to invite you to bring
a case of something you're having difficulty with
very recently
maybe it's in your life right now something that's challenging
which you may or may not have received support with and it could be something the first thing that you brought up earlier it's
okay to go back to it or if previously you chose something from
long ago now something very alive very recent
something that's challenging for you right now in your life in your body and your heart
imagining someone a being could be someone in your life living
passed away
image of a buddha a being of light
a friend whatever works for you
holding presents for you holding you with love and care
they see you they understand hold you
all the suffering with you making it lighter
feeling support supported and held
there could be multiple people multiple beings
your friend benefactor and the buddha all of them holding you
the whole sangha
c
now what if this receiving of love and care
with this challenge awakens awakens your love and care your compassion
even more as you receive it from others
you realize you have more to give it's a giving and receiving
you have so much stability and goodness
to give care to serve others
and now bringing to mind a case of someone who's going through a hard time
in your life again it could be the second scenario that you brought up but something very recent
happening now you might have already been there for
them phone call presence care or just in your mind's heart
in your mind's eye imagining being with them and offering them your care your support
they're not alone you care for them
may their suffering be eased be soothed
if it's helpful for you you can summon being the being of light
with a buddha or any other compassionate being to join you in
holding in your imagination holding this dear being
and their sufferings are with compassion loving care
may you have peace
may your sorrow be eased
if your mind at any point gets distracted bringing the image of your dear person dear being
in your mind's eye more refreshed more bright connecting with them than their
challenge and your care your love for them
may you be free from the sorrow you have peace dear one
may there be ease with you meeting this
difficulty
and for the last moments minutes of this practice period
sing both you and your dear being or beings that you
brought in throughout this practice period
giving and receiving all of you held in love and compassion
all human all beings animals too we have suffering we have bodies
these lives on this earth especially being human as we cognize it
as ups and downs we all suffer at times and we all
support each other have love and care for each other suffering
appreciating that giving and receiving circle of compassion
giving and receiving never too proud
to receive together
there's always something available to get even if we're suffering ourselves it
turns out
share love and care for others who are too having challenges giving and receiving
this beautiful beautiful wholesome
virtues virtue cycle virtuous circle
giving and receiving compassion care love may all beings including ourselves
have ease may all beings including ourselves
be free
[Music]
thank you thanks everyone for your practice
so i'm going to change
the chat settings you're welcome to share in chat if publicly i'll read your name and the
reflection if just sent to me alone i'll only read
the reflection not your name or you can raise your hand what was this like for you
what did you discover in this practice
of giving and receiving what was surprising what showed up what
was difficult anything is welcome and your
reflections know that your insights serve the community serve all practitioners
also thank you to those on the youtube practicing your appreciations coming on youtube
thank you all so
as i wait yes so one reflection sometimes when people didn't show
compassion to me those situations came to mind so i offered forgiveness beautiful
beautiful yeah beautiful
i love reading how wisely you adapted this practice for
yourself to go in a wholesome direction of offering forgiveness
beautiful thank you for that insight another reflection a lot of sukkah
came up but it somehow felt okay to admit to it
i am encouraged enough that it left me and i later felt peaceful and kind
ah nice mary um just making sure did i read that okay
so you meant sukkah not dukkha right a lot of sukkah came up but it somehow felt okay
oh dukkha you meant dukkha that was a misspelling okay just to be okay so i'll reread it because
the second phrase didn't make sense okay great all right we'll bow to that i'll read it
again a lot of dukkha came up but it somehow felt okay to admit it
great great beautiful of course of course it's a part of compassion
to admit to to allow the tuka to be not to push it away beautiful and then the second part i'm
encouraged though that it left me and i later felt
peaceful and kind beautiful and by turning towards it
actually more peace and kindness can open up by acknowledging it yeah thank you for
that reflection yes please stand oops
wait i'm having computer difficulty here we go sam please um
yeah i've just been feeling a lot of stress today and
maybe i didn't even realize how much stress i was feeling you can tell i was in the meditation
[Music] and then it all kind of just came together
pretty heavily um i'm glad that i was aware of it more aware of it
even though i still feel it you know pretty strongly you know i guess i was kind of wishing
it would just go away of course but but the awareness is good
yeah yeah thanks for the reflection and what i appreciate is when you
brought up this sense of so much stress i think you used the word stress i
stressed you were and you may know that the word dukkha or
suffering is often translated as stress we don't think of stress as dukkha so
i'll paraphrase what you said i didn't realize how much dukkha was present all day until i sat
with the meditation realized wow there's a lot of dukkha present
and it's good to be aware of the dukkha because it's here anyway so might as well meet it with
kindness that's my paraphrase of what you said sam how is that is that okay that's very good thank you great great
thank you thank you so much yeah so
so dear ones let's uh turn to practice in small groups
and uh in small groups of three or four and it will start as always with
15 seconds of silent compassion uh
for each other for ourselves and each other for any suffering any dukkha any stress
that might be here in our lives as we all have and then after that
listening to each other holding space for one another and for yourself holding whatever is
coming up whatever is coming up being for each other so i've created the rooms
and such an important place the rubber meets the road where we can be
present for each other so i'm going to open the rooms now take care of yourself
take care of each other slow down slow down here we go
okay welcome back everyone welcome back
i see so many smiles after the uh groups it's so sweet
so we have a few minutes or any reflections that have come up any
insights from discussing yes please kneel
so this was the lovely practice by the way um one of the things i noticed was that
as the meditation went on and there you know there were sort of like two rounds right
someone taking care of you you taking care of someone and then you know a repeat of that that you know that i really appreciated
the the last taking care of someone right by the time we got to that you know you know all the all the love
and feeling cared for and feeling safe and protected really really sort of you know you know got my compassion
juices flowing if you will i think i think that's the buddha said that somewhere along the line
um you know so yeah it was it was you know it was very interesting how it
encouraged you know you know that you know you know being
grateful for you know for the caring you know and and you know in some sense nurturing
yourself really opened the doors to taking care of others yeah yeah beautiful yeah thank you so we
appreciate you naming that that you notice that oh you're going the back and forth in the
back keeps opening up more into feeling the care and being available to offer more care
to others yeah thank you for noticing that meal that was that was the intention that was
the idea here so yay it worked beautiful thank you god your compassion juices
flowing in quotes love it thank you yeah and rebecca i see
your hand just stop and you have just one minute so yes please if it's brief yes
oops you got muted again try one more time
okay uh okay so you can hear me now nikki yeah um nikki i
i had to say in the group that the oneness and the and the sadness and the
compassion that in new england that we're smelling the smoke from california i don't know about other
parts of the country but it's reaching us um i don't know if you
heard that new england is getting uh smoke from california
so tremendous compassion yeah thank you thank you rebecca yes
it on the uh and neil also mentioned it so i'm gonna mute you because this is feedback um yeah and neil mentioned it
on monday because he couldn't go out to exercise and windows closed and all that so yes thank you thank you for that the
giving and receiving of compassion we support each other through this so
so so jerry says dukkha gives to
authenticity gives to authenticity i think there is more there
jerry but since it's already seven we'll leave the expansion of the unpacking
that unless you want to quickly type and chat so like to thank you all i'd like to thank
you all for practicing coming to happy hour being part of the sangha and practicing for your own
benefit and benefit of all beings may all beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you