so formal hello formal hello to all of you and welcome to all the first timers at
happy hour lovely that you're joining this this wonderful sangha um happy to have you so warm welcome
so and just so you know this is this goes on youtube from zoom
but it is private only my image and my name uh gets um
shows on zoom and everybody else's does not because uh and i only see some of you on a tiny
strip on top but you can put yourself each other on gallery view if you wanted to see each other it doesn't
have to be just the the big image of me but just to explain that for the first timers
that on youtube only i show up not you just in terms of privacy
so you know this anyway so so for the theme for today's uh
practice um i wanted to again this is a big topic but just to
take a little bite out of it tonight and a little bite out of the topic of
comparison comparison the comparing mind comparing ourselves
and comparing can come up so easily so easily especially in this
world with um social media you know you might be on social media to
share something or or news and then soon you'll be seeing
other people's vacations and this and that and it's like oh oh the sense of comparison comes up and
wanting and or or other success or good fortune etc
so comparison not just on on social media but there's so many ways comparison come up and
again this is a big topic but we'll take a little bite of it tonight
and one thing i want to invite and so many ways to work with the comparing mind what we call in
buddhism the comparing mind it just it just compares it just compares compares compares
um one quote i like to share and i don't know who said this um is
um i think it's just attributed to anonymous is don't compare your insides
to somebody's outsides don't compare compare your insides to another person's
outside so you only see an image externally of of what is happening whereas you're
comparing your ones here you know the comp you know we're all human we're all human
so with that in mind one of the antidotes again there are many many ways
both through meta practices hard practices as well as wisdom practices because really
this comparison is an aspect of what's called a mana
conceit and that's a big topic that we can talk about in the wisdom tradition but for now
the one way the invitation is to work with this and and actually beautiful practice when
comparison comes up is to turn actually to turn to the goodness
to the goodness in our heart in our lives in our own cultivation because when
comparison comes up the mind narrows it becomes really really tight
and it only concentrates on what it does not have on what it idealizes what it wants and
it does not have instead of seeing all the goodness that
is already available and without actually really seeing the perspective of interconnection
and and all the causes and conditions of our lives other people's lives etc
etc so it becomes it has a single vision
which is very tight and it's not even accurate so through bringing up gratitude we
actually expand that vision we expand that vision and then our heart in fact can become
available to wish the other person well and may you be well may you
shine in your goodness may you be happy on your vacation and your success and you give to the world as i give to
the right may we all play our parts in this world we all have
a different part to play but that expansion of vision can become
possible through the practice of gratitude one of the avenues okay i've spoken
enough this is the framing let's begin
so i invite you to settle to arrive to arrive on your cushion to arrive in
your body
to land
to land in this body in this moment
turning turning our gaze inward
to the goodness that's available in this moment
this body this amazing miraculous body
sitting lying down or standing
functioning
breathing
appreciating the miracle that is this breath
naturally effortlessly
this body breathing itself
with each in-breath allowing more
life more liveliness to be breathed in
to this body each amazing miraculous cell of this body
and with each out breath each extended exhale
softening relaxing the body
arriving more fully in the present moment
spend the first few minutes just landing
arriving
allowing the breath to be breathed into the
belly lower abdomen
full fullness of the breath
helping settle and arrive connected to the earth
landing landing fully wholeheartedly
with the entire body
inhabiting
the fullness of your life
in this present moment so if you're filling your body sell
myself arriving here now
just as the buddha touched the earth
this earth is my witness
i belong here i am here
in this body
in this moment with this breath
feeling the expansion expansiveness
the fullness
of being being here now
quite a gift what a tremendous gift
to be able to sit in this moment
and be breathed
in this amazing show [Music] this amazing
incredible show called their life
to sit in this moment and receive this gift
this gift of the body
healthy enough to breathe healthy enough to sit
to lie down to cognize
to be alive to have consciousness agency
to have the gift
of sangha
people we practice with teachings support that
inspires us
to goodness kindness peace freedom what a gift all of this
gratitude for having a roof over her
head safety from the elements
for this body having been nourished with food
sustenance
the goodness the wholesomeness
the availability
gratitude for the connections
for the people in our life maybe bring
a few of them to mind
people near and dear to you maybe you start with a couple
people who make life richer interaction with them
maybe bring to mind some benefactors
who have supported you
they could still be alive or if it doesn't bring up grief any longer they may not be alive
people you're grateful for grateful too
for their support their love
your heart sings when you think of them
maybe if you like bringing to mind one opportunity for engagement you've
had or have whether it's volunteering
work friendship
community let yourself feel appreciate
let your heart bask in the goodness
this goodness
and as i hear the sirens and so probably can you
to integrate it with our practice
challenges accidents can happen to anyone at any time none of us are immune
to wish well for the being
or isn't that ambulance
ambulances and that in this moment
for this moment could be impermanent as everything else but we have the good
fortune
to be sitting and practicing not in distress
such good fortune we take normalcy for granted often
only when
we get bad news or when the difficulty only then we appreciate
what we considered the boring normal when we considered on what was lacking
what isn't good enough instead of all the goodness
all the bounty of this moment of our life
turning our mind intentionally
not to what's lacking if we focus on that the list can be infinite
but to what is here what is good this list too is infinite
is infinite
choosing to celebrate
the bounty the incredible blessings
that have carried us to this moment
breathing letting yourself be breathed
heart full with all the goodness
breathing hearing touching feeling
fully well knowing
that money fame success etc etc
do not bring lasting happiness
aspiring to goodness we aspire
for excess may we aspire for goodness
for kindness
for peace for ease for freedom
for the gifts can that can never be taken away from us
cultivation of our heart and mind
not things
gratitude appreciation
for the opportunity
to cultivate our heart to mind and service and goodness
shining our hearts our goodness sharing with the world
contributing to life the only way
in the only ways that we can uniquely qualify
with our loved ones our connections
appreciating sharing metta for the gifts of all
beings everywhere letting them shine their light their
goodness their happiness as we shine ours
each light unique not even stepping into the arena of
comparison
celebrating each light
lighting up the world
and as we bring this practice period to a close to sit
sharing the goodness of our practice
our goodness with all beings everywhere letting our light shine
trusting there is goodness may all beings be happy may all beings be free
including ourselves
thank you all thank you for your practice
so so many ways so many aspects to this practice and maybe next
week we'll cover more aspects but for now we have opportunity
for reflections so i change the chat and if you type
your reflections to everyone i'll read your name and if you just type them to
me you'll be private i will um only read the reflection not your
name and you're also welcome to raise your zoom hand to unmute to be unmuted
to share your reflection what did you discover what was this like for you
what was challenging what was easy what did you learn
the benefit of the sangha and if you raise your physical hand i may not see you
but please if you raise your zoom hand that way i will ask you
thank you bill for your reflection felt calm and joyful thank you so much and thank you so much
bill calm and joyful that's lovely
joyful hence happy hour
especially if you're new we'd love to hear from you if you wish to share don't feel you're on the spot but you
can raise your zoom hand if you wish the zoom hand is either
under reactions and let's see somebody's trying to raise
their hand but it's the clap let's see uh it's next to ray's hand is next to the clap try that
again
ah now i have the thumbs up i still don't know who it is oh here genie here i figured out who it is okay
there you go what i realized again and like to be
reminded of is how the ordinary things of every day
get glossed over by me and i don't feel grateful for them but it was nice
to be reminded again that you know simple things like running water and
you know um food and roof over my head and you know those things that are so
important to my happiness and well-being that you know i sometimes take for granted
yeah thank you janie thank you so much for your reflection i appreciate you brought in running
water i heard this uh perspectives on kqed the other day i don't know if you heard this also
someone who's talking about if you go camping and backpacking and you pump the water yourself from the
stream through a pump and every ounce of water is so precious and and if you accidentally knock over
a camping container that you've just pumped oh you have to do it all over again and use the water that you've
cooked with to clean with etc etc and then you come home and you turn on the faucet and it's like
oh a miracle a miracle so just so i've been
appreciating the miracle of opening my faucet every day ever since i i heard this it's just so much we take
for granted so much we take for granted yeah thank you genie for your reflection
other reflections please other and jerry says i agree thanks genie you
do not know what you have often until it is gone yes yeah exactly and i'll say one thing one
version of this meditation i sometimes do is to imagine that something you have like
your leg is you know for example is you you've been in an accident um but this meditation was already
pretty full so maybe i'll try that next week but yes so co please
yes um it's uh not only do we take things usually for
granted but um uh when we when we
stay informed about what's going on in other parts of the world like indonesia having all their
hospitals overrun with cloven patients and or you drive on the freeway into
berkeley and you see all the homeless encampments etc
it's all the more valuable that we don't take for granted anything that
that we have we who are fortunate enough to have a roof over our heads and um um
so it's a very powerful thing to not take things for granted yeah yeah absolutely yeah thank you co
and especially one thing i always wanted to add to this practice is that when we do this
practice of gratitude is and we fill our hearts with goodness
it is so that we actually not that we just turn away from all the
challenges in the world and say oh okay i have it all well and nobody else is but it actually
allows us and we know this but i also i do want to bring it into the space
that it it brings a more generosity into our hearts brings more generosity for us to serve
to be available to share with others so as part of this practice of course we
know this already but wanted to bring this to the to the room thank you ko thank you so much
yeah in the other quick reflections please before we go into our
small group practice
one reflection comes in hearing the sirens the sound of the fan in my house
rising and falling coming and going yeah
yeah so how about we save some time on the other side of
the small groups for more reflections and we turn now to practicing in small
groups in community so in this time we turn
to small groups of size three or four and we start with 15 seconds of meta
silent meta for one another for the small group that you find yourself in and
then [Music] sharing as much or as little as you like
with your sangha with this small group about your practice as you wish and it's just
six minutes it's very short and then we come back and we'll have a little bit of time for reflections
so it's such a precious time to to connect with other practitioners so
here we go and the rooms are open enjoy hello everyone welcome back welcome back
it's lovely to be with you again uh in the in the large group
so we have a few minutes for any reflections that have come up from
practicing in small groups i see a lot of smiles i see a lot of smiles that weren't here before
so especially if you haven't shared yet i'd love to hear whatever you'd like to share for the
benefit of the song questions comments what didn't work what worked
neil please so you know when you said you know
you're sharing the same earth that the buddha walked on you know that was that like set
up the whole thing for me i got like a shiver running through me somehow it had never occurred to me yeah
he you know it was this earth maybe i breathed some air that he exhaled who knows
i don't know it was i felt deeply connected to the practice to
people and everything it was yeah thank you thank you neil that is so
beautiful i feel shivers down my spine and my heart is is filled with joy now yeah
yep yep there were just a tiny tiny little bit of an exhale of a buddha in
that inhale i love the sense of connection
very sweet thank you neil
any other reflections especially if something came up during your your practice discussions in the small
groups with one another how was that
yes please person on the phone hey this is michael
um so the practice groups as usual are really sweet and um beneficial and full of wisdom
but prior to the sitting i had huge mudita for the person who had
their first tomato i mean that just brought me joy
that they had their first tomato and it also watered my seeds of happiness for my
gardening with awareness practice which i'm so grateful for and then lastly i'm really um
finding it very pleasant the topic of gratitude and deep vows for bringing this up during
happy hour and i am excited to hear about more of your channeling the dharma next
week thank you michael thank you so much for your reflection it it makes me
so happy with this the gratitude and the the mudita the vicarious joy you had
for the person who was here for the first who's here tonight for the first time
and and the the typo that created such joy for you that gives me so much joy
that first tomato somebody had a first tomato somewhere in the world today so thank you michael it just oh that
just nourishes my heart yes so i have so much gratitude so much happiness for
for all of you and let's see let's take one quick last reflection
quick quick of them all am i saying your name right uh it's rimmel but it's fine so i'm the
one with the first tomato and i'm embarrassed for having done that but if it's brought somebody joy that's wonderful
yes no embarrassment here it's it's this brought brought everyone
joy brought me joy how this happened this is happy hour the risk is that i might have typed i
could have typed something much worse i got saved i got saved
thanks to the typo thanks to the autocorrect we're having the chuckle and la this is this is fantastic thank you all
and i have so much gratitude for you for this sangha for happy hour for the
chance for us to come together and practice this is so beautiful this is so beautiful thank you
all for your practice may all beings be well may all beings be happy including
ourselves thank you