hello everyone and welcome
and um this week for the
these these meditation sessions i'm offering you a little exercise that
you can include as part of your meditation that corresponds to the later teaching
uh the fourth foundation of mindfulness and
so there's five of five of them five exercises there so giving a little taste
of it perhaps for each day and um
and so yesterday and the idea was to notice desires operating
whenever you were distracted by thoughts today
whenever you get distracted and whenever you get
concerned with something uh even if it's happening in the present moment that you somehow
interrupt the flow of your ongoing contact with
the present moment as it unfolds as it develops now if you start having thinking about
or commentary about what's happening in all these regards distracted thoughts
commentary being stuck on certain emotions perhaps
you know the basic mindfulness practice is to have clear recognition of that clear
mindfulness hold that in awareness without making it a problem without
being critical of it if anything to be kind and just be aware clearly aware that
it's there and then once you've recognized it well enough if it's no longer compelling or strong
you can come back and continue with your breathing today's exercise is that uh
has to do with the idea that one of the primary
catalysts for losing our connection to the present moment
his concern with me myself and mine what we call sometimes selfing
we take things and define the define ourselves by them or define them as my thing or and um
and even something as simple as saying my pain is different than saying the pain
and there's a little act of selfing a little bit of identification with the pain seemingly innocent word my to it
the thoughts you have chances are that you're one of the characters of it or it somehow concerns you
and so they recognize the self-concern that's there and so the word you could use if you'd
like is selfing there's selfing and to please do that without any
condemnation or criticism or disappointment it's an all too human phenomena that
human minds will identify make self construct selves
appropriate things for themselves assume that things are mine all these kinds of things that we do and
sometimes it's kind of innocent but it also is the foundation for all kinds of uh
ways in which we end up suffering end up challenged
in this life so it's a helpful thing to see to recognize it when it happens so when you say if you do the word
selfing or i or my or me or something it's a little little uh
no to recognize that it's happening i do so kindly do so caringly like you care for
yourself or an alternative to that is to be slightly amused there it is again wow
and and it might be very interesting for you to kind of recognize
all the ways and the many ways and the frequency in which um the things that distract you from the breath from the
present moment are somehow related to self me myself and mine
and if this doesn't make so much sense for you you're welcome just ignore it but uh it might be interesting exercise
so assuming a meditation posture
and lowering your gaze to have relaxed eyes
not really focusing on anything in particular soft soft eyes
and gently closing your eyes
and then taking a few long slow deep breaths
as if you have all the time in the world to leisurely breathe deeply and
appreciate each breath each inhaled each exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal
and noticing the rhythm of the body's
breathing in and breathing out
and wherever in your body you most clearly experience that rhythm
let your attention let yourself familiarize yourself with those
sensations that experience
and then to as you exhale to relax maybe relax the muscles of the
face
relax the shoulders
relax the belly
relax your butt and your legs
so they settle into your sitting place
and then settling into the body's experience of breathing again with a simple rhythm of breathing
and the idea is to be as simple as possible
not using the experience of breathing to reinforce ideas of self
just a simple experience of the rhythm of breathing in and out
a rhythm you share with all breathing creatures
that's been going on for millions of years breathing in and breathing out
and will continue long after you're gone and now you're participating in this
shared common experience of breathing in and breathing out
center yourself when you're breathing and if you get distracted or caught up
in something notice what how that might be related to
self-concern self-referencing
and then kindly gently recognize it as selfing
and then begin again with your breathing
if you recognize selfing see if you can recognize it with a light
touch not making it a big deal and in doing so perhaps experience
a teeny bit of freedom from the ongoing selfing
just through recognizing it and stepping back holding it lightly and
then beginning again with your breathing
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps to recognize that
the human all to human
concern with self with oneself
is quite common normal in many ways
but also it's the seat it's the source for a tremendous amount of confusion and
desires and aversions and pain
hurt and suffering for many people so the self is a
is a complicated difficult topic
sometimes with self-criticism sometimes with kind of selfish
self-assertion which leads to frustration and difficulties
to recognize the tremendous amount of suffering that there exists in this world because of
how people are caught up in conceit and
identification and to end this sitting
appreciating the challenges that this brings to people
and to maybe allow yourself to feel care and
compassion for the challenges and difficulties that people have and
and to wish them well to wish all of us
success in finding a way through
beyond our the suffering based on self and selfing conceit
may all beings be happy
without needing to reinforce or build up the self
may all beings be safe
without needing to defend protect or let get hurt
the concepts ideas they have of who they are may all beings
be peaceful free of self-preoccupation
and may all beings be free free of the stickiness the traps
that are set with the self-concern self-preoccupation
and may we support all beings to be free from the suffering of
self-selfing by overcoming some of our own attachment
to this area may all beings be happy
and free
[Music]
so today i continue the discussion about the fourth foundation of mindfulness
and there are five different areas to attend to in this in this foundation
yesterday i talked about the the hindrances the five hindrances today
will be the what's called the five aggregates tomorrow the
six cent stores then the seven factors of awakening and then the four noble truths
so all these wonderful lists and um there's a progression through them and
the progression from yesterday is that the hindrances are we think of them as kind of the
what keeps us distracted in the world of desires and aversions
in our relationship to pleasure and pain and
things of the world the alternative word for essential pleasure the first one that pierce
nesutas is another same list but with the word instead of sensual pleasures is
avariciousness so wanting to acquire especially things of other people or acquire things
and so it has a lot to do with our relationship to things and desires and pleasures and
kind of you think of it a little bit that you know kind of what the self can get what the self cannot get what the self wants and
doesn't want when that kind of desire settles down in quiets
then we're more present for ourselves we then at some point encounter the next layer
of attachment list layer of this of preoccupation that interferes with the deeper settling
into peace and that has to do around me myself and mine self-concern
identification where we take different parts of our psychophysical
being and we hold on to that or we assume or
conceive of that as being this is this is mine this is
me and this is my true self and so um something as simple as um
as seemingly innocent as saying you know this is my hand
now i appropriate it as being mine and in some sense it is
but when i say my my hand and then it's associated with me
and maybe maybe i think my hand is the best hand in the world or i'm the worst kind of hand in the world
and so here i am holding it up in front of us your all of you and if i'm attached to
this is my hand then i could be either completely proud of showing it off or
completely miserable that you're seeing this thing that's a mind and so the idea of my hand is can be
innocent but it can come along with a lot of baggage that that baggage is called selfing
um or it could be that um
uh the um you know that rather than uh
it's me the hand is me and so if someone brushes against it in
a hard way they're they're kind of offending me because the hand is me and so we're
taking what's innocent enough like and assuming that this represents me as
a person or i take my hand as being my true self
that's the essence of who i am handness and and so
and i'm ready to argue with anyone or i'm ready to insist that this is my handness it'll protect my hand at all cost i don't want
it to die or get old and because that's essentially who i am so maybe that's a silly a silly example
but i'm hoping that you can uh apply this to yourself
that there's this action of selfing and extreme forms it takes the
world the word the the form of conceit
very strong attachment to self it has lots to do with identification
that cons not identifying who we are if we're you know some simple
way a man a woman neither man or woman trans
gender nor non-conforming all kinds of other options but if um
if we get attack there's a way of kind of leaning into it too much holding onto it
and and clinging and holding tight in such a way that as the veigars of life encounter us
that uh it either challenges that deep attachment or reinforces it and so there's selfing going on
so in the buddha's teaching then the idea is to be sensitive to
the contraction or the stickiness or the
resistance or the pushingness the neediness that seems to be related to this idea of self
and it can be experienced very simply and sometimes as a kind of contraction a tightness
inner pressure it can be experienced as a wanting as a not wanting
it can experiences ideas that we get we swirl around in
and a lot of these selfing does in fact have to do with ideas and concepts we live in
sometimes so deep that we don't even see we're doing them
you know for example if you know you come to a place where
there's chairs and and there's lots of chairs to sit in and lots of empty chairs
and uh maybe you're waiting at the doctor's office or something
and then you have to go to the bathroom so you've been sitting in one chair for a long wait to see the doctor and then
you have to go to the bathroom and you go to the bathroom you come back and lo and behold someone's sitting in the same chair that you're sitting in
and the initial reaction and how could they be sitting in my chair and
and there's identification with the chair and me that might arouse anger that the person sitting in it well there's lots of other
cheers around and so this can happen in all kinds of small ways throughout the day
and so um so to begin being sensitive this movement of selfing that's possible
we're no longer uh you know caught up in in the more coarser
surface desires of wanting and not wanting and the confusion that comes from that the hindrances
and um and they're very interesting what the buddha wants us to do is to recognize in our
simplest forms of experience the five different ways five different kind of foundations for
what he thinks is called constructing a self sometimes it's the body the form
sometimes it's based on our feelings sometimes it's based on our ideas of things our concepts
it's called perceptions in english the third aggregate and sometimes has to do with the stories we make up the
impulses the intentions the motivations the the opinions we have the fourth
aggregate and the fifth one is consciousness the idea that we can be
aware that we can know some people very strongly associate that with a feeling almost of emphasis i am
and of course that's who i am so these are different areas that people sometimes
focus on in the construction of identity in the construction of self in the preoccupation with self
and you might spend do it as an exercise and spend it maybe today
maybe you know if a period of time on each one each of these five aggregates
and see you know how much self-concern is there around your body and what you
look like and bodily pleasure and displeasure and
how much uh preoccupation and selfing is connected to how you feel your feelings
and um you know you're feeling happy or sad all kinds of ways
and how much of preoccupation and selfing self-concerned about my opinions
my history my story my biography my plans
my desires and the whole kind of inner world of of um
you know the world that we construct with our mind and then consciousness
these are the five aggregates so this is where the buddha wants us to look but he wants us to look and see this for a
particular reason not to not to negotiate not to
abandon it not to let go of it even not to make a problem out of it but to see
it clearly and to see it this way to be quiet enough to see that each of these five areas
um in them when we don't we don't we don't we don't cling to them too much or don't
overlay our ideas on it too much or preoccupation can be experienced as something which is
flowing something that's arising and passing something that appears and disappears
something that's very inconstant changing flexing moving
and it's kind of like a river of our life that our being is a river of changing sensations experiences thoughts
emotions and the idea is to relax into that river and um and float or
be massaged by it or settled in and the attachment to self and selfing is like
you know taking some a bucket of that water out and sometimes freezing it and saving it
for the future but it's no longer the river and
so uh so the idea is not so much to you know attack or feel upset about the selfing
that goes on but rather to look more deeply and see
that underneath the self-concern can we notice how it takes us out of the flow of life
the movement of the present moment if the present moment is a river notice how it takes us out by through
retrospective thinking through fantasy through being caught up in this
conversations in our head and and
the um and such things so the five areas
is the body feelings the basic simple concepts ideas that we
live by the fourth one is the stories we live by the more complicated constructions
mental constructions about our lives and motivations and the fifth is consciousness
and you don't necessarily have to remember them all but you might
become sensitive to how much
selfing goes on i think for many people a primary subject of main character much
of their thinking and what fuels their thinking is the self as me myself and mine
we're kind of either center stage or somehow important in the thoughts the concerns we have and just watching the
thought stream and recognizing how much self is in there and selfing and ideas of self is a
fascinating study and and but to do this as this mindfulness
exercise is to try to see it as um as selfing but see it as a
as a as a reification a solidification of the
ongoing river of of life that we live in and in doing so start experiencing some
freedom some independence from those attachment to self
so um thank you and uh i realized this week is
a bit of a you know whirlwind tour of these five different areas for the fourth foundation
and um but maybe you know hopefully it's useful to have a general sense those of you who don't know of this
this very important part of mindfulness practice and maybe some other time we can go in some more depth with each of them
so thank you all very much