so good morning it's good to uh good to be with you just
watching the uh the chat on the side of my screen
yeah welcome welcome to you all
so um
generally i've practiced in a very technique oriented way
and that's been
of profound benefit and uh lean on meditation technique often
and and strikes me that that sometimes
the urge to reach for technique means that greed or aversion has already
taken hold yeah in the background
the urge to find technique sometimes is an expression
of our reticence to meet
the clinging already present
now sometimes technique is the best way of meeting it but
we want to be a little wary i feel
about using technique to defend against the
wildness of our heart and mind
and so i just plant this this seed as how i will proceed to
teach technique but i plant this seed so that we have some some
appreciation of the the subtleties of the movement towards technique yeah
and um
are careful in a way not to recapitulate
the the clinging in our practice yeah
a little subtle but uh just to consider
so um let's uh let's practice
just all at once the awareness can arrive
just affirming your aspirations for practice
summoning some measure of courage actually
it takes a lot of courage
to truly meet the intensity of the human condition
bringing attention to the sensations of
of breathing wherever they're [Music] felt most clearly
wherever that is just rest the attention and simple way there
feeling the uh
some precision when the inhale begins
and
when the exhale begins and ends
the attentional spotlight on your breathing becomes
steadier and brighter
as we settle there's less and less light that escapes
to other phenomena
the breath is illuminated
and everything else is enveloped in darkness
but that's not how it usually is
the throb of worry and concern
of preoccupation and strategizing
all of this wants to share the attentional light
our thinking
is the kind of top
layer of the top geological stratum
but beneath it is affect feeling
the body under conditions of threat
opportunity
and so when the attention moves away
when that light begins to uh leak
away from the sensations of breathing
to see if you can make a perfect piece
with affect with feeling
in some ways the the breath attending to the breathing
this gentle precise way it it's shelter from
the storm but in order to feel like shelter we
need to have made peace with the storm
to attend to the breathing is to release the grip
on the rest of phenomena
to put down covetousness and displeasure with
respect to the world
so thank you it's good to uh
good to see with you
so we'll continue continue with our theme for the week
a group of um [Music] prominent emotion scientists neuroscientists wrote
a wrote a piece recently in a in a journal prominent journal and
um where titled the the rise of affectivism
affect rise of effectivism and what they said was
there was behaviorism which was uh oriented around
conditioning and reinforcement reward punishment
and then a cognitive phase you know where a lot of the attention was around
around memory and attention and perception and now they suggest maybe we're in a
phase in this cognitive science realm of effectiveness
valence emotion empathy mood motivation stress
well-being so the they write um
the behavioral and cognitive sciences have faced perennial challenges of incorporating emotions feelings
motivations moods and other affective processes into models of human behavior in the human
mind such processes have long been marginalized or ignored typically on the
basis that they were irrational unmeasurable or simply unenlightening
however it's become increasingly difficult to deny that these processes are not only linked to well-being
but also shape our behavior and drive key cognitive mechanisms such
as attention learning memory decision making
emotions do not just shape how we interpret the world but also shape which aspects of the world need our attention
and which can be safely ignored emotions are not just about what is
but also about what matters
so so much hinges on feeling
so much hinges on feeling and in this interpersonal
world you know the interpersonal realm that that's been our focus
uh it's so vital that we become deeply acquainted
there are there are of course thoughts and perception and sights and sounds and
tastes and other sensations but um
feeling is the linchpin arjun tsujita says um
all dhammas converge on feeling
all dhammas all in this context all phenomena converge
on feeling and
experience largely becomes meaningful because of feeling
experience becomes meaningful because of feeling
motivation depends on feeling the sense of urgency
depends on feeling and each feeling state
announces a kind of command
do something say something think something
and so we have to develop a kind of wise clear loving
relationship with our feeling life and this is nowhere is this more apparent than in
enjoying and navigating the you know interpersonal realm
so uh evolutionary uh psychiatrist niece says um
emotions are specialized modes of operation shaped by natural selection
to adjust the physiological psychological and behavioral parameters
in ways that increase our capacity and tendency to respond adaptively to
threats and opportunities
and there are there are always threats and opportunities being with others
entails some threat and opportunity
remember that line we started with from lisa feldman barrett that the the best thing for a human nervous
system is another human and the worst thing for a human nervous system is another human
we are navigating subtle or more demonstrable
threat and opportunity and
this means that our feeling life is very prominent yeah in the
interpersonal realm and while emotion is
designed for uh to promote evolutionary fitness that's very different from saying that
it's designed for enlightenment there are some things that yeah we flow
with the stream of our own biological conditioning and other things we go against the
stream and so we uh
we need deep emotional wisdom for to tolerate
the dependence of love the surrender
that i was speaking about yesterday the
the increasing riskiness of entrusting our heart to
another can
torque our mind in a lot of different ways
to open our heart to another entails a willingness and
courage to to grieve all that is precious and dear to me is
of the nature to change
colleague um gisele jones uh defines intimacy as
the ability and willingness to see and be seen the ability and willingness to see and
be seen and
we need profound emotional skill to be
undisguised in our strength and our poverty
wisdom [Music] and equanimity is uh required to fully enjoy pleasure
not to pinch our pleasure because it feels wild
or exposed or somehow
cuts against our notion of restraint
we we often often talk about equanimity with craving
and that's one thing that's vital but what is
equanimity with pleasure itself
it does not mean to squash it it does not mean to not enjoy it and it does not
mean to be worried about getting attached
what what how do we bring this kind of
skill with feeling so as not to
suppress or get entangled
we need wisdom to navigate the the inevitable
challenges and frustrations and disappointments the cycles of um
of idealization of disillusionment of reconnecting to some
[Music] uh warmth
the tolerance of ambivalence ambivalence this kind of uh
one way of thinking about dukkha about suffering is uh it's about ambivalence
we need emotional skill to um
to recognize that the other
can never be [Music] the end of your seeking
other people in our lives can do so much some things that
only another can do and and
uh the other cannot be the end of seeking
wanting in other words is always different from getting
we need emotional skill to be wrong there's so much so much shame about
being wrong and we're wrong so much
sometimes you maybe you know those moments you you kind of know you're wrong maybe you're having a
conversation with somebody important to you and um
and there's like that that subtle little voice of just like yeah i kind of
know i'm wrong right but the prospect of the shame of of kind
of acknowledging it is just too much so we like double down you know even though we know
we're bluffing right just dig in
i was always inspired by something sylvia borstein said when she said like you know when i realize i'm wrong like
i'll just like pull up right out of the moment just mid-sentence and just say
yeah i'm wrong i'm sorry this doesn't feel right
you know it's like you can feel that you're about to like re-double dig back into your emotional
stance and like the courage of just like mid-sentence you know
so wait a second take skill yeah
skill emotional skill we need skill uh
amidst all of these realms of feeling
interpersonal realm
sergeant uh if it's properly cultivated the body
can provide a mooring post it's the ground the stabilizer
it knows how to discharge energy all that push of the mind sends a lot of
energy into the system sometimes you can get quite heated or feel very
heavy tense tight disoriented that's what's happening
uh what's happening is all that that veina and sankaras are
pushing and driving churning up energy the body knows how to discharge the mind
doesn't not by itself this is how you allow the discharge to happen
relax open the palms of the hands open the
soles of the feet relax the jaw
open the temples of the head sockets of the eyes and the forehead
drop your shoulders loosen your belly breathing out
releasing you begin to see that those mental
emotional psychological patterns have a body correlative correlation
and you work on their bodily aspect
it may not give you clear solutions as to why you feel this way what you're going
to do with the rest of your life how you're going to sort out this person
and so forth but it will tell you how to stop suffering
so as we develop
more wisdom patience equanimity around feeling
this is uh also deepens our empathic capacity
that when we resolve bring a higher resolution to our inner
life our inner feeling life
we can perceive in much richer detail the inner life of others
and this of course is helpful too
so i offer this for consideration
yeah thank you so um we'll complete this uh intensive
tomorrow um a day long at nine nine thirty uh
pacific and um yeah well we'll sit and practice and
have some time in silence and sometime for um i'll offer
reflections and we can have some dialogue and um
yeah sort of uh open some of the some of the threads that
began here um and uh
yeah i realize i i'm uh if you you want to volunteer as a
co-host um i might need some help because i can't disable it's too late for a passcode and
i can't disable the chat the uh the waiting room so if you
want to take a shift for an hour or something letting people in from the weight room um just chat me tomorrow morning that's
appreciated and yeah i look forward to to actually
seeing some of you i appreciate the uh the chats i see things going and um will
be nice to see your your faces tomorrow if you join and um yeah thank you phil and uh
for djing in the background and um i wish you a good uh good day