uh welcome everyone my name's in Chan um I'll be here um sitting with you
together and also offer a short Dharma talk and so
um welcome so if this is a daytime or
morning and good day and good morning and where I am in um California
it's evening so good having you
here we're going to just begin with about half an hour of
meditation so if you like to just take a few moments to uh get
situated um find a sitting posture or
find a maybe find a space where you can sit un comfortably for half an hour and
feel free to do so and maybe um some of you might use chairs or some might sit
on the cushion wherever you are just take a um a couple of minutes to um land
in a space where you can feel
comfortable take a few moments to maybe just just um move your
body and to allow yourself to settle into the sitting
Place sometimes you can kind of just pull the shoulder up and let the
shoulder drop or move your
head neck
and momentarily you can settle settle into a more quiet sitting
posture it's helpful to take a few long deep breath at the beginning of the
meditation to allow ourselves to arrive arrive
here maybe as you breathe out sensing and feeling that you're
arriving here
deeply now the lower half of the body to be rooted on the
ground maybe feel some firm connection of the lower half of the
body to the chairs or the floor
and from a rooted Place allow the Torso and
spine to be
uplifted allow this uplifting to be
energetic at the the same time
relaxed soften the muscles and the
face sometimes you can open the jaws and then float it together
to just release any tension around the muscles on the face
around the
neck and quickly scan the whole body from the head to toe to invite some
sense of ease and
relaxation and when you're
ready rest your ATT tension on the breath or in the Body Sensations in the
body
sometimes I imagine this connecting with the breath
and the body as if we're inviting ourselves to come home to this body
this intimate home of our
body maybe there is sense of
safety [Music] warmth and
ease sense of coming home right
here feeling and sensing in into the
breath resting in the movements of the
breath or the changing temperatures as you breathe in and out
coming home to the present
experience
e e
as a home of our being has a door that's wide
open welcoming the the coming and going of all
experiences sound traveling through
you
smell
thoughts all is welcome
Sensations in the
body maybe tinkling on the
feet pulses on the on the legs
a cluster of thoughts make
come s May Linker for a
while before the
leave
e e
momentarily maybe you're sensing the
quietness in your
being e
if your mind wandered away
your home is right
here a moment you notice that you've wandered away you're
already back at home
the home of
awareness
e
e e
sitting here feeling and sensing that a group of us are sitting
together right
now it's as if we're all sitting in a virtual meditation
Hall practicing
well e
maybe knowing this that we're practicing
together you feel a little more
uplifted more energetic
in staying
present
e
e e
this last couple of minutes of Vis
sitting we have a deep inner bowing to
ourselves showing up
practicing showing up of for ourselves and for each other
it's a virtual [Music]
community deep bows maybe an ignor bowing
gesture to each other for showing up for each other
supporting each other practicing
deep bows to
everyone so um what I had in mind to share today
tonight um is that uh I finished a chanting Retreat last
week there was still quite a lot of energy reverberating in me from this
chanting Retreat so I thought I'd share some Reflections on one of things that stood
out for me that is uh taking refuge in the Buddha Dharma and
S and that is often called the triple gam and some of you probably know this
and then probably have done this multiple times
um and I just want to um maybe just chant this a poly chant um um right now
for everyone and maybe share a little reflection about um the sense of a taking refuges
in the Buddha Dharma and S and so the poly chant goes uh like
this [Music]
[Music] and it often times get translated as I
take refuge in the Buddha I take refuge in the
Dharma and I take refuge in the Sana and this um the typical form is to
chant this three times and so on this a chanting retreat
we chanted this um multiple times and taking this refugees are often
down formally in a ceremony when one commits to become um a
Buddhist to walk the Dharma path a teacher May initiate um the
ceremony and chanting this uh refugees taking refugees is part of the ceremony
and for me when I H did this um
ceremony long time ago um it it felt like a turning point in my
life I felt some deep s sense of surrendering to this dap
paath and so nowadays uh in many uh Dharma centers or retreat ret centers in
particular I know in inside Retreat Center our Retreat Center here uh in
Scott Valley California uh usually at the beginning of the retreat and the group would
initiate this whole Retreat process by taking refugees in the Buddha Dharma and
Sanaa together in monastic settings and many
lay Buddhist communities uh take refuge is very often sometimes on daily
basis so what does this really mean taking refuge in the Buddha Dharma and
S it's quite a worth reflecting um for
me I was I was I feel like I'm very fond of the Chinese translation of buddham
gami this p CH in particular uh the Chinese
translation um of s gachami is that of
return and rely and so and the a Chinese uh version
of taking Refuge is something like this and to the to the Buddha I return and
rely to the s to the Dharma I return and
rely and to the sa I return and
rely I like the sense of returning a lot and the Chinese character used uh
for returning um it often relates to the sense of
returning home or coming back you know sometimes when uh someone has
been um staying oversea in some other places when they go back home and and
this is the character that's being used and which is this returning so what does it mean by
returning to the Buddha coming home to the Buddha this
orientation and the sense of returning and to me is that it's it's
not necessarily going out to
somewhere out there but rather it's just turning Inward and
coming back right here somewhere within us the home of this being this
life and so in this way uh there's a sense of
return and rely um is not a pointing to something
of uh worshiping something out
there rather something deeply inside of us uh in the poly um uh recollection
chants and often times in the monasteries there this form of a chantings that um monastics do on very
regular basis called the Recollections there is a um a particular
chant around the recollection of the triple Jam that is one is to remember
and be reminded of and the qualities of the Buddha Dharma and
Sanaa and the um the qualities of the Buddha in this Rec recollection chant
um is that the Buddha is the one who is an
arand who is completely free from great hatred and
delusion and he's someone who's rid of this kind of a forces
completely and totally incapable of great hatred
delusion and another quality that's often being uh remembered or
recollected um is this um term called V
charana Sano that is one whose wisdom and
compassion are in Perfect
Harmony One is wise and
compassionate and another quality and is that the Buddha is the one who trains
those who wish to be trained like us and wish to be
trained and Buddha serves to teach those who wish to be
trained so there's a sense of taking refuge in the Buddha is like returning
home to this kind of qualities finding true true Safety and
Security in this kind of qualities relying on non greed non
hatred a non delution to live our lives instead of relying on I don't know
money status relationships
power you know many things that um we may rely on um are actually quite
unre unreliable um in the the Dharma
teachings and it's really possible through the practice and to cultivate
this kind of qualities as if it's not that the Buddha would not have taught for over 45 years and by wondering all
around in different parts of India um
by foot so uh personally this sense of
taking refuge in the Buddha evokes the sense of surrendering oneself to this
possibility to this possibility to become free from great hatred delusion
and this P possibility to um be wise and
compassionate the possibility of serving oneself and and is serving
others and often times um through it's through cultivation of um mindfulness
concentration uh ethical conducts that this kind of quality began
to become possible um or accessible um within
us and through the teachings of the Buddha and this tools of mindfulness the
tools of uh cultivating concentration the tools of um of abiding
CA um can allow us to um cling
out the stuff that hinder the access to this kind of beautiful
qualities and this leads to maybe the the second Refuge which is a refuge in
and the Dharma returning and relying on the Dharma so what does this mean
returning and relying on the Dharma in the recollection of the triple
GM the Dharma is said to be here and now
always present timeless
inviting investigation and Dharma
leads is leading inward or leading towards
Liberation and Dharma is to be individually experienced by the
wise and so you hear this kind of qualities that describe the Dharma something that's right here and
right now it's present right here it's not found
in kind know long- winded memories or um fantasies in the
future but it's something that we can touch into right here maybe in the
breath we breathe in and breathe out and in the sensations of the body
in the sound that's traveling
through something that's unfolding right here right now in front
of us and it's said to invite
investigation invites us to see pay careful attention to this quite a secret
unfolding of our lives right here
and it's by this form of quite deeply intimate seeing and clear
seeing of the phenomenon that's unfolding in front of
us and liberating insights can
arise the insights into an nature d anata that is
impermanence stress and unsatisfactoriness and not
self this insights can really lead can lead to the freedom of grasping um lead
from lead um us into the freedom from great hatred
delusion and so that's through this returning again and again to the immediacy of our LIF
experience we can begin to see clearly what is going
on as I was reflecting about um what we
usually rely on or return
to you know when we are when we H didn't uh when I didn't start practicing
Dharma and there lots of external things that I'm thinking that I would depend on
or rely on that would make me feel okay I feel safe you know maybe the weather
needs to be good or and the neighborhood needs to be
nice and the shelter is comfortable and somehow one we another family members
are in Harmony and our bodies are healthy enough
um or maybe you know no one is saying anything bad about you or no one is
looking down on you maybe you have a good job lots of those kind of things
and that um one can put a lot of uh
efforts in to try to get them all lined up so that we can feel feel um a sense
of okayness or feel a sense of safety but after we try for some
years maybe many years we begin to see it's pretty difficult
right no matter what we do somehow um maybe they're always someone who's not
particularly happy with what you said what you did um
things are not always coming together
harmoniously so putting a lot of effort on trying to sort out all of this
external uh
relian may not really work out so this taking refuge in the Dharma
is a calling for us to look in a different way not outside but deeply inside of
us also something that happens Here and Now not in the past and not in the
future and I also say that um when we when we uh follow the uh
Buddhist teaching cultivating our mind and heart we don't
do this alone as I was reflecting on the vast
transmission the corlection and the and the translations of this teachings that
came from more than 2,600 years ago countless individuals have walked
the path countless individuals have been cultivating their heart and mind in the
past and right now just look at all of us here
together practicing
together and there will be um this kind of forces happening in the future
too in the way we are the direct beneficiaries of the stream and currents
of the wisdom compassion from so many people before
us I'm feeling that even in our virtual meditation hall or Dharma Hall um a
group of us are joining the current of the practice the current of the Sana
so here the community of the practitioners who practice well is a
home to return to I'm fond of this particular sutta
where Ananda said to the Buddha one time that half of the Holy
life is s but the Buddha corrected him and budha
said no no Anand don't say that the whole of of the
Holy life is Sana because if the Sana practices the
noble Eightfold Path you will do so as
well isn't that true and so if all of you are practicing Noble
Eightfold Path I will be doing this no
doubt as part of the s
and so for me personally at some point of my Dharma Journey Dharma practice journey I had a re realization that the
Dharma path can't be claimed as mine because I'm
constantly influenced shaped inspired and moved by people like
you by my teachers by the Dharma bodies by the SAA
I'm part
of and when I'm returning to the home of Sanaa there is no doubt that this
currents will drawing force and the practice will unfold will
move each other I remember sometimes uh if I get
caught up in the things of of the world um I don't know worldly
wings um but when I'm entering into a group of
practitioners for a sit or for a Dharma talk or for a event
together often I have this sense of coming
home there is a real sense of safety here I can trust the collect
conscience Collective Good Will kindness and the Beautiful wholesome
qualities that the the S cultivates
together this uh returning and relying on the goodness of the S is a real
Refuge a real home
so um I wanted to maybe and just feeling this and chanting
Retreat energy I wanted to end today's talk Maybe by
chanting uh for a few minutes on on this particular chant that touched me quite
deeply and this is um paying respect to the Buddha Dharma and
S and the the chant is in P um and it's
actually quite a simple chant and if you wish and definitely join me join me and
it's a repeat so um hopefully as you follow along and a couple of times
you'll be able to join in on on this chant and this chant go
like [Music]
this so Vante means um uh reverence or to
Revere and so what this chant um is saying is um to rever the Buddha to
rever the Dharma and to rever the
Sana and so I'm going to begin and if you like to join me and after maybe
listen on a couple of times and feel free to just join along we'll chant for
a few minutes together before we end
[Music]
d s
s s
[Music]
bud [Music]
s s s
[Music]
d [Music] s Sanaa
s [Music]
d [Music]
s bu [Music]
[Music]
Bud D D
s allow the V vibration to Ripple through you
thank you all friends for being
here have a wonderful night for those who are in evenings
or um have a great day otherwise for those who are in different time
zones and take great care