so good day and welcome to the arising of this
meditation session together and it'll now that it's in the process of
appearing it will persist for some minutes and
then it'll come to an end and this uh insight this appreciation
deep appreciation for the inconstancy of experience
is one of the specialties of insight meditation and to really begin to appreciate and
value and be attuned to how things are how experiences how we experience
things is a transient phenomenon that the particularities of what we are
aware of in the moment come and they go and so some of the thoughts that you're
already having now listening to what i'm saying but didn't exist
10 minutes ago and there a few minutes ago then they have appeared and i'm sure someday
they'll disappear as a current active thoughts that you have
and and there's something about observing or recognizing this transient
of experience that supports
a movement towards freedom freedom from being entangled in the transient
experiences freedom from the searching and looking and wanting to hold on to something
just letting go and and so there's many ways to experience
constancy you can be aware of how things arise that something new appears it was
unexpected unplanned and there's a sound there's a thought there's a feeling we can be aware that
things have passed things that were there now are gone and sometimes it can be a surprise where did
it go i've had physical pain in meditation
and then i don't know some point i was aware it was no longer there and i didn't see it pass away but i
certainly know now it's passed away and wow where did it go and
the and uh and it's not just uh you know the
experience that's you know things that we experience that arise in past but it's also the way in which we
experience them the fickle way in which attention and thoughts kind of focus on things
that we might be focused on the breathing and hang stay there pretty well but then there's
a loud sound and we say what's that and the sound has just arisen the thought what's that has just arisen
the thought i better find a quieter place to meditate has just arisen and then we're aware that that's passed
for a moment it's just a thought and because we don't lean into it and hold on to it we don't add another thought i should
find a better place to meditate i wonder what's a better place to meditate we take the time to recognize the first
thought it arose it was there a little bit and then it passed and
and if what i'm talking about you don't understand that you have the thought that doesn't understand that that
thought arose and then maybe persists and then it passes
and so it doesn't say that all things are supposed to be quickly
transient and constant the buddha talked about things arise they persist and they pass away
but there's something about being attuned to how they arise
when they arise that they arise and that they pass is really the art of this and
and uh and part of it what's also interesting is that maybe we're not there to notice when
something has arisen but maybe we notice that our awareness of it
has now arisen we weren't exactly aware of it but oh i'm aware of it now and that
awareness has arisen and then at some point we it hasn't
passed away it persists but we've been focusing on something else we've gotten involved in a fantasy
and then we're aware that oh the awareness of that has ceased for a while and so there's
all these ways in which we see we're not supposed to search for seeing
arising and passing a phenomena as much as settle back and observe it
appreciate it be attuned to it in the way that it helps us to keep
letting go keep relaxing keep not getting involved in things and
searching and wanting and making things happen just settle back and the arising and passing of phenomena
in all the ways that can be experienced happens without our involvement without
our making it so and so to settle back and just observe and watch and watch
so taking a uh i would say maybe i said differently
beginning with a new beginning of bringing attention to your posture
and adjusting your posture and be aware that as you do so there's
something new that keeps arising new sensations in the body new feelings
and then settling into this body
and if your eyes are still open there's the occurrence of closing your
eyes a new beginning or an ending
of the eyes being open
and the breathing itself is uh one of the great teachers for any constancy
that all the sensations that come and go with breathing are coming
and going arising and passing
and in some ways the constancy continuity of the inconstancy of breathing
is also a wonderful reference point for seeing the
inconstancy of the mind's ability to stay focused and present
the arising of new thoughts through persistence of them the changing nature of thoughts
thoughts themselves are not one constant hum but new thoughts ideas
images are constantly streaming through and to be attuned to the inconstancy of the
details of thinking as a way of
not clinging so much holding on
as you exhale relaxing the belly
softening the belly and being aware of changing sensations that come and go as you do so
as you exhale relaxing the chest
as you exhale softening the shoulders
some things pass if the tension relaxes and do things arise in the shoulders
softening the muscles of the face your dear face
softening relaxing giving it a break
and then gently maybe lovingly to relax your thinking mind
maybe on the exhale softening the brain or the forehead
the holding the contraction the searching the wanting
exhale and soften relax the whole body
and then taking that thinking mind of yours
and letting it rest settle back as if it's settling back against a
comfortable tree on a comfortable day
ready to observe the river flowing by
the flow of arising and passing a phenomenon
sometimes we're aware of sensations coming and going sometimes aware of our attention coming
and going our thoughts coming and going
one way or the other something new is always arising
it's one way or the other something is always ceasing and passing away
and you can do all of this seeing all of this in the breathing
settling into your breathing maybe your breathing is the tree you're
leaning against resting in the breathing
floating on this river of change
in the body as you experience breathing changing sensations of breathing
so
uh
there's a way that the arising appearing of new
something new in awareness supports not clinging to anything
there's a way in which the ceasing of things the passing of things
supports not clinging not holding on
if you stay close to how things are appearing and disappearing moment by
moment it can be a little bit like a massage for
the mind the mind's tendency to want and search for and
create think
just let go let go let go with the inconstant
the flow of inconstancy
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
one of the descriptions of mindfulness practice could be that it's being available
for the way in which life is ever renewing
ever-changing to be available for what arises that's
new by not lingering and holding on and
living with what has passed and it's a
wonderful gift to give to others to be available for them as if they are
new as if they are renewed as if you don't know them
but they're appearing fresh without your
old news your old ideas about who they are and what
they've done and your expectations of how they should be
but to be available to see how people are ever new and re
freed of their past
to be available
for the ever renewing aspects of this life so that we can love and care and
be tenderized by what is happening moment by moment
so we can be sensitive to the depth of the present moment
sensitive to the depth of our contact with others
how they live in our lives
and this ability not to linger in the past to hold on to things
to be fresh is a wonderful basis upon which to care
for others and may it be that this practice of ours
helps us to care deeply because we feel deeply
into the newness of each moment
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
so as i've been talking over these last days about the 13th step
of mindfulness of breathing being you're being the observation
settling back and observing the inconstanty of phenomena how things are constantly renewing but
also constantly passing and that appearing and disappearing of
our experience moment by moment certainly sometimes it's unfortunate that things pass away
sometimes we're very fortunate that finally it's no longer here and sometimes we're fortunate that
things are are arising and sometimes it's unfortunate what's arising
it's painful or something and sometimes it's neutral so there's no particular
prioritizing or valuing or or how to say it putting a value on the particular
arising of passings that occur it's not it's not a discounting of
things it's not a celebrating of things necessarily it's just seeing that actually this is kind of the
nature of when we're really settled really peaceful not overlaying concepts and
ideas on top of experience
can we can kind of um that's what we experience we're in the flow of our experience flow of
sensations and experience and but the great value of it is not in
and of itself like we're supposed to celebrate it or supposed to be depressed by it or something it's uh
that we can't it becomes a reference point
for how valuable it is not to cling to any of it not to contract around any of it not to
resist any of it and especially and in meditation
uh in real life you know there's certain things that should be held on to or resisted perhaps
but in meditation to really learn to free ourselves from any movement of being for against
holding on or pushing away and because the kind doesn't work but
also because this ability to observe and not get engaged and attached to things
begins feeling so good i feel that's where freedom is and uh and the core kind of
catalyst for freedom in the teachings of the buddha is this experience this deep insight
into inconstancy and so the way in which the more free we become the more
in constancy is a support for greater freedom the more free we are the more we see
recognize how we're trying to hold on to what is constantly changing or how we've left the flow or how we you know like
put our hand out the window of a car and we have wind drag we're going to have wind drag we put our
hands into the river and trying to stop it we picked up a bunch of handful of water
and we left the river thinking we have the river still there's all these ways in which we recognize
that we've we've kind of left the flow of inconstancy the flow of life
because we've gotten excessively attached or involved or clinging and so see that in meditation
and to see that we're actually better off backing off better off not clinging that
it's not so interesting to cling or to want and so there's a begins to be an inner
psychological change that happens and as some of that is starting to
become a a relaxing the search relaxing to trying to do
something or get something or relaxing the need to know
and searching to know and because all that is kind of is too much it's like leaning forward
when we can just settle back in the sense and then now the
uh all these attachments we have starts we start feeling them as being wind drag
we start feeling them as being um interfering with the the
radiance of the heart the beauty of the mind the freedom of of uh of our lives and we can see that
they diminish us the clinging the attachments that we have things we hold on to and so there starts to be a fading
away disinterest and a fading away of jealousy and envy and conceit
and and craving and hatred and resentments
you know you can go on the list is long of things that we begin recognizing oh this doesn't really serve me this
i'm not so interested in this anymore it's not like i have to be a good buddhist and this is bad that i'm doing
this and i have to stop doing it it's more like i'm no longer interested in this
this is less and less interesting to do i've been resentful for 30 years and i think that i'm getting
tired of it i think i see that it's not so interesting i've been chasing after
having the perfect physical physique for decades and at some point i'm not really
interested in presenting myself always with the perfect human physique whatever that might be
and we start losing interest in it always wanting to make more money or
have status or i don't know what all these things were kind of chasing there's a healthy kind
of oh wait a minute this doesn't serve me this is not the best place to be this is
not the most wonderful way to be to be preoccupied with these things i'm beginning to know something better
i'm knowing something about freedom and ease and peace and i want to stress over again that um
the primary reference point for what i'm talking about here now is in fact meditation because
outside of meditation you might argue well wait a minute isn't it okay to do it here or here we need to do it here
i don't want to get into those discussions what i want you is to really discover that in meditation
you don't have to be pursuing the perfect physique more money more status more
whatever it is that you're trying to do in meditation you can feel it meditation
itself it's better easier just to let go or not be involved and then to really have an experience a
qualitatively high experience of freedom of ease of peace where we're no longer grasping holding
or resisting or tightening or contracting that becomes your teacher
rather than debating me with me about wait a minute aren't you supposed to hold on here or
resist that uh it's not so interesting to debate with me it's
really for real spiritual life you should be debating with yourself when you have this deep reference point
for peace deep deep reference point for freedom that's that's where it gets really
interesting that's where it really comes alive this practice of freedom and uh and really kind of explore and
find out what what is really true for yourself so with this uh observing and constancy
then there's a fading away of the interest in some of our attachments and then there's a fading away of the
attachments themselves and and so
the word for the 13th now the 14th step of anapanasati the pali
and there's two different translations of this word and the one that i'll stress today is
um it means the fading away when observed the fading of the fading away
of these attachments and um the fading away of um
of our interest or our addiction to addictive interest in in certain things
that are not really serving us anymore and so they're fading away of fading away and this speaks to something very
important about this path of liberation in buddhism that sometimes there's a tendency to want to
look for um you know a sudden experience that the key to it all that just unlocks it all a
number free forever just like but a more mature way of seeing it is that
a lot of it has to do with just fading away fading away a wearing away dropping away
drop by drop um everything dries up or falls away the evaporating
of it a phenomenon of our attachment and so raga the root of the word v raga
can mean a dye that we call or cloth with and v raga the v prefix means of fading
away or separating of that dye and so one of the meanings is to fade away the dye you put
you know you dye some clothes and you leave it in the sun for too long and it gets bleached to get the color fades away and so or just time
fades it away and so the fading away the fading away and um and this uh when we really feel
the the um unsatisfactoriness the the offness the the
discomfort of attachment of clinging of addiction of all these movements of the mind that we
have and we start to feel oh this is lightening up it's loosening up
there's a lightening a lifting a lifting of a cloud and
letting go relaxing and then the mindfulness practice is to be available
to that fading to be open to that fading to allow for that
fading because if we go right back into clinging we reinforce more clinging
we strengthen that capacity to cling and attach and resist and be addicted to things but once we
start feeling this process of fading away then the mindfulness practice is to be available to that fading
available to it so we don't reinforce the opposite
so one trains breathing in observing
fading away when trains breathing out observing fading away
and uh and uh so that's one of the meanings of the raga and then tomorrow
i'll talk a little bit about the second meaning which is dispassion and uh
at least that's all you often how it's translated into english and and probably not a very good
translation but that's for tomorrow so um
thank you and this comes to an end