so so formal hello and warm welcome to all of you
ah dear friends so for today's practice theme
this past week we've been exploring um gratitude and
and meta and gratitude so to wrap up this week and continuing with
this theme a couple of insights came up on wednesday that i
wanted to follow up on insights from your practice that came up
and to dedicate this hour to exploring them further formally
and that is the insight of how meta and
gratitude can support each other how they can support each other and and
perhaps maybe a unified way of seeing the two practices
so for some meta might be an easier way to get into
gratitude for some it might be gratitude actually greases the wheels and to get for
getting into meta so and both are good and now what we'll
explore is actually setting the frame starting with some practice of gratitude
to to um grease the wheels as a precursor to meta to see what that
feels like if we enter that way if we enter into meta
from priming the heart with gratitude to experiment that way and see how that
works that's one thing to keep in mind for tonight and then there is another frame
also that i like to bring in and that is actually gratitude
as love huh what does that even mean gratitude as
love maybe we can think about it as the unified theory you know how in physics
the holy grail is to come up with the unified theory theory of everything so here the unified
theory of everything is unified theory of love so what how what if we consider
gratitude as loving loving everything
loving whatever is arising the sense of love as appreciation loving everything
loving even dukkha loving even difficulty loving it all
loving it all so gratitude as love and that's something that i'll
bring in for us to explore a little bit experiment with
so i think that's enough for setting the frame let's just
explore and as i'll always we'll start with settling the mind the body
the breath so let's begin let's begin our formal practice together
landing landing in our bodies
landing
in this moment in time with this breath
can we let go can we let go of everything else
can we let go of expectations
can we let go of needs and wants
is it possible to just put down everything that is not necessary in this
moment
and turn turn inward
turn to the sacred space
within this universe within there is a universe with it
as complex as amazing a reflection [Music]
of the universe without outside
to turn to this holy universe within
where the breath moves
where there are sensations in this miraculous body
where there are feeling tones of pleasant
floating around unpleasant floating around just the same
neutral floating around and to open up to it all
coming home coming home to this universe
connecting with the breath
entirety of the in-breath
entirety of the opera
giving our heart completely to just this
to just this breath in this body in this
moment
putting down whatever is necessary thoughts plans memories
not needed right now thank you thoughts please come back later
just this in-breath just a sack breath
while we are alive in this moment
can there be gratitude appreciation for just this breath
in this moment of being breathed in this life in this form
this body
can there be a sense of appreciation
for this body sitting
breathing the heart pumping
all these complex
chemical reactions happening every millisecond in this body this universe within
the blood the brain synapses the complex
chemistry physiology
which leads to hearing
sensing feeling cognizing
being aware that we don't quite understand but it's
always on
it's the miracle of this moment
can we love
be in awe of what is
even if there is discomfort in the body
when we label pain challenges
can there be appreciation
oh love for the process of this body
even as it is challenged
whether physical sensations or emotions
opening opening up to all of it
expansively expansive loving it all
as much as possible or as little as
possible
and opening up this sphere sphere of awareness
of gratitude
for whatever else is arising not just in this moment but in your life in general if you wish
bowing in your heart and your mind for the blessings for the goodness
loving these blessings thank you
it's not a greedy love that once more but a contented love
that appreciates what is and is content
this being that is you blessed with goodness in their life
and relishing appreciating this goodness
it is wholesome to relish
appreciate your heart sing
in the abundance that we often take for granted
a roof over your head food enough health
to be cognizant right now
taking your time with each blessing
for a minute or two each
the blessings can include the people in your life present and past
teachers people who have inspired you
mentors
all these blessings in your life
now so we appreciate
feel grateful can we feel as if we are loved by these blessings as
if these blessings even if they're inanimate objects
or concepts like health they're loving us they're giving us love giving us mental
giving us goodness wrapped wrapped in the blessings wrapped in the
love in the meta of all that we are grateful for
just receiving just receiving
receiving the goodness the love from our dwelling the roof over her head
as if it's wrapping us in meta in goodwill safety from the elements
the food we eat we have eaten that we're grateful for
loving us serving us
lovingly giving us energy feeling the love in our bodies
as much a health as we have feeling the love the goodness of
it
if we are engaged in the world nor work or volunteering if we're
grateful for that feeling that it loves us too
to bi-directional relationship
the people were grateful for
their blessings feeling that
they give us love meta goodwill
letting ourselves receive like a sponge
the goodness the blessings the love from everything we're grateful for
held held up lovingly
as if a blanket
and now as we receive this love this care this is a blanket we're wrapped in
receiving the goodness
nourished by this love now shining it outward
or letting it be shown outward not so much at doing but witnessing
appreciating
loving having good will friendliness what
however it shows up for you for people
all life
and even inanimate objects in our world everything is stardust including
ourselves
receiving love from the stardust held in goodness blessings
and loving all the stardust
all beings everything
with each breath
in your own time either receiving more or giving more or receiving and giving
unclear who's giving what's receiving
sitting in gratitude and appreciation and love
for the expression of the universe within universe without
this brief miracle of being alive in this form with all its ups and downs all its
lessons all its joys all its sorrows it's
thank you i love you
receiving giving
for the last moment of this practice trusting that you're doing the best you
can you've done the best you can
given all the causes and conditions if could have been different they would have been trust you're doing the best you can
and appreciating this being with you or hanging in here with practice with
everything doing the best they can
with meta and appreciation for this being with you
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
including this being who is myself
[Music]
thank you sanga and zoom on youtube an audio dharma
for your practice
so gratitude as a support for
metta and gratitude as a form of love
as loving what is and receiving love giving love sitting
in love
so we traveled to many different places different
stops in this practice tonight and would love to hear your reflections
and you can share them in chat to me privately i won't say your name
and if public i will say your name and the reflection and
um can also raise your hand so question comes in chat
is the universe grateful for us even when we cause harm yeah
that's a very good question so it's an interesting perspective
so [Music] there are many different ways to see
this so has the do we cause harm intentionally
unintentionally the chances are we do not cause harm intentionally
it's very high it's i don't think even you know people who commit
say crimes etc if we know their background if we know
the way they see they see themselves they see and everything they see
they don't think they don't feel as if they're causing harm so so i want to make a distinction between
that so if we are not knowingly intentionally causing harm is the universe still loving us so
that's the way i like to to frame that question and i like to make it a little
larger so if i say something and unintentionally so now i make it more personal i
intentionally harm you so i've caused harm is the universe
still loving me i think so i think so in this in this view
and the the the with the trust in the goodness in
each of us in the goodness in me that i do want to wake up i do want to do the best i can and
the causing harm is on the path of again it's not intentional it never seems to
be intentional it's along the ways of learning growing
so i think this can be a much longer conversation there are a lot of
different things that are coming in so i hope this gives it just a little bit of taste of
the way to frame the question um [Music] that the universe if you want to call it
but the nature if you want to call it the universe if you if you like god if you like uh
the divine there is a sense of goodness and love in in in and trust that
we in the goodness that we are trying to contribute even in the short term what we do is
causing harm uh without us intending to anyway i'm gonna pause there
and maybe be another chance to talk about that so
other reflections other questions feel free to raise your hand sarah says i like the idea of embracing
everything with love and gratitude even the so-called negative states like anger it opens up more space
acceptance and compassion than pushing them away does thank you sarah that's a great
observation wonderful insight on youtube yeah reflection
um i was moved by the invitation to trust in doing the best we can
at the tail end of the meditation it was something i could hold with kindness
uh to trust that we're doing the best we can beautiful invitation yeah thank you
thank you for that reflection yes trusting that trusting that that we
are doing the best we can and we all screw up every single one of us we are not
perfect of course we make mistakes of course we cause harm of course we do and let's
trust that we're still loved we're still love worthy as we in this
difficult life of being human filled with dukkha and joys and sorrows and we're all we're
still doing our best we're still loved the universe doesn't turn away just because we screw up and
we cause harm um so yeah thank you for that
for those reflections and yeah for the anonymous question the other reflections like to bring up
this is claire please
i just wanted to add a note with something you touched on but i just wanted to expand on it i've you had a gratitude practice for a
number of years and it's really enriched my life and it's i i was able to finally
work work with it when somebody told me that or taught me that gratitude is
wanting what you have yeah yeah and uh it
turned my whole perception of my life around yeah yeah beautiful yeah
it's very important yeah exactly it's one gratitude is wanting what you have
and it's it's a contented love you know when there's a sense of love as i was bringing in the meditation
the same concept when you love what is without wanting more of it it's
a contented love that is gratitude is loving what you have
yeah thanks for highlighting that claire very important
yeah the other reflections please
jerry says i love life with all its sorrows and happiness yes yes yeah
yeah life with all its sorrows and happiness to be human
yeah so there are no more reports
yes co please [Music]
report from the field
okay you're unmuted
are you ready for yeah yeah yeah cool good good um yeah i i
tuned in late but i just loved that same thing where you you mentioned this concept of a
contented love and um i've recently uh
well the english language has all these idioms that are dangerous like falling in love with or whatever anyway i've recently
been attracted to someone for the first time in a while and um
and what you're saying this rings so true and helpfully uh i also had a
teacher say if you fall in love make sure it's mutual and you go slow and i can just contrast how i'm
dealing with this um uh sensitive situation much differently than i used
to i i knew that space was very important to give to the other person but i really
didn't know how to do it but i think now i know how to do it
beautiful beautiful may may you enjoy and relish this unique and
sensitive situation with sensitivity and and a lot of space as you're continuing
that yeah beautiful so far so good great thank you thanks ko yeah and mark says tiknot han
said you need to smile to your sorrow because you are more than your sorrow
yes beautiful thanks for bringing that in mark you need to smile to your sorrow
because you are more than your sorrow exactly yeah beautiful i'm so
appreciating tonight we're we're touching in some very deep spaces we're traveling far and wide everyone
so let's turn to each other in small groups and sharing uh our practice in small groups
so um we'll i'll open the rooms in a moment and
let's start with 15 seconds of meta and gratitude for yourself and each
other in small groups and then opening up and sharing as little or as much as you like
but you practice supporting each other and taking care of each other taking care of yourself
so i'm about to open the rooms and here we go enjoy your practice
together welcome back everyone welcome back so we have a couple minutes
left for uh insights reflections what you've learned especially after
having listened to each other and shared out live what what insights challenges
whatever came up so especially if you haven't shared for a while would love to hear from you please your voice is important the
universe loves your voice and so does the sangha so
especially those of you haven't spoken for a while you know who you are
did you notice if entering into meta this way from
gratitude in this way was different was supportive susan please
um oh i wanted to um just say that this meditation was i was
saying that in my small group how it really shifted a lot of things for me because i haven't
been in a very good place lately and i've been feeling a lot of pain around a lot of things lately so
this really this meditation shifted so many things i felt so much um gratitude just
for all that i had in my life and the people in my life but not only that
like nature and i was feeling like how much nature loved me and that was like so beautiful
um i felt like the universe was really holding me with love and and experiencing um
so much of that was um just a wonderful experience that i don't always have
so often at such such a um uh where i feel so strongly so deeply
from so many different places and then being able to like give back that love to
um as well and with my body as well so it was really a lot of different um
uh love going back and forth with different um yeah
with all these different parts me others the universe nature so it was
beautiful yeah so it was so lovely it really shifted things for me and i'm hoping i'm going to continue
practicing this beautiful thank you susan thanks so much for sharing that
yay yay my heart sings hearing this practice report and thank
you susan and ariana says i really needed to hear that the universe loves me this evening
thank you nikki all thank you yeah [Music] yeah yeah and
one question this exploring tomovicia and metta in the future would be lovely okay so if we have a request
okay all right okey doke well the time has come this friday or whatever
time zone you're in whatever day it is to bring our practice together to close so thank you so much
everyone for your practice for cultivating your
heart for loving with contentment what is and feeling love and serving it's a
way of serving it's a way of being in the world when we see our own goodness and we let ourselves be seen
it it helps us shine it more may all beings be happy
know their own goodness be of service may all beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone