so hello hello and welcome everyone to happy hour it's lovely to be with you wherever in
the world you are in this moment so so for tonight's practice
um yeah i'd like to leave a lot of space for
just sitting and landing we did practice of of enough
and on friday working with the poem um of david white on friday and
and many people said that oh there's a sense of sufficiency and landing into what's here right now it
was very spacious and nourishing so for for tonight i like to
leave a lot of space and at the same time um bring some themes of equanimity
and compassion especially now with the request that gita brought in with um
with the tragedy in up in vancouver so so sharing some um both karuna
compassion as well as equanimity practice not just for ourselves but for
for all beings everywhere especially those in difficult circumstances so
that's the plan and i'm not going to say much more let's just get into it and practice together okay so
so let's get into our meditation posture
landing
planting in this body
this breath in this moment
whatever is present in this moment in this body
whether it's fatigue whether there's heaviness sadness
maybe is excitement and joy whatever is present
can we just sit and open up open our heart to open our body to
what is here the mystery the mystery of this
human life as it's unfolding in this moment in this heart and this
mind in this body can we open to it just as
it is one breath at a time
do
this
letting the breath breathe you breathe this body
moving moving the energy around
there's heaviness energy being breathed into it
life is movement and change
noticing the movement of the breath in the body
do
noticing movement change in the breath
and in the body with each breath
just as the breath moves through the body thoughts emotions too
along with sensations keep shifting and changing
and noticing with all this movement shifting and changing sensations
breath thoughts emotions
moving through noticing
ah is there some stability
groundedness groundless ground
that spaciously spaciously can hold not even
hold but allow all this coming and going
to be
a sense of peace sense of calm stability however it might show up or
spaciousness
that can hold witness to all the shifting and moving and change and not be toppled over by it
a spacious spacious [Music]
okayness with equanimity
and okayness that cares about what arises and passes with metta
friendliness but isn't toppled over
it doesn't fall into or push away
[Music] and okayness
expansive okayness that is not aloof
but stable and caring to all the comings and goings all the
movements and the mind and the heart the emotions the body
and if there's if there is any sorrow sadness challenges
grief
spacious spaciousness stability
can make space for it let it be just as it is
not pushing it away
not trying to make it go away fix it
but patiently caringly
holds presence
this deep well of resource
of okayness pervading
maybe finding knowing realizing that this
this well of resource of okayness is much deeper than [Music]
you have realized
that you have given yourself credit for
this deep well of okayness can nourish
the heart
the mind the body with whatever is arising moving moving through
making space holding space with care with stability
if you wish you can stay
with this spacious okayness spacious
caring [Music] stable okayness
that allows all comings and goings of emotions
thoughts body sensations
to be just as they are sense of stability
vast spaciousness with care imbued with care
stability not toppled over
holding presents
comings and goings internally and what's arising
you can stay with this or if you wish you're welcome to open
to expand further this caring equanimity okayness for
all the comings and goings
for all beings whether they're happy or
facing a challenge with difficulty
and if it starts feeling too overwhelming you can always come back
to the movements arisings and passings here internally
if there is space resting landing into equanimity
[Music] far and wide
all beings were suffering of sorrow
all the comings and goings
holding witness with care
for each breath
10 000 joys and ten thousand sorrows
moving changing every moment part of this human existence
for all beings everywhere
[Music]
and for the last moments of this practice period
holding allowing spacious equanimity of okayness
with the movements of the heart and mind the body during this practice whatever it was
no judgment trying to fix push away regret self blame criticism
it's all okay you showed up
you practiced as best as you could with all the causes and conditions
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so we have some time or reflections if you like to share
questions comments observations about this practice
complaints you can share your your wisdom you're invited to if you
wish please you can type them in chat if you type them to everyone i will say
your name as i read them if you type them just to me i will
keep it confidential the comment you are welcome don who says thank you
thank you all for your practice for this opportunity
so i appreciated this practice ah i'm feeling much more
equanimous with all the comings and goings in my heart
the holding with care not trying to fix make it go away just being and realizing
a depth a depth of well [Music] of resourcefulness
a depth of ah of okayness
that cares that's stable and it's not moved can be with what
arises so so thank you for practicing with me
any recommend any comments
what did you notice especially if you haven't spoken in a while please can raise your
zoom hand or if you're new
and also appreciation time youtube thank you henry and sean
and you're welcome
okay couple of reflections one is
see dawn says a kind of quiet meditation and a quiet groove today yes equanimity
can really calm and and have a sense of stillness where we don't
want to talk afterwards so that's normal megan says very
calming felt like medicine for the soul oh sweet i wonder
one other comment initially i felt some numbness i repositioned to the floor and
felt more grounding and opening and i was able to open my heart a bit more
lovely halfway i appreciate in that recommendation in that
reflection how noticing okay sitting on the floor
moving the body would be more supportive and doing that in the heart being able to open more neil says
i hadn't realized how stressed i was yeah it's interesting afterwards we
notice when we settle and become calmer abraham i see your hand
please uh hi um so
i just do a kind of a breath meditation centering on joy and happiness
um and that to me feels very economist but and i haven't been attending much
is there was there a specific economy exercise that we were doing other than
meditating that i missed can you expand on that
yeah so yeah so what the invitation today so there's so many
different ways to to do to practice equanimity and to open
up to equanimity so the way i guided today the invitation was first
to notice all the movement all the movement of the body the breath the mind the heart so the
the movement life is movement life is movement as um so noticing all the movement and then
in contrast then noticing that oh yes there is a stillness there is a spaciousness
that can hold can be present with all the movement and not be moved so through that opening up to
oh yes equanimity oh there is this spaciousness this groundedness that can
be with all the arising and passing and and then tuning into that more and
more um so that was the in in brief the cliff notes of what i
was inviting us to explore today abraham thank you for the question thank you i
appreciate it yeah susan says i gave up and dropped my
back and let myself think i'm being trained here to be kind to myself like that and
then nikki reinforce that right afterwards yes whatever is needed
susan whatever is needed and if happy hour is a time to cultivate kindness and go to oneself
no don't need to push it don't need to push it and jamie says for me this it was
equanimity practice focused on my kids it allowed me to see i don't have to
take on their suffering or try to fix it all i have to do is accept and love them oh
that's so beautiful jamie thank you for sharing that
so attached yeah and let's see on youtube
couple questions one is what kind of emotion is equanimity positive neutral
or negative all of them question mark none of them and thank you for the practice
and then another question how do you bring your mind back when it wants to wonder what works for you so the first question
about equanimity it's in the teachings
in abhidhamma and the higher teachings it is said that equanimity has a valence
has a neutral valence um so
so um that's what it said classically so um and yet
that the the neutral the neutral evade enough feeling tone
it's it's a can be under the category of unworldly neutral tone so there's a
grace a beauty it's not just neutral it's not just detached and aloof but there is a
it's there is a neutrality that is um
there's a wholesomeness wholesome quality to the neutrality and i'm trying to explain that as best
as i can um and
bringing the mind back is ever so gently noticing that the mind wants to wander and maybe
sean saying not now not now ever so gently bring it back so that you can
give yourself to practice and telling the thoughts if they're important enough to please come back later you'll be here waiting for them
but not right now right now you're giving your heart to this practice so you can try that there's so many
different tools but you can try this and see how that works so dear ones
ah with equanimity and inviting us to
transition with a sense of okayness see if the heart can be okay have a
sense of okayness to transition to practicing in small groups now and if
you have to go it's perfectly fine and if you can stay and maybe stretch yourself a little bit
this might be with equanimity can you stay present with all the movements the comings and goings and the heart and the
mind so with that and the invitation is
in the um breakout rooms to spend the first 30 seconds
with just meta for each other with a sense of spacious equanimity
oh and meta for each other and then then if you'd like to share and hold
witness that is invited so i'm going to open the rooms
and here we go just okay everyone is back hi
so yeah just have a minute if anyone has reflections um something that
came up for you during the group please
maybe there is so much equanimity and peace nobody wants to talk that's what i'm picking up maybe one
reflection anything but nicholas says it's such a gift to be okay with rough
days weeks months together ah beautifully said nicholas such a gift to
be okay with the comings and goings of things the rough days weeks and months
or a year which happens to be what we've had
yeah beautiful thank you for that reflection nicholas lovely so with that
let's let's close our time together so may all of us may all beings
everywhere have the gift of freedom the crown jewel
of this practice equanimity okayness with all the comings and goings with
caring stability may all beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music]
thank you all for your practice