so welcome uh welcome all uh
i'm just seeing the the names uh stream stream through
and uh yeah welcome to to all of you welcome to all of you
um yeah
so here we are again together and
yeah let us uh let us practice together
so finding your your posture
even if it's very familiar finding it again
i'm taking a posture that's both supple but strong
notes are kind of openness to phenomena
we relax whatever tension
can be relaxed
whatever tension remains we allow to remain
our practice is to
to release some of the tendencies we have around
pushing and pulling
pushing and pulling on phenomena
so rather than trying to shape our experience
we just let ourselves be softened by it
let the heart be softened by experience
all phenomena converge on feeling
centrality of feeling
the urge to fix to adjust the shape
the the limits of our equanimity or are felt in
the realm of feeling
so we permit phenomena sites and sounds thought and sensation we permit them
access to our heart to feeling
we're willing to be impacted
we're willing to be still
we're willing to be changed by experience
rather than change it
it's agitating to try to cobble together
a life to cobble together solutions
to cobble together an identity
to get our papers in order
so we stand down
settle back
willing to feel our way through
the flood
of urges
urges to shape experience
to shape ourselves to shape our life
[Music]
when when the the astronauts
first walked on the moon they uh they planted an american flag
and um and i've always thought that they they really should have planted a flag
with an image of the moon right
they planted an american flag and
we plant flags too we plant flags all over the place
and our flag has two letters on it
m [Music] e yeah
and we plant flags uh
to feel safe to feel good to have reference points
but any claimed territory
entails territoriality
and as social animals with social needs
um we do a lot of flag planting
this can turn the world into a kind of stage
and there are many dimensions of the self that are are um
performative not all dimensions of the self are are a
performance but many are and performance is tiring
right actors rehearse and summon energy and confront doubts
and are concerned about breaking character concerned about being found out
stressful so from uh
sociologist uh goffman from almost 70 years ago said
uh the world is not of course a stage but the crucial ways in which it isn't
are not easy to specify
and goes on to say uh choose your self-presentation carefully for what starts out as a mask
becomes your face
in a sense are our performances they're
they're an argument yeah in the legal sense they're an argument
we're making a case we're making a case for me
as valuable in some way and uh
that makes sense but um we want to be careful
yeah because we we confuse a mask an argument for ourselves
and then buddhism takes us deeper and it's not just the mask that's not you
but you are not your face either
this deep
deep assumption i am me
this moment fits into who i was who i will be my
autobiography was a deep
felt experienced and
yet were directed to the the understanding that uh
that clinging to a particular view of self clinging to a particular view of
self is very fertile ground for pain
for ourselves and others and
many many painful
emotional experiences many painful experiences uh they they
they serve to illuminate the architecture of self-view
yeah this the the the structures the edifice of self-view are illuminated by
afflictive emotion by shame by arrogance
by self-righteousness this illuminates
the architecture of self-view and rather than devote ourselves to
endlessly making our arguments to curating ourselves
we investigate we investigate
and maybe find that the
the hallmark of of ego is defensiveness
is that territoriality we claim territory we become territorial
and wherever wherever there is self-identification
there can also be shame
and so we look how does this self congeal
how do we make our arguments
and at some point in practice we become unconvinced by our autobiography
unconvinced by our autobiography and
all the familiar stories the familiar milia
of me the arrogance the sense of unworthiness
the self-hatred all of the style
all too familiar tropes in our autobiography this we
become alienated from all of it yeah
and it's not that we dispute like the conclusions and say no
it's it's other than that we just become alienated from the whole
realm of self-view
and are born into something like
wonder and openness and equanimity of course is vital in
this it's vital in the process of developing
a fluid sense of self it's vital in the process of developing this insight into
not self our points of
identification the arguments we make wanting to be this resisting that
making making the case to ourselves to others this arises as feeling
feeling yeah feeling seen feeling too seen
not feeling seen feeling misconstrued all of this is acutely painful
and our practice is to slowly drain the charge from every egoic
definition
and so notions of self arise yeah the cases we want to make they
arise they arise in formal practice we meet them
we meet those arisings with equanimity
to to know the emptiness of our identifications is to feel them
to feel them to feel the impact of this urge
to be this to be that to prove this to prove that
to decorate one's mask to decorate one's face
to curate the self
we greet all of these these flows and urges with equanimity
and slowly begin to drain the electrical charge from them
yeah so the the solidity of identity begins to
to soften to melt
we grieve anata yeah this teaching on that self we grieve anata before it becomes
liberating uh in a sense we have to grieve the three
notebo three characteristics
before they become free in
no one no one gets to become the person they think they are
yeah there's just no place to rest no refuge to be found
no identity that provides shelter
sense of the heart resting on steady ground
none of this is to turn the ego into a kind of uh
inner enemy right where this practice the theme of equanimity
is not making an enemy of any experience
and so we don't turn a kind of aggression inwards or go hunting down
the sense of self or something like this the self
you know these egoic processes their self is a kind of
sensitivity you know child like desperate
so desperate and it needs love
yeah it needs love
not aggression yeah and so
we give love we offer ourselves love we receive love
and we start to
be to be less congealed
to have less kind of
less and less of an impulse to make our cases
and we're really uh
we're no longer guarding something that is both
precious and incredibly fragile yeah
no longer guarding the sense of the this the fragility the inherent
fragility of self that also feels at moments
priceless yeah we're no longer safeguarding
something that is totally fragile and totally precious
and this puts us at ease this opens our heart
to many forms of love
yeah because uh ownership
generates anxiety
so i offer this for your your consideration
as we practice with this theme equanimity
allowing life to touch us rather than to shape
life
so it's good to be good to be
with you all i have is my little webcam but uh
i shower it my practice is to shower it with uh with meta yeah
okay i wish you uh wish you all well have a
good uh good day and um we'll return uh tomorrow