so warm hello
and welcome
and this idea of welcoming applies to our meditation practice as
well in that when we sit and meditate we're
also welcoming meditation we're welcoming something to
arise or to settle or unfold or to let go we're welcoming
the process and what this implies the idea of
welcoming is the idea that
we are responsible to open the door we're responsible for
welcoming and then if what is standing in front of
the door what's standing there what wants to come in wants to arise and occur
is wholesome and beneficial then we welcome it we allow it to arise
if it's not wholesome if it's not beneficial then we you know say no thank you
no need to get involved no need to pick it up no need to make room for it
but to allow something to happen and so the meditation has this wonderful dynamic between what
we offer in terms of ourselves and what we do
and what we welcome what we allow to arise to occur to
unfold and how much that what the balance is between these two
is variable but that's part of the art of meditation is finding the right
balance sometimes clearly we have to engage purposefully intentionally and
apply ourselves maybe to the breathing or apply ourselves to letting go of thoughts or something
because to not do so maybe means to just continue
drifting off in thought or drifting off into ways of thinking and being which are not useful
but if we're only the one who does and is applying ourselves and think
we're responsible it's up to us to make more effort then there's no space in room for
the welcome for to allow something to appear to arise to come
and so this play of welcoming and allowing the welcome is what we do we prepare
ourselves so that we're there to receive or to allow and so this can
play itself out with our breathing in a sense one half of the
breathing cycle can be clearing the deck
or opening up or opening the door so the other half of the cycle of breathing can be allowing that cycle
part to just unfold maybe it's different for different people which they prefer i
prefer that the um that the the the allowing the clearing the decks
the emptying out is with um that's what i kind of do
on the exhale the releasing and then the inhale there's the allowing
the inhale to happen there's allowing for meditation to unfold it's allowing it's
getting out of the way and then seeing what wants to come and this kind of the cycle of letting go
and allowing letting go and receiving
welcome and letting go and then welcoming it could be the other way
some people might prefer the other way to welcome what happens as we let go and
to clear things away open up open the doors as we inhale
and this can be done gently mildly just a very light touch
riding on the inhale and exhale um and in the way i was talking about it
to let go of thoughts let go release relax on the exhale and to welcome on
the inhale and then as meditation deepens it gets stiller and quieter and more settled
then um each of these movements of um opening and then welcoming
becomes softer and stiller and quieter until neither is happening
it's just we're just there with experience maybe a little bit closer to welcoming
but even welcoming at some point is not no longer needed
so assuming a meditation posture
and in taking a a good meditation posture
you can also think of it as a posture in which you're ready to welcome
and you don't want to welcome a guest by slouching or
receding or making yourself small
you have more you have more of a welcome if you are a little bit
upright or big or fully present so a posture of
fullness full presence but a posture that's there to welcome
our experience
and gently closing the eyes
and welcome a deep inhale
and release a long exhale
like you're welcoming the air to come into your lungs you're welcoming the whole body to
expand
and then you're releasing it all setting it free
so you're ready to welcome again
then letting go and then letting your breath return to normal
and to relax different parts of your body holdings and your muscles
perhaps so that your whole body becomes more receptive and ready to welcome
to allow in some ways tension in the muscles is a
kind of resistance holding back or closing down
the simple ways in which we can relax beginning of meditation
are ways to make ourselves more receptive more sensitive
and then to settle into the body's experience of
breathing
perhaps a gentle with a light touch gentle letting go releasing as you
exhale
maybe so ever so slightly there's a fuller release at the end of
the exhale
and then welcoming the inhale
i'm wide welcome it is not just the welcoming the inhale
but is opening ourselves to allow it all to be here
without involvement without getting caught in
where there's space for all things
so
when you get involved in thinking there's very little receptivity there to
our inner direct experience the welcome is gone
when you notice you've drifted off in thought return to the welcome the receptivity
of your experience here in your body a quiet receptivity
a silent welcome
welcoming as you inhale letting go as you exhale
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to step forward into the world with clarity
with presence with a certainty certainty of really
being here and then with that clarity and certainty
being welcoming for others
allowing people to be how they are and to listen and notice and see
and respect people for how they are
as long as they're not hurting us
can we give them the gift of being respected
meaning to see them again to take a second look and really be
present so that we welcome others into
us empty space of goodness of heartfeltness of openness
where they can be more fully themselves and be known for who they are
and just as as we know ourselves
the dharma begins to move through us we begin to grow and mature and unfold
so when we help other people to be known
they give the experience to others that they are really known
something is welcome something shifts something relaxes something can open in others
may it be that what we learn in meditation practice
can be useful we meet others and relate to other
people and even when we read about them in the news
may that which is a profound knowing in receptivity and openness
be how we meet others in our dedication to live a life
that supports the welfare and happiness of all beings
may we contribute to the happiness the safety the peace
and the freedom of others
may all beings be happy
[Music]
so so today i'll continue to
recount some of the stories that occur in the suttas the ancient discourses texts that
contain the teachings of the buddha and one of the reasons for these stories
is that the stories often contextualize the teachings
or the stories highlight what's important about the teachings and or illustrate them in some way
and so today's story comes from the second discourse in the anthology called the long
discourses of the buddha and it's called long because these discourses these texts
are relatively long compared to
compared to many others in other anthologies and so the second one and uh
it's uh generally called in english something like the fruits of the renunciant life or the ref
uh the fruits of the of the reclusive life further
and it's a samanya pala means fruit samanya means
someone who's a recluse or a contemplative or renunciant
maybe it's a little bit like in the old days in english we would talk about someone who's a religious
and a religious person a religious generally meant someone who's kind of dedicated themselves to a life of the
religious life and so this is a someone in ancient india who dedicated themselves to a
lifestyle of full-time dedication to to the religious life for the times
and um so it involves a in this particular discourse i think of it as being like an opera
a predict and it's and some of it is this huge pathos this uh a display of you know that involves a
kind of a operatic kind of suffering that kind of is a context for the teachings
and um and uh so maybe i don't know if i can uh describe the
scene to be kind of but it's grand like an opera but it begins
with the greatest king of india at the time of the buddha a king by the name ajata sattu
and the king was it was a full moon night beautiful full moon night with a clear sky
and the king was on the high terrace on his palace looking out across the scene above the
treetops the full moon and the beautiful light and clarity and he's there with uh
his ministers and and he's uh exclaiming how beautiful how
wonderful the night is the full moon it's wonderful to see
and then he asks his ministers um because who can i go visit what what
what what spiritual teacher can i go visit the spiritual teachers often gathered on the full moon with their
disciples so it was kind of a time to remember the spiritual life perhaps
and so he said who could i go visit who might bring peace
to my distressed heart and the reason the king's heart is
distressed and we get a sense that comes up at the end of this discourse we understand why
is that he became king by killing his own father and this was troubling him and so he
wanted to go find someone who could kind of settle or calm his troubled heart
and so the ministers uh six ministers each of them uh uh suggested that he go see
a particular religious teacher of the time and each of them the king said no no i
visited before and what the person said didn't help and but this uh a seventh minister i
didn't say anything just was silent and then the king at some point turned to that seventh minister
jivaka i think he was the king's minister but maybe the king's doctor
and said jivaka you're not saying anything do you have a suggestion of who i might visit
and jiveka says well in fact there is a religious teacher who's in town nearby in the woods who
is has a really good report is said to be not only a wonderful
teacher for other people but a wonderful teacher for the gods and the word of
god in ancient india also meant king so it's a either it was so wonderful it is good
for the gods but also so wonderful he's good for the kings and he you know and
was the king and hearing this wonderful report about the buddha i guess he had never seen the buddha
said let's go and and so they assemble a grand pageant
he resembled eight um 500 elephants maybe it's a little bit like
the bradley tanks of modern world the these ancient you know the king would have all these
war elephants maybe but 500 of them were assembled for this going into the woods to see the buddha
and on each of the each of the these 500 was the king and his 500
wives and this represents maybe the uh the setting up a
contrast between the largeness the power the wealth of this great king
and then his great involvement with sensual pleasures which later you can see that's one of his
primary occupations and they march uh into the into the
forest to go see the buddha in the full moon night and as they get into the dark forest the
the king gets really frightened and his hair stands up on end and he says to jiva ka jivaka
uh are you you're taking us into the forest so my enemies can ambush me is
this a trick and jiveka reassures him no no no it's not a trick but
but it's so quiet here and you told me there were 1250 monks with the buddha and i don't hear a
peep from any of them ah that's because these buddhist monks are really well behaved and quiet
they're sitting listening to the buddha so ajata sato gets off his elephant and does the final
distance to where the buddha is sitting by foot but he says ajivaka jibaka where is the
buddha i don't see him anywhere and suggesting that the jubika
is in the assembly with the other monks but he doesn't recognize the buddha but then jiveka says the buddha is up
against that central pillar facing all the monks so the king goes up
to the buddha and offers his greetings and then
the buddha kind of picks up something and he says i mean are you thinking of the people
you love and the king says yes i'm thinking about my young son
i wish he could be this calm and settled as these monks 1250 monks are sitting here so
peacefully and quiet listening to you i wish my son could be this calm and quiet
and that's all he says about his son but the audience who's watching this opera or listening to the
story know they know that the the king killed his own father to become
king and they probably because this was told story was told for centuries
after the buddha died that the audience knows that
ajayatosatu's son later then killed ajata satu to become king so this
petricide continued so there's there's this pathos that's kind of in the air around the suta
and then um sato asks the buddha
what is the fruit of the renunciate life what's the benefit of becoming a monastic and practicing the religious
life and the buddha says have you asked anyone else that and he says yes i asked the six other
spiritual teachers but i wasn't satisfied with their answers and the buddha said well tell me and one
of them teaching was there is no such thing as evil
or badness or demerit and you can just do whatever you want
and you won't do any evil someone else said that that doesn't
exist really people don't exist they're empty they don't really exist and if you chop someone's head off it doesn't really um you're not
killing anyone because people don't exist someone else said that the amount of
suffering and pain that you have enjoy you have is allocated when you're first born and you
just have to kind of just play it all out and it's all predetermined and so nothing you can do makes any difference
someone else said that um they didn't know anything they didn't know they simply didn't know if there was any
benefit or fruit of the practice and and um and so had no answer to give
and someone else they went on these teachings and all the teachings you can kind of feel as these teachings
are recounted that for someone who killed their own father none of them really settled the heart none of them really
touched him or worked for him so he came to the buddha and he asked the buddha then
the same question so then the buddha said it it answered indirectly by asking a
question of the king the buddha often did that rather than answering directly he said dear king if you have a slave
uh so here's the most powerful person in the world at the time and i'm talking and then buddhist talking about one of the most
at least power a slave and your slave decides that there's another way of living and wants to do good in the world
once it wants to acquire merit and not just kind of do this grudge
grunge work for the king on and on for the whole life and so their slave goes off to become a monastic ordains
becomes renunciant lives a holy life what would you do would you insist on the slave coming
back and being a slave and the king said no no if they were really living a
redundancies life and a good life then i would honor that person and i would bring them gifts and food and
robes and support them and the buddha said well is this one of the fruits of the holy life of the
prevented life the king said oh yes this would be one of the fruits if you live that life
freed from slavery and then the king said well tell me something more and the king
and the buddha said well if someone was one of your workers like a minister or something and they
left your your employment to become a monastic what would you do then oh i would honor them and give them
gifts and support them and protect them this too is a fruit of the redundancy of life
and then sato said well tell me is there any other fruits of the holy life
so the third time the king asks the buddha then gives some of his own teachings and there's an ancient
tradition that you don't really teach someone until they ask three times so then um sato says well
as a person hears the teachings from the buddha or some person like that and becomes a monastic
renunciant and then they engage in the spiritual life and as they engage in the spiritual life
the buddha describes how all the what's called the gradual path of practice the practice of morality
of cultivation of concentration to all the way to awakening and there's
all these steps that are described but many of the steps result in
in happiness and bliss and gladness and joy and so the whole practice once we
get into the world of practice of living an ethical life there's a bliss of blamelessness
there's contentment as we practice meditation and the hindrances abate there's
gladness that we're no longer enslaved by these powerful mind states
and as we enter into the jhanas there's all this deep joy and happiness and tranquility of the jaundice that comes
along so the buddha is describing this wonderful gradual path where there's all this benefit this fruit and joy and
happiness and well-being that comes along all the way up to awakening
and when uh and when they when the king hears all this he says wow
yes this is the fruit of the homeless life i'm so inspired from now on i go for refuge the buddha
let the buddha be my teacher and the buddhist kind of nods and ascent and then ajah tattoo is great teaching
and so inspired he says something well i have a lot to do the king has a lot of work to do and
a lot of sensual pleasures to attend to so i had to go back to my job
and uh something like that then and uh and so the king says oh do as you wish and
um and then the king goes off and the buddha's left and he tells his
other his monks who were there and monks and nuns that that that
well if the king had not killed his father in hearing this discourse
he would have attained the first stage of awakening this dharma eye would have opened
but with this heavy you know harm that he caused the fruit of that
the consequence of that is that he didn't say this literally but kind of my interpretation of it
the consequence of that is that his heart is closed to the liberative effect of these teachings
and so that's a fruit of of causing harm in this world that your
heart's heart is much more closed is it permanently closed or not
we don't know my teacher in burma gave lots of stories to me of people he'd known who
not that he killed their parents but soldiers who had killed people and the struggles they had to open up their
heart but they always succeeded to do it to the teachings and to be changed
so this contrast between the king
and the consequence of his actions and the choice of a monastic and the
consequence of their actions their practice and what arises
what's welcomed what's received the fruit that comes from the spiritual life is
the theme of this operatic sutta so
so that's the story for today and we'll continue tomorrow thank you