so hello [Music] hello and welcome to your sangha it's
good to see you good to be with you to practice together
so for today's theme of practice i'd like to invite us to consider
meta loving-kindness friendliness in the form of appreciation
for ourselves
you know normally being human we go through our lives
and given our evolutionary
heritage we tend to focus on what is not going
well what is a problem what is negative especially about ourselves
um [Music] what is wrong with our body
you know if our body is not the right shape size if it's not functioning
the right way if it's not healthy or our habits of mind our behavior our likes
our dislikes we often focus on what isn't going well
you know we spend so much more time doing that than to actually stop and
appreciate wow this body this body this human body
this human body is serving me this this this person who is me
and um so the invitation and and there's of course there's the reasons for that
as i was mentioning are not necessarily great reasons but really convincing and
good reasons because as we have evolved
those ancestors who have passed on their genes they were the ones who were watching out
looking for dangers and what's wrong in the environment those are the ones who
survived those are the ones who survived and managed to pass down their genes
but the ones who focused on the positive and didn't
and and focused on maybe the berries and and what was positive in the environment and
not what was scary and challenging the the wooly mammoth etc they didn't live to pass down their
genes so those are the genes we have we have the ones from the anxious ones from the ones who focus on what's
not going well what's not going right what's scary what's dangerous what's
unpleasant in the environment so knowing that
to bring to bring balance to bring balance by cultivating appreciation for the good
because the more we appreciate the good the wholesome the what's what's good about us the more we
expand the more we expand our capacity for resilience
to take in the good and to also withstand what is challenging what is difficult the waves the
the um both the waves of life as well as the
tornadoes of life you know whatever met what other metaphor you like to use
um we can better withstand if we open up if we cultivate
turning our minds to what is wholesome what is good to increase our
stability our resilience that's one way to think about it
but i want to bring in another perspective tonight and that is um
something that really touched me actually i was i think i've shared many times with you
here that um i have an interest
in many reports that people share people who have clinically died
and what's called near-death experiences and and there are books written on this and various research studies on this and
recently and again who knows who knows not to take it as a word of faith these are just personal
accounts and and yet they can serve as inspiration
they can serve as inspiration so as a way of inspiration not to
to set you know truth that it's one way or the other i was recently listening watching
actually on youtube i can share the pointer later and neil can send it to the google groups
it was a man who who had an experience like that he flatlined in in the er and one experience
they were sharing uh it's quite touching they said
but as they were you know from the corner of the er room as they're being operated on as
they looked down their body for the first time ever in
their life they felt appreciation for who they had been
for who this person was for the very first time they appreciated this person
who was them for the first time they appreciated
this body that had served them through their lives
and is so touching to have that perspective to take on for us to take on
that radical perspective of appreciation we don't have to have an
accident in order to take that perspective on for us to open us up
to this different way of seeing ourselves different way of seeing life our bodies not the habitual way
and also it is said that the closest way to have in in in the experience is
through meditation we can actually access so many of these insights through
actually taking them on playing them
on for size taking them on and just trying them on for size so
so this is the invitation for tonight too as if we were looking at ourselves
from a perspective from a third person perspective as if you're looking down at this body
like wow can we appreciate this person who is me
can we appreciate this body that has served us as well as it has possibly been able to
so i've talked plenty tonight that is the
frame for our practice together so so with that i'd like to invite us
to land in our bodies to arrive
arriving settling embracing
as if for the first as if for the last time greeting this body
not taking it for granted this impermanent body of ours
this gift that is ours and not ours we haven't
chosen it just a miracle
turning the gaze of awareness inward
inviting inviting
hmm
this breath to be received
not the last breath not the future one just this not rushing through the
breaths taking our time
receiving welcoming
celebrating this breath received
this breath celebrated received in the abdomen
turning our awareness inward to our hands
sensations of the hands these amazing hands incredible
appreciating
appreciating the grace of these hands feeling the sensations
bringing awareness to our feet touching the earth
feeling the sensations bottom of the feet
top of the feet
amazing amazing feet so many muscles and bones
then enabler walking
feeling our sit bones our bottom on the cushion
fighting it to let go of any holding tension
relaxing releasing its weight onto the cushion
thereby feeling the contact points
softness hardness
inviting our awareness to imbue our face
our forehead the eyes
hiding them to rest in their socket jaw chin
from her head done to our neck and shoulders hands
chest upper back relaxing the lower back
abdomen sit bones
legs and feet the entire body
this amazing body
receiving the breath breathing on its own no need
to observe the breath from the control tower letting the body
the wisdom of the body receive the breath
appreciating
this breath this in-breath in its entirety
this out-breath in its entirety
received imbibed
as if you're drinking every breath
in this body
filling every cell
from your toes to your hands to your face
appreciating the impermanence of every breath of this
body working as well as it possibly can
serving this being who is me through my life
i'd like to invite you
to take on this perspective to play with try it on for size
as if you're looking at yourself
this being who is you who is you or what was once you
looking down this being [Music]
from the ceiling as if you're in the sailing corner of the room
can our heart open to appreciation to this being
who whom we wear up to a moment ago
this imagined scenario
we are no longer we once were
we appreciate this person this being
their trials their tribulations their intentions
they did their best can we love them wholeheartedly
them appreciate them
for having lived this life for having gone through the labyrinth of this life as best they could
from this perspective can we appreciate this body just as it was
doing its best this mind this heart
can we love can we love non-judgmentally accepting
appreciating non-judgmentally wholeheartedly
given the chance to be this person who is me given the chance to be this person again
can we be kinder gentler more loving accepting
more at peace
with this person who is me
may i love and accept myself just as i am
may i hold myself with kindness
may i love and accept myself
this body this heart this mind
may i hold myself with kindness
care and acceptance
life is uncertain who knows what can happen at any moment
we may stop being this person who is us in this moment
can we love and appreciate this being just
as it is
understanding all the challenges
aspirations
and hold some intentions
the remaining minutes see what's needed would it be helpful to
revisit the perspective of seeing yourself
down below it's a firm corner of the room person
that you once wear does that bring up
appreciation love compassion
the person you have the chance to be to once be
and no longer can't be
or is it helpful to come back perhaps after this
experiment in thought
ah feel yourself here in this body
appreciating
the person you are this body
and your life
for the last moments of this practice
letting go or whatever arose or did not arise
it's all okay appreciating your wholesome intention
appreciating yourself your practice showing up
and relishing the goodness trusting the goodness of your practice
sharing and sharing it with others generously
may all beings be well may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you everyone
thank you for your practice
so [Music] we have time for reflections questions
comments and i wouldn't be surprised if for
some of you at least this practice
proved emotional to take this perspective um or challenging it's all okay it's all
okay and would love to hear what came up for you
so much more i can say but i like to open the floor you can raise your hands
especially if you haven't shared in a while would love to hear from you
and um and you can also type in chat if you type to me individually i won't
read your name just your comment and if you type it to everyone i will
read both your name and the reflection
don says you are on fire awesome thank you accepting myself is difficult
i really appreciate when you said that i did not choose myself yeah
thank you for that don yes we do not choose ourselves isn't that
interesting this life is such a mystery we take ourselves so personally
all the time and yet so much of who we are is not personal
isn't that wild and yet to take that perspective that it's not
personal it doesn't come easily right we need to sit practice in these
creative ways for to really it's not personal
and yet it seems so personal both fred please
i'm afraid what i'm going to ask is going to be just too personal to me but i'm going to ask
it anyway since i have the opportunity so for the last month i've had this
really vaccine tinnitus ringing in my ears after a fall
and it's very difficult to concentrate during meditation
it's very difficult to include the ringing in the experience
more difficult than you know a pain somewhere else and
i'm i'm also exhausted because i'm not sleeping and i wonder if you can just
if you have any advice to me about how i might be able to
um proceed yeah yeah thank you fred thanks for
bringing this up um and this is not the first time
of course that i hear of of something that that of of this condition of
tinnitus so um
and know of other people who have worked with it actually specifically with mindfulness as a way to work with it so
so here's the invitation i have for you fred and others who work with tinnitus or or or other
say pains in the body like this which seem distracting uh disruptive
i would invite you to to investigate with curiosity with openness
with interest if there is an attitude if there's an underlying attitude
of aversion towards this because it really is the aversion
that makes that that hooks it in place and makes it very difficult to work with at the time when
you see the aversion when you work through the layers of a version when it
can be held as just another sound just another ache just another thing
just that that's the moment that it will lose its power
so my intuition my invitation to to explore if there are
either gross levels or sudden level subtle levels of aversion and pushing it
away they're very gross levels there you go fred then that's it that's exactly it
so working with it gently and if the moment comes if the question
comes when the question when the question comes that can i be okay
can i be at peace if this never goes away if it's just
here and the answer comes back yes then that's the moment that you have
freedom it will not bother you anymore you may not even notice it after that
well that sounds wonderful but actually getting there sounds i i don't actually
perceive the course the course is
little by little can i be okay with this just as it is in this moment
the answer might come back no okay then can i be okay with not being okay
with this can i be okay with not liking this evolution yeah i i can accept that
i'm hating this right now so what just acceptance whatever you can accept
will accept that and little by little it will um
[Music] dissolve the the the or rather you'll go through
layers and layers of acceptance little by little so start where you are can you accept that you're hating it right now
oh yes good if you can accept that get relaxed into yeah i can accept that i don't hate
myself for hating it no i accept it if you're there great that's the place
to start see if you can relax into yep i don't like it
ah can i accept that start there see feel the ease in your
body and use that as a starting point to unwind
okay thank you you're so welcome fred
uh one more reflection from christine please
and this needs to be quicker before we go into rooms please christine oh
quicker i don't know about quicker okay then bring it on
yeah i this meditation was highly appropriate to something that i was thinking about
today which is that when i uh
really see how much i have suffered in my life for the
self-hatred that i've lived with um i feel so overwhelmed with regret and
grief that i just can hardly breathe i mean i just like that just hum how much i've lost
and i just and not appreciating myself and i
i just don't and it's so huge this regret i and i and i just don't and
i don't know what to do with it
yeah yeah thank you christine it's
to grieve what to do with it to grieve to grieve it's okay you don't have to
push it away to grieve to just grieve make space for it can you love yourself
and it grieve have to be one or the other
it's okay to grieve without kicking yourself
can you grieve and love yourself because what i'm hearing is that in the grief is a lot of kicking yourself
can you grieve and love yourself does that
does that make sense what i'm the shift i'm suggesting yeah say you're not
and if you want to say something again i see your lips moving but i do oh okay yeah
um can you hear me now yeah yeah i think the kicking myself
is um why why did i do that
how how come how how come i couldn't have done it differently there is no
point my dear in kicking yourself it's it's as you know is throwing perfectly good moments after
moments that are gone so see if you can grieve and love yourself
i think that's the shift so i'm going to leave that with you as a koan and you can come back
to it later if need be okay thank you so i'm going to create the room there's
one more reflection i'll leave that for i'll read it when we come back
but i'm going to create the room style so that you have some time to
check in share be with each other take care of yourself take care of each
other here we go welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed we just have about one quick minute any reflections you like to share
relating to the practice tonight what came up for you any quick ones
especially from the group
thank you oh yeah thank you
yeah i loved it uh i uh certainly on a trip of appreciation down
my whole family tree really down into deep into the roots of my ancestors and um
and and perhaps because i went to like uh susie's uh talk this morning about the
the four elements it reminded me that my ancestral tree goes back beyond
my my immediate blood ancestors found the whole course of of evolution back to
through all of the animal species that preceded the emergence of my species up
out of the the evolutionary process and before the evolution even
the big bang that created all the matter that allowed uh
evolution to even come into existence and before the big bang
the whatever forces that were that made that big bang possible
whatever they were i don't know this is great thank you hugh i love it so not only did this bring up
appreciation for yourself but so many ancestors and causes and conditions this
this wave of appreciation thank you it's beautiful thank you it's a wonderful note
um yeah of appreciation it can can be endless right we start somewhere it's
like a thread it's like a cloth right you keep pulling and pulling the whole cloth is related
um as um uh gosh i'm blanking on who said this but in order the there's a physicist who
said uh in order to make an apple pie first you need to make the whole universe so
in order to make hue first you need to make the whole universe big bang and everything so
uh i see our note bill uh interesting idea i'll think about that
that's a good one and one more reflection that i mentioned earlier was
from someone who said that spontaneously came up for them looking in the mirror and realizing oh there's a
sense of love and kindness for themselves that they usually share for others and not for themselves so a great reminder to be
aware of this more often so dear ones thank you so much for showing up and your practice may all
beings be well may all beings be happy including ourselves
thank you