so good day to everyone and good to be here with you
and the topic uh continues to be for this week samadhi
samadhi meaning usually translated as concentration
and one of the verbs associated with samadhi is abiding
to dwell or abide in these different good qualities of samadhi
and learning to abide is uh
you know is lingering is due is result residing in these states
as opposed to being in these states and striving or pushing or trying to have more
and the tremendous value of when we get settled have landed here in the present moment
feel settled here to learn how to abide in those states
and the biting is not a passive thing exactly though there's very little doing and
it's very consequential which i'll talk about later so to abide also is to be
receptive to abide and allow the goodness of a particular state to
nourish us to penetrate into us so and a lot of samadhi has to do with
letting go and so we could understand it a little bit as
abiding in the goodness of letting go abiding in the nourishment
that happens when we let go so we'll start this meditation
and and we'll do this abiding and receiving of
this nourishment or goodness of letting go of relaxing
so to assume a beneficial meditation posture
with some care to take a posture that will allow you
kind of a maximum amount of relaxation without falling asleep a balance between
remaining alert but allowing for deep in a sense deep body work to happen
as meditation kind of begins penetrating into all the different corners of our muscles
and allowing for deeper and more thorough letting go
and to gently close your eyes and without breathing deeply this time
just simply sitting here i'll direct you to relax different parts
of your body and as those parts relax linger a bit
with whatever good feelings are there with having relaxed kind of let yourself
take in even if the good feeling is a real kind of relief a local relief
of not being tense or maybe there's a pleasure
allow yourself to abide and receive the good feelings that might come
with relaxing so on the exhale then
relaxing the shoulders
releasing the shoulders and
perhaps there's a way to also release and relax the arms and the hands
so from the shoulders all the way down to the fingers
relaxing releasing and then receiving whatever lingering good feelings are there with
that however mild or small
relaxing the muscles of the face
and even if there's also uncomfortable sensations for now receive the comfortable ones the
pleasant ones as you relax your face
as you exhale relax the belly
sometimes harder to feel good feelings with a relaxed belly but maybe there are
some that linger
also in the legs the thighs and the calves all the way
down to the feet is there some the muscles there be released
and feel some good some nice pleasant feeling of vitality or
relief
and then bring your attention to your
breathing and as you breathe as you exhale
see if you can relax your whole body on the exhale
and feel whatever goodness comes from that relaxing
an opening a softening a settling
perhaps more of a sense of flow and vibration in the body
and the exhale itself is a kind of letting go
allow for the full letting go of the exhale
and not always easy to feel but maybe you can feel some parts of the exhale
the release the letting go
as a nourishment as a good feeling
the exhale part of the goodness of the exhale is letting go of thoughts
as you exhale
letting go of thoughts and letting go into the body breathing
and whatever openness receptivity there might be there at the end of the
exhale receive the inhale
let go your thoughts your thinking as you exhale
and allow yourself to feel how that might be good feel good or
pleasant do not be caught up in your thoughts and
thinking and abide rest in
the quiet and openness and receptivity
of awareness in your body
that remains when you let go of your
thoughts
and then as you inhale in the abiding with the breathing
there can be also a receptivity in allowing the inhale to arise
the inhale to arise in the vibrating
flowing tingling vibration of the body
to abide and receive here in this body
and whatever letting go or relaxing you do relaxing the body relaxing the mind
releasing the exhale whatever settling in that happens
feel and sense and abide
in the good feelings that are associated
reside in us in the goodness of it
allow it to nourish you to spread through you
staying close to your breathing
with a letting go of the exhale and the allowing of the inhale
each within the abiding here in the goodness pleasantness
that is also here
letting go into receptive state receptive with your body to the
pulsing vibrating flowing dynamic sensations of the body
allowing them receiving them where part of the goodness
is the receptive state he is the simple abiding and receiving
and to feel the goodness of abiding receiving
this body this body breathing
letting the thinking mind become quieter
so you can more fully abide and receive
so
to abide in whatever goodness
pleasantness enjoyability there is here now
and breathe within that breathe with that
quietly receptively
with an inner quietude that is sensitive available
receptive simply to abide
here and now
with whatever is here trying to make anything happen
just abiding in whatever goodness is
available
so
and as we come to the end of the sitting
to abide here in the present moment
for these last minutes to abide
not to do anything or accomplish anything
but to be at rest or at ease in one own one's own skin and body
and whether you actually can do this well or not you might just imagine yourself
in a circumstance where you can just abide just be rather than do
some place where you feel comfortable and safe and settled
where you have all the time in the world and no pressure
and in this state in the privacy of your own mind and
heart let others the presence of others
abide also here with you
so that others are abiding around you or with you without requiring anything of you
needing anything of you
and in this way perhaps you can open up a kindness a care
maybe even a love good will that it's almost not a doing
but more how the heart vibrates when nothing is needed you feel safe
and you take in the humanity of another person
and without requiring anything that you do or say to the person
to people
can you gaze upon them kindly gaze upon them with goodwill
and may they and all beings be happy
may the people you think of and all others be safe and peaceful
may the people that you consider and all others be free
and may it be that the benefits of this meditation practice
in seeing in unseen ways intentional and unintentional ways may those benefits
spread out to benefit the people around you and the world
around you may the goodness of your meditation
be for the welfare and happiness of all beings yourself and all the rest
may it be their meditation changes the world for the better
[Music]
you