all right so so formally hello and good evening
everyone it's good to see you good to be back
um missed you and finally last week so um
so for this evening
or whatever your time zone might be for this moment in time um
i was thinking it's given that in the united states right now is um
the week of thanksgiving holiday which of course has its historical complications
as we know make and acknowledge and with the theme of giving thanks
let's let's bring in the theme of giving thanks
as it is a beautiful practice it's a beautiful practice in buddhism it's a beautiful practice and
so many traditions um so many traditions to give thanks
to be grateful to have a grateful heart to land into appreciating the
the goodness all the gifts that we receive as human beings
in this life that often we don't acknowledge often we focus on
what is lacking what is missing [Music] what we don't have what is not going
right and instead turning turning our hearts
turning our minds to so many gifts
every moment every moment that we receive that sustain us
and so many different to do this practice of gratitude so with the guided meditation today i'll
introduce a couple of ways for us to engage with and um
[Music] what else do i want to say oh yes um now there is so much research
um on how prac on how the practice of gratitude
makes us happier makes us feel more connected to others
to this flow of goodness the giving and receiving circle the sense of
interconnection and practice of gratitude also
makes us feel more abundant so we become more generous
and in turn share our our abundance with others
so there are so many beautiful aspects to
this practice of gratitude it's not just oh we only do it to make ourselves happy
well that's good too it's not it's it's nice too it's lovely to nourish the heart
and mind so that we can contain more joy and be available for
more challenges more suffering which is every one of us has plenty of that in
our lives so so let's have more joy to be more available for that for more
be able to more be with challenges with more grace when
our heart is full when we turn when we're aware of what is nourishing and what is
[Music] what is good in our lives and also
um has this other dimension not just the
obvious dimension of gladness and goodness and generosity but i want to point out
for us to become aware of this other dimension of gratitude that
is a liberating it it's sustained it supports our freedom
instead of our vision being tight and just focusing on what is challenging
what is difficult it expands our vision it expands our capacity
so that more insight can arise freedom liberation
nibbana arose by any name so
so with that as the
invitation for tonight or setting the stage
let us land let us begin the practice of meditation so
let us land in our bodies see what your body needs maybe you need to move shift a little
bit left and right land in this body
land in your seat in your chair
hello body ah
and as always we start with tilling the soil
collecting collecting the mind the heart before we turn
to our cultivation practice we start we start by landing
just arriving arriving
turning our gaze inward inviting our body to relax to soften
to offer its weight
to the earth to the chair of the cushion
in lieu of the earth
ah letting the feet letting her sit bones
connect land rest
as if sponges soaking
soaking up the sensations of contact connection
so grounding so groundingly
delicious
and inviting every cell of the body to unwind
invite fight every cell
to let go of any tightness or tension
ah
and just be nothing expected
no doing expected
hmm
letting the breath be received
the lower abdomen
perceived by loving awareness
cradled cradled appreciate it
and when each breath in its entirety is appreciated
notice how the mind the heart settles becomes
filled with gladness now hello dear breath hi
thank you here you are
in breath
out breathe
and if thoughts arise it's okay
thank them thank you thank you thought
please come another time and releasing
the thought with generosity if you're releasing a balloon
or a bird into the sky ah
sense of ease letting go
picking up picking up this cradling of the breath
in breath and a breath with awareness
with appreciation
can there be a sense of appreciation
for this moment of just sitting and breathing
this moment of refuge
what if we allow our hearts to light up to be ignited
with the goodness of just this moment
here just
taking refuge sitting and being breathed
maybe you've had a busy day a full day
or you've had a day without sangha and now you're sitting
with sangha where you have a moment to yourself
this moment of connection of awareness
expansive filled with grace
just as it is
this moment has never been
this moment of my life
has never been and never will be again this moment
can i meet it with appreciation can i greet it
with awe with delight
his curiosity interest
with gratitude
knowing that all things are impermanent all things are impermanent
this moment this life the way things are right now in my life
it will change
even if there are challenges this period can i meet this moment with
gratitude as a stepping stone
for opening and if there is there are things that are going well in this moment
can i open up wholeheartedly recognizing their goodness
what what is the blessing right now
in this moment
can i open my heart to it breathe it in fully
deeply appreciating
what is one thing in my life
that i take for granted a blessing that i take for granted
that perhaps there are other beings in this world
wishing for that i take this for glad granted can i
appreciate this blessing
not with shame or guilt but let it nourish my heart
my body my mind not to be not to be taken for granted
let my heart know goodness appreciate blessings
as fullness of our heart with gratitude can inspire generosity can i be grateful for this
really let it in
can you imagine this this thing that you are grateful for
this blessing what if it wasn't in your life imagine your life
in this moment without this blessing
what would your life be like without this use your imagination
yeah squeezing your body squeezing your heart
and now whenever you're ready remind yourself
goodness this blessing is in my life
letting yourself open up to it even more to the goodness of it
having had a vision of life without it
often we can bring more appreciation and gratitude
if we imagine this blessing not being here
say we could imagine our arm or leg being in a cast
not being able to walk not being able to take care of ourselves
to feed ourselves to walk around
but whatever is a lie for you you can imagine that also
so let's say after this practice period he wouldn't be able to get up
without crutches unassisted
from your seat moving around how difficult that would be
imagine going through the day
with your arm with your leg in a cast
i was both in a cast why not
preparing a meal taking a bath
or a shower grooming yourself brushing teeth
the impossibility of going out for a walk
how limiting your life would be perhaps how painful
and guess what your arm your leg is not in the cast
you can get up unassisted after the sit can make yourself tea
brush your teeth go for a walk
your arm and leg are not broken they're not in pain
so much to be grateful for
in the last minutes of the set perhaps considering the gift of your
practice the gift that your practice has been in
your life as support best practice
this opportunity this sangha this medium
what if none of this was in your life
no practice no degree of freedom
insights that you've had none of them this sangha
any sangha
none of that was in your life
if you can imagine that and now letting yourself
ah appreciate appreciate yes yes you have the gift of practice
sangha teachings support oh so much goodness so much beauty
so much grace so much richness
my heart feels so tender
so tender and moist [Music]
gratitude gratitude for this practice
sangha dharma
so much to be grateful for
so much to deeply deeply humbly
be grateful for
may our practice of gratitude open our heart to know its own abundance
open our heart to generosity
to letting go to freedom may all beings everywhere be happy
may they be free
[Music]
thank you thank you for your practice everyone
thank you for being here so much gratitude for sitting together
tonight this moment and as for me towards the
end of this practice as i invited you to reflect on
[Music] what if the sangha wasn't here what if you had never come across the practice
and then imagining that it is in your life for me so much tenderness arose
tears of gratitude appreciation wanting to
kneel and kiss the ground in appreciation
wow wow so grateful so grateful for this
so grateful ah
so so dear ones
the floor is open with your reflections
questions comments appreciations you can type them in chat raise your hand
if you haven't shared for a while thank you for the appreciations on
youtube that i see oh yeah thank you bill
who says wonderful session thank you thank you
bill jane jenny and paul also on youtube
what came up for you what did you notice what worked what didn't
what's coming up for you now how is your heart how is your heart
megan says the visualization resonated with me i have multiple patients right
now with bone cancer two of whom have full length casts on their legs
while i have often felt grateful leaving work for the abilities and health i have
i had not yet attempted to visualize myself in this position with this compassion arose
thank you thank you thank you for that reflection of
of compassion megan appreciate that
yeah yeah all good ben no worries
austin please
hey everybody thank you um yeah reminded me of a stoic practice of
like picturing yourself without something i forget the name of it some
stoic meditation but yeah really reflecting on my health and
gratitude for it and i'm really healthy and i don't think about that like hardly
ever um but i i wanted to ask you
i remember being on retreat with you and you had talked about how
you lots of people when they go to work they get kind of drained from work and then they come home and they say that
they need to like recuperate and kind of fill their cup so that they can go back to work and then kind of
almost like empty their cup and i remember you being on retreat and you were saying
how you gain energy from you could see like 10 yogi's
a day and that you actually gained it i remember you were saying that was mainly through mindfulness of
the body but i was wondering if you could talk about that again
yeah yeah thanks austin first i so appreciate you
sharing and reflecting on on the appreciation for your health that you're
very healthy yay may you continue to be healthy all the time and how you take it for granted and just
really appreciating that that's beautiful [Music] and the sense of being drained
and how you remember me sharing with you that
that the sense of um being nourished from my
work quote-unquote work being with the yogis and seeing many yogis and being nourishing
it is true i i have said that oh it rings a bell it's something i would say
um and that and in fact as you remember well it does come from a sense of mindfulness of the
body really being connected with my body connected here
connected resonating with the person so now the times if i get in my head and to
and energy comes too high up thinking and and engaged too much falling into
emotions then i can lose my balance with being embodied really with the sense of
embodiment emotions thoughts all can be held it can all move
through and there's a sense of um how should i put it there can be a sense
of opening there's a sense of um it's not me not mine
sense of open i guess in some other practices could be called chi or energy kind of moving it's
as if the body is grounded is well you know my mind is grounded in the body and
the body is grounded with the earth so the sense of um yeah the mindfulness of the body
as a friend so and um also being in meetings you know
various things i've noticed the difference if i lose my mindfulness of the body if i unzoom
whether if i have mindfulness of the body and i'm well grounded in my body
being on zoom it's very different for me one is can be very tiring and the other
one can be yeah grounding noticing just letting go of the of the energy as if it's getting
grounded into the earth so those are a few things i can say about that there's so much more to say about my electrons
of the body but is that uh is that okay for now austin
yeah thank you yeah thank you so
dear ones here we are let's uh take time and
engage in the beautiful practice happy making practice tonight the happy making
practice tonight in small groups and the happy making practice tonight is when we
get into our small sanghas of roughly size three the question
the prompt is what are you grateful for what are you grateful for and let's go
around so one person will say one thing they're grateful for the next person says another thing and
then the third person and then the first person again so you go round and round and round
just sharing witnessing what you're grateful for and feeling mudita vicarious joy for one another and
feeling happy for yourself this is such a beautiful happy making practice
so and it's perfect for this week of uh thanksgiving so
i will create the rooms and as always please take care of yourselves
please take care of each other and um yeah what are you grateful for maybe
start with for the person whose name is closest to the beginning of the alphabet
alphabetical order let's make it simple okay have fun here we go opening the rooms
hello everyone welcome back welcome back the rooms are closed
so we have a couple of minutes for any reflections either from the practice or from being in groups
what you notice what it was like to share and hold witness
what you and others are grateful for so please debra
i i just realized i really enjoy practicing gratitude and in my family i
was always the control freak at the thanksgiving table wanting everyone to go around
and every year my brother hated like a few people hated it and my mother just
loved saying how much she was grateful about the children and she'd cry and it
was just beautiful so i just feel kind of like maybe vindicated or something i don't
know what the word is but thank you thank you thank you for this practice
thank you debra oh that is sweet it's sweet to to hear and and and also to
appreciate you know the particularities of of all family members right they're
just the way they are so it's it's pretty sweet yeah thank you for that
and please okay um yeah i changed my zoom setup so it might
be like 10 times more reliable than it used to be see um i also am really grateful for a
moment that sounds similar to what i understood of debra's a teacher who probably several people
here might know oren sopher um sort of gave a talk that like was my clicking point to
um to not experience gratitude as being a performative thing i just like it's
amazing how much i completely at the age of 24 maybe
thought that just like the my whole life gratitude had been this you should be grateful for that or you know let's go
around say we're grateful for as a chore that like you're performing for other people and oran like gave a gave the
metaphor of of just like gratitude is like ringing a bell and i won't go into the the three steps of that except for
the last one which is let it ring which is just to say feel good about good stuff in your life and that's like so
relatable and so much better than i thought before so i'm like super
grateful for that moment and then like over the years since then gratitude has been a really fundamental
practice in my life beautiful thanks so much for sharing
that then that that gladdens my heart so much yeah it's it's a thing as you
brought up it's really that performative it's the should aspect that you should be grateful or we feel like
we should be grateful it's the shirt that really takes the joy out of gratitude it's the show but you don't
have to be grateful you really don't it just it feels good to be grateful you can you
can be if you want to but there's no should um so i think that really makes all the
difference so thanks so much for for sharing your aha moment so beautifully yay yay that is so lovely
so that is all the time we have tonight folks it's 7 p.m so let's bring um
let's bring it to a close when i see your note but not going into it right now so
we'll save that for another time so thank you all thank you for you showing
up for your practice for being here thank you thank you thank you you make
up happy hour so may all beings be happy may all beings be well may all beings know
their own abundance including ourselves
thank you all take good care bye bye