so hello and welcome again welcome a warm welcome to every single one of you every
single one of us so for our practice today we are going to continue with
exploring our new Brahma vihara which we started on Friday exploring mudita
vicarious Joy also translated has um uh empathetic
Joy it's it's happiness for for others happiness and we start where it's
easy um so this this practice of mudita um in poly the word is mudita m u
d t it's a transliteration uh in English is the
practice of gladdening the heart and mind it's the fastest way to become
happy is if you find yourself heavy and just bring to mind someone you care
about and their Good Fortune someone who you just feel happy for when they're
happy and and let their happiness shine through your heart sense of happiness
for their happiness so tonight what we'll do is that we'll um turn our hearts to an we
start with an easy category and then after we've primed our heart and we've
practiced with the easy category then we'll turn our attention to ourselves to
feel happy for our own blessings to feel a sense of celebration celebration in
the heart for blessings that we often have and we take for granted we turn our
hearts to that and guess what when we become happy for our own happiness the
practice of mudita when turned to ourselves becomes
the practice of guess what gratitude yay of course so that's where
the practice of gratitude is hiding in the Brahma viharas a lot of times people
say so where is gratitude in Buddhism there's not much talk of it well it's there it's in the Brahma vhar it's in
mudita when you turn mudita to yourself it becomes gratitude when you're happy for your own happiness
that's what arises the heart becomes grateful so see for
yourself anything else I want to say for frame oh yes and one thing I want to say to frame and we can talk more about it
afterwards is the far enemy of this practice as I mentioned is is Envy so
sometimes when we are trying to feel happy for somebody else's happy happiness oh we want what they have Al
so the kind of contraction come up in the in the heart if that comes up it's
okay this is a purification practice you're not defective you're not doing it wrong it can bring those feelings up it
may not it might and if that may happen please turn
towards that pain that's suffering in that moment with your own meta with your
own compassion because when Envy arises we the ones hurting in that moment so
instead of trying to muscle your way through it musle through your way with mud make it karuna make it compassion
turn to oh sweetie it's okay it's okay you want this also it's all right it's
okay so holding turning with compassion and
care towards whatever is arising so as long as you're doing that turning
towards love care warmth towards whatever is arising you're doing this
practice great so anything else I want to say yeah I'm
I've been looking forward to practicing together today I've actually been practicing as I've been remembering
mudita just makes my heart glad to bring that in um so let's practice it together
and again whatever arises whether it's mud or it's opposite bring kindness to
it and it's all good so so let's get started let's get
started so I like to invite you if you
would get into your meditation posture you may want to move shift lie down it's
all good see what your body needs
as always we start by settling in the
body settling in the body with the
breath arriving arriving and tilling the soil of
presence becoming present in this moment
softening [Music]
softening letting
go e
connecting with the entirety of the INB breath and the out breath
and with age out breath letting go into the body relaxing
softening letting go of thoughts [Music]
preoccupations taking Refuge the Simplicity of this
moment you don't have to have those thoughts right now do
you can gently tell them not now
come back after this practice
please e
just this moment just this breath and thank your thoughts not
now not now
later e
feeling your feet your
legs your sit bones contacting the
Earth Earth on Earth feeling grounded stable here
here
e
e e
arriving continuing to arrive and settle and in this moment in this
body giving your
heart letting it be
immersed with presence in this moment of being
alive in this
breath
e
e e
now I would like to invite you if you
would bring to mind someone who's been a
benefactor they've supported you they've been there for
you at some point in your life this definition of benefactor can
be pretty wide pretty loose it could be a parent or a teacher
or relative ative or a coach or a friend a good
friend can even consider our pets sometimes our benefactors with their
unconditional love and care someone who's
been supportive in some way in your life not in every way but in some way
where there is a sense of appreciation sense of connection heart
connection you feel safe in their presence there's a sense of goodness
appreciation good will for this for this being
for the support they' have offered
you and bringing them to mind as clearly as
possible with a sense of connection and appreciation for their support
let your heart feel the goodness of this appreciation this
connection to this being whether or not they're in your
life at this point
and now bringing to mind some aspect of their life that is a
blessing for them doesn't have to be every aspect
that's that's fulfilling but one aspect of life of their being that they feel happy
grateful for
and let yourself as if you were witnessing their happiness their
joy for this blessing in their
life as if you were holding witness presence witnessing
them feeling happy and
grateful and let your heart shine with gladness with
reflective happiness witnessing their
happiness and gladness notice what it comes what comes
up in you
happiness for their happiness let yourself feel it in your
body in your heart center connect to this gladness to this
Good Will in your heart
you can stay with the feeling [Music] alone or say the phrases of meta the
phrases of MTI
silently reciting if you wish optionally
I'm happy for your
happiness or your happiness makes me happy makes me glad
gives my heart
Joy or may your good fortune
may your blessing [Music]
continue may it increase may it never
end fully well knowing that there is impermanence as the
law of human condition and yet without attachment to
outcome we're sharing our good will or wish for their Good Fortune to continue
without attaching to it necessarily continuing but just sharing with
generosity the sense of abundance of our heart may it continue may it never end
and as a blessing as a wish of generosity from our
end may your happiness [Music]
increase may it never end
at any point if it wains your feeling your practice bring up their
image as clearly as you can connecting with their felt sense with them taking
delight and happiness in their Good Fortune feeling feeling in your bones
their happiness
notice how that can light up your heart and gladness naturally in
connection e
the more you connect with their felt sense their
image with their happiness the more stable this practice can
become e
letting your body be relaxed soft receiving the
breath connecting with each breath to a reflect
Joy generosity of your heart
and now i' would like to invite you to bow to this
[Music] benefactor thank
them for supporting your practice of cultivating generosity of heart in
mudita vicarious Joy now turning your attention
your awareness to some blessing some goodness
in your own life that you feel grateful for that you
feel happy about some blessing you feel happy about
and bring it to
heart and see what it feels like if you said the phrases of meta for
yourself I'm happy for my own happiness
my happiness brings me
joy may this blessing may this Good Fortune of
mine may it increase may it continue may it [Music]
increase may it never
end again not attaching to
outcome with a relaxed heart and mind sharing your own good will for yourself
without tightness of attachment as if you throwing flower
petals blessings upon yourself I'm happy for my happiness
notice notice if it turns if it transforms this
happiness to a sense of
gratitude abundance of heart as if
you would want to kneel and kiss the ground for this
blessing maybe maybe not simply
notice I'm happy for this blessing in my life
my heart beams with
gladness for this Good Fortune of mine
may this
abundance continue and never cease may my happiness continue
I'm happy for my own happiness
I take delight and my good fortune in this
blessing of mine
allowing yourself to feel your own gladness your happiness for this
blessing for this goodness in your life relishing it
with generosity of heart letting yourself relish this goodness
staying in the present moment not in the past not in the
future not with fear right here right now in this moment
present with appreciation for what
is
e e
and now [Music] inviting inviting back your benefactor with whom you
practiced earlier bringing them back and the two
of you now together bringing to mind both of your
blessings theirs and
yours allowing yourself to feel happy for both of your good fortune as
different as they may be different colors
flavors a sense of gladness for Good Fortune for goodness and in the
world the circumstance I'm happy for our happiness
for our Good
Fortune May our Good Fortune
continue may it never s may it never Seas May It
Grow seeing both of you siblings in gladness
appreciate it appreciate of joy
[Music]
thank you for your practice
so to me it felt like time flew when practicing vicarious
Joy practicing mudita such a lovely
practice so we have some time and you're invited dear sa to share
your comments your observations your Reflections what you
observed what was surprising what worked what didn't what was challenging it's
all welcome especially if you haven't shared in a while please raise your
um your Zoom hand in reactions the
bottom or you can type in chat either PR privately to me I won't say your name or
or publicly and would love to hear from
you anything is
welcome Ben asks is this practice related to techniques of magnifying Pleasant Sensations as an entry way to
Janna um not not exactly um it's
not it's no the way you're talking about it it's not about a technique of
magnifying Pleasant sensation as an entryway to Jana
no and yet there are for all the Brahma viharas there are oh let me say what
janas are Jas are states of absorption there when in the practice of samata
samadi translated as concentration when one comes back to the same object over
and over and over again the mind can have a sense of
stability profound stability that can feel like absorption with the object as
if the mind is merging with the object often in the west we teach uh
absorptions with anapanasati with the breath but there are many different
objects so there are 40 different objects in fact in in this uh
tradition so related to your question Ben um there are absorptions there are
Jas or states of stability for each of the four Brahma viharas so MTI vicarious
Joy if one practices it keep keep practicing keep practicing the mind will
become stable and um will get will reach
absorption which feels very different has a different flavor than absorption
through the breath so that it answers your question Jeanie
says I chose my aunt as benefactor she died yesterday morning a it was very
sweet that is very sweet thank you Jeanie for sharing that thank you so
much for sharing that yeah yeah Ben says it sounds like rever
mita's reverse anxiety where anxiety is a vicious cycle Mita as you taught is a
virtuous cycle absolutely it is a virtual cycle yes
bringing the mind to goodness to gladness and there is so much to be glad
happy about for others or for ourselves not just turning our hearts to what's challenging and
difficult any the other Reflections what was easy what was challenging what you discovered what
surprised you especially if you're new would love to hear from you hear your wisdom and
please know that whatever you share is is a gift to the community Jerry says I
had forgotten about a benefactor and realized how I am where I am right now
because of him it made more it made more of aware it made me more aware of a
deeper sense of gratitude beautiful thank you for sharing that Jerry I feel the same way with the with the friend I
was bringing to mind was just such a lovely sense of gratitude and connection
happiness for them I couldn't stop smiling so lovely
take a pause maybe a beat for one more reflection especially if anybody wants to to to say it out
loud and of course we can reserve time on the on the other end when we come back from
groups Charles Le please oh yeah thanks um
I just I I have this this feeling of
of like this this this light um and uh
what I thought of was actually a Christian prayer that she Sav for the
dead which is you know may light Perpetual shine upon shine upon them or
shine upon you but uh but certainly was not thinking of of of death but but was
definitely thinking may just you know the the the beam of the sun shine warmly on on all
beings that is absolutely beautiful thank you charlee thank you for sharing
that as as you said it out loud I was feeling the generosity the The Good Will
of ah May the Sun May the may this beam
upon you and it just it's oh what how lovely to connect these two practices of
the heart how lovely yeah yeah how lovely to pra to
connect them and thank you for sharing that makes me happy lovely so dear ones so the invitation I
have oh one more comment from Jamie I realized my benefactor blessing was a
product of her own efforts and my vicarious happiness turned into admiration oh lovely I love that thank
you profound how these wholesome states of mind can be
connected so for our practice in community tonight before you hop off
listen to what it is so the invitation is as we get into groups
of three um after
maybe well maybe we'll just speak start speaking um share something that brings
you Joy something that you're grateful for in your life one thing and the other
two people will appreciate will have appreciative Joy vicarious joy for your
blessing and then somebody else will share something and then the third person and then you'll again share and
then the second and third and you'll go around and round sharing something you're grateful for while the other two
really ah have the sense of mudita may your blessing continue may it may it
never end may it grow and then you'll get to do it for others it's just such a
fun practice to do now in real time now that you've done it in your mind it's
just see what it's like it's just as I describe it I'm actually getting chills so see what it's like to actually do it
in real real time and be held Witness by others and hold others witness so that's
the invitation then I hope you you stay especially if you have a tendency to hop
off and not participate see how happy making this can be
so so I'm going to create the rooms
and um here we go opening them up
okay welcome back everyone their rooms are closed and we have a couple of minutes
for any observations how how were the groups
what was the practice like to share to share your joy with each other I see lots of people smiling this is great so
we'd love to hear from you please especially if you haven't spoken
yet Joy is infectious says Jerry yes
anybody would like anybody anyone who's smiling ear to ear wants to okay Fred here please there you
go and not so much on our group but I was I was realizing that the the person
I picked as my benefactor who's in fact going to drop by and be my benefactor
again tomorrow um would choose me as as her benefactor too and um and might be
surprised that I would think of her as my benefactor but um there's a kind of reciprocity or
maybe not not even that quite it's a kind of mutuality that's really
uh at the heart of it yeah yeah and isn't that sweet that people can be our
benefactors in in a way that they've supported us not in a big way of being the benefit but just in a way they've
supported us without them really knowing or us being theirs it's just such a beauty in the mutuality that you just
pointed out so thank you for sharing that yeah and Julie
please um uh I just wanted to share that um coming into the um group tonight I
was feeling really tired just a long day
at work and yada yada yada and um it's
amazing how connection can be so energizing and how we we I I thought I
was tired you know and perhaps physically I may still be but um when we
connect like this just as a a larger group like this and then in our smaller
groups it's just like amplifies it and then we get to bring it back here and
then we get to say goodbye and we get to take it into our you know our immediate worlds here and it just when I Envision
it it just you know and on and on and on so thank you all for being here because
without all of you I couldn't be experiencing this right now
so thank you Julie you're getting lots of Hearts as you're saying and it's very
sweet thank you you for saying this and thank you for being here and supporting everyone and yourself in this practice
it's so lovely to hear gives me joy yay
and now Siri's talking to me she said right back at you I guess it's right
back at you Julie s it's serious message that's too funny um few Reflections the
Taren says the most obvious Joy blessing is this practice yes ah isn't it being
being having access to the Dharma and this practice is is a blessing
indeed and Mari Christine you're right Terren it is pure Bliss and how beautiful Julie says Susan and a bunch
of other Hearts so a what a lovely note what a lovely note of joy to end our
practice together so thank you everyone thank you for showing up and doing this
practice I for yourself and for everyone whose lives yours touches may all beings
be filled with joy and happiness and gladness may all beings be free
including ourselves
[Music]