uh welcome everyone all of you here in person delightful to have you and
still feels very special to have people together and meditating and i've been alone here for so long
uh so thank you for being here being in practicing in community
and those of you who are on youtube watching and welcome as well and
i you haven't been forgotten even with the people here in the room and and i appreciate seeing the greetings in
the chat and perhaps on youtube you if you log down a little bit early
you see the people kind of walking in across past the camera and hopefully that just makes you
kind of delighted to see that there's more life here at imc than there has been
and uh so and it feels kind of peaceful in here
it's a little bit more peaceful for me that i hadn't thought about it before but a little more peaceful having people here to meditate
than to have i have some of you don't you ever saw the shots of the umbrellas the light umbrellas i have here and
different paraphernalia and stuff that and so somehow it feels very nice to be here
with all of you so thank you
so um
so meditation is so many different things for different people
and i certainly don't want to narrow it to any one thing
i think uh it's many things for each person over a lifetime of practice meditation
has different functions different meanings different it expresses different things it
realizes different things it's a it's a wonderful varied kind of thing it doesn't even though might look similar
just sitting quietly with the eyes closed the range of things that it can be about are quite
broad and wide and wonderful i don't want to narrow it to one thing only but
i kind of today my feeling a little bit about meditation is uh i'm associating with being on
pilgrimage and uh a sacred pilgrimage
and uh so you you know in the old days they would walk in
pilgrimages you can still do that and go to some pilgrimage sites around the world and
uh kyushu with ireland and japan they have pilgrimage routes and spain they
have el camino and different things and the and uh so the place we're
walking is uh in our own body and mind and sometimes i've thought that the
rhythm of the breath the breathing as we breathe is kind of like the rhythm of walking in
in the time of the buddha that's the only meaning of transportation except for a few very rare kind of wealthy people who had
chariots or something but buddha walked
walked and walked and walked across the plains of india
and uh at a time where there were no asphalt and no electricity and no cars
and and there's something happens in the rhythm of walking
the simplicity the groundedness of it that i think connects people to their bodies connects
people to their environment connects people to the present moment
so for meditation the rhythm of the walking the pilgrimage is done with partly doing the
breathing and just the rhythm and the steadiness and
we're kind of lucky that for most of us unless you have a pacemaker or something
you know we're just sitting quietly with the natural material of life that just like
the buddha did when he sat and closed his mind close his eyes that
sitting with the breathing is the same as the buddhas the sensations of the body are probably
very similar it's the same pilgrimage route same sacred ground that we're going through
and that's the same before there was traffic and cars and electricity and the
complications of life so it's a connection to something that's um
you know it's probably the wrong word to use but it's a word that's kind of in my heart
it's something primordial that we connect to here in this pilgrimage of sitting and being with the
moment so if that uh connotion is nice for you you might think of this next sitting as
a pilgrimage if it's not nice for you then it's more than welcome just let go of it
so to as soon a
posture that respects this pilgrimage we're on
respects this entering into a sacred area sacred ground
entering into the domain of where the buddha traveled
in his meditation and maybe lower your gaze
relax your focus of your eyes
and if it's comfortable for you to gently close your eyes
and to establish yourself here in this primordial world of our
body and breathing to be reminded of it
you might take a few long slow deep breaths
deep enough so that
it's kind of a conscious
engagement with breathing the exhale
long enough that this conscious engagement with releasing letting go
settling in
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and part of the art of relaxing at the beginning of meditation
is to relax so that the breathing is a little bit more
easeful or that you can connect more to your breathing
and so to relax the muscles of your face
soften in the shoulders
especially when relaxing the shoulders if they relax
you're gonna be relaxing into the chest and the breathing
relaxing the belly
not to try too hard at all try just lightly
but there is an art to relaxing in the belly both on the inhale and the exhale
the diaphragm does the work and the belly stays relaxed
and maybe you've entered into some sacred space
special place and it was natural for your mind to become more calm
more quiet in the stillness the peacefulness of the
place out of respect for the place
and so to enter into this body of yours here
as the pilgrim land of their
pilgrimage then the breathing
the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out is how you walk across this land or
through this land one inhale at a time
one exhale at a time
and perhaps have no more ambition with your breathing
than to be present for the next inhale the current exhale
no need to measure your success by
stringing together many breaths in a row in mindfulness just be fully present for this step this
breath here
quiet
allowing the breathing to carry you the breathing to do you
rather than you doing the breathing
then as we come to the end of this sitting
one of the gifts you can bring to the world
is whatever inner peace you have
and if you have no inner peace one of the gifts you can give the world
is the practice you do to find that peace
to connect to it it's one of the great noble endeavors
it's the practice to find that peace
and may we do that not just for our own sake may we do it to contribute to the
welfare and well-being of this world
to help other people be able to find their peace
or to help others feel peaceful unthreatened
as they go through their life peace is a precious commodity
may through this practice that we do may the goodness of it spread out into
the world may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings
be free
thank you
so what's been on uh in my heart my mind lately
is the story of the last days of the buddha's life there's a text called the mahaparinibano
which is the longest suta the longest discourse the longest kind of text from this early tradition
that is also unique in being kind of a travelogue it kind of describes the
travels that buddha did in the last time period of his time and it kind of
also is set up to be maybe because it was the buddha knew he
was dying he was old to prepare his community for his departure and
his absence there and so giving his last teachings his last instructions
at this crucial point but as also you get to see this man walking across india and how he engages
with his sickness old age and death and dying and
it's i think it's quite inspiring to see the conscious careful
considerate way in which he went about his last period of time
so i wanted to share that and talk a little bit about it and
the story of the last days of the buddha's life less days last months it's
the text itself might span something like some we don't know exactly somewhere
between six and nine months of time and uh it kind of bookends his path of
practice and he refers to how he started in this text he refers to how he started his practice 50 more than 50 years
before when he was 29 and now he's about 80.
and and there's a kind of i think mostly probably most likely a myth about the
buddha's beginning of his path but you know he started he was 29 it's
you know what what brought him at that age ripe age to engage in spiritual practice and
set out for his uh to seek for some solution to his suffering
the classic myth is that uh he was uh kind of a prisoner of the palace
uh until that age that somehow his father wanted to protect him from
the sufferings of the world and so kept him kind of in this uh
within the palace walls and he had different palaces that he moved between but he was protected from seeing
some of the challenges that people live under and uh and i can imagine that probably any
of us if we lived that kind of way kind of cooped up and
in a wealthy suburb growing up that way and you know with
the walls around their compound and everything that there probably be some frustration some challenge some feeling like this is
not life this is not you know not that connected and there to be some kind of restlessness and maybe even built up
pressure and that takes the form of the buddha then jumping over the wall
sneaking out and uh and then they say he snuck out four times
and uh each time he saw a different one of what's been called the heavenly messengers
and uh and when i was 10 or 11
i was in nepal and uh and uh
in kathmandu and kathmandu was pretty simple city town when i was there in 1965 i went back 20 years later and it
i don't think there were any asphalted roads when i was there and uh
in the dirt road in front of the palace the king lived and uh
but it was the first time i saw a body a body of a child being carried down to the river to be
burnt then died and so there was like that so i can imagine it kind of so the
buddha buddha saw these three heavenly messengers first trip out he saw someone who was sick
it says that he never knew anybody was sick before him maybe was really sick
for something and so he was shocked and he he was told this is the nature of life this what
happens to people next time he went out he saw an old person that shocked him
because he was live such a protected life right and he was told this is what happens if
you're lucky enough you get old and the next time he went out he saw
what i saw when i was 11 and you saw someone who was dead
and and he was told that's what happens and the fourth time he went out he saw
a ascetic a spiritual seeker renunciant and the renunciant was somehow just
walking through town very peacefully and he'd never seen anybody who embodied such kind of peace
it's something about the renunciant got his attention and he and i get to to kind of indicate
how that's possible in this world of sickness old age and death the world of turmoil of restlessness of this pressure
this probably this deep
deep need that he had from being so cooped up that there was a solution there was a
way out there was some some other way another approach to life so he saw these four heavenly messengers
and that sparked him to then to actually leave his palace life to jump over the wall fifth time
and to go off to become a renunciant himself a contemplative
and which he did for the next over 50 years of his life
and then at some point he had a solution to his suffering he became enlightened and then he taught
and then he comes to the end of his life and there's kind of a wonderful
kind of parallel or something repeating of the same thing
of sickness all these heavenly messengers but this time he's the heavenly messenger
it it the story depicts him as being an old person
depicts him as being sick repeatedly sick in this last days of his life
and depicts him as dying and he's the renunciant he's the peaceful one
he's the messenger of what's possible in this life that we can resolve our suffering and somehow
become a peaceful a messenger of peace a teacher of peace
an embodiment of peace so it's kind of like a wonderful completion to have that at the end of
his life that he becomes these heavenly messengers so we become the dharma
the dharma is not just something to treat as a you know as an external thing
we tap into touch into it periodically it's possible to become it in some very profound way
and um so when he when he's when he had started off practicing this you know
whatever it was he was feeling as a young man when he was 29 that he felt he had to
leave the palace leave his leave his marriage his family even what that pressure was like inside of
him we get a little bit more sense of this from this um
which is probably you know closer to probably what actually happened to him than the myth of going out and seeing
the heavenly messengers so he's talking about how he was
what what he was feeling before he became enlightened
and it's kind of just is describing his distress and so here he is not not
enlightened yet he hasn't discovered his peace yet so he's a distressed young man
violence gives birth to fear just look at people
and their quarrels i will speak of my dismay
and the way that i was shaken seeing people thrashing about like fish
in little water and seeing them feuding with each other
i became afraid the world is completely without a core
everywhere things are changing
i felt discontent at seeing only conflict to the very end
then i saw an arrow here hard to see embedded in the heart
pierced by this arrow dash about in all directions
when the arrows pulled out they don't run and they don't sink
and then uh it goes on a little bit then there's one more verse i want to read that the
maybe a little bit captures what the results of pulling out the arrow
let's give the instruction he gives for others what was before
let it wither away what will be later
do nothing with it not grasping what's in between
you'll live at peace so don't be too caught up in the past or
the future live here this is where the peace is to be found
so in this text then the the story of his last days
um he's it's uh some of what he wrote there is still
true and you kind of have to read a little bit into the text and some
of it's pretty explicit but the top his time as he was dying is changing the world that he knew
is radically changing and
and uh you know if you're old enough that's what you see sometimes but some of the challenges that we have
in our modern times were challenges that they had back then and isn't like our challenges is to have a little bit
different technology that goes with it but the uh but uh you know this human challenges
are so similar back then with the buddha his time he had to live with this as well
and the text begin opens with a king uh he's in the town living in the town
for the time being where the king lives and the king sends his messenger as minister to the buddha
with the instructions that he wants to check in with the buddha about how good ideas for him to attack
his neighboring country that's how it begins wars afoot
now the king who wants to go attack neighboring his neighboring country
he killed his own father who was a friend of the buddha and they'd spent many decades kind of
you know in contact with each other so that represents you know that
things were changing and not what they had been for the buddha the other king who's even closer to who
lived further to the north uh he also had been usurped
by his son just uh in the last year or so the buddha's life
and it was sent into exile and died in exile and uh
and it's possible why the buddha was way down near rob
rajager in india about about 107 80 miles from
where he was going to die from his home country and uh
and uh so there was all this turmoil political turmoil going on in this time and war
was afoot and there's other kind of legends that that uh during that last
year of the buddha's life there was even that his own home country was attacked and first attacked and repelled and then
attacked and then many people killed and
so that's kind of the background that's kind of for the this
the buddha is starting to walk from raj gear
north towards his home country he's an 80 year old man
and uh or so and he's walking across the plains of india
and the distance in some ways is not so great but he ends up walking about 180 miles
but he takes about six to nine months to do that he stops for the reigns retreats along the way
and he stops many places along the way i think someone who is relatively fit could probably do that walk you know in
three weeks and so he's taking his time he's not in a hurry and i just love this idea that
he's not in a hurry maybe because he's uh old and tired and sick and creaky that maybe he has to
walk really slow and take his time and rest a lot one of the repeated refrains in this last text is the buddha telling his
fellow monks or traveling with him i'm tired
let's go sit down i'm tired i need to lay down you don't have i don't think you see
that almost anywhere else in the sutras but this happens a repeatedly as a man who needs to rest
and so he starts heading north and
comes across more evidence of war is about to happen between these two countries that he spent good part of his
adult life visiting and traveling through and teaching and
he goes a little bit further and he gets learns that he has two main
most senior disciples sariputta and muklayana and he learns that
sariputta has died you know and then he learns that magliana his other senior disciple had been killed
so things are changing and you know this is what he's living in so and the buddha just seems like the sense
i get from the text he's just walking peacefully calmly steadily he's not affected by this he certainly
knows it but somehow his peace is more powerful than what's happening
around and and kind of from some of the things he says uh it's kind of like he it it the life
around him is i ain't different than what can be expected
and so he's not like fighting it or he's not
surprised by it he's just walking peacefully calmly living his life teaching doing his final teaching that
he has to do as he goes along but in it he's the he's you know he's
the heavenly messengers um
so he stopped at some point for what's called the reigns retreat a three to four month period where monastics are
staying one put in one place supposed to be during the monsoon season
and so he was doing that during the reigns he was attacked by a severe sickness
with sharp pains as if he were about to die but he endured all this mindfully
clearly aware and without complaining he thought it is not fitting that i should attain
final nibana without addressing my followers and taking leave of the order of monks
i must hold this disease in check by energy and apply myself to the force of life
so it's a powerful statement that you know there's you know you couldn't go down to the local doctor and get
some you know little medicine to pump him up or keep him going and not feel pain there wasn't such thing so he had
to kind of apply himself in practice and energy and and so kind of and keep his life force
going not to let it go up go out i've heard that there are people come to a juncture and
when they get old or sick where the um you know you can almost feel the choice
between still keeping the life energy going and and then letting it dissipate
and move into death so he decided to stay stay alive he had still more work to do
um and uh and then his uh
uh when he gets better from his sickness uh his main attendant a monk named
ananda uh came to him and said i have seen the buddha i've seen you in
comfort and i've seen you patiently enduring when you're sick
and when i saw you this way sick my body was like a drunkard's
i lost my bearings and things were unclear to me because of the buddha sickness
the only thing that was of some comfort to me was the thought the buddha will not attain
final nibbana until he has made some statement about the order of monks
so the last class instructions you know and uh but here's you know again
everything's kind of falling apart here his senior disciple says he's like kind of lost it when the buddha was
dying so the buddha says you know the word and then answers uh it says this
about the final statement to the order of monks but ananda what does the order of
monastics expect of me i have i have taught the dhamma
making no inner or outer meaning no inner esoteric teachings that's secret
and you know in the public teachings i've made no distinction between inner and outer or the secret or the special
teaching and that uh i have no teach teacher's fist
in respect to teachings teacher's fist apparently is that you hold you hold things inside
hidden in teachers in your fist and you only give it to people if they do something
you know so apparently that was something people would do there was a there were other religions at times with the buddha where there were clearly
secret doctrines and only taught to some people it never could be shared with other people
so he didn't that's not his way and then he says it's interesting
if there is anyone who thinks i shall take charge of the order the monastic
order or that monastic order should refer to me
let him make some statement about the order let him do what he does but
i the buddha doesn't think in that way so why should i make a statement about
the monastic order i think we're saying he's not assigning anyone to be the successor there's no one who's going to
be the leader of it and then he goes on
this is a very touching description of the buddha being old
ananda i am now old worn-out venerable
one who has traversed life's path i've reached the term of life which is
80. just as an old cart is made to go by being held together by straps
so my body is kept going by being strapped up it's only when i withdraw my attention
from outward signs from outward experiences of the world
and by the cessation of certain feelings quieting down of certain feelings
and i enter into deep concentrated meditation called the sign list that
my body knows comfort remember there's no pain medication back
then right so who knows what he kind of physical pain he had and so but he had this powerful mind of
meditation that he had ability to drop into and so he was able to find his peace and comfort there and maybe refresh there
remember he was trying to kept his life force going i suspect that this deep meditation is part of what helped that continue
and then he gave as one of the most important last teachings that of his teaching career
uh so therefore it starts it therefore maybe therefore you know given that
we're all uh you know going to get sick gold and dice all of
us someday or there will become at least one of the heavenly messengers
at least one and some of you'll probably be two some three
and hopefully some of you may quickly you know they'll be the last one the last heavenly messenger the
person who walks peacefully in this world
so the voice said therefore you should live as islands unto yourselves
being your own refuge with no one else as your refuge with the dhamma as an island with a
dhamma as your refuge with no other refuge and how does one live as an island unto
oneself with no other refuge here
a person abides contemplating the body as body earnestly clearly aware mindful
and having put away all hankerings and fretting for the world
and likewise with regard to feelings mind and mind objects
this is how a person lives an island onto oneself
with oneself as one's only refuge so this is what he gives his mindfulness practice
four foundations of mindfulness so the last thing the buddha one of the
last teachings the buddha gives is not a doctrine but rather a teaching about practice
instructions for practice and this he repeats in different ways
as he goes along here that practice is what he's interested in
and so he has another place where he teaches
those matters which i have discovered and proclaimed should be thoroughly learnt by you
practice developed and cultivated so this holy life may endure for a long
time that it may be for the benefit and happiness of many people
living out of care for the world for the benefit and happiness of gods and humans
so this is a powerful statement i think where he's talking about this is what he discovered
i'm going to tell you what i discovered and you should take this in and learn this well
but not only for your own sake but for the welfare and happiness of others just going to be kind of a universal benefit
for the world what a wonderful thing to be dedicated to so here's going to tell you what he
discovered and what he says
are practices and he gives a list of practices that he discovered
so again practice is what's important for him so the list is the four foundations of
mindfulness the four right efforts the four roads are to power the five spiritual faculties the five mental
powers the seven factors of enlightenment and the noble eightfold path
so this is uh so that's quite a you know list but you know that what i wanted to emphasize here at the
end of his life he's emphasizing practice and you'll see he comes back to that again a little bit later as it goes
along here so he's going along walking north slowly
resting along the way and at some point he
is invited to meal by a local blacksmith who provides him with some
local food that we don't know exactly what it was there's a lot of you can't believe all the scholarship around
trying to figure out what food this is but it's either some kind of mushroom
it's called pigs the light so it's either the mushrooms that pigs like or it's some
pork dish but we don't you know we don't know but probably the most likely thing is some kind of
mushroom and uh that apparently is uh maybe maybe even poisonous or something
so um after having a meal with a blacksmith the buddha was attacked by a severe
sickness with bloody diarrhea and with sharp pains as if he were about
to die but he endured all this mindfully and clearly aware and without complaint
so again here we have you know sometimes we you know the image we have on the altar here of the buddha which is quite
common is you know the buddha is always well poised and healthy and young and
embodiment of the ideal and sometimes we kind of project this uh ideal spiritual
perfection to the buddha like him certainly he just kind of floated in a cloud and was easy and light and nice and comfortable
and you know all the way to his death but you know his description you know he
old his body creaking and held together with straps and he had a bad back and
somewhere else he described himself as hunched over you know we think it's upright and dignified but he himself
described himself as hunched over in his old age and uh
and uh so it's very human so you know it's kind of like the idea it's almost like we can feel ourselves see ourselves
in here and and the world's falling around his disciples are dying he's sick and old
and he and he's the he's the heavenly messenger for
peace he's calm he's mindful he's steady he has a practice he's still teaching he's still motivated
and he keeps walking known as pilgrimage going north and uh he keeps going
and uh and then at some point he crosses a river and comes to a salgrove saul groves the
salt trees are kind of majestic trees of northern india they're kind of like the redwood trees of india it's apparently
quite beautiful and tall and uh and he came to this grove
and he said prepare a bed between two psalteries
with my head to the north i saying one more time he's saying i'm tired and want to lie down
so they did and he lied down there placing one foot from the other and then he laid down mindful and clearly
aware it's always self-possessed it's always present in a nice way for what he's doing
and uh and then that's kind of like the last time he got he laid down he didn't think
he was there i don't know for a day or two and this the story goes and different people came to visit him and he had
final teachings for people and the very last person who came to the buddha asking questions wanting to be
taught came to the buddha and said you know there's lots of people lots of spiritual
teachers around all teaching the truth who's teaching the real truth how do we know what the real truth is
it's a reasonable question and uh and as he does other times people ask that
kind of point of question he doesn't answer it directly what he answers is
he says i'm not going to answer that but wherever the eightfold path is
that's where you find people who become free so wherever there's the practice
this is what i'm interested in not truth is not so important what i'm interested is the practice
and here is pointing to the eightfold path is the practice
and so that's the last thing he said to his uh in terms of someone who came to him for for teaching
and then um he
he gathered his monks around him this monastic community and uh
asked them you know i'm about to die this is it and uh
and but you have any last questions this is your chance
and i think he asked them three times and no one had any questions for him which i think maybe it was very
satisfying right i mean he's he was very concerned about setting this leaving behind a legacy
of people who were enough people who had tasted the fruit of the dharma
both monastic and lay so that somehow the momentum could keep going and he was he had ascertained in
his own mind that in fact now in his old age there were enough people who had tasted the fruit of the practice
that he was not needed anymore and uh but he gave the monk still one
last chance to get clarify something and when none of them answered then he asked a question
then he said
now i'll tell you this all conditioned things are of a nature
to decay practice
tirelessly all things will pass all things will change disappear
and then the last words you said was practice tired tirelessly
so again practice practice practice that's what he that's what he was most about keep practicing
and then we come to the very end then the buddha entered meditation
entered the first jhana leaving that he entered the second the third and the fourth
and leaving the fourth jhana he entered the sphere of infinite space then the sphere of infinite
consciousness and the sphere of nothingness in the sphere of neither perception or non-perception
and then into the cessation of feeling and perception it's kind of like
he's do this is this was his meditation life going through these states of meditation
and here just as he was dying he went on one last tour he could be visiting them one last
pilgrimage going through these deep states of meditation and then um
and then we reach this very high state called cessation of feeling and perception ananda asked another monk named
anuruddha has the buddha passed away and anuroda who was a
highly skilled meditator himself could read or see
not yet and and so then the buddha
left the attainment of the cessation of feeling and perception enter it goes backwards through them enter the sphere
of neither perception or non-perception then into the sphere no no thingness the
sphere of infinite consciousness the sphere of finite space and then back to the fourth jhana the
third the second and the first so he's going up and down the ladder and then he goes up again
to the fourth jhana and the fourth jhana is
considered to be the place where it's easiest to let go fully
either to let go into enlightenment or let go into passing away
so here's some person who so this is not a this is a he was
fully in a master of himself this last time last period of his life
he wasn't he knew how to die he engaged in a practice that brought
him into a very wonderful space where the mind is very peaceful very equanimous very still
where it just in that state it just feels like the most wonderful
thing you can do is to just continue that process of letting go
to enter those deep states of meditation you have to do a lot of letting go to get there and things become very thin
there's very little left to hold on to and whatever is left to hold on to maybe
the life force or something they just feel so good to let go of that
as well so rather than death being like this drag
remember he said earlier don't concern yourself of what's in the future don't concern yourself in the past
just practice and here he was practicing as he was dying
and it's a practice that involves a letting go that feels so healthy and so good like one of the best things it feels you can
do he was ready to die
he died an old sick man it was it was his time
and he died with one of the most wonderful things the most peaceful most wondrous most luminous thing you can do
that letting final letting go so uh
and then you know then he died so this is a story of a man old man
who had found his peace the world was falling around
falling apart around him the world that he knew and he was at peace anyway
he was calm he was wise he was caring for his the world around him
he stopped and talked to people and lots of people came to see him and he would continue to talk and teach
and he did the slow non-hurried walk some people think he was trying to walk back to his home country
and if that's the case um the world is falling around falling apart
and one form that was he he wasn't able to reach his home and uh you know going back to back to
his home country and he died in the kind of in the woods with his people around him
but uh you know nothing too ceremonious nothing too
nothing really special about the place in fact ananda kind of complained kind of like what are you doing dying here
this is like not a special place it's the middle of nowhere and uh
and uh so
so then the heavenly messenger the messenger of that it's possible to
live in this world with a profound peace and to die with a profound peace
and what a fantastically positive helpful message
it is possible to be in this world and find our peace to have pulled that
that's the story to pull out the arrow in the heart
the the metaphor of an arrow and a heart means that some of the deepest sufferings and wounds and that we carry
with us is something that's been it doesn't belong in there it's
external and it can be pulled out our suffering is not inherent
it's not innate like it's just there and it's always there and it has to always be there
it's in some ways a foreign object and so to practice
to pull that arrow out and when you do then you're at peace
so the buddha's life the buddha end of his life
and so we live in a time of change we live in time of strife
we live in a time where families are riven we don't have
sons yet i think you know killing their parents to take over the throne
but we have all kinds of challenges and i think for the message from the
buddha is yes this is what happens in this life
don't let that distract you from your ability to practice
keep your confidence and your courage and your dedication
to practice no matter what in all this so that you can be a person
who is at peace with it not at peace you know kind of kind of a naive acceptance
of it but the kind of a peace where you're at peace so that you can make a difference in
this world so you could be a messenger for the happiness and welfare of this world you can be a peacemaker
in this world wherever you go to whatever degree that you can do this
maybe you can be a heavenly messenger you will be as i said but maybe you can be
the heavenly messenger that demonstrates peace and i knew i knew i knew one person i've
known a few people actually but one person particular who's uh probably
became the heavenly messenger when she was dying
and they're more so and if you practice then you can know that's when you need to practice you're
preparing to die and the other practice to support you
so take out take out your arrow and
then you can live unhurriedly peacefully in this life taking care of your life that you should live and what
you need to take care of like the buddha was taking care of everything before he died
don't die too soon but do practice
soon so thank you
and and
be well and take care of yourselves and remember to practice thank you