good evening good evening and a really warm welcome
wherever you are whenever it is you're listening to this or watching this a
really warm welcome
so we'll begin with a guided meditation
just arriving arriving at this moment
this place this occasion
and just feeling into this moment breathing into the body
feeling into maybe that general mood is there some anticipation
or maybe some lack of energy some dullness
maybe there's some brightness some uprightness
whatever it is can we welcome can we welcome it
include it
letting the attention rest in the sense of having a body
how do you know you have a body what does it feel like to have a body
and then rest in the attention on the parts of the body that are breathing
the movements associated with breathing
feeling in the chest or the belly
feeling the expansion then contraction
and then expansion contraction
feeling into the rhythm of the breathe
when we notice that the mind wanders as it's opt to do
apt to do we just very simply gently begin again
it might be that there are some sounds
maybe some uncomfortable sensation in the body
can we allow these experiences to be there
after all they are there can we not wrestle with them or push
them away just allow them to be there without
turning them into problems
there is sound it sounds like this
there is throbbing stabbing in the knee perhaps
without trying to shove it away the
experience
but instead having an openness of spaciousness allowing
that experience to be there and it might be that with our allowing
allows something to shift maybe the ecosystem of the mind of the experience
to shift
and perhaps the problemness of the experience drains away
or maybe not
for the purpose of this meditation session
can we soften any sense of having to fix
things make them be otherwise
and instead to allow them to be as they are our
experiences not big conceptual ideas about the nature of
society but our felt experience
in this moment experiences of breathing
the experience of hearing
the experience of having bodily
sensations
allowing doesn't mean that we agree or approve
with our experience it means we're not wrestling or struggling with
the experience
to allow what our experience is
is to put down the the struggle the push
the pushing away that pulling closer that might be happening in an obvious
way or in a subtle way
instead can we just notice what is happening
and let it happen that the experience be there let it arise and pass away
in this way our practice can be more about finding the freedom in each moment
rather than trying to make the moment be something different
and with this orientation and this experience of finding the freedom and our meditation can support our daily
life recognizing that we don't have to fix everything we don't have to change
everything to match our preferences
so that we might have more freedom and ease and what life brings us and
so that ease might also be picked up on or experienced by others
around us so that our practice can be the benefit
not only for our ourselves but for those around us
and for all beings everywhere
[Music]
good evening good evening and a really warm welcome
so at imc sometimes we teach this practice i think gil franz doll and tonya wiser
um developed or i'm not exactly sure what the word is but it's r-a-f-t
it kind of has some tools to help if there's some difficulties during meditation some difficult
experiences difficult emotions physical experiences whatever it might be
r a f t recognize allow
feel in the body and tease apart the experience from
our reaction to the experience
so tonight i thought i would unpack a little bit just the second element allow that can be an integral part of
our practice mindfulness practice is allowing what's there but maybe to unpack it a little bit more and
what does this mean to allow so part of what this when we use this
language allow what it's pointing to is distinguishing between what is happening in this moment
and our reactions our responses our ideas about what is happening in this
moment so instead of getting lost in our
response our reaction is to align ourselves with what is actually
happening that is to just be present with what's happening
there might be these ways in which we are subtly i notice i certainly have early in my
meditation practice i certainly noticed that i was doing this kind of like secretly hoping like if i
ignore it it'll go away or if i push it enough it'll go away
this whatever was unpleasant in my experience or if i wished it would go away hard enough it
would go away so to allow is to put that down
and instead to just kind of in some ways have some openness and some spaciousness
and recognizing oh yes okay that's sensation in my knee is
a stabbing sensation it's a little moving on this small range
maybe and it's not constant and sometimes it feels a little bit more stabby at other times or more acute
than other times or so not pushing or
pulling away from our experience but just to be there
just to notice allow the awareness allow the attention
to land if you will on the experience and to be lying about it
so when i'm talking about allowing i'm not talking about maybe i'll say this
i'll start this way i'm really talking about our experiences our moment-to-moment
experiences i'm not talking about societal constructs and the terrible
injustices and racism that happens and i'm not saying that we should allow this
no no no i'm talking about just allowing that next moment of experience
and then the next moment of experience whether it's a thought maybe an emotion a bodily experience
sensations of breathing whatever it might be is there a way that we can
not push it or try to shift it or shape it into something
different so allowing is to allow both the pleasant and the unpleasant often we
think about we have to allow the unpleasant but sometimes when something is pleasant
too there can be a sense of like oh yes oh yeah right right and this kind of wanting to
grab onto it but allowing is is permitting both the
pleasant and the unpleasant to arise and pass away
this natural movement that's natural with that rhythm
of course it happens at a different pace some experiences seem to be faster and some
seem to be slower but to permit them to just arise and
pass away at the in the tempo that is appropriate
and as i mentioned in the guided meditation it doesn't mean that we have to agree with it
it doesn't mean that we have to approve of our experience right now of this
little uncomfortable experience in my knee i don't necessarily approve of it
but can i just allow it to be there yes this is part of the felt experience at this moment
so can we meet our experiences maybe that's another way of saying allowing
is to just be able to meet it like turn towards it in
some kind of way so often right in our daily life and in our meditation life things turn
turn out better if we are just able to meet it and turn towards it as best we can
sometimes we don't have the capacity at that particular moment we're feeling overwhelmed or
that can't we don't have the resources at that moment we're tired we're hungry
maybe we have a history in our background that makes us really sensitive to particular
experiences so we don't have the whole range of resources we might have if it were another
experience but to allow is to immediately as best we can
and so maybe at the deepest level this idea of allowing is to an invitation to bring an attitude
or a quality of liberation into our experience this attitude or
quality of freedom not getting tangled up
not getting
knotted up not getting attached so can we find a
bit of freedom in all of our experiences and not just those ones that match our preferences
but instead can we find the freedom or be with the freedom with all of our
experiences in some ways we might say that all of
the dharma is about non-attachment or another way to say that all of the
dharma is about letting go maybe another way to say that is all of the dharma is about finding freedom
maybe another way to say that is all of the dharma is about tuning into
the suffering right all of these are related and we might use different
words that are seem appropriate at different times to match our experiences
but one way we might also think about allowing is non-attachment
so attachment is we might say is when there's a lack of freedom
that is that for me i kind of feel like like when getting tangled up like
in a net somehow maybe that's sometimes it's not a nice
visual because i'm often sometimes with that comes suffering of some poor animals that are
tangled up in a net but just this idea of like it's not clear how to get out how to free oneself
um sometimes dharma teachers talk about like they're being a tar baby you know the the story i don't know that
where i can't bring to mind right now where this story is
but um like trying to push something away and it's really sticky so to try to free the hand you know put
in the other hand and then now both hands are stuck and then you know what the story is or it gets a
little bit ridiculous putting the foot to pull out the two hands thinking if you just push it away
and then of course the foot is stuck and then the remaining limb gets stuck and i can't
remember in this story if it's the head also but you get the picture
not a lot of freedom so with our mindfulness practice
we start to see that actually we can get attached or tangled up
with just about anything whether it is a bodily experience whether it's an
emotion whether it's a thought the thoughts about the memory about the future
some way thoughts about the future of this whirring and this um going around and around this
rumination and maybe playing out scenario after scenario in a way that's not helpful maybe it's
helpful at the beginning to do this to play out different scenarios so you can plan and be prepared
but then there comes a time when it's not helpful and instead it's just this rumination
so i would say that's a way of being attached or tangled so sometimes we think of this word of
being attached means that there's um affection
or you know some real bonding happening with uh something else but i'm using it in this
way attachment is kind of like being entangled or you know just an absence of freedom so
when we start to with our mindfulness practice we start to see
the fact that it we can get attached to just about anything and i would say even it's actually normal
it's normal to get a little bit stuck in our thinking and our experience
and as we gain skills and gain confidence and how to be with things
that are uncomfortable so we don't have to judge this when we
notice that we are finding that we're attached we find ourselves stuck to
something very sticky because that in fact would
be some uh getting entangled even more that's a kind of like judging ourselves
and then building a story all around oh i'm overly concerned with this
sensation in my knee i really diana you shouldn't be worried
about the sensation in your knee you're supposed to be meditation teacher and what does this mean that if you keep on thinking about
this sensation in your knee and so that is an example of just being
attached right kind of being entangled is even this response to initially maybe getting lost
in thoughts about it or concern about it and then having ideas about our ideas
papancha this mental proliferation makes story making
or we can be attached to our bodies the way our bodies are we can be attached to
our emotions some some of them trying to push them away
mental states wanting to only have some clarity and some steadiness
so allowing is the opposite of this
just letting experiences to rise and pass away
so to say a little bit more about attachment is and what whatever it is that we find
that we're tangled up with is um i've seen bell uh sorry i've seen
um gill do this where this um demonstration of what is attachment is
to like really be holding on so tightly to this bell striker so i kind of have like a fist
in my hand with the bell striker in my hand and when the hand is gripping tightly in
this way it's not able to receive this hand is not able to create
it's not able to give it's not able to act it's not able to do it stuck and
gripping in some ways we might even say this kind
of gripping is um in a subtle level includes
this really deep very deep and perfectly natural
or maybe i should say normal maybe even natural way to push away that which is uncomfortable
that which is unpleasant but is there a way that we can hold things
with an open hand with the striker line just in the palm of our
hands but our fingers aren't gripping it so that we can hold things without
getting tangled up in them
and so how do we know what the difference is how do we know this difference between
holding certainly we need to hold all kinds of things in our lives our loved ones
our aspirations our skills and our practice
so what is the difference between attachment and holding one is that i is maybe
there's a felt sense about it this idea of gripping my fingers were getting a little bit
tired they're holding that striker so there's many different ways that shows up
but maybe a tail telltale way in which is we can notice when
attachment is there is when there is suffering sooner or later all gripping tangling
leads to difficulties dissatisfaction stress uncomfortableness
so to maybe continue kind of fleshing this out that i'm saying allowing is like
non-attachment but when we hear this word non-attachment i'm saying that to be as the opposite of attachment or gripping or
getting entangled but sometimes when we hear this word non-attachment we might be thinking
detachment that is it might have this cool aloofness we might think that it's
um it's not but we might have this idea like
non-attachment might feel like some disinterest or withdrawal or disconnection
either from oneself or from others so to be clear non-attachment doesn't
mean this standoffishness chilliness lack of engagement
but instead allowing has this quality of love and
warmth and care
right sometimes the greatest acts of love or to allow people to be exactly who they are
and so in some ways to allow our experiences to be the way that they are is an act of love
it's kind of and we can think of it for me it kind of feels this way with some respect and okay this is what's arising
it's arising because the conditions are there for it to arise
it's a rising so i can't make it go away at that moment when i
notice it so this non-attachment has a feeling of
love or warmth and openness spaciousness kind of like how i
talked about holding the striker with an open hand so it's this movement of
allowing is a movement of it's a not a tightness it's not a
contraction it's not a gripping sometimes attachment is born out of fear
this fear of something in ourselves that we'll experience or this fear of something out there in the world
but this allowing is not laced with fear it's instead it's
with us warmth
so to continue to unpack this idea and perhaps all of you know this but sometimes it's
i know for me and i think for a lot of practitioners sometimes it's helpful to hear a number of different words
associated with something that we already know
to remind us of what we already know and to maybe flesh it out a little bit and that is of course this idea of the
second arrow the simile of the second arrow goes
something like this i'm paraphrasing the buddha asks his
followers is it painful to receive a sec to be shot with an arrow
it's not a trick question so they answer yes venomous or it is painful to be shot
with an arrow and then the buddha asks is it more painful to be shot with a second
arrow again not a trick question yes venerable sir it's more painful to
be shot with a second arrow so the first arrow is what life brings
us the second arrow is our relationship
to what life brings us so we might say that allowing is not shooting that second arrow
not filling ourselves with self-recrimination or not um
getting tangled up in whatever way that might be so not beating ourselves up
about what's happening or just noticing okay this is the next moment
because sometimes we have these ideas of what it means to be a practitioner that we should look a certain way or
only be having certain experiences
so one way that we might think about this kind of building on this idea of the second arrow
is allowing is a way in which we might shift our relationship with what's happening
soften our release relationship relax our relationship that can be another way
in which we might think about this because often when we think about we
have this ideas how can i let go of something or
how can i not be attached to something what we really mean is how can i get rid
of this how can i have this not be in my life so without really realizing it we have
some aversion there and as long as there's a version there that's a way in which we're entangled
so can we soften can relax can we let go of the particular relationship we
have to our experience as a way to allow
and maybe i should just um say one more time it's a normal human experience to become
entangled to become attached to not allow in maybe
some subtle way so the invitation here is just to notice
just to notice when this happens
so as to increase um some of the our
understanding about allowing is to talk what are some of the supports
for allowing right if it was i just got finished saying it's perfectly natural and normal
for us to have some attachment and to get tangled up and to not allow and with practice
are we can allow more and more and more but what else what is a support for
allowing and one thing that we could look at is
barbara frederickson a well-known psychologist she has this
idea of broaden and build broaden
and build it's kind of a little bit similar to what we're doing this idea of if we have some positive
experiences it broadens our capacity and then this
with this broad capacity we can build resources and the resources are more enduring than
just these positive experiences so for example
just being curious or having interest kind of um
creates the urge to play with having a sense of playfulness or you know this
curiosity kind of comes with a sense of playfulness or experimentation what happens if i do
this or what happens if this doesn't go this way or it goes another way or something like this
taking in some new information or just being playful with it
in the same way having joy creates the urge to
maybe explore or to otherwise expand out our experience
having some happiness so this when we're having these positive
experiences and we're more apt to do some other experiences explore or play and with that helps create some
resources like maybe we might explore some other ways in which to practice with
um i'm a little bit uh distracted here
somebody just arrived here but maybe we um if we have this to explore
and play for example maybe we're a little bit more apt to um
um yeah so now this word is escaping me but
our health might improve for example maybe we go outside more and go for walks and or maybe we are
more likely to do the physical therapy that has been recommended to us or to take that medication that was
um maybe uncomfortable to take or bothers him to take or something like this
we're more apt to do these things if we have some this idea of exploration or play for
example in our lives in the same way might help our
relationships maybe our friendships or our committed
relationships with our significant others might be enhanced and
then with these greater resources health relationships or maybe just a greater
sense of confidence or resilience
can help us to have this um create the capacity in which we feel
like we can allow things that are uncomfortable we don't have to push them away
we don't have to get so entangled with them so this idea of broaden and build
is to work to have some positive experiences curiosity joy happiness
loving kindness and these experiences help to create durable resources that help
expand our capacity to be with difficulties which makes it easier to allow
things to be so maybe i'll just end with a little bit of some idea about
loving kindness part of barbara fredrickson's work has
spent to look at loving-kindness and its impact on practitioners and maybe when you
heard me say this you're like ugh really loving-kindness
i know a number of people have this experience and i certainly did too at the very beginning but interestingly
that um they measured um or they did a controlled study where some
practitioners were doing love and kindness some were doing breath meditation and some were doing
more like an open awareness meditation and they said that the
average likability for loving kindness meditation was lower than breath meditation which
might be your experience maybe not too however it increased significantly after
some practice as well as the perceived effort and the
beginning loving kindness seemed a little bit more difficult than meditation but decreased over time
and as you might imagine i also discovered that with loving-kindness practice there
was this greater sense of resource resourcefulness and this ability to be with difficulties
and we can translate that to allowing
so to allow to not be tangled up in to not have
attachment to bring forth the freedom that's the
liberation that's available in each moment is to allow and so
may we allow as best we can with what life is offering to us in such
a way that we can have some ease and so that we can allow others to be as
they are and what's happening with them out of care and love and warmth not
out of disconnection but out of respect and warm-heartedness
thank you