uh good morning everyone i'm a bit early but partly i was thinking that uh
say a lot of you who those of you who might have been here waiting for a 6 45 beginning
and so warm greetings and and i received
about equal uh note messages about this 6 45 beginning that we had last
week with 45 minute meditation and the 30 minute and
so i thought it was wonderful to have the longer time and i know it's challenging for some of you
and i'll think about some other way to maybe have earlier
um longer maybe sittings and uh maybe in a month or so and
my family responsibilities lightened up some maybe we could do um some of these
mornings have a second sitting at maybe at eight o'clock and
that way maybe that could be 45 minutes and and that way some of you can
have been coming and getting used to this 30-minute sitting can stretch a little bit and and
discover the benefits of longer sitting and then perhaps uh we're getting close
to the second year mark for these 7 a.m sittings and
second year i mean the beginning of the second year one year anniversary and so it's on my mind about how
to support many of you to kind of take this dharma you know a step or two further building
on what this has been we've been doing for this time so we'll have a community meeting at some point
and maybe have a chance to talk about this and such things and and um so anyways i wanted to say hello
and and we'll start up again in a couple of
minutes that's when more people arrive
do
so
um
so it's 7 a.m here in california and so locally i can offer you a good
morning and happy to be together and good day and greetings for everyone around the
globe for participating and
the um the kind of the theme for this guided
meditation is balance and uh finding a balance when we sit and
the balance i liken it a little bit to us finding the midpoint
of a row boat maybe a fairly stable wide row boat but still a rowboat that
and finding the midpoint where uh there's the least amount of the center
of gravity kind of of the boats and to stand there with our legs firmly on the
floor of the boat and and keep our balance and maybe you know our upper part of our
torso is maybe not moving so much but our legs are in fact kind of going with the rocking of the boat maybe
it's a gentle rocking but still we're constantly making small adjustments
and uh and the stronger we are and our legs and torso and things like that
maybe the easier it is to keep our balance so in meditation we're also developing a
kind of inner strength and a skill at staying balanced both to recognize
about when we get off balance and to recognize and to have the strength to kind of stay
to come back to balance stay in balance and the way it works in meditation
is the most simple way is to stay balanced without
any kind of movement towards our experience or any movement away any wanting
or not wanting any movement in which we get pulled by experience are
pulled into our thoughts any movement pushed by the thoughts or pushed by experience of what's happening
and rather both physically but also you know in the heart the mind we stay
balanced we stay in that center place where there's a strength
and a stability that wisdom can operate and clear seeing can operate that we
lose when we start getting involved in things or we start rejecting things
and staying in that midpoint of the vote of our life and of course we'll go
a little bit off and so part of the equanimity in practice is to appreciate that of course
just like in a row boat we'll get them pulled this way in that way and get picked up get involved and
all these things but hopefully not so much and hopefully with very gentle
maybe even loving course corrections no stay here come back um see clearly what's
happening so we can stay balanced come back to that peaceful place the
still place the balance place inside the dynamic balance the dynamic peacefulness
i don't think that you have to rest on your meditation laurels and just stay peaceful without a kind of being
engaged alert mindful to stay here here
so with that as an introduction to assume a posture that maybe
manifests a degree of balance and uh and one way to
begin then with balance is to rock back and forth if you're sitting
upright and maybe sway back and forth and and then make smaller and smaller kind
of sways kind of looking for a place of balance with the torso balance on the sitting
bones balance of your weight against whatever support
is being received and then to kind of feel up the spine of the torso
and to make small adjustments to feel a sense of being everything's balanced
partly that means that the with the weight of our torso kind of at all stacked up in a way that
feels aligned with this some center line uh within so that we're not leaning
forward part of our weight is in front of that center of gravity and and some of it's not
behind and um something looking for that balance
and to do something where the hands and arms feel balanced as well
so that they're not pulled too far forward or pulled too far down so the shoulders
being pulled if you're sitting you might be able to pull your hands back from the knee a
little bit or sometimes putting a cushion or something on top of your
your your your your thighs or your ankles so the hands are held up more
can feel more balanced and support a balance of the torso
and then to close the eyes and with the eyes closed and sitting
still again feeling the body from the inside
and feeling where there is balance where there is stability in the body
where there's a kind of maybe even groundedness of your
body against whatever supports you upright whatever supports your weight
to feel that stability or groundedness rootedness
and to feel whatever seems stable within physical stability
some people might feel it the lower torso
around the hips pelvis some people might feel it
lower back or in the belly or maybe
in the area the solar plexus behind it above the diaphragm
and maybe there's a can be a feeling of some stability
as you relax your shoulders soften
it may be a stability
in the shoulder supporting the neck maybe in the back of the neck
in the way that that area supports the weight of the head
and there's a way in which tension and holding even if it's
stable tension is a kind of
agitation and greater stability and balance is
found by relaxing some of the extra tension in
the body softening the muscles of the face
these are muscles that are sometimes constantly engaged in daily life
to express ourselves communicate ourselves to the world
smiles and frowns and scowls and
fears held in the muscles of the face
and it's a compassionate thing for the face on the exhale to let
the muscles ease up not have to work so much
around the eyes forehead
draw
and the same thing with agitation and restlessness in the chest if there is something
and relaxing in the chest softening easing up
without the kind of instability that comes from resistance
holding ourselves at our life at bay
and then softening in this belly a kind of release of the weight of the
belly letting it maybe that weight
release downward to create some inner stability in the
lower torso
and then to feel whatever restlessness agitation energetics there are
there is in the mind
maybe in the area where we that we have the brain or anywhere
for you it's associated with your mental emotional activity
as you exhale relaxing the mind
relaxing the mental activity slowing things down in the mind
softening the mind and feeling the softness
of the mind
and then gently noticing
as we sit here for a minute or so any movements towards
or away any being pulled into something like our
thoughts or any kind of movement of recoiling or
pulling back or being pushed back
any wanting any not wanting
and just simply notice that and perhaps allowing it to be there if
it's there feeling it sensing what it's like for
the body the mind to have this movement for and
against
and feel how maybe there's not much balance there
or that there's some imbalance
and then the next couple of exhales see if you can release
any four against wanting and not wanting release it
enough to feel that you're in your life mind heart
it comes to us balanced stability
or comes into a little bit more of a balanced ability than
it was when it wasn't stable
and then to really now
experience the breathing body the body
breathing almost like the awareness gently lands
onto the body breathing
and this is where we feel the gentle row boat where the gentle waves are breathing in
and out the movements of the body expanding and
contracting
the air moving in and out through the nostrils
and if it's easy enough to establish a kind of gentle soft
stability steadiness with the breathing
and as you feel any other pull and push
moving forward against experience wanting and not wanting
keep finding your stability keep coming back to the breathing
let the breathing support you
let the breathing be the place that you stand or feel
so you're not so easily pulled into for and against
staying balanced in the body body breathing
with the mind having landed and on the breathing the
body breathing not easily pulled into
wanting and not wanting
and if there are little movements of wanting and not moving it's okay those can be some kind of
that's the place we use to find back to balance here breathing
centered on the breathing body
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
i have a question for you and that is how might your
kindness your love your compassion
benefit from having an inner stability an inner balance
how can kindness and love and compassion benefit
from not being pulled into
in some way reacting for or against
without being pulled into desires or pulled into aversion
to be able to open our hearts care and good will towards others
while remaining balanced without wants and not wants without
anxiety creating imbalance
perhaps even feeling a stability
in the kindness the good will the love the compassion
and maybe you can imagine that with whatever balance stability
calm you have now
sitting here can you bring to mind someone for whom
you have friendliness good will
compassion love and imagine sitting together
walking together and for you to remain balanced and
stable in your goodwill in your friendliness
not pulled into some of the com complexities that can exist in these relationships of
wanting and not wanting protecting or fear
holding back or giving too much
our friendliness our goodwill is one of the great resources we have
it can be one of the foundations for buddhist practice
and may it be that all beings
find a way to be balanced stable
in their happiness and safety peacefulness
may all beings find stability steadiness strength
their good will their heartfelt care for others
and may we in our balance stability for good will and friendliness
contribute to make it easier for others to be that way
may it be that the benefits of this meditation is something that we
bring into the world of our daily life
that we're ready to share and stay close to those benefits
may all beings be happy may all beings everywhere
be free
um
so the topic uh for this talk is
the equanimity factor of awakening and uh it's the seventh of the seven
factors of awakening and over the last week i've been talked to her about the earlier factors
and and we're talking about these seven factors of awakening in the context
of the practice of anapanasati mindfulness of breathing
where we're mindful of the mind that we experience starts experiencing the mind as we breathe in
experiencing the mind as we breathe out and so we've kind of taken our time
uh to understand some of the things we can start experiencing when we experience the mind the word
cheetah the pali word for mind c i tta is
often translated as mind state and it's not the mind as a thing
like the brain is kind of a physical thing but rather it's the way in which we experience our interior
life our mental life as a whole and rather than the particular details
of different activities of the mind that goes on particular thoughts feelings
impulses intentions it's the the whole of the mind that kind of and how we
experience the whole is personal and contextual and
depending on the different factors of the mind that come together
and and it sounds a little bit strange to say this but the state of the mind
how we experience a state of the mind it depends on the state of the mind or how we experience the shape of the mind
or how we experience this totality of the mind is based a little bit on the state of
mind or which mental factors are strongest and um but as we open to the mind and
feel it it has different characteristics that we can feel now that takes a lot of stability and
really settled in the practice to start feeling this whole mind and the mood or the mind that might be
there but as this practice gets strong there are seven factors that qualities characteristics
that become predominant in the state of the mind that we can experience
different ones of them at different times and sometimes kind of all of them together and these are the seven factors
awakening mindfulness investigation effort joy tranquility
samadhi and equanimity and these all have different functions
they work in different ways as a state of mind mindfulness creates real stability
and uh it's kind of like what there's my that would say differently if the mind just doesn't waver
it's not agitated and jumping around when mindfulness becomes a little bit more or awareness becomes a little more a
state that's present rather than something that we have to keep renewing but i keep making the
effort having the intention to be mindful so there's unwaveringness of
of attention investigation or this ability to see clearly to look
up and see clearly or intimately experience not by analyzing it or
probing but by like tuning into the frequency of the radio and not having
any more static just really feeling it and sensing more fully that what's going on that's of that function
is really important for the process of liberation they say that's the most important
of the seven factors for liberation because we have to get things really into focus
and then the effort factor that can see the difference between wholesome and also unwholesome
is really key in not being trapped by the unwholesome by but finding
a certain kind of healthy escape or stepping away from into the wholesome
joy is provides a deep satisfaction a deep contentment a bodily and physically that
is really kind of feels good and then the last three tranquility
and samadhi and equanimity are particularly useful
and so the joy factor as well these are all feelings of pleasure a well-being positive feelings
that we can have that are tremendous support for practice in helping free us from some of our
addictive patterns some of our attachments attachments to pleasure attachments to all kinds of things where
we searching if we think we're searching for happiness by having more money or more status or more relationships or
more something that's outside of us and that drive can be addictive at times
and and um or the strong uh ways in which fear operates from us inside of us that
itself is compels us to act certain ways and be certain ways and anxiety
phobias and there's something about being settled in these positive factors these states
of mind of joy tranquility samadhi and equanimity that is so
nourishing feels so wholesome that feels like so such a source of well-being
that it creates a reconditioning factor it conditions us in new ways rather than
being conditioned by fear or a feeling of lack or feeling of
being deprived or feeling unsafe for all kinds of ways which life has kind of
conditioned us to be we're starting to recondition ourselves and then it becomes
easier to begin letting go of some of the dysfunctional ways in which we might be living
and so rather than only relying on mindfulness seeing clearly recognizing what's happening
to free us from some of our conditioning which is very hard to only rely on
mindfulness but to really have the mindfulness support this process of settling and
stability and growth in the dharma to begin eventually and it eventually is an
important word here so we don't get impatient start kind of getting nourished
by these wholesome qualities and way of being and the last of these is equanimity and
equanimity for many people who are unfamiliar with this idea and buddhism
will think that equanimity is kind of maybe aloof or kind of dry or kind of not really relevant for
having a good time in life and uh and maybe even not relevant for making
ourselves safe in this world if we're equanimists how do we make ourselves safe
the um and um but
uh and i think when i was before i became a buddhist practitioner i don't think i had any i used the word
equanimity in any kind of way in my vocabulary i probably knew what it meant some somewhat
but it had no relevance for how i lived my life or how i talked about thought about myself but certainly with practice and
meditation equanimity became has become a more and more important quality something that i recognize
and appreciate it kind of as a state there's this kind of feeling that
courses through my whole body a kind of stability and clarity and
openness and and the kind of a freedom that comes with equanimity and it's considered to be one of the
most sublime uh states of being that a person can experience
it's kind of kind of considered the crown jewel of the seven factors of awakening which themselves are the crown
jewels so you know it's that that's
just letting you know that if you're practicing develops over time maybe you'll start
feeling how special this equity manufacturer is and the rich emotional aspect it's not
indifference or aloofness or dryness and the equanimity factor
word it belongs to a family of concepts and states that uh
is championed by buddhism and uh one of them is this uh equanimity which is upeka
in pali another one is a mouthful of words that means literally
something like etymology of it standing in the middle of it all standing in the middle of this
and that's often seen as a sense of balance and then there's a word sama which maybe is cognitively related
to our word same i'm not sure about this how these languages
connect they're distant relatives of each other english and and pali and some uh
can mean can mean something like even it can mean also like light like the same but uh even
balanced also but an evenness of mind and uh it's related to some is related
to words samana s-a-m-e-n-a which
means either impartiality or sometimes it's
that translated as justice so impartiality that uh like the impartial
justice the impartial judging of things is considered a really high ideal and uh
to treat people in a certain impartiality doesn't mean indifference it means that we treat everyone kind of equally and it's kind
of the equal so it's some as equal or same or sameness so an evenness of mind an impartiality
of mind a balance of heart and mind balance of body and mind
and equanimity and for now i will just uh
say briefly a little bit about equanimity and then pick up this topic tomorrow and because it's so important
and the word for equanimity upeka upe kkha
is the etymology of the word is actually quite useful here
it literally means something to have it like to have an overview to have the bird's eye view of what's
happening um so it involves a kind of wisdom that comes from seeing how things are
so it's a kind of a wisdom factor it's not just something that arises because the quality of
some kind of inner balance is strong but rather it also comes from the strength of mindfulness
investigation all these other factors and then being able to not be pulled for
against things not quickly become impartial not quickly be reactive to experience but have a
stability that allows us to have the overview and wisdom operates
wisdom can see that oh that's being pulled into things i don't need to do that that's my anger i don't have to get pick
it up and get involved that's pain i've been i know about pain
i've meditated with pain for a long time and i know i'm better off not getting pulled into its orbit and
preoccupied by it or reactive to it and so there's a little bit of wisdom operating with this
overview having the big picture of how it works and um
so um so it belongs to the the aspect of mindfulness
where we can begin observing what's going on it's a little bit like it's a little bit like
you know stepping back and having the big picture or being up in a hilltop maybe looking down or the
experience that i had this wonderful experience that was very valuable for me many years ago was a
second year in college first time i was living with college roommates and little department and the little
apartment had a deck uh out the living room and one day i was out somehow i was out in the deck
with living room sliding door closed and two of my roommates were having an animated i think a friendly enough
animated conversation in the living room and i couldn't hear anything they were saying
but i could see the animated way they were and i could feel how i was kind of
delighted seeing them but i could feel how i wasn't being
pulled around by what they were saying and how they were i wasn't getting pulled in or reactive to it i was just kind of
sitting peacefully delightfully just watching in a kind of way of equanimity
so this ability to observe and watch and maybe be delighted maybe be compassionate maybe have a
response that's situation appropriate because
of our ability to have the overview and clear seeing of what's going on
equanimity factor of awakening so one more talk on that tomorrow
and then we'll pick up the the pace of uh the 16 steps of anapanasati
so thank you all very much and i do look forward to being together
again tomorrow