hello everyone and welcome to our meditation time together
and um i send my warm greetings around the globe to people
all over who are participating so
this week's topic is mindfulness of mind or mindfulness of awareness
and one of the interesting facets about
our minds or our awareness is that
sometimes it acts like velcro and sometimes like teflon
sometimes what comes into awareness what we know what we see and feel and think
um remember sticks there we get stuck it doesn't leave us we get
preoccupied we got caught in it and and um and sometimes
and actually more often than we kind of realize uh the mind is more like teflon
awareness is like a teflon it just slides right off in the ancient language they talked they
didn't have teflon so they talked about a drop of water sliding off a lotus leaf apparently
lotus leaves were quite slick for water so it wouldn't stay we just slide right off
and so
so it's interesting to notice when it's like velcro and when it's like teflon
to notice that now that i've talked about this teflon and velcro perhaps it's lingering
your mind you're questioning it wondering about it reacting to it and it's kind of like little bit kind of
there to stay for a little while and um
and then some things that are happening maybe in this moment you're kind of aware fleetingly in the
moment but it doesn't stay it doesn't stick um it's just kind of there and passes
through and it could be something in the space where
you're sitting that you're you're aware of something and but it doesn't stick in anywhere so here
in this room here where i'm sitting there are chairs and i've known these chairs for a long
long time and and except for now searching for it to tell you about it i'm aware of the
chairs but you know they don't there's a mind is teflon with it it just doesn't stick anywhere it doesn't cause any
thoughts any involvement any judgments reactions at all and
so the chairs are going through the mind more like on the teflon side of it
and so to notice
and maybe a simple label simple recognition that oh now
awareness is more like velcro and things are stuck or things are
there's an attachment there's a involvement and now it now it's just like teflon
saying with the breathing and meditation there might be all kinds of
agendas about the breathing and judgments about the breathing and and then the mind awareness is more
like velcro and you might say you might even notice that it's velcro you know velcro mind or clinging mind
and sometimes the breathing is it just goes through see smoothly easily there's no resistance to it in awareness
and the awareness just knows it even if the breath is a little bit labored or a little bit tight awareness just knows it
nose tightness nose laboredness just there's no before and after there's no
um connecting it to a narrative a story what it's connected to what i have to do and how it was yesterday and what it
should be tomorrow and what i have to do and it's just a experience of the moment that kind of
passes right through so that the teflon mine just lets things pass through they come and they go
and they just let them pass through and so when you notice that's happening
no you might use a label teflon or if you like prefer kind of you know
lotus lotus leaf or just you know
free awareness is free stuck and free
velcro and teflon so whatever you know you is nice for you
but to begin to sit here and appreciate that that you have both capacities
and the capacity where cultivating and growing is the is the teflon is the lotus leaf
and um and maybe as you sit here you can a little bit
appreciate emphasize that side of the mind
so assuming a uncomfortable alert posture
and lowering your gaze
maybe down towards the floor 45 degrees with your eyes still open
soften the focus
and then if it's nice gently slowly let the eyelids close
and without breathing deeply as you exhale relax
the shoulders
the belly
the muscles of the face
and then very gently as if the gentleness is
a caring touch for yourself take some deeper breaths
and gently more caring for yourself as you exhale
relax the body let go
and then letting the breathing return to normal and again another round of relaxation
relaxing relaxing the face
any tightness associated with thinking in the area of the head
release the shoulders
and soften the belly
and perhaps gently caringly you can
relax deep in your core deep in your being
a softening a quieting within
and then become aware of the body's experience of breathing
and in this cycle of breathing in and breathing out is any of the experience of breathing
experienced more like that with a teflon mind or more with a
velcro mind
and whatever part of the breathing is more like teflon
this passes arises and passes and prioritize that
allow things just to pass right through
and when they don't gently caringly
recognize it as a velcro mind velcro experience
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to consider the mind awareness
when it's aware of other people
and is the mind more like teflon or more like velcro
in its contact with people
either in person or in memory or means of communication
and it's a gift we give others to meet them with a heart that is not
sticky a teflon heart teflon mind
it can be quite wonderful to hold someone's hand but if they have
you know what a bubble gum in the palm of their hand
and you're just kind of you feel the stickiness it probably doesn't feel so good
maybe part of the wonderfulness of holding a hand is that maybe when it's easy to
release the hands nothing sticks
it's a gift to others to be fully present
with nothing sticking
and to recognize when there's the teflon mine and when the velcro mind
can support us help us meet others with less stickiness
chances are it's more comfortable for them there's more room for them they can
relax they can feel safer it's more peaceful for them
and may it be that what we learn about attention awareness
supports us to be more like a lotus leaf more like
teflon in our care our respect our kindness
for other people may we contribute
to the happiness of others the safety of others
the peacefulness for others and their freedom
may all beings be happy
safe peaceful and free
so
so before i give the talk i'm going to make a couple of announcements while they're still in my mind so i won't
forget tomorrow so next week i won't be here
i'm teaching the first in-person retreat at our retreat center in sight retreat center
and um and matthew brent silver will come and give the
7am talks and guided meditation and he's also connecting this uh what
he's doing for next week kind of a little bit larger package for all of you if you want for the imc
community the worldwide community and it includes some evening events and
includes a saturday day long week from saturday and you can read about that on the imc
website both in the what's news section on the bottom right and also on the
calendar if you go for next week you should be able to see these events posted there
and um i'm so happy that matthew's coming back and and with all the guest teachers that we
have coming um you know if if you're at all inclined to
um if you want to make a donation for them for then the easy place to do i think on youtube
there's a underneath the video there's a some text about imc and there's a
link to the donate button and um
the other thing is that um in uh on december 4th and december 11th
through saturdays we're having a next round of something we did last spring
which is a mindfulness circle for black identified individuals so um african-americans africans anybody
identified as black androids and i think it's kristin
wicker wickerman wickerson rickerson i think i'm sorry i
don't remember exactly i don't never met her and um but anne did it before and um
that she's bringing her friend along this time to help her and um it's a opportunity for black
identified people to meet together and have some discussions and little teachings and community around this
mindfulness practice so
i see when the chat someone wrote velcro like lila the velcro can be a heavenly messenger
and that's yes
think what what we're learning to do in this practice is to recognize
[Music] the challenges we have the way we get stuck and attached as messengers as opposed to
as you know as enemies and as a messenger you don't want to
kill the messenger but you want to learn from it you want to use that opportunity to wake up
and this idea of waking up is such a beautiful one this concept
that um waking up when you wake up to something
you're not nothing changes in the world but you now
see clearly you now understand clearly and so um
and so maybe there is attachments in the mind clinging in the mind but you wake up to it and you kind
of it's kind of like you've become bigger than it and you kind of oh that's what's happening
i see it and there's something about the clear seeing
of uh that there's freedom there there's the
big the process of moving into teflon and is there
so the analogy i'm using is that sometimes the mind can be more like velcro more
like teflon sometimes awareness and for this week you know i'm using
these kind of synonymously mind mind and awareness so mindfulness of mind mindfulness awareness for this week
are the same thing and um and it's closely connected to mindfulness of the attitude or the
the way in which we relate to experience and what's happening is we practice
we're restoring there's a restoration process of the simplicity of awareness
the most simple form that's accessible to us and some people would might want
to call it that the natural state of awareness it's a little bit uh
philosophically dangerous topic a thing to claim but it's kind of like that
we just feel so healthy so right this is home to have awareness which it doesn't stick
to anything but allows things to arise and pass through
and and so as become mindful of awareness
of mindfulness mindfulness of mindfulness mindfulness of attention it becomes clear that attention is
operating with a certain level of porousness transparency
um non-stickiness non-clinging that's really it's there's a clarity to
the fact that yes there's a sound outside and it just comes through without any
waves or ripples in the mind it's true that my knee hurts and there's no ripples no contractions
no no stories no agendas around it it's known clearly
and we're awake to it meaning we've kind of
become larger than any story agenda reactivity judgment and the awareness
can just be with it feel it with some kind of clarity like his teflon like his
things just roll off uh or allowed to just float
so the um so
as we do mindfulness practice and this is not automatic for beginners but as we
do it and get deeper into the practice at some point we become aware
of the nature or the quality or the characteristics of how we're paying attention the attitude the engagement
the the extra kind of baggage we have along with it and one of them that's particularly
significant for buddhists is to become aware of the clinging
that has us lingering on things holding onto things pushing against things wanting things
and the uh uh
and so the um um
so we have to have this uh as we see that clearly and and the i you
would certainly let go of it but it's also possible to wake up to it
and this waking up to it is the restoration of this
healthy liberated mind and so it so we certainly can get relief
by letting go and that's please let go when it's easy enough to do but there's a whole other process that
has to do with this um waking up the restoration of
of a clarity in which whatever happens can occur can
pass through and so one image that's sometimes used for this is the mind becomes like an
endless sky and the sky and things you know clouds birds
all kinds of things go through the sky but um uh
they don't stick to the sky is the idea they just the sky doesn't interfere with them doesn't stick to it
doesn't hold on to it um the air the the air the sky just is
just you know kind of just lets everything go right through so there are times when awareness can be
like that and and
it is not necessarily so far away that possibility if we associate that with
this waking up so so rather than saying how can i be mindful of this thing
we can sometimes ask ourselves how do i wake up to its presence how do i wake up to it here
and and what's the difference difference between being mindful knowing it and waking up to it
um and as i've said it kind of associated with certainly kind of with a
expansion of awareness where awareness kind of somehow seems to be
have lots of capacity to know without reacting to what is known
lots of capacity to allow things just be there and the floating in the sky of awareness
without um doing anything having an agenda wanting anything
about it and uh and then this you know and so as we
practice this restoration of a healthy mind of a free mind of a
of a um you know a teflon mind or if you prefer a more
natural is a lotus lotus leaf mine where the water
just water drops or just roll right off a lotus leaf or a sky-like mind
and and this is a very different orientation than how most minds are operating
where most minds are operating focused on what it wants or what it doesn't want
it's focused on the on objects of attention objects of thought
and sometimes blinded by that are completely preoccupied with that stuck on it
and now we're turning the attention uh not exactly it doesn't have to be away
from the objects of mind but we're shifting the focus to uh something that
in a kind of way is bigger than or larger than uh any particular thing that we're
thinking about or wanting or not wanting and in that spaciousness of mind
openness of mind stillness of mind
smoothness of mind there is there is a degree of freedom
there's a degree of space there's a kind of a healthy feeling of
of being alive and breathing and then we can feel with that as a reference point it
becomes clear when the mind gets stuck when the mind gets caught
in something when the mind gets preoccupied it's the stickiness there and this is one of the
great functions of this practice as we get
more and more sensitive more attuned to when we get attached when we get stuck
when we get contracted when we get preoccupied in a way that's not so healthy and
useful and and that heightened sensitivity ideally doesn't lead to more stickiness
doesn't lead to more judgments and self-criticism being caught but becomes almost a delight
oh i see it here and and this is good that i see it great
this is the heavenly messenger as it was said and then
and then to um um you know maybe you ask yourself the question you know um
and you know how do i wake up to this now what is it
like to be awake with awareness
so relaxation
that supports more open awareness the recognition of awareness itself
the respecting awareness and now the restoration of this
wonderful capacity of awareness and then tomorrow the release the release of awareness
so thank you very much