good morning
there's a famous saying by a zen teacher of great note
and the saying is quite simple every day is a good day
it's one of those delicious things that a conventional experience
contradicts and in a deeper way
we can experience it as an opportunity
to discover the fruits of practice
conventionally some days are good some days are not so good some days make
us happy feel success and some days don't
but every day presents an opportunity
an opportunity to be present to wake up and see
that within the life we're living the process of liberation is possible
that the ways the mind and heart can get hooked by thoughts and feelings
is not the only way life can happen
so each time we sit
we encourage ourselves
please take up this practice
it will nourish you in a way it's maybe deeper than we can even hope
for take up this practice
of awareness and see
what's going on in the workings of your being
and how to cause yourself less suffering
and in quite a deliberate way we let that perspective
register in our being yes it's a cognitive notion
but it can be a powerful one it can be instructive and then
as we start to engage the city
and deliberate and simple giving over to awareness
in as matter-of-fact a manner as we can
what's the state of being right now
what is the state of being of mind and heart and body
and how can it be nourished in a way that enlivens it
that helps it to discover its natural sense of aliveness
and that's the attitude with which we notice the body
how can we enable and nurture its natural aliveness
can you bring that inquiry to attending to how you
create the posture of meditation
what is your routine for doing just that
setting a posture that enlivens
i'll offer some suggestions
physically noticing is the body upright is it leaning
forward or back
is there a holding the clenching anywhere
sometimes it's helpful to think of opening the front of the body
the whole way from the groin to the
throat like it's you're opening up the lungs the heart
the diaphragm
softening the abdomen
and then at the back lengthening the spine
the lower spine sort of gently shifting down
lengthening down into where the spine reaches down to how you're
your point of sitting making contact with your seat
and then the upper body like lifting out of the hips
and lengthening up the whole way up through the back of the
chest the back of the rib cage the whole way up through the neck to the
crown of the head
not a forceful engagement
with inviting something setting the stage
creating an environment that will allow something to flourish
and that something is awareness
this state of aliveness
and has been in the body since it was
born
and then noticing noticing the state of mind
and more subtly noticing right now the inclination of mind
is it inclining towards
a drowsiness is it inclining towards
over activity getting caught in thoughts or feelings
it's a very delicate process noticing that mind
so powerful so influential the state of mind
can it be met with a commitment to this simple deliberate
process of being aware
experiencing in contrast
to an emphasis
on creating some preferred outcome
and reminding ourselves
that both shamatha are present in this process
simple as it is
steadying attention
and a directed attention
and then the greeting whatever arises
and then as we've been talking about in this couple of weeks engaging the breath
to support that process that delicate but powerful process
of allowing noticing and experiencing
and engaging the breath in a way that discovers how it can
reflect the subtleties of mind and heart of thoughts and feelings
as we engage the breath
starting quite deliberately with an extended exhale
can that exhale empty out
from the bottom of the lungs sometimes it feels like we're emptying
out from the abdomen
and then pause and then allow
allow the breath allow everything and anything that's happening in this
moment this is the very aliveness of being
and it's also the air it keeps the body alive
and the mind alive
and so making the breath deliberate in that way
extend the exhale and explore how much can you extend the exhale
without the inhale being hurried
and gasping
it's like we're doing a yoga stretch with the breath stretching on the exhale
opening up space in the heart the diaphragm the lungs
to receive the inhale
rediscovering a new directed attention
with the exhale and receptive attention
receiving with the inhale
[Music]
it teaches the interplay of shamatha and vipassana
and then chewing into the breath in that way
letting it instruct you and
is it helpful to maintain that deliberateness for a while
or is now would it be most helpful to resume
the natural rhythm of breath in the body
can you let your body decide
can you let the way you're tuning in to the process of aliveness and awareness
decide how to engage the breath
okay then noticing become more subtle
not just a mental activity
but a body and breath and mind
activity
and noticing and acknowledging
how is mind now
are the thoughts flooding in
are they becoming spacious and quieter
however it is so beard
attending and experiencing as fully as possible however it is
and letting the effort of engagement
be guided by what enlivens attention
what supports awakeness
contending to the breath have a fullness of attention
relinquishing any tendency to keep the narrative going
very deliberately pausing and bringing full attention to
breath
full attention to exhale
nothing in this great flow of existence needs to be held held onto
and with the inhale
nothing in this boundless sea of existence
needs to be resisted
full attention to exhale releasing letting go
of suffering
letting go of distress sadness
fears and anxieties
like a great act of compassion
a deep caring and nurturing of being
and with the inhale allowing receiving
the nourishing enlivening
experience of now
do
and as i ring the bell
receiving the sound of the bow
i'll bring it three times and then letting the sound of the bell
open to all sides
the same way our awareness
opens to everything
it teaches us in an inconceivable way
how this individual consciousness is part of whole being
[Music]
[Music] [Applause]
meditation can be such an extraordinary teacher
of the very workings of our being [Music] which can so often create
challenges problems and difficulties those very same workings when held in
awareness become a profound wise and compassionate gift
to my mind when i reflect on that teaching every day is a good day
the uh the teacher's name was jungmen
and it's intriguing that you know young men was considered a
a wonderfully insightful and skillful teacher
and how the phrase that he's most remembered for
is so so simple in in one way we could say so trite
you know about [Music] at the very same time
so utterly profound yeah
if you take the word good you know what is it to live
a good life about it
what is it to not harm but to do good
[Music] and our meditation is offering us a way
to explore that alchemy
in a kind of elemental way you know even within our own body how do we
nourish it
how do we nourish the vitality of being
day by day breath by breath experienced by
experience interaction by interaction
how do we soften the ways in which we suffer
the ways in which we closed on consider it more helpful to distract
ourselves
how do we nurture the confidence
the trust in who we are and how we are to take on
the challenges of our day of every week
of our life
how do we enliven our relationships
so often an interplay with others
where we want to discharge our negative emotions
i'll say this or i'll do this because something in me is hurting
how do we enliven relationships how do we bring the best out of others
of the situations in our life
in the situations of our world
all this flowering form the roots of awareness
and young men simply saying every day is a good day
[Music] can the challenge of life
be such that can it be related to in a way
that something is nurtured
and supported to blossom
in a way it's a an inquiry
into the nature of panya [Music]
what is the wisdom of our practice
that can help us discover the response to those
existential questions
in part of its cognitive no part of it's pretty straightforward
if you just act out your pain in an aggressive way
you don't flourish and the recipient of your aggression doesn't flourish
and then more subtly how do we see the self being
the self how do we see how it
limits through deep-seated emotions negative emotions how it limits
its own being how do we nurture
the positive deep-seated emotions
for our own benefit and for the benefit of everyone
and then how in a way below thought in a way
beyond thought how do we sense the interconnectedness of being
sometimes so simple the way we say thank you
the way we hold the door open for the stranger who's behind us as they also leave them
in in japanese buddhism the the sacred act of kindness
is revered [Music] it's like a special treasure
the fact that the person won't even notice that you were the person who indeed
acted out the kindness or generosity delightful
you're freed from the burden of oh and then will they
be grateful to me notice how wonderful i am you're free from that burden because
it's a secret you'll never know
and the ways in which our own life has been supported and nourished
in ways that we'll never know
and when we when we allow ourselves to engage that
that our life has been supported by many people we do know
and maybe many that we don't
it offers us a kind of reassurance
in this ferocious world
but in the midst of all the things that are going on
there is the steady beat of kindness and generosity
and the reassurance and the comfort
and the encouragement it offers
this sends the blossoming
of awareness
as we receive our natural tendency is to give
the enactment of our connectedness
we're all in this together right down to the microbes
and the oceans and the skies of being
[Music] so young man says every day is a good
day and our mind can say
oh tell me something profound sophisticated
[Music] but something deep in our being
delights in hearing that every day is a good day
okay and here's the day
and here's a me engaging them
okay let's do it
thank you very much
may every day be a good day
okay