okay now formally hello and welcome [Music]
to happy hour this friday or saturday for some of you
it's already saturday or might be a different day if you're listening on audiodharma
so [Music] for our practice today
as i gave you a slight preview i guess on wednesday a couple days ago
the invitation is to to invite our heart in the practice of
gratitude but the way we will approach it tonight today is a little different from how
we've approached it in the past always a new there's so many different ways to do
these practices have you noticed we always discover something new about our hearts and about our capacity
so the way i'd like to invite us to consider the gratitude practice today is is
somewhat similar to metta in that
we will [Music] uh engage in pri in gratitude practice for the people in our lives as if we're
doing some kind of a life review but with the perspective the perspective of appreciation
perspective of gratitude so just as in meta practice we would invite
first people who are near and dear to us the concentric circles will do that and
and invite them with a sense of appreciation with a sense of gratitude
so tonight in our practice it's as if we'll have a little visit with each
person we'll stay for a little bit just appreciate them appreciate what
they have brought into our lives um [Music] qualities our friendships our
relationships and we linger with them hang out with them
in our heart space for a while and then we move on to the next and
um just to say some a couple of things to note one is
the longer we stay with one person the more the steadier our heart
and mind become so if we're doing this practice for the sake of
concentration developing concentration we would stay with one person for the
entirety of the period which is what we do with meta we usually stay with one
person for a long time so please know that but tonight we're
just approaching it a little differently so if you notice your mind getting a little restless or starting thinking too
much then just stay with one person okay and you judge if your mind is pretty
stable having a visit with one person and then another person enters and you
have a visit a gratitude visit in your heart with this other person then it's okay
you can move on from person to person to person so be your own guide see what
works for you how long to linger with one person um as long as your mind is is pretty
stable doesn't get too um to too scattered okay
and one last thing i want to say before we engage in our practice is that
um as you will notice there are
similarities of course there are similarities between the practice of meta loving-kindness wishes
for well-being and the practice of feeling grateful appreciating for
apprecia expressing appreciation in our hearts for someone
and while you might notice you might notice that
they lead to one another and in fact appreciating having gratitude for
someone easily leads to easily leads to goodwill for them oh thank you for being in my
life thank you for having been in my life oh may you be well i wish you well so you
you might discover that the heart naturally flows from one to the other so be mindful be aware
and [Music] at any point if
the mind needs more stability and quiet just come just come to one person or
come to yourself just stably appreciating this being who is you okay
all right that is the framework for our practice
dear sangha let's formally start
so landing arriving
arriving in our seat taking our place
on this land on this earth planet earth
taking our seat claiming our seat
i am here
as always we start with arriving settling with the breath
and the body
feeling our feet firmly on the ground
well rooted connected
moving to our sit bones feeling our bottom on the cushion on the chair
so many contact pipes
feeling her hands on her lap
contact points between our fingers our hands
our legs
the warmth the coolness heaviness
greeting our breath in the abdomen in the lower abdomen
the entirety of each in breath
beginning middle and end of the outbreath
enjoying each breath allowing yourself to enjoy
to relish the simplicity of just sitting and being breathed
nowhere to go nothing to do in this moment
but to just be
it's like this right now opening opening your awareness
to include all the sensations in the body
awareness wide spacious
it can include anything arising and passing
the breath sensations even thoughts can arise and pass
don't have to follow them
present
spacious body relaxed soft
softer with each out breath
you
feeling embodied feeling your feet
feeling your bottom the cushion your hands on your lap
breath in the lower abdomen
this entire body being braved
feeling embodied i'd like to invite you
to bring to mind your heart space invite
someone from your life with whom you have an easy relationship and
you feel grateful for feel grateful for their presence in their life in your life either from your past or
or present
as if you're having a little visit without words or maybe with words silently in your
heart of appreciating them appreciating their
being their is-ness their suchness
the way they are nobody else is like them
opening your heart with appreciation to their suchness
with gratitude
the goodness they bring to your life the way they are
their mannerisms their quirks all of that appreciation gratitude
and spend some time with this first being
whenever the time feels right
maybe you want to linger longer or maybe the time has come
for you to bow to each other maybe hug each other whatever feels
appropriate for you and someone else enters
the space
sound from your past or present appreciate them
with gratitude appreciation for the role they've had in your life
for the gifts they've they have bestowed upon you
they've given you
through knowing them
lingering as long as needed feels appropriate
to appreciate be grateful and when the time is right welcoming
[Music] another person near and make sure you're embodied don't get too heady feel your
feet feel your bottom on the cushion feel your presence
in this moment you don't want to get too heady with this gratitude practice but keep it embodied
keep it embodied with the breath
senses
now with your own time inviting others as you wish one by one lingering with
each with appreciation and gratitude letting your heart
delight be gladdened with gratitude
you
stay embodied discover your thinking too much
stay with one person for a while come back to the breath
mind is steady connected to the breath
have visits with one being followed by the next followed by the
next with the timing that feels appropriate for you
opening your eyes to see the good to see the good if you happen to
remember in some way they were not supportive etc
let go of that that's not this is not the time for that practice
intend to let go right now
seeing through the eyes of gratitude
allowing your heart to be a light
with gladness
we can choose what we lean into
you
this gratitude practice gratitude circle can invite friends
relatives benefactors
colleagues
teachers coaches
try to connect clearly with each person as if you're seeing them brightly
or hearing them feeling them before you move on to the next really connecting
with each being
review breaths
if your heart feels open to bringing maybe a few people you've had challenges
with and see if you can if there's gratitude for
for them also you don't have to and don't push it
see what feels supportive
you can also bring people you have supported if you've had students or junior colleagues
thanking them appreciating appreciating them for giving you the
opportunity to be helpful
you
as you appreciate those from whom you've received and
perhaps those to whom you have given support see you're in this
interconnected web of giving and receiving can there be gratitude
for yourself or this being who is you
and for the last moments of this practice period
appreciating with gratitude so many people
so many people in your lives
who have graced your life with their presence
so many people
and appreciating this being who is yourself who has showed up
to this practice for this practice as well as you've been able to
thank you thank you me dedicating the goodness of this practice
with gratitude to all beings everywhere may all beings be happy
we all brave beings
be free
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so we approached gratitude practice today
slightly differently gratitude for people in our lives present and past
in the style of a life review almost
and this practice tonight is inspired by some practice in
the book a year to live by peter peter levine
so so love to hear your reflections what did
you notice what came up for you you can raise your hand or type in chat
and again if you type in chat just to me i will only read your reflection not
your name if it's to everyone i'll also acknowledge your name and as i'm waiting for your hands to go
up and your reflections to come in and your or your questions um
oh great i already see your reflection please fred
i noticed and i was struck by the fact that in a couple of cases
people i thought of who i wouldn't say i'm the closest to had the strongest emotional valence
i i felt our connection i could remember some words that we had spoken not about the
so long ago and had a lot of emotion for me it was um
it was it was touching and pleasing and where
so that's someone who's you know a friend a friend but not someone i see all the time and not
not someone i would think of as being in the closest circle of my heart uh still
had a lot of love and energy there and that was a nice surprise
thank you so much for for sharing that friend that gladdens my heart that that
surprise of oh wow as we practice
just these beautiful discoveries how lovely it brightens my heart as as i
feel your heart brightened by this lovely surprise thanks for sharing fred that's lovely
other reflections what did you notice
don please
thank you um i noticed uh all the people i was surprised just uh
it sort of appeared oh wow i haven't thought about you in a long time it was
was nice and um and and the other thing i confess i was
um sort of overwhelmed and uh and i sort of had a retreat after a while and this
were focused on myself for a bit but uh very nice practice thank you
great thank you don i love hearing the sense of just the joy of wow so many people in
this gladness and also really appreciate hearing how
you wisely worked with a sense of overwhelm because overwhelm can indeed come up with this practice like wow so
many people and probably there's so many more people i haven't thought about or whatever however overwhelm comes and
just coming back to yourself wonderful great great lovely thanks for
sharing that yeah that came up for me also that the sense of wow so many
people so many people i hadn't thought about in a long time some childhood friends some family
members some people from way way way way back it was just
so just so lovely so many people who've touched my lives and just being with who
they are they've graced my life with with their presence
jerry says i noticed a much wider gratitude list that i needed
to pay attention to and the nuance of the different types of gratitude
for all of them yes yeah thank you jerry i appreciate that
so a wider list it's just both a white list and also the nuances of gratitude
for different types actually i wonder if you you'd be willing to say a little more
you don't have to but if if you like to um what you mean what you notice about this
nuance that you're referring to i don't where are you i don't see you to ask you to raise your hand uh hold that
there okay try now
um so uh i know i speak uh frequently so i don't
want to hog the time but uh you have you haven't for a while so i'm trying to
restrict myself i can talk a lot but anyhow um so uh
it was the issue that like i really liked these uh sanghas
they really have transformed my life i you know i actually was commenting to someone at lunch today
another colleague and her she recently lost her um husband
and she said haven't you felt lonely in this uh period of of um
covert and i said you know i i don't feel lonely and i was reflecting to my own psychiatrist about this
and i said you know this sangha it is taken me into such gravitas
that a nuance that uh uh
and depth and growth that uh it's not even part of my feelings and
i'm quite impressed by it you know i've gone on retreat as you know with joseph goldstein and they talked about having
you know faith in the dharma faith in the in your practice and in the sang and of course
in a large city i live in getting to sangha and traffic and subway trains and all that i did never do it but this has
been quite amazing and so it's part of the nuances of the gratitude that i have for this sangha that there are so many
different people from different walks of life and and continence
that it has overwhelmed me at times with the
richness and when i go to bed at night and write out three things that i'm grateful for
i'm amazed that the sangha comes up almost each day
as one of the three and i i never thought in my life that that
would be such a major part and so i'm ever so grateful that it's going to continue after covet it's one of the
richnesses of a life that i never thought would when i was on retreat with joseph goldstein
with you as my tutor in 2014 i remember thinking of sangha how am i going to get
to a sanctuary in toronto like it takes me uh uh you know half an hour to go 20 blocks or 10 blocks or something
and uh now i did now i just click on that computer and here you are
everyone from australia to ireland and back so that's an example of the nuances and
there are many others but that was one and i also thought of students and professors and other people who have
influenced where i am today and as long as i'm alive
i will try to make this place a better place
thank you so much jerry good thank you so much for your reflection has brought up so much joy and gratitude
in my heart hearing your reflections and i see smiles on other people's faces as
you were talking and nodding and i have so much gratitude for this sangha what a beautiful beautiful sangha we
have co-created together so much gratitude yeah
thank you yeah very very helpful thank you for sharing that really appreciate it
yeah so dear sangha time has come for us to transition into small groups the part
that so that you can meet folks from ireland to to uh
australia to singapore and all the places in the middle in the u.s and and uh
etc etc so yeah and and richard also on youtube says so touched by your sharing jerry so
thank you for stepping in and and taking the invitation to share so
i'm going to create the breakout rooms dear ones here we go um and as always
take 15 seconds for
silent mental or maybe silent gratitude for each other maybe that's more appropriate silent gratitude for each
other and then share as much or as little as you wish
so the rooms are open take care of yourself take care of each other here we go
welcome back everyone the rooms are closed and we have
just a couple of minutes if any reflections when you notice would you like to share
especially if you haven't spoken for a while or you can type it in chat
yes please
so um i don't know i think that it's been always happening to um
just revisit uh when i was a kid um the teachers
they're such a great they're such a just a big part of the you know little kids
and um i always appreciate that like certain teachers were so supportive me
and they trusted um like they believed me believe
in me and i might probably they already see me that i'm gonna just walk the different
path and other people and um [Music]
i it just it was really nice to have them visit me smile at me
you know we just you know greeting each other yeah it wasn't really nice that is so
sweet i love thank you for bringing up teachers especially teachers when we're very young they're not forgotten they're
part of us absolutely such a strong impact yeah thanks for
teachers bringing teachers in yeah thank you for that
and and um i see one more hand and let's take this and then yeah can it please
yeah as a retired teacher i went to a number of my favorite giggly students
in the past and that was really follow students that always make me laugh my eyes make me
smile i went back with gratitude towards them so that was special for me
oh my god i just love it thank you both i love the back to back comments and and
uh sue hung's as i i always have trouble remembering your name forgive me her comment and your
comment can back to back the student and teacher it just it just
makes my heart so happy in giving we receive and in receiving we give it's
part of the circle of gratitude hence the the gratitude circle tonight so this is very sweet and jerry
says the other thing i forgot to mention was the collective intelligence and especially emotional intelligence of the
sangha at times overwhelms me with gratitude yes indeed thank you for
naming that jerry there is so much wisdom there is so much heart so much
heart in this sangha and i thank you all thank you all for showing up for
practicing for cultivating um for your own benefit and the benefit of
all those whose lives yours touches may all beings be happy may all beings be
free including ourselves
thank you all