so a warm welcome a warm welcome to you wherever you are in the world whatever
time zone lovely to be together to practice
in this moment in time so for the practice for today's
practice um we're going to practice turn our attention turn our heart to the
practice of mudita vicarious Joy with which is the sure way to Gladden the
heart Gladden the mind um both for our lives and for the
benefit of other practices that we do it's it's an important practice and just to bring it to context since the
beginning of the year we've been going through the four Brahma viharas in order
spending time with meta with all the categories the concentric circles we
spend plenty of time with Aruna compassion the concentric circles
expanding expanding our heart and now perfect for a Friday we have just made
our way into the next Brahma vihara which is mudita vicarious
Joy um sympathetic Joy different ways it's it's
translated I'll say a couple of words about the practice before we start and of course similarly we'll go through
this in the next days through the different categories practicing
exploring expanding little by little so the practice of mudita mud in
poly is the practice of when meta which is
Goodwill kindness consider kindness meeting someone who in a neutral s position in
life not really happy not really unhappy it expresses itself as Goodwill may you be safe may you be
happy now the same Goodwill if it comes in contact with
someone who's suffering it expresses itself as compassion may you be free from
suffering may you have ease now the same meta good willll same
warm-heartedness friendliness same emotion same
sense um same sentiment let's call a sentiment if it comes in contact it
touches someone who's actually has blessings in their lives is Happy it
expresses itself as mudita may you be may your happiness
continue you I'm happy for your happiness yay may your happiness never
end so there's a sense of celebration of goodness in the world there's a sense of
happiness for another person's happiness so that's one way to think of mudita and
um the Dalai Lama says if you're only happy for your own Good Fortune you have
one out of seven billion chance of being happy but if you cultivate happiness for
other people's happiness your chances increase to seven billion because each
being each being has something they're happy about some good fortune it may not
be everything in their lives so so it's best again we start this
practice where it's easiest where it's easiest for us
and tonight the invitation will be to start with someone whom you naturally
feel happy for yay I'm happy for your happiness and
again they don't need to be happy in every aspect of their life but one aspect one blessing in their life that
that you celebrate with them you're just happy for them when they call you up they tell you or they share with you you
just you being with gladness for them as if it were your own goodness so we start where it's
easiest and one thing to say is that the
um um this practice the uh near enemy
and far enemy the near enemy of this practice um actually I'll talk about the
far enemy which is Envy which can come up which um again if it comes
up um Turn The Meta to yourself because in that moment meta becomes compassion
you're holding yourself with oh sweetie you really want this thing and you don't have it a so so it
becomes um compassion for yourself so as long as you practiced
kindness um in turned into any way
as long as you practice kindness uh Express kindness for and kindness
celebrating someone else's Good Fortune kindness turn to compassion for yourself
if eny comes up you're doing this practice right okay all right
so so let's get started those are the framing commentary for tonight let's get
started so like to invite you now to get into your medit meditation
posture ah you may need to shift and move lie down which is perfectly fine if
your body needs that
and Landing Landing in your
body Landing in the body with the breath
and as always we'll spend a few minutes just [Music]
arriving with the breath with the
body taking refuge in the Simplicity of this [Music]
moment sense of intimacy with the breath the entirety of the
breath receiving the breath in the ey abdomen I
recommend so there is a sense of settling
arriving the lower body with the feet
letting yourself be breathed Let the Body relax let yourself be
breathed e
and let yourself enjoy
appreciate the goodness of this breath moving through you
as if your awareness with is
tinged with appreciation as if your awareness of the
breath is smiling appreciatively receiving the breath
in the abdomen and the lower
body e
if you notice thoughts arising it's
okay it's part of this practice the mind will continue to
think so appreciate the moment when you realize
when you become awake and aware of the thinking
process bring the sense of appreciative
wakefulness to that
moment smilingly gently letting go and coming
back to the breath tilling the soil settling for a few more
minutes e
inviting your nervous system to relax to soften it's
okay it's okay at this moment putting down whatever you've been
carrying e
enjoying just this Breath Right Here Right
Now
e
e e
feeling sensing your breath in the
body feeling embodied not in your
head bringing the center of gravity down down down from your
head your abdomen sit
[Music] bones legs and
feet
e e
now as we continue to feel the body be
embodied feeling the breath in the
body to be tethered
grounded stable in our
presence I'd like to invite
you to bring to Heart someone in your
life for whom you care flows with ease could be a pet could be a child someone
you care about with whom you don't have much of a
complicated relationship perhaps and if it's a little complicated it's
okay someone for whom you have an easy sense of care Good
Will happiness for their well-being
you're happy for their happiness you celebrate their well-being
their Good Fortune whatever it might
be whatever aspect of their life it might
be bringing this being into your heart into your
mind as you can continue to connect with your body and
breath connecting also with the
image with the felt sense of this being if your visual their
image you're auditory what they sound
like or maybe the felt sense of what it's like to be with [Music]
them using all senses whatever
senses you can to bring them to your mind and now bring to mind
also one aspect of their
life it's going well doesn't have to be every
aspect but one blessing one goodness in their
life that they're grateful for they're happy about
and let yourself feel connect both with this being this
person and how you feel the sense of
connection and your gladness for there
gladness let yourself feel it this this sense of mudita vicarious
Joy this felt sense of happiness for another being's happiness
letting yourself feel this gladness this brightness in your
heart radiating bringing
Joy abundance gladness to your own heart
and keep [Music] connecting to this being and their Good
[Music] Fortune because that is what brings up
the sense of gladness in your
heart this first pillar which is this being and their gladness gives rise to
the second pillar of this practice which is the sense felt
sense of gladness mudita vicarious joy in your
heart the third pillar could be the phrases if you
wish could say them out to say them
silently I'll offer a few different
options again keeping up the first pillar the felt sense of this being
their gladness Good
Fortune connecting with your gladness for
them the third pillar phrases I'm happy for your
happiness I am happy for your
happiness I Delight I Delight in your good
fortune
or may your happiness may your good fortune may your blessing
you can choose whichever works for you may this blessing
continue made increas may it never
end may this goodness in your
life may it continue
may it grow and [Music]
increase may it never
end knowing we know there is impermanence but yet we share this wish
as a way to cultivate cultivate Good Will and gladness in our heart for
others it's an aspirational
practice aspiring to share our good will not attached to the outcome of it in the
world that it will be this way it that it will never end
but sharing cultivating our heart teaching our heart abundance
gladness for others wishing well for
others if any of practice wains or if your mind gets distracted
connect again more brightly with the felt sense with the
image of this being your connection with them how they
make you feel bring them alive in your mind's
eye through gladness and see how that brings up the gladness in your
heart pillar one leads to pillar two
naturally you can share out of pillar two this felt sense of gladness for them can share the
phrases as a blessing for
them I take Delight I take joy in your good fortune in your
gladness I'm happy for your happiness
your happiness makes me
happy may your good fortune continue may it increase may it never
end whatever version works for you best
by connec by repeating the phrases of
choice you can keep connected to the
practice like a thread continuity can
develop see what works best for
you for
you can connect the phrases with the rhythm of your
breathing as if the good good wishes the good Wills coming out of your heart
center the middle of your chest shared
generously
e
e e
and if at any point the for enemy the opposite Envy
arises it's okay it's a practice of cultivation turn your m uh your good
will towards the suffering of the Envy let it hold yourself with compassion if
that should
arise otherwise may your good
fortune continue dear one may
increase may it never
end e
perhaps visualizing visualizing seeing this dear being
happy happily enjoying this blessing this Good
Fortune letting your heart Delight dance with
them in your mind's eye celebrating with them feel free to be
creative in your imagination in your visualization
and for the last moment of this
practice turning your awareness to your heart to the
cultivation of your own heart with gladness and
appreciation appreciation for yourself you showed up you
tried and if mudita vicarious Joy showed up even for one Split
Second in this practice yay celebrate
that as a seed planted without judgment or anything else that might have
happened but just to celebrate you showed up you inclined your mind towards
goodness and generosity of
spirit yay may all beings everywhere be
happy and free including us
thanks everyone thank you for your
practice I have to say with the practice of mudita vicarious Joy it is a happy
making practice it is a happy making practice and
um having practice with you I feel happier now and again might be different
for different people but as I sense there's a sense of more abundance more joy in my heart as I check
in there's a smile showing up on my face that wasn't here before so it's nice to
check in and take a pulse and see what's happening in your heart in your mind so
so we have time for some Reflections if you like to share you can raise your
hand uh the reactions or you can uh type
in chat if there are questions comments Reflections what did you notice what did
You observe um what was challenging what was
easy would love to hear and have you share
your wisdom and with the community especially if you haven't shared for a while or if you're new would love to
hear from you
so yes okay so I have a question and by the way if you send me questions
privately I won't say your name if you send them to public I'll say your name so question coming what is the near
enemy of mudita I said I would I kind of mentioned it at the
beginning so um the near enemy which is what masquerades as Mita they're
different ones one is sense of Pride where there's a sense of oh um my child
or my friend or oh as if you're really taking birth you're becoming this
instead of your generosity of heart sharing your gladness as a gift for them
there's a sense of Pride the self kind of takes takes Center Stage so pride is
one one of the near enemies the other one um
um is um exuberance and this is a fun one
actually exuberance is when there is so much mud there's so much gladness that
it's almost like you become Punch Drunk on gladness and kind of lose your
stability and your settledness um so because mudita can be
bubbly but when it just goes a little too overboard it doesn't have the
stability of gladness it becomes a little too um yeah it's it's overe
exuberance so that's an couple I like to mention tonight and somebody raised
their hand and their hand disappeared who was it who had raised their hand please raise your hand
again Monica please everyone
Hi um yeah I really appreciated how at the beginning of the talk you pointed
that The Meta can manifest different ways mudito or karuna and when I sat
down and close my eyes I realized I had a lot of pain um physical and emotional
pain that I've just been neglecting for a long time and I wanted so much to do the mudita but I thought it was more I
saw it showing up more as karuna so I focused on that and I feel I feel that friendliness much more towards my
experience feel more present and I feel that kindness so thank you so much oh
terrific thank you Monica I so appreciate hearing your inner wisdom
that yes you know this session it's a it's happy hour it's about any of these practices and really what's what's
called here right now is the physical emotional pain so hey I'm going to turn
the Goodwill The Meta towards this and be with it yay fantastic I am so happy
to hear that this is great lovely you and everyone has the license
to to adapt the practice any which way that works for you in a given um in a
given set fantastic Monica thank you for modeling that and sharing that
lovely yeah great the other Reflections you can type them in
chat or raise your hand there's no wrong
question reflection anything it's all
good anything you notice that surpris you about this
practice either in a challenging way or more easeful
[Music] way Neil
please I was surprised at how difficult I found this uhuh you know you know it
it just you know it just wasn't like a lot of feeling that I felt you know it
was just altogether sort of awkward you know you know there was some jealousy at
some point which you know surprised the heck out of me um because you know I I don't you know I can't say I felt
jealous of this person or you know whatever was going on before um yeah
yeah it was you know it was surprising to me that giving compassion over someone feeling pain seems so much
easier than this yeah yeah thank you Neil I am so
grateful you brought this up um and all of these practices these four
Brahma viharas are also considered purification practices so that as you
were saying oh I didn't realize there was jealousy Envy in this relationship
but here it is it showed up how interesting how interesting is that without any judgment so these practices
as purification practices will unearth will bring up things we kind of there
but they'll bring them up to our attention um so that they can be purified so that we can be with them
otherwise they they are already there we just don't turn our attention to to them
and another thing is that different practices might be easier or harder so
um right now in this shape for form karuna compassion is an easier one for
you and this one oh it's my head so not to say that it's always going to be your Edge but okay this right now in this
form this is what can be cultivated in the same way I trust some I trust other
practices had a little bit of Edge and as you did them the heart opened up and
they became easier and purification happened it sounds like this might be
the new way or the New Frontier of stretching a little bit gently gently
stretching so I so appreciate you saying that naming it and I invite you as you
would expect Neil for you to hang in with this ever so gently not pushing yourself too hard but but trusting that
the heart can purify and EXT extend in its um generosity of spirit with this
practice I'm actually I'm going to say I'm glad for you that it's so nice when we find our edges if it was easy easy if
it was all easy right we would be uh there there wouldn't be any places
to grow so now you have become aware rather I want to say you've become aware of this area of your heart that can use
more cultivation as if you know one finds a muscle in the gym like oh look at this muscle this one needs a little
more work the rest of them are kind of you know strong but this one oh can can use some more practice so thanks for
bringing that up Neil thank you thank
you so okay um one a comment sent to me and it's a
longer one I need to read but time is flying so in order to have enough time
for our practice in small groups let me introduce them and open the rooms so
what I like to invite us to practice with in the small groups tonight is
first um the um maybe spending 30 seconds with
meta for each other 30 seconds of Silence just looking at each other
holding each other with meta and Goodwill and knowing that you're being held with goodwi and then you can share
um as little or as much as you wish about your practice um and appreciating
the wisdom of the community so I'm going to create the and and if you haven't
done the breakout rooms or you're on the edge you're scared of them the community is really really nice so I I really
recommend and suggest you hang in there and you hang in here and you um
um yeah you you you try you stay and let's see I'm trying to speak and create
the groups at the same time doesn't always work okay here we go all right so
[Music] um here we go okay so I've created the rooms
and check it out see what it's like here we
go and everyone is back welcome back
everyone um so there was couple of quick question
sent one is how does one deal with exuberance asked Genie you notice it you
notice there's exuberance and you kind of settle and and um arrive
back into the grounding be grounded in this this and then another question was
asked um do you have to use phrases or is it easier uh um or is it okay to just
focus on the feeling it's fine to Fus focus on the feeling if if the word if wordless works better for you there's
there are no shs in this practice so let's take one reflection um if you
haven't spoken we'd love to hear from you how how was the groups for you how was the experience for you of practicing
Community can type it in chat or raise your hand especially if
you're new would love to hear from you
there who is she so I can unmute myself
I um I had a good time I really enjoyed the sitting in
meditation I felt my body just um really really
warm in the middle of it and uh I really love your
voice yeah I feel really happy and uh you know I I did have one question can
that person receive my good wish so it's just the practice for my
S for my own heart how can people receive this intentions the good wishes yeah
yeah so so with with this practice here um we don't ascribe any I mean there are
other traditions and you that ascribe other but here we only really do it for
the cultivation of our heart because if you try to attach to
result then like are you are you happier is is your good fortune continuing it it
just it's did you know I send lots of exactly I send lots of mudita your way
is it is it there yet is it becomes yeah it becomes problematic so yeah just just
a cultivate just the the reward is is the cultivation of your own heart and
generosity and goodwi and it will show up in the way you are in the world and the way you anyway so yes
that's the short answer so thank thank you so um I see comments here Mita for
Jess's cat right now oh my God that's cute genie says it's hard to talk about
it without exuberance maybe we'll talk more about exuberance a differentiation oh it you mean Jess is cat or about
mudita without exuberance I'm not quite sure what it refers to Albatross is happy to be back oh Jess that's funny
you guys are so cute I love this community anyway um so we've gotten a
couple minutes over time let's let's end formally so thank you all for your practice because you do this practice
cultivation not just for your own sake but for the sake of all those whose
lives you touch directly and indirectly so thank you for showing up for practicing for supporting each other in
small groups it's so precious and valuable so may all beings be happy may all
beings be
free thank you