um so for today's practice we're continuing
to explore the practice of mudita mudita
in pali m-u-d-i-t-a um translated often as vicarious joy
sympathetic joy basically it's happiness for another
being's happiness happiness for another being's happiness which is um a wonderful way for us for our hearts
to to light up to feel happy for circumstances of happiness whether it's
somebody else whether it's external or internal internal will be expressed as gratitude usually modita
becomes gratitude external is this joy for another person's joy
taking delight in someone else's good fortune yay yay and
one you know i've been talking and diana has been talking about mudita so so i won't repeat every all the other
things i've been saying at the beginning of the previous sessions but a new thing i want to introduce a new idea i want to
introduce tonight for our consideration about this practice is
sometimes people wonder and ask what is the relationship between wisdom
practices such as vipassana mindfulness seeing things as they are practicing
with seeing say impermanence etc the wisdom practices what's the relationship between those and the heart practices
metta mudita karuna compassion loving-kindness vicarious joy
and of course they support each other and in many ways there are one and the same when you really deeply
practice insight it opens up to love and compassion and happiness for all beings uh good fortune
it just and then the other way around when you deeply practice these practices of the
heart ah there's a sense of presence and seeing
the way things are it lights up for you it becomes easier to see so so what i want to point
out is as wisdom when when our hearts opens up to the wisdom
of selflessness of the sense of yes there is the self we take care of it of course it's important
we bathe it and feed it and yet as we succeed in not always being so
self-centered in our regard we pop out of that ah there's a sense of
ease there can be a sense of um lightness if we don't keep
uh worrying about the gain and loss of just this person that is me but when we expand our vision
through wisdom practices then there's a sense of opening
to gladness of other people when when we're not just comparing oh is
my gladness more than their gladness it's just happiness in the world there's this from
the perspective of the enlightened mind and if if when i say that you think well
i'm not enlightened yet well fake it till you become it assume in
this moment okay what if in this for the next what and for the next 15 minutes i'm gonna take on
the perspective of the enlightened mind like okay you're in here somewhere
nikki says trust that you're in here somewhere enlightened perspective awakened perspective ah can i lean into
that and ah can i just lean into that and uh can i lean into
that um perspective of awakened mind and like oh
[Music] what if there is more spaciousness and other people's gladness
is is not them and me the other not othering if there's no
othering happening but it's just gladness it's just goodness in
the world it's just goodness and your heart can delight this heart this heart can just delight
in goodness in the world in gladness so as we practice tonight with
uh vicarious joy that is the invitation that is the invitation and you don't
need any previous experience i'll guide you and again if the opposite comes up
whatever comes up as long as you hold it with kindness with care just turn towards it
if if grief comes up if sadness comes up if comparison comes up if judgment comes up as long as you turn
towards it and hold it with kindness it's okay sweetie it's okay kindness it's okay it's okay
this universality of kindness from the perspective of the awakened
mind applied now to this pain right here right now this challenge you're doing this practice right
so just applying friendliness friendliness generosity of heart to whatever arises
maybe gladness in the world maybe challenge it's all good okay so
let's practice together i'll guide us let's let's get into our meditation posture
ah landing landing in your seat landing arriving
hmm letting the body relax
softening all the muscles forehead
the eyes the jaw
shoulders let them drop
ah chest let it relax
abdomen lower abdomen that the tightness
be softened let go from inside
let your sit bones relax give their weight
up to the earth your legs upper legs lower legs and feet
all of them all the lower body
ah dropping dropping their weight onto the ears
bringing the attention to the breath in the lower abdomen
being received in-breath without breath
one breath at a time
letting there be an intimacy between your awareness the knowing
and the breath where the breath is intimately known the entire in-breath and the entire out breath
landing arriving settling with each breath in this body relaxing
letting go
arriving settling with each breath every moment a new arrival
and when thoughts arise simply noticing kindly noticing
and gently saying not now smilingly saying not now thank you
letting awareness come back intimately with the breath in the body settling taking this moment of delicious
refuge in the moment
just this breath just this moment
right here right now
now i'd like to invite you as you feel embodied as you feel
your body the breath in the body
settled connected to the ears
the breath moving through your abdomen
settling settling into
the expansiveness of your own capacity
for goodwill this awakened
mind and heart
also called the buddha nature or maybe just referring to it relating
to it as this capacity within that's
expansive
that you have access to you have had access to many times in your life
this expansiveness of intention and vision
this generosity of goodwill and kindness
this connection as if as said to all of humanity trusting it's there trusting it is
available in here
and as if you were sensing sensing with
seeing with buddha eyes or divine eyes looking at the whole world
as if divinity or the buddha or whatever symbol works for you head slipped into your heart center and
shining through your eyes looking at the world
with eyes of generosity and good well
happy for others happiness
and your eyes land upon someone you don't know very well peace
someone maybe you have seen at the grocery store or a neighbor
stand in for all of humanity
this human being
and through these eyes expansive eyes expansive perspective
that's not just limited to you and your self-interest but appreciate goodness
seeing that this human being is not so different from you
just like you they want to be happy just like you have hopes and dreams
and just as complex and inner life
they have just the comp as complex and inner life as you do
for you to appreciate
as if from within
with this divine eye that yes they want to be happy they have wishes
and hopes and dreams offerings and joys they have blessings in their life just like i do
we're siblings they're not so different in this way in these ways
and just as i would be happy for my own blessing or good fortune
my heart can celebrate and take joy be happy for this person's happiness
whatever it might be
maybe imagining a blessing if the person seems healthy
oh if they're walking around or if they have a job
or whatever it is you can imagine the blessing of a happy partnership for example
it's okay to be creative here with your [Music]
imagination
connecting with the humanity of this being this person
a place of expansiveness of heart
generosity just as i want to be happy just as i celebrate my choice
my good fortune
dear fellow human being may your happiness may your good fortune
may you cherish it may you enjoy it may it increase may it never wane
i take delight i share
in your good fortune's delight
wishing well for you for it to increase
it's okay to be creative in your visualization
to connect with the sense of generosity of spirit of happiness for others happiness
maybe you see yourself as a little fairy with wings flying about and seeing different
people in the world and their good fortune and how happy they are
maybe as they hug their young child whom they love and ah
you feel happy for their blessing for their happiness as if you are feeling it yourself as if it were your own
and staying with a neutral person whomever you choose for for a little while
before moving to the next person staying with them for a while
i'm happy for your happiness they take delight
in your joy as if it were my own
and at any point if the opposite comes up sense of envy
the far enemy it's okay this is the purification practice
turn to it with mitta with kindness supporting yourself with compassion
it's okay holding your own heart with
care
may your happiness continue
may your blessing increase may it never end
fully well knowing that there is impermanence in life and yet
sharing our goodwill
for a neutral random person in the world we don't really know very well
wishing them well wishing them abundance
their blessings to continue feeling happy for their happiness
and notice in the moments when you do when there is happiness for another person's happiness
how your body relaxes there's a sense of joy radiating in you happy making
take note of that
please
may your happiness continue made increase may never end
i'm happy for your happiness
connecting with people in your mind that you know you don't know them well
but they're human beings
in your environment just the same
the compelling complex inner life
and for the last minutes of this practice
letting this appreciation
include your own
blessing some blessing in your life
and let your heart celebrate the goodness of this blessing
taking delight happy for your own happiness
i'm happy for my happiness from my blessings
and whatever rose this period of practice or did not arise
consider it a blessing instead of a distraction or a problem
you showed up it's a blessing that you showed up and you practiced as best as was
available to you yay gladness for that
happiness for this blessing
let your heart be light and joyous for this blessing of
showing up and practicing
may all beings everywhere be happy may all beings everywhere be free
including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for showing up and practicing
what a blessing what a blessing
happy for this happiness of practicing with you in community in this moment that's what i'm in touch with right now
as i see you as i look at you what a blessing it is what good fortune to be able to show up and practice
together unexpected gift of covet
so you're welcome to um type in chat or
raise your hand would love to hear from you especially if you haven't shared
in a while and um if you're new i would love to hear what what do you
notice what was surprising what what you discovered
what worked what didn't it's all welcome your questions reflections
support support the community so
it's an act of generosity for you to actually share of yourself
in this way especially if you usually hold back usually hold back thinking oh
my comments reflections are not that important
so
you can raise your hand and uh using the reactions
under reactions there's a raised hand or you can type it in chat either to me or to everyone what did you notice
what happened was feeling joy for somebody else's
happiness blessing did come easy was it challenging
um did it the framing this way which was a little different i'm actually
feeling into this expansiveness as if you're a little angel or a little butterfly with wings
just kind of expensive did you try that on for size did that work for you did it not
oh lovely thank you don says thank you nikki feeling joy for others
was liberating they are just like me oh beautiful thank you for sharing that dawn i love
this as you talk about it was liberating the sense of liberation feeling joy and seeing the common
humanity feeling joy for others was liberating beautiful
lovely yes carlo i do see your hand usually i
don't see people's hand but for you i do hold and i'm gonna ask you to unmute there you go
one thing that worked really well for me was when you said um thinking about the other person's
uh complexities that they have the complexities the same as i do
to think of people as three-dimensional just like like me that
helped uh unleash some good will towards this neutral person
and to see them as a complete human being instead of just a little bit i know
about them right yeah thank you carla thanks for sharing that and as you're saying that i was
seeing some heads nod in agreement with you yeah thanks for sharing
yeah that's that can be key and we can take that then into our lives oh there's
so little we know about these other human beings they have a life just as compelling as ours
wow right it's obvious in some ways but we don't consider it it's interest
it's profound and eric says i really appreciate it that we meditated on our
blessings it reminded me that amidst any situation there are still blessings yes thank you indeed many
blessings one reflection directly to me um
so um i you don't say the names if you're directly to me unless you want them to be public feeling so lucky to
have had this refuge of love and kindness during the pandemic providing constant love out to this
hurting world oh thank you that's such a lovely reflection so delighted that you're part of this
this community and you keep coming practicing and sharing this constant love to this hurting world and this
uh container and um
and terry says i wonder about the sensation that arises from me when contemplating joy it seems to be
closely related to a deep sadness as well are there are they related emotions um
so when contemplating seems to be closely related to deep sadness is it okay if i ask you to say a little
more about this i'm i'm um not you may want to say
so that i understand what it is you're referring to uh if you could unmute yourself please
terry yeah it's um sort of hard to explain but
these things often are yeah yeah um you know tears well up a deep feeling in
my heart wells up and maybe i'm not understanding maybe i
haven't practiced joy enough i certainly it's not a natural or it's some dealing with deep
depression most of the time maybe it's that i don't know maybe it's so
opposite of what i normally feel then yeah yeah thank you for for adding all
the nuances which are actually beautiful and tender so i don't know and so i'm going to
uh invite you to some investigate some some curiosity to kind of sit with because it
might be that there is a tenderness that so it's not
it's not necessarily because what you're describing sounded to me like tearful tenderness that the joy can feel
so tender like sometimes joy can feel tender when um kind of moist you know like
when you look at the little child or maybe a newborn it's like oh my gosh it's so precious there's the happiness
but yes it's tender like your eyes get moist so i wonder also maybe it's that as it's
finding its way as you were saying in the territory of touching into sadness which might be habitual and kind of finding
its way to unbridled joy it's kind of like finding its territory through
tenderness through sadness through unbridled joy so it's kind of an exploration i wonder
terry how does that land for you yeah that really strikes my curiosity in
me too like huh yeah it could definitely be
tenderness yeah and stay with it and be curious and and oh yeah joyful and it's okay it's
okay um yeah great thank you for sharing that beautiful thank you and matthew will let
this be the last comment before we go into uh the groups yes matthew please i just
wanted to add on to that and that i feel like
a lot of these emotions are kind of like different sides of the same coin and that the heart of him is really like
a feeling of like sincerity maybe would be how i describe it and so it's like when
you feel something sincerely it can very quickly change from
like joy to even like to like compassion or sadness it's like it's like the core of them is
sort of similar and it's that feeling of just like it's that feeling of sincerity which
and so it's like if there's a sad tint to it it's sad but you're sincere about it and then if it's happy it's it's
happy but then you're happy about it or something uh and it but it's all of it is a core
of uh sincerity and it's like a level that i think that you know a lot of times
you're kind of on the surface and so then sincerity it's it feels like sincerity yeah yeah
i appreciate the this whole heart and the sincerity theme you're bringing and what i'll add to it what you brought
in here in this context of practicing these different brahmavir heritages as long as we meet them with kindness
with with care with warmth with as long as say that sadness is held with
kindness ah yes it's hell big is hell with compassion when the when the happiness is held with
kindness it it becomes a celeb celebratory wholehearted celebration of goodness and
gladness so that's where they keep their wholehearted balance in this practice
instead of veering into the the the challenging aspect yeah thank you beautiful and
so let's go into groups now so the invitation for the practice and i'm going to open
the groups as i'm talking about it um so the invitation is
um to doing too many things at the same time here uh the invitation is um
to yeah maybe we'll start with 30 seconds of of silent
mudita for each other because you all have complex lives it's it's just like me all these human beings i don't know
their lives but they're complex and interesting so having the sense of
uh vicarious choice for each other is joys and then you can share as little or as
much as you wish later so i'm gonna open the rooms here we go
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed terrific so we've
got a couple of minutes for any reflections what came up for you what you noticed uh
but you practiced during the practice meetings or the first part and again you can raise your hand if you
like or type it in chat so please
i see i see smiles
you will take one reflection before we end anyone i see thumbs up that's great sweet
great but jerry says i noticed how kindness abounds oh that's beautiful thank you and mary okay here you go
okay now it just went out of my head oh treating my sleepiness with kindness
just like okay i'm sleepy nice so i'm learning kindness thank you
hmm oh that makes me so happy oh training treating that that
sleepiness with gentleness with kindness oh beautiful thanks for sharing that
very lovely and susan asks i like mudita
and think there is more are we going to do it some more yes we are we're going to do it some
more before we transition to the next and final brahmaviara to hold you on the edge of your seat but
yes we're going to do some more with data until we transition so so thank you all thank you
for for sitting practicing showing up
for the benefit of all beings everywhere not just yourself we do this practice
for for all beings everywhere including ourselves may all beings be free may all beings be happy
[Music] thank you all thank you