so welcome to this meditation session and
andy unequivocally here we are
to acknowledge
the location that you're sitting in to acknowledge what is supporting your
weight where the pull of gravity meets us
a surface and to really feel that you're here
and one of the
opportunities in meditation is to recognize the space that's around
everything that whatever we sense whatever we feel whatever we
experience whatever we think
that there's a way of seeing it in its own uniqueness as a particular manifestation
and we with around which is the space of
awareness around which it can exist just in itself as it is in a way that can be
seen as respectful for the uniqueness of it for the momentariness
of it but also allows us to
not get involved or caught in it
allowing each things to exist like a star is allowed to exist in the vast night
sky so different sensations and different
vedana feeling tones and thoughts and whatever there's a way of being open relaxed with
awareness to see it by itself
just without diminishing its value you can add the word just
it's just a feeling just a sensation it's just a thought it's just a sound
and that just maybe is to allow you to recognize that whatever
in unique situation event comes into awareness there can be
the space of awareness around it
there can be a gap between what we are aware of
and how we react how we react to it
how we
think about it how we feel about it
that gap that space between them is a space of freedom
the gap and freedom the space between the way in which we identify
with stuff or assume there's a self makeup idea of me myself and mine
maybe it's okay that you do so but there's a space
a gap a pause between each thing
and each thing is independent free of the self-making we do
so gently closing your eyes and taking a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing as you exhale
if you take a deep inhale maybe your torso chest expands out into the space around
you and inhale it recedes
letting your breathing return to normal and on the exhale continue to take a few
moments to relax the body
softening in the face the shoulders the
belly
and then becoming aware of the simplicity of breathing
that whatever sensations are present in your breathing
exist in surrounded by the space of awareness
they exist as particular points of sensation
places of sensation outside of which
those sensations are not seen or felt
the sensations that make up the edges of your body
beyond them their space
in a certain way kind of way inside of them there is space
and you might be thinking about what's happening
but there is a space or a gap between your thoughts
and the experience it's possible to know the experience
in its own simplicity
as distinct from thinking thoughts
the space around each phenomenal experience
might also be characterized by silence a sweet silence
or a stillness
and as you breathe perhaps breathe through and into
the spaciousness here the silence that's here
this stillness that's here
so you don't deny anything but each thing each experience
can exist within the space of awareness as
itself
if you focus on the objects in a room you might not notice the space
that's in the room if you focus on your thoughts and your
feelings and sensations you might not notice the space that
holds all that
we tend to not notice the space
but that's where we can find freedom
notice the space around things
breathe with it
relax into it
let the space help silence the mind
as we come to the end of the sitting
to open the space in your mind in your heart
to take in this vast wide world of ours
a world of suffering a world of joy
a world of oppression and a world of people who care to end depression
a world of poverty and sickness and those who work hard
to alleviate poverty and sickness
it's a huge wide world young the old
those who are alone and those who are together
and to make uh have our heart be wide enough and spacious enough
to allow each of them to be held uniquely in our hearts so there's lots of space
for people to be known and listened to and seen
may it be that we cannot maintain or find
a heart fullness mind fullness
that allows us to meet others and care for others for their own uniqueness
for their own personal circumstance
may it be that this meditation supports us
to live for the welfare and the happiness of others
may that be an extension of what we find in meditation
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe
may all beings be happy
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so this will be the last talk on vedana the feeling tones the effective quality
of our experience that all things
have among all the different qualities that things have experiences have all the different characteristics of
them they have they have they have either have they're pleasant
or unpleasant or neither pleasant or unpleasant and uh and we're kind of focusing on the
real specificity of one of a moment of experience of something in the complexity of life
and many things happening in a kind of swirl of or complexity there could be a
combination of all those that we can identify but when you get quiet and still and really kind of tune into the
details particularity of what it is then um the um the
um you know they're pleasant unpleasant or
neutral and now one of the really fascinating
teachings of the buddha is that people's uh philosophies
people's view of life people's maybe he doesn't say this but even though maybe their politics have at
their base or at their at their root somehow uh a reaction
to what's pleasant unpleasant or neutral and the very sophisticated philosophies
very sophisticated justification for political political systems or views might have its beginning
in a reactivity to things that we find pleasant and unpleasant
and and this idea of pleasant and unpleasant that we're talking about here is not the
raw unpleasant and pleasantness of experience there is no such raw thing because
almost right away things arise pleasant unpleasant with
our perceptions our evaluation our associations with it
so that this pleasant unpleasant sometimes in in is referred to as liking and disliking
so this movement of liking and disliking being for or against is so deep and it's kind of amazing that
uh if we really trace back our where the basis of how we react in the world is
then we have this
you know trace it back you know it all begins with pleasant and unpleasant and this is what i said earlier
so anyway the teaching of the buddha is that the the all these philosophies and ideas of
you speculation speculative views about life the nature of life
can have their roots in this simple thing pleasant and unpleasant and the one that's most significant for
many people and who would interested in becoming free is the way in which
ideas of self identity can have their roots the way we not not
identity that we are born into or that other people assume about us or you know there's a lot of identities
which just come with being human being that uh with but um the act of
identification the act of latching on to an identity and and these all these different
identities that we swirl around in kaleidoscope are relevant at different times if we
latch onto it cling to it hold on to it then we'll suffer and this clinging to identity clinging
to ideas of self it has at the root of it this concern
with pleasant and unpleasant pleasant and unpleasant can be a very deep conditioning for this movement towards
me myself and mine and one way it takes its shape is um when we say when we identify
with the feelings themselves when uh the feeling tone of experience uh
when things are pleasant it's like this is i'm the one who's experiencing the pleasantness or i'm the one who
experienced the unpleasantness this is my pleasant experience this is my
unpleasant experience and um on this very close kind of wrapping
ourselves around clinging and having a sense of self in relationship to
feeling tones is one of the great sources of suffering and one of the great kind of
possibilities of freedom is to allow the kaleidoscope of
feeling tones of how things appear and disappear as pleasant and unpleasant to just come and go and kind of float in
them or or make room for them or be spacious around them and and so
uh and feeling these feeling tones are something that if you really tune
into them and really get close and feel them they're not stationary they're not fixed
they're actually quite fluid and changeable and the analogy that buddha gave for them is
um that they when there's a big rainstorm and
the rain is formed uh falling raindrops are falling on a lake there's a spell the spatterings and
little bubbles and spatterings of of uh you know a splashing of
flake water from the drops and those appear ephemerally they're there for brief moment and then they
dissipate and so the feeling tones whether things are pleasant unpleasant or not neither
have that kind of ephemeral quality to it and if we can really settle back
and open up in the spaciousness of the mind to feel intimately that kaleidoscope of changing
sensations that's where sometimes we can loosen up the grip of self
around the sensations themselves and to let go and it's not meant to let
go of necessarily let go of to philosophical views ideas of what self
is at the core what this buddhist tradition is about is letting go of clinging any kind of
clinging and one of the means to do that is to be aware of the pleasant and unpleasant
and neutral uh quality of our experience and if you could kind of tune into the
the changing impermanent inconstant nature of those feeling tones you'll be well on your way to not
to appreciate that clinging to it doesn't really work and that sometimes
we cling to is not the pleasant and unpleasant but rather the concepts and ideas we
have of pleasant and unpleasant and uh and that makes them stationary seem like they last longer than they
really do and um more constant than they really
are and um and so this idea that um
and so to discover non-clinging through feeling tones
discover freedom to feeling in feeling tones and one way to do that is to appreciate
the space around each feeling tone the stillness the silence within which
the raindrops are splattering and
so feeling tones pleasant unpleasant and neutral and becoming aware of the ephemeral
nature of them and if they don't feel ephemeral they don't feel you don't see them or sense
them as somehow changing maybe flashing in and out of existence so there there's continuity over time with some
sensations but they are actually in the moment they're kind of flashing in and out of existence in a
certain way if you don't see it that way chances are that you're living
in your ideas of them your thoughts of sensations your thoughts are pleasant your thoughts
are what's unpleasant and but if you really turn the lens of mindfulness around
carefully to the thoughts themselves you'll see that thoughts too are
insubstantial thoughts too are like raindrops that come and go and are there for a moment
and then they fade away unless we're holding on to them or unless we somehow
in the clinging are stringing a whole series of them together so they look like they're
constant but in fact there's actually a lot of
space between thoughts between ideas
if we don't string them together if we should allow each thing to be there in its own uniqueness
and in that space there can be freedom freedom of the mind that does not cling
so those are my thoughts on this topic of
vedana and i look forward to being back in a little over a week
and i hope that your weekend is pleasant and in the
pleasantness you see the inconstant nature of pleasantness
not holding on to it not clinging to it but learning how to
enjoy with no clinging whatsoever
so thank you all