so
we continue with this series of talks on
the 16 steps of mindfulness of breathing
and we're now coming into the last
tetrad
that's a tread on observation
on observing the last tetrad is the last
steps 13 14 15 and 16
and they have in common all four steps
in the introduction of a new
verb a new and that's the verb
to observe
and it goes something like this one
trains
to observe x
or tr on trains observing
x when breathes in
when trains observing x when it breathes
out
and so in these uh last four steps
there's something we're observing
and and we continue with the breathing
and there's something about the
continuity of mindfulness of breathing
which is allowing us to observe things
but helping us not latch on to them
helping us not to cling or hold on
there's a kind of way in which by
staying with the breathing
there's a continual kind of letting go
that breathing is where the mind is
resting
and we notice all kinds of things happen
but in a certain way we're kind of
letting go of our involvement
letting go of any prioritization or
doing anything with it or
changing it or or thinking about it
we're just kind of going along with the
breathing going back to the breath being
with the breath
and it's a way of keeping ourselves soft
fluid relaxed
a letting go and allowing the psycho
physical system to have a break
from our active involvement our active
deliberate kind of engagement and doing
and wanting
and uh and letting something deeper to
happen that could only happen if we get
out of the way
and so in these last four steps
uh this is uh represents represented
very strongly by the word
the this verb to observe the idea of
observing
and it's the first time in the
anapanasati this
discourse 16 steps where observing comes
into play
and and
if you go if you read through the
teachings of the buddha and the suttas
we see that most commonly observing
as a practice is a very well-developed
practice when the mind is able to be
really centered in the present
concentrated a strongly concentrated
present
mind is the one that begins
doing the practice of and
so there's a lot of preparation in in
the 16 steps you know the first 12
are preparing ourselves for this
capacity to
to lean back and just kind of watch and
just observe what's happening
without being involved
some translators translate this work
this verb anupasati
as contemplating and
contemplating uh in in the way that i
relate to that word is closer to
thinking
reflecting about something thinking
about something it suggests a kind of
more active
thinking process observing which is
actually the
etymologically what the word anapasati
means anu the prefix means
towards something and the pasati means
to see
seeing uh and to put him together we're
we're gazing onto something seeing
looking towards something
in a sense and um but because of this
uh i think observing works very well
as it as a translation we're observing
and observing does there is a kind of
deliberateness kind of uh
uh in observing but it's not quite the
same
as as actively looking
it's just settling back and just being a
being an observer
and i liken it to being a naturalist who
goes into
some kind of natural setting to observe
some natural behavior of animals or
birds or something
and it's very important that the
naturalist
not interfere with the life there and
somehow stay kind of unrecognized by
what's happening so they
watch nature unfold without the
interference
from the humans and just but and then
just to observe
and um so earlier in in these 16 steps
it begins with breathing in one nose
one is breathing in breathing out one
nose or breathing out
so this idea of knowing is one of the
attentional faculties we have to know
as we begin knowing the breath and no we
never stop
knowing the breath we recognize with
breath we bear with the breathing
but then we're also what's happening
we're experiencing things we're
experiencing the body
we're experiencing joy and happiness
we're experiencing the mind
we're experiencing gladness experiencing
subtleness steady concentration and
we're experiencing
liberation and this experiencing is also
a little bit
uh passive it isn't that or receptive it
isn't so much like we're doing
something we're just allowing yourself
to experience
knowing also we're just knowing
something
and we're not judging it or criticizing
it we're just knowing it clearly
and these two activities of knowing and
experiencing
are here to ground us here in the
present moment
and so at some point then it shifts to
just observing
and um and so this is where the art of
deeper mindfulness is to observe
and um in the other mindfulness
discourse of the buddhism
there there's a lot of language of
observing
and there also if you read the text
carefully it's
there the observing is the higher stages
of mindfulness that's where observation
comes in
and and so it's earlier
than knowing the experiencing is kind of
grounding us in the present moment
helping us stay present
learning to develop concentration to be
resting in the present
and when the ability to be focused and
present in the moment
is becomes uh easy and light and we feel
really grounded and centered here
that is when observation becomes
stronger
and because uh we're going towards being
less and less
intentional deliberate even
less and less um
activated or active in the mind
because the more activated we are in the
mind the more
kind of waves or agitation or clouds
there are
over our capacity to see clearly
and so as we get quieter and quieter and
quieter
what we're left with is this ability
just to observe
and then we learn to trust that to
settle back okay now i'm just observing
i'm not needing to interfere or again no
judging
i don't have to fix anything or adjust
anything or
make anything different i'm just just
watch just watch
and you can feel that in this kind of
very centered place that
if we start reaching out to do something
to fix something to judge something or
think about something
it feels a little bit like we're losing
something we're losing the
open field we're out losing the freedom
we're losing the
peacefulness of just observing and so
it's very clear that observing is a
better place to be
in this deeper states of meditation
and it becomes very important in these
final steps
because we really want to get out of the
way
and not overlay concepts ideas judgments
should
shouldn't on top of our experience we
want to really be able to take it in
things much closer to actually how
they're perceived
actually how before the experience
before a lot of judgments and concepts
and generalizations that we make about
things
just to observe just to observe
and so
so there's a turning with this last
tetrad
from the practices that are more meant
to be concentrating
settling focusing uh to
now we're switching to vipassana
observing is where
the personal insight practice begins
and uh and classically inside practice
is built or or is done
on the foundation of
a mind was gotten very stable
concentrated
still joyful happy soft
at ease content
safe and liberated from the hindrances
and and so and now the mind is ready
for insight practice and the inside
practice
is built on this capacity just observe
just observe the experience and
in fact vipassana the word that we
translate as
insight has the same
verbal root as anupasana
v pasana and um and pasuna in vipassana
again means to see and the v
is usually understood to be a prefix
here meaning um
to see clearly or to see in a it's kind
of a
prefix of emphasis to really see or
clearly see
or to observe to clearly observe to
clearly
be aware
so um
to observe and that's the um
that's the medium through which
we're going to explore these next four
sets of practices of mindfulness of
breathing
then someone asks why is vipassana often
taught as an intro to mindfulness
it also works that way and it doesn't
have to be done
only with the strong base of
concentration
and and so it can be done at fact
practice directly
but a lot of what people are doing when
it's practiced directly and immediately
is sorting their way through all the
ways in which they are not concentrated
and so they're beginning to become wise
about the hindrances about distractions
and and so rather than kind of more
directly getting concentrated
there's a concentration through a lot of
understanding and wisdom
about all the things that keep us going
distractedly
so then we can settle and uh
and with wisdom rather than settling
with uh
sometimes they say settling with faith
when person just
dedicated just being simple and focused
and but sooner or later
if you start with mindfulness the
concentration is brought in
and mindfulness and concentration become
partners
if we start more of the concentration
then
later mindfulness is brought in so they
become the partners
so both are true and both are valuable
and this anapanasati um
can be seen as kind of a hybrid of these
two
with a lot of emphasis on this settling
relaxing
concentrating that that sets a stage
for a strong mindfulness
thank you all very much