so good morning good morning uh that is your time zone welcome to uh
all uh lines of latitude and longitudes nice to
lot of familiar names welcome to
welcome to all of you so
that's uh that's it
just opening and settling your body with
your breath
just having some sense of intention maybe even we say val
that for this time
the awareness is prioritized
over the details of our life
committing to awareness rather than
optimizing the moment
solving the riddle of our life
finding a more direct way to pleasure and more efficient escape
from pain
actually renouncing those agendas for this time
what would we do with the moment if we didn't have to do
our life
maybe we would just rest
and look
we're often subtly imaging the outline of our body
imaging the space of the room
keeping track of self another me not me
very innocent impulse of the mind and we can soften
we keep updating our autobiography
keep adding sentences and paragraphs chapters
to the story of me
in the words we speak to ourselves these two can be known in awareness can be
known as empty
and so the subtle visual image we have of ourself and the
narrative of self all of this can be safely surrendered
to awareness
the urgent energies in the body
just meet those with patience
let them drain right down into the center of the earth
begin to we begin to feel
a little less confined in self
a little less busy
with the tasks and duties the demands of i am this
space starts to run through us
we don't have to figure out what this moment is good for
i will use it
we just surrender to awareness
do
so thank you it's good too um good to sit with you
sorry this the sense of um uh dharma talks there are a little bit
more a little bit of a realization or something the dharma talks they're a little more
they're a little more like some weird species of performance art than maybe
i've realized and um they're less a kind of
transmission of information or something like that and uh
and so i say that just so that we um can
take it whatever impression it makes on our mind whatever is useful we pick up
we leave the rest behind
so yesterday i spoke about um a certain kind of reverence for the pain
of the other and today
it's about reference for their their goodness and their
power
and it seems like it should be should be easy to open to the goodness
of another but it involves some measure of surrender
some measure of surrender maybe maybe even
idealization that's not that's not a word from our orbit you
know idealization gets a bad bad rap in many circles and
for good reason there are problems as i'll say
but that sense of oh yeah we're supposed to be objective and measured but um
idealization has a place in relationships it has a place in our relationship to dhamma
and sometimes to be objective or measured
is actually a lack of courage or a preoccupation
with one's independence
and i know when uh when i was younger i there were
definitely relationships where i sort of like completely
leap frogged the idealizing honeymoon phase
and directly entered a kind of state of vaguely disgruntled ambivalence
you know most people live for the honeymoon right but
that that leapfrogging yeah that kind of hesitation around
certain kind of heart surrender that was not a function of wisdom
nor of equanimity but something more
like fear you know this is
psychoanalyst stephen mitchell idealization is destabilizing it shifts
our values our priorities our purposes it undermines the utilitarian approach
to practical realities that our lives require most of the time
falling is not a viable way of life and so we tailor tell ourselves that the
transition from falling in love to being in love represents a dispelling of fantasy
a landing on solid ground we try to keep our footing sure by
degrading idealization into mere intoxicating illusion
we are wiser and know better now however it is not at all clear that
the solid ground we perpetually seek is any more real
than the idealizations that inspire passion
wallace um stephen said that something like disillusionment is
sometimes merely another illusion
now of course i'm not uh
i'm not talking about surrendering to someone or something
that who lack exquisite care sensitivity
for [Music] your heart and
idealization gets problematic when we're kind of using it to prop ourselves
up where it's problematic when we're projecting all of our needs onto
the other we're trying to extract their power
what i'm really talking about is uh is reverence
reverence how how do we
relate to the power of another do we
do we lose ourselves in their power do we cling
tenaciously to our autonomy
and how do we surrender to dhamma
we don't ask it on the first day but at some point we're going to have to surrender we're going to have to let go
of a certain kind of willfulness and autonomy
offer our heart up to dhamma
and we fall in love with the path
we stay in love with the path we grow disenchanted with it
and we fall in love again
and our relationship with the path our relationship with others is
supported by something like episodes of idealization
for our heart to lean with a certain kind of reverence
now i'm not temperamentally a kind of devotional
person but now when i
when i see goodness i know to get on my knees
as we grow um as we grow to love ourself
more deeply as we grow to understand to appreciate the emptiness of self
more fully
the kind of reverence for goodness and that feels more and more natural
it feels more and more like a sense of of awe
a sense of awe are in the face of goodness
we look up at the night sky we see we see stars uh light years away and we
sense that the vastness of space and time
and in some ways we feel small
yet sanctified holy
and that sense of awe you know it's easy to feel for the dalai lama or
something like this these kinds of people these beings
but i feel like we can actually sense
some of that that awe that reverence for goodness in um
for all the ordinary people in our lives too
yeah maybe it's just some little thing they do
ah some aw
that's beautiful we're not relating
ego to ego when
when it's ego to ego the power or the goodness of another can spark
envy or self-judgment comparison competitiveness
we're so what i'm talking about we're not using the other's goodness as a kind
of measuring stick for ourselves that's the ego to ego
competitiveness yeah and that is the wellspring of a lot of pain
envy yeah um of the seven deadly sins lust gluttony
greed laziness wrath pride and envy
the writer joseph epstein said of the seven deadly sins
only envy is no fun at all it's really no fun
but is that how we get lost in the power the goodness the potency of another
and so the encouragement as the encouragement
of meta practice is to uh
to uh to see goodness to see it
yet to be here to kind of be open to idealization yeah maybe just a moment a
moment just such a reference
to feel it to take it in when we see it
we're learning to find our self-sufficiency and we're
also very much practicing dependency i feel
we're practicing the strength of surrender
the strength of surrender
so i offer this for your consideration
so um we'll um gather together again if you
like um this evening uh
there's the uh the page for um
the zoom call this this evening at pacific time at seven o'clock
and uh it's time to sit and have some dialogue and um
and uh we'll be i'll be back tomorrow morning and um gill and the
the crew is um having uh having their their in-person retreat and
uh at irc so anyway i'm happy to be with you all and um
yeah i'll see you this evening or uh or tomorrow same uh
same place okay thank you
you