so greetings from
imc in redwood city and and i feel
quite contented to sit here this morning and quiet already
so it's our chance to discover all of us how to
be present for ourselves in a way that is supportive is
perhaps supports us with a quietude a quietness or with a peacefulness or with a clarity
of the moment so to assume
a meditative posture meaning a posture that
supports your ability to be alert
and embodied alertness embodied attentiveness
so being careful that it's you're not over emphasizing relaxation or comfort
but also not underestimating or undervaluing the importance of relaxation and comfort
and to find that balance between alert or attentive in the posture
and you see that sometimes in animals or in small children especially
it's kind of there can be a relaxed clear attentiveness sometimes you see it
in the uprightness of the spine and the neck
and the clarity of or of the intentional
focus
and with a posture that's attentive and alert
to quietly calmly close your eyes
and to perhaps breathing in more deeply than usual
maybe three quarters full your lungs
so there's a real intentionality and a real renewed contact between you
and the body the torso that breathes
and at the end those after a deep inhale a long and gentle and maybe
tender exhale
maybe at the end of the exhale
allowing for a release that extends the exhale a little longer
a long exhale in which you also release the whole body relax the muscles
in a way the alertness the attentive body supports
relaxation without giving up the attentiveness
relax deeply
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and continuing the process of releasing relaxing the body
on the exhale softening relaxing the face
the forehead the temples
around the eyes and the cheeks
and the jaws by letting the teeth fall a teeny bit
apart from each other they'll burn lower teeth
and on the exhale to soften relax the
shoulders maybe there's a small adjustment in the position of your hands
that allows the shoulders to release a little bit more
and then to soften also on the exhale in your chest and around your heart
and sometimes just relaxing on the exhale can also take the form of a reassurance
reassuring allowing us our tension and challenges of the heart
to be there and it's okay it's okay
and then also to soften relax around the belly
soft belly breathing in breathing out
and there's a little bit of effort involved in relaxing at the beginning
and then recognizing that effort and letting go of it now
letting go and allowing yourself to simply be aware
of the body breathing
remarkably the body will breathe on its own without our needing to be
involved and it often does that through the day and through the night
breathing is always there accompanying us and now for these minutes
to allow your attention to accompany your breathing
thinking of breathing is a relaxed rhythm
that frees you from your thinking
frees you from being preoccupied caught up in involved in your thinking
your thinking might still go on in the background
but your attention and your intention your conscious involvement
is with the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
riding floating on that rhythm on those sensations
perhaps allowing the thinking mind to get quieter and quieter
as it becomes less and less necessary to think
because we're just
intimate with experience of the body
breathing
it's okay it's more than okay to trust your breathing
to entrust yourself to just being with the experience of
breathing letting all other things be leave them
alone let them be in the background if
possible
and if it's not possible to leave things in the background
then see how simple you can be in your mindfulness of those things
the simplest possible awareness
all as a way of not being entangled with things
so
mm-hmm
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to recognize that sometimes in meditation
we become quieter calmer
more settled or more open
in some way or other we've
shifted our state of mind or state of heart in a good direction in those times when that
happens to recognize that it gives us a
different vantage point from which to care and to love
this world a different perspective from which
to be kind and friendly and respectful of the people in our lives
and people that we run into and
that it's an opportune time to consider
how to give expression to our care to our love
a respect and kindness generosity
wherever it is easy for it to be directed
and to give some voice
to the love or the care or the friendliness
that might arise out of or be supported by our meditative state
and that can be done
by simply expressing expressing the classic words
of loving-kindness of goodwill and let those words somehow give voice
to our care and our love as it comes out of our quiet
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
and may we as we live our lives contribute to that possibility
may we make a world a better place
[Music]
so so it's certainly uh
it feels always an honor to be able to be with people and
in this form and in other ways to talk about the dharma to share the
dharma not just the words of the dharma but a little bit of the
experience of the dharma so here we are
and
i wasn't sure you know what topic to talk about today
partly because of what's happening nationally in the united states
and it feels like it's pretty for me pretty close in to where i practice the dharma what
the dharma is about and seems very alive all the various challenges this country has
and it's impressive statistic that for the last month there have been or so
there's been 45 mass shootings in this country
so it seems like it qualifies to be an epidemic we have the repeated and repeated and
repeated [Music] violence against african americans
some of the videos is quite graphic that you know it's painful to watch and see
and the asian americans who are also the recipient now of hate and
violence and now we have this there at the derrick siobhan's
trial which is coming to a head maybe this week and who knows what direction the jury
will go and maybe any either direction that your jury goes it seems like it's pretty
consequential and and what will happen to this country
so those things are certainly on my heart and in my mind and besides just bringing them up and other
things i just wanted to name them that they're certainly present for me
and that as i talk here about the dharma maybe i am addressing these issues
though it will not be direct not exactly intentionally but those are
definitely close by for me and what i want to begin by doing is talking about this
very famous analogy or parable
that many of you have heard before of the two arrows and i think this is such a profound
teaching it's so evocative and and as such
it is a kind of a koan a kind of a wonderful dharma question and the question is
what is the second arrow where is the second arrow
so the two arrows are the idea is that things happen to us in our lives which
are painful and there's plenty of that in this human life
and and buddhism is not to deny that there's pain that happens and some of that pain
is physical and some of it is emotional psychological
and then that's called the first arrow and the second arrow which makes the
pain worse because being shot by two arrows is worse than being shot by one arrow
the second arrow is what we contribute is the arrow that we shoot at ourselves
implying that there's a way in which we react and respond to the occurrences of our life our daily
life which where we uh increase the amount of pain
that we experience and in one once or one side the second arrow
that pain that's the pain we call suffering the fact that there is pain in the world
that is allowed to be pain and we do the best we can with it and and now as wisely as we can
but the this very powerful significant word for buddhist the word suffering in
dukkha that's what happens with the second arrow
and that is something that we do to ourselves and so the question is what is that
second arrow that we that we shoot at ourselves
and so there's many things that we do one of them is for example
if we feel pain and then because of that we get angry
and hostile and that hostility can be directed towards others
who we think are the responsible for our pain or the hostility can be directed towards ourselves but
irregardless of where the hostility is directed the hostility itself is the arrow it is
the second arrow so certainly you can feel that if the hostility is directed towards oneself
maybe that's like two arrows extra there's the arrow of the hostility
itself and then that's what the what the arrow hits inside of us
and then the hostility is directed outward to someone else it still hurts the person's being
hostile it is a way of shooting arrows at oneself and maybe shooting arrows at someone
else causing them pain there can be um the second arrow can be
not seen as a as an arrow it can be a very strong desire that we
latch on attach on to things that we want and there's something about
the squeeze and the holding on of intense desire really wanting something which actually
feels painful if we really feel and they're sensitive to what it is going on here and we're shooting a
second arrow in ourselves there's uh jealousy and there's uh envy
and there's greed and there's um you know there's a list of things that we do
that are called the second arrow conceit is considered to be a second arrow the
conceit of uh of you know that where we latch on to we hold on to
tightly some idea of me myself and mine like i'm special i'm wonderful i'm different
than others i'm we compare ourselves to other and put ourselves in in that we're better than or they're worse
than to be very critical of oneself and have a negative view of oneself
is a is a second arrow and certainly life is difficult so this
teaching about the two arrows doesn't deny the difficulty of life it just makes this distinction between
where the pain is and where the suffering is where the first arrow is in the second arrow and can all
forms all these forms of conceit the buddha said that he could not he did not know of any
concept of self idea of self philosophy around who the self is that didn't bring on the second arrow
that's a powerful statement it's not the same thing as denying there is a self it's just that to be wrapped up around
the conceit of a self is a second hero and
there's second arrows around getting wrapped up around opinions and views and philosophies and politics that
being right and insisting on it that insistence of being right and
in asserting one's views even if the views are true and accurate the
assertion of them the attachment to them is a second arrow what happens when
people practice something like meditation mindfulness meditation we become more and more sensitive to
so we recognize better and better these second arrows people who don't have that sensitivity
don't see that hostility is hurting themselves don't see that the attachment to pleasure or to
views philosophies politics attachment to conceit is an attachment to themselves is a
second arrow because they're not attuned to where the pain is where the contraction the hardness is and
where the the the um the um
where we get hurt so easily so one of the challenge one of the
things about these second arrows is they often don't just live by themselves
a second arrow is a kind of agitation a second arrow kind of lives within us
and then you know if someone has an arrow stuck in them and someone comes along and wiggles that arrow
i probably it's going to hurt a lot more in the skin or whatever it's pushing in and so we have these second arrows and
there they can be embedded in such a way that all kinds of people can come along and
do things and say things that are shaking twisting that second arrow to make it
more and more difficult and the second arrows are
often sticking out the most so that they're the ones that the world around us
will often hit first that the difficulty of the world what people say to us and do to us
will often hit the second arrow not something deeper inside of us
because second arrows are what's sticking out so what i mean by this is that if if we have a kind of conceit for
example that i'm better than everyone else then uh the slightest little that's the
second arrow the slightest thing someone says that undermines that or or criticizes that will um
will threaten hurt agitate that second arrow of conceit
if we're angry or hostile towards someone or towards ourselves then
any threat to that hostility any trying to dampen it down or quiet it down or
any uh thing that difficult that happens around us kind of vibrates or affects
that hostility to kind of irritate it more and so we get more hostile strong
attachment or wanting something all kinds of things can happen to threaten that desire
or that attachment and so because it's threatened it hurts even more and and
so in each of these times when the second arrow is sticking out so far that's what the world hits when it hits
us um it's uh it is um we start adding more
than second arrows third arrows four four arrows and the more arrows we've added to ourselves
the more we're become fragile the more we're ready to be irritated or be agitated or be
you know for all those arrows to be twisted in us even more so to be that so it's very important to
learn to recognize these second arrows and one of the ways to recognize them
is through agitation second arrows are always come with a degree of
agitation in fact it might even be fair to say if you're agitated
there's a second arrow operating and the task of mindfulness would be to
discover what is that second arrow or the task is to settle that agitation
and one of the functions of meditation is to quiet the agitation enough
so we can be more observant and see more clearly when agitation begins and not to give
authority to the agitation not to get swept away by it or treat it
as of course i'm agitated or taken for granted just agitation is just happening and i have to go along with it
i have to do something and run around and fix something or be angry or do something
but to really when we're agitated to stop and look
and uh because agitation as a second arrow is something that when the world comes
does something which is maybe unfortunate around us that if it hits our agitation hits our
second arrows our response is very different than if the
events of the world doesn't hit their agitation if this if the events of the world
are received in our peaceful heart our settled heart if the agitation the
difficulties of the world and what people do to us and say to us is received in our calmness and our
openness without any second arrows without any agitation
then it's an amazing thing begins to happening the amazing thing is that there's a way
in which we can feel as if those things don't touch us as if they go right through as if there
is a vast emptiness space if there's a a transparency
or there's a through which things occur they're still
known and felt and even painful things can be felt as pain but it feels like they're not
lingering or being held on to or being stuck anywhere it isn't like they're embedded they
the arrowhead hasn't been embedded anywhere and there's this wonderfulness when
there's freedom like a vast open window that sees you sees clearly everything kind of the
breeze go through clearly wonderful spring breeze perhaps but
when the neighbor kid throws a baseball against the window it doesn't break the
glass it just goes right through hopefully there's nothing in the living room but
as a my and my kids in my home it wasn't so much the neighbor kids throwing a baseball
from outside out our window was my kids throwing the baseball inside and if the window is open they're not
going to you know we're going to hit anything outside that would break so the idea you know
to when there's no second arrows it's like the windows are all open
and then there's a room in the heart and the mind to experience the challenges of this
world and we know that we don't have that room for it
when we get agitated certainly we could have a lot of respect and care and
and compassion for our agitation but to recognize oh this is agitation
oh i'm agitated i've heard about that in buddhism agitation
is a very thing that's extra is the second arrow i don't know how this is a second arrow
it seems like it's pretty natural pretty obvious i don't know that of course you should be agitated in this
circumstance aren't you supposed to everyone i've ever known in my life they always got agitated when these things happened
so isn't this what human beings do they get agitated and yes many people do get agitated in
all kinds of ways many people do as a matter of natural course of how they live their lives
shoot a lot of second arrows but
it's not necessary and so to know this not to be shoot another
arrow at yourself so i'm a bad person because i'm i'm agitated but to know this and get
curious and to and take the agitation as a as a strong encouragement
pay attention look see what's going on here where is the second arrow and the
agitation i think even though it might be a second arrow i think it's actually very
helpful to respect it and and see it as representing what's
important for us and if it represents what's important for us
then um then it's imp then it's the more agitated we are the more it gives us a purpose a
direction and now i know what to do
and that is either to look inside see what is this agitation get curious
sit and meditate get quiet and study and feel and really get to the bottom of this
agitation what is it and settle the agitation and see what happens then
or like for example if you're agitated about something in the world
maybe to get to get caught in that education
is to miss a golden opportunity it's to somehow get too involved in the
s in the second era we're doing to ourselves and not appreciate that maybe what we're
agitated about doesn't need our agitation but it does
need our attention so this way of respecting agitation it's either
it's a prompt to look inside more deeply or it's a prompt it gives direction and
meaning and purpose to look outwards and study be intent and
look and learn better what's going on with your friend if you're agitated by a friend you know
that maybe talk about that talk to them and find out what's going on for them and and you know really really be present if
it's appropriate if you're agitated about what's happening in the world
if you're really agitated enough then you have a sense of purpose you can
okay i'm gonna turn my focus of my attention to learn more about it don't
don't rely on social media don't rely even on the on the mainstream news articles if
you're agitated it's important enough that you should get to the bottom of it and understand and do some research and really learn as
opposed to just continue to kind of swim in the agitation and continue to read the kind of news
that only agitates you more then you're not really studying and getting through to it and
doing research so um and so this is always
both these ways are ways of no longer living with the second arrow
and both of them are ways to offer something different to ourselves
than just twisting the second arrow more and more it's giving us something to do
and those two can be done together we can both look deeply inside and settle the agitation find out where
we're attached or we can and we can also
look and see and study and read about or learn about what's going on in the world
or even better we can actually bring our focus to do something about it
and even if it's a very very small thing to to act and do
because then we um we're going where that is sometimes a way of pulling out the arrow or that's
the way of not allowing the arrow to keep getting twisted more and more
so there's a marvelous thing that happens when we have started to pull out these second arrows
and um is that there's less and less that the world strikes there's less and
less windows for the world to break in our hearts the heart becomes more and more open
so we have to be very careful with these second arrows because there they are
oftentimes the primary source of more and more
pain and suffering so it's not just simply the inner one simple little arrow second arrow
that's gone in that's causing a suffering but the continued uh twisting of them and striking of them
and rubbing up against them that the world does and that we do makes them kind of more and more
more and more suffering arises and happens so to take out the second arrow to
understand this idea of second arrows and to understand that there's a whole
other way of living it's possible to live as a large open
window it's possible that the things of the world
that we can care we can be involved in we can respond to
but when we are aware of it when we know it when it comes to us when someone is angry with us
it's possible for that to just go right through and are the open window of our heart
and in doing so we can remain steadfast present
looking maybe kindly but really looking at the challenge looking what's
happening looking at for example the angry person
sometimes it makes angry people more angry if they have no effect on us so
some people find that very satisfying but i think more importantly is that if
we have no reaction to people who are angry with us
maybe or to the difficulties and challenges of this world and politics and what's happening around
us i hope that
we get motivated to be wise about it to see it more clearly
to be curious and look to turn really and stay present with eyes open
and looking in that direction seeing what is this having an open heart where nothing in
the world can touch because everything just goes right through does not mean that we become indifferent
it just gives a lot more room for our wisdom our care our interest and our love
our compassion to operate and those things love compassion
wisdom interest those are not second arrows and those do
not stick out in a way that people can twist and hurt us even more so
so in summary what i'm hoping in offering you this
talk is that uh you'll get interested and curious
about your second arrows what are they and
and if you're a little bit like me then perhaps sometimes you'll see clearly what it is
and sometimes you won't and you'll say what what is the second arrow i think there's a second arrow here
what's going on and get curious and and um and to keep this kind of on the
forefront maybe forever but maybe for this week maybe talk to friends and journal about it reflect on it
meditate with it what is my second arrows what are my second arrows
and in what way do my second arrows what way are those second arrows the
very things that the world keeps twisting and twisting and turning in
deeper and deeper so thank you everyone and thank you for
being here and and i hope that you have a wonderful
week and and when you've
pulled out your arrows um put them down don't put them in your
quiver put them down and retire them
so thank you