so good day everyone and the way we could say perhaps um good
year and kind of like good morning good beginning of this new year for us on this
7 a.m sitting and teaching so i'm happy to be here for this anniversary day and so we'll have a zoom
meeting afterwards and for those of you who don't want to be on zoom
i think i'll just keep the youtube on and you won't necessarily
get all of it but you'll get half of it of myself responding and talking in a little bit and and and
the zoom link is the is at the very top of this chat and i'll post it near the bottom
when we finish here as well it's also found on the imc website in two places
in the calendar section of it where it's listed as an event and on the
what's new there's a little notice also in the bottom right hand side of the home page and if you use those
links you have to use the password which is meta m-e-t-t-a if you use the link
that's uh on the chat you click picture right there and i won't turn it on until i finish here so
there might be a minute or so in between
so so um
as a child i spent a lot of time swimming in water and i loved to go underwater and
swim as far as i could without and holding my breath and that explains maybe a little bit why i
um a little bit i paid tiny bit attention to
people who do free diving and people who do records for free diving
underwater the longest the deepest distance down into the water or or in
the ocean or perhaps a whole you know swim the longest underwater or be longest underwater
and i think they're one of the records i believe for staying underwater without breathing is about 11 minutes
so it's kind of phenomenal that people can train to do that but one of the things that people who do
that learn to do is to quiet their thinking
because thinking takes up a lot of oxygen you need a lot of energy and to think and and so they
they're certainly aware and engaged what they're doing and very hyper attentive to what they're
doing in a very particular way but they're ordinary um
energy draining battery draining app has been turned off the discursive
thinking the commentary they that they do
and so this also happens in meditation it's one of the reason why in deeper meditation it seems that we stop
breathing because there's very little need to breathe when this
heavy app that we have that's really kind of going on all the time in the background and
you know it's one of these apps that kind of take over and and work even you know
behind the scenes our thinking app so to uh to as we get into meditation
uh the idea is to enjoy it settle into it and settle into that
enjoyment into the contentment into the quiet into the piece of it even if it's just hints of it
kind of orient kind of a paradigm shift where we're orienting towards something else besides our thinking
and we're orienting towards the breathing and the peacefulness the quiet the
stillness the the joy and the contentment that comes from developing samadhi
and with that uh there's a shift away from the thinking mind the commentary
mind the dis having discussions and plans and memories and all that
and so to appreciate the value of that appreciate how good it feels to let that
part of the mind go quiet and if these deep sea divers can do it certainly we can do it as we do our own
kind of version of deep sea diving which is dipping into samadhi deeping it
deepening into this kind of states of goodness and wholeness
that don't require us to think and think a lot and when we realize how safe it is and
good it is and nourishing it is then we begin to let go of the the tremendous
interest the mind has with this app um the thinking app
so to assume a meditation posture
and to relax tremendous amount of what we're doing in
the going into samadhi is in fact relaxing letting things become tranquil
not only letting go and relaxing the body
but also taking some of the mental apps offline they're not needed or energy drains for
human battery and they can come back online again
later but we're letting go or relaxing
doing less and less except for us settling in steadying
ourselves on the breathing and enjoying it
so taking a few long slow deep breaths and on the exhale
thinking of it as turning off so much of the unnecessary app so we
have running the tensions in our body
softening the shoulders especially
softening the belly
and if you are taking some deep slow breaths then as you stop that appreciate that
you are letting go of that effort
and now you're just letting yourself breathe in a more easy way
and then to continue relaxing the body a
bit the surface body of the shoulders the face the belly
and deep in the body the deep holding resistance bracing
the deep holding ourselves
even holding ourselves together
and then to also
orient yourself to the quietude of the mind
let's let yourself become aware in the ways of the mind
quiet clear relaxed
and as you exhale settle into that quiet
letting go of the thinking mind and if it doesn't let go completely it's
okay for now let it recede into the
background and then with the mind
let the mind land on your breathing
and have the mind the attention
find uh establish yourself to be steady on the breathing
steady the mind and its focus on the breathing
and much of our physical experience of breathing is in fact silent doesn't require
thinking the silent feeling and sensing of the body
steady yourself on that experience of sensing
the changing flow of sensations as you
breathe
as you exhale letting go of your thoughts and letting go into
a quiet steadiness on breathing
and if you use any thoughts at all let it be thoughts of counting the
breath counting up to one or up to three or up
to 10 or simply the word yes
so said so quietly in the mind that it's almost like you imagine you're saying it
steadying yourself on the breathing and whatever good feelings that come
with a quietude and steadiness breathing in and breathing out
appreciating the quietude that's here even if your mind is
thinking a lot look past it
to the quietness steadiness of attention on breathing
a paradigm shift away from your thinking mind
to a quiet steady awareness of breathing
and whatever goodness is in that attention
switching from thinking to a quiet seeing
a quiet sensing aware of breathing
steadying yourself on the breathing
[Music]
so
and then as we come to the end of this sitting appreciating the paradigm shift from
thinking to seeing
seeing with the quietness of the mind
so we're not seeing through the filter of our thoughts ideas opinions
but we're seeing through the quietness
steadiness and safety of
simply seeing simple awareness of what is
and in the maybe the comfort and safety of meditation
can you turn the gaze of this quiet
steady seeing awareness
to the people in your life
those who are close and you have contact with those who are far away and you don't have direct contact those who you know
personally and those who don't
and see if you can simply from meditation gaze upon them
quietly silently without the judgments and the stories and
anticipations of what it means just gazing on them quietly
and see if that gaze that awareness can be kind that in the quiet and safety of
privacy of your own meditation a kind steady gaze
be still and gaze upon all everyone kindly
not complicating it with your stories ideas memories plans
just the simplicity of others
and perhaps that kindness then can be expressed in the words
of kindness you might repeat after me
may they be happy
may they be safe
may they be peaceful
may they be free
may all beings everywhere be happy [Music]
[Music]
you
so continuing on the topic of samadhi
and the 11th step of mindfulness of
breathing
and samadhi is sometimes the word samadhi is sometimes
the generic word a general word for meditation
or the meditation and cultivating our mind our body
cultivating ourselves in the meditation practice and then
when we look kind of within this universe of samadhi there's all kinds of things that we're
we are gathering together we're unifying we're coming together
that to develop and grow and enhance our experience and samadhi is not meant
to be an experience that diminishes us that makes us less and deprives us
but it's actually the opposite it's one of the richest ways of experiencing ourselves
enhances fulfill very fulfilling very filling very nourishing and it's developing
these beautiful wholesome qualities these beautiful wholesome states of mind
but in doing so it's also kind of getting out of the way of our but not adding all this extra
tension and stress that uh can exist in the mind and moves us to less and less stressful
states of mind or states of being less and less activated
places of agitation and moving to deeper and deeper peace and as we do so even wholesome states of
mind wholesome activities of mind that are more energetic than need to be
begin to be shed or relaxed or settled and it's a movement from more energetic
states to quieter and stiller states and not that quiet stillness i think some people have very
negative relate experiences of quiet and stillness and silence so we have to kind of try to put those
associations aside and somehow realize that the quietness
and the stillness silence that we're developing is letting go letting go it's kind of like filling us with
feelings of real goodness and contentment and fulfillment satisfaction but there is this movement
towards less and less agitation less energetic movements and things that in that in
that context of the mind getting peace more more peaceful things that were wholesome and
wonderful before can be felt now they feel like they're a little bit too agitating
they're a little bit stressful to be there so for example one of the things that happens in samadhi is there
can be a lot of joy but joy at some point seems like it's too much it's too agitating
and even though at the beginning it seems like this is the best that anybody could ever experience and um but as we get more familiar with
it it's the energy of it seems like too much and then we um
and then we settle down more and more into um um into um
you know a piece or a more quiet place that feels even more satisfying so this movement and this is kind of the
general trajectory of deepening samadhi developing samadhi
is this movement from more agitated more energetic states to less energetic states that i feel
more and more satisfying as we go into them and so i say this because it's a guiding
principle for tuning into our practice that um
that the the kind of the way to see the path forward in samadhi is to appreciate at
some point that really feel at some point that what felt really wonderful
at one one stage of practice we're ready now to let go of it or let it become quieter and move to a
less energetic less activated state and uh and as that's the movement that's
the direction that the practice is going and and and then there are
various landmarks along the way that stand out as we do this process of
settling and settling and settling that goes on more peace that happens but the principle is
removing in this direction and it's helpful to keep that principle in mind
because sometimes when people read about samadhi they learn about like four stages of jhana four stages of deep absorption
and it becomes a little bit mechanical or technical like am i in the right place am i at the first john i'm at the second
jhana and there's a kind of like samadhi my numbers that goes on which
can get overdone sometimes and people are too preoccupied about the technical definitions and aspects of
this rather than living in the organic flow of samadhi that we can and just allowing things to
unfold and not be so concerned about the numbers and stages and how far we've gotten and
it's easier to do that if you understand that principle that we're going from more activated states to less activated
more stressful to less stressful more from more agitation to less agitation
and so there is a kind of a trajectory kind of a path and some of the landmarks of that
are is first is a real appreciation
for no longer any kind of relief from no longer being actively engaged in unwholesome ways of thinking
so if we have spent a lot of time with resentment just like why did that person do that or desire just really want
something hostility fantasy and you after a while
we feel the flatness of it the two-dimensionality of it the way in which it keeps us stressed and so
with somalia with developing meditation we're starting to let go of those things and when we really are become separate
from it's temporarily put aside or deactivated those apps of greed hate and
delusion the unwholesome it's such a relief and there's a kind of a gladness and joy
that wells up but more important as uh this relief and the goodness the
happiness of this relief now the meditation can really begin to do our gentle work of practice
uh staying present applying the mind and staying there and this idea of the gentle work of just
okay stay here be with us hang in there come back be here
now it's done without the stress of having to struggle against unwholesome
distractions and difficulties of mine but there is a kind of gentle work of okay stay here that can be represented
by what happens on the in-breath uh we have to the in the beginning then breath is a whole
new experience the mind has to connect to that and then we stay there for the full in-breath
then we connect again to the beginning of the out breath and stay there for the whole time it's a very gentle some people don't
even notice that they're doing it but there is a kind of little movement to these two movements of the mind
little working massaging kneading the dough kind of experience but it
comes along with the relief and the happiness of not being distracted anymore finally
being able to be here and do this as we settle in and we at the steady
we land and and there there's a steadiness and the um we there's less and less of
this need to make the work of connecting and staying it becomes second nature the mind is just starting
to become stable and we're just able just to rest in the breathing and just stay there's
very little tendency to wander off just there we're here we're finally here and that gives birth to a different kind
of joy of just being really now being able to put aside that extra work of
connecting and being and there's a kind of gliding soaring sliding
on the experience of of and so it kind of feels like it's like petting
the cat the pep begins to purr we're kind of there
being touched in some deep way and um and it's kind of like the uh pleasure
principle where we're just kind of being touched this beautiful feeling of just staying with the breath and
being there and being that a different kind of joy arises and that can be quite strong and
energetic at times and after a while that joy feels like it's too much
and so then uh it's ready to kind of to let go of that level of agitation
activation and by tuning into there's actually a deeper satisfaction
feeling of contentment and feeling of mindfulness feeling of
clear comprehension a simple awareness simple recognition of what's happening
simple awareness of what's happening and the goodness and contentment of just being in this happiness or
this deeper sense of pleasure and we let go of the joy because
and then as we go deeper in that happiness feels i don't know if it feels like it's
too much but the happiness begins feeling begins to soften and relax and it falls away
into something that's much more satisfying which is a deep sense of tranquility equanimity
and where the awareness is very pure very pure awareness sometimes it depends
how we translate the pali the buddhist teachings on is but its awareness is very closely connected to equanimity
that its awareness which is purified by equanimity and so the awareness is very peaceful
very aware and and uh very still and because there's so little mental activity so
little stressful activity much of our ordinary way of experiencing ourselves has temporarily fallen away
people even have the sense of not really being in their having a body the body edges fall away
and no sense of being in a body and it's not being disassociated it's
actually the opposite we're so connected that uh and so still
that we don't need the reference points we usually have so um
so the principle of this movement to lessen less activity as we go into samadhi and part of the
purpose of this is to clarify our gaze our ability to see to observe
so it doesn't have a lot of agitation or filters or disturbances of
unwholesome thinking but even our thinking and projections and ideas and concepts that we overlay even if the
concepts are accurate enough to no longer be overlaying concepts on our experience
and and so it isn't that samadhi we're doing it for its own sake but for the way in which there's a
cleans the our perception cleans purifies awareness so we can start
seeing in a deeper and deeper way for the purpose of liberation