hello and welcome everyone to this edition of happy hour
practicing together so before i hit the record button we're talking about
smokes fires lockdowns so much happening
externally internally so for today's practice i'd like to
invite us to
to approach the practice of compassion which is love meeting suffering
love meeting suffering and for this addition we'll be
practicing self-compassion so our own suffering whether it's physical whether we have
civil physical pain suffering illness
[Music] anything that's happening physically or whether it's
it's emotional psychological [Music] pain of the heart not
literally both literally but but also metaphorically
and and two invitations tonight to invitations for
our guided practice the first is to consider that
to consider a meeting meeting or pain meaning or suffering or sorrow
surrounding infusing holding it with love complete love the way we would hold
a baby a newborn a tender young being just holding
them with tenderness love completely engulfed in love that's
one invitation that i will be weaving through
and the other invitation the second invitation
is considering that our
self-sense our self-sense in the suffering is quite malleable in
the story of course there is pain there is sorrow there's suffering and then there are
different ways there's different self-senses so for example you can think of the buddha who could
have you know his story instead of one of nobility one of nobility
and service and strength awakening etc instead of that
narrative the narrative could have been oh
you know yeah i was a prince i was you know i couldn't get out of this prison of a
castle my dad didn't let me get out and then i got out and
and you know and then oh yeah i couldn't you know no one would would
um in um you know after i got enlightened oh nobody would believe me and you know people turned
around and like so so it could be a sense of oh poor me poor me which would be a funny way right i mean funny way to even think
of that story it's kind of exaggerated but the same way
can we think of our own suffering our own pain our own sorrow however shows up
with nobility with nobility as if this challenge this sorry this
pain we are we are bodhisattva just like the buddha before his awakening we're
bodhisattva we're offering we're holding this pain we're um in ways maybe we can't quite
understand we're offering it to all beings everywhere for their awakening for our own awakening
for all sentient beings bodhisattva bodhi awakening satva sentient beings
for all sentient beings including ourselves this suffering this sorrow it's
the sense of nobility in enduring and offering in being with this
difficulty so that can bring a sense of um again nobility
strength power to being with both the sensitivity the tenderness
in the image of holding with love as if it were a newborn and this sense of nobility
um so these are two invitations that i will work i will invite us
through the um [Music] guided meditation as ways to consider
as ways to enter and also i want to give credit uh to robert bay i heard these two
mention these ideas as a part of a longer talk and just got me thinking that oh this
can be a whole practice and the talk uh he mentioned this in
just to give it reference is love healing and emptiness which i have mentioned before and
and i believe neil has sent it to the sangha and the google groups mailing
list so so without further ado let's start our practice
let's get into our into our posture
as always starting with settling with arriving
this body this heart
this breath
connecting with each breath in breath opera
just landing and arriving for the first few minutes of this practice
on our own pace in our own bodies
contacting the floor the cushion the earth
each breath filling our hearts our heart center our abdomen
our whole body
just this breath
ah letting go relaxing into this body in this moment
inviting awareness to be present with the breath with the body
with whatever is happening in the heart gently embracing touching
with your awareness the body heart and mind
fully present with what is present
let engage breath
awareness of each breath
radiate feel more expensive
as if our awareness expands not just through the body but beyond
as if we are sitting
comfortably relaxing into spacious awareness
not so much trying to push it and pull it and expand it just
it's more expensive than we realize oh
oh yes can relax into this gentle spaciousness
whole body can relax into it
our hearts can relax whatever they're holding in this moment
our bodies can relax
to spacious awareness
and what if this spacious awareness
spaciousness is also tinged with care with gentle
with gentleness
permeating through our body
around our body
holding us as if a soothing blanket
as if our aching heart our aching body
our mind
is wrapped lovingly
as if a newborn a baby wrapped lovingly in this blanket of care
it's okay it's okay
breathing in with each breath healing soothing compassionate love
in this body around this body
it's okay it's okay
with each breath
here it's okay
soothing healing loving compassionate
awareness with each breath
experimenting if you wish with putting your hand the palm
of your hand in the middle of your chest the proverbial heart center connecting
with yourself holding yourself this being that is you
touch can be so soothing
comforting healing
experiment something might open up when
unexpected
can also feel empowering
supporting this being sense of empowerment
in the career
this sense of empowerment
nourishing supporting
yourself ah also offering
offering this challenge the stuka
for the benefit for the awakening of all sentient beings
as if bodhisattva you are a bodhisattva whoever is on this path
is a bodhisattva awakening not for our own sake alone
but for the sake of all beings all life
all forms of awareness
offering this gift this dark gift of suffering
that is opening us up in the ways unknown and unseen
perhaps as of yet training us in compassion
and patience and love for ourselves and the world
offering enduring being with this challenge
for the benefit of all beings
sense of nobility
in being with
opening to more dimensions of meaning
that we are not alone
burning with the stuka for the benefit of ourselves and others awakening
in that way it can be transformed it may be released
transformed into compassion for ourselves and others
perseverance love
find out for yourself
can there be a sense of nobility
in the self-sense
and empowerment of being with this dukkha
this challenge
offered composted for your own growth awakening
and those of others
no mud no lotus
this mud this lotus
as our offering
maybe finding you can endure
with resilience much more than you thought possible
and for the last minutes of this practice period
offering the mud and a lotus
the mud of our suffering our challenge physically emotionally
whatever it might be right now
specially exacerbated by the pandemic
nomad no lotus offering our mud and the lotus
of our awakening growing in compassion
as little or as much as possible
offering it wholeheartedly for the benefit of all sentient beings
may this serve may it serve
maybe of service
this challenge i have been given
given the causes and conditions may be of service to all beings everywhere
and this being who is me in waking up
may all beings everywhere
know their own abundance their own goodness
their own capacity and beauty their own magnificence may all beings
be free
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so couple of things
invitations today the first the theme of
enveloping the challenge difficulty dukkha with with love as if
a baby and then with that the invitation to hold our heart center
or heart with our palm and to bring in a sense of nobility
this sense of self-support a sense of empowerment supporting ourselves and then
transitioning into this sense of
offering the mud the lotus or suffering
for the benefit of all beings finding changing the self-narrative
from one of perhaps poor me to sense of resilience
so would love to hear your reflections what you discovered
what was new what was your insight questions comments for the benefit of all beings
or sangha patricia offers who's joining us from
ireland middle of the night there 2 a.m or 3 a.m now almost
such beautiful practice thank you thank you patricia for joining and practicing
you can type in chat your reflections as always if it's just typed in me i
will only say read the reflection not your say your name
it's time to everyone i'll read the whole thing you can also raise your hand especially
if you haven't shared a reflection in a while what did you discover
was there a sense of nobility a sense of opening up as if oh
there is empowerment there's beauty there's grace there's i can endure there's so much more here
did it unearth abilities that you didn't realize you
had yeah question comes
up from casey what if one is overwhelmed with constant suffering and is tired
yeah so the overwhelm is probably happening because of the fatigue because
of being tired and
different different possibilities one is to come back to the body simply
mindfulness of the body and holding and the other actually is this this
practice can bring up more empowerment more sense of not being overwhelmed by it it can
change the narrative completely you can change the narrative from feeling
overwhelmed it's too much to actually wow as a bodhisattva here i am
there's so much more that this heart can contain it can expand
our conception are conceiving so hang in there don't give up give up
on it victoria says happy to be back here and being part of this beautiful practice welcome back victoria
i was previously familiar with the phrase no rain no flowers really enjoyed this rendition of this so
gracious and delicate thank you so much you are so welcome thank you for joining victoria
no rain your food no flowers i like that also one more reflection coming in
i had a sense of separating and sitting above the physical and emotional
pain i've been ex i've experienced this week as we worked through covet ah
wow so being above it sitting above so this expansiveness above the physical
and emotional wow thank you that to me that it sounds from what you wrote it
was a beautiful experience of of of transcendence of
okay there's so much more here so of being in the midst of it overwhelmed by it
rising above it thank you so much for sharing that reflection anonymously beautiful
i'll pause if any more reflections or
questions
so we'll save some time on the other end when we come back from small group
practice sharing with each other and also holding witness for one another
in this practice so as always we'll start with 15 seconds of silent
um meta compassion empowered for ourselves for each other
and then you can share as little or as much as you like with um with your small group
and again taking care of yourself taking care of each other in compassion small groups is really
where the practice where the rubber meets the road such
an important opportunity to be present for yourself for each other slow down slow
down slow down and listen to yourself slow down and listen to
yourself slow down and listen to one another this is profound practice
okay i will open the rooms now
okay welcome back everyone
we have a few minutes left for any reflections that came up especially
after discussing conversing in small groups and feel free to raise your zoom hand
or type in chat
we haven't had any any uh verbal comments so yeah raising your zoom hand would be great
i see jerry's physical hand let's see jerry here um you can unmute yourself
jerry please i'm dressed i know it's crazy i live in toronto but it's so hot and
humid here that i had to turn the air conditioning on and now i have to wear this coat to say warm in the house it doesn't make sense so
that's the uh the nature of uh living in canada at least on the east coast so what i
thought about was just the end of the small group this whole like you know it's been raining a lot
here and uh and humid but the grass looks amazing and the flowers look wonderful
so without rain there's no flowers or without mud there's no lotus and i thought without without covid
we wouldn't be and have met in this particular group and uh you know that was really quite
i didn't i sort of thought about it and maybe someone's already said it but i was like thinking wow out of necessity
was born some beauty
thank you jerry yeah thank you so true and
eileen says in chad this was a new perspective for me
nobility in the face of dukkha it's different from feeling a second
arrow in the heart yes eileen well said beautiful mark asks about
the talk i mentioned the talk on dharmaseed is by rob
berbaya b-u-r-b-e-a a wonderful teacher there and neil
already put it in chat thank you neil nicholas please
yeah this uh this practice really hit so i might have to talk a little slower um
yeah i feel like
i've just seen very clearly how much life kind of for me centers on the drama
of like it's my dukkha and i have to get rid of it and i have to figure it out and it has
to mean something to me and it's it's really touching i think the
nobility is like just kind of shining on it you know
it's like it has my cat's fight in the background beautifully
you know it's just the nobility it just there's just that feeling of like the
heart just shines on it and it doesn't do anything specific it doesn't outsmart
it it doesn't beat it it's just it's just there
and it's so noble so yeah i'm very grateful for this practice today thank you
thank you thank you nicholas i'm grateful
to you for your practice today and your nobility
in showing up for the benefit of all beings including the being who's
nicholas that is a profoundly beautiful
reflection to end
this edition of happy hour with thank you
and thank you all for showing up for practicing with all our nobility all
of our mud his nickel is beautiful he said nobility can shine
not out not too outsmart it just shines it's just
it can shine and transform
so thank you all may all beings including ourselves be
well male all beings including ourselves be free
you