welcome and uh warm welcome to all of you and to being here together for our
meditation and um
the general idea of mindfulness meditation is or the underlying kind of
kind of a practice or direction or attitude is
that of being simple uh being simple with the instructions being simple with the practice moment by
moment and in the simplest way of describing that
is just to know what's happening as it's happening but the buddhist path
has two primary components of this kind of using our
mental attention and our minds and practice
one is to relax
or as it gets more deeper in practice to let go
to let go and then to know
but because it's uh difficult to just sit down and let go
um the uh first uh
is to be here here be really really be here in the
simplicity of this moment
relax let go and know
so and then you do it again here
relax and know know what's happening very simply
know it without any reactivity without any interpretations without any story
just know the simplicity of this moment to relax is to relax
in the simplest way that's available to not have ambitions not strained to
relax to relax what we can to let go
to let go of what's appropriate the meaning of letting go in the teachings of the buddha
is the primary orientation around it is to not let go of things
but let go of our clinging to things or grasping to things ideas identities
desires and here
just here nowhere else so maybe that can be the
rhythm or the practice if you'd like for these this meditation and you can say to yourself this this
the sequence here here to what's this here what's here for
you the simplest possible way of recognizing that just here
letting go relaxing maybe relaxing first later letting go
maybe letting go first then relaxing and then recognizing what's here
recognizing that we're in our bodies
here in our bodies recognizing the breathing in the body
here with the breathing relaxing with the breathing recognizing there's inhales and exhales
here with the inhales and exhales recognizing some of the sensations and
that come in with the inhale some sensations that come with the exhale
letting go of stories around breathing what's supposed to happen around breathing
and then recognize just recognize what's here maybe recognizing the breathing more
fully or recognizing the pleasure of having let go of stories
and expectations agendas and then here
and whatever is here it's easy and obvious that's here and now
in the simplicity of this moment and as we to go through these cycles
of hear relax know perhaps it hit them it's a movement of
becoming simpler and simpler with what's here less story
less future less past less interpretations less reactivity
a contentment to just be here with this experience
so um taking a posture
that you think is suitable for you
to be both alert and maintaining some physical
presence alertness stability to let go deeply
while the body is aligned if you're sitting upright
aligned in an upright posture it doesn't collapse
and then to let your gaze
be relaxed maybe gazing down at about 45 degrees
relaxing around the eyes not looking at anything in particular
soft gaze
and then gently closing your eyes
taking a few long slow deep breaths to become established here
just here
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and i'll go through this these three part sequence for a little bit and you can follow
along
so very simply recognize what's here
experientially in the present moment for you
it's more like just be here with it here you are
and then as you exhale perhaps you can relax
let go
and then know what's here very simple
maybe one word recognition it's
and then again here may be given what you have known
be here with this be here with your experience
as you exhale relax let go
and then know recognize what is here
recognize what is obvious that's simple and obvious to know
here in your experience not elsewhere
not other places and times not about anything different than what's
experienced here
and then here be here with whatever is close in
whatever the experience is that centered here
relax let go of any holding tightening
and having let go and relaxed know
something about this present experience that stands out
no need to search just what comes
and then here
relax
and no
and then as you do this relaxing and knowing perhaps you're settling in more
and more into your experience here in your body
your breathing
here relax
and know it whatever whatever rhythm you want
whatever pace and as you get settled
if you want to drop one of the three and then two of the three
and then all three drop them in order drop here
drop relaxing
and only if you're very very still relax
knowing
remembering to be here in your experience
remembering to let go relax even if it's micro relaxations
and to know to recognize what is obvious
in this immediacy of direct experience
okay
so
and as we come to the end of the sitting perhaps to consider
that doing this practice of hear
relax recognize
how that benefits the people we interact with through the
day how is it to be really here with
someone how is it to be at ease
while we're with them and what is it to
really know what's happening with the person with yourself
between the two of you what benefits comes
how are these relationships enhanced and developed this way
the practice we do on the cushion can serve us so well
in in our world in our being with others and relating to others
and to offer the benefits of this practice to be shared with others
and to feel how the practice benefits us in social situations
can deepen how we practice when we're sitting alone
may we share this practice with the world in how we
are present how we are at ease
and how we see clearly
may we bring the benefits of this practice into the world to contribute to the welfare and
happiness of all beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
so continuing on this theme of the karmic stream and the dharmic stream
and the karmic stream the karmic momentum of our lives and how
karma is shaped how action shapes our ongoing
experience i keep wanting to refer you back to
how you can know this for yourself directly so it's not a metaphysical idea or abstract idea about
imaginary futures or pasts that you can actually watch it work
in your mind in your body here and now if we pay careful attention
and it's one of the primary principles of that dolphin comes along with this
karma teachings teachings about action actions that have ongoing repercussions
in our lives that actions which condition us or influence us
ongoingly in a way sometimes that we don't understand why we're so compelled to act and be certain ways
um is so the the the way that our actions condition us influence us or has lays traces within
us imprints things within us is based on a very simple principle
that in order to make this very simple
i'll do it in two steps the first step is it's based on the notion
that we can know what brings with it an ouch
and what brings with it an ah and i use those little expressions so
that we don't get and narrowed down by the words that might express that
so for example we have the idea of good karma and bad karma and as soon as we say it that way which
is a common enough expression it narrows it it's confusing it can be confusing it can be
imply morality all kinds of things are kind of come along with that but maybe it's very simple just to
recognize experientially that does some things we do as we do them as part
of it is ouch and some things we do has an ah
and uh and so that's the first principle the second one is that um
those things which are are propelled by or or conditioned by or come along with an
ouch they tend to produce more ouches those things which are compelled by are
pushed along by an ah they are um
they produce more of the same ah and um
this is not the same thing as comfort and discomfort but uh something deeper a sense of
the buddhists like to call suffering or happiness but
that principle the key thing is here is that what propels it what is the motivating force what's the
the um atmosphere or the the condition which we something is done if we say
something do something or even think something and what's propelling it
is some feeling inside some motivation inside some uh something inside
which uh in and of itself just feels like if you're really careful and
pay attention to it we feel oh that hurts that's ouch um and uh or we can feel it that's what's
good it's ah that's good ah that feels right and um
and so uh karma is uh when when things are acted
on from that kind of compulsion or propulsion um then uh they tend to produce more and
you can watch that in your mind with your thoughts if there are thoughts that are
being propelled by our our anger and our hostility or our attachment or our
um um greed that uh if that's kind of the
propulsion of it then it a thought of greed a thought of anger
tends to produce more of the same not necessarily more anger or more greed but it kind of that
the very movement of anger and greed is another ouch
so if what propels it is an ouch then the thing itself is an ouch and it
creates kind of more propulsions more influence more conditionality
for further thinking that way and
so if for example there is greed for something because there is a feeling of
of a feeling somehow very critical of oneself and we want
someone wants relief well the movement for relief through through greed
is being propelled by an ouch that criticism for oneself the greed itself is an ouch and that
whole movement then brings along more um criticism of self like now i'm greedy
and bad or uh creates more conditions to be more greedy or think that's the answer or if there is a little bit
relief from the greed because it's fulfilled we get what we want then that reinforces that this is the
way out to get more relief and so we end up in a cycle
and uh classically they say that the what creates the momentum of karma the
karmic repercussions is the intention uh for uh what we do
um but i think that it's not just intention it's uh it's what propels it what uh
it's more than that then tension seems kind of narrow and almost philosophical or or like an agenda or a
very clear idea it's more like the mood behind it or they
that's there and so in mindfulness practice one of the things we do with our thoughts for
example when there's a lot of intense thoughts is um they were caught in them
is to uh notice them the emotionality the mood
uh the conditions that out of which the thoughts are being coming and we're getting uh more and
more as we develop mindfulness we start seeing that underlying the surface expressions of our thoughts
the thoughts we can see or the actions we can see there's layers and layers of of um
conditioning of of um attachments of clinging of motivations
that um uh are really the real issue the real thing that that shapes and influences
karma extreme now some of this karmic stream can be positive it can have ah in it
and but it still involves a kind of a propulsion a kind of movement that
is keeps us active it kind of promotes a kind of agitation even though it can do
a lot of good for ourselves and the world uh when there's a propulsion a compulsion to do these things there's
this uh it might feel pleasant but there's a kind of agitation there
it is not ultimately uh the best for us and so there's a whole other line we can
take which is a dharmic stream and uh the positive the ah
karmic stream supports the dharma extreme it creates the conditions that leads us to
uh being a good place to enter this dharm extreme the dharma extreme
is is found through two primary ways that we enter into it
one is to let go and the other is to know
so to let go and to know and these are the kind of the core practices of the
buddha can be put in these two two categories some of them are more focused on deep
letting go and relaxation and some of them focus more on knowing
the ones that have to do with letting go are the ones that tend to produce the most happiness
the ones that have to do with knowing produces the most clarity and but this this happiness and this
clarity is not something we're willing intending it's not something that we're
creating it's not coming from a constructed action that what we're doing it's not part of the karmic stream
um it's almost like uh we're getting out of the way we're not interfering we're not pushing
we're not there's no compulsion to act and to do and
and so letting go is a lot to do about letting out getting out of the way and allowing
something to move through us not a compulsion but an inspiration
um we're not pushing something but something is
is is flowing
rather than pushing and then uh we're not um
uh caught up in our agendas and reactivities and what we
want to have and looking for and trying to understand the way forward to fix things we're just knowing in a very
simple way and that's that produces clarity and clarity also has space for things
and so the the dharm extreme involves a kind of a whole paradigm shift to change about
how we live our lives what motivates our lives or where the center of our lives is
it is not a life that's based on the on the wanting that
characterizes somehow one way the other the karma extreme including wanting what's good wanting
the ah and it might seem like why not want
what's good and healthy sure it's fine to do it and it can be a lot of very beneficial
but it's only half the half the picture it's only half the story of what's possible for us
and most people only live in the karmic world and that's what they're navigating and negotiating and always moving around
and it's a little bit like rearranging the deck chairs in the titanic
the the dharma stream is involves a whole different paradigm
and it's like learning to how to float to swim so we don't have to move all the deck
chairs around as the ship goes down and uh and they said and how we float
how we swim is we learn how to uh let go
of reactivity let go of clinging and wanting and this compulsion of the karmic stream
and we learn a kind of very clear and simple knowing that brings clarity
uh a clarity it is not agitated by by the wanting mind
and um and in that letting go and clarity and getting out of the way
something supports us something begins moving through us something gets awakened
that uh there is wisdom clarity and letting go
makes available a lot of wisdom and clarity but what's happening here with ourselves and the world around us
it gives room in the heart for love and care and and compassion in a way it's very
different feeling for it than any kind of compassion that's maybe genuine enough but has um wanting as
part of it or has self and self-concern as part of it clarity and letting go
is radically selfless and because of that it's not exhausting it's not tiring
in the way that the karmic stream is when some of it much of is motivated by me myself and mine
so um so you might you know see today as you go about the
day what's going on with your thought stream and
is there an ouch or an awe in how you think
and if you notice an ouch look more deeply and see if there's a deeper mood or place that those thoughts
are coming out of and see if that also has an ouch probably it will
and if there's an ah in those thought streams then look below that and see if there's
some deeper mood or way of being that also feels like comes from an ah
stay close to the ah and see if that's staying close to it supports you
to let go relax
and to know clearly what's here so thank you and
i hope this little exercise today is nice for you to do