so good day everyone
it's good to be here and maybe for some of you as it is for
me it's also good to be in your meditation posture one of the
pleasures of regular meditation is that the body gets
familiar deeply deeply familiar with um the posture and the
entryway the posture the body can be for reconnecting to a
you know a deep sense of intimacy with the present moment with
oneself and really be here and perhaps some of that is that we can
we know in this posture how to recognize what it's like
or to recognize the place within where we are aware where we're
present there's a sense of being present to something that's wholesome and good
so to
continue briefly with this idea of recognition clear recognition that mindfulness practice
has many components many aspects but two primary ones one is awareness
and non-discursive present moment attention awareness awareness which
maybe has no words to it awareness which has more to do with our capacity to
receive perceptions and sensations and kind of a openness of mind to
be receptive and the other thing that mindfulness has to do with mindfulness
practice is recognition and the recognition recognition is quite
powerful clear recognition and what i want to
emphasize is that when we bring this recognition recognizing
aspect of mindfulness into play it isn't that we're analyzing
it isn't even that important we should recognize kind of accurately what is obvious
what's observable perceivable in the present moment and just leave it that way
it's not the past the future it's not digging into it and understanding some deep way
it's just how it's perceived how it's recognized and that and that there are times when i
meditated where you know just kind of lots going on i didn't quite know what was happening
and and so i recognized it as chaos and uh didn't try to delve deeper than
that just oh it's chaos and as i recognize it as chaos then something opened up and i started to see
a little bit more that you know more specifically but it wasn't like i was searching for specificity
it was just the recognition one recognition allows for the next recognition
what i want to emphasize this morning is so is that it isn't that you have to understand in
some deep way what is happening and maybe the recognition almost doesn't have to be
accurate it's the act of recognition which can be
freeing the act of recognition creates space
the act of recognition helps us not be so entangled or caught
in what's going on and so that's the one of the important functions of recognition
and so when we when we kind of say to ourselves hearing hearing is happening
so we might say it casually and we're completely concerned and caught up in what we're hearing and but
to really to do it clearly clear recognition of hearing oh that's hearing hearing is happening
it doesn't have to be those kinds of words but with that kind of feeling to it there's a kind of oh and there's a
moment of freedom a moment of space moment of of allowing moments of
clarity that's what the wrecking power of recognition can provide
and so we want to take our time to recognize clearly to feel where in the recognition there's some
freedom and then take a moment just to open to that
and then recognize the next thing or the same thing again if it's still there
so that's all i'll say today and now we'll sit and we'll sit
quietly and many of you have been doing this for a long time and
and so maybe i don't have to do the introductory words of settling in and you can do it for
yourself as you see this as it works best for you
and remember to recognize what's happening
you
so
what can you recognize now that sets you free
do
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
there is something quite special about clear recognition
when it comes to recognizing other people
to clearly recognize others without the filter of our agendas
desires and aversions our judgments and bias
but to recognize as if we're looking into people's eyes and seeing their hearts
to really see the full humanity of the other person to really recognize this person
for themselves
and the training and clear recognition is a training and clear attention
that allows us to accompany people to befriend people
to be a witness to their depth and their their full humanity
and may it be that this practice of ours of mindfulness attention recognition
being present listening to others supports us
or say differently supports others so they can discover their full humanity
so others may be feel feel at ease and comfortable and
have the ability to recognize themselves their own goodness
may this practice of ours make lots of space
for others to feel unseen and heard and recognized
and in that way may this be a way to live for the
welfare and happiness of others may all beings live together in safety
may all beings live together in happiness
may all beings live together in peace
may all beings live together freely
and may our practice of mindfulness support that for all of us
so continuing now with this second talk on some pagana
often translated as clear comprehension but for these first uh first day for
this meditation the translation i liked was a clear recognition
in this simple simplest way which we do mindfulness practice we bring together our ability to be
present and aware with our ability to clearly recognize
and sometimes we emphasize one more than the other and we go back and forth but as the
practice gets deeper and deeper more and more still quiet peaceful
sometimes the part that needs to be emphasized and really helps the
this mindfulness practice come to maturity is the recognition the clear recognition of phenomena
what's happening in the moment the clear observation that recognizes and that recognition gets quieter and
quieter itself more peaceful almost as if there's just a whisper in the mind or
something so this recognition is an important factor
in other situations life outside of meditation sampajana is sometimes better translated
as clear comprehension or clear understanding and uh
and this speaks to how a buddhist life maybe a human life involves more than
mindfulness more than moment-to-moment awareness and recognition of what's happening now
but also involves contemplation reflection wise thinking
about what's going on that does in fact involve understanding things that um that you know where things come from
and where things are going and and and the kind of the context for why we do things and
and what motivates us to do things and now this fullness of the human life
that we're able to kind of navigate or swim in the all the different aspects of our
psychological emotional physical social life and understand and navigate and that
is part of what makes life rich and it's important part of life
and so then clear comprehension in the world of activities is
is part of part of a wise practice and so in mindfulness practice there is
this instruction that i read last week about mindfulness in activities
that as we reach out our arm bend our arm there's clear comprehension as we
as we do put on our clothes or as we eat or as we go to the bathroom there's clear comprehension of these
activities this list of things that and um but in every every ordinary
non-ordinary human activity we engage in there can be clear comprehension of the activity
and the ancient commentaries have four different areas that we can
reflect on or contemplate so we can live a wise life and so these are a clear comprehension
of purpose clear comprehension of suitability clear comprehension of the pasture
and clear comprehension of non-delusion and uh and to kind of take some time
with each of these and and long enough so they come a little bit second nature
isn't so we have to kind of bring out a checklist and go through this and live this kind of truncated life of
analysis but rather these four areas are meant to open us up
and free us live a wiser life so the first is clear comprehension of
purpose and that's to ask ourselves what's the purpose of what we're about to do what's the
purpose of the thing we're doing what was the purpose of what we just did
and uh sometimes what we think was the purpose might not really have been the purpose or things shift and change or
sometimes we're not really aware of the subconscious reasons why we're doing something that some sort of reflection afterwards
is very helpful but especially before if you're wondering what to do to really understand what's the purpose
for doing this so uh going and standing in front of the refrigerator ready to open it
if you ask yourself the question what's the purpose of opening this refrigerator and really ask yourself that question uh
simply to answer it in order to open the door that's a fine answer uh in a certain
kind of way and some people make that kind of answer as a kind of um i don't know spiritual superiority that
you know look just uh that's all i'm doing the simplicity i'm just being present for
this but still the um the opening the refrigerator door has a purpose i'm looking for a snack i
want to fill my loneliness with something or distract myself or i'm really hungry and
if i don't have some food now the next conversation i have i won't be at my best
and um or my my family's hungry and i'm going to cook for them or i need to kind of go
shopping i need to see what's in there and um and what's the purpose so you keep asking what's the purpose of this
and um but more more importantly than kind those kinds of things like that is
is the purpose wholesome or in self is it a wholesome purpose is it a beneficial purpose or is it not
so to ask this question what is the purpose it's fascinating to do this with speech
in fact i've often taught that if you really want a shortcut to the depths of your inner
life and maybe the royal road to the unconscious is to keep asking yourself
why do you say why are you going to say what you say
what draw it drives what motivates you to speak and and to really kind of
because many people speak somewhat impulsively subconsciously or unconsciously or
without much reflection and there's a reservoir wellspring of motivations
behind what we say and to ask ourselves the question why am i saying this
why am i going to say this can begin revealing some of these layers and layers of what drives us what the operating
systems we have and so sitting down to meditate
what's the purpose of meditation not just not to evoke a lot of
reflection but to be clear about it i've sat down to meditate just out of
rote habit this is what i do and and sometimes i've done that and i
haven't really been that involved in my meditation it's just like i'm still kind of moving along in my train of
thoughts and a little bit distracted and concerned about things and i've sat down to meditate and said
what's the purpose of meditation now and just that question even though the
purpose might be this you know same answer then every day like you know i'm here to be present
i'm here to let go of my my clinging and attachment to really be
here in a clear way so all kinds of you know answers to that question
so even if it's the same answer every day to really say it to oneself oh this is the purpose that recognition that
acknowledgement can give us a little bit more kind of stability or emphasis to okay
let's do it let's not just let the the habits of the mind continue to have their own way let's
really show up and be present here and do the practice
so asking ourselves what is it what's the purpose we have
and it's a great question we can ask if someone asks you know a
in the conversation in supporting other people sometimes it's very helpful to ask them
if they're struggling with the decision what's the purpose of the decision what
is that what is the underlying value of what you're trying to do or
intention or direction you're trying to go so this this is a to ask these kinds of
questions is to live a reflective life a contemplative life
and uh one of the things i think is very helpful is spend some time uh with uh
that kind of contemplative thinking i like to go for walks by myself and
just that's where i contemplate and um you know i'm delighted by the different things that will pop up in my
mind that won't come up in my mind if i'm living my full life doing all the usual things
i need to have a fallow time or some time away from everything to let things percolate and bubble up often
for me exercising does the same thing it's actually something about exercising where i give my freedom to my mind and there's
a kind of contemplation that begins going on and reflection that kind of happens naturally
so to live a not just a mindful life but to live a
mindful life that's supported by and guided by a conte contemplative life a
reflective life and one of the key forms of contemplation reflection
is to ask the question what's the purpose of what you're going to do
and that might be for the particular event particular activity for right now but also occasionally it's good to kind
of open up that question and ask you know what about what's the purpose for
my life for what i'm doing for my work and uh and to really kind of explore
and it's when the purpose is whatever purpose comes up for you is that really the purpose you want to
stand behind that you really want to devote yourself to what purpose of life do you really want to devote yourself to
this nourishing freeing opening that really feels that it's nourishing
and enlivening and purposeful for you in a good way
and one of those things is to walk the buddhist path the path to freedom
so um thank you and
may you reflect today in the next 24 hours on purpose clear comprehension of purpose
in a relaxed way may be supported by the simplicity of recognition keep
things simple and just kind of kind of contemplate and
and see what uh benefits and aliveness comes from a clear understanding of purpose
so thank you all very much