so good day to everyone and welcome to this meditation
there are times especially when i was a relatively new meditator that i had two different
things i would tell myself about meditation and different times different ones and
the kind of mindsets that i had for it and one of them was um
and that is in particular i use these when things were challenging if i had a lot of physical pain or something that
was difficult to be present for
and if the first one one i would say
to myself moment by moment that i would just be present for this
moment and then the next moment and i'd be try to be content with just
being here for this for this and that would be um and then i can
somehow if it was just this moment that's all there was then i could be with a difficulty
the other thing that i would do is say to myself what if this is forever
whatever was happening what was this this was it and i suppose it could be
the reason to despair or be depressed or something but for me when i'm when i said that
what if this is forever then there was no reason to fight it no
reason to try to change it or try to escape it which is okay this is what i have to
accept and that also would loosen up something in my mind that would also make it easier for me
okay this is this is what i'm going to stay stay here for so those two mindsets
are used sometimes and the consequence of both of them was a kind of uh
just okay this is it i'm just going to steadily do my practice show up be present
in an ongoing way and this ongoingness okay this is what i'm doing
this is where i am and uh so if there was real if sometimes that wasn't so difficult to do
if things were going well but you know there were all kinds of times when it wasn't going so easily and
but just okay this is what i'm doing and this kind of inspiration to the ongoing step by step
by step or breath by breath moment by moment just this just this and this taught me to set the
course it taught me not to be so caught up in goals and trying to achieve things and
trying to change my experience or get away from it and it taught me to really appreciate to
value to even enjoy the momentariness of each moment of
showing up being here being here being here and as i you know and then
sometimes as i got into that then there started to be kind of a flow in in the present moment this movement
with the present moment ongoing is that at some point felt like
more like i was carried by the present moment rather than having to show up for the present moment
but this you know this steady it's very simple calm
kind of a modest approach to meditation just the ordinary ongoingness of this
moment this moment not making it complicated not making it looking for something
grand and wonderful not belittling anything not
denying anything not criticizing anything not being in some ways for or against
anything just the ongoingness it's kind of like
going for a walk up the mountain where there's all kinds of things on the mountain
difficult things to see easy think wonderful things to see [Music] steep difficult places rocket territory
smooth easy places to walk but if it's a long long way up to the top of the mountain
it's just the ongoing step then step and step and step so
the ongoingness of practice the ongoingly ongoing the momentariness
of each moment of practice
so to prepare yourself for that journey
establish yourself in a posture that seems conducive to remembering
to be present a posture that supports you or
guides you into being present for your experience
and so perhaps a posture that is a little in a bit intentional
a little bit like you're really in the posture
a little bit more slightly more alert than usual
not over emphasizing being relaxed and comfortable
but not looking to be uncomfortable either
but so there's a little bit of intentionality
and gently close your eyes
and then gentling yourself in your body a gentling of your inner life
maybe a few deeper breaths maybe today
deep enough to be half of how full you can breathe
a little bit more than you would without effort but little effort to fill your br
fill your lungs and then that gentle releasing of all
that on the exhale so here too there's an intentionality
in how you're breathing for a few breaths
and the intentionality of the practice is a way of gathering yourself in the present moment
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and part of this intentionality is the intentional activity of relaxing
to soften and relax the muscles of your face
to soften and relax
your shoulders
to soften and relax your belly
and then becoming aware of your body breathing
and here with each breath each inhale in each exhale
settling in for the ongoingness
of one moment at a time of attention one moment after another
one step in a sense in the ongoing journey
of being present here and here and now
and to bring a little bit of relaxed intentionality
a sense of purpose or dedication maybe even devotion
to calmly steadily
going on with being here now with this with this
perhaps being supported by the ongoingness of breathing
breathing keeps breathing over and over again
there to remind you to be present moment by moment
ongoingly
being mindful of the ongoingness of mindfulness
this simple calm ongoingness of
now and now
and now
so
as we come to the end of this sitting i'd like to apply
the idea of ongoingness of practice to kindness to ongoing kindness
and one orientation that has supported me in
this regard is to imagine that
kindnesses can be very simple and modest
that it can be a simple interior attitude that i carry with me ongoingly
without needing to express it externally
in words or in deeds and just giving myself that permission
not to need to express it externally
it makes it easier to be devoted to it
internally not to give it up not to allow it to be
an ongoingness an ongoing friendliness
or ongoing warm-hearted caringness
that's not dramatic maybe unnoticed by others
and the ongoingness is to be very careful not to sacrifice it or give it up
easily but to stay
in the simplicity of private feeling of kindness
as you go through with the day
an interior feeling of good will or caringness
and so in this way knowing that it doesn't have to be
expressed externally maybe it's easier to end the sitting
with a wish for the welfare and happiness for others
may whatever benefit that has come from this meditation today
may it keep each of us close to an interior kindness
of wishing all beings to be happy
wishing all beings to be safe
wishing all beings to be peaceful
in wishing all beings to be free
and that we in simple appropriate ways
stay close to this wish open to the possibility of contributing
to the welfare of others may all beings be happy
so
this morning there'll be another day of uh storytelling from the discourses
of the buddha and this time some of the story will be constructed out of the
evidence the pieces that are there it seems that for the most part
the people who composed these earliest discourses of the called earliest discourses of the buddha
weren't particularly interested in history or even biography weren't really doing
much of a biography of the buddha but there are all these little snippets of stories that exist
and some of them we can then connect the dots and understand a little
bigger piece of the history of the times the life of the buddha
and so i'm going to tell some of this what comes from the early discourses some of its piecing pieces together and
some of it comes from a little bit later the commentaries
that also tried to piece some provide the bigger context for some of these stories
and um and a piece of what um inspires this uh this little discussion today
is uh some of the work of steven batchelor who's done some of this work of also piecing together some of the evidence
so it has to do with the end of the buddha's uh life the context that his times that
he was uh coming that were that he was you know in his last year of his life
and what we begin seeing if we start looking at the pieces is that the society around him much of what the
society he knew and his people he was close to were dying
or were the societies were beginning to fall apart and
war was it was happening and kings were being usurped um from power and uh the buddha's own
disciples the senior closest disciples that were dying this last year of his life
and um and so and the buddha seemingly through it all was calm was peaceful died very
peacefully under some trees and this contrast between the
kind of i call it the society falling apart around him and his peacefulness is quite a contrast
and and maybe it's something that's also relevant for all human times and
it seems like maybe almost every generation thinks that the world is falling apart around them
so this piecing things together begins with
um um maybe
uh in the last year of the buddha's life maybe when he was about 80 and i think
it says that in this in the text that the king come the king comes to talk to the buddha and the king says you know both of us
are 80 years old so buddha is up in his home country sakya
up in the foothills of the himalayas in parts of nepal
and he was magnus on retreat or just living quietly there in his old age
and uh nearby was another kingdom of um where there was a king pasanidi
who uh they had been friends for 40 years early in the buddha's teaching career they were at the same
age they were same age and they had struck up a friendship and for 40 years they had her
they had 46 years or something they had seen each other periodically and and were considered friends and
the senate personality was also a student very devoted to the buddha
and um this king uh in his uh was out and about and
wanted to visit the buddha maybe one last time in their old age and uh so he went with
his um minister who he apparently trusted and um and they rode into close to where
the buddha was in the forest and
the king got off his horse or his elephant whatever he was riding and then he had said he said to his
minister i'm going to go in there and see the buddha alone and here
hold these things and he handed over to the minister all the insignia all the paraphernalia
that represented the power of the king of the king his sword his
maybe his crown or his turban and different things that he had that were represented his authority and the minister was a
little bit perturbed like what's going on here some secret plan uh uh that he doesn't
want me to be there and hear what's going to be talking about and and so he was a little bit suspicious about what's up what was happening
and then um the buddha the king goes into the forest and sees the buddha and
and um the king gives almost like a eulogy for the buddha it's almost like he
is going to see it maybe one last time and he's he speaks so in a high praise of the buddha
and um and that's the end of the story oh that's the suit that just ends right there
um but so the buddha is you know 80 years old old man
and then we have another discourse that has to do with the last it's called usually called the
english the last days of the buddhist life it's the story of his passing away and
that's a little bit more of a chronology over many months actually but it begins with the buddha being
almost about as far away from his home country as he could be in the in the world that
he lived in it in northern india and maybe some 300 miles i'm not sure
exactly how many but quite far so here was a man who was 80 years old
who had been in his home country and then some time later and then
over the next year we don't know exactly when he was 300 miles away
in uh and far to the south and i think the bay of near the bay of bengal something like that
and um near what's now called patali putra i think and and so how did he get there and why
did he go there but this one the story begins almost begins with the story of the buddha now
walking back home so he came all the way down this 300 miles
only to kind of more seemingly turn around and go back up back home to his home country
and and what was you know what why why such a quick trip so the piecing it together
one idea is that the the minister of the king who took all
the king's paraphernalia what the commentaries say
is that the king this minister had a little bit resentment for the king and so he what left and abandoned the
king there in the forest and left him with a horse and one attendant
and went back to the capitol and handed the the symbols of of power to the king's
son who thereby usurped the throne and the king came out of the forest
without anything really except a horse and so he went down to visit the other
king at this place where the buddha was ended up going
and the other king was his relative i think it was a son-in-law or his cousin or something
and they had been at war with each other over those 40 years time but they also had made
some enough peace and there were relatives and and the king pessaneti had nowhere else to go
supposedly so he went down to see his relative the other king and so he made this long trip himself as
an old man and he apparently was not in very good shape they some of the texts say that he was kind
of fat and and a little bit lazy and so he made this long trip and he came to the capitol where this other
king ajata satu the one who'd killed his father the story i told earlier
was raining and he came at night and so the city gates were closed and so he stayed
into some place slept in some home or hall or something outside and then he died
that night the piecing this together it seems that
the buddha knew about this that his friend the king had been usurped and
headed south so the buddha followed maybe to offer support for the king or
to intervene or some something but when he arrived at the
capitol his friend had died so there was not much reason to head
back home to stay there so the buddha then started marching home but before he did ajata satu
sent a minister his minister to talk to the buddha and said i'm thinking about attacking
the neighboring country the country that's between ajato sato's country
and the buddha's home country the place that buddha had often
and it was kind of a republic it wasn't really run by a king it was um and um
and that and the buddhists and he asked them yeah the minister said uh do you have any advice for us about
what do you think of this us attacking and conquering this neighboring country and the buddha gives some advice and i
won't tell you what he said because of the time and
and so he prevented he prevented the war then and there but in fact he gave in
giving his advice about how why he shouldn't attack the buddha
unintentionally gave the clue for what it what what the king had to do in order to
attack the neighboring country which he did then three years later successfully as the buddha then
got up to leave and start heading north to his home country he passed he was going to cross a river
and there he saw another minister of the king ajata satu who was beginning to lay down
the the ramparts or the walls for a great new fort in preparation
for war so here war is at war is at hand war preparations are
going on the buddha begins walking north and he describes himself
as an old man and i wanted to read you this um description the buddha gives of himself
and um
buddha says himself that
i am now old worn out venerable one who has traversed life's
path i've reached the term of life which is 80.
just as an old cart is made to go by being held together by straps
so that the tagata's body is kept going by being strapped up it is only when
i meditate deeply that this body my body knows
comfort is at ease so here's a person who's 80 in the
ancient world who's being held together by straps and bodies
falling apart in other words and he's in pain and uh only in
meditation is he free of his pain back then they had no pain medication
and he's walking this old man is walking he's in pain
his minister his close friend his king had just been usurped and had died
the other king is about to conquer a country that had embraced the buddha and had been a kind of a place that
would have lived a lot and it was and that was being attacked they were getting ready to attack it
and in this long walk across back north to his home country he learns that his two closest disciples
had died one had been killed by bandits and the other had just died and buddha keeps walking
and at some point he gets diarrhea or dysentery he's quite sick with lots of pain
and he gets revived enough and he's heading home but at some point he realizes he's going
to die he doesn't reach home and he finds two magnificent trees to lay down underneath and he lays
there and that never to get up again and there he lays and
spends his last time teaching his disciples and then he carefully asks them do you
have any other questions for me before i die no one asks anything and so the buddha
finally says his last words
be all things are impermanent
everything is impermanent practice diligently
carry on diligently ongoingly carry on
and then he dies and he dies by going into deep meditation states
and goes as deep as uh possible in in the what's possible through meditation and
then he begins coming out and then in the fourth jhana which is one of the most sublime places
to be maybe the ideal place in which to die his life passed away and this image of
this man peacefully dying at peace with himself surrounded by his disciples giving his
last teachings and then peacefully going into the one last journey
in his deep meditation states and in those states his life goes and passes away and all
around him so he's spiritually easy in his inner life is deeply at peace and
peaceful setting in the woods under trees but all around him
kings are being usurped war is about to happen people are dying the
buddha's he's an old man sick in pain
walking up you know through india and he doesn't reach home he's trying to get back to his home
country so the juxtaposition
of a world out of kilter and the buddha
at peace this is the end of the buddha's time his
life so what we think about that and how we
live with that and understand that in relationship to our own life perhaps the the
the buddha said as his last words can apply to our us as well all things are impermanent
practice diligently so thank you