okay got it so formally hello and welcome
to happy hour so nice at the beginning with our informal well uh start to welcome ourselves and
each other to the space it always warms my heart when folks say hi and type it in chats
along with the weather report in different places in the world you are so so for today's practice
for today's practice i'd like to invite us to explore
meta in the form of
radiating meta there are many different ways to practice cultivating goodness
cultivating care cultivating um friendliness
cultivating loving kindness for ourselves and others and there are many phrases
that we use as skillful means and yet sometimes phrases
can be helpful and sometimes they may not be and it's nice to have facility with either using phrases may i
be well may i be happy may i be safe etc whatever phrases you use the simple ones
or the traditional form or
just sitting in the state sitting in the feeling of metta um and radiating so
and sometimes what happens for many practitioners is that phrases
are used as support at the beginning to prime the heart
and it could happen sometimes during some sits or some retreats
that phrases then seem heavy and then the phrases naturally drop away and one
just wants to sit with the feeling of meta feeling of friendliness feeling of kindness
so there is no one size fits all is what i'm trying to communicate here
some people love phrases it helps them stay grounded stay with
the feeling some people don't like phrases they seem like distractions some people like them and then they drop
away they use them to prime the heart so
so so the invitation today um
maybe what we'll do is maybe we'll start by as always we will start
with um [Music] settling into the breath with the body
with awareness of body and breath just to settle and arrive and
this being friday for those who are joining live perhaps after a long week for you of
activity so i'll include a lot of silence
that's beginning for us to settle and then maybe we'll conjure up some of
the phrases just for a little while to prime the heart and then we'll drop them see what happens if you drop them
and just sit with the with the feeling of friendliness radiating radiating friendliness ah
radiating friendliness goodwill even if it feels especially if it feels
like work it's not yours it's not yours to generate imagine that it's just it's
there there's this there is this sun shining in your heart it's above and beyond you
it's something bigger than you the sense of good will friendliness that is just there
so i think that's enough for setting the frame let's practice
together so invite you to land
land in your body
land with your breath with your in-breath
and just as importantly with the entirety of your out breath cleansing releasing
breeding yourself at your own door
at the door of your awareness ah as if you're coming home after a long
trip you're tired it's been a long week perhaps
hello dear hello dear welcome welcome home welcome
home to your own body especially if you've spent time
away from your body worrying thinking in your head welcome yourself
ah oh it's nice to be back in this body
it's a turtle back cozily in its shell
ah this home this body
breathing the body greeting yourself in the body from the inside
with each breath
maybe dropping in hello hello dear hello your name hi
welcome home with each breath
and if thoughts plans worries from the past or the future arise
in this moment
giving your heart to being present here with the body
and asking the thought to come back later thank you for visiting please come back
later i'll wait for you now i'm giving my heart
to itself in the simplicity
of just sitting and being breathed at my home
in my home inside my home my body
having arrived home after a long trip as if it's after a long trip
ah blending landing in the body
with the breaths
putting down putting down whatever is not needed in this moment whatever is extra
if worrying is arising it's extra self-judgment
definitely extra comparing yourself it's extra
being simple simply breathing
as best as you're able to showing up
in this moment in this body
and dropping in the question in this moment as if you were dropping a pebble
into a lake letting it reverberate dropping the question
into your body not answering it from your head dropping
it in why am i here
what is my highest intention
in this practice in this moment of my humanity
what is my highest intention why am i here why am i practicing in this moment
connecting connecting with whatever arises on whatever level it arises
breathing with it breathing into it recognizing its goodness
your goodness
the beauty of the inner goodness
letting your goodness shine this goodness this intention
whatever it is
whether it's for you for others i want to be kinder
i want to be happier i want to be gentle
i'm here to serve
i want to connect more deeply whatever it might be
let this goodness this intention for wholesomeness for goodness
let it shine let it shine
appreciate its goodness
knowing that any goodness you wish for yourself
will impact others
letting the wholesomeness the goodness continue to shine
as if there is a sun as if there is
a bright sun [Music] shining in the middle of your chest
the proverbial heart center it's shining it's this goodness it's this wish
this wish fulfilling jewel
shining whispering into the world
shining its light into the world more goodness happiness ease
love peace
service kindness
noticing that the rays of the sun touch you warm you up first
bring you ease and peace goodness
ah they shine upon you first
and they shine outward unto the world
maybe it's a part of this message of goodness friendliness
happiness love and care
maybe for a moment the whisper becomes more audible
may all beings may all beings everywhere
including myself may all beings everywhere including this being
be safe from inner and outer harm
letting this light the sun radiate ah this message this whisper
this light this wish of safety knowing the world isn't
safe always we know that and yet it's a wish it's an intention
it's a good will that we share freely really
and maybe the second phrase of menta becomes audible now
may all beings everywhere including this being that is me
may all beings everywhere be happy joyous
filled with happiness may their hearts sing with joy with gladness with contentment
letting your inner goodness inner sun shine
brightly resting with its goodness
the third metaphase may all beings everywhere
including me myself my all beings
enjoy physical well-being made their bodies may my body
be healthy and strong
again knowing that it may not always be possible
you may not be fully healthy right now but it's okay sharing this as an intention as a wish
it's the generosity of your heart as an inclination
may all beings have this goodness including me all of us all of us beings
on this planet and beyond
feeling in your bones ah the goodness the generosity of this
wish spread far and wide
and maybe now the fourth metaphrase the whisper of it it's been shining
becomes audible in your mind in your heart
more so may all may all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere including myself
have ease
may their lives unfold with ease may i meet this moment with ease
you're welcome to consider hearing the whisper of the phrases or whatever version of them you like
or let the shining of your inner goodness inner wish
for happiness health safety love ease to radiate through the world
shared with all beings in silence
you decide what's best for you
whatever you choose let it be easeful let your body relax resting in the
goodness of matter
if at any point the light might feel dim [Music]
reconnect with your wish with your intention
why are you here why are you practicing
what is your highest intention
as a human in your life
reconnect reconnect with the beauty with the sacredness
of the sun shining within you
[Music]
and for the last moments of this practice
feeling your body embodied sitting a little more upright perhaps
ah breathing in and out
the goodness of your intentions more fully letting
them shine into the world unto yourself unto their fellow
practitioners in the zoom room
on youtube across time and space
and if any judgments have arisen no i failed i was distracted
not good enough let this shine let the sun of your goodness shine on that too with
kindness with friendliness
shining on yourself thanking yourself thank you thank you dear
for showing up as best as you were able to in this moment for aligning
your actions with your intentions showing up
thank you
may the goodness may your collective goodness
expressed shared
cultivated further more deeply via cause and condition
for awakening full freedom of all beings everywhere
including ourselves may all beings be happy may all beings
be free
thank you thank you for your practice
so this practice we explored at the beginning coming home to our bodies embodiment
welcoming ourselves home and then we connected with our intention
with our highest intention and through that allowing this intention
whatever it might be for goodness or happiness for peace for love for joy for health this
goodness allowing you to to permeate through the world
allowing it to permeate and to actually see that this
the inner goodness this inner wish is not so separate perhaps from meta
this wish of goodness for the world because when we allow our most beautiful intentions
our aspirations to shine in the world they serve the world it's as if we're wishing the world well
everyone will safety and happiness health and ease so
seeing that those are not too far away and then dropping them if we wanted to
dropping the phrases and being with the primating of meta so
a lot of different things we explored and i wonder
what you noticed what was a lie for you in this practice would love to hear your reflections your
insights in service of awakening both for
yourself to be held witness and also in service of community you can raise your zoom hand because
your physical hand i may not see and or type in chat i've just changed
the settings if you type them publicly i'll say your name as i read out the chat if it's just
to me i will read the reflection but not your name so
so why did you discover sharing for the benefit of all beings
dear sangha was there a part which particularly spoke to you or was newt for you
or a part that didn't work for you and you have questions about how do i work with this
or maybe how you feel now compared to the beginning when you arrived
at happy hour i can tell you i feel a lot more calm and rested than i felt i was pretty tired when i
arrived it had been a long day a long week i'm i'm rested now i feel
happier yay sarah please
i really liked it when you um were saying uh coming up being at home
being in your home in your body in your home and it it brought tears to my eyes
because sometimes i feel alone and and i
and and that helped me feel like i'm not alone because i have i have this body i have a place to be
so i really liked that thank you sarah beautiful i am so
touched i moved my body's resonating with what you said happy making yay home in our bodies
yeah nice bill says the idea of connecting with highest intention
appeals to me but i frequently wish for a change now need to be patient nice
nice thank you yes and one thing to say about that is yes need for patience the practice of
patience and the highest intention is an aspiration it's
something that we keep waking up to waking up every day working towards little by little
by little so yes patience forest says when you had us drop in the question at
first i was squeezing trying to figure out the answer but then i realized
it was very pleasant to treat the question itself as my meditation object could you say more about how to use
questions oh lovely i love that question forest that's fantastic
um so so that the the way that you actually use the question
um what is my highest intention is that how you used it first i i wonder
uh if you would say a little more just so that i'm a little more
more clear about how you used it as a as an object yeah it was when you had us ask what our
highest intention was which i know i've also been doing since gil fond still introduced that
and um then i switched to just keeping that question as my object of
focus but not thinking about it just like keeping the question continuously as my object of focus which was interesting i
don't know if that was how you're supposed you know how you can work with it
yeah yeah so so the question the question actually being what is my highest intention in that way ah beautiful
i i love that that's a beautiful way to use the inquiry it's kind of like
dropping it in so so you can use it that way and sometimes i've used another way to
work with this is to to um to repeat it in tension to repeat it multiple times and repeating
putting dropping it once see what arises maybe nothing arises dropping it again and see what arises
sometimes different things arise as you drop it drop it in so you know you might drop it in an
intention can come up oh i want to be happy i'm here because i'm tired i'm just exhausted okay that's great
okay oh because i want to serve or you know different layers can come up that's another way you can
work with dropping in the questions see what arises and sometimes just as you were saying nothing might
arise so so you work with this as a oh my highest intention it's it is sacred to actually be asking
this question what a beautiful question to be asking and that's how you ended up working with it lovely
thank you for that what a gift beautiful stephanie says oh same here sarah oh i
love that stephanie too that's great and i see claire's hand is up so um let's make it brief because
i realized 6 49. so um yes tell me what's up what's up claire yeah it was i had two
contradict totally contradictory experiences it was very funny when you talked about speaking versus
non-speaking i was originally trained uh to practice
by focusing on a thought or a visual anything and letting go of all my
thinking all together and just and that's the way i prefer so i thought i was going with what you were
saying and saying oh god yeah i'm gonna go back to what i know because it really works for me
and then you started to talk and you talked about the door and coming back home and it was so
helpful to me this doesn't make sense i just said to myself you know no talking but
because i'm i tend to be out of the world a lot i like to interact with people yeah and i forget to come back to myself
i love it i love it claire and this is what it's doing for me
great i love it i love it i hear it so it's like okay it's quiet silence yes that's what i
mean but oh wow this talking actually these guys the guidance is so helpful because i forget beautiful
thank you claire that's lovely it's heartwarming and kenneth i wonder would it be okay to come back
to you after the groups i see your hand is up yes okay great
because it's uh 6 50. i want to make sure we have time for the this is around the time we transition so
when we come back from the groups kenneth you're up so i would love to hear from you so the invitation
now is as we go into the small groups the invitation so the invitation is
no we a lot of times what comes up for practice is comparing mind we compare ourselves less than
greater than bigger than my son is bigger their intention is bigger what if we drop all that
my practice better theirs is better just dropping all that what if we just drop all that
so if you're just showing up just
so so that's the idea i want to invite us today a slightly different flavor
of of showing up for each other with each other of course with meta we start as always
with 15 seconds of of silent meta for one another for each other
uh but this sense of just you're showing up as if with beginner's eye as
a beginner's eyes as if you're a first-time practitioner you've just shown up you're you're being a martian
or your baby you've just shown up on this earth you're just ah here are other babies see what that
feels like okay all right let's let's try this out
and the rooms are open enjoy okay hi everyone
everyone's back and we seem to have just one minute left and
kenneth is kenneth here i think kenneth had to leave so okay can't hear from kenneth but
does anybody have any quick comments to one comment to make something you
noticed about this new way of being in the group perhaps different way or
going once going twice okay gone all right since it's seven
o'clock let's let's wrap up and i trust that i'll i'll stay a couple of minutes extra
actually today if anybody has any questions or comments uh it's the friday special so i'll stay a
couple it's like you know at imc i would sometimes i would stay late so that people can ask questions or
just hang out a little bit so maybe i'll just stay a few minutes extra afterwards
um so but let's formally close our beautiful session of practice
together thank you for showing up um for your practice
for yourself and for all beings everywhere may all beings be well may all beings be
happy