hello greetings friends greetings from the northern hemisphere from mountain view
california unseated olonyland it's uh lovely to be with you in this
moment in time where it's chilly it's a chilly morning here
so let us gather let us gather in community
this day and continue our explorations
with the practice of generosity the practice of generosity
donna and the invitation um
today is the culmination of four days of exploring this topic
together is um during our guided meditation
actually we might as well just start and i will whatever you need to know i will invite
you during the the meditations oh so let's just begin let's just begin
so arriving landing in this body first
um here
here
here transitioning from from the busyness
from whatever has come before
greeting creating this moment
creating this moment of being human being alive in this body in this form
here just as it shows up
it has never been and will never be like this ever again [Music] greeting this
passing moment with a smile [Music]
arriving at your seat again internally arriving at your seat
taking your seat on this earth
you are alive i am alive taking your seed in this moment in time
in this body
relaxing softening
receiving [Music]
receiving the sensations of the body just as they are
pleasant unpleasant neutral
it's all a gift it's all a gift
pleasant as well as the unpleasant and neutral oh
holy gift can we see it that way is it possible to open up just for a moment
just for a moment
receiving the breath the breath is gift
enlivening
bringing life to this body
just receiving the breath in the abdomen lowering the center of gravity
from our head where it usually is down to our lower abdomen
as if as if the abdomen the belly is an organ of perception
as if it knows it receives
the breath on its own senses
and now i have an invitation for you to try on for size
if you would bring to mind
someone for you represents
complete generosity of spirit generosity of heart
complete it could be a person a being
someone you know have known
it could be a cultural icon someone is someone historic
maybe like the dalai lama
or martin luther king or it could be an archetype
that works for you whatever works for you can be non-denominational could be the
buddha it could be jesus could be being of light
make it whoever works for you whatever works for you or even divinity themselves
this sense of complete generosity complete generosity
generosity of spirit generosity of heart
which includes loving kindness forgiveness
letting go [Music] vast perspective
whatever whoever
helps you tap into this
vision bringing them to mind
and imagine them saying okay let me show you what it
feels like what it looks like for this moment
and you invite them please show me please show me they agree
as if they enter your heart your eyes your body looking out
through your awareness inhabiting
your senses so that your practice of meditation
[Music] with breath with the body with awareness
is infused with ultimate
gracious open-hearted generosity
for some for some it might fail again if it's appropriate for you the
eyes of god expansive spacious
or your inner buddha
make it personal what is meaningful for you
based on your history and background no should's here
it's just tapping into the sense of generosity of heart
however is accessible
and just sitting resting nothing needs to be done
sitting in with this perspective of expansive generosity of heart towards
yourself towards all phenomenal thoughts
sensations emotions that arise that's it
simple
and if thoughts and distractions arise
see how they are met from this ultimate ultimately generous perspective
how does your attitude the way you relate to yourself to your practice changes
through the eyes of unconditional
generosity
unconditional
goodwill openness of heart
generosity of spirit
nothing to do nowhere to go but just sit
be receive witness from this perspective
and if something arises thinking an emotion heartache
how does your inner generosity guide you're
ultimately generous
how do they see deal approach what has risen let them
show you
your inner generosity mentor
let them lead
expansive spacious
abundant
this generosity of heart
meeting everything everything
as we bring the sitting to a close
appreciating thinking
your generosity guide your generosity mentor
for gracing for gracing your heart gracing your heart and mind
supporting you in this vision
and knowing that any time
anytime you wish you can invite them to support your practice
to be filled with spaciousness and grace of generosity of heart
and ease that that brings
bowing to this image thanking letting it go
and together let's offer offer the goodness of our practice
our cultivation our intentions for goodness
generously as the best gift we have
the highest gift we have in this world
share it with all beings everywhere may the goodness of my life made the
goodness of my heart my practice as service
support bring goodness in ways i can't fathom to
all beings and myself included
may all beings
know their own goodness may all beings be happy and three
[Music]
thank you for your practice
so hello and greetings everyone
so today being the fifth day of our exploration with this topic
so the guided meditation
invited us to to tap into to invite this meta
the the generosity mentor this before because we all have this sense
and yet sometimes we need creative ways creative ways to really access
what it's like to have a heart of generosity sitting sitting with generosity with what arises
instead of judgment instead of grasping pushing away what is the spirit
of generosity spirit of ghana that can support
all of our actions all of the actions of our mind and
and the actions of our speech the actions of our our body to all kinds of actions
so [Music] treating generosity as i mentioned
before in this this short beautiful list that one of you emailed and really
appreciated so many lists in buddhism this is this one is simple um
donna generosity dhana sila bhavana
ethical conduct
moral conduct ethics non-harming non-harming
and bhavana bhavana cultivation cultivation of the mind and heart which includes
both samadhi and vipassana so donna can see donna actually this
generosity of spirit both supporting the other two really so
generosity of spirit when we offer others
safety from ourselves it is offering
it is cultivating ethical conduct morality offering non-harming it's an
act of generosity when other people feel safe in our presence so we can see that
as an extension of generosity and also generosity donna as
the basis for bhavana for for cultivation
and leading to liberation so
liberation and this is actually quite important liberation
awakening is not something you get awakening is not something you get it's
not a badge okay i've passed the first uh
stage of awakening enlightenment you know i've got it i've got the badge yay it's not
something you get awakening it's not a thing you acquire it's a gift
it's a gift that uplifts you uplifts others it's it's
it's a gift that uplifts your heart and uplifts others so
it's a gift it's a letting go it's a giving it's a gifting awakening you realize that awakening is
a gift really it's a gift that you cultivate to give to give to the world to give to
this being who is you so generosity as the ground for
awakening and it is said that the two wings of the bird of awakening one wing
is compassion the other wing is wisdom wisdom and compassion wisdom
and compassion and generosity of course supports both it supports
compassion we know this because compassion is it comes from the
generosity of our heart when we care for someone or with self-compassion there's a sense of generosity it's okay it's
okay it's okay instead of well it should be this way you should be feeling so there's a generosity of spirit
that supports compassion for ourselves and for others it's an act of giving it's a giving of love it's a giving of
care giving of meta and
similarly generosity with cultivating wisdom
and i'll get a little detailed for a moment so cultivating wisdom
and seeing the three truths seeing the three characteristics
the characteristics of existence
impermanence unsatisfactoriness in personality or not self
not self it's not personal so generosity supports us helps with
cultivating wisdom seeing these three um characteristics of being human
so generosity when you're generous it helps you to see impermanence they're
intertwined it is impermanent things come things go
yes i let go of this thing that either this object my time my
my um [Music] you know let go give you my affection et cetera it says i need it it rises and
passes it's not for us to keep it's not for us to to hang on to it's not you know here's this bell oh it's not for us
it's it comes it goes so there's there's generosity helps us
cultivate and really see anita impermanence also
with dukkha unsatisfactoriness there is unsatisfactoriness with holding
on to something holding on to everything for our own sake we know this the sense of scarcity
the sense of scarcity the sense of uh tightness
that can actually create unsatisfactoriness can create suffering so generosity
can help us see and uh and work with dukkha
and perhaps most importantly it's anata which is not self impersonality
so ultimately generosity helps us see that it's not
about me and it's also not about you
that there is no separation between the giver and the receiver and on some level
there is no giver there is no receiver
i'll leave that as a coin it is said
that the gift of the dharma is the biggest gift
and i like to invite you not to just think of that as you know being a dharma teacher and and
talking dharma but dharma is is much more expansive the vision of dharma what
dharma is so you can give the gift of dharma to a friend to a colleague
to a parent with your presence we say
don't be a buddha don't be a buddha i'm sorry
don't don't talk about buddhism be a buddha this is often what we say at the
end of retreat so when people go home we say okay because everybody's excited they want to go home and proselytize and
tell everybody to go on a retreat you should go on retreat we tell people okay don't talk about buddhism but be a
buddha be a buddha so show up show up with kindness show up with
generations show up with generosity of spirit that is the biggest gift it's the gift
of dharma you're giving a gift of dharma to others you're enabling
their heart you're enabling their dharma their beauty their goodness to to glow
and grow as you support as you give them the gift of your presence your gift of your dharma
um so so we can all give the gift of dharma with
our presence with um the way we show up in the world the way we can be a buddha
you don't necessarily need to to talk about it um and
last thing i wanted to um yeah
maybe i'll skip this part there's so much more to say maybe i'll say this briefly
um generosity of spirit is also thought to
be um the pillar of of joy and here's a reference for
those who liked like to read the book um
by dalai lama and desmond tutu called the book of joy they talk about eight
pillars of joy which is a beautiful book highly recommended
actually i spent a series during happy hour last year covering the different pillars
and when they get to the last pillar they get to generosity which is the last pillar and they say oh actually
generosity of spirit in many ways it includes all the other pillars of joy
it includes compassion it includes gratitude it includes forgiveness humor humility acceptance
and and wise perspective it includes everything so basically if you practice that
generosity of spirit everything else is included in that
and i like to end with um with this invitation
that can we think of generosity expand our view of generosity this
generosity of spirit towards ourselves towards others can we
offer everything we do we say everything we think
can we consider offer our life
as an offering as an act of generosity
can everything be a gift can we consider our life the way we live what we think say
and do as an offering
to others as an offering to ourselves what if we consider that set that
intention even if we align for it just for a few seconds or minutes a day
it will grow it can grow and transform the way we show up and the way the way
we live so so with this invitation dear ones this
brings to close this this week we have spent
together which has been lovely for me i thank you i thank you for
the generosity of your spirit in showing up and practicing
and cultivating your heart for yourselves and for the benefit of all beings
everywhere thank you
may you be well may you be happy