i was just sharing my delight and being here with all of you and
wishing you a wonderful day if it's a beginning of a day for some of you in california
or continuing of a day or end of a day
so
so let's see
so the topic of uh this week is loving kindness
and one of the you know there's a lot of emphasis in
buddhism on these emotions these social emotions that connect us to each other and
and and allow our hearts to be touched by others and
and maybe to touch the hearts of others and loving kindness in our tradition is
preeminent in those and but one of the things that's important to appreciate
it's not an obligation to be loving or kind or friendly friendly
but it is very helpful to do so it is a way of loosening up some of the
constrictions and and um fears and
tensions that we carry with us it's also a byproduct
of becoming peaceful and to think of love and loving kindness meta as a
something that that follows uh becoming free the free year we become
the more peaceful we become uh the more available the more
more open and more space there is for our good hearts and
uh and we all have good hearts i believe um you know if you just uh clear enough
of what's covering it over and so buddhist practice can be um
so no sound let's see a lot of people saying that there's
trouble with youtube but i don't know
it seems that uh it's okay here
um so
so [Music]
so we all have a good heart
so let's sit with our hearts and uh if you believe if you don't believe you have a good
heart if you don't believe that somehow inside of you there's a source of peace
a source of love even and kindness then why don't you used to
maybe you can just kind of carry along my confidence that it's in there
and maybe for these next minutes that we're meditating together at least put aside any idea
that it's not there you don't have to believe that your heart is good at the center
but maybe you can put aside any belief that it's not good any belief that gets in the way
of what i call the good heart so you don't have to believe
it's good just don't believe it's not good so taking a meditation posture
and
then maybe you can uh sway forward and back and side to side
maybe even twist a little bit as a way of kind of just making room for your body to limber up
and be a little bit more relaxed and soft and and for you to be connected
to your body and gently close your eyes
[Music] maybe in a gentle way
taking some deep breaths three quarters full feeling little bit the stretch as you
breathe in
and as you breathe in more deeply than usual when you get to the top of the three-quarters full breath you
might pause for a second
just long enough so it feels a little bit more significant that you're going to exhale
like it's a relief to exhale as if you're doing a good thing for
yourself to exhale and then a long relaxed exhale
maybe releasing at the end of the exhale so you exhale continues just a little
bit
and if you'd like at the end of the exhale you can also pause for a second or so
again so that you don't inhale automatically but when you allow the
inhale to continue to begin it just feels like a good thing you're doing for yourself
it is a good thing to be breathing
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and to allow your body to relax
the ways that you have been maybe
busy engaged in life and you've been holding your body tight and tense ready to do and
go on to the next thing relax maybe an overactive body
perhaps you hold yourself defensively
against the world against danger
holding fear in your body
and just maybe only as much as you're comfortable with maybe you can also relax the fear body
the defensive body
relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the belly
and there can be a lot of agitation and tension in the mind
maybe in the area of the brain
see if you can let your mind relax release
the brain also the mind also overworks we overwork it
we require so much of it to do and figure and
figure out what's going on
allowing the mind to relax rest
and then bringing the attention to the center of your chest
maybe the place where your heart is or your heart center
feeling maybe any tenderness that might be there
any warmth
any gentleness or maybe even vulnerability
and for a few couple of minutes see if you can just allow the feelings
that as they are in the heart to be there
and breathe with them breathe through them
as if what you're feeling there is allowed to be there whether it's pleasant or not
a generosity of attention to just feel and sense what's in your
heart
and then maybe connect it to the heart
can you find within you
the simplest possible good will
for yourself the simplest possible
friendliness or well-wishing kind regard of yourself
and to breathe with that breathe through it
holding yourself in a kind regard
letting go of your thoughts letting go of any kind of belief
that you're anything less than a good person at the heart
letting go of any idea thought feeling
that you're anything less than a good person at least for these minutes they were
meditating
and to sit quietly with your breathing breathing in and breathing out
breathing in that space in that heartfeltness
where we might have freed ourselves for any negative view of ourselves
and if we're not free of it and see if you can hold that negativity
in a kind way
the negativity might need
to be held in a wholesome way and not condemned or belittled
just known kindly
gently letting go of your thinking
chances are you don't need to think what you're thinking
and instead breathe with your heart
breathe
breathe free of any negative
any thinking view of yourself just breathe in what's left
with the absence of negativity
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to once again see if you can relax
more deeply let go
of tension in your body soften the body
see if you can let go of tension in the mind
softening the mind
quieting and letting go of any beliefs
that you're you're anything less than
good and if you can sit here quietly openly
peacefully without any idea that you are less than
good you can be confident you have more to offer the world
then perhaps you can bring a simple kind regard
in your contact with other people not dramatic loving kindness
not great acts of generosity and care for others
but a simple basic human good will kind regard
and may it be that as we come out of this meditation and
engage in the world of other people today and tomorrow
may we bring this kind regard with us
so that in our hearts we may be delight
in wishing people well
there's a kind of joy simplicity
a smile in the heart may others be happy
may others have smiling hearts
may others relax in safety
may others find ease in a peaceful environment
and may others be free of any belief
that they are less than good at least in the depths of their hearts
and may we believe that under the layers and layers of
where what people how people live that there is
goodness in there there is beauty in each person
and may we contribute to the possibility of
letting each person's beauty come forth into this world
[Music]
so then we come now to the fifth talk on the meta suta so i i guess on monday i
said there'd be four parts but because of the five parts week you know i divided into five
parts and so we come to the last part and uh it should be there on the youtube
description of the youtube underneath if you want to read along with me
and also if you don't not on youtube and you can find this uh my translation of this
in um in the home page for imc's website under uh reflections from gil on the
bottom right hand corner there and
let me read you the last section so the section before it talks about
cultivating loving kindness meta goodwill in a boundless
in way unlimited way and meaning it's not held in check or restricted by any
attachments any hostility any greed any kind of way in which we um
define and limit ourselves and there's a kind of openness
and freedom within which or in which this good will
this good heart can kind of radiate and then it goes on and it says standing
or walking sitting or lying down as long as one is alert may one remain
with this recollection with this perspective this
is called a sublime abiding here and now
this is a sublime abiding here now so abiding means a way of living a way
of of existing and whether you're sitting quietly in
meditation or you're going about your life there's a sense of that we're kind of
resting in a lot of goodness they were resting in in the case of loving kindness
resting in loving kindness resting in good will and in a sense it's almost like a disposition
it's almost like a a attitude that just comes along with us
as opposed to something we keep practicing and for it to be that way then whether
we're standing walking sitting or lying down and whatever we're doing when we're awake during the day
it really is really imperative not to be caught up in our thoughts not
to be ruminating not to be lost in preoccupations
not to be involved in resentments and annoyances and complaints and everything that's wrong in particular
not to be cut up and involved with negative self-thinking and um and a lot of what buddhism
focuses on is the absence of any thing unwholesome
in the mind and the heart so the the one the description descriptions of the ultimate goal in buddhism
is to be free of greed hatred and delusion and we realize that hatred and delusion
and greed are kind of embedded very can be embedded very very subtly in us
and some people say well being free of greed hate and delusion is not good enough we should have a greater goal
like for example love but it's pretty wonderful to be free of
greed hate and delusion uh great hate and delusion causes a lot of harm to ourselves and others
and just simply be free of these things so like being free of any negative self-thinking
being free of any hostility towards oneself any criticalness any free of any idea
that you're anything less than beautiful there was a song from i think about 30 years ago that
the lyrics went how could anyone ever tell you that you're anything less than beautiful
how can anyone ever tell you that you're less than whole
well some people tell themselves that and so as a minimum what we're trying to
do in buddhist practice is to free ourselves from that and have an experience of ourselves without the
negative self-thinking and to somehow
feel confident that it's okay to do so that there's no authority that's hanging
over us telling us that we should be that we're wrong we're bad
we're somehow less than or unacceptable in some way
and to let go of all this negative self-talk to let go let go of all the ideas that
more more and more only if i have more then i'll be happy only if i get more
then i'll have more then i'll be happy then i'll be respected then people will love me or something
greed is also a way of limiting this good heart so how could anyone ever tell you that
you need more to be beautiful how could anyone ever tell you that you need more
in order to be whole your wholeness and your beauty doesn't depend on getting more things
and having more experiences it's already here waiting for us
so to rest in that and find that attitude and just trust that and then live that uh in our lives to
carry it with us remember it and so to remember to have a kind regard
as we go through the life so this is kind of what the text is saying
and then it goes on to say whoever is virtuous endowed with vision not taken by views
and having overcome all greed for sensual pleasure so i'll read the last line later but
virtuous to be virtuous is again to not be caught in the constrictions
of unwholesomeness not to be caught in meanness and
hostility towards anyone or greed in relationship to other people
it's a living from a very different place than from greed hatred and delusion
endowed with vision to be quiet enough and still enough or calm enough so we can really see clearly in a way we
can't when we're agitated and spinning in thoughts and jumping from one thought to the other and jumping
to conclusions endowed with vision to be able to see well what's going on here
and then not taken by views means not to be involved in fixed use not to
be attached to a particular view there are views ideas opinions which have some value
interpretations that have some value but when we hold on to them tight and insist that we're right and this is the right
way it tends to cause harm to self and others and buddhism puts a tremendous
emphasis on not holding on to fixed views and um and being fluid and relaxed and
and flexible with things and not insisting always our views has to be hammered into other
people and overcoming all greed for sensual
pleasure so these are very high level of maturity in buddhist practice so this is
kind of kind of talking about where buddhist practice is meant to go to evolve
to drop into to to be virtuous endowed with vision
not taken by views and overcoming all greed for sensual
pleasures since your pleasures are okay it's the greed that's the problem
all if you do all those things then uh you will not the text goes on says one
will not be reborn again and and this is a code word code
expression phrase not being reborn again for a heart which is liberated
because a mind that has a heart mind that has no clinging no grasping no attachment
the theory goes that when you die the the heart won't reach out grab on
and to the next attachment to the next life and that without that attachment that
greed we allow the uh what in buddhism is considered a beautiful thing
a freedom to be the the end result of life and
end of life we kind of let go into kind of a freedom not one more grasping we've done enough
grasping in our life and and to come back and grasp grasp more and buddhism is not considered ideal
i tend to interpret this stuff about rebirth as being uh how we get born and reborn
moment by moment day by day and and that when we no longer get reborn
this moment moment's way then we live in freedom we also live
in love or in goodwill or in metta and this is one of the great things
about liberation it really releases and frees up the
goodness of the heart the goodness that we all have and uh the good will that's there
the compassion that's there the the care we have for our fellow humans and our fellow living
beings on this planet may be care even for the planet itself
that um we see in the text in the ancient text teachings of the buddha that uh with liberation
comes an ease easy access to all four of the brahmaviharas to to
loving kindness compassion appreciative joy and equanimity so these things
in a sense live in us and and they get revealed they have a chance
when we've let go of all the things that get in the way
and some of the things that get in the way is not believing in ourselves not believing
and trusting and valuing the goodness our own the goodness of the
good heart that we have and um and it seemed like other things
are so much more important but i'd like to say that the good heart we have is probably the most important
wealth that you have the most important asset you have stay close to it protect it allow it to
grow so much goodness so much wonderfulness comes when the good heart has a breathing room
to be part of our lives and when we lose contact with that good heart then
in the buddhist perspective were impoverished and no no
amount of wealth and and defensiveness and acquisition
will ever be enough to
to fulfill us we're fulfilled from the inside out when
we relax and open and give room breathing room for our good heart
so the meta the discourse on loving kindness and so i hope that my
my uh spending this week with it is a nice
thing it's a wonderful text and uh you might consider
memorizing it uh it's said in buddhism that it's one of the protective chants
that if you have these chants and you can say them to yourself they protect you and the loving kindness
one in particular is that and probably it protects you most from yourself
and that's probably where we need the most protection but also who knows how it uh what kind
of wonderful field of goodwill it helps to create when we chant that text and that
maybe it protects us from others as well so um i certainly encourage you to
memorize it and and and recite it to yourself
so thank you and may you be be happy and well and
appreciate yourself thank you