[Music]
so
so good day and hello everyone
and for the today's meditation i'd like to offer something a little bit different
and that is that um
rather than thinking of meditation as something we do as a work
think of it more as an undoing so that
there is a little bit of doing we do of course but mostly it's avoiding or not doing
so many things that we normally do that add tension and stress
to our moments of being alive
so in this meditation you might try to assume assume
a or touch into some modicum
of being peaceful or calm it can just be most you might be mostly
not be that way but maybe somewhere you can touch into a little bit of being calm in the middle
of the storm and then uh let everything kind of
settle into that calm or peace that's the reference point
to see how much you're actually doing and so for example tension in the body
is a doing it's an activity that we're engaged in and it's tiring to be tense and as we sit kind of with the modicum
of calm or peaceful let that tension in the body release
let yourself settle into that piece a little bit more
some modicum of calm or peace can be a shield that protects you a little bit from too
easily wandering into thoughts which are stressful and a lot of doing
so we're undoing the engagement in active thinking coming back letting go into this peace
staying close to that and when we're focusing on the breathing
it's kind of like we're we're aware from that peaceful place
through the peaceful place where we're aware in a calm calm way
as if breathing is held in a sea of calm
so um sitting upright or submitted entering
into your meditation posture
and perhaps gently closing your eyes
and without doing anything more can you find or touch into
some degree of calm or ease or peacefulness that's here now for you
the calm in the middle of the storm
maybe it's found someplace in your body maybe it lives in your chest or your
belly in your hands or
in whatever modicum of calm or peace you can feel
let your body relax into that relax the doing of tension holding
of your shoulders
of your belly
of your face
in a calm peaceful way becoming aware of your breathing
so it's not work to be aware of the breathing but almost as if the breathing
are the waves of the ocean gently washing across the shore
the sand so gently the
your breathing washes across whatever is calm or peaceful for you
especially as you exhale i kind of return to a peaceful place
staying with the whole exhale settling into whatever calm there is
here
and notice if you start thinking if that's extra work for your mind
and the overactive mind is tiring
sometimes in the mind there's physical tension from all the thinking
we do that can be tiring if we really feel it
undoing the doing of thinking
let the thinking mind relax
not so you don't think at all but so your thinking becomes calm and relaxed
the thinking becomes thinking about breathing
gentle slow thoughts about being present here in this peaceful place
and so for this meditation stay close to a feeling of peace or ease
and notice what takes you away from it
and whatever takes you away from it can you relax
settle back let go into the piece again
and then notice what takes you away from it
[Music]
touching into some degree of calm or peacefulness
or ease within and trying to stay close to that
open your heart now to the people around you
to the people you might encounter today or people in your lives
neighbors strangers colleagues
and what i like to bring them to mind with a peaceful heart
a heart which is not doing much that doesn't have to react or
immediately pick up all the things that should be done just be aware peacefully
and perhaps peacefully without expectation or work
a gentle calm
of aspiration that is our aspiration that we can
contribute to the welfare and happiness of others calmly peacefully
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may our peacefulness contribute to that
may our ability to be peaceful make space for others
to be free to be happy to be safe
maybe our contribution is simply to stay peaceful and calm
and in that peace and calm to be present for others
for our friendliness simple friendliness to shine forth
okay
so yesterday morning's teachings on karma are an important
aspect of buddhism and to appreciate
that are all our actions have consequences and to be careful of what we do
and to do the things that are health producing that are wholesome and
helpful supportive that move us towards freedom and to avoid those who do the opposite
so this is an important teaching but it can be heard as if
now we have to get to work like this is a lot of work now every single action i have to track and
monitor and and think about and try to do it just the right way
and so it can be taken as a teaching that you have to kind of work
and sometimes it can be even be exhausting just to hear this kind of teaching because it just if the implication is a lot of working
and sometimes to be passionate inside meditation practice in general when it's taught
might lend itself to the idea that there's a lot to do there's a lot of instructions and
and you can now hear hear all the instructions and you can actually what do i do now and do i do this now and
now now there's a lot of emotions and what i was supposed to do with supposed to you know go through the list of the
different uh raft or rain or whatever it might be and
and it could be done just uh keeping her end up being busy
but that's not how it's supposed to be um
and i think that uh closer to the idea is what we did in this meditation is to find some degree
of calm or peace or ease and let that be the reference point
for not making things worse to recognize that when
the mind gets caught up in preoccupations in a sense you're losing touch with that peace and that ease
you're not being peaceful anymore and in a sense you're making things worse
if you start you're peaceful but then you start rushing and feel tense and they're rushing in a
sense you're making things worse if you
start complaining about something in a sense you're making things worse maybe for yourself and for someone else
and so to have this reference point of some degree of peace and calm
and have that as a reference that don't make it worse and it's not a lot of work to do this
it's more like stay stay close to the peace stay attentive and notice
when uh it becomes not peaceful when it becomes agitated when it becomes stressful
when it becomes contracted or tense and with time we start becoming quite
sensitive and familiar with the feeling the sensations the experience of things
getting tense or tight or contracted or agitated
and we recognize it early and earlier and then
question is it really necessary to do this and maybe not
come back to the peace you can still do things and take care of things but do things from this calm place
and so the attentiveness of mindfulness this attention to the moment and to the consequences
can be very simple it means stay calm and peaceful the best you can and notice
when you lose it and probably if you uh you lose it you're making the
situation worse and one of the fundamental principles of this karma teachings
is don't make it worse whether you can make it wonderfully wonderful for people or do wonderful
things for the world that might be difficult to figure out
and kind of burden to carry that responsibilities it's nice to be supportive and do nice things for people
for sure but the minimum is don't make it worse
making it worse is probably some kind of activity we have to work to make it worse
and so if we're a little bit hesitant to do meditation because it seems like a lot of work
uh we're probably overlooking the the all the work that we do that makes situations worse for ourselves and
for other people and don't make it worse and then
trust this place of calm or peace or subtleness
and if you have these reference points of some modicum of peace and calm and again it doesn't have to be dramatic
i mean it might not be might be that you're quite agitated but
a little bit you have a senseless sliver of calm you have some sense of what it is
that becomes a better reference pointer to highlight how you are tense
how you are contracted or agitated and then to stop and take a good look at that
become familiar with that that's when we bring our attention to
sometimes my instructions that i give myself and you know what i do in meditation or in daily life
is i stop for suffering i go about my life peacefully happily
along but if i start suffering if i start getting agitated or tense that becomes a mindfulness spell okay
here's something i should pay attention to now i should notice here's something for me to learn
what did i just do what did i just believe what is arising out of me what's the
reactivity that's happening here and those questions uh of investigation of looking at it
begins to take some of the authority away from it some of the automatic nature of it
so that i don't have to kind of go barreling into or participate in this suffering
producing kind of state that i'm in for some people
it can there's very strong uh counter forces to being peaceful and
calm and one of them is a belief that it's not okay
and the belief that we're supposed to be agitated or i'm so terrible person that i have to kind of
make up for it and just kind of really try to run around and fix everything up and make everything safe and everything
good and tidy and being peaceful just means that i'm lazy or good for nothing or something
and my worth is only found in doing and so if i don't do something i would will have no inner worth and this piece
implies some kind of not doing and so that then where's my worth if i just sit and be calm
and this is you know not necessary to think this way because it's possible to do all the things we
are supposed to do our responsibilities with through with our calm with peacefulness we can do it peacefully we
can do it calmly and some people have found that they do things better that way
it's more effective it has a better impact on others on our oneself that by time some activity is over we
feel more settled or more focused than if we did it agitated way and time
is over we felt we feel exhausted by it tense by it
so this idea that buddhist practice is a lot of work um is a
misunderstanding that's easy to come up with and i'd like to think of it it's almost
the opposite it's like the undoing of work it's the undoing of
all the different forces that are work that are exhausting or tiring and discovering a place of ease from
which we can do things and um and enjoy it and and that's fine
that's a wonderful place to be and trust it in some deep profound way
so in this way the instructions in meditation that we give sometimes are not really prescriptive
less less than what we do and more what we notice
less what we're doing but more what we're undoing so if the attention is to
the breathing then it's noticing how we add extra work to breathing to the attention to
breathing like when we're trying too hard and trusting that it's possible to do it
in a peaceful way in a relaxed way if you bring attention to our body
feeling that we have to fix every ache and pain in the body and so we get busy trying to
focus on pain and get rid of the pain and do something with it and
and as opposed to being peaceful with discomfort oh i'm supposed to pay attention to
discomfort let me do it peacefully and no agenda no work emotions
all these wonderful instructions we give on emotions can seem like a lot of work
but what is it like to be with emotions in a peaceful calm way and to use the instructions and
emotional emotions to support the peaceful way a calm way
and thinking you know a lot of thinking makes it worse a lot of thinking is difficult and stressful
but what's it like to hold that peacefully and look upon it kindly
and not be too caught and preoccupied by it
so
our actions make a difference our actions have consequences and the actions that are done peacefully
will have peaceful consequences at least locally
and the actions that are done in an agitated way unpeacefully will have unpeaceful consequences
so hopefully that simple teaching will encourage you to
stay peaceful and not to use buddhism as some as a
as a lot of work it can be ongoing it can be continuous it can be the center of our life
um but it's more of a undoing than a doing
it's kind of like um we put a lot of work in
to stay at ease and stay close to the place of ease and there's a paradox there if you put a
lot of work to that you can't get tense in order to be at ease but you can't
have a continuous attention you can be have a heightened awareness that keeps you close to that place of
ease and peace a heightened awareness which is itself an expression of that peace itself
and that becomes a protection and this easeful mindfulness is a really a protection becomes a shield
from all the ways that we get caught up in excessive work in the mind and the heart
so thank you and if you take one thing from this uh talk
um live a life where you don't make it worse whatever situation you're in don't make
it worse so um
i look forward to coming back tomorrow and then next week we'll do i'll start the sati patano start the instructions on
the buddhist instructions on the four foundations of mindfulness and we'll go through it probably over a few
weeks it's a like we did last year with anapanasati so thank you
you