so hello everyone and welcome to our meditation
and
there's an important distinction that we do in mindfulness
practice and that is the distinction between
the experience we're having and the subjective way in which we know
that experience so the what is known and the knowing
it's probably fair to say that much of the time people are involved
in what they're experiencing and this could include what they're thinking
uh or what we're feeling the emotions we're feeling or the or the um
the thoughts we have and any anything any experience any thought any
that can be the object of attention is what i'm calling the experience
and then there's the attention that knows it the awareness that knows it
and and in mindfulness practice that attention that awareness that
mindfulness over time becomes stronger at first if you hear a
irritating noise outside and before practice you might just be irritated and ready to write a letter to
the mayor of the town that there's something needs to be fixed the noise is so irritating
and and then over time you learn that you can be mindful of it
and mindful of the irritation and let go of the irritation mindfulness reactivity let go of the reactivity
and over time you learn that you can just be mindful of it there's no reaction just aware of it mindful of it
and then you then you might over time notice that your mindfulness your becomes more acute more sensitive more
uh able to kind of really stay present in a strong way for the sound
and then as that mindfulness gets stronger then um the mindfulness itself
becomes something that's valued the awareness itself becomes valued and recognized oh this is
valuable this is important and in fact the awareness of the sound it's still maybe still in
you know an unpleasant sound but that that recedes in importance
you're not denying that it's unpleasant but what seems more important is the fact that you're
aware awareness becomes like a jewel the capacity to be
attentive the capacity for being mindful uh becomes like a jewel like a precious
thing it becomes it's almost like a its own experience so
rather than awareness only being aware of other experiences awareness itself becomes the
experience and uh and it just feels so that there can be a rightness to that or
a goodness to that or a joy to that freedom to that in the knowing itself in
being aware and over time that awareness begins um
free becoming freer of of self of my ideas of being the agent
the one who's doing the one who's the victim the one who's the the engager and
it's just like awareness itself kind of it doesn't need so much baggage around
me myself and mine it becomes this kind of kind of thing that is just so
like i kept saying a jewel so there's a whole there's a whole
journey that can go in mindfulness practice in our relationship to how mindfulness is
experienced or operates within us at some point
as doesn't somewhere along that line along that journey
mindfulness awareness just becomes such a welcome thing to do to be mindful
that there's a wonderful little one word that can be used
that um sometimes can really kind of spark a little delight or joy or
or welcoming or receptivity or really kind of put us in the
present moment in a you know kind of a
wonderful way and that is to say the word yes
whatever you're mindful of say yes
and it isn't that you're saying yes to the experience so much some experiences might be nice
it isn't like you're condoning valuing approving of what the experience is
but rather you're saying yes to that receptivity that welcome quality of
awareness that's there to meet that that holds that's aware of it yes
it's this is good to be aware of it yes i can be aware of this
yes let me hold this in awareness and this wonderful
little word yes can kind of be a
a cleansing agent to cleanse us of our reactivity or
or all the extra baggage we carry along in our relationship to what we're being
mindful of and maybe we'll put you into a place that's more
simplicity and clarity and without being entangled or reactive to
what's there just yes to being aware of this so if that's nice for you you could try
this today and if it doesn't make sense or it doesn't uh work for you please by all
means don't do it so sitting upright
or sitting in a way that's meditating in a way in a posture that works for you
and relaxing your eyes
for some of you it might mean closing your eyes some of you might mean half closing the
eyelids and gazing down at a 45 degree angle
and taking maybe three long deep breaths
and then letting your breath return to normal and then take three
normal breaths but do it so consciously giving yourself over to those three
breaths
then on the next exhale relax as much as your body as you can
and the next two breaths do the same
and then settling in to the body's experience of breathing
and as you get more settled in here you might say to yourself softly gently
yes to whatever experience
arises for you it could be a gentle soft yes
to being aware of the in-breath or a yes to being aware of the exhale
rather than resisting anything
whatever you become aware of mindful of maybe the mental note can be yes
yes to being mindful of it
to receiving it an awareness
to your ability your capacity to hold it in awareness
ready
you
if you're drifting off in thought keeping up a regular pace of saying yes
might cut through your thinking might return you
to being aware but do so without
self-criticism or disappointment just
a wonderful yes to being aware again
you
three
perhaps a yes it also
is a reminder to calm the thinking mind
yes it's good to bring the thinking mind to rest
to a kind of silence that allows for greater awareness
you
okay
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
whether you use the word yes or not
it's good to be to affirm awareness
affirm any moment of mindfulness you have
not actively thinking affirmations
but a deep inner appreciation valuing
of being aware and with time that affirmation that
appreciation allows awareness to grow
which is synonymous with the growth in our capacity
to be aware our capacity to hold in awareness
any difficulty at all any joy at all
and this and this is one of the keys to freedom
is to make lots of room in awareness so awareness has capacity to hold
within it the joys and challenges joys and sorrows
of life
to say yes to awareness for each thing that we're aware of
helps us to become less and less entangled with what we're aware of
reactive to it afraid or
desirous or have expectations or
projections predictions yes
just yes to the simple being aware
and then
in the center of that awareness
there can be love there can be generosity
there can be care for what we're aware of
to relax with into awareness and then allow our care for the world to
come forth not as an obligation
but in a way that is personal for each of us
in our own way to be open in awareness
so the joys and sorrows of the world resonate with our good heart
and so that we might be motivated
to speak and to act and to think
in ways that benefit this world
may it be that the practice that we do individually and all of us collectively
may it be for the welfare and happiness of all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
may all beings everywhere have the safety
that allows them to discover the goodness of their own hearts
so for this third talk on faith
i'd like to attempt to talk about the quality of faith that is akin
to love or related to something we might call love or
that when we have faith in
dharma faith it's because something inside of us
resonates with the dharma something inside of us
we recognize something inside of us that is
maybe akin or represents the buddha dharma and the
sangha the key objects of faith in buddhism
there is an intimacy that we develop with ourselves and or an intimacy we develop with the
world with the sensitive um tender awareness that we might have
and that intimacy can come with a feeling of warmth of
joy of deep sense of satisfaction
excuse me excuse me and um
and so to um [Music]
and it's that it's a love or a joy or a kind of a desire even
that's a since ancient times misunderstood that faith is a kind of desire it's a desire to be close to
something it's desire to uh live in close to something that's we
have faith in something that we find valuable and if the dharma is found or this intimacy
with the dharma is found through meditation then um
there's something about the desire to stay close to that the tenderness the intimacy the
warmth the joy the the sense of uh well-being
that seems to be somehow related to this it's um the faith is more than just a
knowing it's a knowing through experience we know something
because we experience it and um
and so uh to love
the practice to love in a sense
uh the dharma another one way that this expresses
itself that faith sometimes takes the form of devotion devotional practices
a certain kind of heartfelt um you know a motive
wanting to serve wanting to be close to wanting to
offer ourselves in some kind of way to the dharma or to the practice
in our vipassana inside tradition there's you know very little chanting and very little ritual
and people have asked sometimes where's the devotion in this practice and a common answer that
as it's given is that mindfulness itself is devotional activity
and of course it isn't automatically but as we develop this practice we start
feeling that that there's something really religiously or spiritually or sacredly
vital or enhanced through mindfulness that mindfulness awareness itself
is something to be devoted to something to be um to love to serve
to uh to and it's to to dedicate ourselves to with love or
care or generosity and and so faith has so many different
qualities so many different aspects and and but for some people
or some people sometimes there is a quality that's akin to what
i'd like to call love today and i think we all know that the word love is very vague and covers a wide range spectrum
of what of emotions or feelings and so maybe it's more like a koan more
like a question that i'm offering you that if um faith
has a quality of love in it or characteristic of love and love is a very and it's very
personal how this is is experienced what corresponds in you
to what i'm calling love for this warmth um this intimacy this uh
this the kind of uh place where we can feel like yes this is home or this is desirable this is
satisfying this is something that feels like the the warm warmest and tenderness and
forms of dedication love wanting to serve wanting to be generous one to care for
maybe it's kind of a caring kind of love you want to care for this thing
so some what what how does it what what do you have in yourself where do you find yourself that might correspond to
this to this you might use very different words but maybe if i'm using very broad terms
what specifically works for you or if i'm just giving you kind of a rough idea maybe you have something that's
somewhat corresponds and you have other words for it and so um
and so uh it's a kind of love or faith or dedication devotion
where the pull or the desire to practice to live the dharma to live with the
precepts and ethically just seems like a love affair seems like more of an expression of something that
feels really good and right a rightness to it and
and that seems to be embodied or seems to be heartfelt
it's not so much a cognitive belief or thought or idea that this is good
and it's something that comes from feeling at home in oneself or settled here in the heart
and then the goodness of the heart begins to shine and move forth
and for some buddhists this expression of um of what i'm calling today love
in relationship to faith is most actively expressed in uh the refuges in what's called going
for refuge and um and i love this expression the pali word is to walk to refuge but it
can mean going as well and say me like in english but going for refuge is kind of like a
entering into being willing out of one's own free will in a sense
to go somewhere to go in a direction and this is the direction to go it go in that which is most
meaningful most warm-hearted most uh something that we just feel so
um delighted by or pleased by or
inspired by so what i'm pointing to here is that uh
faith sometimes has a very strong very strong heartfelt qualities to it
and um and it's can be an aspect of the heart
and so what does it re what does it take to be close to this to allow for this to happen
and i think that one of the accesses to it is um
through um being settled enough having
quiet enough not not just less and less distracted less caught up in desires and aversions
and really settle down and so that the uh we're really intimate and present
with our direct experience so that maybe this word yes that we use for the
meditation is an expression of that love yes
to be here an awareness to be here practicing the dharma to be here
in this ethical goodness that we feel not that we have not that we
impose external ethics moral rules on top of us but we recognize the ethics that comes
from a settled clear peaceful heart and yes this is right this is good
this is what i love this is where i want to center my life base my life on
this this is a a source from which
to live my life and what it would be like for you to live your life
with a source for that life is love dharma love
not erotic love this not not even love for friends
but some kind of deeper existential love some way in which we're not
afraid we're not troubled we're not uh
anguished by anything but our but all those things that cause anguish
and trouble are held in a wonderful capac growing capacity of
the heart to hold everything and there's expression in our sin
in our inside tradition that ended up a title that sharon salzberg's book
called having a heart as wide as the world
so maybe that is one of the purposes of this deep heartfelt faith
is to have a heart that can hold all things those wide as the world
and then to care for the world as a as a um
to care for the world we live in as a natural expression of that
so um thank you
and um and uh we'll continue two more talks on
the word faith concept of faith and then i thought that on friday
uh at the this ending time we could switch over to zoom those of
you would like and we could have more of a meeting i could maybe answer some questions maybe we can have
some small breakout groups so some of you can meet you've seen each other's names and it's been a while since we had this
and so at an outpost a variety of places the
zoom link so we can have that meeting so thank you all
you