hello sangha hi welcome to happy hour and if the audio's alright give me
thumbs up awesome fantastic so greetings all greetings hi neil
hi bill hello claire hi peggy hi linda from smokey utah worst air
quality in the world today oh so sorry linda oh
yeah yeah i hope you can stay inside yeah hello wayne from near point
richmond hi kenneth from albuquerque hi na from singapore
good morning to you ah sweet to to see all the hellos and you're all
also uh welcome to unmute yourself if you like to say hello if you wish um
hi eileen from honolulu hello good afternoon to you oh sweet
nice to see you all sangha coming together this friday very sweet or or saturday for
uh for nav and uh and others joining from other uh
time zones so ah so let's get started
formally let's get started and this is a queue
neil is going to post information about happy hour google groups any moment oh there it is
yes thank you neil so as you guys already knows where you can join
information is shared information about happy hour quotes and resources
and and information amongst yourselves so and at this point i changed the settings
so accidental unmuting is not possible and that chats will only come
to me if something urgent comes up say if the audio drops out or something
and and i also turn on [Music]
recording for the sake of audio dharma
okay hello and welcome again to happy hour practicing together
[Music] so
so it is said that the buddha was was asked if
spiritual companionship spiritual friendship is half of the holy life
and he said no ananda no it's not half of the holy life it's all
of the holy life it's 100 of holy life
so walking this path together walking this path practicing together
supporting each other and we are not alone we don't do this
practice alone just knowing that just showing up to happy hour and there are other people
showing up with you um and if you wish you're welcome to
put yourselves each other on gallery view so you can see each other i can't do that because i'm
for security and privacy reasons as i
said i i uh spotlight myself my image so that only my image shows on
youtube not yours not your names but anyway just to get a sense of appreciation as
you look at each other as you look at this anger we just have a sense of the sangha
um supporting each other supporting each other we wouldn't
um happy hour may not be happening if it wasn't for for you showing up for you showing ups
or appreciating yourself appreciating each other knowing that
you are providing support for others
you are providing support by others for if you're providing support for others by
just showing up and of course i trust in so many other ways
but simply by showing up so
so we'll use this as the basis this reflection for the base as the
basis of our practice today
and um yeah maybe that's it as always we're
gonna start with selling the body with the breath and given that it's friday or saturday for
many of you we'll start with a lot of silence to just arrive and settle in the body together so
so let's begin let's arrive
arriving in this body
in this breath in this moment
feeling the feet grounded
touching the earth
your sit bones your legs perhaps touching the earth
bringing awareness landing landing
connecting arriving here here
awareness turned into word
connecting with the entire in breath and out breath
calming soothing
with each breath
connecting connecting with yourself with this body with this breath
awareness holding awareness and awareness expansive
expansive holding holding off
that rise and pass away in this moment's experience
here not the last moment not the next one just here
the magic the magic of the mundane
it seems perhaps monday but it's amazing this moment
right here
i'd like to invite you to bring to mind
one of your spiritual friends and maybe up until this moment he really
didn't think of this person as a spiritual friend but someone
who loves the dharma was dedicated to cultivating themselves
in kindness in awareness and mindfulness
might be a good friend a close friend or it could be someone that you've met maybe at happy hour
or other sanghas you know this person they inspire you you feel supported by
them
just the fact that they practice supports you
bringing this spiritual friend up to your mind's eye
feeling your connection with them your appreciation for them
and if you're having a hard time choosing one friend it's okay we're gonna invite other friends in the moment just
settle on someone it's okay it's all good
maybe you've had a conversation about practice with them
shared something that has inspired you or you've had a vulnerable conversation about
dukkha about suffering about challenge
challenges of life and they've invited you
just by showing up to see it from the perspective of the dharma the
way things are cultivation ethics etc
feeling your connection to this person
a spiritual friend will call them this moment
and wishing them well in your heart thanking the spiritual
friend spiritual friendship is all it's a
hundred percent of the holy life
thanking them in your heart appreciating
them and wishing them well
sharing meta
good will kindness
may you be safe from inner and outer harm my friend
may you be happy and joyful my friend
may you be healthy and strong in your body my friend
you may have ease may you have ease
need the moments of your life with ease my friend
continuing the phrases of meta if you wish whatever phrase you want to use
or not sharing goodwill with this spiritual
friend
and now let us see ourselves from the perspective of this spiritual friend
they too see us as a spiritual friend
the fact that we practice that we cultivate our hearts and minds
that we love this practice
as much as we do even if it's a tiny bed
it's sin it's inspiring to them our showing up is inspiring to this
friend this spiritual friend this kalianamita
spiritual friend seeing their appreciation for us
letting ourselves be the recipient of their appreciation their meta their friendliness their goodwill
as a spiritual friend may i be safe from inner and outer harm
joining our good wishes to theirs for
ourselves
as a spiritual friend may i be happy
joyful as their spiritual friend may i
be healthy and strong
as their spiritual friend may i have
ease meeting the moment of my life with as much ease as possible
knowing that you are spiritual friend to others you support others
by showing up may i may i be well
may i know my own goodness may i recognize my own goodness
may i be well
may i wake up to my own goodness
now bringing to mind your friend again your spiritual friend you've brought in
and yourself the two of you
supporting each other all the ways that you inspire each other have inspired
each other may both of us be well
both of us wake up to our inner goodness
letting it shine brightly
supporting each other ourselves in the world may both of us be well
feeling feeling your connections with his friend
receiving the giving the goodness of the flow the engagement
now if you wish opening up and inviting other spiritual friends
other kaliana mitta who've inspired you
with their practice it could also be teachers in this
class this path friends teachers are spiritual friends it's not
a guru model
friends spiritual friends teachers guides inviting them all
fighting your sangha
your mind's eye to your heart
and wishing each individual well thanking them in your heart
for inspiring you supporting you
knowing that you support others with your practice you inspire others
sharing mental
friendliness good wealth
from all
friends
allow your heart if you wish to celebrate the goodness of friendship
the gift of friendship spiritual friendship
you
for the last moment of this practice
allowing the meta the goodwill friendliness to be spread far and wide
to all friends to all friends
all friends who support you or challenge you even
spread it to all beings everywhere
all of us beings we are just walking each other home
may all beings know their own goodness wake up to their true
nature may all beings be free
including ourselves
thank you all thank you sangha kalyan amita spiritual friends for your
practice for showing up so we have time for reflections
especially if you haven't shared in a while if you have shared especially verbally
pull back if you haven't in a while pull forward please
and you can type in chat your reflections if you type them just to me i won't say your name and if you type
them to the whole sangha i'll read your name also so
what did you discover in this practice
what was it like for you what showed up
and again your insights your questions your discoveries are a gift to the sangha
or his support are inspiring for other practitioners fred please
hi you know i could feel why that was important i could feel the
the uh you know the emotional energy i could feel a lot kind of churning there
and thinking about about friends but i don't really understand it could you explain more why this is so
important um why is
spiritual friendship is important ah yeah yeah um
well it's it's really um i would say
it's something it's actually i can answer that let me let me ask you
something and then i'll answer um when you were saying that you felt emotionally emotionally churning
um you felt it emotionally would you say a little more about that please fred
i could very readily feel the connection and the good feeling for uh for the person and then
the people that i began to to picture i could feel the the connection between
us um and i suppose you know i i might feel
the same thing with friends of you know long duration and
deep experience i see that i'm beginning to answer my question here that uh there's it seems that there's a
kind of um leap over years and leap over
time spent together in the context of spiritual friendship so that suddenly while we
i might think of a spiritual friend who i haven't spent anywhere near as much time with or not even physical proximity with older
friends still there's a lot of a lot of good feeling and emotional
energy there beautiful did i answer my question i think you did you you answered it any
better than what i was gonna say i'm just gonna let that go fred and honor what you said it's beautiful thank you
okay thank you lovely and parents please
oh good thank you um i found this to be like the most
important kind of practice i've done in a while um i felt myself in a sense connected
with the many people over the years of practice and there was this kind of responsibility or
kind of as you use the word last week nobility that i felt and being engaged with them
and and it helped me dive more deeply into my um into my
practice of being sensing and hearing since hearing being present in a sense for them as
well as with them this is great very good nikki thank you
thank you terence um i'm inspired by your words
and and this nobility it's it's it's beautiful and as i was leading
it too there's a sense of oh yes my practice my i connect with it more it's
it's it serves others it's not just about me it's serving others there's that beauty of nobility
that you are beautifully naming terence yes thank you lovely thank you
kenneth please
yeah hi nikki uh that was uh really really sweet for me
my heart started to glow in the middle of that it was really really sweet and i i just wanted
to mention one other thing that came from this sangha is that um i woke up the other day kind of
contracted and i held it with tenderness because somebody had talked about holding
it with tenderness and my higher self told me what to do i said you need to do
this and i was like thank you so that came from this song so i thank you that is so
lovely my heart glows hearing your heart glowing with this practice
can kenneth's and and just the the the sharings of the song go and somebody
shares from their practice so hold it with tenders oh yes that oh wow it transforms beautiful i'm getting
chills this is so gorgeous thanks for sharing that
and jerry says i love your comment of your spiritual friends walking you home
i felt enveloped by this sangha it felt i felt it felt safe and
nurturing for me and all beautiful thank you and kia says i
am not ready to share my full reflection yet but want to echo a lot of what people are saying
i felt less alone and more tender for the past hour not that i typically feel lonely this is
my first time in this group thank you for a wonderful first meditation welcome welcome deeply deeply welcome
so happy you're joining us yeah sense of connection with one another
beautiful so dear ones
especially given that tonight's practice is about spiritual friendship let us
turn in small groups in small groups of size three or four to practice for a few
minutes with each other just holding each other with tenderness just as kenneth was talking
you know holding our hearts tenderly holding ourselves tenderly holding each other tenderly these beautiful beings
who just like us suffer we all have suffering every single one of us
we have challenges and all of us every single one of us has gifts and beauty and insights so let's turn to practice
for six seven minutes in small groups listening to each other hearing each
other ourselves and as always we start with 15 seconds of silent
meta for ourselves and each other and then um share as little or as much as you
wish okay so the rooms are created and now they
are open enjoy
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed and we have a few
minutes for reflections what might have come up from the group conversations from spiritual
friendship conversations don't be shy
you can raise your hand if you wish or type in chat
bill please hello um well i i think i stumbled over
something here when you were talking i seem to do that a lot um but you talked about mentioned about
you know the spiritual friends being all the path and i'm i started obsessed with the fact that
the vast majority of my friends have nothing to do with the dharma at all and i just i just kind of went down
the wrong lane i think and i started obsessed about that and it i i'm not quite sure what to make of the
statement in that context that spiritual friends are all the path does that mean a big part of my path is
i'm a lot of my time i'm just not on the path or i don't know where i'm going with this so
there you go yeah yeah yeah yeah no problem yeah so
so um maybe one one way to think about this
um is that you know and and maybe i'll come back to what i
was saying earlier uh when when fred asked the question and and then beautifully answered his
question so i didn't say anything but you know in general you know even if we take the buddhist context completely aside
and practice and mindfulness and cultivation if we just forget about all this for a moment and just think about psychology and
social psychology and and just what we know about anthropology and social psychology
well the friends you spend time with people that you spend time with they
impact you and you impact them i mean duh of course right that's we know this as human beings
that's why parents you care so much about what kind of people their kids spend time with and and you
know there's plenty of research too and all that but um so so that's what i would say and
and maybe uh instead of going down the rabbit hole bill what i would consider is that
you know the friends that you spend time with do they inspire you do they support you and and
wanting to cultivate you know they may not know anything about mindfulness it doesn't matter but do they inspire you
to be the best person you want to be good that's all thank you yeah you're
welcome so yeah you don't have to be strict about it so much but yeah spiritual friendship could could be more
general more be more people who inspired and bring the best out of you yeah
thank you thank you for that yeah yeah and jerry says discovered mudita
tonight in the small group because of the sangha occurring over covet 19 yep yes it's
i have so much gratitude for this sangha uh over covet 19 it's and
um it's been a gift to me and and from what i hear from many
people it's been a gift to many folks so yeah and it is seven o'clock abram i see your
hand raised so if it's quick if it's very quick go ahead thanks i i just really liked
your comment about um just as i have been sending warmth loving kindness compassion
tenderness to my dear friends just to stop and think that they said that to me
uh you you you somehow expressed that in terms of uh they also have love and
kindness for me so i just really appreciated that thank you so much for reading that up
yeah so nice to grock that yeah yeah thank you
sweet sweet so dear ones the time has come for us to
bring our practice in sangha this edition of happy hour to an end
thank you for showing up and cultivating your heart and minds for your own sake and the sake of all those whose lives
you touch may all beings be happy may all beings be free
and