greetings sangha greetings from mountain view california
unseated oloneyland where i am to all of you all over the world as i see
from the beautiful hellos and good mornings good afternoons good evenings coming in
so [Music] turn down this ipad here we go okay so
um so this week we are exploring together
the inner dimensions and the outer dimensions of the practice of generosity
as a support for liberation and also as a support for
as a basis for compassion so generosity both as a basis for
compassion and liberation necessary the building blocks of both
and as we've been building these practices and exploring different
aspects today what we'll explore in the guided meditation
[Music] is the aspect of bringing mindfulness mindfulness to this
letting go to this part of component of generosity which is the release the letting go
and i'll say more about the different aspects and the dharma in terms of
bringing mindfulness and different ways of cultivation so
so without further ado let us begin let us begin our practice
together so
landing [Music] landing in our chair landing in our cushion in our bodies
creating ourselves greeting ourselves greeting this body in this moment
noticing what it needs how can we be generous to ourselves in this moment
ah does generosity mean a shift in posture
maybe getting a shawl or a blanket
or landing with a deep breath in our sit bones
appreciating [Music] the sensations the feelings of
connection [Music] of her feet on the earth noticing
yes feet legs sit bones
connecting [Music] to the floor to the cushion
standings for the earth yes
appreciating [Music] the connection the holding the support
same way that a newborn is cradled and held held supported
in the arms of a parent
we are held
held by the earth
appreciating the connection letting go letting go trusting [Music]
trusting that we are held gravity is not going to change its mind
letting go of the weight
of the body the limbs the muscles
trusting trusting the earth with its gravity holding connecting
ah
the delight of this heaviness
which also has an aspect of lightness
uplift
felt in our aspiration in our breath
our bodies supported connected grounded into the earth
and our breath filling [Music]
lightening every nook and cranny
now this body breathing in life
breathing in aliveness waking us up making each cell up
as if we were as if this body
were a beach ball
getting inflated more full or a pop-up doll
with each inhale exhale breathing life
to all the areas that are contracted crinkly deflated
feeling this body come alive fill out from the inside
mindfully with loving kindness with loving awareness
with the breath
allowing it to happen on its own
there's no doing for you to do just notice that it's happening on its own
already with each breath
receiving each breath
with a little appreciation
lowering our center of gravity so we're not in our heads but the center of gravity of awareness
is low low in our lower abdomen our sit bones
not in the control tower of the head
as if your mind was in your belly
receiving the sensations the breath
and the belly
allowing mindfulness awareness awareness to be
spacious
loving awareness lovingly aware
let it be spacious as if we are sitting
as if we're sitting in this container this supportive container
spacious wide
gracious
the body can relax
the mind and heart can relax
into the spaciousness of awareness
whatever arises and passes
in this sphere of loving awareness
it's known it gets known effortlessly
non-judgmentally
landing relaxing in this space of loving awareness with the body
if and when [Music] it is noticed
that there is an entanglement
that has arisen which is which is not helpful in this moment
knowing the entanglement non-judgmentally oh this this is what the mind is
resting on now
celebrating the moment of awareness
then as the mind inclines opens its
fist its hand to let go to relinquish
this movement of the mind letting go
bringing mindfulness even more awareness to what is present
the intention around it
how it is done the attitude of the mind
yesterday i invited you to notice if there was joy in letting go
notice if that's present or any other attitude
or intention in the mind
the moment surrounding this relinquishing letting go
and returning to rest in the spacious awareness
of all things including the breath and sensations coming and
going
is there anything any attitude that blocks sense of generosity to ourselves
generosity to the mind and heart
not to go looking for it
but if it presents itself to see see clearly
infusing this loving awareness
as if dropping a little drop of color
to your awareness the drop of color being the question
the curiosity what blocks generosity
to myself the heart and mind
generosity in the form of love compassion
or wisdom in the way of letting go relinquishing
if any there may not be anything revealing itself
relishing the peace and joy of this moment
can there be a sense of trust in the abundance in this heart and mind
and as we approach the end of the sitting together
inviting loving awareness
to hold to be aware of what's good
of the goodness that we have showed up
we've practiced as well as we were able to
not attaching to the outcome we did our best
if it could have been any different it would have been
given all the causes and conditions we have done our best
to trust and not judge it's for it to be
lesser of lesser value to appreciate the goodness
the beauty the merit generated
from our wholesome intention [Music] ah and from this sense of appreciation
gratitude
feeling the abundance of our hearts for this opportunity with this opportunity
to practice and share the goodness
freely generously
with all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere including
ourselves may we benefit
in ways unfathomable from the goodness
of our intentions and actions may all beings be free
may all beings be happy
thank you for your practice greetings dear sangha
so for today the fourth day of our exploration with
this beautiful and
important theme of practice generosity
not as a moralistic vow shall be generous but as a way as a
movement of the heart as a as a beautiful lovely gracious movement
of the heart towards ourselves and towards others
so so as i invited us to
at some point to bring interest loving interest
curiosity gentle curiosity to to the intention
and if there is a lack of generosity at any point in our practice
i wanted to today talk about um
some things that might block or not not support generosity or attitudes
or or our own judgments about it just to to bring awareness bring loving awareness
it's not a moralistic practice it's just to know it's a practice like anything else
the same way that with mindfulness we cultivate
awareness and we don't judge ourselves ouch bad you were bad you are not mindful it's not about that it's just oh
yeah mindfulness is lacking right now okay how can i support it
maybe i'll sit upright a little more maybe i breathe a little more deeply if i'm sleepy oh yeah that's how i can support
it so um it's a way of understanding understanding the system and how can we
support ourselves on the path to liberation how
how can we support ourselves for our hearts to be free it's just about that
and the moralistic should or judgment or judgment does not support
our hearts and freedom it it contracts it
so
one quote i wanted to share from the buddha which i find so inspiring
it's from itty wutaka 18 and
the buddha says practitioners if people knew as i know
the fruits of sharing gifts they would not enjoy their use without sharing them
nor would the tame taint of stinginess obsess the heart
even if it were their last bite their last morsel of food they
would not enjoy its use without sharing it if there was someone else to share it
with so he's pointing to if people knew as i
know if people knew as i know
then they would not then they would not even if it was their last morsel of food
they would not enjoy its use without sharing it they would enjoy
sharing it even more they would enjoy them more so even more if they shared it so and trusting the buddhist wisdom
and and also looking into our own experience um [Music]
that that generosity it frees our own heart it
frees our own heart it brings us joy it's it's a deep goodness that's really
the buddha here is inviting us if people knew as i know if people knew as i know
so come come see for yourself hey pasago come see for yourself come experience
for yourself so not just trusting the words of the buddha but come see for yourself explore it for yourself
and um similarly when they asked gandhi why do
you give so much why do you serve all these people
gandhi answered answered i don't give to anyone i do it all for myself
that's interesting right i do it all for myself which really points to again
similarly it points to these two quotes point to that the aim and the
fruit of generosity donna as a practice is twofold
it's we give to help and free others but we're
giving to help and free ourselves that's the beautiful dimension the twofold
dimension of ghana we're doing it to free ourselves so with this spirit with this setup then
now let's bring our awareness to to this process to the internal process
is there joy in giving as i was inviting you to to tune into that because there
can be joy there is joy in in generosity
is there and uh and also to to notice if what happens in the body what happens in
the mind is there sometimes perhaps a sense of a lack that
there isn't enough um that the heart feels contracted
sometimes maybe you know in thinking about giving thinking about relinquishing
is there a sense of ease and openness and loving kindness and compassion in
the heart mind and body sometimes there might be sometimes maybe there's a feeling of
depletion weakness fear anger confusion the body and mind so being curious about
this all not be ashamed of it um just be a scientist of your own mind
what is going on what what is happening uh with with uh
generosity um what's happening in my mind what's happening in my body
um are there are there stories do i have stories ideals some beliefs as to how it
should be how giving should be how it's supposed to be how it's not supposed to
be seeing both those stories as well as um
if there are seeing our own intentions and again here be generous with yourself when you're
seeing your own intentions because our intentions can be mixed and
it's okay it's perfectly okay just see just see there could be this beautiful
intention of oh yes i want i want you to be happy i'm i would like to give this
to you may you be well in some cases say we're giving a gift we're giving a big gift like oh i want
you to like me also or i want you to see me as generous or i want you to
to give me a bigger gift it's okay see those it's all right we're we're mixed
bags as human beings get to see get to see don't be ashamed
to see what comes up but get to know with mindfulness with loving
um awareness get to know get to know yourself
and trust and trust that generosity is a purifying practice over time
as you get to see the intentions as you get to see what is
arising in the heart and mind it gets purified it's a practice like anything else it's we're not supposed to be born
perfectly generous people it's it's it's it's a practice
and and a couple of practices to support
are this cultivation one is as i mentioned yesterday gratitude
supports gratitude supports generosity the more grateful we are the more we feel the
abundance of our life of our heart the more our hearts want to release let
go of everything let go of of grudges let's go of lack of generosity of spirit and
be more generous so cultivating gratitude cultivates generosity
also what cultivates generosity again as a way of letting go as a way of
freeing our hearts is is the practice it's said that
the more we practice generosity the more generous we become and the more generous we become the more we practice
generosity so it's a virtual cycle it is said that in the tibetan culture
there is this practice of you hold um you give a potato from one hand to the
other you give yourself a potato you know one hand gives something to the other ears you know you give something
so that you practice you know one hand practices letting go to the other and then
apparently as i've heard this practice then you practice with more and more precious objects you know one hand gives
it to the other so you get the sense of yes this is what to let go of this is what what it's like to let go and and
really feeling so similarly cultivating
um this this this relinquishment and tuning into the joy tuning into the ah
lightness that it brings and and tomorrow i'll talk more about given
that it's our last day and it's it's the culmination of
four days of practice i'd like to talk more tomorrow about the
practice of generosity as a liberative practice we talked more about we talked about it before but i
want to talk more about generosity and generosity of spirit etc tomorrow
one last thing i want to bring in today before we close
is another quote from the buddha from an 5 148
which is how a person of integrity gives a gift
and buddhist says there are these five are
a person of integrity's gift which five a
person of integrity gives a gift with a sense of conviction
so number one sense of conviction number two a person of integrity gives a
gift attentively person of integrity gives a gift in
season a person of integrity gifts gives a gift
with an empathetic heart with a loving heart
number five a person of integrity gives a gift without adversely affecting himself themselves or others
so the last one the person of integrity gives the gift without adversely affecting themselves or others and the
last one is important also um not giving too little not giving too
much so the act of giving of course mindfully it needs to be supportive of others
supportive of ourselves so generosity is goes both direction
it's not just about completely giving everything and feeling
as i mentioned feeling there's weakness depletion so it needs to really work both ways so the five again in case you
missed it sense of conviction
attentively giving the gift attentively giving a gift that is in season yet the
person needs it it's not something you're trying to just get rid of it's it's appropriate it's a gift that's
appropriate giving the gift with a loving empathetic
gender empathetic loving heart heart with meta and finally
giving a gift without adversely affecting oneself and others
so thank you all for the gift of your attention and your practice
i look forward to being with you tomorrow and concluding this this lovely series together which
i've just so appreciated generosity is such a lovely practice
liberative practice more tomorrow thank you all take good care of yourselves