good morning welcome once again
good to see you those who i see and good to see all the good morning welcomes on the
chat it's really been lovely being here with you connecting with this
sangha thank you so we're continuing today
moving in the elements now to the element of space and yesterday i sort of hinted at this
way that we're moving uh further and further into
the ineffable the unseen the
um [Music] more towards emptiness
and as i'll say a little bit more about later a little bit more into
mind into the nature of mind so we'll do a practice
starting to our practice this morning will be a meditation about space
and i want to read you a quote from the suit i've referred to a number of
times 62 and this is again the instruction that the buddha is giving his son rahula
and this is what he says rahula develop meditation that is like space
for when you develop meditation that is like space arisen agreeable and disagreeable
contacts contacts will not invade your mind and remain
just as space is not established anywhere so too rahula develop
meditation that is like space for when you develop meditation that is like space
arisen agreeable and disagreeable context will contacts will not invade
your mind and remain there's a phrase in there i want to
bring your attention to which is he says
just as space is not established anywhere so too rahula develop meditation that is
like space this idea that
your your meditation just as space is not established anywhere and that you could
have a meditation that is not established anywhere
and that is an interesting idea and it's also a little unnerving for our systems
that we are we're used to settling on objects
we're used to landing somewhere recognizing it having our perception
name what it is and then having a opinion about it or at least a vedna a
feeling tone a pleasant or unpleasant so when we land on space there's this
there can be this uneasiness and an immense neutrality and
i'll speak more later about how useful this neutrality can be and how useful it
is to not be established anywhere but as we move into this meditation i want to
name that you may at times in the meditation sort of be a little like what am i
paying attention to and that's natural because we're shifting
instead of paying attention to objects we're paying attention to the space and that can be a little different
so find your comfortable meditation posture
and we'll begin as we always do sensing our contact with the ground
letting your self feel the ground through the seat
through your legs or feet
let your attention be aware not only of the pressure and
the contact but also of the ground beneath you of the place where you're sitting
let yourself land land here right now
let yourself grow roots
notice the parts of your body that have some tension and see if you can bring some ease or relaxation
particularly in the shoulders around the eyes
let the belly soften
and let your attention come to the breath and just feel the flow of breath
and see if you can find a place a way of connecting with your breath
that has some sense of ease in it it might be as we
played with yesterday sensing the whole body as you breathe
it might be finding letting your attention ride with the breath as it flows in
and then as it releases flowing out
and as you feel yourself established in this place
sensing the body feeling the movement of breath
no need to be resistant or push away thoughts as they arise simply allowing them to float with
the breath being breathed in and breathed out
and begin to pay more attention on the exhale
follow the exhale
and as you notice the exhale let your attention follow it as it
leaves through your mouth or nose or both follow the exhale
and ride the breath right out to beyond
your lips and nose right into the space there
you begin to have a sense of your attention in this space just beyond
your body
and when you inhale you might notice that the attention comes back in
and then on the exhale allow it to flow out again into that space
and with each exhale perhaps allowing your sense of that space to expand
getting a little bit larger
and after a few breaths you might find that you can just allow your attention to rest in the space
even as you inhale and then with the exhale allowing your
attention on the space to get a little broader a little bigger
perhaps extending a few feet or more [Music]
beginning even to fill if you're in a room filling the whole room in front of
you if you're outside letting it extend out
maybe as far as first the closest object
begin to explore a little what it's like to have your attention on this open empty space
notice if the mind struggles a little bit to land somewhere
or notice if there's some stillness or peace we're just calm in the space
don't need to make it a particular way just explore it
and allowing this sense of space to expand as far as
it's comfortable it can keep expanding out and out
go through the walls let your attention go out through the
walls beyond the walls if there's walls in front of you to what's beyond that
so that you allow yourself to have the space outside the building
and if you're outside allow your attention to expand further and further
the objects are not a problem they too are made of space so just let your attention flow right
through them [Music] not really attending to them in any
detail just on the space
letting it extend maybe as far as the horizon
you might notice that there's moments when there's just sort of a little confusion
and a or even an unease and just notice that
or there might be moments where you feel almost like you're falling into the space
and then giving up any effort and just come back and feel your body
landed on the ground sensing the breath
then begin to notice just imagine that you could breathe out to your right side
so now imagining the exhale coming out the side of your head instead of out the
nose and and letting that exhale take you into the
space to the right side of you
at first it might be a little awkward and your attention will come back in as you inhale
but then begin to allow your attention to rest and with each exhale
allowing a little more a little more expansion in your attention
again allowing yourself to sense the whole right side of where you're sitting
perhaps in the room or out into the space if you're outside and then going through
the walls if you have walls and beyond
beginning to feel the vastness
this empty open vastness you might even if you can sense your
attention going out into the sky
the limitless sky
and then again dropping all effort noticing if there's any tension that's
accumulated in your body and letting that soften
feel yourself anchored here feel the flow of breath
and then continue by breathing out behind you
so allowing the exhale to take your attention back behind you
and this is sometimes a little more challenging because we're not as aware of the space behind us
but i encourage you to sense it as you do this you'll tend to rest further back
into your back body perhaps softening some
see if you can sense the space not just behind your head but behind your back
and letting this sense grow out further
perhaps with the exhale or perhaps it just naturally your curiosity
leading you outward behind you
let your attention go out behind you through the room through the walls
out into the vaster space as far as is comfortable perhaps it'll be out into
the distant sky perhaps just a little beyond what you know
is there
and then again relaxing feeling your body
noticing if there's any tension [Music] you don't need to work hard at this
and then letting your breath now go out to the left side
becoming aware of the space to your left
close in first and then in your own time in your own
way expanding out
and then letting that go feeling the body
landed here
and then very gently inviting your attention
to breathe out in all directions
letting your attention get broad and open you might notice that there's a way it
moves but it feels like it moves around and then you might find moments where it
just rests in the open space not landing on anything in particular
not even landing on any particular point in space
let yourself sense the sky above you through the roof
through the walls the trees
sense the space behind you
let yourself rest into all this open space
might feel like resting in a soft cloud
might be a little uncomfortable or unfamiliar and that's okay
it only needs to be as big and as broad as you choose
notice in this open space
that the objects don't interrupt it that the space even
might seem it goes right through the objects the objects can arise
we're having a sense of them but they don't disturb the space the space continues
you might notice as you rest in this space
perhaps this space continues right through your own body
that this open emptiness also includes right here
and in this open empty space there are objects sounds might arise
sensations in the body will happen thoughts float through
sensations of the heart and the emotions
let them all come and go nothing needs to be resisted or pushed
away but allow yourself to stay resting
in the space with this open relaxed attitude of
allowing allowing everything to come and to go
and you simply rest in this big open space
if your attention contracts and comes back
that's okay just begin again opening back up to the space
and allowing yourself to rest
[Music]
so the first thing that i'd like to name about space
and i won't go into this is in as much detail but that space is often used and avail
for very good reasons as the portal to the nature of the mind
to connecting with and understanding this mind itself
so i'll read you one quote from longchampa that is pointing
to this he says the mind is like the sky beyond assertion and negation
and just as in the sky the clouds take shape and then dissolve with no change to the sky
which stays forever pure the nature of the mind is likewise
always pure it is primordially enlightened uncreated
naturally present ultimate reality long champa is a
12th century teacher in tibet and he traveled in tibet and
bhutan and did some of the most detailed writing and instruction around the
nature of mind
so this quality of space that the
this quality of space that allows room for everything and this
is part of what the buddha was pointing to in the specific things of agreeable and disagreeable can come and go
and there's space doesn't have a preference it doesn't it as far as we can tell certainly
space doesn't you know something nice something not nice
something difficult something that's wholesome unwholesome
pretty ugly whatever it all comes in
into the space and then when it leaves the space is still there
resting unaffected
it's never harmed by the space
and there's an invitation here what is it like to have a meditation a mind like
space where things can come in and be known [Music]
and then leave again and that natural reactivity that we get
into when we're focused on the objects giving our mind a little break from that an
alternative it's not like we're never going to be aware of objects but it's
giving ourselves an alternative a way of being with things where we open up
sometimes it can be as simple as looking at something you see someone and they're giving and you're in a really difficult
situation and you look at them and then you can just broaden and look at the space around them
and all of a sudden there can be a calm a kind of like oh
this is just an arising in space oh perhaps it's a disagreeable one
but the space is relaxed and open and we can feel that in us
this sense of space also hopefully in the meditation you touched into it there
can be some aspect of stillness or peacefulness
this we can access this like in the meditation we did but there's a very important way we can
access this regularly in our meditation in our lives which is watching when things fade so
we're paying attention to some object it might be an object of our mind something we're
thinking about or it might be the breath breath is a good example then or
something that's happening in our emotions or with another person and if we stay with it
if we don't move our attention and get distracted onto the next object if we
stay with that one there will come a time when that object
of our mind or the obsession with it or the clinging to it is really what i'm
speaking to the clinging to it softens
and in that fading away there's a gap there's a space when i
said you could feel this in the breath we're very familiar with this at the end of the exhale there's a little gap
at the end of an emotion there's a space when a thought fades away there's an
opening and all of those are pointing into this aspect of space
into the freedom and ease that's available
between the objects there's lots and lots of space time
opening between objects but we're so trained to look
at the things that we don't pay attention to the space
and so this element of space is an invitation
to notice all the places where there's gaps
and an invitation to notice that there's ease and freedom even freedom from
clinging in that space
and perhaps as i'm talking you can sense that this is
uh very accessible if we turn our attention to it
access to equanimity equanimity has this
quality to it where it is allowing everything to come and go it's not that
we're indifferent or aloof or sep or not you know not paying attention
cut off from it dissociated it's the opposite everything can come and go
but we don't grab hold of it and so this quality of paying attention
to the space can give us access in a very visceral way
to the quality of equanimity
i think in this day and age when we live not that other
ones were different but just naming that we have so much happening
and the ways that things are not as we would wish
and if we can open up and see that there's a much bigger
container it's like going from here tight small to much bigger open and then whatever
arises is a rising in that whether it's the challenges of climate change of loss
in our own lives of the social injustices that we see
it doesn't it's very important it doesn't mean we ignore it and we don't respond
but we're giving ourselves some calm some stability
from which then to be able to respond if we're caught in clinging
we cannot respond with wisdom we need to
open up and give everything the room to come and go without being reactive
i know for myself i expand this not only into space but when we get a very expansive sense of space we can also
start to have an expansive sense of time and as we crunch down you know with
things that are happening this expanded sense of time and seeing long distance i
mean sometimes for me it really helps to see the rocks and see the expanse
geologically and that is an access
for equanimity not for non-responsiveness but for equanimity where this as the
buddha said what's agreeable and disagreeable context will not invade
your mind we let things in by clinging to them we're letting them invade our mind
and so finding ways to not be invaded a simple practice you can engage in
is just look around at the spaces between things you can do it right now
right as i'm talking look around and see what it's like to look at the space
you may have done this practice before not on not uncommon one
but it's interesting to try to remember it and notice as you look at the space
or another way is even with your eyes open looking around see if you can sense the space behind
you and notice what happens is you sense the space behind you
in this case you just let your eyes go soft and have peripheral sort of a sense of
peripheral vision and then sense the space behind you and notice what happens if there's a kind of
settling in the mind so for each of us we can find our own doorway what allows
us into this place of non-clinging
i'll end today with a little a short poem
i am beyond limits i contain all things
yet you will not find me unless you look between the rows and its
petals i am the silence between each moment
the space the leaf leaves behind as it falls to the ground
when the crickets chirp incessantly and the sky is jammed with stars
between the soft brushes of warm breezes you will find me everywhere
stretching out my arms i cannot be found because i never hide
yet i beg of you to look for me for it is when our eyes meet
that every dewdrop is filled with love
so thank you all so much for being here and spending this week and i
hope you take your practice outside and play with the elements
and expand that aspect of your practice if you have found this useful
and i'd like to dedicate the merit of our practice this week may it be of
benefit to each of us and to all we come into contact and to all beings
everywhere to whom we are so intimately and inseparably connected
may all beings be free thank you