so good day everyone and welcome to our meditation session
and um and so here to sit
and include your body as part of the meditation it's helpful to have the body be
at the center of your meditation partly because
centered in the body ground in the body gives us much more capacity
for patience for openness for an ability to be present for what is
here and uh cultivating cultivating developing our
capacity to be present for all the different things that can come in our lives
is one of the tasks of meditation because they're sooner or later they'll be very challenging things that we all
have to experience and have to have prepared ourselves with developing our capacity for
to be present to be open to be patient
is so important so gently
taking a comfortable but alert meditation posture
giving some care to adjusting your posture whatever way that's appropriate for how you are meditating
so your body is a little more active not completely passive so not to be a
just completely so even if you're lying down
to have your forearms pointing to the ceiling maybe your elbows resting on
the ground or the surface and the arms pointing to the ceiling
gives a little bit more activation
and if it's comfortable closing the eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
taking your time with the inhale as long as it's comfortable to breathe
in taking your time to breathe in
feeling maybe the comfort or the pleasure of that
taking your time to exhale
as long as it's comfortable to exhale
perhaps enjoying the extended exhale
and with the extended exhale to relax in the shoulders
soften
soften the belly
and relax the whole body down into your
wherever your body is in contact with some surface
chair the floor
and release yourself to receive the support of that surface
so that there's a feeling of maybe being grounded or centered rooted here
letting your breathing return to normal
and on the exhale perhaps you can soften your face
around the eyes
the cheeks and the jaws
and also to relax the area of your brain
or wherever there might be some contraction or energy
associated with thinking wanting resisting
relaxing
and then as you sit here now spending these few minutes settling in
can you recognize inside of you in your body your mind your heart
the capacity to be patient with what is
a patience that maybe is an openness
or a supportive
tolerance for what is uncomfortable
a recognition of the challenges it might be here while you're meditating
that in the very recognition there's a patience
a kind of acceptance openness
in that clear recognition of what is uncomfortable or
difficult
and what is often underappreciated is that what's valuable is not what is
happening but rather the how we're aware of it
patiently openly
non-reactively
being aware with clarity clear recognition now this is what's
happening and developing the capacity
to be present for what is especially when things
are uncomfortable
and coming to appreciate not that you can be with the uncomfortable
but appreciating how you can be with what's uncomfortable
and one support for this grounding in the body for ability to be patient and open
is the constancy of our attention to the breathing
the rhythm of breathing in and out becomes the beat
that keeps us steady and going and
maybe uninterruptable
and our attention here in the present
you
if you are more settled than you were at the beginning of the meditation
recognize that maybe recognizing it as
a capacity to be more patient more open
to what's happening and if you're not more settled
recognize that and that is the place to be patient
open with how things are
and as we come to the end of this sitting
to perhaps appreciate that when we can be comfortable
or when we can be patient with discomfort
then that patient cannot patience can be used offered as a gift
to others that we can stay calm or non-reactive
when the situations are difficult maybe when people have difficulties that
are uncomfortable for us our patience allows us to stay present
attentive non-reactive
so that our generosity our kindness our care
has space and room to operate
may it be that our development our cultivation
of greater capacities in patience attention kindness
can grow through our meditation practice in such a way that we can
it can be a gift to the world we can dedicate it to the world
so that we can live and act and speak in ways
that benefits others that supports others to
feel more at ease or more present in this difficult life
may it be that our meditation practice helps us to improve the world for all
beings may may we be a force of good
so that all beings may be happy all beings
may be safe so that all beings
may experience peace so that all beings may be free
may all beings be free from oppression
and attachments
may all beings be happy
[Music]
[Music] thank you
so warm greetings on this sunday
and i would like to talk a little bit about patients or use that
as a as a topic to talk about something which might even be more important
and that is that how buddhist practice one of its functions
is to develop our capacities to develop to cultivate and develop our
abilities to that native natural abilities we have
so that we have greater capacity for being present for discomfort and
challenges and greater capacity
to be at peace when things around us are difficult not at peace
so patience is part of this task we have a capacity for patients and we can develop it the word for the
pali word for patients is kanti k-h-a-n-t-i
and it's a rich word has many connotations that maybe are greater than the english word patience
it sometimes has the association with i i mean i don't know for me an
association with an openness a willingness to be present for experience
a openness to be present for whatever is happening including what's difficult
it also has the connotations of some kind of healthy deep acceptance
of what is true even if what is true is difficult or challenging to some of our cherished
attachments that we have that that there's a a patience a
willingness and acceptance that is willing to work with us and stay present and find our way
and that capacity those these capacities of openness willingness
patience are as i said capacities that can be developed and
i have the impression they're going to have very kind of generalized and speaking very generally
that many people don't have enough appreciation for
delayed gratification that or that they want results
from their meditation from the buddhist practice that
they want good results rather than more than developing inner strengths
so sometimes people are searching for some having an experience of peace experience of bliss or happiness or
something and but there's all kinds of ways we can fall into experiences of peace and
happiness that don't necessarily involve developing ourselves cultivating
strengthening capacities that we have and so if we always need to find refuge
in places that are peaceful and quiet and still we might be able to relax and feel nice
and good in those place safe places but it hasn't helped us
to feel at ease or feel a certain kind of inner peace as we go into situations that are
challenging and maybe even sometimes threatening and and so to only kind of retreat into some
kind of inner peace is not so helpful in the big picture
in the bigger picture especially of the buddhist path what we really want to do is develop our capacity to be present for what's
difficult for us present for our suffering and challenges so we can go through them and find our
way with them not so we skirt around them or avoid them or or hide from them
and it goes along with this principle that
we have greater capacity greater ability
to have mastery of our own mind to adjust our minds to change our minds to
to work with our mind then we might have with changing the
world or the circumstance around us and if we think that we always have to change the circumstance around us to
feel good to feel safe then we're always going to be outwardly directed and constantly needing to
change and fix things and it also sets up a can set up a kind
of unfortunate tension between us and the world if we have to
change the world so that we're safe then the world has to accommodate us and
we have to assert ourselves or there has to be a push in the pull and of course that's appropriate at
times but but if that's all we know how to do then we actually make ourselves less
safe because we always need to have the world change for us
but buddhist practice is about developing an inner safety inner strength and inner capacity
to be present and so this capacity
buddhism is a capacity building practice and now that needs some delayed
gratification it takes time to develop ourselves it takes time to develop strengths of all kinds of different
forms it takes time to expand the capabilities we have
so they become strengths so uh what you know and as we do so our
relationship to the world around us shifts and changes so um
so um the um so there's this uh
little story or something from my book the monastery within and um
the abbess once instructed the younger monks and nuns with the following
if a fly lands on the back of an ant it's a big burden for the ant
if a fly lands on the back of an elephant it is a very small thing for the
elephant you will have many challenges in life
it's up to you whether you face them like an ant or an elephant
so this ability to develop ourselves so that there is a kind of something as there's a large
capacity and that largeness of our capacity to be patient to be present to be mindful
to be to let go to be non-reactive to be generous
oh we have a lot of capacities to be equanimous as those become
stronger then we're not pushed around by the the events in the world and what people say
and what people do so much we carry our peace with us and um
and we take our choice we you know that we discover we have as we develop our capacities we discover
we have more choice to choose mastery of our own mind our own hearts
as opposed to giving away the power we have of our own minds to
others based on what they say or what they do and and we're just kind of you know put out to wash out to see with
the slightest little insult or difficulty that happens around us
and so slowly slowly develop capacity and it does involve some letting go
um i'll tell two stories the one about letting go that develops capacity in one
um no it won't i'll give one then i'll then i'm going to read a little poem kind of
the there's a famous kind of zen story that has to do with a scholar
someone who's a erudite scholar buddhism spent decades studying buddhist texts knows
the ins and outs of buddhist philosophy and um and goes to visit a zen master
and um and uh wants to ask questions uh of the
zen master or be in a debate or discussion about these erudite kind of ideas and opinions about what buddhism
is and so the zen master says oh welcome let's have tea first and so the sun
master gets the tea ready and makes the tea and and offers the scholar a cup
and then starts pouring tea into the cup and when the water gets to the top of the rim of the cup
the denmaster keeps pouring the the water in so it starts spilling over the top
and the scholar says stop stop it's already full you could you can it
won't take any more tea and the scholar then the zen master then stops pouring tea and says well in the
same way you're so full full of yourself full of your ideas that there's no space to take
more of teaching more understanding of what i have to teach
so sometimes we have to let go of our ideas our thoughts our projections or
our stories that get in the way of our ability to be patient that
there's very reason maybe we can't be patient because we're caught up in the swirl of these prediction predictive
stories of what will happen or what volume
and then as we develop these capacities like we become an elephant rather than an ant
is uh i wanted to read this wonderful uh i don't know i don't know if it's a poem
it's either by this wonderful zen master that i studied with in japan named shoto harada roshi or it's by his
student hogan baze so i apologize i don't know which one it is
the form i have here associates it with the teacher roshi
in this passing moment karma ripens and all things come to be
i vow to choose what is if there is a cost
i choose to pay if there is a need i choose to give
if there is pain i choose to feel
if there is sorrow i choose to grieve
when burning i choose heat when calm
i choose peace when starving i choose hunger
when happy i choose joy
whom i encounter i choose to meet
when i shoulder i choose to bear
when it is my death i choose to
die where this takes me i choose to go
being with what is i respond to what is
so this certainly seems like a this willingness to
respond to what is and be present and kind of meet what is in such a full way
that's a testament of capacity
testament of cult having cultivated one's strengths and abilities and cultivated enough letting go
so that our strengths are not inhibited or held in check by
our fears our anxieties our angers our desires
so to cultivate and develop these capacities so we can face our
challenges and so you know it's all teaching that
you should spend time with people who don't try to protect you
from the challenges of life but spend time with people who appropriately encourage you to face the challenges
to be present for what's difficult in your life because sooner or later
things will be difficult sooner or later buddhist practice will bring you into
places of letting go and faces places of where where the usual orientation
stability place ways in which we hold on to safety are no longer available
and some people will retract and pull away and won't take the path all the way
but to cultivate our ability to slowly steadily to to
develop strengths that hold us present allow us to be their
presence so there's strengths and one of the strengths
that the meditators develop is the strength of being still
not moving in the middle of whatever is happening in meditation
sometimes there can be a lot of restlessness there can be fear there can be anger
there can be strong desire there can be a lot of agitation and there's something very significant
about not giving into it physically and not getting up and pacing and
running around or not giving up on the meditation or also not collapsing
the idea in meditation is to neither collapse nor retract nor get up and run away but
to sit still in the middle of it ideally sitting in some kind of
posture that does express a little bit of strength and confidence and over time we're developing
a confidence a physical strength a physical malleability to be able to stay present
for all kinds of difficult energies that course through us and that's uh but anything that's
cultivated is cultivated gradually
by repetition and so people who don't have capacity for delayed gratification who are
expecting instant results to have instant enlightenment or instant peace or or to really have a wonderful
experience in meditation sometimes shortchange themselves in this gradual slow cultivation development of
these strengths of confidence of strength of being able to sit still and not move of letting go of the forces
inside of us to react and to run away or to
move or to collapse especially today of collapsing the wonderful thing about meditation
and is that it can be a place where we can feel
the sorrow the challenges the grief the angers we have the difficulties we have
but to do it uprightly with this kind of dignified confident posture
and we might feel like it might be feeling like it's overwhelming like just too much and we should collapse
but while we're meditating the dedication is never collapse unless
it's impossible not to but to really stay there and that develops a capacity to be
present it's not rejecting the difficulty or the strong feelings it's actually building the ability more room
and space inside to hold them and so over time we're developing this
ability to hold more and more difficult things and uh and if you meditate every day
the wonderful thing about that is then sooner or later your whole life goes through that
days which are good days which are difficult days which are joyous days days which are sorrowful
they all get processed they all have their chance to be experienced in this and now in meditation practice
and so we're developing in doing so we're developing this greater and greater capacity to be with a range of
experiences a range of what's happening for us and in doing so we're developing we're cultivating
ourselves we're expanding our capacity and eventually
maybe our capacity becomes so big and so huge that most things that come along
don't agitate us not because we're aloof from them or distant from them
maybe we can feel them even better than we do than we did before because when there's a lot of reactivity
and swirls of stories and ideas and judgments
that's kind of a veil between us and ourselves the us and our story but as we
get quieter and stiller and less reactive and less swept away in the stories and judgments
and and commentary of what's happening then we actually more present to be there
and maybe there's greater and greater capacity to hold it and at some point what we come to
appreciate is or it kind of identify with is the strengths we have the capacities
we have more than what our experience is the experiences that come and go as we
go through our life and that gives a a
ballast to our life that gives stability to our life because then we're not so easily swayed and pushed around and
and uh impacted by the vagaries of life that ups and downs in life and
that are huge like i don't want to dismiss or or diminish how huge the challenges we
have that we can have but to um
but you know we learn to choose we learn to choose an attitude we learn how to give away
our freedom if someone
criticizes us or treats us as somehow being
inferior we participate if we start feeling
inferior because of that then we are participating we are actually choosing it ourselves
and to let other people have that kind of influence on us so that we are choosing to go along with it is really
sad and this ability to master our mind see our minds what it's
doing is one of the great skills of mindfulness meditation or buddhist practice
there is a kind of self-mastery we develop so that we can choose how we are we can
we can develop an ability to be present more widely and then we have hopefully
with our wisdom an ability to respond appropriately
we're not here just to be patient with things and accept things and that's that's the end of the story
i hope we're here also to make the world a better place and to stand up and speak up when necessary and
and um and to change this world for the better and and to speak up against injustice when
we encounter it we don't want to just simply be patient with injustice in the world but we want to have developed patients
so that we are not coming from a reactive place a place that where our capacity for
difficulty has been diminished but rather we want to come from capacity a place where capacity is expanded
so that uh we're have a level of ease or peace or
or non or non clinging
in how we then respond and act in the world i came across recently a quote by viktor
frankl who was he wrote the book the man's search for meaning and he spent
time in the german concentration camps in world war ii and he uh
a lot of his philosophy and and that he that he developed and his
teachings that he developed i developed because he was inspired by the people in the camp and camps who
he said chose not to chose to respond to each thing
with a mastery with not giving up not not abandoning their their
their um autonomy or their ability to choose how they
what they do with their minds their hearts with their speech that somehow they would always choose not to collapse
but rather many of them chose to help and support the other prisoners
so this ability to develop capacities
and i probably have said this enough now but i just want to
really as i finish this talk underscore that
very important part of buddhist practice is cultivation it's called in pali it's called babana
b-h-a-b-a-n-a and it's sometimes the word for practice
in english we might say i have a spiritual practice it's um the word bhavana it's also
sometimes used for the word for meditation but literally what it means is
cultivation or development and so the idea we're cultivating something and developing something
and for some people this is an exhausting idea for some people it's a difficult one because
if it kind of gets entangled with ideas i'm not good enough and i have to prove myself or
i have to now strain and try to get something beyond the present moment
then it can be you know it can be quite a burden
but but cultivating the ability to be patient cultivating the ability to be open
cultivating the ability to be willing to experience what is here
this is a one way one thing to cultivate and develop that goes along with
not trying to change the world not trying to change ourselves
so hopefully don't get so entangled with the cultivation part because what we're cultivating is cultivating capacity to
be present for what is and that is i think subways the ultimate
capacity we're developing in buddhism and and hopefully it'll support us
in times of difficulty in times of joy sometimes the
capacity to hold joy is more difficult than the capacity to hold suffering
and and eat both forms of holding both forms of being
present for without being caught in it leads to wisdom and to freedom
so may you cultivate and develop um
your native capacities so your capacities grow and support you
and may you become like an elephant or
maybe you have another animal big strong animal that you prefer to be your
your model so thank you very much