good morning everyone and uh happy to be here with you all
and i'm going to start with an analogy
and if you uh maybe you go on a cross-country train trip
and um you're going along and after a while you just settle into the
train trip looking out the window and and you pass many things many little sites
and after a while you find yourself on not commenting on what you're seeing or not having preferences for what you see
or not being you know having any reaction to what you see you
see and you know a beautiful tree goes by just a
tree and it goes by kind of quickly it's you see a ugly house it's an ugly house you just
see it and there's so much change so much variety so many different things coming through it's just kind of like it's almost like
you're settling back relaxing just seeing seeing it all without making anything of
it reacting to it preferring one thing over the other you're in the train looking
out the window out the window is just the scenery it just goes by and it's kind of interesting it's kind of
relaxing and kind of nice not to have an opinion about everything and and just to let it
be as it is simple and then halfway through the country you
go through your old old town where you grew up in and right through the middle
of it and suddenly it was oh no they tore down my school or oh look at
that they put in nice park how could they build this big skyscraper like that in the middle of this place and and
suddenly there's all these opinions reactions intensely interested in everything and being foreign against it
and then you finish going through your town and you off into some part of the country
i've never been before and and you realize wow that was exhausting all that reactivity all those judgments
all those preoccupations and then slowly over time you settled back and then it's just the scenery
going by and you clearly see it but it's almost like you enjoy just the sight and just being relaxed and looking
it's not like you're actively enjoying or reacting negatively to anything it's just
just it's a pleasure just to look out the window and see so that one opportunity in meditation is
kind of like being sitting in a train looking out the window and experiencing what happens to
us with that kind of freedom that kind of non-involvement
of just going through the countryside in a train and not succumbing to the kind of
attention we would have if the train went through our town where everything is so important
everything is something to have opinion about or react to or want or not want or something
get involved in it's not not it's wrong it's not that it's wrong
to be reactive or be involved in the sights and sounds
for the purpose of meditation it goes in the wrong direction it doesn't lead to abiding peace or
insight or or developing mindfulness it can actually go in the other
direction it pulls us into the world of stories ideas memories plans for the future
so i i use that
i use that analogy to to represent the kind of recognition
we do in meditation one of the for mindfulness meditation one of the great
keys great practices that really at the heart of
mindfulness is a simple recognition of what is happening in the moment
without searching for it recognizing the obvious and um
and then doing so uh like you're going with trains going through the countryside and just kind of
seeing it you're clearly seeing things but there's no reactivity there's no
assigning me myself and mine to that experience it's just clearly recognized and we allow the
train to keep going to the next recognition and the next recognition and there's something in the
simplicity of recognizing something where there is a kind of a freedom and kind of a piece
it's a little bit hard to find because often right together with recognition is
our preferences our stories our ideas our ways of
liking and not liking or all kinds of things it's seldom that we allow ourselves a chance to recognize something simply
so uh just now there was another train whistle very faint in the distance i don't know if you could hear it
and um and i didn't i did a teeny bit with it and thinking i
would tell you about it but the first passing of it was um
you know in my coming to my years it was like i recognized it as a train whistle
but it was just you know there was nothing for against it i didn't make anything of it
i didn't think about my story that i told you and
um so one of the things we want to try to learn to do in mindfulness meditation
is to some degree start learning the art of recognition
that is radically simple this recognition is represented
by this thing called mental noting some people like to do it some people don't
it's using a one word note label
to help us be with a simple recognition of the experience
so it could be sound when i heard the train with soldier's sound i have an itch itch
i feel the in-breath in out breath out the theme for this week is thinking
and it's possible to note thinking people who normally don't like to use
mental noting as they meditate we'll find that the one place where it's useful to note is with thinking
it's a way of using thought to step away from our involvement with thinking
just a thought rather than thinking and and rather than being swept by the thinking
so the art of recognizing thinking just thinking
and it could be the most horrible thought anybody has ever had but just thinking you're on the train
you're looking out the window there's no need to be involved in good or bad it's the most beautiful thought
anybody's ever have we don't have to appropriate or congratulate ourselves it's just a thought thinking
having a memory just a memory remembering planning
thoughts of planning planning fantasy mr fantasy fantasy
and to and it's very simple if it's um it's kind of refining our freedom from
it and finding the middle way between being for something and against something
it's a tremendous power not to get pulled into what we like or pulled in the way into or away from what
we don't like just to hold steady thinking thinking
planning having a conversation remembering
and in doing so we begin pulling back away from our entanglement
our involvement our participation in the world of thinking and we start becoming free
so let's go on start the meditation so assuming your meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal and continue a little bit to relaxing as
you exhale
settling in
relaxing the mind
the thinking muscle
and if you're thinking a lot see if you can slow down your thinking
think a little bit calmer
and then settling down into your breathing
and if you find yourself involved in thinking
take a simple moment to look thinking right in the eye
and like you're relaxed on the train looking out the window
note thinking where the note note the recognition of
thinking is not the same as thinking more
it's stepping away into a place of non-reactivity
quiet openness receptivity
and if it's obvious to be more specific you can do that remembering planning
fantasizing discussing something
and see if you can find some freedom and calm and peace
in the the most radical simplicity simple
aspect of our capacity to note and recognize
when it feels that you found some freedom from your thinking then begin again with your breathing
until thinking pulls you away again
if you're involved in thinking take a backward step away from it
then clearly recognize that you're thinking
simple radical simple recognition
you might feel for or against your thinking but in their recognition
there can be no for against
just recognition
in the simplicity of recognition it can be almost like a light bulb goes
on in the mind that simply recognizes oh it's the oh
it's thinking it's just thinking
nothing more nothing less nothing true nothing false
nothing right nothing wrong just letting it be simplicity of thinking
in that recognition
when we are not glued to our thinking
there is room then to not be influenced by the thoughts we
have to not be caught in the mind stream of
thoughts and instead to observe them to be free
of them to recognize them and in that simplicity and freedom of
recognition there might be room to think
in beneficial ways
in the end of a meditation it's good to think in ways that have good will
for the world that you'll encounter today
thoughts of generosity and kindness care
well-wishing
and you might say these words to yourself silently as representations or as representatives
of the good will that you can find inside
of yourself may all beings
be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may whatever benefits and merit that comes from this meditation this morning
whatever learnings we've had
may it work for the benefit and welfare of the world
may goodness spread out from this meditation out into the world
may all beings be happy
thank you
so we come to the second talk on mindfulness of thinking where the emphasis is the power of
recognition and the art of mindfulness of thinking is
not to thereby think more it is uh
to be able to recognize more clearly what's happening as we think and there's lots to notice as we're
thinking and but before we talk about what we can
notice in thinking it is uh how we note how we notice
the way in which recognition happens which is as i said earlier is the art of mindfulness meditation kind of one of
the central features of it and that is recognition is the way in
which we know what is happening as it's
happening and not know it in complicated ways like no story why it's here
but just the simplest uh knowledge recognition of what it is
the thing what's happening what's occurring so if i'm breathing to recognizing just the
breathing is happening not to connect it to other breathings and just breathing is happening
if there's a sound just a sound just hearing is happening and
and as we settle in meditation that is to be as simple as possible so we're not caught or reactive to or judging what's
happening just a recognition it's not an easy skill to learn but it's
a powerful one because it helps us be free in the midst of whatever is happening
to stand in the middle of a complicated life and to be able to just take it in and recognize what's happening
but not be swayed by it or or react it reactive to it just there i just see it and clearly then we have
access to our wisdom inside our clarity about what to do in a way that we don't
if we're caught up in the enmeshed in the drama of it all
so learning's ability to how we recognize radical simplicity and meditation is a wonderful laboratory
to discover how simple it is we can i would be in recognizing and in that
simplicity find some peace find some rec some some freedom
from what it is we're recognizing so it could be that we're tremendously depressed
and it's difficult to be that it's uh you know very sticky to be depressed
but as mindfulness gets stronger it's possible to recognize oh this is depression
and somehow for that moment maybe just a moment of recognizing this is depression
there's a little bit of like light bulb goes off or a little bit clarity the fog clears or something just for that little
moment and um and sometimes you have to kind of
say the note a few times until we really are standing in the note and not standing in the depression
depression depression anger anger whatever it might be
and slowly slowly like this crack opens up and we begin identifying more with the
recognition than the state emotional state we might be in oh
there is you know sadness sadness and then and then the sadness is not
diminished the sadness is not disrespected it but it's clearly known so we're not
influenced by it or caught in it it's an amazing capacity
as we do this we also start seeing more clearly what's happening as we're thinking
and that also gives some freedom and so one of the things that's useful in meditation
is to distinguish different kinds of thinking so that both the more clarity
of what we're recognizing but also to recognize what kind of thinking is useful for meditation and what is not
so for example maybe somewhat little bit going from coarsest
most least helpful to maybe going closer and closer to what's most helpful there could just be a dream like
fantasies just that have nothing to do with the present moment there's maybe images that
are involved and and we're caught up in a fantasy world of the future what's going to happen
tomorrow and um and we're kind of entered into the realm
through the imagination of tomorrow or of the fantasy and so those kind of thinking is just
recognized as fantasy and it's recognized that it's really a disconnection from reality
we're not really present for what's immediately here for ourselves
another kind of thinking is discursive thought and that's when the mind is having a
conversation either we're talking to ourselves and or we're having a conversation with
someone else we're repeating a conversation yesterday to try to come up with a better response or something
and um reviewing it and reviewing it and it's kind of like having a discourse
discursive thoughts a discussion in the mind and and that also is not about the
directness of mindfulness it's kind of removed into a kind of abstraction
and and so to recognize oh discursive thinking is happening discursive thinking
then there's a simpler kind of thinking which is a getting closer now to
a thinking that recognizes what's happening it could be still a sentence it could be
i've sat down to meditate it's true we've sitting down to sat down to meditate and it's kind of recognizing
what's happening a certain way i'm feeling hungry i wonder you know
i'm wondering what i should have for lunch and then as we begin thinking about what to have for lunch there might be and
then it becomes a discursive thought or a fantasy but the simple uh you know thought i'm
hungry and and i'm thinking about lunch that's a kind of recognition of what's happening
here and now and then it's simpler and then it might also be
very simple thoughts in the mind in meditation that are directing the meditation
i'm thinking about lunch because i'm hungry maybe i'll bring my attention to my
stomach where i'm hungry and just feel that um and so that's kind of like very simple thought telling you let's go pay
attention there or let's go back to the breathing it was nice to be with the breathing i don't
have to think about lunch let's go back to the breathing and feel the breath
so that kind of thinking it might not necessary to have this clear recognition
that just kind of guiding you pointing you to the present moment you might have the thought i think i
should practice in recognition now and you know you could have infinite regress
if you say well let me recognize that i'm thinking about recognizing i'm thinking and it's kind of crazy making very quickly so it can
be really simple so some very simple instructional kind of thinking and meditation
can be very supportive provided the instructions is very relaxed and ease and not demanding not
not stern or something and then we get even simpler thoughts
which is uh this thing that's closely related to mental notes it's one word um it's rather than i'm hungry what's
for lunch it's hunger or there might be tightness a pang in the belly
hearing uh there might be um a warmth
not i'm sitting in a warm room but just a feeling of warmth because the feel of sitting in your eyes closed sitting in a
warm room is kind of an abstraction but with eyes closed what directly direct experience is just
warmth coldness coolness as meditation gets quieter and quieter
the more relevant it becomes to keep it that simple warmth coolness hearing
in-breath out-breath pressure release of pressure expansion
contraction not it's not a job it's not like work that you're supposed to kind of but it's supposed to be this it's
getting closer and closer to having the mind be very clear clearly aware
of what's happening in the present moment as it's happening
so we're thinking we're just so easily getting pulled into so easy to get trapped by or caught by
this is where mental noting sometimes is very effective um it's a way of kind of stepping out of
them you know if you're like you're stuck in the mud in the quagmire and stuck in the money you
can't get out like quicksand you have to have helpful to have a one
foot on dry land to be able to pull yourself out there the classic example is if two people are in the quicksand
and one person tries to pull the other one out the one pulling sinks deeper so
the first one then the other one tries to pull the ones going deeper and pull it out and that person sinks in
deeper and they just kind of progressively make themselves go deeper but if one of them is up on dry land
then that person can pull the other person out so with um
we're thinking the simple recognition is meant to be standing on dry ground
being in the train and in the train looking out the window not involved with what you see but clearly recognizing it
so clearly recognizing thinking thinking remembering remembering
one of the nice things about these mental notes is that you can pay attention to the
tone of the voice that's making the note and if it's harsh or
afraid or irritated or something you can feel that in the tone
and the idea is a tone to be very relaxed easy untroubled by what we're noticing
that's where we start feeling the freedom of recognition and um
so um so it's maybe not easy to discover but once
we get the hang of look at how a simple moment of recognition is a kind of freedom a kind of peace
it kind of cracks the universe open and you start feeling much more space
and start feeling more more peace and and also kind of delight i just find a
delight sometimes oh um i'm thinking about
i'm thinking about i need to get my oil changed in my car thinking and i just oh that's what i'm
thinking about and i kind of like oh it's kind of like i'm no longer in the thought
and i'm kind of delighted or kind of amazed you know wow this mind thinks isn't that quite
something and um and it's easier to be amazed or to be kind of just
delighted or just free if we step back up on drug land and just
really recognize the thinking thinking now it's possible to get busy with all
this recognition and and then hopefully you recognize now i'm getting busy i'm working too hard at it
and doing too much too much of it the idea is to do just enough to support you
and uh some people will not do the active recognition the noting when they're resting with the breath
being with their breath in and out um but as i've said they they definitely use it when they
find themselves in thinking because it's a with some practice it becomes a really
clear way the easy way even to step away from thoughts not be enmeshed in it we're going to turn the
light of attention onto the fact we're thinking thinking thinking
over time as mindfulness gets stronger it's a interesting skill to learn to be
thinking about things allow yourself to think because you need to think about them
but also to be aware of what it's like to be thinking and to adjust the how
so the thinking is not so fast not so forceful not so addicted not so harsh
whatever it might be and find a supportive and a pleasant enjoyable way to think
thinking can be a wonderful thing and meditation is not supposed to be a critique of thinking at all costs you're
not supposed to think or something or thinking is bad but we are trying to um
restore thinking to a way that is harmonious and peaceful and
supportive for our lives and the path to that in meditation
is to step away from thinking and in meditation it's the one place
where you barely need to think at all certainly don't need the discursive thoughts don't need to think about things that
are not present only thing to think about is what is present here and now
but without analysis and asking why and keeping it very simple just simple
thoughts about let me see if i can hold that in awareness let me meet that with kindness
can i feel that in my body and just and then with as we settle in
oh just pressure warmth tightness simpler and simpler
so i hope that that makes some sense and uh if what i'm saying seems
not quite right for you or understandable at this point just uh kind of file it away
and now there'll come a time i think where you'll recognize where it's valuable to do what i've been talking about today
and so then we'll continue tomorrow with mindfulness of thinking
thank you