good evening good evening welcome welcome
wherever you are and if you're here in person
live or if you're listening to this sometime in the future warm welcome
so we'll start with a little bit of a guided meditation i tend not to do
a lot of guidance
just maybe dropping in some direction
that we might consider
but checking in with the body
feeling connected and grounded embodied
and feeling the pressure against the body from the whatever it is you're sitting
on the chair the cushion
the bench the couch whatever it might be
and then letting the attention rest on the sensations of breathing
feeling the expansion and contraction
in the chest or the abdomen
or maybe feeling the air going in and out of the nose
nothing in particular needs to be happening
just being with the sensations of breathing
and when the mind wanders as it's apt to do
we just very simply gently begin again
with the sensations of breathing
feeling the in-breaths
and feeling the out-breaths
and can we acknowledge feel into
that we're sitting together looking at the chat box
from ohio brazil seattle
chicago here in the bay area
feeling the support of sitting together with others
even if we are all of us in our own space
still we're sharing sharing this experience
there's a kind of delight to be connected with others
while we sit
in some kind of way we're connected to others who are
sitting right now but also
there are others who have made it possible for us to sit now
whether it's in a direct way they're watching the kids or
have agreed to not disturb us for this time
or whatever it might be or perhaps a little bit or indirectly
helped us with the food on the table
the person in the grocery store
the person who helped put the fruits and vegetables
maybe somebody helped you with your car if you drove an oil change
the clothes you wear were purchased most likely somewhere
a person made them package them sold them
drove the truck taking them from place to place
feeling this connection with others
can we feel supported
in this way
knowing that even if we are sitting alone in a room
are ways in which we are connected with others
you
this recognition that we're
not as isolated or independent
as it might seem or sometimes we feel
it's true certainly with this pandemic many of us spend time alone
but it's also true that we're not completely independent
we're connected this just naturally becomes more obvious
as we practice and as we practice we just naturally
don't want to cause harm not only to ourselves but to others
so with this recognition of the countless ways and
which we are connected and support one another may this practice
be a support not only for us but for others
and may all beings be free from suffering
[Music]
good evening good evening welcome welcome
it's a buddhist practice might seem like it's a solitary affair something that we do
by ourselves there's certainly in this who does a lot of emphasis on
becoming awakened and this idea that
we we are the ones that walk the practice walk the path do the practice for ourselves
and certainly we sit in meditation with our eyes closed
but the more we practice the more we realize how we're connected and specifically
we recognize nothing arises for no reason no experience
no object nothing everything arises for a reason
maybe unless we want to talk about the unconditioned which i'm not going to talk about tonight
so with this recognition we could say that the path or this path of practice in some ways
brings us into the web of life more fully recognizing and appreciating feeling
some connections that perhaps before we weren't so sensitive to instead feeling
separated independent isolated perhaps
but rather than cutting us off from one another instead the this practice can kind of
highlight our relationships and
and nourishing an appreciation for the ways in which we're connected
and certainly the buddha is often depicted as a solitary figure
it's pretty rare certainly in this tradition to be see anything except a buddha by himself
sitting and if you read in the suttas some of them use this word seclusion
this idea of uh being separated but one way we can interpret that is
that in ancient india the society was a little bit different than how it is now and kind of the bonds of family and
community were really closely knit and so this sense of individuality or
doing something to quiet the mind maybe needed to be highlighted
in that time and to be sure also buddhism grew i mean that buddhism as a religion as a
tradition as a practice grew out of a sense of community and
connection to be sure right that at the time of the buddha
the community whether they were monastics or lay whether they were women or men
they had to rely on each other in order to hear the teachings
of course they certainly couldn't tune in to you youtube
or listen on audio dharma or something like this right they didn't at the time
of the buddha they weren't written down the only way you would hear about
the dharma is with an interaction with another person is with somebody
speaking it and you were hearing it and perhaps you was talking or maybe you were just
listening or maybe it was chanting and just listening so
individuals had to rely on each other in order to hear the teachings
and of course they were preserved right through all these thousands of years because people
thought they were valuable and even sacred and chose to preserve them
so buddhism these practices of course is really
dependent on some of these relations of people passing things on from one to the next
so one thing that you might notice or might know is that
actually the buddha he placed immense emphasis on the company we keep
and in this there is this passage where the buddha is saying i do not see even a single thing
that so causes wholesome qualities to arise as good friendship
i do not see even a single thing that so causes wholesome qualities to arise is
good friendship so this recognition that especially back then right they were
completely dependent on who they knew or who they had access to or who they
spent their time with there's also this passage
just as the dawn is the precursor for the arising of the sun
so too having a good friend is the precursor for developing the
noble eightfold path many of you know the noble eightfold path is a path to awakening has eight
elements to it hence the name i'm not gonna go into the details of what that is but just this recognition
that having a good friend is the precursor for developing the path to awakening
and maybe i'll say just for me that um
having meeting people that were practitioners of the dharma that had more experience
than i did and had such a big impact to
somehow to be able to talk about the dharma after
the dharma talks or something or to see people who
how they moved through the world and how they handled things to learn from them
and to see how they seem to have much more ease in their life than i was having
and to be inspired by okay so there were the teachings but there's also people who are listening to
these teachings and putting them into practice and i i think it's uh i could honestly
say that my life would have turned out differently if i hadn't had the great good fortune to
meet some drama practitioners and to develop some of these friendships
so this uh and maybe i'll say also that some of you
know that now when we do so many things on zoom and it's also on uh youtube
that and certainly when we um we're live here at imc in person
that there's so many um practices that we do so many courses that we do so many
offerings in which we try to make these opportunities in which people can connect with one another
whether that's the small practice groups for person or when we're on zoom we're
doing breakout rooms if you're sitting
retreats they're often practice discussions or group practice discussions
there's also in the beginning in the ending retreat often some breakout rooms
just this recognition that we learn a lot from each other and also this recognition that
everybody has some wisdom of course they do i heard this quote once now i can't give
an attribution because i don't remember but this idea that nobody is smart enough to be
completely wrong like you would have to know everything that's right in order to make sure that
it's wrong or i don't know i like this idea but all of us all of us have wisdom that we
can share with others so the buddha of course recognized this
as well so there's this story in the suttas about megia
megia was the buddhist attendant before ananda was the attendant
and going for alms around one morning megia saw a mango grove that
seemed attractive to him that seemed compelling and he wanted to practice there
so he asked the buddha i'd like to go practice there in the mango grove and meditate for the day
and the buddha said why don't you wait because nobody else is here and he he was the buddha's
attendant and the buddha wanted him to stay but megia
insisted and the buddha said okay you can go so then megia goes to the mango grove
and sits to meditate and he had a difficult time he had a hard
time so he returned to the buddha and reported what had happened when he
was at the mango grove and uh here's what he says pante which is a
word for uh like teacher or yeah of a teacher or something ponte
while i was dwelling in that mango grove i was overcome by three kinds of harmful
unwholesome thoughts sensual thoughts aversive thoughts and
cruel thoughts it then occurred to me this is astounding and incredible
out of faith i have left the lay life and became a monastic
yet i am filled with these three kinds of harmful unwholesome thoughts
right so megia is maybe like surprised that even though all of his practice and
he's dedicated his life to be a monastic he's dedicated his life
to practice and he still has these unwholesome thoughts sensual thoughts aversive thoughts cruel
thoughts and not only has he become a monastic he
is the attendant of some would argue the best meditator that humankind has
known and yet he himself is still he's probably heard
countless numbers of dharma talks but he's not quite able to
himself to find that meditation that uh is not without sensual thoughts aversive
thoughts and cruel thoughts so he goes back to the buddha
after and he tells him just what i said and then the buddha responds megy
when mental liberation has not fully ripened that is when they're not
completely awakened there are five things which are conducive to full ripening
what five so now that buddha is gonna let him know what here are some things that he can do
one the buddha doesn't says one this is a my editorial edition
megia when one has good spiritual friends
good spiritual companions good spiritual associates
two one is virtuous three one there are conversations which are
supportive for developing humility and helpful for opening one's mind
four one has energy for abandoning unwholesome qualities and acquiring
wholesome qualities and five one is wise
endowed with the wisdom that knows the arising and passing of experiences
so then the buddha continues so magya when one has good spiritual friends good spiritual comrades good
spiritual associates it can be expected that they will be virtuous it can be
expected that they will have conversations which are supportive for developing humility and
helpful for opening one's mind when you have good spiritual friends it can be expected that you'll have the
energy for abandoning unwholesome qualities and and
acquiring wholesome qualities and when one has good spiritual friends
one will be wise endowed with the wisdom that knows arising and passing
so here the buddha is pointing out that what if we are associating with the right people it's more likely that we'll
have some of these other qualities that can help us on this on the path towards awakening
and we saw that with the earlier quote where the buddha is saying that just like the dawn is the precursor of the
morning so good spiritual friends is a precursor
to developing the noble eightfold path but one thing that i appreciate about
this passage is that there's these three different words spiritual friends companions and associates
translators can argue about you know exactly which way to translate them but the point is that it's three different
words so i'm interpreting them as three different levels of intimacy
some are good friends maybe some people are just those that you see maybe you
don't have a relationship with but you see there the way that they move in the world the way that they show up or
some action that they do sometimes when we're on meditation
retreats in person probably all of us have had this experience where we're
doing something going to the hall leaving the hole going into the dining hall whatever it
might be and we see somebody who is behaving really in a mindful way it's
like oh right i'm supposed to be mindful. so maybe that's just somebody that's uh
sharing the space a fellow retreat and so this this different levels there's
good friends that we might have maybe there's people that we would only chat with or when we see them in the zoom
breakout rooms for example i mean we don't speak with them outside but maybe then and we're happy to see them and
share with them our experience or or maybe there's people that we don't really know but we see
and are inspired by so we could interpret this that the buddha
recognized that our minds have a whole range of potential
we can have this selfishness aggressiveness and
sensual thoughts thoughts of cruelty thoughts of just some general unwholesome unhelpful thoughts
all of us have this potential in the same way all of us have the potential for
wisdom and compassion kindness and warmth
and the buddha also recognized of course that we don't live in these hermetically
sealed vacuums our minds are not completely independent
of course we are influenced by others of course we are influenced by our
environment this is why the buddha often suggested you know going to the foot of the tree
and meditating you know going off into seclusion but he also suggested that you have good
spiritual friends and we can say well what's the definition of a good spiritual friend
and we could say it's one that supports your practice supports this movement towards greater
freedom some greater ease so which of these potentials for
unwholesome thoughts or wholesome thoughts which ones of these gets realized
is influenced by our environments our friends and maybe we could also bring into
this the which media we consume
dharma books or social media and which are the intention is to be inflammatory and
divisive or news sources this memory right the news news sources all of them have a business
model and their business model is to get readers
so of course they are going to point out
things that are catchy or grab our attention
maybe they're not all inaccurate but maybe they are have a particular point of view in which they're emphasizing the
worst or the best or something like this
and maybe others just silently speak to the hidden potentials within us maybe there's
something inside of us that gets inspired when we see another or
we read a dharma book or listen to a dharma talk or have some drama friends with we
talk about i think all of us probably can look back on our lives and see oh
yeah why being influenced by different people even
you know parents sometimes will restrict kids from you know i don't
think you should spend so much time with these kids i notice that when you do that you're
cussing a lot or whatever it is whatever it might be
so in the suit does there's also where the monastics help one another
at the opening scene of the anapanasati suta that is the discourse on mindfulness of
breathing mindfulness of breathing of course is a key practice that we do and
and reading that suta i was primarily interested in you know the steps with breathing these 16 steps the
four tetrads but i never forgot this opening scene that really did touch
me and it goes something like this now at that time the senior monastics
were advising and instructing the junior monastics some senior monastics instructed 10
monastics while others instructed 20 30 or 40
and being instructed by the senior monastics that junior monastics realized
a higher distinction than they had before so just this small little
i don't know often we tend to kind of like throw away some of these uh sentences in the sutras but this
recognition that the there's a teaching going on and i believe my understanding
is even in the today's monasteries there's a lot of teaching that happens between the monastics
and here's one that um i'd like to share this is from the terry gotta that is
these are the verses from nuns that have been awakened
and this is from the nan uttama and she's describing a little bit of her story of
how she became awakened it goes like this
four or five times i left my dwelling i had failed to find peace of heart or
any control of my mind i approached a nun
in whom i had faith she taught me the dharma
the aggregates sense fields and elements
when i had heard her teaching in accordance with her instructions
i sat cross-legged for seven days without moving given over to rapture and bliss
on the eighth day i stretched out my feet having shattered the mass of darkness
quite something to sit for seven days i don't know if we should take this literally or not
but i appreciate very much she starts this nun i had failed to find peace of heart or
any control over my mind so then she goes to a nun in whom she had faith so
maybe she had noticed this other nun maybe she had noticed or maybe this nun
was patatara we don't know it might be panachara some of you know
that we had we have a padachara statue this right here now is the buddha
but we also have one that's padachar who's down at the retreat center and she was
one of the premier nun teachers one of the first teachers so perhaps it was patatar but perhaps it
was another nun that uttama went to received some teachings
and then she did the teachings and became awakened shattered the mass of darkness
the mass of darkness we can understand as pain ignorance or delusion so that
she saw clearly
so what is it what would it take to have these good spiritual friends
often it's not easy to i'm using this expression good spiritual friends it's a translation of
kaliana mita some of you may be familiar with that expression
there's a number of different ways we can translate it but i'll keep it as good spiritual friends
and so to develop these types of friendships probably requires some patience
some deliberate effort of course being friendly and having
warmth and being a good listener right everybody knows this you don't need me
to tell you this but maybe these types of relationships grow
of course like all relationships with honesty and being authentic and not trying to be
more spiritual or something like this right not trying to fit ourselves into
some mold but not only that is a willingness to learn from
and be supported by others that is to be teachable
there are some people who just feel uncomfortable with the idea that somebody else might know something
that they don't know or they just have to spend their energy showing how
much they know and aren't really teachable
so in order to have these good spiritual friends friendships
we have to be willing to be teachable and can we be inspired by others with
without a feeling of envy without a feeling of
oh they have everything i don't have anything you know without our inner critic getting
activated maybe there's a little bit of envy maybe a little bit of the inner critic gets activated but not in a way
that it is a hindrance or is a burdensome or
problematic for our relationships can we just recognize that other
people's lives unfold differently than ours of course they do
of course they do earlier i was talking about how well kind of connected so there's all these conditions
people are have been influenced by different conditions different people in their lives so of course their lives
unfold differently than ours can we receive feedback
either directly or indirectly we might notice as i said earlier that
when we see somebody who's been mindful our mind mindlessness might be highlighted
or maybe when we see when somebody's their speech is really clean their their own gossip
they aren't divisive they're not you know speaking in such a way that it's
denigrating to anybody and that might be
a way which can highlight for us oh yeah when i was complaining or wanting to
talk about somebody else they didn't join me in this instead maybe they could
like skillfully change the topic
well maybe we do have some conceit about our meditation practice or our
attainments that we believe that we've had and we feel like we somehow feel like we have to show
them or let people know but maybe we it might be softened if we
spend time with people who hold themselves slightly or perhaps don't even show any interest
in our uh spiritual attainment so to speak but
instead they are interested in just us as individuals
so this is part of being a good spiritual friend and maybe also
say not to being attached to our views or
our group that is are we just looking for confirmation of what we already know
or are we open to learning from other people that are different from us maybe have different life experiences
have different backgrounds different meditation experiences
so this idea of cultivating good spiritual friends is such an
integral part of our practice and the buddha recognized this and i'm sure all of us recognize this
too how this practice to walk with others but of course not in a way in
which we give up our discernment not in a way in which we give up our
ability to say this doesn't quite feel right and to
not give up our autonomy or anything like this but instead to allow ourselves to be
influenced and to use our wisdom so that we can be
not only have a good spiritual friends but be a good spiritual friend
and in this way can kind of um with this connectedness that we recognize
that we have with each other one another that we can support
one another and maybe those who feel supported can support yet other people and and in this
way there the support can grow and more and more people benefiting from our practice
to may all beings benefit from our practice thank you