all right so so a warm hello or a cool hello wherever you are
whatever is appropriate for your weather conditions in this moment in time
um greetings greetings and welcome to happy hour
so for today's happy hour um i'd like to continue as from the
beginning of the year we've been planning to go through the brahmavihara
and through the different categories systematically so we went through the different
categories of of meta loving kindness and i wanted to start with
the next brahmavihara the next cultivation which is compassion cultivating
compassion so compassion what
is compassion how is it different from from menta what's the difference between
karuna in pali and metta in bali compassion and loving
kindness what is the difference between the two the idea is that when meta when kindness
when good will when friendliness just a sense of good will and kindness
it meets suffering then it gets expressed as compassion
so compassion is if you if you like formulas compassion is metta
which is loving kindness kindness good will warmth friendliness plus suffering
so suffering that is held with worms is compassion there's so many different
ways to hold suffering not very helpful ways one is to kick ourselves well get it together why are you upset where
are you sad why are you hurting or the same way to others well why or whereas
ah when it's held with care oh sweetie this is hard this is hard acknowledging first and
foremost that something is challenging and also bringing kindness bringing warmth and
care to it another way that we can think about
compassion is that um this is a more poetic way to
think of compassion is that compassion is the love child is the love child of loving kindness and
suffering is the love child of loving kindness metta and suffering so the two of them again
when they come together it gets expressed in our hearts as compassion so compassion this practice of
compassion karuna is one of the brahmaviharas heavenly abodes there are four heavenly
abodes first metta second one being karuna compassion third one sympathetic
joy and the fourth one equanimity and we'll get to them in the next weeks and months
and these hard practices when you practice them they feel good they they
are relieving they are softening they're tenderizing
so compassion isn't supposed to feel painful or bad or tough or or
um or heavy if we veer into heaviness into sadness
we might have veered off from compassion into overwhelm into grief
into what's called empathic distress where meta where the kindness is not
balanced with suffering there's too much emphasis on the suffering
so when we practice compassion
we want there ideally to be there there to be a balance between how much we're
tapping into the suffering and how much kindness we're holding it with
so that there is this sense of holding and if there's too much feeling into the
suffering without enough kindness to hold it then it can feel heavy but that's okay
that that will happen don't judge yourself it's perfectly fine
it will happen it might happen simply they really turn towards the suffering that's coming up and hold
it with care with men with warmth
so so much to say about this topic but i'll just leave it at this brief short
dormant and let's practice together let's do it together
so so i would like to invite you invite us all to get into our
meditation posture and see what is appropriate for you in
this moment ah you may need to shift your posture
you may need to lie down that's okay [Music]
you may need to sit up straighter with a sense of integrity in your seed
in your cushion ah landing landing
arriving in this body in this heart
in this mind in this moment
or this human experience
softening letting go of any tension that you notice in your
body maybe in your forehead maybe your jaw
maybe your neck and shoulders your chest
abdomen relaxing softening
your sit bones letting go from the
inside
if there's any tension [Music] your legs your feet
your hands arms
ah with the next out breath softening letting go
hmm
and inviting your heart to settle in this moment you're hard to
arrive your heart to trust to trust
in your goodness to trust in this practice
in your own capacity
letting your heart land and trust
settling into your bones
letting your mind settle too
hey if it were a snow globe your mind
with all the shiny little objects twirling around let it settle settling it down
letting it land
relaxing receiving the breath one breath at a time
and if thoughts are twirling again no problem just see them smilingly
settling down sitting down this twirling shaken snow globe
just letting all the shiny objects of thought land settle
uh
giving your heart giving your heart to the practice in this moment
setting aside all else a dedication
of yourself of your heart fully
holy wholeheartedly in this moment
just being breathed in the body
settling arriving
uh
now i would like to invite you if you would bring to mind
a good friend might be having some challenges right now so when you
care about who's experiencing some challenging
aspect in their life could be a friend could be family member
benefactor just someone whom you care about an easy person
an easy being [Music]
so when you care about is experiencing a challenge right now
taking some time [Music] to connect with their felt sense with
their image
using all the senses to really connect with this person with this being
could also be a pet that's fine if they're having challenging time right now
or a child
bringing them to your mind's eye as clearly as possible
your visual their image if your auditory maybe what they sound like
when they talk to you
maybe their smell how they move how they speak
whereas if you were as if they were in front of you or maybe
easier to imagine if you're having a zoom conversation with them or facetime
or phone call just bringing them to mind as clearly as you can
with them and connecting with the with what they're going through right
now
and as you connect with the pain sorrow the suffering they're experiencing to meet it
to let it be met for you to meet it with kindness
with good will with care with love
with tenderness
imagining that each breath as you breathe out each breath
you're breathing out comfort ease care support compassion
for this person and this situation for this being in this situation
letting the goodwill the care envelope
caress hold the suffering your care
as if it were a soft comforting blanket
of love and care
and you don't have to try too hard if it's effortful relax relax your heart relax your body
your mind let it be easeful
the image your breath connecting to the challenge
connecting to your kindness your good wish your good will for them
me
if you like you can add phrases phrases of compassion just let it be worthless see what
works for you experiment can use any phrase such as
i wish you ease may you have ease and peace
in the midst of the sorrow this pain the suffering
i wish you peace i wish you ease
in the middle of the sorrow or pain or suffering see what works best
for you
hmm may you be free may you be free from
pain may you have peace
may you have ease
or i care about you i care about you and i wish you well
i wish you ease
i wish you goodness
hmm
me
and if it feels too heavy or too sorrowful too much grief
then lean more into the good will to the good wishes to your care
love kindness sense of glowing radiating good will
care towards them that can hold
the suffering can hold any suffering maybe you are surprised how powerful
your care is
and if you lose touch too much with the challenge you can lean into that
some more so you decide what's needed in each moment
which more of is needed
me discover how differently your body
your heart energetically feels as you lean more into the meta powerfully holding
the pain the suffering meeting it a few years more into feeling the
suffering become aware notice
hmm
may you be free from this sorrow i wish you well
i care i care about your challenge your difficulty
i wish you well dear one
you can try it in your mother tongue if you wish welcome to experiment
me
hmm
imagining visualizing that you care maybe your breath each breath brings
this being comfort soothing sucker
and maybe you're caressing them gently with your care whatever works for you
visually and linguistically
as israel
may you be free from this sorrow from this challenge my dear
hmm
me
let it be easeful don't have to push it
let the practice do you it can flow it's okay
me
hmm
and for the last moments minutes of this
practice letting you be the recipient of your own compassion
if there is any challenge or difficulty happening for you right now
the same energy of care and soothing
holding yourself dear may i be free
may i have peace and ease with this challenge with this suffering
sorrow pain
may both of us both this dear being in myself may we both
have ease freedom from our challenge
expanding this circle of compassion to all beings
or practicing with you right now knowing that they all have something
some challenge in their life some stress some difficulty and they have friends
loved ones they care about or going through a challenging time perhaps
wishing all of them ease all of them all of us
it's the human condition none of us are immune
none of us are immune from challenge and difficulty
and expanding the circle further all beings everywhere
may they all be free from sorrow and challenge
whatever challenge they're facing and their lives may
they have peace and needs may all beings be free may all things be
happy including ourselves
[Music]
thank you all thank you for your practice
so
if you'd like to share reflections on what you noticed what came up for you what which was challenging what was
interesting what you discovered susan i'll ask you to unmute
yes hi hi i was noticing how
the phrase that caressing care just really touched me deeply and i
noticed how i was having some difficulty giving this person i love my sister-in-law this caressing care
and i noticed it was difficult because i needed to give it to myself first so
i started giving it to myself and then it just flowed very naturally to her before i
was feeling that resistance and i felt that happiness that i was able to
realize that maybe i needed it first and then it could just flow naturally to
her and and it felt very lovely then
beautiful thank you susan what a beautiful insightful discovery
that when your heart was soothed that that was needed then it was more
resourced to care for another being beautiful discovery thank you for sharing that yeah and
these practices we start wherever it's easy so if you discover it's easy
to turn the compassion to yourself by all means please do that
um and just to share with you since you brought this up susan i was actually going to tonight i had pl
i'd been planning to start with compassion for ourselves and then i thought well maybe i'll do it
more in the the canonical order which is first the compassion you do with with a being
who has a challenge and then yourself like okay i'll do it canonically but it's fine to start anywhere that it's
easy for you and if yourself so there's no right or wrong really at all so i really appreciate you
bringing that in susan lovely any other reflections especially if you
haven't spoken or shared in a long time in a while or
or if you're new would love to hear your reflections your thoughts your
questions your complaints it's all welcome
and you can also type them in chat if you wish
bill says i had difficulty focusing until i came upon the phrase may you be comforted for some reason
that made it work great great beautiful i love your self-discovery
here and sharing it that's great wonderful this practice is often you
know we try things we try this like oh yes and something connects yay we know we experiment see what
connects for us and what i bring are just invitations
for it says i realize that some part of me thinks that there is something wrong with suffering
ah that's a great realization that's a fantastic realization forest
um and great to see that like wow check that out and
to perhaps perhaps as i'm kind of seeing that in in your
in what you shared is that suffering dukkha is a part of the human
condition is a part is a mark is is in buddhism is called one of the three
marks of existence one of the three characteristics of existence
is dukkha's suffering it's just part of life just part of life so
and by the way i'm teaching a retreat on the three characteristics in a couple of weeks it's on my website if anyone is
interested in exploring this dukkha this suffering as a as a characteristic of
of of you being human jerry says i noticed a calming effect of
just letting it be at the level of amount of comfort that i was capable of tonight great great yeah
glad to hear that not pushing it clark says i often find it difficult to get a felt sense of the other person's
suffering and then it just seems like i'm doing plain meta how important do you think it is to
really connect to the person suffering should i try to imagine
them upset in as many ways as i can
that's a good question to how to support um well it's
so here's something you can try again without pushing but one thing you can try
clark is is to put yourself in their shoes like what they're going
through right now imagine oh if i were them in this moment and if i were going through this
right now how would i feel how how would that be and again not you with
your practice but if you were them with their background with their upbringing with their resources
right now how would i feel right now oh it'd be really hard so that's one way perhaps to find a way into it
knob says how do i cultivate more empathy for people i feel distant towards we'll get into that in a few
days now hang on to that question that we're just doing the concentric circles hang on
come back uh kyla clark italia i was wondering if i
connected too much to the person suffering and as a result ended up in the grief realm
yeah it's it's kind it's a balance right it's it's quite a balance between the two another reflection i
appreciate your words of leaning into the compassion if the suffering is difficult a friend of mine just started chemo for
cancer oh this was so very helpful tonight nikki for the framing how i can be with her suffering and mine
in not wanting her to die thank you thank you so much for sharing that yeah thank you and that was a direct
message so i'm choosing not to say the names if it seems like it's just directed to me but
if you want it to be public you can send it to everyone violet related to force comment
sometimes i feel like my suffering is evidence i'm not meditating enough oh
that's fascinating yeah yeah yeah suffering is is is part of life
so it's um yeah this is an interesting complex area
and i want to talk more about this there is a difference between pain suffering
personalizing it but realizing that actually dukkha is a characteristic of being
human and how do we respond to it is it first arrow first arrow is just the way life is second third fourth
arrow is what we add so have the wisdom to see if is it the first error if it's the first layer it's just life
it's disease it's illness it's what or is the second or third or fourth so
and even if it's second or third or fourth still meet it with compassion uh meet it with
compassion that's why this compassion practice is here right otherwise it wouldn't be part of the the
canon right otherwise you'll be just perfect we'll just have the first arrow and none of the other errors and all be okay
just that's why we're practicing cultivating compassion for our suffering yeah
wishing everyone on this call peace at times of suffering thank you pete lovely so there's so much more to say
but then hey guess what we have many many sessions on compassion in the coming days so i'm
not going to try to cover it all let's let's transition into practice into small group practice and
this is the invitation i have tonight as we get into groups don't start talking spend
30 seconds in silence just wishing well trusting that those
these other two beings two three beings in the room with you are suffering just like you they're
human beings who have challenges just like you and then when you choose to speak if you choose
to speak you can share how the practice was or or whatever you wish so i'd like to invite
all of us fellow suffering human beings because it's part of the human condition
to practice together so um going to create the breakout rooms
now here we go
okay and they're open now okay great all right all the rooms are
closed welcome back everyone so um we have maybe just a minute
if you'd like to share about what the practice was like today in groups or
the meditation especially if you haven't shared and know why i would love to hear from you let's take one comment
yeah thank you dawn it says i so appreciated sharing but also being
silent oh beautiful yeah being silent with each other
nice what else maybe one one verbal reflection
we have limited time come on don't be shy go for it
oh julianne i see your hand let's see i'm gonna try to uh
there you are i'm gonna ask you to
there okay go um i this is my first evening and uh i
didn't realize how um happy and peaceful i would feel after
the little breakout room and i didn't know you were going to do that to us so at first i panicked and i
wanted to run away but i'm glad that i didn't because i met
two new friends so um and i've been listening to you nikki
for a long time well about three years now and it's so nice to see your face
and have a face to your name so um you've changed my life in a number of
ways i discovered your podcast after a retreat so it's nice to be here
oh thank you julian it's lovely to meet you it's i'm so glad you're here yeah me too
thank you thank you so much for joining the commute now you're part of the community
yay i've been looking for an online sangha so oh this is great great this makes me
so happy please come back please come back this is great oh it makes me so happy lovely to meet
you oh sweet so so dear ones
it is 701 and let's see a couple more reflections
elizabeth says a feeling of being held oh by the community the windows in the groups that's sweet and jerry says
i noticed that in the silent period that i found suffering more authentic when someone says
they are suffering rather than when they say happy ah
interesting yeah the profoundness of the silence
is nice so yeah and then asked does nikki have a podcast
well i've been i've been interviewed and different podcast which is on my website
but also audiodharma is a podcast for so yeah that's what julianne was
referring to odd dharma so dear ones okay so let's dedicate
the goodness of our practice together so ah so thank you all for your practice
and the goodness generated from our coming together practicing together with trusting
ourselves the goodness in our hearts sharing our goodness
with ourselves and with each other for the benefit of all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings
be free thank you so much everyone