so good day to everyone
here we are together and from all over and
uh gathering ourselves for this period of meditation
and this topic they one of the subjects is practicing with
mental activity which has been my most common
translation for sankara sometimes translates mental
formations and
so say this about it is that these mental activities that we have
as we practice as we settle in meditation as we begin to let go of attachments and
clinging the direction the mind is going is to becoming beautiful
to have a beautiful mind and that the feeling that not just a feeling the
experience or the quality of physical calmness that happens when the body relaxes
and the quality of mental relaxation tranquility that comes as the mental activities calm down
it's referred to in the buddhist tradition as beautiful as beautiful qualities of
mind and that many of these uh factors of mine that start coming into play
that of faith and and engagement with the practice attention
wisdom mindfulness samadhi all these things they're they're
considered uh beautiful qualities of the mind and so
we are we one of the orientations for meditation one of the
things to kind of kind of be considering is how do you practice how do you do the
activity of meditation so it itself has some quality of beauty
or maybe another word is harmony i love the hopi indian the indigenous
people of new mexico the i love their expression of walking
in beauty so what would it mean to engage the mind
in beauty and sometimes there's such a strong orientation towards
avoiding which what is not beautiful or it's difficult or painful or
there can be a lot of criticism in the mind self-criticism and a lot of judgments that whatever the
mind is doing wondering often thought is somehow wrong or
worse and maybe so but but what we do how we
show up to be mindful to be present to be engaged with the breathing how
would you do it if you did it in a beautiful way or in a harmonious way
because that's the direction that this practice is going and especially with this calming of
mental formations calming of the mental activities we're feeling our way into a place of
harmony or beauty of peace of clarity of lightness
of uh sometimes the ancient tradition talks about a kind of a clean mind a cleansed
mind so for this sitting today maybe you can um
you can um orient yourself a little bit with um
what would it be like to sit here in beauty not because you're looking for it it
might be there it might be here but also because you engage
in the practice that way that the very way in which you are present
the way very way in which you are mindful is in harmony or is in beauty what would
that look like and i know it might be a stretch or it might be you might not have an easy reference for
this but i would suggest that you imagine you do
imagine yourself in this way and if so
to assume a meditation posture and even here as we get into as we take
the posture how would you do it
as if the activity of assuming your posture meditation posture was itself a movement
in beauty maybe in gracefulness
and maybe gracefully kind of rocking forward and back maybe slowly
maybe not sideways and then slowing down and finding
a balanced posture most balanced for what's available to
you with all the different challenges you might have and so your your posture itself
begins to feel like a small stepping stone to beauty
to harmony
and then
softly peacefully closing your eyes
and then what would it be like if you approached your breathing with
trust with care
with relaxation with some quality or feeling of
approaching your breathing
in a harmonious way or in a beautiful way
what was your attention what would attending to your breathing
be if you were attending in a beautiful harmonious way
and perhaps it could be that you invite your body
to gently breathe more fully
expanding the chest expanding the belly as you breathe in
maybe three quarters full so you're not straining
and perhaps allowing for a longer
peaceful exhale as far as it's useful to exhale
so and then to as you exhale
to relax the body to calm the bodily activity of tension
holding contraction in the body releasing it
and letting your breathing return to
normal and then as you exhale
to also relax and soften the thinking mind
if the if you can recognize any tension or holding
contraction or hardness
agitation or forcefulness associated with breathing
as you exhale relax the mind
and if you can't relax it that's okay
perhaps you can recognize that awareness attention to the tense
mind is larger distinct and different than
the mind itself the activity and then hold
the tense mind in the beauty of open awareness
and then entering into the body breathing breathing naturally and easily
with a very light touch not trying too much
seeing if you can attend to breathing in a way that feels harmonious even
beautiful with its care its tenderness its openness
its willingness
perhaps with its feeling of respect for breathing
a reverence
for being here
and perhaps there's something in the breathing itself
which feels harmonious or beautiful pleasant
and to sit here
present for your breathing while attuned to
that which is harmonious or beautiful here and now no matter how small it
might be
if possible relaxing the mental activity of anxiety
mental activity of
discouragement or resentment
letting those settle and recede to the background
and in the foreground as you're sitting here
sitting meditating in beauty
some of them which might be whatever feeling of pleasure
well-being joy or happiness
that might be here right now breathing with it breathing through it
as you breathe is there any little place inside of
tranquility calmness peacefulness
a calmness of body calmness of mind
breathe with that breathe through it
gently allowing that calmness tranquility to spread and grow
so that its influence perhaps a beautiful influence
can begin to move through you breathing in and
breathing out
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
looking inside of yourself to see if there's any
shift inside in the course this meditation
are you a little more settled if not more settled are you more
aware a heightened awareness of how you are
both the subtleness and the heightened awareness can both be seen as something beautiful
or are you more open more peaceful more
more sense of well-being have you learned something about your
own capacity to attend beautifully harmoniously
in whatever sense you have of an inner beauty or harmony or well-being
bring to mind some people that you know and imagine that they too have the same
capacity they have the potential for this
and that more than worldly success
that to experience this inner harmony this inner peace or beauty is one of the great potentials
they have a potential which is not dependent so
much on what happens in the world
and perhaps you can very gently lovingly harmoniously
have the wish that in fact they could feel this inner
well-being and harmony
that they might know their beauty
and beyond the people you know even the people you don't know and the
people who are a challenge for you
how wonderful would be if they could stay closely attuned aligned with their own inner
harmony and beauty their own potential for an inner
well-being that is so ethical in nature because it doesn't depend on
getting anything or making anything happen in the world
may it be that all beings
touch into their capacity for happiness may all beings
experience safety within
peacefulness within
a full inner freedom the heart set free at ease
this beautiful heart that we all share may all beings
be happy
so the topic for this week is uh what
in pali is called um chitta sankara c-i-t-t-a
s-a-n-k-h-a-r-a and uh it's often translated as mental
[Music] formations sometimes mental dispositions
sometimes mental constructs for this week i kind of been using the
expression mental activities and uh it's those activities of the mind
which are planning creating uh uh imagining actively thinking about
things so a simple perception of uh something uh seeing a wall across the
hall the room here that wouldn't necessarily be called an activity that's just it is an activity but it's
not a one of the formations or constructions that we make and what's fascinating the number
of things that are fascinating about this idea of mental formations mental constructions
sankaras and um is that um one is that
um many things that we take to be kind of inherent or just the way things
are turn out to be an activity of the mind and so to give you one example boredom
when we're bored it can feel like just the thing that we're doing is boring just this event the situation is boring it is
boring but in fact it's the mind's activity that creates the feeling the sense of boredom
it's a kind of maybe even a subliminal judgment evaluation
it's holding oneself apart from experience it's uh it can be a resistance
it can be a loss of intimacy with experience uh and so there's all these things going
on in the mind that construct that activate this
feeling the idea of boredom and the idea that we're constructing it where it's an where
we're kind of forming it making it in the mind uh gives us a very different orientation
to boredom than if the situation is boredom because the situation is boring the situation is
to blame and so we better just get away or change it but if we're responsible because it's an
activity of the mind then we can practice with it and that's one of the things we learn through
meditation is how to practice with these mental formations these mental activities so that we're not caught in
them and not pulled around by the nose by them but we learn how to settle them or
become more expensive of them or freer of them free of them even when they're there
so with boredom one would turn around the attention 180 degrees from the
situation that's boring whatever it might be it's internal external and have the attention
really look at the boredom itself and look it right in the eye and say boredom i see you and feel it
and be with it and experience it and to learn how to kind of uh dissipate
the boredom because we really see it clearly is very empowering
because it shows us that we don't have to be the victim of our own mental activities and that's
one of the great good news of this buddhist teaching is that so much of our suffering
has a relationship to the activity of our mind and and whereas we can't necessarily
change always the situation in the world we can we have some care and attention to
shifting how the mind is constructing these ideas and concepts and even constructing ideas of self that we
have so it's a phenomenally good news if we have the mindfulness and attention
stability to really see how this works and um
and so mental activities to really see it that way and learning to tranquilize it calm them relax them
and uh now this tranquil mind is considered in the buddhist tradition
to be a beautiful quality so tranquilizing the mind is not just becoming numb
not just it's not becoming numb at all it's not becoming kind of less than it actually begins tapping into
something that's really wondrous amazing about what's available inside that can
arise with this idea of a mind that's very tranquil clean transparent smooth easy
and and this points to uh one of the problems one of the in the
english language translating the word sankara as formations or even
other activities because uh some of those are just uninspired mental formations it's like what is that
and it's kind of uninspired translation mental activities maybe means a little bit more but i don't think it has too
much inspiration value in it i believe that in the in the indian context ancient indian
context the word sankara that we're translating as formations had very positive associations
and and one of the early indian associations was it's a word that was used in the
pre-buddhist brahmanical traditions to describe sacred rituals
and in fact sankhara sometimes is it means to make something sacred
and at least that's what the dictionary definition sometimes has and and so this idea of
of something sacred uh a ritual which is uh maybe for some people
very heartwarming and a deep connection has a very different idea than um than just you know mental
activities because this inner this mental activities of the mind
it um it's also it's it's a it's the quality of the mind that makes things
and prepares things or constructs kind of our sense of self and universe and ideas and
all that but as that gets quieter that movement of activity mental activities
can have a quality of sacredness reverence wonder but also my favorite
word is beauty which is a translation of a word in pali
kaliana that is often translated as good and one of the places where it's
translated as good is in discussions about karma karma
means action and the primary action that we're dealing with in meditation is the mental action so
the mental karma and um and sometimes it's translated
that there's three kinds of there's two kinds of karma there's good karma and
bad karma and but the word for good is kaliana which its primary meaning
is beautiful and you get a very different feeling about actions if you refer to them as being
either beautiful or not beautiful and and so this idea that
we can have the potential in the mind or having the mental activity become
beautiful has is much more inspiring than simply calming the mental formations or being
are experiencing the mental formations so the mental formations the the seventh
step of anapanasati breathing in experiencing the mental formations mental activity
breathing out experiencing mental activity happens after
experiencing some modicum of joy well-being and happiness and meditation
and that's important to remember that all these things are situationals contextual these steps of meditation
and we're not we're not supposed to be in a hurry to get past it and if you hear instructions that you're
not there yet just take it in and and file it away for the future
no need to feel bad that you're not there we're all going to be cycling through
these 8 16 steps and be at different stages of different days different minutes different weeks
because of what's happening in our life and all kinds of situations so the 16 steps are always
um you know we're some it's kind of good to think that we're always beginning in step one
and not be in a hurry not feel like you have to always be following this these steps that i'm
going through i'm going through it linearly but the trap of that is assumed that you're
supposed to be right coming along and i'm trying my best to kind of make it come alive for you but
i've got to trust where you are and that trusting where you are is part of the beauty that we're
developing in this practice that trust and trust appreciation
reverence care love for oneself that i can just be where i am
and practice there and trust that this process will unfold this anapanasati
process is a natural process in its own way will unfold for you
no need to be in a rush or hurry through it and so this trust is part of the beauty of the mind and so
rather than seeing mental activity mental formations as neutral uninspired kind of you know
just stuff in the mind we're touching into a capacity of the mind
to be beautiful to be wondrous to be something that maybe borders on or
feels sacred and this is the great value of this practice is to really
discover a rich wondrous beautiful inner life that really can
inform how we live in the world i'd like to think that as we discover
this wondrous inner life we we get turned inside out and what was
inside is no longer inside but something that that we share with the world around us
so mental formations so as we continue next week maybe you'll keep
this in mind that uh we're working with a capacity we have for inner beauty
and inner something that's wondrous that lives in us for sure uh even though
some of your mental activities that you're living by and that kind of are you're caught in
the grip of and you don't even know you're in the grip of some of these mental activities um might be standing in the way for now
of seeing how wondrous it is on the inside for you the beauty that you have
so thank you for today and i look forward to continuing next week