so hi hi everyone a warm welcome to happy hour so nice to be with you
ah so so for today's practice together
um i'd like to consider i like to consider
the theme the consideration of of our practice our
practice as a service what if our practice
is service to ourselves to the world and this practice happy hour
this practice of celebration cultivating joy cultivating
meta cultivating kindness cultivating goodness i want to share a poem as inspiration
and this poem is called service is joy
it's by robin dranath tagore i spell the name
r-a-b-i-n-d-r-a-n
tagore t-a-g-o-r-e it's a very short poem i'd even memorize it
i slept and dreamt that life was joy i awoke
and saw that life was service i acted and behold
service was joy isn't that a great poem
gives me a lot of joy i'll read it one more time i slept and dreamt
that life was joy i awoke
and saw that life was service
i acted and behold
with that as the theme with that as the inspiration what if
our practice our practice this offering our practice is joy
what if our practice is service service to ourselves
service to others practice as joy practice as joy practice as service all
of these the same exploring the equivalence
of practice but to practice in general but here in particular practice of meta
cultivation of kindness good will for ourselves for others
a service this cultivation of joy and service
service is joy practices joy so that's the invitation for tonight for this afternoon this for
this moment in time wherever you are for our practice together so
having set the frame let's begin formally
ah let's land let's land in our bodies
landing in this moment in time
arriving in this body in this moment whatever the circumstances
connecting
the felt sense of the sit bones on the cushion
or bottom kissing
the earth our feet kissing the earth
our body
softening relaxing into the earth kissing the
earth
this
connecting with the breath
maybe slowing down the breath slowing down the in-breath
slowing down the in-breath slowing down the out-breath
just here relaxing slowing down
the body
into this moment unwinding
slowly giving yourself space
slowing down your body your heart your mind
your breath maybe maybe breathing to the count of
five breathing out to the count of five
letting go of the counting slowing down even more
if you find if you wake up to the mind having
wondered ah dear mind oh sweetheart
it's okay it is
of the nature of awareness of knowing of the mind to think
it's okay
seeing clearly what is arising in this moment what's
hot
smiling at it
hello sarge hi friendly
lighthearted
and landing back landing back
without any judgment no need smilingly
landing back the body with the breath
enjoying enjoying this process of sitting
and being breathed
if we don't judge ourselves if we don't reprimand ourselves
force ourselves expect
a tight way for things to go a certain way
in our practice to have aspirin
but not expectation become easy
freaking become joyous practice as joy
practice as joy
see if you can give yourself space
to relax to stop down [Music]
enjoy
this moment of quiet of solitude
of turning inward sitting and being breathed
now can there be a sense of breathing in well-being breathing in
goodness gladness
good wishes for your son breathing it in
as if it's offered to you an each breath filling your body
feeling your lungs and then breathing it out reach out bring it with the whole world
may i be safe in the opera in the in-breath and in the out breath
ah may all beings be safe
in breath may i be happy out breath
may all beings be happy in breath
may i be healthy
out breath may all beings be healthy
in breath may i have ease and then turning and sharing and
expansively with the whole world just as i wish for myself may the whole world
all beings have ease this might be reduced to just one word
if you synchronize it with the breath breathing in breathing in
safety safe breathing out safe
happy breathing out happy
as a wish to all breathing in health
goodness breathing out health
beings breathing in
ease out knees
just simply breathing in good will [Music]
gladness well-being whatever word single word works for you
bringing a breathing out same for the whole world
maybe just simply that if it's starting to feel complicated
can we consider our practice breathing in goodness breathing out
shining out goodness unto the world a service
a service practice as service
to ourselves
breathing in good well friendliness breathing out good well
mental love friendliness
trust you are needed
you are needed your service your participation in life
in the unique way
that you show up is needed
trusting trusting your participation your service
your noble service is needed
breathing in love breathing in mental reality
letting good well mental love be breathed and
not yours simply offered trust
trusting
that love is offered compassion is offered
you are held in it
by the universe
and your participation matters
your cultivation is service to this goodness
receiving good will care and love with each breath into every cell of your
body letting yourself be nourished by it held
by it trusting its goodness
breathing out letting your heart shine
with good will friendliness for others may all beings be well
and if any thoughts or judgments come up i can't do this this is hard my mind's a mess i'm a
failure i can't do this practice you don't have to believe any of these
thoughts smile smile breathe with them take them along as you breathe in
care and breathe out care
let these judgments be transformed if any
through the breathing in and out of love and care friendliness
invite them to breathe with you
see what happens when you invite the judgments to breathe
in goodness and breathe out goodness with you
do it light-heartedly see if anything gets transformed or shifts
for the last minutes of this practice
reconnecting with the framework as if we're sitting
ah and offering
our practice bowing and offering our practice as service as
joyous service putting it on the altar the universal altar
of goodness service to ourselves the deepest sense service to all
[Music] in beings joyful way
we offer out of generosity our hearts gifts
there's a joy that comes
here please have the best of me the best i have offer in this moment
regardless of how i judge it to have been if my mind was distracted if i was
sleepy or in pain or anything else this is the best
way i could show up i did my best letting go of any judgments
putting your intentions your beauty your goodness of your cultivation of your service on
the altar
letting your heart be uplifted with your unique contribution
you are needed you are needed
may all beings everywhere
may all beings be well may all beings be free
including ourselves
[Music]
thank you all for your practice for your participation
you are needed can you take a moment to take that to
heart you are needed
your participation is needed your practice your practice
as service to yourself and all beings
and practice as joy not forced
so we have time for reflections for questions
for comments especially if you haven't shared in a
while especially if you're new would love to hear from you
and if you type in chat to me privately i won't read your name if it's
typed to everyone i will read your name and the reflection
and also you can raise your zoom hand would love to hear your your vocal reflections questions
comments one reflection breathing in loving care for myself
breathing out loving care for others ah lovely
beautiful thank you for that so powerful
so powerful
oh alison says showing up tonight was an extreme act of loving kindness towards
myself oh yay [Music]
thank you for showing up and it's also an act of loving kindness towards all of us and everyone all
beings everywhere an act of service yeah
marie christine says lovely words thank you for that allison and i see hearts
lit up by others um one more reflection before we go to
diana's raised hand i sometimes have such an urge to bring goodness into the world it's nourishing
to think my practice is this gift oh yay oh
oh that makes my heart lit up to no end
oh that's so beautiful the urge to bring goodness into the world it's nourishing
to think my practice is this gift yes yes it is absolutely
oh yes thank you for that my heart lights up feeling that resonating with you with
that reflection thank you thank you
and again i'm honoring when you send it directly to me i won't read your name and if it's sent to
everyone then i read the name so that's as i said i'm honoring that [Music]
so diana please
i just wanted to say that i was watching you a little bit during the meditation and
it was inspiring because i kept thinking you seem to be having such a good time
you just need to be having fun and i really mean that doing this i didn't have a sense that you thinking
about dinner tonight or anything you seem to be there enjoying yourself
truly and i so that's been that's fun for me to see that it kind of
spreads so thank you thank you diana thank you for sharing
that it's um it gives me great joy that that this medium you know in the past it
would be just audio don't mind me audio drama is fantastic and it's great to be able to listen and yet i think it is
nice to have the visual right the visual and and it delights me to know that yes
i was having a great time i was my i was delighting in this practice
absolutely delighting in this practice of oh yes breathing in i mean all the aspects that
i was sharing with you i was practicing myself which is giving me so much joy
to be practicing with you and practice it just connecting with this so yeah thank you diana i'm delighted that
inspires you that supports you thanks for thanks for saying that
sweet yeah lovely
any other reflections yeah appreciation from youtube thank you
all on youtube for joining thank you cedric and others
in the other reflections questions
i see a thumbs up is that a raised hand [Music] uh because let's see
do you want to share is that
cedric yes
[Music] oops oh i think we had a
you're muted again i wasn't sure if you wanted to raise your hand cedric um or that was a thumbs up i asked you
to unmute and then seem like anyway i think we're having some technical difficulties so tell you what i think
what we'll do is given that it's 6 48 we'll go to small group practice we'll
go to small group practice and when we come back we'll reserve a couple of minutes at the end for
reflections and raise your hand again if you would cedric um to
[Music] yes you log on i'll got it yeah sounds great okay got your message
on youtube so so let's turn let's turn to
uh practicing in small groups together so
considering that you are needed your participation is needed you are needed
so um supporting yourself supporting each
other knowing that your practice your way of showing up your unique expression
in this world in the way that you show up is
is a gift is is service is service the way you show up for yourself and showing
up for others we serve each other in this practice
so i will create the the rooms now the breakout rooms and
um let's take the first 15
seconds as usual uh to just care for yourself care for others
in silence in silence meta for yourselves for others and then
share as little or as much as you wish and here are the rooms and they are open
take care of yourselves take care of each other your rooms are closed everyone is back
welcome back everyone so uh
oops great all right so we have uh
yeah we have a few minutes for reflections questions comments and feel free to type
them in chat raise your hand don't be shy
what did you discover
nice
see great cedric i see your hand fantastic and
there and by the way just to say we had a bit of a confusion because there was a there's another cedric
oh on youtube oh that is you oh okay i got confused
all right that is you i thought so so lovely to have you with us cedric
so yes uh thank you very much uh
this is my first time here and it's it's a it's a wonderful experience
i really enjoyed the meditation and the group that i was in what i
shared was my experience with meta
and if i'm out running errands or doing something like that and
i'm not able to stop and give assistance to an automobile accident or
say hello to a homeless person uh i send them meta
and using meta practice uh i feel it on an emotional level
and i feel that that's when it's most effective for me
thank you yeah beautiful beautiful thank you so much for sharing this cedric and welcome
to happy hour lovely to have you with us yay
and and really appreciate what you shared there's a sense that and i want to highlight what you said um
because there are times there are times in the world that it's not possible for us uh to to act
uh to to physically act out of compassion and yet sometimes you know we don't want to turn on our eyes and just
avoid looking at people or avoid them all together because that's painful to that's really painful that avoidance of
oh i can't rhyme in a rush but but what you are really highlighting and what you're bringing forth is this sense of
good will kindness i care for you may you be well i i see you i see you in my
heart i see your suffering and i care for you and i care for me because in this moment i can't
help you support you and and i see you i care for you i wish you well so it's it's
it's so much better than avoiding or distracting ourselves it's it's it's
sharing good will even if we're not able to if we were able to and again it's this hip it's it's it's almost like um
it's along the lines of training our hearts because you actually if you know you are moved
you arguing the meta it's like well actually maybe i can stop to help you know who knows you know that turn
actually can happen which is very different from turning one's one's gaze all together so thank you for bringing
that in beautiful beautiful practice of compassion in in real time in the world so
a couple of other reflections laurel says lovely meditation lovely sharing lovely people yes i agree
lovely sharing lovely people i completely agree what a beautiful song you are
beautiful people and alice says i'm not the only one who struggles with meditation and awareness
it isn't always perfect and that's okay yes absolutely and it's lovely that that
becomes clear especially when we talk in small groups and we realize no
it's we're not defective this is just part of this practice the mind gets just
distracted yeah beautiful so dear ones oh
namaste you i offer my hearts as you beautiful ah
offering our hearts as service our hearts as service cultivating our hearts
and goodness for ourselves for others so thank you all thank you for showing up
for your practice for your service to yourself and to the world
may all beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music] thank you