hello and greetings sangha
greetings this sunday morning afternoon evening whatever time zone you might be
in and it's wonderful to join you in this moment in time
scattered around the world in sitting together practicing my name is nikki murgafury
and i'm one of the teachers at the inside meditation center
many of you may recognize me from happy hour [Music]
um so gail is teaching a retreat
and it's my delight to support him and support us in sitting together and
practicing together in this moment so
so we'll start with a sid i'll leave a lot of space and silence
for us just to sit together and for those who might appreciate just
a few words of settling i'll offer that at the beginning so
so let us begin let us begin together let us begin
landing
arriving in this moment of time
this right here
in this body
softening relaxing the soft tissue of the body
and letting go of thoughts plans
all that has come prior to this bowing to them smilingly putting them
down
gratefully and turning
trusting trusting this moment of refuge
nothing else needs to be done trusting that this is enough
trusting that the loving awareness knows how to meet how to meet this
moment
trusting that you know how to do this
if there is any doing there is to be done
trusting you're doing your best
given all the causes and conditions and relaxing your heart and your body
greeting your breath greeting your body greeting whatever
arises on the lap of loving awareness
hmm
um
and if thoughts are rising twirling all around you
these shiny objects
ever so gently set down set down on your body this snow globe
this agitated snow globe just settling it down
on the mindfulness of the body and letting all the little specks of thought
shiny objects ah letting them all settle letting them
settle as they will
if you find the snow globe has been shaken again no problem
no problem part of this practice
to gently lovingly patiently
set it down again and again as a practice of love and patience
letting there be clarity
of awareness in the snow globe now and then
as much as possible
um
hmm
giving your heart holy fully to this moment
receiving the breath in the body
giving your heart to it
hmm
it's okay
whatever it is arising in this moment
from a spacious perspective it's all
okay
hmm
um
hmm hmm
me
hmm
okay
okay
me
and for the last
few minutes of this practice together
and we each have a sense of appreciation
and trust in our own inner goodness
our own values and intentions that have manifested in
this practice however shoddy we we think it to be we judge it to be
but can we trust trust in our own hearts
appreciating the goodwill the goodness the highest intentions that we have
and hold this being that is me that is us with care
with kindness appreciation good will tenderness
gratitude
thank you me for having shown up and practiced as well as you could
in these moments
and letting this kindness goodness trust in our heart
radiate
radiate outward with each breath
with rays of kindness and good will for all who are practicing with us in
this moment our dispersed sangha geographically
but all of us together
with warmth appreciation good will for all doing their best
and showing up
and spreading spreading radiating this kindness and goodness goodness
with each breath further beyond
may the light of my life
my goodness my devotion trust
and service and goodness
may it support all beings everywhere
in goodness
gladness and freedom
so sharing our goodness
the brightness of our light trusting there is brightness
even if we can't see and recognize it right now trusting it's there
may it be of benefit to myself others and the world
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
including ourselves
thank you thank you for your practice
for the benefit of self others in the world
so for reflections today
i'd like to speak share some thoughts
about trust about trust
as i was alluding to trust in the meditation dropping it in here
and there trust the sense of trust that can be so supportive
for practice for our life or humanity for the way we show up who we are in the world
supporting ourselves and others so trust the word in pali
often transliterate transliterated or written
as s a d h sada sada sada
beautiful word literally means to place our heart upon to place our
heart upon so sada it's not an intellectual
endeavor to place our heart upon something to give
our heart to something to trust in it to give our heart to it it's also
sada translated often not just as trust but also faith or confidence
or even inspiration
for some they arrive in the practice of
meditation mindfulness buddhism turning away from faith
perhaps from this idea of faith or blind faith that's requested
in theistic religions that you have to believe in something before you can
[Music] be part of the practices so for some people that resonates so they come to
to this practice from an intellectual place perhaps um and that's okay or from a place of
suffering perhaps but not not wanting to have faith place faith
in something it just seems too much and some people in fact turn away like faith again and buddhism
faith wait i thought i got away from that so you might resonate with that or not
for some people um trust in the divine is not in opposition
to this practice there are many practitioners of of other
theistic religions and faiths who also practice mindfulness buddhism
etc and there is no opposition to trust in the divine and also
have have trust in the buddha sangha dharma buddha dharma sangha as i'll talk about
it in the in a bit so and yeah there is no
there's no issue there's no opposition yet some others
after practicing in this tradition [Music]
they actually open up to more divinity and to the sacred through this practice
through this practice as as many of us might feel into touch into
experience something that's quite profound and unfathomable in our own first person
experience so it might feel opening up to a
dimension of sacred or divinity without without putting it
in the box not letting it be in a box
where wherever whatever you resonate with or not
and maybe having curious curiosity about what your resonance is
with perhaps the terms as i've introduced them so far
trust faith confidence inspiration different nuances of this
word sada of this word sada so what is surely true and prominent
in in this path that we practice together is as the buddha has said
come and see for yourself come and see for yourself you don't have to sign up
to anything at the beginning you just come and see for yourself if it works for you
great and if it doesn't great it's come and see for yourself
so in many ways this practice excuse me
so in many no still the tickle in the throat is here hold on sick
okay let's try that again
all right i think it's going to come and go i trust it will be okay and we'll see so
i hate pasako come and see for yourself so
um there is a sense of you know there needs to be still even
with that come and see for yourself there needs to be some sort of trust
some level of faith some level of trust but okay i'm going to give myself to it
because even if we you know if we come to it with the
invitation of ahipasico we come to it but we're just apprehensive we're not giving our heart
to it um it it may not work we we need to give our hearts to it trust it
at least for a certain amount of time and then if it's working great if it's not then
it's not working for you but but if we're checking our watch every five
minutes okay is it working is it working um do i have more ease freedom am i enlightened yet
oh it must be enlightened you know just just if if there's not a sense of trust giving yourself to this practice
with humility um it it probably won't work
so there needs to be that sense of trust or faith and it could be
and they could be borrowed trust it could be borrowed trust or bright trust they're
different borrowed a bright trust before it becomes
verified trust and then if it as it moves to
unshakeable trust so so it often starts with bright trust we see
someone we who who's different who's acting in the way we want to
be in the world or act or they have more freedom they have more ease
um so that sense of um bright
that sense of brightness of of the trust there's sense of brightness there
um like oh i'm attracted to this there is something there is something that inspires me
there's something that's inspiring my trust ah and then
there can be borrowed trust borrow trust
which can be similar to bright trust in that you're borrowing trust from from what
you're witnessing in another person and i often actually work with borrowed
trust and practice meetings with with with students where
i can see their capacity i can see their beauty i can see their goodness and
when they are hesitant and then they say well i don't know about this and i say okay i have full trust in you
i i fully trust i fully trust you um with this practice with this
invitation with what you're about to to to undertake is it okay if i hold it
for you and for you to have borrowed trust to have the trust that i have that i
have in you to borrow from that for now until you see for yourself
and it becomes verified trust becomes a verified trust because then after a while it feels like wait this
this thing works this thing works oh there is it so it becomes verified it's not
bright or borrowed anymore it becomes verified yes you realize you look back
perhaps in your life and see again it's practices like stock market don't check
on it every single day every single hour but look at it long term if you've been practicing for
weeks and months look look at months or even years
consider some areas of your life where you used to
be very upset anxious etc etc things that were really
challenging for you that are not challenging anymore and c oh
verify trust something is shifting i have more peace more ease more love
more gratitude whatever it might be whatever it is you're you're serving and trusting
and after a while of doing this practice it becomes it becomes unshakeable trust
your your trust becomes unshakable you know it works of course it does
and yeah you might have a day or two or a week or a month when you have monkey mind and this and that
but you have unshakable trust that you're planting seeds it's working
quote unquote working in some ways that you may not be able to fathom and in some ways it's opening you up
even if in your in the way
you're judging it it seems like it's not working but trust try you becomes unshakable trust yes of
course i'm giving my heart to this i've given my heart to this
so so trust or faith i will use that word faith there's a sense of faith
that gets developed after a while after a while and a sense of confidence
confidence in yourself i like the word confidence somehow
sometimes it might feel a little intellectual and yet it can also feel
embodied a sense of ah confidence in the heart i like to point
in the heart center but sense of confidence like yes trust confidence
so it could be that actually these different terms these different translations such as inspiration for
example it can refer to the earlier um to the bright trust like ah
inspiration and then later it becomes maybe again we can
i can wax philosophical about all these terms but maybe after a while when it becomes
unshakable trust there's it's actually faith that that translation works better for it
but maybe at first inspiration works better as a translation of sadha
maybe later borrow trust verify trust confidence as one of the
translations and then unshakeable trust or faith just putting the cards on the table at the
end so so trust is needed it is needed
and in fact if it wasn't for trust we wouldn't be here right now practicing together because
the buddha after his awakening the story goes that he didn't want to
teach he didn't want to teach he thought oh the dharma is
i can't teach this people won't get it why why do i bother and and he was asked
by his friends his his the the five disciples by his first five friends
no please please they're bonte dear sir there will be people with little dust in
their eyes with little dust in their eyes who will understand
who will understand the dharma so he trusted that there are people with
little dust in their eyes that yes there might be other people who
won't understand won't listen won't get it but that's okay trusting that there will be people with
little trust in their eyes who would understand and that's such a beautiful metaphor little does we
we all have dust we little dust isn't that great it doesn't say people with no dust in their eyes yeah
little does we still don't see clearly we have confusion and delusion and you know all that um you know hatred
ill will and attachment yeah a little dust but still
to see the dharma to see the beauty the beauty of these teachings the beauty of this path that
can open us up in these profound ways so thanks to his
trust to to have shared what he discovered here we are
so and of course going even further had he had not had he
uh had no trust in his ability in his own um in his own being
etc etc all the inner trust and faith in him actually sitting under the bodhi tree and saying
i'm not going to get get up until i'm awake and all that trust all that sense of confidence
that that really went through his own discovery and and to think that he wasn't a god figure
he was a human being just like us the same dna and a human being just
like us so so with with the idea
of of trust or sadha sadha um in this tradition
it's it's often invited for the triple jewel
so i want to say a little bit about that as i referred to trust in buddha dharma sangha earlier so
what does that mean let's decode it a little bit because we can take it by face value oh yeah
trust in buddha this human being that existed trust in the dharma the writings and the teachings
or trust in the sangha the the community of practitioners now and in
the past so yes that's absolutely one way to um to interpret it and yet
and yet there is a much more profound i would
say deeper another dimension for our hearts to open to what actually this
idea of trust in the triple jewel means for us to have a meaningful
even more meaningful even more meaningful personal relationship to it
so first and foremost trust in the buddha
in addition to the historical figure but the buddha within
to trust that this being right here is not broken
or damaged goods or bad that trusting that you are inherently
you are inherently good you're inherently lovable you're inherently loved
completely loved beyond all the imaginations beyond all the ways
that you judge yourself so trusting in the buddha nature trusting in the
goodness in your capacity for awakening that yes
you too i too it's it's here it's here and
it's a trust that above it's above and beyond the personhood
it's trust in something that's above and beyond what you can control so much
yes there are things that we can do practices and we do our best we do our part we do
we hold our end of the bargain and trusting that the other part something that's above and beyond
what we can fathom control that yes there is this goodness
so trusting having faith fully trusting giving our heart to
giving our heart to giving our heart to
the goodness the beauty that shines and trust it's here trust it's here
even if at times we can't see it or it gets lost trusting that it's here
the second of the triple jewel the dharma trusting in the dharma
yes the amazing teachings the paulie cannon all of this
that's passed down yes this is pretty awesome and yet
another way of relating to it another way of relating to it is
trusting the lawful the lawful unfolding
of of the universe of the world this the lawful unfolding it's it's unfolding
according to laws according to to order that i don't understand
i don't understand but i trust but i trust
i trust it's goodness i trust it's goodness
and this is something that has been brought this this importance of this trusting this this
the universe the lawful nature of universe we see that both in in here in this practice and
so many different practices that it's important to to make that choice
albert einstein my hero one of my heroes puts it
quite beautifully actually that one of the most important lessons or one of the
most important decisions that we make in our lives is to decide
whether the universe is a good
is whether there's goodness in the universe whether we trust it or whether it's
neither good nor bad that god is playing dice with the universe is
what he said or that it's actually unfriendly we don't trust it
he said this is the most important decision we need to make because if we decide that the
the the universe the lawful nature that nature in its lawful way it's there
is not goodness in it it's there there's ill will and we don't trust it then
we use all our might we use all our science all our
energy in order to to defend ourselves destroy it there's a sense of distrust
that that comes up and we don't revere we don't appreciate
nature etc if we if we think that that the world universe dharma is
neither filled with goodness nor nor it will but it's kind of like ah
it's random random random then then he suggested that we end up
kind of feeling lost and nihilistic like uh whatever what's the point it's
it's all random and yet the third choice if we have a sense of
trust in the goodness and we can choose to do that if we have a sense of trust in the goodness
of the natural laws then we use our science our minds our
hearts to defend to defend it to support it to love it to
um and and we actually will be happier ourselves it turns out there are studies or
psychological studies that point to how
both personal or personal as well as societal happiness
is linked to the level of trust wow who would know who would know
that trust is related to both personal and societal happiness and it turns out societies that are more
trusting and of course than personal persons who are more trusting
there is more happiness more well-being and also there's links between
kindness that can actually increase level of trust and happiness so
kindness some there's a study that suggests that it
works as a link between trust and happiness so random acts of kindness maybe try this
out don't take my word for it don't take the research of this researcher don't
take their results for it see what happens if you if in some relationship for example or in some
community you start doing acts of kindness random acts of kindness to to notice over time how that might shift
how that might shift the the link between the happiness and the trust in between
this community and this relationship there are also more studies about the
connection between trust and oxytocin and how it modulates fear depression it's it's absolutely
fascinating trust giving our hearts to giving our hearts to
so the third of the triple jewel being the sangha again as i was
relating to it having this sense of trust in basic human goodness and humanity and
people around you with you and and humanity at large that even if people are expressing their
anger frustration and in the will that that there's still common humanity there is but in nature
in every single being and in fact every time you get into a car you're trusting
in the basic goodness of humanity there is this this this social
trust that okay i'm going to stay in my lane you're going to stay in you're like we're going to do our best and of course
your things could happen but you're going to do your best i'm going to do my best it's kind of a sense
of a trust if there was no trust in the world nothing would would ever happen get done
so much more i can say about that but but time is short so
so as a practice
trust can serve so in so many ways it can serve us in so
many ways and i invite you to to explore and discover it for yourself
in one way that it can show up is as an antidote to anxiety fear and
worry
and the practice could be trusting trusting that it's okay so if in this
moment anxiety arises having a sense of
perhaps spaciousness like actually can i trust that it's okay this
anxiety can be here but it can be held in a wider perspective trusting that it's okay no matter what
it's okay ah trust trusting in the okainess no matter what
similarly with fear which is often future oriented um i had this experience recently a
thought came up thinking and i felt a tightness in my chest oh
ouch what if this thing happens then i thought what came up for me was um
i trust that it'll be okay no matter what even if this thing awful
thing happens it'll still be okay there's a basic okayness and
and oh it just it just released to release the sense of
the sense of um fear or worry and in fact awakening
nibana nirvana one of the translations is fearlessness and this is the path of
fearlessness where there is no fear no matter what happens
what or what is happening like whether we deem it to be good bad
if we take ourself out of it with in a bigger sense of spaciousness
and having unshakable trust that gets developed as we practice more and more and more
this sense of fearlessness no matter what there's nothing to fear because nothing can truly happen
to you and i'll say that it may not make sense but there's
nothing that truly can happen to you if that's you it's all okay
you're really okay it's all okay and i'll drop drop that in as a zen koan
which i fully believe and i'll leave that be as huh and i won't try to explain it
because it's not one of those things to be explained it's it's to be experienced
and one last thing you know it's about um you know you've said fake it till you
become it well fake it till you make it but i like to say fake it till you become it
see what happens if you bring in trust if you bring interest if you practice it if you
practice it until you become it you really become it
so what do you lay your heart upon what do you trust
and i thank you all i thank you for showing up in the best way you've been able to
we've been able to showing up for ourselves for those we love for all beings
everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings
have fearlessness may all beings be free
thank you so much