so good morning everyone good day
and uh welcome to this meditation and your meditation
where you have the opportunity to meditate
both to both with yourself and with a large community
and the large community is meant to support us so that we are more inspired more content
to really sit here in our own direct experience knowing that there's a wide field of
support of mutuality of companionship
on this path and that you're not alone
but and no and knowing you're not alone the willingness
to put everything else aside the best you can to be right here not so much with
yourself but with the experience that's immediate
and current and i love the word current because it
means both in the present moment and the current of a stream a river and so here we are in the
current of time in that little window of it that's always moving
always changing always flowing that we call the present moment
so to
assume a meditation posture
and close your eyes and to give some
nice attention to the body to adjust the posture
it could be large adjustments small adjustments
just kind of get everything as best you can lined up in harmony enough to what's available to
you and your body to support being here
in the current of the present moment through the experience of the body
your body is always in the present moment your mind in a sense
seemingly wonders off in thoughts about the past and
future and fantasy and in a sense is not so then grounded
here in the present moment and so here to bring the mind
into harmony with a body with your capacity for attention
with awareness not so much awareness brought to the
body but allowing for the awareness which is in the body
and then within this body taking a few long slow deep breaths
to begin attuning yourself to the rhythm
of breathing the coming and goings of the in-breaths the comings and goings of
the out-breaths that here this body breathing
is where you'll be centered
and as you exhale relaxing your body
is a way to continue to center yourself here
now
letting your breathing return to normal
and from the inside of the body
noticing where there's tension and holding in your body
almost as if you're you discover the awareness that's inside the tension
and gently as you exhale to continue relaxing the body
relaxing the belly
the more relaxed the belly is the more it's part of the river of
change with no sensations frozen in time
the sensations of the belly just move and
appear and disappear flow by making room for the next one
relaxing the shoulders maybe a deep relaxation of the shoulders
the top of the shoulders shoulder joint down the arm
and feeling the vitality the pulse of life the energies that are
a little bit freed up when the muscles are not so held tight
and relaxing the muscles of the face
as if the face could sit back in an easy chair and just take a break
rest
and then within this body as part of this body
become aware of how the body experiences breathing
breathing in and breathing out
and to bring a little more careful attention to the breathing so the awareness is more continuous
with each inhale and each exhale
stay stay stay right there with the whole length of the inhale
and notice how the sensations that come into play are changing during that length of time
stay with the full length of the exhale notice how there are changes in the
sensations connected to exhaling
and not that you're leaning into it or staring at your breathing the more
you're settling back and opening allowing receiving
the full length of the inhale the full length of the exhale it's the receiving of all the changes
that come into play as you breathe
and then notice
the path that some sensations pass away
the sensations of inhale come to an end
as we begin to exhale some of the sensations within and inhale
pass away come to an end before the end of the inhale
just settle back and without trying too much or straining just receiving
appreciate the help how sensations pass away
and if they don't don't worry about it just notice the ones that do pass that are no longer here
they might return but just noticing noticing their passing
or noticing that they're now gone
so
without thinking or reflecting on it you can also open your awareness more
widely to be aware of any sensation
in how it passes notice what comes to an end
passes away and maybe it starts again but just noticing the passing of it
or notice the passing of our attention on it this week attention is on one thing and
then it pulls to something else
i appreciate all that is passing away
coming to an end
as you notice that things are in the process of passing away
whereas you notice they have passed away
appreciate that then at that moment those moments
it doesn't make sense to cling to anything to depend on something which is fading
away which is gone and see if you can appreciate that
openness that non-clinging to it
the freedom and space that that provides
that in and of itself when things pass away in the passing
there can be a feeling of freedom spaciousness peacefulness
in and of itself settle back into the flow of present
moment experience appreciating all the things that are
passing sounds sensations thoughts
anything that changes is also there's part of it that's passing away
chances are the thoughts that you had at the beginning are not the same thoughts you have now
those thoughts have passed away some of the sensations of your body that
were current at the beginning of the meditation may no longer be current something else
is what you were feeling has maybe changed
it's no longer here
appreciate the absence that's left behind
when something disappears or
no longer present
don't be a hurry to feel the absence appreciate
the openness the spaciousness the freedom that comes
when there's nothing there to cling to to hold on to or to resist
because it's no longer present
and as we come to the end of the sitting if you have some sense some feeling for
the openness or freedom that comes when something passes away
and how it doesn't make sense to cling to something which has passed away in the process of
passing away will pass away and even if it's inconstant it comes and
goes and comes and goes it's going can teach
us the value of not holding on
not expecting demanding wanting but allow it to pass
and to remain open and free
for the next thing to arise
and if the next thing to arise is another person
as you go through your day and you meet a person you communicate
with a person you think of a person
to become aware of that person in that
way of the way of non-attachment the way of openness receptivity
the freedom that can come when we don't cling
to what is passed away and then maybe we don't cling to what
arises we stay open
non-clinging non-contentious without need or demand
and this can become our gift to others that we receive them and know them
without the filter of our attachments and our demands
expectations bias prejudice
that in the freedom that we learn
we meet people with an openness a peacefulness
and maybe this is one of the gifts that we can offer the world
from our meditation practice because may it be that our meditation
practice not only benefits ourselves
it benefits others maybe at some point it's even more
valuable for us to meditate when we know we do it
for the welfare and happiness of others
what a gift to be attentive and aware and present for
others without any filters of attachment
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
so we're still lingering in the 13th step of
mindfulness of breathing that of observing
inconstancy and that there's something about inconstancy and observing it that leads
to the 14th step which is usually translated
into english as dispassion when we'll get to the meanings of it
maybe tomorrow but soon but there's something about seeing
impermanence that is onward leading seeing in constancy which opens
something up that allows something to unfold and deepen or move along and the very common
uh term in the buddhist scriptures is the idea of the dharma is onward leading and it's
armored onward leading to greater and greater freedom and one of the things that's very much
so a part of this onward leading nature is this settling back resting in
awareness in a sense and becoming more and more aware of the
transiency of experience the inconstancy of experience sometimes it's called impermanence but
as i've said that's going to imply for some people only means that sooner or later something will no
longer exist it'll die or be gone forever and well there's wisdom to that
understanding for sure and it can be freeing in itself in a certain way the core insight of the
buddha has more to do with the momentary and constancy of things that everything is kind of part of like
it's he didn't say this but it's like the inconstant waves or ripples
on um on a river that flows by and the little wavelets come in and go they
exist and don't exist and and um and they're in constant they're constantly being reborn
constantly passing away and so many of our sensations are coming and going coming and going
sometimes they stay longer than we wish but uh sooner or later they pass and
maybe come back again but to really settle in and really start
seeing more and more precisely or intimately uh closely how much of our experience is
it's a flowing experience the changing sensations is a things are peering and disappearing
sometimes in rapid succession or sometimes it can just feel like everything is just
flowing sand and the reason for flowing sand rather
than water as some people say is that sand is a little bit more like particular so it's a little bit more
particular sensations that have some kind of clarity to them whereas
water flows but there's no sense of a particularity to each molecule of water
whereas then there's a particularity or some people it feels like snow just everything is just like snow you
know or raindrops but the flowing sand and
everything and just really settling back and getting very still and then appreciating how everything is
arising and passing this was a very significant insight for the buddha was like his
in the ways described in some texts is like this was his big aha moment this is what he in seeing this he
realized this is the path to liberation with seeing this arising and passing the inconstancy
there was light there was wisdom there was clarity there was
the path opened for the buddha but in particular what was particularly both seeing
arising was very important for him but seeing the passing was very important as well
and it seems like the passing and the ceasing of things was even more important than seeing their arising
i know exactly you know i'm not sure but one reason is that when we know that things pass even if
they're in constant they come back we know that they're not permanent
we know that it's not always that way and uh and uh and that frees us from the
mind that it's that kind of unconsciously or subconsciously we relate to things
as if they're always going to be there and um as opposed to relating to them as being
oh this is just part of the flavor of the moment this is what's coming here now and in due time it'll pass and in fact
if i replay really careful attention to the particularity of the moment it's already
passing and then arising passing and arising and so knowing that it's not constant so
that's very helpful with things like suffering if we think that suffering is
durable stuck solid unchanging then it's very hard to get in
this like concrete it's very hard to get in there and try to do anything with it but we see it
as more as flowing sand or flowing water then you know you try to reach into
water and hold on to it grab a fistful of it it just disappears
through your fingers very quickly and um and so we realized suffering
doesn't have that solidity we thought before self all the things we think of as this
myself or we identify strongly as being this is who i am to to really see that it also has a
certain way a certain way of inconstancy that it comes and goes the sensations the
experience the thing the role the ideas the feelings the intuitions the
whatever it might be that we think is it this is myself we start seeing that too as part of this
flow and current of a river and we can't quite hold on to it and so there's these gaps
in the arising and passing there's this moment of freedom and the passing begins to teach us not
to cling not to grasp and we start seeing it's simply not worth grasping it's um and this is a powerful
insight that comes uh many many times in life all kinds of ways but in deeper and deeper meditation
there's a sense of well-being or freedom and openness lack of clinging that's so palpable
that we begin feeling that any movement to contract any movement to resist any movement to
hold on tight or to linger and be involved with
something that's going on um is a loss of some of the peace
we're actually better off in the freedom we're better off in this deep subtle quiet peacefulness and in that
we can learn it's not worth clinging we lose something in the contracting
we lose something in the resisting and it isn't that we are told you know
it's a good buddhist you should let go of clinging it's more like there's no
admonition like that it's more like pay careful attention become quiet and when you notice for
yourself that you're worse off clinging then don't cling and one of the lessons for
this that helps this is when we realize in certain deep states of meditation
that clinging doesn't work at all because whatever it is we're clinging to is also
constantly passing away constantly passing away and whether you don't have to be in that constant
passing away place in meditation to begin appreciating how much does pass away
and how in the passing away it is possible to tune into a kind of
peacefulness a freedom a spaciousness an openness that that kind of allows or makes room
for permits if we don't cling to the next thing that comes up
kind of allow it to pass and in the space that it leaves behind in a sense
just be open there be relaxed there take that in the next thing will
something else will arise but rather than being you know preoccupied by it or caught by it or
analyzing it or reflecting on or doing things with it allow the next thing to arise to rise in
that space in that openness in that field of awareness that just lets it comes and
goes and and in the process of doing that we
learn more and more about letting go we learn more and more
we're not holding on to anything and and
i need to charge my battery
and so because batteries also pass away and it's probably good
for the next couple of minutes to keep it going
so the um
and so uh this teaching on not-self that is often perplexing for people
is a teaching that makes more more sense when we understand that nothing qualifies as an enduring self
there's nothing that we can find inside of ourselves or in direct experience then we're really intimate and close to
direct experience not that that qualifies as oh that's myself because it passes as well and the idea
being that anything that passes cannot be an enduring self and
any theory any um for the buddha's point of view any doctrine of self any theory about
what the self is uh lends itself to a kind of reification a kind of solidification on what to self
that's not possible when it's things are constantly changing it's kind of like there's no place to
hang your hat there's no place to tack with thumbtack no place to attack
any philosophy idea concept theory about what the self is uh you know it's
like taking a thumbtack and trying to stick it into a river and have it gets you know stuck it doesn't stick
anywhere so any theory about self just doesn't quite stick doesn't quite work when this
constantly flowing in constant nature of experience that begins to open up in deep vipassana
practice so this the core deepest kind of
important insight of inside meditation is this inconstancy of phenomena the
changing nature the current of of uh phenomena as it flows through and arises and passes
here in the present moment so to settle back and observe that and
this 13th step is what's talked about and as we do that we begin feeling that the things that we
cling to have passionate lust for passionate
hatred for that all that kind of um
the ways in which we're driven or about things passionate around our attachments
just doesn't make any sense as well and it stops losing its allure it stops losing its enchantment we start
stop falling under its spell and then we begin observing
that we're less and less interested in clinging less and less interested in
lust and hatred and you know this driven driven attached kind of passion that can
happen like the passion for money or the passion for power or kind of the negative understandings
of passion and so then the 14th step is observing this dispassion
so um so then it will end and this will pass
as well and we'll make room for the next thing to happen and and chances are
it's simply inconstant and we'll meet again here tomorrow at the same time thank you