so good day everyone and
it's nice to see all these names on the chat and some of you i haven't met but i've met your name and your greetings
many times and uh thank you for it
and also thank you for all those those of you who are
going to be listening to this later i think that our community our meditation community
extends way beyond the people who actually show up here live
and and i appreciate so much that there's this wide circles of uh community that
gather around this practice together so the topic for today is respect
in relationship to the basic mindfulness practice we do
and also this week the focus is on the body
and so certainly it's valuable to respect the body and uh i'll talk more about that uh
during the little talk after this but for now i want to i emphasize that
as we attend to the body as we bring mindfulness to the body that it's also important to respect the
awareness that we're using the attention the mindfulness
with which uh we uh perceive this body
that we're aware of this body that we recognize the different aspects of the body that we focus on
and so i want to guide you through a little exercise that i've done many times before so some of
you have done it and even though it's more or less the same exercise it's not any different i don't think of
it as any different than you know just sitting down to meditate to focus on the breathing and we've done
it before but we do it again and again for for some of us for decades
and uh and so this is a exercise in respecting awareness or to say it
differently in seeing if we can find an awareness
that the attention a way of being attentive that's calm and that it's free of certainly hurry
but free of extra baggage so the awareness is very simple
and in such a way that we could think of it as being
um
there's a we think of it as being
awareness is very simple not uh avoidant or held back or
and not coming along with uh forcefulness or expectations
without uh aversion without resistance without
um just very very simple and so the exercise is to guide you
through this kind of simplicity that we might be able to do and then to
and then that can be used for attending to the body as different
body sensations come along in the meditation practice
so um
so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing the eyes
and
and then gently taking a few long slow deep breaths in
and then with maybe a little longer exhale than usual let there be a wave of relaxation
through your body and that wave maybe from the top of the
head as you exhale progressively kind of like moves down through the body just
relaxing softening all the way down to your seat
down your legs even and then do it again
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and maybe for next three or four
breaths on the exhale continue with maybe a wave like relaxation moving
through your body from the head all the way down to the feet
and then to
begin this exercise
bring your attention to one of your hands maybe the right hand
and if your hand is complicated maybe it's hurt or in pain or arthritis or something
maybe you can find something else that's more neutral maybe one of your feet or
maybe an elbow something that's you know doesn't have any particular complications with it
pain or discomfort
and then feel the sensations of this place feel the sensations of your of your hand
feeling the palm of the hand
the back of the hand
the fingers
and feel the simplicity of the sensations there
simplicity meaning without needing think about it or remember what it's
been in the past or associations and meanings you attribute
to it just in the moment now
maybe there are sensations of touch if your hand is touching something
maybe there's warmth or coolness
maybe there is tingling and vibration
sensations of pressure
of weight heavy and light
some sensations might be hard and soft
and letting the awareness recognize or know how the hand experiences itself
in a sense the hand doesn't have a name for itself is at the hand
it's just the sensations that it feels
and then notice how you are being aware
are you perplexed
are you eager
are you trying to do this like a school assignment
trying to do it right
or are you disinterested or even resisting
all these ways of being have an influence on
how we are aware how we are mindful
is your awareness pulled back and you're kind of watching or thinking
about the hand from the control tower in the head
are you intimate and close and touch almost like
you're in your hand
and can you adjust your awareness so that it's
very simple but clearly connected
to the sensations of the hand maybe letting go of thoughts and ideas
like you would if you quieted your mind maybe closed your eyes
to listen to a faint sound far away
and then calmly deliberately
slowly maybe move your awareness to the other hand
and adjust your awareness your attention your mindfulness
so it has as little extra baggage
extra attitudes expectations or aversions desires
so it's just feeling the hand
feeling how the hand experiences itself
respecting your awareness so your awareness can just be a simple
and clear as it is when it's alone when it's not
influenced by attitudes desires aversions
when awareness is also not under the influence
of ideas of self
ideas that i have to do it right or i'm doing it wrong
i don't understand right i'm doing it
great just simple awareness of the hand
so awareness respecting awareness is allowing awareness to do its work
without a lot of extra
and then calmly and deliberately
bring your attention to some sensation in your body
that's uncomfortable or unpleasant
maybe not dramatically so but calmly bring attention to it
and see if you can be aware of that area of your body in the same way you're aware of your
hand
in trying to respect the simplicity of awareness
without it coming under the influence of your ideas about the discomfort
your aversion or your
desires and instead letting your mindfulness
feel know how that part of your body experiences
itself as if it's allowed to be just the way it
is even discomfort is allowed permission to
be there in this simple awareness
if there is impatience or worry
or aversion maybe on the next exhale you can relax
that even for just for a few moments
relaxing reactivity and for a few moments just feeling
the area where the discomfort is to feel the particularity of the
sensations there the pulsing vibration
pulling pressure tightness
and then i'll ask you to move your attention one attention one more time
and this time con connect to your awareness your
attention to see if again you can move it calmly
deliberately simply so this simple awareness now
moves to experience that part of your body
where you accompany your breathing
feeling the area of area of your body where breathing is where you feel your breathing your body
breathing
and allow yourself to be aware simply of the sensations that come into play as
you breathe
maybe every breath is like a windshield wiper
that moves aside any extra attitude that complicates awareness
any wanting or not wanting judgments
like the windshield becomes for a moment clear
so the awareness becomes clear clearly aware of just the breathing
and as we come to the end
to evoke the metaphor of a windshield wiper on a rainy day
we're driving a car and it's raining
we don't talk this way or think this way but there's some truth to it
that as we use the windshield wiper we're trusting
the value of a clear windshield
we're trusting how we see when the windshield is cleared over the rain
you can feel the lack of kind of kind of trust or ease
if the windshield wiper doesn't work and it's raining hard and we have to really strain to
try to be careful driving probably shouldn't be driving
and when we use the windshield wipers to keep the window clear
we are safer driving but also
we become safer for the other drivers and the pedestrians
we offer mutual safety
and so if we are able to clear
the window of awareness from our preoccupations our
attitudes our fears our aversions and to respect
and trust a clear awareness in the moment
we become safer for ourselves and safer for others
in a sense we can give the gift of safety to others
and on this day coming out of this meditation
perhaps we can reflect and consider
how we can live so we bring greater safety to others
how can we keep our awareness present attentive
clear and simple trusting awareness
respecting our capacity to be aware
and in doing so becoming bringing safety in all
directions it may be more than safety
a dedication to live for the welfare and happiness of
others may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
so
so continuing today with the
discussing mindfulness of the body as part of the overall practice of mindfulness
and today it's respect so respecting the body
many years ago i saw an article in i think was mother jones
magazine and it was um the title struck me
the title was the body friend foe or total stranger
and so we have complicated relationships to our body and
some of it's uh been acculturated into us by the way that our culture relates to the body and
some of it has to do with life experiences and maybe what individuals have told us
about our body and our features and a tremendous amount of suffering
goes on in our society that's related to our bodies and uh you know to name just one there's
there's many i mean there's attitudes our culture many cultures have towards skin color
body size um height
um you know all kinds of all kinds of things that goes on
and um and so we live under the many of us can live under the weight of
thoughts preoccupations about our bodies you know my nose is too big too little my when i was
young i was very concerned about having too high a forehead and worried i was going to lose my hair and
in seventh and eighth grade and um
and i would spend an inordinate amount of time in class measuring
the distance from my nose to my forehead my my my scalp i would take my
finger like this and and kind of feel the distance to make sure that i wasn't uh you know
losing hair um i could probably also write a
maybe a somewhat interesting autobiography all from the perspective my of my hair
that my hair length what i've done with my hair over these decades of my life from
crew cuts when i was a little kid who um long hair
you know halfway down to my belly button uh later in my life and then
a shaved head when i was a monk and on and on
and um so you know what was that going on what was the associations the beliefs the attitudes going on
so all this idea of our bodies and uh
and um and so there's often an overlay on top of the body
of our judgments and ideas or preoccupations and one of the things that's possible maybe
discover the exercise of the hand that i gave in this last guided meditation
is to experience a difference between the hands experience of itself
and our ideas of the hand so the idea is my anger my fingers are too long too short my fingernails are
this or that or my hand is chubby or too whatever it might be
it can be kind of debilitating and depressing even some of these ideas and thoughts
but the hand itself doesn't have those thoughts and ideas the hand itself it just feels itself
what it is it has no judgments about what it is and to it's a tremendously respectful
for the hand to leave it alone to free it from our judgments ideas associations
and to experience the hand or whatever part of the body whatever's going on in our body independent of the culturation
independent of the life experiences even and the judgments the ideas and how we've been treated
and um and part of mindfulness practice is to give ourselves the gift give our body
the gift of allowing it to experience itself independent of all these other
comparisons we make comparisons with other kinds of hands what it should be and not be and um
you know there are um you know if um
you know if you know if i might feel you know because i'm hanging out with a certain group of people i might feel bad
about myself for being too short and just oh you know i'm too short and this is unfortunate and there are people
looking down at me all the time and you know i have to look up high and and it just happens to be that i'm
hanging out with the national basketball association basketball players and um and so in comparison i'm short
but you know in comparison to many people in our culture our society i'm a little bit tall but i kind of make a story and get
caught up in it these differences and comparisons cause a lot of suffering and i don't want to
dismiss and the suffering and the challenges that all this makes
we need to address it wisely but in meditation we can give ourselves the gift of
experience the body in and of itself free of all that if we really want to respect the body
we want to somehow be able to distinguish between the judgments the stories the commentary the associations
that we pile on top of the body from the body's experience of itself
which is often very simple and that can also be relevant when there's pain discomfort in the body
that uh we have predictions that oh if this continues you know i'll have to my knee pain i'll have to
amputate my leg and it'll be the end somehow and certainly there are dangers with the
body being uncomfortable in pain but sometimes there's not
one of the great things that can happen through the heightened sensitivity the respect of the body by really paying
attention to it in meditation is we can tell the difference between
pain that is a danger signal and pain which is not
and if it's a danger signal then change your posture but i'll by all means don't don't live with a danger if you're in
doubt of what it is change your posture don't stay with pain that way but if there's no danger signal
um i like to think of the the you know the pain is a signal there's a
message and part of that message is not that something needs to be changed that we have to do something but
rather the message is that we can offer it the medicine of awareness
to hold it in awareness um and then so part of this respecting awareness that we did in that last
meditation is that the awareness with which we hold
discomfort and pain needs to be simple needs to not be piled on with these
judgments associations fears ideas of self that kind of makes it so
much more complicated very simple awareness so for example uh if um if someone goes
around with a clenched hand because they're afraid or angry or something uh you could come with a maybe a play a
crowbar or something and kind of try to open up the fingers you get one open and then when you start the other one the
first one closes up again and you're kind of like kind of like
directly trying to fight the clenchedness another way to do it is to come along
with a loving soft caring hand and hold the person's hand and support it
and just let it just tell them here rest in my hand
feel your weight and let it kind of rest and settle into my hand and then slowly
people's hands will begin to open because they feel the support and the care
so the same way we can do for ourselves that as we bring our awareness
to the area of tension or pain perhaps what we're doing is allowing something to thaw something to relax and
open work we're maybe bringing making space for the body's ability to heal
to heal itself just like you know if the tight clan clenched fist
is kind of the i don't know what to call it but this metaphor the illness then we're holding it so that it can it
can so that's the medicine so it can release and relax itself
and perhaps it's not always relaxation maybe it's just simply that bringing a lot of attention to an area brings more
blood to it or the micro tensions around it relax
or we begin seeing that the experience of discomfort in and
of itself is different very different experience if we just feel it in and of itself
then if we see it through the filter of our ideas even the idea that it's pain
is kind of an abstraction oddly enough and when you really feel it directly
it's not you know realize that pain is an abstraction what's really happening is
there are sensations of heat or stabbing or pulling or tightness or pressure or
strong contraction and all these kinds of particular sensations that are intense
but they are all kinds of different sensations and we start feeling the particularity
of it then we're not overlaying an idea like pain which comes along with
a lot of baggage a lot of other ideas about what pain means some people experience
associate pain with failure i'm doing something wrong and that's a little bit debilitating to
have that idea and um and so just to feel feel it and be with
it the and then as we feel more deeply into
discomfort for example uh there might be a message there and that message might be that uh
maybe there's some some uh embodied emotion in that place stored up
from long time ago that maybe needs to be released and maybe it comes gets released with tears maybe it gets
released with heat or something else but it's i think it's nice within this
respect of the body respecting the body to think that there's a very huge difference between
the corporal body that we have when we're a corpse and the
animated body and the body that has sensations in it
and um and the sensate body is i like to think of it as a
messenger system it's always there to inform us about something
so and foremost you know simple as it's hot outside or cold take off your sweater put on your
sweater but everything is a message and and how do we read that message
and with mindfulness meditation it isn't so much that we're actively reading it
but we're allowing this respectful careful simple awareness to hold the
experience to be with experience so that we get to know it better and something
begins to happen the self-healing functions of the body can operate the message system of the body can
reveal something to us more deeply the and maybe what we're learning is not
necessarily about the discomfort or the pleasure that we might feel
but rather we're learning that the message is you're not free in relationship to it
you're caught up in it you're somehow attached to it or aversive to it and your awareness is not free your
awareness is not in that place of freedom and simplicity and that's where the work is that's what the message is
that that comes back to us so to respect the body
and and so in the instructions that we have here at imc
is to stay with your breathing that's the default that's where we develop some concentration
but at a moment's notice if some experience of the body is more predominant more compelling
which means that there's a tension set up between trying to stay with the breathing and this
other sensation the body kind of calling attention to itself you can just let go of
the breathing and then see if you can bring calmly deliberately a clear
simple awareness to hang out for a while to hold for a while this compelling
sensation whether it's pleasant or unpleasant and when it's no longer compelling you can either continue to be aware of it if
it feels like the right thing or you can come back to your breathing so respecting your body
it's definitely worth it and a friend foe or total stranger
i would a wonderful thing that can happen as we do this practice is our body becomes our friend
and we become its friend so may that friendship last for a long time
thank you