so good day good afternoon good morning
good night good greetings to all of you and
as a introduction to this meditation
uh i think that buddhist practice has a strong association with letting go
and for some people that's inspiring for some people it's not
and then sometimes instead of letting go
teachers will encourage us to let be and letting be is a kind of letting go
um we're letting go of our ways in which we don't let things be the ways that we
want to fix them or push them away or let them go even um
or hold on to them or you know all these ways we get involved with what's happening
and um and letting be is a very important part of vipassana
practice especially in the deeper quieter places of meditation
but these two uh uh come together in a sense for the i think very
i think very significant way we have to hold these two together letting go and letting be and in this
way that we let go of what is unwholesome
unhelpful and we let be what is wholesome what is helpful
we let go of that which isn't interferes with our compassion or
freedom or the best qualities of who we are
whatever interferes with these best qualities of ourselves that we let go of that interference
so these qualities can flow through us and we let be those good qualities
and so learn to dis distinguish between what is wholesome and unwholesome and how to let go is part of this
practice and it's a little bit simplistic but we
can understand that in in the teachings of the buddha what is unwholesome always comes along with
craving some form or other of compulsive desire
and and that itself also comes along with tension or or contraction
or straining or a obscuring of our wisdom our connection to
ourselves there is a closing down that happens
that what is unwholesome is un is unhealthy in a certain way or
has a certain level of suffering or pain inherent in it and as we get more sensitive in
mindfulness we recognize more and more that underlying tension
suffering strain pain that is in the unwholesome the
contraction and we have a better sense of this is what we let go of
that that we let go of the tension the contraction the tightness that's around this or the pushing that's
around it and uh what is wholesome has a flow to
it has an opening quality to it has a sense of being nourishing or a goodness to it or
rightness to it that seems to flow and maybe sometimes you know maybe even
radiate or glow or it just feels like it's there's an ease to it and i'm closer to happiness
than to certainly pain and suffering and so to learn to recognize those two
and let go of the unwholesome and allow the wholesome and those are the two move
very important movements of this meditation practice and we can't always let go
and sometimes what's whole especially if we let go in unwholesome ways like we don't like
something i want to push it away and um and uh
and sometimes uh even with the unwholesome it's best just to let it be because if
it really lets something be then it lets go of itself if it's
unwholesome if it's wholesome if you really let it be it often can grow or expand or morph
into something more beautiful so letting be is often a wonderful practice to do
but at times it's quite appropriate to let go and we begin the meditation that way by
a version of letting go which is relaxing
which is letting go of the muscular tension we carry
so um assuming a posture and it allows you to
be both alert and relaxed and gently closing your eyes
and take a few moments to gentle yourself into your body
to gentle yourself into this living body that you have
to center yourself here in this body
as if the body is your meditation hall the body is the location
that you enter to meditate
and then taking a few long slow gentle in-breaths
in long extended exhales
breathing in deeply enough so that you really feel your torso expand and stretch and really feel your
embodied existence
and in the exhale to relax and settle into this embodied existence
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale to relax the muscles of your face
around your eyes your forehead
in your cheeks and your jaws
and maybe there's also a little relaxing in the mouth maybe the teeth are touching
each other firmly can you let the teeth fall away from each other just a little
bit and exhale relaxing the shoulders
all around the shoulders a little bit around the curve of the
shoulders into your lower arms
the shoulder blade area
and then to
soften in the belly
and as you soften in the belly simultaneously maybe you can relax your
arms and your legs a releasing of the holding in the body
and also perhaps relaxing any tension or contraction in the
mind
and as you do so
quieting your thinking
as if you have a volume knob and you can turn down the volume on your thinking
softening in the mind
and then as you're sitting here
is there anything that would be appropriate to let go of
it's not needed right now it's not useful right now
and maybe even it's unwholesome
and chances are most of your thinking is not needed right now
even if thinking is about thinking about good things
if we can let go of it maybe then you can feel or sense
something in within that's wholesome some embodied feeling of
rightness or goodness
tender care love warmth
a clear sense of honesty honest presence with what is
and from within what is wholesome becoming aware of your breathing
as you breathe in allowing letting be what is wholesome
as you exhale let go of what is unwholesome
or what is not necessary now just here
quieting the thinking so there's a greater
almost embodied awareness of embodied wholesomeness
and if it's easy enough letting go of what is unwholesome
and if it's not easy let it be
that is similar to just leave it alone don't be involved
to let go or to let be
which allows you to be more present here
to let go or let be that is the question
and then the time comes when the question is
what to let forth what to express and allow for to move through us
in the end of a meditation in the end of any significant dharma
activity there's an ancient long-standing tradition
to dedicate the merit and for some of us the idea of merit
doesn't quite
it's not quite understandable maybe but the buddha wants to find merit
as happiness so to dedicate the happiness
dedicate dedicate the benefits that have come from our meditation together
for the welfare and happiness of others to have a clear kind of opening
and inclusion of the world
so that with all beings may we live in such a way
that the world benefits from us and especially those who suffer
the tremendous challenges of the african-american community in this
country the challenges of the asian americans the native americans
immigrants of all kinds the poor those struggling with drugs
poverty the list goes on
may it be that our practice and our good hearts and our the goodness
within that we tap into the wholesomeness may we dedicate it
to making this world a better place for all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so the topic this week has been refuge and uh
one of the probably most important or among the most important religious
sentiments of buddhists can have of course the word religion religious
doesn't kind of not in the vocabulary of some people who practice buddhism
but it is a kind of a it's associated with a deep um feeling
inspiration uh it's this kind of the source of inspiration or the quality of
inspiration that goes in the direction of
freedom goes direct of insight goes in the direction of aligning our life attuning our life with
the wholesomeness and the freedom we are discovering with the practice
with the deep sense of knowing and connectivity intimacy that comes with doing this
practice like here is a valuable way of living here is a valuable place from which
to be in the world that is i like to use the word deeper than
what happens to us when we're spinning around on the surface of things
and the stories and ideas and memories ideas kind of telling ourselves
preoccupations and thoughts based on our desires and fears and animosities
that to learn to let go of the spinning mind the agitated mind
the surface mind that we can often live in
and discover that there's a deep mind or deep heart that we can come from and i made that distinction between
wholesome and unwholesome and that one way to be taken
have refuge in action is we take refuge in the wholesome we take refuge in doing that which is
beneficial and for the for me the wholesome feels like
that comes from our depths the unwholesome feels like it's skimming the surface
of our life in our experience and it involves the surface tension and if
that surface tension can really relax and really allow ourselves to come from the depths then
we have something so good that it's worthwhile being our refuge
so what we discover through meditation practice is seen as represented by the buddha
dharma and the sangha and so when we go for refuge in the buddha dharma sangha
it's really a way of saying i go to refuge with the inner buddha dharma sangha that which
resonates with these beautiful external refuges and then
the buddha said make a refuge of yourself and so there's this kind of come here
don't be so looking outward and even when he you synonymously take be a refuge to yourself
he he then immediately followed kind of giving a synonym for that which
is uh be a refuge in the dharma and there's something about discovering the dharma within us we
become the dharma practice is to kind of not to make us different than who we are
or to brainwash us in some way but to free up what's most profound and
deep and meaningful so a source of support that's within us the dharma
and to discover in some kind of way we are the dharma when the surface tensions fall away
and this wholesomeness can come forth and then take refuge in our actions
you know be able to distinguish between wholesome and unwholesome and move in the direction of the wholesome as we do this
the buddha talked about two other refuges that exist and the first i'd like to
mention is the four noble truths and uh and in talking about the four noble
truths thinking of them i think of them as first and foremost deep
insight so we live in a wholesome way we settle we settle the surface mind the tension we'd
be able to drop down and really find a way to be connected and intimate with this lived experience
with a quiet focused mind so we really begin seeing more and more clearly what's
happening here and with that we start seeing something of the underlying process
the movement the process the unfolding of how our psychological and heart mind
kind of move and operate and we see something called the
four noble truths a very rich set of concepts that has different connotations different
applications different elaborations at different times um but at the heart of it one of
one one classic way of understanding it is that we really start seeing deeply deeply
deeply how limiting it is to crave to contract to be compulsive
to lose our freedom in a drivenness in our thoughts and thinking and our emotions and our desires and our
aversions and to really see that thirsting that's underneath it all
and to be able to see the possibility of letting go to see beyond it to the freedom the
other side of it and so that we're not blinded by it thinking this is what life is and freedom is just giving in to all our
compulsions but we see on the other side of it something that's really wonderful
the level of peace and happiness and freedom that is possible so it's an insight
to see and there are other aspects of this insight but the foreign to really see this
insight that shows us another possibility so to take refuge in
that insight this is right and then the last uh refuge the buddha mentioned is that
uh when we have this deep insight and we realize that
or not necessarily we realize but our heart realizes the heart is given the space to really
settle in and become whole and at ease and relaxed then there's a
phenomenal letting go or releasing it's not something we do
but a releasing a stopping and ending of something three things that we say
over and over again and so because we say it and i say it so repeatedly it um
kind of maybe gloss over it or oh yeah yeah you know this is kind of buddhist stuff
but it really lays at the heart of all unwholesome behavior
and so it's so significant and that is greed hatred and delusion that
they get released to let go and that absence of great hate and delusion that
is a refuge and to have experienced that refuge that protection that understanding that value
of being without greed hate and delusion without these these deep
unwholesome tendencies is is the most powerful refuge we can have
and at the end of his life the buddha said that he had made a refuge of himself
uh and what that means is that he had um he had done the practice all the way to
the this complete letting go of greed hatred and delusion and delusion he had done the wholesome things that
he had really connected to something really valuable within that led him to this deep release
and in doing so he made himself a refuge for himself he made himself safe for himself
and safe from danger and that's the possibility for this
practice for us is that when we really kind of go for refuge take this refuge we
are affirming the value of doing this practice we're affirming the value of
following the eightfold path the four noble truths following the path of what's wholesome
we're affirming the value of this deep letting go of everything which is unwholesome
and uh and then kind of putting ourselves on that path and we do so we make ourselves our own
refuge and the further we go on the path the um the more we um we will
um you know be create this great inner safety and
there's a way in which the greatest danger we have is not externally from us the greatest
danger is what how we react and and respond to what happens to us in our this life of ours
that the clinging the attachment the closing down the self-criticism the ways in which we send
arrows into our own hearts and to have made the heart made ourselves safe for ourselves
that there's a place of refuge here no matter how difficult the world is around us in here is a profound abiding
refuge that comes with the absence of greed hatred and delusion
and then finally is um in one translation in the sutras
it's not quite right it doesn't work use the word sarana refuge but there's one translation of buddha's
teachings where where it says the buddha says make yourself a refuge for others
the literal word that's used as refuge here is safety make yourself safe for others
and with this movement then once we discover the refuge in ourselves then
then then the opportunity is there that we become someone who is safe for others and
that is a wonderful quality not enough people in our world in our society have the sense of
safety and so to let go and
and then be able to offer yourself as a refuge as a support as a
compassionate caring presence for others so um
refuge so thank you all for this week and just a reminder
that starting monday i'll be teaching the next week but uh the teaching will also be part of
a another program that i'm doing for san francisco zen center and we'll be joined on youtube with you
know the people from the zen center program and um and that
and so i'm not quite sure how i'll teach next week it'll be basic bipashna teachings but i
think i'll try to shape them in a way that is in harmony with zen teaching in fact
the name of the program that i'm part of is called the harmony of zen and vipassana and now you'll get
more of that because the in the following two weeks after that it's a three-week program
um the abbess of green gold zen center and and uh former abbot paul haller
fushrader and paul heller will do the 7am teachings so you'll get a whole different flavor of
practice for a couple of weeks which should be quite you know enlivening i hope
so thank you all very very much and i look forward to our time together on
monday