so good morning here good day everyone
and uh here we are
and uh here you you are over there
you're there as you're here my there is here so i'm confused
with this worldwide way in which we're all present on this
globe at the same time so
to start this meditation to see if you could enter into
a meditative posture kind of from the inside out
adjust your posture maybe sway back and forth a bit
sway forward and back and see if you could maybe twist a
little bit and find a place where you feel
most aligned
with alertness and a kind of alignment of things that
your whole body can begin to be unified in harmony here
one aspect of meditation is coming into a kind of unity kind of a
harmonious whole where there's no divisions
no borders as if different parts of who you are made up
of distinct countries the mind the body the heart
the emotions these are not distinct countries with
sharp borders but you are made up of a unified
seamless whole where all of who you are
can be included all of who you are
has a place here
and then to gently close your eyes and
taking a few long slow deep breaths maybe as if you're breathing from deep
inside and spreading the x the inhale
expansion through your whole body
bringing your whole body into play as you breathe in deeply
and as you exhale
to let go
relax and settle into this body
having a longer exhale than usual but only as long as it's comfortable to
let go and release settle
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and perhaps a normal breath
maybe just maybe you can find that a light touch in relationship to
breathing
that the body that receives the inhales do so with a light touch
the body that settles as you exhale
there's a lightness maybe even a tenderness in the exhale
and the body breathing out
breathing in and feeling the activities of your mind
the energies of thinking
the feeling sensations of having concerns and worries
and as you exhale to soften the mind
quiet the mind
to light not lighten up
to maybe lift up release some of the
weight of the mind so the mind has a lightness
or at least your awareness is a light
touch
and then to settle into the body
breathing
and whatever you're aware of any moment when you're aware and
especially consciously aware
to let that conscious awareness have a light touch lightest of touch
there's no force an assertion and there's no hesitation
just lightly touching feeling sensing
the experience of the moment
and the metaphor of touch suggests that there's always it's always
in the present moment touching is always a present moment
experience and to have your awareness
touch and be touched by the experience of breathing body
of feelings of whatever is happening here
staying here in the present moment relaxing the thinking mind
quieting the thinking mind to be just here with this experience
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to allow your attention now and your thoughts to lightly
consider the people of your life
the people that are in your neighborhood or community
the people that maybe you're aware of through the news or through
communication of some kind
and gently to let your awareness spread out across the lens
as if it can reach out towards where all the people of the world live
and as you breathe to breathe in
the suffering and challenges and
that people live with offer to take it from them
not so it's stuck in you but so you can transform it on the
exhale with the blessings of your good will
the blessings of your well-wishing and care for others
and to always at the end of a meditation
to consider how the meditation practice can be for
the welfare and happiness of others
how whatever benefits we have received from meditation known or unknown
to have them be happily spread from us out in the exhale
out into the world
so we take into account the people we share this planet with the beings we share this planet
with and we offer our good will
our care and kindness our mutual
support and then you might say these words
repeating them after me maybe silently in your hearts
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may i contribute even in the smallest ways
to this possibility
[Music]
so this is the sunday after earth day so some some of us
sometimes will commemorate earth day not on the 22nd of april but
on the sunday following it or close to it
and i certainly would love to speak a little bit about
this home that we live with in this home that we share
and the care of it and uh as many many of you know the
prefix eco eco like ecology
means in greek home and so ecology is the study of our home
and i just finished the two days yesterday two days of the training that i teach i co-teach
on buddhist eco chaplaincy
the spiritual care in relationship to our home that we live in this home that
we all share together and you know when people live
together in a home roommates family um
there's a whole different relationship we have to the mutuality of that that home space
and the mutual care of it and keeping it clean or taking
uh you know creating an environment that's nice for everyone there caring for the
people under the same roof so we share this global home
and that we call the earth and um and in the way that i like to
see things in words it's an ancient game that buddhist teachers
vacuuming back into ancient india love to take indian words and and
do kind of not exactly etymology but to tease apart things
from the word and so it turns out that the word earth
and the word heart both overlap with the letters
a rt art and and the art
and maybe the meeting place of our hearts and this earth is in the art of living
and this expression the art of living um is a uh offers a kind of i think a rich
series of connotations that life can be a form of art
and uh more than it is work the work of life more than it is
a duty or a burden but an art is something that uh we offer
our hearts to our care our creativity our attention or
to detail and uh and so this earth of ours
do we live on it with the art of living and the
so one of the most powerful uh i know most powerful one of the i think powerful images uh coming out of
buddhism our relationship to the earth is
the image here on the buddha and all altar has this what's called the earth
touching mudra i guess i'm blocking it a little bit with my shoulder but if i
lean a little bit to the side i think maybe you can see that the buddha's
right hand is reaching down over his knee and his fingers are
just about to touch uh the earth or maybe he's just touched the earth and
he's pulling it away and but you can see the
delicacy the simplicity the very relaxed way in which the hand is draped over the
knee and it's a relaxed kind of going forward to touch it's not grabbing the earth or attacking
the earth it's a light touch just the tips of the finger is going to come down and touch
the earth and um i can't help but to
think of the image on the sistine's chapel where michelangelo has painted the touch of god on
the fingers of adam and adam is just coming alive being touched by god and and there also
we have this light touch this gentle it's not a gentle touch
and to live touching the earth to live lightly on the earth a light touch in
how we live our lives the buddha there's a wonderful verse in
where the buddha says that like something like head like a bee collects
pollen from the flower without harming the flower so um a wise person
walks through life without harming anyone or anything so
certainly you know we get our food our water we get our things to take care
of ours what sustains us from the earth but to do so in a way that it's a light touch that doesn't
harm the very thing that is sustaining us like a bee
so here the buddha is touching the earth lightly and the story of this is a it's part of
the mythology of buddhism you don't find this story in the earliest layers of the buddhist records
from the buddha's life but some maybe 500 years later after the buddha
you find this story that is really colorful it's i think of it as
uh you know this is a time in ancient the world where there was no technical or movies there
was no color photos and um it was a very much an oral culture and uh and so
it was orality that would paint these dramatic pictures of of um that were evocative in
in this imagery maybe not just to entertainment's sake
but also to evoke the emotions to evoke a sense of awe at this life we live and so the story
goes that the buddha was sitting on the ground and the statue we have behind us we
uh it's not sitting really on a pedestal that's he's meant to be you know sitting you know on
the ground on the earth um the night uh in the evening
before his enlightenment he was sitting there uh in his quest for awakening for freedom
for freedom from suffering to really get to the bottom of what suffering is
and to find a way not to suffer what a that's considered to be one of the great
noble quests to bring suffering to an end not as a
fantasy or a fable but as a real possibility for human beings
and that was his dedication and uh so in this fable this myth that
was the um there's a lot of things a lot of forces
that want to prevent the buddha from becoming free of suffering of discovering this peace and stepping away
from the attachments addictions hostilities of the heart that might you know that
have such a strong compulsive pull and demand on our attention and these are represented by mara
mara and mara's army armies and mara came with these and the
descriptions are you know like lord of the rings and you know the huge
evil forces that are marching across the plains and with all kinds of ogres and orcs and
all kinds of awful creatures and um huge elephants that must have been like
the um broadly tanks of the ancient world fighting elephants and came marching to
um to chase the buddha away to destroy the buddha to prevent him from becoming enlightened
and the drama of the stories is you know worthy of you know something like lord of the
rings and and and they throw every possible
um uh weapon they have at the buddha arrows and javelins and sharp
edge discs and you know everything these and um and the buddha as you see in the
statue is unmoved and relaxed and breathes at ease and doesn't react or doesn't
doesn't flinch in any kind of way and in fact all the arrows and spears as
they get flying through the air at the buddha tens of thousands of them the air is buzzing and
howling with all these armies and dragons and things that are just kind of
attacking the buddha and all the weapons turn into flowers and the flowers land
on the ground so after a while mara realizes that violence is not going to dissuade the
buddha from his calm his peaceful endeavor his calm discovery of where freedom from
suffering is and so mara comes with
his last weapon and that is to sow doubt in the mind of the buddha to challenge
him that or to claim to him you have no right to become awakened
you have no right to attain this highest capacity of human peace that a human being can experience
and and this idea you have no right so i
interpret all this as being all kind of psychological forces inside the buddha himself
that are casting all the forces they can to prevent him from letting go of this how he usually
has been the attachments don't want to don't want to be let go of and and his self-worth has
huge doubts whether it's appropriate for him to become awakened isn't awakening and freedom of freedom
suffering kind of a isn't it kind of an abandoning of people isn't it a kind of a
you know attaining something profound and beautiful for oneself and is that okay to do when everyone else is
suffering and there's all kinds of doubts that can come up
and um and so and one of the things that that mara says in sowing that trying to
sow doubt in the buddha's mind is that you have not
benefited people enough to deserve being awakened you have not practiced
enough generosity you haven't given enough to people in the world and
and without you know having lived for the benefit of others it's not appropriate for you to become
awake and um and the buddha says well then
i'll bring a witness who can bear witness to all that i've
done to support this world all the generosity that i've done
back over the many lifetimes i've lived in lived and he said i'll call upon the earth as
my witness and here we have this provocative idea that the earth
that's been around for so so long is the witness that keeps the record
of what we have done i grew up in the coast of italy and it was
remarkable to see it was kind of it was kind of beautiful at first seeing the islands
that around where we were lived and then to realize that they were
completely denuded of soil mostly bare rock because they had been
over farmed with grapes and olives 2 000 years ago or in the roman times
and all the soil had washed away and the over farming of them and nothing was left they'd cut the
trees and they'd farmed so the record is still there
and the records of the record of what humanity is doing to this planet that
the earth remembers it's here what do we carry with us but the earth
remembers also the good and and so the buddha asks the earth to
bear witness to all the generosity and all the benefit he'd brought people over his
lifetimes and to assert his right the okayness to let go of his clinging his
attachment to become free and experience the happiness of liberation
and and so that's when he reaches down he's going to touch the earth
to ask the earth for be that witness and i love this that
he doesn't assert his right for awakening he doesn't rely on his own feeling that
yes it's okay for me to become free that he's calling on something that's
larger than himself or beyond himself that for the support
for the validation for the encouragement yes
it's okay and if we see ourselves as part of the
natural world part of the earth we are the earth because we're part of the earth
we are made up of a hundred percent recycled material that has been part of the earth for eons
for a long time and in a sense were arise out of the earth and uh
as part of the earth and we are the earth that can see itself where the earth that
can hear itself through the earth i can taste itself and
then walk on itself and so here the buddha is touching the
earth this light touch of the earth and then the earth
in reply to bear witness to his right to be awakened and all the generosity and good he done
the earth has an earthquake and then the legions of morrow's armies
realize that the buddha has indeed
the right to be awakened and they get frightened and they run away in all directions
and they say the text says no two of them going the same direction or the same path
and they run run away and and then in the vacuum that's created
all these deities come to create light and celebration and
but the buddha just sits there and as he's sitting there uh he's sitting he's sitting under the
bodhi leaf tree the bodhi tree and as he's sitting there a few leaves
from the bodhi tree gently fall from the tree and land on his robe land on his lap
and there's no explanation about what this is about but it's a beautiful
imagery again again the buddha is in nature under the uh sitting at the
base of a tree and now this gentle movement of a
leaf of this body treated leaf that looks coincidentally a little bit heart-like
uh comes down and lands on the on the buddha and and sits there and and i take it as
being a little bit again this this intimacy with nature the natural world
that and then only then does the buddha see deeply into the nature of this world and
um and he sees something about the interconnected nature of this world and
paticia pada is that word for this and um and in doing so he becomes
liberated and free and and then there's a in this
technicolor mythology it's the whole universe gets lit up in light even the dark crevices of the
universe light up with the buddha's enlightenment
and then he gets up eventually and he walks he walks a long
distance across northern india to find people that he can begin teaching to find
people he think are ready for his teachings now that he's awakened and so his
awakening is not the end of the story but in a sense it's the beginning of the story and in this
ancient text that talks about this it's actually made up in three large chapters
and and the third chapter begins with after his awakening it's a
new chapter in this buddhist life when he goes out to be of service and to serve and to help the world
and so um we have this wonderful myth that uh is evoking
our connection to the earth as part of practice as part of the natural world
and um and the idea of the buddha sitting under the buddha trees sitting on the earth
touching the earth being caressed by the leaf that falls down it's also said in this
mythical story that with his awakening the flowers bloom and the other trees
around and those flowers begin kind of falling petals start falling as well
and so the art of living an art of caring living in such a way that
we live beautifully it's one of the associations i have with idea of art
certainly not all art is meant to be this way but when i think of the art of living i
think of living beautifully living with a beauty living with an ease living with a
creative source from within that is not burdened by distress
not caught in hostility and aversion not caught up in self-condemnation
and feelings of guilt not caught up in
giving up despairingly giving up but rather one that feels the natural
aliveness and lived life that wants to meet life wants to be connected
that when it's intimate and connected to what we love the most then we'll treat
it like a bee taking pollen from a flower without harming the flower and to
sit and sit or meditate and become free and then have access to us in intimacy
or a closeness or of a love for what we see and what we
what we do in the story of the buddhist enlightenment this mythology
the whole universe gets transformed with his enlightenment as i said the flowers and also fruit
bloom out of season music starts being played in the skies light
spreads throughout the universe beautiful things happen and for me
this is a metaphor for how we see the world when we become free
when we settle and become intimate and present and clear and we've cleared away the distractions and
preoccupations and fears and worries that we live under
the eyes with which we see the world it changes and we it isn't that the world has
changed and it's not kind of to be polyanish about what goes on in
suffering in the world at all but the eyes see the world tenderly the eyes see the
world and see beauty and or see love or see sweetness in this mythology it says all
the oceans of the world turn into sweet water when the buddha when the buddha be fresh water when the
buddha becomes enlightened and so there's it's as if everything
changes and there's a there's a beauty in this world
so to live beautifully and uh one of the ways that the it's lost often in english translation
of the buddhist teachings is the buddha talked about beautiful
karma beautiful actions in the world and the word he uses kaliyana
and and sometimes in translation as good karma and then there's bad karma
but in many teachings the buddha talks about not doesn't use the word good but uses the
word beautiful and so that our actions how we live our life
um has a beauty to it and a gentleness or a tenderness to it
and part of that is to live beautifully in relationship this home
that we have the earth and to care for to love for it to love
it in the art of living and um and uh the art of caring for this world
and so the ques you know but to do make that be kind of the to be
really a not a subsidiary thing that we do
a sideshow for us but to really live in a way that we care for this
world the people of our lives the environment we live in
the planet we live in so that it becomes it's not a duty
and it's not a burden it's not like we make ourselves now so much more busy
but rather it becomes a innate expression
of our love our creativity the artfulness from which we are living
our lives so that this is why we practice
we practice every day we practice all the time not because it's a duty not because it's
an escape per se but rather because it allows the best of who we are the
most beautiful qualities of who we are and the most richest ways in which we can see the world and hear the world
becomes um you know becomes natural for us becomes
where we live from we live from freedom we live from ease from peace we don't live from hurry we
don't live from greed and wanting and
filling our plate and attacking and we live with a light touch
and um and the earth will bear witness
the earth remembers and the earth hears and one friend of
mine says it's because the word earth begins with
e-a-r with here that we know that the earth is listening
the earth is listening to us watching us and certainly caring for us and
and it kind of keeps our record and perhaps when you're ready for your enlightenment
you can call upon the earth to bear witness to your right to becoming free
i think the earth will support us if we care for this earth that we live on may we care for it
together as if it is our home because it is our home
on this earth day earth week of 2021 so
thank you