so
the topic for this week is uh
what in pali is called
chitta sankara c-i-t-t-a
s-a-n-k-h-a-r-a
and it's often translated as mental
[Music]
formations sometimes mental dispositions
sometimes mental constructs
for this week i kind of been using the
expression mental activities
and it's those activities of the mind
which are
planning creating uh
imagining actively thinking about things
so a simple perception of
something uh seeing a wall across the
hall
the room here that wouldn't necessarily
be called an activity
that's just uh it is an activity but
it's
not a uh one of the formations or
constructions that we
make and what's fascinating the number
of things that are fascinating about
this idea of
mental formations mental constructions
sankaras
and is that one
is that many things that we
take to be kind of inherent or just the
way things are
turn out to be an activity of the mind
and so to give you one example
boredom when we're bored it can feel
like just
the thing that we're doing is boring
just this event the situation is boring
it is boring but in fact it's the mind's
activity that
creates the feeling the sense of boredom
it's a
kind of maybe even a subliminal judgment
evaluation
it's a holding oneself apart from
experience
it's uh it can be a resistance
it can be a loss of intimacy with
experience
and so there's all these things going on
in the mind
that construct that activate this
feeling the idea of boredom
and the idea that we're constructing it
where it's an where
we're kind of forming it making it in
the mind
uh gives us a very different orientation
to boredom
than if the situation is boredom because
the situation is boring the situation
is to blame and so we better just get
away or change it
but if we're responsible because it's an
activity of the mind
then we can practice with it and that's
one of the things we learn
through meditation is how to practice
with these mental formations these
mental
activities so that we're not caught in
them and not
pulled around by the nose by them but we
learn how to settle them or
become more expensive of them or freer
of them free of them even when they're
there
so with boredom one would turn around
the attention 180 degrees from the
situation that's boring
whatever it might be it's internal
external
and have the attention really look at
the boredom itself
and look it right in the eye and say
boredom i see you
and feel it and be with it and
experience it
and to learn how to kind of dissipate
the boredom because we really
see it clearly is very empowering
because it shows us that we don't have
to be the victim
of our own mental activities and that's
one of the great good news
of this buddhist teaching is that so
much of our suffering
has a relationship to the activity of
our mind
and and whereas we can't necessarily
change
always the situation in the world we can
we have some care and attention to
shifting how the mind is constructing
these ideas and concepts and
even constructing ideas of self that we
have
so it's a phenomenally good news if we
have the mindfulness and attention
stability to really see
how this works and um
and so mental activities to really see
it that way and learning
to tranquilize it calm them relax them
and now this tranquil mind
is considered in the buddhist tradition
to be a beautiful quality
so tranquilizing the mind is not just
becoming numb
not just it's not becoming numb at all
it's not becoming kind of less than
it actually begins tapping into
something that's uh really wondrous
amazing uh about what's available
inside that can arise with
this idea of a mind that's very tranquil
clean
transparent smooth easy
and and this points to uh
one of the problems in the english
language translating
the word sankara as formations or even
other activities
because uh some of those are just
uninspired
mental formations is like what is that
and it's kind of uninspired translation
mental activities maybe means a little
bit more but i don't think it has too
much
inspiration value in it i believe that
in the
in the indian context ancient indian
context the word
sankara that we're translating as
formations
had very positive associations
and and one of the early indian
associations
was it's a word that was used in the
pre-buddhist
brahmanical traditions to describe
sacred rituals
and in fact sankara sometimes is
it means to make something sacred
and at least that's what the dictionary
definition sometimes has
and and so this idea of of
of something sacred uh a ritual which is
uh maybe for some people very
heartwarming and a deep connection
has a very different idea than um
than just you know mental activities
because this inner this mental
activities of the mind
it um it's also it's it's a it's the
quality of the mind that makes things
and prepares things or constructs kind
of our
sense of self and universe and ideas and
all that
but as that gets quieter that movement
of activity mental activities
can have a quality of sacredness
reverence
wonder but also my favorite word is
beauty
which is a translation of a word in pali
kaliyana that is often translated as
good
and one of the places where it's
translated as good
is in discussions about karma karma
means action and the primary action that
we're dealing with
in meditation is the mental action so
mental karma
and and sometimes it's translated that
there's three kinds of
there's two kinds of karma there's good
karma and
bad karma and but the word for good
is kaliana which its primary meaning is
beautiful
and you get a very different feeling
about actions
if you refer to them as being either
beautiful or not beautiful
and and so this idea that
we can have the potential in the mind
or having the mental activity become
beautiful
as it is much more inspiring than simply
calming the mental formations or being
are experiencing the mental formations
so the mental formations the the seventh
step
of anapanasati breathing in experiencing
the mental formations mental activity
breathing out experiencing mental
activity
happens after
experiencing some modicum of joy
well-being and happiness and meditation
and that's important to remember that
all these things are situationals
contextual these steps of meditation
and we're not we're not supposed to be
in a hurry to get past it
and if you hear instructions that you're
not there yet
just take it in and and file it away for
the future
no need to feel bad that you're not
there
we're all going to be cycling through
these 8 16 steps and be at different
stages at different days
different minutes different weeks
because of what's happening in our life
and all kinds of situations
so the 16 steps are always um
you know we're some it's kind of good to
think that we're always beginning in
step one
and not be in a hurry not feel like you
have to always be
following this these steps that i'm
going through
i'm going through it linearly but um
the trap of that is assumed that you're
supposed to be right coming along
and i'm trying my best to kind of make
it come alive for you but
i've got to trust where you are and that
trusting where you are
is part of the beauty that we're
developing in this practice
that trust and trust appreciation
reverence
care love for oneself that i can just be
where i
am and practice there and trust that
this
process will unfold this anapanasati
process is a natural process
in its own way will unfold for you
no need to be in a rush or hurry through
it and so this trust is part of the
beauty of the mind and so
rather than seeing mental activity
mental formations
um as neutral uninspired kind of you
know
just stuff in the mind we're touching
into a capacity of the mind
to be beautiful to be wondrous
to be something that's maybe borders on
or feels sacred and uh this is the great
value of this practice is to really
discover a rich wondrous beautiful
uh inner life that really can
inform how we live in the world
um i'd like to think that as we discover
this wondrous inner life
we we get turned inside out and what was
inside is no longer inside but something
that
that we share with the world around us
so mental formations so as we continue
next week maybe you'll keep
this in mind that uh we're working with
a capacity we have for inner beauty
and inner something that's wondrous
that lives in us for sure
even though some of your mental
activities that you're living by
and that kind of are you're caught in
the grip of and you don't even know
you're in the grip of some of these
mental activities
might be standing in the way for now
of seeing how wondrous it is on the
inside for you the beauty that you have
so thank you for today and i look
forward to
continuing next week you