so good morning everyone good day
welcome and um
today's analogy for mindfulness of thinking
is to imagine that you are
you have a colleague you work full day five days a week
and you have a colleague that you work here that you work very closely to
close closely with constantly actually in communication about the job and what's going on
but the thing about uh working together you only work together on the phone
and because it's so constant you have a headset on and i earbuds or something and so
you're constantly talking and you've never met your peer your colleague
and know anything really about them but except for their voice and talking
about work and sometimes you get distracted and talks about politics or talks about
sports or the weather and sometimes it's hard to get back to work
but all you have is the person's uh you know the phone communication
and after many years of this there's finally an occasion where you can meet in person
and you're stunned to meet the person the person is so different than what i've ever imagined
different different body type different
all kinds of differences that different kind of clothes they wear different kinds of mannerisms different
kind of gestures different kinds of ways in which they look with their eyes
different emotions that seem to come through and you start you realize that listening to the person on the phone
you only had kind of like one dimension of the person and that when you were in person it's
multiple dimensions and and now you have a feeling for the person's emotional states and
and concerns of the day in the moment and how all the little subtleties and ways in which you're responding and reacting
and you're aware of the person's body and and maybe the body has some kind of
challenge to it that that makes you particularly sensitive and careful with a person
who knows all kinds of things so i think you get the idea that um
some of us relate to our thinking uh that way
that we just relate to the thoughts the content the ideas the stories
the plans and we're involved in the content of thinking and um
and and in mindfulness meditation you're finally getting to meet
the thinker uh the person who you're communicating with and talking with and all that of
course it's you but um you start becoming aware that this process of thinking
is not isolated it's intimately connected to
the fullness of who you are you're it's connected to your body all the
little micro tensions and movements of your body in response to thinking
the energy energies and temperatures in your body shift it's also related to your emotional
life and in fact emotions sometimes are the underlying
fuel for the thinking we do it's related to
all kinds of different aspects of what who we are our history and everything
and so to sit in mindfulness and respect your thinking is to open up your eyes
and away from the content of what you're thinking to the process of thinking
to the mat to all the different processes within you that are engaged and involved as you're thinking
then you can respect the full range of what's going on with um
with thoughts so to not get
and in fact they often say that it's often said it's a little bit not 100 true but
that content is not important for the process of mindfulness but being present for the process
and almost like you can ignore the content and sometimes when i meditate i imagine
that um my thinking speaking a foreign language i don't know
and uh and then i try to just like i would listen to someone speaking a foreign language i tune into so many
different aspects of what's happening as they speak because i can't understand the words the tone of
voice the speed in which they speak the energy by which they speak what they're doing
with their body the emotional kind of kind of background or tone which they're
talking so the same thing with ourselves to settle back
open up and respect thinking as a large holistic process
throughout our body so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and if you do this opening up your eyes to the process of thinking now
rather than what you're thinking how it's like for you to think what do you notice
is there any physical manifestation
expression manifestation of your thinking
is there any tension in your body
is there any emotions moods
that are part and parcel of thinking
if you open to the process of thinking
i mean holistically what is the space within which you are
thinking is there mental space or space of awareness
or is it claustrophobic
how much energy goes into thinking
so then having done that now take a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing as you exhale
relaxing down to your core
then letting your breathing return to normal
but continue now on the exhale to relax your body
whatever softening you can do in the face
letting the muscles of the face fall away from the bone
relaxing the shoulders
and perhaps calming the belly
letting it be calm and relaxed in your belly
and now again notice your thinking
has anything shifted in how you think are you calmer
quieter in your thinking or not
and opening up wider to the process of thinking
physicality of thinking as simple as where in your body is a
location for thinking for you if at all
any tension
and as you exhale relaxing
the physicality of thinking
noticing the mood or the emotion connected to your thoughts
might be a very subtle pleasant mood or emotion
or it might be something that's maybe not so pleasant
whatever it is it's okay for now just notice it
relaxing around your mood your emotion
a softening
and what's the energy with your thinking is it an insistent
fast strong or is it weak quiet soft
and perhaps you can gently calm your thinking
the energy of it let it settle
and then allow yourself to more fully receive the experience of breathing
breathing in receptively
receiving the inhale
as you exhale allowing the exhale
and if quiet gentle thoughts are in the background just
you don't need to be concerned with them keeping the breathing in the foreground
but if thoughts predominate open up
your attention to the process of thinking
the holistic experience of thinking in your body
your emotions
stepping away from your in the interest in the content
to see the hole
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
see if you can adjust your thinking
so that you can think kindly compassionately caringly
with a voice or with an attitude that's gentle
peaceful confident
and unassertive and to gently think thoughts of goodwill
well-being for others well-wishing
may the people in your life be well happy and safe
may the people in your communities be happy and well and safe
may those people you encounter today who don't know
may you be ready to think of them with goodwill
may they be happy
well and safe
and to spread out to the whole world gentle
thoughts of how wonderful would be no matter how unrealistic
it's not unrealistic to wish welfare and others
may all beings be well and happy and safe
may it be may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and almost as if it's second nature that easy and natural
may we contribute to that possibility
so here we are at the third talk
for mindfulness of thinking the day that uh
focus on respecting thinking i like to think that uh
in dharma practice we're learning to respect everything
i remember the surprise i had when i was sitting in the meditation hall
for a retreat next to a japanese and monk and at the end of the retreat uh
people came into the meditation hall to retrieve a little cup that he'd used during the retreat
for drinking tea we all had little cups and before he handed out handed away the
the teacup he bowed deeply to the cup and and i kind of wondered why i wouldn't
bow to a cup but um they kind of opened my eyes to a whole
different way of living living living with respect for all things
but to do so wisely so thinking it doesn't need to be an enemy for us
and we can respect it respect it deeply sometimes i think that thinking
is um you know what we usually think of as thinking it may be the thoughts that the
words the inner voice that we speak or the images if we see more in images
that pass through our mind that they're kind of the tip of the iceberg
and we're mostly kind of involved with the tip of the iceberg but uh there's much more to it or maybe
there's a metaphor which is not so icy cold maybe um
it's um you know going to going to a city park
and at the entrance way there's a little lawn and you spend all your time just on the lawn
and it's just a little part of what this park is all about and the natural preserve perhaps and someday
you go into it and you discover there's so much more to it so
the um thinking you know there's there's a surface the content the content of the
thought and it isn't necessarily we're respecting the content of the thought i
think some content of thinking is a little bit nonsense and sometimes worse maybe it's very
unfortunate to certain some content but there's no need to berate oneself or feel bad about oneself for what the
content is unless we act on it and then if it's nonsense or if it's
actually harmful it's very unfortunate but what we learned to do the way we learn
to excuse me for a moment
the way we learn to respect thinking
is to not be so involved in the content not be glued to it
not invest so much important in the content especially for purposes of meditation
but rather bring mindfulness to the holistic experience of
of uh thinking and so the art of learning
all the component parts of thinking and this is a part of mindfulness in general that
to begin seeing things or to think in terms of components
composites that things come together from causes and conditions different things exist together in
relationship to each other and when we start seeing that we stop kind of reifying or
getting too focused or fixated on one particular part of the whole
so we're thinking there is one of the most really important areas of thinking if
it's really obsessive thinking you're really caught in the grip of thinking strong thinking
is there's chances are high that there's an emotion which is fueling it
or with out of which it's coming so planning more often than not arises out of some
kind of apprehension anxiety remembering something can come from a
variety of things it can come from happiness and delight it also come from a desire to
to relive it maybe because we're lonely now and we want to kind of remember
they can come from anger and resentment that you know review the offense over and over again as a way of
somehow making the past better
and you know making the past better is kind of a hopeless case
past won't change so much but we can shift how we think about it we can shift how we relate to it
and so if we're caught in the grip of resentment and that's what's fueling the thinking
then we want to bring respectful attention to that resentment is respectful attention to the anxiety
whatever it might be the loneliness that might be fueling it the discomfort
that we might feel that kind of music discomfort which is kind of like producing the tension of
thinking so each thing to be respected
means to take give it a second look to feel it to be present for it
and i sometimes think of thinking the content of thought as um like a messenger that's saying
nurse i see it as a signpost sometimes it's uh that this uh the sign is
pointing in a direction what's written on the sign is not that important what's important is the
direction the sign is pointing and so thinking is pointing back to the emotions out of which it arises
as we feel the emotions and get to know them do mindfulness of emotions as we talked about last week
then it might be a time to respect that deeply it might be a time to
feel it physically feel the physical manifestation of the emotion and that's also a place where you start
noticing the tension in the body that's related to thinking
because the more tension there is in the body the more obsessive the thinking will
become usually there's a way in which tension in the body
is creates a kind of a mental tension
that presses out thinking or or makes thinking more desperate or more important or more insistent
and there's a kind of reciprocal relationship between how much we're invested in the content
of the thought and the tension in the body and how much tension we have in the body
and how much we are caught up in our thoughts and it's a chicken and egg thing it's hard to know which one comes first
but as we get quieter and quieter in meditation sometimes we can see some of that
we can see a tension arise in the body and lo and behold certain kind of thoughts arise
or we feel certain thoughts arise and we notice a tension that follows in the body
so all this kind of opening up to be more holistic has a number of wonderful functions
one is we learn to wear to place our attention mindful attention and
so it's it's onward leading it's productive it helps us become free
and sometimes putting the attention into the content of the thought just encourages to think more and more
but to put the attention on the emotion underlying it begins to allow the emotions to settle
or to open up or to be processed it also means we're not feeding
our thinking with our interest with our involvement with them
and thinking generally will start to dissipate if we're not directly interested in them
and involved in them uh if we just kind of let them go um
there's this wonderful teaching and some of you know this better than me i'll never never remember
that the number but there's this idea that emotions never last more than some like 90
seconds unless we're feeding them and fueling them and
so it's relatively short it's kind of surprisingly short the researchers have found and i have no
idea whether that's true or not but i certainly know there are times when if i bring my attention to my emotions and
really be present for it it seems to kind of relax pretty quickly
but thinking is even faster that uh if we no longer fueling the
thoughts they they last a millisecond it's very short and so the perpetua perpetuation of
thinking has a lot to do with how we're feeding it and involved in it and engaged in it
and this idea of respecting thoughts is to open up more widely to feel
the wider ecology of thinking that's going on the emotional the energetic
the physical the motivational sometimes it really helps to notice what motivation is
behind the thoughts uh if we might be planning a lot maybe the motivation is to make ourselves safe
when we show up at some event and to recognize oh that's the motivation
um then and feel that maybe that needs our attention it's like a signpost pointing
back and then oh i'm anxious let me feel my anxiety let me practice
with that and breathe with that and as we do this mindfulness and respect it begins
opening up the space in the mind or the space in the heart so there's more space more room
to hold all things to hold our emotions hold our thoughts
without being glued to them or trapped in them
and this idea so it's a wonderful idea this idea that we're making space
rather than getting rid of things rather than fixing something we make more and more room in space
and then lots of things don't have to be a problem uh when there's lots of space for them
and when we're claustrophobic then it's like we're troubled by it and pushed around by it
so this idea of respecting things both is valuable for what we're paying attention to but also it's a
it's a means by by just kind of stepping away and
opening up and holding things with a wide open a mind wide open heart
and uh and not being troubled by what the content is and finding our home
in the kind of a spacious open relaxed uh um field of awareness field of
kindness field of respect field of freedom that uh that holds all things
and this is a really wonderful thing to open up to this wide
kind of scope of attention that where there's freedom
to be found without changing anything and
and it's a power it's kind of a superpower to do that and um it's uh changes kind of as a game
changer in many ways for our life so um
may you respect your thoughts no matter how difficult they are or painful they
are maybe they're messengers pointing to something deeper inside of you they're
the tip of the iceberg that you really what you want to tip of the
you know whatever that uh you really want to start dipping down into the
fullness of who you are and really seeing there it's a way of respecting yourself
to really take time to get to know all of who you are not just the voice that's thinking in
the head so um thank you all very much and
we'll continue this process tomorrow