good evening again
good morning good afternoon whenever it
is you're
listening and a warm welcome
so today i'd like to talk about a topic
is
something that um maybe for some of us
isn't our favorite topic
let's say this i know it certainly
wasn't my favorite topic
before i actually kind of shied away and
felt uncomfortable with it and
maybe even a little bit angry about it
and
some kind of way
and that is to maybe build a little bit
on what this
on the guided meditation this idea of
confidence
that comes as we the more we practice it
grows and really can be a support for us
but that's not what was making me angry
or people shy away from
but sometimes the word faith is used
rather than the word confidence
sometimes we might also use the word
trust or
conviction
but i thought i would unpack this a
little bit for us
and explore and examine and tease apart
some of these different parts or these
different elements of faith
trust confidence conviction
and specifically to say that the topic
of faith can be difficult for some
people because
it's associated with mindless
belief perhaps with this idea
that we have to proclaim allegiance
to a particular doctrine or creed or
something
and not only do we have to proclaim an
allegiance
but then we will be judged by this judge
ourselves or maybe we're judged by
others
by one's degree of
compliance or one's degree of
belief or something like this
so when we use faith in a buddhist
context it's
very different from this very different
but it's natural of course that we might
um
have some different associations with
this word
with the whole concept the whole idea
of faith
but faith is a part of buddhist practice
it's just not
this kind of faith where that's we have
to
pledge an allegiance to a doctrine or
something like that
but um maybe i'll start with this
little a quote of bef that the buddha
gave
before he was a buddha
so he talks about faith here but clearly
it can't be
faith in buddhism or faith in
him or something like this because he's
not a buddha yet
when he's saying this and
where it's in the context of
the commenting how the buddha wished
everyone a better life he wanted people
to have a good life
and it was summarized in this verse
faith morality learning intelligence
restraint and justice much good else
wealth possessions partners and children
flocks kin friends colleagues
health beauty and happiness
these things he wished for others that
they might
keep and never lose
so faith is here at this beginning of
this long list
of all these desirable things that
people might have in their life and
he was wishing that everyone might have
this
so clearly faith here isn't um
isn't maybe what we're thinking it might
be instead it's
goes with the possessions partners and
children and health beauty and happiness
so what what is faith and the way that
it's
here and how might we consider it in the
buddhist practice
well i'd like to suggest that faith has
different aspects maybe you won't be
surprised to hear that
and we can consider some of these
different aspects
in one aspect is that it has
a relational practical
cognitive value to it
that is it provides motivation to
do something that it's underlying like
activity or
action it's like a readiness to do
something
with the belief with the confidence
that this thing that you're going to do
will lead to
go in a particular direction that you'd
like to go
so one aspect of faith is kind of a
mobilizing force as a way to
stir up the energy maybe to
do something because you have a belief
that what you're about to do
will be supportive for you and your
practice
and we can see that um in in one
particular
um quote from the dhammapada
where faith is associated with diligence
and it's uh um
it's contrasted with laziness and
sluggishness
so this um two little verses here in the
dhammapada
says whoever lives focused on the
pleasant
senses unguarded and moderate with food
lazy and sluggish
will be overpowered by mara as a weak
tree
is bent in the wind so overpowered by
mara
mara we can understand is this
personification of things that get in
the way of awakening
so being focused on the pleasant senses
unguarded
and moderate with food lazy and sluggish
these are help or help create the
conditions in which
things will hinder will be an obstacle
to greater freedom and then the next
verse
says the opposite whoever lives
focused on the unpleasant so
we're not saying that we have to focus
on the unpleasant all the time
it's just uh countering focused on the
pleasant
so it's this recognition that there's
and unpleasant and neutral in our
experience
but sometimes we're always only focused
on the pleasant
whoever lives focused on the unpleasant
senses guarded
that means to not always be
if we know that it's the equivalent of
if you know you don't want to eat a lot
of cookies not going down the cookie
aisle in the grocery store
if you know that you really need to
sleep more
it's not starting that movie at
midnight that you're going to watch or
something like this
whoever lives focused on the unpleasant
senses guarded
moderate with food faithful and diligent
will not be overpowered overpowered by
mara
as a stone mountain is unmoved by the
wind
so in this verse faithful and diligent
counters in the earlier verse lazy and
sluggish
so it's this way in which we can
consider faith as a way that
provides some motivation some
inspiration
to act to do something
it's a it's maybe it's a um
aligned maybe with an inspiration has a
heartfeltness
so it's not just an action
because um we feel like we have to do
something to make something unpleasant
go away
but it's more of a feeling like yeah
this this
is the direction to go this is the
direction for greater freedom
greater peace greater well-being
so the practical volitional
cognitive aspect of faith
and then another aspect of faith might
be this heartfelt
this emotional affective aspect of faith
that is maybe this feeling of reverence
devotion love esteem
this more of a heartfelt
this um
yeah what is how what is a way to
describe
devotion but not devotion with a sense
of
zealots or um
or that's blinded or something like this
but with a real commitment
maybe a warm commitment something like
this
maybe this feelings of confidence that's
coupled
with an attitude of devotion and
commitment
and it's maybe this is like we can think
of a belief
in something
so this heartfelt
confidence a warmth a warm confidence
and we can find um a short
uh little verse that also talks about
this
aspect of faith
and this uh verse takes place in the
context there's a number of
brahmins so these are non-buddhist they
aren't the followers of the buddha
instead they're
priests of the dominant religion at the
time
and they go to the buddha and they ask
him questions and
after the buddha answered all their
questions they
were so inspired and touched by what the
buddha had to say
that they became his followers
and one of the brahmanas pinga
he returned from after seeing the buddha
and he told some of the other brahmanas
how wonderful the buddha is and one of
these other brahmanas
said to him but ping pinga
why don't you spend all your time your
every moment with this person gotama
is the clan name of the buddha
and pinga responds this way
my faith joy mind
and mindfulness do not go away from the
teaching
of gotama whatever direction the one of
great wisdom goes
to there is the place i incline
so according to how his heart and his
mind are
inclined towards this direction of the
buddha
even though he's not there all the time
with him like physically there but
has this connection this commitment
we might say this word devotion
so that's another aspect of faith it's
not a devotion that asks us to
get rid of our intellect or our rational
thinking or
unre reasonableness it's not a devotion
that
asks us to give up our
autonomy but it's a warm
hearted commitment that's borne out of a
recognition that there's something
special here
something that's worthwhile
and then how do we know that or how do
we tune into that is maybe the third
aspect of faith
which is more the intellectual cognitive
mental
aspect of faith and this way we might
define faith as provisional knowledge
that is we have this belief that
so maybe it's not so much belief in but
belief
that it makes like this belief that this
is true
it makes sense to me it's consistent
with my experience it's consistent with
my understanding
but i don't know it first hand myself
right now
so it's a kind of provisional knowledge
a provisional
understanding that implies a
willingness to accept on trust
certain teaching certain propositions
that
we can't experience for ourselves
directly at this time or we haven't yet
so this willingness to accept on trust
so it might lack adequate it might
lack adequate evidence at this time but
it isn't irrational it's not
necessarily inconsistent with our
experience
we could see how perhaps there could be
experience that leads that direction
through practice we a big part of
practice is where we
make this transition from belief into
knowledge
maybe you had this certain belief that
meditation practice would be helpful
and would be a support and
use initiated started meditation
practice
through some before you had the first
experience there was something
that supported you encouraged you
and then you did some meditation
practice and
and said yes there is something here
that's valuable
and continued so maybe your confidence
in the practice grew maybe your trust
and the confidence grew
so there's three different aspects of
faith
one is you could use this word practical
but
it's kind of supports action
the second one is an emotional maybe a
heartfelt
commitment or confidence
the third is intellectual like a
provisional knowledge a belief that
something seems reasonable but i don't
have direct
experience yet and when we think about
it
in fact there's so many things that we
have this provisional knowledge for
right
black holes for example like okay
it seems consistent that there might be
this
place and space where gravity pulls so
much
that light can't escape but
you know i i'm not a physicist i
don't know this for myself but i'm
trusting that
uh those people that are talking about
it know what they're talking about
seems consistent with what i do
understand about physics
so there's so many things like this
right that we
have this i'm using this expression
provisional knowledge but
there's a little bit of trust we have
trust or or this confidence that what
they're saying makes sense even though
we don't have this direct
experience
so i've been describing a little bit of
some of these aspects about
faith but another way that we can unpack
or examine
or look at faith is well what function
do we see it playing in buddhist
practice what role does it do
how do people use it how is it
supportive and
rather than just describing what it is
how is it
show up in people's lives how does it
affect people
so there's one way it's a little bit
about in the guide meditation
is this recognition that this
confidence that we can gain through
having more and more
experiences can provide
encouragement inspiration
dedication and not in a zealous way not
in an
overt exaggerated way
but in a way that helps us to feel a
certain amount of
reassurance or a certain amount of
contentment
yeah this is this makes sense to me this
is a direction i want to go
my my heart is in here too
it's not just my mind but my heart
so one way that faith shows up
in the buddhist teachings is in a number
of lists
some people are like oh no please not
the lists
i'm one of those people i like the lists
i kind of
enjoy them but uh
one thing that i'll point out i'll share
i
few lists with us
and one of maybe is the obvious one is
um
i did a list of the five faculties of
course faith is the first element
in that list faith energy
mindfulness concentration and wisdom
you'll notice that faith is first and
wisdom is last
so there's maybe two things i'd like to
point out here
faith is not standing by itself
it's with four other elements
so when the buddha talks about to
cultivate and develop
the faculties it doesn't say
cultivate and develop faith by itself
it's with these other qualities
and in the beginning of this talk i give
this long list
of things that the buddha was wishing
for other people
and faith was part of a collection of
positive things
and that's the case this is how faith
always shows up
is part of a group of practices or
qualities
or things that can be cultivated or
developed it does not show up by itself
and very often i think actually every
time it's the
first element in the list which suggests
that it's a starting place
so faith is not the end it's not the
goal of practice it's a support
and it's a place to begin for our
practice
so i'd like to introduce you to
some maybe some other lists that talk
about faith
the five factors that support meditation
it's also called the five factors for
exertion
and sometimes these get translated
these two different ways
the first element is faith the second
element is
health that's defined as being seldom
ill
or afflicted and having an even
digestion
so faith health honesty
honesty here is defined as revealing
themselves as they really
are to their teachers and fellow
practitioners
so completely honestly knowing oneself
and being able to share that with others
who are
wanting to support you in your practice
so faith health honesty for this
energy we um
are familiar with this it's a in
a applying um a little bit of effort
towards abandoning those things that are
unwholesome and cultivating those things
that are wholesome
so a certain also maybe a steadfastness
or perseverance
and then wisdom so here we are again
wisdom is the last one and faith is the
first
these five factors that support
meditation
and faith is one of these elements
and then here's another list don't worry
this the whole talk is not going to be
just filled with list after list
but i wanted to share one more is it
five
qualities that allow a person to live
happily
we all want to live happily and if those
of us who have meditation practice we
want to
have supports for meditation so
five qualities that allow a person to
live happily
it says in the suta if a person has
certain qualities they will live happily
without
distress anguish or fever
i think they of course don't mean fever
literally it's more
metaphorically without getting agitated
and
upset about things okay so what are
these five qualities
faith is first conscientiousness
prudence and then here's energy
and wisdom
so this list these um what i'd like to
point out here is that
faith is just a support for our practice
as different elements it's not the
purpose of practice
it's not instead of practice
but instead it's a way to help us find
our way with cultivating wholesome
qualities and abandoning unwholesome
qualities
our way with allowing
wisdom to rise
and then maybe the last way
that i'll look at faith here so first we
talked about there's these different
aspects and
then we talked about what function does
it have and it functions with other
qualities to
be a support for our lives
and then we might ask well is it ever
actually flat out defined
anywhere and the question would
with the answer would be yes sometimes
faith is defined
as a person
as a person of faith a person of faith
is one who places faith in the
enlightenment of the tatakita
places faith in the enlightenment of the
tataugata
many of you know tattogata is how the
buddha speaks of himself
this is faith in the boot and the
enlightenment of the buddha
there's two different ways we can
understand this
one that enlightenment is possible
the enlightenment did happen
or we might have
faith in the buddha's
enlightenment that what he is teaching
is comes from a place of
awakening a place without greed without
hatred and without delusion
so this faith that enlightenment exists
or maybe faith in the buddha as a
teacher
maybe each of us gets to find our own
way with this
and maybe it changes at different stages
in our practice or
different circumstances
but i like to think about this sometimes
that
how both are true the paulie supports uh
interpreting it either way
faith that enlightenment exists
and faith in the buddha as a teacher
this can be a support for us maybe it's
some provisional
knowledge maybe we see there's
it makes sense we can see how we have
more and more freedom and ease with
the more we practice maybe there's
some some heartfeltness a commitment to
the buddha and his teachings maybe when
we take
refuge in the buddha dharma and sangha
there's a heartfeltness
and maybe faith that enlightenment is
possible or
even in the buddhist teachings supports
us
helps us to continue with meditation
practice
continue with uh listening to dharma
talks
so in this way faith i'll have to say
maybe this is one thing that i love
about
studying and practicing together is
there such a depth
here there's so many different ways or
like a richness
it feels um
a certain like juiciness if i'm allowed
to use that kind of language you know
like an aliveness
faith it's we're invited to
explore and examine and
investigate these three different
aspects of it
how faith might work with other
qualities other factors
to support awakening support our
meditation practice
and to support living happily
and may our faith be a support for us
so that we can be a support for others
of course we're not just practicing for
ourselves but
for others so that we might make our
communities and
those we come in contact with
a place where people can bring their
best versions of themselves
so thank you