hi thank you uh we'd like to welcome amana to our imc sunday dharma talk
and uh a little bit about ramana amana brembi johnson is a core teacher at the east bay meditation
center in oakland california and a guiding teacher for the center's
spiritual teacher and leadership training four decades of contemplative practice in
multiple traditions contributes to a form of teaching meditation guidance and mentoring
that offers a diverse range of access to practice amana's life work emerges from the
intersections of spirituality social justice body awareness and intuitive creativity
thank you for joining us
thank you kevin and welcome everyone
and thank you for putting the chant back on during the break it's so soothing i loved hearing it
again so um
as we come together today um i'd like to take a moment to acknowledge
the land where we are and the indigenous the indigenous people who live
on this land i acknowledge that i am on traditional
unseated land of the first people of oakland the lausanne aloni people both past and
present who speak that your chin your language
i'd also like to offer a lineage acknowledgement of our practice of
buddhism which is an asian heritage and tradition
a tribute attributed and and and it comes to us through
500 years of written language
of unwritten language and was recorded in sanskrit and pali
before other language translations
and let it be acknowledged that these practices were preserved nurtured and handed down for millennia
before reaching western shores and western languages
that in many ways the people and cultures of origin can and in many
instances have been erased much the same way that the people who
originally inhabited inhabited these lands have been
erased so let us remember our ancestors and the ancestors of this
land who survived pandemics
the destruction of their known world and their ways of living
may we hold their names dearly in our hearts and minds
and may this acknowledgement serve as a reminder of our inextricable
connection to the practices we share and the places we inhabit
as well as a reminder of our connection to the earth across species and across
time
before i go into the talk i'd like to share with you an excerpt from a public notice sent
from the east bay meditation center in regards to the rash of violence
against asian and american asian pacific islander communities
the east bay meditation center expresses our collective grief
and outrage at the ongoing violent targeting of asian and
asian americans and in the wake of the most recent tragic attack
in atlanta we stand in solidarity with asian and
asian americans in beloved community
these violent acts of hatred are arising due to the current and
historical oppression of asian americans in the u.s
they are the direct result of our nation's deep roots in white supremacy
imperialism and xenophobia
i'd like to invite you all to participate in a moment of silence
as i recite the names of the beings whose lives have been senselessly taken during the atlanta
mass murdering spree which happened just on tuesday
you may choose to place your hand over your heart or slide the eyes closed
or simply just be present
soon chung park yoon jung grant
sun cha kim delina ashley young
paul andre michels xiao ji tan
dao yul fang and those whose names i do not know
names that have not been spoken or names that have been forgotten
[Music]
uh and even in the midst of all this it's
so important to focus and bring to mind the beautiful
qualities that exist in our lives
and it's a pleasure to be here with you today and to share my experience of the dharma
on this first day of spring it's a day of great significance as a
time of birth and rebirth of renewal and awakening
with hope may may it mark the dawning of a new day that follows a difficult period of
isolation massive death and deep
internal grief we've been living in a difficult time of disease and
hatred living in a triple pandemic really on many levels
the most obvious is the coronavirus that has plagued the earth with a cloak of
illness and death the more disguised virus of white
supremacy that has infected the infrastructure of systems
and institutions all around the world with hatred of difference and the loathing
for the natural diversity of life itself and a third pandemic of
untruths lacking why speech
a blatant spreading of deceptions that have blinded and wrecked a scourge
of mass confusion and metastasized delusion for so very many
we've been living in a time of massive individual and communal grief
and what is fortunate is that the dharma is immensely vast and far-reaching
that it touches into every aspect of our lives the scene and the unseen acknowledging
the known the unknown and the unknowable
there are many paths to enter the dharma some resonate sweetly within our hearts
and others present difficult challenges to overcome
the undoing of our harmful conditioning
you know life has always been hard to pin down but lately the reality that we are not
in control of our lives our futures
our circumstances has been even more apparent
right now we're living in a liminal realm a transitional groundless place
here nothing is certain we are at the threshold of an unknown
the threshold of an unknown this invisible cloak of delusion
the delusion of predictability it's been pulled back to reveal the truth of uncertainty our
lives today have brought into the open the instantaneous
passing of each moment
and this truth has been there all along yet these current circumstances have
forced an entire world to not only face
but to embody the truth of the moment to moment change
in every breath of our unpredictable lives
the buddha states that every life is marked by three characteristics
of existence impermanence
anitcha the pali word suffering or dissatisfaction dukkha
and egolessness sometimes referred to as not self anata
our intuitive understanding and somewhat forced embodiment
of a nietzsche impermanence is the characteristic that opens the
door to our release from attachments which is the true source of personal
internal liberation from suffering
to release to let go
to settle to feel into the emptiness
of this existence and as the truth of the unreliability
of life continues to unfold we can choose to embrace tremendous
suffering by clinging on to old habits and familiar comforts
or we can welcome the stillness within us that holds the power of awakening
intellectually we know that nothing in this life in this world
will last forever and that the longer we live we will certainly see everything
that we have come to know and love wither die vanish
into the intangible however true understanding of
impermanence is non-cognizable we can only know the truth of it in the
unnamable experiential terrain of our bodies where there is a resonance of memory
that is a part of our very being
sati to remember
to remember it's there within us you know the ancestors are not out there
somewhere those who have come before us they live within us
they move through our bloodstream they're in the marrow of our bones
the chain of dna in our bodies that gets passed on from generation to generation the
memories are there
not only of experience of loves and hurts and pains and traumas
but the memory of what we are it is there
but these these memories are easily forgotten because we live in and are conditioned by a culture of
memory loss and dwell in the immediate gratification of short-term memory and distraction
we move about barely present to the moment enchanted by a a world of rapid
information bites the media technology and corporate
marketing schemes that create a culture of attention deficit beings
and now that the wheels have all but grinded to a stop
we are even more susceptible to the enticements of distraction
being out of our comfort zone being able to move about in the ways
that we've always moved
the deep insight necessary to cultivate an easeful and fulfilled life in the midst
of chaos and horror and the enchantments of delusion
arise when the mind is still silent and unencumbered
aware it's quietude that allows us to see the
trappings that lead to our own destruction it is stillness that throws
open the doors to our discerning internal wisdom a wisdom that is
unempirical and immaterial
unquantifiable when the loud noise of want and desire
and dislike have been quieted the unspoken wisdom contained in the deepest recesses
of the body arises the wisdom of ancient knowing the wisdom of all that has gone before us
the wisdom held in the whispering earth all become available to the conscious mind
this is a wisdom that reminds us remembers to us that we are all a web of connection that
is unseen and unbroken that there's really no space between us
that we are part of the space the air the void that we are the pause
this is a time for remembering what it is that we have forgotten
connecting with the memory contained within the body
mindfulness of the body is no accident the first door to awakening
the first of the foundations of mindfulness
our cultural default is wired to do too many things move too fast take on
too many projects and juggle too many jobs in our endless efforts to make ends meet
or to acquire the things that we have been told and conditioned we need for a fulfilled life
and accompanying this normalized way of life are deeply seated feelings of overwhelm
overload fatigue sleep deprivation
these are all systems and mental states that keep us from remembering
that we are sacred in our very flesh that we are light beings of infinite
energy living forth just a brief
whisper of a moment on this material plane
that we are interconnected to all around us both animate and
what is seemingly inanimate i read just the other day that
it's been noticed that trees have a heartbeat
so spaced out that it's not hardly at all perceptible
everything we touch vibrates with the energetic charge of life the same charge of life
that is apparent in our senses when we allow the mind to settle and be
with what is
constantly juggling the balls where do we find the time to reflect
upon the moment when do we stop to take in the effects
of that incident that arose today yesterday on tuesday
and before that where do we tuck away the horror story
that we witnessed or the daily infractions that got stuffed down
packed on top of the other the other the other unresolved stories now
absorbed in the body awaiting their time when attention will be turned in that direction
you know living like this is to constantly stub the toe and not take the time
to attend to it in the rush of getting to the next task
today in the quiet of our homes for those of us who have homes
we get to turn over this rock where the slippery lizard of privilege
remains hidden from sight you know lately we've heard a lot about
white privilege the privilege is not only white
each one of us has a degree of privilege that others do
not have if we are listening the current
circumstances can help us tremendously to bring our
awareness to where we fall on that scale
where do we stand when placed amongst those who experience these circumstances these dire
circumstances as a continuation of the threat of death that has always
been there
you know before the pandemic hit i said oh good goodness
there are more in larger tint cities everywhere all over the place
as i turned the key to come into my home that i've made
comfortable and a beautiful refuge safe from the outside world
and now on the few times that i leave the house and drive down the street the ten
cities are still there but they're much smaller
what does that mean
i think it means that i've had the privilege of being
sheltered away sheltered away from death and disease
for a few moments and that there are many who had no
shelter no shelter in place no access to medicine
these words that i'm sharing with you are about memory and what it means to remember what it
means to turn a kind attention
to all about us all around us to wake up to see
to remember all that it is that we have forgotten
as the vaccines take hold in our lives begin to open up a bit
can we can we remember what it was like to stop
and bring awareness to our stub toe
will we choose to return to the abnormal life of rushing to make plans and cramming as
many tasks as possible into the time frame of each moment
will we examine the ways in which we ourselves contribute to systems of harm
in the world through our livelihood and our speech
and through our actions
and should we choose to engage in those examinations will we ask ourselves for forgiveness
for the ways we've been complacent and contributing to systems
and institutions and ways of life that are harmful
to all beings and to the earth we all have a part in this
perhaps as our world reopens little by little we will be we will welcome
with open arms the innate compassion that has been
waiting to fully emerge from within
have you felt the beautiful qualities knocking at your heart's door
qualities that have been waiting to be shared with others
even those beings outside of our chosen beloved communities
maybe this life experience this trial just maybe has shaken us up
just a bit out of our conditioned trance in a way that we
might cherish the pure gold of this breath of this time this very brief
time of our lives
maybe we will deepen the practices necessary to explore the essential parts of our
being
the time is now it's always now the time is always now
but the time is now to draw upon our deepest most precious resources
that we have been practicing and saving up especially for this occasion
what have we been practicing for
to re-imagine to draw upon all of our intuitive
wisdom to remember the wisdom of the ages that
flows through our veins we recognize the truth when we hear it it resonates
in our bodies it perks us up because it's there
this is the time to re-imagine a new world
not a remaking of the old world but something never before seen to envision how we can live
in the deepest most beautiful way possible
you know i want to share this quote from clarissa pinkola estes my friends
do not lose heart we were made for these times
i have heard it from so many recently who are deeply and properly
bewildered they are concerned about the state of
affairs in our world now ours is a time of almost
daily astonishment and righteous rage over the latest degradations
of what matters most to civilized visionary people
and you're right in your assessments the lustre and hubris some have aspired to while
endorsing acts so heinous against children
elders everyday people the poor the unguarded the health the help the
the helpless is breathtaking yet i urge you jen told you
to please not spend your spirit dry by bewelling these difficult
times especially did not lose hope most particularly because the fact is
that we were made for these times
she goes on to say that when a great ship is in harbor and
moored it is safe there is no doubt
but that is not what great ships are built for
let us not forget that we are great ships
so on this first day of spring
let us join the prayers of many in the northern hemisphere who honor the
spring equinox and plant during the time of the growing
moon and set a collective intention to create
to fashion a better world
with our words with our actions with our deeds to bring the ethics of the dharma of our
practice into these areas of our lives
to create a world free of hatred and the violence of terrorism
this starts in here because we are the contents of the world
it is an internal as sylvia borstein says it's an inside job
thank you for your kind attention i'd like to just take a moment to
let the words fall away to bring your awareness to the resonance
in your body to notice what is activated or what has
arisen there to drop the storylines
the questioning the judgment the interrogation
to free ourselves of any anything that we don't need
and simply listen to the wisdom of our bodies
[Music] um
and as we close
i'd like to bring a dedication of merit
today we have generated good deeds that entitle us to a spiritual reward
as an act of generosity we offer the merit generated from our actions today
to radiate outward into the world at large and to land upon and rest with those who are less
fortunate than we are may it reach its long tentacles through
the illusion of space between all that there is and defeat the
enemy of wrongdoing may it land in the hearts and minds of
those who are steeped in suffering those who are stalked
and hunted those who are hungry and imprisoned in the trance of
ignorance we offer the fruits of our merit to all
living beings who crawl on the earth and swim in the waters of this world
all who fly and hop who walk and climb
all those who see without eyes and hear without ears we offer the merit
of our practice to all creatures above us below us to the right and the left seen in the
unseen the known the unknown and the
unknowable may all beings all beings be free
[Music]
so you