so it's 7am here in california and so
locally i can offer you a good morning and happy to be together and good day and
greetings for everyone around the globe who are participating and
the the kind of the theme for this guided
meditation is balance and uh finding a balance when we sit and
the balance is i liken it a little bit to us finding the midpoint
of a row boat maybe a fairly stable wide row boat but still a row boat that
um and finding the midpoint where there's the least amount of the center
of gravity kind of the boats and to stand there with our legs firmly on the
floor of the boat and and keep our balance and maybe you know our upper part of our
torso is maybe not moving so much but our legs are in fact kind of going with the rocking of the boat maybe
it's a gentle rocking but still we're constantly making small adjustments
and uh and the stronger we are and our legs and torso and things like that maybe the
easier it is to keep our balance so in meditation we're also developing a
kind of inner strength and a skill at staying balanced both to recognize about when we get off
balance and to recognize and to have the strength to kind of stay to come back to balance stay in balance
and the way it works in meditation is the most simple way is
to stay balanced without any kind of movement towards our
experience or any movement away any wanting or not wanting any movement in which we
get pulled by experience pulled into our thoughts any movement
pushed by the thoughts or pushed by experience of what's happening and rather both physically but also
you know in the heart the mind we stay balanced we stay in that center place where
there's a strength and a stability that wisdom can operate and clear seeing
can operate that we lose when we start getting involved in things or we start rejecting
things and staying in that midpoint of the boat of our life and of course we'll go
a little bit off and so part of the equanimity and practice is to appreciate that of course
just like in a row boat we'll get them pulled this way in that way and get picked up get involved and
all these things but hopefully not so much and hopefully with very gentle
maybe even loving course corrections no stay here come back see clearly what's happening
so we can stay balanced come back to that peaceful place
still place the balance place inside the dynamic balance the dynamic peacefulness
i don't think that you have to rest on your meditation laurels and just stay peaceful without a
kind of being engaged alert mindful to stay here here so with that as an
introduction to assume a posture
that maybe manifests a degree of balance
and uh and one way to begin then with balance is to
rock back and forth if you're sitting upright maybe sway back and forth and
and then make smaller and smaller kind of sways kind of looking for a place of balance
with the torso balance on the sitting bones balance of your weight against whatever
support is being received and then to kind of
feel up the spine up the torso and to make small adjustments
to feel a sense of being everything's balanced partly that means that the with the
weight of our torso kind of at all stacked up in a way that feels
aligned with this some center line within so that we're not leaning forward
part of our weight is in front of that center of gravity and and some of it's not behind and
something looking for that balance and to do something where the hands and
arms feel balanced as well so they're not pulled too far forward or
pulled too far down so the shoulders being pulled if you're sitting you might be able to
pull your hands back from the knee a little bit or sometimes putting a cushion or
something on top of your if you're here your your your thighs or your ankles so the hands are held up more
um can feel more balanced and support a balance of the torso
and then to close the eyes and with the eyes closed and sitting
still again feeling the body from the inside
and feeling where there is balance where there is stability in the body
where there's a kind of maybe even groundedness
of your body against whatever supports you upright whatever supports your weight
to feel that stability or groundedness rootedness
and to feel whatever seems stable within physical stability
some people might feel it the lower torso
around the hips pelvis some people might feel it
lower back or in the belly
or maybe in the area of the solar plexus behind it above the diaphragm
and maybe there's a can be a feeling of some stability as you relax your shoulders soften
it may be a stability
in the in the shoulder supporting the neck maybe in the back of the neck
in the way that that area supports the weight of the
head
and there's a way in which tension and holding even if it's
stable tension is a kind of
agitation
and greater stability and balance is found by relaxing some of the extra
tension in the body softening the muscles of the face
these are muscles that are sometimes constantly engaged in daily life
to express ourselves communicate ourselves to the world
smiles and frowns and scowls and
fears held in the muscles of the face
and it's a compassionate thing for the face on the exhale
to let the muscles ease not up to work so much
around the eyes forehead
jaw and the same thing with agitation and
restlessness in the chest if there is something
and relaxing in the chest softening easing up
without the kind of instability that comes from resistance
holding ourselves at our life at bay
and then softening in the belly a kind of release of the weight of the
belly letting it maybe that weight
release downward to create some inner stability in the
lower torso
and then to feel whatever restlessness agitation energetics there are
there is in the mind
maybe in the area where we that we have the brain or anywhere
for you it's associated with your mental emotional activity
as you exhale relaxing the mind
relaxing the mental activity slowing things down in the mind
softening the mind and feeling the softness
of the mind
and then gently noticing
as we sit here for a minute or so any movements towards
or away any being pulled into something like our
thoughts or any kind of movement of recoiling or
pulling back or being pushed back
any wanting any not wanting
and just simply notice that and perhaps allowing it to be there if
it's there feeling it sensing what it's like for
the body the mind to have this movement
for and against
and feel how maybe there's not much balance there
or that there's some imbalance
and then the next couple of exhales see if you can release
any for against wanting and not wanting release it
enough to feel that you're in your life mind heart
comes to us balanced stability
or comes into a little bit more of a balanced ability than
it was when it wasn't stable
and then to really now
experience the breathing body the body breathing
almost like the awareness gently lands
onto the body breathing
and this is where we feel the gentle rowboat where the gentle waves are breathing in
and out the movements of the body expanding and
contracting the air moving in and out through the
nostrils
and if it's easy enough to establish a kind of gentle soft
stability steadiness with the breathing
and as you feel any other pull and push
moving forward against experience wanting and not wanting
keep finding your stability keep coming back to the breathing
let the breathing support you
let the breathing be the place that you stand or feel
so you're not so easily pulled into for and against
staying balanced in the body body breathing
with the mind having landed and on the breathing the
body breathing not easily pulled into
wanting and not wanting
and if there are little movements of wanting and not moving it's okay those can be some kind of
that's the place we use to find back to balance here breathing
centered on the breathing body
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
i have a question for you and that is how might your
kindness your love your compassion
benefit from having an inner stability in inner balance
how can kindness and love and compassion benefit from not being pulled into
in some way reacting for or against
without being pulled into desires or pulled into aversion
to be able to open our hearts and care and good will towards others
while remaining balanced without wants and not wants without
anxiety creating imbalance
perhaps even feeling a stability
in the kindness the good will the love the compassion
and maybe you can imagine that with it whatever balanced ability
calm you have now
sitting here can you bring to mind someone for whom
you have friendliness good will
compassion love and imagine sitting together
walking together and for you to remain balanced and
stable in your goodwill in your friendliness
not pulled into some of the complexities that can exist in these relationships of
wanting and not wanting protecting or fear
holding back or giving too much
our friendliness our goodwill is one of the great resources we have
it can be one of the foundations for buddhist practice
and may it be that all beings
find a way to be balanced stable
in their happiness and safety peacefulness
may all beings find stability steadiness strength
in their good will their heartfelt care for others
and may we in our balance stability for good will and friendliness
contribute to make it easier for others to be that way
may it be that the benefits of this meditation is something that we
bring into the world of our daily life
that we're ready to share and stay close to those benefits
may all beings be happy may all beings everywhere
be free
um