so i want to continue
uh my thoughts on
topic of these two weeks wholesome and
unwholesomeness
skillfulness and unskillfulness
and this week i wanted to to continue a
little bit more
focus on the unwholesome
next week more the wholesome
so begin with a story uh so when i was
27 i was ordained as
a zen monk then
and um zen priest
and um you know it was a big
turning point in my life to enter into
the religious life and
as a as a calling as a
something was going to be my my life
and one of the surprises to me from
doing the ceremony the ordination
ceremony
was that afterwards you know i had a
shaved head i
wore robes and i was now a
much more of a public figure or
someone who people could see that i was
publicly
demonstrating or could see
in my my in how i shaved my head and how
i
the clothes i wore that i was dedicated
to this religious life this
dharma life so
um i felt much more accountable to
people
i felt much more acutely
sensitive to other people's you know
studying me and seeing how i behave and
all that
so i i think as a consequence of this i
became much more acutely
aware of my own shortcomings
and i had lots of them so so became much
more acutely sensitive to them
but at the same time and this was the
remarkable thing
is that because i had been ordained
i felt kind of metaphorically or
figuratively or something
that i was now a child of the buddha
and so it was more okay to have the
shortcomings
i was accepted in a sense with them
and this combination i thought was
really precious
that i became more aware of my
shortcomings and it was more okay to
have them
um in a certain way it didn't mean that
i indulged in them and now i could
had a free reign to kind of act them out
or or just continue
merely going along with my shortcomings
um i had a practice and to look at it
and to work with it
and to find freedom from it with it
and and
and so i um but this combination of
heightened sensitivity to one's own
shortcomings as a good thing
as a helpful thing at the very same time
uh not to be troubled by it not feel not
be defined by it not
feel somehow belittled by it or
or ashamed of it or anything this is the
way forward in the dharma
and one of the we keep saying that many
of the pasta teachers
when we give talks about the hindrances
the hindrances are five
unwholesome states of mind and wholesome
forms of behavior and thinking
when we get caught in in greed
we get caught in ill will and
caught in sloth and torpor or
restlessness and regrets
and caught in doubt um
the apostle teachers will often say
don't take them personally
don't define yourself by them don't
judge yourself by their presence
it's completely natural for a human mind
to produce hindrances
you know we have millions of years of
evolution behind us
that has shaped us in the way we are and
we can't
undo that in some automatic way
you didn't choose um you know
how many arms and hands you were born
with
uh you know you're sitting there kind of
as an embryo forming your body parts and
so
and this this time i'm gonna i think i
want four arms or six arms you know and
i can be much more efficient and do more
things and
that would be a good idea uh we're kind
of
our genetics you know
operates in a certain way and and
before we're consciously aware and can
make choices
so much of who we are has been shaped
and
by the mon the continuum of the
of the evolution of genetics of
this kind of natural unfolding of our
lives that's
part of the natural world and with that
comes the tendencies
to behave in certain unskillful ways
on wholesome ways on beneficial ways
but uh to see this as part of nature
as opposed to see it as as somehow a sin
or you know a great moral crime that we
should behave this way
um and so to have a willingness
to see clearly to acknowledge
to recognize our shortcomings
if we don't if we think even the word
shortcomings is a little bit judgmental
maybe you could say your foibles
or maybe you just say to recognize our
unwholesome
states of mind a wholesomeness to
recognize or if
even that seems a little judgmental you
could use the translation of
kusala as unskillful well that's
unskillful
and and unskillful
you know can be much more simple
straightforward like oh that wasn't
useful that's not
beneficial that's not a good skill to do
and but somehow or other this
combination of
being willing to acknowledge we have
shortcomings
sometimes be amused sometimes maybe be
a little bit sad that they're there and
because
there's a way of causing harm harm to
self and others
and and but not to be
not to carry the weight of them and not
allow yourself to be defined in some
negative way so that they're
you they add more
suffering on top of suffering on top of
suffering
so just to see it as natural and
and then work with it and and be wise
about it and
be very careful not to cause harm with
it
there's a wonderful list of unwholesome
states
in the suttas and the teachings of the
buddha
and in this particular teaching seeing
the presence of these so really
acknowledging them
and then seeing when they're no longer
there when they're somehow definitively
clearly
absent shows us the movement
and the potential of what we're looking
for here in the dharma
we're not looking just to simply accept
our foibles
we're actually looking in the dharma to
to live without them to be free
and this is a radical teaching that
that some people feel is you know
unattainable or unrealistic
but it's phenomenal how much we could
redo the software of our minds and so
that
certain tendencies habits that we have
can fall away
it takes practice it takes dedication
it's not going to happen
happen from wishful thinking but to see
the
see the presence of these unskillful
states
and then to really experience the
absence of them say wow
this is a possibility and to be inspired
by that and
and this is what inspires me to practice
this possibility of freedom of fresh air
open space of clarity of
freedom this is possible and now that i
have a taste this is what to practice
with so this wonderful list
i think it's a wonderful list about
wholesome states what's
interesting about it is um almost all of
them
are social in nature meaning that their
motivations we have that are usually
exist
in relationship to other people and so
these are unwholesome states where we
can feel i think many of these as you
hear them
how they are painful for the person who
has them
and they are inflict pain or suffering
or problems
for the people who these are inflicted
on
these are you know applied to
so um uh here's a list
of unwholesome states of mind or
unwholesome motivations
so covetousness
coveting the things of other people ill
will
having ill will or hate words towards
others
anger having anger is often directed
towards others
resentment resentment is often directed
contempt towards others
insolence envy envy is often related to
others
everest so again it's usually
wanting the things of other people maybe
deceit usually we do that in relation to
social situations
can deceive yourself but fraud even more
so
in relationship to other people
rivalry conceit
conceit is often formed in rel in
in relationship to others we're better
than others we're worse than others
we want something from others and so
they conceit one status one something
so without other people around maybe
there wouldn't be much reason for
conceit
arrogance same thing arrogance is often
done in relationship to
others and vanity
so maybe vanity is also that way
all these things could be addressed to
oneself perhaps one could
maybe have ill will towards oneself
anger resentment
even contempt and um
could be some deceit towards oneself and
self-deceit to the in rivalry some
people have
inner wars between different sides of
who they are so they can be within us
but uh i want to highlight how much
these are
social emotions and uh
and so this idea that the unwholesome
uh is um is
uh to you know if we want to
contribute to a better society a better
world if we want to contribute to a
world where we don't want to harm others
how useful it is to settle and resolve
these unwholesome states on ourselves as
we do that
we don't experience the self-harm that
all of these create
and i think it's really fantastic
amazing
that it's also a natural thing that we
can resolve
settle undo this for these forces in our
life
and simultaneously it benefits ourselves
and i don't know exactly simultaneously
benefits others or
or benefits others maybe not in the
moment but it will
because we're not going to go around
with these acting on these unhealthy
kind of behaviors
so um bringing it brings motivation
for us hopefully to
look at our unwholesome states to look
at the unsc skillful things we have
greed hatred and delusion in all its
different forms
and in doing so
not doing it unskillfully not doing it
in unwholesome ways
to look at our unwholesome behavior and
thoughts and motivations
in ways that you know
does more the same has ill will in it
that just you know
bad suffering upon suffering the dharma
approach is to see it as natural
and in certain way impersonal to see it
as if you maybe if you'd like you're
you're a child of the buddha your child
of
nature of the world and
and the world's not judging you nature
is not judging you
um you're accepted you're belong here
and so it's so but but please
uh in this deep kind of sense of
acceptance
and not non-criticalness of oneself
be realistic and honest about
shortcomings and
unwholesomeness that we have and in
certain kind of way be inspired by that
wow if i see this in me now it's
possible to be
to work towards freedom without knowing
it there and seeing it clearly
where's the freedom as well and
and so
this is a call to
a loving a peaceful and
very clear recognition
of your foibles
your shortcomings your unwholesome
tendencies
what you do that is not healthy and try
to
see it be with it relate to it in
healthy ways in skillful ways in
wholesome ways
and inspired by the wholesome and that
will be the topic for next week and
we can't really separate these two so
much they'll go back and forth a little
bit but
so next week we'll look at the wholesome
and what i have in mind is to do so more
with the
translating kusala the pali word for
this
by the alternative translation which is
skillful
so we'll look more at skillfulness next
week
so um thank you so much and
i look forward to next week