so uh so welcome folks welcome all um sweet to uh see the comments here
um yeah my name is uh matthew brent silver and um
one of the the teachers at imc and happy to uh to be with you quite happy
and um you know it was i don't want to feel like i'm crashing a
little family party the family uh you know 7 a.m sit gil 7am said but thanks for the
the warm welcomes and happy to uh yeah see see a lot of uh familiar names
and so um yeah i'll follow the
the custom around these parts and we'll we will um
sit together for about half hour and then i'll offer some some reflections on
a theme this week and
yeah yeah so i know gill left off with um
three weeks on on greed hate delusion and um and uh freedom from non-delusion
from from delusion uh was the the friday talk and theme and um
yeah and this week uh i'll be be exploring uh the the theme of equanimity equanimity
uh woven into uh really the fabric of our of our practice and so much of the
goodness that unfolds and so as we as we sit we'll
practice the way one of my teachers put it
shenzhen young is will practice uh sort of the
non non interference with the arising of sensory experience
yeah the the nervous system not fighting with itself
and yeah we can actually get a feel for that what it is like to
not be in contention with ourselves not be in contention with experience to give a kind of
radical permission for phenomena to to arise
and pass to give it our blessing
so uh yeah finding a posture that is uh sustainable for you
just feeling
that upright axis of the spine
the rest of the body hanging loosely
from that uh gently upward reaching spine
and remember this crucial aspiration of our practice we
practice for ourselves and for others
we cultivate our own heart such that
we become a cause of more joy more safety less suffering in the world
the attitude we take the attitude in line with this theme of equanimity
this is a kind of um deep non-violence towards
the whole of our experience
wherever it feels like two solid objects colliding
the solidity of some ache and the solidity of a contracted mind wherever it feels
like a collision we soften
awareness like space
this means we can't get what greed wants we can't get
what hatred wants
we renounce the objects of clinging
when we make peace with the
imperfection the human condition
the forces of of grasping
have been a source of agitation forever
source of kind of inner friction friction in our own nervous system
so we give up the fight at least
for this moment
relax the body relax the mind
even though equanimity is known for its its coolness
it actually deepens the poignancy of life
makes our heart more rather than less responsive to suffering
more rather than less responsive to joy
more attuned not less
[Music]
so
so um good morning to you all uh
welcome to those uh just just joining uh my name again is matthew and um
uh it's good too it's good to sit with you
um yeah i was listening to um to gill's
friday uh session just to see exactly where he uh he left off
and you know it struck me that gill he makes teaching look so easy
and i make it look really hard but that's the situation
i'm uh no no problem with that either i'm happy to
to be with you all and i trust we'll we'll uh feel each other's hearts and
that'll be uh that'll be plenty
so um sometimes people say uh you know
about their practice you know matthew i'm paying attention on being mindful and everything is still terrible
you know and
it's important to to acknowledge that that simply using our attention
doesn't generate wisdom attention in other words is not a
um is not not necessarily wholesome in itself or unwholesome yeah
it's we're using our attention all of the time it is the kind of most basic currency
of um of of uh human beings you know the most
basic resource and we want to use it wisely we want to use our
attention wisely appropriately and wise attention
means that it's it's connected to to wholesomeness yeah it's conjoined
with wholesomeness it's conjoined with among other things equanimity
what i was alluding to and
more and more it feels like equanimity is a kind of like
the foundation for this path you know um that this path as gil said as he left
off with this path is about non-clinging and non-clinging is very
closely related to equanimity non-clinging is very closely related to equanimity
with um not getting the promises that craving makes
yeah not getting the promises that greed makes that that hatred makes yeah
and so um sometimes it's defined as a kind of inner balance
and and the way i i tend to think about it
is it's um it's a non-compulsion
around our preferences yeah there there's no compulsion to act out
our preferences we may still have preferences but there's not a kind of compulsion to
enact them in the world to live out this greed to live out this
hate and that can refer even to just how
the way we act out greed and aversion hatred in our sitting
yeah the kind of way we're subtly lured into
um imagining that this moment can somehow be fixed yeah that sense of like the moment
can be fixed we relinquish that
and so we may still have preferences but um but we're not feeling so
compelled to enact them
sarah lazar and her colleagues describe equanimity as a kind of a widening of of the perspective
more readily engaging incoming sensory information
and disengaging kind of cognitive and emotional
reactivity yeah so widening the perspective that
in our clinging clinging is always claustrophobic yeah it's always claustrophobic
everything feels hemmed in pinched
we widen our perspective rather than uh solidity meeting solidity
we it's it's maybe like solidity meeting space yeah
this ache meeting the space of awareness
and we're relinquishing maybe renouncing the kind of
defensive coping strategies that we have to deal with the imperfection of the moment
so um the one of my teachers shenzhen young
described it as the balance point equanimity is the balance point between suppression on the one hand
and identification on the other
michelle mcdonald i believe said um equanimity is is uh is the courage of
low expectations which is very funny um the courage of low
expectations and i think she would add the courage of low expectations but
very high aspirations yeah
in a way i don't want to give one definition we'll sort of unfold a range of definitions over the
course of the week because something like equanimity has
many many flavors many facets and so hopefully rather than starting with some
simple reductionistic idea of exactly what it is we live into it we practice into it
and it takes a lot of equanimity just to open to
the human condition you know to the intensity of the human condition
to dukkha to suffering in a way even after all of these years
every time dukkha arises it feels a little bit like this freak
accident you know it's like i still haven't fully acclimatized to the first
noble truth you know it just has this feel of like the universe is off its rails
and it's like no matthew you just stubbed your toe you know it's woven into the fabric of
of uh existence and to actually open to that is no
joke it's no joke yeah to really begin to appreciate
what is this this inner life and or our outer world this
this entails a measure of equanimity otherwise it's too much it's too much so we open
now maybe i say all of this and um you think like
ugh you know like equanimity it sounds tiring yeah sounds
tiring and
i want to kind of celebrate equanimity as it's it's very generative very
generative it is so closely tied to peace to love to
release and so this is the focus of
of the week so the the last weeks as i said go had
done on greed hate and delusion the the kind of wellsprings of
self-generated suffering and um and even enlightenment itself is is
sometimes described as the absence of greed and delusion and what i want to begin
this week with is to say that uh to work skillfully with these forces with the
defilements with grenade and delusion this requires equanimity yeah
and uh in a way the the greed the hatred
are readily uh observable right the greed the kind of
um that hole in the heart like we um try to
to get what we think we want and we act out that um
[Music] that craving so often but um but craving
always over promises yeah what we get never actually
satiates the craving but compounds it
we might get some fleeting something but it actually deepens the habit of
acting out craving and so we want to begin to see
how the objects of greed the fantasy of what i get when i get what i want
it's always over promises
so we develop equanimity with longing that's very tender
it's very tender if hatred um
if you haven't noticed there's uh there's always something wrong something can always be better
and so we develop equanimity with imperfection
and so if greed is the kind of hole in the center of your being and hatred
feels like your heart is on fire what is delusion
well delusion feels exactly like the truth
until it doesn't so the question how do we see
what we can't see and what i would say is that delusion
yeah for sure is more subtle than greed or hatred but delusion launders our greed
and launders our hatred it serves to justify and dignify
the forces of greed and hatred when we launder money
i through some criminal enterprise i get money and then i make it clean
running it through some legitimate business right when you launder greed you make it look
like hope and fun and excitement when you launder hatred you
clean it to make it look like righteousness like clarity like discernment
this like uh the delusion serves to um obscure
the greed and the hatred and so the invitation is to
if we can have equanimity with greed with hatred we do not have to build
and fabricate and proliferate the stories and perceptions that launder
that dignify our defilements yeah we develop equanimity with
greed with aversion and this makes the kind of delusion that serves to make
that disappear to make it look like wisdom to make it look like fun yeah
we no longer need to um enact that delusion but it starts
with the equanimity with these these pushes and pulls on the heart
this is uh the terrain of of exploration for the week so i uh
i offer this for your uh your consideration and um look forward to
to being uh being with you tomorrow tomorrow morning okay
thank you uh thank you all i'll come check out the the comments here and see you
see you tomorrow so thank you and thanks thanks kevin for uh