so warm greetings i'm happy to be back and
i had a wonderful time backpacking uh long hikes beautiful places
and adventures with california fires and mostly the smokes and a
closed trail because of the fires and now i'm happy to be back happy to be
here with you all
and so in the kind of meditation world
that uh we practice in this kind of spiritual inner spiritual
life or this inner life that we develop and turn inside out there's a principle that
wherever there's an illness there is the medicine and now we're talking about kind of a
spiritual or dharmic illness but that if you can recognize where the
suffering is the dukkha the illnesses that the recognition is clear enough
that you could also it's possible to find the medicine right there so if you clearly recognize
your mind is agitated chances are right next to it close by
is the medicine which is a calm mind calm attention
if you're caught up in greed the clear recognition of it
you'll can see or feel that potential or that place in the mind the heart
where there's no greed that's the medicine for greed same for hatred and delusion
and to some degree it's also true for fear if you can this the capacity to clearly recognize fear
and then to look around and not be contracted or not be fixated on the fear preoccupied by the
fear but to see it clearly but then look around a lot along the
edges of it beyond beyond underneath it or below it somewhere within and you'll see that
there is the medicine for it there is courage there is confidence
and or there's peace something that's non-fear
and so this clearly involves recognizing what is going on inside
without that there's no medicine but the medicine comes with a clear recognition
so it's kind of a wonderful good news that each of you each of us has within us the medicine
the spirit the spiritual medicine or the mental medicine that we need for
spiritual illnesses and but it's a little hard to
pull ourselves away enough from the illness the so-called illness the so-called dharmic
dukkha that we might have to pull away or to disengage or not
be overly preoccupied with it so we have the capacity to see something else
and so one of the things that we can do in meditation is find something that feels basically
healthy and appropriate or good to focus on that's very simple something like the
breathing or some people use clear recognition itself the simplest clear recognition of
what's happening and as a way of of
not giving our the energy of attention to the illness to feed it even more
to kind of not feed these mental kind of preoccupations that
we call you know illnesses or dukkha and just stay with the breathing stay
with the breathing and then slowly the interest the preoccupation the feeding of this kinds
of spiritual illnesses abates without us having to do anything
without using the medicine even until we find ourselves settled enough calm
enough un agitated enough that the medicine kind of spreads through through us throughout
the medicine of peace the calm of non-reactivity the medicine of non-greed non-hatred and
non-delusion so taking a
comfortable posture that will also promote your capacity for
attention for clear recognition
and to gently close your eyes
and take a few long slow deep breaths
and if you take those long deep breaths unhurriedly
it can be start being medicine for our hearts and our inner life
as you take a deep breath maybe relax and soften the body
as you exhale
perhaps allow your body to settle as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale now the medicine of relaxation
on the exhale softening the face softening around the eyes
as you exhale softening the shoulders
as you exhale softening the belly
and gently as you exhale to soften in the mind
relax the thinking muscle whatever contraction or tightness that's
there associated with thinking
maybe you can identify in your mind your heart somewhere within
some something that has the potential to be medicine
for your for whatever ails you spiritually
mentally maybe there's some spaciousness
or calm or peacefulness
or compassion
care inner respect for yourself
and then to settle into your body breathing
simple caring attention
to breathing in and breathing out
caringly receiving the inhale
caringly allowing for the exhale
receiving and allowing inhaling and exhaling
one after another
so
you
if you can recognize it the medicine you need is always within
the dharmic medicine
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
when we learn to recognize the inner medicine
the heart's medicine for what ails the heart
that very medicine is the medicine that the world needs as well
and to appreciate the value of your inner medicine as a contribution to
this world when we are unagitated it's medicine for
the agitation of the world when we have compassion and love it's
medicine for the world's hate when we have generosity and contentment
it's medicine for the world's greed when we have wisdom
clear seeing and recognition it's medicine for the world's delusion
and when we encounter the suffering of the world it's medicine to see it honestly and
clearly and caringly without being oppressed by it
or de-stressed by it
and may it be that this meditation that we do today and
may or may it be medicine for the world knowingly and unknowingly intentionally
and unintentionally intentionally we live our lives
so that we make this world a better place
so that all beings may be happy all beings may be free of suffering
all beings may be free of fear and distress
that all beings may be free of oppression
may all beings be happy may all beings be well
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you
so good morning again and welcome to the beginning of the week and beginning of a series
and uh the series for this week and actually for the next three weeks
address is an issue which is huge for human beings both personally and socially
so in terms of an illness that spreads within and without
and has a big bearing on the buddha the buddhist spiritual life the topic is greed hatred and delusion
and uh i'll say in a little bit about why i you know there was a time in my life
where i would hesitate to spend so much time talking about this and maybe that will support some of you
for whom that's uh maybe a little bit i don't know not inspiring to hear that
that's this is going to be the topic for the next few weeks and the plan is to um
each week to have a same pattern of five talks related to each one and
we'll see if plans work out but the idea is to first the first day on monday to talk
about the opposite the absence of the particular of greed or hatred or
delusion and this wonderfulness then the medicine of non-greed the medicine of non-hate
non-delusion the value of it as a reference point for studying this topic
then on tuesday to talk about a particular topic itself and i've done
this recently and hopefully can do it in a different way and and then on wednesday to talk about
the basic vipassana practice in relationship to it each of these on thursday to talk about
composting each of the composting greed composting hatred and delusion
and what composting mean and transforming and then on friday to talk about
liberation from each of these and and living
as a living a life that promotes the ending of greed hate and delusion and others as well
to support others to uh in this world of ours to um diminish the
the the greed and hatred and delusion which is rampant and you know some way or other needs to
be addressed and maybe we can be a agent of change
in this particular focus so um
so for this week it's uh the topic is greed and and
so i want to start with the idea of non-greed and part of the value of this importance
of it for me personally is that when i was younger when i was first kind of encountered theravadin buddhism and
there was all these talks over and over again in reference point to the greed hate and delusion and at that time
when i heard it i saw this is being reductionalistic i felt like i was being reduced
to this kind of and felt puritanical and moralistic and kind of like who i was was being reduced
to this very kind of limited unsavory kind of thing of being someone
who has a lot of greed hate and delusion and you're supposed to uproot it
and it just didn't resonate with me in fact it was a little bit off-putting for me to have this emphasis and
but i went along and did the practice of mindfulness and and and what i discovered and
now in retrospect i can say i discovered non-greed non-hatred and non-delusion
i discovered a capacity for inner health and well-being that um became a very important
reference point for understanding myself and my life to unders to have a capacity for
you know a strong capacity or touch in strongly to a non-agitated mind a mind that's
peaceful and calm that seems to be operating in a healthy way
to tap into a capacity for a confident mind a clear mind
a loving mind or heart to start discovering this wealth of
beauty that we have within and that is not reductionistic which is actually
enhancing or fully or filling um
and there's a nun in the early buddhist tradition her name was punna
which meant uh full like and she said she's full like the full moon
and this idea of becoming full of beautiful things and radiance so to start to do the practice
and start discovering these wellsprings within of well-being um and then to start wrecking this is
what happened to me and start recognizing when i had creed
that was what was reductionistic that's what that was diminishing me when i had hate
i would eclipse this beauty i would lose it and i would be diminished i'd be reduced
to something that wasn't very pleasant and if i caught an delusion that that also limit me and in some ways
i was very alienating alienating to be in delusion it kind of separated me from myself separated me
from the world around me and so understanding this non-greed
helped me to understand the the shortcomings the danger of
having greed and and then it became much more interesting the teachings on
greed hatred and delusion it be more interesting to understand greed in a deeper way it became interesting to practice with
greed practiced overcome it learned how to
compost it and learn how to you know live a life liberated from it
because i could recognize how the limitations the suffering the dukkha
the distress the the the the way in which i was
shortcoming myself when i got pulled into greed or hatred and delusion
and that's not an easy thing to see because these are these forces are very compelling
and any resistance any restraint to having them flow through us freely can that can feel
just uncomfortable that can feel like our freedom is limited and if we're supposed to be free let
these things roll let them flow through us you know greed you know it's
it's so almost valued in much of our society that uh it just
seems like it's all good to be greedy and certain kinds of greed are not recognized as greed
uh you know i think i think that it seems like every 10 years or so the 80s late 90s late
first decade of this century and maybe i don't know but now but uh there was this huge economic
collapses in this country that um that uh we discovered that there
was these bankers and other people who were operating our tremendous avariciousness
and and you know illegally or unethically acquiring huge wealth at
the well at the expense of other people but did we use greed did they understand
themselves as being greedy or was this the american way to just kind of get more acquire more and more
more wealth and material things and um and uh
so to begin understanding how the unabated
unrestrained kind of giving ourselves over to greed to hatred and to our delusions um
it is not an expression of real freedom it's actually an expression of
being in bondage being caught being enslaved
by forces inside of us that have taken control and pushing us and that
what we're looking for is how not to be an automatic pilot not to be compelled by
these strong human instinct instincts or drives but also not to hold them restrained in
a way that can feel very uncomfortable and a lot of work to do but to allow them to just uh to learn
how to dissipate them or or come into the op the other end of other side of them
where there is peace and and uh and um you know the inner beauty begins to
shine forth or we feel full and enhanced now one of the reasons why people might
be very resistant to the idea of non-greed non-hate and non-delusion is that the drive the compulsion for
desires for wanting for pushing away and having a hospital hostile are there
for a reason try to get what we want and the idea of not having them can
people can feel like there's no motivation that we can't take care of ourselves or get what we need or protect us from ourselves from the
encroaching masses which are going to destroy our life or something
but um you know if we do when we start discovering this beautiful capacity for peace for
calm for inner well-being uh what we also start discovering
is that we can take care of ourselves we can act in the world without greed and
act beneficially there can be wholesome desires there can be desires to do good
to be generous there can be um it's they said that faith in buddhism is
a kind of desire because buddhist faith is the desire to develop the fullness to develop the freedom
that we have and and so there are there's a there can be
tremendous beautiful motivations coming from a peaceful heart coming from a heart of well-being
that is not agitated not pushing not resisting
not you know fighting this world of ours and feeling good to fight and for everything
we can get but there's this kind of movement of aikido a movement of kind of
of not resisting not fighting but discovering the wellsprings of a
different kind of wisdom a different kind of a wisdom a generosity
love a compassion a sense of peace where there's a tremendous capacity for
creativity engagement but it's not one that's so centered on
self me myself and mine the idea of a personal identity who i am what i
need what i have to do what i have to do to care for myself protect myself
the excessive focus on i excessive focus on one's personal
identity and maintaining it is part of the what complicates greed
hate and delusion and makes it really mucky and dangerous even
and to discover there are motivations beautiful motivations within that are not self-centric
they're certainly within us so in that sense they're part of ourselves but they're not centered on the egotism
or the conceit or the selfishness that often goes along with greed hatred and
delusion and so one of the reasons to not want to give up greed hate and delusion
it seems like then we're giving up self giving up self identity because people maybe are rooted in
some contracted sense of self and self identity but to discover the that which is not
self within non-contracted self the place of non
preoccupation with identity to discover this beauty inside the fullness inside
where motivations can well up from this wellspring of goodness within from the wellsprings of beauty
within without this preoccupation with self
this is a fantastic thing and so this inner beauty is the reference
point for one reference point for becoming interested in studying and understanding greed and
hatred and delusion because it um because then we really
understand how greed and hatred delusion diminishes us reduces us limits us
and how much more wonderful this we are and oddly enough
the world is when we live without great hatred and delusion
so that's uh so we'll i'll continue then tomorrow on this topic of greed and
we'll take our journey uh our five-day journey through this these three topics and um
and hopefully you'll appreciate why uh this is such a valuable topic in buddhism
and um and how the liberation from greed and hidden
delusion is one of the most potent and expressions of what liberation is in
buddhism so um thank you very much