so greetings and welcome to the continuation of our
exploration of mindfulness of breathing and by now i think you'll understand
that mindfulness of breathing involves much more than breathing but that breathing
mindfulness of breathing is kind of a foundation in which we begin to open up our
awareness to more and more of our experience
and at some point this you know as we open up to our body our feelings our minds
our mind activities mind states and so there's kind of an expansion
opening the metaphor i like to use and so it's not narrowly focused only on
the breathing and at some point as we do this the
the very idea of opening the feeling of opening the experience of opening becomes more and more salient and more
and more experienced experientiable that more and
more this stands out the sense of opening and in contrast to that it's possible to
feel a closing and this movement is that i'm calling
opening and closing can be represented by many words many ideas and
the buddha used the word as a word obstructing that sometimes we cover over and we get
certain activities of mind obstruct and others remove the obstruction and has more
expansion and openness of attention and we can see that i think relatively easy in some
circumstances in life where in know very quickly we can suddenly get
completely caught up in some concern completely you know the mind attention
everything gets focused very tightly around a preoccupation someone says
something to us which is maybe disrespectful and the whole universe
collapses around that disrespect our feelings our ideas our thoughts or maybe our fears
resentments whatever it might be and where it gets swimming and that's the story of it
and so maybe there's not much openness anymore uh to take a bird's eye view of the
situation and what just happened and what's happening with us and then
other times we have that bird's eye view we have this broad field of awareness and we're
relaxed and open and someone might do the same thing say something disrespectful
but we don't close down in fact maybe we do the opposite we actually open even more and like oh
what's going on here what's happening here let's let's uh i don't even know i don't
i don't quite understand all this but this is a time to be present and open and take in the full
range of what's happening myself the context the other person and there's a clear feeling of opening
being preoccupied caught up in things is something that the buddha says brings
blindness and a lack of wisdom this movement towards opening is
movement towards wisdom and vision
and so getting starting to get a sense of this difference is an important part of
this practice and this has this becomes more more relevant
when in the process and in the process of mindfulness of breathing we become more
attuned to the state of mind because it's the state of mind that shifts and
changes and so to uh so we certainly can know that we're preoccupied with resentment
or or uh caught up in our our hurt or whatever it might be
and um the uh or in our desires and we lose touch with
everything else around us and we can know that we're involved in that but to appreciate the impact that
preoccupation has how it shifts the mind state it shifts the quality of awareness the openness of
awareness the ease and receptivity of awareness that becomes interesting
and and so to notice this movement between closing down and opening up
covering over preoccupied versus kind of available attention that's open and
available because it's not preoccupied as practice goes along
there's a shift of attention from the details of our life the stories
of our life the history of our life a shift little bit even from our beliefs
and ideas desires aversions opinions and to the quality
of the mind state and we become the custodians
of that quality no one else can be the custodian of our inner the quality of our inner
life and so to begin finding a relaxed easy way
to to track it and know it and be able to gently
keep opening keep finding the way of peace keep finding the way where the mind
state is receptive and open with wisdom with real wisdom so that
we're safe in the situation and can take care of ourselves
so that's kind of the background for this meditation so if you can
begin by assuming a meditation posture
and if it's possible to do a posture that already in the posture
expresses a kind of openness availability
to life to experience
for me sitting cross-legged i sometimes really liked taking my hands on either side of my
hips on the floor math next to me and lift myself almost off the cushion
like i'm doing now and so i'm lifting up and then as i'm lifted up then i roll my
shoulders back a little bit and release and if i do that the shoulders roll back a little bit and
the chest kind of naturally kind of feels more open and that openness of the chest
can be one of the reference point for being open
and then gently closing your eyes
and this idea of openness we can be open-handed
and you might take a few moments to relax your hands and maybe even
turn your hands to palms upward so the hands are open and
available sometimes expressing openness in the
posture is supportive for the heart and the mind to do so become open
and perhaps you can as you exhale
relax the shoulders soften in the shoulders
and whatever softening release that happens in the shoulders let that travel down into your chest
and whatever reference point you have for being open-hearted
see if you can establish yourself as openhearted
open chested
and then as you exhale relaxing in the muscles of your face
sometimes those muscles are very intimately connected to what's happening in the mind
the tightness scrunching up the pulling in very subtly the micro
muscles of the face it's as if there's
the mind is a puppeteer with strings that go into the micro muscles of the face
to relax the face
around the eyes forehead and temple
the cheeks and the jaw might even be helpful to open your mouth
slightly so the jaw is not clenched
and then gently softly float
the teeth back together the mouth back together so there's a light touch with your lips
and whatever reference point you have for this as you exhale can you allow your mind to
become open to be open-minded
to your experience now
open-handed open-hearted open-minded
and taking a few moments also to set your body at ease
be easy with how things are in your body
maybe easing up if there's any heaviness or contraction
resistance in your body
see if you can find some even a slight sense of ease
being present for your body
and if possible set yourself at ease in your heart with your emotions
ease up on how you're feeling be easy with it
and then set your mind at ease
in whatever way it's you can a little bit ease up on what's
in the mind or be easy with it
so the awareness becomes a little broader
more available to receive
awareness is not recruited
to help us focus on our thoughts and desires and aversions fantasies
instead of being recruited to close down and narrow its attention
letting the awareness be at ease and open
receptive
and then within whatever openness that's here whatever ease that's here
to attune yourself to the breathing
the in-breath and the out-breath breathing through or with
open awareness ease full awareness
as you exhale letting go of your thoughts
and as you do so also see if there can be a
opening to a wider awareness or opening to opening
allowing the mind to have more space and room to silently
be aware of breathing body
appreciating any sense of openness or ease or
in the state of mind state of heart
breathing with it and notice the small and big movements
of losing that openness contracting
getting caught up in something
nothing you have to be feel bad about or criticize yourself for
but simply to be sensitive to that distinction
sensitive to the way the mind moves can move from being open to being more closed
relax to being contracted
preoccupied or being available and open
breathing with it all being easy with it all
but clearly aware of the difference and how the mind can move
around to different degrees of openness and less openness
no need to analyze or figure anything out or
stay very simple with appreciating if the mind gets more open
or more closed appreciate which direction mental activity is
taking you and see if you can keep choosing to stay
open move more it's very forgiving
it doesn't require a lot of understanding of what's happening
or justifying or criticizing it's just a very simple movement
opening or closing and when you can choose the opening
choose awareness
being upset about the mind closing down
is to do even more closing to be
equanimous about the mind closing down is to contribute more opening
as we become more aware and simply recognize what's happening
allowing the recognition to be wide and
open
[Music]
ah
and then in the last minutes of this sitting maybe knowing it's the last minutes
you could let yourself become more open
maybe quiet the mind more and open up in a way that the heart mind is
broad and silently receptive
whatever degree of ease just being here
in a certain way nothing to do nothing to be
nothing to prove just here
with awareness open relaxed maybe even soft
and perhaps trying to keep it that way and see or see what happens
bring to mind some person that has been part of your life lately or
will be today and see if you can hold the image
the idea of this person in your mind without closing
without getting caught up in thoughts and stories and feelings
just for a few moments let the persons the idea the person float in the openness of the mind
and in doing so does that make it possible to have more
wisdom more clarity about something about yourself and them
might it make little bit more room for a simple good will
friendliness or generosity of heart
and if so maybe softly gently
give expression to that good will with these words
may this person be happy
may this person be safe
may this person be peaceful
may this person be free
and may you in staying open and at ease
in some ways contribute to this being possible
in some simple ways can you contribute to their happiness safety peacefulness
and freedom so at least they're safe from you
and then to expand that goodwill out into the world more widely
but without closing down
the air on the side of staying open and simple
and in that openness may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
so the mindfulness of mind or
breathing in experiencing the mind breathing out experiencing the mind
and i'm in you know what the exactly cheetah mind is i'm sorry arguing that we can't really
know what the buddha had in mind but i wanted to read you part of the
definition in the polytech society dictionary so them more or less a standard poly english
dictionary it was written over a hundred years ago now but it's still excellent resource for
understanding this and um and they have a wonderful little entry for cheetah the word that we're
mostly translating as mind it says the meaning of chitta is best
understood when explaining it by expressions familiar to us
as for example with all my heart and soul i have no heart
to do it blessed are the pure in heart singleness of heart
all of which emphasize the emotional and cognitive connotative side more
than it's the mental and rational side it may therefore be rendered mood
disposition state of mind so some people prefer to translate this
word cheetah as heart or as heart mind it kind of touches into the emotional
side of all this more than the word mind might even feel a little bit this
emotional this you know and not so connected to our emotional life
and uh and also when some people like me treat mind and awareness almost as
synonymous sometimes as we get into deeper meditation that also might kind of lend itself to
the idea that we're kind of being removed a little bit from the embodied emotional life that we have
and which may be a little unfortunate maybe this whatever cheetah is whatever the mind is
whatever awareness is maybe it's a rich world that includes our emotionality to some you know to
important ways and so uh
in the step eight seven and eight of mindfulness of breathing it's looking at the mental activities
recognizing the mental activities in the mind and now then relaxing those mental activities and they were or
tranquilizing or calming them which is that movement or opening having the mind
become open uh not contracted and as i said earlier the mind that's
preoccupied gets in my mind gets hijacked attention gets hijacked
by um our desires by our aversions by our
doubts by our restlessness our anxiety and um and it's almost like the times
are like a black hole that attention falls into and it doesn't really come out there isn't like we step
back and get the bigger picture we get swept away and our preoccupations
our thoughts our fantasies the stories our resentments all these kinds of inner
world of what goes on and um and uh and these are all mental
activities that hijack awareness and there are other mental activities that enable awareness or
open the mind that doesn't hijack but rather enhances the quality of the mind so uh the buddha
made the distinction between mental factors that do the closing the mind those that open is
a distinction between what's called the five five hindrances and the seven factors of
awakening the five hindrances are strong sensual desire
lust craving aversion ill will hostility when it's strong
sloth and torpor lethargy resistance
and and then agitation restlessness anxiety regrets kind of agitated states
of preoccupation and then confusion uncertainty doubt
that can really we get lost in the rabbit hole of doubt and confusion and these can have very strong
gravitational pulls and we you know we get pulled into them they can come sometimes with a lot of authority like this is really important
i have to be involved in this and but the consequence is that attention gets hijacked
and for the buddha when attention gets hijacked like this he calls that a loss of wisdom a
blindness an obstruction to the mind a covering over of the mind
a makes the mind fragile and brittle and hard and and
whereas the other that opens seven factors of awakening those are awareness mindfulness itself
um a clarity of mind that's sometimes called investigation
a effort joy tranquility samadhi
concentration and equanimity and all those can work together as a
whole and each of those can operate singularly to really kind of open the mind up and
open the inner quality of the inner life and this is where the emotional side really comes to play
i mean some of the most one of the most sublime beautiful emotions that's hard for the
people who haven't experienced it to appreciate is the quality of equanimity
um it's a you know it's uh just it's it's a beautiful kind of feeling
uh tranquilities has a kind of almost an emotional quality to it it's really strong and embodied and
broad and has a warmth and clarity to it stillness and peacefulness
joy of course seems emotional samadhi is an integration of bringing
together of all aspects of our life including the emotional so um but the the um the
the the what what these seven factors awakening are they are characteristics or supports
for awareness itself for mindfulness itself and so the more they operate together
with awareness they tend to open awareness strengthen awareness they create vision they support wisdom
they remove obstructions they remove the coverings that keeps us from seeing things clearly and
they make the mind malleable soft workable
ready to do the work receptive maybe to do do work and so here we're talking
about mental activities kind of that represent this divide between
becoming more closed or more open and and it's possible to cultivate each of
the seven factors awakening by itself to be attuned to them and learn to recognize them and support them
and it's also they they tend to grow in the wake of really emphasizing mindfulness
attention here but being attentive that the mindfulness
whatever way we practice it in and of itself is not a closing activity that it hasn't
uh there isn't some other factors that come along with mindfulness like striving or
or expectation or pushing or contracting around the
mindfulness that begins moving it in the direction of the hindrances closing down
so this ability to track the mind state allows us to be to protect the
mindfulness from being hijacked that way and so we can tell the mindfulness
now it's getting closed more as i try hard and maybe i can find a way to be more open
more relaxed and this simple movement from being more close to being more open well
yesterday i used to for gail fransdel the technical terms
ouch and ah what involves more stress or more suffering more discomfort
and what goes in the opposite direction to be able to see that simple divide is one of the primary
characteristics of the second factor of awakening as i said usually called investigation
but is really a clarity of mind that sees this surveillance sees this distinction
between the ouch and the ah being closed and being open um becoming blind or lost in our
preoccupations and opening up and having vision and and clarity what's happening
so this is one of the great advantages of beginning to tune into the mind state and i as i said in the meditation it's
fascinating i kind of said it's fascinating because they're very valuable and even healing
because just being attentive to that simple movement can free us from having to get caught up
in the details of what's happening whether it's right or wrong or am i good and bad
person because of what i'm doing this way and you can have the worst thought that
any preoccupation that anybody has ever happened in the history of humanity
and in this mind state thing it doesn't really matter that it's the worst thought anybody's ever had
it just matters that you recognize that you closed down you got tight and that there's an opportunity
then just to allow yourself to open and not and just let it go let it kind of recede
and move towards the openness of mind and so that's simple movement that's the direction to go can make the practice some ways
much simpler and very forgiving
so the mind state and so um that's
what we're doing today and
and we will continue tomorrow and then starting on monday the idea is to go
through these seven factors awakening uh and hopefully as we kind of linger in this area of the
mind state it's such an important one and and then we'll um go on from there
and um so thank you very much and i look forward to our time together
tomorrow