so warm greetings and welcome to our adventure with
breathing for today and um it's kind of a lifetime adventure to
practice meditation and life attuned to breathing in touch with your breathing
and aware of how your breathing is going in any given time
and it's awareness of breathing helps us to avoid
spending unnecessary energy in as we go through our life
especially the unnecessary energy of tension or anxiety or or
ambition over efforting many of the ways that we because we could become stressful has to
do with an over exertion of energy in the muscles that they're tight too much and also in
the mind and so that's gets all that gets
translated into the breathing the breathing gets shallow gets tight it moves up into the chest
rather than being deeper abdominal breathing behold our breathing and so being
attuned to the breathing and breathing in a easy relaxed way
is a way to um
to not over effort in our lives so
to assume a meditation posture
and to close your eyes
and to feel the weight of your body against the surface
that's keeping you from falling to the center of the earth
your chair your cushion the floor your bed whatever it might be and feel
the contact of your body against this surface
and maybe rock side to side sway forward and back
or in some way kind of and then settle in
wiggle in a little bit to really settle into that spot where
there's a surface holding you
and then take a few moments to feel the edges of your body
your skin both where your skin touches your clothes
where the skin touches
your cushion chair and also wherever the tingling and vibration the warmth and
the coolness sensations on the skin become apparent
as you're sitting here kind of a global wide
awareness of sensations along yours all over your body on your skin
maybe it's a flowing sensation a tingling a vibration
maybe there's some sensations that fleet in and out of awareness
spark in and out awareness as your attention roams around
and then notice where the contact of your skin may be against
your clothes or if you're lying down against the surface
you're lying down and on no to feel we're breathing has an impact
we're breathing in the inhale the expansion of the chest or the belly
lifting of the shoulders causes more contact
with your clothes or some surface
and you can feel the sensations of movement of contact
feeling the rhythm of sensations of the contact of the body breathing
moving as you breathe against your clothes or your
back of your chair
maybe even there's this very subtle movement a sensation of pressure way down to
the cushion you're sitting on
sensations in the front rib cage the back ribcage
the sides of the ribcage
maybe even the belly
and then bring your attention inside of your body maybe not far from
the skin bring your attention a little bit inward
to where you usually experience your
breathing
feeling the movement of sensation the changing sensations with the inhale and exhale
and as you exhale
relax deeper into your body soften the shoulders
as you exhale let this the belly become
softer
as you relax the holding in the body the tension you're relaxing or the extra energy
you're expending
softening relaxing in the face and there's less energy going into
holding the muscles
relaxing the shoulders and the arms unless energy is expended
and paradoxically with less energy expended in tension
more there can be a feeling of vitality or maybe even flowing energy
the same thing is true in the mind the thinking mind if there's any tension
or pressure agitation there maybe as you exhale you can relax
let go
expend less energy conscious energy
in mental activity
it turns out the mind works much better more creatively wiser
when less anxious or tense energy everything goes into it
and then settling in to the body
breathing
and here too the art of meditation
is to stay committed with breathing without a lot of extra
energy without any strain
and for some people it can be helpful the notion of being receptive
to the inhale
and to allow the exhale
maybe relaxing a teeny bit at the end of the exhale
to have a little pause micropause
so that is more sensitive to receiving the beginning of the inhale
how the inhalations were trounced how the inhale
how the inhale arises on its own
receptive to the inhales allowing the exhale
as maybe you would floating
on the sea gently
being lifted and gently lowered by the small waves coming and going
allowing yourself to be held
by the buoyant water
allowing yourself to float on the inhales and exhales
some effort is needed to be receptive and allowing
while at the same time letting go and
allowing the breathing
to come to awareness
letting go of your interest in thinking
and letting your interest be
in floating on the gentle waves of inhales and exhale
like you're floating on your back on a wide peaceful sea
gently being lifted and lowered by the peaceful waves
relaxing the tension associated with thinking
the pressure the contraction
allowing the thinking to become quieter
so you can trust staying with the breathing more fully
and if you can imagine yourself floating on the your back on a peaceful sea
imagine that as you're looking up into the sky and a few clouds are drifting by in the
blue sky that way stay connected
stay floating on your breathing but notice whatever thinking
is happening like thinking your clouds drifting by
not to be involved with the thinking but to have a kind of a view from a
distance
where there's very little energy
it used to be thinking letting go of the extra energy to think
to be involved to be engaged in thought relax the energy of thinking
the efforting of thinking and while you stay with the inhales and
exhales without a lot of effort
be aware of the thoughts that flow
through
and notice that as you're thinking do you think more in words
or more in images
or is it kind of equally both
and then in recognizing whether it's more words more images or equal
both is it easier for you to notice
your involvement with thinking the energy expended to think
the tension involved in thinking
and if so as you exhale
can you relax and quiet that energy that effort
and as you do so
settle more into your breathing
our bodies and our minds
operate more harmoniously
when we stop using unnecessary energy
effort
the very
effort to try hard at something unnecessary
it's counterproductive it interferes with the natural wisdom
the natural sensitivity and the natural harmony
that's available when we don't apply unnecessary energy
before we learn to not do so it's useful just to recognize
when there is unnecessary energy in the form of tension in the body
and the mind in the thinking
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting perhaps you can intuit or feel
oh without without tension
without this extra energy of tension and pushing and trying
there's more room in us for happiness
for well-being or there's more room for us for love for
good will compassion
and to end this sitting being open to the joys and sufferings of this
world and to be open to it without resistance
to breathe with it
to be willing to be a companion
to the world's joys and the joy the world's sufferings
to breathe with the world and in doing so
before needing to do anything more complicated perhaps you can be your kindness
spreads out from you to the world
a simple kindness which wishes well for others
wishes the best for them may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings
be peaceful may all beings
be free
you