so good day everyone greetings
and you know we've come together to do this
meditation and
the obvious thing is that the act of coming down to meditate sit down here to
be here to meditate together is an action and
meditation itself is a kind of action or in the traditional buddhist language
it's like it's kama karma which literally means action
and many people associate meditation with being rather than doing but the movement
to let go to allow itself to be um that is also an action that we do something we're doing
we let go so we can be and um and the
buddha tended to define people if he defined people or described people
by what they do not by how they are in a sense of
how they're born especially in ancient india that born into a particular caste was not
interesting for the buddha but how people acted and behaved did they behave ethically or not
and this is all leading up to the idea that um that in meditation sometimes people
focus a lot on their experience and they maybe they're not having a good experience and so they're trying to have
a better experience or let go of something that seems you know not good and
and fix it or something and and or try to do something that creates a great
experience and so they measure themselves by how they are and
in another whole approach is to let let be in a certain sense how you
are and now focus a little bit more on what you do
the actions so in meditation there are two actions
related to concentration that are important there's the action of
beginning again the action of the mind wanders off and we place it back in this case on the
breathing and we connect again with the breathing and the second act action is the action
of hanging in there with the breath once where we've landed on the breathing to continue
on the breathing and uh and and that's a little bit of an action
to do so and some people don't engage that way and so they're able to connect to the
breathing but they quickly wander off again because there isn't that second action okay now
stay there linger there hang out there get to know it better feel and explore the the breathing
really stay present and now so that's one whole thing but
the other thing that's the one what i want to stress today is that the orientation
around action is to do it in a way that's nourishing
to do it in a way that's enjoyable that's wholesome that nourishes us
has a good influence on us so that it's not just the action to do something quickly and
get it done with but to do something with an action that has a nice influence so it's
nourishing it's wholesome for our system so the very ideal way in which we the
mind wonders often thought the way we come back from that where we recognize that come back
reconnect to the breathing that's an action that we try to do it in a way that's
wholesome that's nourishing that's pleasant that has a good influence on us so he
wouldn't jerk the mind back we wouldn't attack the breath again bear down
we wouldn't be ambitious with greed and and for some kind of meditate meditation
states we're not expecting something demanding something it's more like like almost like a
tai chi movement you know that the movement itself is satisfying the movement itself is
meaningful that we come back and we just enjoy the coming back
because it's nourishing and wholesome and like we come back with care with love with with um
and then the second action of sustaining the attention over time hanging in there not bearing
down not keeping the mind in check not reigning the mind in all these forceful things but how can we
be stay in a nourishing supportive wholesome way a caring way and this art
and this exploration of how to have the actions we do in meditation the mental
actions be nourishing be satisfying be
you know enjoyable gladdening for us is part of this art and uh so learning exploring thinking
about this as we meditate so that um you know
we are not so goal oriented with the action but rather maybe like tai chi or
beautiful qigong practice where our dance practice we're just doing the movement
is so satisfying and meaningful that's the important thing not where it gets us and so
the movement of landing and staying on the breath the movement of of staying there and
sustaining it that's that's what supports uh a
uh nourishing samadhi nourishing concentration
um so to assume your meditation posture
and prepare yourself for the meditation a bit
to consider how you can be here in a wholesome way
how you can be here so that you enter into your the activity of
meditation with a sense of beauty or nourishment or
wholesomeness not in a hurry
not resisting anything
not expecting or demanding that your meditation should be a certain way
and then beginning right away to see if you can land on your breathing
connect to your breathing in a nourishing way in a nice way
wholesome way so the very way in which you take in the breathing and aware of it
has some maybe spaciousness care [Music] love tenderness
some way of being as you would be with a a good friend you care for
and the way you attend your garden when you're in love with your garden
and then in this caring nourishing way taking a slow gentle deep breath
allowing yourself to take in and feel the goodness of a deeper breath
and the goodness of allowing that to happen
and then relaxing as you exhale
relaxing your whole body
letting your breathing return to normal
and can you adjust a little bit your state of mind your state of your heart
just a little if that's all that's possible so you have a nice attitude a good
attitude wholesome
as if you're getting ready to
do tai chi or mental tai chi or mental gardening
and mental caring for something that you
love perhaps by relaxing the thinking mind
softening the energy of thinking
relaxing the muscles that are connected to thinking the pressure the tension to be here
and then gently calmly connecting to the beginning of the
in-breath receiving the beginning of the in-breath
and then sustaining the attention for however short or long the in-breath
is so you're there with a full in-breath sustained attention
connecting with the beginning of the out breath
and then sustaining the whole out breath
and these two movements of connecting
receiving the beginning of each in-breath and out-breath and then to
sustain the attention on the full out-breath the fallen breath
can you do that in a wholesome way nourishing way
it is an action can you make it an action which is free of greed or hatred
or delusion confusion free of
wanting it to be different
pushing something away aversion
is simplicity of maybe generosity
love and care
and the attention to the breathing
and to support the sustained attention through the exhale especially
you might count the exhales
a gentle careful count of one that maybe gets stretched out the
whole length of the exhale one [Music]
and then the next exhale two
if you lose count start over again and count up to ten or up to three
or up to one
exploring the wholesomeness and nourishment
of attending to the breathing
so then as we come to the end of this sitting
what do you know about having your mind be wholesome
nourishing
the mind which feels satisfied
and if the mind is not that way
can you remember that the mind is a collection
of mental activities it's not a thing
what can you adjust mentally your way you think what you think
what you're oriented towards what you're expecting hoping for
so that how you are mentally or heartfully
feels as if it has a good influence on you maybe if things are hard that what has a
good influence is to be forgiving
or to be friendly
or to be generous towards yourself
to have compassion for the challenges
to appreciate whatever wholesomeness is here
nourishment there is here
and let that be a reference point stay close to that or either feeling it or imagining it
and then again imagine that you're with someone who is challenging for you
but you don't have to speak or do anything you're just sitting in the same room together
and staying close to your nourishing mind your wholesome mind and heart
without having to do or say anything what happens if you take in the other
person the challenging person
if you think about them is there some way that
then there's a chance for your care your friendliness your tenderness
to be touched by that other person
and you staying close to that place where you feel wholesome
a way of being that feels satisfying for you
so not getting caught up in shoulds and shouldn'ts he said she said the resentments
the fears just staying close to what's wholesome for you
has a good influence on you
and then imagine that you do so for the whole world that you include the
whole world and your wholesome heart your wholesome mind your wholesome
awareness
that wholesomeness is the reference point for how to think and feel about other
people may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
you