hello everyone
i think it's one of the really wonderful things to do is to sit
down to meditate i think it touches into some of the
it relates to or it is connected to some of the more profound aspects of being a human being that are often
overlooked if we spend the day distracted spend the day preoccupied
and that if we can learn to stop everything in a certain kind of way
stop the busyness of the mind the preoccupations of the mind the spinning of the mind
that we have an opportunity to connect and feel
the depth of us or that which is at the core of us or that which is
has the most integrity or the most create a sense of peace and well-being
and it's a great thing that uh to do this so today um
we're still on the week of focusing on delusion
and today i'd like to offer you what could be considered a little bit of a
maybe advanced practice so don't feel like you have to do it well um but maybe it'll give you a taste of
something that will help you appreciate the absence of delusion or if not the
absence the opposite the prevalence of delusion in the mind
and this meditation has two uh two stages or two steps
first is uh the warm-up step just the kind of way of getting started
and warming up getting settled preparing ourselves getting ourselves ready for the second one
and so to engage in the first one with interest and a certain dedication
like okay this is worthwhile and let me kind of think of this as uh
as going through the warm-up exercise and so give yourself over to it the best
you can and then the second stage is um
to sit and meditate uh doing nothing except allowing awareness
to be open allowing awareness to be present for whatever wants to come into
awareness and the awareness in this circumstance and knowing the awareness the
mindfulness is with the mind that does doesn't move
the attention doesn't get directed anywhere attention doesn't get uh doesn't move
from the breathing to a sound or to you know anything
all those things can be known but the mind doesn't move the mind doesn't is not trying to do anything
it's just there doing nothing and what that can allow us to do is to
see how much the mind wants to move how much the mind goes this way in that way how
much desires are operating aversions are operating and delusion
and in fact the theory or the idea is that any time the mind has
greed or aversion and moves for that reason and uh there's some delusion that's
operating and perhaps even just theoretically or hypothetically any time the mind moves to go someplace
or pick something up or to avoid something or analyze something or fix something that
maybe there's a little bit of delusion operating there the delusion that the mind is not
capable of having profound peace by itself
so something like that so two stages of meditation today so for this first
step assume maybe your regular meditation posture
with giving some care and attention to establish yourself in that posture make
making small adjustments
to kind of get yourself aligned
and attuned to your body from the inside out
and to gently close your eyes
and giving yourself over to it giving your attention over
as if it's the only thing you need to do
take a few long slow deep breaths
and then as you exhale deeply fully relax the body
especially the shoulders
the whole upper torso let it settle and soften
and then letting your breathing return to normal and again also as you exhale
maybe a deeper softening relaxing first of the face
maybe more in the shoulders
and in the belly
and perhaps as you exhale you can also quiet the thinking mind
allowing the thinking mind to calm a bit slow down
and as you exhale relaxing the thinking muscle
the tension pressure to think
and then to settle in to the body's experience of breathing
not so much making a lot of effort to stay with the breathing
but to as you breathe
to shed the concerns for thinking
as you breathe and let the thinking recede like a water like a boat moving through
water that doesn't stop for the water and
but somehow just keeps going straight and the water just washes off the side
of the hull and is left behind stay on the breathing and let your
thoughts recede in the wake
in this first step of meditation is to let the thinking mind settle and quiet by just staying closely
connected to your breathing
um
as you exhale gently maybe sweetly
soften your body a softening move wave through the body
and as you exhale
gently sweetly a softening wave through the mind
as you exhale let there be a simple softening in the exhale
and then at the end of the exhale
let there be a stillness a silence
a kind of momentary pause where the mind becomes quiet
letting go of thoughts and concerns and for a moment awareness just is
without any rush of thinking and thoughts
the moment at the end of the exhale maybe the mind is quiet
like it would be if you were going to listen to a faint sound far in the distance
the quiet the stillness
where awareness just is for a moment without any doing on your
part
and that pause can be quite momentary but perhaps you can then
maintain this quiet still mind
as you inhale maybe it's a gentle receiving of the
inhale
where the sensations of inhale fill the space in the mind that is
normally filled with thinking and thoughts
seeing if you can let the mind the awareness consciousness
be still and quiet
noticing that aspect of consciousness where there's no work
no engaging inactivity of
being conscious or doing awareness
we're breathing in and breathing out is allowed to simply appear
in consciousness
and then letting go of any focus on the breathing see if you can let go of any doing in
the mind and if you start thinking that's a doing
if you intentionally focus on the breathing that's a doing
and rather than doing anything it's more like the mind is just very
still quiet peaceful nothing to do
experience appears in consciousness
breathing might appear sensations might appear
sounds without any preference for what appears
settle back into the still quiet mind
with nothing to do but where consciousness
in consciousness present moment experience
simply appears and maybe disappears
and if in this way of practicing it highlights how much the mind wants to
do then the exercise is working
you're seeing clearly
the doing momentum of the mind
but see if you can see it let's see if you can rest behind it or underneath it
to that place where consciousness doesn't need to do anything
consciousness just is and it's aware of the things that come
and go including the tendency to do
you
if you're thinking you're probably doing and involved in it
see if the mind cannot be actively involved in anything
the awareness not involved
except that phenomena appear disappear in consciousness
but consciousness itself is unmoving
awareness is not directed anywhere they're just very quiet and still
with a 360 degree
range of perception
you
and in the last minutes of the sitting
continue sensing or
maybe even imagining the sweetness
of consciousness which is at rest in itself
that doesn't have to work or do anything or avoid anything
consciousness or the mind is as at ease and peaceful and unmoving
as you've been in the best times of your life of being at peace or at rest
maybe a time when you finish the day's
work
and then perhaps within that awareness
you might spill or search for a place of sweetness tenderness
some people might call it inner goodness
with which now you can become aware of the people in your life
those you know because you don't know
people spreading out from where you are now out across the lands
across the oceans into the lands of other continents
and to take a few moments to appreciate
the basic humanity of all people
and offer a basic goodwill well-wishing
for all beings
and perhaps a wish for yourself that you could be peaceful
settled enough
to care for the welfare and happiness of others without that care being agitating
or any pressure with it may it be that you care for the welfare
and happiness of others in a way that's easeful
that actually is nourishing for you
with his ease wishing may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may you contribute to this possibility
so this will be the fourth talk on the topic of delusion and it
certainly builds on the first three and uh and the topic
that the kind of the title of it is is composting delusion
and i think of this uh as a kind of an advanced practice
because it does involve um it involves allowing delusion to be
present and delusion is one of the primary
sources of causing harm in the world or harm for ourselves so that's why it's an advanced practice
to allow for it but to do it without getting entangled with it without getting
caught in it and certainly without being motivated by the delusion
and um and so it's an alternative to the
attitude or the approach that when there's something undesirable
maybe even unwholesome going on in the mind that it's an alternative to trying to
fix it trying to make it better make it go away letting go of it
and which in and of itself sometimes is the operation of delusion so for
example there could be the idea that i will only be a good meditator or a good person
if i get rid of this delusion so i i have to do something to get rid of it
and there's a lot of baggage and some of it perhaps elusive around me myself and mine about who i
have to be operating in the movement to get rid of something or to stop it or fix it
of course sometimes it's completely healthy to fix something or let go of it so i don't want to say it's always that
case but the problem there's more delusion in that movement
than most people realize and so the alternative is to not try to fix anything or make anything
go away but without being caught in it and this
is where having a stable strong capacity of being still or present
especially in meditation where you're kind of committed to not moving or not saying anything during that time
and then it's safer to just allow things to be there and so we
if we are present enough to recognize something as to delusion then
so for example it could be there's fantasies that involve delusion of
grandeur delusions of how great it'll be if i could do x y
and z and and and you've done this so much that you see it clearly or this is kind of a
fantasy world that i'm living in and so we see it clearly
but we don't try to judge it or judge ourselves for it we don't try to get rid of it
but we do tr we allow it in a certain kind of way we allow it while we know
it is the illusion and that does a number of things one thing that's very important is that
it allows us to become more familiar with this tendency more we get to recognize
and feel and sense what this delusion is and one of the uh one thing one
principle is that it's things you only let go of things in
a healthy way when we really understood it if we let go of things before we really understand
it it might not really be letting go we don't really we maybe let go just the surface
symptoms of it and not really what's happening and there's there's a lot of wisdom that
comes from familiarity and just seeing something over and over and over again it's a little bit of a
bad news this idea because it may be uncomfortable to see something some things over and over again but in fact
to see it with a non-reactive mind to see it with without being entangled or caught and
without trying to get rid of it allows a deep something deep to begin
happening within us and one of the things that that can arise with that
is a very healthy kind of enough already a healthy feeling that
you know i'm not really i don't really value this anymore i don't i'm not behind it i'm not
motivated by it i don't care for it i see that this is actually this
particular delusion i'm having is not really healthy for me or for the world
and um and uh that insight that real clear seeing like that
is not aversion uh it's not um you know any kind of
hostility or but it is just a clear seeing oh look at that it's like if you put your hand on a hot
stove um if you do it long enough and become familiar enough with it uh you want to
pull your hand away like this enough of this i don't want to do this anymore and for most of us that
we don't need a lot of time on the on the stove on the hot stove i mean just uh you know milliseconds
we know that we don't want to do that that's not wise but some of the illusions of the mind it takes longer for us to see
oh the healthy movement oh this is not for me and um and and building on that
especially if the delusion continues and we don't necessarily doesn't doesn't necessarily stop
it can be a source a wonderful source to be motivated to practice and feeling
you know i don't really want to live this way anymore i think that the only way i know to really get to the bottom
of it and work through it is to practice is to meditate and so a person might dedicate themselves to
meditation or a contemplative life for a while so that they can really tap into something
deeper than the surface mind of delusion and preoccupations that maybe we've been
living in so this allowing of delusion to be there to become familiar with it
can produce a healthy feeling attitude of enough already and a healthy motivation okay i'm going
to get serious about my practice let's do let me practice more
the other thing about allowing delusion to be there this composting is digesting of it is that
i think it's often useful to think of things like delusion uh as being a symptom of something
deeper and if we allow it to be there just without reactions without being for against
it it allows something deeper to manifest or allow something that maybe
metaphorically is a seed within the delusion that's healthy it's beautiful to sprout
and and uh and uh maybe it's the opposite of some
of the uh some of the conditions for the delusion to be there
maybe uh what some of the conditions for delusion is anxiety or loneliness
or insecurity or very strong desire and but as we sit
quietly and allow the delusion to be there knowing its delusion then we begin recognizing over time that
something inside begins to morph and change and settle and the opposite of those unhealthy
movements are there there's we can recognize there's peace there that's growing within it we recognize there's um some feeling of
security some feeling of well-being and ease that's kind of growing there and it's beginning to show itself
that has a lot to do with the ability to sit still and not be engaged and
reactive to it so um and this is very respectful this
attitude this idea of composting or digesting or allowing things to be so something can
be transformed and changed in a deep healthy way i like to think of it as
being very respectful of life everything can be respected
everything nothing has to be seen as a problem nothing needs to be seen as uh even
in a sense maybe unnecessary it's all it's all to be respected as a deep
unfolding and working of our humanity and um and we have this amazingly fantastic
wondrous potential to move towards healing to health to wisdom to freedom
that uh it doesn't have to be intentionally worked on it's like we have to be the
doer of it as much as uh as getting out of the way
for this deeper potential to kind of really show itself where mindfulness awareness
this unmoving consciousness that's really present for things is the field or the soil out of this
transformation can happen and so um this composting of greed
hatred and delusion that i've been talking over this last weeks on thursdays i think of it as a it also
helps us discover this deep respect for everything a respect that doesn't celebrate
everything it doesn't condone everything but it's a respect
that doesn't condemn anything it doesn't um you know
disrespect or treat as being just wrong whatever is happening for us
in that field in that container of a clear awareness
of what's happening without being entangled with it and without being motivated by what's unhealthy and that's
why i think meditation is such a powerful laboratory a place for this to so the composting practices i've been
teaching these last thursdays please be very careful with them think of them as kind of advanced practices
and a little bit dangerous practice because it's so easy to fall into
to believe we're doing non-reactive and then believe that whatever's arising from within is somehow wonderful or important
or wise and we should just make room to allow things to just um you know then
some some kind of inner intuition or inner deep knowing can flow
as we get out of the way uh that attitude can be a kind of delusion as well and um
and so you'd be very very careful with this that we don't in no kind of way or giving in to
something that's going to cause harm to ourselves harm to others harm to everyone and
anything that perpetuates other delusions like delusions of self and
self grandeur and things like that so and with the composting practice i've
been talking about these last weeks it's probably if you really find it valuable or something that's meaningful
it's probably good to check in with a meditation teacher a little bit to make sure that you're on
the right track because it is possible to go a little bit off track doing this kind of practice so
thank you very much and i look forward to our last talk on this topic delusion
tomorrow