okay so why don't we go ahead and get
started this evening
it's nice to see at least uh
on the screen a couple of comments there
know that you're out there and um
welcome to our monday evening sit
uh diana is away so i'm very happy to
be here some of you uh know me
i've taught a number of times at imc for
a while
and it's a delight to share this time
with you
so let's go ahead and get started with
our meditation
so finding a posture that's
upright also relaxed
and something where you'll be able to
sit for a little while
just feeling a sense of settling in
so knowing that you've arrived
for the sitting
and if you're comfortable doing so you
can
close your eyes just let your eyes
gently
close if you're more comfortable with
them open that's okay
but usually in our practice we would
keep them closed
maybe taking a couple of long slow deep
breaths
to really bring the air into the body
and then on the exhale
encouraging the shoulders to drop
the body to soften up the
spine to still remain upright
so we're settling into
a posture that is at ease
and also alert
and then you may begin to bring the
attention
inward and just
encourage some ease
in parts of the body that we often hold
tense
so softening the muscles of the face
the forehead around the eyes
jaw
softening the eyes and the eye sockets
especially if we've been looking at the
screen often the eyes get a little tense
and down through the shoulder area
letting the shoulders drop
maybe thinking of the shoulder blades
sliding down the back
so we don't slump as we
soften the shoulders
down the arms into the hands
releasing any tension in fingers from
typing
[Music]
and down into the torso area softening
the chest
maybe deliberately feeling the front
back and sides of the ribcage
also when we look at the screen a lot of
our energy tends to go
forward in the body so it's so helpful
to
bring the attention to the back
the back of the ribcage
down through the belly letting the belly
be soft
all the way down into the hip joints
feeling the seat against the chair or
the cushion
or the bench wherever you're sitting
letting that support you
and softening down through the legs
[Music]
releasing any bracing or
tension in the knees or the ankles
and if you can feeling all the way into
the feet
so then having invited ease through the
body
just returning attention to the full
sense of the body sitting general
overall
sense
and just being at ease mentally with how
the body is right now
it's fine just as it is
gently allowing the attention to settle
onto the sensations of breathing
these sensations are very simple
almost elemental
touch of the air on the nostrils or the
upper lip
sense of coolness and nasal passages
some sense of expansion
maybe the shift of clothing against the
skin
maybe even a sense of tension near the
top of the
in-breath and then that stops and
we begin the out breath there's a
different kind of movement
maybe warmth as the air exits
it's a whole kaleidoscope of
simple sensations in sequence
and we can just flow along with that
just as we invited ease through the body
we can begin to encourage ease of the
mind
perhaps using the body is a simple way
to
stabilize the mind body is sitting still
relatively
so we encourage the mind to become
simpler stiller
certainly the goal is not to end our
thinking
or eliminate any emotions
present but more to have a simple
presence
with whatever is here
just as we can be simple with the
movement of the
breath in the body we can be simple with
the movement of thoughts emotions
the normal activity of the mind
let me just try not to get so caught up
in it
but instead just to hold it in simple
awareness
and if the mind has gotten caught up in
thought some concern
it's no problem as soon as you notice
just returning to the simple
presence of the body simple awareness
can anchor in the breath or the body
in fact we may even notice that
the moment that we come back when
there's
presence again there's a little bit of
joy it's actually
slightly pleasant to be
present
so i encourage you in this sitting to
notice
the simple joy that accompanies
mindfulness
even if what we're mindful of is some
discomfort in the body
or in the mind the mindfulness
itself has a certain
quality of joy to it
i'm just seeing if you can notice that
from time to time
as you continue with regular practice
oh
in this meditation continuing on
if you begin to feel
some degree of ease in the body
or the mind just from
having settled even a little bit
you're encouraged to tune into that
feeling that pleasant feeling of
well-being
or a little bit of peace or
softness in the body
or a mild kind of joy
in the mind
we don't need to only be
neutrally mindful about our experience
it's actually fine if we're feeling
meditative feelings of well-being
to open to those
include them explicitly
bring our mindfulness to those also
so that they are supported and nourished
in a natural way and if you don't feel
so much of that that's okay
too
but just to be aware when such
sense of ease arises and allow it to
to be nourished
you
the monk tanissero bagu
says that sometimes as he practices with
the breath
he just has the simple idea
of not adding any new tension
on the in-breath and
releasing a little bit more tension
on each out breath
that could be physical or mental
tension
and practicing in that way it's very
easy to tune into the ease that's
present
so that we're not adding anything on the
in-breath
and we're deepening into the ease on the
out breath
whatever use is available
and in the last few minutes of this
meditation
[Music]
i'm going to invite
just a brief reflection
if it's of interest
as you continue to sit in meditation
with the breath with body
bringing the mind into the present
moment
just reflect
on any sense of delight
or joy or gratitude
for the dharma for
your practice for
having a path to walk however it is that
you
think about this role of dharma in your
life
consider the appreciation or positive
feelings from that
just keeping the mind simple maybe even
feeling in the body that feeling
simple sense of joy and the dharma
however that is for you
i'm just resting and breathing with that
that feeling
[Music]
you