okay great so formally hello and welcome everyone dear
sangha to happy hour so so i missed you on friday i was
teaching a a day long part of a
leadership program i've been teaching in five month leadership training the reason why i mentioned that is that
one of the themes that um i was
sitting with and it's been a lie for me and i want to bring in that theme tonight is borrowed from
that context of what makes teams what makes you know
when you have when you are working or volunteering or
or even your family units you know you have a team of maybe you're throwing a party and you have you know people
you're working with so any team what makes teams
successful what makes teams really really work at their best and it turns out
that there's a lot of research about this and and google for example being
you know that there's so many scientists there and so they've done so many studies and it turns out that the number
one there are many value variables there are five they come up with but number one is psychological safety
wow isn't that interesting the number one factor that makes teams
really cohere and work and succeed psychological safety
which to me is ties in with meta i'll i'll tell i'll
say more in a minute but the idea of psychological safety from this context is
offering yourself and offering team members um
this the sense of you know they can disagree they can say what they want there's not
a sense of retribution you know people won't be shut down immediately
for voicing their opinion or if something is going wrong or for for making a mistake
making a mistake there's a sense of psychological safety it's okay
it's okay and those teams the teams that have psychological safety succeed the most
uh which makes sense right if something is not going right if people are scared
to speak up then it will continue to go off the rails but
that's one way people have the ability to brainstorm make mistakes take risks
so now let's take that idea for ourselves for
our team this team that is me with all my voices inside you know all
the the uh the ways i speak to myself the way that i show up the way that i put myself down
the way that i disagree with myself the ways i the way i tell myself stop you can't think that you made a mistake bad
bad bad so as a person as a being with all these
voices that come up for us internally
how can we offer ourselves psychological safety so that's what i like to bring in
tonight as as a practice of meta and also
to tie it into meta in the following way remember the first phrase of metta
is may i be safe from inner and outer harm may you be safe from inner and outer
harm ah safety hello
here it is you see the connection this idea of offering safety especially
to ourselves may i be safe from inner harm and inner harm is the harm that we call
ourselves through not offering ourselves this
sense of safety the sense of psychological safety not opening our own heart
to ourselves so so [Music]
that's the connection i like to bring in for the practice of method tonight offering ourselves
safety offering other safety so that people feel safe in our presence
they can disagree they can say what what's on their mind and it's okay
we won't shut them down right away we won't be angry we have the sense of
stability and resilience and open heart to be curious they can
make mistakes they can fail yay they can fail
and not be quote-unquote perfect and it's okay they can feel safe we can offer
people safety psychological safety the safety so
[Music] in meta practice safety is number one is
the first phrase of the four phrases and in research in multi-variable
research and industry and you know various places psychological research oh
it turns out psychological safety too is number one far more than the composition
of teams etc etc so i think that is
not surprising not surprising at all so
ah with that as the setup let's
practice let's begin so so i'd like to invite you invite us
to land to land in our bodies
letting all the words go no words needed at this moment
arriving
arriving in this body in this moment
offering ourselves safety psychological safety things don't need to be any different right now we might be tired
we might be sad we might be anxious we might be achy
whatever is showing up right now is okay it's fine
ah the next exhale relaxing into the body making space
for whatever is showing up in this moment
reality as it is in this body in this heart in this mind
maybe we've had a hard day it's okay maybe we've had a lovely day
okay opening our hearts
opening the door of our heart letting in letting in all the guests
okay it's all right come in
there's plenty of space in this heart for disappointment sadness confusion
heartache joy [Music] excitement
body aches body energy whatever
ah welcome welcome them all welcome
welcome them all
and inviting this body the muscles to relax
to soften
starting with our eyes let them rest in the socket
our forehead let it soften [Music]
the jaw relaxing
neck and shoulders
the arms and the hands giving their way to the earth
feeling the sensations in the hands
relaxing the chest
fighting the heart the heart center
the proverbial
space for emotions to relax be just as it is
fighting the abdomen to relax and soften
bringing awareness to the sit bones
fighting the lower legs the upper legs the knees
the feet to offer their weight to the earth
entire body feeling a little heavier
deliciously heavier settled
receiving the breath in the abdomen the lower abdomen the abdomen receiving the breath
each breath the entirety of the breath in and out just to settle and
calm your mind just to arrive
if your mind wanders to a thought
or memory or daydream it's okay it's all right
no need for judgment offering your mind your heart safety
safety the mind will wonder it's okay
it's all right
just notice simply notice what it's resting on
ah this yes this
and then ever so gently inviting
the puppy of the mind to return to
return the breath and the abdomen to settle
aware of the breath this is part of the training
is coming back without judgment with curiosity with kindness
knowing that all minds do this it's not just yours you're not defective
offering yourself safety kindness
maybe even the next time you notice the mind is thinking
has gone off maybe try saying it's okay sweetie it's okay it's all right
smiling feeling the breath in the belly
and smilingly joyfully
coming back home coming back home to rest
with the breath
offering safety to yourself your poor mind
this often restless mind this heart this body offering safety
to ourselves it's okay it's okay dear it's okay
maybe there was something your day or your week
it was challenging for you you tried your best it was confusing difficult
maybe you made a mistake or failed in something
it's okay it's all right
offering yourself safety psychological safety safety
see what happens when you offer yourself safety
and don't be afraid that you'll become a slacker
couch potato it turns out that through offering our
self-safety with care and compassion we take more responsibility
so see how that feels internally for you
let that fear if it comes up let that fear feel safe it's okay fear it's all
right come here hang out i'm not gonna push you away or
give you the reins of my mind
can you offer safety to whatever is coming up
in this moment
just breathing receiving the breath
with kindness
may i be safe from inner arm
i offer myself safety
may i love and accept myself just as i am whatever version works for you
or without words
notice if there can be more ease and peace in your heart and your body and your mind
you offer yourself safety every time the mind wanders you don't yank it back
jerk the mind back into the present moment with force but just gently
it's okay dear it's all right ah
sense of ease it's all right it's part of this training this is how we trained
our mind our puppy gently gently returning every time
now you can stay with yourself offering safety kindness
as an expression of mental loving kindness to yourself as a part of this training
the most important part of this training
so either stay with yourself or if you like
and consider someone in your life or someone's in your life you like to
offer more safety too from you for more psychological safety too
may you be safe from me may i be safe for myself may i be safe
for you i wish to offer you safety
psychological ease and safety in my presence
radiating as if your heart your heart center is radiating
slight as a warm caring light of safety
touching you first relaxing your body your heart your mind
and then shining out offering safety
touching with safety
the ones you are considering in your mind's eye right now
may i be safe for myself and others
may i allow space for ease for mistakes
for imperfection in myself and others
i feel the goodness in myself and others
offering safety from judgment
and ill will internally and externally
recognizing you're doing the best you can so are others
given all the causes and conditions that have come to be
every time you find your mind has wondered relax into safety some more
into ease no need to judge yourself
relax
and for the last moments of this practice period together
offering offering yourself safety from judgment
from however this practice period was so you were sleepy the mind was
distracted it's okay you showed up you did your best
offering safety without judgment to yourself
it's okay offering appreciation yay i showed up as
best as i could
it's the best any of us can do
trusting there is goodness there's goodness and just showing up even with
one moment of awareness and kindness
to yourself and or others planting seeds
trust trust your planting seeds
and offer offer the goodness trusting in the goodness offering the goodness to
yourself and to all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere
be safe from inner and outer arm may all beings everywhere
be happy and free including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
ah safety
so the more i have practiced with metta
the more i have discovered that it's not accidental
that the first of the four phrases of meta have to do with safety
i'll say all four phrases traditionally they are may i may you be safe from inner and outer
harm may i you be happy may i you be healthy
may i you have ease in our lives so safety happiness health
and ease are the four wishes of course we can change them many teachers change
it and it's all fine and you can change them to be whatever worked for you
so in some teachers shift didn't change it make happy to be
number one may you be happy start with that and safety comes at the end that's how originally i had started to practice
with may i may you be happy being the first one and then later when i was starting to step into the
role of you know being a teacher and sharing the dharma i looked at the order and he looked like
oh safety is first i wonder why so i practiced that way intensely i
remember one retreat it was a month-long retreat meant to retreat where i did
happy as first and realized wow there needs to be i'm sorry i need i
need i did safety is first ah let me rewind i did safety as the first
one as canonically off suggested that you do may i be safe may you be safe as the
first wish of the four i discovered that this wish for safety is so
fundamental this feeling safe feeling safe our bodies and mind and heart is so
fundamental it's really it's it's what holds everything else it holds happiness and health and and
ease until you have a sense of safety in your heart in your mind
and also um it ties in with the attachment theory of bolby's attachment theory in terms of
safety in our hearts anyway there's so much ears and and now also this connection to the world of research
about teams and work offering ourselves and each other safety so safety what an important
[Music] gift to cultivate it's a gift to cultivate gift to cultivate for
ourselves for others so i'd like to invite you to share reflections
in the space please especially if you haven't spoken for a while you're welcome to raise your hands or
type in chat if you type to me alone on zoom i will only
say read out your reflection not your name if it's to everyone i will read your
name also so what did you notice what did you observe
our questions comments anything is welcome
neil says a lovely practice i feel all warm and cuddly ah
thank you neil yeah it is a lovely practice isn't it offering ourselves safety
yeah sweet yeah
ah our hearts feel more ease did any of you try especially you know
when your minds went um off to say it's okay dear it's okay sweetie
and kind of easing into safety a little more did you try that
yerba says this meditation made me feel cozy and empowered ah thank you here but
i'm so happy to hear that yay cozy and empowered beautiful
dimensions of just feeling contented and a sense of empowerment coming out of that thank you
yerba aurora says this was very timely in the middle of a covet scare and really
needed to offer myself safety ah thank you aurora yeah
safety yeah safety to our minds
another share it was a difficult sit initially because i have been having trouble feeling safe
in my body due to some health challenges so when i remembered safety i decided to
lay on the floor with a blanket and it helped soften some of the edges fantastic
great i am delighted to hear the inner wisdom
to to say hey body's feeling challenged
and lying down with a blanket with just blankets make us feel safe right
safety blanket and and softening the edges beautiful thank you for sharing that beautiful yeah delighted to
to hear how that came up and how you worked with that thanks for that share
the other reflections i was asking if anyone tried the being kind especially kind to your mind
when it goes off mary says in practicing first to give myself safety i was able to see how a
friend who's often critical of me perhaps is not feeling safe themselves
i was able to offer safety for them oh beautiful what a beautiful insight
what a beautiful insight yeah that's often the case when people feel threatened
themselves then it's it's hard for them to offer safety to others both with friendships and also
in work relationships jamie says it was nice to be preoccupied
and then distracted and then sleepy and no it was all okay yes great yeah sense
of safety and and jamie did you when when you noticed all that and it's
like oh was it a sense of ease and safety um that
just said like it's okay i don't have to feel bad about it it's like so the one yeah you see your nod and smile yes
and so then that moment that actually one comes to like oh yes there's a depth there's a settling that can happen in
that moment when there is safety if you notice that it's like yeah the mind was sleepy in here like
ah now i can settle let's notice that moment it can be
very nourishing very nourishing lovely yay internal safety
so dear ones let's turn into small groups and see if
we can continue to offer ourselves safety and offer each other safety
and let the rubber meet the road of of relating to each other
in this sphere and the space of safety so important to practice and and if
you're on the edge if you're like oh no no i don't feel safe getting into small groups maybe stretch stretch yourself
just a tiny bit given that this is the theme see what it feels what it feels like
so one reflection i notice that when we are
in breakout rooms i feel safer when talk taking the time to do a few seconds of
sitting quietly before we share to know that i'm with like-minded folks beautiful yay
so we'll do that again tonight we'll start with a 15 30 seconds of meta silently for
yourselves for each other offering safety to each other to yourselves in silence
and then share as much as little as you wish about your your practice take care of
yourselves take care of each other and the rooms are created and now they
are open here we go okay
welcome back everyone the rooms are closed so we have um a few minutes for any reflections that
came up for you that you liked each that you like to share please
especially if you haven't spoken for a while neil please
so this practice reminded me of a time i went horseback riding when i was six years old
maybe seven i don't really recall it was just me and my dad my dad's standing right i don't think he ever
touched a horse if he could avoid it um you know he was a brooklyn boy
um and we were in a little corral i was just going around in circles and some horses
galloped on by and my horse took off it was like crazy you know
and my dad he didn't yell stop neil right instead he jumped in front of the
horse right i don't know what he was thinking i'm sure he didn't know either but you know sort of you know i keep
thinking about that because it kind of like was obvious to him telling me to stop was pointless
you know i was not the one in control of that right i was being taken for the ride
you know you know and there would be no point you know him yelling at me for having not stopped the horse would have
been ludicrous right i mean gosh i didn't want it to do that either
um you know so that thought came to mind here tonight you know you know you know sometimes
your mind just takes you for a ride and you just have to figure out how to manage it
hopefully not getting run over and trampled in the process
yeah thank you neil i appreciate what you're talking about is really a lesson
in you know thanks for sharing the story first of all and and how frightening that must have been as a little boy for the
for this horse to just take off and your dad trying to support and also his wisdom not to say you know shouted you
but realize yeah but just you know you're not in control and having the same sense of oh yeah my mind i'm not
always in control of my mind and that's really an insight into anata not self
it's like it's impersonal you can't say my damn it it's you know bad it's like oh sweetie it's okay you're running off
again okay come come so it can only tame it or train it with with this gentleness
with this kindness yeah thank you thank you
jesse please
hey thanks uh yeah just uh along the lines of what you said about the mind wandering what struck me today is that
it really is just a fantastic opportunity to practice kindness right at that moment and i was wondering
if you are recommending like saying a specific different other phrase like so like i'm normally saying
may i be safe maybe happy but then when my mind wanders i'm drifting off i'm just wondering if that's
um should i say like good job or welcome back or you know i'm just wondering what what types of
how i could be supportive to myself in that specific moment of noticing that the mind has wandered
yeah yeah yeah very good very good point so so it's um
what um what feeds what supports what nourishes
you know there is the carrot and there's the stick right method so the moment that you realize that you know you
become awake you know your mind has been gone forever many minutes right just
minds do that and and the moment you become awake instead of going oh bad mind you've been
gone right and so and you're and so you're not you know
but i'm giving the complete picture and i'm going to get to your the details every question for a moment and now you're asking so in that moment do i
just bring it back and continue and say may i be safe you know continue the practice or do i actually acknowledge in
that moment do i do something more in that moment so great so in that moment it is helpful it
does feed it will like it's a carrot to actually celebrate
that moment to actually say yay i'm awake now oh sweetie it's okay come back you know it's something positive you
know bringing something positive in that moment instead of definitely not something negative like how bad you were
sleepy and and and neutral is fine but it's kind of nice to bring in yay just a
little bit of a smile oh yeah a moment of awakeness yeah i'm awake now i'm yay and
oh or or what i was suggesting tonight like it's okay it's okay there's a sense of comfort there oh it's okay and so try
that yeah it's okay when you find yourself you've been gone and see if that it's okay with kindness
if it lands you deeper than just going back so that's what my
recommendation is you experiment with it for a while and some
you know or for a long time so yes does that does that make sense
thank you great thank you jesse christine over time so this needs to be really
quiet really quick or i'll stay over time
not sure what you're saying my dear oh okay yeah
it just occurs to me um that i i think when when david sat in
for you was he was that he's sitting in for you here at happy hour where did i hear him yeah and he
suggested when when you come back well that when my mind goes away it is always
going it is always going somewhere to try to make me safe
it's going somewhere to try to figure something out to make me safe right
and so he suggested when you come back to say oh thank you for
working so hard to try to make me safe like um great great that's that's it
whatever positive thing you put in there whether say it's okay sweetie welcome back or thank you as long as it's it's a
positive reinforcement you whatever works for you christine as long as it's a positive reinforcement
basically in psychological terms yeah sounds good thank you all thank you all so much for
showing up for your practice for offering safety to yourselves and others
and i want to share this link by the way for for those who might have been intrigued about psychological safety at
work that i shared it's in chat and let's bring this session to a close
maybe we'll do this theme again more later may all beings be safe may all
beings be free may all things be happy including ourselves
thanks everyone