so good day everyone and welcome to this meditation session
and uh where this week we're looking at this category of this idea of
that all experiences are either pleasant unpleasant or neutral neither pleasant
or unpleasant and and these tie into
the teachings we had a few weeks ago in the wholesome and the unwholesome and there are some feelings of
pleasure or pleasantness of happiness that are wholesome and some that are not
wholesome and this simplistic way perhaps of
distinguishing between the two is if there's craving some kind of attachment
connected to it to the joy the happiness the pleasant pleasantness it's considered unwholesome unbeneficial
but if there's no attachment to it and and no
yeah no attachment to it at all then probably it can be considered wholesome
it's beneficial and so there are beneficial forms of well-being beneficial forms of
of pleasure that are used in meditation
and it isn't so much maybe used as the wrong word but are where we avail themselves of them we
allow them we make room for them uh in a certain way we kind of prioritize
them not strongly or intensely or with attachment or expectation
but we learn to recognize them and in their recognition of them
it supports us to be present the mind wants to be with things which
are pleasant and there are feelings that we can have that are
um within our body in our in our inner life which um
have no attachment in fact that some of them actually arise
with non-attachment with non-clinging or non-craving there's just goodness and this freedom
this lightness this ease that comes when we don't contract around desires that i just feel so good it's so
pleasant like a fresh air after being in a stuffy place for a while
and uh so as we sit in this meditation um rather than looking at the
pleasantness of
the conditions around us or the pleasantness of the conditions of
you know if you happen to be sitting in a very comfortable chair it might be very pleasant or there's
nice music playing or nice temperature it's nothing wrong with that
but that would not be the pleasure or the the wholesome well-being
that somehow is made in the space of the heart space of the in the inner
life that is opened when we let go
and so to sense and feel the wholesome well-being sense and feel the
the the uh that inner well-being
inner pleasantness inner uh that comfort which seems to be opening
seems to help let go of distractions let go of preoccupations let go of clingings of
all kinds or even let go of let go or fade away
anxieties and clinging so we have this within us as possibility
this capacity and it requires a little bit shifting our paradigm
shifting the orientation with which we are moving through the world especially
in meditation if we move through meditation
with the habit of selfing of referring everything back to
the self me myself and mine is probably some attachment there so there's less room for these pleasant
things if we are always pursuing
pursuing pleasure we actually narrow the space within which to feel the
wholesome well-being and joy so to assume a meditation posture
and maybe sway back and forth a bit sideways and
forward and backwards you kind of have to maybe even rotate around
as a way of kind of connecting to your body helping you find a
a comfortable upright or comfortable posture in which to
settle into
gently close your eyes
and taking a few long slow leisurely
breaths maybe three quarters full on the inhale
maybe a little fuller release of the exhale
deep inhale and then on the exhale
relax and settle in to your body here and now
and then letting your breathing return to
normal
and if you appreciate your physical body
does that make you a little bit more prone
to feel what is pleasant in your body
if you appreciate your inner life
in this body does that make you more prone to
feel and sense an inner sense of
pleasantness pleasure
well-being even right next to any feelings of
the opposite
and then there's there anything if you appreciate your body breathing is there anything in the
breathing that's pleasant
or has a rightness to it or that you appreciate
letting go of your thoughts quieting your mind so there's more space
and awareness to feel
the body's experience of breathing
and letting your mind become quieter
not as a fight with the mind
but as a way of letting the mind feel and sense
something wholesome something
connecting something tender gentle pleasant
here as you breathe in and breathe out
breathing in and breathing out
breathing with
whatever is simple and pleasant
especially that which has to which you have no attachment
no clinging letting go of clinging an attachment
so there's more space to feel the goodness
that remains
if you are involved in thinking you're missing out on an
intimacy with the pleasant the wholesome
that's within
so
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to see if there's some room you can make within
to feel some inner well-being
a place of tenderness or softness or
warmth something that you appreciate
that is has a sense of goodness or rightness
that's within you in your heart in your chest in some part
of your inner life maybe as you exhale to
settle into it as you inhale
expand it
but resting in this place of what's pleasant in your inner life
now imagine that nothing is required of you
nothing you have to say or do but people
in your life come in front of you and what is it like
to receive them in this place
in your inner life of goodness of pleasure well-being just to receive their
presence without needing to react or respond or
want anything almost like you're welcoming them to also
feel the rest the pleasantness that's there
maybe receiving them as a pillow receives your head
not going out towards them but just to being available
to perceive and sense and be present for them in this receptive way
so that others have a place
in your inner well-being and from there perhaps you can
evoke well-wishing for these other people
extend your good will to them and to all beings
so that your inner well-being your inner freedom
includes a profound connection to other human beings
may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all me beings
be free and may we contribute
to the welfare and happiness of all
um continuing on this series talking about
the vedana the pali word for feeling or feeling tone
and uh it's the feeling tone has to do with the subjective
experience that the nature of our experience so that when we
feel something physical like say we feel the warmth of the sun that um certainly their their senses are
activated uh maybe you can say on the surface of the skin just for the sake of that the thought
exercise but the feeling is a little bit deeper inside
because it's the interaction of the sensation a little bit with our response to it our
evaluation our perception of it and so it isn't just pleasant in
and of itself but there is uh some degree of it is also our
how we receive it how we meet it and so it's considered to be a more subjective
and so if we begin by going at the physical level like at the skin level with feeling
toned we're going a little bit deeper inside into what's more subjective it's it's
something that uh only we experience you know somebody else might experience the warmth that they're standing next to us
but only we um the uh you know have our own experience of that
subjective experience of of the warmth and it might be a little bit different than the person next to us
because as the warmth hits our skin and is felt subjectively
the subjective nature of it is partly this interaction with our mentality our
history our associations our responses to it and the person next to us has a whole
other set of those so we're starting to get into something very personal subjective
and we're beginning to take a movement deeper and deeper into this inner life and this is one of
the channels into it so the feeling tones are pleasant unpleasant or
neither pleasant or unpleasant and and it's it's it's simplistic because
every experience can be has these simple qualities to it
of course pleasant can be a wide range of things from just a mild sense of comfort to intense
ecstasy the unpleasant can be again mild discomfort to extreme you know
pain and um so there's a whole range but to reduce it to this very simple
label or pleasant and unpleasant or the literal poly is more like happy and
uh and painful is um
is um makes it can make things a lot simpler and help us become freer more simply so
if you go into a social situation that's very uncomfortable people are arguing and
and all kinds of terrible things are happening in you know in this conversation at a party for example or
something at work at a meeting and uh and um to try to figure out what's going
on and to understand the details and what you have to do and it gets very complicated but
to take a moment and recognize this is unpleasant
i know how to be with unpleasant things when things are unpleasant i can just kind of open up and be still
and quiet and just feel the unpleasantness i don't have to be reactive to it i know
how to be non-reactive which is just unpleasant it's intensely unpleasant
and and simplifying it to that level free of the drama and the stories of all connected
can be a given avenue a doorway into relaxing and opening up and finding
our balance getting grounded in the situation that might be faster
than trying to you know navigate the situation in order to to feel that so same things with things
are very pleasant oh this is pleasant and i know about pleasantness
and i know how to be present forward to experiencing it without leaning into it and without chasing
after it or something just allowing it to be there and feel it and this is a very powerful thing to do
if you want to start becoming free in the midst of your experience
and there's a number of ways you can to kind of experiment with this depending how motivated you are
how far you want to take some of these things one of the things that i did in my early years of buddhist practice
was that when i had an occasion to feel pain like for example i was i was
working on a farm at the at the zen center or different kinds of physical work that i
had to do some of it was painful for example i remember having to carry heavy objects
for a long distance and after a while it hurt a little bit i'll carry this heavy object
and so i made it an exercise that not to hurt myself but to see where can i find equanimity
with a pain where can i find non-reactivity with a pain just to feel it clearly recognize it's there but
but not get reactive to it and not take it personally not have pity for myself or
get angry at the situation around me just to feel the simplicity of the pain so i wasn't intentionally hurting myself
but when these things occurred i would take them as my practice until it felt like it was no longer
appropriate and then i'd put the thing down that i was carrying or whatever it was
another thing that a place to discover if you're motivated that i think is generally generally
probably pretty safe is is to take cold showers
and see if you can stand under the stream of the cold shower and find your equanimity find your
non-reactivity find your ability just to breathe easily and calmly and
feel the cold going going over your body and not cringe and not pull back and not
complain and not feel panic at the cold just and it might take a
while to kind of be able to stand there and just feel the cold uh and and say this is unpleasant but
um but then um you know okay i know how to be here and and in
the process of doing that you might not get to some wonderful result but you'll learn a lot about your reactivity and maybe you'll learn to
kind of settle and quiet some of the reactivity around the cold shower and these things in
working with pain working with um with the cold showers for example
is a training to really kind of understand our reactivity to understand the option
of not being non-reactive and in fact some things that they're initially uh
we know their fields you know we would subjectively say are very unpleasant can actually shift and become pleasant
i've done this exercise with the cold showers and after a while sometime i learned to relax and relax and relax
i came to really enjoy i felt it was actually felt pleasant to take cold showers but i needed to
have the body begin to relax and soften and and be there
but it isn't so much that you know have a life of cold showers but to use that to learn about how we
can relax and open and because
what's more important more important in terms of dharma practice
with time we're connecting to something that's deeper than physical pleasure of any
kind at all deeper than the kind of pleasure that it's not even pleasure anymore
but rather it's a deeper sense of well-being or happiness to the people who can make a distinction
between pleasure and happiness that's a happiness that can be there
even when things are unpleasant uh we're opening to the kind of pleasure that's considered wholesome
a kind of pleasure that is not connected to directly to our senses being stimulated
it isn't because something nice is touching our skin our tongue our eyes our nose our ears it's a
pleasant sound for example it's also because not because the world out there
is telling us things which are pleasant for us to hear if someone says oh you're such a
wonderful person you're like the best person um you're great um
that is kind of an external stimuli which is stimulating something that you
know or conceit or something but there's a well-being that can well up from the inside
that is not because anything is being stimulated by stimuli from the outside
or stimuli from the inside if we're telling ourselves stories or fantasies
or something and so to discover this place to open to relax to be non-reactive
not for the purpose of being non-reactive so much but to make room to start sensing and
feeling the well-being that the pleasure that is not of the senses
and and so this distinction between of the senses and not of the senses a
little bit my vocabulary but that distinction is there in the buddha's teachings on mindfulness practice at some point as
we start continuing to practice with this vedana the feeling tone
the idea is to begin differentiating between a wholesome
pleasure wholesome well-being and that which is could still be wholesome there's a
distinction and of the senses and not of the senses
and this whole substance a wholesome experience of not of the senses um is something we
open to and then if we really discover this then we carry our well-being
with us wherever we go we're not so dependent on the conditions around us be just right so that we feel
at ease and feel peaceful so this uh you know dramatic exercise of standing
in the cold shower it's not so that you can learn to stand in the cold shower it's to learn how to release and relax
the reactivity we have to unpleasantness and then to discover that that
non-reactivity gives us access to open and re and connect to something quite precious and
beautiful something that a feeling may be of abundance or goodness or
or warmth or safety that lives within and i'll talk more
about this tomorrow and and tell you a little more about the buddhist languages of it
but um so some people are very oriented towards
their senses sense stimuli stimulating them and
and there's a whole other way to go through the life which is deeper and fuller and more profound
more sublime which is this welling up from the inside out that's not dependent on outside in
and that's one of the purposes of meditation is to discover that
so thank you so we'll continue tomorrow