okay so again warm greetings and happy to be here with all of you and
this week where we're considering exploring the topic of calm calmness
and one of the frequent references in
teaching so the buddha to calmness is physical tranquility
so not just a mental calm but a physical calm as well and uh in preparation for this
meditation imagine that you are maybe
you know a little bit tired and worked hard during the day or something or came in out of the cold
and you sat down in a very comfortable chair
and you and it just felt so good to be received
by the chair and settle into the chair and you can just let go and relax so many of your muscles and everything
so in the same way it's possible to take an alert posture an upright posture a
good posture for meditation and then inwardly
somehow in that you know in the back side of your muscles
or something i have the same feeling or movement of
settling into a comfortable chair so settling in even if your body has some discomfort and it takes some work
to effort to hold your posture upright
the um something inside of you perhaps can have the feeling or allow it to have
the feeling of relaxing into the posture
into a posture that's not moving that's still a posture that will
receive you that'll contain your experience
and to settle in and let that the stillness of the body
the calmness of the body whatever you can feel be a support for the meditation
so assuming your meditative posture
and gently lowering your gaze relaxing your gaze
and if it's comfortable to close your eyes
and take a few moments to with your eyes closed or
to make small adjustments in your posture
small adjustments in the alignment of your spine
the positioning of your shoulders sometimes shoulders can come back a
little bit so they're not rolling forward
feeling how the weight of your body centers itself on your sitting bones
is the center of gravity in front of the sitting bones behind the sitting bones
can you make some adjustments so the center gravity of your body is
comes down through the sitting bones
and then taking a few long slow deep in-breaths as you exhale
settle into your posture relax into your postures if you're settling into a comfortable chair
and then letting your breathing return to normal and continuing the process of
relaxing into your body as if the body both relaxes and the body is what
receives the relaxation maybe starting with the muscles of the
face as you exhale relax the face
so
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
as if the shoulders when they release a little are received
into a comfortable place
on the exhale relaxing the chest
relaxing the chest into whatever support the torso provides so the chest doesn't have to
work or be tight
and relaxing the belly
letting the weight of the belly to be received by the softness of the lower torso
on the exhale relaxing your arms and hands
perhaps all your hands are re received by whatever they're touching
the fingers can soften
and then relaxing the legs so the thighs
lower legs releasing any
clenching or holding and the legs are received
by whatever supports them
and then sitting here where in your body
do you feel the most tranquility
the most comfortable stillness
feeling whatever is calm in your body maybe there's a particular place that
relative to everything else in your body is the quiet place the calm place
and as you're sitting here
let the calm place support
a calmness of mind
in whatever physical calmness or soft stillness there is
let your breathing breathe with that
breathe through it
maybe that exhale settles into that place of physical
calmness and the inhale somehow begins from there
on the exhale either relaxing into whatever calm place
there is in your body whatever calmness there is
or if agitation or tension in the body is stronger
every exhale relax the tension
so
feeling whatever calmness there is in the body no matter how small
and see if the mind can rest in that
the mind can learn from that to also become
calmly feeling breathing
so
imagine that any ways in which the body is calm
tranquil
is a blessing on your heart
to allow yourself to receive that blessing
and imagine that the calmness of your body
any tranquility in your posture and bearing
is also a blessing on the world
in an agitated world
a calm person is of tremendous benefit
and in whatever way that we can be unagitated
may that be the vehicle through which
we care for the world care
to the care for the world with our basic friendliness
kindly kindness
generosity
perhaps assuming there's more goodness in others
than even they realize
may our ability to become
be the foundation for living for the welfare and happiness
of all beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
thank you
so in the topic of calmness buddhist buddhism puts a lot of emphasis
on tranquility of the body
in fact the word that's often translated as tranquility is most often in the ancient texts associated
with the body the body becomes tranquil i think of it as a soft stillness
that has a feeling of clarity in it the body starts becoming feeling clear
so it's not calmness where that's a soporific or kind of a kind of
kind of letting go and luxuriating in some kind of
inaction it's a tranquility that feels vital
feels clear maybe even kind of um
i like the word clear if you uh there's an ancient analogy
having to do with water that in running water it's not often the
surface is so agitated or so rippling and wavy that you cannot see through the water
into the bottom of the river or the lake
but in uh you also cannot get a reflection of yourself but if the water is still
or flowing very very harmoniously and quietly and almost you can't even see it
flow you can see through it to what's below
and you might also see your reflection of yourself in the surface
so that analogy is used for the value of tranquility calmness
that it's hard to see the world accurately when we're agitated
and it's hard to see ourselves accurately when we're agitated
but that if we could have some modicum of calmness
the minimum calmness needed is the calmness that knows that we're agitated
really knows oh i'm agitated i'm tense i'm stressed out
that's the beginning and then to begin but then as the calmness greater
calmness sets in then we start seeing more clearly
and this is one of the great functions for calmness it's not to calmness for his own sake
but calmness that sets the sets the ground for deeper states of clarity
stability and wisdom
so right today the topic is physical calmness
that the mind and body are closely related in some sense they're maybe not
too distinct from each other they have a very powerful relationship between them they kind of work in tandem or together
and how one is affects the other and if we are agitated in the mind jumping
around distracted jumping between one thought another
racing ahead in their minds trying to you know a crowded traffic jam of thoughts for all the things we have to
do or trying to solve or trying to fix or something
that has an impact on the body the and you can see the energy of that kind of vegetation
can um can be in the fingers and you know kind of uh tapping our fingers
playing with our fingers uh kind of two fingers with two hands kind of coming
together and kind of rubbing each other it can affect
our uh how we stand and our posture we can get the posture can get tense or
tight or contracted or um somehow in misaligned
uh it can affect what we do with our feet and like we're sitting down the feet begin swinging a lot or tapping a
lot and and it's all these are kind of an expression of this inner
agitation that might be there but the posture is something we have
more control over we have if we pay attention to the posture we can adjust the posture and what the physical
activities of the body it's possible to stop swinging the legs or tapping the legs it's possible to
stop playing with the fingers it's possible to have the arms uh relaxed in such a way
that the elbows are kind of just kind of flapping loosely on the side of the body they're not tense or tight
um and uh it's possible to uh
sit upright or stand upright in a balanced posture
tendency is when we're agitated we kind of lose the balance posture
and and then once we start finding a physical posture that has expresses or holds
still or holds tranquil that becomes a mirror uh for the other the agitation that's
going on the state of the minds that we have so and that's this is considered good in
buddhism that you start seeing what's actually happening rather than having the agitation
compelling you to move or shake or agitate or
fidget or something um we're beginning to kind of
take our our [Music] take our life back to ourselves
and and we begin feeding
begin supporting the calm body
this idea that we have a calm body that's available to us it's uh sometimes it might be called a
spiritual body or a a
deep body the deep body that we have and so the calm body
is something that we need to feed or support and it's one of the great assets that we have
because of how much clarity it provides how much reference point it provides for understanding what's going on
how much it it clears the the the inner eyes in a sense
so that we see what's happening rather than being pushed around by what's happening within
so uh you know we have as i said we have some control
over our bodies uh uh some not the inner physiology of the body but the
posture the activities the body's engaged in and so
if we're too distracted to know what we're doing with our fingers
when we're fidgeting with our fingers then chances are
that that level of distraction is limiting your wisdom
limiting your intelligence limiting your creativity limiting your ability to see clearly
and so to use your fingers fidgeting as a mindfulness bill
as a reminder oh i'm not supporting now or feeding or nourishing
the what's most wise and what's most kind what's most supportive for this body and
mind let me see what i can do to support the calm body
not so you can go around to completely calm but so that you're calm enough
that uh you're you're not being controlled by
agitation by anxiety by desires
uh compelled to keep moving and compelled to react and and uh or compelled just to be
distracted and caught up in thoughts and ideas
so to become more attuned to your body
and in particular how the body is agitated
and how you have some ability to not
act on that agitation but rather hold the body quiet let the posture be
calm let the posture be kind of like a
loving container that holds the agitation
i like it a little bit to a small kid on the nursery school playground who somehow
has stumbled and scraped her knee and
and she comes over to a teacher and then she's upset and crying and she throws herself into the arms of the
teacher and the teacher just holds her for a while and uh and she cries and
after a while being held she has enough and she wiggles out of the arms and runs back on
the playground so the posture can be that nourishing supportive person that can hold the
agitation we have and it takes kind of the in a sense the teacher in us the adult in us
to be the one who holds the posture still enough quiet
enough so it can hold the agitation that's deeper the impulses the
the tense agitated energies that are there so there there's a container for them
there's a nourishment for them there's support for them so they can begin to relax and settle
so physical calmness physical tranquility and
and in the teachings of the buddha physical tranquility has a wonderful kind of reciprocity
with joy and happiness that's somehow that
with joy with tranquility there can be more happiness with happiness more
tranquility with joy there can be tranquility with tranquility there can be more joy
and um and so it's not just kind of a state tranquility of of you know of
apathy or indifference or you know just holding yourself frozen
it's actually the opposite something comes alive when
when we can relax and open the body open excuse me
when we can open something can relax when we can open
the the wonderful vital energies of calmness
of clarity in our body so may you become interested in the
calmness of your body today and perhaps you can also begin to
maybe understand how a physical tranquility
is a support for a kind of physical clarity and maybe even mental clarity
so look and study your body today study the forces of vegetation in your body
and how you might support that agitation to calm down to relax
and maybe in a sense for some of you you can reclaim your body from your agitation
so that the calmness of your heart can
have space to come forth so thank you
and i hope you enjoy your day