so hi everyone good to see you welcome wherever you are
in the world so for today's happy hour in practice
i wanted to invite us to consider the practice of forgiveness
forgiveness which is one of the beautiful practices of the heart
it's an act of generosity of the heart when when the heart lets go let's go of
rocks a rock that it has been carrying and in some ways we can think of
actually gener forgiveness practice is another aspect
is another dimension of meta loving kindness
household so if you consider meta loving kindness
cultivating good will as as the generosity of our heart
as generosity of care towards ourselves towards others
this act of generosity can explain itself can can express itself in
a generosity of letting go of something that has been carried when
the time is right when the time is right to know that forgiveness cannot be rushed
cannot be pushed cannot be forced but it can be cultivated
the same way that kindness and good will can be cultivated they
can't be forced but they can be cultivated as we turn our minds gently towards kindness
turn gently towards generosity of good will
ah it tends to become as the buddha says the proclivity of our
minds whatever you ponder upon whatever you ponder upon frequent
frequently becomes the tendency the inclination of your mind says the
buddha so we can incline our minds our hearts
towards kindness good will trusting that oh it will become
the proclivity of our heart our minds the same way with forgiveness we incline
our mind our heart towards forgiveness not forcing not saying okay now forgive let
go now you have to that's not the idea that can become really forced
whereas if we incline if we turn our mind may it be possible you
know can is it possible to let go is it possible to forgive in this moment inclining
inclining our minds our hearts to make it more possible
it is said that there is this saying that is said for awakening that awakening is
an accident and meditation makes you more accident prone
so in the same way we can think of forgiveness kindness love all of these
can be accidents that just the heart opens up to right their heart can open up to forgiving and
this meditation these cultivation practices make us more accident prone they set the
conditions for for these beautiful
gifts to occur on their own
one last thing i want to say before we practice is there are different
dimensions to forgiveness and we will explore a subset of them today
maybe we'll do more in the next sessions there is forgiving ourselves there is forgiving
others there's asking forgiveness from others in our hearts
maybe not in person but in our hearts and then the fourth aspect is offering forgiveness to the causes
and conditions that brought us brought
you and another being or another group of beings an entanglement in some kind of entanglement so
forgiving the causes and conditions that you can't control so off so and that's
a that's where wisdom really the wisdom practice comes in with the forgiveness
practice is acknowledging that yep not not all of these cause and
conditions are within our control so so we'll explore
perhaps one or maybe more of them today we'll see how it goes because i want to leave a lot of silent space
also for our settling and arriving today as we practice
so without further ado let's engage let's engage with our
practice so to invite you to get into your meditation posture
whatever your body needs in this moment sitting upright
ah or lying down shifting moving whatever the body needs
but first we arrive with the breath
with the body just settling tilling the soil before we turn our attention
the topic at hand just to arrive
just to settle turning our gaze inward
connecting with the breath
letting go letting go
as much as possible offering up
the thoughts the cares the worries the activities that have come before
all the words and just connecting with the breath
in the body in this moment taking refuge
the simplicity and the beauty the grace of this moment of being alive
and just sitting and breathing being breathed this
is enough this is enough
in this moment just this breath is enough
just this in-breath is enough
and in the enoughness there's a sacredness beauty
as if entering this moment this moment's experience with all
we're all alice's in wonderland
this breath this moment's experience is a wonderland this breath
breathing itself not to be taken for granted
and if thoughts are arising it's okay
noticing noticing the balloons of thought
it's fear opening your hand letting go of the strings let them float
away letting go releasing
ah feeling lighter
and if the thoughts feel heavy like rocks can we not hold them weighed down by
them but just respectfully lovingly put them down for now thank you
not now pick you up and i have more
space not now not now
so
do
now i would like to invite you
as we incline our minds or hearts towards the practice of forgiveness
i'd like to invite you to bring to mind
an image of yourself
as a beloved other
this image could be of you at this time at this age or a different age
maybe younger
see what brings up a sense of connection for you the present image or past
and you can explore going back and forth you don't have to stick to one if one doesn't work
connecting with the felt sense of yourself as this beloved other
this being this being who has goodness
who has kindness
as good intentions and aspires to live according to values
that they hold that they uphold they hold dear
this being who has gifts
capacities aptitudes
the ways they show up in the world
and seeing seeing this person's goodness
inner radiance
the ways they are generous the ways they are kind
the ways they are thoughtful or whatever the
the gifts are
that you well know
and also connecting with the ways
this being this image of yourself as a beloved
other the way
they suffer the challenges they have
physically with their body emotionally relationally
appreciating connecting with the complexity
the complexity of their inner life their goodness their challenges
and for any ways for any ways that in the past
you have not seen
this beloved other fully
for all the ways
you have neglected them perhaps
forsaken them
haven't treated them well
you haven't been kind to them
have berated them have been judgmental
asking asking for forgiveness
for all the ways that have harmed you dear beloved other
it was me for all the ways
i've unknowingly
harmed you i ask you for forgiveness
for all the ways knowingly or unknowingly
i have harmed you by doing choosing what's not best for
you in action
in deeds and thoughts
and words
i ask you for your forgiveness
in any ways i have abused you
in body
and thoughts and speech in any ways i have forsaken you or
abused you i am sorry
i ask for your forgiveness
in any ways that i haven't been kind or generous to you i ask for your
forgiveness
for any ways i haven't completely seen you
your fullness your grace your capacities
your strength
your inner beauty your inner light
have undermined you
taking you for granted
i ask for your forgiveness
in any ways that i have harmed you knowingly or unknowingly out of my
ignorance shortsightedness not knowing any better
i haven't cared for you protected you
i ask for your forgiveness
this
now see if it's possible
to shift perspectives
and looking at yourself from this perspective of this beloved other that is you
in your full beauty grace the fullness of your being in the
fullness of your being with access in ways that may not be
fully understandable to you fully x access
for the access to your kindness forgiveness
looking at yourself in your humanity in your common humanity doing the best
you can doing the best you can
to navigate in this life with all the causes and conditions
of your life and as much as possible offering
forgiveness
and all the ways i've been harmed knowingly unfortunately
not being protected being stood up for being undermined
not cared for berated
judged as much as possible in this moment as much as it's available to me
i forgive you i offer you forgiveness
fully knowing the causes and conditions
of your life of this life with my life that you've been doing the best you've
been able to i offer you i offer myself forgiveness
see which direction works better for you you can better connect with
i'll stick with you
i let go as much as possible and forgive
for all the ways i've been harmed
not seen fully not appreciated fully
making peace with you making peace with
myself
you know you've been doing the best you've been able to
if you could have done any better you would have
as much as possible in this moment i forgive you
and for the last moments of this practice
however this practice period was whether there was sleepiness distracted
thoughts judgments ah releasing offering forgiveness to
yourself it was exactly as it had to be
releasing letting go
may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you for your practice
so
so forgiveness forgiveness
so the practice we did tonight today
is perhaps the most important aspect of this practice which is the relationship
to ourselves forgiving ourselves asking forgiveness
to ourselves and of course we can do this practice may i love and forgive myself just as i
am forgiving ourselves which is lovely we can explore that later and this other way of actually seeing ourselves as this
beloved other with capacities with beauty with grace that we often don't kind of see when
we're looking inside but seeing another like wow this being that is me there is so
much light in this being and then asking for
forgiveness relationally and then turning and looking at ourselves from this perspective and
offering forgiveness can be quite powerful can be for some can be very powerful
some may not connect to it like any other practice so i offer it um in this way
yeah i think what this brings up is a shift in perspective because again we
take ourselves for for granted whereas this allows it invites another way of seeing
another way of seeing ourselves which we usually don't which we usually don't
may not be available in our common way of relating so
so happy to hear your reflections what insights came up what you
discovered if you like to share or any questions you like to ask
you can type them in chat if you type them to me privately i won't
say your name one of you just typed loved it you're welcome another one typed thank you thank you
that was great lovely i am so glad i'm so glad that
it worked for those of you who connected with it and of course you can raise your zoom hand if you like to share your
your reflections insights and questions if it's your physical hand i may not see
you i'll take your pause again if you type it
publicly in chat i'll say your name if not it'll be private
um yeah harley says that was powerful but also challenging
tough to forgive oneself yes yes it is it is
actually forgiving ourselves is often the most challenging category it is absolutely
neil says i found myself hugging myself ah comforting myself for all the ways i've
harmed myself it was lovely oh thanks for sharing that neo oh i want to hug myself reading that oh
so much tenderness there ah linda says very refreshed and was
able to visualize me forgiving myself and accepting the offer beautiful
another refract reflection private it was hard to stay there so that makes
me think it was very much helpful beautiful and i invite you to consider this practice again
if the mind stuff especially didn't want to be there another reflection private i noticed i
become distracted and irritated when faced with forgiving myself yeah similarly if there's something
there if irritation is arising and distraction and irritation the mind doesn't want to go
there it's be kind be gentle that's the pointer that there's definitely something there to stay with
this practice kyla says conceptually very difficult
at first a meta stretch yeah yeah it can it absolutely is thank you
for that reflection melissa says this was beautiful thank you i felt myself as beloved
other feeling love and compassion toward the part of myself asking for forgiveness beautiful
thank you for that reflection melissa fm says this visualization also made me
think of all the ways i've supported and cared for myself too beautiful and recognized that there's
gratitude for myself at moments as well as forgiveness yay that's lovely that is just so lovely that
insight that comes up for appreciation gratitude beautiful bill says this practice would have been
harder a year ago but doing meta over the past year has allowed me to forgive myself to an
extent yay yay i celebrate that with you bill yay
the practice of meta really cultivating and one more reflection jerry says helpful to have moments of
kindness to myself and was enlightened even today of how i may have harmed myself in my
racing periods today in a meeting oh that's that's wonderful to
to have kindness to see that carol says loved loved loved thank you
yeah and gurgle says thank you and mucho mita from ireland oh thanks
google it's in the middle of the night for you lovely that you're joining us and i see nick and violet
have their head one of them has their hand up please
hi um my comments kind of similar to two of them in the chat around um
yeah i was like looking in my recent past for a moment to like forgive myself for treating
myself badly so i was looking for like okay what's something i've done recently where i was like berating myself or like
doing something against my values or somehow betraying myself and i couldn't find anything very
readily and i was like wow that is a big difference than me
really at any other point in my life um so yeah like what bill said about
like the difference of doing meta for a year like i really
don't have as like i'm just not betraying myself as much as i used to it's like well-being is like
it's created its own momentum um like a ship that's now like heavy enough that it's not so
easily like blown off course and i saw this thing on gratitude the other week that was like don't forget
how badly you once wanted what you have right now and i'm like wow yeah i didn't
um yeah i feel grateful for the stability so this helped me tap into that thank you yay
thank you violet that makes me so happy i'm filled with medita
just thank you for your beautiful reflection and yeah there's nothing more i can say
beautiful thank you testimony it's your practice yeah
one last reflection from carol loving yourself takes a long takes so long so multifaceted such a
beautiful sitting oh thank you carol oh thank you [Music]
yeah and appreciation for violet from bill and jerry that's great yeah especially loving
being grateful for what you have now yeah yay yay so let's
take let's take the sense of gratitude for what we have now and forgiveness and let's practice
together now in sangha that the rubber meets the road and let's start with 15 seconds of
silent meta practice and and then share whatever feels authentic
to you whatever you like to share as much as or as little as you like to share
and um yeah let's let's do that let's start
by okay i'm going to open the rooms actually one more second
i need to shift some things last minute shifts always happen
okay one more minute you can do meta for me as i quickly try to do this
ah here we go all right dear ones oh one more okay here we go
i'm opening the rooms enjoy practicing together
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed
so we have about a minute for any final reflections if you like to share what came up for
you especially uh practicing in groups so please don't be shy you need a type or
raise your hand
oh somebody i see a clap let's see oh it went away i'm not quite sure who
that was uh because i can't
let's see please do that again if you're trying to raise your hand oh there it's kim okay there you go
sorry about that it's all good um it was a great practice it was very
helpful i was telling my partners in the small groups
that i was working on forgiving myself but i still had some
tightness in my stomach and they were
quite lovely and uh and then when we came back i realized it
was gone like it's just went so thank you partners and group
oh that just delights me to no end yes practicing inside thanks so much for
sharing that kim that is so sweet it makes me so happy let's see a few last comments here i really says
thank you i feel totally different from how i felt an hour ago uplifted and happy and grateful yay
hence happy hour please come back again early that's great oh terry says aware of psychological
safety and vulnerability of the range um and the small group that's lovely the
psychological safety that you're talking about and i think this is what allows this the softening
um that um that was just shared a moment ago so um
and melissa says this was my first time attending yay and i found it well so welcoming and personally meaningful and moving thank
you great melissa welcome and please come back again please come and join our sangha you're part of the
sangha now and oh yes uh jerry says not range but rather sangha
yes uh says of the sangha yes yes sounds good anyway dear ones we're out of time
so thank you thank you so much for your practice for showing up and doing this cultivation not just for yourself
but for all beings whose lives you touch may all beings be happy may all beings
be free including ourselves [Music]
thank you