welcome a really warm welcome
for everybody welcome whoops here we go i have to get all my gizmos
straight so we'll start with a guided meditation
just a light guidance not a lot
to finish arriving
to our seat here
that is to sit either literally or figuratively
to sit and to know that you're sitting what does that mean
to know that you're sitting while you're sitting bringing the attention
bring in the awareness
to the experience of the moment in this moment we're sitting
part of noticing that we're sitting is noticing that that we're connected
we're grounded connected to the zafu we're sitting on
the cushion maybe a zabuton a mat
maybe a chair or a bench whatever it might be
it can be helpful to feel the contact of the body with what's supporting the
body
and then to rest the awareness on the sensations of breathing
feeling the movement of the chest or abdomen or feeling the air going
in and out of the nose
and noticing in a way that's relaxed and yet
purposeful
finding the balance between the amount of effort
we're applying
and when the mind wanders is it likely will we just very
simply gently begin again without making a problem out of it
without building stories around it we just begin again with the sensations
of breathing
sometimes when we come to meditate we find that
the energy is low when we feel kind of drowsy or drifty or
not really present
one thing we can do is put a little bit of attention on the
posture sitting up just a little bit straighter
letting that little extra effort with the body help energize the mind
something else we can do if you find yourself with low energy
is to bring a sense of curiosity to the experience
where does low energy show up in the
body maybe it's a heaviness in the shoulders
maybe it's a slouching posture
how do the thoughts feel if there's some drowsiness or
tiredness are the thoughts kind of wispy and
not clear dreamy maybe so just having a sense of curiosity kind
of investigating wow what does it feel like to not have a lot of energy
does that also mean there's low enthusiasm but just to bring the spirit of inquiry
can help raise the energy a little bit
if our energy is flagging
something else we might try or is just to reflect on what inspires us
about this practice
the potential for freedom
opportunity to and suffering for ourselves and others
the buddha maybe we have a heartfelt connection to the buddha
sometimes it can be helpful to bring these to mind
sometimes when we meditate
the energies not available for us
maybe a number of reasons why
but we can use the body to bring in a little more
energy or bring some investigation or curiosity
or bring to mind something that's inspiring that why we're practicing
so that our practice those times when we're on the cushion
our practice can be fruitful or meaningful or
useful or not just sitting and whiling the time
away so that our practice can support us and
be a benefit for our life and so that we might have energy and
be able to support and be a benefit for others
so in this way may our practice be for the benefit of all beings
everywhere
[Music]
good evening welcome welcome wherever you might be and whenever it
might be a warm welcome
so today i'd like to continue on this series of the pyramids
first so maybe i'll say just a word about the parmes sometimes we translate them as
perfections these are qualities that can be a support for our life and
for our practice that's a list of ten the first one
is generosity second is ethical behavior and then renunciation and then wisdom
and now we're tonight i'm gonna be talking about the fifth one energy
and energy is the translation of the word viria gets translated in all kinds of
different ways sometimes perseverance strength effort
courage vigor but for the most part i'll be using this
word energy and derma teachers kind of interpret
this fifth parame sometimes is along the lines of right effort and
sometimes more about energy and this is something that i appreciate so much about the dharma
that there are so many depths and sometimes like if you pull one little
thread you discover like oh this thread is connected to so many other things
and maybe what's interesting or inspiring today i want to be what's
interesting and inspiring you know for you for me next year next week
tomorrow so i i really appreciate kind of the richness
of this so i like it when there's this word viria that gets translated or
interpreted in a real breadth because i feel like sometimes maybe one
interpretation will be really helpful and supportive and maybe the others don't feel quite
relevant until they do maybe sometime later
so one way that we might understand this word viria gets translated as energy is the
willingness to stay with what is that is to not bounce off of those
things that are uncomfortable suffering for us to
learn about suffering take some viria to really understand it to really
find our way with suffering without running away or or turning away
but in some ways to engage with suffering in a way that brings freedom and awakening
so there's the um teachings of the pyramids are not from the earliest layer of the text that is
the buddha isn't he doesn't himself teach about the parmes but instead it was um sometime later
and this this is kind of what the tradition holds that there is the question of why did
the buddha become the buddha what what was uh so
exemplary about this individual that became a buddha and
one answer that came up was because he had perfected the parmes these ten qualities
but in that kind of that literature um describing uh the pyramids this is
um the pyramid of energy is this um
[Music] exaltation i'm not sure what the word is kind of
a divine i don't know it's not divine but an utterance
may i be filled within inexhaustible energy vigor and fortitude
and cultivating the path to enlightenment and in working for the benefit of others
so that's kind of how party of energy is described may i be filled with inexhaustible
energy vigor and fortitude in cultivating the path to enlightenment
and in working for the benefit of others for me personally i feel a little bit
overwhelmed like oh my goodness inexhaustible
energy vigor and fortitude it feels like a little bit
either i want to be kind of dismissive like oh that's just hyperbole that's just uh from the language of
thousands of years ago or i feel like wow who can do that you know somebody other
than me or somebody other than anybody i know can have inexhaustible energy vigor and fortitude
but then i felt like so if we and beaker body writes about this a little bit he's a well-known scholar and
translator he writes about as energy is needed
because our own natural tendency
is to either flow with the stream of desire
or to just drift along with whatever is the tendency of the mind
so flowing and drifting in some ways kind of being pushed around
but it takes energy to not be drifting to not be flowing
to either be going against this dream or even to just stop moving
so then when i consider this then it feels like it makes a little more sense that it takes this inexhaustible
energy vigor and fortitude is more about not just be drifting and
flowing all the time
i know that there certainly have been times in my life when i was just drifting feeling like kind of like going the path
of least resistance and i found myself and not happy with my
life it wasn't uh rewarding in the way that i was thinking or expecting it to be
it wasn't until that i really started to look at my life and to make some changes which was not
easy it certainly took effort to kind of go a different direction or to even look at things
more clearly more candidly so this idea of energy so that we're not
just flowing and drifting but it takes energy where sometimes we
just don't have this energy so where does it come from we're human beings
we have a limited amount of energy so what might we do to support our having energy
and the classical teachings in the tradition is some vega this is a poly word some
vega i like the way it sounds some vegan
and this is um a word that describes what gotama the person who was
going to become the buddha but before he became the buddha this is something that he experienced
the tradition holds that after he had seen them the mess and the heavenly messengers the
old age sickness death and a monastic then he
felt moved he felt compelled to go on this quest
so some vega is what he had this sense of urgency this sense of
this yes this is what i'm going to do i'm going this direction and there's a sense of
energy that's associated with that and so it's this comes along with a
sense of resolve a sense of dedication and might uh be a real support and a feel
for us as we kind of go through the vicissitudes of practice
in the teachings of the buddha we don't hear about him having doubt but do we hear about some of the
the tremendous effort and determination that was put forth and so
sam vega and teneth robico he i appreciate very much his way of
expressing this and he says that um
it's a difficult word to translate that there isn't exactly an english equivalent to it
because it has a complex range according to tinnisropico
and he says there's three different aspects to this idea of some vega
one is the oppressive sense of dismay terror and alienation that comes with
realizing the futility and meaningless of this life of just
going flowing or drifting so this first feeling of like oh what
have i been doing with my life this this isn't going the direction i wanted it to it
this just doesn't make sense i this feeling of dismay terror and alienation
these are powerful words so this recognition that just drifting
is not what we want to do and then the second aspect of san vegas
this chastening sense of our own complicity complacency and foolishness
and having let ourselves live this way
this sense of for me i had a little bit of anger to this anger of i thought that if i
you know kind of drifted in this direction everything was going to turn out fine and it wasn't turning out fine
so and also this sense of our complacency and foolishness like oh why
didn't i know better so these three things of the
this sense of dismay a chastening sense of her complicity
and this sense of the sense of urgency sorry that was the
third one i didn't say this the sense of urgency of trying to find a way out
so these three things together the sense of urgency sense of complicity and this dismay
really or can be the fuel for practice
and sometimes we only experience this after a grave difficulty after some tragedy in our lives
is when we have this real sense of urgency to practice as we're trying to find a solution and
trying to make sense out of things perhaps but we don't have to wait until there's
a tragedy in our lives for this some vega there can be this
recognition of the suffering and it doesn't have to be the most terrible suffering but there can be a
real wish to understand this suffering what is going on here
how did i get here so this wish to understand it
which is a lit which is stronger more powerful than the wish to avoid it so we're
willing to investigate and get curious about
our difficulties and then that brings us to another way in which we can increase
our energy so first with some vega this sense of urgency and second is
investigation to have some curiosity to have a
engagement with whatever it is that we're doing
whether it's meditation have a sense of curiosity of the breath or what the mind is doing
sense of curiosity about what's happening in our life the way that we're
behaving i think we've all have this um this uh
experience that there's we have a sense of energy when we're interested
like we can sit through like some a podcast for example that other people
might think like oh my gosh this is the most boring thing but because it interests us we have like
a sense of energy and are really engaged with it with hobbies with whatever it might be
and so we can bring that sense of curiosity or investigation to our
experience whatever our experience might be
that is um instead of like slapping a label on our experience
that's boring this is painful that's hard we could really tease apart what are all
the different elements and then this also ties in
with the fourth pyramid that is the one that precedes energy is wisdom
and one way we can understand wisdom or part of wisdom is that it's a discernment or
distinguishing that is seen with some clarity with what really is
when i talked about wisdom i talked about the owls having big eyes that is seeing clearly and part of that
is to make the discrimination between this and that instead of just lumping
things together so one thing that of course is important
to investigate as part of our practice is this question is what is helpful and
what is unhelpful what is helpful to find more ease
more freedom what is on the path to awakening enlightenment
which is not on the path and maybe i'll say even asking that
question is on the path so to have this question what is helpful
what is skillful what is wholesome what is this we could even say
what is this kind of pointing to the self maybe as an investigation who is doing
the investigation it's more about the openness and the
questioning than than finding the answers it's more about
being receptive to learning something new rather than thinking that we have it all
figured out so our mindfulness practice of course
brings us face to face all the time with what with difficulties
as well as what leads to suffering and what doesn't lead to suffering
as well as the suffering that leads to the end of suffering
so part of wisdom part of investigation and something that can increase our energy increase our
engagement with what's happening is to have the asking these ques asking these
questions this leads to suffering but is this uncomfortableness is this suffering
lead to the end of suffering looking at my ethical behavior
maybe it's painful maybe we realize oh there were times in my life when my
ethical behavior wasn't so clean i told lies or i
took things that weren't freely offered whatever it might be it might be painful to recognize that in
ourselves but that can be part of the
building of our ethical behavior in the in the present as well as a
part of the diminishing or um putting it aside at
those things which might decrease our energy that is not being ethical really
dissipates and takes away our energy because there's always a part of the
mind and a part of the heart that is
busy busy with whatever it is that we did wrong i'm using this word wrong whichever was
unethical which wasn't helpful let's use that language
so some vega an investigation can increase energy so that we
might not just be drifting or flowing through our lives something else that can increase our
energy is joy joy and happiness
sometimes we might feel that our practice is drudgery it has fallen into the category
of being one more chore that we have to do
it's uh something we just have to squeeze into our day even though we don't really
have time for it and it starts to feel burdensome that's just you know one more thing we have to
do and maybe it's one more arena in which the inner critic
gets to play loudly and have a commentary about the quality of
the meditation or how long we're meditating or how often we're meditating
so this sense of kind of this drudgery of course there isn't going to be a lot of energy
there but can we connect with some of
in the beginning of the well while we were still in the honeymoon phase of practice
that is it used to be that we perhaps would like open up dharma books be feel inspired by them go to dharma
talks feel inspired by them can we touch into what is inspiring for
us maybe it is listening to dharma talks
maybe there's a devotional element of your practice maybe there's something about um
doing bowing or prostration that is nourishing and feeds the heart in the way that just hearing a dharma
talk doesn't maybe chanting for a lot of people chanting is a beautiful practice
maybe suit does studies for me there's something about this who does that i really love
i was um doing some suit to study with some friends recently and one person said it's kind of like a
puzzle and you know kind of like the how and what i was thinking like it's
interesting how in the newspaper we have sudoku and we have crossword puzzles but in some ways this
suit does just kind of that a joy of like engaging with them and like what is being pointed
to here and what is the context here and how do we understand this and how is
this relevant and applicable to our lives so for me i love doing this it's not for
everybody it doesn't have to be for everybody but what is it for you that brings
energy to the practice but it might be also that sometimes we
have this idea that well yeah but if i'm happy or having fun doing it or it's joyful then
it can't be spiritual it can't be proper if it feels good
so i would just invite you to investigate that belief
the you might recognize i've been i was talking about energy and then
investigation and i'm talking about joy these are three awakening factors that is these are
three energizing factors of awakening the buddha identified
these qualities it's a whole list of seven i'm only giving three out of the seven here
but these three are the ones that are uplifting and energizing and my point is that joy
is on this list so joy is energizing and supports our having
energy but it also is a factor of awakening
it's an element it's a necessary element to the practice so the encouragement is
to find your way with joy and happiness of course
in a way that's with kind of keeping with the ethical behavior and wholesome and helpful and skillful
but we need to stay connected with these areas these areas that really nourish and
fuel our practice so if we want to look at energy it's
also helpful to look at well what blocks energy or what dissipates
energy or what gets in the way i already talked about unethical
behavior really subtracts takes away from our energy
another one is just distractions
how many notifications is it possible for us to have we just heard one on my phone earlier my
apologies about that so just that we're often whether it's
our phones or our computers or something where often our attention is
being pulled in so many different ways maybe we're trying to multitask and
do a few things at once and so there's a way that kind of like
fragments our energy dissipates our energy to to always be multitasking
there's something a little bit more fulfilling and satisfying if we can
uni-task as best we can just to bring some focus and some
intentionality to our effort to whatever it is that we're doing as opposed to just drifting
or or flowing with it but to bring some intentions to it
of course this is obvious but something else that can takes our energy is just
not getting enough sleep maybe that goes without saying but
i'll just share for me just noticing what a difference it makes when one has
a good amount of sleep this should be such a priority
and i'm happy that more and more these days people are talking about the importance of sleep
and so i talked about a little bit earlier about
being inspired this is also if we're not inspired if we don't have
a sense of a direction that we're going
sometimes in spiritual circles they don't like to talk about goals but maybe if we could talk about the
direction we're going i would say we can't talk about goals we can talk about awakening
or less suffering less stress but sometimes we shy away from having
goals because we have this feeling like well maybe other people can do that but i
can't somewhere there's this kind of lack of self-confidence that is prohibiting us
from dreaming big or even having an aspiration
and so sometimes not having that can cause there to not really
um give an occasion which the energy to coalesce around or the energy to come
together so not having a direction not having an aspiration not having a goal
using whatever language feels appropriate for you but what what is the purpose if we want
to use that language for your practice
and maybe sometimes that feels too heavy-handed and maybe sometimes it's really helpful
to connect with your aspiration so we can have some curiosity about that
bring some investigation to that
so i've been talking all this time about increasing energy so that we might with this pyramid of energy
have this inexhaustible energy fortitude and vigor
but of course we can have too much energy in terms of it spills over into restlessness
or doesn't allow the um if it's out of balance with
concentration then there can be uh then the mind can't quite settle if there's too much energy
and pointing to that is this simile of the goldsmith that's we find in the suit and
it goes like this suppose a goldsmith would prepare a hot furnace
heat up a receptacle take some gold using tongs and put the gold into the
receptacle so like this the gold is sitting in a crucible
and um it's getting heated while it's the crucible is in the furnace
and then from time to time the goldsmith would blow on it sprinkle water on it or just look on
as the gold was heating if the goldsmith were to only blow on it
it's possible that the gold would just burn up
if the goldsmith were to only sprinkle water over it it's possible the gold would cool down if
the goldsmith were to only just look on it's possible the gold would not reach the right consistency
but if the goldsmith would from time to time blow on it from time to time sprinkle
water on it and from time to time just look on the gold would become purified bright
unblemished rid of imperfection malleable wieldy steady
and attained to imperturbability then whatever ornament the goldsmith
wishes to make from it whether it's a bracelet earrings necklaces or a garland that can
be achieved this is significant because the way that
the buddha is describing the gold here when it has just enough heat by blowing on it or let just enough water by
cooling it he's describing the goldust purified bright unblemished rid of imperfection
malleable wieldy steady and attained to
imperturbability the buddha uses these exact words to describe his mind right before
awakening so he's describing not too much heat
vigor not too much coolness not too much standing back but from time
to time so to have a balance with our energy
probably many of us are familiar with this also another story but sona i'll just say
who was a loot player like a stringed instrument and the buddha teaching the strings
should not be too tight or too loose again pointing to the importance of balance
with our energy so may we use our energy in a way that
helps us on their path to enlightenment and i'm let's see what that's i'm
looking for the definition here of uh how it's used in the
may i be filled with inexhaustible energy vigor and fortitude and cultivating the path to
enlightenment and in working for the benefit of others and working for the benefit of
others thank you