okay so good evening or morning or whatever time it is
why don't we go ahead and get started welcome to the monday imc sit
and dharma talk i'm kim allen i think many of you know me so
please find a posture we'll start with the meditation now finding a posture that's upright
and also relaxed
really allowing yourself to feel like you've arrived
sometimes we've rushed around a bit before turning on the computer
or we've just been looking at something else on another window so just
taking a moment to sense that now you're here
now you're with this meditation and allowing the body and the mind to
come into harmony with that if you're comfortable doing so you can
close your eyes bringing the attention inward
i'm beginning by connecting into the body grounding in the body
so feeling the sensation where you're sitting your seat against the cushion or the
chair or the bench in your legs or your feet
against the floor
having that sense of stability of being supported
and also softening and relaxing and allowing yourself to be supported
by what you're sitting on
and then rising up from this stable base is the body with the spine in the middle
we may even feel like it is buoyed upward or pulled upward like a sea plant
rising off the c4 it's anchored at the bottom but then can float upward
could the body be like that letting the arms float like the front of
the plant letting the head float on the spine
finding in these images a way to be upright and also relaxed
some degree of ease sitting here
i'm deliberately softening the body releasing various areas of tension
so perhaps beginning with the face and the head softening
the muscles of the forehead around the mouth
softening the eyes and the eye sockets
the jaw the throat
down into the shoulders shoulder joints
letting the shoulder blades slide down the back
down into the chest area
softening the ribcage
releasing the diaphragm
down into the belly letting that be soft round
finding some ease in the hip joints softening a little farther into the seat
and letting go of bracing in the legs all the way down to the feet
so having a sense of inviting ease throughout the body without needing it to be any particular
way
this sort of simple usefulness at the beginning of a sit
helps set a good tone where the sitting brings in the
different parts of the body and mind
allowing the attention to connect with the breathing simple sensations of the breath coming
in going out
not trying to do it a particular way
having a sense of beginning fresh is if you don't know anything about the
breath
you
we may notice that the mind is caught up in thoughts
concerns emotions of various kinds
this is normal
when we notice that just gently reorienting to
present moment experience body
mindfulness at the beginning of a sid it may take
a little more attention [Music] to steady the mind
and then as it settles more there can be a lighter touch
so perhaps noticing in this portion of the sit
how we touch the mind to help bring it back
how frequently how strongly could it get gentler and quieter
in line with the mind settling a bit
as the mind continues to settle
even if it's just a little bit
if it's of interest you may wish to direct your mindfulness toward the
beginning of experiences
can you notice the very beginning of the in-breath
beginning of the out breath
the beginning of a sound
or a body sensation what is it like when you first notice it
maybe even the beginning of a thought
it's meant to be done usefully not tightening up the mind ready to
pounce on something that's arising
just gently within your regular mindfulness practice
inclining toward beginnings
uh
okay
[Music]
uh
oh
and for the last five minutes of this meditation
just release any effort to practice
just allowing the mind to be natural
letting things arise pass
i'm just aiming to rest in the present
moment
resting the mind in what is already happening
beginnings endings we don't have to create either one
okay so good evening i wanted to talk tonight
about beginning well so wherever you are in the world it's
clear that this pandemic that we're all living with
is entering a new phase there's an increased availability of vaccines and all the
complications that come with different variants
but nonetheless it's clear enough that things are starting to shift a bit and
sometime later this year will be will be different so as we move toward
whatever post-pandemic life looks like it is helpful to consider
how to pick up new activities well so in this case we actually have
the luxury of time of considering what it is and how it is that we might
want to pick things up as we go forward in some sense we don't
ever really have this time it's just an illusion because every moment right
experience is arising it's arriving and arising and we're meeting it and so there's
always beginning every moment there's a continual process of beginning but nonetheless there are some times
when we can imagine that we have a beginning that we can think about or move toward in some
intentional way so it is worthwhile when we have this time to
begin things well to begin things well so when this is done when we begin well
then experience unfolds more naturally and also we're in a better position to
learn from experience as it comes and also to make uh the the necessary adjustments to to
staying on course all of that a lot of that depends on beginning well
in some way so what is this you know what does this mean what do the buddhist teachings say about
beginnings we hear a lot about endings about cessation and letting go
and being free you sort of imply something dropping
away maybe ending suffering the end of suffering is the aim of the path
but what about the beginnings the buddha did talk about beginnings and
how to do it well and the teachings mostly focus in three areas
our understanding our intention and our effort so we'll talk about
those things tonight
i think it's no surprise that we are instructed to pay attention to the mind
as we are beginning things you know that's considered a really important place to to notice as we go
forward there's the well-known opening stanza of the dhammapada that begins
mind is the forerunner of all things so that's pretty clear that
how we are in the mind is going to have a major impact on what happens as things go forward
and then more specifically there are other teachings there's one in the majima nikaya that
says quite directly right view comes first right view comes
first so this is about our understanding it doesn't mean let me unpack that a
little bit the right view doesn't mean that we are sort of
passively applying the view that we receive from the teachings or from our teacher or something
and just sort of sticking it on okay here's the here's the belief i need to apply
in order to begin uh it's actually more subtle than that so whatever view
we're using and there always is one we always have some kind of a view coming in that's going to provide the context or
the orientation for what follows so then
what right means about right view is that we should adopt an orientation or a view or an
understanding that is appropriate for the task at hand for what it is that
we're beginning so in practice and this is the context for that quote right view comes first
if the task is walking the buddhist path to the end of suffering to peace to
liberation then what we would choose is what is called right view
which means an appropriate view for doing that and you know this generally has two
forms because it's this right view is useful for whatever we undertake to make it
part of our path so the two forms of this appropriate
or right view the first one is the understanding that
actions have results and that we have some choice about that so we live in a world that has laws of
cause and effect in going on you know they may be more complex than we can exactly see all
the details of and they may operate in different ways at different times but generally speaking actions will have consequences
and we have some choice about that so in particular actions that come from
a mind that's oriented toward harm will lead to our own
suffering our own dukkha and in contrast actions that come from a
mind oriented toward peace or toward non-harm will tend to bring happiness to us this
is one of these of these some of these basic laws of action and consequence so even if we have kind of no idea about
the long-term or large picture of what we're doing we can at least in this moment choose to
do actions from an orientation of non-harming and that will be good in some sense
and so people can feel great relief and having this at a as a guide you
don't actually have to have it all figured out in the whole big picture because things are complex especially in
something like this pandemic or in a complex interconnected world like we live in so we can you know make some
attempt to think about our views and our orientation in the bigger picture but
what matters really is that right now we come from a place of non-harming that
will have good consequences for us for our happiness and and those around us
so that's one wise orientation wise view and then the second dimension
of of right view or appropriate view which is actually not so different
is to see things specifically in terms of dukkha and its end or suffering in its end
or stress in its end so we can notice in a situation what feels stressful or
tense or somehow unsatisfactory we can notice that attune to that
and then move toward its release so if i'm entering a room and i feel
some tension in my chest i can notice that and then
take care of that in some way notice all my feeling afraid in some way or and what you know what might i do
maybe just being mindful of the fear sufficient or something else but
tuning toward dukkha and its end is a way of orienting toward the four
noble truths toward what is it that's challenging right now how am i somehow holding on
wanting something in order that that's coming about how could i apply something i know from
practice to somehow ease or release some of that suffering you know without making it complex but
this orientation of dukkha and its release is very much in line with what we're doing on the path so that's
a good guide for our actions as we as we undertake things so even
you know just another everyday example is if i'm beginning a work project with somebody
and i'm going to talk with them about this project so it's a beginning how do i orient i could orient
toward cultivating kindness active listening a healthy relationship with this person
that i'm going to be working with or i could practice mindfulness of not
drifting off into my own thoughts but actually staying on task and being clear about
what's happening in the conversation those are both forms of this appropriate view that i just talked about
and those are very different than say orienting toward okay i've got to convince this person to
do it my way i've got to get my point across and make sure that i stay in control of this
thing as it's starting that's very different right so that's going to have a major impact
on how things unfold so and this works on the cushion too we
did it in the guided meditation he said if we sit down and we orient toward uh bringing some
ease to the body some ease to the mind some sense of what we're doing that will have a different effect than
if we don't do those things to orient at the beginning of our sit these simple acts can have very
important results for how the meditation proceeds
so in general we're asking how can this be wholesome or supportive of the path as i go forward
now how can i reduce stuka through this beginning so all of this amounts to right view our
understanding and our orientation as we begin a task go into something
so right view as you may recall from the steps of the eightfold path
it feeds into the next step which is called right intention and that is actually the crux the sort
of key point the crucial point of how we engage skillfully with beginnings i would say that's
the key one so classically there are three wholesome intentions that we
orient around as we go forward each of which is set up to counteract
some kind of unwholesome intention that we might have in the mind some sort of tendency so the intention
the first intention is typically called renunciation people don't always connect with that
word so we could also call it letting go or
even being at ease if we you know wanted to extend it a little bit so it counteracts
the unskillful pursuit of sense pleasure you know just wanting to grasp with the
pleasant part wanting to get things that are good and pleasant and useful for me
you know these sorts of graspy kinds of orientations the the intention of being generous or
renouncing the need for those things is is this first orientation and it's it
has a an effect of coming in with an open hand with an open heart with an open mind
and then the the second and third of these right intentions or wise intentions are
stated as clear counteractions so they're stated as non-ill will and non-cruelty
so we also come in with a mind that isn't oriented in a negative or aversive or
oppositional way as we move into things or if they're named more in the positive
they could be named as good will or as compassion
so these are um essentially these three set the tone of our engagement with
things so um and the tone the tone that we're setting in life matters so much that's
worry that's based in our intention so i guess i'm thinking about work projects today because another
i'm thinking of another time that i was beginning a work project and i was
sending an email to one of my colleagues about about the project and i noticed that um
i kept wanting to include some kind of comment about um
their experience with this and a little bit derogatory like you know i know you don't have so much experience
with this or something like that i i don't know um but i noticed that there
was a slight feeling of tension around that and i realized that i was kind of
trying to question my colleagues level experience of experience in order to elevate my own
and therefore show that you know i was going to be able to contribute very well to this project or
something so but i i caught this you know luckily as an intention of ill will
and i um instead changed what i wanted to write to something that was more
inclusive more connecting at the beginning of this project not highlighting their lack of
experience or my experience which was a little bit delusional to think that way
and i'm certain that that set a much better tone than if i hadn't done hadn't made that
change would have changed the relationship right at the beginning of the project
we can also set the tone in advance of an experience or a
situation that we're going into and then just trust that it will carry
us in so for example if we're about to go into a meeting
or even a social encounter or a party of some kind
we can as we're walking toward the door or sitting in the car before we go in
we can set an intention of good will or of mindfulness or something like that
and just orient the mind that way and then you know you don't have to constantly think about it and bring it to mind and
be distracted by it during the counter you just you just set it and then walk in and
trust that it will carry through in some way it may not carry you know entirely through the entire
encounter or it may but generally this is a good thing to do with the mind just to orient it well
when you're starting i remember a friend of mine went to
practice in asia and she was doing intensive retreat practice but even in
that setting the abbott of the monastery used to ask the people who were practicing there that in
the morning when they woke up before they got out of bed to start their day that they spend a few
minutes doing loving-kindness practice and the way he said it was this will set
the tone for everything else you do and then you know the rest of the day they were doing mindfulness practice vipassana
concentration you know sort of more traditional wisdom practices but he wanted them to
do this loving kindness at the very beginning to set the tone for the for the rest of
the day so you might try this also see what you can remember to do in the morning before you get out of bed
just to meet the day well so in general we're aiming to
act and speak and even think from a place of non-greed non-hatred
and non-delusion that's the overall picture and so the three right
intentions that i just named are very clearly covering the first two of
non-greed and non-hatred so renunciation for example would cover non-greed
and in on non-ill will and non-cruelty would cover non-hatred so it encounters
those first two you know clear defilements of the mind but then we might ask
you know where is non-delusion in terms of orienting ourselves sometimes
people have questions about the second step of the path because it doesn't seem to include non-grade non-hatred versus
the non-delusion it turns out that that is covered by right view by what we talked about first so um
you know having the correct view that we're moving towards suffering in the end of suffering and that
our actions have consequences and we have some choice that is non-delusion knowing those
things so this three-fold purity of volition if you will non-greed non-hatred
non-delusion is the fundamental way to begin and also to proceed and also to end
the buddha says very clearly in a different suta that volition or caitanya lies at the heart
of action of kama so that strongly influences the results that we experience
so that covers a lot of the territory but um all of that is kind of the
prep in the mind and so there's also the actual active beginning and what what else do
we need to begin well the third thing that i area that i named is that there's something to do
with our energy as we actually engage with the
beginning of a task and so let's let's talk also about this area of energy
the buddha talks about the importance of generating wholesome energy or iberia
that's the word for energy or effort as we undertake a task so in particular this is a very stock or
standard phrase you'll find in sutas like it goes like this one generates desire makes an effort
arouses energy applies one's mind and strives so
i know that that sometimes sounds a little too energetic for those of us in the west who are a little
bit uh action oriented and result oriented in some word we're told not to strive quite so
strongly but that phrase is very common in the pseudos one generates desire makes an effort
arouses energy applies one's mind and strives so we might just encapsulate all
of that into that middle phrase arouses energy so that's a viria a roboty that's the poly phrase
and arabity means to engage with or to undertake in a sense
so we should be willing to put forth some effort for things to go well as
we're beginning so we orient our mind and then we bring forth this kind of wholesome
energy to get it going in a sense so instead of being a little bit more passive or
lackluster about how we get started on things later when there's momentum then we're
encouraged to back off and be a little bit more effortless you might have heard that phrase effortless
effort and we did that a little bit in the meditation where at the beginning we were a little bit more attentive and
then at the end relaxed our effort and just allowed
experience to unfold that's often a good way to think about the energy in a project so
why is effort means the right amount of effort and
that's one aspect of it is to bring the right amount of effort not too much and not too little and at the beginning
when we're just starting things out sometimes for beginnings a fair amount of effort is needed because we're trying
to generate momentum or else change direction of momentum that we already had so you
might think of beginnings as requiring a little bit more energy a little bit more focused effort
to get going in a good direction so
considering beginnings i've been kind of orienting us around beginnings in daily life
particularly also in this bigger picture of beginning what's going to happen as things start to open up and
people come into more contact with each other and maybe we start interacting with more people than we
have been these things would be very good to keep in mind but actually there is um quite a bit
about beginnings that happens on the cushion too and i also alluded to this in the
meditation there's a stage of insight practice where we become very attuned to
beginnings i asked you to do it consciously during
the sit but it there's a time when it just comes um without needing to be deliberate about it so the
mind um gets really interested in beginnings it's a very it's an interesting
fun time of practice because mindfulness gets really sharp because you're you're catching the first
moment of things it's like oh you see the the breath um come into being from a moment before
when there wasn't one and you see uh you know the in-breath tails off and then the out
breath begins we see that first moment when there starts to be uh the air exiting instead of
entering and it's exciting and maybe we see um the first shift in a mood you know
where we're feeling angry or irritated and but we're we're don't get caught up in it
we're mindful and then there comes a moment when it's like it's like the mind sort of
turns away from that and we feel something else come in a sense of relief or or joy or peace or many other things
we see that first moment we know ah there's the moment where the anger turned and we might also see
um the first moment of a thought you know we're sitting it's not that
there's absolutely zero thoughts but we're kind of between thoughts and we're not really noticing thoughts
at that moment and then we'll see a little spark like the mind starts to form an idea and we see it
kind of arising out of the matrix of the mind this idea we can see oh that's going to be a
thought in one more instant it's going to break the surface and i'm going to know what those words are
and every once in a while one of those will come and we'll be mindful of it and it will just
dissipate before it ever forms into the image or the word and we wonder what was that thought
going to be you'll never know but it's a fun time of
practice seeing these beginnings the wiz there's a lot of wisdom in this to see
and feel um beginnings means that we can also see and feel the very first moment of
clinging we were peaceful calm mindful
and then the mind started to uh form an identity or attach to something
or hold on no don't let that go and we see that we see that little grip and we
can feel that the moment that we begin to cling is the moment of the arising of
suffering we see the second noble truth is that clinging and suffering are identical and we can only be sure of
that if we see them begin and end together so it's important
and so then we can start to get wise about how we engage with beginnings because stuff is coming every moment
we see if we grasp it we're going to suffer so we learn not to we learn to let it arise as it is
to let it be itself as it comes into being without grasping it as mine without
putting it in a box so i know what that is and immediately labeling it without controlling
letting it arise and have its life whether it's going to be big or small can we just trust that it can come into
being as it is so we start to we start to see this and
there's a lot of wisdom that comes from getting intimate with beginnings and with how we relate
to beginnings on the cushion and then that will of course feed into
how we do it in life also when things come in that are surprising as happens all the time our
partner we don't know what her partner is going to say next can we meet it can we just let that be there
we turn the corner and see something unexpected can we open to that or do we close off or get scared
or try to control it or try to make it what we want it to be we'll see again and again how we're
relating to life when we start to see on the cushion how we relate to things coming in beginnings coming into our
mind and our body so this is an important area of practice
beginnings and as we learn to begin well and engage in ways that are
open and connecting and filled with peace good will all those
right intentions that too will help us learn to end well to let go
to let things cease to let them end to not clean so
all of this is feeding into our wisdom
and our compassion so i wish you well in exploring beginnings
a very interesting area and also with whatever is beginning in your
life beginning in this springtime maybe it's autumn if you're in the southern hemisphere
beginning with things opening beginning with seeing more people
whenever that occurs you might consider how to meet that well
so many blessings for your practice take care