hello friends hi and welcome to happier
hi and if you can hear me okay if the audio's working thumbs up fantastic
great so let's begin as we always begin
informally first by welcoming ourselves and each other to the space
by saying hello and i start by saying hello i'm nikki in mountain view california
unseated land who is here in this moment in time unzoom
i am wayne in richmond okay wayne
dawn in dc hi dawn and hi hugh on youtube
hi bill from dallas from british columbia
hi kim and heinz oakland hi fred in oakland hi
elisa from berkeley diana in new york hi diana
hi neil barbara and alameda hi barbara
terrence in squim terence and mark instagram washington hello the swim
contingent good to see you
and linda in utah hi linda i'm peggy in redwood city hi peggy
welcome i think welcome
the montreal contingent and hi violet from san francisco and
hi murray christine who says from sydney australia good afternoon to you hi
also william says hi from chicago and richard from cleveland
sweet and deborah from san francisco ah our international sangha has assembled
and hi kyla from redwood city up the road hi sweet oh my heart is are already warmed
i love this part of happy hour just the sangha assembling saying hello
very sweet so so let's formally get started i ask you
to mute your uh speaker uh your your mic rather
if it isn't already muted might change the settings at this point
in preparation for the guided meditation and the little dharmat
so that unmuting won't be possible and also i'll
change the settings um on chad hi jerry from toronto and thank
you neil for posting information about google groups happy hour
um happy hour google groups uh some lexical challenges tonight happier
google groups where folks can join and share information and resources are also
shared on on our google groups mailing list
and last but not least i will turn on recording for the sake of audio dharma
it will ask you to confirm unzoom here we go okay
so formally hello and welcome to happy hour dear sangha
so [Music] so for today's theme of practice um i'd like to invite
us to engage with the fourth brahmavihara today the brahmaviharas the
um about the four practices of the heart meta being the first one where we spend
a lot of time and happy hour working with metta and all the three the three
other ones also are different expressions of meta they're not separate the second being
compassion another expression of meta when meta kindness meets suffering
the third one being mudita or vicarious joy when metta meets someone who's has really good
fortune either ourselves or someone else gladness arises vicarious happiness
no and the fourth one is equanimity equanimity also thought of as the crown
jewel of buddhist practice and it shows up in so many different ways so many lists and so
many different flavors the way it shows up on this list on the
brahmavirus is practicing for ourselves practicing for other beings
it shows up another list such as the seven factors of awakening etc etc but
here it shows in this way in the way of practicing with respect to ourselves with respect
to other living beings so and remember that equanimity is related
to matters in the same family so there is care in equanimity it's not aloof it's not oh okay whatever
it there's care there is love in the sense of equanimity in the sense of equipoise
holding what is and the way i like to invite us to explore of course we've explored all the
brahmaviharas in so many different ways creative ways over the past year and a
half now on on our online global saga but the way
i like to invite us for today's practice is the following way
to consider um perhaps times maybe right now
where there might be a friend there might be a relative there might be a loved one
who's having perhaps a challenging time and part of your instinct perhaps caring for
them is to jump in and swoop in and just
make it all better or maybe there's a sense of frustration like oh why are you doing this to yourself and can't you see
so so there's so many different unwise
responses that can come up here when there is lack of equanimity whereas
what would equanimity look like perhaps in in this particular case in this
particular instance scenario so
appreciating appreciating understanding the person's autonomy really granting
them autonomy respecting their choices caring
offering support whatever support you can
but without both trying to step in and and make it
you know fix it all in your way not respecting their journey not respecting their
choices not respecting um that this is their life
and in the traditional phrasing of the equanimity phrases
um it is said that you know all beings have their own journey they
have um and and their happiness and unhappiness does not depend on my wishes
for them it's respecting their journey and yet it's not aloof it's not cold it's not
turning your heart away at all there's care there is love
there is holding witness and supporting helping in any ways that are both
helpful well filled with love both for the person for the friend relative and also
for yourself remember metta equanimity is 360.
so if you're swooping is swooping in and
just taking over and and giving up your own responsibilities in
life it's not really filled with meta for yourself care for yourself
so the wise question why is consideration is how can i
how can i support how can i be present how can i have mettas show care love compassion
both for this being in this situation as well as for myself
as well as respecting their autonomy respecting their journey
the choices they have made that have brought them to this place
and the choices they need to make the lessons they need to make
and similarly for you the choices you have made and the lessons you need to make so how can you be present
loving and also have a sense of 360 degree view
of life its ups its downs
trials tribulations all of our choices all the lessons that
we have to learn as beings in in our interrelationship so
so that's plenty for setting the context today so i'd like to invite you to let
go now of all the words there were too many words too many concepts let it go
let's let's land together let's practice together
let's land in our bodies letting go of all the words we're going
to try on for size this practice just try it on
even if there are but but but complains and
and concerns try it on for size and see what arises
as you practice in your body in your heart
so landing landing in the body
landing
feeling sensing [Music] your feet these feet rooted
touching the earth the contact points
between the feet and the earth
just tilling the soil just tilling the soil
of mindfulness awareness one breath at a time
arriving settling
receiving each breath in the abdomen
the fallen breath received the full out breath
received
taking refuge
in this moment the simplicity of this body
this breath this expansive moment just here
putting down thoughts just gently saying not now thank you not
now
i'm connecting with awareness
i like to invite you to imagine you're sitting on top of a mountain
where you have 360 degree view all around
just imagine you're sitting comfortably
feel your bottom feel your feet feel embodied
feel embodied in the body
notice a sense of spaciousness all around you
your space all around you
as if you could see far into the horizon from all directions
clearly just imagine top of the mountain let's
take another few minutes to breathe
to settle with a sense of embodiment and spaciousness embodiment and spaciousness
now like to invite you to imagine
sitting sitting in this high place top of this mountain seeing all around
as if you could see as if you're looking into
so many interrelated causes and conditions
past and present
so many things have come to be
because of so many causes and conditions
now if as if you would invite
this friend relative or someone in your orbit
choosing this being the practice of equanimity
the practice for them and if you're having a hard time
choosing someone or there is this sense of entanglement
but wanting to keep equanimity you can't come up with anyone
it's okay to choose yourself
i'll do the guidance for this other being though whatever being you've chosen
so seeing the circumstances this being [Music]
life circumstances
seeing them holding them
with a sense of care with metta goodwill
you wish well for them you want them to be safe
and happy and healthy and have ease
and from this view 360 view far and wide
you can see that there are so many causes and conditions
so many beyond their control beyond your control
there are some choices they have made but
perhaps you also get to see so many
cultural
environmental educational family genetics
systemic zeitgeist historical
and breathing breathing spaciousness
so many interconnections so many interconnections
past and present
and the interconnection you have the connection you have with this being is one of them
is one of the very many
infinite causes and conditions
it's not all up to you just as it's not all up to them
they are doing the best they can
and can you accept that you're doing the best you can
as much as you can with menta both for them and for yourself
don't start thinking but but just feel into it
for a moment and see what might open up often our thinking mind
cannot see beyond a particular way of being
holding this being with care and spaciousness
acknowledging all the causes and conditions
equanimity is not aloof it neither pushes away
nor falls into
with grief
has wisdom connemity is the marriage of matter and
wisdom
i'll offer a few phrases of equanimity maybe no phrases
are needed just holding the space spacious space
with metta acknowledging
that we the two of us are players and this
big scheme called life this mystery doing our best
holding presents with menta
here is one phrase if you wish
all beings have their own journey
all beings all beings have their own journey
may i accept
the arising and passing of all things with equanimity and balance
or i care for you
i care i care about you but cannot keep you from suffering
i care for you about you but i cannot
keep you from suffering
or i care about you and i am not in control
of the unfolding of events
i can't make it all better for you
i care about you and i'm not in control
of the unfolding of events i can
i can't make it all better for you
i can't make it all better and i care about you
i'm not in control of the unfoldings
if the mind wanders bringing the image of this being as clearly as possible into your mind's
eye connecting with them connecting with the practice
and your meta your care for them
and that not everything is within your control
i care i care about you
i care about you
and i'm not in control of the unfolding of all things
and for the last moments of this practice period
can we have equanimity hold with spaciousness this period of practice whether it was
sleepy or distracted or whatever happened acknowledging that
there were so many causes and conditions maybe we didn't sleep enough last night
maybe we were really upset earlier today maybe we're tired we're sick so many
causes and conditions that go into the moment's experience
having meta for ourselves we met for ourselves that we showed up
letting go of any judgment acknowledging this period of practice
was born of many causes and conditions our intention was just one of them
appreciating our intention our intention for wholesome cultivation
and dedicating sharing and merit the goodness generated
with all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere be happy
may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you thank you all for your practice
so the practice of equanimity
it can be a little more nuanced or challenging or subtle
compared to the other practices hence it being the fourth of the brahmavihara
so if your experience was a little
nuanced or [Music] not quite sure it's okay it's all okay
you're practicing you're practicing so i'd love to
open this space up now for any reflections for any questions that have come up any
insights in your practice that out of generosity you're willing to
share with the sangha to support others practice
from a place of a gift oh this is what i discovered this is what was interesting
this was what was challenging so and if you type in chat in the zoom
chat if you type just to me privately i will
read the reflection not your name so i'll be private if you send it to everyone i'll read
both reflection and your name and you're welcome
to raise your hand bill says thank you for this it was very
timely for me as i have a friend going through difficulties ah thank you bill
and barbara please
you're still muted okay there perfect i no i thought this was a
beautiful um thing to meditate on and that
um considering someone who's suffering and you want to jump in to fix it
so often comes up with parents and children adult children
where you still want to fix it you still want so
this is something to really meditate on and how do you
communicate the love and the boundary
uh at the same time it's a the potent thing to think about
yeah absolutely thank you barbara it's
yes very important were there was there any other insights that came up for you
and you're welcome to unmute yourself and if not it's okay with this particular
important relationship in your life
yes you're unmuted barbara oops yeah
uh for me personally no it's just uh it has
come up a lot yeah yeah just appreciating that this is this is significant this is challenging
and how so many conditions that uh
you know you are not in control of and you realize the other is not in control
either and that you just have to con yeah be be kind to yourself and be kind
to the other one and yet realize you can't you can't fix it
exactly yeah thank you for that barbara i appreciate how important that yeah
that the wisdom the meton wisdom how can they both how can they both come together
and patricia says as a single parent i should do this once a week at least
so thanks for bringing up what you brought up barbara yeah
so when i see your hands i'm gonna pause and let others um because you shared
last time so just for pulling forward pulling back those who haven't shared in a while i'd like to invite you to pull
forward please peggy says it's advanced practice thank
you jerry says thanks very helpful as i got email today that a very good friend
that she has six to 12 months to live with cancer oh
it has helped to see that each being is on their own journey and that does not
mean that you do not deeply care yes yeah
thank you jerry thank you for that yeah
the other reflection especially if you haven't shared in a while i'd love to
to hear from you sangha would love to hear from you
and also if it was challenging or problematic something difficult came up that's okay too we'd love to
let's let's bring it up let's be real
just to say in a meditation [Music] community there's no such a thing as
awkward silence it's just silence it's delicious silence
dawn please
yeah when you said use this as an opportunity to take
refuge um i i really appreciated that it resonated
with me you said that at least once maybe more and
it was uh it was challenging equanimity and for me it was sort of meh
and uh i and i think part of it was like choosing
the right person and didn't make sense to choose me and i wasn't sure like who to choose
and and so then i just sort of devolved to the sort of like just practicing loving kindness and sort of listening
and and you know i'll try it next time and uh and it's practice and um
and so i very much appreciate that yeah
great great thank you don yeah beautiful i appreciate the ease with
which you practice and you're sharing your report like okay
couldn't quite land on someone you didn't choosing yourself didn't seem appropriate and just okay then i'll
listen and i'll engage with metta and i'll engage later
i love that that's ea for that practice report which is beautiful it's it's not
you know the alternative so many unwise alternatives could be like oh i can't
choose the right person i'm a failure i can't do this practice this is terrible
i've been practicing for months and months and months and i can't do right
ah sweetie right so to have compassion for that frame of mind also and yet
but i so appreciate hearing what you're saying is like well it's not quite clicking but yeah i'll engage with meta
yay this is a period of practice fantastic as as i've um
haven't said this actually in a long time but i used to repeat every time during happy hour that no matter what
comes up during happy hour as long as you engage with it with meta yeah you're doing the practice
perfectly right so don you're doing the practice perfectly right you're engaging with mitta with
whatever came up so thank you so much for sharing that and and and supporting the community to hear
that to really to hear that reflection thank you so
so dear ones it's time the time has come this is a time and if i wait any other
any later we won't have enough time for the small groups so the small groups again
as always we'll start with 15 seconds of meta for ourselves for each other
the community and then sharing as much or as little as you like about your practice
what came up for you what was interesting or was challenging
and sharing it with equanimity it's like this so many causes and conditions for this practice
so the rooms are created take care of yourselves and
take care of each other okay all right so
here we go
welcome back everyone the rooms are closed and we just have a couple of minutes
for any reflections that might have come up anything you realized
especially if you haven't uh spoken in the recent times you're invited
especially if you're new to ipr if you haven't spoken before
eileen says these sessions help to take refuge in the sangha
beautiful thank you for sharing that aileen taking refuge in the sangha
ah yay indeed
yes and that ties also in with what uh don was saying earlier taking refuge
taking refuge diana you're
i am told you're raising your physical hand which i can't see
let's see diana okay there
asking you to unmute deny your camera is off also
technical difficulties okay um
my question is i can know these phrases and i've been
getting some success with it internally but i
ponder what to say to a person socially after been sitting listening to all this
and caring these tortured lives it just
somehow seems odd to say i care for you or maybe i can say give
me a hug or i can uh or i can just yes got it and for yeah for sake of time i
think i'll uh i think i got the gist of the question um since it's seven o'clock uh i'll
so yes this is not something that you're going to say externally like you know you're not going to stay with someone
may you be safe maybe be happy like it sounds so stilted right so so all you
all you need to do is to hold space is to hold space you need to hold this
space internally for yourself you don't have to say it out loud um hold the space of care with a whole
space of spaciousness for yourself and for the other person and they will feel it
there's so much that we communicate without words but with just the space that we hold thank you for that question
diana that was a really good one yeah thank you so dear ones we have come to the end of
our time together thank you all for your practice for aligning your
actions with your intentions may all beings be safe may all beings
be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you all