okay so hello and welcome to happy hour
everyone so for today's practice
i'd like to invite us to consider the practice of meta
without so much self occupation in it without self preoccupation
so i'll say a few words to set the frame and then i will lead us into meditation
so we explore it together and see what kind of flavors come up what we discover
so
when we care when we have meta love kindness
different nuances of meta the word meta loving kindness friendliness etc
a lot of times um there is a sense of preoccupation
self-preoccupation that can still be in there um either in the relationship or in the
moment so it could be a sense of oh um i like you
i wish you well there's you know there could be some attachment in it you know there's this self involved maybe it's
conditional care oh i may you be well i love you so that you will love me back so that you would
think that i'm worthy and i'm nice and i'm kind and
you know there might be just nuances i may not be too overt but there might be nuances of the
self being entangled in their love like oh i am wishing you well what a wonderful practitioner i am human being
i am wishing you you know there could be different nuances flavors of the self kind of budding in instead
of just pure care love without the self uh
concern those are some ways it can show up it can also show up in the way
of the moment of practice that oh i'm too tired or this is too hard for me
or this is where i'm having too many emotions or my mind is not stable enough or i i right you know just
different nuances flavors of self um occupation preoccupation can come in and
and i'm kind of making light of it a little bit making a caricature of it just to kind of point out it may not be that
gross but might be more subtle might be more subtle again it's um
it doesn't make you a bad person or a bad buddhist or bad practitioner it's just interesting to notice right
because we cultivate awareness we cultivate mindfulness so that we're aware of what's happening
and the invitation tonight as i'll guide us through it is what if it's not about
me it's not about us what if it's not about me
about this being the self of mine what if it's not about me at all what if
it's just an expression of love expression of care expression of good will regardless of
what i get out of this regardless whether i become happier out of this
during happier regardless of what you will think of me or our relationship or
regardless of any of that just sitting landing being
in goodness kindness and letting it radiate
from nowhere could be through you or just is you're reflecting it perhaps
you're like a mirror that maybe take reflects the kindness from the universe and we reflect it back and
and the mirror is just reflective it's not like oh look at me i'm a mirror and
like it doesn't absorb it doesn't it doesn't kind of color the light it just reflects it
just without without showing up too much so we'll play with different metaphors and
just to bring one other consideration in is for those practitioners who like the
practice or or um have been practicing for a while and perhaps
are familiar curious with the concept in buddhism practicing not self it's not
personal it's not personal this is one way that the practice of metta
cultivating good will can really merge with the practice of anata not self or shunyatta
emptiness but there isn't really so much about us this entanglement is just love
flowing love flowing out of emptiness so all right without making it
too heady let's practice let's come to our bodies first and foremost
so invite you to arrive arriving in your body landing
however you're sitting [Music] or lying down
inviting this body to relax to soften
to land to land in this moment
as if you are putting this body down
lovingly kindly
allowing the breath to move on its own in and out
not so much controlling the breath the breath is breathing you
it's been doing it all these years so let it continue
without making breathing a project
with each breath each out breath
letting the body relax soften
land connect more with the earth
supporting you through your feet under your sit bones
all the contact points
and just knitting inviting the awareness
expansive spacious relaxed awareness
to receive the breath and the sensations of the body
just to settle and calm and calm abiding [Music]
for the next few minutes arriving
settling
here here
now
notice if there's any joy delight the process of being breathed
simply in this moment
and if thoughts and pure occupations arise in this moment
kindly gently noticing what's arisen and is it possible
to ever so gently put down put down the preoccupations
the stories
isn't it interesting they all have to do with me myself and mine
having some humor some lightness
kindness with your mind as it likes to think
gently lovingly thank you sweetie thank you dear mind
it's okay we can put this down right now
it's okay thank you for your hard work
this moment just being breathed simply simplicity delicious
simplicity of just sitting and being briefed
and notice we're not trying to get rid of the self just noticing that it's arising
with all self preoccupied thoughts
lightheartedly smilingly oh here it is
can we gently put it down the next out breath maybe just for one breath
noticing for those breaths when there is no preoccupation
ah oh freer how much freer more open
the heart and mind feel how much more spacious
okay
now i'd like to invite you to bring
to your heart to your mind someone for whom your care
your affection kindness meta wishes of well-being
maybe love flow with
and you think of this being [Music] it could be a person could be a pet it
could be a child you think of this being maybe there's a
sense of ease sense of safety maybe a smile shows up just
naturally wish them well
bringing bringing them to your heart to your mind to your mind's eye
and now instead of seeing them from your vantage point
through your eyes imagine this being it's just being held being seen
as if they're standing on stage in an amphitheater a performance hall there they are
there's space all around them
it's not just you they're being held and can they be held in care and love
and good will can they be showered
in goodwill
you could be witnessing it but it's not about you it's not about you it's not about us
your visual and this visualization might be helpful
imagine them being showered with flowers
coming from every direction as if it were meta these flowers
flower petals
maybe all the beings maybe there are beings in this
concert hall all around or maybe the seeds are empty see what
works best for you but somehow from all around
the phrases of meta are being directed
to this being to this dear one
i'll say the traditional phrases you can use whatever phrase works for you
may you be safe may you be safe from inner and outer
[Music]
harm
imagine imagining them receiving that
again maybe there's a chorus where it's silent
so it's not about you you could be joining or you could be witnessing with care
with love but it's not about you this menta
freely offered this care this good wealth
may you be safe from inner and outer harm dear one
hearing the second phrase of meta chanted maybe by all the participants
are somehow coming through the empty seats see what works for you
may you be happy may you be happy and joyful
the third metaphrase may you be healthy and strong
may you be healthy and strong
the fourth metaphrase may your life flow with ease
may you take care of yourself happily
may you be safe
may you be happy
may you be healthy
you have ease
and watching witnessing [Music] beholding your dear being
comfortable maybe sitting standing could be in a comfortable chair on the
stage just receiving the meta the care all around them
all these good wishes for their safety for their happiness
for their health and well-being
what do you want for them what do you wish for them
they're receiving it
you're wrapped in it showered in it
maybe it occurs to you that your dear being there are many people
who hold this person with affection with worms with care
all of you all of you joining your hearts your good wishes
so it's not just about you wishing them well all of you
all the people this person's life perhaps feeling this hall
[Music] all around together you're wishing them well
wishing this being well
it's about giving love
freely generously not about me not about mine
such an act of generosity
as if you've organized the surprise blessing ceremony for them
they're being showered with good will care good wishes
okay all the people who care about them
and whether you feel tired the mind feels distracted
the body feels achy [Music]
can you remind ourselves it's not about me it's not about me in this moment
it's not possible for just a moment to take self preoccupations out and just
generously witness share good will kindness
see what happens
for the last couple of minutes of this practice
letting go of your self-preoccupations and this being who is you
shows up as you and the world let them step in
step into the center together with your dear being
and both of you receive good will good wishes just receiving
generously offered from all the beings in the hall
and not get in your own way with self-preoccupation but i'm not worthy of it
not good enough letting that go this being who is you just receiving
it's not about you get yourself out of there just receiving
meta just receiving goodwill
letting it land letting it be received
sink into your bones
this being who is you is deserving of care of love
of meta as much as anyone else
in some ways it's not about you
the self reflections preoccupation just the being who you are
deserves absolute love and compassion so let this being receive it
may all beings
including ourselves know their own goodness
that they're deserving of love
may all beings be free
thanks everyone thank you for your
practice so
i'd love to hear your reflections what do you notice what this was like for you
what might have opened up in this different way of entering into meta
[Music] and i'll change the chat settings you can
if you type in chat to everyone i'll read your name if you just send it to me privately i won't read
your name you can also raise your zoom hand to share your reflection it can also be
about the first part about calming and settling our minds did you
notice if you with the out of breath if you put down preoccupations
if there was more spaciousness more ease when the preoccupations were put down
and also maybe how this practice of
creating a circle of benefactors for your dear being in the past i've taught
circle of benefactors when we created for ourselves and we receive from people who care about us but here
you basically threw a surprise party a blessing ceremony for someone you cared about in
your heart to see oh what does that feel like how is there a sense of generosity goodness
that can can come up when we take ourselves out of that so i'd love to hear what you noticed
how this was for you
and you can raise your zoom hand it's under reactions or
under participants depending on the version of zoom you have
yes kim please
it was lovely um very spacious and
um i could a nice progression from
um my breath feeling kind of contrived or thick to
uh to it feeling fresh and cool
and that was nice i chose my son who's
an actor so it was like you know but he's a tv actor and but yeah
imagining him and he's he's filming right now and so he's like everybody's
on the set and then all his friends added and then all the people that are watching him
um the show and that felt really good and then um bill i hope you don't mind
i was so pleased to still see that you were back and that made me you know i was joyous when
i when i came on and so bill came into the circle when i came in and said like the
three of us carlo and bill and i were like you know this huddled and we had all this
all of carlo's friends and the set and the the uh the actors and
the people viewing him we were taking advantage of that
that's pretty cool oh my god kim it just makes me so happy i'm happy
i'm happy here hearing your your practice reporting just it's so joyous what you're describing
with your son and on the set and and being happy that bill has come here and him joining your
your and and bill says glad to see you two kim in the chat that's sweet you know this this this song of support in in your
practice it just delights me to no end thank you kim it was really sweet to hear
the progression from the contracted breath to all the joyousness that you're
talking but i loved it thank you delights me to know it yeah sweet
any other reflections you'd like to share any challenges any questions jerry says
it felt more nurturing and less just about one to one and as a result more powerful
for a crowd of folks wishing a person well yeah
yeah beautiful thanks for that observation
and what also i noticed too i was having a great time um imagining my dear being just being
showered and just like oh so there was also sense of mudita
vicarious joy for them being showered it was interesting to explore the sense
of self kind of getting a little softer or not being so so out there so they're so strong
this way and another message i've had a hard time in the past trying
to hang out in the field of meta but with this image i could really
access that yay oh that makes me so glad yay for the person who sent me this
this reflection yay i'm celebrating yeah that makes me very glad yay so
great this is always available to you this way in great it's wonderful to know what works
we explore so many different things and each way just opens up a new dimension
so dear ones we can save some time for on the other end when we come out of
practice groups and um and in the practice groups yay now you
can come together with a couple of other practitioners and have a little meta party
together oh kimberly says one has one more reflection i'll share this
and then we'll go into groups um i chose someone that i saw briefly someone that
i couldn't relate to at all and for whom i felt a kind of repulsion because she was smoking a cigarette
and looked contracted and self-centered i found that she was soaked in the safety but only after
shock and awe and then she was able to open to the support and love that was coming her
way and when we were together we were holding hands and reaching out
to our support group wow thank you kimberly i'm getting chills reading your reflection
yeah you went for the challenging category i love it and it opened up in this way
oh beautiful beautiful that's profound thank you for sharing that
yeah lovely oh i am so inspired by all of your practice
everyone just i'm so inspired by all of your practice thank you
so so let me make the breakout group so it'll be groups of
three and let's start with um 15 seconds of
meta silent silently for each other then you can share as much or as little
as you want with your practice partners yay practicing community so
here we go opening the rooms enjoy okay the rooms will be closed and
they're closed everyone is back so welcome back everyone we have
a few minutes for any reflections especially if you haven't spoken already or if you haven't spoken for a
while we'd love to hear from you what did you notice
don't be shy love to hear about your
insights and you're welcome to raise your zoom hand
yes the voice that says recording in progress is a new zoom edition so that when i
turn on the recording everybody gets notified so that's what's happening yeah um richard please
am i unmuted yes oh i just wondered about if you
find yourself sending meta to someone who's ill for example i mean does it turn into
compassion is it all right if you mix the two yeah yeah so um
basically when metta which is love and kindness which is good will sense of may you be well may you be
happy just sense of good will comes in contact with suffering it
becomes compassion it gets expressed as compassion compassion is meta plus suffering
so that's what you're experiencing it becomes compassion it holds the suffering
um is so is that what the question is also
if there's more needed here i'm not as confused as i thought no you're not at all you're right on
right on richard thank you jeff please uh
yeah thank you nikki i guess one thing inside i had was that you know what we commonly regard as love
in our culture like the romantic version of love is just totally and totally about self really i
mean that's really what it's about it's like i love you because of what how you're going to make me feel
and um and this is just like taking the self out of it takes away that romantic you know that
romantic type of love just takes that seems like to me it takes that just off the table it's just a totally different
kind of a thing but i'm just curious what what do you think about the relationship between you know meta as we're practicing and
the romantic love is there some overlap perhaps that i'm not seeing yeah yeah there's absolutely
overlap jeff and i so appreciate you bringing it in um so the um often our
concept of romantic love in this culture is is love affection plus attachment
plus obligation con a contractual you know i love you so you love me
it's not it has strings attached right so so it is possible to have romantic love
without attachment so we do we don't have to limit it to that it it
can be i love you just as you are just with generosity um
and there are some couples many couples who actually reach that stage and it's
such a beautiful stage of romantic love that you just love the other person
just as they are with a sense of unconditional love and it's it's sacred it's holy it's
beautiful it's non-transactional so absolutely
there's there's overlap but let's let us not limit our
concept of romantic love to be this small version of what it can really be
yeah thank you for that so dear ones we have come to the end of another happy
hour together thank you so much for the gift of your
practice may all beings be happy may all beings
be well including us [Music]
thanks everyone be well take care see you on wednesday