so good day greetings and here we are beginning of our
meditation session and there are two things i want to
bring forth at the beginning of this meditation where the overall context is
or focus now on this practice of mindfulness of breathing
is samadhi the unification of mind the
serenity of mind the concentration of mind and um a very strong association with
the deeper concentration in buddhism in the early buddhism is the idea of
assurance some people some translators translated self-assurance or
confidence and so that uh we're kind of looking for or we're
evoking or we're resting on some where we're um beginning to prioritize or
recognize in us and providing in us
is a deep sense of internal assurance
internal confidence that comes along with somebody with this unification
but also supports it so certainly for many of us something
deep inside in our hearts probably it could use a lot of assurance
the world is in big change and a lot of challenges and
and to be able to discover a place of deep assurance so that
we can let go of our thoughts our concerns our everyday preoccupations really let go
and discover us the tremendous goodness that resides within us and have that
goodness be a resource for how we live our life so that's one thing assurance the other
is that one of the primary one of the great analogies or similes buddha uses for a particular state of
concentration is that of a of a mountain lake
that is not being fed by any water any rain or any rivers feeding into it
but the only feeding of the lake the nourishment of the lake replenishment of the lake is an
underwater spring maybe right in smack in the middle of a lake underwater spring with an underwater
fountain of water that gets sprayed up and out and fills the lake with a new water
fresh water clean water and so the idea of there being a found
a source within us a spring within us that really is a little bit is
peacefully wonderfully uh flowing moving dynamic
this sense of flow a vibration of aliveness of vitality of
of joy of assurance that we are opening to allow for
and so these two things assurance and this inner flow of goodness of warmth of of energy
of vitality requires something of us requires of us to
create the conditions for to allow it to fill us to allow it to
live in us and one of the requirements is not being preoccupied by things not being off run
running off to the races and thinking about things and worried about things certainly it's
difficult not to put down it's difficult to put down our everyday concerns and emotions and feelings
so i acknowledge that but it's also possible to begin orienting
oneself in in the kind of level of receptivity
and softness and kindness that generosity inner generosity
that begins making it possible to invite or to sense or feel or receive
a kind of assurance and a kind of vitality and aliveness that samadhi
is so not samadhi is not this narrow laser focus that we all get tight and
contracted but rather it's an opening and letting go
into the bottom of the bowl into really being centered here
in that center maybe somewhere there you feel more alive and vital this flow
of goodness maybe very subtle so assurance and receptivity
a willingness to receive and be here a willingness to be here to allow all to
invite all things to come in and be unified be gathered collected here
so taking a meditation posture
that maybe for you will somehow some simple way
in some simple way that will
invite goodness invite nourishment invite
what's that what's really good in you reassuring in you to be here
a posture of assurance and to gently close your eyes
and allow yourself to relax in your body
so that with some assurance your inhale begins
and the exhale is allowed
the inhale has characteristics of this inner
this the inner the spring and in her leg something that arises and flows
and moves and expands through the body
and to allow the beginning of the in-breath
to allow the all the sensations of breathing in
to be received and felt
and then to as you exhale allow yourself to relax the body
relaxing the face the shoulders the belly a kind of relaxation that becomes
an invitation for your body to self-organize
the body to become whole
and as you exhale allowing the mind the thinking mind to relax
and soften
adjusting the mind a little bit so the attitude the way of thinking the way you are in
the mind is
is kind enough for pleasant enough friendly enough soft enough
that the mind gathers together everything in the mind is welcomed to come into a hole
and as you exhale again to settle in
let go with the exhale deep inside of you
to a place maybe where there's some assurance confidence
some place of peace or tranquility
allowing the body whole body to be receptive
to the vitality of itself the physical vitality of life
flowing and moving through you
relaxing into that opening
and then at the center of it all steady yourself on your breathing
breathing in breathing out a gentle steadiness
with a mind that's softening quieting
breathing with inner
assurance
breathing with whatever inner wholesomeness there is or maybe in some people's language
whatever inner goodness that's here not that you're thinking about it
but a felt sense
a vitality aliveness of goodness
of which the movements of breathing are part of
and then instead of counting the breaths today maybe at every exhale
there's some there's a similar thing you can do a single word
to place you into the experience in a receptive soft assured way
and maybe you don't say the word with your inner mind your inner voice
but you do it so quietly that it's you imagine you're saying it
and every time you exhale imagine saying yes
just yes to your experience to being here to breathing
to steadying yourself quieting yourself
on the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
the breathing that occurs within the vitality aliveness
of your lake
yes on the exhale
yes and letting go of your thoughts
hey yes that comes with a small subtle smile
barely perceptible turning up the corners of your lips
yes of delight
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to find within you
a place of assurance
confidence
even if it's quite small find the place where there is
located within you embodied expression of
confidence assurance and breathe with that
maybe as you exhale letting go into that assurance that confidence
a confidence and assurance which the buddhist tradition associates with a
peacefulness
and as you're sitting here meditating
maybe with some assurance and peacefulness confidence
and without needing to say or do anything for anyone here in the privacy of your own
meditation open your heart and mind
to the people around you in the town you live county
province you live in the people maybe you'll interact with on
through technology or people you're likely to think about
and just settle back in your assurance and gaze upon these people kindly
relax back safely in your place of assurance
and gaze out imagine everyone engaging upon them with good will
maybe even imagining what some of their faces would look like
if they were happy smiles they would have
maybe a little sparkle in their eyes
and imagine how good it would be if they could be happy this way
and let there be inside of you if you'd like an attitude and thoughts of goodwill and
well-wishing for these people may they be happy
may they be safe
may they be peaceful
and may they be free
and may you carry with you through the day this private place within
whether you have enough assurance and confidence that privately you can gaze
upon others consider think about others with good will and well-wishing
for their happiness and whether you act on it or not is a
secondary thing
to allow to bring at least your inner life
to have love or care or goodwill for the people around you they don't
have to know
[Music]
so breathing in one
concentrates breathing out one concentrates the mind
breathing in one steadies the mind breathing out one steadies the mind
breathing in one unifies the mind breathing out one unifies the mind
so all these words concentrate steady unify are all kind of
uh facets of the same thing developing and deepening
meditation practice and it can be helpful in the deepening of practice
to have some landmarks so have some signposts some some kind of sense of
where we're going or what we're looking for what we're valuing as we develop meditation practice
because the you know subconsciously unconsciously
the mind is valuing all kinds of things and and that's why the mind the thoughts go
off thinking about the past future fantasy what we're worrying about what we want because we
value we have we we prioritize or we put value into those concerns
but if we have value in the process of meditation and the signposts the experiences of
meditation and enough to recognize them then we make space for them to grow
we they we make space for them to nourish us and support us and provide more confidence more reassurance
oh this is good this is the right thing to do so it's easier to put down our preoccupations
and so with this deepening of the practice there's uh things like the mind becomes
stiller quieter the mind the body becomes softer
more malleable there becomes a sense of well-being of different kinds joy and
happiness subtleness the the um there can be a
sense of joy and happiness there can be equanimity uh there can be a sense of being really
embodied i could not really feel the vitality of our life coursing through us and
really feeling present and whole or settled ah it feels so good to be at home in this body
and the same thing with the mind the mind can feel have assurance to it be peaceful
the mind can start feeling expansive as if the mind has a room for all the little details all the
dramas of our life all the concerns we have all the little experiences
the details anything that's a detail can be held now in your mind that's
really broad and wide like a very large large room that can hold all the
everyone everything everybody inside in a peaceful spacious way so this expansive mind
open mind there can be for some people a sense of brightness even light that comes on that
feels really good but i wanted to provide you with the three similes
analogies that the buddha uses for this deepening of meditation practice and
the advantage of similes or analogies is that each person kind of interpret it
or find themselves in it more easily than with a clear kind of technical description of
what might supposed to be happening in meditation similarly analogies are a little black
poetry they're evocative they touch our kind of imagination maybe even our emotions a little bit
these things also have get a little bit kinesthetic or somatic sometimes the these images so that our somatic
involvement with associations come into play as well and um and uh and there's a lot of room
for personal uniqueness so our own way of finding ourselves
in these analogies so i want to offer three of them and they they're kind of
three progressive and now uh deepening stages of meditation and the first uh and they all have to
use the they all have they all use water in the analogies and
it's never been explained to me why water keeps being used in these similes
analogies what it represents but i take it to represent the mind or awareness itself
and that's the medium in which we're operating right now or the mind the awareness and and so this
awareness begins um takes different shapes different
forms as it practice deepens so the first simile is water
being sprinkled into in our modern equivalent into flower and as the water gets
sprinkled in the water gets folded in kneaded in
stirred into the flour until the flour becomes dough you know to make bread and so what's
important is that all the all the water that's being sprinkled in gets kneaded in and spread out evenly throughout the
dough and so part of the kneading of the bread eating of the flour the dough is to get
that spread out the the you know equally around so that the dough kind of could hold the
flour can hold together into one hole so that's the analogy and uh
and um in a sense the the flower is the body and the
and the water is the awareness or the mind and we want to bring these together so the awareness
is um immersed in or penetrates throughout the body so the body and mind are to be
in the same place at the same time if the mind is thinking about other times in other places
then the body and mind are separated but if the mind starts focusing
awareness starts entering into the bodiness present for the body like for the breathing then the mind is kind of in the same
place in the same time as the body and uh and
by doing that uh what we're looking for is the body and mind to end up in in a kind of harmony with each other um
a kind of unification and harmonious working together where there can be real
experience feelings of health and healthfulness healthiness and wholesomeness that can't be felt
if there's a real dichotomy real separation between these two parts of ourselves and um
and so we take awareness and uh we bring it into our breathing
and and work it's kind of nice the breathing itself is kind of a massage a kind of a kneading
but we bring our awareness and we place it we sprinkle it into something like our breathing
and then we want to knead it we want to stay there with the breathing and those are two different movements
that i talked about yesterday the contact the placing of attention somewhere like with the breathing
and then keeping it there and keeping it there is not holding it necessarily steady but a gentle kind of working it
and staying there staying there be there and then we have to do it again because the mind wanders
off we come back and connect and stay there and stay there and and that's a sprinkling of awareness
into our breathing into our body and we're kneading it in we're kneading it in and so there's a massage there's a
rhythm of coming back and applying yourself staying there reconnecting and so for every beginning
of the inhale and begin the exhale there's a kind of gentle reconnecting that goes on there
and then it's staying there stay there be there so the massage and so slowly
um we're beginning to uh penetrate awareness into the whole experience of breathing
so it's continuous and and fills the experience of breathing wherever that might be in the body
and then and then there's a kind of uh as we get a hang and we're doing this hang of doing this and
feel like this is going well there can be a rise a kind of gladness certainly the gladness
and happiness of relief of not being lost and preoccupied in some of these thoughts
that thinking that we have that maybe not for some of you but for many of us you know is not so much fun
it's not a great thing sometimes to spend a lot of time caught up in thoughts and ruminations
and stuff and what a relief it is to have the thoughts received enough and not be pulled into their orbit and be
settled in here so there's work involved there's this kneading the sprinkling in
coming here the next analogy is that what i used in meditation
is that now the is the mountain's mountain lake with the underwater spring that flows
through it and now in a sense uh awareness has become very stable
and expansive and big and kind of penetrates or is resting or is maybe coterminous with
the body that somehow now awareness in the body are not so distinct
but we really feel the fullness the vitality the aliveness of the body
where the sensing the sensory apparatus of the body's sense endings of the body are part of the
awareness system and so awareness is not just cognitive
mental observing or knowing but there's a broader feeling of sensing and aliveness
that's part of awareness and so the body and mind now are are there together as partners and then
uh within that the the concentration the steadiness the
real kind of intimacy with just breathing is um if he has this inner goodness and
nourishment to it that there's a welding up of a kind of joy or well-being or delight
that's not evaluative it's not like we have to think ourselves into being happy it's almost like some people say that
there are joy hormones or serotonin and endorphins they get released
in this steady massaging staying with a focus of concentration a sense of
well-being wells up and there's a flow of vitality that feels like it comes from the inside out the joy that comes from
the inside like a spring going forth the last analogy is now
the deeper meditation the sense of flow and vitality and joy settles away
into a very deep satisfying peacefulness and the analogy is that of a of uh
the lake has now become or lake has become really still unmoving and there's lotus is growing in
it meaning it's not a cold mountain lake or something but now it's a very nice temperature lake that's very
comfortable to be in and there's beautiful lotus many different colored lotus flowers
submerged in the lake floating on the lake and and this sense of everything's very
peaceful everything is calm very still and everything that's known within that
calmness even though conventionally it might be something that's not
maybe a little bit of i don't know something not not so nice maybe but everything that is touched by
awareness now touched by the water is like beautiful lotus flowers floating there peacefully in space in the in the
water so additionally there's work
in the with the kneading of the dough and then there's no more work and it's just a flow that's happening
we're being carried by the flow and then the flow comes down
and we're just kind of in this very peaceful place very still place where everything just
feels beautiful and there's and it's in that uh and in these states
where there's a lot of reassurance a lot of confidence a lot of equanimity um and it's a beautiful thing to tap
into this capacity for deep confidence deep serenity deep reassurance it does the heart a
tremendous amount of good to have it and it does not depend
on the things in the world around us being just right being fixed
it's uh this very private inner place inside that uh becomes a resource for which we
can kind of enter into the world in a in a wonderful way
so maybe those analogies are interesting for you to play with and work with and
maybe this topic of inner reassurance assurance and confidence is something that you can
explore how that lives in you as you go through the next day and i look forward to seeing you tomorrow thank you
and then to mention again that um monday we'll have a community meeting
after our our um you know
seven o'clock sitting in the dharma talk so around 7 45 i'll post a zoom link a variety of
places on the imc calendar for this event and the imc
what's new section and also i'll put it on the on the chat here for the youtube as well and we'll have that
meeting as a kind of uh marking our one year of doing these uh seven a.m sittings
so i look forward to those of you who'll come thank you