greetings greetings sangha wherever you are in this moment on this
planet earth good wishes to you so
so we continue today our fifth day in the series of exploring
supportive conditions for somebody for concentration for calming
settling unifying the mind heart
and um just to briefly remind us
what we have worked with and all these conditions together are
really support each other it's not just one versus another all of them together
the fabric it's as if samad is a fabric and and it's made of
all these threads all these threads
relinquishing what is not helpful and on the other side of the coin
noticing there is joy in the present moment this moment is enough there is beauty
wonder awe and this the simplicity of this moment
and then there is relaxing the body a relaxed body so that it can support a
relaxed mind and that is only possible it becomes a
wise effort if on the other hand we have atapi gentle persistence
coming back over and over again as well as what we discussed vitaka and
vichara initial application sustained application connecting with the breath serving the
breath sir surfer enjoying surfing the entirety
of the breath today we could have gone on more and
more and yet today what we will add here is our attitude our
intention our interest because the way we approach
this practice makes a difference is the mind tight is the mind curious and interested
to learn no matter what does the mind have zest does the mind
have a wanting i want the mind to settle does it want a state does it want an
experience so what is the attitude is is the heart
giving itself is it dedicating as as if it's honoring as if it's
putting itself on the altar um as if it's a sacred
act this practice are these dimensions of beauty and sacredness in the practice
or do we have a work orientation we bring the mind that we have in daily
life the achievement the achievement orientation do we bring that what is the attitude what is the
container so becoming tuned to that again without judgment if you notice
oh yeah i really want to state i really want to get concentrated and have uh absorption
and and uh uh somebody the access concentration and john is
okay yeah there it is so sweetheart yeah i know that brings that brings tightness that brings
pain it practice becomes a source of suffering so just know just notice
so so with that let's let's settle let's
settle and begin [Music] ah settling into our bodies
blending
turning your gaze inward to the simplicity
delicious simplicity
of taking refuge in this moment
taking refuge
this body and this breath
in the goodness in the goodness of our intention
of wanting to wake up wanting to cultivate goodness kindness peace
offering ourselves offering ourselves wholeheartedly
trusting the goodness of our intention
connecting to something above and beyond our selves
trusting
this expansiveness spaciousness of this goodness
that we are a part of whether or not we see it we have
access to it trusting trusting it and relaxing
into it trusting the stream
that will carry us
letting the body relax soften
as if you're floating floating in a gentle gently
loving stream of goodness if your body is tight it's harder
imagine yourself floating on top of the water with ease
stream of the dharma the goodness you're a partner
turning away for what is not helpful
recognizing the joy the delight of coming back connecting with the breath
staying on the breath as if you were surfing
this beautiful wave of the breath this gift of the breath
for as long as possible before dropping off
and connecting catching the next wave
with interest with reverence
not with expectation or tightness
but with grace
let the body be soft and relaxed letting go
of any tension
with each breath
calming soothing subtly
checking in now and then is the body relaxed
ah is the mind relinquishing turning away
from what's not helpful in this moment recognizing the simplicity
the joyful delicious simplicity
of what's already here
connecting with the breath in the lower abdomen if the mind is busy
today the lower abdomen is most settling
observing the breath as many breaths
as available enjoying surfing
the joy of surfing the breath
what is the attitude of the mind that's meditating
and as we end the sit
having appreciation acknowledgement gratitude for having
been able to show up as much as well
as it's been available
letting our hearts bright [Music]
in the goodness trusting there is goodness
letting go of any judgment although distracted sleepy it's
okay you showed up
you showed up to the temple as well as you could walking bouncing crawling you showed up
it's all that matters appreciating appreciating yourself
and sharing this goodness this goodness
as a gift as a gift of generosity
with yourself and all beings everywhere
be our practice our cultivation of peace and goodness
support awakening of all things everywhere
including ourselves may all beings be happy
may all beings be free
thank you for your practice
so greetings greetings international sangha friends around the
world this green blue planet of ours
so for this week we have been exploring supportive conditions for
cultivating samadhi also translated often translated as
concentration but perhaps more preferably translated as calm
unification of the mind calm abiding
etc so that there is less of a sense of tightness in the word that there might
be associations for some people with concentration and
today we combine them all together and brought in the container the
container that holds them all which is our attitude intention
so again we had started with relinquishing what is not helpful
and on the other side of the coin realizing oh yes there's beauty there is grace there is
delight joy in the simplicity of the pleasant present moment they work together
they support each other these two supporting conditions and then the
other couple of supporting conditions we talked about one was relaxing the body
relaxing the body so the mind can relax
and then if the body is just relaxed well maybe maybe the attitude becomes a little too
relaxed but then on the other side of the coin with a relaxed body we have
coming back again and again gently atopi coming back perseverance gentle
perseverance and together vitaka and vichara
connecting connecting and sustaining connecting and sustaining vitaka
containing initial application which are sustaining so
all of these four and and you see two and two the the the first two are kind of a pair the
second two are kind of a pair and then what holds all of these is is
our attitude our intention the mind that is meditating and attitude intention is so important
um that actually i have been weaving it through all of these
teachings all of these supporting factors our attitude is not separate from them it is in the way we
show up in the way we approach each of these factors it's not separate and yet
it is important to name it today as the container that holds it all holds our practice holds our cultivation
so a few notes on on attitude on intention
so otagenia um a burmese monk
i've practiced with he um likes to he has an an interesting way of
putting attitude and he often says what is the quality of
the mind what is the mind he says what is the mind that is meditating is it a
greedy mind is is it a mind that has
aversion and ill will in it is it a confused mind so is it a mind that are is infused with the three poisonous
roots already or is it the mind that is infused with their opposite
with ah relinquishment the ease generosity is it a mind that is infused
with kindness good will is it the mind that is infused with
wisdom with trust with faith
so knowing what is the mind that is practicing what is the mind that's
meditating is it the mind that wants okay all right i want to get concentrated i want this i want that
what is the quality of the mind and at first if you're beginning in our practice
sometimes it is hard at the beginning to notice the quality
of the mind because we might be a fish swimming in water it might be hard
to know what if the if the water has dye in it has a little bit of color in
it we may not notice but just gently keep noticing what is the attitude in the mind what is the
attitude in the mind and i tell you especially with the practice of samadhi
practice of samatta leading to the state of samadhi
i've seen so many practitioners get exceedingly tight
exceedingly tight and unfriendly and um and you know the sense that
okay you know for say that i'd admit in a meditation hall and practicing under retreat
they become so attached without seeing it they become so contracted attached to the quiet to
the connecting to the breath to this to cultivating this that become they become really brittle the mind becomes really brittle
and irritable every sound every door that closes every
noise outside every breath next door is like oh make it stop quiet quiet i'm trying to develop
concentration it's ouch ouch ouch notice so if that arises for you it's okay just realize
that the practice is becoming their source of suffering because of the attitude in the mind it's
okay it's okay is the mind does the mind have generosity and kindness
or or grasping craving and aversion just notice what is the
mind so that is one question you can drop in
now and then and become attuned to it become attuned to it in a very friendly
gentle way because again it's the water that we swim in in our practice
and similarly the sense of intentionality is what is
the intention is it is the intention me me me i want
this me me me you know what is the intent you get to know it is it an intention of service are you
giving your heart to this practice without expectation
there is it's wonderful to have aspirations but not expectations so
are they different an aspiration is a beautiful intention
to have an aspiration an intention a design an intention you use the word aspiration
for waking up for service for for generosity for kindness
so as an aspiration it lifts us up it supports us
in our path whereas expectation i expect to wake up i expect
to become more generous you see it's much tighter this expectation tightens us
it makes us smaller it becomes about me me me i expect
whereas ah aspiration aspiration
as if we're putting ourselves we're putting our our precious minutes precious moments on the altar
of humanity together it connects us to to something above and beyond ourselves
that we are a part of we are a part of it expands us
it expands us
so attitude
intention another thing i wanted to bring here which is
important is an attitude of
interest and curiosity interest and curiosity
so whatever happens even if your mind is distracted
if things are coming up if it's sleepy as long as there is interest curiosity there is zest oh this
is interesting ah this just like a nick just like a scientist of your own mind
there is no failed experiment because you always learned as long as you have that
attitude as long as the attitude is one of open openness curiosity learning
interest chanda zest this interest in practice instead of okay
all right it's all right i got it sit down it's my 30 minutes all right okay i
gotta do this just just as i brush my teeth and yeah i'm supposed to meditate because i read
in whatever news articles but it's good for me oh don't don't if if you're
showing up like a soldier like every day it feels like it's
drudgery stop practicing for a week just just don't until you
love it until you you miss it until like oh yes even actually for longer until you
really feel the desire the love the the curiosity interest
so do it with love do it because of love not because i have to that's the
perfect way to to kill aspiration
so
so dear ones there's so much more to say about samadhi about
this beautiful practice of cultivation and as i said it's been a primary practice
the jhanas have been the primary practice for me
and i do like to mention with gratitude really with love um
my burmese teacher packs ayada jhana master who's the living master
jhana master with a lot of devotion and yeah and love
so so um offering the goodness yeah offering the goodness of my
practice with you this week to him and and all beings and all beings
everywhere so so um come and visit us at happy hour
um diana clark and myself every weekday pacific time six between
six and seven pm pacific time um we are on zoom and also monday wednesday
friday i'm also on youtube come visit us come practice with us come practice
um cultivation of the heart meta loving kindness compassion
good will vicarious joy gratitude forgiveness all the practices of the
heart we explore them we've been exploring them for a long time so so come and join us it's a lovely
sangha many of you i recognize the names are part of that sangha also so
come and join us when you can when your heart is called to it not
because you should but if your heart wants to cultivate come and
join us especially on zoom because we have small group practice which is very intimate and sweet so
thank you so much for the gift of your practice
may you may all of us may all beings everywhere
know the goodness know their own goodness may they be safe happy
healthy may they have ease may they be free including ourselves
thank you all take good care of your dear selves