so um but i want to say some words for people who might be listening today in audio dharma
because maybe some of you are on audio dharma today wondering what happened because it's not
not being broadcast on youtube today because somehow we're having a trouble with uh streaming from the from the
computer and um so then we'll work on it and i'm sure
we'll fix it
and then kind of an announcement is that um
it just felt right to me at least that uh for the next two two weeks after tomorrow we'll take a break uh meeting
in person here at imc and just to kind of get our bearings a little bit with this new
covet situation and and so uh
and then probably we'll start again again in two weeks on the monday the 17th in person it's my guess but we'll
see how things develop and go and i don't feel so myself i don't feel so
worried but maybe it's not maybe it's from stupidity
but uh the um i mean i think a little influence that i don't all of you run out of here at
once but about two weeks ago my son came home from college with omicron
and so going through that whole kind of monitoring that and learning about it and what it's all about and
that was partly the motivation to close for two weeks but also part of the reason why i'm not so worried about it
also if we had the precautions we have here are pretty good
and i think that it makes it pretty safe for everyone and
so but when we open again we might uh certainly request but maybe require
that everyone also be boosted the boosters make big difference and
my son went through he almost wouldn't have known he had it
except he was told and then he got tested and he had very minor symptoms
and and then all of us quarantined and all of us got you know tested at the
right time and so it's all good apparently
so um so that's kind of the announcement
so then for the talk
this is the last sunday talk for this year let me get ready to welcome in a new
year and i remember that in 20
when we we brought in 29 2020 that because of the you know this 2020
vision thing that some of us talked about you know there's the year of clear seeing
well maybe it was in some ways
but but now i'm thinking about this 2022
and i would love it if it was a year of care a year in which we cared
and it seems that it's particularly important that this juncture of human
history that more of us care and it really makes a difference if we
really come together all of us to care about so many things we've learned this over
the last year over the last decades to care about that are worth caring about
and then i woke up this morning to learn that desmond tutu had died
and you know he was a very inspiring person both because of his fight against
apartheid but also because of a phenomenal work with this
truth and reconciliation process in south africa i mean that was so inspiring it's one
thing to set a person's people free from oppression like he did which is so
important it's another thing to come out of that and try to heal the society that was so
divided and probably south africa wouldn't have managed so well if it hadn't been for
the truth and reconciliation process and that inspired so many people in south africa even people who didn't go through
it formally and you know the proceedings they had they just appointed a different way of
being together and uh
and then thinking about what i was going to talk about today i read about his a little bit about his
biography and i just wanted to mention that um
that apparently he had polio as a kid and he was his right hand was atrophy
because he couldn't use it and also when he was 18 he spent a year
and a half in the hospital with tuberculosis but there was a episcopal priest who
came to visit him and became his friend and that's what set him in motion to become a
priest himself and then become the archbishop and then
become such a big you know big influence on south africa and so
you know he was a great person inspiring person but also we remember that there was
people who cared for the inspiring people the people who believed in them enough so that they
could move forward and into and become someone wonderful
and perhaps you know they say this idea of care
emphasizing care there's a story
traditional story from somewhere i have his ideas from the middle east
sometime in the time of old there was a family that
gave birth to a baby girl
and as it was there was a old wise
woman who lived not the edge of town and she came to see this new girl that was
born and she said oh she's a wonderful girl for sure
and she will die on her wedding night
well so she grew up and she was a wonderful person and she got engaged she got married there
was the wedding and then there was a wedding feast that evening and the parents got they didn't tell
anybody about this prediction but they were kind of like little bit on the edge you know
she's going to die tonight and now so it was a big feast everyone
was partying and feasting and dancing and things and there came a poor beggar
to the door of the party knocked and asked to have some food and everyone shooed the person away no no no
no but the bride
somehow saw what's going on and of all the people in the party was the one who went out there
to give food to the beggar the party went on there was a wedding
night and everyone woke up the next morning and they were alive so the parents went to find the old
woman and said what happened we've been living with this idea that she was going to die
oh but there was one thing that was going to save her and that was if she
did an act of kindness on her wedding night but i couldn't have told you that
because then it wouldn't have worked it wouldn't have been kind it would have been done it you know for that purpose
so the act of kindness that saves someone the act of kindness that will save us
the act of care that will save us
what will we save through our care
and there's lots to care about now we know as i said and now they say that in terms of the
whole climate change that's happening it's not a matter of stopping it but now
our care can go into reducing the damage and in some ways that makes it easier
because the idea of all or nothing is kind of hard but the idea that we can reduce it
each of us can reduce it in an important way
maybe by saving one life one animal life anything anything we can
do to make it better to care but one of the things that
we save if we care is in fact our care
maybe caring compassion kindness is one of the most important resources and
that we have and it can be lost it can be forgotten it can be
submerged in despair it can be lost in anger it can be lost in all kinds of
things and distractions in netflix
but to care to let that beautiful maybe what's saved is our care and that counts
who knows what our cares need will be needed for there's another uh maybe middle eastern
near eastern story of a sufi who uh
some genie comes along and offers this sofia uh one wish
or two wishes i don't know how you because you'll decide whether it's one or two so the sufi wishes
um may i help everyone i come across
wherever i go may i be helpful to people but may it be that i don't know that i'm
doing it and so he's given this big bag this
burlap bag to carry that's filled with seeds of
fruit trees maybe date date palms or something
and it has a little hole in the back of it and so as he's carrying it
and on his back for his shoulder it slowly loses these seeds out the back but he doesn't see
them falling and he keeps walking as he wanders around his part of the world
and he doesn't see that over the weeks and months and years after him it grows his fruit trees that benefits
the people around him so who knows does your care need to have
proof that you've succeeded is it enough to care can you care
but sometimes we do get the wonderful fruit sees the fruits of our care and
sometimes it comes back to ourselves maybe this is a very trite example but
it was a little bit inspiring maybe because it happened during retreat at the retreat center and so it kind of
everything kind of magnified a little bit there so those of you haven't been there we have a little coffee tea area
and then under the counter there's a small little refrigerator where they have dairy milk
different kinds of milk things and
and so one day i noticed that there was no milk there
so i went out of my way to go get milk bread unopened
container and i put it in the fridge for someone who was going to come so i didn't think about it anymore
a couple of hours later i decided to have some tea and to put some milk in it and i opened
the refrigerator and there was a full unopened bottle of of milk there
the person who had benefited was me
you know i'd care you know so it's a silly example right but it comes around but i'll tell you
i'll tell you another way it comes around that happened this week or so
so my mother is now in a memory care home
is now in hospice and so it was a week or two ago and uh
and so as all this kind of hospice care comes into play
so i received a call i get all these phone calls now from the hospice but you know all kinds of issues and stuff
and this wonderful wonderful place mission hospice here in san mateo
and so i got one of these phone calls and this woman says you know i'm i'm the
mission hospice chaplain and i'm getting ready to visit your mom
so it's nice but turns out the woman who's my mom's chaplain
was introduced to becoming a chaplain to chaplaincy by doing the buddhist chaplaincy
training that i offer here at imc some 10 years ago 11 years ago she went
through the training and learned about all this and so i you know i was supporting her i
wanted to you know it's a wonderful thing to train chaplains some of you in the room have been in the chaplaincy program i can see at least three or four
of you here and um
and uh and so you know i just love doing it i feel like it's a kind of pyramid scheme
for joy because people go out and benefit others and then guess who benefited it
comes around so so that's that's nice you know so
who knows what our characters in the world maybe we don't need to know but who knows the good we can do
so there's another story of a christian monastery
someplace that the few monks that were left in the monastery were getting quite old
and no one came to visit the monastery anymore and there was no one joining the monastery
it seemed like the monastery was just dying away and they could see that in a few years none of the monks would be left and what
would happen to the monastery they'd be just you know it was kind of there'd been a thriving monastery
in their youth but now it was kind of fading away so the advent was a little concerned
about this of course and so it was quite perplexed and said i'm going to go visit this there's supposed
to be this very wise rabbi in the next valley over or something
and so the abbott went to the rabbi and said you know we have this
issue in our monastery and it's dying away no one's coming it's it seems like it's you know
it's coming to its end but you can you have any ideas of what we can do and what might revive it
and they had tea and talked about things and the rabbi said no not really
i don't know about monasteries and but then the as the as the abbot was
leaving to go back home the rabbi said oh by the way oh one of your monks back at your
monastery is that is going to be the messiah the next messiah or something
and so the abbot went back to the monastery and the monks that were there were kind of eager to find out what they learned they all wanted to know the
device they would what advice they were going to give in the abbot said well he had no advice for us he didn't have
anything to say but he did say the strange things as i was leaving as i was leaving he said
one of us is going to be the messiah and they said wow that's strange
but then in the next days and weeks the monks was like well you know who
could it be well it can't be father lawrence
he's always so grumpy however
he's always helping he's always at the right place when someone needs help he's all right there to help
could he be no no maybe well maybe but what about father
joseph brother joseph he's just so lazy
he's just like you know no one does less than him in the monastery but whenever he does something
he's always so kind and then he went through everyone that
like you know could it be that person could it be that person and as they had these thoughts and
recognize that each of them had something a little good going for them
they started treating each other with respect and care and reference in a way that they hadn't maybe hadn't done for
for a long time so that was nice but then one day
some young people from town came to have a picnic on the monastery grounds
and they felt something and they had little conversations with some of the monks and they felt
something special so they came back and they came back and more of them came
and then some of them joined the monastery became monks and after a few couple of years the place
was thriving again with young dedicated monastics
so um care what happens when we care for each other
we respect each other we revere each other what are the conditions we put in place
and it doesn't take a lot of thinking that there are very different those are very
different conditions than being mean being indifferent
but to be to care to love to be kind as if your care is important
as if you matter that what you do and maybe it doesn't have to be big
you don't become a desmond tutu but maybe it's that uh you cared about a
neighbor you cared about someone who has a flat tire and you pull over to help them
you're saying that i remember once in palo alto uh someone's car was stalled in either
intersection the woman's car was stalled and standing there wondering what to do and it seemed like dangerous so i got out of
my car i parked my car the side and i pushed it to the side seemed like a nice thing to do right now
or the right thing to do and i haven't thought about it in 30 years but
there's now so to care
who knows who we're meeting do you know the people you meet do you know who they are and what their
destiny is and do you know anybody really
who knows maybe they're like father lawrence maybe they're the messiah maybe something special there
in 2013 some people cared for a 13 year old girl
who was shot
two years later that thirteen-year-old girl received the nobel prize of peace the
peace prize
pakistan
who would have known that the care of caring for her would have such a big impact
in 2018 a 13 year old teenager started skipping school
a year later the forbes magazine listed her as one of the most
100 most powerful women in the world
and she ended up on the times
magazine person of the year and that was greta thornberg
who would have known
in 2020 a 17 year old teenager working at the mall the local mall
changed america by taking the video of george floyd
dying daniela fraser
and then before that there was a teenager or a girl who lived and went to
13 different schools before she graduated high school
and then went on to be a single parent cared for by friends and living on food
stamps what would happen to her
she is now currently the u.s secretary of interior
deb holland a laguna pueblo from the laguna pueblo
tribe
who knows who's out there who knows who we meet who knows who you are
some of these people are ordinary people but who knows what comes their way
so all these things are you know maybe inspiring also a little daunting when you mention
such great people who do such you know monumental things
but maybe care each of them each of them needed people who cared for them
and the people who care i think don't have to know what the impact of their care is
maybe care what's important about care is the caring
without much thought about long-term impacts just kids take care
to live a life of care
so how would you live if you lived as if your life mattered
well how would you live if you really thought that you could make a difference
and i think our lives do matter
probably many of you know it's kind of just stereotypic idea now that
you know in the holidays some people watch it's a wonderful life wonderful world is what it is
maybe we can all be george bailey the man who didn't think that
he'd done anything good in life and was going to jump off a bridge and commit suicide and
then the angel comes right and shows him what his life what life the town would have been like if he hadn't
lived at all and it was awful so here we are
we do matter each of us more important
so we ended up with kuan yin on the altar just kind of didn't have actually been up there that i know of
it's kind of nice to have her there especially for this talk and care compassion and kindness
there's a story about kuan yin that uh sometimes uh
there's there's kuan yin is said to have 11 heads sometimes a thousand arms
and the story is that um how she got those eleven heads and living arms
apparently she worked tirelessly to save people
you know to just apparently one day she had everything all tidied up
imagine that everyone was good
and then she woke up the next morning and sure enough people are suffering again it didn't take long for the suffering to
come back and uh she did it again but then the suffering
came and she saw the immense suffering of this world that seemingly she couldn't
keep up with and so i guess in english she would say she was
heartbroken but her head burst head broken
and at the 11 heads and the house and arms so because she can be even more
effective and more helpful than help the world and the thousand arms are there because
each arm has each hand as a different tool implement to help the world
so and she and she has all these heads to look everywhere and i like this story a little bit because
some of us are afraid of having our heart broken the issue if it's difficult to have your
heart broken maybe you haven't had it broken enough
maybe maybe there's the art of letting it break really break
maybe then you'll be kuan yin your heart will break into 11 hearts
or some people say that if your heart breaks into many pieces it just has more surface area
in order to feel and sense and be caring for this world
i don't think we should be so afraid of having our hearts broken i think that
if we can learn maybe through the practice we do the mindfulness practice to not resist it not be oppressed by it
not be afraid of it not be submerged by it and not give up because
of it there's something something about caring in spite of the broken heart
something about a sense of dignity and value and
presence that allows us the heart to break and something kind of
to emerge from that caring for the world caring for others sensitivity love kindness
maybe if your heart is broken enough what else is there but to be kind what's left if you do it thoroughly
so these thousand arms and somalia i think of them also as hands that reach
out and touch the whole world and it's remarkable that we live in a
world now that is you know it's kind of also a stereotype or a little cliche
that the world has gotten so small but i can't help but to keep thinking
that it's getting smaller and smaller and the way that what happens elsewhere in the world affects us and what a video affects the
world i mean there was someone apparently
less than two months ago two months ago who got sick with covet in south
africa was discovered to have if one person discovered to have this new variant
when did i care so much about what happened in a sick person in the other side of the world
but that one person from there maybe where were represented where somewhere it began
and spread out across the whole world and now the whole world is
pausing in a certain way from omicron we have this invisible force we don't
see it in our normal eyes the virus and it's the fact that it
spreads and connects all of us all over the world and what happens in south africa what happens elsewhere
has a huge impact on us can we just close our borders and just
care for ourselves as if we can that's enough
if we want to care for ourselves i think we should care for others
it isn't just mothers going to nursing homes having chaplains come that we can
experience the how it comes back to us but it's also
if we don't care for the world don't care for others
then what virus will come find us
i kind of love seeing people with masks on and i'm troubled by it of course
but my assumption is that when people wear masks
that they're caring for me and certainly when i'm wearing a mask
i'm caring full of you and the fact that there's liv in a room
full of people where there's the care is visible i think it's such a beautiful thing a
wonderful thing love made visible these masks
and as we care for the wonderful thing about cove it is wonderful can we say the wonderful around it
the wonderful thing about covet is that this simultaneous thing where
if we care for others we're simultaneously caring for ourselves it's kind of represented by the masks the
mask also we care for it's a way of caring for ourselves you're protecting yourself with the mask
and you're protecting others through the mask and so it kind of like this situation
where you get to have the benefits of both you both get to benefit yourself and
better better care for yourself care for others and so you might as well get credit for both
so don't just do it for your own sake and don't just do it for other people say do it for both you get a lot more
credit wherever with credit is stored i don't know where it is
in your heart i think i think that's where the credit is so you know it's a beautiful thing to
to develop to grow this heart to expand this heart sometimes by breaking it and
letting it grow it makes a difference
your care makes a difference makes a difference for you it makes different for the world
so perhaps just like the monastery if everyone
if we treat everyone as worthy of care worthy of respect or their reverence
everyone
it is a care that i think will return and benefit us as well
not least because it's good for our hearts it's good for our inner lives
to treat people that way to see people that way i think of it as a
myself i think of that as the natural way of being anything short of that
requires resistance requires contraction closing down pushing away
being selfish
so the year of care
i was thinking about this i was thinking that
some people have calculated that unless we do change something a million species of plants and animals
will be extinct within the next hundred years so what will die if we
don't care certainly care will die
and do you want to live in a world where there's no care
i'd rather live in a world that cares than anything else
and with our care some things will die and one of the things that will die is
our selfishness would that be so bad
i think it'll be liberating to do that
so 2022 may it be the year of care
and then by the end of next year you'll know whether it was a year of care
if you cared that you'll be the proof of it
may you benefit this world and in doing so yourself
thank you