hello everyone and welcome to our meditation time together
and i'm offering this week one exercise for each meditation
that goes along with the fourth foundation of mindfulness and
so today's the fifth one and the final one and this one i want to give a little bit
more introduction for if i'm walking in in the city and i notice my
shoes are dirty i might notice it and say oh when i get home
i'll clean them and that's it don't think about it again or i might notice my shoes are dirty and
immediately start uh ruminating about this i'm stuck on this idea and
and thinking of how everyone's judging me as i walk down the city streets because my dirty shoes and my value as human being
is dependent on being having clean shoes and i'm in trouble with these dirty shoes and my mind is
stuck on this idea of dirty shoes but then i go along and i see a window
of a shoe store and i see the clean shoes in there oh i should buy some of those shoes and that'd be good
i'll come back and buy some new fresh shoes and i'm walking down thinking about how i'm going to buy these new shoes and
then my mind is stuck on buying these new shoes and then i start ruminating about how
well i don't quite have enough money to buy those shoes they're quite expensive and then i'm ruminating about that and
i'm stuck on that idea and then i occurs to me that i'm a
buddhist and for dharma's sake you know i shouldn't be stuck on thinking about shoes and and caught in that web of
shoes and now i'm stuck on the idea that i need to be a buddhist in certain way but then i remember buddhism and i said oh
look at that change just in the course of a minute walking down the street
my mind has gone through all these changes and i was stuck and i was stuck and i was stuck but the commonality is that
they don't i move on to the next stuckness the next stuckness and some of them only last a few seconds some of them last for hours
uh maybe some for decades but there's kind of stuckness around these things
but in recognizing the change it's all changing all the time then there's a different kind of oh okay
it's just changing i don't have to take it that seriously and isn't it quite something how much my mind goes from one stuck thing to the next
and um and but now that i see it i can kind of flip it float above it or away
from it or not gets pulled into it sucked into it so strongly
so the last exercise of the buddha's teachings on mindfulness has a lot to do with seeing change
in such a way that we are liberated from being stuck and so the mind becomes unstuck
and now there's something profound about noticing change both the change in our
perceptions of what we perceive the sensations of our body and sounds
around us whatever it might be but also um the change in
what we get stuck on that you know the mind is kind of fleeting it stays stuck sometimes on one thing and
even if it's one thing that's the primary theme it jumps around inside that theme to be stuck on different
ideas and thoughts so to recognize change
is an antidote for that so for this uh meditation
my recommendation is that um you recognize change how things are
changing both in your experience and in your what you
what you put your mind on and if you find yourself stuck on something involved in distracted thought
remind yourself that things are changing all the time that you weren't stuck on this some time ago
and you will be you probably won't be stuck in a little while it might be a theme that reoccurs over
and over again but that doesn't mean that you're stuck every moment and to recognize that there's uh
change and um can begin loosening up
the ways we're attached and caught so change you might just say that word
to yourself periodically change so assuming a meditation posture
and whatever posture you're in can you
adjust it so that there's a little bit more energy in the posture
just uh maybe i just adjust it so that the the spine is a little bit straighter or
the chest is allowed to come out even if you're laying down in a bed you can sometimes
move it so your shoulder blades go down the the back a little bit and the chest maybe can comes up a little bit
and now so there's more space in the chest to breathe
and lower your gaze about 45 degrees to the floor or whatever 45 degrees is to straight
ahead and
relax your eyes your gaze
and then gently close your eyes if that's comfortable
and then taking a few long slow deep breaths and as we do so
we are attuning ourselves to experiences that are changing
the changing sensations of breathing changing sensations in the body with the
breathing breathing in deeply
and exhaling on the exhale relaxing on the exhale
taking a deep breath and relaxing
and then letting your breathing return to normal
continue relaxing as you exhale with a normal breath relaxing the muscles of the face
the shoulders
the belly and whenever you're able to relax that's also change
when you move your attention from the face the shoulders the belly that's change
and to make another change now let your attention center itself
in the breathing where you usually experience breathing
and allow yourself to receive to experience
the body breathing and as you do so
you're experiencing change the changing sensations of breathing
and if you get involved in your thoughts chances are it's a little bit of a
stuckness there stuck on some idea or theme or concern
but appreciate how even our thoughts are fickle and change
periodically you might just remind yourself there's change
ever-changing change
and to relax into the changing of the experience
not just to focus on breathing but to rest in the changing nature of
breathing the changing nature of everything
that's interrupted when we get stuck on something
and when you're stuck remind yourself of change
so
if you're stuck on something now in your thoughts that's just the current way that change
has ever come to it'll change again and again
appreciate change and relax
let go into the flow of changing nature
when we're not stuck there's just change
in the course of this meditation chances are there's been a lot of change
in your thoughts your concerns your focus your attention to the body
your breathing
in what way does recognizing change loosen
stuckness
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
may we through this practice learn to walk through the world
unstuck not fixated on anything
so we're able to be so we're ready to respond
to the circumstances we find ourselves in
so we're ready to respond with care kindness compassion
ready to respond with clarity honesty
ready to respond being self-aware of what's going on inside of us
being ready to respond really sensitive to the people we're with
and through being unstuck
may we live in such a way that we support
the welfare and happiness of many people
that maybe that's one of the great tasks of human life
to live for the welfare of happiness of many including oneself
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
which is another way of saying being unstuck
[Music]
so good morning and uh
so this is the final talk on the fourth foundation of mindfulness
and uh this is the area of mindfulness practice that we're studying being attentive to the ways
that we get stuck in the ways that we get unstuck and or to say it in more buddhist
language how we get attached where we get attached the nature of detachment and how we get unattached or free
liberated and and i've presented this as a kind of a
process of first we spend our time moving through the layers of attachment
we have the layers of stuckness and getting more and more subtle
but at some point when it's subtle enough when our preoccupation stuckness doesn't predominate
then meditation practice opens up to a native and natural feeling of well-being
that's here and which is the seven factors of awakening which
we don't be so concerned with exactly all seven but right now i just want to say a sense
of well-being tranquil happy equanimous
feeling a kind of being at ease deep deep way in this world and that is the foundation
for the last foundation at last exercise which sometimes is called the four noble truths so it's not
called that in this exercise and it's a little formula that appears
repeatedly hundreds of times in the teachings of the buddha and that is to
to know suffering to know the arising of suffering
to know the cessation of suffering and to know the way to the cessation of suffering
and and sometimes this is called the four noble truths as i'm but but that confuses it a
little bit because what the four noble truths have become down through the ages of wonderful teaching
is a little bit more complicated than the simplicity of seeing change
and in this fourth uh this fifth exercise is seeing rising and passing a phenomena
rising and ceasing of um of things and really kind of uh uh
because we're so at ease and quantumnous and peaceful then we're at a
have a readiness and ability to um kind of flow and go along with the
changing nature of the present moment the river of change that's happening here and
uh the changing sensations of breathing body emotions thoughts sounds
um they're all changing except for when we get stuck in the concepts of ideas and stories
related to it and that also has layers of subtlety so if we're
at the grosser level we're stuck in the stories at the most refined level we might be
stuck in very simple concepts ideas of what things are and the idea of breathing is not the
breathing itself and you can think about your breathing and have no connection to your breathing
and but to really feel and sense the breathing and not not so drum so strongly through the
filter of the concept the idea and then we're able to see the changing
nature of all the little sensations are coming and going and rising and passing and um and to really start resting or
taking in this radical way in which things are flowing changing
all the time is a kind of a massage on the remaining places in our mind in our hearts that
are stuck that are frozen that are tight and um and so
uh it's a little bit hard to keep that stuck keep it there and so there starts to be a
willingness and a relaxation into this place of ease and freedom
that comes with resting and change resting in how things are always moving and changing
and and become more and more sensitive to the subtlety of being stuck
and it can be even the idea that i am aware
or i'm here and that's the change that i'm watching is a very very very subtle kind of
innocent almost a stuckness that also begins to dissolve when you
really kind of rest in the ocean of change and just be with it and um
and the um and so at some point this experience of just seeing a rising and ceasing becomes
the predominant experience of meditation and mindfulness meditation and it doesn't really matter anymore
what you're experiencing like what it is it's just the fact that everything is arising and passing and and there's no
overlay of concepts on top of it and um and now there's
you know that even the subtlest kinds of stuckness are no longer operating at least for the time being while we're in
meditation and then at some point the ceasing the rising and ceasing
the ceasing happens more dramatically and there's a ceasing that really feels
like something has radically dramatically stopped something that's been in like the hum of
the refrigerator suddenly stops and um and it's like wow that i didn't realize was humming even
so and so something that we didn't even realize was there drops away
and falls away
evaporates collapses into itself or
just set free in some way and and then to recognize oh
being able to see change at this level that's the way to freedom and and in
this fourth foundation of mindfulness that's what it means at the last last you know
knowing knowing that this is the way to um to the cessation of suffering
is to stay in the current of change and now the language here is suffering
knowing suffering knowing the rising of it knowing the ceasing of it and knowing the
the way to the ceasing of it because as we get more and more into this field of change
then um the it's that stuckness the place where we still suffer that stands out in the
highlight and um and um it stands out above the flow
and so then we bring our attention to that to to be present and see that until we start seeing that it too breaks
up and is made up of rising and ceasing of things and so at some point in in
you know after meditation is quite deep um and there's a lot of like i said the seven factors awakening are established
there's a lot of well-being um that that
kind of the name of the game becomes um just tuning in to the subtlest forms of stress
of uh tension contraction all words for the subtlety of suffering
in deeper meditation so definitely buddhism is about
addressing suffering and we do it all along the way and
and because any place we're stuck has to be somehow resolved in order to drop into
change and so at the coarsest level you know we're caught up in the hindrances
and that might take years to work through some of the stuckness we have at a more refined level we're stuck on
self and identity issues that we're attached to and then in a more even subtle level
we're still caught up in comfort and reacting to pleasure and pain and
wanting or not wanting and in the world and the sensations we have
and so kind of working through that it's not an easy process you know but boy is it worthwhile
it's a fantastic thing to practice mindfulness and and and make go through this process
and end up in a process of radical change and and that's a change that's freeing it's
liberating all along the way throughout the four foundations of mindfulness throughout
the whole process of what happens in meditation the basic practice actually is always
the same it's just to be mindful attentive carefully attentively to
what's happening now and in doing so slowly learn how to free attention from any kind of
stuckness any kind of agendas any kind of attachment to self any kind of reactivity to
anything at all and um so it's first we start meditating mindfulness is not so so
uh clean but that's okay it's always the same practice just do
the best we can to be mindful of what's here and keep going doing it over and
over again doing it in daily life doing it in meditation develop the capacity to be aware to live in awareness
to live in awareness more and more and more and so as we go through our life
we're living in a field of awareness we're present and aware for what's happening in our minds and our hearts
and all around us and as we do that process the pro the practice is always the same being aware
being mindful and at some point especially if we do enough meditation
we drop into this world of change and the change that is liberating that's
freeing and um and so um
the um so that is uh
the exercise the the fourth foundation and hopefully that's uh
was clear enough there's maybe many other ways of understanding it or interpretations
but this is the one that that i liked like to present and uh
and um so if um
so that's enough thank you so announcement so next week i'm going on a small vacation with my wife up into
the mountains to go hiking and so happy that nikki mergaforie will come
and teach she's been here before for our morning 7am sitting here at imc and a wonderful
teacher here at imc and you'll be in good hands with nikki and i'll be back the following week
so thank you very much