so good day and
i certainly feel kind of full or happy to be here with
you and also feeling a little bit quiet so
i'll leave it at the welcome the
navigating between the skillful and the unskillful
the wholesome and the unwholesome is the path of practice
because navigating towards the wholesome and away from the unwholesome towards what's beneficial
and the wholesome is seen as that which is healthy that which is
nourishing and also uh one of the connotations of the word
crusolyze that which is clever clever not in the sense of i don't know
being tricky or something but wise and being able to differentiate between what is
unwholesome and what is wholesome
and in in doing meditation practice one of the central areas to
distinguish between this is uh with how
we are responding to the present moment and if we're
responding with mindfulness attention how we are attentive
is the attention wholesome or unwholesome is the attention
nourishing or does it feel healthy is it inspiring is the way that we're
paying attention is it do you feel the goodness of it as opposed to paying attention which
sometimes people use their attention and practice both for mindfulness and for concentration
in ways that if you really pay attention to it would not feel so
inspiring or so beneficial they're straining and pushing and and a
sense of heavy duty and and ideas of i have to do it right i'm not good enough for this and this is
so hard a feeling of discouragement there might be some complacency
lackadaisical nature kind of yes we're kind of paying attention but we're really
not that interested and and we're here kind of on road so
there's all kinds of ways which the attention if we pay attention to how we're attentive
it doesn't really inspire anything but there's ways of doing it that does
inspire but inspire not in an excited way
but in a in a way that arouses interest arouses
engagement that is peaceful that feels settling that feels
beneficial it feels like a a ambrosia of sweetness
that settle us or it's so as we do this meditation today
you might see if you can distinguish between the kind of attention that you're using
the kind of engagement and mindfulness that maybe carries with it some unhelpful
qualities and some that carry and then if you can see if you can
explore how to bring some helpful qualities of attention
and one of that is a simplicity and a matter of factness just just this engagement in a clear
wholehearted way but without any strain or pushing something that is opening to experience
or resting an experience or or lovingly receiving the experience
for example the breathing so to
enter into a wholesome or skillful posture
which is always very personal the posture that is beneficial
take some time and adjusting the small details of posture
that gets things kind of lined up
and then to close your eyes
and this is moving towards the wholesome
to what's beneficial begins right away can begin right away
so maybe you could find a nourishing or nurturing attention
maybe the attention can be free of
greed or aversion
maybe the attention ever so slightly qualities of generosity giving our
attention
qualities of care love or kindness
maybe valuing appreciating
attention itself and that we're attending
to our experience
and with this kind of attention to take a few long slow deep breaths
settling in as you exhale relaxing the body
as you exhale deeply
give in to your weight settling into your seat
the place that's holding you up
and letting your breathing return to normal
and then a wholesome attention to the breathing
or noticing any unwholesomeness any thing that's not inspiring about
the effort the way that you're attending now to your experience
and orient yourself quietly to a quiet attitude
that's maybe free of greed or aversion
simplicity
and as you exhale to relax and soften the muscles of the
face
relax and soften the shoulders
relax and soften the belly
and this dedic this dedication to the wholesome means that even the effort to
see the wholesome and avoid the old wholesome
is done wholesomely not anxiously
not with the idea that you have to do it right there's a wrong way that you're good or you're bad
just a simple appreciation and recognition
that if you're doing it in an unwholesome way there is a better way
rather than there's a right way there is a nurturing way
so we're not condemning anything or condemning ourselves
just they're here to attend
wisely carefully lovingly
to each in breath and each out breath
being a friend to the in-breath and a friend to the out
breath
here attending to the breathing
in the wholesome way that you would attend to someone you cared for a lot
if you're lost in thought is your thinking wholesome or unwholesome
and even if the thinking is wholesome maybe it's not nourishing supportive
for the wholesome presence of mind in the present moment
so let go of your thinking
and enter into the world of attention awareness
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
it's a time to turn our attention outward into the world that we will maybe
encounter today of other people activities
and hereto the buddhist orientation is to avoid being in the world
unskillfully unwholesomely
but to orient ourselves to what is wholesome and beneficial inspiring and nourishing
and so to orient ourselves to the world in a way that doesn't involve grim duty and obligation
but rather has a kind regard for others
a care for others compassion love friendliness
that is not forced and not in a sense required
but which is inspiring
and is expressed in personal ways so that we know that is it is beneficial
for ourselves nourishing and self-inspiring
and that way how we relate to the world and to ourselves becomes part of the path
of liberation and freedom because it brings these good qualities
for to the forefront in our lives
and so to turn the attention outward now to the world into the people and in your own way
gazing gazing upon the world kindly in your own way
having thoughts of well-wishing good will for others
in a way that you feel good about having it like because it's your own way
to the extent and interest that you have
and with that in mind maybe these words can express
your good will represent them may
all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings be free
and may each of us in our own way that's nourishing and wholesome for us and for the world
contribute to the welfare and happiness of all beings
[Music]
okay
so i think it works now okay so
yeah there's only three buttons i have to push but sometimes that's too many
for me
okay so so the um
in talking about wholesome and unwholesomeness this week that
today i'm going to talk about the unwholesome and i think that understanding what
the buddha's teachings are on this topic or how we saw this topic that
it helps us to study and investigate how it is for us personally and um
uh so it gives us kind of ideas or orientation to really see what
the impact is of some of the attitudes we have some other of our behavior some of the ways
we speak so even some of the ways we think because some of that maybe occasionally
can be unwholesome or uninspiring or
unskillful or unbeneficial and and so
um so to look at this topic of the unwholesome in particular three what's called the
roots of the unwholesome kind of the source for all things which are unwholesome so first the unwholesome
is um is described as um involving suffering
in this very life involving stress in this very life and the word
suffering sometimes people take it to be only the big things in life are suffering but the word dukkha can be anything
deranged from even mild forms of
um um of uh stress or of um
not not just discomfort because that's too broad but um this mild forms of distress smile
forms of of you know the mild forms of suffering
and so the unwholesome whatever is unwholesome always involves some degree of dukkha
buddha goes on it says it involves vexation despair and fever so those are strong
words so we have to understand there also that there can be mild versions of it and
but it always involves some kind of way in which it uh it it harms ourselves
that there's a kind of self-harm involved so uh
and it involves discomfort so unwholesome always involves dukkha
harm and discomfort and and so
so when we act with hostility when we act in a mean way to people when we
are consumed with meanness or criticalness of ourselves when we are greedy
it's not a moralistic teaching like shouldn't do those things because that's the immoral thing to do
and with some abstract morality coming from outside but rather the pragmatic and
experiential orientation of the buddha is always how does it feel how am i experiencing
myself what's the impact of this on myself here and so
rather than looking into the rule books the moral rule books to find out you know is it okay to lie is it okay to steal is
it okay to um to you know um
gossip negatively about my friends uh what we can do is uh in practice and
this is why mindfulness is so amazingly useful when you develop strong capacity of self-reflection self-awareness
you don't go to the rule books but you go to your own heart you go to yourself
and you see what's the impact on this on this behavior this attitude this way
of speaking and it's possible with heightened sensitivity to feel the way that it causes suffering
for oneself pain for oneself discomfort for oneself it's not nourishing it's not inspiring
in fact to really be mindful and see some of the impact the way we are some people actually get
distance disinspired they get dismayed and discouraged and they feel
the way some of this stuff even though some of the ways of acting on wholesome lies are energizing
and people feel that the pleasure of being alive when they're hateful and
angry at other people there is a way in which uh it really is draining
some essential vitality and goodness within us some wholeness some being really
connected to ourselves because the kind of anger and many times this unhealthy behavior
is um the focus is outwardly directed um in such a way that we are out of
touch with what's behind that outward movement and that's a true for ourselves as well if we're really
mean or critical of ourselves then there's a way in which we treat ourselves as an
object and we don't see what's behind it we don't see the the way that we're aware we don't see
the impact it has on closing us down or contracting or the discomfort of it
so so this reference point of the impact that our attitudes
thoughts speech behavior has and and really taking that in in a deep way
i've known people who've only only experienced the impact of their behavior
what they've done years later where they finally kind of woke up and they were just shocked like it sometimes
became like lightning like oh my my wow i can't believe it
and i really hurt someone and and so it's better later than
uh than never but even better is to feel it right away and so for the
buddha the unwholesome is um in modern english we talk about
instant karma there's this instant way in which simultaneously acting on it we can feel
how it's debilitating or draining or it limits us or closes us off and compartmentalizes ourselves so
we're not really whole and full anymore and now this is uh so
uh vexation despair and a fever even when it's really strong
so we can certainly look at all this and become aware of it so that we can
then not do it and think that's good or that's fine in itself
but we don't want to it's important not to underestimate the value of this for the buddha who has a very pragmatic
orientation towards the dharma towards his teaching very functional very experiential and
um and immediate and it wasn't uh metaphysics there wasn't uh abstractions
and there wasn't some kind of divine authority beyond or everything everything unfolds here
in our experience um this is where we discover peace this is
where we discover how we're not at peace and so the buddha talked about how is it
you can know the dharma
really for yourself and the way he talked about it is this dharma that he's teaching or pointing to
is visible here and now it's immediate it has to do with right now
it invites you it invites itself to be seen by you
by oneself so it's kind of like come here can you look at this there's a kind of pull
of attention towards this if you're really attentive and it's onward leading
it has consequence that's beneficial that leads us more and more goodness and it's
personally realized by the wise so again it's very personal pragmatic
pragmatism so that's the dharma and how how is it that way when you know
there is no greed no hatred and no delusion
within you and when you know oh when you know there is greed hatred
and illusion first you have to know it's there and then you know
that it's no there's no greed no hatred and no delusion within you
to see that movement to go from the whole unwholesome to the wholesome
the absence of the unwholesome and then the presence of the wholesome
that then you know that the dharma is visible here and now immediate
inviting inspection writing to be seen um onward leading and personally
realized by the wise and so um and so this emphasis on the
on greed hate and delusion here is because the buddha in the buddha's eyes in the buddhist
experience all things which are unwholesome
and maybe it's almost the definition of unwholesome all the things that are unwholesome are in one way or the other rooted in
greed hatred and delusion and again it could be very mild forms of greed
craving compulsion compulsive desire or hatred or it can be you know can be
very mild or can be very strong but the mild forms of
unwholesome maybe have mild forms of greed hate and delusion but this kind of this is a common denominator for
all things which are unwholesome and so that's why to really get down and see
underneath our behavior and see the greed hate and delusion and let go of it have come to an end of
it that is how we see this pragmatic teachings of the buddha
orientation of the buddha this experiential approach that he has which is very
personal because this is only something that we can know for ourselves in the way that we experience and know
it for ourselves and and so
so the emphasis today is on this uh very personally experiential
reference point for the dharma for the buddhist teachings for the path
of liberation and for if you use modern english
terminology for ethics for morality that that morality springs out of
it can spring out of a very deep connectivity connection to oneself
and um and uh and we know for ourselves and that is kind of inspiring to have
our ethics our morality how we live in the world really well up from a deep understanding within that is kind of a
wellspring a kind of a source of goodness that
carries us along in that goodness as opposed to carrying us along in um in you know a sense of grim duty
or or uh fear of fear of some retribution or something
so um the unwholesome so it might happen that in the next 24
hours for a few of you that you might have some
thought or speech act or behavior that helps that you recognize
as being unwholesome and if you do then take that opportunity
to turn the attention back on yourself and really see what um how it's impacting you
yourself and see if you can see the way that it has a negative impact and maybe
an impact you don't really want to have it's not very inspiring and and the stronger your bout of
unwholesome is uh the better it is for this exercise don't go
invent unwholesomeness for the exercise but the stronger your you're about of somehow doing something
unwholesome expressions of greed hatred and delusion or something then i think the more clarity you can
have in this exercise of really seeing the impact it has on you
and then we'll continue with this tomorrow thank you