so good day to everyone
here we are together and from all over and
uh gathering ourselves for this period of meditation
and this topic they one of the subjects is practicing with
mental activity which has been my most common translation for sankara
sometimes translates mental formations
and
so say this about it is that these mental activities that we have as we practice as we settle in
meditation as we begin to let go of attachments and clinging
the direction the mind is going is to becoming beautiful to have a beautiful mind and that
the feeling that not just a feeling the experience or the quality
of physical calmness that happens when the body relaxes and the quality of mental relaxation
tranquility that comes as the mental activities calm down it's referred to in the
buddhist tradition as beautiful as beautiful qualities of mind
and that many of these uh factors of mine that start coming into play
uh that of faith and and engagement with the practice
attention wisdom mindfulness samadhi all these things
they're they're considered beautiful qualities of the mind
and so we are we one of the orientations for
meditation one of the things to kind of
kind of be considering is how do you practice how do you do the activity of meditation
so it itself has some quality of beauty or maybe another word is harmony
i love the hopi indian the indigenous people of new mexico
the i love their expression of walking in beauty
so what would it mean to engage the mind in beauty
and sometimes there's such a strong orientation towards avoiding which what is not beautiful
what's difficult or painful or there can be a lot of criticism in the mind
self-criticism and a lot of judgments that whatever the mind is doing wandering often thought is
somehow wrong or worse and maybe so but
but uh what we do how we show up to be mindful to be present
to be engaged with the breathing how would you do it if you did it in a beautiful way or in a
harmonious way because that's the direction that this
practice is going and especially with this calming of mental formations calming of the mental
activities we're feeling our way into a place of harmony or beauty
of peace of clarity of lightness of uh sometimes the ancient tradition
talks about a kind of a clean mind a cleansed mind
so for this sitting today maybe you can um
you can um orient yourself a little bit with um
what would it be like to sit here in beauty not because you're looking for it it
might be there it might be here but also because you engage in the practice that way
that the very way in which you are present the way very way in which you are
mindful is in harmony or is in beauty what would
that look like and i know it might be a stretch or it might be you might not have an easy reference for
this but i would suggest that you imagine you do
imagine yourself in this way and if
so to assume a meditation posture and even here as we get into as we take
the posture how would you do it
as if the activity of assuming your posture meditation posture was itself a movement
in beauty maybe in gracefulness
and maybe gracefully kind of rocking forward and back maybe slowly
maybe not sideways and then slowing down and finding
a balanced posture most balanced for what's available to
you with all the different challenges you might have and so your your posture itself
begins to feel like a small stepping stone to beauty
to harmony
and then
softly peacefully closing your eyes
and then what would it be like if you approached your breathing with
trust with care
with relaxation with some quality or feeling of
approaching your breathing
in a harmonious way or in a beautiful way
what would your attention what would attending to your breathing
be if you were attending in a beautiful harmonious way
and perhaps it could be that you invite your body
to gently breathe more fully
expanding the chest expanding the belly as you breathe in
maybe three quarters full so you're not straining
and perhaps allowing for a longer
peaceful exhale as far as it's useful to exhale
and then to as you exhale
to relax the body to calm the bodily activity of tension
holding contraction in the body releasing it
and letting your breathing return to
normal and then as you exhale
to also relax and soften the thinking mind
if the if you can recognize any tension or holding contraction
or hardness agitation or forcefulness
associated with breathing
as you exhale relax the mind
and if you can't relax it that's okay
perhaps you can recognize that awareness attention to the tense
mind is larger it's distinct and different
than the mind itself the activity and then hold the tense
mind in the beauty of open awareness
and then entering into the body breathing breathing naturally and easily
with a very light touch not trying too much
seeing if you can attend to breathing in a way that feels harmonious even
beautiful with its care its tenderness its openness
its willingness
perhaps with its feeling of respect for breathing
a reverence
for being here
and perhaps there's something in the breathing itself
which feels harmonious or beautiful pleasant
and to sit here
present for your breathing while attuned to
that which is harmonious or beautiful here and now no matter how small it
might be
if possible relaxing the mental activity of anxiety
mental activity of
discouragement or resentment
letting those settle and recede to the background
and in the foreground as you're sitting here
sitting meditating in beauty
some of them which might be whatever feeling of pleasure
well-being joy or happiness
that might be here right now breathing with it breathing through it
as you breathe is there any little place inside of
tranquility calmness peacefulness
a calmness of body a calmness of mind
breathe with that breathe through it
gently allowing that calmness tranquility to spread and grow
so that its influence perhaps a beautiful influence
can begin to move through you breathing in and
breathing out
so
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
looking inside of yourself to see if there's any
shift inside in the course this meditation
are you a little more settled if not more settled are you more
aware a heightened awareness of how you are
both the subtleness and the heightened awareness can both be seen as something beautiful
or you're more open more peaceful more
more sense of well-being have you learned something about your
own capacity to attend beautifully harmoniously
in whatever sense you have of an inner beauty or harmony or well-being
bring to mind some people that you know and imagine that they too have the same
capacity they have the potential for this
and that more than worldly success
that to experience this inner harmony this inner peace or beauty
is one of the great potentials they have
a potential which is not dependent so much on what happens in the world
and perhaps you can very gently lovingly harmoniously
have the wish that in fact they could feel this inner
well-being and harmony
that they might know their beauty
and beyond the people you know even the people you don't know and the
people who are a challenge for you
how wonderful would be if they could stay closely attuned aligned
with their own inner harmony and beauty their own potential for an inner
well-being that is so ethical in nature because it doesn't depend on
getting anything or making anything happen in the world
may it be that all beings
touch into their capacity for happiness may all beings
experience safety within
peacefulness within
a full inner freedom the heart set free at ease
this beautiful heart that we all share may all beings
be happy
you