hello and greetings dear sangha it's lovely to be with you
in this moment in time and to practice together even though we're separated in space
various time zones different places in this world and yet to feel
the generosity of each other's presence supporting supporting each other supporting
ourselves in this practice so
so we've been exploring or inviting our minds swimming
in this beautiful practice in this liberative practice of of generosity the
past couple of days and today we continue this exploration
and today we'll be opening up to the dimensions of joy
dimensions of joy in generosity delight gladness
which buddha talks talks about and i trust and know that each of us have
experienced so we'll open to exploring joy and delight
in our meditation and then i'll speak more about it in the dormant so
so with that let us get started let us land ourselves
in our seat in our cushion wherever we are in the world
in this moment in time feeling our presence
arriving landing
an opening opening her mind opening her heart
the sensations of this body first to get embodied to land to arrive
on this earth
inviting our bodies
to relax to soften
to give their weight to the earth
our heart can be uplifted while our body is connected and deeply rooted
our heart uplifted as if to the heavens
our spine the sense of integrity lifted up
and our muscles relaxed soft
both holding in tension with the uprightness of the spine the
uplift let's say the uplift of the spine the
heart
uplift and the rootedness groundedness of the body
as if we have wings our hearts have wings this morning this
afternoon evening our hearts have wings
and our body has roots well rooted
connected
and our breath connects the two our aspiration
aspires inspires us
and helps us feel connected rooted
each cell of the body
each breath received each breath received
in its entirety the beginning of the in-breath middle end of the in-breath
the out-breath beginning middle and end of the out-breath
and as if we were tuning [Music]
or allowing it to be tuned turning our antenna
to pick up waves that are already here
tuning into receiving the gifts of being here
sitting in this body with as much comfort as possible there might be pain present but
there is enough health and cognition the gift and we are here
practicing together receiving sharing dharma
can we tune into the good fortune just joy
the delight of yes i am here practicing
with sangha in this moment on youtube
wow how wild is that
how lovely how delightful hundreds of people around the world
i am one part of the sangha
feeling the interconnection the hearts of so many beings right now
their smiles their presence their wholeheartedness
inspiring inspiring yours with every breath with every aspiration
tuning into the gift receiving the gift graciously
the joy of being here practicing breathing
in this container container as if we're sitting
in this interconnected joyous container
receiving each breath the entirety of each breath
one at a time
and know that joy
delight can transform after a while into peace peacefulness
it's the other side of the coin of joy
so perhaps that becomes more present
and notice if and when
you wake up and realize that the mind is thinking
which does happen will happen whether with the release with the
letting go of the thinking
the story whether with the release
there can be a recognition of joy ah ease yes letting go of this oh yes
relinquishing with a tinge of delight
gladness yes for the benefit of myself and others
i return to the body and the breath the peace and ease the joy of being here
notice if with every letting go every link
relinquishment generously
releasing every thought or story there can be a delight
oh yes thank you yes lovely
and how that might transform your practice
as if as if you're putting every thought as you release it
as if you're putting it on the altar here dear buddha hold it with me
for me
here sense of generosity and giving away not
needed right now
here released
released joyfully released
offering the release putting the release on the altar
as the gift
the letting go the release relinquishment of each
thread of thought the release as the gift as our offering
taking delight in each of these offerings
every time you release your relinquish thinking entanglement
notice the joy the lightness the ease that comes from their release
their release offered as if you're putting
a flower on the altar as a gift here offering your release
you're letting go as a gift
of your practice
the hard feeling more joyous and lighter with each
gift of letting go
the last moments of our practice
offering our practice the gift of our practice with generosity
a gift of service a gift of service to support ourselves
support all beings everywhere in ways we can't
fathom may our practice may or letting go may our generosity be of service
to ourselves to others
may we all wake up together may we all be free
from suffering
may we all cultivate loving and being loved
[Music]
thank you for the gift of your practice
greetings greetings sangha lovely to practice with you
and in this practice today we tuned into the invitation was to tune
into the joy the delight of of
release letting go which is one movement of generosity
and in as an inner dimension how generosity as an outer dimension of giving
supports the inner dimension of practice is to consider every time we let go of
entanglement thinking or perhaps a
yeah an entanglement the times when it's useful to let go there are times that it's
helpful to to be aware and be present with it and there are times that it's it's just skillful to let go
to to consider that letting go that relinquishment the the ease the joy
the delight of that instead of oh you were thinking you were entangled instead of the judgment really tuning into the
delight the the beauty the grace of of of of this letting go and considering this
letting go as a gift as a gift of our practice as a gift of generosity
that we put on the altar of humanity of of the buddha of ourselves of this
practice so in that way making a gift out of every moment of
release in our practice making a gift out of that so really bringing the sense of
generosity into our practice in every moment
so so speaking of
the joy of generosity the idea is
is not of course you know this already it's not to be generous or let go from a moralistic
stance of shooting but but
to gladden and inspire the heart as as a practice as an inner practice
um and the buddha i love something that buddha
said and really impacted me actually early on in my practice when i saw this
from angutta nikaya 3 6 37
and the buddha says in this world there are three things of value for one
who gives what are these things before giving
the mind of the giver is happy while giving the mind of the giver is
made peaceful after having given the mind of the giver is uplifted
so happy before so when we're considering giving a gift of generosity
our mind is happy and you know this when you're thinking about how delighted someone will be
when they receive the gift that you're thoughtfully preparing perhaps or
and while you're giving it um the delight that it gives you to be to
be doing something for the benefit of someone else and this this this release this this act of service giving can
bring up joy and peacefulness as the buddha says and then after having given the mind of
the giver is uplifted and this can happen for a long long time
in fact i appreciate receiving a couple of stories from some of you in
email about stories of of generosity acts of kindness that
still uplift your heart and and um
for example for me one story one brief story i wanna share
is um is um i love persimmons i love persimmons
the fruit of the fall and in california and other places in the world
iran where i was raised the persimmons it's endemic to that area
and japan etc so i love persimmons i grew up with them they make me happy and
um the best persimmon i've ever tasted
is the one i never ate and the one i gave away it still makes me happy to this day
um i was at an airport about to board a plane and i have so
many dietary restrictions so i have to really pack my food and i had got two
persimmons from the farmer's market and i was eating one of them when i was waiting um
to board the plane and and the lady came up and asked me oh where did you buy it in the um
uh airport and i said oh i got this from the farmer's market and she looked a little disappointed and
were and went and sat and i thought wait you know i have to i have i'm eating one this one i have another apple i can i
can give this away so i went and gave it to her and said please have it it's already washed it's from the farmer's
market it's organic enjoy and just are you sure no please yes so
that was that and i was happy and she was happy and then later on the plane she was sitting a few rows behind me
and uh when i got up at some point she uh said you know
this is of course long before corbin she said you know um i grew up in japan and in
our yard and uh there was a um
a persimmon tree from my childhood and i live on the east coast where there are
no persimmons and um and the way she was sharing how precious
how important it was for her it's that persimmon to connect her with her with her
um parents grandparents it moved me so much that to this day there's this
uplift there is this delight there is this joy of the persimmon i never ate
i've eaten so many i forget their their taste but that one still tastes delicious with joy and uplift knowing
how it it uh supported this person so and who knows these acts of generosity
that that we give we really don't know the impact they have um and this is just
a tiny little story and i trust i'm sure every single one of us we have so many
stories that uplift our hearts our minds when we think of them uh and and inspire us to to to be
generous as a practice as an inner practice so a couple of things i wanted to bring
in as i promised not that we need any scientific research
or studies to support this important inner practice that we know is happy making and and as we discussed yesterday
is is supportive of release nibana awakenings the same movement of the
heart as we discussed yesterday so it turns out that um
a couple so couple of studies one in 2008 was done and was repeated actually
by others in 2017 the 2008 was a study by harvard business
school professor michael norton and colleagues and the 2017 similar one was
by park ital which also brought in fmri so they
found that giving money to someone else uh lifted participants the people who
participated in the study it lifted their their level of happiness
more than spending the money on themselves even though even though before um the study
the participants had predicted that spending the money on themselves would make them happier
but actually spending it on others made them happier when they actually went through the study so that also not only
tells us that generosity makes us happier but also that sometimes
we're not a good estimator we cannot exactly predict what
will make us happy and trust that generosity will make us happy and a
similar study by sonia leo bomsky
at university of california riverside saw similar results when she asked people to perform five acts of kindness
each week for six weeks the level of happiness went up there's also a study of what's called
study was 2006 by jorge mull and colleagues that
there is [Music] areas that are associated with pleasure
uh and social connection and trust and what's called creating a warm glow effect um
actually the warm glow effect and what's called the helipers high
which is associated with release of endorphins producing positive feelings
uh happen when we are generous so the buddha was definitely onto something he was a neuroscientist
in his own way he had studied the mind so clearly knowing that
giving generosity brings brings happiness lights up the heart the mind and
of course scientists with their fmri's and all of that their their
studies they're confirming the same yes it does make us happy generosity makes us happy
and another thing i wanted to bring in is also a couple more things one is studies
about what's called targeted generosity um so
being generous in general is wonderful and specifically there are some studies
about when you know the person you are giving to you the person you are
supporting uh directly that targeted generosity
um it also has some other aspects it increases the feeling of social
connection uh and and heaven knows these days
in covet times we all need we can all use increased sense of social connection
to feel socially connected to one another so targeted generosity when you know the
giver directly support it helping someone increases the sense of social connection
and also it turns out it potentially has some health benefits reducing fear anxiety
and the amygdala activation so i thought that was interesting about targeted generosity specifically
and one of you had asked about the relationship between
gratefulness gratitude and generosity in email that i received and yes
absolutely of course and we know this first actually let's tune into our own heart before i
talk about the research study we know when we feel more grateful when we have gratitude
um we feel the abundance of our heart we feel so abundant we don't feel
miserly we feel we have so many resources we're grateful we're grateful for life for our bodies for our clothes
for our roof over our head for food for all the good we turn to the good we see
the abundance of our of our life and our heart instead of what's lacking and that
sense of gratitude not only makes us happier and heaven knows there's so many studies on gratitude making you happier
and and and supporting well-being
and liberation too of course and also that that that abundant heart
becomes more generous of course and the last thing i'll say is studies by
christina carnes uh fmri studies where he where she
suggested that participants engage in writing a gratitude journal for three
weeks and then in the fmri machine study there are the activities
of their brains and they derived there was more
delight more joy more pleasure from giving
when people had engaged in gratitude so as she puts it you can proactively
choose to retrain your brain so it gets more pleasure out of giving
increasing neurotransm transmitters so and the way you proactively choose to
retrain your brain so it gets more pleasure out of giving is through the practice of gratitude so these are
absolutely connected so i'd like to invite us
if you wish to for today if you'd like to um so yesterday the
invitation was to look for an opportunity to be generous in some way
your choice of course and today um but looking for an opportunity to be
generous and also observing before during and after what is the state of
your mind noticing what the buddha talks this delight this joy of generosity before
the act of generosity during generosity and after again it could be
um your resources it could be your time it could be your affection your smile
calling a friend anything but notice notice what happens in your
heart and mind and we will continue tomorrow thank you for the generosity of your practice and
your presence may you be well and free see you tomorrow or feel you tomorrow