so good morning everyone and maybe we'll use this as a sound check
that uh see if uh you can hear me and also if uh
it's a relatively buzz free compared to what it has been and then we'll start in a minute or so
great so wonder oh wonderful thank you
and um
so
so starting uh this morning's meditation with an image
and the image is that of maybe uh taking a
flat stone kind of stone that you would maybe skip along the top of the surface of water
and you just kind of drop that stone uh into
a pond into a lake and the paw and the stone just kind
of falls down into the depths of this of the pond
to the depths of the lake and settles in the bottom and rests there quietly
so that image for meditation practice
that we are settling ourselves
and placing our attention within in a certain way and letting it just settle
drop and come to rest settle down and
there's a way in which even if the attention might is focused on sounds the world around us for
meditation some people do that there is a way in which the quality of attention
the source of attention um becomes intimate
we kind of drop within a certain way to a place to a reservoir to a lake where
attention can rest in a vast kind of spacious
space like a like a beautiful open lake when i was a
small child at 10 or 11 12 i i spent a lot of time
at the seashore swimming and i would love to dive deep deep wasn't that deep maybe five six feet seven feet deep into
the water and to the bottom and turn around and look up and it was so peaceful and i would see
the waves kind of going around up above me but where i was it was so peaceful and calm
so to to find ourselves inward in a certain way
in that peaceful calm place where awareness can be open to our experience
and so
to assume a meditation posture
and you know any posture will do that supports you to be alert
sitting upright has some advantages and in terms of this image maybe it's a
little bit easier to imagine this the stone of awareness just dropping
to some deep place inside
when you're sitting and then maybe you can let your gaze
relax and focus downwards at about 45 degrees maybe the eyelids become kind of half
closed and not really looking at anything in particular
letting the eyes rest in their sockets if it helps them relax you can even
imagine that your eyes are gently looking backwards or downwards
into your body and if it's nice for you you can also
close your eyes
and it's a ancient
technique for getting settled is to take long slow deep breaths at the
beginning but deep breaths that are long breaths that
are relaxed easy gentle
just far enough that there's no strain or we don't get winded or
and as you take the deep breaths in to relax your torso your so your belly
expands out your chest expands outwards
there's even the back rib cage you can maybe feel them expand as you breathe in
and then as you exhale also a longish exhale
relax the easy about it but maybe longer than you normally would
exhale but not to the point of it being a strain
just as long as it's comfortable deep in breath deep out breath
at the beginning of a sitting it's sometimes nice also with the long deep breaths
to take a few moments to pause at the end of the out breath
however long these moments are comfortable for you easy for you
without a strain without getting agitated but to pause
in that quiet in the way the body becomes still
and as the body becomes still and quiet perhaps you can allow your thinking bind
to also become quieter and stiller
attuning yourself to the physical
stillness
like you're listening to a musical note someone is playing and you tune your guitar to that note
tune your voice to that note so you tune your mind
to the quiet and stillness that's within
then letting your breathing return to normal
on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
on the exhale softening relaxing the shoulders
on the exhale softening the belly
and then see if you can find within a still quiet place it's any place in
your body that you associate with
stillness quiet peacefulness or calm
whether or not you feel it now is there a place inside you associate
with those states
and then in a moment i'll ask you to take a deep in in-breath and on the long exhale
imagine you're dropping a stone into a lake and stone settles to the bottom the same
way let your mind become quiet and settled
dropping it close to this place of quiet within resting in the inner stillness
so taking a deep breath exhaling and dropping yourself into your
body to the place of quiet and stillness calm
and letting your breath return to normal
relaxing on the exhale
relaxing the thinking mind and relax into the inner quiet
of breathing in and out softly gently
then gently continue with your breathing perhaps if it's easy breathing
together with the inner quiet or stillness or peacefulness
whenever you are exhaling letting go of your thoughts
there's nothing you need to think about except staying close
to the quiet stillness of breathing mindfully
in your body
you
every time you exhale see if you can let go of your thoughts
and let your attention drop relax into
a place of quiet stillness within like a rock dropping into a lake
uh
relaxing your thinking mind on the exhale
and noticing has there been any shift
in your mind state from the beginning of the meditation to the end
the quality of your mind or your mood mental mood
or your mental attitude is anything shifted
and if it has
is there a new perspective that provides it is beneficial for you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to turn your thoughts your concerns your vision
out into the world around you
and is there some way that you can stay close to a quiet still place within
or whatever way that you benefited from the meditation not to lose that
but to become aware be reminded
of the tremendous suffering in our world
the struggles of covid and so many hospitals around the world
so many bedsides
challenges of fires and
floods hurricanes heat
war earthquakes
we live in a world where these are parts of our world
and from our meditation can we gaze upon it kindly
can we gaze upon it with eyes that are supportive and inclined to help and to care
without becoming anxious without becoming despondent
but from our meditation to just say relaxed and simple
kind of ease and simplicity of looking upon the suffering of the world
and then wishing that we as individuals and as a
community and as a world
can live for the welfare and happiness of the world can we contribute to it
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
so on this monday
start a new series of new theme for the week and the theme will be the third
foundation of mindfulness so the classic teachings on mindfulness is taught by
the buddha comes from a discourse called the four foundations of mindfulness
and and therefore domains areas of our life where within with which we develop our
mindfulness our awareness so it becomes strong and clear lucid
relaxed and these four are the body
the feeling tones of our experience pleasant unpleasant neutral the state of minds that we have
and the dhammas the the uh mental operations activities
with which we either get pulled into the world of suffering
or get pulled out of it into the world of freedom and
the um so this week we'll talk about the third foundation
in july the theme for one week was um the the
first foundation and talked about some other teachings there and it was in june i think and then in
july at the the topic was uh there was a week where i did the feeling tones
and then i wa in august i talked about for one week each the greed hatred and
delusion and their opposites and that was actually meant to be a preparation for talking about the third
foundation and um and so with um
and now i'm following up on the third foundation and so i feel a little bit sorry that maybe they're not
these these series and the four foundations of mindfulness are not uh right after each other so that they
make sense to build but a good number of you are familiar with your four foundations so maybe you can
just pick up here on the third foundation i like to think of these
four foundations as kind of providing a kind of like a path uh i just really
like the metaphor of depth so i apologize for those of you who don't like this kind of metaphor going in going deep
but another way metaphors out of intimacy that
with the first foundation uh we can be very intimate with our body but the focus is on the body
and uh the coarser experience and sometimes some of the exercises actually to be aware of the body in activity as
we're walking laying down and sitting eating just be aware of the body
and some of the exercises are involve reflections considering the body
developing a new relationship with the body that's helpful and um but so it's a little bit uh
and it you know provisionally will say a little bit coarser attention more obvious more
you know something solid you can maybe connect to as we connect to the body and get
intimate to us intimate to it then we start becoming aware of the subjective
experience of pleasant and unpleasant that comes along with being grounded in the body
and it's subjective so it's a little bit deeper than the body it has to do with the interface between
a lot of our inner mental life and the sensations that we experience and that
interface we can experience it as either things as pleasant or unpleasant
and enjoyable not enjoyable comfortable not comfortable and now we're getting something closer
something that in some ways is more meaningful and more impactful for us because as to it pleasant and
unpleasant there can be a lot of pain for example or a lot of pleasure that's felt
and then as we settle into that and we start discovering that um there's
different two different kinds of pleasant and unpleasant there's that which has to do with the body itself and
this ordinary senses like so if i pinch myself it hurts or if i get a massage it
feels good and and i'm sitting in a cold room i might be uncomfortable sitting in a
comfortable temperature room i feel i can relax perhaps a cold day the warmth feels very nice
and soothing and so um so there's that has to do with stimulating the ordinary senses of the
body but as we settle in in meditation we become aware that there's a deeper
sense of a pleasant unpleasant having to do with in modern world
language might call it our psychology though with our inner mind state our inner state of being i like the
expression state of being and i know it's kind of a vague expression and not everyone understands
what it means perhaps but the the quality the characteristics of our
state of being that's independent on whether the world is providing us with pleasure
or with pain and so this inner sense of well-being inner state of being
is getting closer and deeper and more intimate with us and this state of being now as we is
become aware of it this is very closely connected or maybe the same thing as
the state of mind a state of mind the word is chitta
c-i-t-t-a it's a very important word in the term in the teachings of the buddha it's
sometimes translated as mind sometimes it's translated as state of mind
sometimes it's uh translated as thinking thought and so it's different context it means
kind of it's cons that's the constellation of things that the word kind of points to
but it points to i like state of mind or quality of mind or quality of being it's
the mood overall mood or attitude through which we're aware of things
so for example if i'm angry i can be angry
as a flare-up in the moment about something in particular and then it goes away and i'm
my basic disposition hasn't changed but when my disposition becomes an angry
disposition then we say that the state of mind has become angry the inner quality the
quality of our being has a kind of characterized by anger it's an attitude
or a mood that we carry with us that is more enduring than the flare-ups of the moment
so the same thing if i feel just tremendous goodwill
for that goodwill you know is not just that then it's not just a momentary goodwill
and some encounter that i have but there's a disposition of goodwill that characterizes the
state of being the mood the state of mind that we have
maybe for some of you it might be meaningful to know that some people translate the word cheetah
c-i-t-t-a as heart and so it's this quality of our heart
and now with this third foundation where we focus on this state of mind or state of heart
state of our inner being now we're getting much more intimate we're getting into something that's uh
uh much more impactful closer into what feels most intimate
with us that's not have not not so tied to the vagaries of changing phenomena in the
world and a place where has a big impact on our mood our sense of well-being where
we might feel a pervasive feeling of dread or basic
feeling of of greed or wanting desperate wanting for something
or we might feel a pervasive mood of ill will hostility
where we might feel the opposite of that we might feel a tremendous mood or attitude of
of uh generosity and open-heartedness where we might feel
love or kindness good will and so um so now this is the mind state
and so as we settle and get quieter and quieter maybe the breathing gets quieter the
body comes still and quieter we feel at ease it relaxed and now things are comfortable
and enough that we start noticing what stands out and highlight is this
inner disposition this mood the mind state the heart state how we are and
sometimes we discover that that's a difficult place there's all kinds of ways with which
our inner life people try to avoid it they don't want to know it they stay busy so they don't feel it because
there might be some real sadness or grief there or something we're very much afraid of or
some inner sense of conflict between different parts of ourselves but to
start becoming aware of this deeper interstate that we have it allows the healing to unfold it
allows the purification the term that's often used in buddhism purifying ourselves of the
of the afflictive states that we have and buddhism in that sense is very
optimistic it's very encouraging that it is possible to
change ourselves that we're never stuck in any particular mood any particular mind state that is afflictive
that it that harms us that is difficult to be with but that there is a path through it
and uh recently we've talked about faith and talked about patience and
these are all important states and qualities for being able to work with these deeper mind states
to have a lot of faith in the value of practice and enter into it uh to have a lot of patience with what
is difficult for us and and then it's possible to work through
these work through or open up or settle the afflictive mind states settles a good
term because afflictive mind states involve a certain kind of overactivity of the mind
it's a there's action activity of the mind that's generating boredom generating
hatred or ill will generating fear despair and as the mind gets quieter and stiller
that activity settles away and we experience ourselves without those afflictive mind states
and as we do so there's two different things that can happen
either we start making room in our hearts for the opposite of the
afflictive states to begin to appear generosity love wisdom
that's one thing that can happen the other is that uh the mind state itself begins the
quality or the characteristic of it the texture of it begins to change where it starts becoming expansive open
uh if it starts feeling it an ease that's related to freedom and
like the mind the heart can now breathe easily because it feels free and unrestricted
and these are also all these things are part of mindfulness of the mind state the third foundation
becoming mindful of mind states that are afflictive those that are the opposite of
afflictive and those that come as the mind becomes freer and freer and to feel this freedom of mind state
freedom of heart is one of the great important teachers
for us on this path of mindfulness we become our own teacher as we begin
recognizing the very changing states of mind that we're capable of having and beginning to notice and
appreciate ones that support the movement towards freedom and wisdom and compassion and
care and such things so that's the introduction for this theme for this week
and uh and i look forward to sharing this important
part and i'll say to end it that
what we're looking at when we look at the mind state or the heart state that we have
is the quality of our inner state quality very inner being
and and it turns out that we are we are the primary or maybe the only custodian
of our inner well-being and so it isn't if we if we assume other people
are custodian of it and our inner well-beings depend on how other people treat us or what they do
for us then it's not really a reliable place to find happiness and well-being
but to learn through mindfulness to be the custodian of our own well-being is what's possible with this um a third
foundation of mindfulness so we'll talk more this week so thank you very much