so
warm greetings to our meditation time
together
and i want to start with a principle of
meditation that
is not well appreciated i think or
taught and that is that
in some of the challenges we have for
meditation
the art is rather than fighting the
challenge
is uh transforming the challenge
into something that helps us to be
present and to enter into the meditation
space
and um the um
so for example if there's a lot of
thinking going on
and you really can't stop the thinking
and just like you know really obsessing
about something or other and
think you know and you try to come back
but just it's
hard or you keep spinning out then
rather than struggling with your
thinking
you might reorient your thinking
to think about meditation think about
what's actually happening in the present
moment
and thinking about meditation is not the
same as meditation exactly
but it's certainly better than the
alternative
because you're pointing the thinking
into the present to what's actually
happening what you're dedicated towards
and so a variation of this has to do
with the imagination
that if we're thinking about the past or
the future
it's partly an act of imagination
we're thinking thoughts of fantasy it's
imagination especially when there's
visualizations going on we're
visualizing things
and to some degree imagination is at
play with a lot of the ways in which we
drift off in thought
and that's one of the reasons why it can
be so compelling
and so it's also possible then to use
imagination
to be present to point us back into the
present moment
and and ideally for the purposes of
meditation
this would be a very simple act of
meditation of imagination
imaginations which support is settling
and concentrating and becoming more
attentive
to the present moment but to harness the
power of imagination
to be present is something that the
buddha never taught
explicitly but in his teachings it's
kind of
implicit and i'll talk about that later
so i'll offer you some simple
i'll offer you some simple uh acts of
imagination that maybe can help you
gather yourself together and become
focused and present here in the moment
and so if you hear as you hear these
little exercises in imagination
keep in mind this is this is the purpose
of them to help us really be
here in the present moment
so to begin to uh
some care for your meditation posture
and
the attention to the posture is the
beginning of
mindfulness meditation being mindful of
the posture
making mindful adjustments
and as you exhale mindfully relaxing and
softening
parts of your body
and gently close your eyes
and to begin the process of
being present in the place you're at
here in this body
this time
slowly maybe tenderly
take a few long slow deep breaths
breathing in and deeply
and maybe lovingly exhale long exhale
and then
letting your breathing return to normal
and then one more time one more round of
going through your body
and on the exhale
relaxing the parts of your body that are
easy to relax
and as you relax
relax into the pull of gravity
and then sitting here quietly
meditating quietly in your meditation
place
evoke your imagination
that with your eyes closed imagine
yourself
sitting meditating where you're
meditating
imagine yourself in this space
imagine yourself on your spot
imagine you're seeing yourself in your
meditation posture
in a sense you're using your imagination
to imagine what is actually happening
here
but it is an act of imagination a little
bit removed from the
direct experience
imagining
your spine your back
have a picture in your mind perhaps of
what's happening with your hands
your legs
if you have an easy ability to visualize
maybe visualize yourself sitting here
quietly peacefully
just here
and then imagine
that side by side with you is a person
who
really inspires you in in the dharma
maybe the buddha sits next to you
or kuan yin available
or some teacher that greatly inspires
you
and they're meditating next to you
and what would it be like to have this
inspiring meditator
side by side with you sharing with you
in the meditation
in your space
and then imagine that
see sitting here in your own experience
you're sharing a lot of experiences with
this
companion of yours
both of you feel the temperature of the
room
both of you who hear the same sounds
around you
in this inspiring person next to you
imagine how this person feels the
temperature
hears the sounds
and like you this person is breathing
and while there might be differences
between your breath and theirs
there's also a lot of similarities
they also experience their rhythm of
breathing in and breathing out
and maybe imagine how this person would
sit peacefully and
feel that rhythm and sensations of
breathing
and like you this person feels
their body maybe there are some
differences but a lot of similarities
to be in this body to feel it and sense
it
and imagining how this person meditates
and holds and relates to their body from
the inside out
maybe with peacefulness or calmness or
ease
and as you're sitting with yourself here
can you feel or intuit
within yourself some degree of calmness
or peace
embodied calmness
settledness
which receives your breathing the
experience of breathing
imagine what it'd be like for you
to be peaceful maybe you're not peaceful
particularly
but imagine what it'd be like
maybe remembering a time that you were
peaceful or contented
settled at ease
remembering what it was like at that
time
physically the actual experience from
the point of view of your body
what was it like in your body to be
peaceful and settled
at ease
and then to let go of the imagination of
your companion
of some other time and place where you
felt peaceful
even the imagination of yourself sitting
here
but allow the there to linger some of
the qualities of
peace or calmness
and gently tenderly now
allow the experience of breathing
to be received in whatever calmness or
peacefulness that there is
receiving the experience of inhale
allowing for exhaling
letting there be an ever so short
pause before you inhale
then pause where the mind can get quiet
in which then you can just receive the
inhale when it wants to begin
an ever so short pause at the
before the exhale
so that you can feel more fully how good
it is to allow
for the release the exhale
imagining that all around you and all
within you
is lots and lots of space
lots of room
and breathing
has lots of breathing room
room with space which is peaceful
expansive
peaceful
and breathing in and breathing out
allowing and releasing
is intimate with all the space and room
peace that's also present here
imagining the mind
what it would be like if it were there
was a refreshing silence in the mind
a silence which was maybe
that may be spread through all the space
that's here
silence that makes your thinking
not so important
silence that allows the thinking to
relax and dissolve
diffused into the silence
breathing in and breathing out
in space and silence
having a very teeny pause at the end of
the
out breath the end of the in-breath
relaxed pause
can be a little protection
from being caught up in your thoughts or
your imagination
little reminder stay here with the
direct experience of breathing
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting
take a few moments to imagine
some of the people that you'll encounter
today or
communicate with today or maybe think
about today
and imagine what it would be like if you
could encounter them
being peaceful
having a simple good will
without any animosity or anxiety
or any strong
desire that their expectation for
anything
imagine what it'd be like to meet them
in a peaceful goodwill
that is not so strong
to
disturb them but just nice for you
imagining that possibility
and then wishing aspiring
that whatever benefit and goodness
that's come from this meditation
then it might be translated in your body
and your heart and the mind
to walking through the world in a way
that brings benefit
to others whether seen or unseen
whether you know knowingly or
unknowingly
may it be that the merit the benefits
the goodness of
our meditation together
spreads into the world
with kind actions supportive actions
generous activity for the welfare and
happiness of all beings
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be
free
you