[Music]
so good morning everyone and
welcome to our sitting and and i'm happy that to be morning
everyone i'm happy to be back and happy to hear the
appreciation of the other teachers who taught here while i was away so that was nice
matthew and andrea so um
in the sitting today i want to emphasize a three-letter word
and that is the word now and if you want to
add a letter so it's a little more sophisticated you can add the k in front
so that it's no now then now that's to be known
and the task in meditation mindfulness meditation
is to have develop to have greater confidence
in now that in confidence in the present and
the past or in fantasy and commentary abstract thinking
to have confidence that being present presence presencing
now is valuable it doesn't it's not a dismissal or
rejection of past and future but if we're going to be involved in the
past and the future to know that we're doing so now
to always know what is happening and unfolding now
as the foundation for our life and their life just kind of unfolds so
much more beautifully and remarkably and wisely
when we are centered here and now with what's unfolding
what is the flowing what is arising what is passing what is occurring now
so in this sitting today you might if you would like
to use the word now as a little not exactly a mantra but as a
as a guide as a support as a reminder and just periodically say now
you might even say it at some point in the cycle of breathing
beginning of the inhales beginning of the exhales the end of the exhale just anywhere it
feels comfortable very relaxed and easy but this regular reminder
to be awake to be present for now the experience of now
with the idea that we're developing either we're developing
greater confidence in our ability to be present now or
we're learning that we actually have more confidence
in other things or the mind has more confidence in distraction or the hindrances or
conversations in one's head or thinking about the past or planning
the future and then is it really
to your best interest in meditation to have confidence in these other things
and can you lovingly shift your attention shift your confidence your trust
to now to being with what is now presencing
what is now so
assuming a posture for meditation that's appropriate for you
with a guideline that that posture that helps you both to relax and to remain alert so you don't drift
off in sleep or sleepiness
and if it's nice for you you can gently close your eyes
if you keep your eyes open because it feels better you might want to
have your eyes cast downwards towards the floor and about 45 degrees
and whether the eyes are open or closed to see if you can relax
the eyes as if the eyeballs can rest
in the sockets as if the eyes are no longer
searching scanning the external world looking outward
but rather [Music] resting backwards settling down
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
filling the rib cage as you inhale
relaxing as you exhale
allowing a settling in your body as you exhale
and then
letting your breathing breathe normally
and relax your body on the exhale
maybe the whole body can release relax
as you exhale setting and settling into the place where you're meditating
as you exhale relaxing the face sometimes relaxing the face
it can be a relaxing of our thinking a tense face is almost like
squeezing the thoughts energizing
thinking and relaxing around the face the jaw the forehead
also maybe allows a calming of the thinking mind
and the same with the shoulders
and exhale softening the shoulders
letting the thinking mind become calm
and softening the belly releasing the belly into now
here
and perhaps there's some way you can relax the thinking mind
or any physical tension associated with the thinking mind
if we think if we're thinking a lot there's a kind of disassociation that
happens with a body a separation from that which is able to
settle in the settle in the heart
and then if it's comfortable for you settle into the experience of the body
breathing
and wherever you feel you're breathing in your body the sensations of the body breathing
at the edges of them can you relax more can you soften
and as you sit here if it's nice for you
you can periodically say the word now [Music]
maybe with an inner voice that is calm and confident
so that you bring your confidence into the practice of being present to
now
maybe nothing needs to be different than what it is
except knowing more fully that whatever is happening
is happening now thinking is happening now
feeling is happening now sensations are happening now
now
and the reason to be present for now is that each unique moment each now
is only here for brief moments
you
remembering to be here and now especially the now
is there recognizing being with what is occurring
now
you
and as we come to the end of this sitting to consider that
now the present moment
is the location for love
for care for kindness goodwill
all these wonderful qualities of generous qualities of care and
friendship
they are motivations feelings attitudes
that when felt and known are occurring in the present moment
and as we come to the end of the sitting perhaps you can
bring your attention to the place within that you associate
with goodwill compassion
kindness
and center yourself there as you exhale relax into that location
even if you don't feel it right now the place
that seems to be activated energized
when there is love and kindness good will
breathe through that place breathe with it
and knowing you're doing so from the present moment
reflect on what encounters with others you might have
on this day
or if it's evening for you to tomorrow
and consider look upon the people that you might
encounter and known and unknown strangers and friends
people you'll communicate with through technology
people you might talk to on the phone or meet with
and gaze upon them kindly
gaze upon them with calm sense of
love or good will friendliness
and consider how in a way that has integrity for you seems appropriate
for you how you might
live this day with greater care and kindness
for the people you'll encounter
consider ways you can offer more care
or do things that improves the lives of others
even without them knowing that you're doing it maybe simple ways
of supporting others and may it be that this meditation
practice we do and practice of the mindfulness we develop may it be as a support
for us to live in this world to make this world a better place for
others even in the smallest details can we
contribute to the welfare and happiness well-being
of others may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free free of oppression hostility
free of suffering and despair and stress
may all
beings discover what it's like to have a heart that is at peace
you
so good day to our monday
on this first day of the week and so the theme that i would like to talk
about is um
faith and um and i think the motivation to
talk about faith is that uh i've been feeling lately quite inspired
by it and heartened by this faith quality of buddhist practice
and so it's mostly to be able to talk a little bit share a little bit something that's in my heart
and um and there are different qualities of
faith so in different times in different ways this the pali words sada
which often translated into english as faith has this has different qualities
and so therefore often translated then differently and uh in context and so sometimes it's
trust sometimes it's confidence
sometimes it's devotion or love and
so whatever it is this uh and the english word the associations we have in english for
faith if those don't work for you other words might work or you might put
those aside and just realize the provisional nature of the english translation of sada
as faith but i like the word faith myself because it's um
uh to me and it might not be for others uh faith is not so much about uh tenet
of belief you know what we believe and we have to believe a belief that we don't have any verification for
but rather faith is to have some kind of trust or confidence
in what can be called the dharma but not the dharma that's out there that you
read about but the dharma that's found in the heart and so one of the
definitions of this faith in buddhism that i like is that
it is um the attitude uh the quality
that calms the heart and sometimes it said it's what clarify
clears the heart or clarifies the heart that clears uh and the word clear
and then the analogy for this in the ancient world is uh
uh if um the water like a pond it's all muddy it's
like some some animal has run through it it's all muddy then there's apparently an ancient india
a magical stone that if you put it in the in the in the pond in the water
it clears all the mud away and so faith clears away mud the mud
of our destructions preoccupations the things we swirl around in
and the ancient texts say specifically that there's something about the power of faith
this kind of deep trust that calms the heart that clears it
of the hindrances clears it further grasping at
desires and aversions uh being pulled into the world of
restlessness resistance uh tiredness not tiredness but kind of a
slothfulness and doubt so the way that we reach out and hold on
to these things or get caught in them and there's something about the deep trust of that the dharma can provide
that settles those things because the hindrances are an expression of mistrust
they are expressions of not having faith in where the heart can settle where the
heart can be at home in itself when there's uh when we put faith in sensual desire
we put faith in something that keeps us a little bit dissociated from ourselves a little bit reaching out beyond
ourselves and wanting something same thing with ill will but faith and ill will is not a good place to have
faith in or trust in but most people won't say they have faith or trust and ill will but
functionally that's what kind of is happening unconsciously that oh this is how i become safe this is how i get what
i want this is how i protect myself is by or how i create myself as a person is by
expressing my hostility my anger my criticism complaints and so there's confidence in
that world of complaints and criticism and all that and and so what we're doing in the dharma
practice is to find some place to be at ease and at rest in our own hearts and
our own being that is not dissociating it's not reaching
out and relating to the outer world in a way that desire and ill will does and
even doubt though sometimes that uh it's really a
settling it's what settles the heart that clarifies the heart
and um and one of the classic purposes of faith
in the dharma is not faith for its own sake but rather a fake
faith that provides the resolve dedication the intention the
motivation to practice to live a different way
so it isn't passive faith to just sit back and kind of be taken care of by
you know in some passive magical way by what we have faith in but rather it's a faith certain kind of
action a certain kind of walking they're walking the the
the moment moment steps of dharma practice of showing up and being mindful being present
but as faith gets awakened the the practice the action of practice
the engagement and practice uh can be uh have the same soothing or
settling or clearing quality as faith does because faith is
comes along with it or is part of the practice we do and when we practice without faith
without this warm-heartedness or this love or this
care or this um
trust then the mindfulness sometimes itself can become a little bit
dissociated and disembodied even as as if it's a technique that we're doing but
when it comes out of faith comes out of the deeper trust then it's not dissociated it can be more
embodied or more presenting or more inspiring even inspiring for ourselves
so uh so the um
um you know so faith so so in these days i'll talk about these
different heart qualities qualities of heart that come into play
in different ways around this word faith this concept of faith and
so i thought of tuesday tomorrow talk more about trust
and then wednesday about the quality of love in relationship to faith
and and then on thursday confidence
in relationship to faith but you know the question is what do we have confidence in and there's many things buddha dharma
sangha and things but on thursday i want to talk about faith and non-clinging
and this wonderful kind of holding together like left and
right hand holding each other of non-clinging and the warmth and the
goodness of faith and then on friday talk about
kind of about in a sense faith as devotion that has expresses itself in
service expresses itself in acting for the benefit of others
and and that that that act of service is can be can be
an expression of dharma devotion that's where the devotion kind of of the
practice can really maybe take a a get an expression in itself
and um so
um and my hope is in talking about faith
that um we really you know i hope i can talk about it in such a way
that you can begin recognizing it in yourself because i don't you know that's that's
really where the faith lives is in ourselves in our hearts and our in our inner life
and we all have the faculty of faith so
so in in buddhism you wouldn't say that you have faith in certain teachings or something
because that's a little bit more like intellectual exercise
faith in buddhism is considered to be a faculty like confidence is more like a faculty
and and equanimity is a capacity of faculty
loving kindness is a capacity we have a faculty we have we have an ability to
have kindness and goodwill and generosity and and
so it's a uh in that sense uh this uh faith is a faculty
is a an ability is a capacity that we can develop and grow
in and in that sense it's something that already lives in each of us though it
might be dormant or it might be resting or maybe the seeds of this dharma faith
is a way sitting waiting to be watered but it's it's there in everyone and so
we want to kind of i'm hoping these talks will be a little bit more of a of a have some resonance inside of you
of something that you can recognize so faith
trust confidence love
inspiration motivation devotion service all those kind of are in the sphere
of what i'm calling faith or sada so thank you and um very happy to be
back here and look forward to this coming week thank you