chair we're good okay
good morning everyone and welcome to imc's sunday morning program
we're going to be having a little different format this morning because we have a guest teacher gregory kramer and he's going to
interweave meditation with his dharma talk for the whole period so i just like to introduce our guest
teacher we're delighted to welcome gregory kramer he teaches meditation rights and is the
founding teacher of the insight dialogue community he's been practicing since 1974. he
studied with esteemed monastics including anagarika damadina
venerable balangoda ananda matreya mahanayakatero ayachan sobin
namto and venerable punegi mahatero and others he began teaching meditation
worldwide in 1980 his primary focus since 1995 has been
developing and sharing a relational study of the dharma and insight dialogue an interpersonal
form of buddhist insight meditation and groups are now active worldwide
he also developed dharma contemplation a text-based contemplation practice
and he's the author of several books on these practices the most recent is a whole life path
a lay buddhist's guide to crafting a dharma infused life
and this wider audience is actually joining some of us here at imc in the middle of a two-day retreat on the topic of the
whole life path so welcome everyone and i'll turn it over to gregory
thank you
yeah we've been exploring a whole life path now a day and a half
in a retreat embedded in our lives
and for the retreat but also for this one talk this one session
if we can gain a sense of each moment
being infused with a sense of path
just that one piece i think we're doing really well
and the particulars like eight path factors and all this kind of thing
are really ways of populating that of supporting that that perspective that brings about
experience and so we'll begin by reflecting on
why i have a path at all because that gives us a sense of direction sense of purpose of the path
and the way to gain some you know
experiential sense of the dilemma that the buddha was confronting
is to perhaps attune right now to how the path is manifesting to how
the human experience is manifesting so
as you see me let's say on the screen or as i see you
the actual practice or process i mean of light touching the eye
and there's you know awareness of seeing this experience of contact
and in this moment of contact moment by moment by moment
there's a uh through the the seeing door the contact with hearing you and i
are sort of instantly involved in these processes of feeling and perception
so you not only see colors but you
have the form that is saying ah it's a person and particulars perhaps
it's oh my god it's another old white man teaching dhamma might be your perception
but it also might be like oh a human being you know like ah and so as soon as that happens
the instant the body mind recognizes that this is a human being
all of these other sensitivities come forward in that very moment
our entire process of human evolution as a social species pops up brain
structures are activated that are relational hormonal systems built
to foster relatedness are activated both in terms of stress and in terms of
pleasure so all of that's happening right now in this moment of
interpersonal contact you just see me and that's happening
and likewise when we perceive
anything in the world there's this exquisite sensitivity
to physical touch as we said to seeing to hearing so as you hear my voice for
example right now automatically your entire body mind is
assessing you know who is this person or is this
worth listening to you're coming to know me through the
quality of my voice through the things i'm saying
perhaps there's a sense of safety or unsafety
credibility or not
and like all of the learning that you've done moment by moment throughout your life is
operating right now to get oriented in the world
to assess the world in this case me speaking
so this is uh just one piece of this exquisite
sensitivity of the entire organism
so here you are you've perhaps sitting in your body
feeling perhaps the form of the body the shape of the body
and all of those nerve endings that tell you ah here's a map
of this form this rupa bodily form
that sensitivity begins to take uh you know the construct of i me
my body but also just like the construct of taking in the light and the touching and
then the perception and then there's gregory and then there's a person and he's out there i'm in here
so that whole sense of me you and meanwhile all the air
touches the skin just like the sounds touch the ear molecules touch the nose molecules touch
the tongue when you eat something so all of these sensitivities to the world are constantly operating
pleasant unpleasant interpersonally pleasant and unpleasant
socially in the bigger framework a thought comes up of our society or of
our sangha some is pleasant like our sangha some might not be like our politics
so we're constantly responding to that just like we're responding to light
and air pressure waves that touch the ears it's quite something how sensitive we
are i mean right now just the slightest wiggle
of my vocal cords with air coming through gets picked up by a microphone the
microphone diaphragm vibrates it gets sent over the internet as a
digitized signal comes out of your monitor your speakers your speakers vibrate the air the air
pressure differences touch the ears the nerves you know the auditory nerve
sends this signal to the brain so every vibration of my throat
moves through that channel to wiggle your ears
and so my throat and your ears your tympanic membrane are coupled
right now so sensitive it's so intimate
but we take it for granted and not only are we in contact through
language through sound but through the meanings so what is in my mind is reaching your
mind through this language not everything in my mind
aren't you lucky but actually you know a dhamma contact so now
not only is there visual contact auditory contact there's mind contact through language
right now as i'm speaking this that right this is this is our
sensitivity operating
and right now in this moment
it's operating in service of conveying dhamma
a sense of sensing sensation sensitivity touch contact passage the poly word for
contact and the veda now that comes the pleasant and the unpleasant the sauna the
perception of things and qualities so i'm conveying dhamma
from this mind to you you hear these words you understand so there's contact and through that
contact that channel of contact dhamma is flowing right now
right you see what i'm saying okay so
that relational that relationship we have of spiritual friendship
is established in service of seeing things as they actually are
that's what we're doing right now so this is a path factor practice of right
view the voice of another right now is me and wise attention he only saw monastic
that's connection between one person and another the buddha said the voice of another and
wise attention are the necessary conditions for the
arising of right view necessary
wow unless you're a self
buddha right this is what he's talking about
so we can begin to get a sense right here right now
of the path functioning a wholesome path
and the path factor that's i'm just naming is right view we're practicing it through discussion
and buddha also named that we could practice it through study as
a path factor practice of right view also through tranquility
conditions right view because when the mind is calm you can see what you can't see otherwise
insight obviously a practice of right view we are we usually think of the methods
of mindfulness and concentration but the actual uh
you might say uh in service of you know the mindfulness and the samadhi
in service of right view so this is practicing right view as is
sitting in vipassana and seeing things as they are
so
path is operating and we're just seeing one of the ways it's operating
now why does that matter
the whole purpose of the path has to be understood and it's understood in the context right
now i'm suggesting of this human sensitivity
to the world to all these contacts to so much going on and the complexity that the mind builds
up out of all these contexts my preferences
and the things i dislike and that scare me i build those build up
all the things that are familiar and unfamiliar i begin to develop a sense of
uh the ways that i create safety in this complex
world that i don't control is by exerting control where i can get it because i'm
so sensitive i'm so you know i need to survive
i need to get safe and i want pleasure and i want to avoid pain so the organism
is functioning with all these imperatives this is what i this is what the nature
of my life is is getting the pleasures avoiding the pains and stabilizing the self
because that's survival
so how do we survive how do i stabilize
this sensitive being in a world that is out of my control and that
effort and all the strategies
begin to form the basis of the tension that we call
self and the strategies that we call personality or behavior patterns this is
like how i get through the world making it work
so perhaps i learned for example to perform in some way by being
particularly beautiful or particularly smart or to get seen and to exist and to
stabilize a sense of me and get the supplies to keep that me well guarded well well regarded
and so i you know i could have a beautiful voice so i could make beautiful drawings
or i could just scream a lot so that people will pay attention to me so that's like
that's see me so i can exist and i pleasure myself so i feel like i
exist and i enjoy those pleasures and i can surround myself wrap myself in pleasant stimulations
and temporarily keep out the unpleasant ones that just keep
coming back in whether it's something as simple as this
sensitive body getting hurt by things like poked and stuck and in the suit as you
see you know insect bites and the beating of the sun and you know very
direct kind of you know very earthy sense of the human
experiences conveyed in the discourses the body growing old is described with
its you know its gray and thinning hair and its missing teeth and its bent over
form these are the aspects of dukkha that that kind of the world
constantly out of my control pressing in and i'm trying to wow i'm trying to make
i'm trying to stabilize and make it work within that
and so the pleasures i can paste them over myself
and still the world keeps happening
i can't keep the flow of pleasure high enough to make it work
so this human dilemma continues as the world presses in and i
when it's too much i want to get out rather than exist and be seen and you know and uh kind of become
in the world i now want to get out of the world also at the same time because it's too much
because i'm so sensitive sensitive to other people sensitive to
the touches on the eye the touches on the ear the touches on the skin and the touches of my mind
beating on me what's next what do i do how do i do it
who am i am i safe who am i relationship with i
feel lonely i feel overwhelmed
so all these
qualities of the human dilemma call it dukkha first noble truth right
this kind of underlying challenge
because of our sensitivity and this is the context of our path this is what we're living
with suffering in the end of suffering
addresses both the most subtle anxiety and how we meet the world
all the way through the totality of aging illness and death
so the urgency
of getting and having the urgency of wanting
of loneliness and so on
so as we practice right view right now
coming to see this nature of the human experience we say wait a minute i could be doing
this anytime i'm observing my life in a reflective way
and one way to sort of keep your bearings is when the dhamma is a reference point
and we say okay how can i bring the practice of right view
into my everyday life i'm not going to run around just looking at a dhamma book and i can't always have
dharma discussions i can't always be in meditation
i can always be practicing morality which is also practice of right view
so can i begin to invoke the dhamma
as a frame of reference just in my life and most of us have done some of this of
course with let's say a reflection just take it through your life on impermanence
and this can be the very accessible stuff like noticing the impermanence of the
world which is really the impermanence of the sensing of the world
so okay wow yeah the wind is blowing or this tree is rotting or
cars are drifting by or sounds never stop changing
reflection on dukkha
where's you know where is the kind of the stress and the fear and the separation operating how is the mind constantly
wanting not expecting it to stop but we're just talking about right view
just now simple simple simple practice don't try to try to transcend it don't
try to anything just it's a practice of right view to notice that continuity of noticing
so what you're mindful of is this aspect of experience
so it's practice of right view and all of a sudden wait a minute that's also a practice of right mindfulness
we begin to see ah i can observe the mind in its frantic ways it's
difficult ways it's sometimes unkind ways
and if i'm observing and not falling into fusion with it that's the practice
of right view and right mindfulness
so we begin to see this sensitivity for example that's a reflection on the sense doors a
reflection on contact reflection on consciousness itself but it's all
in the experiential side of it is simply sensitivity so you might notice that now
what's it like to be contacted with the world right now
in the middle of a dharma talk on a sunday morning
the touch of the world
you can notice also the touch of the mind world
as thoughts continue to self-fabricate
sensitivity to the image to the sound and the whole feeling tone
that's been conditioned by this talking that's been going on
from this guy this moment conditioned by that
so putting the sensitivity to work in service of understanding
some aditi of right view and right
mindfulness is what's knowing this yeah practicing right mindfulness right now
so there's another path factor that's operating that we just haven't named and i'm going to name it now
you might notice that as you're listening and you go let's say perhaps try the things that
i'm suggesting you look at the mind you aim the mind this way you're paying
attention perhaps to what i'm saying let's look at the energy that
comes in to pay attention like oh as the buddha said lending ear
you're lending ear right now notice the stepping up the energizing of the body
mind to hear these words to pay attention to them
to notice the qualities in the pause
noticing that energy that's an aspect of right effort
you're applying yourself you're offering your attention
you're showing up right effort
so right now already as we sit here simple listening to this talk being
together in this already the path factors of right
view are operating being being developed
right effort is operating and being developed as we like wow i'm really you know i'm i'm here and right
mindfulness attending to the path noticing your own body mind functioning
all of those path factors right now
are unfolding and developing not just
flat any time that you're in your life
and there's sufficient uh motivation
to look for the path in this way you can find it that's good to know
it's never distant that's really good to know
but we are greatly supported if we learn
what that feels like we learn it rationally like i'm offering all these words to
support it and how it feels in the body to just sort of say ah
what's it like to be on the path it's like this you get a sense
of right view right effort operating right mindfulness operating it's like a
whole embodied experience this relational experience that we're in
right now spiritual friendship the voice of another wise attention being together as
a sangha has a certain feel and a sangha is a collective experience aimed
towards understanding suffering in the end of suffering this is it this is our sangha experience
path it's the path aspect
whole life path so let's attune now to this sense of
shared direction that we have aiming of the mind together
okay so we're understanding this human dilemma of sensitivity
and all the urges that push this sensitive being towards pleasure
away from pain towards becoming away from becoming we kind of were sensing that and saying ah
it doesn't have to be like that there's some notion in here that together ah it doesn't have to be
so fraught we don't have to be trapped in this there's some we can wake up there's a
sense of that and here we are together in that in intention that aim of the heart
sensing that direction that feeling the kind of the feeling tone of the
direction of our lives the direction of this very moment
can you look into your own mind into your own heart right now
and feel this kind of maybe a percolating sense of purpose
sense of possibility
as we grow that sense of possibility as we explore it together
as we surround ourselves with things that remind us of this possibility
we're practicing right in tension we're cultivating wholesome intentions
or the aiming the direction of the heart so right now
these words that we're sharing this sense of being in the dhamma together that we're
sharing is aimed
right intention right here now with these very words so you see the
connection between right view and right intention when we see things a certain way like constantly
trying to fill that empty hole in in my senses in my heart
is never gonna work oh so there's another way this kind of way
of letting go a way of love and compassion that is not just a
built around trying to protect and satisfy a me that's never gonna work it's painful it
will always be painful except for those little moments of success that then pass and there you
are again bereft and
something else is possible in this letting go and the opening and care that happens
when we let go oh that's also possible and you feel
that and what happens when you see that clearly
you aim that way right you say that's what i want that's where i'm gonna go the the the
animal body wants that even the animal body doesn't just want pleasure the animal body wants stability
and all those mental constructs
of me and how i get my satisfactions and how i protect myself
oh that's never gonna be satisfied that's never gonna stabilize
but if i enter into a care for others
as a natural consequence of coming out of this shell of self
that's something this that this body mind can say oh yeah
that move is the connection between right view and right intention the aiming of
the mind that comes when we understand that sama-san kappa
so those classical right intentions of renunciation or relinquishment and
of loving kindness or non-anger non-hatred and of non-cruelty non-harming
or compassion so onset put in the positive sense that renunciation
love and compassion those are the classical wholesome intentions
as opposed to the unwholesome ones of course of sensual accumulation and gathering and
trying to get right and then when you can't get what you want or
someone's in the way or things don't work out there's anger there's hatred that intention and the downright cruelty
that the human organism is also capable of
right wow just saying it hurts to think about doesn't it so but
then the turning of the mind saying this is a way to go that can
actually bring happiness rather than this frantic deluded thing that's you know i can get happiness
out of you know somehow somehow these anger of mine is going to
make me happy or this cruelty or this insatiable
sensory gluttony will somehow
bring happiness kind of from the outside it looks a little absurd but this practice the
bright view that we're doing and right effort paying attention
bringing ourselves together even showing up here today right view right effort and right
mindfulness because we're monitoring experience and saying ah this is what the body mind is doing
we're holding the dhamma in mind that's also right mindfulness and this is aiming the mind
in a wholesome way so this is right intention
and in the whole of our lives
we're embedded in this process in this
um uh very tangled complex world
we're not doing this like some out in outer space in some vacuum in a little
bubble it's here and now in this world like this with this body
with your relationships and in this culture that's just how it
is you can't get out of it you have no choice we have no choice
this is how it is
so there's some hard work there but there's also some really good news
i'm gonna name a little of the hard work first if you don't mind
that being embedded in our relationships
means that these are the conditions these relations
form the conditions for my path the unfolding of my path
and no matter how much work i do on the cushion
if i am functioning in a way that is harmful
cruel shut down greedy
that the body mind will continue to suffer and insight will continue to
mostly uh evade me
and if we shut down likewise
from the pressing suffering not only of our immediate relations but
now opening out into our cultural relations to our society
then what that is it's a form of a vija ignorance where there's all this
suffering that i've shut off from the mind as much as i can because it feels like
too much so i've chosen to maybe unconsciously
chosen to shrink
and the unaware of injustice economic injustice racial
injustice gender injustice and so on i've decided somehow in my heart
maybe consciously maybe not climate change is just too much hyper consumption is just too
much the insanity of our media life is just
too much and you say i can't you know i can't i'm not going to pay attention to that
and so there's this vast world that we've now shut off and when
we go to open to the world we really only open to the bare edges of our bubble
and the tensions that surround us are continue to press in on the heart
so this is difficult news because we often carry a sense of going
off to the meditation hall as uh
an escape from that rather than as an awakening that allows
us to be with that in an awakened and equanimous
way it's a very different thing one is which is to say
get me out it's the bypass of the world through spiritual practice
and it's the bypass of relationships and relationships are complicated
so whether it's the relationships with society or with my significant others my family
of origin hey this is complex stuff
how could that possibly be part of the path we say but i'm going to ask you another
question how could your primary relations not be part of the path
if every moment conditions the next
how could those relations not be part of the path
so let's pause for a moment and sit with that
okay so every
moment of the constructing processes of the mind
conditions consciousness moment by moment so we pause right now
sensing into the rising and vanishing of experience
and this very moment is conditioned by all that came before
so it's conditioned right now most obviously by this dharma talk i'm offering
you could sense into how that feels
this moment is conditioned by something as simple as what you ate
for breakfast or how well you slept let's pause for a moment and see that
this moment moment by moment is conditioned by all your prior
relational contacts every one of them so perhaps you can sense
the presence in some sense the conditioning impact is what i mean of your mother
your father and his siblings just sense how they condition the sense
of you sitting here right now in your dharma chair right now
the poly for all of this is independent origination sankara pachaya vignana so
all prior formations volitional formations all these contacts
condition the arising of consciousness moment by moment
so the whole experience of body mind right now
being known by consciousness
and conditioned
and this is constantly being formed and reformed with every contact with the world
every volitional contact with the world so how could your relations possibly not
be intrinsic to the dharma path of freedom
it's not possible
so here we are now arriving at the path factor of right speech
wow what a powerful thing huh i mean we're using speech now skillfully
at least i hope so it's a vehicle for dhamma
but what about you know speech as a vehicle for loving kindness for care
how are you today sweetheart what did you do today i care and something in the body mind
lets go it's like oh yeah
can i help you with that yeah i know how you feel
this is speech conveying something of the heart
and i don't want to press it too hard but wrong speech or harmful speech
lying to someone is like a rip in the fabric of the universe
how can you live the buddha went so far as to say one who would utter untrue
speech there is no evil that they may not do it was like the
fundamental thing so here we are understanding
the practice of right speech in terms of human sensitivity
and the power of that path factor of right speech what you listen to what you take in how
you speak and what you express do you think right speech doesn't include your emails
does it include the photographs you publish it's not verbal language it's a
imagistic language so it's all of the art we make all of
the expressions we have through our blogs or our podcasts or
whatever
and write action now when we sense right action as all action
we have sort of the core of a body the power of a body to do
harm action right action so wrong action
of killing you know wow just to really think about
intentionally harming other people and you get a sense in this conversation we're having now
wow how does that condition the mind going forward and we see on my path of non-harm
disenters from myself and creates safety for others and when i
participate in creating an a universe
that is safer for other beings that good will conditions my mind as well as
conditions my immediate relationships and it extends and infuses out to the
world so i can participate in making the world safe for others
so that might look like you know political action it might look
like a simple gesture of holding a door open for someone each of us finds our balance in the
active aspect not just the refraining aspect of right action but the active
part of it of creating safety
and care and extending that
as the buddha said you know caring for oneself
is good caring for others is good and the
highest and the best is caring for both self and other
unambiguous that's the path he's describing a path
suffering in the end of suffering internal external and both
so how we engage
with harming and stealing and sexuality and so on is this relational
uh manifesting of the path
forming the mind forming relationships and forming writ large our culture
actively participating in that as dhammapath nothing left out nothing is left out
so let's just pause for a moment and sense into each each of us take a moment internally
and sense into the direction of your life
in speech and action and livelihood
how you handle money how you spend it how you earn it
how does this manifest the path at all times
so mindfulness is operating right now
right effort right intention developing right
intention aiming the mind towards the relinquishment and the compassion
to understand the power of right speech right action and right livelihood
a sense of the whole life nothing left
out
and the nature of the mind the body mind to become tangled
is great neural patterns form hormonal
habits form and these tangles we act
from these tangles we see the world through these tangles that go very deep
so there's compassion and there's patience and there's the deep work of right
effort and right mindfulness says were you seeing now
but also right mindfulness and right effort in formal practice like inside dialogue
like vipassana
so let's look at the role of sama samadhi in exactly this framework that we've
provided here this sense of being intoxicated with the
self being being lost in ignorance and tangled and not
and understand that samadhi's unique power
when the body-mind settles and gathers calms down
and gathers
to see things as they actually are which is to say
the nature of the tangle and perhaps to touch the experience of
being of untangling of a letting go
of the knots of the gathered self of the gathered
personality of the crunch of i am
and all the fears and the aggression that comes out of fear and all of that
getting down underneath to where it's all formed like right down at the bottom to
where it turns into from just the flux
of experiencing body mind and it becomes like wow now it's a me
that has to do all these nasty things but there's a relaxing of all that
beneath and it's all just flux the samadhi the sama samadhi comes not
only through our lifestyle that is changing towards
morality and tranquility and decency and sanity but also towards
formal practice so we have a place on the path
for formal practices where we can experience things in a way
that the normal conditioned habit mind does not cannot it's too
noisy it can't hear the signal because there's so much noise in the air
so we lower the signal to no we lower the we increase the signal to noise ratio we
lower the noise we increase the signal of things as they are simplicity
impermanence the qualities
of the flux rather than the self experiencing rather than the grabbing of
experience experiencing as process and samadhi can
bear this samadhi can witness this there's sufficient equanimity sufficient
stillness and that insight those
insights that come with sati and samadhi in formal practice then can infuse
the totality of our lives and we say oh now i have a new benchmark
for what's possible in the way of for example calm
i used to think i was calm sunday morning drinking coffee reading the paper
i now have a new understanding of passati of tranquility at
that i didn't have before so i can see the tension more clearly i also now have a new understanding of
you know all of my the manifesting of my personal strategies
to get by and to get what i want and all this kind of stuff you know it's pretty tense now i see
that and i'm still doing it because it's a habit i've got and i'm working on it but i now see myself doing it
it's like oh oh ouch it kind of hurts a little bit we begin to see the pain where we thought there was
pleasure it's quite something so
we see the role i mean there's many more things we could say but we see the role of formal practice just as we see
in inside dialogue the way we keep others at a distance or we hunger for
others and there's a releasing and letting go of that insight comes
so to sum up
the whole of the path includes every moment of our lives it absolutely
you know it's just like patently how it is that nothing is left out of forming and reforming our
minds each moment so the actions of our body and our
speech you know everything's conditioning the next moment so path is always on
let's do it skillfully that's the message let's do it well rather than haphazard
like whatever you know i mean our moms and our dads and our teachers and stuff they taught us
what they could but let's keep learning you know and there's a place for formal practice
on the totality of the path and let's honor that and let's see the whole of the path and
you know in all that we do and the more we learn what the path factors are the options
how they can be manifest and grow that's the that learning process
then shows us at any moment that we choose
that there are options the path is always operating we now have the skill to see how
that's it so it's just about time to end
um i'm going to say that for those of you who don't know latest
book is called entitled the whole life path a lay person's
a lay buddhist guide to a dhamma-infused life and it really goes into all these path
factors and the reason i can so shamelessly to tell you about that book now
is because it's all of them whatever money comes in goes to the inside dialogue community there's no personal
gain here i want you to know that that it's really offered in service
and i hope that that's helpful for you
and uh i'll close by
sharing that um the observation that the great privilege we have of
meeting we with each other of having the technology of having the safety
to pay attention and not have to run away from marauders and bullets and that we have
enough to eat so we can take this time because we don't have to run out right away and find our next meal
those are all amazing conditions for practice and there are many who do not share
those conditions so we let ourselves be touched by that
actuality that there is a lot of suffering in this world
and that our practice is on behalf of these beings as well
so may all beings without exception share in the merits of our practice together
may all beings be free
may there be peace may there be peace
may there be peace