so good day everyone and
welcome and so meditation practice
the analogy that is coming back to my mind today about
sitting down to meditate is the idea of
not staying in the control tower but rather to uh be the airplane
that's coming in for a landing and i imagine that the pilot and if the
airplane was animated was a living being would be focused
for the landing would put aside
concerns and thoughts about the future in the past and they would really kind of enter into the
moment of landing and if the airplane was an animate being it
would stabilize itself it would enter into its very body its wings and really
become stable interesting stability to really be focused the way that some of you might be
focused if you're doing a craft or an art or something where
it takes a careful attention you have to give yourself completely over to the event and everything else kind of falls aside
and even there might be people around and you're going to do something careful and
and and so you kind of the sounds around you kind of fall away
you don't really listening to anyone anymore but you're just really kind of there for that experience
so to when we start the meditation practice to think of it this way that we're
somehow dropping out of the control tower in the head
into the body of this being that we are coming in for a
landing gathering ourselves together being centered
feeling ourselves here so then so assuming a posture
that would help you feel present in your body
as if your body your body and your posture
are the means of meditation so taking a posture that maybe is
upright if you're sitting upright a little bit straighter than usual
and then to gently close your eyes
as a way of beginning to turn your attention inward to your body
and to prepare yourself for [Music] so that you can give your attention over
to this body dropping out of the control tower
you might take a few long slow deep breaths
in a relaxed pace only as deep as is comfortable for you
then exhale fully
long exhale but not too long just long enough that
you have a sense that you're participating in the exhale
as if the exhale is the plane coming down for a landing
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and continuing with your breathing with the exhale
the relaxing of your body
is a gathering yourself together around your body so coming home centering in
the body it's more than just relaxing your face
or your shoulders or your belly
it's a remembering of yourself bring your members of your
body together
relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the hands
relaxing the thighs and the legs
relaxing the back ribcage
and relaxing the control tower relaxing the thinking muscle
tension tightening pressure to think
breathing in and breathing out
here
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to once again on the exhale relax your body
if it feels okay just gently taking some deeper breaths again
very gently and then see if there's
further forms of releasing in your body you can do as you exhale
releasing the belly
relaxing in the chest
softening in the face
releasing tension or pressure in the thinking mind
and to feel yourself established present
here in your body and to consider that
our ability to offer embodied attention
our ability to be present for others
is the root the origin the support
for anything that follows for any compassion or kindness
friendliness and not to rush ahead to
be kind or friendly compassionate so that you leave behind your ability to
be rooted or centered here
in your ability to attend
sometimes what's profound with the profound offering to others is our
presence our attention our ability to accompany others
sometimes that's more important than our compassion our kindness our care
so staying rooted here in your relaxed attention
with that as a basis to dedicate the benefits from this
practice for the welfare and happiness of others
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello again everyone
what's on my mind this morning is the
interesting fact that the in the language of the buddha
the word for grasping sometimes is translated as clinging the
word for grasping is also the same word used for the fuel
for grasping so the word is
and it's um upa and a
and it's um it can mean the fuel for a fire
what on what fire burns and it could also mean grasping and clinging
and there's a way in which grasping something being clinging being attached
is the fuel for more grasping and so if i'm allowed to do this example
of you know if i keep my hand open
that's fine but if i make a loose fist with my hand
now something exists that didn't exist before when the hand was open now there exists a fist
and now it's possible to become attached to the fist and
and so i might hold on to it tighter clenched a little bit more tightly with my hand
and if i go around with my clenched hand for a long time the it starts to hurt and be uncomfortable
and one response i might have to that discomfort is to clench even more to tighten up oh
this is not field doesn't feel good and so there's a progressive way in which i start with something which
doesn't exist i create something which is new a grasping of the hand
that's uncomfortable or that's something that i'm attached to and progressively i
each step along the way i'm grasping to what is grasped
the very thing that i'm grasping to is the source for grasping even more
and so there's a cycle then of attachment if we see attachment
is the fuel for more attachment and that that cycle cannot be broken
if we keep doing more attachment to keep grasping even more
and so this uh you can see this sometimes in the thinking mind where there's a drive a push to think a
preoccupation a strength we could say an attachment to grasping to thoughts to ideas to trying to figure
things out to make plans to make ourselves safe you know just swirling around
reviewing the past what did it you know repeating the same conversation with someone over and over again
and there's a kind of a drive a pressure to think and that pressure
is the very source for having more pressure
grasping to certain ideas trying to accomplish something with our thoughts is on can become uncomfortable
that discomfort our system reacts to wants to find more comfort and
if it thinks that comfort is found through thinking then the very
this very the very thing that's causing the discomfort is what we'll give ourselves over to
more to try to figure out even more so it becomes a kind of cyclic cyclic
where uh we are attached to something we're cling to something we grasp at
something and um uh and
that sense of motion sits in motion or sets the ground the foundation for
doing more of the same and so this thing of doing more of the same that reinforces the same over and
over again uh when it when they were doing something which is unhealthy and
stressful for ourselves uh is not you know a sooner or later we
have to realize this is not working and for some people they don't discover that for decades
it's uh not an easy thing to discover that the very approach we have to help make
ourselves safe or get what we want or or
you know is not is the very source from which is making us unsafe making us stressful
and so grasping is the fuel for more grasping attachment
is the fuel for more attachment so the at some point we have to step out
of this cyclic movement we have to kind of be willing to somehow realize oh that's not the way anymore
and so in meditation at some point it becomes a
hopefully a clear idea a clearer sense you know and for me to continue thinking this way
it just doesn't work this this kind of thinking is i'm caught in a labyrinth a self-fulfilling
perpetual motion labyrinth that just keeps fueling itself
and um i'm going to stop investing in it i'm going to stop
giving myself over to it i think it's time to step away
and and we step away into awareness into the mindfulness that
the mindfulness is not the attachment the mindfulness of the attachment is a
way of stepping away we can step away into our body
and begin to relax our body the tension the stress of grasping
is often expressed or found in tension in our body and so if we can
relax the body reduce the tension of the body it goes a
long way in helping us relax the tension in the mind sometimes the tension we have in our
mind we don't have we can't find our way to see well where do i relax relax where do
i let go how do i stop this it's really hard sometimes when we see
it just as a mental thing beginning to relax the body quiet the
body and maybe use mindfulness or breathing or some kind of meditation to begin um
calming thinking mind and this progressive calming and quieting at the body of the mind
releasing attention at some point we get to the point where it seems oh you know
i can just not think anymore this way i don't have to be caught in this discursive thinking say okay enough
and then maybe for a few moments you can get quiet for a few moments you can have this mental peace and quiet and then you can
focus more on the breathing and then um and then so just as grasping
is a fuel for more grasping at some point the equation switches over
that that peace is the fuel for more peace
calm is the fuel for more calm clarity is the food for more clarity
and um and uh you can feel that so if i open my hand
and feel how nice it is to have an open hand it's relaxed and open and at ease
then that is feeling that ease is support for having more ease when i
do it i can find myself feel the ease of my hand i feel my shoulders release a little bit
and and i value that and so i stay close to that feeling of
ease and so the slightest little movement to tighten up i notice oh wait a minute
the peace that's there that's the way forward and so i relax my hand
so to begin understanding this principle can be very helpful
um that to
to be willing to see that grasping is the fuel for more grasping
and letting go of that grasping is the way towards peace
but it's not as linear way to peace sometimes while we were grasping is to
protect ourselves or get away from or cope with difficulties in our life strong emotions
difficult emotions that we might have and and so
that we have to sometimes go through that and really feel what's going on so the example i gave of grasping the
hand if i do a light grasp clenching of the hand and then that feels uncomfortable i'm
trying to get away from that discomfort and i clench even more as i relax the hand i might feel that
initial layer where it was uncomfortable and it might feel very very uncomfortable i'm not i don't like being
there and and then i clench even more so we have to learn to be willing to go
through this feeling of discomfort as we do this layer releasing the layers of
grasping that we have until we come to the place where peace
is uh the fuel for more peace clarity is the full for
fuel for more clarity so thank you
for all very much for all this and um we'll continue tomorrow and um
maybe by tomorrow or next day we'll have a sense of the theme for the week um today i'm just kind of didn't didn't
come up with a feed theme for this week so i just uh kind of
coming along as we coming coming along as we go today this week next week
there will be a theme and uh and that will start the
the the series on the four foundations of mindfulness on the based on the sati patana sutra the
discourse on the on the on on mindfulness to the buddha taught
it'll be comparable to them how we did anapanasati at the beginning of last year the mindfulness of
breathing but it will go through it systematically over a few weeks
so so this week maybe no theme yet thank you all very much