okay so it's 9 25 here or 25 after the hour
and that is our unusual start time for this sunday morning or evening sit
so let's go ahead and begin with the sit
so finding a posture that's upright
relaxed settling into your seat
if you're comfortable doing so you can close your eyes
just let the eyes gently be soft
and as we bring the attention inward to our inner experience of the body
first we may detect the sense of sitting we're sitting in
perhaps an upright posture or perhaps you're lying down that's fine too
so just feeling the overall posture of the body
maybe feeling the places where your body is touching what it's resting on so your seat against the
cushion your feet against the floor
just feeling those contact points and finding some balance so that the
body is sitting with relatively little effort
if you're sitting upright you can even rock back and forth a little bit or forward and back a little bit
just to find a balanced posture
just softening so that you're not bracing against that contact point
letting it support you
paying a little bit of attention to the posture right when we sit down is a way of
supporting not only the body but also the mind and meditation
we're more stable and relaxed in the body that can be true in the mind too
so then it can also help to soften a bit as we settle in
so softening the muscles of the face
softening the eyes that tends to get a little tight when
we're looking at a screen
softening the shoulders
letting them drop down a bit maybe imagining the shoulder blades
sliding down the back
bringing some ease to the area of the chest
the arms the hands
softening the belly area
also the muscles of the low back
just allowing that whole torso area to be supported by the straightness of
the spine and letting everything else hang off of
that and then down through the legs
letting the knees and the ankles and the feet
be soft open
allowing the attention to tune in to the natural sensations of
breathing however your breathing now is fine
just noticing how that is
maybe on the out breath inviting a bit more softening a bit more ease
letting the natural release of the out breath carry away any additional tension
that's willing to release
but if any tension seems to be remaining in the body that's fine however the body
is right now is fine just include that
we may have various things happening in our mind and heart also there may be
emotions present or memories of something that happened
just recently in the day we may have various thoughts in the mind
plans
these are okay mindfulness is meant to be inclusive
so we don't need anything to go away right away
but mindfulness is also not entangled with experience
so we have some sense that these things are allowed to be there to come and go
but we're not involved deeply in them during meditation
there's a part of the mind that is independent of the comings and goings of sensation
and thought and seeing if you can connect with that
part of the mind that is present but not entangled
uh
if we find that we have become caught up in something in the body or mind
when we notice that we're already present again
so we're just gently connecting in again with the part of the mind that is present but not entangled allowing experience to
flow on in awareness
you
[Music] um
we may begin to notice certain qualities of mind that get in the way
of being present but independent of experience
if we want something to be there
or if we don't want something to be there both of these are entanglements
actually there's a certain
attitude toward experience that is the most useful
sometimes it's called receptive
sometimes even kind
but a certain stance or attitude toward what is arising in passing
it helps the mind to be present but not
entangled sometimes just a small adjustment is [Music]
helpful and when the mind does get caught it's
helpful to smile smile with the tendency to
get entangled
you
as we continue to abide with presence and non-entanglement
we may begin to get a sense that mindfulness itself is something of a
balancer in the mind simply being mindful of how
the mind is how the body is there can be adjustments
a simple knowing of what needs to be adjusted slightly in order to stay present
not really something we need to do but just a sense of how to stay balanced
the way we can stay balanced on a bicycle without consciously thinking about it
once we have some familiarity with [Music]
writing
uh
you
um and in the last few minutes of this
meditation [Music] we may open up a bit
perhaps reflect use this kind of gentle presence
without entanglement could this be useful in our daily life
interactions also
we may notice that
being unentangled is actually creating the space for us
to be more responsive be more caring
in that space love and compassion could come in
more easily than if we were wrapped up in what was going on
sometimes we hear the message that
carrying or showing concern
must involve entanglement and anxiety and worry
to show that we care
but maybe through our meditation we can discover a dimension of caring
that comes from this strength of heart
of unentangled knowing
so it may be that what we've been practicing is directly serving the other people in our
lives maybe even beyond two people that we
don't know
so we hope that our gentle receptive presence
we wish that that brings some ease and peace to those around us
and invites stronger presence of love and compassion in our lives
here and beyond
may it be so
[Music]
so here in the united states
today is called independence day and it's interesting to me
that what we celebrate is not actually the day that we did become
independent but the day that we intended to become independent
by declaring that that was that was our aim and um so there's something special
about um directing ourselves toward an aspiration so maybe we can all
celebrate our intentions to be free to be caring [Music]
long before they come about necessarily
this idea of of independence can be a little bit complex um
most of us would like to have certain kinds of choice and agency
and determination of our own life but we also like connection
interdependence participating in things that are larger than ourselves
and of course in the buddhist teachings
we we know that there isn't such a thing as an independent separate
being that's considered an insight that we have but at the same time the buddha did talk
about a certain kind of independence and the discourses there is this idea of
being independent in the dhamma or independent in the dharma
and this is actually quite an important idea in the in the suttas in the teachings
and it's what i would like to talk about today so let's unpack this term a little bit
so as i said it's not that we are going to be independent you know as an individual and it isn't
considered a deep insight to understand that really completely that we are not a
separate entity operating in a separate world
so instead this kind of independence that the buddha was talking about
it refers to a very positive transition that people go through whereby
the dharma becomes internalized it becomes embedded in the heart to a degree
that the path becomes self-sustaining from the inside if you will so being independent is said
to be one of the qualities of a person who has entered the stream of dhamma
so they've maybe understood something about how the path works
and it's um it's very satisfying this kind of independence is said to be
a reliable form of safety that we can have on the path when the path has become somewhat
internalized so i want to talk today about kind of a cluster of qualities
that are associated with entering the stream and becoming independent in the dhamma
but it's important to know that all of the qualities that we'll talk about today
develop somewhat continuously starting from the very beginning of practice
so what i say is relevant for everyone who's doing this practice
and also the qualities that i'm going to bring forth today are things that we can emulate always
before they become fully internalized we always we're always aspiring towards certain
qualities that i'll talk about today
so maybe we could see this as kind of a general gathering up of the changes that are
happening in our mind and heart as we walk the path what is happening in the mind and the
heart as we do this practice so i'll talk about three different areas
there are some things that are gained along the path and there are some things that are lost
along the path and we also come to see differently
come to see differently along the path and then those three kind of come
together to add up to being independent in the dhamma
it's also true that these three areas are intertwined and mutually supportive so you'll see
how each one kind of contains the others
so beginning with what is gained um the first thing that it said that we
gain with this entering of the stream is confirmed confidence
that's a that's a translation of a term that means more literally confidence based on knowledge so
in particular it refers to confidence in the buddha the dhamma and the sangha
so the three quality items that we take refuge in maybe early in the practice and so
um it really amounts to a very deep form of trust that we develop along the path and again
this is kind of incremental it might be that some of you have taken refuge in
the buddha dharma and sangha at some point and that's kind of a an initial offering of the heart to these
beautiful qualities these beautiful things that we feel are somehow reliable for us
and that's maybe it's nice to know that that confidence or trust or
placing of the heart just continues to deepen all along the path
one way that this plays out in terms of our actual way of being in the world is that
we will get less upset about the vagaries of life so the more trust and confirmed
confidence or confidence based on knowledge that we have about how the path works and what's
really reliable the less we need to
get thrown off by the natural changes that happen in life the surprises that
continue to happen all along the path we know that we can't know what will happen next
in our life but we have trust that if we stay with the path that'll be the best we can do i've had
times when things were a little wild in my life and
i could just remember okay but i know i have a path if i just stay present with this bring
forth the best qualities that i can that'll be the best it can unfold
so we have something to orient around given the changes of life so one thing that we gain more and more
is this confirmed confidence confidence based on knowledge
and then the second thing that's noted to be gained along the path
is excellent ethics so people who live in the stream of dhamma
are said to possess the virtues dear to the noble ones unbroken
untorn unblemished unmodeled freeing praised by the wise
ungrasped leading to concentration that alone is a very interesting list
but it um it points toward the internalization of ethical conduct as just a natural way
of being and also that it supports the path in that two of the qualities listed were
freeing and leading to concentration so we we can see that ethics is just a natural
support for walking the path and it deepens and it continues to deepen all along our
our practice so then another thing that is gained is
generosity and the sutas use such phrases as
a person walking the path delights in giving and sharing
and this is a natural kind of non-possessiveness that comes about through practice
and it again is something that deepens maybe from day one we've started to become a little bit
more generous as we uh sit with our own mind our own
body as we start to be more mindful in life and it just goes deeper and
deeper so this is something we can look forward to gaining more of this beautiful quality
and then because it's named in the teachings i'll mention that another quality gained is
fearlessness concerning one's death so that's interesting
i said we become less and less governed by that subterranean
existential anxiety that we can have about the possibility of our own death
so it might be that fearlessness about death is something like gaining that is something like losing
our fear of death so gains and losses maybe go together so
shift then to what is some of the things that are lost along the path you know what are what
are we freed from what do we let go of of course we let go of many many things
along the path of practice but there are three especially important
ones that are singled out as being part of this process of becoming
independent in the dhamma and these three are part of a larger list called the
ten fetters better is a little bit of an unusual word so
a fetter is a a bond or a restriction and they're said to be ten of them but
the um the first three are the ones that are really
relevant in this case and the first one you know maybe is a little hard to
describe sometimes but it's it's often translated as
doctrine of self so we lose having a doctrine of self the word literally
means existing body view sakaya ditty
but you know put into more common language it really just means a firm belief in an unchanging
self or entity some kind of a permanent self or permanent inherent
qualities and this is you know this is profound of course to deeply investigate this
but i don't think we need to get really wrapped up in it um it's it's
something that begins quite soon as we start practicing in that most people can see that as they
practice meditation and mindfulness there's a way that they become
lighter somehow now once we start practicing there's
fairly soon we become less burdened by restrictive ideas of who we need to be
we become more able for example when we're in a conversation with our partner
to see their point of view to take a pause before we react to
maybe give up our you know something we would have grasped at
before and be willing to see things from their point of view all of these are
our small ways that we're letting go of things that we had identified with before
aspects of our self that we were holding on to as our doctrine of who i am and who i
need to be so essentially what we're losing is some rigidity
we're losing some rigidity along the path and in particular rigidity around
ourselves so i think this is fairly something we can connect with right away
and then you know let the let the deeper parts of it unfold as they do
and then the second main thing that we lose or let go of one of the other
fetters is doubt and this refers specifically
to doubt in the buddha's teachings and the path to liberation it takes a lot of forms this doubt can
be outright disbelief it can be a lack of confidence in our ability to walk the
path or it can be a kind of a subtle uncertainty about what is referred to
in the path of liberation and so abandoning this fetter or releasing it
is essentially just the counterpart to gaining confirmed confidence in the
buddha dhamma and sangha so we see as we walk the path and we get clearer on
what's going on we have less and less doubt about the direction that we're going
you know even if we can't know as i said before what's going to happen next in our life
we have no doubt that the practice and the path will be supportive
in meeting whatever comes along and again we can just let that doubt
slowly wither away you know to the point where the practice becomes internalized and we
essentially have no doubt about the buddha the dharma and the sangha
in our life and then the third main thing that we
let go of in the process of becoming independent of the dhamma is said to be attachment to precepts
and religious practices that's how it's translated usually so that first word is
important we're losing our attachment to these things are grasping of them essentially of
course a person would not stop following the precepts remember that one of the qualities gained
was excellent ethics excellent virtue and respect for ethical conduct so
it's not that that really changes but the attachment or the grasping and we
don't believe that the precepts alone are sufficient for awakening
or that they amount to the only thing that we're striving for on the path and the same is true for
various kinds of religious practices that we would undertake rituals or devotional practices
these can of course still be done in fact might be done even more deeply as we walk the path but
we don't have the attachment to them that they alone are what brings about liberation
or that they alone are the point of what we're doing so they're they're used properly as
skillful means so it's interesting if we step back and
reflect on these three fetters the the doctrine of self the doubt
and the attachment to precepts and religious practices all of those are fetters that are
related to our understanding so they have to do with how we see things how we
relate to things how we view things how we imbue things with meaning and so entering this entering the stream
of dom means releasing some of our key misunderstandings that inhibit walking
the path and that's essentially what these three fetters are they're misunderstandings
that we walk around with and that we don't maybe you don't even realize are
inhibiting our ability to walk the path and so as we release them we become freer and we feel that we are
entering into this this stream it's important maybe to
say at this point that we're not talking about really an intellectual understanding you know i'm
using words and explaining things and talking through things and that's important as we listen to the dharma and take it
in but eventually what we find is our understanding is a direct experience
it's a an experience that goes deeper than just our cognitive understanding of things
being able to repeat lists and so forth so we we take it in in this verbal form
but you know please let it enter into your being into your heart so that it becomes a deeper
understanding so then that leads naturally into the
third area that i wanted to talk about which is that the understanding aspect of independence
in the dharma is that we start to see things differently we start to see
in less habitual ways than we did at the beginning of the path
this is what's meant by the term right view also translated as wise view or maybe
appropriate view it's not really a right and wrong kind of thing it's something that we slowly
move into the way that we see gets clearer and clearer as we practice
and i think this is also something that nearly everyone has experienced no matter how new or
old in practice you are so we start to see as soon as we have
mindfulness we start to see more clearly what's going on in our body and our mind
and so you know all along the path our vision is is getting clearer
but in the context we're talking about today the particular understanding that we're
that we're talking about is some kind of experiential understanding of what are called the four noble truths
and these these pertain to a certain quality of experience called dukkha which is could be translated as
unsatisfactoriness it's of course often translated as suffering which
might not capture all the aspects of dukkha sometimes i just think of it as offness
you know the sense that it's hard to get everything aligned all at once and keep it that way and
there's often a feeling like that's not quite right that's not quite working that of course is something that we made
that we're generating in our own mind but this quality of dukkha the buddha identified as very important to
look at so these four noble truths are to know that there there is dukkha in life to know
that it arises in dependence on craving and clinging there's some
wanting that is present if we're feeling dukkha or unsatisfactoriness
or suffering and then to know also that it can end and to know that there's a path
to ending it so those are the
sort of a concise statement of the four truths but what this means practically is that the mind begins to orient
towards seeing dukkha seeing the clinging and craving that accompanies it
seeing its release and seeing the path to releasing it and that doesn't mean that in every
moment we have to rush to try to figure out what all those things are it's more that we just have an
orientation toward where's the difficulty the suffering the tension [Music]
and where is the release of that how might that be released so
this is sort of an orientation to the mind and maybe a second important aspect of
understanding that all i'll mention because it's so prominent in this quality of entering the stream
is that we start to have genuine uh wisdom around arising and ceasing
so there's a statement in the suttas that people often say when they're declaring their
independence and what they say is all that is of a nature to arise is
also of a nature to cease so i understand people understand that
everything comes and goes literally everything and you know how how would somebody know
that for sure well it could be that the person has experienced something
ceasing at a deep enough level that it makes an impression on their understanding so a lot follows from that
simple statement everything that is of a nature to arise there's also a nature to cease
it can get a little abstract sounding we're talking about truths and things like that so it's maybe also
important to know that as we practice our understanding of truth actually becomes less and less
abstract so we start to see that dukkha and the end of dukkha are about this
particular experience happening right now just recently i was traveling on an
airplane for the first time in a year and a half and i got delayed at my stopover and had to spend a few
extra hours and so my mind i noticed it kind of veered toward thinking that the unpleasantness
i was experiencing was going to end when i finally got home but then
you know it's like okay looking into the future when is this going to be over but then something shifted and i
realized that the duka was the suffering that was happening at that exact moment
you know my impatience my irritation with bling travel has not changed in a year
and a half and it was being added by my mind and so i was actually
able to relax right there in the crowded airport it was still unpleasant but i wasn't
suffering so there's a way in which these four noble truths become
about this moment you know it's not that there is dukkha it's that this is duka or not or this is
the end of duka happening right here so we you know we get brought into the
present moment really through this practice so happily this turns out to be a much more
satisfying way of seeing in our usual way you know to see immediately what's happening in this
present moment how it might be released into freedom
how it might this experience itself might be the basis for liberation brings a form of joy to have that
accessible right there in this exact moment of experience the simple joy of being present
with being in touch with what's happening now and the joy of having a wise orientation
so this um this kind of present moment wisdom that starts to come in pretty
pretty quickly and then grows gets deeper and deeper it provides a subtle but important
support for walking the path in our life you know it's going to support us all along the path so seeing accurately
is so important so we have that some good qualities are gained some
restrictions are lost fall away and we see more clearly
so all of that adds up to a kind of robustness of heart or inner
strength that is what the buddha called independence independent in the dharma when it
becomes internalized and this is what we're working toward or working too deep in in
our practice so i want to consider this
stock phrase that is said about this transformation of understanding and it's said about a lay follower named
dupali so lest you think this sounds impossible upali was an active community member
a busy householder um who was doing a lot of things in the
world but nonetheless he listened to the dharma and
add a realization and then the buddha says about him upali saw the dhamma attained the dhamma
fathomed the dhamma he crossed beyond doubt did away with perplexity gained
intrepidity and became independent of others in the teacher's dispensation
so this path is about knowing for ourselves it's about knowing for ourselves what
the teachings are referring to and being able to embody them in certain ways that's what
it means to become independent in the dhamma and it benefits everyone around us really
so there is another teaching that mentions a few things that are sort
of specific actions that would be done by a person who is independent in the dhamma and i think that some of
them are interesting i'll just name a few so a person like this will instinctively
draw back from committing ethical violations and they will immediately report any that they have
committed you know they will feel uncomfortable if they know that they have lied a
little bit or um maybe accidentally taken something that wasn't theirs
they will feel so uncomfortable about that that they will go and find the person that they need to
talk to about that it's a very beautiful quality of heart that comes with this excellent ethics
and of course very useful for relational life also
also a person who's independent in the dhamma will consider practice to be of primary importance in their life
there is a way in which they can't become so busy and over committed that they're no
longer able to practice because that will be too important to them also a very beautiful quality and also such a
person pays close attention to dharma teachings listening eagerly
said that this person will feel inspired and confident and joyful when the dharma is being taught
and they will know that their mind cannot be obsessed to so great a degree that they could not
see things as they are i like that one in particular so there's a sort of a
non-obsession that comes about through being independent in the dharma it's not that the mind never gets caught
up in things um or you know temporarily obsessed but it that gets greatly reduced and essentially that
gives us this space to become more flexible so you might consider if you have these
ways of being or if there are ways of bringing in more of these ways of being you know being clear about our ethics
making practice more primarily important in life
listening to the dharma with a heart of joy really taking it in and feeling the goodness of it and also
um taking care that our mind is not so obsessed with things um such that we would not be
able to see things clearly that's a little bit what we did in the meditation just practice the
non-entanglement of the mind so independence is freedom
um but it's not freedom to do what we want it's you know just do whatever we want it's it's a sort of a deeper and more
profound kind of freedom you know it's the that we're free to be responsive without
getting entangled in self-interest or in our own universities
free of our past habits such as strong desire and aversion
these habits that limit being wise and connected in the moment
also freedom to see broadly to see a variety of perspectives
and to see beyond our previously limited view of things to have a flexible viewpoint on the
world and free to trust the unfolding of life
in all of its glory and all of its pain and all of its triumph in all of its reality so this is a
transformation of heart that we're doing it's a slow change toward having
less and less impedance and suffering in our heart and more and more
freedom and flexibility and responsiveness in our life so i want to end with a poem
maybe maybe speaks to this the wine in the glass remembers the long
days in darkness how it couldn't breathe how it lost its
scent of grape and became more grapefruit more green pepper more grass
how it lost its harsh taste lost its astringents and became rounder more smooth
more wine i too am changing in these long days
i too am converting what i've known into what i will be
i too am becoming something i almost don't recognize heady with transformation yet tethered
by memory to what it was like to feel trapped what it was like to steep in that
darkness to have to learn to trust whatever came next
so wishing you all well on this independent
stay and may the dhamma embed itself deeply
in your heart and bring you freedom in life thank you