so hello to everyone from redwood city here at the inside meditation center
and uh i would like to uh do this meditation beginning of this
meditation a little bit differently than usual and in that i would like to um
do a little guided imagery to begin using an analogy that i very i've used many times for some of
you and i'm very fond of and uh um
just to take a couple of minutes if you would just you know maybe you can be comfortable if you'd like maybe in meditation posture
and close your eyes and and maybe just to settle in just breathe
a few moments maybe breathe deeply a few moments relax your body
settle in a bit
and then to imagine yourself sitting
against the trunk of a tree maybe or some other comfortable place next to
a river and perhaps you've
have a day off maybe you've gone for a nice walk there's nothing you need to do and
things are taken care of well enough in your life that you just sit there in a
comfortable afternoon weather and maybe in the shade or
and uh watch the river watch the current and the flow of the
water the movements of little wavelets
you're watching the flow and ongoing and it's in some ways ever changing
and forever changing a constant constancy of inconstancy change the flow
sometimes some leaves are floating on the river and float down along
sometimes the twig sometimes a boat
sometimes a duck floats down the river
and you're just observing gazing at this just taking everything in but not really
studying anything not staring at anything just relaxed and
present and you let your thoughts do what they do there's no censoring yourself
but there's also no big involvement with your thoughts and particular interest in them and because
everything feels good and easy relaxed just as nice just nice to be
here gazing at the river
and this idea of just sitting observing watching gazing
gently relaxedly at some point in meditation
when we're established well enough
in the present moment we've kind of done what needs to be done
and we can just sit back and allow the practice to unfold
by by observing watching allowing
ourselves to be aware of all the changing phenomena in our
body the river of life that is a constantly
shifting and changing panorama of sensations
perceptions thoughts feelings even if something stays for a while
you might try um
to just stay and watching the flow
and one of the places to do that is in your breathing
the breathing there is kind of like a
kind of like in in the way the river is it's a constant
flow of inconstancy in that each in-breath comes and goes
flowing into the out breath
there's a beginning of the in-breath middle and an end
the beginning middle and end of the exhale
and all that can be felt as sensations in the body so it's not so much
observing the breath as it is observing
the kaleidoscope of changing sensations in your body as you breathe
settling back relaxing as if you're leaning against a tree
watching a river observing
how the sensations are breathing
go on and on they arise and they pass
some of them spark into existence for a moment and then vanish
like a little wavelet on a river that is there for a moment and then
returns to the river
and to settle further into this watching breathing
take a few moments to relax your body more softening all over
as if you're relaxing the whole body in towards the breathing
relaxing so that the body becomes a soft foundation
for a soft
river of changing sensations
and the more relaxed the body is the more the body's
flows and changes and things come and go arise and pass
the more tense we are we have the illusion of things being tight and constant continuous
relaxing softening the body settling in
and then again
gazing kindly on your breathing
being sensitive to the aspects of breathing that are
constantly changing the sensations of breath that come and go that one morphs into
the other
relaxing the mind the more relaxed the mind is the more it
can be part of the flow of the river
the more tense the mind is the more it tends to produce the illusion of
constancy of something of being unchanging
softening the thinking mind resting in the mind's ability
to observe to perceive to sense experience
centered on your breathing all around it is also change
the changing fluxing sensations of your body
the changing experiences that come into awareness
sometimes this sometimes that
wherever there is change changing sensations experience
relax with it open with it
allow it as if you're allowing it
to relax you open you further
as if this anything that changes that comes and goes
freeze the mind further as the mind lets it pass through
so
change is an attribute of the present moment
the present moment itself is constantly changing
in more ways than we usually notice
settle back and observe how it is that the present moment is a
constantly shifting and changing phenomena represented most by the breathing
the body's experience of change as you breathe
relax into the river of change
float on all the changing aspects of the present moment
sometimes we're resting in the change observing it
and sometimes we're swept away in it our thoughts are also always changing
even if even if the same theme persists and sometimes we get carried away in the
flood of thoughts
and the idea is to come back to the
to on the ground of the body and from there observe the change
in the present
sitting quietly observing change
gaze upon all things kindly
to the best of your ability in a simple maybe even
unremarkable way gaze upon all things kindly
and the ability to do so has a lot to do with the ability to be
confident in resting in awareness
feeling safe to rest here in awareness
in this print from the safety of being aware
to gaze upon all things kindly
to gaze upon all change in a compassionate way
those who understand how things are constantly changing
are less surprised that things go and things come that
things change and being less surprised
there is more space to be kind
to have good will and generosity and compassion for this world of ours
may it be that our meditation practice together
allows us to enter into the world with gift bestowing hands
enter into the world
with a orientation that's kind and supportive and friendly
compassionate we have these beautiful qualities of
heart that can flow more easily the more we
rest in change may all beings
be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings
be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be
free
uh
as i talked about yesterday the fourth tetrad the fourth
and final group of four practices or steps to
mindfulness of breathing involve observing
and to settle back and observe our experience and part of a big part of the ability to
observe what's being implied here is not to be assertive or not to be
doing things interpreting changing fixing escaping
our experience but learning have the stability and the ease and the strength of
awareness to settle back and just really see clearly what is happening here
to observe clearly the moment and and when we don't overlay
our ideas and our concepts what we see is change we see things are much
are changing all the time and um it doesn't take a lot to appreciate i
think that even aside from any ways in which we think things are unchanging
that moment by moment there's always change that the day changes the lighting
changes slowly over time maybe sometimes imperceptible if you're in a
city the sounds of the city are constantly changing and
the sensations of your body are changing through the day and you can watch the changes as
we get hungry and we eat and we don't feel hungry we feel uncomfortable we we engage our body in different ways
different muscles are used at different times and therefore different sensations come into play
there's a constantly shifting changing landscape of where attention focuses and what it
takes in and even things that don't necessarily change themselves
what's changing constantly is how we're perceiving it how we see it if i look at the wall
that's opposite me here that the natural thing when i'm relaxed
is to have my eyes kind of not fixate on a spot but just kind of roam around and even
though the wall is not changing what's changing is the the where my left
where my eyes land on or the flowing of this of perception of the wall so whether
it's something that's constantly shifting like a river flowing and we're watching it
or whether or it's the the act of perception is constantly shifting and moving and
going around um what we experience is a constantly shifting landscape of
change and it turns out that this is central to uh the deeper insights
of buddhist meditation so in the fourth step of anapanasati
the fourth tetrad it begins when trains experience
observing in in constancy i breathe in
one trains ex observing in constancy
i breathe out and um so in constancy here is one of the words
for change and and things uh and so here is to see
really begin appreciating and seeing the depth of how things are changing all the time
and one of the reasons why buddhism put such a strong emphasis on being present in having a present
moment attention is that that's where change happens that uh if we're thinking about the past
the past in certain kind of way is not changing anymore except in how we remember it perhaps the
futures maybe it doesn't really exist to change it's just kind of a projection of our imagination
and um and the the um but in the present moments where
we see the change it's kind of like where that's where the river flows by of change and all that
and everything is changing is according to the buddha everything is inconstant and
this is not necessarily obvious in ordinary consciousness and ordinary ways of being but but it's really
central to what happens in deeper and deeper meditation in meditation itself
where we're kind of no longer paying attention to the wall that's in the opposite side of the room or a mountain and saying well the mountain is not
changing and then we have to use our logic and say well it's slowly being worn down and eroding
but in meditation with the eyes closed sitting here that as we begin to
really open up to the present moment experience and really feel it sense it experience it observe it
what we experience in that kind of context of meditation is a constantly shifting of flow of
phenomenon it's experienced after developing strong stability and
part of the paradox is that in meditation the more
still the more stable the mind is the more the mind observes change and
impermanence the more unstable the mind is the more scattered and preoccupied the mind is
the more unsettled the more we tend to impute permanence the more we tend to
get caught up in our ideas and thoughts and stories which often carry with them a feeling of
things are constant or permanent this is the way things are and um and i've certainly have fallen
into the delusion of permanence without you know it being kind of unconsciously
even and if i think about it of course i don't believe what i'm feeling
but the way i'm acting sometimes since i remember one day many years ago having a difficult day
with my child and and my wife and i were kind of like
hovering over him and trying to manage with this highly spirited child
and and then my wife just looked up at me and said we're having one of those kinds of days
and as soon as she said that then i realized that i was kind of emotionally operating as if this is it
we're always going to be this way it's not going to change of course i if i thought about it i wouldn't have
been that way unknown that to thought that but the emotional feeling of it was of perm this
is it and as soon as you said that we're having one of those kinds of days then i relaxed and like you know okay
this is it's the manifestation of the moment this is how it is now and it will change it'll be we'll have a
different day tomorrow and something so this imputing of permanence even
or emotional feeling like this is it interferes with our ability to step back
and benefit from the wisdom of change and the wisdom of how things move and constantly shifting and this is one of
the key insights of the buddha it doesn't say it this particular way
but this is my interpretation that things are always changing
and change is not random change happens because of the conditions
that precede what's happening now that can as conditions shift and changes
the direction of change how things change unfolds accordingly that um that uh
generally we don't have rain without clouds the clouds are the condition for the changing weather of rain happening
and and so when when i feel cold
then perhaps uh it's harder to get sometimes harder for me to get concentrated when i meditate i've
meditated sometimes in very cold weather and i haven't really you know the conditions were not there
for me to get settled and calm there was still change happening and things were being and all kinds of
different ways but it wasn't one that supported becoming concentrated and there are
times when the weather has been comfortable or been bundled up nicely and my body is not you know coping with
you know cold and shivering that that i have different conditions of
being cozy and settled and it's easier than to the conditions are there
to allow the changing of into a concentrated state of meditation
so depending on the conditions that are present change go and go in different directions
and the key one that uh really central to the buddhist teachings is that things can go either in a
helpful direction an unhelpful direction in a wholesome nourishing direction or an un helpful unnourishing direction
and the and so we're a little bit responsible for putting the conditions
in place to support the directionality of change
we can't control it absolutely we can't make things be a certain way but we can
put the conditions in place to support a tendency in healthy directions beneficial ways
and and so so a deep appreciation of change
shows us that also things are malleable things are changeable because they're always changing
and we have a little role to play in the direction of that change if we're
floating in the river down a current in the river we understand that you know we're being
carried by the flowing change of the river but we also understand
that that which part of the current we're in how we avoid the eddies how we avoid the
parts of the current that takes us up against the shore and we can gently kind of guide ourselves
in that river in a way that keeps us in the central current and we keep flowing down the river and
the um so being attuned
to change is part of this uh uh 13th step of the 16 steps of
mindfulness a 12 step 12 13 13 step of mindfulness of breathing
and um the um and it's to um observe
in the word is inconstancy and i'll talk more about that tomorrow
but it's a part of this family of concepts that relate to change things
becoming different and and impermanence
so so to observe in constancy observe change
and to find some degree of freedom in the same kind of freedom that we
would have if we're floating in the river there's a freedom and being carried and
but then we're also careful about what current we go in how we're where we're floating the river
maybe even which river we're floating in and um so this might be the theme for
this next 24 hours for you is to notice change
and notice how change arises changes in ways depending on conditions
and how and also how your role and where you find yourself and your change your
relationship to change and how you relate to that change
puts you on different currents if you're resisting change or if you're fighting change or if you're
attached to a change that puts you in a different river than one that is with change in an open
relaxed way so so there's different words different
concepts different ways of kind of talking about the same thing the buddha used different words and now
for now i'm using the word inconstancy and and are focusing mostly on change and
tomorrow we'll pick up this idea of inconstancy more directly in
a word that is in palis often or in english is often translated
as impermanence but that we'll see tomorrow that inconstancy um
might be a better translation so um so thank you all
very much and i look forward to tomorrow