um welcome everyone i'm joining you
from south africa my name is nolita to be specific i'm joining you from
johannesburg and it is evening here
so good morning good day good evening wherever you're joining us from
i really appreciate your presence here gives me an opportunity to
reflect on this practice and these teachings
aimed for our liberation
so we're starting with a guided practice so you can find
the posture that best supports you
just taking your time to find that posture
the intention is to be a lot awake and yet relaxed
bringing the attention to the body noticing how the body is welcoming this
body as it is
noticing the solidity of the body on the chair the cushion
spine is straight neck is long
the head is balanced at the top of the neck it's helpful
to tilt your chin towards the chest
it allows for an opening where the top of the neck meets with the
skull that allows for easy flow of energy
the hands rest the left
if you move your lower back just a little bit towards the belly
you will notice the lifting of the upper body
opening of the chest area
and shoulders easily relax without movement of the lower back
moving towards the belly
softening the face dropping the jaw
allows for release of tension enhancing a sense of relaxation
aware of the whole body release the body weight into the chill
the cushion and noticing the pressure
where the butt meets with the chair of the cushion
if you are on a chair notice the sensations in the soles of your feet
where your feet meet with earth
noticing the movement of the breath
resting your attention with the breath
taking your time to find a good posture
a bright and yet relaxed a way can alert
can be helpful at the beginning of your seating to take a few long deep breaths in
we're allowing the breath to return to its normal rhythm
we will use the breath as a place of anchoring attention
whenever the mind goes away gets lost in thought
when we're not as that we bring back the attention to rest on the breathing
noticing where the breath is most felt
could be other nostrils as you breathe in the coolness of the air
as you breathe out warm air
is experienced
or it could be with the expansion of the chest
and the contraction of the chest as you breathe in
and breathing out oh it's the rise and the fall of the
belly just take your time and see
of those three places where is breath most experienced
then let your attention rest away
mind will go away or to the future
we don't make a problem out of that this practice is about returning
bring back the attention to the body
resting their tension and the breathing
can be helpful to make a soft mental
note that goes breathing in
breathing out breathing in
printing out
as the mind settles here with a breath you can release
the mental motive
we continue to up the rest of this setting to bring the mind
back allow the mind to rest the breathing
noticing how the breath is
maybe long maybe short
maybe smooth it is staggered
deep shadow whichever way it is
that's just fine
as the mind settles
we open our awareness
to any predominant experience that is there
sounds maybe sensations
quotes and notice
what is here
one can always return the attention to rest the breathing
in a moment i'm going to add another dimension
to this kind of practice
where we reflect on the theme of good will
generosity
aim is enhancement for evolving
when we cultivate goodwill cultivate generosity
so i invite you to remember how it has felt like
for someone to be generous to you
someone may have supported you in a way that just clicks in a positive
way for you
i'm just allowing the mind to linger on the actual feelings
how it has felt
to receive generosity from another
taking your time to be with the thought experience
staying with how it shows
allowing the body to relax with these
feelings to support this experience i invite you to bring to mind
someone who gladdens your heart
someone you're grateful to maybe respect
but your sense of respect brings joy to the heart
getting the feel of that cut feeling
joyful glad because of this person
adding to this experience i invite you to bring an image
of a good friend or a beloved pet
imagine this person or this pet giving you
full attention
get a sense of how it falls to be in a space like that
maybe there's a feeling of warmth
welcoming space a friendly space
carrying space
allowing yourself to be with these
feelings
now invite you to imagine opening up the space
and sharing it with other people
notice how it falls to open the space of warm space of
friendliness space that's welcoming
to as many people as you can imagine
i'm just noticing how it feels to do this
now you can release the images and focus
by bringing attention on how the body is just now
attentive to the body
away with the body at ease maybe
relaxed refreshed
so
foreign
as we come towards the end of our seating practices
i'd like to invite you to pause
and think about what is here now that you can appreciate that wasn't
there the beginning of our sitting
and just know to round
[Music]
i um you know we'd like to thank nalitha for joining joining us all the way from
johannesburg south africa um for those curious it's 8 p.m there now
and as we're transitioning from the winter to the spring here in california in south
africa they're going from summer to fall so it's a good time for a good
transition period for everyone so nolita
is a guiding teacher at the dharmagiri retreat retreat center in kwazulu-natal
south africa she will be completing a four-year teacher training under ims and irc in may of this year
nolitha is a student of kitasaro and tanisara who are students of ajahn chah
growing up in a culture underpinned by the principle of ubuntu which means i am because we are
and where the power of generosity is greatly appreciated and being introduced to buddhism and
living in a place where there aren't many buddhists felt like coming home for her nolitha is
also a single parent to a 23 year old son in a culture where villages help to raise their children
so thank you very much for joining us
thank you kevin i'm delighted to be here
um so the theme i've chosen for reflection
is generosity so under the theme of generosity
i'm going to talk about giving sharing
a key practices and buddhism in all buddhist traditions
called dana that's the pali word for giving i'll also
talk about training in ethics would have referred
to training in precepts as the great donor
it's another form of giving [Music] i'll also speak about relinquishment
letting go poly word for relinquishment is kaga
letting go is also a form of giving and lastly
i will talk about forgiveness forgiveness is a form of giving
when we give each other fearlessness when we forgive
so the cultivation of generosity is really the foundation
for training of the mind
it is the foundation for mindfulness and wisdom for liberation
so i noticed the words i'm using
giving and sharing precepts relinquishment forgiveness
these words can bring up interesting experiences in the heart
you can bring up discomfort
i know for a long time for me the world's precepts and relinquishment
would bring a sense of terror to my heart
i don't know how it is like for you these words maybe you're well ahead in
this path these words bring joy to your heart
that's what they are aimed for actually to bring joy
so i'm going to start off with a story that for me highlights
the beauty and the grace of generosity
a friend of mine i teach with here in south africa moira shares a story about being in zambia
zambia in south africa share border so she says here she is in some village
in zambia driving on a ditcher road
the car starts to give her problems
she drives on and suddenly notices that there's this homestead
near the roadside and there are scrap cars
old cars in the yard and she decides to stop here
thinking this would be the kind of place that can give her help
in fixing her car at the homestead
she's welcomed by an old man
she notices children playing in the sand
and also notices signs of great poverty in this household
she mentions seeing a few chickens without any feathers
so she explains hannah hanid and the old man organizes all the boys
they look at the car kai is fixed and then about to leave moira offers
this old man some money he says no
he then offers some fruits in the car he says no and she says but it's for the
children he says no and then he says
if we can't help each other that would be really sad if we just cannot
just give how
for moira this was a new experience
and receiving this experience foreign is white person old man is black
and i'm mentioning the race here because i'm joining you from south africa
and uh issues of race are still a big issue
moira shares that from this experience she felt deeply connected
and she also mentions that she felt like she didn't deserve that connection
so acts of generosity allows for these benevolent connections
with each other
hmm
generosity acts of kindness giving sharing this is what the buddha
has to say about sharing
if beings knew as i know the results of giving and sharing
they would not eat without having given nor would the stain of selfishness
overcome their minds even if it were their last bites
their last mouth full they would not eat without having shared
if there was someone to receive their
gift hmm
so when growing up practice of generosity was truly a way of life
i remember that growing up in a more rural
countryside parts of south africa
always there would be an extra plate of food set aside in case
there's a visitor or someone passing by
who can be offered a meal
i also remember that there was no time that we ever were a nuclear family
only our home was always a home to many cousins aunts uncles
sometimes i didn't i wouldn't even know how we are related to that person who was there to share our home
for as much time as she needed or he needed to be there
my parents were doing what their own parents did so i don't know a lot about this kind of
giving i must admit though moving to the city
getting ebonized plus less and less of this kind of generosity
so i know generosity personally but i also know generosity at a country level
the world often wonders how did south africa manage a bloodless transition
[Music] from apartheid south africa to
a black led government many think it was because of nelson
mandela [Music] rightly so he did play a critical role
in what the world thought of as the miracle
a miracle that gave hope to the whole world
to us it wasn't a miracle to what to us it was this was
so because the african culture is underpinned by the principle
of ubuntu i am because we are
if i cause you harm i'm causing harm to
myself steve biko who is the leader was the
leader of black consciousness movement a hero a struggle hero who died in the hands
of apartheid south africa
is speaking to this principle when he says our contribution to the world would not
be in technology our contribution is africa to the world
will be to give the world a humane face
the face of humanness
so to be fully human is about being generous giving sharing and forgiving
so in the country i also noticed that we're really great at coming together at times of crisis
and this has been the case during this crisis of covet 19.
i have a few stories to share with you about these acts of kindness shown
by people not only here but really everywhere this is what people have done they've
remembered what it is to be fully human by giving support in any way that they
can we know medical care and related
professions would even risk their lives to save lives so i have a friend who's
an academic so she had a task of collating these
stories local stories of kindness during this period of covet
and she's actually in the process of compiling a book titled archives of
kindness so i am going to read to you two of these stories
actually what she did was to ask a number of us to choose your five
top stories so this is this is the two of the five
that i'm going to read to you
candace in cape town in french mooc rights
i've been living in friendship now for 12 years we are a small village but as with most
places in south africa we have a polarized society
of the wealthy and the poor some of whom live in the township
setting for a small village we also have a hugely successful
and vibrant hospitality sector which means we have many hardworking people in
all levels of an industry that with some of the hardest hits during this lockdown
over the years i've been amazed at how many people have done extraordinary things in their private
capacity because it's the right thing to do like building schools and sports centers
for poorer communities but during this crisis we reached a whole new level so many
people contributed and did awesome things coordinating relief turning restaurants
into food kitchens checking it out that everyone was okay in all different parts
of the town
a lady from um the township diploma in johannesburg
writes my landlady is an angel she has given us a free stay for
two months all five of her tenants she's unemployed
and depends on her rant but she's seen how we're all struggling
in the yard she says we will share whatever food we find
she is now trying to find someone to donate nephews for my son i'm embarrassed she's an old lady
during this time she has the strength i'm lurking she is my hero and a mom to all of us
may god give me strength to pay it forward one day these are joyful stories this is what
happens to the heart when there is generosity
so the buddha in teaching when teaching to new people to the
practices he would always or mostly start off by teaching about generosity
he would then proceed and teach about precepts
only then when he has the sense that these teachings of generosity and training in ethics
have landed will he then introduce meditation
ajahn chah my teachers the thai forest master
when this theme says with virtue as a basis for everything you do your mind will
become kind clear and quiet meditation will grow easily
in this environment so through the practice of generosity
virtue we can recover the connection with ourselves with each other
and with mother nature through generosity we recover the
hearts potential for sensitivity
the parts potential for opening
who lives in zimbabwe also zimbabwe shares a border with south africa
baba is known as an international peacemaker he is a guardian to our center here
founded by kitsaran tamizara zamagiri
when they speak about baba kitty talk of him as a contemporary of agent
chair baba says
we have been disconnected to ourselves disconnected from each other because we
are disconnected from nature
and because we are disconnected from nature
we take whatever
we want from nature without giving back
as the world we are in an ecological crisis because we do not see ourselves as part
of nature we abuse nature for our greed
and our great is endless through this we lose this heart
sensitivity the intuitive intelligence
it is said that we are the only species that destroys its own habitat
with lost connection with the goodness of the heart
and i think we're paying a price for this
from each other disconnects it from ourselves we feel separate
we create us and them in mutton bubba's language
we create i it relationships it is through the cultivation of these
practices of generosity that we can recover what
matumbruba calls the i and thou relationship the i and we
relationship with the we identity we can remember the
truth that we all suffer and we all want happiness
our sense of conscience and concern can be reawakened
i'm going to talk about generosity as relinquishment
relinquishment is a form of letting go in letting go
we let go of greed craving which the buddha
has identified as the cause of our suffering the second noble truth that we suffer
because of craving and the task in this path of freedom for liberation
is to let go of the craving as practices of giving
can support us help us to let go
craving has no end it feeds itself
it is true understanding it is through these practices
that we can release craving
what underpins cravings is ignorance
confusion see how we can look for what
is this heart's longing in wrong places
when we follow sense objects to satisfy our craving that has no
end desire feeds itself we look for fulfillment incense
experience since experience changes what is pleasant becomes unpleasant
there's a story i um delight at in buddhism about this
confusion of looking for fulfillment in the wrong places
it's the story of nasruddin nasruddin is a sufi mystic
he's sitting outside in a ruby and spice shop and he's eating these hot chilies
his his wife has a watering a friend comes by and says what are you doing
eating these hotels with your eyes watering and you're sweating
astrudin says i'm looking for the sweet one
this is what we do you and i right we
look for the freedom which is the longing of the heart
heart lungs
freedom freedom from creates hatred and delusion
lastly i'm going to talk about
forgiveness as a form of giving
how is forgiveness a form of giving when we forgive we
give fearlessness
when people know that we hold no grudges we hold no ill will when we have been
their victims it gives relief it gives happiness
i know personally about this kind of relief that comes from
one who i have harmed holds no ill will
towards me
i can't remember what here it was but it was the year that nelson mandela died i'm not sure whether
that was 2011
i leave home and i notice the feeling of anxiety
and between leaving home and
maybe it kind of mean even 10 minutes after i left home
my phone rings i'm driving and i answer the phone within no time
between that moment of answering the phone while striving
i drove into a biker
get out of the car in shock
and this man is on the floor
is on the ground
i can tell he's in great pain
i go near him he is screaming at me
you wear it on your phone
and then in no time your other people
who stopped to check what was going on
and i remember just at one point i had a feeling that was running across
my heart of fear in that moment i was thinking oh this is
going to become ratio i look around people here are black it's
me in the security guard i offer to take the man to the hospital
he refuses he still screaming at me
an older white couple decides to take him to the nearest hospital
i wait for the police
wait and wait then i'll be so i decide to go to the
hospital i get to casualty
he is with medical staff
i sit across him he's laying down on a bed i take a chain and sit right across him
when i maintain eye contact but ignores me
and then at some point he says you don't need to be here
you can go where you need to go my response to him is i want to be here
and i'm really sorry
um so i continue to just sit here
and then at some point i decide i have to go and report this to the police
as i'm about to leave he says to me tell them that you own a cell phone
i'm thinking oh interesting i go and report the case i come back to
the hospital and he has been discharged
and apparently he suffered really serious injuries a broken collar bone and a crushed ankle
now what do i do i decide to go to a grocery store
i buy food i buy flowers i buy bottle of red wine
i organize a script for strong pain killers go to the pharmacy i
get the medication oh only at that point that i realized oh
i must have decided that i'm going to visit him at his house he had given me an idea
where he lives so i drive there and then i get to the boom gates
and
they call him lolita is here
allows me in and as i'm parking my car he comes out one of
his arms is on a sling and with his free um he hugs me
and places a kiss on my cheek and then i smile at lena and say
are we good he smiles
people come and visit and he introduces me as the one who drove into him people are not sure how
to respond to this cut lord long story short
uh about two weeks after that incident it was mr mandela's funeral
so i i invited him i've been checking on him daily just to find out how he
is most of that first week he was in terrible pain
couldn't even work and this is a man who works for himself
so with mr mandela's funeral and uh we're watching it um i'm watching
it with him from my home over a meal we talk about south africa
we talk about racism
and from that experience i
had an experience of what is it to
be forgiven i know what it is to be offered
fearlessness at a country level we know the power of
forgiveness through the truth and reconciliation
commission where
people would committed serious atrocities of harm
[Music] police soldiers
the law enforcement officials had during the
period just before the first elections in south africa 1994
post the elections trc was instituted and
those perpetrators were brought together
with their victims
had to tell the victims
all they had done under the apartheid government
intense intense experience where the
victim and the perpetrator are given an opportunity to find
each other through forgiveness
i think that particular practices gave hope not only
to us as south africans but to the world
i mean our problems are not over as a country by any long short much as we are led by
black government we are stuck in material structures
of white supremacy
the poor in south africa has a black face
and there is corruption ongoing corruption
but i know my south africans we do come together during times of
crisis
so generosity is a foundation for practice of mindfulness and wisdom
for liberation i think we all have opportunities
especially in these times the world is on fire
in many ways we have opportunity to cultivate generosity
i'm going to end this reflection with words from arjun shah
on virtue and morality virtue and morality morality are the
mother and father of the dharma growing within us
they provided with the proper nourishment
and guidance
so sustaining deepening our cultivation of generosity
is the way that we can support ourselves each other
in this quest for freedom freeing the heart
from hate creed credent delusion
thank you grateful for this opportunity
to see these beautiful teachings of the buddha
so uh kevin and mark i am happy to take some questions
based on this reflection on generosity
so if anyone has anything that they'd like to ask novita you can either raise your
hand in zoom or post your question in chat and um
nolita maybe about 10 minutes of q a okay okay jerry you can go ahead and
unmute yourself
um hi um jerry quigan in toronto uh a bit away
from south africa but uh a country i do want to visit so thank you very much and i guess uh i
was interested in your last words about virtue and morality
and the interrelationship with that with generosity so recently
i um was in a situation where uh i'm a physician here and the group
that was negotiating a lease with the landlord some of them had their income had gone down and they
wanna and another problem was uh one of the people were leaving and of course there's a
covet epidemic uh going on here as there is in the world and they're uh it's difficult to find
replacements so they proceeded to write a letter to the landlord initially in a general way wanting to
get a reduction in the rent and um asking the landlord you know out of
generosity and the landlord wrote back uh saying that well because they had said that the
one person isn't renewing and they're going to find it difficult to find a replacement for them and that the
people were working at home albeit at a reduced capacity well some it applied to but it really didn't apply
to others and it resented because i was signing the letter that i didn't speak out that it didn't apply to
everyone so i felt that misrepresented to some degree what had been said and then the
landlord wrote back and said well tell me how bad it is and give me a global estimate so the letter never got to be written
but i was then pressured to uh indicate that uh
uh you know they said well we'll put the specific numbers in about how much people had increases or decreases
and they then proposed a letter which was not uh accurate and i said look i can't
participate in this letter go ahead and send the letter on your own and um then
they will they called me said listen uh you know and i was uh disgusted that they hadn't
uh indicated the specific amounts having said that they would about how incomes went up and down in the letter
and so uh i had just listened to a dharma talk here in fact
at redwood city and california via the wonders of the of the internet and
um the person had said you know sometimes why do we do mindfulness we do mindfulness
to uh uh develop an ethic so that uh we will speak the truth and
avoid the defilements of greed um and uh uh delusion
and hate and uh so anyway they wanted to speak with me
and they started to the conversation after some niceties saying look uh
you know about the letter and i i said look i said i didn't want to participate
and then they said come on you don't we can put the specific amounts but you actually have to put this amount and then i said
listen you've uh lost your moral compass this is disgust me and it uh
is uh um the letter as originally composed was uh
dissembling and uh so this of course i was speaking the truth but i guess in
retrospect uh the letter never did get written and the group disbanded and were moving
apart to uh with the peoples that uh where uh there's a group of six and
now there's four and two which is fine but i guess i wondered whether i should have
related it more toward in a generous way look i feel uh that it's um
uh i would be immoral to sign the letter i feel that this is dissembling instead i
projected it on to the other person and i just wondered whether or not that is uh would have been a more generous
approach so i realize it's very specific and detailed but it's the issue about
um in trying to be generous and also at the same time trying to be moral
getting caught in the approach that one might take to try to be generous
kind but also hardened and courageous when you feel that
a group is going awry
sorry for the launch what's the actual question summarize it for me make it specific
so the specific question would be would you just speak to yourself and not sell someone else that you've lost your
moral compass even though you feel that they did
are you saying is the feeling that you acted in ways that were not ethical
i felt that they did oh they did
by not representing what they said they would by putting the specific amounts in the letter and then calling me to now
ask me to sign the letter which i said i wouldn't and then i i basically very specifically
named them i said this you've lost your moral compass this letter is dissembling and uh
i'm disgusted with you sorry another way that can help me to understand your
question how does it relate to this buddhist teachings
on training in morality well in the sense that the mindfulness
helps you identify not getting caught up in greed
and so i did it i felt that this was greed
misrepresenting results that would of course not be helpful for them to say that well one person's income went up
i don't have a wise response to this
because it is not necessarily about your own experience of
acting uh unethically so i'm not sure i'm a bit lost i i
really don't have a wise wise answer to you because i'm not even
sure that i'm understanding the question well i guess the question i'm trying to
ask is should you just direct it to yourself or when you see unethical behavior in a group
should you identify that unethical behavior and not and and name it or just say listen for
me to participate in this it's unethical rather than tell them that they are unethical to proceed with
this approach even if you believe it socially do you appreciate
that in the buddhist teachings this is training
so it is it is not about
shoots or shouldn't sin that way it's not very helpful
so if it's training it means all of us are going to fail
and we do fail to act ethically and yes you are right the practice of
mindfulness allows you to see that it's hard to
not see with a trained mind when you act in ways that are not
ethical and also in this
practice you can only start again it's not about punishment
it is about developing it is about
training
so let's leave it there let's leave it to their jewelry thank you very much it's helpful thank
you thank you okay okay so i guess we have time for one more so i think miriam is next so miriam if you want to
go ahead and unmute yourself kevin is okay i see there are two if oh okay okay
okay okay here i am uh you're next so go ahead oh okay um i am i'm rooted now
yes okay well um so nolita i want to thank you for your
generosity for sharing all that um i'm from the congo and i live in california
but i'm really emotional because this is the first time for me to hear someone
from africa doing buddhist teaching so i don't feel like alone
but um and for me my struggle about generosity sometimes i
feel like i'm not kind to myself when i'm not generous to other person like when i'm
specifically like i'm um like i know some people like who are gay
in my community but i know in african culture that's not acceptable and i really feel
um sometimes not generous when other people have strong idea
like against that but i don't accept them not being open-minded and that's the
struggle that i have um yeah and i don't know how to deal
with that what is great miriam is that you
see what is going on that you are struggling so the encouragement would be
to turn towards that experience of pain with kindness
with an attitude of openness and allowing
because this practice of mindfulness is exactly about that it is also about opening the heart
towards ourselves and what we struggle with
that is what i would encourage you to do
because rightly so we are products of our cultures
some of these beliefs are part of our psychology
what mindfulness can help us is to see which of these beliefs
are beneficial and wholesome and which are of these
that are harmful not only to others but also to ourselves
i would encourage you to really be gentle and kind to yourself in meeting
with that pain okay next
is jill uh joe you can go ahead and unmute yourself
um thank you very much for taking the question um i i need to share that
that for a very long time uh the concept of forgiveness uh
there seems to be a very strong divine element to it something
something outside of just myself and that if i had the power to forgive someone for
a great harm that it seems very very bold and outside of my own entity
so my question is can am i misunderstanding the definition
of this word forgiveness or what do you think might be coming from my sense that it's
the ability to forgive is outside of my
power
jill when you say it's outside of your power what does that mean that
it when true harm is done i i i would not understand the
motivation of that other person or the deep reasons that it it is beyond my um
not capacity but that and perhaps this is just because it's it's a leftover
from training of another religion which was very rooted in the concepts of guilt and only
god has power to do things so maybe that's a part of it but even in my best of buddhist
moments and my best efforts to feel generosity i know i can change my feelings in my
heart about this person who has caused great harm but i feel that the the
the true washing away or something so maybe it is a leftover religious
thing belongs to a power greater than mine so it sounds like
you've answered your question then so i'd encourage you to notice the
experience of unforgiveness and open to that
allow that
be with the actual experience of unforgiveness [Music]
not making it right or wrong but just meeting it
with openness
stay with the sensations of the experience not so much the thoughts the stories
stay with the false sense of unforgiveness
so that's what i would advise as a practice and really being gentle with yourself with
that as well very helpful thank you okay okay
thank you thank you no letha there's a question in chat i don't know if you have time for one more
oh okay yeah let me take it kevin yeah so uh cindy asks nolitha how do you practice generosity
in an environment of racism white supremacy it has been present in this country the
u.s since its beginning and it is very difficult and is a very difficult thing to forgive and understand
just notice that
in a moment isn't um
wisdom that's present for me in responding to that
but the fact that this person is is thinking about forgiveness and
just not knowing how is already a generous place
to be that there is
a desire or a curiosity to what forgiveness might look like in that
situation
hmm stay with the idea of
being with the desire to forgive