so my friends
we continue with this anapanasati
and the topic is the
14th step one trains oneself
breathing breathing in observing
fading away or a different translation
is
one trains breathing in observing
fading away observing
dispassion
and in this word translated as
uh the word is v raga v-i-r-a-g-a
uh you know it doesn't quite work for
some english speakers
because over time the word passion has
acquired many positive associations and
connotations definitions
in english in some circles and the
original i think the original meaning of
it that the passion of christ
where it meant suffering is kind of lost
but i think still there's remnants in
english that the passion
can have negative connotations you know
it's a is a source of suffering so
uh you know someone say someone has a
passion for power or
passion for sex or a passion for
you know something you know that it's an
intense engagement
in something and intense engagement
can be um very painful
so the um so i want to talk a little bit
about this uh
dispassion this uh b raga
uh maybe in with a indirect way
so buddhism is often considered a
religion
and once it's called a religion it's
reasonable for people to
try to understand what are the
fundamental tenets
and beliefs of this religion and in
doing that
it's kind of looking at the
generalizations just being universal
statements about things
and and so one of the universal
statements
is that buddhism emphasizes that
everything is
impermanent or inconstant usually people
say everything's impermanent
and then we have this universal
statement and then we're contending with
this universal statement like is this
really true
and this is always the case and and this
seems like you know
maybe rather depressing way of seeing
everything or all kinds of reactions to
this
almost like a philosophical statement
general statement
as if it's you know some universal truth
that buddhism teaches
and so looking at this using a universal
statement says
yes you know they understand buddhism is
one approach
i think the the practice approach to
understanding buddhism
is not to understand buddhism in the
abstract
but not begin there but to begin with
oneself
and one's own experience and
and so to the degree to which buddhism
emphasizes the possibility of being free
from suffering
then we begin with ourselves and look
what is
um the suffering
here that i have what's my pain
emotional pain
what's happening here and they say it's
possibly free of it
well how could i become free of it what
does it take
and um and in and in this very personal
kind of
exploration and feeling and being here
then buddhism says well if you really
look carefully at your experience
you'll see that there's a very close
connection
to the experience of
inconstancy change transiency
impermanence
and our ability to ease up from
our suffering to soften it to
calm it down even to have it fade away
and
disappear and so we see then
in this kind of going from this
direction where personally
the purpose of seeing and constancy
is not to have some universal theory and
belief and philosophy about
life but rather it's a pragmatic
practical idea that
that in the observation of change and
inconstancy
this is an antidote this is a medicine
for what buddhism calls suffering
and there's something that eases up when
we can really kind of
feel the flow and be in the current of
change
and whether impermanence and constancy
is a universal philosophical universal
metaphysical
concept or other is really besides the
point
it's the point is that we're pointing to
in constancy and permanence because of
its value
and helping us loosen up lighten up
free up the places we get caught
and uh and that's enough we don't have
to then make it a big
leap of philosophy to make a universe
versatile claim about
now i know something about you know the
fundamental nature of the universe the
physics of
physics of the universe that everything
is impermanent and changing all the time
it's an interesting idea but that idea
is not really what
you know buddhist practice is about
so so but as we see things
shifting and changing and transitory
nature of phenomenon
and we get more interested in the
process of change
the process of inconstancy than we are
with the
content of our thoughts content of our
feelings
many times we're focused on the meaning
of things or
the content the purpose the what's
really you know the
ideas and the particularity of what is
going on
but in a sense at this point in
anapanasati
we're stepping back and in particular
what we're thinking is not that
important just to see the thinking
itself
is an inconstant phenomena it comes and
goes
probably you've had some of your
thoughts repeatedly they've come and
gone for
days and weeks months years and they
just come and they go and after a while
if you see how much they come in to go
maybe you ease up about it
and so then um
so then uh
and also with our emotions sometimes the
meaning of the emotions the story around
them
even the emotion itself what emotion it
is and what it means to have that
emotion and how it
reflects back on ourselves as a human
being comes into play
and but at some point meditation we
shift from
all that complication to not even
caring whether it's sadness or joy
but rather tuning into how the process
of how it
it is a shifting and changing and
morphing and
and moving and
coming in and out of existence and all
the how attention awareness picks it up
and puts it down gets distracted by the
train whistle
and for a moment is not sad because it's
just a train whistle
and then we pick up then we're aware of
sadness again it's that is arisen
and then we hear more more whistles and
you know it's all this kind of going and
coming and going
and it's that coming and going that
begins to loosen up
it's like it's like a lubricant that
begins
unsticking the ways in which
we are kind of uncontrollably
caught in our emotions
or in our activity and our motivations
so and one of those is raga and raga
can be translated as passion or lust
but it's translated as lust some people
feel like it limits it too much to
sexual
passion and um but one way of it's
uncontrollable
the one definition in the poly tech
society dictionary
is uncontrolled excitement
so there's something about i like to
think of it as driveness when there's a
driveness
to our uh draw you know to our drives a
driveness we're driven
by lust driven by greed
driven by hatred and ill will
and there's some way in which something
has taken over control and we're not in
control anymore
this power of that level of passion and
um
describing the way i the way i do it
seems kind of dramatic
but in all kinds as we get quieter and
quieter in the mind
we see the subtler and subtler ways in
which we're caught in the grip
of certain driveness anybody who's been
to meditates tend to see that
you know that how it's surprisingly how
much we get swept away in our thoughts
or
pulled into our thoughts caught in our
thoughts that represents a little bit of
a kind of uncontrolled excitement or
interest or engagement
as we settle back into
into just observing we can see
that this doesn't serve us to be
involved in this uncontrolled drivenness
and caughtness and
preoccupation and so there starts to be
coming this process
of disinterest losing interest and
continuous doing that i've had the same
thoughts for months now
i'm not interested in doing it anymore i
have the same preoccupation with certain
emotions and feeling as if they're the
most important thing
and i'm not so interested in anymore and
i don't want to give much more attention
to these things
i've given so much attention to them
i've been kind of driven to pay
attention to my
anxiety and i think it's okay to put the
anxiety to the side and
i know i'm anxious but i don't have to
be so driven by it and
i can ease up i can just observe it i
cannot be so
involved or entangled with it
and so the movement to being non-driven
movement being no the dropping of
compulsion
is this uh thing called v raga this
fading away this dispassion and
it's very closely connected to freedom
it is a kind of freedom
and after a while we begin appreciating
that
freedom is sweet
freedom is a breath of fresh air freedom
is uh a kind of joy and delight and
vitality and
a kind of health a healthiness
and so to begin to feel that be have a
feeling for a sense of freedom
as we observe there's freedom in the
observing
and that freedom the observing is a
guide a support
to lose interest or lose our
preoccupation with our drivenness with
the things that we're caught in
and so there's this fading away of
compulsion
of a a um
that a process that some translators
will translate as dispassion
a movement towards this passion towards
freedom
the word viraga is a celebrated term in
india
more often than not it's a kind of a
kind it's
in in to liberation itself
the freedom itself and um
the end of raga the end of compulsion
drivenness lust in
all its forms passion and all its
negative forms
and and it comes when a peaceful it can
come with a peaceful way
i like to think of this whole process as
a process of
settling into an ease easing up
relaxing softening fading away
into not not into nothing so much
but fading into a peaceful happy
healthy liberated way of being
so breathing in
observing fading away breathing out
observing this passion as it comes along
here
so um thank you
and we'll continue with this and
i i believe i
apologize i didn't check my calendar but
i believe that on friday
we could do another session where
afterwards if you want to stay and ask
some questions
that was very nice last friday and and
as we're doing the santa panasati maybe
it's nice to
for you having more questions about this
so thank you all very much