good morning good day everyone so welcome you all
for our 7 a.m pacific time meditation and a little dharma
we'll begin momentarily oh thank you i i i do hear on that
yeah if someone is still pointing out my sound this may still be a little i will
try to speak a little louder today just being conscious of it i do have a
somewhat of a high ceiling so it may have a little bit of echoey
effect here
so good morning everyone my name's ying ying chen so i'll be
offering meditation and dramatic today
um so we will begin again with this
arriving sequence that i shared about yesterday the arriving sequence that i learned
from dana dipoma to arizala
up a moffitt and so a writing sequence contains three components
arriving arriving here and now
and making ourselves available avail ourselves to this moment
and then aligning aligning with the wholesome intention
and so this is um what we will do
see if there's any other thing i can do on my end about the sound before we
begin yeah my microphone is actually right in
front of um my computer i tried a few different microphones yesterday
none of them seem to work as well as the computer microphone so
let's see if there is a little more that i can do here
yeah for some people the um the sound seems to be okay and
for others the sound seemed to have a little challenge here
okay so thank you thank you for for your uh
yeah thank you for letting me know okay
all right i think we're gonna begin just as is um
and i'll be mindful about my sound and so today i will go over this
arriving sequence again and to familiar ourselves with this
sequence as we begin the meditation and then today i'll incorporate
an additional element of our practice and that is the air or
the winged element in our meditation so uh so let's begin
arriving
arriving home home to this body
arriving here and now
i'm offering an image of arriving home maybe by letting go and putting down
the bags maybe you were carrying the plans projects
memory preoccupations
if for now we can put them away
we arrive here this moment
feeling the connection of your body with the ground
feeding your feet legs contacting the ground
maybe a few long deep breaths to let yourself
arrive as you breathe out
momentarily we avail ourselves
to this moment a sense of availability
may be that a mindfulness is a present here
nothing dramatic just being available
receiving the sitting posture the breath
sound of my voice
the sense of availability
isn't incompatible with the demanding certain experiences
but opening and receiving
whatever arises
maybe we go back to arriving process again
gathering ourselves and center ourselves
right here
maybe there is a physical felt sense of alignment
from where we sit
alignment of the pelvic area the spine
neck and head
maybe there is a sense of alignment inner alignment of the heart
the mind and our body
align with our aspirations
maybe hold some qualities
maybe aligned with inner integrity
and the word integrity has the felt sense of coming together
everything included
nothing gets pushed out
taking a few long deep breaths
resting into this moment
with a sense of deeper registration
deeper connection
and turn our attention to our physicality of the body
palp pelvic bones supported by the ground
making ourselves available to the felt sense
of the earth element this earthy body
resting on earth
the earth element
is hard heavy
you may feel the weight of the body
settling down downwards
may feel the earth element with the quality of stability
settled unmoving
however earth element manifests so
we receive as is
letting go of big ideas
conceptualization of what earth element is
the body knows
body is an organ of perception
letting go of trying to figure it out from the head
resting in the felt sense
of earth element
you may feel some sense of a stillness stability
or any hint of it
resting the stillness of the earth element in this body
i'm moving
like the big pillars
of an ancient temple
with a stillness in the forefront
of our experience
stability
will invite without sense of the air element
wind element
maybe you feel the movement of the breath
and letting stillness drop in the background
turn your attention to the movement of the breath
maybe movement of the belly rising and falling
expansion and contraction of the torso
maybe vibrations in the body
moved by the winged element
being available to the first sense of
moving wind
wide range of movements in the body
with the steadiness and the stillness of the earth element in the
background maybe the winged element
feels quite alive vital
life-giving breath
being available to the air element in this body
letting go of trying to figure it out
just available however this is for you
wherever you are see if you can make yourself available
to the sense of contentment ease
relaxation maybe that's found
in the body
maybe there is some felt sense
with the earth element
resting on earth
or the ease of the breath
kind of a contentment that is independent of
our experiences
the experience of the pleasant unpleasant
can be content with that not leaning in
to grasp or pushing away
the suitor that i've been sharing yesterday
and the buddha offered instructions to his son rahula
meditate the life of wind when you meditate like a wind
pleasant and unpleasant contacts will not occupy your mind
suppose the wind were to blow on both cling and unclean things
like feces urine spit pus and blood
the wind is not horrified repelled and disgusted
because of this in the same way meditate like the wind
when you meditate like a wing pleasant and unpleasant contact will not
occupy your mind
okay
[Music]
so today we'll continue the reflections on sila
virtuous behavior and today i'll speak about the second
precept undertaking the training rules of not taking what is not given to us
or maybe a simpler kind of translation for that is
undertaking the training rules of abstaining from stealing
and so again i wanted to explore this from the
perspective of the inside out kind of orientation
i invited you to sense into that inner integrity
and inner dignity in our meditation
and so uh we will explore that from that place
and see how we relate to them through maybe the expressions of those
and again i'll use this triple a framework that we talked about
aware abstinence and align aware of the inner dynamics inner forces
within us and learn to discern the wholesome
skillful versus that is not and we abstain from the unwholesome
unskillful and we cultivate a line with wholesome
qualities instead
and so in the last few minutes of our meditation i invited you to check in
to this quality of contentment and ease as we were cultivating
mindful awareness kind of contentment that's not
pulled or pushed away by the forces of a wanting and
greed aversion delusions
and so we know you know as we meditate that the act of grasping
or being aversive to something easily take us out of that kind of a
contentment and a well-being and so in this way the second precept
that we're going to explore today abstaining from not taking uh um from
taking what is not offered to us is coming from a place of non-grasping
non-cleaning non-aversion free of a fear
we all know sometimes the fear will drive us to take what is not given to us
we've all probably seen this in the pandemic when we're fear fearful of running out
of certain kinds of resources we can grasp grasp more
than what we might need
of course and this particular uh precept um
is about to a one degree not stealing
that are not engaging or participating in kind of full-blown criminal
criminal acts like robbing banks and you know stealing expensive
jewelry or personal information online now of course you know i think all of us
don't do that right and yet
as a training [Music] as a training in support of
liberation and freedom and this precepts is also inviting us to look into
the subtle the small impulses or maybe sometimes a big impulses
of grasping claiming perversion in our inner being
and so it invites us to maybe become aware of the areas that sometimes
we may overlook and this is where the cultivation of awareness come in
and we began to pay attention to our activities
during the day are movements in our mind
and you know i just use a few examples that many of you might relate to
and so for example what about taking a piece of the paper from work
what about taking a pen a pencil from work
what about taking an extra plate of a food out of a buffet table
even though they're offered to us
so some of this maybe we act out of um wanting to be convenient
and isn't it convenient to kind of sometimes just or take a piece of paper you know what you know
not not such a big deal right and i remember for myself
many years ago i was printing out a personal
thing at work because i thought it was convenient right and
fast a printer and on the way back driving downhill from work
i remembered this action and then all of a sudden i felt my whole body was une
uneasy it was a felt sense of something off in my body
and there was a a powerful moment for me i realized that oh
this kind of actions have an impact on me
and there's a dukkha in this and so i vowed not to do this ever again
in the modern day societies that we all live in today and they're
you know we're all driven by uh the convenience and comfort
and maybe we take a moment to kind of reflect a little bit convenience and comfort are quite related to each other
and yet there is a cost to the obsession of
convenience and comfort
and the the tricky thing about living in our modern day societies
things are interdependent in so many ways so we may not actually understand the
impact of leaning in into convenience and comfort
for generations to come maybe it's the next generation that feels the impact
and for example you know these days i know there is a
black friday for those who live here in united states
cyber monday and i don't know what today is hopefully
it's something good um
and all of this we can just push a few buttons on your computer on our
computers and things will show up at the doorstep and they're even cheaper right
why not get two or three of something anything
shoes clothes and games and whatever
um when it's cost of a one right why not
and so this is why it's important to become aware of our inner dynamics
to begin to become aware this kind of impulses
now someone is typing in given giving tuesday i love that i hope this is a good one
we'll talk about the giving in just a few moments yeah
um i wanted to point out that as we cultivate awareness for this specific
precept we can begin to tune in and recognize the difference between
needs versus wanting or wants
a need for me at least in here today in the way that i'm going to share
needs are related to some form of care and care for our body our mind
knowing what's appropriate in our body need food needs shelter and
medicine it comes out of a sense of care and wisdom and so we want to take care of
this body and others wanting
wanting is a form of agreed it comes out of a sense of
discontentment with what's here happening right now
and so something else must happen
so many forms of violations and reach of the second precept
are based on wanting
and a strong desire operating underneath
so this precept invites us to abstain abstain from
acting out of the impulse impulses and abstain from taking what is not
given and began to align more and more with our sense of inner
contentment and ease so this speaks to on the other side of
not taking what is um or the the other side of the taking what
is not um offered to us is to align [Music]
with the hosan qualities and cultivating donna and so today is giving tuesday wonderful
i guess it's a perfect timing for this cultivating generosity
giving cultivating contentment to ease
simplicity of our being in the meditation some of you might have
felt some sense of this when we're content not driven by some of the underlying
impulses of jumping out of where we sit
our heart is open and soft
so there's a sense of meditating like when doesn't have to be just a sitting here
meditating but as we go about our lives
can we be meditative like the wind
anything comes through the wind is not horrified repelled
disgusted it's a wide open free air
here sense of a freedom here and so the pleasant unpleasant contacts
and sensations will not kind of get us caught
and so again i've been talking about um
cultivating the sense of vasila as a
form of a blessing so today i'll end with a few words from this mangala suta again
and let's talk about what the highest blessings are
and so here it says giving and the righteous conduct
contentment and gratitude this is the highest blessing
so may you all faith in inner integrity and ignore
addicted dignity may the expression
of your virtuous conduct benefit all beings
so thank you for being here everyone i'm just delighted to share this space
and this time with you all and we'll continue tomorrow
so i have a wonderful rest of the giving tuesday for those who are
studying tuesday take care everybody