hello everyone hello and welcome
and um part of the value of our gathering
together for sunday mornings meditation and talk is the gathering together of a community
of people and this connection to community to others
human beings is an integral part of buddhist spirituality
that might easily be overlooked if the emphasis is uh too much on meditation
meditation where maybe we close our eyes and are kind of you know not
paying usually too much attention to the people around us
in the teachings of the buddha meditation clearly has an ethical
component or say it differently that meditation clearly
has a very important role for how we live our lives in relationship to
each other that an ethical life in buddhism
is arises out of a kind of um a sense of well-being
feelings of wholesomeness nourishment that is possible to feel for a human being
and so rather than starting with ethical principles
so much or if you'd like principles starting with a principle of
being attuned to one's own wholesomeness one's own inner will sense of well-being
subtleness and so part of meditation
is not only to become calm and peaceful but to
awaken inside of us a disposition that is free of ill will
that's free of any inclination to harm and that this position disposition
arises out of touching into something within that feels wholesome that feels
healthy that feels nourishing a certain way
so part of the function of meditation is to feel that nourishment it's not of course of course not easy to
do but but it's just interesting to know at least
that in the teachings of the buddha this is actually one of the purposes of meditation
so that then we can live our lives without the ill will we can live our lives with good will
live our lives with care because it's our disposition not because we're following rules that
we should do so so as we sit today perhaps uh
you can give yourself the benefit of the doubt perhaps you can somehow
go under the radar of the thoughts ideas that you might have
that you are somehow not able to access
an inner sense of wholesomeness or goodness or well-being
that sometimes is referred to as something within that's beautiful beautiful states that we have
that maybe all of us have access to something if we as i said go under the radar because we
have sometimes these very strong orientations that beliefs and preoccupations that
give us the message that no this is not possible not that kind of way
so assuming a meditation posture
and part of the
road to inner is wholesomeness assume a posture
that allows you to have some feeling of confidence
maybe some modicum of strength
some degree of
respect a posture of respect and it can be done in any posture at all
but maybe an adjustment that maybe maybe straightens the spine
opens the chest positions the head better
so those qualities might be a little bit more evident
or perhaps it has to do with the position of the hands letting the hands be in a position where
maybe they embody kind of confidence strength
and it helps very much to be rooted to be grounded here and now
the radar the messages we have that we are not wholesome not good
our message is kind of from the control tower when we're kind of swirling around in thoughts and ideas
swirling and feelings that are a little bit maybe disconnecting and disgrun
non-grounding so to take a few moments to ground
ourselves here taking a few long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale feeling the contact contact against the surface that holds up your body
as you exhale maybe imagine that you're getting firmly established
here and on that surface
and then as you exhale to relax
you need any extra holding you have tension in your body
maybe so you can relax into that support of the surface that holds up your body
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale with a normal exhale relaxing the muscles of your face
the forehead the eyes
the cheeks and the jaws
maybe there's even a way to relax your scalp as you exhale
throughout throughout the day we can do so much work with the muscles of the face and the scalp
responding reacting to letting their face get have a break a
vacation
and on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
on the exhale relaxing the belly
and then for the next three breaths breathing intimately closely
but allowing on the exhale for your thinking mind
to also relax
relaxing any tension or holding or pressure associated with thinking
and for the next three breaths staying close and intimate with
breathing see if you can also if it's easy enough
if you can recognize it to relax the pressure
around any emotions you might be feeling
any tension connected to them
and then settling in more with your breathing
can you also notice
any place within where you feel wholesome
healthy where there's a feeling of inner goodness or
well-being
or when you do feel such things where in your body do you tend to feel it
and if there is a place in the body that you associate with inner wholesomeness or goodness
as you breathe you might gently breathe
with that place so you're aware of both breathing and
the location of your goodness
or you might breathe through it
and if possible stay close
to your inner goodness as you sit here
part of the reason to let go of thoughts is to be under the radar of
the beliefs ideas the concerns of the thoughts so you can be more here and present
for your inner well-being
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to again
is there now some degree of well-being
or inner disposition towards that which is wholesome within
and if there is
to imagine yourself living closely connected to this
maybe it takes the form of a disinclination to ill-will hostility
may be an inclination to become have a healthy concern for the
impact your behavior has on others to not cause harm or pain
perhaps it's an inclination for good will
for simple friendliness and care for compassion and love
may it be that our meditation
frees us from any disposition that's hostile
of ill will and establishes in us a disposition of
good will and may that good will
travel in no in insane in unseen ways out into the world
so the benefits of this meditation practice extend outwards to others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
so before giving the talk here
excuse me for a moment
so before giving the talk i would like to make a few announcements
the one is i don't think i've said this here on sunday that a few weeks ago we
had a little big fundraising drive for a couple of days for
haiti after the the earthquake there
and um and we raised money for a non-profit that does grassroots work
there working in partnership with local healthcare workers and
and they're called partners in health and it was delightful that
we raised about 32 000 dollars for that and that i'm confident can make a difference
for the people of haiti in the communities where the partners in health goes in and partners with people
so that was very nice and the other is that um
we're beginning to think again about ways of opening imc
maybe in october and maybe with more
restrictions on it than we had were planned originally in august and um
so maybe fewer people and and proof of vaccination and things like that
and that um so i thought that for those of you who are interested especially the local
people we could have a community meeting about this on april 4th on um
on october 4th um so and it's a ways away but uh
and then next week i won't be here i'm teaching a retreat for the next two weeks and so for next week i'm happy that max
erdstein one of the teachers here at imc will come and give the talk and
i'm delighted that max will uh be able to do that he he had a baby in um
i think in april so he's been a little bit uh not teaching so much
but he's ready to do some teaching and so he'll be here next next
sunday so for the talk i've been thinking some this
week about an important discourse of the buddha called the kalama suta
and it's one of the more well-known sutas in the west
and um and the buddha kind of teaches i think kind of brilliantly in this text
and they're taking his audience the kalama people on a journey
i think of it as a four or five step journey where he reframes their question to him
in a sense he reframes it by turning away from abstract questions of
abstract questions of truth and falsehood and and questions of who is it that speaks
the truth and who is it that speaks the falsehood to um directing people's attention inward to
themselves uh with ethical principles of attention
and then applying that in their behavior and then
leading it into pointing to the absence of ill will and
the presence of good will so it goes from kind of buddha talks about kind of principles
to behavior to inner dispositions and so it's kind of leading the audience
through this and so it begins by the buddha visiting this
country where the kalama people live and they've had a lot of spiritual
teachers visiting and they're perplexed by them because they all seem to say things
like i'll quote the text um
they say um
they explain and elucidate their own doctrines but disparage denigrate and deride and
denounce the doctrines of others so they champion their teachings but they
criticize dramatic terms the doctrine of others um
and uh so and they say we're perplexed and have doubt they're all saying the same thing that we teach what's true and
other people are all wrong and so they asked the buddha
which of them speaks the truth and which of them speak falsehoods
it's a question about what is true and what is false and
and so so the buddha i guess he doesn't want to be just one more person that champions
his doctrine and certainly doesn't want to denigrate anybody else so but what he does is he changes the if
he reframes the conversation uh he doesn't actually answer their question directly
about who speaks the truth and who's false he first says uh
what you should not rely on in deciding what is true
and then he points to how you can know something for yourself
and he doesn't say it's the truth exactly but maybe it's implied but you'll see for yourself and when i
go through this and so when the buddha responds and says yes
it's reasonable you should be perplexed and have doubt given that all these people are coming making claims and then
criticizing others and um and uh but here's something you should
be careful for don't re these are some things you should not rely on
in in order to rely on these things these are kind of spiritual sources of authority common
ones for many people that they take these sources as providing some access to the truth
and the buddhist says don't don't rely on these and after a number of scandals
and challenges in western buddhism here in the united states there
was a wonderful zen teacher named yvonne rand who's now passed away and um she was i had a very strong
orientation towards uh being ethical and addressing the ethical
unethical behavior and that was going on in buddhism at that time and she once said that these uh
this little what i'm going to read you now she said it's kind of dramatic uh tattooed on the in the inside of
people's eyelids she wanted everyone to know this really well
um
so he says do not go
by oral tradition oral tradition because it was all oral oral tradition back then there was no
books but i guess don't go by the traditional teachings in books or because it's uh the tradition these
particular teachings don't go by traditional teachings
or by the lineage of teaching so if you're in a particular lineage of teachings in particular
organization religion denomination just because it's part of that lineage
don't just accept it as a tr by the just automatically by that don't go by hearsay just because you've
heard it around and maybe it sounds good don't depend on hearsay
don't uh by a collection of scriptures so don't because because it's in that's
a scriptures that are particularly important for you or your tradition the fact that it's in scriptures doesn't
make it mean that it's true and don't go by logical
reasoning so to establish what's really most valuable at least from the buddhist point of view
don't go because it seems reasonable or logical don't construct a logical
argument for it and don't go by inferential reasoning
kind of intuition for example and by reason cognition more of the same
thing and and by some kind of acceptance of it
just because you've thought it out all kind of similar kind of kind of mental
kind of consideration or
by the seeming competence of a speaker just because someone has charisma or seems confident or seems
very convincing in how they are that's not a reason to accept something
and then finally uh don't accept it don't rely on
the ascetic is our guru just because someone you think is because oh because my person is my
teacher i should accept it so all always be very careful don't
accept naively or simplistically these other these sources
it's not a rejection of those sources but rather that's not that you might get
ideas uh you might get encouragement inspiration uh things to think about
from all these sources but they are not the place to find out what is true
now the buddha doesn't actually talk about what's true he doesn't use that language but now he um
he talks about principles of what you should go by and
he says but
but when you know for yourselves these things are unwholesome
these things are blameworthy these things are criticized by the wise
these things if accepted and undertaken lead to harm and suffering then you should abandon them
so um when they're uh when they're in the word for things here can mean action when
there's activities that you do that involve that are unwholesome that
you can feel they they make you feel bad they
deflate you they somehow feel unhealthy in doing them
then uh uh don't do them you should abandon them when uh
they're blameworthy and exactly what that means we don't know but if they seem unfair or injust
abandon them and then they're criticized by the people who are wise which means
take into account the people who you respect
and maybe they know something that you don't know maybe they had more experience or something so here we're really it says
here when you know for yourself but here we're lying a little bit on
other people um those people who are wise and what that means
is not relying on them on what's true but relying a little bit to be careful about how we act in the world
and and then if you know for yourself that these things
if accepted and undertaken lead to harm and
suffering so the idea is we don't want to do anything that has the consequences as
harm either to ourselves or to others but then he goes and says the opposite
um uh if you know for yourself
these things are wholesome these actions these actions are blameless
these actions are praised by the wise these if accepted and undertaken lead to
welfare and to happiness so that's the principle he's offering so it's a principle of your own
evaluation with the help of the wise people that's only one of four or five criteria
and so here the emphasis now is on what you undertake the actions we do
so the buddha now switches the conversation from the question which is about truth and
falsehood to action behavior and this is a indicates an orientation the buddha has
he's often certainly disinclined to get involved in controversies around what is true and false
so you're not getting involved in the the question that was asked but he's pointing people to
a behavior to their actions and he's talking about principles for which to evaluate your actions
and there are consequential there's two things about them that i would emphasize
one is the um that there's a reference point to what
feels wholesome inside what feels that has a goodness or a rightness to it
it maybe shouldn't be the only criteria but certainly we want to avoid what
feels unhealthy to do a kind of inner sense of when well-being is
diminished as we do these things and then also where it involves
consequential thinking do these things lead to harm and suffering do they lead to
to benefit to welfare and to happiness and so it involves some reflection some
thinking some based on experience perhaps where we have some sense of the harm that this thing or the benefit that
comes and the text does not specify to who so it could be either to oneself or to
others and we are meant to be they are custodians of our own well-being
and being careful not to harm other human beings this is a
central orientation principle of the buddha's teachings and i probably can't underscore enough
how central and important this is so here he's bringing it up
and then because he's talking about behavior he then applies it to
particular forms of behavior which we can understand is the four first four of the five precepts
um um we also go zonda says well he applies it not to a behavior
first but rather to mine states and the behavior that comes from mind states and he says is greed wholesome or
unwholesome is hatred ill will wholesome or unwholesome is delusion wholesome or unwholesome
and the answer is that great hatred and delusion is unwholesome that it harms the person who has them
there's something unhealthy about the presence of greed in the
person who's greedy it's often invisible because greed is so focused on the object of what we want
people are not paying attention to what it feels like to be greedy with ill will or hatred same thing
people are often focused on what they dislike and so they're not
noticing the effect it has on them but it's considered unhealthy
and uh if we act out of that then that is also un-wholesome
so an example he gives is if we kill steal
engage in sexual misconduct or lie
based on greed or based on anything that's unwholesome and those things should not be done
so they lead to harm but if we analyse analyze or evaluate
the situation that this is wholesome we recognize the goodness in it
and that it doesn't lead to harm then we do it but
jumping around a little bit he does the same analysis with non-greed non-hatred non-delusion
and so non-non-greed is not
only the absence it's a wholesome state he asks them is non-greed wholesome and
they say it's wholesome the kalamas do so this kind of care and sensitivity this
might seem abstract it might seem kind of theoretical or principle based it is little bit
principles but they're principles that are meant to be oriented towards an inner sensitivity
an inner capacity to feel and sense for oneself what is healthy and what is not healthy
what harms ourselves and what does not harm ourselves what is beneficial for
ourselves and what is not beneficial and this kind of capacity for clearly
being present being mindful is something we're training ourselves to do in the mindfulness tradition
and this training to be present and be mindful as we go through our day has this ethical component because as we
are more and more mindful in the present moment we have access to these feelings the sensations inside
of what has an ouch and what has an ah in it we
kind of feel we become we become our own reference point our own guide for what kind of behaviors to do
that supports us then to avoid greed and stay close to non-greed avoid hate
and stay close to non-hate avoid delusion and stay close to non-delusion this is the
the direction that buddha is going as we do this as we do this kind of care and attention to
the present moment experience that arises within us of wholesome and unwholesomeness as we pay attention to
the presence of mind that allows us to pay attention to the
to consequences this then tends to lead people
to living without ill will to live unconfused
and to live um with kind of clear comprehension of what's happening
so the buddha now is leading the columbus and he evokes this based on living this way
then there is this non-confusion
there is clear comprehension and a lack of ill will
with those three states strong the buddha then moves into
being rooted in good will rooted in compassion rooted in
appreciative joy and rooted in equanimity and these are these inner dispositions
that can arise from wholesome states of being
um and uh and and so and these are dispositions they're social dispositions
or social emotions they're how we relate to other people we relate to them with goodwill
or when it's when it's appropriate with compassion when it's appropriate with appreciative
joy feeling joy appreciating their success in other people's happiness
and with a certain kind of love or care called equanimity which is to be caring
for people but to do so without being caught up with with
any reactivity any reactivity around it and um so um
so we have this journey the kalamaz ask about truth and false
and who has it the buddha answers differently than the questions been asked
he says he focuses on what you can know for yours yourself
he describes the principles for how of what is what's useful to know for yourself
and especially the idea of wholesomeness and leading to harm and suffering
he then asks this question about greed hatred and delusion these inner dispositions
towards create hatred and delusion and help people to recognize that these are unhealthy
and that behavior that comes from them is also unhealthy and then he does it for the opposite and
this is all kind of turning the attention in towards oneself so he's not answering abstractly
philosophically but he's kind of pointing them inwards and i see this as a progressive talk almost like a guided
meditation if you will encouraging his audience to recognize this in them these things in
themselves and if they do this well that leads to
a state where there's no ill will and there's no confusion anymore about what to do and not to do
because it's a we have clear criteria for avoiding harm and doing good
and then there's clear comprehension there's a clear sense of presence and attent attentiveness
to what we're doing not just mindfulness but a mindfulness where we just be aware of something but
a wise understanding about behavior and action and impact of what
we're doing that leads to a disposition and exactly how it leads to it the
buddha doesn't explain to these things that are highly valued in the early buddhist tradition
which is good will compassion sympathy appreciative joy and equanimity
and so one of the things i want to highlight in this discussion is that
uh in in switching the focus from truth and falsehood
the buddha offers central teachings core teachings of what he wants to emphasize
and all of these could be in western terms be considered ethical they have to do with how we behave in
relationship to ourselves and our relationship to others how we behave in our mind how we behave in our behavior
physical and verbal behavior and so there's so such a central feature of the buddhist teachings
has to do with how we get transformed so we live in the world
in a beneficial way that the transformation that buddhism looking looking for is not just to make
people who are peaceful and calm and free for themselves and they go off in
kind of an enlightened retirement and have nothing to do with the world anymore but rather the whole enterprise is
couched contextualized in in in being ethical in nature
or if you don't like the word ethics it's contextualized
in the healthy relatedness that we can have have with the world around us the people around us
and it's not a practice and a goal that is only to benefit oneself
it's a goal and practice that's there to benefit self and others and both self
and others that's one of the so this is my reading of the buddhist
teachings is one of the really central components of it and this kalamazoota
is a wonderful text both because of the challenge it is to us about what we use
to rely on to know what is true and the buddha's
brilliant way in which he turns that towards avoiding questions of truth and falsehood and rather focusing on
behavior and if you follow through on what the buddha is teaching here
all really thoroughly not only is it beneficial for the world around us does it lead to
a disposition ethical disposition it also brilliantly if you do carefully
leads to awakening to the spiritual liberation that the buddha also champions
these two are not separate they're closely connected intertwined to each other
so thank you and um and uh this kalamazoo is found in the numerical
discourses of the buddha in the chapter three and um
and it's a delightful text so thank you all very much