so hello and welcome to happy hour everyone
lovely to be with you and to practice together
so so for today's practice um
i wanted to bring in um
into our practice practice space internally and
externally um something that's really important perhaps is synonymous in some ways it's
synonymous with meta with loving i
yes that that idea that concept that way of being in the world
is um is generosity generosity of spirit generosity being in some way synonymous
with menta with loving kindness with care both for ourselves and for others
and i recently actually wrote an article on generosity how important generosity
is which showed up in uh i think just recently came out in the buddha dharma
magazine which is a lions roar magazine it's online so maybe later i'll send
the pointer to that to neil so that he can share it on the google groups
so you guys can see that but but many reflections
on the importance of generosity one thing is that there is this list of what's called the
ten perfections in buddhism the ten perfections ten beautiful qualities of
the heart loving kindness is one of them there is equanimity
there is perseverance there's patience
many beautiful qualities of the heart and guess what is number one [Music]
number one is generosity generosity the spirit of generosity
and generosity when i bring up the word let us not
limit ourselves to the idea oh i have to be generous i have to give
stuff to people it's not about that at all and really that's a sub
sub category of generosity well the shooting is not part of generosity or if you feel
like you should be generous just don't be kind to yourself instead but giving things to people is is a sub
aspect of generosity really generosity of spirit giving people the benefit of the doubt
giving them or giving yourself care and kind of being generous with
yourself for example when you're hurting when you're having say physical pain or emotional pain that aspect of generosity
is really synonymous with love with meta or to others or giving others your time
giving them your attention or giving them the generosity of not giving
them advice just giving them your presence just listening with kindness all of these
are aspects of generosity and not only is it important
interactively but as i want to point out tonight in our guided meditation
generosity can serve as a container for us to relax
into for the mind to feel its own [Music]
expansiveness its own generosity and relax with more
cohesion with more coherence maybe more concentration one word to use but really
with more um settle into ease of it's okay it's okay again
meta and generosity being synonymous there so that's the practically speaking that's what i'd
like to bring in tonight into our guided meditation this exploration of
of uh of generosity or in pali the word is donna
giving to ourselves others sense sitting in
this sense of graciousness really so
that's all i want to say to set up the space let's just practice together so
so sitting landing
in your seat i'm saying what is most generous to you
what is a generous posture right now that's most both supportive of your
body it allows your spine to be as straight as possible and yet
and yet it allows a sense of ease
a sense of gracious
largesse to your body oh dear body
ah this perspective
generosity to our body as we gather ourselves in
the sitting or even lying position in this moment before we begin
[Music] as we begin
letting go letting go is also an aspect of generosity when you release
it's the same movement of the heart same movement of the mind when you don't cling to something you release it
you let it go with ease releasing thoughts
releasing tightness tension holding in the body and the mind
same practice same movement of the heart as generosity
i'm feeling the generosity of the earth of the seed of this chair or cushion
holding you supporting your weight
ah accepting the generosity and the gesture of releasing your weight completely
releasing your weight
arm to the chair the cushion to the earth
and letting awareness connect with the breath this generosity of the breath that
fills the lungs fills the body with oxygen as if it's a gift being received from
the universe this breath
a gift every moment
and every time you notice the mind is wondering perhaps
lost in thought it's okay can you be generous to yourself
generous to your mind this in this moment when you realize
you've been lost such an important moment to be generous
it's okay it's okay we can release we can relate smilingly
as if we're returning a gift
to the universe thank you this thought that has come up i didn't choose it it just came up
i'll release it back release it back into the mystery
right where it came from no fuss no judgment
releasing releasing into gentle generosity for yourself
trusting there is generosity of course there is
in your heart and mind
and receiving the generosity with each breath
each in-breath in each out breath
letting each breath
perceived received imbue imbue the body the heart the mind
with the goodness of generosity
again every time you may find your mind wandering can you be generous to yourself
this is what minds do this is what's happening right now or maybe you're sleepy
can you be generous and kind yet bring in more energy
maybe deeper breaths maybe sit up a little more straight
to support yourself
i'd like to invite you to consider now
you're sitting you're sitting in a container of generosity this whole body is held
an interweaving interconnected world supported by so much generosity yours
and others offering our work our heart our efforts
all of us
through the generous work of so many people who have come before us
their dedication because they cared so much
so many things in their lives as possible it's available
people who supported us who reared us
family friends
strangers
and maybe someone comes to your mind
has been particularly generous in your life
to you or maybe not to you specifically but when you think of generosity they come
up as someone whom you relate to
as an example someone who exemplifies generosity of spirit
maybe giving the benefit of doubt or sharing their time their attention or
maybe their affection generously
letting your heart your breath connect with this being in your mind's eye with their goodness
feeling nourished that they exist or they've existed
it could be someone you know personally or an archetypal person you've heard of
say could be mother teresa with her generosity of actions in the world
see who works for you
as if with each breath you were feeling into appreciating the goodness of this
being's generosity awakening yours
maybe you consider the gifts you have received
from this being if you know them personally
the kindnesses you've received
the sense of gratitude
which helps you feel the abundance of your own heart
and giving to yourself and others
feeling feeling the risk receptivity the receiving difference
c
notice if your body relaxes if it melts a bit
when you consider the gifts you've received the kindness that you're held in
kindness
no need for feeling undeserving or anything like that
you're a child of the universe we are
all deserving of kindness generosity good will
let your heart receive
the memory of the kindnesses the generosities
that have been bestowed upon you
and now what if this person that you're imagining [Music] this generous being in your life
whispered in your ear or spirit in your heart
and their gift of generosity their gift of
spaciousness of spirit
all of a sudden became yours as if you're stepping into the shoes
looking at your own life through the gaze of kindness generosity
and also to others
how would you show up how would you share your time [Music] your affection
your presence your resources
your benefit of doubt with others with yourself
with each breath connecting to generosity
within and without
receiving giving their breath
your gifts your care
time is short after all we all have limited time on this earth
to be generous to ourselves and others
maybe you've had teachers who've been generous to you
feeling into sharing [Music] their generosity
outward receiving giving
circle of generosity
and if judgments arise internally externally can you be
generous see what happens
when you receive when you meet the judgments with generosity
instead of believing them
generosity of spirit largesse of spirit
assuming the expansiveness spaciousness of your heart that you know
is available it has been available at times
and it can become available at well
expanding expanding through cultivation
this
for the last moments of this practice period
reconnecting with the body with the breath
receiving the breaths generously offered the sensations of the
body the support that this body offers
the earth the air the mystery of being alive
relishing relishing the generosity of being alive
is precious human birth
with all its joys and sorrows its mystery
and offering generously offering our goodness our practice
to all beings near and far
may all beings everywhere
be safe especially those in war zones may they
be safe may all beings be happy
and healthy and have ease
may all beings feel the abundance have abundance
and also share whatever they have generously may all beings including ourselves
be free
thank you for your practice everyone
so we have some time a few minutes
if you like to share questions comments reflections aha moments
complaints it's all welcome you can raise your hand
janey i see your hand oh nikki
thank you that today was your generosity dharma talk today was my generosity experience day
on sunday night i had lost all of my sensory motor functions
temporarily to meniere's disease and had been a tough week dealing with that
afterwards day by day until last night i was losing i was back in contact but not happy and
not in any way able to feel generous in any way to myself or to anyone else and
i went to bed thinking you know i just don't have that touch of happiness in my
life anymore and i awaken for some reason i awakened fully back in touch with myself there i
was there was my body functioning not only functioning but happy
and i meditated and i went did as i am one to do go online
and there met immediately a note thanking me for the generosity that i
had given to my daughter and then from the church that where she where i had taken her as a child where
she wanted me to give the money from both of them from my generosity which i had remember
i had given and then i told my closest mindfulness
friend anna who knew you through the retreat as i did
and she was generous in her acceptance of me i can't believe that all that was
happening to me today and then i see a note on social media from a woman who
had given me the experience of my lifetime taking me underwater to be able to visit an
octopus in his den at a safe distance where i didn't threaten the octopus and
there was a note from her saying she in belize is beginning a new beginning
shelter for all the animals it sounds like yeah and you gave me that and then
finally i'm receiving your generosity again nikki thank you thank you jamie thank you long story
yeah thank you for sharing yeah so many feeling feeling cut off feeling cut off
with so much back again yeah and then feeling generosity
received and generosity giving to the world beautiful to feel as a part of because
we really are every moment even if we're cut off from it even if we don't feel it even if the mind and the body
you know that even if we feel there's nothing there of course it's there of course it's there
and it's your example the story you shared is beautiful to remind us we're part of this web of generosity even if
we forget even if we forget at times yeah thank you jamie yeah thank you
yeah lovely any other reflections
on generosity any aha moments
problems anything
catherine says i feel so grateful for ginny's generosity and sharing her story oh that's sweet
thank you thank you both thank you all yeah
so let's turn if there aren't any more reflections you want to share in either
chat or in person let's turn to um small groups and just holding each other
um present oh there's one question that just came
i feel clinging to the person who is generous how to be generous but not
clinging um you feel clinging to the person who is
generous um i need to i guess how to be generous but
not a little unsure about the fullness of the question i think there's more you
mean here if you wanted to raise your hand or if you wanted to type more because like i'm
not there two different things you're asking here someone's clinging to the person who's generous and then
like me who's generous or another person legit
if you feel like if you feel like i'm muting and sharing your welcome where you can just type
okay since i'm not seeing anything come through yet
just pause one more moment while i give the instructions for the breakout room so
so for the breakout rooms again as always we um
speak please speak from our your own experience only your own experience not
managing or asking probing questions of others just let them have their own experience you
have your own experience and so what you're offering could be silence you could be offering your presence holding
holding others and you offer one nugget just one
brief relative nugget and then the next person will offer a nugget about your experience of this practice
period we have and the next person next person will go around tonight we'll go who's whoever has the
birthday closest to january 1st will speak first
just to mix it up a little bit and have fun with generosity as if you
were the generosity you're holding others with your generosity and others
were and um others are holding you see what it feels like to take the practice off
the cushion into uh into the small groups into
this interacting with others so so i will create the rooms now
and um and let's see what do i want to say um i
think that's it creating the rooms take care of yourself take care of
others here you go okay welcome back everyone the rooms are
closed and we have just about a couple minutes any reflections what came up in
the groups um you can raise your hand you can type in chat or if you have any
questions from before can still follow up still have that one question i didn't answer but i
can't quite decode it so any reflections
neil so we talked in the group
right about how you know generosity seemed to just make more generosity
right someone else mentioned it i know i felt it too you know i felt more generous to the world and
you know by the end i was like oh gosh so many people have been so generous to me you know and
you know i mean that certainly wasn't how i went into this meditation you know so it was just sort of
interesting you know the way it it yeah right it was like like a a
a a skillful benevolent um positive cycle
yeah yeah beautiful skillful benevolent positive cycle i
love it i love it yeah it's another word that just came up which is not as elegant as what you said
it is kind of the snowball effect you start to realize oh wow yeah this
is bigger than i realized and in in a in a beautiful way so lovely thanks for
sharing that neil thank you that's just lovely yeah especially they didn't of course as
you said come in this evening with that intention but realizing wow so many people have been so generous to me what
a beautiful feeling for us to take into the weekend together or into the day or
month and year and lives so many people have been so generous to us and it opens
our heart to generosity to give back to to share our gifts with with them that's certainly how i feel
yeah so yeah oh i see the question came through let's
say i meant when there is a sense of lack i tend to be claiming oh yes of course
of course yeah when there is a sense of lack so the the the
what i suggest there to actually notice how much you have how much you
have received and how much you really have sense of gratitude um really supports generosity and i make that
point in the article i wrote so i'll i'll ask neil generously to send that to
you and on the google group so thank you all thank you for your generosity in showing up and supporting
yourself supporting others may all beings be happy may all things be free
[Music] thanks everyone