hello everyone
that this last meditation of the Year thank you for all of you
being part of it however long you have and um
so to just jump right into the meditation
one of the interesting perspectives
of for meditation is to consider what you trust and what you
don't trust and certainly there are where is your
mind involved in what are your thoughts do their thoughts your preoccupations of the Mind what you're involved with with
your mind is it some is it based on trust or is it based on some mistrust
and of course there might be something in between who are neutral where you're thinking about things that
you can either trust or don't trust it's not an issue
but for meditation you want to stay in that side of trust
and um for this uh the minutes of the meditation
trust being present trust mindfulness
trust the meditation and be sensitive that when you are not
in the present moment is it because you're mistrusting something
in the kind of the broader senses of a term that there's some kind of mistrust
and uh or nothing at all no trust involved
and if so a better place to be is with your trust
the trust that helps you feel the goodness the rightness of being
awake of being aware being here the trust of being mindful of breathing
where the operating word is mindfulness mindful of the breeding breathing aware of the breathing trusting being
aware of it and maybe you have some maybe it's not a
strong Trust but maybe what takes you away from it all
what has what is stronger for you could be understood as being mistrusting
or are you putting trust in the wrong places
maybe you trust planning
but maybe planning is based on fear which is mistrust
maybe you put your trust in Remembering something ruminating over something that happened
maybe it's nice to remember but maybe also it's driven by
the kind of betrayal or loss of trust
that happened
maybe you don't trust the present moment maybe you don't trust being aware of the
present stay close to that
so that you can see through the other side of it where there's Trust
for the present moment trust for mindfulness awareness
stay close to trust and maybe after this week of
considering the Readiness of mind the malleability of Mind mind free of
the hindrances a inspired mind
maybe today stay close to trust
and so without taking a posture maybe a posture that
for you represents
a strong trust a trust which has strength to it
a confidence
have faith a certainty
gently closing your eyes
and gently become aware of the body breathing with no special breathing just notice be
aware of your body breathing
most of the time for most of us we have an implicit trust that will keep
breathing
except for maybe when we bring our attention to it
but maybe there's the body's Trust kind of willingness and ability for the
body just to breathe
that's been going on for a long time
let allowing the body to be receptive to the experience of breathing
and awareness riding on the body's receptivity
a second level of receptivity and being aware through the body
and whatever attention preoccupations you might have body and
mind let it be okay to be that way
trust it's okay as long as you're aware of it
aware with it breathing with it
trusting being aware of the presence
for these minutes trusting it is the central place to be
trusting it with a receptivity
has softness
his simple awareness that's free of the hindrances
a kind of simple inspiration
here now aware
trusting awareness so you linger with it
a kind of resting inexperience
because you trust being present for whatever your experience is
breathing with it all in and out
whatever you're involved in is there trust what are you trusting
are you trusting something unwholesome
or something wholesome are you trusting mistrust
stay close to trusting the present moment interesting being aware
here
experience
foreign
trusting the present moment that allows us to be close to
the coming and going of all things in the moment
when we're in our thoughts the thinking kind of lingers
with things to make them more permanent more outlasting as if they're
takes us out of the the river of constant change
trust the present and after rest in the river of things
coming and going trust without clinging to anything
receptive trusting
non-clinging to the comings and goings of the present moment
whatever is part of the world of suffering your
suffering the experience of suffering
has a nature of appearing and disappearing coming and going
the direct experience of suffering is part of the river of change
Trust floating on that River
not holding on to any of it
stay close to being aware of the changing nature
of the present
and to be close to the changing nature of reality
how things change through the day through the hours through the minutes
and to have a receptive mind a ready mind for whatever change might come
to have a soft mind soft heart for whatever change is coming
to be free of hindrances
to be inspired by the value of staying present receptive soft free of
hindrances to trust
being receptive and soft free of hindrances and inspired
so that when people come into your awareness
people do the surprising unexpected things that people
do that you receive them in this
field of awareness field of softness
non-resistance non-clinging
to be able to see and know others in a deeper way than if we react
though with greater wisdom and clarity know ourselves better
and so be able to remember
kindness friendliness
basic human care of others good will
wishing
may it be that in the freedom of our hearts
that we can meet everyone
with good will
May those people that I encounter may I wish them well
may I wish them to be happy may I wish them to be safe
may I wish them to be peaceful
may I wish them to be free
and with those wishes may I be friendly
kind supportive of others
May the practice that we do for all of us as a community
may it be a phenomenal contribution to the welfare and happiness of this
world may it spread from each of us and collectively
we will make a difference for this world
[Music]
thank you so so we come to the last of the talks
that are titled um ready ready to change
it could also be titled ready for change but I think that um first we want to
think about it for ourselves ready to be to be ready to change ready to
um be changed for the better and as we that happens to us then we're
more ready for change in the world we're able to receive and be part of
that change without unhealthy resistance and unhealthy fear
and projections and desires and Despair and and
you know the all kinds of things that contribute to our our sense of
discomfort in this world they contribute to a deep distrust in this world
that those things have to be different things shouldn't be this way and maybe trusting anger trusting greed
trusting fear trusting mistrust
so the Buddha when he was teaching was orienting his teachings towards
um cultivating these really wholesome states of Mind in people so they'd be ready to hear profound
teachings that could liberate them or what the language of it was it opened their
Dharma eye that they would see in a new way and that's a powerful teaching the idea
that we're not looking for a new experience like a better experience
we're looking to see our experience in a new way that's liberating
and some people are so focused on change making some change fixing something solving something
but rather to open and see it in a new way so
um if um so that Buddha would be giving these
talks that would inspire people and in that inspiration he would their minds
would become receptive ready to hear something deep
their minds would become malleable and soft their resistance for example and
their stubbornness and their you know laziness and their greed and whatever it
was would soften would would settle and they'd be really right there and so there's kind of softness and willingness
to hear and take it in and kind of lower their guard in a
healthy way appropriate way perhaps and then their minds would be free of hindrances for the time the giving those
talks they'd be so connected to it that they wouldn't be caught up in greed and anger and
delusion they would be inspired
and they were the last thing that would happen passana was a Pali word
and this is a wonderful word that we don't have a particular
meaning in English for it and the the different meanings of it that we can
make out of it is a range that we have different very different English words for it
and so the I think the delightful task is to consider how they all are one
thing that somehow in that ancient Indian World they saw this as it's kind of like
made its own thing maybe like they had a different emotion um than we have because they divide up
The Human Experience in a different way or hold it together in a different way than we do in English
so you have to use your imagination a little bit to hold these different meanings together into one
maybe you'll come up with a you know I've been thinking about an English word that might hold them all but so far
haven't maybe some of you will um or maybe in a non-english language
so the um the first meaning is clear or bright
so Luminosity a Clarity like the you turn on the light and there's this
wonderful Clarity the fog as the smog is cleared and it's clear
and it's there's a brightness and Clarity to the mind to the heart the second meeting is that it's a heart
that is happy uh has uh just delighted and happy
and the third meaning is that it's a mind that has trust in it that is reconciled with all things that
is um pleased or satisfied with what's here here but that it word trust is one
that's what people often fall fall on or confidence so Clarity happiness and Trust
is there a single English word that captures all three of those or can you somehow fold them in to
somehow recognize maybe all of them I mean they are you know a sense
if we have different qualities at the same time are they different qualities or is there
a gestalta hold that they're part of in the present so this idea of receptivity readiness
softness malleability free of hindrances inspired elated
um clear happy trusting and for now I'll settle in the word
trust and um it's a fascinating kind of concept to or state to kind of Orient to
ourselves kind of the exercise of uh what is my mind doing right now
does it express some kind of trust or mistrust if it's trust what am I trusting
am I trusting anger am I trusting fear by trusting mistrust where do I put my
trust in a sense whatever the mind is doing most there is a kind of trust there and sometimes what we're trusting
is not healthy for us to trust something healthy to trust the
wholesome not the unwholesome to trust trust more than mistrust
to trust really being here fine and what does that do for us to
settle us relax us the confidence of Faith something about really being here
so the Buddha prepared people with a mind like that and then he would offer his deepest
teachings and it would open people's Dharma eye and it said that when people's Dharma
eye opened they would exclaim they would say a particular thing
they would say whatever and it might not seem very interesting or very profound just
hearing it but it's really a significant you know this is this comes with an
experience of Awakening so it's not to be treated lightly and dismissed because it sounds like that's not much
uh hit the Buddha which the people would say oh
whatever has the nature of arising has the nature of seizing ending
they would say something the Dharma eye would show them something very profound
about the comings and goings the arising and passing of phenomena
and that and what's it possible when we see that what's possible is to see how
much the mind doesn't allow us to stay and be there because we climb on WE grab
we hold on we have thoughts and so when the Buddha was very specific
when he gave his profound teaching he was saying that suffering has the
nature of arising and passing and to understand that we have to understand that it's the experience of
suffering so if we've had a profound loss the loss is not
coming and going it's it's it's permanent now or if we have some kind of permanent
medical condition that debilitates us um that's there or you know that's not
going to change what do they mean right coming and going it's the psychological experience of
suffering that of how we relate to that has a nature of coming and going it's
not permanent it's not solid it's not and if we trust the present moment
enough trust is being present for the river of comings and goings we discovered that place where all our
psychological suffering belongs to that River belongs to the
comings and goings of phenomena and when we see that when we wake up to
that then we realize it's possible to let it just be the river of change
we don't have to cling to it and hold on to it whatever has a nature to appear
has the nature of disappearing let's allow it to come and go let's not
stop the disappearing let's not lob onto it cutting it let's not think about it
in such a way that it becomes kind of continuous just let the thoughts arise and go
it's like someone might protest and say what do you mean my body is not coming and going my body's just here
the body is constantly coming and going the experience of it the psychological
experience of the body the thoughts the concepts the feelings Sensations
the body doesn't come and go but it's a general thing when we're into the direct experience is what we're talking about
here that's where the Dharma eye opens to the direct experience Here and Now
and here our suffering comes and goes psychological suffering
so this idea of you know the Buddha has of teaching people to create the context
of a heart and mind that's ready for teaching is not to kind of
be pollyanish about life and to just make it all kind of nice and sweet it's really to prepare us for the
existential difficulties of this life of ours the places of suffering and stress and
challenges that we have and what a wonderful thing what a
wonderful thing to cultivate the wholesome to cultivate these wonderful capacities of our mind for wholesome
States not to be blind to what's going on in
this world but to be able to see it and be present for present for it in a way that uh
we are able to bring the best of ourselves out we're able to stay awake and present and non-reactive
so that the best of us can meet and respond to the world and I hope that this practice we've done
over this last year that it really does make us
better able to contribute to the welfare and happiness of this world
may we really do this practice not only for our own sake but even more than for our own sake let's do it for the sake of
the world after all um as we settle
and have this open attention this ability to be free and aware that in that openness and awareness
maybe it doesn't matter so much
you yourself and Me Myself and mine what's important is what that awareness
beats and encounters and how we care for it
may we care for this world and let's care for it better
because we've gotten to the bottom of our suffering and learn not to cling to anything
so thank you all for this year for this week for this day
and uh very glad to have shared with you this time and this teaching and this practice
and I certainly look forward to doing it again starting in the future in the far future
next year in 2023 so when that time comes then I look
forward to being with you next Monday thank you