hello everyone hello everyone and all the places that
you're connecting from and i value very much the wide
network of people meditating right now
and different time zones continents
so um the topic for this week is emotions
and these are very rich parts of the human experience and to be respected to be
listened to to really pay attention to them carefully for many reasons i'll talk more about
that as we go along here but one of the wonderful
possibilities especially with this mindfulness practice is to have emotions be simple
to not pile on top of our emotions evaluations judgments
predictions meaning just let the emotion be there in a simple way
and one of the ways of having our emotional life and other
parts of our life be simple as we meditate is to do a simple shift if you can if we
can and that is that instead of saying
any something like my emotions i am having emotions just refer to the emotions that
are occurring as emotions so if there is
sadness just recognize their sadness but refrain
from calling it my sadness or to say i am sad
uh if you're angry if you're happy if you're delighted if you're
confused one way to make it very simple is to
free the whatever the state is from the identification with it
mine i i am
it's maybe reasonable enough to use the idea of me and mine
in ordinary language but it tends to come along with a lot of baggage it tends to come along with a
lot of ideas of who the self is what it means to have certain emotions what it
how it reflects back on ourselves and the world can get very complicated very quickly
and what we're aiming to do is to have the emotions be simple and at least when we're meditating
just the simplicity of each pristine emotion of itself
and so if we're sitting now you might see if there's some simple way without making it complicated
see if you can periodically notice a shift with a difference between shifting from
so maybe some unconscious pattern of identifying things as my pain
uh i'm i'm having pain my distraction i'm just i'm distracted
my thinking i'm thinking to just thinking just distracted
just pain the pain the destruction um
and so whatever it is shift to a non-identification
non-identification way of of being present for your experience not my breathing but the breathing
and with the goal to keep your attention very simple
and it's a simplicity it allows things to settle and become peaceful
so assuming a meditation posture
not your posture but a posture the posture
and gently close your eyes
and taking a moment to see if you can notice the simplest way
of being here now the simplest things to notice about the present moment
the simplest things to notice about your body
the simplest things to notice about your breathing
not my breathing or just the breathing
and the simplest ways of acknowledging whatever mood or emotional
state is present for you now as if it's free floating
without any reference to me myself and mine
and then within this experience settling into the experience of the body
breathing
on the exhale relaxing
physical relaxation relaxation of the face
around the mouth
of the shoulders
and relaxing the belly
perhaps allowing now the breathing to breathe itself
not your breathing but rather
the breathing
and as we go along here today
when it seems easy see if you can switch from ways of recognizing what's
happening from identifying with it as mine or i
to simply the experience the emotion
floating free of identification
so
recognizing thinking as thinking not my thinking i'm thinking
recognizing your emotions his emotion
not mine or i am pain and sensations in the body
whatever is happening let it float free
from identification
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to bring forth the simplest sense of goodwill
may be free of i have good will or i
am loving just goodwill
and letting that good will live in your body
and to make a bridge between this meditation and her wider wider social life
have that good will now extend itself to the people around you and your
communities work family friends
neighbors strangers
and letting the focus be on them and not on you
may others be happy
may others be safe
may others be peaceful
may others be free
and now to bring the attention to you in this way it's useful
that you say may i contribute to this possibility
may i contribute to the welfare and happiness of everyone
so
[Music]
um
so hello and we're here to continue on this topic of emotions
and an important part of mindfulness of emotions is to recognize
how some emotions arise out of
uh an appraisal of the situation and evaluation of the situation we're in
i know i like to call these secondary emotions that arise from the
stories the judgments the meaning we assign to the situation
and i call primary emotions those which don't require much appraisal evaluation
assigning a meaning to the situation if [Music]
there's you know certain kinds of things can happen suddenly and you're working in the kitchen
and with a knife and the knife suddenly falls off the counter and maybe towards your
foot the there might be a sudden very quick reaction of fear
and response that doesn't take much evaluation isn't like you look at the knife falling and
say oh there's a knife falling the point of the knife is heading to my foot this wouldn't be a good idea to have it hit
me there's not enough time for that level of evaluation it's just very quick
or fear that arises very suddenly because maybe a car appeared out of nowhere
right next to you driving fast you know and and so there's fear
but some emotions arise because of the valuation and
then sometimes those evaluations have to do with me myself and mine
that the situation is what it is but that we then refer to
ourselves and we hit or we or we
evaluated in reference to how we identify ourselves how we think about ourselves how we consider ourselves
and so for example if we have this idea that i'm supposed to be in control
then all the time in every situation then that we bring with us a
pre-established evaluation meaning idea and when
the idea of control doesn't work then we're disappointed or is despondent
and so that's a secondary emotion because in my vocabulary because it arises not out of the
simplicity or the basicness of the situation we're in but the situation travels through
our need to be in control we have this idea that i should be capable of taking care of things
and so if we don't take care of it properly then it goes through that idea i should have
been able to do it and then there's disappointment or there's angry or grief
and so this idea of referring it back to some idea of self
and then emotion arising out of that is not a primary but a secondary
and maybe in being secondary maybe it's not always needed
maybe sometimes it is and but uh but to be able to consider how this works
and to be able to question it uh is this emotion i'm feeling now
is it more primary or is it more secondary and some emotions uh lend themselves to
being more primary primarily secondary
so for example if um if uh
something like guilt uh many reasons for guilt
but one aspect of guilt is with it when we have the idea
that i am who i am myself i'm wrong or i'm bad
and um and so i've see people who feel guilty for no
reason that i can tell that they have done anything wrong but they have this almost like a pre
conceived policy that if anything in the in the world is going wrong they should
say i'm sorry and they feel guilt or they feel somehow
you know something the anger
we can have self-concepts about ourselves and if those self-concepts are
threatened or are attacked we can get angry sometimes there's other reasons for
anger but so i'm sitting here today and maybe i read
the news and the news says that
that
self-respecting dharma teachers should own only wear blue shirts not red shirts
and uh and so then wow you know where is that coming from now i get angry i've
chose this shirt carefully and i'm happy and proud of my shirt and and this is essentially kind of
is a it's a broadcasting of my importance as a dharma teacher to wear a red shirt and so now someone is saying
something different and i'm angry with them for somehow threatening me or hurting maybe or because i have this
idea of what a dharma teacher should be like the or perhaps i i read the headlines and it
says that you know dharma teachers should wear blue shirts and now i'm in front of you all of you you've read the
same headlines and now i'm afraid because i'm afraid of
the judgments i'm afraid of that now i'm wrong and uh and i'm going to be threatened in
some ways all about this image about who i am i'm defined by the shirt i wear
and sometimes boredom is a sign that the self
that we a self-concept we have is not being pumped up it's not being
reinforced sometimes when our concept of self gets praised
or it gets criticized then we feel um energized by that
uh maybe we feel a certain kind of uh joy when we are praised maybe we're ready to
be angry if we're criticized or and or if something doesn't really
support or challenges or our status or sense of self
but when when nothing happens it doesn't neither neither supports itself nor threatens it
then boredom can arise a particular kind of boredom that arises from somehow
evaluating everything through the filter of my self-concept and who i am and how
i'm being supported or or undermined by situations
so um so all these different there are secondary emotions
that all of these can be primary emotions in the sense that they can come just from a
moment's experience without going through the channels of my self-concepts my self-definitions
my ideas of who i am being myself and mine and um
and um but so much of the so many emotions people have
are triggered by some idea that it's threatening or praising or challenging
for some idea we're carrying around with us of how things should be
some of those ideas are probably fine and may be appropriate even but some of them are not and
particularly the ones that are most painful have to do the ones where we're attached
to some concept some image of ourselves that we want to hold up or want to
defend or we want to use to create safety for ourselves
some idea of self that has to do with status conceit but i'm better than others
and uh and how that how does that get threatened some idea that uh what a self is what a
being is we have ideas of what we're supposed to be to be a successful human being
and so if we don't have that success then we can feel despondent
because that's what a good human being is supposed to be like and
so certain these secondary emotions uh can do very uh we do very well to
ask ourselves what are we believing what are the stories what are the
evaluations what is the appraisal we're making that has triggered this emotion
if we don't do that investigation we might think that the emotion is a primary one act this is just built
into the nature of the universe that if someone says something about the color of my shirt that
that casts some kind of you know character on who i am and who i need to depend to
defend myself for who i am um but uh maybe i could look at that and
see in my mind that uh you know maybe even if people do judge a
dharma teacher by the color of their shirt um that's their problem that's their
thing to do i don't have to why do i have to pick up what their judgments are their ideas are
um i can you know i can be free of that and i'll wear what i'd like to wear and
and let it be that way so i don't know if my example is very good but the point being that there are emotions
that arise that are primary that are core central emotions that are maybe important to
listen to they have important messages for us and then we have some emotions
where the message what they're about is not really to our best interest
they come from appraisals they come from valuations they come from ideas of self
concepts that are not really well founded or very useful
but when those ideas of self ideas of whatever ideas
encounter situations with threaten them which support them which
offend them which you know then we can have these secondary forms of guilt and anger
and fear and boredom and despondency or joy or
or excitement or all kinds of things and it's these secondary ones
that i'd like to leave you with today as an investigation and that is
as you go maybe at some point through the day a couple of times maybe end of the day
sit down again maybe with a pen and paper or with a friend or something and going
for a walk and review a little bit some of the stronger emotions of the day
and ask yourself did those emotions get triggered by some
evaluation some appraisal of the situation some idea and concept
that we carried with us and that in and of itself the situation didn't trigger an emotion but it only
triggered an emotion after it went through the appraisal
and was that appraisal that evaluation some somehow related to your self-identity to the concepts ideas of
who you think you should be and how you should be in the world and
uh and then once you do this exercise then ask yourself
is there a simpler way is there a way to be present for that
experience any experience without the filter without the curtain
of these appraisals evaluations self-concepts can we set
our experience free of of the sometimes the incessant
ideas and concepts we're using to constantly appraise situation
often in terms of what it does for me me myself and mine
so um
so um i hope this isn't useful for you
and we'll continue in this exploration of emotions tomorrow thank you