greetings greetings friends good morning good afternoon
good evening whatever the time is from all the various places you're
joining wonderful to see your hellos um
your greetings these expressions of metta for each other for the sangha
greetings greetings so lovely to join you this moment in time
to practice together so this week we're exploring
um the mind's body the mind's body so today we continue to explore that
and um [Music] without further ado let's practice
together let's practice together and explore explore
this mind's body this body's mind this mind's body
so
arriving
arriving wholeheartedly
in this body inhabiting this body
allowing inviting this body to sit tall
with a sense of integrity like a mountain
upright
a new well rooted like a well-rooted tree connected to the earth
through our sid bones our bottom our legs our feet
well rooted connected to the earth
all the while the top of this
tree tall reaches up to the sky
and let the branches the leaves the limbs
ah be relaxed
offering itself offering themselves to gravity
letting our awareness trace
trace the body the outline of the body
as a horror drawing three-dimensional drawing
brushing [Music] our entire body worse than the
edges with our awareness
this whole body sitting
and then letting it be filled out
letting the breath be like watercolors
filling out the whole body
not effortfully but let it just happen on its own all we
do [Music] there's very little doing here if any
it's just to turn our awareness turn our awareness
our attention to a particular perception
a way of seeing
in this body right now
and as the breath
is received by the body
entire body the whole body breathing bellowing
turning awareness to the entire body bellowing the breath entering
leaving letting the body be relaxed
let the body be an organ of perception
so that we're not noticing the body from the top of our head from the control
tower
but as if our mind
is in the body in the perceptions the sensations of the body
itself
you're noticing your breath in your belly right now say
the belly is sensing itself the mind is in the abdomen [Music]
as if your abdomen has eyes ears
trusting trusting that the body knows
how to sense how to breathe how to perceive
relaxing [Music] relaxing it's not
hard trust your body your body knows
how to sense
the body as an organ of perception
perceiving receiving the breath
from within
the body knows senses simply
sensing the sensations
whatever wherever is most prominent use the abdomen for this example
sensation sensed on their own
in the sense to only the sense
and the felt only the felt no distance
no separation it's just a sensation
no need for commentary
from the inside of the abdomen of the sensations
themselves being sensed
pressure tightness
movement
vibration
maybe even warmth and coolness
everything we need to weaken is presented to us
in the body in this long fathom body
we just need to pay attention in a particular way
so today let the body
have its own mind the locus
of perception of sensation in the sensation itself
the knowing in the known itself not from afar not from a distance
so as a sensation presents itself in the body
whether the breath or something else
let the mind relax into that sensation
be drenched in that sensation from the inside
and hang in there it will become clear on its own
if the thought arises i can't do this what does it mean and
you believe that and you go with it it will take a long time to click or it might
never hang in there trust trust that the body knows
how to sense and perceive
without the need for analysis and commentary
this particular way of perceiving is not quite clicking yet
i invite you to imagine [Music] that you
whoever you are or if there is a you you are in the abdomen
in the sensations
and stay stay
with perceiving in this way
whole body perceiving sensations
from the inside
just points of sensation
no need for you
the self can drop out
just points of sensation
and as we bring this sit to a close
together holding ourselves with kindness or whatever arose or did not rise
we've showed up we've done our best
whether distraction arose or sleepiness or
whatever else it's okay
we've done our best even if there was one moment of
awareness clarity mindfulness that's infinitely more than zero
[Music] moments
so appreciating that we are planting seeds of cultivation
towards clarity awareness
knowing awakening kindness
goodness and offering this goodness ours and collectively
wholeheartedly trusting there is goodness here co-created
offering generously to all beings everywhere it's not for us to keep
not nothing is for us to keep in this impermanent life
nothing so sharing our goodness our heart
our actions wholesome actions
for the benefit of all beings everywhere including ourselves may all beings
everywhere
know their own goodness may all beings
be happy may all beings be free
so greetings greetings dear sangha dear international sangha all around the world
so we are continuing to explore the mind's body this week
and [Music] for today's guided meditation
for today's exploration just a few words and what what we did
and what the basis for these invitations were
so we tend to pay attention in a regular way in in
what we're used to in the world going around as a human being
and many of us most of all of us kind of consider that our mind or
our mind whatever our mind is and of course philosophers and scientists
so many treaties on on the mind unconsciousness we still don't
know what it is and where it is and all that so but we have this pers
this perception that our mind is somewhere in our head
and we perceive somewhere in our head behind our eyes there's the self here
that perceives the world
and and when we are noticing say the body
sensations in the body the breath pain it's always this dualistic relationship
there is the self there is this me there is
this awareness consciousness whatever it is it's up here it's up here and oh yeah
there is there is the abdomen there is my foot there's pain in the foot itch
there there's this dualistic relationship um
subject object
and [Music] and particular relationship arises when we
pay attention in this usual habitual way particular perceptions arise
that are not exactly conducive to to waking up to awakening
so the invitation today
was to really
consider paying attention in a different way not from the control
tower you might have heard that before but maybe in the brief pith instruction and then other instructions after that
but really really land in the body as if the body is an organ
of perception itself it's perceiving in and of itself and i
was giving invitations to imagine the you or whoever you are
there's perception in your abdomen you're perceiving the sensations or in your whole body or wherever
the sensations are arising and and you need to stay with this because
for most people with this instruction um you might think that oh what from the
inside i'm sense i'm in my abdomen i'm sensing the sensations from the inside
of themselves not from the control tower like how does that even work i don't know how to do this ah
so so that is very normal that can arise and yet if you give into that way of
thinking it will never click it will never this perception can never shift this new way can never open up
so what needs to happen if it didn't click for you or even if it did click you need to
stay if it comes up oh i don't know how to do this like wow this is unfamiliar i always paid attention from the top like
what does it even mean what the heck is she meaning to to sense the sensations
from within themselves so stay stay stay you need to stay and it
will shift it will make sense on its own so jake don't give in to the thoughts of i
don't know what this means because of course it's a new way i'm inviting you to try something completely different
it's like riding a bicycle if you've never sent right ridden a bicycle before you need to stay with it stay with it
and then what can arise what can arise is
a sense of perception perceiving the sensations in
the body in and of itself there is no commentary
there it's just the sensations being sensed in dissents only the sensed
only the sense so these sensations being sensed in and of themselves without a
point of reference so these points of sensation
all over the body all over quote-unquote the body
and then it becomes just points of sensations being sensed in space
and the body will drop out to just be points of sensations and the self
drops out as well this is one way to have insight
into not self into anata there's so many different ways this is one way to see that and i was
guiding you this morning and albeit it's a daily meditation it's only 30 minutes but yet
some of your minds might be ready to have an insight here to see it for a split second or maybe take this practice
into the future and sit with it maybe it will plant seeds for insights to open up
and this teaching um the buddha gave a beautiful pith
teaching to um [Music] to bahia so i like to read actually let
me tell you the story of bahia so so bahia the wanderer
and the time of the buddha he was a dedicated practitioner
and um he was practicing very hard but not
he was not a buddhist in some other tradition and he thought he was awakened and the story goes that
um [Music] he's told that actually you're not awakened yet go find the buddha he can
really give you the true teachings and take you to the end so he um
comes and shares and finds the buddha and arrives when the buddha
is about to go for arms around
to get his daily meal and he says the buddha have come all this way please please give me a
teaching and the buddha says no this is not a good time
um i'm going for alms come back later she says well
please please second time please please give me a teaching and the buddha says i'm going for alms
and he says the third time and then buddhist stories whenever you ask they put up her third time he will give an
answer so please you know life is uncertain who knows what what
might happen please please give me a teaching and the buddha knowing the context he's hungry he's going for alms around
he gives him the most pith teaching and the most awakening pith teaching way to awaken
and it's a beautiful teaching to keep practicing there's so many levels so many depths so many layers of
depth and if you feel like oh you understand it trust that there is more to this teaching so i'm going to read the punch
line for you and before i read the punch line so when bahia hears this he becomes
fully awakened and buddha goes for his alms round and bahia later that afternoon gets gets
killed by a cow and and
but he's fully awakened so so here we go
bahia in the scene is merely what is seen
and the cognized is merely what is cognized
etc actually uh it's summarized well here it is
in the scene
oh here in the scene will be merely what is seen in the herd will be merely what
is heard in the sense will be merely what is sensed
in the cognized will be merely what is cognized in this way you should train
yourself so we were focusing in the sensed merely what is sensed that might be the
easiest way to to first way to understand this teaching in the sense to merely the
sensed and then the buddha continues when you practice in this way in the sense to
only the sense etc
then bahia you will not be with that when bahia you are not with that
then bahia you will not be in that when bahia you are not in that
then bahia you will be neither here nor there
nor in between the two just this is the end of suffering
just this is the end of suffering so this is in the bahiya suta if you want
to go and read it later yourself so shift in the perception the mind's
body inviting ourselves for us to see things differently
leading to just this is the end of suffering
in the sense in the sense merely the sense merely the sense so
so staying with it and sensed could be the sensation is in the knowing itself it's not
separate and it will the perception will shift in amazing
ways we're all capable of it give it time give it time
so speaking of time we are out of time so
thank you all for your practice for joining
either in real time or practicing later may you be well
may you be free take good care and
see you tomorrow