hello everyone and welcome to the meditation session
and now as we're doing the section of this sati patana suta on
what's usually called mindfulness of the four elements i like to call a mindfulness of the four properties
i'd like to do a meditation on these four and
what it involved is first beginning with just settling in in the usual way
and then at some point shifting the focus from the breath i
like to have the breathing as a primary focus for meditation the anchor
but to let go of it to some degree and open the attention up
to uh have the awareness kind of in a relaxed way gently slowly
calmly let the awareness float around the body
to [Music] become aware of the different sensations
in the body as they appear as they call attention as awareness floats in that direction
so it's a kind of random maybe and there's not much choice sometimes this
kind of meditation is called choiceless or directionless we're not necessarily directing the attention anywhere
but we are staying in the body to feel the sensations and just kind of move
the attention moves or different things kind of parts of the body speak and some of them become predominant and
strong and we're resting there for a while and something else sooner or later will get our attention
and shift and change or if it's a compelling area of the body
it might be that this such the attention wants to stay there it seems appropriate to stay there but
within that area the attention kind of floats around and feels different doesn't get fixated it
doesn't get zeroed in on something but rather kind of just feels it around
and the analogy that's uh you know given is having a bowl or a bell bra spell and just taking
a cloth and and wiping it from all the different sides so just kind of randomly kind of be with
something specific floating around on it until something else takes it takes in
your attention so it's mindfulness of the body but with the kind of choiceless floating
awareness that takes in slowly gradually
whatever wants to come so beginning by assuming a meditation
posture and it can be helpful if the posture
itself expresses the intention
to be present to be here in this place in this time
sometimes a posture where we start feeling a strong good foundation
for the to hold the weight of our body and to feel that contact
sometimes a posture that is sitting upright
alert
gently closing the eyes
and then gently slowly some little bit deeper breaths
using the inhale to connect here to the body now
letting the exhale be a time to relax and let go into here
and now
breathing in and breathing out and then letting your attention your breathing come back to normal
and for a few more breaths relax your body on the exhale
on your exhale see if there can be a settling into your
body deep in your body so that you're here in your body
on the exhale relaxing the thinking mind
any pressure or energy to think any tension associated with thinking
perhaps an exhale that can be softened
ironed out
and then gently now letting your awareness
be free to wander around your body
the whole body becomes the anchor to the present moment
the whole body is the
where awareness resides
but within the body let your attention your mindfulness
not be directed but rather receptive and open to
wherever sensations appear wherever attention wants to go in the
body
there's a lot of sensations don't try to rush between them just in a relaxed way
settle for a moment in one place where there are sensations
and then as as the mind wants as the body speaks
let the attention float somewhere else or if it feels nice you can just let the
attention rest in one place
maybe gently letting the attention float in that particular area
taking it all in
noticing when the mind gets caught up in thoughts and ideas
see if you can set them tension free again so it can freely roam
through the body in the body
taking in whatever sensations appear and disappear
appear and persist
whatever calls the attention to it
perhaps there can be a global awareness within which
a more intimate mindfulness attention floats
around and touches different parts of the body
as the sensations there become known
rooted in the body letting the flow of bodily sensations
be known in an open relaxed awareness
settling settling back and observing the flow of sensations in
the body
as we come to the end of the sitting
for the next few exhales ride the exhale into your body more
deeply ride the inhale
to spread your awareness through your body
for a few moments here almost as if you let gravity
settle your awareness deeper into the fullness of your body
and then as if your body
is an organ of perception like the eyes and with the body
you could feel or sense or take in the people of the world
not through the eyes not through the usual mind and ideas of
self but this with a deeper
the body itself
in some way can know there are others on this planet
just as our body is made from materials that rises out of the earth
so does their bodies just as you have sensations in your body
of pleasure and pain so do they
just as your body is the house which holds
your heart so it is for them
and perhaps we could end this sitting
with feelings of warmth and tenderness and care for others
calmly peacefully from this place where we're meditating
a simple warmth and tenderness gentleness
in which goodwill can glow
radiate from us
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
so hello and so this will be the last talk on
this fifth exercise of the sati patana suta the exercise on
mindfulness of the elements or what i like to call is mindfulness of the properties
the earth property the water property the fire property and the
air property and this is a meditation mindfulness of
sensations so the basic sensory awareness exercise of just being
present for the sensations that are direct and immediate as they occur for ourselves
and there's a variety of ways of practicing this and one of the ways is the way we did in
the meditation today which some people find easier than meditating on their breath
and that is to just be just be grounded in the sensations of the body if the mind wanders off come
back to the body and the flow of sensations with the the attention
not particularly not any more directed to the body than it is to the whole body just there
rooted in the body and then floating and roaming around touching into the present moment with
the different sensations as they flow through and come into being some people find that they their
breathing actually works as a better anchor to the present if they stay there they can develop their stability their
concentration and their mindfulness and there also it's a sensation meditation it's the same meditation
but now we're doing the being aware of all the sensations that come into play as we breathe
so technically the this four elements meditation
is what we're doing in vipassana when we're tuning into the breathing
now the attention though is in a much narrower smaller area of our body just in the area where the breathing occurs
or where the breathing is predominant and um and so we are um
we're there with the flow of sensations the and we let maybe the attention kind
of float within the location where we're focusing on the breathing and letting the sensations
come into that floating awareness or let the floating awareness settle and the ripple of sensations that come into play
as we get quieter and quieter and the breathing gets stiller and quieter it's easier to kind of just stay with the
simple sensations that come and go as we breathe it's still a sensation meditation it's still this four element meditation that
we're doing but because it's it's more rooted in a particular place some people find it
easier the mind doesn't wander off as much and it's easier to settle in simpler that way
and as i said some people find it simpler to do the whole body some people uh what we do is sometimes
in mindfulness as we uh what i like to teach is we are rooted in the breathing that's
kind of like the default that's the place we cultivate stability and steadiness of mind to stay in the
present moment but if something other sensation arises in the body that's more compelling
then we contentedly relaxedly let the attention flow to that other
place and then begin doing the sensation meditation in that place in the knees or the back
or wherever the sensations might be strong and there too the idea is not to fixate
the attention but rather to uh let it roam around let it come like you're like you're
you know maybe like you're touching a cave wall in the dark and you can't see it but you just let your hand
go around and feel the wall and the texture the temperature or the
whatever it might be so
but the direction that it's going with this kind of sensation meditation is the
same direction as all the different exercises of sati patana and that is to be able to steady stable
enough in the present moment the mind is not wandering off anymore we're right here in the present moment
and then um and we're just feeling the experience and because the mind is now stable and not wandering off easily then
we can settle back and just observe the experience and this idea of observing
the experience is meant to be a peaceful experience that
we're not interfering or making a lot of work it's very receptive allowing
just observing it as the flow of sensations the experience as it comes through
and in particular as we settle back and there's more more stability in the present moment we're just right in the
present moment then we see that in the present moment everything is passing everything is
moving i don't know if it's a good analogy but
if you uh take you know an old uh film that's made up of all these little squares that
and you have it passed by you have a little little slot and you have the each frame
come in front of the slot to come in front then another one comes in slot if you just settle back and watch then you
see that there's they just allowed if one comes one comes one comes
and now you see they come and they go they come and they go so in some kind of relaxed flowing way
we start seeing more and more things just come and go and come and go and this opens up to
deeper places than now of letting go of not clinging so that's the direction we're going
and but how do we get there one ways and the tradition
is um that uh is if a look at the analogy or the
simile that's used for this particular exercise i think it's so the simile is
if we do the four uh the four element meditation being aware of the sensations
in these four categories and um and it's like a
uh so i'm sorry for this little graphic that but a butcher who has uh cut out cut up a cow
and to um and put out the different pieces of the cow for uh people to maybe come and buy or
something and at this point people are not relating to
the pieces of meat as the cow is just pieces of meat
you know and they see the pieces of meat independent of the cow so i think maybe it's unfortunate
for many of us this graphic kind of analogy but the idea is that um
we often are living in thoughts and ideas of that we take in our whole self like how
we identify ourselves in a particular way some of the identities are accurate enough
but if we live in the whole the identity then we miss the parts
and this is a meditation to not be in the idea of the whole but rather to begin
tuning into the particular elements parts that make up the whole or that we apply
the concepts and ideas to and so for example if i was to think i'm a
lousy person that's a generalization of the whole if i then feel the sensations of my hand
the sensations themselves are just sensations and there's no lousiness in the hands and no sensations it's just
if i think i'm a great person that's a generalization if i think i'm a lousy person whatever it is
and uh and the um the um
the um the idea is to kind of have an
experience of ourselves where we drop below the coarser identities the coarser ideas
of who we are because often those ideas are sources of suffering
and even if they're sources of happiness they can also be they limit us
to drop into this deeper settled relaxed observing place observing the present
moment as it flows by so by beginning to look at this at the
sensation level of experience we're looking at the parts in a sense
of the cow not the cow as a whole we're looking at the parts of ourselves not the generalizations of what we have of
who we are and so we're dropping down to a deeper level and this is can be quite healing quite
healthy to do this because some of the ideas and attachments to the ideas that we have
involve contractions and tightness and they involve a disconnect
with our lived flowing bodily experience and to be able to drop down into the
lived bodily experience and let that flow the sensations flow and move and
not be bottled up not be restricted not be contracted is a really healthy spiritually really
healthy physically just a healthy thing mentally to be in this kind of flow of sensations
where the mind is not fixated on its painful ideas or it's whatever ideas
it has so um
so this idea of dropping down into the parts to the direct experience what's actually
happening more than the you know the ideas and thoughts about things
is part of what this exercise is about what it helps us to do
is to bring the mind and body together in harmony if the mind is thinking about tomorrow
or yesterday thinking about fantasies delusions of grandeur delusions of
for me or something uh we tend to be disconnected from our bodies
and um and the body is always in the present moment and so the task of meditation is
to when we want to harmonize the body and mind is to let the mind join where the body
is and since the body has a lot to do with sensations that's where we can find the harmony
that's where you can find the meeting the joining better than if we just stay conceptually
thinking about how wonderful the body is and celebrating the body with ideas we're in the sensation level of
experience and that's where this harmony happens is coming together
and this will see as we move on in this becomes really helpful
for to to connect to deeper dimensions of our heart deeper dimensions of our inner life
so we'll get there and but tomorrow we'll do the start uh doing a few
sessions on the sixth exercise of sativatana and i want to uh maybe i should warn you
that this involves contemplation maybe even visualization
of of corpse and um and i'm not going to make it
graphic but it'll be kind of very simple but this is the exercise there's
actually nine different uh contemplations on the progressive decay of a corpse
and i don't think it's meant to be gruesome um but it's meant to somehow in its own
way help us maybe value at the present moment and really show up
here in the present moment so that there's a qualitatively improved
aliveness to our attention and dedication to this present moment experience
so hopefully
this will be supportive for you to spend a couple of days on this quartz corpse com
contemplation it's a long tradition in buddhism to contemplate death
and so we'll do that for a few days as part of this satipatana suta
so thank you