so hello hello everyone and
welcome warm welcome
and uh there's all these warm good mornings and
hellos on the chat and i appreciate them all as a large
network of warm warmth greeting goodwill that we're
participating in here whether you're on the chat or not so thank you
so imagine that
there's a door that it's a glass door
and that glo glass door has never been cleaned
and you don't really know what's on your other side but because it's so dirty you can't see
and then it occurs to you to wash it you clean the door
and all the dirt is on the inside where you are and lo and behold you can see
i see out and there's a beautiful
beautiful natural setting wow that's pretty cool
and then it occurs to you to open that door and all you do is open it big door you
open it wide and now you stand gazing upon that natural setting
and in a way it's easy to forget that the door is open
the door is clean there's a clear view because the natural setting is so so
beautiful and such so interesting and you've never seen it before
but what is uh then then the evening comes and you look out the
door and you see the sunset and wow never seen a sunset like that
and then you go there late in the evening when it's dark and you look out and
it's spectacular to look out that open door and see this the night sky and the stars
and then you're there early in the morning dawn and you see little birds and little animals coming out and
it's so special you didn't know it's wonderful to have a clean and now even an open door
at some point it dawns on you how special it is to have a clean door
how special it is to have an open door the openness of the door
is special the openness of the door is
certainly allows you to go in and out but allows you to see unobstructedly
so when we do mindfulness practice in part it's a cleaning of the of the
glass so we can see clearly but it becomes more than just cleaning
it at some point it becomes opening the door opening wide
and not only being amazed or not of what you see through
the open door but to be
appreciating that the door is open
the open door doesn't need to be open or closed the door doesn't need to be open and closed
the space that's the open door doesn't really
is not ruffled concerned contracted repulsed by anything that's seen through
the open door and so the same way in our
when we can let go of our clinging let go of
needing so something to happen doing something all the time and just find the open door in our minds
and our hearts we can gaze upon things
simply we can also gaze upon the openness
where nothing is needed where there is space
where there is freedom where there's no obstruction
where there is no resistance
and this can be in the nature of how we're aware
so assuming a meditation posture
and assuming that your door is already wide open
really assuming that's the case no matter what is happening it's just seen in the
vista through that open door
whatever thoughts agitations have whatever reaction you have to my words
whatever attention you have in your body nothing needs to be different
for now for a few moments here
nothing needs to be different
except imagining you're seeing it through an open door clean open door
and everything is allowed to be itself
and the gift that we give when we look out the open door in the natural setting it is a kind of gift to let each thing
in the natural world be itself not to appropriate it or do it or
improve it just be the natural world be
so yourself at this moment whatever is happening
let it just be
whether it's comfortable or uncomfortable something you desire or don't
desire it's just the view through the open door of the
mind
any attempts to do something
is this it can be just seen through the open door that doesn't need
anything to happen he can just marvel and see
the attempts to do something or to get away from something fix something
judge something it's just part of the natural setting
that is seen through the open door
so
the door is always open
it helps to remember that we're seeing through it
until all things
so
foreign
and as we come to the end of the sitting imagine you're sitting in a easy chair
relaxed at ease gazing out upon
through an open door not into a natural setting
and how it is to be at ease nothing to do calm
settled and if you don't feel that way now you
might adjust your posture so you'll be more comfortable
for these last few minutes
and imagine again you're sitting quietly peacefully
gazing upon a natural setting and then you turn that gaze inward
as if you're looking within the natural setting within you
looking inward into the depths of your hearts
into a place within where you recognize your ability to be
friendly
whether that's through thoughts feelings intentions
through a warmth or an inspiration
friendliness gazing upon
all things in a friendly way
looking upon yourself
in a friendly way being your own friend
and looking out into the world to be a friend to the world
not an enemy to anything
but a friend and as a friend
as an expression of friendship
to have well wishing for this world
may all beings be happy
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe
and may all beings be free
so they can know an open door
for their life
[Music]
so
thank you
so coming this last week on the sati patana suta the discourse on the
foundations for awareness for establishing awareness
so i want to uh to tell you a little bit about this text is it's kind of uh cliff notes
it's kind of it's uh it doesn't go into you know great ex explication of what's really being
taught it's more like brief statements and uh and then down through the
centuries teachers have then expanded on it and clarified it for people
used it as a basis for giving instructions and those underst the instructions the understanding have changed over time or
the text is amenable to many different ways of understanding and interpreting
and maybe that's one of the reasons why it's remained so popular is that it's uh
you know it is more notes where the meat of it is
comes forth in the teachings that are received about it
when i was in the first many years that i studied this text and enjoyed it
um what i kind of the the lens or the interpretation that i used to under
understand it i had a lot to do with the very common verb expressed in the text
which is repeated many places in the different exercise is
to understand or to know uh paganiti to know
and and there's so many of the instructions were to know something
not to fix it not to be concerned with attaining anything or getting anywhere
it was not about judging anything or having commentary about things but just to know the simplicity of it
and i came to appreciate how powerful it is to just be present for something to know it to be aware of
it giving it the gift of allowing everything to be itself
rather than we are becoming free maybe you'll never be free
what we do though is that we give freedom to everything else and everything receives our freedom from
us including our inner life so much so that maybe there's no sense
of talking about a self doing it it's everything is given
its freedom to be itself and
and so i found it so freeing and so satisfying to have this very
clear present moment awareness that was just abiding in the present allowing things to be as they are
it was very freeing very nice then as time went along
i came to appreciate more and more a different aspect of the sati patano suta
and that is that i understood it now as uh describing a
journey and it begins by saying there is a a um
is nowadays popular to say the beginning is there is a direct path
for the purification of beings for liberation and
and another way of understanding the word direct here literally means the word one
is um in the early you know the first things translators did it is
there's one way and uh and that kind of it was a little bit jarring for many of us just there's
only one way and then became the direct way but i think
that nowadays interpreting it more and i think it's very likely what it originally meant the word one here
we meant unified there's a unified way and all these parts of ourselves get
unified all these practices all these four foundations get unified and work together
but they and they work together in part as a journey as a path that unfolds over time
and there's a number of things in the sutta that to me suggest a path that we follow
and and one of them is that just the idea of going from body to the
feeling tones to mind states to the inner activities of the mind the
dhammas is um it goes from the uh goes kind of from the outside
into the depths of who we are i mean to the deeper deeper areas only we can see
so with the the body uh that's you know you can see each other's bodies we can see our body other
people we can see people's bodies externally and a lot of it has to do with things
that we feel and sense maybe a little bit more um in our
physicality feeling tone and that's what that's the way the ancient world talks about it
it's the physical aspect the other three foundations are often seen as as a part
of the inner mental world so the feeling tone
is uh something a little bit deeper it's like how the world has impacted us
um and in a way of that it's pleasant or unpleasant or is uh
you know welcoming or not welcoming it's a little deeper kind of the deeper re uh consequence in ourselves for
feeling something we're not neutral it has a kind of effect on us
more deeply it's the state of our heart the state of our cheetah our mind
that is maybe more intimate more personal than just what happens in our body
and and then more deeply it becomes the operating system the operating activity of the mind
that is really the linchpin for everything else and how we relate to
everything and how we live in this world and the choices we make and
and so that going from the body feelings mind states to adamas is this journey i like to think of a
journey home coming deeper and deeper into ourselves to the place where we can make a difference
or the practice can really make a difference to transform something very deeply and the transformation in this fourth
foundation foundation is a transmission is represented by the transformation from the
being caught in the five hindrances to being uh in
having awakened the seven factors of awakening and one of them leads to
they say to darkness the other leads to light one leads to
obscuring wisdom the other to revealing wisdom
so this journey and the other place where the journey is manifested is in the refrain we
talked about many weeks ago and each of the 13 exercises has a refrain it's the same refrain
and it begins by kind of once we're settled
and the awareness is strong then there's ability to kind of be 360 degrees aware within ourselves outside
of ourselves internally and externally
and then as we settle further then the they're starting to see the changing
nature of phenomena and we see things arise and then as we also see things cease
and then we see things arising and ceasing together it's a kind of a journey to deeper and deeper stillness
until the rising and seizing happens together and then we go deeper still and there's
a deep kind of equanimity of just just a clarity of mind
just a clear awareness lucid awareness and just enough knowledge to know what's
happening in the moment in the most simple possible ways it's a mind that's very equanimous very
peaceful very at ease where then at some point because of that ease
there's no more effort to protect ourselves or build ourselves up or try to have something or to be anyone
and something deep in our psyche can release that the tradition refers to as clinging
and clinging to nothing whatsoever in the world
so it's a journey of awareness that we do so on one hand in the early years i
thought of it there's no journey just being present for what is and then later i came to appreciate that described a
journey and then i came to appreciate how these work together that as we practice just being present
for things as they are uh giving each things the freedom to be its
own thing not trying to manipulate anything or change anything just to see it and see
see this this this just that not needing anything to change
that involved that brings about change and one of the ways it brings about change is that
uh we're actually no longer doing the common human thing of always
instigating the change always trying to fix and maneuver and get and understand and you know figure
out or analyze or plan the whole world whole
domain of human activities comes to a rest when we all we do is be
present not trying to do anything not doing anything is a radical thing
and it's kind of like this house of cards has been built and we're holding in place running
around keeping all the cards in place when we stop doing that everything settles and the cards come to rest on
the table and the the the house of cards that we built is often one that's not needed
or we don't need it all the time and to be always shoring it up and building it up is exhausting
and so the very practice of being present for things as they are without needing to change anything just
appreciating that um
begins a process of change and it puts us on a path
of maturing in this practice and you almost can't
can't avoid maturing in this practice if your your practice of mindfulness of
attention is sincere and if you're practicing a certain
thoroughness or certain um wholeheartedness or a certain kind of
um persistence like this is what you're doing and and so
day by day week by week month by month the practice of mindfulness just being here
practicing meditation every day something settles just being present for what is
the advantage of having the sense of a path is that it's a little bit encouraging to
kind of give ourselves to the practice more fully to know that it's leading to a good place
the disadvantage is that people will huff and puff and strain and expect and be discouraged because they're not going
the way they want the advantage of just being present for things as they are
and just not just being aware of them in a simple way is it's a very freeing and relaxing
the disadvantage sometimes is that people don't have a sense that of how far this practice can go how
radical transformation it can bring about in us and so they shortchange themselves
they they don't kind of let their inner system um go through the open door
they don't let the kind of like the ch the uh there there's something inside that is
held in check or not really allowed to kind of let go and move and flow
because that maybe can happen easier if we know there's an open path to walk
open door to walk through so there's different ways of kind of
interpretations for understanding this text and many more than what i said but for me this has been very important
this distinction between um or this the distinction and then the harmony
between these two very different modes of practicing sati patana one is just being present for things as
they are and that's it and the other is being present with the uh with the
orientation towards a path of practice that we're developing and because it's a unified path
um we include everything everything comes together into this
open space of awareness practice
so thank you very much and we'll continue with a summary or
conclusion for this text for the rest of the week thank you