so good morning again
and a good day
and today I will continue with the mostly sitting meditation and not going
to do any guided meditation with the idea that it's valuable to
to just sit with oneself as we are
guided meditations can kind of change the context of sitting and
which is often valuable but it's also valuable to spend some time just sitting quietly without any input
but I would like to read um quote a couple of things from the Buddha
that pertain to what the topic is for today and
for the Dharma talk
someone comes to the Buddha the man named udaya and
kind of a refers to how somehow refers to the idea of
remembering past lives and knowing future lives or something like
that and that other teachers somehow this relates to other teachers in India at
that time and the Buddha responds to him this way
let the past be
let let be the past let be the future
I shall teach you the dhamma this is an important
very important Federal phrase you know put aside concerns about the past about the future if you want the dhamma the
Dharma here listen to this
when this exists that comes to be with the arising of this that arises
when this does not exist it does not come to be with the cessation of this
that sees us this is considered to be the teaching of the pendant arising
and rather than explaining it the important point of this is that um
in the present now put aside the past and the future
sit you see the Dharma if you see
the river of time the flow of change Here and Now how one thing leads to
another one thing sets the stage for something else to occur one way or the other things are arising
and they're passing they appear and they disappear and some of that is that the thing
itself a sound comes and goes and some of it has to do with how we experience something
so if I'm holding this book and I was just holding it the book
doesn't disappear just like that but my awareness my attention to the book shifts and changes as it goes to my
words that I'm speaking to holding the book to thinking about you know other things
here in the room and and uh all kinds of things that can happen
and so this idea of staying in the place of arising and passing coming and going
here now now a fascinating teaching the Buddha gave
is he said um um
it's basically to have uh he said you know to avoid the idea didn't say it doesn't it's not true but
it's just to avoid the idea that things exist and that things do not exist
for someone who sees that that things appear they can't say that things don't exist
for those who see that things disappear cannot say that they exist
if you live in this world of the alternative to positing existence and non-existence is again this world that
we live in the world of experience the world of how we perceive this world
comes and goes so now
so one of the things you might do in this sitting is very gently lovingly to yourself as
you may be at the every exhale or every inhale whichever you like
say the word now but say it word now
so that it becomes a time for to know now know now
this that comes and goes now
so with that we'll sit quietly thank you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
I'd like to evoke the wisdom of three questions and
answers that one form or the other repeated many wisdom traditions
and the first question is when is the most important time
and the answer is now
who is the most important person
whoever is present so if you're with someone else might be
them if you're alone it's yourself
and what's the most important thing
to not obstruct obstruct
the openness of your heart
to keep your heart open and not have it dim or obscured
by thoughts stories opinions
and so we come to the end of the sitting
and the important time is now the most important person is
each of us individually and as a as a collective
and the important thing is to keep the heart open and may it be that as we move out into
the world and end this meditation that the meditation
reminds us reinforces for us the possibility
of keeping and staying with an open heart a loving heart
that's ready to Delight in others
to love others to care for others
and may it be that as we go forth Miss meditation they can we carry with us
an attitude expressed in these words
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
[Music] foreign
thank you
so this week we're reviewing again or going
through again these five qualities of the Dharma
it's in part the teachings of the Buddha the this famous saying that we're kind
of relying on is the Dharma is well spoken by the Buddha
so something well spoken beneficial helpful and the Dharma as a teaching points to
something here and now and the the teaching and what we awaken
to are inseparable what we enter into in this practice is in separate inseparable
and uh kind of a simplistic way of saying these five qualities
is the first is about the Dharma is here unequivocally here
it isn't and today the second one eight is now
the third one is that it's Dharma instructs us to look
the fourth one is flow along
and the third one is the fifth one is feel
the flowing along feel the freedom know the freedom and this
being of blowing along with here and now in the presence so here now look
flow flow along feel freedom
so today is now a Kaliko and it's a
what's immediate what's present for us in this present moment
forever long it lasts for us than now that we can live in
and uh one of the ways to appreciate the value
of it is how easy it is to lose touch with it and meditation is one of the place one
of the benefits and one of the things to celebrate about meditation is how it
shows us how we don't meditate very well rather than seeing our ability to not be
present as a problem for meditation meditation is to highlight for us how
the mind works and we get to see how much the Mind departs the present moment
one of the ways to do it to see is what you know the thinking mind so for example there's a retrospective
thinking it's hard to think about the past there's
um anticipatory thinking thinking about the future
and you can feel ourselves leaning into those or being Ling I like think of them
as we're lingering in our thoughts and as we linger in these thoughts there's a way in which we no longer
linger in the present we no longer present for now
as it unfolds as it's present and so something as simple as being with your breathing breathing in and
breathing out breathing is always in the present and then you can find yourself thinking about something and no longer in touch
with the breathing or hardly in touch with it and you can actually feel the quality of
losing Touch of lingering in those thoughts and those thoughts might feel rich and
valuable and important and substantial but they aren't they are ephemeral impermanent changing
fickle and it's possible to be so centered in the present together with our thought thinking that
we don't linger in them they just feel like loose and light and soft and kind
of coterminous with space just thoughts of floating through now
here and now we're now tricked into them we know them as present moment things
and one of the really wonderful aspects of meditation is well mindfulness meditation
is when there's a really a clear grounding clear sense
that when I'm thinking about the past the thinking is happening in the present
when I'm thinking about the future the thinking is a present moment phenomenon
when I'm involved in fantasy the fantasy is a present moment phenomena
so the repetition of the word now in meditation just now
or the sense of now here now not to dismiss or deny anything but to
wake up to oh this is what the present moment experience is
we don't have to be at war with our thoughts we don't have to be of the war we're thinking about the past and the future
but at least in meditation to discover how
uh much that's thinking about thinking takes us away from the flow the
connection to Here and Now and so and then and then learning to
wake up to oh this is this is the flavor of now
there's this thinking and the thinking in seeing it this way is now we're not tricked into the living
in the past living in the future in our thoughts we just see oh I'm thinking about it
and maybe we begin to feeling the insubstantial nature of thoughts the lightness of thoughts
um thoughts can feel very heavy and they can feel very light but they're not heavy by themselves
they're heavy by our involvement with them are lingering in them are are
leaning into them by themselves
thoughts are very light thoughts are coterminous with space
they have as much substance as the sky
-like thinking so to come here and be now
and Here and Now this is where then we can start loan
recognizing how we obscure or dim or narrow
the open system sensitivity of our love of our Delight our appreciation
our friendliness our love our care
and um we have such potential
now for the beautiful qualities to come out and as I said last night in a talk
we have we get caught up in so many different things in our life that seems so important
and we lose touch so easily with what is most important
to be present here for this life with a full attention
it might not seem important it might seem dull and boring from the point of view of the mind
that's spinning and chasing and wanting things and not wanting things and protecting the self it might seem that
way that just being present is not much of Interest but to do the thought experiment
that if you know that you have only one hour to live
you're dying and maybe you'll be fortunate to die consciously and without any pain
but clearly you know you're dying there's no this is this is the time
and at during that time would you suddenly realize how important
it is to go back to your 2009 tax returns because you think you pay too
much and you need to fill out paperwork in order to get
350 dollars back that uh you're you know is yours after all
the last hour of your life you probably won't that's not what's the most important thing
the last hour of your life probably not the most important thing is to start
planning vacations planning for the future in some way and anticipating things
you realize it's not happening it's no point
to uh would that last hour what's important
and I would like to propose that to really find the wealth of life that
the potential beauty of life to at that time to really know how to be
present to be here and now the there's a way in which that hour becomes
Timeless that hour is not part of time the idea that an hour away you will be
dead doesn't have to have any relevance in the fullness
of just now this moment where love can flow or Delight where
Freedom can be where the heart is not dimmed where the heart is not obscured
where these thoughts that are heavy don't get in the way don't interfere
but we're simply looking out the window and seeing the leaves and the trees blow
and blow in the Wind can seem like looking at Paradise the
jewels not because it is you've seen it many times before but the quality of now when
presence is so rich and so unobscured and so
unencumbered by the things that dim it that
keep it from seeing the sparkle
so um now
a Kaliko immediate here
to be seen in this life to be seen here
to be seen now this is the Dharma of the Buddha
and so I'd like to recommend that um for this day that you carry with you
the English word now
and um and um and if you want to do some little I like
to play word games letter games um and if the you take the first two
words of now no and think of the W as being the first letter of a another word
it's so now it's then for no waiting
no waiting just now
and um no wishing
just now now so to carry that with you
and not that you're able to stay in the now but as I said at the beginning of this
little talk made it this mindfulness meditation is not so much about being successful and
being mindful and the way we might think of being now but in saying now
seeing more clearly what you are doing now we're so much an automatic pilot so much
Carried Away by our thoughts and involved in things we don't really see in some higher quality way what is what
we're actually doing now so this word now
show up for yourself see what's happening here don't be an automatic pilot
and when you're now what is the most important thing
what would be the most important thing if you had only one more hour to live
and I hope you can do this exercise for many hours so thank you very much and um
I want to make one announcement and I'll make it again but I wanted to
make sure that you a number of you can hear it if in case you don't come you're not here when I announce it again
um so for the next three weeks after this week starting on Sunday I will be
on Retreat teaching every three week retreat and so I won't be able to do these seven AMS the last week that uh I'm away uh
Matthew Brent silver will come back and teach uh I wasn't able to find someone for the
next two weeks the people are on Retreat doing doing all kinds of things that I normally would invite
and um so what we're going to do is to replay
the uh two weeks of these sittings and Dharma talks that I did in December of
2020. a week on loving kindness in a week on compassion and I think these are quite important
topics and so I think that the topics are still fresh even though the talks
are almost two years old and so that's the plan and so you want uh some of you
might not even notice that I'm not here because I think it'll be played in a way
that looks like it's fresh though you'll see that I'm younger maybe in maybe longer hair or something so um
so thank you and I look forward to tomorrow