so good morning everyone
and perhaps i hear that getting ready for meditation
i'm already becoming quiet
maybe if i look for words to say i won't find any but if i maybe just talk maybe
they'll come
one of the teachings implications of buddhist buddhism
is that nothing that we see and touch and smell
and hear uh
or say this is the way everything that we see and touch and hear and smell and
and even think is made up of parts
is made up of other things is a composite
made up of things that have proceeded that led to it conditions that led to it
and also um coming together of different elements
different other things and those things are composite as well
and in that composite nature of these things there are actually no things
they're only processes some things arise and persist for a
while and then they pass but one way the other all things are in
process and when we look at our inner life our emotional life
our mental life the things that we can know there uh
except for concepts ideas give the semblance of nouns of things
that this is the way it is but
all our emotions our thoughts our body sensations everything that we can
feel and experience and sense is made up of other parts
it's a composite and in some way or other is in process
and moving and it's when we get caught in nouns
it's possible to be caught in nouns and this is the way it is
that we get hung up we get caught we suffer we
leave the river of change we leave the dynam dynamism
of a life made up of all the comings and goings of our life the life around us
this dynamic inter interdependent process
interdependently rising of phenomena so
we sit to meditate in the middle of many many things that make us up
this moment we are dynamic processes
though our thinking might not think so
so assuming a meditation posture
and the posture you take is a composite made up of different
parts of the body assuming different positions
the body itself is composite made up of bones and
flesh and muscles and organs and nerves skin hair
and we take this composite body this and assume a posture that
promotes attentiveness
to here and now
and then to gently close your eyes
one of the dynamic processes that's costly shifting and changing
one of the important pieces of the whole is our breathing
and to gently breathe more deeply
we're fully maybe three quarters full
and a long exhale settling in
to the body
exhaling and relaxing into the body
and letting the breathing return to normal
in an ordinary life part of the composite of who we are that contributes to the whole
is the tension we have in our body the holding patterns
we create a different whole when we begin to relax and
let go the body
on the exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
on the exhale softening the shoulders
softening the belly
and then to settle your attention into the body breathing
feeling the movements of the body as you breathe
and the experience we call breathing is a composite made up of
other parts other activities
it's made up of the inhale and the exhale
the movements of the body
the air going in and out through the nostrils
one way or other the breathing is under the influence of often under the influence of our
mood or emotional state
breathing is under the influence of the level of excite the level of excitement in the body
activation
breathing is little bit influenced by it whatever degree of
pleasure discomf comfort or discomfort
that comes along with the experience of breathing
the experience of breathing is made up of
the choices we make the interests the ideas we have about breathing and
about how to notice breathing where in the body to pay attention
and finally part of the experience of breathing
is the awareness of breathing itself
without some awareness there's no experiencing of breathing
and all these things all these parts of the experience
i don't think we can very well control them or guide them or
make them be just right
perhaps you can surrender into the experience of breathing
let it be what it is a dynamic process
made up of many parts
that you can allow to operate as it does and for you
just to be aware of it
so
minutes
uh
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
one part of human life is
what motivates us the wishes we have
and of course there are many wishes many motivations to be had
we end with the particular form of love good will friendliness
that is wishing well for others being motivated
to bring about the welfare and happiness of others
and may it be as we end this meditation
that we spend these next two minutes reflecting and thinking about
whatever motivation we have whatever desire wish we have for the that others be well
that others be happy safe
our wishes for the welfare and happiness of everyone
may all may everyone be happy
may everyone be safe
may everyone be peaceful
may everyone be free
and may it be that each of us also has the wish
to contribute to that may it be
that we contribute to the welfare and happiness of all beings
so
thank you
so today i'll continue this five-part series on getting wise to emotions
a wise relationship to them and part of it is to realize that
emotions are not a singular uni uh unitary thing
but they are composites they are made up of the elements and pieces
and they're made up of elements in different ways different parts make up emotions in different ways
and maybe that's part of the reason why it's not so clear exactly what an emotion is
and we don't have to know exactly what an emotion is as a category we might want to know what anger is or
we might want to know sadness or happiness or love there's a whole range of these things
that fit under the umbrella term of emotions and whichever ones we fit in there
[Music] they are composites they're made up of component parts
and why that's important is that sometimes people will have
attitudes beliefs relationships to emotions
with it with the idea that it's a singular thing anger is anger and it justifies things
it drives us it we have relationship to anger as a you know it's good it's bad
but when we start kind of not looking at it as only as a solid singular thing
but start seeing the component parts then we can have relationship to the different parts
and the relationship to the whole becomes different we might realize that some of the elements that
can make up an emotion are actually more important and perhaps
more important for for our motivations for understanding
for our healing for finding our freedom with it all
sometimes it's hard to uh work with an emotion when we only see it as a
singularity as a solid thing in and of itself and
and it can be kind of overwhelming but once we kind of drop down underneath the veneer underneath the label or the
general kind of solitary concept we begin seeing it in a different way and have a whole different relationship to
what's happening so i'd like to offer you some of the things that make up emotions and you
maybe you can think of some more as well so part of an emotion is
a bodily experience a physiological shift in change that
happens in the body when an emotion becomes present for some people the physiological change
is very strong and clear for some people it's very quiet and maybe even they
would say there is no physiological change but i think that emotion is always something and the quieter we become and
meditation for example the more attuned we can be to even the subtlest changes
of physiology as we have emotions activations of uh
muscles of energies probably of hormones and biochemical things that all this
stuff begins to shift and change in the body as we as emotion arise as it persists and as it dissipates
some of that physiological change might precede the actually rising of the emotion
itself we might have a lot of stress and the stress hormones the stress
sensations that tightness in their body is a condition
for the arising of anger and
or fear and and and it we might and that the condition
that precedes it in the body is often sometimes the way to heal it as well
because sometimes as the body relaxes and settles then the fuel for the particular emotion
is not being provided the physiologic physiology sometimes
drives the emotional lives so dropping down into the body and really
getting familiar with all the different bodily expressions of emotions bodily
manifestations of them is it can be very important
another thing that makes up a good number of emotions is cognitive and we might start with the
stories that we have um you know it's a kind of a classic
thing in meditation is to be relatively calm and peaceful and minding your own business with your
breathing and for some reason that is not obvious at all your mind produces a thought from long
ago of a person you knew maybe a person who harmed you or hurt you or annoyed you
and and uh and just thinking about that story and what happened to that person
our physiology changes the energy in the body that maybe goes from being centered in our
torso and up into our head maybe the hands get tight their jaws get tight
or they feel a contraction in the mind and because the story still has a lot of
juice a lot of impact on us and what's fascinating there is to see
that the movement is from the story that arises to the story is a condition for the
bodily manifestation and the body was fine by itself
but then the story kind of evokes something very powerful
and then the bodily expression came and uh when stories are part of emotions
then when we we are we can be if we are storytellers telling
and retelling the story that can perpetuate the emotion that can keep it going can strengthen it can
can influence very much the course of the emotion because of the nature of the
storytelling sometimes the stories change as we tell it and so then the emotions change as
well and we might have started off for example being angry and we telling our story about
about how we've been you know slighted by someone and then we tell ourselves a story well
if that person knows that i'm angry they'll probably retaliate and now i'm afraid and
and now suddenly fear arises and then uh we realized something with
another story we maybe we realized oh the person's actually moving to another continent
and um and they said never going to come back to this country and and then you say oh you can feel yourself relax and
then there's a happiness that might arise and so we tell ourselves stories and the stories have meaning
associations another part of this component part of
emotions that's sometimes more obvious with the story is that there's a self in relationship
to the emotion self understanding self how we view ourselves how we
have other people see us how we are personally affected by the story the
events of what's going on what emotions mean for me what's going to happen if i'm
maybe i feel happy and and i'm the one who's happy i'm so happy that i'm happy and
and um and this will be great my life is made i'm gonna be happy forever
and um and there's a lot of uh eye making and me making and part of the happiness might be in relationship to
i'm the one who's happy and so the the self-identification with the emotion
and the role of i and self-understanding of who i am and how that that's a
component part of motions as well i'll talk more about that tomorrow
and there's also motivation that's part of the
emotion um i talked about that a little bit with metta earlier that
emotion like loving kindness is one that has motivation built into it
it's wishing someone well wanting them to be well maybe wanting to support that to happen
if there is anger there is a motivation perhaps to get rid of something to push it away
and get angry with your computer and you throw it across the room to kind of get it away
there is some emotions come with motivations and intention uh something needs wanting something to
happen and sometimes that's really helpful to notice what motivation comes along with an
emotion what motivation comes along with sadness or what comes along with joy
just noticing this shift and changes what's what what wants to what's the motivation what's the desire
that's connected to it emotions are also connected to
perceptions um and it's a little different than the stories but overlaps with them
and that is um what we what we are what we think we're perceiving the ideas
we have about things and the um
there's a ancient chinese story of that the vignette that's told of a man who's in a
sailboat going across a lake big lake and another sailboat comes along and
unexpectedly bangs into his sailboat and the person gets furious
and then he lifts up and looks over the edge of the boat and sees that there's no one in the other boat it's just
somehow gotten loose since floating around and the anger was there
thinking there was a person in charge that they could be angry with and then the person realized well
he should always be attentive to what's floating around and paying attention
and [Music] we perceive things a lot differently
when it's done by some another person versus if it's done by
a natural phenomenon if a if some beautiful
deer maybe walks across your garden
uh maybe you're upset uh or maybe you've never seen a deer in your property that haven't been around
for you know hundreds of miles and you're like rather than upset you're just like amazed wow there's a deer with it's fawn
and and and but if a neighbor comes across and walks across your garden maybe accidentally
um there's a lot that we perceive it differently and we interpret it differently
are the perceptions we make the most useful perceptions are they optional are they particular
interpretation of events maybe they're good perceptions good interpretations but to see it as that
way so these are some of the i can go on further but um
to spend some time looking at your emotions as they occur uh at what is the
physiology of it what is the stories related to it
what are the motivations related to it what are the what's the how do how are
you as a person as a self as a your identity your idea of yourself how does that come into play
and what are the perceptions and ideas that operate when an emotion is there
and are they built into the fabric in the of the universe that that's the perception the idea the interpretation
to have or are there others to be had there are others that are more
maybe appropriate or more peaceful and and maybe there's a range of interpretations
and maybe they're all equally valuable but why choose the one that's stressful
for you maybe choose one that brings you a sense of awe and delight and joy
so um so what you might do this next
you know 24 hours is take some time to
sit down maybe with a piece of paper and and kind of map out
the different component parts that make up your emotion and
different ones you have especially the ones that are live but also you can review other ones you've had
and maybe lay them down piece of paper like a little mind map or you know like a mandala of what they all are
and then consider the component parts themselves what kind of permanence what kind of
solidity what kind of art do they have what kind of relationship do you have to
the parts and as you begin looking more carefully at the parts of
an emotion what happens to the emotion does the emotion shift and change
in surveying the parts that make it up so thank you
and i hope your emotional life is rich and valuable and
supportive for you and if it's not i hope that this deeper investigation into it
will be supportive thank you