welcome back and welcome for the first time david
come on in make yourself comfortable um
so hello youtube people out there welcome
if you have questions along the way feel free to place them in the chat and we'll be checking in that periodically
so how was your practice this week
invited you to you know continue to sit
every day right um let's see there was an invitation to
spend a couple hours with your body being aware of your body as you were
engaging
what else were you invited to do anybody remember my homework assignments
mindful eating have a meal mindfully great so i'm jogging your memory and then i'll
also sort of summarize a few of the key things that we focused on last week in the class
at least they were key to me and one was
that sensations are the language of the body and feeling
them is the way that the body is heard right so tuning into them
and and doing it in a ideally trying to meet those sensations
without a lot of mental interpretation protection projections
but more like in the raw data kind of way of listening
and we talked about how the body is a gateway to the present moment
that when we connect with the body in the present moment and the sensations
and the breath these things are only happening right here
right in this moment so it's a nice way for us to help bring our
awareness into the present moment yeah
we also talked about um pain and the conditions cotto talked about
the conditions of that creep pain or like the conditions that create the formations of different
clouds right so different conditions come together and like clouds
they also keep shifting and changing and the pain sensations can we be with them
in a way that is tracking and noticing the change the changing nature of the experience
instead of as a fixed unmoving thing
so with those prompts i'm wondering if anybody has any reflections questions
anything they'd like to share from their practice this week
and there's a sveta has a microphone so if you can speak into it that would be
very helpful for everyone's sake
maybe richard will come get the microphone and help hand it around assuming we have somebody willing to
to share
and hold it close to your mask thanks um so i have
more of a question which may be helpful as a kind of bridging point between this last meeting and today but
how can you stay present and aware and not get involved with um
i guess like mental narratives with bodily sensations that are closely also tied up in emotions so
say like i don't know like kind of difficulty breathing or tightness like well the solar plexus like
in my experience at least when i tried to like be with it it like launches me right into the like emotional part of
things
so as you remember that experience
how can you describe the physical sensations that you experienced are there words that you have
um so i guess just like um tightness or constraints it kind of like
like clearly like impeded breathing activity um tightness con constriction and i didn't
get that other word i guess like um an impeded like breathing
if that makes sense what's the word impeded impeded impeded yeah impeded great okay
yeah so that's all descriptive language
[Music] so
meaning there it's pointing to an experience a feeling the one that's maybe a little bit more mentally
complicated is impeded right
pressure pressure can you notice the pressure
and be with it or and notice if it's changes with the inhale and exhale
you're able to do that yeah so
and then so you're able to say all these things but you find that the mind then wants to go into the emotional content
and uh maybe explain why you're feeling this way or
yeah yeah yeah and you
clearly saw that was happening and then you would bring yourself back to the sensations
i definitely tried um but yeah i found myself kind of flowing right into the kind of
like i don't know there's no like better word for it than just like ah sensation of
like this does not feel good this does not go right yeah so um this is where then the you
did the vedana like naming unpleasant so having some of these key simple words
to realign can be really helpful unpleasant this is unpleasant
right there's neutral unpleasant and pleasant so this is great and then what else
happened um i found myself like sticking with that kind of like emotional feeling of
it like you you gotta get closer i can't hear you yeah sorry um i find myself
like kind of leaning into the emotional experience instead of the the bodily one which is where i felt like i was like
getting off track great but you you can you just described it beautifully i found myself leaning into the emotional
experience right it's more compelling right yeah
so it sounds like you know you were practicing with difficult emotions trying to bring awareness back to the
body and describing what it feels like to have the
experience of difficult emotions which are quite powerful right they can be quite powerful
and it is a beautiful lead-in to today's topic
yeah and so i'll save you know saying more about working with the
emotions themselves but i really do want to highlight all the things that you were able to describe right and this is this is the
practice we're cultivating you know and it's beautiful you clearly were trying to okay i know but let me try and stay
with the body that's what i'm trying to do this week which is building this capacity so that's
going back to the sort of the way the class is structured is it really does build
one week concentric circles starting with that breath awareness
and then we add to that the body based sensations and this week we're going to add to that
the emotions and then you'll find pretty quickly we're going to what's next
they're going to show up there too those thoughts those little buggers yeah so
um just you know doing our best to try and help ourselves notice just even noticing how entangled
and difficult it is to resist is beautiful
yeah do you want to add anything cardo i don't think quite yet i think uh i think that was the perfect
segue into week number three thank you why don't you go ahead and shift sure
sure yeah so we'll come back everyone
as tanya was just saying uh the way the class is structured beginning with the breathing
including the body with the basis of the breathing in the body awareness of emotions
with the basis of awareness of breathing body and emotions then we develop our skills with thinking
and then open even more broadly
and the arc here what we're doing is we're cultivating this very simple
faculty of attention cultivating this very simple faculty of
attention in order to be more free
with all aspects of our experience nothing left out
so we develop our facility in a simple place first with the body running or with the breathing right in the core and
then we work our way but throughout something we're practicing is maintaining a simple
relationship to experience so to go back to the breathing
the practice with the breathing has been to direct the attention to the sensations of breathing
a felt sense of breathing through the body experiencing the experience in the breathing almost from the inside
out and by basing ourselves there basing ourselves in that felt sense
we have a more simple relationship to the experience can easily become complicated by
drawing out a story in the past or the future about the breathing but just here
just the felt sense of breathing so simple so simple
so we're using our attention to go more deeply into our own experience
and to discover something about how attention can be free
something we cultivated while working with the breathing in the body was
based on a recognition many of us have seen over these weeks
probably the mind keeps generating thoughts keeps generating emotions through the
body so we're developing a skill knowing that of foreground attention
and background attention if we're meditating on the breathing
keeping those sensations of the breathing in the foreground and if a thought comes up it can just
pass right through it doesn't have to take all of our attention but it doesn't have to
interfere either so sustaining contact with the breathing
body in this way just more and more of our experience gets revealed
we notice details of the breathing notice details of the body
they shift they change and then something else arises
so the practice has been to focus on the breathing and then when something else uh becomes compelling when something
else an experience becomes compelling maybe a strong thought so far we've been focusing on
if a body sensation becomes compelling and compelling enough to interfere so to
speak to draw our attention away from the breathing compelling enough to draw our attention
then the practice is to turn more fully toward that and get to know that sensation and once that uh once that has run its
course to come back to the breathing i'm reiterating all this in part because
this is the basis for what we're about to expand into which is practice with emotion
i'd like to say by way of preface practicing with mindfulness of the body
can facilitate a very long awakening of the body it can be a it can be a sustained
process i think it's really fruitful to spend a lot of time with mindfulness of the body to develop that
develop that skill and we'll see why as we turn to mindfulness of emotions
one of the things we come to learn about about through mindfulness of the body is how the body is big enough
metaphorically it's a big enough container to hold pleasant and unpleasant it's big enough for anything to pass
through whatever the experience
so let's turn more directly toward emotions first thing i'd like to say about
mindfulness of emotions emotions in general very important part of our human life
i actually like to say that it's it's um this mindfulness of emotions practice is
one of the most explicit invitations we have to bring our entire humanity
into the mindfulness practice there's welcome
there is for purposes of the practice there's no inappropriate emotion
if any emotion arises during mindfulness practice nothing inappropriate
it could be anything it may be uncomfortable and uh in fact the chances are pretty
high that we'll we will run into some discomfort as we practice with emotions
um but everyone's welcome everyone's welcome
practicing mindfulness of emotions i think it's also one of these areas where we really get to know how the
practice takes time for an emotion to arise and to process through the body
it's a process that takes time and it's a process that works really well if we have trust
trust that the body can can hold the emotion and trust that the emotion will work its
way through
one of the most important principles of mindfulness of emotion is that our emotions
we recognize and experience through the body that's why mindful one of the key
reasons that we develop a skill and mindfulness of the body before we move on to mindfulness of emotions
you can even pause now and just think for yourself when i'm happy
how does it register in my body how do i know maybe there's a little lift or lift to the posture
maybe a little smile comes to your face maybe there's some bright metaphorically some bright energy in the body
how do you know sadness through the body how do you know it
how do we know anger or fear or appreciation gratitude
through the body the felt sense of the body
it's very easy for the the energy of an emotion as we were just talking
about to draw us into story fascinating how that happens it's like
that it's like emotions have their own gravity their own orbit they're just like we're gone
something that's very interesting to me in terms of mindfulness practice is that a story
can strengthen the sensation of emotion in the body and the sensation in the body could also
like if it's not observed given its time given its space can also reinforce the story
and it sort of loops it can kind of leap but with the practice of mindfulness
again the story can be there but we parse the commentary from the
felt sense of the body bring our awareness down into the body
and watch how does it play out how does it play out what do we notice
and give it its time
so in terms of the capacity of the body i want to mention
i grew up near a very broad river the brazos river valley
it runs sort of diagonal across texas it's one of these really really wide rivers you can imagine
these river banks with shrubs and trees and this like flat
flat still water at the end of the river they're 3 000 meters a second going out
into the ocean there's a lot of movement happening
here i imagine the body is like the riverbed so much passes through this river
so much passes through whether the water is moving quickly whether the water is moving slowly
the riverbed just holds it and allows it to pass through same with the body and emotions
if the body is like the riverbed and the emotions like the water sometimes they flow through quickly
sometimes they flow through slowly but all the while the body the body
holds it all
great timing i i have a um i have a i'm a type 1 diabetic and i have a
little beep so i'm actually going to pay attention to my body and care for this it'll take me about 30
seconds
richard it might be a little cool
so one of the things i'd like to call forward with the this image of the river this image of
the riverbed and the holding of water as it passes through is that change
is part of the process and change is totally fine sometimes sometimes these uh
big thunderstorms would roll through and fill the fill the river with a rush of water and sticks and you can
imagine waves and whatnot water might be cloudy and rough
but still the riverbed was right there other times we wouldn't have rain for months and this riverbed would be so
still so still any variety of emotion can pass right through the body
one thing i also want to draw out from this from this image of the river is we also want to take care of
ourselves not to be an overwhelm when we're practicing with mindfulness of emotions you can imagine
say there's too much flow or there's a flood in the river that can actually like harm the banks or we start eroding
from the edges so taking care with yourself taking care of yourself
i think one more idea about mindfulness mindfulness of emotions is
that in terms of in terms of mindfulness we're not condemning and we're not condoning any emotion at all
this is part of part of the fact that uh whatever object arises
it can it can be met with a clear attention in such a way that our mindfulness is strengthened even if it's
uncomfortable so all this pointing toward a simple
relationship with emotions as they arise so there's a story classic
classic story of the buddha he's with an assembly many of you have probably heard this
story before he says uh it was a pop quiz for the assembly
and he says monks suppose someone were struck with a dart would that hurt if someone were struck
with an arrow would that hurt and the monks were sharp and they said oh yes that would hurt
good now if someone were struck with a second arrow would that hurt all the more
yeah yes yes it would good good he says you're right
the first arrow is the discomfort the pain
the suffering that is part of this human life
a function of having a human body and in the second arrow
the third arrow the fourth arrow are the complicated relationships we stack on top
generalizing as far as emotions are concerned being with them simply
they run their course they've come and they've gone so much of how we suffer in relationship
to emotion is how we complicate it what we add the uh the stories of
say self-judgment or criticism or doubt or
they shouldn't have or i shouldn't have or on and on right we all have our own
variety uh gil has a hilarious i think anecdote
of walking along and stubbing his toe first arrow
pain of having a human body
then then he adds gil who's been teaching for 35 years gil
you're um you're a mindfulness teacher you're a buddhist teacher you should really be paying attention
second arrow second arrow a little self-judgment and then it gets worse
gil you are the worst walker the self-criticism intensifies third
arrow more complication and we could go on and on from there it
could it could go they really should not have put that sidewalk there
that curb really really shouldn't be there that is totally their fault fourth arrow and on it goes right fifth
six seven eight nine and so on at some point we wake up and we realize oh 100 arrows
while we're emphasizing a simple relationship just that moment of waking up
you're you're right back here you're right back here it doesn't doesn't matter for the purposes of
mindfulness practice if you wake up at arrow 99 just that you're right back here
so we will stub our toes i imagine or hurt our fingers or
we will have an emotional life and the encouragement here is to
investigate for yourself what are the ways what are the ways in which i can have a simple relationship with the emotions
that are that are coming here what are the ways that that happens and then what are the ways that i complicate
it what are the ways that i magnify or multiply
the suffering
i think it's a good time for us to move a little deeper into this in a guided meditation
so we find ourselves in a upright
alert balanced posture
we're looking for
a posture that can express our attentiveness
awake yet relaxed
and before we move into the meditation very far
the invitation this exercise is to feel into whether there's any mood
present any emotion present for you now most always there's something there so
maybe give it a moment if it's not obvious some kind of state
what's there
so from here the invitation is to begin directing our attention to the breathing
it may help us settle in to take a few long slow deep breaths
just at your own pace
and then letting the breathing return to its natural rhythm
awakening this felt sense through the body
relaxing any places of obvious holding
a gentle relaxation maybe of the face
the eyes themselves
mouth and jaw
maybe the back of the head
shoulders down the back
inviting the front body to relax
the arms and hands
the hips seat
legs
and the feet
and now sensing into the breathing
taking just a little bit of priority
to notice any shift in your relationship to the breathing from simple
to complicated
and noting that returning to simplicity
now i would like to invite you to let go of the priority of breathing
of attention to breathing and turn your attention to
the prevailing mood or any emotion
state
sensing into that emotion through the body
where do you feel it and how
in the language of sensation the felt sense
as you attend to the emotion through the body
how are those sensations shifting changing
seeming to stay the same
if the emotion disappears
just notice what happens next
now having given some attention to the emotions i invite you to bring your
attention back to the breathing
and as this sitting comes to an end
just to take a few deep breaths
long breaths
welcoming yourself and when you're ready
you can open your eyes
so [Music]
so an introduction to mindfulness of emotions
how was that for you anything you'd like to share about
the meditation any questions about what we're practicing with so far
yes
i was wondering if um it matters if our attention naturally
wanders between breathing emotions
and sometimes thoughts and awareness of the body
or is the goal to ultimately also in meditation practice
to intentionally draw our attention to one or the other
sure sure great question sort of naturally comes up doesn't it um
yeah there's the they're these separate or different but interrelated modes of attention
directed attention and sort of receptive attention and sometimes sometimes our instructions
are to look at something particular and stay with it
and at other times it's to be sort of wide open over the course of the
the the five weeks together just speaking for this particular kind
of meditation we're gradually gradually moving to include more and more
in the experience and that would mean in the in the way that you stated it
the mind or the attention will move between breathing the body emotions and
thinking the question that remains is are we with it
are we a companion with the attention as it moves from thing to thing and we'll we'll talk more about that as we as we
go there's no um there's no ultimate right answer to your question actually
it uh to my mind if we're doing a sort of a mindfulness
meditation with these kind of parameters a lot of movement of attention can
happen if we're doing something that that emphasizes more
samadhi or concentration practice we may direct the attention more deliberately to one
thing so in some sense it depends on the practice you do but in this arc we're including more and
more and along the way it can be really useful to direct the attention to just
certain zones in the way that we're directing toward the body we're directing toward emotion
directly toward thinking is that does that address yeah thank you sure
sure
or if they're not printed oh there we go in the transition i was also going to
say if there are no particular questions but there's something you'd like to share from your sitting i'd be very curious to know how it went for you um
so i identified the emotion and i sat with it and
i started to feel just like tightness heaviness in my chest
right side not quite the heart so and that was interesting
and so i just paid attention and tried to breathe through it and
eventually that sort of lifted but then it just kind of hovered over my fore front
and that's how it ended so nothing exciting just something i noticed
i appreciate the tracking very nice yeah yeah
that was my observation too
wow
okay uh hey everyone hi thank you
uh i just had a question about um what was when you see like a ball of like
energy like i saw like a white and then it just started changing colors i saw like green and purple
is that does that mean like low pressure does it doesn't mean like low blood
pressure or something i don't know i was like when we were meditating uh and i started like to relax more i
started seeing like uh just like a white thing and then it started like having colors around it oh i don't know what i
don't know what that means yeah interesting interesting yeah blood pressure i'm not a doctor
[Laughter] what's interesting to me here
as far as what it means we don't know we don't know what it means um
what is what's really interesting in terms of the mindfulness practice is that you had a very clear observation of
it yeah and how it changed over time yeah and then the that that's very direct
the sense of sight is very direct even behind closed eyes in a very clear sense what was happening
and then there's this extra layer that's maybe a little bit removed that's like the
what did that what does it mean which is even maybe separate from the impulse that is like curious right
there's like observation curiosity and then what does it mean up here maybe so yeah
i think the invitation would be to let the what does it mean hang out if it wants to be here in the
background and focus on the the direct sensate experience gotcha thank you
anything you'd like to add that was beautiful oh great yeah
yeah you guys want a little story
i feel like you know we're we're calm but emotions are not always so calm right
i was um watching uh 13 lives has anybody seen that
yeah remember the soccer team in thailand the the 13 boys and the coach
that got stuck in the cave so it's a really nice document it's a
movie but it's very much based on the story the facts
um they don't show a lot of the boys in the cave they show some of them
and the boys with the coach at the very like i don't know it was like two kilometers three kilometers into the
cave right there many crazy passages and these other
areas the cable open and tight and there's all these stag delights dropping down so these sharp
cones of rock coming from the ceiling and most of this is just completely filled with water it's just a monsoon
rain that that got them stuck and um so the kids it was one of the kids
birthday that day they had practice they had played soccer and they were all like well let's go to the cave before we go
have your birthday dinner and so they're in this cave and and they get stuck
and it's a total of 18 days in there and at some point uh and it was probably
quite a while before they even got them any food they they were just in there and you know like in their shorts and
t-shirts and um they showed this moment
because the some divers finally made it all the way and
you know the kids turn on their flashlights when they hear the sound to see because they had some flashlights a
couple flashlights and they keep them off mostly for the battery but you know they see those
divers come in and um and then the divers have to leave and
they're like oh my gosh really we have to stay you know they can't take them back right and
so then they're kind of trying to get settled again and and one of the kids um
starts to kind of be activated be afraid
and um sort of he's having trouble sitting still because they're all kind of like you know there's not not a lot of space
they're just kind of hanging out in this little spot so the coach
what a sweet coach this guy was apparently but he he went over to the kid and
he said okay so fear is here fears come in fears come into the body
that's what's what's happening here so okay everybody let's sit down and calm
our minds let's calm our minds and
this this must have been that they did this amen and that's what they talked about is he taught them how to meditate
to make it through this time and i think you know fear is like
lightning right it's so intense
and if you can imagine it in a small space with water and a little cave
fear coming into that how it would just spread
right just just ignite just just fill you up
and this is the practice what guides us and helps us is building
the awareness is building our capacity to be mindful with
emotions helps us sit down and be with it in a
way that it doesn't just blow up right
another analogy is it's like um if you think about lightning it's conducted by
water and things fear is conducted in our systems if we aren't mindful and
if you there was a recent story of three women um being hit by lightning near the white
house under a tree in a rainstorm one of them had on these doc martin high platform doc martin
shoes and she survived and
it's not that she wasn't affected by the lightning but the doc martin the rubber doesn't
conduct the lightning in the same way and to me this is a simile for what
awareness being mindful can do with emotions and emotions can't kill us but they can
make us very miserable and emotions without
a lot of doc martin awareness
can really move and undulate and impact us and kind of we can get in circles
caught in circles with our thinking and the even the feedback loops of just the emotion itself
each emotion if you measure it biochemically lasts about 60 to 90 seconds
that's how long the biochemical makeup of a particular emotion lasts
when they study it in the brain but what what why then does it feel like we have a
feeling or an emotion for hours or weeks we keep
reigniting it we keep feeding it so
this is uh i'm trying to bring a little life and to like connect us to this
facet of our life that is so impactful emotions
invite other comments questions reflections before we
move into the next part you guys yeah great and the microphone
is coming your way
thank you hello good evening um i i just have a
you know with meditating and sitting with emotions i've just been having a
hard time differentiating between being self-aware and feeling self-conscious
and so i know one is rooted in negativity
but then it's like okay i know i'm feeling bad what do i do about it you know
i don't know i and then i've been trying to
shorten the 10-minute non or unguided meditations and
i just i haven't been i haven't been like
awake for them so i'm like oh my gosh and i want to be alert but
i guess i i guess i'm not really taking enough time to take care of myself and
so now i'm back to where i started feeling frustrated and measuring how i'm meditating and
comparing all this that all the sessions thinking oh this wasn't as successful as i wanted it
to be so now you're you're starting to see a pattern maybe in your mind
maybe you just described a pattern that's nothing more than a pattern
can you see can you like maybe so you know you you feel like oh i'm not
doing it right i'm not doing it well enough so
how many arrows might might we you know
so the next thing is i'm just i'm not so do you hear what i'm saying you use tracking with me are you still so bought
up and and believing you're you're not doing it right you know so here we go
you're trying i feel like the arrows are so deeply lodged and i just enjoy
yeah really really bad because i know it catastrophize everything great great and
i just it's it but it's just something that i i i've done for many many
compelling it's compelling it's habit it's a pattern
right and you know um kodo used the word um that it's a
i don't know has energy magnetic energy emotions i often talk about um emotions
as their intention is to get you to do something
they're they're they you know what we all know what happens
what we do when we feel sad right we lose our energy we fall forward we might
cry there's a slumping energy this is what what we do right when we're happy
there's a different thing we do when we're angry so these emotions have energy in them
they come with this is why i like the lightning like there's a lot of energy in them
and so and now what you're describing too is like okay you have a little it sounds
like a little um spurt of self-criticism or doubt right
and so you get a little release of that that that that emotion and then that emotion triggers the same
but maybe stronger and then you know it just sort of has this perpetual kind of cyclical cycle
in it right is this familiar to you guys maybe your words are a little different
but can you look around you are not alone you are not alone what you are seeing is
it's so good you could name it right there here and do this right it and the fact that you can see
it is is amazing now we just need to get disenchanted
right to to learn how to when that so that energy that emotion comes up
it bumps up the energy right it like oh okay so can we just ride that 60 90
120 second emotion out okay okay and then you know watch it
fade the mind's going to want to grab it's one of going to want to go and offer
another arrow but can we just learn to
and then enjoy even 15 seconds before the next you know like we're just gonna try and stretch it out
make it less intense are you tracking me am i with you you with me we got it okay
everybody else you tracking this is our work the work is in not responding
not reacting not following the compulsion
and that's a lot of work it gets exhausting
and it's also freedom it brings us you know
this i don't know your name but you know you did a beautiful job describing how the feeling which didn't sound so
comfortable started in your chest and you watched it and you tracked it and it shifted and it moved and then it went
away and this is this is what we're learning how to do
to let it move through and the though those extra arrows we
start to see oh there's another one okay all right i don't you know like we lose interest in them
don't buy it it's not a fact and we'll get to thoughts next week
because this is this is you see we're leading we go into emotions and then we're going to we're going to find the
thinking because they're it's all connected but if we can try and see it energetically yeah
yeah so any clarifying question comment anything at all for you
no okay
yeah that would be nice
all right so i just want to double check before i start to move into just talking
a little bit more about emotions and then a practice to work with them i'm going
to offer you a practice but just before i do any other final
little comments or questions nope okay
so ordinary awareness when we're not mindful um
is you know with the experience of getting carried away in our thinking carried
down the river by our motions it's the ship that isn't anchored
right and so that's that's the untrained mind
that's the the mind without mindfulness without awareness
daniel goldman is a psychologist and researcher
and he studied a lot about emotional intent intelligence and emotions themselves
and here's a little teeny tiny quote from him he says self-awareness
is a neutral mode neutral mode a mode of being
so you were talking about self consciousness versus self-awareness so the self-awareness the mindfulness is
more of a neutral state it's not for and against right it's aware it's present
that maintains self-reflectiveness even in the midst of turbulent emotions
even in the midst of turbulent emotions so that's what we're wanting to grow
right and we really do have this innate it's
already happening it's in you there's an innate capacity to be aware in this way
it gets covered over by reactivity and our thoughts and our
all kinds of things but it's here it's right inside of you each one of you
and you know we may want to do spiritual bypassing around emotions
i don't get angry i'm not jealous right there's a lot of ways that
we want to maybe be that better person but you know emotions
we're humans we're humans and they're we're going to have all kinds of emotions and
you can't block the negative without blocking the positive
it's a flow thing so we got to learn how to be wise with
them we got to learn how to you know be that riverbed and
maybe we're not ready to be that big and wide of a riverbed but maybe we can be a small riverbed for
two minutes at a time to let it move and then we need to take a break and
then we come back two more minutes of letting it move okay okay you know and maybe that's what it's like for a while
but this is how in bit by bit this is how we grow our capacity
this is how we do it
okay i think i'm going to introduce a practice now [Music]
it's called raft and it has several steps to it it's on your
handout and so you don't have to try and
you know memorize at all the handouts are on the stage and they're also
online with the talks and raft is
a wonderful word to think about because actually this is in a simile the buddha taught
he taught that growing mindfulness is like building a raft and that it carries
us from the shore of suffering to the shore of freedom
and you know he taught that you build this raft you have to bring the sticks and
the twigs and the things together and the rope and tie them together to create and build this
raft that carries you while you're kicking and paddling to get from one shore to
the other so this is this is that work we don't just float
we have to work to get to this other place this other shore
and we're not going to be tying sticks together to build our raft but we are
building you know by using our mindfulness practice
our breath right all the things that we're learning
all become like the sticks that were kind of holding us up helping us cross
the river so the first part of building this raft
is to recognize the r r a f t t in my reversion raft with an
extra t recognizing is absolutely essential we need to recognize what's going on
recognize the looping recognize you know the that we're suffering the
emotion and it can be really simple oh i'm angry
just like that oh i'm frustrated
oh i think i'm stupid oh i guess i'm being self-critical right just
this recognition a pure little simple seeing what's going on
this is the beginning this is this is necessary beginning
the next part of building the mindfulness with what's happening is the a
which is working to allow ourselves to be with what is
so allowing it allowing ourselves to be with what is means kind of being able to
ride that 60 120 second wave of the emotion
without trying to get rid of it or adding to it we've gotta we've got to work on this
capacity of allowing because it's that capacity of being with that allows
things to move when we don't allow we're trying to block we're shutting down right we're
trying to we're closing something that should be moving
it's different than endorsing allowing does not mean
you know i'm agreeing with sometimes there's things that are going on that we
if we start to get complicated um it's not that we're allowing ourselves
to be abused or somebody else to be abused it's it's a working with an experience we're having in the present
moment does that make sense okay f
r a f we're going to the body we're going to feel it
we're helping ourself not just get carried into that emotional thought
stream that we've been talking about so we're going to slow it down we're going to find it and feel it in our
bodies so you've had some great examples of
people describing that finding feeling tracking right so that's it it's so simple
and not easy okay and then um the next part of the raft is
to start to when so at some point you may
it may be so simple what's going on for you you've been that emotion that 60 seconds 120 seconds
it's over it's resolved there may be nothing more for you to do
but if it's a complicated situation or tends to get re-triggered
the next part is teasing apart and that's where we start to do
we're gonna kind of start to see that thought pattern
and say oh this is a thought this is the judgment
right and and so okay here's the judgment and here's the feeling we're teasing apart these things oh and
here's a memory oh this is me when i was five and i was still having this issue
okay and so i like this image of having a large dining room table with lots of
chairs so that all the stuff that comes up i get i say you can sit down here right
here sweetheart this feeling this story this memory this belief
this thought just give them a place just invite them to have a seat and
you're creating all this room for these pieces to not be entangled with each other
and the final part of it is t the second t is
trusting so koto mentioned earlier you know it's when we're working with
emotions it's really important to have a sense of trust a trust in our capacity
to be with the emotion to know the emotion won't kill us to know the emotions will move through
this finding what we can trust is incredibly important to help us with this letting go
and finding a sense of groundedness so
let's do a small practice with raft so find your posture your meditation
posture and i'm going to invite you to bring
something to mind to work with that is connected to emotions but i highly encourage you to choose
something you know you can be with
so not choosing the hardest thing going on
so feeling your breath taking three maybe longer slower deeper breaths
feeling your feet thank you feet thank you body right here
right here giving your weight giving your weight to the chair
to the floor
taking a minute to resource yourself before you bring an emotional
event or memory forward
and when you're ready bring to mind
something that you feel you can be with and so we're using our imagination right
now so you're going to help yourself by
bringing forward some story and some images perhaps words
maybe remember what you were feeling
and then when you're ready just turn toward what you're aware of feeling right now
right here so you're practicing in the present moment with what you're feeling in the present
moment based on a memory or story
recognize simple naming okay
whatever emotion you can name right now
can you just say okay this emotion is here right now
i see you and i sense you and then can i allow you
to exist with awareness can i allow this experience to happen
right now and if there's a sense of yes
find and feel it in your body if there's a sense of no i can't allow
this then work with okay i can't allow not
allowing is happening and can you allow not allowing can you
allow resistance to be known and then find and feel a resistance
so taking a moment to scan the whole body
maybe noticing areas the body feels neutral and fine
and noticing where you're feeling the emotion and maybe noticing pleasant unpleasant
or neutral
and let's time i'm going to give you uh 60 seconds to just see if you can ride
like a wave just ride simply the emotion that's present
before we move into the next phase
so
and now just noticing what's here now
maybe opening up around it creating that sense of spaciousness
maybe imagining that giant round table
and are there things that you would like to invite to have a seat that are part of
this experience that you've been working with my mother
my boss my kid just what's there
can you kind of recognize and allow each
each part the memory
the story the belief the interpretation the reactivity
it all has its own place us
being generous and curious
nothing needs to happen right now just getting to know what all is present
you know it's possible to have tea with any one of these visitors
and it's possible that you might need some of them to wait a while before you're ready to sit down with them and
that's okay
so at this point in the meditation we're gonna shift when you're ready so
there's enough room for you to finish up what you're doing and and then connect with what you can trust
here
trusting the dharma trusting the fact that you can be with these emotions that you
could do as well as you did with this practice however well that was
can you trust that giving spaciousness helps pausing helps
breathing helps being present helps
just take another minute with a space of trust cultivating
it by attending to it
resting in it
maybe noticing that you're okay
and we tend to want to move away quickly from what resources us
i want to invite you to linger here three to five conscious breaths
breathing with what we trust
so
so raft recognize allow
find and feel tease apart trust
so open to any response any reflection
i'll start by prompting around trust what did you trust what
could you place your trust in anybody willing
to share i guess richard yeah this is for you
you all sat here so i know you found something to trust
um so i'm doing this practice as part of
like therapy um ifs and so um it's internal family systems and so i uh i
trust the lazy part of me great it's a sloth and so like
just wants to sleep and sit all day and so it's gonna this is perfect great beautiful so you have that resource
right there okay i can just rest with this i know how to be still beautiful
anybody else and again wide open took any comments
and questions this is uh such a richness there's so much richness
in working with our emotions
yeah great richard i it was there was a lot it was like a dam
that was overflowing with you know at first i'm like okay i can deal with
a disappointment and then something else took over that was kind of masquerading
as what i thought i was going to want to think about and
and but i trusted myself and knowing that i could
have that awareness to be a small riverbed as kodo had mentioned it was
uh but it was still something that i had to you know
sit with but no but when you had said after the 90 seconds because that's how long usually an emotion emotionless like
okay let me not get carried away with the same story that i tell myself but it's
i wish i had you in my head every now and then whenever i want to loop into that but i
know i could tell myself like that's right there was like a table of all those negative emotions and on the other
side was like faith and family and and i'm like you know they could have a seat at the table but
i don't have to keep serving or feeding the one thing that i choose to feed yes
you know yes choice beautiful beautiful
um so kind of going off what she said joyce i
trusted that i could make space for this thing that i'm feeling or
whatever um you want to call it and it's not because
you had said like you can allow yourself to like confront it i
don't you don't use the word confront but you can or not so i was like i see you but i'm not
gonna talk to you you can have a space here so it's the same thing as like you can sit down but i'm not gonna save you
anything or not ready yet so anyway you're not alone
beautiful it's so so helpful right to be able to be wise
and to sort of say okay i see you here and i know i can't quite dance with you right
now right it's okay have a seat maybe we'll tangle later
[Laughter] yeah what else happened for you guys
hi i'm learning great hold on richard can you bring him great
hello so um i'm just i'm just explaining why i went outside is uh i went into
a memory that we brought about strong emotion
and usually how i deal with strong emotion is to exercise
so i just did some push-ups outside but
typically i'm in like a yoga studio so when i do push-ups it's not a disturbance to others
um but i was just thinking i really need to lift weights right now so they can
uh you know get back to that kind of get the endorphins
in and all that stuff so but yeah it was a nice
setting to explore emotion beautiful um and uh it's
just strong emotion so i gotta beautiful that's so wise i'm so glad you gave yourself you know
permission to trust your wisdom right to trust what you know works for you and we all
i really want to commend you and thank you for taking care of yourself and doing that it's beautiful
all right well thank you yeah thank you
do you want this i think i'll just use this
we've just about come to uh another close breathing body emotions
i'd like to just mention a couple of suggested bits of homework
for the week as we've been saying all along um
if you meditate between the sessions can really help prepare you for the next
for the next one if you only meditate while you're here i can't speak for tanya that's fine with
me just fine with me and it can really put you in a good
place to pick up the next bit of material if you have some practice with what we just did
so we will encourage you to this time lengthen your sessions to 25 minutes
daily um at least once during the week see if you
get an opportunity to ride out the emotion that tanya was talking about 60 90 120 seconds
when that emotion comes on if you feel up for it take a seat in your chair
or wherever you're comfortable and just say just for those
60 90 120 seconds i'm not going to get up i'm just going to stay right here and feel this out i'm
just going to ride it out and we'll see what happens
as we're working with emotions important to keep up resourcing
important to keep our resources full i'm glad we finished with trust
one of the ways that you can practice this throughout the week is that throughout the day see if you can tune
into any just even tiny sense or feeling of well-being or
contentment or even like little pleasant emotions throughout the day we can do quite a lot when we finish
that that last exercise with three to five conscious breaths with resource that felt like way longer than i
typically spend with a resource right so we can dip into it throughout the day
and then
you can also give some some little bit of attention to something something akin to noticing
patterns it's like what kind of emotions draw you into story most easily
and give some attention to that so simple
simple three other things i want to mention i
think we can do it in the last minute uh one is a lot of what we're covering here
and much much more is uh available in this bound book called the issue at hand
that's right by the front door great essays on on this practice
so that may be it's a resource i go back to over and over for years
um also newsletters by the door too so offered freely oh thank you always
offered freely please please know that thanks richard i appreciate the reminder and just like everything else we do here
everything we offer at imc is offered freely and if you feel inspired
and want to make a contribution to help support what we do here uh there are
uh places you can give little slots by the door pretty the labels explain pretty well or there's a
kiosk around the corner and then if someone's on youtube yeah you can go to the inside
you can go to the insight meditation center all one word dot org and there's a paypal button and you can
donate on the paypal button right on right on the website so
great i feel thank you tanya i feel encouraged
thank you all for being here thank you for your practice and i look forward to
more more of this mindfulness practice next next week we'll move into
thinking see you again thank you so much