so thank you all for being here on this hot day
and um i came across a poem today by mary
oliver that i didn't know and it's had a nice impact on me it kind of
inspired me quite a bit it wasn't actually the poem that inspired me
it was the title of the poem and then i looked at it i liked the poem
well enough but i almost thought that this was probably i kind of assumed
mary oliver probably thought of the title first that was really the poem and then she
had to find a poem to go with the title
and it's a title which i think can be adapted in all kinds of significant ways
so it uses the word prayer in it some of you might not
have much connection to prayer or might actually not want to hear that word being used
generally the buddhists in our circles don't do much prayer or any prayer
so we'll see about the word so the title
is the real prayers are not in the words
the real that's half of it their real prayers are not in the words
but in the attention that comes first
but in the attention that comes first so here she's associating prayer not to
praying for something but rather a certain kind of attention
that comes first and the question is what kind of attention is that
lets you consider attention as a kind of a prayer so now we can adapt it in buddhism
buddhist terms perhaps in buddhism we talk about meditation
and maybe we can say real meditation
is not in the technique but in the intent attention that comes
first real meditation is not in the technique
that you're doing but in the attention that comes first
or refuge or buddhist real refuge
is not in the words i take refuge in the buddha in the dharma the sangha
but rather in the attention that comes first
so what attention is it that comes first what way of atta attending what being in
the world what way of being aware knowing what's happening
so that seems like the obvious question to this title and so maybe the rest of the poem is the
answer to that question that you'll maybe the rest of the poem is trying to evoke or describe or point
to maybe to evoke the kind of attention that she's
referring to so i'll read the rest of the poem and
with that background for it and see if this might do it for you maybe this evokes a
certain kind of attention or maybe it raises questions about
what what are you doing when you paying attention when you're bringing attention to whatever it is you're
paying attention to what is it that you're doing
when you're aware that can never be called a prayer
that it can never be called a refuge that you would never associate this is meditation
so the poem goes like this the little hawk
leaned sideways and tilted
rode the wind its eye at
its eye at the at this distance looked like green glass
its feet were the color of butter
speed obviously was joy
but then so was the sudden slow circle it carved into the slightly silvery air
and the squaring of its shoulder and pulling into itself
the long sharp edge wings and the fall into the grass where it
tussled a moment like a bundle of brown leaves
and then again lifted itself into the air
that butter colored clenched in order to hold a small still body
and it flew off as my mind sang out oh
all that loose blue rink of sky
where does it go to and why
so here she's watching something that some people will find inspiring or
beautiful or captivating to watch a hawk soar in the wind it's so
sore in the sky it can be quite beautiful to watch and see and sometimes you can feel lucky to
be outdoors and really get a good view of this beautiful majestic bird
so here she's watching it then and then she sees watches it as it
dives down to catch him i pray
and it does and what's remarkable for me is
she treats the catching of the prey in the same simplicity and almost like
the same kind of awe or something as she does just watching the hawk
circle around and she doesn't seem to miss a beat or
doesn't seem to to uh to
i don't know to you know somehow shuddered oh my god it's a mouse
you know gopher has been just been caught just like it's just nature watching it
so she so she's watching it and all this and then
but then the most remarkable part of the poem for me is the the bird lifts up and goes into
the sky and if sometimes you go see a hawk or bird flight this guy it kind of disappears
high enough or something and then she has this question first
oh all that loose blue rink of sky
the only place i know that the word rink is used is an ice cage rink
so i'm probably just doing that you know this this bird is skating and that's where that's the that's where the
bird skates on he's referring to our sky
that way oh all that loose blue rink of sky
where does it go to and why well you know have you ever asked
that question it's kind of a silly question right why did where does the blue sky go to
and why it's not a question that maybe a really rational scientific
person would ask in fact the first time i was out in the high
mountains when i was i was 15. beautiful high alpine place
where i was going to a boarding school it was a reform school
and it was beautiful high up in the mountains and snow capped mountains and
stuff and i was walking one of the little country roads with my older friend from school
and i was just in awe of what i was seeing and i just in that awe i said
why are we why are we here what's this about and he looked at me and said don't be
silly then something in my heart closed when he said that it took years for that to open
and so here she has this you know this aw and this amazement that she asks a question that don't tell her she's silly
something might close that shouldn't close but why this blue sky why is it blue
it's not like a question that wants an answer i think it's a question which is just
open to amazement to possibilities to
something that may be that we can't understand or don't want to understand or
something that maybe what is it associated with is that kind of reference is it kind of respect
mystery what is it so she uses this whole example of this
hawk and the hawks soaring off and having this question you know where does the sky go and why
has an answer to the title
the real prayers are not in the words but the in the attention that comes
first so what is it what is it the attention she's referring to
that's being described in the poem why is that before prayer why is that
the prayer why would she call that prayer
why would she see it in that kind of religious terms or in value like that
i think that's the question this wonderful poem leaves us with
so i don't know some of you don't care for poetry i just cared for the title
but um what do you think what do you think what kind of attention
do you think she's referring to when she says but it is found in the attention that comes
first before the prayer what do you think anybody if you want to yes so if you could use the mic
um can is this working it sounds like it is perhaps the
simple awareness you referred to at the end of our meditation i think
that's my answer uh-huh thank you yeah that that was kind of what was in the back of my mind when i did that meditation was this poem
kind of maybe maybe even prepare for hearing the poem maybe thank you
anything else that occurs to you um
i just think sort of grounding in simple awareness
can really open up a lot of space kind of like you described actually was really touched by the quote of
when awareness is simple uh leaves space for the heart to participate in the world or something
like that i didn't quite get the wording right um but i really find that to be true that
when awareness is simple then there's this beauty there's this awe there's this
sort of fascination with the world and perhaps that's what she's referring to um thank you
very nice
what was your what was your name i'm john john sage hi there um
i am in fact sage um so the attention that i thought about was
um kind of attention that just belongs to people in general the way they like hack
is i don't know a better word for this but like built to do the thing that it does and to like
attack the mouse it might go up i thought it was kind of like juxtaposition like it just did its thing
like the attention is what we do like we've evolved to like
i don't know be able to like exert a lot of like power over the world natural world
but at the same time like why are we evolved to appreciate like a blue sky like that doesn't seem necessary and um
and to ask a question like where does it go and why of like something that has no utilities
the attention that sounds like prayer to me just kind of like
fantastic i like that so this idea if i understood you that the hawks doing what it's doing
and uh there's something about you doing what we what's what humans can do when we watch kind of an awe at the talk and
see what's going on and ask questions that have no utility in a sense
but but we have so many things we can do with our wonderful minds
why do we do that when we can go out and make money you know we can work more extra hours
and over time you know isn't that more important the question
what what evokes for me your your wonderful statement is um
you know you have no utility when it's your time to die
say if you're lucky enough that you're dying not really in any pain but you're definitely going
it's like this is the last hour maybe you have
would you rather be doing your taxes wait a minute in 1999 i think i paid too much and
was all these things that you know or would you rather kind of like look at jobless things to see like i need a
promotion what would you do during that last hour and in that last hour
with that a question that has no utility would that be really the best way that
you spend that time would that be the most amazing wondrous way to be in the last hour just
looking kind of in in a certain kind of reverence in awe
because we've learned that it's found in the attention
that we have in our capac natural capacity for attention
where attention has been set free of our preoccupations our fears our desires our
hates latching on that even laying at our deathbed
and looking up in this air and the dust motes are glittering through the sunlight
wow where does that light go why is it here
but just just watching it you know what would you do on your last
hour which which direction would you go what would you do with your attention do you know something about how to be
present that becomes your refuge on your deathbed
that it's so easy in this kind of life that many people live here in silicon valley
to say what sage said oh so well i thought but
you know to do that some people might say sage and say this but it has no utility
we have this capacity for all reverence for using our attention a certain way
discovering a new character that is that may be the most one of the most precious things we have
and to put it in the context of one hour to live was just a highlight for you
oh oh well in that hour
what has utility what does that mean in that hour what's most important
and this is a very important part of buddhist training is to consider this
kind of thing like the last hour because it highlights our values
highlights what's important highlights a possibility that we don't have to wait for our last hour to live by
and people who shy away from any discussion of death
any consideration of it sometimes are losing losing that possibility of using that last hour
as a wonderful treasure as a reference point as an exercise
how can i how do i want to be now
so anyways i talked too long i'd love to hear some of you more about
so back to the idea of prayer i i don't see prayer as
a different state from meditation i feel like it's an outpouring of your of one's heart
whereas i think meditation i'm more in a receiving mode and so
one has to do with awareness or like the attention i think it seems to me that it's the
prerequisite to open your heart to begin with so it can begin that outpouring
and so when you say you know nice attention is required for prayer
to be a real prayer that's sort of how i connect the dots
great yeah so yeah so i like it very much what you said how you started off by saying maybe
a prayer meditation doesn't have to be two different things it depends what you mean by prayer of course but i think
that there's something profound profound possibility in prayer that is very similar to what we do in
meditation depending on how we use our attention
any other thoughts about what kind of attention that that this that mary oliver might be
pointing to and maybe not you know trying to explain her but maybe explaining yourself
what would you how would you understand this for yourself
i'm i'm not sure exactly what to say but
there's something about prayer that to me is asking that is what it's an asking
a request or and the attention more is appreciation
or an awareness they seem different to me great great
yeah some people associate prayer with asking and uh and this is something very different attention
um but not everyone associates prayer with asking and so there's other whole other
associations people have with prayer and um
so
so i'm thinking about this attention and what comes what comes to my mind is
there's no need to interpret anything no need to assign any meaning
just watching and it's kind of like no burden of needing
to assign meaning or interpretation and
so prayer for me i i think about my grandmother who prayed a lot
and when i asked her any questions about what she was doing she didn't have any answers
she didn't she didn't know what like i'm just doing it um there was you know specific steps but
it didn't mean like it didn't seem to to have a meaning she was just doing it
so no interpretation so this freedom from interpretation freedom of putting something adding anything on top of our
experience and um or wanting anything from our experience or
avoiding something just being with something in a very simple way and maybe that's what she found
and maybe to put words on it would have maybe she was a great zen master
and she knew that putting any words to explain any explanation or words on it just would ruin it
maybe great
anybody else yes this could
so for me not so much about the poem but for me personally i grew up christian as a child so prayer was like a very um
that's just what i learned to do right and and was very much part of my daily routines i would pray at night before
going to bed and you know wishing for well thanking for the things that went well and wishing for things like that i
hope would go well like the next day and then certain you know experiences in my life made it such that i couldn't
really believe any more in a kind of omnipotent god that i can sort of directly talk to in that kind of way
and there was a difficult difficult period in time than for me when that was gone and it wasn't yet
sort of replaced or that the void hadn't been filled and for me then sort of finding you know meditation and
meditative practice in some sense then filled filled that void so it was the switch in some sense for me from prayer
to this more attentive kind and and then i guess there was one ted talk that i
saw some some time ago and i forget exactly who the pastor was but he and i actually
also don't know whether that is exactly the meaning of of namaste but he he said um at least in that ted talk that at
least part of the meeting with namaste that greeting in in india is that um
i greet that part of god that i recognize in you and i found that to be very nice because that sort of combined the two things for
me in some sense and saying that okay well if you know god's still everywhere in some sense but now
it's the awareness that you practice through meditation that you need to recognize it in others so it's a different way of sort of relating to god
than it is in this sort of more cognitive direct way of asking for things or thanking for things
so that was sort of what came to my mind not so much about the poem but yeah very nice thank you
and your words reminded me of something that when i was a i did quite a bit of growing up in europe
and so i had some kind of contact with catholic monasteries there i don't know
how but they were kind of on the edges of my my my life there so at some point when i
was a teenager i had this desire to
go become a catholic monk and i wondered if they'd take me as an atheist
because um and what what attracted me to it was not the religion
but exactly but there was something about something up in me resonated or felt something
about the lifestyle that brought a kind of uh awoke a kind of
embodied attention embodied presence a kind of embodied
awareness that felt like kind of a wholeness that things felt complete or felt
settled or peaceful or so i felt i had this very rich warm feeling
and and uh and i wanted a place i knew or
associated with this feeling that i had was the monastic life that these monks are going around i have no idea if it's
true but but that's uh that that was what the attraction was to the monastic life back
when i was the teenager and and um it probably came to kind of a peak
um when i was 18
and i went to a monastery maybe the cathedral
called mont's son michelle i don't know if any of you know of it in france
and uh you it's kind of like from a distance it looks like something they'd draw for a disneyland cartoon uh you're
going across this flat kind of plains of northwestern france and right down the near the coast
and this on this little island off from the coast comes up there rises this huge kind of soaring
kind of cathedral with a big spire and when the tide is in there's a kind
of a little bridge that goes out to it ties it out it's it's kind of
i suppose you could walk all the way without the bridge and so i was there and i had a lovely i
i don't know why i went there but i was just traveling around and i found a place to stay the only
place to stay apparently for me was at a pax christie
hostel a little christian hostel there and it felt like a kind of
semi-monastic it was just very lovely i loved it they're very simple and
and then in the morning i got up and i went up and had a tour of the church the cathedral and everything and and we went
all the way around you know all kinds of places and we came to the um the the oldest part of the
complex the monastery was a little one room stoned chapel
that had been built on top of the island top of the hill and everything else had built around it
and covered it filled it but at the very heart there was a soul and we went in there
to this little chapel immediately i felt so much peace
it was like wow and then when everybody in my tour group they all left
i kind of stayed back as long as i thought i could have permission to stay back just to feel that peace
and um so that was kind of like the peak of it and then i didn't have that kind of peace
again until i started meditating and then this whole thing that i kind of intuited as a teenager when i was young
was something that then then became accessible to me um in meditation practice and
and and then in buddhist monastic life which i did for a while but this beautiful way of being
so they said for me this attention that she talks about is something that
is something that is not cerebral it's not like the eyes looking at
something only the eyes but something that is um
a sense of whole presence and attentiveness that's that's fully here
and always like just here presents
and um the seeing the hearing is part of it but it's not it's only part of it so
there's a bigger hole here and it comes with a feeling or sense that this is complete
that this is this is being fulfilled this is deeply satisfying this is you know this is
feeling this fulfilled without having to win the lottery or get a better job or
have a better relationship or all kinds of things that in the world we're trying to do to make ourselves feel complete
so that's the prayer that's that's the real prayer attention
to that's ability and i think as that has talked about this it's something that's
mostly found by being very simple not filling it with desires and wants
and doing and wanting and running away but just here just here a simple way
so um i hope that's be nice for you to consider
and to that real prayers are not in the words but in the attention that comes first
i think it's a wonderful little thing to consider and it raises questions
and maybe this is one of these if it does raise questions for you what is this maybe it's a kind of question that
shouldn't be answered too easily