thank you for your practice hello to people on youtube welcome everybody
one thing i like to say um
is that uh at imc um
membership is a matter of wanting to belong so anyone who wants to be part of the
sangha you are part of the sangha just so you know
so i want to talk about effort today the practice of effort
and just notice if you can what quality of response do you have in
your being as i bring up the word effort is that uh when i say that word
do you feel a sense of like connecting to having to work hard
or a sense of i don't want to think about effort just i think this word is um
what it points to is incredibly important but our relationship to the idea of it may
not be as useful as it could be
i've heard is actually the most common quality that is listed by the
buddha for awakening effort is woven into everything we do
it's the stuff of energy and it seems to me that it takes on the
resonance or the tone of whatever is guiding inspiring or directing it
in particular the qualities of the heart and the presence or absence of wisdom
can really be noted in our our efforts and [Music]
to me recognizing the
the visible experiential results of making effort is something
that's always possible we can really tune in to the kind of effort
we're making by noticing the results of what we're doing and i'm going to talk a lot more about
that but and um
i guess i'll say this other thing which is that um you know we always we have a
we always have choice and whether that's conscious or unconscious choice habitual choice
there's always some choice happening
and with the teachings of the buddha and the science of neuroscience neuroplasticity
i think it's particularly useful to to use effort to cultivate mind states
that are beneficial to ourselves others and and both
and if we aren't kind of consciously tuning in to the kind of effort we're
making or what we're doing
the results of what we're doing are going to be determined by our past karmic efforts our past behaviors our
habits and patterns this will shape the mind this will shape
what happens in our next moment
so i'm going to kind of go through a long list of things that i want to cover because i actually don't know how much
of this i will cover so i'm going to kind of give bullet points of all the different things that that i've been sort of reflecting on around this this
quality of our life our experience
so there's a beautiful
suta called it's about sona who's a monk who's practicing
and the buddha comes to talk to him when sona is about ready to give up his practice and return to lay
life and the buddha shows up and and
really essentially the teaching is and hopefully i'll come back to the suta is that our mind is like an instrument
and the way that we play it is like we play an instrument he was a
musician zona was and so when we play music
we can notice the tone right and we can notice how hard we're
strumming or the effort we're putting into playing so the buddha essentially is teaching
sona you can work with your mind the same way you play an instrument so we are our own
instruments our our mind our body our hearts are our own instruments
it's um you know everything we do requires some
amount of effort or energy regardless of our consciousness choice of these things
we can learn a lot from the effort we're making sort of a window into
you know it becomes what we're doing internally becomes visible in our experience and our actions the
results of our actions and there's uh different types of
effort needed at different times in general there's effort that requires
activity in a way and there's effort that requires receptivity
opening up allowing receiving and it's uh a dynamic thing
what is needed um is always gonna change something that we need to tune into like
an instrument when we travel when we do various things set it down
temperature affect the tone and the quality of the music
another question for me around effort and noticing is where aren't we applying effort
where aren't we putting effort into our lives into our practice
and where aren't we noticing the effort i in high school
i volunteered in the [Music] in the classroom where people who were
neurodiverse or learning diverse and i was profoundly impacted by
one of the preparation exercises i did that was given to me by the teacher who runs that
classroom and what she said is to go home and sit
down and write out instructions for tying your shoe
i was shocked as i started to try and articulate step by step with words
what it took to tie a shoe try it
another important thing to
you know know in the buddha's teachings on wise effort the function of effort
is to increase the wholesome and decrease the unwholesome
the buddha teaches that there are four types of wise efforts so there's lots and lots of types of effort but the four
types of wise effort are efforts that
can be kind of summarized in this very simple way if it's not bad don't make it
worse if it's bad stop
so these are kind of moving toward acts of renunciation right letting go or
stopping and if it's if it's not good make it good wholesome
supportive and if it's already good sustain or maintain the goodness the wholesomeness
so those are the four types of wise effort and to know if we're um
you know what kind of efforts needed we really again need to bring our awareness back to what we're trying to do
and how its impact is and then
one of my final points not that it will be the last thing i talk about but
um effort is uh
i feel like it's very much impact but impacted by the stirring of the heart
resonance of the heart energy and there's this uh
when the heart lifts up when the heart is bright you know
inspired maybe you can just think about a moment of that and what happens
there's a natural just following of energy and has a certain vitality or quality to it
that can really support the um [Music] the capacity to receive
um to open up which is a form of efforting
right but to be receptive instead of active a lot of what we think about
i think in my mind anyway with when we connect with effort is
the energy we need to exert so a very simple analogy might be
a scooter i have a scooter and uh
when we start to ride the scooter we need to take the foot pump pump pump right
but then at some point it's very skillful to stop putting the foot down and just glide
right that's actually gills
similarly i have my own later but it's a it's a good one right
so let me talk a little bit about sona
the venerable sona was meditating in seclusion he was off you know in the woods and
doing walking after doing walking meditation um which he did until the skin of his
souls of his feet were split and bleeding and so after he's like ah this this
thought rose in his mind which is of the blessed ones disciples who have
aroused their persistence so effort here right i am one
but my mind is not released from the effluence through lack of clinging sustenance
so then he thinks so now my family has enough wealth it would be possible to enjoy that
wealth and make merit so what if i were to disavow training to return to the lower life enjoy wealth and make merit
and in the beautiful little story somehow the buddha hears he's nowhere near but somehow the buddha hears
and then magically appears right in front of the sauna right after he has this thought and then the buddha says
hmm did you just have this thought and he repeats the thought and sona says yes
lord so the buddha says
now what do you think sona before when you were a house dweller
were you skilled at playing the vini vinna yes lord
it's a string instrument and what do you think when the strings of your vinna were too taut
was your vinna in tune and playable no lord
and when you think what do you think when the strings of your vinna were too loose was your vinna in tune and playable
no lord and the buddha says and what do you think when the strings of your vinna
were neither too taut nor too loose but tuned established to be on the right pitch
was your vinna in tune implable yes lord
and so the buddha says in the same way sona over aroused persistence over over
efforting leads to restlessness over slack persistence leads to laziness
thus you should determine the right pitch for your persistence attune
you know and use your self as an instrument right
those those words were mine
so maybe just take a moment to think about um how this might
be relevant for you in your practice where might you notice that
it's almost like becoming brittle when we over effort when we're striving right there's too much
pushing there's a tightness contracting for me in the mind and body
and when there's not enough you know we might fall asleep or we drift we dream right we don't hold our
posture so just this is our instrument this is sort of the visible
results of our effort can be seen in just this simple way
so i mentioned you know how critical effort is in the buddhist teachings right
so i'll just read a couple of pseudo quotes this one's from the dhammapada actually just
to give you a sense of how much value the buddha placed on it
better than 100 years 100 years lived lazy and lacking in
vigor there's the effort and vigor is one day lived with vigor and exertion
and then the other this is from the vicidi maga when initiated properly it meaning
effort should be seen as the root of all
attainments the root of all attainments
so there's a list of the 37 factors of enlightenment and it's a comprised of a bunch of lists
including four foundations of mindfulness oh no that one's not listed four supreme efforts four means to
accomplishment four five strengths no blightful path seven factors of
enlightenment and there are five frequently found uh qualities in those lists
those five qualities are faith energy mindfulness
concentration and wisdom so of these qualities faith energy
mindfulness concentration and wisdom what do you think is the most common one
if just you know what would you think
well the one that's listed the most is energy effort nine times faith is listed twice mindfulness eight
times so right up there concentration four times wisdom five times
so i mentioned uh the value of learning from the effort that we make
the effort we make will have different results in our lives
let's see
one of the um the buddha's emphatic invitations was to come and see for
yourself don't just believe what i teach right try it for yourself
the dharma is is very incomplete if it's only
something we believe or think about the dharma is to be engaged with
to be practiced and we need to make an effort to do that
and if we aren't attuning to the quality of our effort
we might sit down close our eyes sit up straight
try and stop the thoughts get really serious about meditating
and have a horrible experience meditating and decide at the end
i suck i can't do this i tried really hard and i'm not going to do it again
forget it i can't do it this is a gross exaggeration for a purpose right just to to really
kind of step back and say when we have a practice session or our experience and
interaction in our lives something we're working on
when when it doesn't go well there's a lot to tune into not just
you know just really there's so much subtlety in this area there's so much
subtlety and there's that hurt quality i mentioned right what what where is the
heart in relationship to what we're doing based on what i was describing about you
know sitting down and making all this effort to meditate properly where was the heart in that
for me in the way i was describing it there wasn't really heart in that it was
more of a striving to do something perfect to become a meditator to be a good
meditator to have a certain kind of experience
a heart quality when we sit down to meditate would be much more like
you know well i care about what i see in my mind i care about
how i'm staying in my body and my heart
may i have a sense of kindness to myself and to what arises
you know these this is a kind of a setting the tone of a practice
so just in summary with that section of what i'm talking about right which is
we can learn from the effort we make by noticing the results of what we're doing
and not assuming that we can't change the results if we don't
change our approach change the quality of the heart what's guiding us and what kind of effort we're
putting in so
the next kind of point i wanted to make was different types of effort are needed at
different times obviously sometimes um
yeah no i definitely hear this from people they're trying to figure out what the
right amount of effort is to put into a practice
one of the things i love to teach is loving-kindness practice and
i remember this person was i was talking about the effort we bring right really paying attention to the effort we bring
to that practice and one of the yogis was really trying to
think about okay how do i find that perfect amount of effort
and feeling a little frustrated because he couldn't get the same results in his
practice every time and it's it's uh because you know like everything our
mind is never the same twice right what's happening in our life in our
hearts and our bodies changes all the time the presence our absence of pain
presence or absence of conflict presence or absence of a concentrated
mind or a distracted mind these things our minds are constantly
changing so the effort needed for a distracted
mind is going to be very different than the effort needed for a kind of a mind
that's grounded settled whole
so it's our habit because of how we are designed
genetically biologically speaking to kind of have these shortcuts for
everything we do like tying our shoes and if we aren't tuning in to
that we might end up bringing effort that is not wise effort to whatever
interaction meditation whatever it is we're doing
when i um i've been a swimmer on and off throughout my life you know
various times i'm i have a membership to a pool and i swim a lot and then there's periods of time in my life where that
wasn't happening so much in the last in the most recent return to swimming
i was just so happy to be back in the pool and i am someone who i just i don't like
to swim inside i like to swim outside right and that's because of for me my mind is
very much impacted by the open sky the sense of openness and
of course when it's blessed enough to be sunny that feeling of the warmth
but also the smell in a enclosed pool the smell of the chlorine is quite
strong so there's all these things about swimming outside that i particularly love
and so when i first got back in the pool i was all about just enjoying being outside and
the sky and the sun and i was just very much like you know working on my form
just taking my time remembering the form getting the body back into kind of and look up
looking at youtube's about current swim techniques and but in this very you know just joyful relaxed way
and i started to call my swimming a source of sukkah joy right i would just have so much joy
and um you know i don't know for the first couple of years maybe um
i'd be swimming a lot in the summer and then when it would get cold in the winter i just would be like
my whole body would tense up and it was just like i can't i can't do it i couldn't deal with the
the vedana right the unpleasant bait and the coldness
and uh you know and then i'm sort of realizing over time oh
then i have to kind of start over again every spring or summer and you know sort of
and i'm missing out on the you know what i if i continued my practice of swimming
which i consider a mindfulness practice how that would be beneficial despite the cold so i started to turn in tune into what
effort i needed to make to to bring to my swimming to keep me going
and i remember one day i was it was really really raining it was
intensely raining and i'm walking out you know i just wear my suit from the locker room out i'm not covered
up i'm just going out and so i'm walking and i can feel my body wanting to duck
i don't know the best word for that but to try and avoid the drops of rain and it was so absurd to see it i just it
just was very freeing actually it was like okay look at this just turn toward the vedana the unpleasant stop reacting
stop trying to get away from it and and uh you know so that was an effort bringing some effort right
noticing my response right and so my effort maybe would have
been to just get out to the pool as fast as i can right that was sort of like putting a lot of energy noticing oh when
i'm doing that that just is kind of fueling the sense of reactivity or negativity right
is unpleasantness and so then the effort needed to shift to receiving to being okay to staying
with and not trying to get away from the coldness or the raindrops which is
impossible anyway and just then over time learning to swim
through the winter right swim through the winter another uh really significant thing i
noticed about making effort with swimming was
when i decided it was time to pick up my pace you know i needed to start to swim a
little bit faster i wanted to i was conditioned enough i was swimming you know no problem
distances and and amount of time no struggle at all so it was just time to kind of try and pick it up
and so um what i started to notice was that when i
get out of the pool after making this extra physical effort was i wasn't
feeling that sense of joy i wasn't feeling that sense of uplift
from my swimming so i started to watch what was happening in the mind as i was swimming and it was
like when i was pushing efforting to go faster
and you know this might be just fine because it might be the kind of effort i needed at that time right maybe to kind of
increase my conditioning but what i noticed was that it was almost like pulling a hood up and over
my body my head it was like my senses everything kind of
honed into this smaller point i stopped seeing the light in the water right
sort of having these blinders on and it was like just contract there was
this contracting and so then i started to
work on trying to have effort with the swimming while opening up while working
with the mind to be open and receptive and trying to find this balance right this right tune meant to the
how tight the streams were right
um when we're in on retreat um any of you go on
residential retreats yeah well one of the great things about going
on retreat is you know everything becomes sort of under a microscope right because you
start to get more and more kind of simplified and everything's more clear
and for me i could so much see the how much effort needed to change all the
time sometimes if i had a really concentrated sit
i needed to go out and do fast-paced walking right i needed to balance out what was
happening sometimes we need to walk slow sometimes we need to walk fast sometimes moderately
attuning to the body sometimes during the course of a retreat you'll see
it's better to sit longer sits and sometimes
we have to consider what's happening in our bodies and maybe we don't go to the hall for the sits because we need to sit
less time right so
other things that sort of really helped you know that were examples of taking effort
would be to reflect on the buddha the dharma and the sangha the three jewels right could would be a way of
sort of brightening the heart and that would affect the energy i brought to my practice
or one of my favorite things is to go out and look up look up at the sky
it's like something about it from my mind is just like oh yeah i remember how to be open
i remember that taking in the light and that sense of broadness
sometimes i think about effort as having [Music] the quality of a temperature or
consistency to it right like and i'm i'm offering this
because we all all of our minds and hearts are tuned differently we might notice different
things i was just going to offer a couple other thoughts about how to be paying attention to your own
you know the results of your own effort so there's effort that can feel cold and hard and brittle right thus often
thought of as striving and there's effort that can feel like it's hot and saggy right
and then there's the not too hot not too cold right middle way
sometimes i think about um i can feel in my body and i have this image of an ostrich
and it's like is my effort right now like an ostrich with its head in the sand like i'm not really looking i'm not
really doing anything i'm just kind of shutting down or is it like an ostrich
running right and you know when i think about an ostrich running it's like they're
running that way and thinking about what they're running away from or something you know it's just not this taking in
and then there's like being more upright right
the here's another dharma quote the diamond is for those who are
industrious not those who are lazy that's from the anguttara
so i'm i guess i'm inviting by sharing all of this this is kind of industrious creative ways of thinking about and
seeing effort and i think we do need to be really
receptive and sensitive and tuned in and creative and how we work with our own
effort and bring the heart and the wisdom to it
so um where aren't we putting in effort or
where aren't we paying attention to our effort and our lives
this is a question for me too you know
the practice can be everywhere in our lives right not just on the cushion
and you know one thing is um
there there is effort needed to even orient toward the wholesome because our
the negativity bias in the mind right rick hatson calls it the negative sticks
like velcro and the positive stip is like an egg in a teflon pan
and this is sort of the hard wiring or the soft wiring of the brain is to
orient us toward that which is more of a threat than that which is a gift
and but we can counterbalance that tendency by consciously resting our awareness and
being receptive to the good by savoring or appreciating being grateful
this is an effort too
another area um that i think there might be a
certain amounts of places where there's maybe a not noticing a sense of
you know delusion maybe even or taking kind of things for granted in our lives
there's often in those areas pockets of not bringing appropriate effort to things
and i think some of that is around identity like who we think we are
right we sort of just kind of can get going in a groove
and um just sort of assume we're a certain way
right and and if you think about that what i was talking about we're constantly changing our minds are changing our hearts are changing but if
we think oh i'm a patient person right because we have this idea about
ourselves we're not maybe going to notice when we're being impatient so much
right at least not in the beginning there's also things like um
that we can bring more awareness and more effort in our lives that can make a big difference
and those might be things like where do we have areas of assumptions in general about others
where where do we make effort some people are really good at learning people's names and some people aren't
and some of that might be just the way our minds are but some of it is how much effort are we bringing to learning
people's names or how they pronounce their names is that important to us
does our heart see the value of that
so here's a little quote from wynton higgins
we can live ethically without caring about ourselves or we can't i'm sorry we
can't live ethically without caring about ourselves as well
as others and we can't be mindful without caring about what is happening here and now
care underpins the radical attention the dharma practice accentuates
so to tie that piece together with caring
can help us bring more awareness and effort to the areas where we maybe aren't tuning in
and could tune in more
so i'm going to try and just say a few more things and wrap up and allow time for
reflections or questions just a reminder the function of effort
is to arouse and maintain wholesome states
so let's see and actually in the um
you know description of the of effort in the vici maga
it says vigor is the state of
virya energy its characteristic is exertion
its function is to support or consolidate related mental qualities
its manifest as non-collapse
and stirred one strives wisely so stirring of the
heart right it's that stirring of the heart that helps bring wisdom
to our efforts
so it's uh again i just think it's super poignant space for practice
i think it's so much immediate feedback right right here and now if we notice
sort of and play with the kind of effort and the kind of heart quality you know
we bring it's it's very tied to you know wise
intention and wise view right all of these path factors are it's
and last night of course i was thinking about this talk and i had this dream and i had my dream i had this image of
um granite and how all the different minerals and
colors weave together and you know i think this is the dharma
right any any place you enter you can pretty much find everything else in the
dharma so for me i'm just sort of offering effort as one of those ways in ways
through in the window of kind of learning and seeing in our practice getting more intimate with this
so the for right efforts
if it's not yet arisen if it's not making it worse don't make
it worse if things whatever's happening is making
it worse stop
if what we're doing isn't making it better start
if what we're doing is making it better keep it up
abandoning what is unskillful is letting go developing what is skillful is
cultivation so this important balance even here
between the cultivation and the letting go
so we need to sort of be ardently tuned in to the results because
life is dynamic it's always changing
i've seen with people that um maybe even myself but
i'm a therapist so i do a lot of work with others and i've seen where they're trying to
abandon something that's unskillful something that's making something worse they're trying to stop it
and what actually happens is the reverse things get worse
anybody ever experience that no well
sometimes if we're having a thought maybe i'll make it a little more sort of specific
if we're having a thought we don't want to have because it's hurtful or
we think it's harmful what happens when you try and stop that
thought has anybody ever noticed that it gets a little louder or sticks around a little
longer yeah so
sometimes instead of trying to make something stop
actually what we need to do is not be trying to make anything happen to it
to let it be and maybe turn our heart
our energy towards something that feels supportive like being kind to ourselves with this thought
yeah and sometimes when we're trying to cultivate a sense of
wholesomeness in ourselves so this was an example of trying to get rid of something that's you know not not
wholesome not helpful and we get the opposite and sometimes when we're trying to cultivate something
that feels wholesome like loving kindness we actually start to find our mind
becoming more prickly more irritated more critical
so even though we're doing loving-kindness practice and that's supposed to make us happy and warm and kind
we need to maybe stop doing the loving kindness practice right
and just sort of recognize that that in itself at this moment
is resulting in unwholesome states
so in a way we feel like i just i just really want one other thing i guess
sometimes we're doing all four at the same time essentially they don't they're not always so
independent from each other
okay all right so i think i did it i got
through all the points so i'll just kind of go through them very you know to summarize
we're our own instrument the sona suta
effort is extremely important in the role of awakening and freedom
everything we do requires effort or energy to some extent or not whether it's
exertion or receptivity we can learn so much by watching
the effort we're making and then the results of that effort
it's always going to change staying attuned so reflecting before
during and after is always important where aren't we applying effort or where
aren't we noticing the effort we're putting into things
the function of effort and wise effort is to increase the wholesome and decrease the unwholesome
the heart the stirring of the heart is extremely supportive
for the the effort we make finding some quality
that is has some warmth or tenderness to it to varying degrees
right can help us you know str you know play our own selves
with care
all right i think that's it thank you for your kind attention