foreign
so hello everyone and um
the main focus of this week's meditations and
teachings it has to do with the different ways in which we perceive different ways in which we
receive data from the world including our own inner world
and um so we you know Through The Eyes the ears the nose the tongue
uh through all the different kinds of sense uh capacities sensory capacities
we have for information and from the world and one of them that
the Buddha put a much emphasis on was uh
what he called what we sometimes called the English feelings of Pleasure and
Pain and that which is neither Pleasant nor Nora unpleasant
and um and so we'll do a meditation on Pleasure
and Pain but I'd like to do it in a different way than Buddhism usually emphasizes
I think some ways Buddhism for very wise reasons will sometimes
narrow the focus on the feelings and feeling tones of Pleasure and Pain to
the Simplicity of just a pleasure part and the pain part because in some ways that's what we react to the most or it's
one of the Avenues of learning how to be equanimous learning how to be comfortable or equanimous with pain or
pleasure but in terms of uh our our attentional
faculties how we take in information the world of Pleasure and Pain has a
much uh has a big impact on us uh it involves all these pleasure
involves all these different pleasure centers in the brain all these different uh information comes
through Pleasure and Pain something as simple as thirst when we start feeling uncomfortable with
the balance of sodium and other things in our you know in our in our
in the fluids of our body the fluid balance we feel thirsty and that's a
kind of and that can be kind of uncomfortable it's kind of uh unpleasant experience that motivates us
we can drink plenty and feel pleasure and that pleasure is an indication that you know that we're doing well we're
hydrating ourselves and so there's lots of different things that are happening with Pleasure and
Pain that our system is taking in and operating under and and we're adjusting
accordingly we don't just simply sit quietly knowing Pleasure and Pain we our
system our body biologically physiologically hormonally all kinds of ways
um uh are involved in processes that involve Pleasure and Pain
so to meditate is not uh with Pleasure and Pain and having Equanimity about it is not
just to have equanimity but it's also to be able to be more
attuned to the uh to the full spectrum of what's
happening when we have pleasure in pain to be able to listen deeply and what else is being conveyed here with those
Sensations with those feelings and this is not a time to think a lot about it and react and figure out things
what to do but rather certainly to have Equanimity about it and just kind of continue
practicing but the um but the idea of equanimity and mindfulness awareness of
Pleasure and Pain in an open way is so that we can kind of go through the door
of Pleasure and Pain to allow our whole system of attention focus awareness
to operate more harmoniously more fully the way that it does even
unconsciously even without us trying to do something
um it's all operates much of this is operating on a deep level within us but it up my proposal is that the whole
thing works better when it's done uh when we create room
and awareness room in attention kind of imaginary room that allows it all to be
there without any interruptions without any hindrances without any interference on
our part so hopefully that was a little bit quick and and uh understandable enough
and we'll start and I start sitting here with some
pleasure of being together with all of you and being able to share this practice with
you and perhaps you have some pleasure in a simple maybe very mild pleasure
to be getting ready for meditation
and to gently close your eyes and to feel
make room for whatever sense of pleasure there might be your body right now
it could be as simple as some tingling in your arms
it could be the ways in which your body is comfortable in your posture
that pleasure of being able to begin a session of meditation
may be a pleasure of anticipation the pleasure of relief
the pleasure of becoming more connected and intimate with oneself
there might be simple physical pleasures of the hands touching
the feeling of warmth if you're warm or
if you use recently had breakfast or coffee or something before sitting down
maybe there's some lingering pleasure or physiological pleasure in the belly and
in you
from what you ate and drank
there might be a range of Pleasures in the body
that if you sit down and just matter of factly kind of begin focusing on your breath
you wouldn't notice or even recognize
and then very gently not too much
take a few long slow deep breaths as if the exhale the egg as if the
inhale is spreading throughout all the areas of pleasure in your body
even if you have pain it's okay to let that kind of be in the background for a few moments
and just with the inhales it's like a wave maybe of a tension from
the inhale out throughout the body feeling the pleasures
and on the exhale letting it all relax all settle
they exhale the body even the pleasures can settle
gently let your breathing return to normal
and finding the areas in your body where there's pleasure pleasantness
feeling of satisfaction or contentment
simple physical pleasure even though the mildest kind
and as you exhale let that settle and spread a little bit
around wherever it is
and then with the mind
as you exhale let the mind or thinking mind relax
the thoughts become quieter
and if any of your thoughts are Pleasant
feel the pleasure of them as you relax and quiet the mind
if you're not thinking pleasant thoughts
maybe calmly and quietly see if you can have pleasant thoughts
that are appropriate for you to have
and feeling the pleasure of those thoughts the pleasantness
if it feels Pleasant to have the thinking quieter and calmer
letting go of thoughts difficult thoughts let go
settle the thinking mind
and then with a quiet mind quiet attention that's not trying to
change anything make anything happen anything go away
not trying to analyze or understand very simple attention
Let There Be awareness of the pleasures
within the body and the heart and the mind
making room for it all
breathing with whatever Pleasures there are
appreciating that pleasures
might be connected to Deep Integrated Systems of
your biological mental processes
built into being a human sitting quietly breathing
with all the pleasures that's available sitting here allowing it to be there making room
and you become quieter in your mind so there's greater sensitivity to the
pleasures of Within
every time you exhale letting go of your thoughts
so you're more sensitive to pleasure
foreign
if you have sensations of pleasure
there are two things happening the sensations
and the sensing of them
if the sensations are Pleasant is sensing
also Pleasant
and if the sensing is Pleasant
is the knowing of pleasure The Knowing of sensing the awareness of
it might it also have some pleasantness pleasantness or pleasure as part of it
the broader sense of being conscious
does it share in some of the pleasantness pleasure that's known
and if there is let the pleasure of awareness
however small it is let it spread
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
imagine that the pleasantness the pleasures you feel
your body your mind your awareness
radiates from you flows out into the space around you
out into the world
touching others has a bridge to others
that will carry your wishes well wishes for them
riding on whatever way you feel pleasure
offer these wishes may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may the simple awareness of pleasure
be a guide to happiness safety Peace and Freedom
[Music]
thank you and little afternote
um I want to apologize to those of you who's have chronic pain and that that is
really prominent and an emphasis on Pleasure like this maybe
makes the pain even more challenging and so I apologize and there's a whole way
of doing this kind of meditation with pain and as well that can be very useful but maybe we'll get to that at some
point and I also apologize a little bit for all the Talking I do during these
meditations it'd be nice if there's more silence and so but I'm also trying to teach some
things and it would be lovely if you made up for my talking by meditating
later with some silence and finally
um well I have about water and stuff it'd be nice to have some comments maybe maybe a very brief comments a couple of
words or something word two or three about what it was like to do that meditation and um and then
helps me prepare me for what I'm going to say next thank you
so thank you for the comments and I appreciate appreciate the full range of them
and and I'll read I'm going to start now with the teaching and I'll read the rest
of that come later I appreciate them very much
so as a repeating what I've said the first few days I understand
Consciousness or awareness I use the words more or less synonymously
as in the sense what people have that it's a a thing uh you know that we have this
thing called consciousness um whatever that might might be kind of a something that's always there maybe
something that has some kind of you units here you you kind of uh
United feeling or a whole feeling people talk about Consciousness that
um as a thing the degree to which it is a thing it's a
um it's a Gestalt It's a combination of many different things integrated together many different biological
physiological and mental cognitive faculties kind of working together in a
whole um and uh without necessarily our choice
or our direction for how it's be done and um and the the holistic working of
it all can make it feel like there is such a thing as Consciousness which is uh its own thing
um and with the idea that when every some people have the idea when everything else disappears but always
will remain to some kind of pristine consciousness uh I don't think that's the idea of the
of early Buddhism but um the idea that uh that what we call
consciousness of the idea we have of it is a sum total of all these different attentional faculties we have in
cognitive functionings that we have I think is a very rich idea and um and is conducive to uh putting
greater value in our capacity to be aware to be attentive because the whole
attentional system works better when it's kind of all being known or
there's space for it all to be there there's if we're caught up in preoccupations it's like we almost limit
how much space there is in the mind or how much free um Ram there is in the mind for
processing and working of all the other things that can be going on and sometimes even the
um you know we reach the limit of how much our active memory can handle and so
we get stressed and and things begin kind of breaking down and the kind of psychological biological system
uh I mean something as simple as being so busy with work and activities and
doing things that we forget to drink and even though their body has signals it'll
tell you you're thirsty they're overridden by the intensity of focus on something and so that's true with many things in
our life that that if we're too focused or too preoccupied we're not going to
Avail ourselves or notice the uh and allow to function all the rich uh
systems of attention and data Gathering and processing that exists within us
and so one of those is the pleasant the capacity to feel
Pleasure and Pain these are very important parts of life without this our
life would probably not really work people who don't feel pain sometimes
will damage themselves tremendously because they don't have to get the signal that um that you know they put
their hand off the hot stove or that they should stop uh you know sawing into
their fingers when they're actually trying to saw the bread or the vegetables
the idea that pain um you know there are a few people in the world apparently can't feel pain
there's a and imagine there's people who can't feel pleasure and that's unfortunate just for the pleasure's sake
but uh pleasure is the vehicle in which other information is coming to us
and uh and other systems within us that begin operating and as I said before I think in Buddhism
where there's a very strong mindfulness practice strong emphasis on being
present for the pleasant and pleasure of of our experience that's a very valuable exercise to do
it's very valuable to tune into it and develop Equanimity to it but then but it's also valuable because if we have
Equanimity and allow the Pleasure and Pain to be there we might also start appreciating that
it's part of a uh it's can it's not just kind of mechanistic Pleasure and Pain it's uh the part of it's the kind of
visible or the felt part of a bigger system of uh of uh
of human functioning going on uh behind that Earth as part of it so if something
simple as a human touch human touch can feel Pleasant and and that's nice that
it's pleasant but there can be so much so much can happen physiologically and psychologically with physical touch if
it's Pleasant that it can be reassuring it can be nurturing uh you know
um you know touching a a child or holding it baby holding a preme is necessary for them to
really be able to mature the whole system of a premature baby
um and so this idea of touch uh supports
the growth and the development of some of human beings as they grow up as
children touch is valuable for our sense of safety a sense of social connection a
sense of um nourishment inside and so the pleasure of social touch is fantastic
there's the the pleasures then of sexual touch and um and that can also be wonderful
but sex that has a very different mechanism maybe or other things going on involved there too and and a sexual
touch the pleasure there is so clearly connected to so much more than just the
place that's being touched it's part of a bigger system and
hormones and all kinds of things going on aesthetic pleasure where does that come
from and what what are all the systems that are operating when we see something really beautiful in nature or or we see
beautiful art or something the sense out of satisfaction inspiration you might feel that the
inspiration might feel very pleasant that pleasure is more than just some simple pleasure there's probably all
kinds of processes within us that have been activated
and apparently there are many pleasure centers in the brain
and so uh so these you know just pleasure is not just you know physical
pleasure or the sensations the sensing itself being Pleasant it's processed in
the brain and um and so to allow ourselves to have
sinful pleasures and not deny them can be very helpful
for this integrated awareness full awareness that we're trying to develop
in mindfulness and um and as that gets developed it
also then hopefully develops our capacity to be with pain that we're not holding on to pleasure or
expecting it to be there all the time but we're also learning a a
non-reactive uh way of being with all of all things because pain too is an
important system for us and what I've learned through mindfulness practice is that I've
learned to pay careful attention to pain when it arises um because part of the function of pain
sometimes it's a danger signal and sometimes I pay attention and if I
could feel that there's a little bit of signal of danger or in the pain itself and I can't specify how that is or how I
know but sometimes it's clear there's a danger something's about to go wrong or
bad and other times it feels like okay this is this pain is okay it's you know
who knows I I injured myself the injury injury is over over but now it's healing
and and now there's pain they're just there that's left over that needs to be there until it settles down and I don't
feel a danger anymore and so if I feel danger then I'll then I
don't just practice mindfulness and acceptance of it um I will try to avoid the danger if
it's possible I'll try to like if I'm sitting in meditation and I feel a sense of danger in how I'm sitting I'll change
my posture but if I don't feel that sense of danger then I don't
so this pain is also connected to all kinds of uh deeper systems that are
providing information and so as we begin tuning into this world of Pleasure and
Pain uh the um that itself can feed back onto
what we might call Consciousness or the sense we have of awareness and the sense of awareness and
Consciousness can take a different shape depending on
uh you know I know exactly shape is the right word these are all metaphors or something that doesn't really exist but
we have a kind of a intuitive sense for and so uh the Consciousness or awareness
can can feel either contracted or expanded expensive it can feel tense if
there's a lot of pain and they can feel the pleasure and in it and the kind of goodness and it then it expands
and so so much so that some people feel that Consciousness in and of itself
um has Bliss as part of it and I don't know if it you know I don't
think it's in and of itself but as things get simpler and simpler and quieter and the an awareness can can
tune into these other systems that are working in harmony the sense of Harmony
it creates a pleasure for awareness itself and so there's many Pleasures the
pleasures of sleep the pleasures of eating the pleasures of of the drinking the pleasures of sex the pleasures of
exercise all these can provide Pleasures not just the physiological surface pleasure of
the moment but they tap into something deeper Within and maybe a sense of satisfaction and
inspiration something so so this is the Pleasure and Pain is
part of the part the pieces of this Gestalt this whole that contributes to
our sense of being conscious and so what I'd like to suggest for you
if you would like for the next 24 hours is to give a kind of respectful
attention maybe even reverential attention to The Simple Pleasures and pain of
daily life with the assumption that they're not simple
they're just like kind of like the tip of a vast inner Network and maybe even
interpersonal Network that is somehow being conveyed or carried or evoked by
the Pleasure and Pain and offering respect to that means make room feel that feel what's going on in
some bigger bigger way allow yourself to feel that pleasure allow yourself to feel the pain so you
can not feel pain or pleasure for itself but see if it kind of helps you connect
to uh some deeper or Fuller dimensions of who you how your system how your body
mind works so um
thank you very much and um I look forward to continue on this theme
of our attentional faculties tomorrow