if you want to do a sump check I don't think I hear anything
I'll keep talking okay you all hear me okay yeah good in the back yeah
all right so good morning and good to be here with
you all um in the hall and also those who are on YouTube
um through the webcast so what began this morning with um
meditation I'll offer a few words alighted guidance
and light guidance in our meditation and the invitation is to consider
the meditation as a ritual and so
so for today's practice whether it's
them silent set or in the Dharma talk
consider this is a unfolding ritual
and so um will begin this ritual what the sound of
a bell [Music]
as a ritual there is a beginning a middle and end
of a process and that's the beginning involves
maybe some setting up ourselves are preparing ourselves from meditation
and so take a few generous moments to allow ourselves to arrive
maybe arrive at Here and Now
if you want to take a few long deep breaths
as you breathe out riding along with the out breath
to arrive at this space
In This Moment
there's the arriving processes as if we're entering
into a sacred Temple Ancient Temple
a temple of this body this mind in this heart
maybe there's already a sense of reverence humility
as we arrive and enter
into this Temple of the body
taking seat in the center of our being
maybe first a few moments just to check out the global sense of our being
the physicality of the body the posture
the moods emotions that came along
becoming present and aware
and momentarily we can settle onto our seats
as if we're sitting in the center of the Temple
the Temple of this body this mind in this heart
taking a few moments to feel and sense into the contact
of the lower half of the body with the floor cheers
support it by Earth underneath
our settling into the seat
maybe you'll feel into this grounded
solidity of the Earth element in the body
naturally settling downwards naturally grounding
may be feeling into the bones the set bongs
thigh bones
Farm study
and bones throughout the spine torso
uh Earth elements in the body naturally grounds
settles down
they're transitioning to
the next part of a ritual of our meditation
from this grounded place
may we open to whatever arises
and passes away in our experience
as a ritual we open to the gifts
of the process and letting go of our wanting and
desires expectations
offering ourselves up
to what arises what emerges in our experience
and welcome the movements of the breath
welcome the dancing Sensations in the body
welcome the waves of emotions
and treat each experience as if our offering
the blessings to all of those experiences
nothing excluded
foreign
and there's the last a few minutes of our sitting together
I invite you to gently reflect
our notice if there are any effects
when we consider our meditation as a ritual
and maybe it's a felt sensing the body
without sensing the heart New Perspectives in the mind
whatever it may be
notice any effects
that may be present or not
rituals often touch Us in the subconscious level
if there are any effects allow them to emerge through the body
will end the sitting with the sound of a bell
foreign [Music]
signifies a little transition so feel free to take a moment if you need to shift your
posture or need to stand up and do what is needed for the body
and for your being
and this will transition us to the next part of our unfolding ritual
which involves speaking and listening
and so today and not surprisingly the topic and I had in mind to share
is a ritual and our Dharma practice
I realized that this is not a popular Topic in the Western teravada centers
and especially um maybe a you know lay community centers
um and there can be certain um
we can't have a certain kind of a relationship when the words ritual gets
uttered and and some may consider this as superficial
or even cultural baggage are not necessary as part of the
Buddhist practice um and I can totally relate to that and I
for me I've been to Chinese temples with
lots of Rich rituals and involves incense burning and money making and so
that can feel a sense of baggage associated with it
and yet rituals whether they are seeing unseen
um they are part of Many religious
traditions and the spiritual life in some of the cultures like the culture
I came from the Asian culture our rituals are quite significant and
prominent I remember once a visiting venerable bikubody
you know who lives in a Chinese monastery and
and I asked him what is the biggest difference between
kind of a the Western teravada traditions and the Chinese Buddhism in
his experience given that his loving a Chinese monastery
and he said much is in common but where he lives and there were a lot
of rituals and they can be quite long hours and hours of bowing and
[Music] um and so um
and often and they are involved and kind of bowing chanting different forms in
the rituals and they are rich in a lot of different cultures like myself coming
from the Asian culture in the Western teravada Center like this
inside Meditation Center um many of us come to the center may not
even notice any ritual whatsoever but rituals are here
and so those of you who come through the door and another maybe a not so obvious
for those who are online on on YouTube
but entering into IMC what we often do is put our shoes on the
shelves and we come into the meditation Hall some people bow in front of the Buddha
statue and then we take our seat and at the end of the session often
people bow out and leave and so there are those rituals present
even in a center like this but many of us may or may not associate
with them as a rituals and so today I wanted to kind of maybe highlight some of the dimensions of it
um so I personally wasn't paying attention
to the effects of rituals until much later in my own Buddhist path
but as I reflected back and I can say that in many ways rituals
played quite a significant role in my own Dharma life
I just didn't realize that for a long time and I remember the first time first
exposure to this was when I first came to United States very shortly I lost my
grandpa and who was very close to us he lived
with our family the whole of my life basically up to that time
and he passed away in China and it was very clear that I wouldn't be able to
make my way back and to be with him in any way uh for a wider variety of reasons I just
got here so I was very confused and a little lost
and just not sure what to do um and I happened to go to a pure land
Buddhist de Sangha in my University Town
there through a college roommate that I stayed
with and not knowing what's possible I just
told them that this situation I'm in
and they spontaneously predict put together a ritual and that
um honored remembered my grandpa for who he who he
was and honored him
and I just offered a very brief kind of a description they put this kind of very
beautiful and yet simple ritual around it and offered the chanting and
um offered a blessing for him to have a blessed afterlife which I didn't really
know but it did something to my heart I felt
I felt quite E at ease and I felt that there was some kind of a closure
out of this and so that was uh first uh Encounter of
the Buddhist the ritual and ending some
maybe miraculous ways and probably created a certain affinity
between myself and Buddhists and Buddhism and I got very curious about it
and it began kind of exploring and seeking the Buddhist practices and and
the teachings um
and rituals can have many potent functions in our spiritual life
I wanted to share this um quote from an article that Gil francs
doll wrote about rituals in Buddhism
and so here is what he said rituals are a form of language that
expresses many dimensions of our Human Condition including our relationship to others and
to our spiritual life and then later on in the article it says
rituals to share many characteristics with poetry theater dance in evoking
emotions intuition and New Perspectives because rituals touch more aspects of
our mind and heart than simple prose and the didactic explanations
rituals like the Arts can enrich our lives
and engage the full range of our being
and so I really resonated with that quite a lot
so today I want to share just a few dimensions of the functions and effects
of rituals in our Dharma practice maybe as pointers there may be many
other dimensions on and and that's accessible to some of you
but those are just a few uh that why I'm maybe pointing out today
so the first one is a relationship of rituals and our hearts
and so in a way when we engage in rituals wholeheartedly
rituals themselves become a hard practice
just like a Brahma vejaras it becomes a heart practice they can touch and open our hearts and
the beings and deeply and so for myself in my own case
rituals had opened my heart in ways that maybe beyond my own
logical analytical mind they touched something deeper inside of me
in our traditions a simple bowing when we do it wholeheartedly
it can become expressions of many beautiful qualities of our heart
and reverence reference towards whatever our bowing towards could even
just be Earth sky and everything in between animated on animated
um and so there can be a deep sense of reference
another possibility bowing it carries a deep sense of gratitude
humility and the suggesture of two hands coming
together can also symbolize Harmony coming in harmony
and unifying in some way in our being
and so for me recent months I've been carrying out a ritual of 108 bows each
morning before my own meditation practice
and this particular practice was called force and because for a while I was
experiencing or encountering a lot of illness aging
death some really close and my own family family members relatives
and people I know of and people I don't know well and this kind of there's a lot
going on there hence I've felt a calling in my heart to
express a deeper sense of care and love and
compassion and one day I just decided I'm gonna do
there's 108 bows each morning and the dedicating each bow to whoever
comes to my mind for their well-being and piece
and I had thought that maybe after a while people are getting better then you
know at some point I'll stop um but new people keep on getting added to
this list so it hasn't stopped
and yeah to this practice has really becoming my own meta practice our Brahma vehara
practice not necessarily sitting still on the cushion but in a form of a bowing
and so um so simple practices like this can really
open our heart in new ways that way may not be
um opening to previously
the second function or effect and about rituals is that
the process of ritual involves making ourselves available to that process
unfolding process and so when we offer ourselves up to
this process and the process can become a force of transformation
and a ritual often leads participants through a process
and opens people to New Perspectives or new insights
but the transformation is only possible if we put down some of the
self-centered agendas you know I want to get something as I remember
going to the Chinese temple before oftentimes people go there want
to get something even if you know that's something in the belief system that you
know or get blessed by something but that the process of ritual really is
an invitation to open to something rather than getting something
one of the most significant Buddhist the rituals and that function
and as this kind of a transformation is the ritual of taking refuge in the
Buddha Dharma and Sangha the triple gem
some of you probably have done this Refuge ceremony yourselves
and others may have done this on retreats we often do Refuge ceremony at
the beginning of the retreat for the retreat duration of a retreat we take a
refuge in the Buddha Dharma and Sangha and taking refuge in the Buddha Dharma
in Sangha for life and Beyond evokes an alignment of our life
with something that we may aspire to
and so for some people this can be quite significant and it has a lot of
implications you know maybe maybe making commitment on how we live our lives
I remember for myself um many years ago when I did this Refuge
ceremony with my monastic teacher on who's my
preceptor offered on this Refuge ceremony to me and so on this English Refuge ceremony
he offered me a small card and on that that was my Chinese Dharma name
and um and the date that the Refuge ceremony took place
and it has the refuges and the precepts on the two sides of the little card
so at the end of this ceremony I felt as if I was reborn into a new
life and kind of like a kind of a birthday
into the Buddha's lineage
and so I was rather significant it was a kind of a gut feeling very intuitive
sense but it was a rather significant
um the transformation happens very gradually over time
but if I reflect the back um this was a significant ritual in my
life already began to shift little by little in how I choose to live my life
and this may be the case for some people who's done uh um a ritual like that
and the third one maybe is one of the most important one function
about ritual is that rituals are when they're done
consciously or whether heightened awareness it opens us up to many dimensions of our
inner being that maybe otherwise unseen and unknown
and I remember and sometimes especially on the early phase of my practice
sometimes coming to the practice we can carry this kind of a mainstream
materialistic attitude you know I'm coming here to get something or get rid of something that we don't like and and
so let's get really quick and we just you know get to our sitting cushion and
pull with sit and then when it ends we dash out
and so when we show up with kind of this narrow focus a narrow
um uh or narrowing ourselves into this
set of the things that we want and we want a ging we want to get
um and the practice probably have a different effect on us it's always using
it as something to get some more things and get rid of some things we don't like
um I'll share another example that was a vivid teaching of the sword for myself I
was um I was in a Chinese Sangha for a long time we had a beloved Taiwanese Dharma
teacher who once coming to offer a teaching we haven't seen her for a long
time so we were all very enthusiastic we got to
our little Center early and we set up the desk and on the mic and we were all
sitting on the front row waiting and so um and that by the time the teacher showed
up and she walked down the hallway it was really just a living room in
old house in Sunnyvale and it was not a big place but she just walked into
the room and you know get to the desk and sat down
and then he just looked around in the room and the kind of different parts of the room
and he you know and then her head landed on a corner of the room
where there was a big pile of messy cables all around
you know kind of cables that connects to the mic and and it was a big spaghetti right over in
the corner and so she turned her face looked at us and then said that too is the practice
so we were all sitting on the front row really embarrassed I was like what
and I really don't remember much about the talk but I did remember this that
was a significant teaching for me that um
when we began to open the field of our practice
ritual is a vehicle for us to begin to open to all of these processes around
included in our practice including the sitting and the talking and speaking and how we
show up
um and so as a ritual each ritual has a
beginning a middle and end and so
you know when we walk into our space and this is a part of the beginning how we
walk into the space how we take our seat and I was inviting Even in our sitting
meditation as a process of a ritual on how we began this process of a
meditation what are the orientations that we have
and so open ourselves up to all of these different dimensions of it
as when we consider our practice as a ritual there may be a sense of
sacredness that can come in and that as if it's kind of attaching
our heart right there and so sometimes when I consider this
meditation as a whole field of ritual whatever practice we're engaging in
we're already bringing the heart practice with us
and what kind of integrating all of these Dimensions into our practice
um
yeah I want to just take a pause to see what's coming up right now
one thing that comes up for me right now is that in our relationship with the
meditation often were offered with meditation instructions around breath
body emotions and our thoughts and
instead of considering this our instructions for our meditation
um we can maybe see them as a description of the unfolding meditative process
kind of describing a process of a ritual meditative ritual
and when we see it this way it may help us to kind of let go of
me doing this me doing the instructions instead
we're kind of offering ourselves to this process of meditation or it's a meditation
process meditative process being offered to us through the ex through the the
words and the phrases that are are offered instruct in the instructions
so in this way um
we may be receiving all of those instructions through a sense of
opening to something rather than getting something receiving something
and there are many possibilities when this is done and there can be different
kind of beauty that come in for me today and in the in the middle of
the meditation I opened my eyes and look at all the folks who are
sitting here and Imagining the folks meditating on the YouTube together
and so there was an immediate sense of belonging to the community that came
along and belonging to maybe the world and
that were part of and when we're not cluttered by our
thoughts of a wanting and desires Clarity can also come in
and this is where the New Perspectives can come in and as part of the Insight practice and
the insights may come along maybe not even expressed in words just yet maybe
it's some form of embodied way how we walk out this meditation Hall when we
finish and so
um allow this ritual process to be
expensive maybe including all different elements and that come
along with it and sometimes I'm considering the Dharma
practice if Dharma practice itself is an overarching kind of ritual that has its
beginning a middle and end we can consider many it has many many rituals
within like Mandela fracture or fractals kind of you know in our session today as
we walk into IMC you know all the way to the end we had many rituals of sitting
meditation we had a ritual of Dharma talk engaging with speaking and
listening and we may have another small ritual towards the end where there is a
community Gathering and can we consider
incorporating on this uh
this kind of a dimensions in our practice can we treat each day as if a
word living um a ritual of the day how do we wake up
how do we want to live the day and how do we want to end the day
and so I don't have kind of a fixed idea about
this and but the invitation is for you
to consider the possibility and what it might um
uh how it might affect you in your own practice
and so there may be many different forms of rituals needed for different seasons and different situations and on
different days yet no matter what rituals we engage in
it's an opportunity um to live with a clear heart a clear mind
and open heart and so may the ritual of our practice
allow us to touch the depths of our being may it support all beings
so thank you for your kind attention
and we'll open up for some Reflections and questions and
are sharing you may have you may have your own relationships with this
you look like a rock star okay um
um I asked this with a lot of hesitation kind of thought about it whether I
should ask or not and what I call of myself is not ours to
any rituals as such especially being raised in in India you
know it's part of culture and I have been from not being okay with them with
being okay with them although and I'm not too um worst with the terrorda style of
literature or you know books or what before I have read and
from what I have heard there is something called path to enlightenment and from being a one-time stream enterer
to being in our hand the first step it says um and I don't know where this
comes from but it does say the one-time stream enterer loses
of what probably I don't know his or her rights and rituals right so it's I mean
it took it took a lot to ask this question because I felt I don't want to sound yeah yeah or
cocky or whatever but the idea is
um it's hard for what I call of myself for ego whatever to reconcile that fact
with or maybe it's just a sense of attachment to rituals yeah yeah
so it's a it's a great question I I kind of contemplated a letter to talk about
that or not um but the the it's interesting that uh
the Pali term gets translated as it writes and rituals but the poly meaning
is not necessarily rights and rituals and so what it's really signifying is
the first stage of Awakening is letting go of a dogmatic holding of certain
rules and and so in fact
yeah the direct translation wouldn't map to rights and rituals
and in the um a broader Buddhist to sing especially monastics Buddhism
rituals are always a big part of it and then and how we hold them
is what we're asking and so are we holding them as I must do
this and you know uh and what's the first uh first stage of Awakening is
letting go of a dogmatic holding but it allows us to open up to discern
what is the supportive of our own heart and mind and the path of Awakening and what is
not and so today what I'm offering is the
possibility of considering the dimensions of a ritual that might be
supportive in our practice and not necessarily saying that we must
all do this you know this is it and and so that becomes a dogmatic holding
does that kind of make sense yeah thank you thank you
so we now I think about it every evening my
wife and I do a sitting for 20 minutes it's kind of become ritualistic in the
way it's evolved it's not anything we said this has to be done this way or that way you know in fact it wouldn't be
formally approved so to speak because the cat gets on her lap because it's so settled
and we do this and and it's evolved out of necessity of you know
especially my wife's challenges with sleeping due to
the Heavenly Messengers and uh World situation and all these different
things have and what seems to have helped calmed our help of sleep and
helps me too of course yeah and that is a way I guess I could see how rituals
evolve in that way and it's not yeah beautiful and then part of I was what I was hoping
to point to is to begin to become conscious of how those processes and
elements of ritual can have different effects on us and so for me it was many
years not realizing it's actually doing something unto my own heart and mind
but becoming conscious of it oh oh this can be very supportive
and this can be and then we be then we begin to able to to learn what really
supports us and what does not support us and so there's uh yeah there's a
recognition has a role yeah it's a noticing and recognizing oh does it
become part of my life yeah yeah great
seeing Chen thank you so much for your talk um what came to mind for me was uh
many years ago I I was um bothered a pretty deeply bothered by
feelings my mother had passed away and I hadn't been with her at the time so I
felt bad about that and I looked over in my life with her and thought of like a
number of times I had been unkind or not as kind as I could have been
couldn't really forgive myself for that so somehow I came up with this idea of
creating a ritual for myself because I I felt like I would write on a little
piece of paper every unkind thing that I could think of of course there were lots
of little pieces of paper then I made a I filled a pan with water and one by one
at my gas stove I burned these and threw them in the water threw them in the
water and then at the end I could like toss out the water and I felt as if my
mother was just um if she had been alive she was holding me and saying I know you
love me yeah and I forgive you and it really worked so that was just a one-time ritual but
it was powerful for me yeah beautiful thank you for sharing that story
uh Griff a grief ritual is powerful for many people that for myself in the sense
of my grandpa passing away they're definitely some sense of grief and confusion and
offers such a closure and a healing
um and so yeah absolutely and open to new possibilities and that's
also another form of transforming you know because otherwise we could be holding a lot of regrets or
it's just kind of attracting us and as it becomes a process allow things that are unprocessed to be
held in safety and and kindness and so that it
can get processed yeah thank you okay
it's one more there yeah
thank you um my um this is a question for you I guess
just um my experience with rituals there's
been periods of time where I've hesitated participating in them
and then I've gone back to look at maybe I should give it a second chance or third fourth chance
how is that a typical cycle
yeah yeah um yes I and I appreciated this question
and I think uh I kind of connected with the first question also in some way
sometimes we may have been exposed to the way of doing rituals that are
harmful to us and we can kind of shut off ourselves and I certainly had a very
dismissive attitude towards them at the very beginning because of my own
exposure it is like you know going to this big Temple and that the people just
you know it's just Smoky and crowded and just I'm like busy getting I don't know
things and and I just kind of felt very lost in them and I didn't have a very
um and then I didn't have any really
positive relationship with them until I
began to notice and you know some of the rituals I participate
uh maybe not even aware kind of a state at
my subconscious level and I wasn't really aware what was happening but I
didn't know that it's doing something to me and through began to become aware oh
this wasn't kind of a How uh uh uh what
it is kind of um like what how I associated with it before and so I began
to open to the possibility that well this may have something different to
offer to me and so yes we can go through some of the cycles and
then especially some of the rituals can be done in very dogmatic way and kind of
like you've got to do this and we make and feel very
distant with that kind of attitude yeah yeah thank you thank you for the for the
question yeah it's kind of like a whole territory and so I just invite
um maybe considering um open to this a little by little and
and becoming aware of the effects on us
yeah yeah
maybe we need to yes [Music]
yes I will be around for a little while so I probably just um are we just gonna
be outside or in the Community Hall okay I'll Stand somewhere
so thank you everyone for being here and let's um maybe end with a typical ritual
in our in our scene that is a dedication of a marriage
so may we all just take a moment [Music] um to settle
in our bodies and our seeds
maybe just bring forth on this last few hours being together
any form of a goodness that you can touch in in your own being
in small ways big ways
and allow this goodness to expand and touch your whole being
may it supports our well-being
and may the glow of the goodness expand in all directions
and may it support all beings everywhere
may all beings have well-being
may all beings be free
thank you