good morning everyone and welcome and um
so we're continuing with our satipatana series the practice of mindfulness
and mindfulness gets pretty this is a very simple capacity for being
aware becomes pretty revolutionary after a while and
one way to maybe mention this is um to look at the way the buddha referred
to himself others people sometimes called them
gotama sometimes they called him very common they called him the bhagavan the blessed
one sometimes people it's translated into the lord in some translations but
and uh but when he talked about himself he's most commonly referred to himself as the tatagata
t-a-t-h long a g-a-t-a
and it's a kind of enigmatic title for someone it seems to have been
a title used in india before the buddha there's many ways of
describing what it means that word most commonly one is to say it means the one who is thus gone or thus come
it can also mean the one who is thus the one who is such
so imagine that you go to see someone and you ask someone who are you
and the person says i am thus i am such
the person doesn't highlight any particular characteristics
of who they are they don't define themselves in any of the usual way you think wouldn't be fine just say i'm i'm like
this so what you kind of like what you see is what you get
uh but maybe you know just so the suchness that just thus
and so when we often in our lives we are defining ourselves by different
characteristics different ideas different values that we have i am this i am that
and when the buddha said i am such i am thus he was not defining himself by any
particular thing so this is one of the revolutionary aspects of mindfulness
it is possible to sit and be present for the details of experience
but in no way define ourselves by them no way judge ourselves by them or no way
build up itself around it to simply be thus
be such each thing is allowed to be its own suchness each thing is allowed to be its
own experience the in-breath the in-breath the out-breath the out-breath the itch
an itch sound the sound an emotion just the emotion
a thought just a thought and uh
the um
so we will just sit here today and maybe this idea of sitting in your suchness
just as you are you're thus just as you are without needing to define anything about yourself or
judge anything or be anything except being present for the details of
experience that arise so
assuming a a meditation posture that allows you to be
alert and relaxed
and to gently lower your gaze maybe to 45 degrees
with your eyes open let your eyes gaze at nothing in particular
let me lose focus letting your eyes be cool and relaxed
and then if you'd like you can gently close your eyes
letting yourself take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe in a gentle rhythm of breathing in three quarters full breaths
as if you're gently swinging on a swing
safely relaxedly enjoyingly
breathing in breathing out
and letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale
relaxing the muscles of your face
softening the face
letting the face be the face without needing to identify whether
make a self out of it
defining yourself by the face
softening the shoulders maybe feeling the tension in your
shoulders relaxing
and if there is tension in the shoulders let it just be in a relaxed way without
it to saying anything about yourself
the suchness of shoulders being tense
and as you exhale softening your belly
as you're exhaling softening your whole body
relaxing into your body
and feeling this body without making it a self without
defining yourself by it
without identifying who you are or judging who you are
just the body from the inside out feeling the suchness of the body
and then centering yourself on your breathing
maybe as if there are gentle waves on a wide long
ocean and you're you're gently floating
on the rising and falling of the of breathing
for a gentle wind
that comes and goes
letting go of thoughts as you exhale maybe at the very end of the exhale for
a moment beware of
your experience when there is no thinking
even just for a moment
beyond your thoughts what is the experience
as the inhale begins allow it the suchness of the inhale
an inhale that exists whatever way it exists
without defining yourself by it or
relating it to your idea of self and your your idea of the doer
just the inhale the suchness of the inhale
as you're breathing if you become aware of any feelings of
pleasant or unpleasant let it just be
in the suchness of pleasantness the suchness of unpleasantness
without defining yourself by it or
relating it to yourself what it means about you
your preferences let the pleasant and unpleasant and just
be there in the suchness the simplicity of each
thing by itself
so
whatever emotions you're feeling mood or state you're in
can you let that be in the suchness of the feeling without
appropriating it to self relating it to self
without it having any definition or connection to any idea of self yourself
just the emotion existing by itself maybe you're breathing through it
breathing with it
not doing anything with it just allowing it to be there
as you breathe mindfully
in whatever you're thinking to leave it alone the simplicity of a
thought without it having any
role in how you define yourself characterize yourself
have any role of judging yourself
even in the evaluation of yourself as a meditator that you should or shouldn't be thinking or
just let the thoughts exist in their own simplicity radical simplicity
without any real bearing on
who you are what you are just thoughts
maybe this way you can easier to just be with a simplicity of breathing
and thoughts can just be in the background
nothing to be concerned with
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to take a few breaths to breathe in the simplicity of just being alive just
being here simplicity
of being present
beyond the ideas thoughts judgments
associations the mind makes about being alive being here
breathing into the fullness of our simplicity the suchness of just being here
and not narrowing ourselves down to some particular
aspect of our life suchness of just being
in that suchness of being to welcome in now
thoughts and images ideas of other people people you know
people that you'll encounter on the neighbors hood communities places of
work people you don't know around the world
people who struggle and suffer around all kinds of things including this idea
of self and minds racing and
minds that don't rest in the suchness of their being
and then let your care your love extend out
into the world of other people and may your ability to be calmly simply
present be a source of kindness
care for others may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
so good morning again and welcome to our series on this
patana suta discourse on the establishment
establishing of awareness and
there's many ways in which awareness is lost or subsumed or collapses into our preoccupation with
our lives and one area is with
all the different aspects of our beingness who we are whatever that is
that we can identify and cling to as me myself and mine
and and we now we get to this next exercise in the sattipatana suta
it has to do with five different areas in which we cling
especially clinging to me myself and mine but five prime when we one night one
idea is these five areas are areas which we if we cling we're clinging to one of these five areas and
the kind of the literal meaning of the poly word for this is heaps big heaps of
stuff so it's not a very technical idea though because it's
it became kind of enshrined in buddhist philosophy psychology it's kind of took on it or
technical feeling the word is an a usual translation into english is aggregates
the bollywood is kanda k-h-a-n-d-a and um
it is um five heaps of stuff
and sometimes we'll find in the modern dharma teachers will say something like
the buddha taught there is no self but what there is it are these five
aggregates these five heaps the problem with that is that the buddha never said that
and in fact the buddha if anything
saw the five aggregates of five heaps as problematic something which was
burdensome that they did us to kind of overcome this burden of the five heaps
so to try to explain so this next exercise has to do with these five heaps and the way it's uh
described is the five heaps of clinging so the word of clinging is added to it
and so these are five areas in which we cling five areas from which we cling that the five areas in the world of
clinging and so we're looking uh deeply into this area of clinging to these five things
and uh and seeing deeply into its nature in a very particular way in this
this exercise in the third fourth foundation of of mindfulness of awareness
and so i want to give an analogy
so imagine that it's a beautiful peaceful day and
you're out maybe on the beach or if you don't live near the oceans maybe some cup make up some place big
big big beautiful meadow or field that goes on for a long while but
imagine a beach wide longs beautiful sandy beach with very clean sand
maybe very soft fine textured sand and walk barefooted just feel so
nice and comfortable to feel the warmth and of the sand and the softness of it and
the the beach there is a very gradual grade so it's kind of easy to walk on and
and it may be many hundreds of yards and from the water up to the wherever the vegetation begins and
you can see up the coast for a long ways
and that's just an inspiring day with lots of sky lots of beach and you feel see the suchness of the
beach it's just a beach it's just the suchness of it it's inspiring it's nice you can wander freely the sense of
freedom is wandering aimlessly up and down close to the water away from the water
and just to feel so comfortable and so nice and you have such a wonderful day maybe
a picnic at some point you can turn around come back and just being in the beach you come back a
week later to thinking you do the same thing because it was so nice but now
the local [Music]
beach authorities have made a decision to give easier access or they thought to
the beach to everyone so that everyone would have equal ability to kind of just walk the beach
don't have to worry about people kind of getting in front of them or
you know blocking their way or something so they've decided to put
fences down the whole length of the beach that maybe are maybe you know
it could be ten feet wide or five feet light wide and so they're they're making lanes
and so you have to get a ticket and and uh and reserve a spot beforehand and
you're assigned a lane and now there's these like you know 10-foot or something fences on either
side of the lane so people really stay and they have their privacy in their lane because they you know the privacy is important
and so you're given your lane maybe you're lane 38 and now you can just kind
of uh and you're free to walk straight on that lane
for as long as there's the beach and so and everyone is free to walk their lane and this way it's equal and
everyone kind of equal access and though you can pay a little bit more to be close to the ocean
and um and so what you're lost then is a suchness the vast freedom just the beach by
itself now it's been defined and laid out this is you know
so it's a kind of ridiculous analogy but uh this is what we do to
ourselves uh we are like a vast open beach without
any definition in the sand but we make lines in the sand
and we say that um you know that define one thing over another
and the five lines that these five heaps are the five kind of lines that we make
and so they are uh the word
often the first word is called form or sometimes body that people say but form
um i prefer the word appearance the physical appearance but form or physicality but not our physical
physicality but rather the way it appears to us the second is the feelings of pleasant
and unpleasant the third is the basic perception sensation of sensations that
occur uh the the fourth is um the kind of mental world of other mental
activities concepts ideas wishes aspirations memories
and the and the fifth is consciousness and
it makes some sense maybe to divide up our experience this way but the buddha is suggesting you don't
have to divide them up this way once we divide them up this way we cling to them and hold on to them in particular ways
and now if we cling to them it's like making a fence making a line making a lane in our experience
and we're selecting part of who we are to cling to at the expense of a disconnection with
the rest of it some people cling a lot to their body some people to their comfort and
sensuality are pleasant and unpleasant some people to their perceptions their sensations their
ideas of things some people to the whole inner landscape and psychology and
and you know all the i think it's a particular special speciality of the
psychological modern world where we're so hypersensitive to the little nuances
of what we think and what we feel and and
how we judge and how we operate psychologically and there's a lot of clinging there
and then there's also this idea of clinging to consciousness to awareness itself as being ultimate as being special
and um and so these are five areas of clinging so rather than saying that that
the buddha taught there's no self but rather these five aggregates the buddha said
that there's no need to cling but these are
the five areas in which people cling these are five areas in which we divide
ourselves up and then get attached to those divisions and
and the idea is to be able to let go of those clinging to allow things to return
to the suchness of our experience the simplicity of just the beingness of
things that arise and pass and come and go in fact that's the exercise is in fact
to see the arising and passing of each of these five heaps and as we see the arising and passing
then at some point the sense of the division the lines the fences and and sand fall away
and we start being able to see then the rising and passing of all all phenomena
and the suchness of things that occur and um
so we are in the simplicity pristine simplicity of who we are
we don't make any lines we don't make any fences and divisions everything is allowed to exist in its
own naturalness its own as it appears and there are sensations in the body there are pleasant and unpleasant and
all these things but they exist in this wider broad peaceful
uh you know beach and now that there's no lines in it you're just all it's allowed to exist
without clinging to any of it and the first of them is appearance
which is um the physical appearance of how we are and
so it's not literally what our physical body is the physicality of it but it's
um the concepts ideas projections um
ways of selecting out our physical experience that we get attached to
so for example our physical you know physical appearance of our nose our skin or
our height or our size it's all these physical ways in which we appear to ourselves and to others
and that is not just um kind of the way things are
but has something to do with how we select out this is important to judge people by or comment people or
notice about people notice about ourselves and the tremendous amount of suffering occurs
in the clinging to appearance and to this you know how things appear to us
in our body and and the buddha's suggested suggestion is
that instead of focusing being caught in the
the appearance and concerned and preoccupied by it step back with mindfulness
and see that the world of appearance physical appearance belongs to the world of things
that are inconstant changing moving partly because
the uh one form of clinging to the appearance
is to think that our appearances are constant or permanent this is who i am
the world of appearance is a interactive world between
our physicality in the minds values perceptions
concepts judgments selectivity project projections that mind makes and if we pay careful
attention we see that there's a kind of reconstruction of appearance reconstruction of what's
important by selecting what's important and clinging to it and judging it and
building up ideas around it and that is what begins to relax and soften as we begin seeing that
appearances um both in some way one way or the other as we rest back into the appearance of
things that uh there's a flow of inconstancy of a rising and passing that goes on
and then the clinging can begin to relax the the the prioritization of certain kind
of um projection or certain kind of judgments or commentary can begin letting go
and we can begin experiencing the suchness just or the simplicity of being
the beingness or the or just be at peace and at ease
with how things are with ourselves here
so the five aggregates the five heaps and now so that'll be the topic for this
week and so each day i'll take one of the heaps and discuss it some and today was
the appearances got kind of short discussion because it was introduction to the five
so thank you and i wish you well and
look forward to being back tomorrow