so thank you all for coming here this evening and uh
i'm still marveling at what it's like to be together with groups of people in this way
i've now done a few on in-person retreats at our retreat center and then a few of the sundays and fewer much
fewer of the mondays and uh on and off since november we've met a
little bit but i still marvel at it and i don't take it for i don't take it for granted
i feel like it's a pretty wonderful thing that we come together
the first time i uh came together with people after
i think was back in august i had an occasion to meet outdoors with a group of people
and and i was surprised
that i was surprised surprised by how surprised i was
at the wonderfulness of being with other people this way three-dimensionally
i knew it'd be special i knew it was special to be with people in person but i was surprised that i was so
surprised it was like i'd forgotten something it was like i understood being together with people in a new way
that i hadn't known before or had i taken for granted or and because it was invisible because it
was so common so i kind of more i kind of marvel at being together with you all
here and appreciate it and it's very nice and then there's a group of people also on
uh participating exactly more people participating on
youtube then he's here today and so it's i find it delightful that we have this extended
feeling of connection and we live right now at a
perilous time for this world and i don't know if
in my lifetime if i felt so so much peril in the world at one time
i do wish to have memories of some of you maybe old enough for this memories of
60 years ago doing uh
atomic bomb drills and uh they had very special desks for students
back then because they had these desks that protected you from a nuclear bomb they went off nearby
if you just ducked underneath it so we would have these surprise ducking
exercises in the middle of just in the middle of classroom with no no no
no expectation of it suddenly the teacher would yell out duck and we were supposed to just dive under
the table and put our arms over our heads and and survive
so that was you know it had a formative impact on me that's possibility of nuclear holocaust in the
19th early 60s that we had my parents went through they were young
but they went through world war ii and my grandparents went through it and the parents-in-law went through it and
some of them are very difficult
and i grew up with lots of stories of war and it always felt like war was close by
and so we have um you know not just the war in the ukraine
but that's the most that's in some ways the most dramatic for us but there are
other wars in the world people are busy and engaged or
kind of overwhelmed by the local wars that they probably don't even know what's going on in ukraine because they're just dealing
with their own and it seems that
war is a phenomena of hatred and
competition greed power which doesn't bring out the best in
human beings and the sad thing is when it brings when the
war brings out the worst in human beings people otherwise who would have been nice but
and uh and it just perpetuates the awful ways in which people are
together
my i think coming out of these years many years decades now of doing buddhist
practice i have a strong sense that the world
that i live in begins with me not that i don't think it's a conceited sense that begins with me like that but
we're also to start let's but through through my experience the way that i have contact with
through my senses with the world around me and reading and learning about things far
away and and so in my consciousness it radiates
from here that contact with the world and the way that i perceive the world
is not a is not an indifferent bystander or
innocent bystander just seeing it as it actually is the way we experience and see the world
is very much connected to how we
the eyes through which we see the and if we see the world through eyes of
anger we see it one way if we see it through the eyes of kindness it's another way
if we see it through the eyes of greed it's one way if we see it at the eyes of generosity
we see a different world we attuned to different experiences to
different sites and sights and the sounds and different things we noticed
they've done studies of people who were and actually encouraged to be kind
and when they were encouraged to be kind they saw more kindness throughout the day and more opportunities for kindness
but when they they weren't told that they had this control group that wasn't told anything about kindness
they noticed fewer less kindness in their world
and so if the world begins with us then how do what do we put what do we offer this
world and i feel very strongly that if we want to live in the world that's peaceful
don't be expecting other people to make the peace if you want to live in the world where
you want a peaceful world be peaceful yourself be the be saving the world to save the
world but that begin with you don't look elsewhere for it
for one thing that means that if you look elsewhere someone else to do it
then uh you're not engaged and it's a kind of despairing not to
engage it kind of makes us discouraged and gives up our agency and
and then we get disappointed when other people don't behave the way they're supposed to or not successful
it's just so good for the human heart to be active to be engaged making a difference
it doesn't matter how big it is you're not going to chances are none of us here or today are going
to stop the war in ukraine but maybe we can help a little bit so
i'm you probably know but imc this week has a fundraising drive
to for money for save the children and one of the highest rated charities
to help them in their work with the refugees and the ukrainian refugees and
so that's something we can do as of i think this morning we've raised
40 30 43 000 it's you know it's a drop in the bucket for the billions that are needed but
it's something and and for the kids in the refugee camps
who don't have water or don't have food or blankets or something i don't know what their needs are
that's pretty big deal for them so to do
to engage and it's kind of a one of the it's remarkable we don't do more of it this
way because it turns out it's good for the heart it's good for us
to be kind to be generous there's been studies done on kindness
it's kind of phenomenal right finally i think they did uh studies on anger
first many years ago but now slightly slowly they're getting to these more
positive emotions and studying them and kindness uh
so one of the things people researchers say is what many of us already know that if you're kind
i can feel good for the other person but it can feel good for yourself the other day i took a taxi
and uh and the taxi driver was not a good driver
the taxi driver wasn't particularly pleasant to be with and at some point i
and was talking a lot in a way that was just not so pleasant also um
i didn't wear his mask except under a chin i thought that's kind of strange still
this time of day this this kind of time and uh okay you know i didn't quite know where
he was going exactly i had to kind of tell him where to go and uh so it's a little unusual
and uh but when i when he when i we got to a
place where i was going i just felt delighted to be able to give him a big tip
the big tip was not like oh you did a good job it was like oh you're a human my tip was
you're a human being who's struggling in life trying to make life get by and i felt that i got a sense
from this as a man who things weren't easy
i said oh you're you're a human being who's trying to get by and struggling and i don't know why the pandemic's been
hard for him and i just wanted to kind of do i just felt kind of cozy and friendly and kind
and as i hear and he was quite surprised to get a nice tip
and i was then i was happy again i was happy to be kind it felt nice to have that kind of
instinct of generosity but when he reacted so like wow
it wasn't you know that big but you know he wasn't putting his kids through
college or anything but you know just it was just like oh he felt you know he kind of lit up and
i thought oh great i did send like a good deed today i just cheered him up a little bit
did he deserve a tip big tip and that was not how i was thinking that was not
interest that kind of way of thinking was maybe if he'd done like an extra mile
that did something really special something maybe i would have done the same or more or something but
my generosity was not contingent upon him deserving it it was contingent about here as a person
who it can make a difference in this person's life and to care for him and
express some kind of goodness and kindness to it and i felt good that it was not i kind of felt kind of
cozy in my heart oh that was nice i wasn't proud it was just like oh and i didn't think about it again until
i was thinking about giving a talk on kindness today i remembered my the other day
it was a surprise uh this the way that being kind or compassionate or caring
can produce some very good feelings in the person who's kind i don't know if it's automatic but i
but i think that it works best to be kind if we feel confident and safe and comfortable with the situation
and if that's the case then i think kindness
creates a kind of mood or goodness or a warmth or a
softness in ourselves if we do it in a nice way a kind of if we're kind in a kind way
it does it does good for us and i remember uh
the first time i really felt this in a strong way was uh i was in a kind of hike and a desert
kind of area with a group of people i think was a lead group
but it was a little bit difficult because somebody had to climb over these little boulders and like little
in through these little valleys that they had the ledges you had to get up and over and there was a person on the hike
who had trouble with that so i just kind of stayed behind to help
this person up the ledges and over the elders and and i was just i didn't think much about doing it just seemed like the thing to
do but then after a while i started feeling like how good it felt
i just started feeling so good inside and i couldn't wait until there was a next ledge
and after a while like you know who was benefiting who here was i helping her was she helping me or
was i the one who was fortunate to be helping because i did such a good thing to me
or was she the one who was fortunate to be helped i don't know exactly how she felt by it but uh
but i felt isn't it i thought they said pretty cool pretty amazing
that if you want to be happy one of the ways to be happy is to help other people be kind to other people
generous to other people if you don't want to be happy
then it's recommended you don't be kind to anyone you'd mess up with your lack of
happiness if you uh if you start being kind
but uh the fact that we can be kind and and it does good things for us and
then it's self perpetuating once we start being kind we start seeing the world through those
those eyes we start seeing the world through those softness and that that orientation
and we start seeing more kindness in the world research people do a lot of good things for each other i mean small
things and the
and big things and so you're seeing and they start
living in a world that's not only
you know the horrific things we're seeing and reading about in the ukraine
that's still true we don't want to deny it and pretend it's not there and
but that's not the whole story even in the ukraine
there is a lot of people who are trying to help a lot of organizations who are rushing
with their their work and their money to provide for the refugees a lot of people who are there
going to help the people who are wounded and you can see you can see sometimes the horrific
pictures of someone being helped out of a building they've been bombed and there's blood on their face
and it's kind of horrific to see but then do you notice the person who's helping them
has their arm around their shoulders and leading them out that's pretty phenomenal that people are
doing that and in some ways it's me it's kind of that
helping is more dramatic it's probably dangerous to help in that way but the helpers are the people who are
making the world a good place to live in the kind of world that we want to live in so one of
the principles i like to live by is
i want to be live
my life as if i'm living in the world i want to be in
so what i mean by that i want to live in a world where people are kind to each other and supportive
and generous and caring and that world begins with me
being that way being kind and generous and supportive and uh
that's the world i want to live in it so much that world i prefer that or the value of that
i don't want to live in a world of violence but i don't want to turn my back on the
violence and pretend it's not there i don't want to be the ostrich you know putting my hand in the sand and ignoring
it but i don't want to succumb to that to anger succumb to despair succumb to
greed succumb to violence i don't want that to come out of me into
the world i don't i don't want that to be the influence i have on this world i don't want to live in a world that's
like that and
i would like to suggest that that take that sometimes takes a tremendous amount of bravery to do that
people who go to war to fight are said to be brave they risk their lives
sometimes they risk it for great causes
what about risking our lives for the sake of kindness
what about risking our lives for the sake of peace is it worth is it appropriate
is that worthwhile to have that kind of bravery as well to have such a high value
on on love and care
that if we want to have be a world like that
maybe we do have to sacrifice some things maybe it needs bravery maybe it is it then foolish
even to put our lives in danger going out into the battlefield to bring
back the injured or to stand in front of the tanks so that
they don't bump some people
i don't think that kindness is
is avoiding
to live dedicated to kindness or love or care generosity and
i think to really do it realistically for this world that's so horrific
we almost need like a kindness core you know people who
are so dedicated to it that they're willing to really give themselves over to it and perhaps even risk their lives
with it so it isn't just be you know well okay that's good i'll be kind to my cat now
when i go home it's nice to be kind to your cat but
but it's you know i think i'd like to think if we want the world to start with us
and we and how we are is what creates the world to some degree
do we have the bravery to hold on to
the values that we would like to have in this world to experience this world too
if you want to live in a world of peace
and you're contributing to it
how brave do you need to be
if society
struggles with some of the difficulties of effects of the war like
i mean something like the rising gas prices and energy prices
do we just complain do we have to be brave and wise and
clever about how to not use more so much gasoline
rather than being complained about gasoline prices do we find people to give them money so
they can give them gasoline people who need it more than we do how do we live in a world
how do we make the world the world that we want to live in that's the
that i think is one of the principles that i've learned from buddhism
and one of the reasons one of the reasons one of the ways that's represented in the teachings of the buddha
is this with the world the word a world in his language
it's loka loka has the same varied
meanings as the english world english word world it can mean the earth kind of
but you can also say the world of my senses you know just what i'm aware of in the
moment or the world of my emotions
and in the for the buddha the word loka sometimes just means
the direct world of your immediate experience here in this body
that's the world but also the globe is the world as well
and here we have the same word used for both and i think that there's something very profound about this
that they're not so separate and so it's from this kind of idea that
if you want to live in a kind world a supportive world a caring
world well there's a world where you in which
you can do that which is your world and your world
is connected to that wider world spreads from you and who knows
who you'll touch who knows where you where it'll take you
so what i'd like to propose to you all is that
if you are despairing about what's happening in the world
if you are angry with what's happening in the world
and you spend a lot of time in despair and anger you're wasting your time
it's a kind of an indulging it's reasonable that we feel these that
stuff but it's also possible to act differently it's possible to do and act
so that the what the world needs what you feel the world needs comes from you out into the world
and it makes a huge difference for your heart huge if you do something
if you're only reading the news that's all you do you know that's not good for the heart
the buddha who was a man was a man it was a they would have taught
action in a way that sometimes is not so obvious when we're
teaching buddhism through a meditation tradition where come and meditate and be quiet
but the teaching was really about action the world begins with your action
every day when you wake up you create a new world for yourself what's that world that you want to
create and each of us is capable of agency
each of us is capable even if it's small things
saying hello to a neighbor
picking up the trash someplace where no one's picked it up for a while
i have a friend one of her things is that she goes with uh periodically on the weekend
down around i don't know exactly downtown river city but somehow somehow somehow east of el
camino and she collects trash like from the train tracks and other
places and that's what she does all kinds of things that are possible
now if you're not despairing and not angry maybe that's a different
different i don't know what you know but if you're if you are despairing in anger and angry
i think it would probably do you a a world of good
if you acted in the way in the ways that create the
world that you want to live in in ways that are good for your heart
feed it and support it to nourish it so that you benefit from the goodness
that you do there's this wonderful mutuality that we do good for the world if you do it the right way
then it we benefit from it it's just what's fantastic it's almost like we should all be
selfish in this kind of way because in this very particular way
to to want our hearts to be radiant and glowing and warm and loving
what a great way to be and if you can be selfish around that
boy would you do good in the world and you wouldn't be able to stay selfish or very long
because selfishness is limits the glow of the heart
so you're welcome to start selfishly it's okay because it'll melt away if you're what you're doing is
benefiting yourself from love with love care kindness
so i would say the world needs kindness now
more than any time that is needed in my lifetime that i've known this is the great need we have
there probably is no hope for us unless we have people who care and act
on that care you love and act on that love
so i hope that this practice that we do our meditation practice or mindfulness practice
to
your love and empower power
and uh
so those are my thoughts for today any of you have any thoughts you want to
share about this topic
yeah you can use the mic and i see that uh something funny happened with the people on for youtube
and uh i i look like a one of those
mirrors in the amusement parks it's all stretched out i think it's a problem with our software
here i had a occasion earlier today where i was
doing something helping the community and this isn't about me and like what i was doing but
there's a lot of rote uh doing something over and over again where my body kind of gets tired and
but there are there's a larger community that i can interface with and be with
but while i was just mindfully just doing something over and over and over again to
do something was a good cause my brain came up with a song i haven't sung in decades
what a wonderful day i kind of had a headache my body was doing rotator cuff was
bugging me but this spontaneously song just came up
um that i haven't sung truly in decades and i don't know where it came from but there was just this
upwelling of a a song yeah very nice yet i love it the uh
one of the one of my ideas of uh reference points for being happy
it do is having our hearts sing what makes your heart sing
and so to live live live that way and so you can i guess your heart starts singing
beautiful very nice very nice thank you
hello i am irina in my neighborhood
there is some very strange thing happened i was going for a walk and then
i see the pile of flowers by the wall and there is a teddy bear can you hold
it like this and and there is a teddy bear and i have no clue what what's happening
and then a few days later somebody told me that it is for the homeless guy
and i asked the lady about homeless but we literally had only one homeless guy
hanging around neighborhood i gave him sometimes money and but i never seen him interacting with
anybody talking with anybody but you see a person dies and
people's hearts opened to him people brought him flowers
it was very surprising and just like
i don't know it's act of kindness or definitely empathy uh
very strange sounds like it sounds like people were touched by him yeah in some deep way yeah
and it was not just two three it was a pile of flowers
nice very nice yeah
someone on youtube's wrote today i helped a neighbor whose electric wheelchair ran out of charge near my
house it felt good even though i was busy but the connection was super sweet
i bet that person didn't wake up in the morning thinking that they were going to do that but
who knows what will come our way sometimes i like to think that
it's good to be ready it's good to be in the world ready to be kind ready to be loving or caring
and sometimes we don't we're not in those states when we're harried and busy and trying to do too
much and then the question is what is what's most valuable way to be and again again it's
kind of in the theme of the talk i think one of the most valuable things to to waste to be
is to be the world that you want to live in and if you want to be in a world where
you're running running after your to-do list trying to do as much as you possibly can through the day just being hairy and
busy well that's the world you want i guess
there's a lot of a lot of people around here who can help you do it well
you know that people are skilled and uh but that's not i don't think
that's what the world we want to live in so please your life is so important and
so valuable and and each of you is important
an important part of this world important for making a difference for this world
and who knows who you're going to touch who knows whose life you save or close
to it who knows what your smile your care your good will can do
who knows when you give a live more than is expected and someone smiles and is delighted and
feels wow there's good people in this world it's not all people who are just trying and take advantage of me
and argue with me because they feel like i'm charging them too
much for driving them someplace there's other people too
this kind the world has kind people it has helpers
so when you'll see the photographs from the ukraine be sure to recognize the helpers as well
maybe they're the ones who are the most brave
so thank you for this evening thank you for being here and
i look forward to our chance to sit together again