uh good evening everyone welcome
uh several weeks ago Diana Clark asked me if I would give a talk tonight I she's
away and at the time that she asked me I was
working in South Korea and hadn't been attending IMC
since I think early June uh or early July
and I was somewhat out of a loss of what to talk about
um so I decided that I would talk about
sort of how I Spent My Summer Vacation I worked for NASA
and in that capacity I
um have a an instrument that flies on high
altitude aircraft for measuring atmospheric gases and so for the last several years I've
been preparing to get that ready to to go to uh on this aircraft than in into
Korea and it required that I go to Houston Texas
in late June and early July of this of this year and I knew that it would be hot and
humid but it was record-breaking hot and humid they had more days over a hundred
than they'd ever had before and so
I had to deal with just the the discomfort
of being in hot humid um
uncomfortable environment for generally speaking short periods of time
just between the building that I was working in and the my car or between my
car and a restaurant or the restaurant and or the hotel and the car
and I realized I didn't think about it too much but mostly my my way of working
with that discomfort was sort of a a stoic endurance of it
you know just kind of
not kind of tuning it out in a certain way or
um hardened hardening myself in a way to that experience
and I was really looking forward to to leaving it and going to South Korea
which I thought would be much more Pleasant
and so I was working at a Osan Air Base outside of Seoul
and I couldn't have been more wrong Soul had it's the hottest temperatures
that it had ever in addition to having floods and our
typhoon and all sorts of other challenging conditions
and on this base I didn't have a car I
didn't there there were taxis all over that kind of hard to get hold of at
certain times so it required walking through the heat for is about a mile from where I was the
lodge that I was in to the flight line where I was working
and all of the places to get food were about
almost the same distance they were about three quarters of a mile from the flight line
so in some ways I was forced to walk
in hot humid conditions bright Sun absolutely no wind
uh and I found that I I started out with
that same sort of stoic endurance strategy
and it turned out it just was it was miserable it just didn't work
and then it dawned on me oh I know I know how to work with this I'll
do mindfulness meditation and this is something that I've been doing now for multiple decades
but for some reason it hadn't really occurred to me to to apply it in this
situation um
so I made a kind of a modified version of uh walking meditation
and I'm curious how many of you have had some kind of training in Walking
meditation okay some of you had and so you know that
um you know it's mostly paying attention to the sensations in your feet or in your
lower legs as you um
lift one foot move it place it lift the other foot move it and place it
foreign I decided I would try I wonder if I
wonder if this will really work under this kind of extreme condition at least it was extreme for me I'm sure that
there are people who have lived in uh even more challenging
conditions than that but for me it was um
not a common experience for me
so in the teravadan Buddhist tradition there's a teaching about how to do
mindfulness meditation formally
which is based on the four foundations of mindfulness
so these four foundations of mindfulness the the First Foundation is mindfulness
of the body and that's perhaps straightforward to think about you know it's like
paying attention to the sensations that occur in the body
moment to moment so in in addition to paying attention to
the feet and paying attention to the legs
uh I could pay attention to the entire body in particular the skin
and all of the perspiration that was coming up from the Heat and the humidity
uh The Sensation from the clothing that was getting rapidly getting very wet
from sweating um
I was walking about three to five miles a day which is more than I typically do
and so I was noticing the sensations of soreness of the muscles
um I was carrying about a 30 pound computer bag so there was you know the sensations
in the shoulder and the arm
uh I was having some back issues so there were Sensations in the back
uh all of those kind of Sensations are included in the category of
mindfulness of the body
and so and what made it somewhat easier to do was
that those Sensations were pretty predominant they weren't subtle at all
so I didn't have to you know kind of really try hard to notice what was going
on with the body uh the second Foundation of mindfulness
is mindfulness of uh feeling tone sometimes called vedana
it's like is the Sensation that you're experiencing is it Pleasant
is it unpleasant or is it neither Pleasant nor unpleasant
is it kind of a neutral have a neutral feeling tone to it
and again yeah well and it's that can be a very
important thing to pay attention to because often
were unconsciously driven to seek out that which is pleasant and to
try to avoid or push away that which is unpleasant and kind of ignore what's neutral what's
kind of neither Pleasant or nonpleasant we just don't pay attention to it
so uh so vedana of the feeling tone is the
second Foundation the third Foundation of mindfulness practice
is mindfulness of Mind States like what
what is the state of the mind is it
open or is it contracted um
you know is it is it sort of friendly or is it hostile
um is a curious or is it contracted
there's some formal names for the different uh mine States but I kind of make them up for my myself like kind of
noticing what what states of mine tend do I tend to experience
and there's a differentiation between mind States the third Foundation of
mindfulness and mind objects or mental formations thoughts
in that the mind States tend to be things that
last longer you know if if a certain mind state is
developed it may be around for a while whereas mental formations thoughts tend
to just kind of come and go fairly rapidly so
uh here's the paying attention to mind
States and then the fourth Foundation is
mindfulness of uh mind objects or mental formations uh thoughts you could say
um what kind of things are going on in the mind you know what kind of stories what
kind of opinions what kind of beliefs
um you know all of those things that can
occur so those are the four foundations so of
mindfulness so for this particular situation where I
decided I was really going instead of trying to mentally avoid paying attention to the
discomfort this discomfortable this com uncomfortable
um experience of Walking In The Heat I decided that I would really
Let It Be an opportunity for me to just practice developing
mindfulness the muscle of mindfulness the muscle of being able to be actively
aware of what's going on and see what happens you know does is that
uh does that uh help in some way or not
and so
uh you know as I was saying earlier that you know mindfulness of the body was was pretty obvious
um you know that I'd pay attention not only
to the to the Heat into the sweating into the soreness
um but there were some Sensations that um were more subtle like just the the
feeling of the feet on the ground um and some that were even
mildly Pleasant given that um
I would often be kind of soaked in sweat any little breeze any little air motion
any little um uh walking into the shade temporarily
had a um had a pleasant feeling tone to it you
know it was was noticeable I could feel oh yeah that was good uh
occasionally on the way back to my uh lodging I would stop at this mall this
food court which was air-conditioned walking into the air conditioning was
really noticeable and it was really really Pleasant
at least at the beginning um [Applause]
and so over time you know so so mindfulness of the body
was a very um
I'll say easy practice not that I liked it but that it didn't
require um a lot of energy or effort to be to be
aware of the body similarly with feeling tone you know
similarly with the the pleasant the unpleasant and the
neutral for for many of the experiences that I
was having a lot many of the uh physical Sensations and also mental
activity um
I could notice I think I I tended to notice most
predominantly what was unpleasant you know that was that was really
stood out
and then the third Foundation mindfulness of Mind States
I could I could tell those times when
there was strong aversion that was a very aversive mind was often set by the conditions
that I had experienced that day like did I get enough sleep
or was I rested or was I tired um
was I hungry or was I pretty well fed
uh had I had a lot of success that day or not
had the instrument worked well had we solved some problems
or had we found new problems and you know
so success and failure would often influence how
what the state of mind was that I was experiencing
was I thirsty I have to say
um I was very tuned into the fact that
being out in the heat had a certain danger to it
you know that that it is possible to get dehydrated to have a heat exhaustion or
heat stroke in fact there was a chemistry professor from Berkeley
that I knew who had died of heat exhaustion while taking a
short walk in Utah just a few weeks before I went to South Korea
so I realized that these these things can sneak up on you
so I was very aware of of drinking you know at least two to three liters of
water a day so I didn't often get
anywhere near dehydrated but I would get I'd certainly get tired I would
certainly get hungry um there were other
times when I just get frustrated and so
I'd see how how the
um what was what was the state of my mind as I was walking
and then finally the the fourth Foundation is mindfulness of of I'll say
thoughts mental processes mental formations
when I first when it first occurred to me to do mindfulness
as a way of meeting the discomfort that I was
feeling um I had a lot of strong thoughts
I I hated this experience I just really I just really hated it
um I you know had thoughts that this shouldn't be happening it shouldn't be
happening to me somebody needs to take care of me you know somebody's needs to be chauffeuring
me around so that I don't have to experience this uh
self-judgment about why am I suffering and all these other people are just walking around as though
you know everything's fine
um and so it really was those thoughts of
of hatred that caught my attention
and made me think hey there I must find a better way
to deal with the the discomfort of the Heat then just some kind of
uh you know stoically enduring it
and it occurred to me that in the teachings of the Buddha he talked there's there's
a story about the Buddha asking one of his monks
he's um oh paraphrase the story but it it goes
he asked the monkey if you get hit by an arrow somebody shoots an arrow and it sticks into you does that hurt
and the monk said yes you know yes uh
yes Buddha that that would hurt and he said and if somebody were to shoot a second Arrow
into you would that hurt even more and he said oh yeah yeah that second
Arrow would you know that that would also hurt
and so the the point of the story is that there are
some things that happen to us being in hot uncomfortable
conditions is like the first Arrow it's that part's unavoidable
the second arrow is everything that we add to our experience all of the thoughts about it
all of the um either wanting it or or clinging to it
or trying to push it away or ignore it
all of the all of the ways that we relate to that first Arrow are really the second Arrow
and so I could see that well there was no avoiding the first
Arrow of of the Heat I could avoid the second
and third and fourth arrows that uh were my responsibility
you know that that I was
that I was choosing in a certain way by Choosing by not paying attention
yeah and so
I found that over time as I started to do this mindfulness as I would walk
out in the midday Heat that
it wasn't it was better I certainly I never reached the point
that I liked it that I found it an enjoyable experience
but I wasn't hating it I wasn't pushing it away I wasn't
I wasn't um fighting with it there was a certain level of acceptance that I was accepting
this is this is this is how this is what this moment is like
and that was quite a change
and that was just about the time that Diana asked me if if I would give a talk and
so I decided that I would look into this a little bit more
and about the week before I left Korea I saw that Eugene cash was giving a talk
up in San Francisco at San Francisco inside
and his talk was about loving
in the present moment loving whatever experience you're having even if you don't like it
and it was an inspiring talk I didn't
really think that that I would get to the point of loving the
experience and that's sort of a can often be a loaded word
but there were other things that I I could do I could find a level of acceptance
you know this this is this is this is what my present moment experience is like
by turning my attention to rather than away from the discomfort
there came to be a certain um a certain intimacy with the experience
that it wasn't it wasn't um you know kind of like
looking aside and wondering is it going away yet but really just welcoming it in
a certain way um
and so it was helpful then to hear uh Eugene talking about
the just how precious the present moment is
whatever it is you know whether it's whether it's uh comfortable or
uncomfortable joyous or sad
um
connected or lonely
um there aren't any moments that we have to that we have to reject
that we have to push away that we have to turn from that we can have this intimacy
with our experience and that was
you know that was part of the lesson for me in in being in Korea
when I got back I listened to a talk yesterday morning by a Tibetan teacher
Anam tubetin up in Point Richmond
and he was speaking about a very similar um
principal in Tibetan Buddhism about
cultivating within yourself a place of luminous awareness
a place I'll say a place it's it's
well who knows maybe it is a place inside that can be aware of what's going on
and unperturbed by what the content of the present moment is
so it can be aware of discomfort it can
be aware of longing it can be aware of joy
it can be aware of brightness
you know energetic brightness it can be aware of dullness
um and that
that place of luminous awareness
is sort it's it's up to us to
um create in a certain way or maybe find
or strengthen
so I think this this mindfulness of
mindfulness of heat meditation that I was doing for
oh I think it was about a month in Korea got me on that path got me more
motivated to to see is it possible for
me to reside more often in this place of
luminous awareness and not so much in the reaction to the my experience or the
um the thoughts about or the opinions about
so I felt very um I felt grateful in a way that I first
of all that I've been exposed to this practice for so many years
that it's kind of sinking in
and towards the end of my time in Korea the
the temperature is actually cool down a bit down to even even below 80 at times
um and so I thought well this is a valuable lesson I'll put this one I'll put this one in the can and I'll I'll bring it
out when I need it again and of course I got back to the you I got back to
California last Wednesday in the midst of a record Heat Wave here and so I
realized okay well I guess this isn't just something that's now occurred and
is you know it's a great story and I can tell it but it was like okay
you're not Beyond discomfort you know the discomfort's gonna always be present
no matter where you are geographically
um yeah so
and it isn't a practice that's just about being hot or just the discomfort
of um the kind of the conditions we've all have been experiencing in the last week
or two uh I'm sure in a few months I'll be I could probably give a talk about
um cold meditation you know I think it's going to get cold this winter
it always has and if it's not that there's
um there's all of the aches and pains that
come with getting old so um
so working with discomfort is a pretty important part of life
you know like letting the discomfort be a teacher
um rather than just something that needs to be avoided or
um pushed away is an important
um important lesson for me
yeah so that's that's what I have to offer tonight
and we have a fair amount of time left if there's anyone that has any questions or comments or
uh would like to talk about experience they've had either dealing with heat or
dealing with any other kind of discomfort or anything else
so thank you
oh and if you do have a question I think there's a microphone so that people
online can hear
oh
okay oh thank you I just wanted to say thank you for the part where you said let the
discomfort be the teacher because I do often want to avoid discomfort and I'm
currently experiencing discomfort to the point
where I'm like can I handle this for an entire school year I don't know but
i instead of just thinking well I I mean I'm gonna be
I'm gonna be with these kids let me let me learn from them and let me not just
uh because boy it's a hard class and I just
there are times I just don't know what to do the end but as you said just I've
been resisting it a lot and I just just thank you I maybe treat
it as a let me learn from them you know because I was often very like
the self-judgment thinking why should I have to deal with this well I'm I'm
above this or I've been doing this for almost a decade now I can I can deal with it or why does it have to be this
hard again after the pandemic but no there's going to be discomfort at
every point in life and I need to be or I'm just being that having that luminous
mindfulness Within at least what I'm trying to cultivate is
something that I'm trying to strive for every day so just thanks
thank you for sharing that yeah one thing that it didn't say that in
addition to just being aware a strengthened awareness
that I found that over time there was a certain compassion that arose
in me compassion for myself caring about the experience
and wanting to do something so it isn't just a practice about
observing but there's also can be a much wiser
response the way we respond to our our experience can be
wiser if we're more connected with it so
hopefully you'll find some wise ways to work with your pain
thank you
the other side thank you
yeah something that when you were just speaking now about stoicism makes me
curious about myself because that's often my experience to adversity
and I'm not sure
but what you also said I think following that was like being Mary I'll paraphrase but like the
you can respond with some wisdom with uh
really being present to whatever is there also feels true like the stoicism is
kind of a coping mechanism but it's not as accurate so
it feels like something for me to sit with more maybe an egg sorry face adversity so
yeah I think it's when I I when I say kind of stoic and endurance
it's more like kind of white knuckling yeah you know it's like you know just
bearing down and and um you know trying to
you know kind of use the force of will to get through the experience rather than really allowing
and I I suspect that there's probably more years than I'd like to think of
where I've sat on a cushion in pain thinking that somehow if I if I
experience enough pain I'm going to have some you know transformational
experience but the pain alone didn't really do it it it's really how one relates to it
that's and and how one is relating to it that's
perhaps the the more important part
thank you yeah thank you
foreign
well I think that uh we can
end at this point I'll be around for a few minutes if
anyone has a specific question they want to bring to me personally
so thank you all for coming and uh may you be
um skillfully
uncomfortable [Laughter]