so hello everyone
and it kind of warms my heart to be able to sit down here and
be able having the opportunity the honor to be able to teach this
so thank you so earlier this week a lot of the
emphasis has been
staying close to what is directly visible Here and Now
that which is immediate the extended moment the leisurely moment the
ability to really stay here to see what's happening in a deeper way
and um
and responding to a kind of a call come
come look into this ability to be calm and settled
and extend that comes with this extended present moment this time you have time
for the present give yourself time for it
there's also a call to I see it to be here and what is the call to see
and the call to see what we're asked to see what's available to us that's not
available when the mind is stressed and jumping around a lot or preoccupied with things
it's uh it sees a path to what is wholesome path to what is
freeing a path to um peace and happiness
that it's difficult to see if the mind is preoccupied and caught when the mind is preoccupied caught
stressed that itself more likely is going to help
produce more agitation more anger fear
greed being caught in desires and aversions
but when we take time to for this present moment take time for
time then we have a chance to see something
that is maybe hidden from the preoccupied mind
and we can see the difference between where what the Mind does
that has an ouch in it and what the Mind does that has an ah in
it we can see where the mine gets involved in stress
in in suffering and and where the mind can be involved in
letting go and being peaceful where the mind can kind of follow
uh you know in that which kind of says Ah this is good this is good
and as that path to ah this is good it opens up
then things that are good things that are ah that involve stress that involve
agitation or a lot of energy that part of it is seen oh we don't need
to do that let's go to the Ah that's more peaceful and more settled
so this is the advantage of sitting quietly and being kind of open to the
present and taking their time with it that something shows up something
appears come come see to hear to see the difference between Ah that's
an ouch and that's an ah we don't have to analyze it figure it
out to understand why it's there but to in meditation to
in that peacefulness and then not doing so much in the mind to allow yourself to kind of
go in the direction of the ah where it's peaceful and quiet and settled
a lot of wonderful things open up there an analogy for this meditation a little
bit would be that there's something that you're searching for that is really
fantastic for you maybe it's a a loved one or a long lost friend or maybe it's
a wonderful treasure that you know about and you're told that you have to follow
the clues in the jungle to find it or clues in the
city Wherever You Are and the clues are something that's you have to it's not so difficult to see
if you're quiet and peaceful if you're kind of attentive and not preoccupied
and so you stay attentive You're motivated wow yes I'll follow this Trail
that's onward leading to this wonderful thing
so as we sit today maybe this can be the orientation is to
give yourself time for time so that your your heart your mind can be
sensitive to what you're doing in the mind and the heart that's either a ouch
or an ah and lean in the direction of ah trust
the ah have confidence that that you don't have to be involved you don't have to be committed to or
entangled with the ouch be committed to the ah
the Simplicity of it the opening to it
so assuming a meditation posture and gently closing your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
with the exhale relaxing with the exhale
making space for time
leisurely time to breathe in
to breathe out
letting your breathing return to normal
and no matter how you're breathing
maybe you couldn't your attitude your feeling about your breathing
can switch from somehow an ouch to an arm
whatever way you're breathing is okay is their way of holding it being with it
with a mind that's has an ah attitude about okay this is
how it is
on the exhale relaxing in your body
and then settling into your body breathing
maybe with a feeling in the mind the whole body that
you have a lot of time infinite time just to be here with your
experience Here and Now
and as you exhale to calm the mind
for these minutes here meditating there's many things you don't have to be
involved in it's a good time an ah time
to trust the quieter mind
that's not in a hurry
not trying to engineer something in meditation just here
and if you find yourself with thoughts and high feelings
attitudes emotions which have an ouch to them
it's okay but in the quiet of the meditation
can you feel and sense that there's a way to tap into the ah
and up head wholesome attitude
an easier way of being
not being entangled
and then as you sit here being with your breath
be sensitive to the path of all
just ah here now breathing
be quiet enough to feel the direction of awe
and if there's an ouch which remains
see if you can shift a way of being
that the way you your attitude of ouch is closer to ah something good
so you're not limited by the ouch
but you move towards the unlimited ah it's part of the unlimited now
foreign
and then to end this sitting you consider how when we're stressed and
harried deeply troubled and caught up in things
how there might not be much room
to feel and sense and take in the humanity of others
to really sense their fullness and who they are and
that's maybe deeper than what they say and what they do sometimes
and to reflect on how it's like to meet with people
when we have time and availability our hearts available
we have plenty of time to sense to feel to see
others maybe the time when we feel safe and comfortable
and nothing needs to happen except being together accompanying someone
and probably the latter there's more opportunities for ah
more opportunities to feel and sense
how you can
move towards kindness and compassion generosity
care so at the end of meditation session
chances are more often than not that here in a state of
way of being they can access a greater degree of
healthy sensitivity healthy attitude towards others
and to give voice to that to take a few moments to
give time for that what comes out of that
as a way of also supporting and reinforcing a positive way of being in the world
so to end with dedication of the benefits
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may each of us have the wisdom
and the presence
to support this possibility
foreign [Music]
[Music] thank you
so my friends we continue now on the
five characteristics of the Dharma and this uh
little statement is often chanted it's part of the probably daily Liturgy of
terravan monastics
the Dharma is well spoken by the Buddha
it is visible here it is immediate now
it invites us to see
it's onward leading to be experienced
personally by the wise so the today the topic is onward leading
this is a beautiful and wonderful quality of the Dharma quality of this practice we do
that it is onward leading it leads to what's really good it leads to Freedom
it leads to peace to a kind of dharmic happiness and um and how it leads there is also
quite fascinating because um uh we certainly have our role
in the practice and going the path to practice but there also there's a way in which we
end up kind of doing this practice in the current that carries us
in the direction of these uh what's good and healthy that there's something that we discover
that is leads us to Greater peace and happiness
and so it's in this way the dharma's onward leading
um carries us on and how does this work what is this
and um and some of it is has to do with this
ouch and the ah that I talked about in The Meditation today and that is that it's simplistic to just
Orient ourselves to feel and sense things from the point of view of an ouch and an ah but the benefit of it is it's
so simple the outers don't have to be understood in all their complicated ways just to
take it you know whether it's a you know some irritation and having an
you know I don't know it's a meditation cushion is too hard to having
some major world of difficulty happen for us we just see ouch
and those stories no complicated things no trying to understand why
and the same thing for the ah um we can get sensitive to what feels good and feels right
and move in that direction without making it complicated for us without
appropriating it for self For Me Myself and mine identity not making it a big
project the engineering project understanding why we're doing it and and um and questioning what is this all a
for or am I doing the right thing there's a way of making it so simple
that comes from a sensitivity and ability to be really here and present
so this is not thinking about things it's more closer to feeling things or sensing or or experiencing the ouch and
the Ah that's the other advantage of this these words is they're more experiential than they are
Concepts and ideas so as we're able to kind of stay here in
our direct experience as we're able to stay in the direct experience now in this extended now
and maybe even Timeless now really stay here time for time just relax and not
rushing and being ahead of ourselves here and we we respond to the call to to see
more carefully what is here what is this experience what's going on here
and to see as simple just oh that's ouch and that's ah
if I'm breathing in a way that feels a little bit shallow and deep it may be a
little uncomfortable then I might have a thought that um wow
you know I ate too much breakfast and I'm always eating too much breakfast and and I'm a lousy breakfast eater and now
I can't be a good meditator all those sentences all those attitudes have an
ouch to them if you're really quiet if you're not if you're in the thoughts if you become the thoughts then they kind
of Drive the show and we'd almost don't even see the ouch in them but if we're
quiet and peaceful and calm enough we go that's an ouch there's another ouch I do a lot of
ouches these are the second arrows that we talk about in Buddhism how we pile we might
have something uncomfortable some suffering and then we add suffering on top of it and on top of it there'll be
layers and layers of self-criticism or blame on the world or anger or despair
or all kinds of extra things and and so this Simplicity is oh that's
an ouch and have time for that oh not in a hurry
not pushing it away not judging it just Oh that's oh look at that that's
certainly an ouch and because of that time lots of time we have to be here then we
can also feel and sense there's a direction there's something that opens up in the direction of an ah there's a
way of being that's onward leading there's a way of of there's another way in fact the simple fact that I'm giving
time and and space to feel the ouch that is an awe that is good
the ability to step back and see it to be curious and not entangled in it
but to see it from a place of some modicum of calm that's enough
trust that use that as a guide that is onward
leading stay close to the ah the uncomplicated r
if there's an ah that do we stand appropriate for ourselves and say oh that's really good I should really kind
of luxuriate and really kind of indulge in it or relish it or this is my chance and
and um if you really if you do in fact give yourself time to feel what's going on to really see it you'll see the
stress in those attitudes you'll see the ouch in it the onward leading way is the way in
which mindfulness is self-correcting or corrects us mindfulness gives us information
for what is ouch and what is on and as the practice deepens we get calmer and with the ah opens up to more
time or space more present and moment attention more sensitivity
um uh it works beautifully to help us not get caught in the ouches and to move
towards a more and more valuable ah a more valuable way of kind of
moving towards greater peace or greater freedom the word for onward leading in poly is
in that phrase it's uh
copernico and and the the upper is a prefix that could
mean upward so and then on
is to lead and so oppa can be upwards leading upwards which is kind of a
metaphor for moving towards freedom it could also the upper also has a
prefix meaning of near leading close to getting extensive this leads closer to
Freedom this lays closer to peace this leads closer to what really feels right
here full present and and sometimes we follow that path
towards you know what's onward leading upward leading brings us closer
and sometimes what you can feel is that we're being brought there that the Dharma is leading us the Dharma
is guiding us we're in the current that flows in that direction and a lot of what the practice becomes
is just continuing to open and let go of anything that gets in the way of that
process it's letting go of all the ouches all the
self-centered efforts we might do and and uh and part of so part of the
practice is to know when to let go when to trust that process and that takes this very deep
sensitivity of it comes from being present in a Timeless way almost to really feel and
sense what's here so we can sense and feel when we have to when it's best for us and most healthy
for us most ah for us to come back to apply ourselves to let
go of something and be more actively involved because the alternative is worse
and when the best alternative is not to do so much just let go let go let go
and then they're not letting go feel like being carried and moved along
so it's one of the great uh kind of aspects of the Dharma is that the Dharma
is not external to us it's found inside of us and it's found inside of us in this
onward-leading way in which our psychophysical system moves towards Freedom given a chance
that has a capacity to move towards the greater ah the greater ease the less
stress to um to the absence of stress the absence of strain the absence of
inner oppression that we can often live under
so um so
try today to go through parts of the day or the whole day
see how simple you can make this and this understanding this observation
of suffering in your life and happiness in your life make it so simple there's an
ouch and there's an ah and see if in that Simplicity whether there's a little more freedom around the
ouches and a reminder to kind of take say calm
and mindful and a greater awareness of the ah the possibility
that you don't have to sacrifice that maybe you don't want to ignore that you
want to make space for this ah because it's onward leading it creates a good environment it's also creates a
more onward leading healthy direction for our social relationships
and uh and that's part of the value of this Dharma it it also supports our
communities our relationships to move in healthy direction so try today's keep it simple
and if you can have enough time to really feel that maybe you can feel the onward leading nature the door that
opens up from the ah that can take you in further in the direction of ah
so enjoy and uh and um
and I look forward to giving the last talk on this series tomorrow thank you