I haven't tested this voice yet tonight there we go thank you
hello hello the voice is working good
welcome to Monday night looks like my glasses I'm not going to be able to see anybody either
so what I would like to talk to you about tonight
begins with beware the conditioned mind
beware the condition to bind I've been talking to a number of people
lately that have have a similar issue with life which is I keep
practicing and I keep working and I'm so disappointed in the outcome
why isn't it better how come I'm not more equanimous I just want to be peaceful
I keep doing the right things how do I make any difference
I try to be kind to people and then they're not happy
and in general what's happening is that people are becoming
discouraged because things don't match their idea of
what it should be like you know if I do we make these unconscious contracts all the time if I
do this then this will be the outcome if I do diligently practice this would be true
if I consistently meditate I'm going to be a great meditator if I do all my practices well then
I'm going to be a Quantum Miss and by the way equanimous means peaceful and easy and happy
but it turns out Equanimity isn't about being happy
Equanimity is about balance in the face of things just as they are
Equanimity is about looking at ourselves and seeing ourselves just as we are not
how we would like to be Equity Equanimity means that we're not
measuring ourselves to see if we're improving if we're closer to that person that we
think we ought to be
the end of suffering does not lie in the future it only lies now
it lies in this moment in this experience there is a a Triad a famous Triad that
is repeated often in the sutas and it has to do with
um disenchantment
dispassion cessation of suffering and after that come those things like
peace and knowledge and nabana
but it really begins with this realization that what we have is a conditioned mind
what we think about things is conditioning our experience and is it self-conditioned by that
experience and if we can't see this if we don't see when it's happening
we are condemning ourselves to constantly repeating all of the Habit patterns we've always had
so the problem with talking about this is it's at this great intersection point it intersects with the Aggregates and
with the four noble truths and with mindfulness it everything kind of comes
together in this experience that determines whether we suffer or do
not suffer all of our intentions
all of our practices and somehow we think that if we do all of this that eventually we're going to
get to the place where we are free of greed hatred and delusion and I say may it be true
but I want to know how do I stop suffering right now
now when I become a better person not when I become a better meditator
but right now how do I end this suffering In This Moment
so I was inspired by something that came in the email there was a quote
from Joan Halifax on the subject of Hope
and she talked about the existence of wise hope that ordinary hope is is sort of
attached to some expectation that we would like to realize in our lives and I
hope this will be true we have this this great longing for something to be true
and if it doesn't become true then we are disappointed and we consider it a misfortune
or we condemn ourselves or we blame somebody for why this has not happened
and her point was that the difference between ordinary hope
that has to do with a dashing of expectations and disappointments that we might feel
that wise hope is not seeing things unrealistically but rather seeing things
just as they are including the truth of suffering
both its existence and our capacity to transform it
both its existence and our capacity to transform it it's when we realize we don't know what
will actually happen that this kind of Hope comes alive in
the spaciousness of uncertainty is the very space we need to act
in the spaciousness of uncertainty so if I am convinced that I am this kind
of person and that I will always react this way then I'm going to never give myself the chance to be anyway other
than I am or that you're that kind of person or that you approach the world this way all
of these beliefs I have these opinions I have about experience about life about
myself all of those things that we know
are not based upon the knowing of experience
but they are views that we hold
and they leave no room at all for the spaciousness of uncertainty
and impermanence
they leave no space at all for what's actually happening
what's actually happening so the other day I was um we have these these bowls in our our
house they're they're little Bulls they're they're not Pyrex but they're something like Pyrex you know you can
you can put them in the freezer you can put them in the microwave you can put them in the dishwasher and they they're
they're just a really handy size I always have them at hand for chopping
vegetables and putting things in or putting a few berries in or putting olives on the tables these little bowls
and we have a stack of them up on the Shelf I can just reach for them they're always there
and the other day I went to reach for one to put some berries in
and suddenly the whole stack Came Crashing Down out of the cabinet and hit the stone of the cabinet and shattered
into I don't know how many pieces it spread all over the kitchen
the first crash that came down uh was was quite startling and I
screamed having experienced myself screaming which was actually wonderful because
it caused me to think why am I screaming there must be something wrong with my body and it took me right into my body
and out of my head so it took the head a while to get to the point where it was whose fault is
this why did it happen you know all of those other kinds of things about why it shouldn't have happened
and I I said oh it's just glass I'm okay
nothing's hit me how interesting that I screamed
and in the midst of what might have been oh how am I going to clean all this up you know I don't have time to clean this
up I have something happening in a few minutes and there's glass all over and I don't have any shoes on and all of those
thoughts that came after that about how to deal with what was there
no problem I was calm as can be
because I was already in my body I had come back into the body to say oh it's
just glass and then it was just glass you just clean it up
and when the thoughts would come all those other thoughts came coming into the mind it was I didn't have any
opinion about them they were neither good nor bad nobody was good or bad
I could tell you a story about why it happened that would establish fault and blame
but really it doesn't matter it was just glass
the drama of the moment fortunately took me into my body most
times the drama of the moment takes you into trying to figure out what to do about something how to think about it we
have opinions about everything this is good this is bad this is better
this is worse I'm better this is better that shouldn't have happened that's your
fault oh this always happens this never happens
it is the ability to come back into the body out of the head
to say what am I actually feeling what do I feel
so that we don't get caught up in the stories about all the things we know already
that ignore what's actually happening the practice of getting into what's actually happening is the practice of
coming back into the body to say what's happening here what's going on with me every thought we have has some kind of
emotional content attached to it oh how did that happen blame blame blame
something blame I can hear the blame in that voice it wasn't curiosity about how it happened it was it shouldn't have
happened and to hear your voice speak the difference between
blame and curiosity is useful information about what
actually is happening what's what is truly happening
so I can hear Blame in my head I can hear Blame in the thought
and say oh blaming blaming is here but I don't have to continue blaming
I don't have to explain it to myself I can just say oh blaming is here
I don't have to become all of those thoughts
I don't have to become the person who always has to clean up
I don't have to become that if I Can See Clearly oh that's here oh
that's happening or maybe what I see is instead of feeling calm I feel shaken
mostly by my scream and I'm conscious of the shakiness
and so then I'm careful not to let the thoughts run away with me because I'm shaky I can feel the shakiness I
don't have to name it something that has a whole story attached to it
I could just say it was shaky
the conversation going on in our heads usually has the flavor of I know what
this is or I'm afraid because I don't know what this is
because we don't like to say oh I'm afraid
it's easier to say I'm at fault or I have a problem or this shouldn't be
happening than to say I don't know what's going on because that feels like it's out of our
control that feels not right that feels not familiar
it's easier to blame ourselves than to be in the space of unfamiliar
if you think about how you go through your day
you will notice that sometimes you have a very optimistic attitude toward what's
going to happen and other times you have a very defeated feeling about what's going to happen
so this afternoon I had planned I know I had planned his I
had a doctor's appointment this morning in several errands to run and I said okay this
chunk of time this afternoon I'm going to spend working on my talk and I know kind of what I'm going to talk about here's the well it didn't
happen this happened that happened something else happened and what I noticed was the mind was
running to there was a question that my husband and I had talked about should we get this carpet cleaner
and there was a cyber monday sale and I hadn't decided what kind of carpet
cleaner we should get and here I was busily thinking about carpet cleaners when I said
this is being driven by Cyber Monday and I want to get a deal
and it and I said really really do I have to buy a carpet cleaner
today because it's Cyber Monday yesterday I wasn't thinking about buying
the carpet cleaner no no I don't have to think about this
and I went to my husband and said if you want to think about carpet cleaners feel free but I'm going to go do something
else now and and to watch the difference between how much tension there was around the
fact that it was Cyber Monday and these silly carpet cleaners and how much Freer I was to consider
what I was going to talk about tonight when I gave up the idea of buying a carpet cleaner
just to feel the difference in my body about how much space there was around me
when I let go of the need to get a deal which you know I could label it
something like greed or uh procrastination I mean I have all kinds
of stories I could tell you about why that was happening
but the important part was being able to see clearly that I was trapped
unnecessarily by something some idea I had about what needed to happen today in
this space and I was so grateful to be able to feel
that release of that the tension that was there
that had nothing to do with what I was going to talk about tonight it just had to do with
some imperative that I had imagined they had no basis in reality
that I was triggered I was triggered and to notice where are triggers show up
is not to say I'm always triggered by that or I am somebody who is triggered
by that but rather oh that's something I need to be familiar
with that trigger so that I can see the trigger I can be triggered and say fine
but I don't have to go there to see that we are independent of what
we see clearly we still have the ability to make a decision about it we don't
have to just fall into it just because it's a mind habit
when we become familiar with the Mind habit we become
disenchanted we no longer have to be drawn into the
Enchantment of that point of view of that way of being of that need to be
when we see it clearly there is the possibility of dispassion
we lose the energy of the drive
and we can just see it to not have an opinion about it
releases us from being drawn into it
yesterday maybe the day before things are running together for me a bit right now
my uh my grandson was playing in a soccer tournament
and there was there were several teams and mostly kids had been pulled from
different teams for this turkey tournament and so he was playing with people he was
not familiar with and the coach wanted him to play goalie
and it is his belief that he's a terrible goalie and a great defender
so he didn't want to be goalie and he stood there with his hands on his
hips not wanting to be goalie and sure enough somebody kicked a really
hard ball right at him and one of the Rules of This indoor soccer game was that you couldn't touch it with your
hands or the other team got a point and so this ball came right at his face
and just put his hands up to block it which any sane person would have done I
think I can tell you all the things you might have done instead but that's what I
would have done and of course the other team got a point well this just confirmed for him
that he's not a goalie and the rest of the game he was just furious so they lost they they actually
were the only undefeated game going into the finals and the final game they were beaten by a team they had beat earlier
in the day and he was goalie and he was convinced it was all his fault that they were in second place
and he was crushed and I watched this blooming and blossoming and and falling
into and he went running out into the dark and hid behind a rock it
was all my fault it wasn't that he didn't that he was unhappy about being in second place it's
that it was all his fault and I thought about how often we do that
when Misfortune happens when something happens that we don't like it's all my fault
what if it's not your fault what if it's just happened
but if it's really not your fault
you know somebody was telling me that she was in a conflict with someone
and she tried to several ways of working it out I you know I'm doing this and I'm
writing letters and I'm you know and nothing was working I'm just a failure
and I said you know you might consider that it's not your fault and it's not her fault
but that you're seeing things from a different point of view each of you has a different point of view
there doesn't have to be Fault In conflict
you don't have to be a flaming idiot because you don't agree with me you just don't agree with me
is that possible
you know the the tendency we have to know the right answer
limits the possibilities and leaves us in a place where we're
constantly struggling and we're tied up in the struggle I'm working on this big project with my
homeowners association and it's a speculative project and somebody managed to get themselves
put in my team who uh is opposed to the project doesn't want it to happen under any
conditions and so this other person is constantly trying is constantly undermining me you
know while she's doing this she's doing that she's not doing this and so I talked to her and said you know
I haven't even made a proposal that you know you're fighting against a proposal I haven't made I don't have the data yet
that didn't matter she was Furious and I thought about it and I said okay I
don't need this and one possibility is you remove yourself from the conflict right you
just walk away from it I don't need this I've got mine by the way
anyway I'm just doing this for other people all these virtuous thoughts and
I thought well you know mostly I'm feeling hurt that I'm being attacked
oh well that's interesting why is it hurting
well because oh and the the more I
dug into what was I actually feeling
I said well maybe I'll wait until the morning to decide whether I'm going to walk away from this and in the morning I
just got up and started again because part of what was happening was I
was just plain tired oh
when I gave up being sure I knew I was being unfairly attacked
then I could just get up the next morning and start again
we don't actually have to respond to everything that the mind tells us we
need to respond to we can just notice it's there
and we can give ourselves the space to maybe not know the answer
to maybe not be clear about what's happening it's okay to say you know I'm confused
at this point one of the things that happened this
morning was that that it was an annual Wellness visit that I did with my doctor and that I'm of an age that they do all
the age-related testing for you and so they were doing the the mental tests
and curiously enough my husband and I were talking about these tests yesterday and he told me about this drawing of the
clock and it you know it and uh how you you put the numbers on the face of the clock and then they tell you to find to
draw 11 uh 10 minutes after 11 and this is a measure of your mental acuity and
and oh and then the three words and then they come back later and ask you what the three words are well so she's
starting as soon as she told me about the clock I thought you know this isn't fair because I I worked this out in my head yesterday I know exactly how to
draw that clock [Applause] and here I am going through all of these
arguments about how this should I tell her is it honest not to tell her that I said wait a minute this is about what
do you remember and if I'm remembering yesterday then clearly I'm doing pretty well at remembering what's the problem here
but there was this sense that I was cheating because I knew about the test
and I could feel that oh I'm cheating I could feel the shame
and I could laugh about it but it didn't make it didn't change the
fact that it had the thought had been there and if my attitude had been a certain way I might have
devolved into a long story about how what a cheater I am
what it takes is a little bit of space in the habit of noticing what it feels
like with the what the trigger feels like in your body with the the thought
patterns that you typically have how they feel what's the energetics of that
what are the energetics I'm bringing to this moment
one day last week I had this really horrible dream fortunately I can't remember at this
point but I woke up just oh I know it was something about divorce so I was
being divorced you know my husband and I are happily married thank you very much and here I
was having this dream about divorce and he wasn't the person I was divorcing either which you know just added to the
confusion and I realized that something was going on in my life that what that I felt
rejected you know there was there was a feeling of rejection and I could feel that rejection
so from a psychological point of view it was useful to try to figure out why I was feeling rejected
but from a mindfulness point of view from an end of suffering point of view what was important was to realize that I
had a feeling of rejection and so I should be careful when I interact with my husband if he doesn't
say hello to me I should not feel rejected because he doesn't say hello just because I'm carrying that attitude
with me I should know that that's there
so that I don't add that knowing onto an experience and label it something it's
not so that I'm not Enchanted by what I know
so that I can't see clearly what's actually happening
because when you see oh this is what's happening oh there's resentment here
when you see oh resentment is here it breaks the energetics of that
resentment you can stop telling yourself the story about well of course I resent this
because this always happens
of course you're always going to take advantage of me and to notice how often
the familiarity of being the last one in the kitchen cleaning up feels good
and it's only the knowing that you're taking advantage of me that's causing the suffering
when in fact I like just making sure it's all clean
at the end of the day how how we formed the mental ideas about
of our experience is mostly about habit and inclination
and the inclination changes all the time
so if we become familiar with what things feel like in our body
then we have the information that allows us not to get trapped and Enchanted
by something that reminds us of something else
and in the dispassion of not having an opinion about it oh anger is here I
hmm I don't have to justify it I don't have to tell myself why it is I don't have to
reinforce it and I'm free to just let it
be unentangled not part of who I am not part of who I need to be
there's so there's a poem here I want to read you see if I can find it
not following my text very well here we go so this is a new poem by Jane
hirschfield called uh two kerosene lanterns
the cat the cat walks the narrow shelf beneath the
window where many delicate things are arranged polished
ammonites a dried starfish three turtle netsuke
a few curls of birch bark too long unused kerosene lanterns
as if on their own two hands fly up to cover the person's face to cover the eyes already closed the crash as it must
arrives the hands lower slowly the cat sits on the floor in the room's
middle calmly licking one paw the law of cats is simple
one Arrangement becomes another people are strange
the law of cats is simple one Arrangement becomes another
people are strange it's our expectation that something's
going to happen that leads to the disappointment
but when we truly grasp the idea and the feeling and the
experience that things arise and pass away
we're much less likely to be subject to knowing the outcome
knowing it's always going to be this way it's hopeless to even get to try this
because it's always going to be this way and we have the energy to start up again
and again and again and again and again and again
and we become people who experience equanimity
as being the the condition in the moment of just seeing oh it's that way
oh this is what's happening oh things were a little chaotic at the
moment the glass is all over the kitchen yep the glass is all over the kitchen
I can have an opinion about that but it doesn't change the fact that the glasses all over the kitchen
and I'll probably clean it up
yep that's what happens that's exactly what happens
and there's no suffering in that it's just glass it's just two kerosene lanterns it's
just one Arrangement leading to another arrangement
when I say it that way it sounds sort of pollyannaish you know just wait and it'll all be better
but in fact it is still broken glass all over the kitchen it's not pleasant and it's not wonderful
it's not beautiful and I have to replace the Bulls or do without them
but I don't have an opinion about them that leads to suffering for me
I don't have the need to explain it away my clumsiness you're putting something
where it doesn't belong it just is and the sense of it just is
the place where we can free ourselves of the enchantment that leads to
suffering it just is
and the next moment I have my intention and my next step
my intention and my next step
it frees me from having to be better than I am while having an intention
that is consistent with how I want to be in the world not who I want to be in the
world
tashania calls mindfulness practice not a self-improvement project but a
self-unraveling project I kind of like that way of thinking about it a self-unraveling
where it's a process as we see more and more clearly what's actually happening we become
disentangled from all of the conditions that we that impose on our lives
and in that disentangling we can just see it oh
all of us do things that we're not proud of
or there's an outcome we're not proud of
well I I the other day I made a pie actually it wasn't a pie it was something else I deliberately don't want
to call it a pie because it didn't look like a pie in the end
and it was a recipe I'd never tried before and I you know here's his thing and I looked at it and I thought God
that looks awful but you know it tasted really good if you didn't call it a pie
it was pretty good but calling it a pie put it in a
category where there was an expectation about what it should look like you know it was awfully dark for a pie
but it was really good you had to just uh look at it
with the idea that it was a pie so my husband who wanted a pie went
around telling everybody about how I had made this pie and I kept saying oh it's not actually a pie
who knows with the people who were eating it were thinking but how you felt about it had something to
do with what you named it what category things that it went in
you know so we we think we think that uh
the way to peace that in a peaceful State we're going to be relaxed and at ease that at ease is
is you know you can imagine yourself settling into it
and everything is sweet you know every piece is about sweetness
right not really not really I ran across something
a description this afternoon I see if I can find the right tag here
yeah so this was this was something written by uh ajan mahabuwa
he was talking about his uh meditation and how sweet it was
and he said the radiance this Radiance of meditation is the ultimate counterfeit
at that moment it's the most conspicuous point you hardly want to touch it at all
because you love it and cherish it more than anything else in the entire body there is nothing more
outstanding than this Radiance which is why you're amazed at it love it cherish
it dawdle over it want nothing to touch it but it's the enemy King unawareness
once when I went to practice at watto damachetti the problem of unawareness
parentheses ignorance had me bewildered for quite some time
at that stage the mind was so radiant that I came to Marvel at its radiance
everything of every sort which could make me Marvel seem to have gathered there in the mind to the point where I
began to Marvel at myself why is it that my mind is so marvelous
looking at the body I couldn't see it at all it was all space empty
the mind was radiant in full force but luckily as soon as I began to Marvel
at myself to the point of exclaiming deludedly in the heart without being conscious of it
why has my mind come so far at that moment a statement of dhamma
spontaneously arose this too I hadn't anticipated
it suddenly appeared as if someone were speaking in the heart although there was no one there speaking
it simply appeared as a statement if there is a point or a center of the
knower anywhere that is the agent of rebirth
that's what it said as long as there is identification with
anything any sense of nowhere we are still Bound
by the conventional conditioned mind beware
of ecstatic States and lovely meditations that convince you everything
is wonderful it is at that moment that you are re-entering the cycle of
samsara because you have identified with that
experience it's in the identification with the experience that the suffering arises
the ability to just see the condition ah now we're in a different space
it is not me it is not the knower it is the being
is the being that gives rise to the space where anything is possible
where we truly Embrace impermanence and the arising and passing away
of what's there
it's not in the giant understanding that we find the freedom of nabana it is in
the small it is in the everyday small
oh this is what's happening may you all see clearly
may you know the end of enchantment
the freedom that comes with disenchantment with dispassion
with things just as they are those are my thoughts thank you
sorry I went a little too close to the edge here anybody has any comments I'd be happy to hear the questions
no great so
to the spontaneity of noticing the arising as well as the
passing away I wish you all a good night