so good morning good day and here for our meditation
and one of the [Music] remarkable tools that we have for
meditation and for living a wise life is our physical body
this body of ours is a finely tuned instrument of perception it's as if it's an antenna
that picks up so much sense data from the environment from within side of ourselves
and even if our we doing i don't have uh
all our senses operating properly as i get older my eyes are not seeing as
well my ear ears are on here as well and um
still it's a phenomenal apparatus that we have
and if we barrel ahead in our thoughts and activities it's all too easy to not be attuned
tuned into this wonderful instrument this wonderful
antenna this wonderful source i would say even of wisdom
because there's so much understanding that can come but what i'd like to emphasize for today
is that the body that is
uh if we have um uh
when we have mindfulness of the body when we're aware of our body
the body tends to move towards equilibrium to have homeostasis
the body will will find its way to the midpoint balance point between
stress and excessive relaxation or or slumping or
and it'll find its balance between
pulling back and moving forward find its balance in so many different ways
and one of the ways it does it for people who are tense is it you can feel the body wants to
move towards relaxation to releasing the tension and
it's one thing to feel the tensions of our body the holding we do it's another thing to feel
the momentum the call the the the almost like the desire the the tension
has to relax to release to feel the momentum towards relaxing
in the opposite end of the spectrum if we're too slumped or too kind of collapsed
if we really feel that and tune into that we'll feel the body's movement and
this almost like desire to uh be aligned to be upright to have its energy moving through the body
in a uh in a good way in an energy energized way alert way
and it's possible to tune into the body and follow the body's kind of
kind of directions towards balance directions or tendency towards
equilibrium and it doesn't have to we don't have to do a lot of
it's not even not possible it's not even necessary to do so much of the work ourselves
but rather our job is to tune into what the body is going on in the body and the body will find its way or tell us
clearly what needs to happen so to begin
what is the posture that your body wants to take right now
putting aside ideas you have of what a good meditation posture is
if you feel your body from the inside out what would be nice for your body right
now and whatever it might be
it will be probably temporary sooner or later
there'll be a time to be a different way
and if we live in the policies in our minds about how we should be we won't listen or hear or feel
what the body is about
gently close the eyes
and often on these morning 7 a.m sits
i discussed beginning with a conscious effort to relax different parts of the body
sometimes with deep breaths but for this morning
don't do that rather let the body do it as it sees fit
take a few moments now little time to scan through your body
and check in with it are there tensions anywhere in the
body are there places of holding tightness
resistance
and not to do anything about it right now but rather
let it be there but feel it well sense it
until perhaps you feel that within the tension itself
there's a desire to relax
then relax but not before
or then allow that part of your body to release
there might be in the body a global embracing ourselves against life
by tightening up in fear of
some unknown future life itself
and feel that if make space for it give time to get to feel that bracing
holding back
just because your mind doesn't like it
don't start with the mind directing the show
feel the body
or maybe there's some contraction or pressure in your body of wanting doing
the eagerness of leaning forward a restlessness
make lots of room to feel and sense how that's experienced in the body
there may be physical tension associated with thinking
[Music] pressure constriction
take your time to feel that until you feel that within that
constriction
there is a request to relax
and now become aware of your breathing be aware of your body breathing
and without any effort to do anything different
notice if there's any tension or resistance holding in the breathing pattern
let yourself be okay with that your job is simply to know and feel
any tightening or holding associated with breathing
and then for the rest of the sitting continue in a relaxed way with your
breathing or with tuning into your body
and if you wonder often thought take that as a
instruction as a reminder to come back to feel
your body settle into your body's experience of
itself as if you can trust the body will find
its way if
you have a clear non-reactive awareness
awareness without an agenda just aware
listening sensing feeling breathing the breathing body
body breathing the body itself
whatever you might thinking now might be thinking now
consider that for now that your body is more important
the experience of your body
is where the meditation will unfold
and after these minutes of sitting quietly
has anything shifted and changed in your body
how does your body feel now
and might there be some movement in your body
to be sit be more upright to open up more
be straighter
the healthy opposite of relaxing
what is the call within the body more relaxation or more
a brightness
and coming to the end of this sitting
sometimes we come to a place through meditation
that we're not living from our mind as much as we are
from our body and not so much from our body but from
the body sensitivity and antennas and the body's resonance
with the world around us
where things like kindness friendliness love
seems to well up from the body independent of
the policies and beliefs and ideas of the mind
and as we sit here in the last minutes
is there any even slight
place of kindness tenderness love or good will
that you can find in your body
maybe for yourself
maybe for the people in your life
maybe the kind of good will you might have
for even people you don't know
and if there is such a such care or love compassion that
arises from your body from your torso your heart
or even if you just wish it did that wishing that that was the case
is very significant and from this place nor this wish
give words to that kindness by repeating
quietly to yourself may others be happy
may others be safe
may others be peaceful
may others be free
[Music]
so good morning good day good evening
and um so we're continuing with this discussion of anger
and as i said now that anger is a sign
and one way of saying a message and one way of understanding that is
that it's a sign that something is wrong somewhere or other something is wrong
and some wisdom is needed to not assume automatically that this
what's wrong is out in the world or to assume automatically that what's wrong is within oneself
but it's a sign that something is off that something needs attention
and it's one of the first things to do is to learn from it to find out what it is to stop and take a good look what's really
going on here and when we meditate especially this is a great place because we don't have to
then hopefully when meditating say anything to anyone or do anything in the world
you can just really be present and feel it and be so we want to learn from it
one of the things to learn is that [Music] how anger motivates us
and that's part of the danger of anger that sometimes anger comes with very strong motivation to do something to say
something just very forcefully to someone or to act forcefully or something
and and and when the motivation sometimes has
the upper hand and that's why for example for example expressions of anger are speaking angrily
people lose touch with themselves as they say it the motivation is so strong and so
powerful that they don't really know what's happening in their body and their hearts their minds they've lost
sometimes in extreme versions they're kind of possessed by anger and they don't have not really touched
into what's happening here and this losing touch with oneself when we're angry
is a great uh hindrance a great shortcoming
the wisdom the clarity the ability to be able to act wisely and
speak wisely in the world happens a lot from being grounded in one's body
to be present here and and that can happen even when we're
angry and that way we won't lose ourselves in the anger
and so training ourselves to kind of be in the body stay present so it helps to think of
of anger as being part of part of what anger is is if there's a motivation in it
and so ask yourself what is the motivation here what is the desire what's the wish that you see happen
and regardless of what the degree of anger might be it could be irritation it could be
um and no even annoying something relatively mild what is that
this becomes particularly important when anger annoyance irritation
is hostility has become it's a low-key and chronic
and so it has nothing to do with any particular incident that's happened but rather it has to do with it become a
way of living a way of kind of an attitude which we have and the whole assessment of chronic
anger hostility is very different than the analysis or
the consideration of incident specific anger where there's something happening
right in front of us and the chronic that goes on for a long time that's that is particularly
debilitating that tends to have a powerful force
to help people actually not be in touch with themselves that they might feel the opposite because the energy of anger is
so strong that they feel humming with it but actually there's there's such a big cost
we lose something the buddha gave this um a list of the
downsides of anger of being angry especially maybe chronic anger
that maybe he give it gave it to people to motivate them to
do something about their anger not to live this way and so
he said that the ill effects of anger include
looking ugly being in pain
making mistakes the loss of property
falls into disputes and disgrace
loss of friends and then a rebirth in hell
so um
the so i don't know if that motivated some of you like oh wow all those things can be there with anger chronic i think of
it as chronic anger this kind of persistent stream of it so um
so one of the ways to respect anger is think i believe is not to give into
it as a motivational force to say or do something but rather take the time to feel it and
to know it and to feel and know it in the body and the body
can process this the body knows how to unfold and relax and open up and reveal
and and sometimes when we take the time to sit down and feel
anger in the body it gets stronger there can be murderous rage that arises
but when you're sitting still maybe that's the end that's the whatever has happened is so powerful
that something has been is erupting inside of us and we it's and
if we're not acting on it or expressing it meditation is about letting that
eruption happen or meditation but letting
the whole thing dissipate and dissolve because sometimes what keeps it going is
the telling ourselves stories repeating ourselves the the injury that's been done or it's the repetition of certain
trains of thought which keeps the anger the annoyance the irritation going
and so to sit quietly and feel it in the body is an alternative to all those stories
and then the body then you can allow the body to do what it wants to do you know
the deeper process to do what it was to do and it might be an eruption
or it might be dissolving and it's not your job to choose which it
is but to really be attuned to see what needs to happen here and hopefully be quiet enough still
enough go for a walk long enough that you allow the whole process to
to maybe come to some completion in ordinary life especially with
incident specific anger and we have to kind of act on things it's very useful to learn how to diffuse
the anger how to be with the anger so that it doesn't automatically trigger motive
motivational actions we say or do things and here again
training ourselves so it's second nature to be mindful of the body so we feel
uh what's happening the body can be a source of stability to come back to the body and just sit and
be or stand feel you feel your feet on the ground the body can also be the means by which
we diffuse some of the energy of anger some of the intention and motivational force of
anger that interferes with our ability to really be attuned more deeply
what's happening attune to the deeper emotions that might really be the bigger issue that's happening
more attuned to the situation we're in and to take a better look at what's happening
more attuned to ourselves to if we're if the anger arises because of a story we're telling ourselves
to question the story is that the right perspective that we have
so to tune into the body and then to find ways to diffuse some of that energy of anger
by relaxing breathing breathing breathing breathing deeply and
relaxing breathing and relaxing on the exhale breathing and feeling the
expansion of the rib cage in the torso as a way of kind of grounding yourself
in the body and feeling something that's really primary the primary experience of
breathing notice your posture when you're angry maybe the posture
is one that does not doesn't lend itself to diffusion to settling if you're you know both both hands are
in a fist um it maybe it's not that difficult to relax the fist to relax the hand to open
it and doing that is part of the diffusion process
settling it quieting down and diffusion is not the same thing as repression
or denial or escaping from it diffusion is to
settle some of the some of the uh ways in which we're getting disconnected from ourselves
and to feel more deeply what's happening to be more present and to settle the tr the motivational
triggers that might come with with anger so that we're not speaking from the anger or
acting from the anger and and we can kind of feel and sense what's going on
and so finding out where you are each of us probably has our own
specialty of where in the body anger is most expressed it might be tension and tightness in the
belly it might be in the chest it might be in the face or the jaws it might be in the hands
sometimes the eyes i've seen angry people in their eyes are feel so tense
and fixed and locked in it might be somehow in the forehead and
there's places where we get headaches because of all the the tension associated with maybe irritation
and anger so wherever your way is your place get to know it so that when you go about
your life and it's an incident of anger you know to go to that place and maybe relax and settle
um the um learn skills of diffusion lose skill
learn skills of being grounded in the present so that
anger doesn't get the upper hand so that
you can learn from the anger rather than act on the anger
the expression of anger is not something we want we want to do
very often i once asked one of my buddhist teachers
um if it was ever appropriate to express anger and the teacher says
i said something i've got exactly that the date the time frame but the teacher said yes
once in a blue moon once at once in a great while like once every you know
five years or something um so i don't know if that guideline is the right one
but um it was fascinating to me this idea there might be a time but not that often
and so to have the ability to step back and the advantage of that
is that if anger involves something that needs to be addressed in our life
it's often addressed much more usefully motivated by other
emotions and feelings and ideas than the motivations that come from anger itself
so again it's not denying the incident was anger producing it's not denying the difficulty of the
anger but it's questioning the motivational value of anger
and that's where it's very rare that anger is useful as a motivational force
some people are quick to defend anger because a lot of good gets done in the world with anger that people are
motivated for justice and fight for it so maybe that's good but it's not so
healthy for the person who's angry and i feel a little sad when people
justify anger for that reason what i wish they would do instead is find an equal
or even stronger motivation from compassion
don't set up anger as don't justify anger if there are better
motivations to get the job done so diffusing anger so for this next day
you might if you find yourself irritated annoyed angry rageful
simmering resentful whatever you might feel
today see what you can do by tuning into your body
and like we did in the guided meditation tune into what's going on in the body really well
and see what the body wants to do see if the body wants to relax see if the body wants to be energized
if you if you do this during a walk as i've said before i i process strong
anger with walks does the does the body want to walk faster does it work slower
what what does the body want to do here to uh and um
and then also explore where can you relax what settles you into with the emotion
and um this is a personal skill that each person needs to learn for themselves so
how do you defuse anger so thank you