welcome back from lunch
and just maybe taking a minute to fill your bodies full not hungry hopefully I'm not too
full feel the impact of being with Sangha
socializing quietly or actually
notice how the heart and the body are stirred the mind is stirred
taking some deep breaths into whatever is happening for you right now
foreign
instructions on mindfulness of emotions and thinking a lot for one sitting
and to add to that before I'd like to talk a little bit about love
and about the feeling of being at home
I have a little quote from Anne Klein
says attention is the start of love there can be no love without attention
and cultivating attention or cultivating a possibility for intention
and possibility for connection and that's to ourselves as well as to
others to all
attention is the start of love there can be no love without attention
so have we been attending today
and then notice our relationship to how we've been attending
what we've been attending to has there been love there
[Music] has there been love and how we're
attending to our experience of breathing of itching of pain
of restlessness
of body
hopefully some maybe even a lot
it's very um different experience
to cultivate awareness that meets things with love
maybe so different it's hard to stay with sometimes
this is important because of this other word I want to talk about
home
what is it to be at home
what is it to be at home wherever you go
right here even is it possible to be at home in the body
to be at home with awareness
much more likely if there's love there
this idea of being at home maybe could also be described as
embodiment as presence
that feeling of being yourself or being with somebody who feels
right there right there
and often we think about home in the external world or homeless in the external world and
if we're at home in about in a structure
there's this belief
often truth but not always that okay the doors are shut I'm here
it's my space
if we're homeless without a structure
there's a feeling that anybody at any time can come along and shoe us off
what if we apply the idea to
our practice if we can be at home in our bodies with
awareness what is it that helps us
feel settled present
and what is it that makes us feel like we're being pushed out pushed away
very often it's our thinking or our emotions
what if it's possible to have emotions and thoughts
and stay at home to not get pushed out
of our presence not get pushed out of embodiment
to not abandon ourselves our awareness
what if it's possible to be with all of these things that are happening internally
without getting pushed out without losing
that sense of home of righteousness
of embodiment of presence
awakeness
sometimes hard to do that with emotions
sometimes hard to do that with thoughts actually
there's so many ways we're compulsive habitual reactive
so many ways the sound of a phone an itch
somebody's breathing anything at all
if we're reactive to it
so what we're doing here is simple but not
easy simple and that there's not a lot
complicated about it it's staying
being with
but that's not always easy
and sometimes we miss delightful experiences because we're so busy bopping around
getting caught up in a fantasy here and there
so we'll start the meditation working with emotions
and and transition to working with thinking
in the same way that we started the morning with an anchor and the breath of
course we'll start there too in this meditation pretty much always that's the starting
options when you're trying to focus on thoughts but we'll try and use our awareness our
choicefulness to be more tuned into an attentive to
certain parts of our experience so we can get to know them a little better
we can get to know the compulsions the habits the emotions and even the
thinking patterns better
so this idea of love loving attention
and if you don't like the word love maybe you like the word caring or kind
or allowing finding the word for you
that supports and inspires a way of relating to whatever comes up
that helps you stay present stay home
and one of the things that we'll do is focus on emotions
not the thinking about them but the experience of them
how they come alive manifest show up in the body
where you feel them what they feel like
emotions can get a bad rap
sometimes we try not to have emotions sometimes we try to just have really
good emotions but the thing is is there it's energy
that moves through us and we try and block negative difficult
emotions we end up blocking all emotions
so when Koto and I were teaching intro
Series in August he brought this beautiful metaphor to
working with emotions the idea of being like a river
thank you and being the river the water itself perhaps being the stream of feelings
emotions in this particular situation and the bed
the body being our awareness our capacity to
allow things to move through the way a riverbed allows the water to flow
we can be wide Broad and Deep River beds
everything and just keep moving through there's no problem
and other times it might feel like we want to contract close up build the dam
put water like emotion is pretty amazing it can find its way around
so maybe we become smaller reverse we try and just be as wide as we can and
let as much as we can come through
foreign to be into that bed the riverbed to feel
the water the emotion moving through us
so let's find our meditation postures or re-establish them
maybe breathing in deeply and with it feeling the spine and the shoulders lift
maybe rolling those shoulders back and open
and just noticing if there's anything needed for your posture to be supported
a pillow a shift
and taking some nice full intentional deep breaths right now
as we begin the formal practice of meditation with the body prepared
we bring it more oxygen with these deeper breaths which tells the body it's okay to relax
and feeds the brain and you can even possibly feel
the blood or the oxygen moving through your system
being aware of breath and body at the same time
coming home into this body In This Moment
feeling into it
sensing the experience of being here
and whatever your anchor
when you're ready picking it up in your practice
with devotion with care
letting it help you come even more fully
in a continuous way breath after breath
foreign
maybe bring your awareness into the heart into the chest
with your anchor just notice the emotional tone
or emotions present
maybe as you see them just to say hi and name them simply
hello hi there
I see you peeking over there
anything from boredom to Joy to grief
to anger to happiness welcome them all
part of the richness of living in a human body
his emotions
so we're beginning a practice called raft
the r is to recognize bull recognition
of emotion
no a in raft is to allow
to give space to the emotion
being that riverbed
and maybe choosing one emotion in particular to work with that doesn't
feel too difficult
something you know you can be with
thank you
and then to feel it that's the F of raft to feel it in your body
how it's living being expressed this is the sensation the language of
the body and feeling it is how we let the body
know it's heard
foreign
to seeing if it is changing in any way
moving
maybe simply noticing if it feels Pleasant unpleasant or neutral
working here with the direct experience not the story
but the manifestation the experience the sensation of the feeling
and when you feel you have felt the emotion
and if you feel ready to move to the next part of raft
you might imagine a great room
lots of space
there may be many chairs or a giant table in the center
and you could invite this emotion to have a seat
and if there were some thoughts that were connected to this emotion
maybe each thought memory story
judgment reaction can also have a seat
in their own spot in this way we're teasing apart the
experience of many things coming together around
the emotion
and maybe just getting a feel for how many characters how much history how
much story who's involved in this particular feeling
and maybe almost alone at the table you may be in a crowded room
but what happens when you give all of it its own space
bowing to each part
I think them untangle from each other
and as you're ready we'll shift into just mindfulness of
thinking practice you can allow this
collection of thoughts and emotions to reside where they are or
maybe they're moving through
maybe imagine that the thoughts are like leaves or boats on that River
awareness being the riverbed Waters being the energies and emotion
little boats or leaves can represent the thoughts
coming and going
and to keep it simple
you might want to just start by noticing the types of thinking
that is happening types of thinking can be visual
seeing images they can be auditory hearing
they can be literally words spelled out
it can be like a mini movie multimedia collage
just seeing them in this simple form
not all minds think in the same way you might not realize it but the person
beside you can be thinking entirely differently
so can you recognize the way you think how your thoughts appear and disappear
another simple way might be to notice and label Thoughts by categories of
planning or conversing
or rehearsing
or remembering maybe just simply thinking
it's also possible to just notice the volume or intensity of the thoughts
they may be coming rarely slowly
in groups clusters
what's the pacing what's the level of intensity
what's the speed
and sometimes we'll find a thought really sticking around
if that's happening maybe very useful to notice if there's
an emotion present with the thought
and then you can do the practice of raft silently in your own process if it's
helpful to recognize the emotion allow it to be there
feel it in your body and teasing apart the pieces
foreign
it might be possible for thinking to kind of go to the background
and for awareness being with your breath or Sensations
sound to be more primary
letting the flow of thinking move through
not needing to speed it up or slow it down change it
and just remembering that moment that we recognize we're caught in thinking we're
aware already aware
home and then love
Love Is Possible
can we just let thoughts be thoughts events in the mind
what a mind does the same way a sensation arises in the body
they come and they go
and not me not mine even
just the nature of the mind to make thoughts
foreign
right here at home
In This Moment aware
knowing thinking knowing sensing knowing hearing
knowing breathing maybe feel into the awareness that
recognizes this all
thank you
[Music] thank you
[Music]
taking your time [Music]
moving slowly to walking practice we'll be back at 2 45
for our next practice session thank you
so I have this idea
that IMC has a specialty
and that that specialty is simplicity
simple name Insight Meditation Center
simple situation here simple room
and the practice of a simple straightforward awareness
if I were pressed to come up with a one sentence
summary of The Practice it might be something like
clear awareness of present moment experience
with a ballot with a balanced mind
clear awareness of present moment experience with a balanced mind
and so the way I understand it is all of the instructions we've been giving this morning and
we'll go for the rest of the afternoon are all elaborations on that one simple
practice to be aware of what's here
I think if we started with just saying oh be aware of what's here there's so much we might miss
so we go bit by bit starting with the breathing
settling in with the breathing connecting to embodied experience
than including emotions including our thinking
to be at home right here
simple not always easy
so with this next step of instructions
keeping that simplicity nearby
the next step we will take is that to include all of our experience
everything that comes in our experience
rather than focusing on one area everything
including everything one thing at a time
so we call this practice open awareness
there's another very old metaphor to share after these hours of practicing it may
be a comfort to think of yourself in this metaphor as sitting sitting back
in an easy chair sitting back in an easy chair
in the middle of a simple one-room house
one room house one door four windows
and we're just sitting in our chair peacefully
the one room house was this old metaphor for our being
and each of the let's say each of the windows in the
door is one of our senses the eyes the ears the nose the tongue
the body and of course the mind
so here we are sitting in our easy chair
and in mindfulness practice and open awareness just letting whatever comes
arise and pass away so we're sitting in the easy chair and
maybe a one of these neighborhood dark gray or black squirrels runs by the front door
we see the squirrel run by we don't get out of our chair we don't pursue it
we don't pull away from it we don't follow it
or tell ourselves a story about it that just comes right by
and then maybe a bird lands on a windowsill
and then flies off
we don't move toward we don't move away just clearly aware ah the bird and there
it goes
house cat same story
for our practice to stay back in the easy chair just having an easeful
simple relationship to whatever arises
at any of the senses
again put in one phrase as we're sitting back in the easy chair
whatever comes we just know and we let it be
we know and we let it pass
whatever is known
with an as easeful or kind attitude as is available
so in terms of the meditation practice we've been doing
we can here again begin with our breathing settle in with our breathing as the
focal point
and then as anything becomes predominant
say a sensation becomes predominant let the attention land there
just know it and let it pass
the change we're making with open awareness is this one
it's not it's that we're not making any deliberate effort to direct the attention one place or
another but attention is allowed to move about
freely
that might look something like
I noticed the inhale I noticed that then the attention moves
vibration in the foot sound
train horn sensation in the shoulder
to wherever attention moves on its own
we accompany it
foreign in this sense you can think of attention as like a soft spotlight
that lands in one place or another
the soft spotlight points to this object
it becomes known in our experience
and then without our doing anything Spotlight has found a new object
known in our experience Twan after the next
if you find that the attention becomes
difficult to follow or you find yourself moving into distraction
just come back to the breathing or whatever your anchor happens to be
settled back in
perhaps for a few minutes
and then again release any intention to accompany the breath
just accompanying attention as it moves here now there
now there
at times
the attention may seem to move from thing to thing
from experience to experience
perhaps that's why one name for this practice is choiceless attention
we don't choose what arises
or where the attention is to go
so we accompany the the attention
and recognize what is known in a simple way
so at times the attention may be seem to move
and at other times it may feel or seem
like the attention like the Mind itself doesn't move at all
and instead experiences come and they go
almost like the vast openness of the night sky
doesn't seem to move but there may be a little Sparkle of a
star or a planet or a twinkle
comes into space and then vanishes
foreign
any experience
internal or external
to accompany attention
knowing each thing simply
accompanying attention
now here now here
and if the mind is currently prone to distraction
no problem
just direct the attention to the breathing for some time
simplifying
and then when you are ready opening awareness again
to choiceless attention
thank you
foreign [Music]
attention open awareness
every experience that arises can be incorporated
every experience that arises is welcome
maybe counter-intuitive experiences may be pleasant they may be
unpleasant it's not an indication that something has gone wrong
but with choiceless attention open awareness we're knowing
feeling sensing our way along the path with whatever experience comes
and maybe to hold as a question
what is the freedom that's to be known right there in the
knowing in that simple experience
so now let's take care of our bodies we have about 15 minutes for a stretch break
um we'll we'll continue to keep silence here and then we will come back at
oh 3 45.
thank you
thank you coming back
near the end of our day of practice together
maybe it's worthwhile to just notice the impact
how are you feeling how's your state of being
we're switching the schedule up a little bit in case you were following it closely
and I'm gonna give a little talk now and then we'll create space for some
Reflections questions we'll do a little loving kindness
practice and um I'm gonna bring it to an end
so I thought it might be helpful to um
bring a little energy back into the room as we transition out of quiet and still
and just notice how that lands inside of you right now that idea
sometimes people are ecstatic and looking forward to you know moving out and talking and
sometimes there's a bit of a pain
reluctant or abrasing to go back into a lot of a lot more
stimulation expectations
ours and others so just checking in
and noticing you know what's true for you
it's an unusual sound
remember how you felt when you walked in the door this morning
do you remember your first sit which was pretty much silence for the
first half hour and then the guided breathing meditation
and then the walking period
and then the mindfulness of body
and then the lunch
coming back to mindfulness of both emotions and
thoughts another walking
an open awareness practice it's a lot of meditating a lot of ground
to cover in one day nice work
some of you this may be your first time doing a long day long or first time in a
long time nice job
yeah wow
I'll read you a little poem by Sarah jodakau
when the mind is not mindful it feels like a homeless person very insecure
very unhappy when you're mindful
you feel really at home so mindfulness is my home
when you're mindful you are at home when you're not mindful you are on the road to going nowhere
he says get in touch with the spiritual Part of Yourself the beautiful part of yourself
be mindful
I wonder if you felt a sense of coming home at all today
a sense of coming back into connection with more or
all of yourself
I wonder if in the guided instructions or in the before the emotions talk
I made it clear enough this idea that um you know when strong emotions come up we
want to leave our bodies often right the feeling
it can be so strong we we want it to stop we want out
and that's an example of becoming homeless right
of of having emotions come in and
losing our capacity to be with them
and there is a way with this practice we cultivate the capacity to be with really
intense things emotions thoughts experience
and we can have this capacity
to maybe be like I say Weebles that wobble but they don't fall down
probably you guys are too young to remember this toy it was called the Weeble and it was a
they were like kind of little people but they had these round bottoms this round base
and so they would be on your you know the table and you could knock them and they'd
wobble but they don't fall down they wobble and they come back up
and so we can Compass you know cultivate the capacity to be like that ourselves
to be like a tree that bends in the wind but we don't lose our ground we don't
get uprooted we don't completely fall over we can let
it come and move through us and okay right here right here
sometimes our thoughts you know I see people really having a
hard time with their thinking I've seen people hit themselves because of their thinking they're so upset and distressed
it's another way of leaving and not meeting our experience trying to
escape from it
so we're cultivating in this practice we're learning how to see that these
things come up and they go away how to stay grounded how to use an
anchor to help ourselves not get unknowingly carried out to sea with
these thoughts and feelings and compulsions and habits
the conditioning that's been building up our whole lives
it causes a lot of reactivity
so we're learning how to see these things come up and stay and in that process
we're freeing ourselves we're bringing an end to that conditioning by not responding
in the traditional way the habitual way
so I'm going to just kind of go back over some of the instructions from the the day
maybe to remind you and also maybe to bring them up so if you have questions about them they're fresh for you
as we move into the question or response reflection time
so we talk a lot about this anchor this idea of having this anchor
and very frequently the standard is the breath we talked about using the sounds
or Sensations as optional anchors and this is something our anchor is
something actually we can really create a relationship with that we can start to cultivate a very
fond familiar rapport with our anchors
and they can go with us everywhere and in fact we can start to if our breath for
me it's been the breath or breath and body or breath and sound sometimes I do a combo
but it's like um when I'm walking the breath starts to come into Focus
driving the breath starts to be my companion doing the dishes the breath starts to
show up starts to come into the foreground again so it's off it's always there in the
background of how far back and as we grow this familiarity this connection
this appreciation for our anchor it really can start to show up more and
more and more for us help us come back come back into this moment and the next
one so you don't just have to think about
using your anchor when you're sitting on the cushion you can actually cultivate it when you're walking
or driving or stopped at a stoplight that can help you
stay on your path throughout everything you do
so that's kind of how we started the day and we wove this in
and then getting to know the breath and how it expresses itself in the body
you can feel it in small parts the nose at the throat or the belly or the whole
body there's so many ways to experience breathing
and then we talked about the body and how the body expresses itself it's a
storehouse of memories and it has Intelligence and it expresses
itself it speaks through Sensations and the way it's heard is by us feeling
those Sensations whether they're emotions or itches or pains
but they're designed for to be heard to be known
so we practice with the body becoming more and more comfortable and
familiar with all the ways it speaks to us less reactive to the ways to speak to
us getting to know that too and how that is
this tremendous part of our experience
kodo talked about the Sixth Sense doors right six of them one is the mind
the rest in the body that's where we live
we find the gateway to the presence of this moment is through this body
foreign we're working with emotions
I offered the raft to recognize allow find and feel
tease apart this can help us kind of pull the
thinking the story the energy behind the emotion kind of tease it apart so that
we can meet the emotion more like raw energy that moves through us
without refueling it re-tripping it so an emotion if we measure it
biochemically you said to last about 120 seconds
now do all your feelings come and go in 120 seconds no right why well because we
we trigger them with more thoughts more fuel so this pulling apart helps maybe slow
down this process of feeding and refueling and re-triggering emotions
and then we worked with thinking and we tried to work with it around noticing
um kind of how we're thinking are we thinking in images movies
are we thinking in conversations narratives words that are typed across the screen
sometimes it's just sort of this background noise
we all think in different ways some of us don't see images some of us don't see words some of us it's dominantly talking
in our minds what how do you think what did you learn about your own
thinking
when we moved to open awareness so we spent all day right differentiating these parts learning how
to meet each part of our experience and then we learn are invited to sit back
in our easy chair with the one door and the four windows
kind of like the five senses in the body and just let things come up come in come
out flow in flow out and as one thing becomes dominant we're
with it and then it passes away and we're maybe with our anchor until the next thing comes up
foreign less awareness we're not choosing what to be aware of but we're allowing
whatever comes to be known
so the practice is simple really it's natural we're not trying to make
anything happen we're trying to learn more about how things do happen arise
and pass away we're inviting more ease
and we're learning that we can be mindful of any experience that we can meet any experience
it is possible to meet any experience and this is good news
it points to the fact that we can use and be supported by mindfulness in every
aspect of our life on the cushion off the cushion on a retreat daily life
when somebody's screaming at you when you're looking at a car accident at
any moment we can be mindful mindfulness can become a very
trustworthy friend I'm going to end by reading the same
poem I started with it's not mindful it feels like a
homeless person very insecure very unhappy when you are mindful you feel really at
home so mindfulness is my home
when you're mindful you're at home when you're not mindful you are on the road to going nowhere
[Music] so
now we would love to hear your voices we would love to hear how the day has been
for you any of your questions reflections
we battle to you for your practice your endurance
the way you've shown up stayed here and there's really been a gift to be
here with you today so we've got the mics
and we're also open to YouTube questions or comments if they come up and so Sage
will check so who's willing to hold the mic and speak
thank you
this keeps coming up again and again in my practice
I can be mindful and what I consider a good Buddhist for about like all day and
um and and do my meditation and
uh but by at nine o'clock or right before you know like that it's like okay
you've done it and I want to just be human I want that ice cream and I want
more of it I don't want to have to think about oh everybody is worried oh every
bite is great and I don't want to have to I want to I want to think about all
these people in all those situations that I've avoided all day because that's not good intention I have an hour to do
this and I want to go for it and I keep running into that you know I'm exhausted
and I want to just you know just just have that for me
and so I don't know whether I'm capable of extending this practice
24 7. I don't know I really don't know
I don't know would you like one of us to venture a response Noah okay and do you have any
sense of what would be most helpful to hear
I'm not what I am open okay great Cody you want
to give it a go oh sure do you have your mic on I think so okay great am I
audible okay yes um first thank you very much uh for the honesty and the passion and
like the real Flesh and Blood Humanity of your what you shared
uh to speak for to speak from my own perspective Dharma practice
is about real life it sounds it can really sound like
uh we're just dealing in ideals especially when we're talking about instructions
um but the the place that the practice actually happens and what it actually
looks like is it's the messy Humanity messy that's the
term Endearment for me it's not a judging term um
and then and then what I what I hear in that last hour
um it sounds like it sounds like actually you're recognizing what's happening
but there's a the tension seems to be what what's happening is at odds with an
idea of um maybe skillful or wholesome conduct
I think to me the the the conditions for an onward leading
practice are already there and that's like clear awareness of okay what's it like now
to be saying to myself I'm setting aside my practice for this hour that you can you kind of still have it
because you're asking yourself okay what is it really for this moment to happen Okay this is craving I'm really going to
dig into this ice cream and I'm going to have it what's that what is that what's that like in here without
um without adding or without a without without the the
evaluation being in the foreground that may still be there too it can just be in the background
that's my that's my first impression I don't know if there's anything you would add I want Kanye to say something
because I think you like ice cream oh okay
um well what I was gonna say um is I love what kodo said I agree
absolutely and I would say I wonder if there are small things in the day many
many small things in the day where you're doing a little bypassing where you're you're shutting off your
process because you think you shouldn't have a reaction and that those little bypasses are
building up it's like it sounds like you know building building and you get to nine
o'clock and it's like okay I can't do anymore I can't breathe anymore and and
so then it's like okay I'm taking the lid off and what would happen what would
it be like if there were little more a little more time lingering when you feel
upset a little more time when
um you know with most likely the things that aren't
so pleasant the thoughts the feelings the exchanges
appetite yeah so maybe you're also you're using your
reservoir of willpower up you know if you're trying to resist
eating craving whatever it is the appetite for food or other things
you're repressing that you know you may be getting you're doing too much of it
and so it doesn't mean we have to give into a
craving necessarily for ice cream or alcohol or whatever it is
but we might need to be figuring out how to um
we fuel ourselves along the way
there's a book by Kelly McGonagall called will power Instinct she's a yoga teacher mindfulness practitioner she was
a professor at Stanford she talks a lot about the willpower
um that you know we have we only have so much we can't just keep saying no all
the time right so there's two parts there's the saying no restraint but then
there's also processing the emotions and the feelings and the thoughts that don't get addressed because of what's going on
so both both pieces not totally bypassing the little bits that maybe add
up and and then also looking at how much you're having to work to say no to things and how can you make that easier
for yourself so what do you think Noel
I thank you both thank you
for I feel like my question has been honored great I definitely honor and bow to your
question
who else would like to say something
Joe would you like to talk about anything about the day
right here Joanne right here okay
okay hi is this Omnia Okay so
this way towards you like yeah yeah it's all ready
okay yeah yeah okay so so this was my first
retreat the first hour that was the longest meditation I had ever done
I'm surprised I lasted the day
but I'm I had an inkling I would hmm
things came up for me that
like I bought the next I was expecting other things to come up for me and it didn't but what I was
working on instead of I was probably in
anticipation of what was coming up so I was controlling it to a degree
but I also resonated with the story the
storyline running through our minds
so that made me more aware and also this leaflet
like on the covering page it's either you have a wholesome mind or
non-wholesome mind and that was a really simple distinction for me
because I like to be happy I like to be joyful so it's like okay well let's
focus on that but I should still be mindful of when
the sad things come up and that I can still process them but they just Fleet in they squeal oh squirrel cat dog
and the other thing that was coming up it's like sometimes how to process things
yeah so if you keep looking at things like cat dog
squirrel are you really closing things out because they tend to go with the thought
to reach a conclusion so then I feel like I've processed the
thought so a couple of those instances came up
okay that was wonderful to hear Joanne and
I'm really grateful you hung in there with us today do you um do you have any want any
response or a question in there you just sounded great you sounded aware I don't know if there was anything in there that you want a response
I suppose the question about processing you know when events happened to us or
around us like the leaf blower and when the Deep blower came I was
telling some of people here at lunch I wanted to run out
and tell him to switch it up then I wanted to run out and tell him they were going to be banned next year so we
wouldn't be able to do it and then I wanted to run out and have compassion
for the person blowing it he wasn't wearing a mask because of all that dust
that was going into his lungs or through lungs I should say
and then I was just watching my thoughts go but yeah I suppose the question about
processing and sometimes we get carried away on our thoughts to find the root of what's
bugging us so or sometimes I'll just put it in my mind and look like literally I
have like all these little locks in my mind and it's gone behind the lock and I close it but sometimes it'll pop up to
be processed again so what's happening there no you
well since I didn't get to say thank you for hanging in there today first
how wonderful taking a moment with that
in terms of processing such a valuable way to get to know ourselves
to to be with thoughts to their conclusion I think that's one of the reasons that a journaling practice is so
powerful you know um one of the
I think one of the that's one of the reasons that I keep a journaling practice sort of in as an adjunct to
what I do in meditation because they process in different ways uh I'm going to borrow the term process
and apply it to meditation to my mind and to my experience
the the activity of knowing seeing sensing through the body
processes just in a different non-discursive way it's like things get maybe instead of
processing they get metabolized or they get digested um
as as we heard today the body is like a storehouse of memory and often our thinking will be
cued by processes that are happening in the body it may or may not be aware of as we were talking about earlier so
as far from the perspective of mindfulness practice one of the routes to take
is to sink down into the body again you can let the thought go on back there I
keep doing this as if it's somewhere in space not not deliberately pick it up just for
the the time span of meditation if it's important then you can pick it up after
and then go into the body and all the sort of like cascading Sensations and changes and the combination of that
with clear knowing it's like it metabolizes and digests just in a different way
anything to add that was lovely um I guess the only thing I would add it's
a small thing but that sometimes by um
maybe if you imagine that the raft practice when you're sitting with all
these different pieces um if you can just sit there and watch what happens you'll notice patterns
and if you can if our normal pattern is to go with the first thing that comes up
we miss that there's other things connected or other things to see as well
so that's a reason to process in this
slightly different way is it may it may just reveal some other things that that
we weren't so aware of if that makes sense foreign
great two questions
can you hold it like this and a little closer Yeah question number one is
um like today was a longer seat so you you know when you get out of it
you have that peace the serenity which lasts for maybe few hours
he do a longer retreat maybe say four or five days you take the peace and
serenity the ability to be I would not call equanimous but at least you know Center may be the world where
you don't get so hindered or you know perturbed by what's going around you it
it's it's just wonderful to see that you know after the retreat if you have done
a normal Retreat it lasts a little longer let's say you know the four or six day Retreat will last
two days and then when you it's it's like you know you're living two lives of sorts
when the effect kind of weighs down then you know your old
conditioning or whatever you call it it kind of clashes or you know your own it
kind of comes back you know you see it because you're enough mindful to see it the idea is one question to it
is does this require you know prolonged degrees of hours and hours of meditation
to kind of make it your own as if not that peace doesn't kind of have this
running away kind of phase the part two of the question is occasionally this
happens very occasionally it probably with me it happens with a little bit of try to kind of you know unhook the idea
of self it happens only when it's deep deep inside and you know the mind is
kind of a little rare I don't know if that's the way to say it it's kind of a little thing and that's when you get it
when it if you get it there is a sense of fear and you kind of go into it and
then you try to hold on to it but I think somewhere either the Mind comes in
or the fear comes in is is a is this
heard of or is this normal or is this something that people experience because
you know it's hard to talk about this to a regular person
two is um what is the way if to kind of you know hone it because hey I assume that's
where you want to be some point in your practice wherever at
least during the practice if you can hone it I think bringing it to you know walking talking in the world might be a
little hard but at least for that you know half an hour of practice to hold it
a little longer but
you might want to hold on the mic just for to see if uh okay
yeah yeah let's let's both yeah yeah so the first part of your question
um you know was about the the how long the more calm or Equanimity lasts
and um and I would say that um
foreign with devoted practice practice happens
all the time right so there's a way in which
um you know given a normal day practicing as you're going through life staying
aware that that peace that ease that balance
stays with you as you move and then there's going to be times maybe where
it's a little bigger there's too much and things build up I mean part of what
happens in meditation is we let things move through that are getting backed up and I think that's part of what um
inhibits our our ability to stay equanimous
so that's part one of the question does that feel like an answer to part one a response great yes
to let go and try and let go be aware enough to let go yeah but that's also
you know this idea of the riverbed you know sometimes we can be a big river and
a lot can flow through and it can move and it is it's just gone but sometimes it's it's either too much for us no
matter how big we are or we're just not that capable in the moment so we have and
that's going to change it's a fluid thing how much we can let move through us and
so it's noticing the residual and maybe sometimes we have to practice more and sometimes less you know depends on
what's Happening yeah okay do you want to take part two sure sure
great question um thank you for the question and I I'm related I I believe that they're related
I do too these are these two questions uh I want to start by saying at the at
the end of a very long retreat I asked the teacher in a practice
discussion um do I have to go back because
I don't want all of the all of the distress to come
back the um the the states where we're just so
nourishing and so beautiful and he said to me
anything that you can regard as a state will pass away
but you may see something as as those glacios are rearizing
you may see what an important period of practice this is how do I pick them up how do I pick up
my habits of mind and appropriate appropriate them as mine
what are the processes by which I fabricate a cell
and that's where the the second part of the question comes in and I picked up there was a word you
used that was like sinning thinning sinning
um I think you described the mind as very thin so it's easy for the sense of self
to not arise so true and the
just to directly directly address one of the questions you had about that is is
the the sort of fear normal and yes that's that's part of the
process I feel like that that deserves many minutes so I'm sorry to have to be brief about that
the part about thinning is not only does the Mind become thin
but the the influence of greed and hatred and delusion
and sense desire gets very very feminine and then in our daily life in the way
that Tanya was saying it's like things don't move through quite as much so those those two get thicker it's like
they get thicker our self gets thicker and our one of the ways I see the training is
that when we're off the cushion looking for the keeping an eye out for
and watching the processes for of grieve hatred and delusion and
how they're like how they're operating in our daily life like I said are there ways that I'm showing up in my daily life that are
thickening those and thereby thickening a sense of self
there's a lot of ground to cover in what you said so I think maybe we'll start there
thank you so much
it's 4 28. we did great 428 is great 428 is great and um I'm sorry if anyone
wanted to say something more and they didn't get to because it was delightful
to hear and um to be with you so just the briefest of
meta practice and then Sally is here to help with cleanup so
um it takes about 15 minutes to tidy the Sangha so if you're all willing or able
to stay after many hands make light work and Sally's a master at making it all
dance so um all right back in the body
taking a breath bringing in just maybe the spirit of good will
the spirit of Sangha the teachings
the generosity what a gift that we are in the space
that actually comes from Donna people gave money to create this space to make it possible
for us to be here may all beings be so blessed
may all beings everywhere be safe and protected from inner and outer harm
may all beings ourselves included everyone included
be happy healthy and at ease
and may the benefit of our practice be for the benefit of all
foreign [Music]