greetings everyone it's a delight to be here with this beautiful sangha
and i should have mentioned this yesterday at the outset i've been um i had a wonderful visit from my daughter
and grandchildren last weekend but they all had coughs and i've been fighting off a sore
throat all week and yesterday i could barely talk i could barely make sounds with my voice
so i hope it'll be a little bit better today but if it's a little bit scratchy you know why
so let's begin our meditation today as we've done every day this week by
first of all leaving all our concerns preoccupations agendas worries and
responsibilities outside the door for the next 30 minutes
so take a moment to do that put them out there carefully
knowing that you can come back to them when you're ready
so we'll begin again our meditation by inviting sati
awareness our best friend to the forefront
this is so helpful because as awareness becomes strong we can see
when unskillful thoughts begin to arise and then we have a little opening in
which we can make a choice not to pick them up
so now bring your awareness to your posture
balancing aligning the whole body
you might wanna adjust a little bit back and forth side
to side
and now connecting with the earth feeling
the connection of the body on whatever is supporting it your cushion your chair your bed
and imagine words going down deep into the earth
and now inviting the grounding energy of the earth to flow up through the seat
through the spine providing stability
maybe confidence assurance we're here on this earth
and then as the energy flows up the spine we let it exit through the ground of the head
and now we can open to the energy of space
we can imagine that the body is suspended from above by that invisible thread
so ideally we have a comfortable posture that is both grounded
and spacious balanced stable
open
we'll begin by relaxing the muscles of the face
softening the forehead the eyes between the eyes
the cheeks the lips the tongue
the jaw the neck
relaxing the shoulders
the arms the hands
the torso and the belly
relaxing in the legs the feet
and let's take up residence in this body just as it is
and as we become more and more present in our bodily experience of breathing in and
breathing out there may be a subtle joy that arises
simply from being present
so now closing the eyes
breathing in being here
breathing out peace
breathing in i'm here
breathing out i'm okay with the way things are
here in this body breathing
breathing out peace
and with our receptive awareness [Music]
maybe a subtle feeling of joy and really being present
in this moment
breathing in joy and breathing out peace
so we shift to inviting joy on the in-breath
breathing in joy breathing out peace
grounded in the breathing
breathing in inviting joy
reading out peace
and from the joy of being fully present
we now invite tranquility
breathing in calm breathing out
peace
inviting the body to relax inviting the mind to relax
tranquil quiet breathing in
calm breathing out peace
right now i'm okay with the way things are
the body however it is is doing its best
mind is doing its best i don't need to change how things are to
be okay this moment is enough
i'm happy that i don't have to fight with the way things are
for minutes just imagine uh take in the wrong being
of the contentment the happiness
of being okay with the way things are right now
now without really using words
we'll breathe in the well-being of contentment and breathe out peace
in well-being
breathing out peace
if the mind should wander because that's what minds do
come back with a smile to breathing in
the well-being of contentment breathing out peace
coming home to safety there's room for all of me here
i'm home in this body in this moment
breathing in safety breathing out peace
with quiet joy calm the well-being of contentment
i'm safe here at home breathing in
safety breathing out peace
as we come to the end of the sitting let's bring to mind the people we'll
come into contact with today strangers as well as the people we know
making the wish that through our presence
our example we may offer them peace
no matter what the circumstances are if we have
clear awareness we can always find
a way to be peaceful and we can offer this
to everyone
so by abiding peacefully ourselves
may we offer all beings ourselves included safety
peace happiness
and freedom
[Music]
greetings everyone it's a pleasure to be here with you all
today is the last in our series this week on cultivating peace
in the early texts of the buddhist teachings there are many synonyms for nibana
complete awakening one of which is the supreme peace
another is the unconditioned
so i'll read it to you in something from the samyutta nikaya 43
1 the buddha says to his disciples
i will teach you the unconditioned and the path leading to the unconditioned
what is the unconditioned the destruction of greed the destruction of hatred
the destruction of delusion this is called the unconditioned
and what is the path leading to the unconditioned
mindfulness directed to the body this is the path
leading to the unconditioned
so oh with complete awakening the poisons of greed hatred and delusion
are completely eradicated never to return
and then the buddha says that the essence of the path leading to the supreme peace of the unconditioned
is mindfulness of the body
as we've seen samadhi or unification is the last of the preparatory
conditions from which the insights necessary for liberation
arise when the meditator can dwell in samadhi
the insides leading to awakening will gradually and spontaneously
unfold
and in all the wholesome stage that we find in buddhist teachings each one
can arise in a wide spectrum of depth or intensity and that entire spectrum is valuable
including the first baby steps samadhi for example encompasses a range
of increasingly profound states of meditative absorption
and before entering into samadhi proper there can be access samadhi
when all five hindrances are in advance and the mind is settled
for most practitioners it's unlikely to be accessible in a 30-minute meditation
on a weekday and a silent retreat offers
the ideal conditions for cultivating samadhi
that said we may have tastes of samadhi outside of a retreat center
when the mind is at peace unified and these small tastes are valuable
and should be savored they give us an idea of what is in store
so for samadhi to arise we put in place the condition of peaceful contentment
the body and mind are suffused with a sense of well-being
which is calmer and more satisfying than joy
so let's briefly review the steps along the path of liberative dependent arising
which put in place the conditions for entering into the sacred state of
samadhi it all begins with an honest confrontation with our suffering
we live in a world of 10 000 joys and 10 000 sorrows
which arise and pass away and we need to know our suffering
in order to start the process of becoming free
and then it's important that we have confidence in the path we've chosen to follow
the stronger our confidence in the path the greater our resolve can be
then with confidence that we're on the right track gladness naturally arises
we see that indeed there's a light at the end of our tunnel of darkness
next step is joy which is directly proportional to how absorbed we are in our practice
when awareness is strong we feel the joy of being fully present
the miracle of each moment
and these first steps of confidence gladness and joy
have a very useful function of dispelling anxiety
and agitation they put in place the conditions
for tranquility
when tranquility becomes pervasive
the conditions are in place for peaceful calm contentment to arise
the gentle happiness of sukkah we are at peace
with the way things are with a deep feeling of well-being
with agitation dispelled through tranquility the well-being of calm contentment
allows the mind to become unified in samadhi
so we're on this beautiful gradual path and it may be more gradual for some than
for others it doesn't matter if we're a slow bloomer
or fast bloomer we all have our karma to untangle
our knots to untie and this will take the time it takes
we need to study how we get caught and to learn what works
and doesn't work for us on the path to freedom
the good news is that no matter where we are in the past there are always opportunities for meeting or suffering
skillfully and in that encounter
if we are mindful we will see the forks in the road that continually arise
and we can choose the peaceful road that leads to freedom
if we're not mindful chances are we'll be caught in reactivity
and without even seeing the fork we hurtle on down the samsaric path
of dukkha it's also good news that as our practice
develops we do get better and better at recognizing the forks in the road
and choosing the wholesome one over the unwholesome
we learn that we don't need to be at war with ourselves we're at war with the way things are
in any situation we can choose peace
obviously i'm uh not saying that we shouldn't defend ourselves if we're attacked
but i am saying that blind reactivity is our enemy on this path
as our mindfulness becomes strong and we begin to live in the practice of mindfulness
more and more we choose the path of peace
one of the most powerful things i learned from my root teacher suzuki roshi
was that he taught the dharma most powerfully by his example
he radiated the buddhist teachings and that's something that we can do too
so in the context of what we've been exploring this week we can incline our minds to the supreme
safety the supreme peace through our practice we cultivate joy
tranquility the well-being of contentment
and unification and we can share these beautiful fruits of practice
with everyone we come into contact with so the invitation is to live in peace to
the extent we're able to
we can begin to contribute to peace in the world by cultivating peace in ourselves
if aversive thoughts arise we look for peaceful thoughts
we try to ensure that our speech is peaceful our actions peaceful
and through our practice little by little with help of sati
lucid awareness we can be peaceful
in everything we do we offer peace to ourselves
and to everyone to all beings
and we can make the aspiration to be a safe haven of peace
for all beings everywhere
thank you for your practice
you