okay great so hello everyone lovely to be with you
lovely to be with you all Wherever You Are
um Wherever You Are In This Moment In Time on this planet of ours
it's nice to feel your presence and uh also welcoming all those who listen
afterwards on Audio Dharma and who are part of the Sangha
even if not in time um but in space so
so for today's practice um I want to try something different
instead of speaking about what I'm going to talk about and then doing the guided
meditation I'm going to switch it up a little bit and just start the guided
meditation together and [Music] um you don't need any experience
whatever is needed will be presented to you in the guided meditation and then
afterwards I'll speak a little about where the topic and and what we did so
are you ready gang yes let's see thumbs up yes great
all right sweet all right dear dear ones let's let's start practicing together
let's sit let's do sit together so
so Landing Landing in this body
This Moment In Time
first arriving by relaxing the body
relaxing relaxing the muscles
muscles of the face
of the jaw
the eyes
with each out breath releasing more
releasing the neck and shoulder muscles
ah with the out breath releasing the hands
the arms
releasing the chest releasing the heart
whatever preoccupations you have had
self-talk a monologue sometimes feels like a dialogue or
cacophony inside
can't be released right now put down just for this moment you can pick it up
all later choosing to put it down
releasing the heart
not needed In This Moment
take refuge
spacious silence
releasing the abdomen and the back especially the lower back
releasing the groin area let the weight of your entire upper body land
land in your sit bones offered to the Earth
releasing the legs upper legs knees lower legs and feet
let that feel heavy on the Earth your entire weight
offered to the Earth
relaxing the whole body letting the breath move through
receiving the breath in the abdomen
the entirety of the in-breath can you stay with it receive it
the entirety of the out breath exhaling letting go
can you stay with it
for the next three breaths challenge yourself to stay with the entire breath
no challenge yourself for the next three breaths which stay with the entire breath
now relaxing you're receiving three more breaths
Etc
thank you
if you feel lost at any point no problem
release smilingly and reconnect with the next three breaths
just the next three breaths staying present with the next three
breaths and when you find yourself lost
reconnecting again
no need for huge determination just for three breaths that's it that's
all
and now just for the next two breaths releasing some more
and now just connecting with this in breath this up breath that's all
just one breath
thank you
and if you feel lost at any point not a problem or at least
just connect with this one breath right here
as if it's your first breath as if it's your last breath
the only breath we really know right here that's all
right here right now
as we connect with just this one breath also connecting with
the goodness the Good Fortune
of this breath in this body
to Gladden the Mind glad in the heart
Let each breath as you connect with it breathing in
some blessing right now that you feel
maybe that there isn't a lot of pain in the body connect with that
or if there is pain maybe it's not too strong
or if it is strong you're able to sit with it
or be with it a blessing
maybe you're sitting somewhere where it's comfortable sitting on a
comfortable chair cushion
let yourself connect with the goodness of that gratitude for this
here right now no past no future right here grateful
for this the immediacy of this
a roof over my head safe from the elements
gratitude for this
our ears that hear how amazing
go slow take your time slowly connecting with each breath in
the body blessing
to brighten your heart your mind right now In This Moment
explore for yourself
let yourself really savor before moving on to the next take your
time
it's wholesome the blood and the Heart
Inspire the mind
thank you
you find yourself lost just reconnect with the breath
just this Breath Right Here and when you feel embodied reconnect
with the blessing brighten your heart and mind with goodness
foreign
filled with the abundance of your life the sorrows and problems and scarcity
but all the blessings of which each of us have plenty of as
well as the challenge is difficulties
turning towards the good
you had a meal today maybe friends family
you're able to connect to in the past week
so many gifts
as we begin to bring this sitting to a close
let yourself feel the goodness of knowing the Dharma knowing
the practice having met the practice
what a gift that is readily accessible
through technology these days and that you have met it here you are
wow how lovely
blessings of a community of practitioners
blessing of the capacity to wake up in this very life for each and every one of
us yes yes we can
wake up
be free be light be loving compassionate wise in this very life
for whatever level of freedom ease love joy
that we have
we have had on our path to celebrate take Delight
give thanks
give thanks for our Good Fortune be born as a human being
with all its trials tribulations all its gifts all its Joys all its sorrows
what a ride what a ride
how amazing how amazing
give thanks to give thanks
a good fortune our blessings for our challenges that have brought us here
have made us more Hender compassionate
more human
give thanks for all the lies who's touched ours
and they're all the lives we've touched
all the love we have received all the support
and all the support we have given this web this interconnected web of
humanity
your thanks give thanks for our place in it
and be heartened with inspiration aspiration
sharing sharing your gifts your gratitude your goodness
your life as an offering
with all beings everywhere may my life
may my practice serve
as a cause and condition for my own Awakening my own well-being my own
Freedom joy happiness freedom from suffering
may my life serve Freedom Awakening
happiness goodness for all beings in ways I may
not be able to fathom and the little self that I see myself I
offer I offer my goodness goodness of this practice to all beings
everywhere link which include myself may all beings
everywhere you see happy healthy and have ease
may all beings everywhere including myself be free
thank you all thank you for your practice
what a joy to practice together what a gift what a gift to come together on
this Zoom or YouTube or whatever it is what a gift to be able to do this
together I feel happier and more grateful through this practice
together so what we did just a quick um recap we started
with settling in the body with the breath first relaxing the body relaxing
starting from the head going down relaxing relaxing Landing in the body so
we can become embodied and then we connect it with the breath
receiving the breath in the abdomen I invited you to uh
to receive the next three breaths so that was a pretty low level of
commitment just stay with three person then you would refresh your commitment
when you got to the end of the three breaths and then after a while there could be a tendency to pull
forward and not be with one breath but just kind of pull to the second and the third to the end of the race so we
pulled back just two breaths and then we pulled back even more after we had the scaffolding of the three breaths we
pulled back to just one breath just this one just and then just this in breath just this out breath
and then as we stayed with the breath for a while we connected the breath breathing in
what we're grateful for right here right now in the immediacy of our experience just like our breath the immediacy of
the experience cushion we're sitting on the warmth of where we are the roof of
our heads maybe the meal we have eaten that's giving us energy
I invited you to explore for yourself brightening your heart and mind which is skillful it's wholesome
do this with with the blessings in your life because we usually turn to see what
where the problems are we don't turn to what's good and then when we turn to what's good it's like oh my goodness I
am so blessed yes there are problems yes of course there's sorrow suffering but
yes so many blessings and ah and at the end we turned to to the
blessing of the triple Jewel the Sangha the community of
practitioners how lovely that we're practicing with other beings right now
other human beings on this path with us and then we turned to
the Dharma the the teachings the having met the teachings how awesome is that
wow through technology here we go on Zoom who would have thought on YouTube
and then turning to Buddha within the possibility of our Awakening yes we can
of course we can otherwise they Woulda wouldn't have taught it and and we know
we can we know there is goodness within this being trust there's goodness here of course
and that's that serves as as a source of Joy Delight so that was the Arc of our
practice so now I'd like to invite you all if you have Reflections questions
comments complaints you can put them in charge you can raise your Zoom hand what
did you discover from this practice and the invitation especially if you
haven't spoken for a while um if you have recently spoken I invite
you to pull back allow other people to pull forward and the offering is really for the
benefit of everyone Christine
hi Miss Nikki that was great exactly what I needed to hear tonight
um I'm getting ready to fly to the east coast tomorrow and I just know coming tonight
because I've been keeping myself calm today trying not to listen to the news and uh you know I just felt this sense
of peace that all is well all is going to be well tomorrow and having
like you said having a group of people that I thought I'll share this and you know everyone can take that to the heart
and it's gonna be okay and just that breathing just kept it
there's no Panic in my there's no Panic in me it's just like it's gonna be okay so thank you so much for this this uh
exactly what I needed to hear tonight oh beautiful thank you Christine thank you so much
for sharing your reflection lovely and and so beautiful to Glad in our hearts
right glad in our hearts and Minds a sense of peace and ease that arises and
this is available and and and again travel can be stressful and
unpredictable and all that and if it arises remember this is available to you you know if you're sitting and I don't
know if your flight is delayed or something again you could be sitting in the lounges of stressing out like okay yeah I'm just gonna
remind myself breathe in with all the blessings that are happening in this
moment all the blessings and when you said everything is going to be right I um
I want to share with you actually so um this is a poem uh this is a haiku
actually that someone wrote recently on a retreat I was teaching I taught a mindfulness of mortality
Retreat a couple weeks ago at at Spirit Rock on land and and the retreatings
were invited to to um towards the end to write haikus to
um capture some of their wit insights and so here's this one that that I've
that I saved [Music] um and they say I've now understood that
it's already all right everything ever
isn't that it's I've I've now understood that it's already all right
everything ever and that is an Insight that is an
understanding sorry to you all right everything ever even when things go wrong it's already
alright everything ever so I offer that to you Christine that that uh for your
travels yeah thank you any other Reflections comments
ah
as I wait for your Reflections either in chat if you want to share them or raising your hand
I'll share reflection with you that before starting to teach I was feeling fatigued I had an intense day of trying
to finish something accomplished something and and uh and I feel less tired now there is a
refresh I feel more refreshed not just in my mind but in my body which is very
interesting right the the the uh relationship between the mind and body
so Sarah
please hi everybody uh thank you so much Nikki
that was just such a beautiful meditation yeah you have such a soothing voice thanks
I just I wanted to um just reflect back on the the um so often
when when we're in pain um how it can become overwhelming it you
can become the theme of our days and our sleep and everything that revolves
around alleviating finding comfortable positions and uh and I have some knee
pain that I've been struggling with recently and and uh and so I always have
to get creative with my meditation posture and it and it's
interesting because um as you brought that up during the meditation I just reflected on the fact
that I I can be with it I can't be with it it doesn't have to pull me into
you know the sensations but that I can be an experience a multitude of things
along with paint and pain being present and still not let it detract from this
experience yeah so that was really helpful to me yeah thank you Sarah beautifully eloquently spoken exactly
and when there is discomfort especially in the body and the heart too they're similar on our Focus becomes Narrows and
that's all we see is like oh yeah it's a microscope and that's all we see takes over and yet can realize just as you
said yes I contain multitudes absolutely I contain multitudes yeah the pink and
beer doesn't have to take Central stage and the answer can be joy and gratitude and gladness and the pain too yes pain
welcome join the party right there's just so much here yeah that's that's
lovely and one thing to say uh as you were saying you have um knee pain and to be creative with your posture uh if I'm
sure you already know this but just just to say that you know that it's okay to say it on a chair to stand to lie down
whatever has come you don't have to sit cross-legged or any particular posture
you know that already right yes thank you yeah of course we have complete permissions there's so many postures the
Buddha has taught so this is lovely in fact um thanks Sarah and I'll share this with
with everyone um I was in in Thailand a um a couple
months ago already gosh time flies and there were many um statues of the Buddha of course there
are statues that the Buddha sitting in the sitting posture and and and lying down and standing there all these
postures and there's also uh I saw um uh
statues of him sitting on a chair that was pretty fun to see that was pretty
pretty cool and pretty pretty cool to see so yes and it is said that the next
Buddha is going to be sitting on a chair or something put off the next age anyway just giving permission for for physical
comfort with you guys already know that anyway so I'd like to invite us to now turn to
practicing together in small groups and the prompt tonight is and we go round
and round in a spiral is what are you grateful for and it's such a joyous
experience practice to say it out loud and be held Witness by two other people
with with care with appreciation and and when you also hear other people's Joy
you know if you've already done this practice you know it's infectious it's a joy that's infectious you start to feel
happy for other people's happiness as if it were your own happiness it's such a beautiful practice I love doing this
practice um so so one person will share one thing they're grateful for and and maybe came
up for them it could be as simple as yes as a comfortable chair I I have little pain in my body or I can I can be with
the pain right now that I have or anything might be um and then the next person and then the
third person and then back to you and then round and round then let's go in alphabetical order
um there will be an average of three people in the room and be kind to
yourself be kind to each other just share from your own experience no questioning directing Etc and uh have
fun this is such a joyous practice all right I'm gonna open the rooms here we go
take care of yourselves actually wake up I need to recreate the
rooms hold on hold on hold on let me do that hold on okay here
we go all right take care here we go
the rooms will close in about five seconds we'll wait until everybody is back
okay the rooms are closed everyone's back and we've got just
couple of minutes for um reflection so what it was like to participate
in sharing your gratitude and hearing others and again
if you haven't spoken in a while I'd like to invite you to move forward please if you always fall into your
pullback you rarely do you like to pull forward
is this Michael it is I must not be muted
but since I'm called I'm sharing sometimes has trouble with with muting a
phone so you're on Mike go ahead oh deep thoughts so this is Michael and I just
had huge mudita listening to my comrade share and it was just a beautiful soup
that was made in the Dharma sharing so deep boss oh that's very sweet thanks
for sharing that Mike that just makes me happy yeah lovely sweet
yeah any other reflections even if you're muted especially if you
usually don't share what what came up for you
love please I think one of the
the Lasting Impressions I have from the group is the Gratitude of noble friendship the Gratitude of being able
to practice with people in any tradition any lineage or just interested in exploring wisdom of our passion in ways
that are really posed about so very great beautiful thank you for that love yeah
gratitude for for the wisdom and compassion and and and
spiritual friends on this path yeah love me Claire
last reflection of so mundane you've got to go beyond me
uh I hit the wrong key on my computer and abruptly left my group so I wanted
to apologize to them uh
oh that's sweet also all right it's just sense of responsibility
it's a sense of care so I appreciate that that's that's very sweet sense of care like oh I I left too too early dear
grew that's very sweet I'm actually so touched by that I'm getting teary like
sense of care like oh so thanks for sharing that Claire that is sweet
oh so dear ones it is 7 P.M Pacific and
uh we have come to the end of yet another happy hour thank you so much for
your practice doing this work for not just your own sake but all those whose
lives yours touches directly and indirectly may all beings be safe happy
healthy and at ease may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music]