warm greetings from here the Insight Meditation Center in Redwood City
California and uh in the United States on this planet
Earth which we all share and uh
of all the places we could be in this earth we're all sharing the surface of it
and connected through the surface connected now through
electrical grid of wires and
signals nice to be together
so um
one of the common presentations of mindfulness
is that it is a some form of
non-judgmental non-reactive non-interfering attention
that somehow we allow things to appear in awareness
so that they are clearly known but we don't try to fix it or push it
away or hold on to it we don't need to get involved conceptually with uh
judging its worth or our worth because we have this thought this feeling this
thing is happening to us and um
and so one of uh one of the ways this is taught sometimes and uh in the Insight
meditations tradition is um
to make the distinction between listening and hearing
we're listening is something we intentionally do actively
do like you know someone says listen to the sound from outside and then you
direct your attention a particular way to listen to those sounds and you know and uh
maybe in some cartoonish way we're kind of like if we're going to listen to
something on our left kind of like the left ear kind of it gets bigger or stretches or something
um in order to hear in order to listen and distinct from that is hearing
and we can hear even if we're not actively listening
and so sometimes teachers will give instructions on um hearing
sound meditation where the focusing is on relaxing and
letting things be and just letting things be heard um and so there's a selectivity process
to the to the ear but it's hard to interfere
with what we hear unless we go over and do something about it but just allow it to arrive and
appear and be surprised or what comes to the ear whatever sound
comes and some of it we clearly are not Manufacturing and some people find that by doing just
listening to the Ambient sound that it keeps them in the present moment
in a very nice way and it allows them to relax deeply because they're letting go of the any
effort to try to make something happen within them in the same way
that we have the distinction between seeing and looking and looking is the active
and seeing is the I see that's what they do and it doesn't have to be an
intention or a direct directive to to see you cannot say ask someone notice
what you're seeing and um as opposed to look at you know the sunset
and so in the teachings of the Buddha the both kind of these are used these
ideas but the primary one is seeing that we're practicing we're developing
ourselves capacity to see with the Mind's Eye and sometimes that's called the Dharma
eye but we are learning to see with the inner eye or inner perception you know
doesn't have to be choosing the organ of seeing as the inner ear or
the inner perception inner knowing that is non-interfering non-judgmental
um you know non-entained unentangled with what's going on
and and this ability to rest back
in just a seeing let there be just a seeing it requires a stability of mind
because if the mind is jumping around a lot to distraction destructive thoughts there isn't a continuity of seeing
and the Buddha teaches the continuity of seating over time just settling back and
and observing and seeing what's there and and this is a very important
capacity for attention taught by the Buddha so
assuming a stance for meditation
a position where you are going to be rooted and established
Here and Now
and gently close your eyes
and if there are some sounds around you
allow them to come peacefully quietly to your ears
or receive them peacefully and quietly
maybe as if you were listening to a symphony or
some peaceful music letting it wash over you
not straining to hear
just hearing
relaxing any tension between the ears or in the mind or anywhere
in the attempt to hear and let it almost be a surprise
what comes
the sound of my voice
as you're hearing
maybe a little piece of your attention goes to the breathing
just enough that you're aware of the exhale
and you relax the body as you exhale
and then letting go of hearing and instead
Let There Be sensing of the body breathing
a sensing that's has equality is more like
hearing rather than looking more receptive awareness
than an effortful awareness
allowing whatever Sensations there are associated with breathing
to Simply appear on their own
into awareness
maybe on different breaths
somewhat different Sensations show themselves
different locations
different intensities
almost as if your body is a canvas
and the sensations that appear are like The Strokes of pain that wash
across the canvas
and they were quite sure what will come but the canvas receives it
as you're feeling the sensations are breathing a little bit on gently on the edges of
awareness let there be a relaxing in the body on
the exhale
mostly sensing them paint brushes of Sensations across the
canvas sensations of breathing
but peripherally gently as you exhale relax the mind
the thinking mind
and as you quiet the Mind relax the mind
maybe it can be like the canvas expands in all directions
becomes larger
and then imagine that you're sitting quietly comfortably
in an ease each year gazing
watching the painting of the canvas
how it all occurs Sensations and sensing knowing
it will occur is this something that you can sit back and just watch
seeing without actively looking
at ease content
relaxed gaze of the inner eye
that doesn't need to fix or change or judge what's happening
but gaze is kindly upon it from the easy chair of awareness
foreign
and settling back further not even
not that only looking at the breathing watching it
settle back without any particular direction of attention
hope into everything but with the mind's eyes you're seeing
what appears not as paint on a canvas
but as Birds butterflies clouds appearing in the sky
settle back and observe watch
the comings and goings of anything and everything
and as we come to the end of the sitting
to gaze upon everything kindly
to gaze upon this world of ours kindly caringly
foreign to gaze upon ourselves
kindly caringly
maybe as if seeing gazing kindly is at the center of
all things and the seeing radiates out and sees
through yourself sees all of yourself every good bad the ugly it's all just
seen kindly as it travels through you and then out into the world gazing
kindly caringly and the good the bad the ugly
just kindly
caringly
and when we gaze this way with kindness and care
we don't have to be loving we don't have to be liking what we Gaze on the people we see
but it is a wondrous human ability
that we can gaze kindly with care
and may it be that our kindness our care
becomes the most natural thing to carry with us through the world
so that we gaze upon the world with good will
with caring instincts
may we care for everyone may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we walk through the world with kind eyes caring eyes
so we can contribute to the welfare and happiness of all
[Music]
thank you
so we come to the fourth talk on the series labeled consciousness
and the premise here is that what we call consciousness
um or what I'm calling Consciousness we
don't actually know what it is for sure but what I call Consciousness is the
synchronized working together of all the different
active capacities faculties we have for attention for perception
and they can come together also with our attitudes and our motivations and
many of the cognitive functions of the mind as well and it all comes together to create and
the mind creates an image or a sense of the whole um that is greater than the parts a
whole which is partly a a painting that the Mind paints of what this thing
is that the whole the unified hole the thing that Consciousness can seem
and there's a wonderful coincidence that in Pali that
the word for mind and work which might easily be
translated as Consciousness at times um is uh is um a homonym same
pronunciation as the word for a painting and uh so you know the mind maybe
Consciousness is uh this kind of construct this that the painting The Mind makes of itself
that um that is somehow brings together all the different parts
into an image or a sense of something and um and so these different uh
capacities we have for perception for attention are key to this component
parts to this painting that's created the sense that's created and um and one of them today is um
they're talking about is the ability to see um to see clearly what's happening
and the Buddha uses this language of seeing uh as a metaphor so that for the
inner way of perceiving the inner way of kind of sensing knowing
that is somehow uh in the mind rather than in
the sensations so that's the kind of knowing quality of the mind that knows I'm sensing
um warmth cold coolness the sound a taste the smell
the tactile sensation body and um but it's not so much that cognitive in the
sense of recognizing what it is it's not the recognition factor of the Mind but it's more like just the the uh the
level of the mind that can just kind of do the equivalent of of of hearing or
seeing in that hearing and seeing are different than
listening and looking in that hearing and seeing are receptive
are not directive necessarily they're not active engaging of those scent
stores but those sense doors are on
and Sensations sounds or site objects arrive and come and they are seen they
are heard but they're not looked at they're not
listened to in an active way and um and in both of these uh
metaphors of the hearing and and seeing uh I think Builds on the idea
that uh what is seen and what is heard is actually usually uh at some distance
from the ears and the eyes I mean it could be distance could be you know just
a few centimeters away but still there's a there's a there's a gap there's a distance the medium through which the
information is going through the ear and this air the space
creates a little bit the difference from that's different than feeling Sensations
in the body physical Sensations uh you know like we feel pain or pleasure
that there's an intimacy there to uh to ourselves in a certain kind of way
and um but uh and so that intimacy sometimes because of you know being pain or pleasure it becomes something that we
are you know prone to get actively involved in or concerned with or identify even with
but the things we see in the distance see a tree we don't usually identify it as being you know me who I am the tree
it's all about me the tree and if we hear traffic Outdoors uh it
you know we're not again defining ourselves by the traffic we might find it uncomfortable and have a reaction to
it but the um but the uh but the hearing itself does not react the that's deeper in the
minds that it begins reacting and and um
and uh making meaning and values and preferences in there
but before these other layers of the Mind get involved that have to do with judgments and evaluation and reactivity
and preferences and emotions there is initially this very simple and
I would suggest relatively innocent Act of just hearing the sounds seeing the
sights and um and so that this is translated now for
the Buddha or adapted to the Buddha to talk about the inner eye and an inner
way of seeing and here also the idea is to do it in this receptive non-active way
um and so the Buddha never tells us in his instructions to do seeing with the
Mind's Eye the inner seeing um do the perceiving but rather to abide
in it and this he uses this word abiding a lot when he's talking about deeper
meditation that it when when we get settled in practice and meditation are able to kind
of course in the present moment then it's more like settling back and abiding
dwelling in something in a state and a way of being and a way of perceiving
then it is actively trying to do something and make something happen and it's a remarkable shift when that
can happen some people find that they can tap into that early in their practice some people it takes a long
time some people can do it early and then they can't do it for a while because they're going through layers of
leading to do some real inner work to sort through and settle down so they can
settle back for the Buddha it's it's the latter we do all the work of practice
and a purification practice a cultivation practice a settling practices
understanding practices and then with with enough practice and some point we
can just settle back and observe what's happening
and and this is a and then an abide in the observing abide in this inner seeing
um and um uh where things are everything's allowed to be itself it's very respectful of everything it can
almost be reverential that everything's allowed to be kind of its own pristine thing every sensation
every sound every sight every everything that's known uh
um in this seeing can be seen with the reverence or with care or with
um with um Simplicity radical Simplicity just allowing it to be itself
that becomes the foundation for for the kind of insights that Buddha emphasizes
the most the insights that are part of the inside meditation uh path uh are
insights that don't come from actively looking for them but rather when we
settle back and can observe and see in this kind of way that I'm talking about today
now as we see this way uh the seeing is somehow
free of what is seen in the sense that in the seeing
we're not entangled we're not caught up we're not reacting and so what's being
seen is clearly left alone just like seeing with the uh with the physical eye
or hearing with a physical ear
we're not actively involved with you know looking you know the tree and
interfering with the tree as we're gazing upon it we're not interfering with the sound of the car outside it
just does its thing independent of us and um and so
um all things are allowed to be this way and be seen in such a way that then
insights begin arising and um and that's maybe for another time but
um but the sense of what I want to emphasize today is this way in which the seeing
there's a freedom in the seeing and independence from the freed and the freeing there's kind of a spaciousness
and allowance of things as they are in this kind of interceeing that goes on
and um and so in that seeing as one of our intentional
faculties when seeing has this quality of freedom in it it can give
um uh when when we construct this idea of Consciousness Consciousness then
begins feeling like something that's a place of Freedom a place of um of
um allowance space of openness a space of
receptivity and but in particular there could be a
feeling that in Consciousness itself is something we can place we can rest in
the kind of Freedom the Consciousness almost can feel a very broad the spatial
of the uh the way that the body the my inner mind or the constructs a spatial
sense of uh awareness where it constructs spatial space spatial ideas of location and when that spatial
location gets relaxed and soft that also starts having a broad almost boundless
quality to it and so the construction of Consciousness can now starts feeling not
only is it free and and um and peaceful and Broad but it also feel and Untouched
by the things of the world but also it can feel like it's boundless and open and expensive
is consciousness actually boundless is it actually you know
anything at all um more than you know it's hard to say and there's strong
opinions about this but the view that I'm presenting here that it's yes it's
boundless in the sense that the construction the image of it the sense of it that the mind creates has no
boundaries but it's a it's kind of a a
a wonderful composite image Gestalt
image or idea of all these wondrous faculties that we have that come back
come together and work in some kind of Harmony together to to give us a sense and then we try to
make sense of it we try to understand it we try to have an image of what it's operating and then the mind creates that
image of it all so and then we can abide in it we can
rest in it we can allow it and now it can be very freeing and very supportive to to have a sense of Consciousness like
this so um I hope that uh
this is useful for you and gives you something to reflect on and explore on
your own and I would encourage you for these next 24 hours
to um use hearing and seeing the physical ones and also the Mind's Eye his ability
to see and hear and perceive to experiment uh with gazing upon things
or he uh hearing things in a very receptive open allowing way
to feel the refreshment that can come how the eyes and the ears get refreshed
and cooled and calmed and peaceful when they're able to just see rather
than look rather than searching rather than straining or staring
and the same thing can happen to hearing uh when we hear rather than strain to
listen or or something so uh thank you all very much and
and I am looking forward to coming back uh tomorrow morning