so welcome welcome welcome everybody
such a great thing to be able to practice together so thank you
to come and be here
so i recently just finished teaching a loving kindness retreat and
it was quite something it was very tender as you might imagine
but a number of people at the end commented that
they don't usually necessarily do loving kindness and i thought well they'd do this retreat to kind of maybe
get their practice going and at the end of the retreat they were wondering wow
why didn't i do this earlier why didn't i do this you know earlier in my practice because even
though i've been doing all these wisdom and insight and mindfulness
just noticing that having a container of warmth
somebody described it as kind of having this golden sheen to everything all the
practices makes a difference makes a real difference
and so i was reflecting a little bit about this idea of you know what is practice how do we think about practice
and so tonight i'd like to talk a little bit about one way not the only way
one way we can think about practice in kind of a simplified generalized way
and to be sure that there are i'm i'm like moving towards simplification in this talk and
to be sure there's ways in which we could really get into the weeds and make it you know complicated maybe if
that's opposite is simple and sometimes i like to do this but
but sometimes it's helpful just to be reminded oh yeah there's a big forest here not just the trees
so why is it helpful to sometimes think about simplifying practice is
if we find ourselves feeling a little bit stuck like
i don't know like a dryness a i'm not sure where this is going i'm not feeling
inspired i'm doing it because i feel like i ought to or this is what i have been doing or
something but if we feel maybe a little bit of stuckness or dryness
maybe that's perfectly fine and that's just a part of the season of practice
but also maybe there's a way in which we can look at it in this kind of simplified way and might see if there's
a way in which we might look at things a little bit differently that can provide a support for practice
so i'm using this word practice what do i what do i mean by that
i would say the way that i'm defining buddhist practice as this general something that supports the movement
towards greater understanding either of ourselves or of others or
how the world works or doesn't work as the case may be
or this general movement towards greater ease or peace or happiness
or a greater [Music]
diminishment maybe of suffering so this elimination of suffering letting suffering go so this movement towards
understanding ease and less suffering in some kind of broad brush
so this real simplified way is to think about there are two types of practices
one is cultivation practices in which we're creating
maybe not creating as much as building or developing or supporting something
to become a little more steady or reliable or
stronger cultivation practices and then on this side
simplified way we think about letting go practices shedding
releasing renouncing letting go so on one side we're kind of like
building up making stronger maybe a bigger we might use those kind of language
and the other side we're letting go kind of shedding and this is kind of
a different type of movement and to be sure we need both types of
practices kind of this cultivation and this letting go and
one way we might understand it is in um suzuki roshi's very famous saying i don't know how many
times i've heard this many perhaps you guys have as well here's this quote
each of you is perfect the way you are and
you could use a little improvement kind of this we might think of it as a
paradox but in one way that we might understand it too is each of you is perfect it's the way that you are
this may be an invitation to let go of anything that makes you think otherwise
and you could use some improvement is to cultivate those qualities or those properties
properties doesn't sound quite right but those qualities mind states experiences that can really be a support
so this recognition that this inter-relationship or the
dependence on both types of these practices but it's not uncommon for people to have a
preference for one type or the other
and sometimes it has to do with an aversion towards one type or the other
for example this whole idea of cultivating building [Music] developing
might feel like exhausting like i'm already exhausted from my life the last
thing i want to hear about is something that needs to be done more something to the addition of it's the
last thing i want no thank you i just want to sit quietly
or there could be this sense that they find it feels a little bit offensive even to imagine that
something needs to be different i'm perfect the way that i am and i just the whole rest of the world needs to start
behaving itself how dare you kind of suggest that i need to cultivate something
so those people tend to prefer kind of this idea of letting go and they might use language like letting
be but there's also kind of this sense of well i don't want to do letting go pros
uh practices because i'm just barely hanging on
and i'm it has everything i it takes everything i got just to hang on
and you're suggesting i let go but i that's not it's not even
that's exactly what i don't want to do or there might be this idea that
everything seems so slippery so this whole idea of letting go but they're
feeling like i can't even hold on to anything what do you mean let go nothing is
everything is sliding away there's nothing that i can hold on to
and different people different seasons of their practice different times of their practice might kind of have a
preference or one in which they find a little bit more ease or comfort or that just naturally arises
so this recognition that both are needed and there may be times in which we
are going more one direction than another and also i'm making this distinction between
cultivation and letting go but let's be honest it's maybe entirely
artificial to make this distinction also because in some ways they are the same
the obvious ways we could look at the practice of generosity we think of it as a cultivation practice
but generosity itself is a letting go so we're cultivating and letting go at the same time that's
an obvious example when there are indistinguishable these two qualities
but there's another way in which we could even say with mindfulness practice
we cultivate mindfulness being here in the present moment and with the experience but
at the same time in order to do that we're letting go of all the ways in which we intentionally distract ourselves
so this idea of cultivation and letting go and separating them you know sometimes
he's useful and sometimes isn't
but this to say a little bit more about what does it mean this idea of cultivation practices that
there are many parallels between cultivating the mind cultivating the
heart and cultivating a garden
one thing is of course that we just don't think about
seeds being planted and watered we actually do it
right so it's not only about believing or thinking or wishing or something about
that but it's a it's an activity a certain type of activity
and cultivation practices are very much like planting seeds
we plant them and
we give them what they need without explicitly
making them grow right seeds have the potential to grow inside them
we're not giving them that potential it's already there and we're just creating the content the
conditions in which that potential can be actualized
in the case of plants sun soil nutrients water
in the case of our practice attention
intention and
a willingness to allow things to unfold in the way that they're going to unfold
instead of insisting that they be a particular way
so this recognition that we're just taking care of the conditions
rather than the specific making them grow
and i think all of us recognize that depending on what we value we will
cultivate different things because no matter what we do we're
cultivating something with this idea of neuroplasticity
so if we have this habit of
getting filled with outrage when we hear or see or read the news or
something like this right then it just the more time we spend in outrage
the easier it becomes to become outraged
i'm not saying that these um emotions or ideas
aren't appropriate but i think we all know this that whatever the mind frequently ponders upon that
becomes the inclination so not only the mind but the heart and the emotions
and so of course the buddha encouraged us to cultivate those things that are going to be
helpful that are going to lead us towards this happiness and greater understanding and
less suffering and chances are that you don't need me
to tell you this idea that the buddha encouraged us to cultivate
ethical actions to behave in the world in a way in which we don't cause harm
neither to ourselves nor to others and sometimes that's not so easy
so it requires us to see if there might be some creative way in which we can work with something in
which there really isn't harm being caused also requires us to be sensitive
to maybe some of the subtle ways in which harm gets caused with our words with our language
and the buddha also talked about maybe before i leave this idea of um
causing harm not causing harm i'll add to this also to become sensitive to the ways in which the ways the inner critic
sometimes rises up and causes harm for you know the way that sometimes we
talk to ourselves or some of the language or you know berate
ourselves turns out not to be so helpful
and harmful
the buddha of course also called encouraged us to cultivate a steady mind
so that we can see more clearly so that we can see what's happening and see the consequences of our actions
just allowing the mind and the body to settle
these days it seems so often that there's these um prompts to get a little bit agitated in
some kind of way i'm using this word agitated really broadly but
it seems like um we've created a world in which we're often like poked if you know notified and or you know somehow
there's this way in which we get uh
i'm using this word poked sometimes it feels like that
maybe you have a better word but um you know there's you know the media of
course wants to promote this way of outrage too right so
this idea of to cultivate a steady mind in the face of this recognition right
that there are industries out there who are created specifically to keep us agitated in some kind of way
the business models of there's these aren't bad individuals it's just this
recognition that what they are promoting isn't necessarily for our long-term welfare and happiness
to sensationalize or to notify or
incessantly
the buddha encouraged us also to cultivate a warm heart so a steady mind and a warm heart
so with brahmavahara practice loving kindness practice and it's the beautiful part about this
it's not only to cultivate a sense of warm-heartedness
but also to have this movement towards the boundlessness of this
warm-heartedness so that it's not just for those we know and care about those who
are we feel the most comfortable with or are most familiar but
to cultivate this way of this boundlessness for all beings everywhere
and this does take cultivation it's not something that humans naturally do
and this idea to also with a loving kindness and
all the brahma-gaharas compassion sympathetic joy equanimity also this unconditionality
is there a way that we can express this
without having any sense of whether people were or deserve it or not
taking that out of the equation just saying no this is this is what this heart does this heart loves
this heart cares this heart has warmth independent of
oh the specifics the particulars of the individuals
and then of course you know the buddha has all these lists seven factors of awakening 10 permis
like there's like seems like there's no end to the things that we can be developing and cultivating and
but we can get out of balance if we emphasize this cultivating part
and i know this has happened to me in my practice like unknowingly
i felt like okay buddhist practice kind of supported this self-improvement project that i wasn't
even quite so aware of and so yeah i gotta cultivate this and
this and this and all these handy lists that i never could quite check off right we can
easily fall into that kind of a mind state or
understanding of practice and to be sure there are plenty of zuta passages and
teachings that are about the importance of effort and diligence
but it might be a way in which we just take that on it's like yes i'm never
going to be finished this is a huge project i have to keep on working
and let's be frank we are a pragmatic and goal-oriented culture
that we like to put effort into our jobs our relationships our vacations
recently i've learned this expression you know to have relationship goals you know like so there's all these
ways things you know that we're supposed to achieve in like all areas of our lives
which is great there's nothing wrong with that with having a vision of what's possible and a orientation of a
direction we want to go but outside of kind of the buddhist
practice and outside of the meditation circle there can be a sense of well just try harder if you
haven't reached all these goals or haven't accomplished all these things that we
might have these expectations about
try harder just try harder oh ouch right this is exhausting
it seems like there's no end so there's all this cultivation and that is
a part of practice but we can get out of balance
and we might think that we just have to try harder and strive and strain
but then we end up kind of like tight and i've got this with my body because it's kind of how it feels
and then everything feels you know has this flavor of inadequate and not enough and
need more
so instead we might have i need more effort
i need to put more energy in i have to try harder without looking at it well maybe there's
a different type of effort a different type of activity
and that is the letting go kind of the releasing as opposed to acquiring and building
instead this movement of letting it go
so there might be some if we call letting go like relinquishment or giving up or something
like that that sounds uh a bit uncomfortable it can sound like a renunciation or
surrender which can sound like deprivation like that's not the direction people want to
go they don't want to feel deprived of course and that's not the direction we're going
we're not going towards any way that has this personal
diminishment or in a way that suggests any type of weakness
that we just have to let go because we're not able to hold on or something like that
no it's something different it's about a more like a shedding
just in the way that snakes shed their skin when they grow
and during the different seasons the animals shed fur and birds
molt feathers just like oh it's just a natural thing to be letting go it's kind of like this
natural process and sure we can see that maybe animals are
scratching a little bit when they're that fur is uh shedding and the birds or when they're
molting sometimes are preening a lot so there can be a little bit of
uncomfortableness but still this recognition like oh yeah this is the direction we're going
and something that i like is this story that's uh in the vineya about ananda
the buddha's attendant and after the buddha died
they got together they being the senior members of the buddhist
followers all the fully awakened senior members
to recite the teachings to get together like okay what did the buddha say we
have to preserve these pass it on to different generations and ananda of course
was the one that had memorized them all because he was the attendant of the buddha
but he wasn't awakened completely and this
was only for awakened people so what was he going to do so
the evening before this big grand meeting he's huffing and puffing and striving
and straining to get a weekend and all of us have tried to huff and
puff and strive and strain too i think right this is just part of the way we tend to approach practice but
so he meditated strenuously and and just
nothing happened so i gave up
i went to bed sat down on this vet
this is how the story goes and lifted his feet up to put it in bed
and before his head had hit the pillow this big release
when he became awakened so it was when he had kind of relaxed
given up this idea that things have to be a particular way
it was maybe straining and striving and said okay i just can't do it and let go
and it became a weekend and i hear about this a lot on retreats
and myself i've had this experience too that sometimes during a retreat you know sit walk sit
walk you know for days and days of sitting and walking and people can get really tight and
be trying so hard and sometimes retreats are really hard
there's maybe something about there's the transition of you know finally the bell rings at the end of the set like
oh my gosh okay i made it and then they go to stand up and just in
that moment of kind of relaxing with the standing up there may be something that oh a new
understanding that happens so this recognition of letting go
is just a natural thing that happens and sometimes it happens just during the
transitions we're not making it happen it's just a
an unguarded moment allows the mind and the heart to open in some kind of way
and to be sure we let go all the time in daily life we change plans the weather is now
raining we're not gonna have a picnic or through our life our preferences have
changed i used to hate ketchup when i was a kid ketchup is fine now
i'm sure all of us have this idea right of things that we didn't used to like and we have different priorities
and in our older life that we didn't have when we were young so it's just this
natural thing of just letting go and to be sure learning to let go is a
skill for a happy healthy life
and so as part of buddhist practice letting go is
not only of what makes us tight i can't help but i do this with my body
when i'm describing it because this is how it feels but there's a way in which um there's
not only letting go but also the compulsion
to want to grab on in the first place when we notice we're have grabbed on we
can open our fist but there's just this movement of wanting to grab on that gets let go too
that gets softened and diminished as we practice
this sense of this enduring self that's at the center of
everything and that has to be bolstered and protected and
highlighted and let go that let it be softened like
oh yeah sometimes there's this in sense of self but other times i'm busy with
other things and there isn't a sense of self and this recognition that it arises it gets
constituted and then it goes and does something else
so letting go of the sense of an enduring sense of self
letting go of ideas being permanent anything being permanent
and letting go of the idea that when things are uncomfortable that
somehow it's a terrible mistake and there's got to be an error somewhere and
who's to blame for this suffering is part of life
and i think though unfortunately there's only one way to really learn that is that is to have suffering
so what if we kind of reworded or re-languaged this idea of letting go
i think i i'm not exactly sure where i heard this first it might have been from gil but this idea that instead of
letting go is this idea of giving up as in like towards the ceiling
because i guess the origin of this idea of giving up is like to put up on the
altar so to make a a
an offering in this way it's an act of generosity
or we might think of it that somehow maybe it's a sacred act this it's a
movement of the heart this idea of giving up
and then some ways then it feels like oh okay so it's in the service of what's wholesome and
what's virtuous and help support this beneficial states of
mind and is in the service of creating this
spiritual wealth this inner treasure inside of us
inside of all of us so this letting go this giving up
is for one way in which we help create the conditions
for the seeds that we've planted with the cultivating practices to sprout
and to blossom
so we can let go into something beneficial something
supportive wholesome
so with deepening meditation practice and we have this greater range of what is wholesome and beautiful and
meaningful these inner states that we
discover explore become more familiar with
let me just start to recognize oh yeah a little bit of letting go here allows
me to tap into tune into that particular state be sensitive to
that state and letting go or giving up
just becomes more and more something that the mind and the body and the heart just
want to do
so one thing i do want to say also though about letting go i'm describing like letting go into
beneficial states but chances are if you've
had a practice you know that sometimes this letting go
we could also use this language of kind of like i've heard this language uh
purification cycles so it's this sense of
letting things get disgorged maybe something that's
i don't know exactly what's something that maybe we've been holding on to for a really long time that isn't helpful or
maybe we don't even know what it is but the sense of clearing out something
uncomfortable and or this sense of discharging or
maybe even vomiting up because sometimes practice is
painful and it feels like stuff comes up and maybe it gets expressed with tears or
gets expressed with nausea or something like this so
to be sure this letting go part can be uncomfortable
and we don't always like get to choose or dictate exactly how it happens
or when it happens or which manner or something like this
so this idea of maybe sometimes it's helpful to look at our practice
in a simple simplified way cultivation letting go
and maybe to look at in this big ways if we feel like we could use some support
maybe just uh is there is there something that wants to be let go
is there something that can be cultivated and maybe we don't even have to know precisely the
answer but it's just activity of asking that question is there something that
can be let go or something that can be cultivated
and just having that curiosity might be a way in which we can
i don't know something new can unfold and we can become aware of
to help guide us
so i offer this that may be a support for your practice and
your life this way of
cultivating and letting go thank you
and i wish if you'd like to ask some questions you you're welcome too or
i know i just sprung this on you jim about this idea i mean i didn't tell you before that i was going to open it up to
questions but if anybody has one or otherwise
we can call it an evening too
is it was on when you tapped it but now i
don't feel like i can't hear the microphone did it run out of juice
green lights fading is there another
maybe the these poor batteries you know maybe with this pandemic they sat there for a couple years
losing their juice how about this yeah there we go okay
um i hope this question doesn't seem too wonky or cerebral um
early in the talk you mentioned newer plasticity yeah
um this is something i've been wondering about for a long time
i associate newer plasticity mainly with if you've had a stroke
and then part of your brain just isn't functioning but over time and with effort
your brain your the neurons in your brain you affect a workaround
and you can regain movement that you didn't have or regained cerebral
ability that you had lost so the brain has this kind of rerouting
potential how about this though uh i think you
were referring to a different kind or maybe it's the same thing that's my question
if if we have bad habits or we've been conditioned in certain ways
and our brain our mind gets in this groove and it's really harmful
then we start to see because we bump into a a buddhist group or
read a book or we just saw someone doing something kind out on the street
and oh there's a different way but you can't just change right away it
takes effort effort effort but eventually it can wear some new grooves
would a neuroscientist think that that's newer plasticity also
that's my understanding that we can uh one think of neuroplasticity as any time
we learned something new actually there's new neuronal connections
that weren't there so one way we could understand it is like you know anytime you learn something new
and like really learn it then that's would be an example of neuroplasticity but you know bill i have
to say that this is not an area of my expertise so i i
appreciate what you're saying but i like this you're using this word grooves that's kind of how i think about
it too right is that what we do repeatedly it just becomes easier and easier to do just because
there's and i don't know how this works down at the level of the neurons
somebody does i'm sure our friends at mr mrs google know this type of thing
but so if the answer to my question is yes
then everything we're doing exactly here is newer plasticity yeah and our newer
plasticity makes it possible everything i would say that's that's my personal
assessment i also just want to thank you for your
talk i probably missed half of it because you said something that reminded me of
my situation and my thoughts were going off onto oh yes yes and i was feeling a
little oh yes and then it came back to your talk so thank you you're welcome you're
welcome bill okay thank you thank you all