hello everyone and today this week we're very much
here to experience our body at least that's what the
instructions for for this section of the discourse on the
for foundation of mindfulness what this section is about and
one of the things we're contending with as we
bring mindfulness to the body is a tendency of thinking to take us away from the body
and i found i found it helpful sometimes to think about thinking to consider thinking
uh my my thoughts to be a little bit like thought bubbles in a cartoon in the comics it was floating above the
head and the reason i find that sometimes useful is sometimes it's very clear
that when i notice that i'm thinking or have been involved in thinking that i'm not really connected to my body
very much there's not any sense of embodied presence embodied attention
and that when i then settle into my body it's a richer certainly more embodied
experience of myself but also it becomes more three-dimensional
whereas thinking by itself is one-dimensional or two-dimensional
it's kind of flat even though the what we think about might be exciting and
emotionally evocative and all kinds of things there's some way in which the embodied
life feels richer or more valuable and so whereas this first foundation of
mindfulness is uh becoming has to do with becoming embodied
so um to when we're sitting today
you might study a little bit the difference before you
between being preoccupied in thoughts when you notice you are that way notice
what it's quality of the mind the body the quality of your experiences
when you are so involved in your thinking that you're not connected to your body
and then but then when you switch modes and come into your body through the breathing and settling what's that like
how's that different the image i like to use myself
in those kind times when i get preoccupied in thoughts is that i'm
now i'm going to dip back into my body like i would dip myself into a refreshing pool of water
that or a warm pool of water if it's a cold winter weather right now
so dipping myself into a wonderful pool of water and as i'm just kind of like
settling myself into the water of the body the
the and that image of settling in and to water
is very nice for me and helps me kind of settle into my body a bit more
so taking a meditation posture
and
taking a little bit of time with the posture
knowing that mindfulness of posture is one of the practices of mindfulness
mindfulness begins as we attend to our posture
perhaps making a many small adjustments just to get aligned and
get everything just right
closing the eyes
and noticing the degree to which you're involved in thinking
is there a lot of energy in your thinking right now
and if there is feel that energy feel the activation
that's connected to thinking
feel that activation physically what does it feel like in
your body is there tension or pressure
is there agitation physical agitation some part of your body that's connected to thinking
and then as you breathe maybe breathing a little bit more deeply than usual
breathe into the place that's activated breathe into the place where thinking
predominates and as you exhale relax the thinking mind
as you exhale calm the mind
maybe slowing your thinking down a little bit
or lowering the volume
if you think more in images maybe you can imagine the images are
further away from you projected into space
at a distance so you're not so involved
then taking a few longer deeper breaths on the exhale
settle into your body as you exhale
exhale and relax into the body
breathing in and breathing out
establishing yourself in the physical sensations of breathing
and maybe the ways in which they are the sensations
come and go with the rhythm of breathing in and out
so
and then coming to the end of the sitting
dedicating this meditation
the effort you made dedicating the
practice for every breath that you were present
for dedicating it to for the welfare and happiness of others
and yourself dedicating it for the well-being of this
world including yourself
may all beings be happy including yourself
may all beings be safe including yourself
may all beings be peaceful including
you may all beings be
free may you be free
each of us is as important as the every other person in this world
when we dedicate the what the merit the benefits of practice may be all inclusive
for self and others self and others for this whole world
may this whole world be happy
thank you
so we're spending time these days with mindfulness of activities
so that overlaps quite a bit with what's called mindfulness in daily life
and the list of things be mindful of in the text we're going through
is quite extensive and uh when i was in japan practicing
there then monastery they had a
practice called gatas they would recite gatas four line verses
that they would and we were given all these verses like a little book of verses to memorize
and uh before we were going to eat before we were going to shower wash our hands go to the bathroom
all these kind of sit put on the clothes there all these ordinary activities we did we did
and the idea was to recite these four verses that you memorized they were specific for each one
and it was an aspiration verse may i as i as i do this activity may i
and it was always as far as i remember all of them had to do with um
dedicating it for the welfare of everyone benefiting everyone from this
when i was at the here in california at the sahara zen monastery they used a little bit of that
and mostly it was when we go to the baths they had these natural hot springs that were that piped water into the baths and so
it was kind of lovely place to go and shower and then bathe in and but there was an altar as you entered
and you would bow to the altar and you'd recite the four line verse that was
written on above the altar and um
and it was i remember exactly how it went but it went something like
as i enter the bath with all beings you know something like cleaning
myself inside and out uh or something yeah i remember now i don't
remember but uh it was a little bit and but you would recite this and so
the the we have one at the irc or retreat center that was written a few years ago
and i'll read it to you that i have here
it had to do with hand washing because it's so important when 40 people are living together and
touching the same utensils serving food and all that everyone washes their hands before we use the buffet table and serve ourselves
but to really emphasize the value of it and we have this little verse that's posted on the
cleaning my hands i clean my heart and mind cleaning my heart and mind i clean the
world for others and uh if you memorize these kinds of verses
and when you do something it takes a certain amount of attention and time to do it
you're preparing yourself for it you're in you're funneling your attention your energy
your and your time to do the activity you're doing so you you don't think do things in a
hurry when you recite a four-line verse before you do it
and so the so uh by doing this in design monastery
it was a training and learning how to take your time slow down don't be in a hurry just do
the thing you're doing when you're doing it kind of the idea of when do when you're
doing something just do it when walking just walk when eating just walk
and um and uh i thought i would read one that um
do i have it here i know i don't have it here maybe tomorrow um
by tiknot han tignan is a whole little book with these kinds of gatas four line verses
and um so um the um
what i'm trying to convey here is um when you're practicing mindfulness and activities
don't do things in a hurry it doesn't necessarily mean you have to slow down
but you can do things fast sometimes without hurrying hurrying is being ahead of yourself it's
propelling yourself through kind of through something or to the other side of it as quickly as you
can whereas mindfulness is meant to be being there for the activity
if it needs to be done quickly then be fully there in the as its surrender to the activity
i was a fast order cook for a while after being in the monastery and what i learned the monastery about how
surrendering to each activity be really present for it um i learned to do in the kind of a fast
or a cook i was i would just that's all i did was the dance of spinning and
turning and cooking many dishes at once and that's the only thing i did was all
that i kind of surrendered to that dance and i would usually leave
my job feeling more concentrated than when i entered because of how i gave myself over to it
so giving yourself over to the activity without a hurry
and uh for to to live a mindful life to live a life where there's some
momentum where for mindfulness to grow and enhance our life grow in our life
it really is uh valuable to start bringing a
good quality attention to what we're doing when we're doing it in the present moment
so i'll go through these this list with again
acts in full awareness when going forward and returning
so if does it go someplace you have to go
to the bathroom and come back if you have to go to the kitchen to get something come back if you have to go to the bookcase to get something and come
back that's a time where if you want
can be your meditation time that's a time for
cultivating your capacity for awareness it's not just to be aware of what you're
doing which is valuable but it's also what we're trying to do here with this sati
patana this four foundations for mindfulness
is to do these activities so that awareness becomes stronger present moment
awareness becomes more second nature then it is something you have to remind yourself to do
so there's both for the purpose of being present and for the purpose of enhancing and developing
awareness it's like a muscle awareness and you can develop it
uh when acts in full awareness when flexing and extending one's limbs
and so if you're going to reach for something in thailand
i don't know if it's still there but there was a school of the pasuna school of insight meditation
that relied on not the breathing but rather
you know in breathing you're watching maybe the movements of the belly as it comes and goes
in this school you um you watched your arm as you moved it you
would lift your arm put it down to the side lift the arm up put it down to the side
and you'd be very focused and concentrated on the sensations of that movement and the mind may get concentrated a lot
of calm would develop and and for some people this movement of the arm was easier to track
than the breathing and you know eventually the people who did it a lot became concentrated there and with a
concentration they would develop the further uh steps of the pipasana
so uh bending and extending one's limbs
wearing one's uh robes and carrying one's bowl so
wearing one's clothes so putting on one clothes wearing them
in the for the monastics uh being mindful of your robes is important because one of the minor rules you can
violate is um you know monks wear kind of a skirt and
then a outer robe over the skirt and the big outer robe extends down to the edges of the skirt
and and the robe has the bottom of the skirt the hem has to be lined up
parallel to the bottom of your skirt and uh if you don't do that then
it's a little violation and so the um so you have to be very these
robes that monks wear you know take take certain amount of mindfulness to keep them just right so you have to be
attentive to your clothes and i when i was a monastic i loved i i was surprised by this but i came to like
this a lot quite a bit because it was a call to constantly be mindful
constantly be attentive here and rather than seeing it as a nuisance i saw it as a kind of way of staying relaxed not
rushing ahead and not getting complicated just staying present
one acts in full awareness when eating drinking consuming food and tasting
the word for tasting apparently is not exactly tasting but more like savoring
so certainly you don't want to be attached to it but to be really present to feel and sense the taste
and there's a part of a lore of buddhism or part of the records
from the ancient commentaries is that a lot of practitioners became
enlightened while they were eating so something about the detailed attention
and the first kind of opening real opening kind of
experience i had in buddhist practice occurred while i was sipping a cup of tea
so the idea that these simple things can be really powerful
if we're really present for them and really give ourselves over to it sense it and be with it
um full awareness when defecating and urinating sometimes it's said to be
a kind of you know a really good poop is kind of like i'm
you know a minor nibbana niner minor awakening so really be present for
these bodily functions that we do every day and when walking standing sitting
falling asleep waking up talking and keeping silent i find it very
nice when i go to bed at night to be present for the experience of being there and
relaxing my body being mindful and checking in and and letting go of any any stresses
that's easy enough to let go of and just be their present and my teachers in burma they wanted us
to be aware right up to the moment of sleep and actually be able to know if you fall asleep on the in-breath
and the out-breath i tried i tried that for a long time and it's something i've never been able to do so i've given up
on that and then to be present when we wake up and to know if you woke up on the end
breath and the out breath also something i've never been able to do and
but then to wake up and then us begin the mindfulness as soon as we remember
so what i try to convey today is is how valuable it is to practice in
activities it's both valuable because it gives a heightened attention to what we're doing
which is nice but also it's a way of strengthening developing our capacity
for mindfulness capacity for awareness and that these activities that we do that's listed in this text each of them
is quite quite valuable and has a lot of potential even potential for
realization for waking up drinking uh you know drinking eating our food
drinking tea going to the bathroom all these things you know you don't want
you want to be present for them because who knows maybe today
the active some activity you're doing today is the activity that's going to be really
dharmically significant for you for your practice really significant and you don't want to miss it you don't want
to have glossed over it and um so but we don't know which one it
is so maybe be careful today with all your activities and who knows which one will bear some
wonderful fruit so um
there's a there's a uh data from tiknathan before starting the car i know where i'm
going the car and i are one if the car goes fast i go fast
thank you barbara so um so there's lots of these wonderful verses and uh you can
write your own four line verse as a way of supporting you to
enhance your engagement with whatever you're doing so thank you
and i look forward to seeing you tomorrow
or being here with you tomorrow