just in case a few people come in late and is that okay with you Diana yeah of
course just adjust a little
anybody have concerns about my taking my mask off Diana okay
um Sage do we have anyone on YouTube hello beautiful people and YouTube land
welcome
I sometimes talk about it as the people on the other side of the camera like we're on this side and they're on the
other side nice
so um we wanted to create a space to talk
about you know practice together and um the
the four weeks of let's talk about practice this week is Sangha is the
focus talking about Sangha next week would be effort the week after
would be mindfulness in the week after concentration
and so we'll do um Diana will give a some talk Talking
sharing reflecting and then um I will too and uh
but tonight mostly I'm gonna focus on um teaching incorporating and moving into
just discussions using mindful speaking and listening
so I'm glad you're here my dear Sangha
my dear Sangha Diana and sage and Richard out there
so you ready to share okay
so welcome welcome everybody for those of you who don't know me I'm Diana Clark
and uh I'm so delighted to be teaching with Tanya and especially on this topic
of songa because we've been friends for quite some time and we talk about
practice all the time right we talk about Dharma things and what a delight it is it makes such a difference
which one you just have a new part of my life has made a difference so
I wanted to start by talking about a little bit of a story that in the suit does that we find in this kind of the
ancient Buddhist literature and this story is about this character's name is megia
and he's the attendant of the Buddha some of you may have heard like Ananda
is the attendant of the Buddha but this is before Ananda so before Ananda was attendant megia was the attendant
and this one day maggia went out for alms around in the morning
you know nothing unusual about that and as he went out he noticed like oh
there's this mango Grove wow it looks so peaceful I think I'd like to go meditate
there this is a wholesome thing right he has this idea that he wants to go meditate
so after he comes back from the alms he says to the Buddha I saw this fantastic mango Grove I'm paraphrasing obviously
I'd like to go meditate there and the Buddha says no right now is not a good time
and Megan says no but I really want to and the Buddha says this is not the
right time and then magia says something like well
you don't have any more work to do but I have work to do and I really want to go meditate like recognizing he's not
awakened yet and he really wants to become awakened so the Buddha says okay
so Mega goes off into this mango Grove that he had seen he sits down in my mind
he's having it's you know ideal setting because he really wanted to go and he
has this kind of Gusto for practice and and he's sitting there in the Grove and
he's uh starts to meditate and he discovers that his mind is all over the
place and in not only that not only is he distracted but he's having all these
unwholesome thoughts that just keep on arising
hangs in there spends the day meditating and he says to himself I can't believe
it I think uh in the quality I don't remember the Paulie words but in English it often gets translated like this is
incredible that my mind is so out of control and all these unwholesome things
are happening [Applause] so he comes back at the end and he tells
them Buddha to the Buddha this my mind was all over the place and I had all
these unwholesome thoughts arise I know for me I thought well this is
kind of surprising because maggia right he's a he was a monastic he
had completely dedicated his life to practice so this was you know in order to ordain means this is like the most
important thing ever and not only that was he a monastic but
he got to hang out with whom we might say is the world's greatest meditation teacher the Buddha right that was his
own personal teacher and he got to serve him and he has and he had all these
difficulties so this is what the Buddha tells him when after magia says this
for those whose freedom of mind is not fully mature he's just acknowledging
that Maggie is not quite awakened there are five things that lead to maturity what five
the first one megia a practitioner has a good friend a good companion a good
comrade this is the first thing that leads to freedom of mind
and then the suta continues with four more things I'll just mention them we're not going to talk about them virtue
having opportunities to talk about Derma topics having energy and effort which
will be next week and having wisdom it's striking to me that the Buddha his
instructions to maggia the first thing he says is the importance of good comrades good Associates and good a good
friend companion and comrades so it's not sufficient to dedicate your
life to practice but I also appreciate that the Buddha he's using three
different words different translators do it differently and this translated as friend companion
and comrad I'm understanding this to point to different levels of intimacy
like some people are our friends and we share lots of things with them
some are companions that maybe we don't share so much maybe some are comrades
that we maybe we don't even know their names maybe we'll never know their names but they were just people that were in
the meditation Hall with us I have this one time when I was sitting
a long retreat those of you who have a retreat practice you know how it is that you at the beginning of the retreat
before it's started you um often choose a sitting place and you choose you like
put your cushion there or you'll put something on a chair if you're going to sit on a chair and I kind of I have like a certain
region in the meditation Hall I like to go and I put my uh cushion on a zubutan
on a mat there and nobody else was in the hall so I had no idea like where I'm gonna be
and as it turned out when there was came time for uh you know all of us to be in
the hole I had a woman on one side and a man on the other side and um they were
both kneeling maybe a little bit like hamidra is here and when you're in the kneeling posture you're a little bit
taller so I felt like oh I kind of have like Mom and Dad here right you know next to
me it turned out to be so great they were
like so steady and I don't know I felt kind of like protected and
a happy and I was just an amazing Retreat for me actually just sitting
between these two people as it happened this was a long retreat
and it was a three-month retreat but I was only sitting six weeks so at the end
of the six weeks I got up you know and left and they were staying in silence so
I never knew their names I couldn't even tell you what they look like because right I saw them from the side of my
eyes but just this recognition that other people really support us and those people
probably will never know how much they supported me either so this idea of
good companions good friends good Associates is being foundational for
practice and then in the suit of the the Buddha is using this word good good friends
and the word good here is kaliana many of you might have heard of this
expression kalyanamita meet does the word friend and coliana
can mean good but it can also mean beautiful
so this idea beautiful like the way that maybe inspires us or touches Us in some
way it could also just be good it doesn't have to be you know elevated up into
something that's the the highest but does this recognition that we can
support one another and be supported by others but it's not so easy as just sitting
next to people silently I mean that's one way but it's not the only way because
there's a way in which if we're going to really learn from
people that we spend time with be influenced by or allow ourselves to be
supported by people that we spend time with there's a way in which we have to
be open to that we have to be like a willingness to
learn from others to be influenced by theirs so can we be teachable
sometimes there's people who show up and kind of like don't want to they are so
busy showing you how much they know that they don't uh ever learn anything like
they don't really want to acknowledge that there's something that they don't know so it's a little bit of humility to
recognize well can I learn from others can I be inspired by them and and
without feeling a sense of Envy or this sometimes we can have these mixed
feelings when other people have some knowledge or some experiences that we
don't have it also requires that we're not so attached to our views
it's related to you know having an open mind but it also includes views about
ourselves and the ways in which we've set up Us Versus Them me versus you kind of
dynamic in our life my type of people are like this not
those type of people you know in whatever way that we've done that in our lives and it's the human thing to do
right to kind of want to hang out with people that are similar to us but is
there a way in which we can relax that and be open to
whomever I mean here in the context of IMC and as a practitioner I've met
people from all kinds of different walks of life and different backgrounds different ages right that I would have
never have learned back in my kind of a the life that I had before where I was you know surrounded with people that had
similar livelihood than I did or the same neighborhood or something like that
so not only does it mean that we have to be open in our views but this may be one
way to say is to let go let go of some of our biases let go of some of our
assumptions about other people and
this is why I think that the Buddha is when he's telling megia how to
as a support from Megan's practice he's saying that the first thing is good
friends Companions and Associates because all the characteristics that
allows a person to be ported by learn from to and and to
support others are all the same practices the same way in which we're showing up in the world
for just freedom in general this letting go and willing to be
influenced and willing to have different experiences but I also want to say that there's
maybe uh something else here is this idea of discernment
this idea of good spiritual friend well how do we know
that's good and what's not
so we can ask ourselves does it feel like it supports greater freedom
and we all know that doesn't mean that it's Pleasant all the time right sometimes we have relationships with
people and it's not always smooth and you know rainbows and hearts
sometimes it's you know we have difficult conversations but is there a way in which people
are allowing the best sides of ourselves to show up
they're giving an opportunity for us to be the best versions of ourselves and
allowing the wisdom that all of us have to for us to tap into it and for it to
come forth or do we find that so the
habits are bad habits quote unquote that we have maybe tend to come out when
we're with somebody and we're finding that we have less freedom and more regret
when we spend time with them and this can be a really difficult thing
when we start spiritual practice I I think it's pretty common for people's
relationships to start to shift as they start to have maybe different priorities
or they understand themselves different or they understand what it means to really show up fully
and they're realizing oh yeah this relationship that I've had for so long
but now I feel like I maybe will limit though a time that I spend with this person or something like this or maybe
they realize wow this person here that I've kind of didn't I knew them but I
didn't spend that much time with them turns out to be really a great support
so discernment is also needed and of course this is something that the
is a big part of our practice is okay what's helpful and what's not
helpful so then maybe I'll just
um introduce something just a little bit here I've been talking about good spiritual
friends and Tanya introduced this idea as a songa so what's the difference between good
spiritual friends and songa maybe there's no difference
maybe there's a way in which we can understand Sangha as fellow practitioners or comrades in practice
I think that's in a kind of contemporary parlance we often use that language as kind of the song is just those people
that we practice with and those that are supporting our practice
in the literature of early Buddhism
the Sangha is defined as those people that have a certain amount of Awakening
I don't we don't use that so much uh these in fact I don't know anybody that does but it's also a nod to there are
people who have some freedom and it makes sense right there's people have been walking on this path longer than we
have to just kind of acknowledge that and is there something that we can learn from
them is there something that we can maybe emulate or be inspired by or work
with or something like this maybe maybe I'll just stop there as a
kind of like talking about introducing this idea of Sangha and good spiritual
friends so thank you thanks Diana
I have an idea but let's see if if it feels good
I wonder if we could make a circle that you guys could come a little closer
and instead of doing you know small groups or whatever let's be one group let's make a you know a Sangha
and um not make it but you know what I mean
um and uh Sage if you can come over with us
and um Sage maybe if you bring the microphone
um and Ben maybe you can scoot your chair a little that way and then people
on YouTube might be able to see I don't know maybe if you pull back the camera a little bit the people on
YouTube might be able to see our group yes and it's a virtually a part of us
oh good great that's what this blue tape
yeah yeah to help so that somebody doesn't sit or
yeah it comes come closer Sage thank you now I feel I feel you more not
that time that's okay
now it's live I don't know let me did you did you set it that's okay I'll set
it and my mic's still a little too loud your mic yeah is it this one here say
again my mic is there that's better okay yeah and let's see this is especially so
that you guys are close yeah so this is uh three
okay does this feel okay to all of you
nice Jeff okay with you okay yes yes very good
so I thought we could just um practice mindfulness of speaking and
listening with each other I'll kind of you've got the handout but
I'll kind of talk about what those guidelines are and um and then I'll I'll introduce a
maybe a way to get us started talking and listening mindfully
but um I think a huge part is uh
well let me say it is inspiring me to me to think about being here in this way with you right that at the time of the
Buddha people practiced in community
people didn't learn how to meditate on an app by themselves at home
they they learn to meditate with others
and um and you know people tell me a lot how uh and I experience it it feels
different to meditate with others you know it feels different than
meditating at home not that it's not nice to meditate at home by myself but but there's something profound and
obviously with everyone here but Ben maybe has been on a retreat
um but Ben's been here a lot and um
so there you really kind of almost need for the amount of meditating you do
you're carried by everybody's practice around you and
holds the frame holds you up in a way so you know just uh
yeah and and thinking about being in the kind of
community that the Buddha taught would be more like being on Retreat people are
practicing they've got their however many hundred rules that they have to
follow to keep them Mindful and um
so here we'll just have a few rules you know that we're working on paying
attention to but first feel your bodies to me this is a huge support for staying mindful is to
feel our bodies here in this room and the space
and maybe I'll just say every part of you all of
you is welcome here every part of you all of you every feeling all of it is
welcome here Diana talked about
you know inclusion or in group I was thinking about the terms other ring and selfing
we do so much other ring and suffering and so my thought was let's invite each
other not to self and not to other during this practice and this little
group that I don't have to be any selfing
person that you make another and I don't need to make myself a self I can be in this experience and aware of
it as it's happening and unfolding and with you and your experience as it's
unfolding so that what helps stop othering meaning
creating some idea of who you are what you are like what your story is what who
I what I think you're going to do next what I think you need to do
instead of all of that my my goal will be to sit back and be
surprised to let each of you surprise me by however it is you show up whatever you
do or don't share to not try and
make it into anything but to receive whoever you manifest into In This Moment
and being you know in my body and being grounded and feeling our feet
feeling having awareness of speaking and or of
listening as we listen or speak actually makes it kind of hard to do a lot of
othering and suffering it gives us something to let go into
instead of all of that creating of ourselves we devote that energy that
we would to creating a self or another to being aware
so no I'm speaking when I'm speaking
no I'm listening when I'm listening
talking a little slower than normal normal General conversation helps
tuning into the impact of my words or your words on my body
in my heart
allowing space for pausing not planning what I'm going to say in
advance allowing myself to speak spontaneously
when it's my turn so that I can keep being Changed by whatever next happens
whatever next I hear
it just like when we're sitting relaxation is helpful
so when you find yourself feeling some tension maybe tune in
and see if you can soften or support whatever it is that's tensing up
maybe even being able to be aware of breathing as you're breathing
and talking or listening
and maybe you just choose one of these things in particular that you want to
practice tonight it's a lot of different things but maybe you just tune in to one of
them in particular that you feel would be supportive for you
so what I thought I'd share first what I thought would be nice is Diana shared a
story about being on Retreat and feeling supported by the two people on her side
and that made me I could I felt a lot of warmth when you were sharing that and
just that sense of being supported by others and it reminded me of a story
a very different kind of story where I felt supported by a spiritual friend kalyanamita
I was um I had been here for a Sunday morning talk
and was with um several of my friends at the time and
we decided to go out to breakfast together and we were in the car on the way to the
breakfast or on the way back I don't remember which I don't even remember what we were
talking about but there was the conversation
started to move in a Direction where there was some
critical elements to it there was
I don't know what it was but there was a little bit of um like somebody could maybe be harsh or
it wasn't anything blatant or awful but there was one person
who just got very quiet they stopped talking when the
conversation started to get a little edgy and I really noticed it I could feel it
I could feel their Stillness I could feel they're not kind of you know when you're doing gossipy thing and people
are going yeah yeah but nope this person was not nope and I felt it it was like it was
like a a weight that pulled me back and made me mindful
and aware and I chose to be careful about
how I engaged and for me I was really visceral
experience it was very powerful because this person said nothing their whole
impact the whole thing they did was to say nothing and I felt it and I was supported by
that it was a beautiful gift to me from us kalyanamita
so that's the story about Sangha I'll share and then
we we can popcorn it or we can go around in the circle and I'll invite should we just go in a circle so it's
predictable yeah Richard would you start would you be willing to share a story
for you that speaks to kalyanamita with the microphone
well to be honest I'm a little reluctant to do so because I just finished Gill's three
week and one of the things that I became very uh
aware of is my tendency to story hmm
and it's not so helpful to me just as honest as I
can about it and
but I can't imagine my life at this point
without the friends who support me in in this
practice and that I support in this practice so I have
countless examples of that you two sitting there is one example
so and this young man am I right we just sat this Retreat together and it
was very very special for me to have him there so
that's about all I'll say right now vows to you Richard thank you
hi my name is Jeff um yeah just coming off retreat
um yeah being at the retreat
with experienced practitioners which yeah um
it was really inspiring there were there were people that just
were so embodied and so they just felt like they were really
Mindful and with their experience and I tend to watch people
and I think I learned from doing that so
um yeah just seeing seeing people on that Retreat I I feel like I learned
from just being in their presence and it was it was a beautiful experience
is this okay beautiful Ben thank you yeah um as I was listening to talk just now
um um I started my mind started wondering
and that
I mean I wouldn't call it an epiphany like I think I always knew it but it kind of solidified it for me
that um all of these teaching
is about it's teaching you teaching me at least I'm learning
how to live better in community with other people
and all of these sitting still
being quiet being observant
it's it's it's not about you
it's about everybody that's that's why
um so Ben and I are married have been married for 30 no yes I don't know some
years 30 some years um we just forgot our anniversary last week
so um but what thank you
and we've been practicing for a few years maybe me a little bit more but both of
us at IMC and I was thinking
how valuable that is that has been more and more every day
and I noticed that driving here tonight we have we're both on this email
chain with with a group of friends one of them is now in Iran and was had
just written a story of what's happening in Iran and she also has her mothers in ICU so she
was kind of reporting on all all events um
and I had responded to her some people just reply to all so you see everybody's
replies there's a group of like 30 of us on there um so we were talking about that
and I started talking maybe not very nicely
about something someone had said he's a writer so he writes beautifully but
I started saying it was a little bit of exaggeration and
what Ben said made me realize what I'm where I'm going and I
stopped and then I thought about how valuable it is that
we're both practicing and we're both I feel like he was helping me
he helped me get reminded of you know what my value is about
being kind even if the person's not hearing it and that keeps happening more and more
these days at home or our conversations or um
I'm so grateful for that I think that's that's a good example of
um our son got home
um so my song story is about somebody that I didn't share a language with
but it's really interesting experience and I like I think about it all the time
um the very first Retreat I went on was at Shasta Abbey like really far the like
north of California um and I went there by myself and I must
have really wanted it it was like five plus hours to get there and it was like a three-day Retreat so I was
basically gonna get right back in the car and as we were practicing
uh it was a silent Retreat we just got to know people if I just got to look looking over the like uh dividers they
had between us kisses like a Zen monastery um in the second we had time
to talk to one another this woman like walked up to me and like brought one of
her friends like they were all part of a group who had tried to go to a different Retreat that had been canceled because of kovid and just kind of hung out a
shot um and she like started talking to me and
like went like this under my chin and like her friend was like she says like
quit looking at the ground you're like always looking down and like never look like never looked down like you like
yeah you're worth always looking up and I was like
it's kind of crazy like it was just I don't know quite a while into the retreat and the
first time we had anything to say it's like like that kind of observation that had such a like profound impact on me and
like I still think about it all the time and yeah we never got to really talk because I didn't speak her language but
it was really special
do you want to say anything more we I I was waiting for Tanya to direct us
yeah I could say I have uh all kinds of stories
we love your stories Diane I don't know about that but uh
um so years ago Gil used to do Dharma
practice days here maybe some of you have been to them and that was like a
day long and it would include small groups and guided meditation and talks a lot of what we do online but it was in
person and a friend of mine that I had met here
and that you guys know very well also that um
he said Diana you should come to these Derma practice days they're really great and you learn a lot and you get to
meditate and you can meet other people and I was like oh my goodness I don't want to go to something like that
but uh he's I was like just afraid like in these small groups like what am I gonna say I don't know why this would
just be sounded scary to me horrifying or something and he said I'll go I
actually I think I asked him will you be in every single one of these little groups with me
and he said yes so I sat next to him and then when every time we had to make small groups that I dragged him along
you know great day I learned a lot and this
really kind of kick-started my Dharma practice to to practice in community with other people and to hear how other
people were understanding right in small groups we kind of talk about different ideas and just the whole world opened up
like oh not everybody thinks exactly the same way I do and this I don't know just I feel so
touched by this person who said Diana you really should come to Dharma practice days and what a
big impact that had on me and his willingness to get into every group with me after that it was fine but uh so
that's one of my stories that's a great story
so I'll invite us to go around the circle one more time
and I'll give you um a couple options invitations
one is you could share what you're noticing what you've been noticing when you've
been mindful of speaking as you speak or listening as you are listening anything
that's you're kind of coming up for you as you're aware of it as a practice
so you could share about that if that feels right
or if you have another Sangha story you would like to share or
you could if you have a question about Sangha this Sangha or Sangha in general
you could ask a question and we can see what the group response
is so does that does that give you each something feel great okay Richard do you
feel there's a mic right there too is it not on okay
okay thanks
um
I'm pretty pretty aware of
really not wanting to talk too much right now um
very very enjoy hearing other people
right now just listening to what's going on um
I think I have uh peeled away certain levels or layers of
armor that I think this culture has a tendency to build up through different
ways distracting and
foreign
I'm feeling a lot of emotion right now more than I typically do through my
normal life prior to sitting The Retreat so it's
there's a fragility in my emotions right now that is uh
not common so that's what I noticed
so I think well I've been trying to practice with
um just trying to stay in my body um it's quite difficult but
um yeah when when talking um
I try to try to stay with my breath and also when listening to others
um yeah just go back to the breath and I notice it
it really helps me get out of like if I'm like being judgmental or having like
a view or an opinion it just helps me um
yeah just kind of drop back and um I don't know like feel more compassion
or um calm or yeah so
um um
the the only story that comes to mind for me right now is uh
um
because of what's happening in Iran I get up in the morning first thing I do
I check all the news feeds Twitter this and that to see what happened
and then I know I'm not supposed to do that before I admit it I just get up like 5 30 6
o'clock I did I just gotta I just gotta see what just happened overnight in Iran
and then I think it was Monday I was sitting
there listening to Gil and I was looking at my iPad with all of these like three
four hundred people on it and I was thinking
why I couldn't be like this
why couldn't it be just like this it's very simple
why why are we doing this to each other why what why are we doing this to each
other Iran yeah yeah yeah yeah I mean we all have our own excuses why but yeah
and I was just thinking
if we just did nothing how much energy we would have saved now
what we could have done with it all of us I mean I think my small way is
somebody's big way but uh I don't know I'm an engineer I
always think about entropy entropy there's a lot of entropy
and I saddens me Henry yeah thank you Ben
I had a question but I about
um community and how
during our life it changes even without a practice like
this it kind of changes as we change
you know and I um I have a hard time with um
thank you I don't have a hard time with with knowing what I'm what how my needs have
changed and what I want in a community of close friends
but I have a hard time making that change
I don't know if that's clear I
I think if I could just be myself
if it was just me and I would just leave this place and go somewhere and start
all over again it would be easier but you know I'm not gonna do that obviously
so I don't know if there's any suggestions or you did say about community that um
to look be Beyond all our judgments and all ours
you know biases and what all the surface things where I do agree
that we're all all the same
but um when you are
I don't I don't know if I five if that's enough for you to know what I'm talking about or should I go on
I can try and respond and see what happens I really appreciate what you're bringing
up Mitra a lot about um you know maybe if when we have a group
of people that we've known and then we come to the practice and we start to change how we want to show up
um that group doesn't necessarily change right
um and if you think about gossip as a simple you know but super common way people
actually tend to relate and connect so if you think if I think about that as just a simple example
um I think a couple things come to mind one is
um you know the story I told is kind of
about that and it did change me feeling the other person right but that's because I was
inclined that way and it makes me think about the story tick knock on tells about
refugees on a boat where um
you know the refugees that were coming right leaving Cambodia going on these
boats and small boats all these people in these boats and Pirates would come pillage and rape and worse
and the stories that take not Han would hear about and
what he would say is that all it took was one person on that boat
who stayed grounded equanimous mindful
and it could save the whole boat or most the people on the boat because of
everybody gets on fire emotionally
about capsize people jump over people do irrational things but one person is
enough to save a whole boat of people
so that's the second thing that comes to mind
foreign that person needs to be far along further along than I am
in the practice you know um
so let me tell you about a story somebody was sharing with me about something that they did which was
to go and sit and not speak when they were in a difficult situation
and they just sat there and they even cried because it was so hard but they
were determined and by that action many people weren't harmed
and I think that's where I am right now at this stage I I see the harm
um and I don't for the most part I don't participate in it
I hear it and I don't like it and also another thing I'm saying I'm starting to
notice is that I'm not I'm not hating it as much you know I'm
not um judging it as much either I'm a little
softer on like you know I I notice it but I
don't feel like oh my God I'm so much better than that um so that's not really making another
yeah and not necessarily having to make yourself into something better or yeah
yeah and I see that that that's happening and that's a great thing to happen I think the other but my point my
dilemma is that time is so limited and um
we only have time for a few things in our life in our day so
to choose some things really have to go and
choose that is sometimes difficult when you're already have established you
know 30 40 50 year relationships and but yeah that's something I mean I I
think I need to keep working on myself
foreign
I guess I I have elected the song a story
two option um so my song story is actually the story
of two sanghas um since I uh I started
coming here to IMC and to Canada and uh Mountain View a couple months back
like basically right after I had like gotten out of the hospital and like fit
in Courage by like a chaplain to like receiving spirituality and is that a
particularly like difficult time in my life and I was very much alone and like since
I've been coming to IMC and over to Canada um
I've definitely felt more like I'm part of something and it it matters like deeply to me it's
something I and get really excited about like glad to
get my time so song has made like a huge difference for me even if I'm
not necessarily like talking about like Dharma friends and like giving you the Dharma sense of it
uh yeah that's been good for me
thank you for sharing so if what would you like should I speak
to or what would be best Tanya or
um for you to check in and still was right and we have this piece of paper that has
this little schedule yeah there's a schedule and there's guided meditation that you were going to do and so I think
you can decide um how much time you want to spend with that versus how much time you want to
share and and reflect and when and how I'd like to share a little story
great just kind of a really short one this was a long time ago
I don't know 15 20 years ago maybe I don't remember exactly how long but where somebody said
something that uh really had a big difference for the way that I kind of
understood how I was showing up in a way that I hadn't really noticed before and uh this person
talked about she used this expression bonding through mutual outrage
maybe it was something like that and and I hadn't really noticed how this is at
that now it's pretty obvious but at that time I hadn't noticed how people myself
included at that time would get together and like oh that terrible thing or that
terrible person and like and this and then did you hear about this and then this and then this and somehow kind of
like this good feeling like okay well we're not that person but then so I don't know it started to feel like it
just didn't quite feel so good as soon as that got highlighted for me I started to notice oh this is sometimes the way
that we bond with each other is to complain or something about something
else and I don't know that had a big impact on me when I said I'm gonna try not to
do that anymore and maybe that speaks a little bit to what you're this othering that you've been talking about
and I know when I there was a time when I worked in Corporate America and you know there was this was something that
we would do literally like around the water cooler is complain about that person in that department and can you
believe it and you know this kind of stuff so I don't know that that I still think
about and even today like with the way kind of social media at that time right
social media didn't really have a role on the news cycle everything is all about this
bonding through mutual outrage I don't is that the right expression but whatever it is so
I don't know just this story that had a big impact on me to see how
we like to do that it turns out not to be so helpful always did you did you say the word outrage or
Outreach oh outrage anger outrage yeah
okay so maybe we'll do a little guided meditation
that's good to me so this idea of
kaliana Mita and Sangha and practicing together is
a way of you know about connection and and there's so many different ways we
can have connection we can be you know literally touching
somebody or maybe it's just softening that which is inside us that is maybe
um Making Connections a little bit more difficult
and so I'd like to do a little bit of loving kindness meditation because I
find that this really can help soften kind of our inner experience
[Applause] I keep on looking at this uh schedule
I'm a little bit confused about okay here we go
so just arriving this moment
take in the posture that feels comfortable comfortable enough
for the next little while we won't be here for too
long checking in with the body
connecting with the body feeling where the body
rests on the chair or the cushion feeling the pressure against the body
feeling the feet on the ground we're connected we're here
this location
and having this sitting posture and just to know that we're sitting
how does the body feel in this posture
connecting with the breath
connecting with the sensations of breathing
right now there's nowhere else to be and nothing else to
do we're just here
with the sensations of breathing
and then to begin our loving kindness practice
bring to mind a lovable being
the most lovable uncomplicated straightforward
for many people these might be kittens that they see on internet videos
something that kind of just makes you smile and in a warm-hearted way
maybe there's a teacher or author that has touched you
maybe there's somebody in your life that you have a relationship with whomever
bringing this really lovable being somebody for whom it's straightforward
to have a sense of warmth or care for
and and any way that makes sense for you to
connect with this lovable being
might be by bringing an image of this lovable being
can even be an imaginary it doesn't have to be an actual being
or maybe there's a way in which the Heart Center a little bit of a radiation and
connection
and as a support for this connection and cultivation of
warm-heartedness can say these phrases
you're welcome to modify these phrases there's nothing magical about these particular words
a simple wish warm-hearted wish for another
may you be safe
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you live with ease
may you be safe
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you live with ease
just keeping us simple
with warm-hearted wishes for this lovable being
connecting with this lovable being
just allowing ourselves to feel the warmth or feel the care
and it's perfectly fine if you don't feel anything in particular that's okay
to but if you do allow yourself to be supported nourished
by this feeling of warmth respect care love Goodwill benevolence
for this lovable being
and then to expand our loving kindness to include ourselves
of course of course we do loving kindness for ourselves
so in the same way that we have this warmth and care for
the lovable being can we stretch or expand that
to include ourselves
may I be safe
may I be happy
may I be healthy
may I live with ease
and then can be really helpful really supportive
do a little bit of equanimity practice
for this practice bring to mind somebody who's a little bit troubling or
Troublesome for you bothersome or annoying
on a scale of one to ten choose somebody that's like a two or a
three just sometimes a little bit irksome
bring this person to mind somebody that you care about
and we can say this phrase I wish you happiness
and I cannot make your choices for you
I wish you happiness and I cannot make your choices for you
I wish you a happiness and I cannot make your choices for you
[Music]
this idea of loving kindness practice is a support
for Sangha for kalyanami does it's important to like soften maybe
Tanya talked about sulfane and othering to soften that but also for us to have
some care for ourselves it's so important but not in the way in which we're
willing to like sacrifice ourselves or tried to control other people or not set
boundaries or those kinds of things so it can be helpful to also do some
Equanimity practice as a support for that and then maybe we'll just open it up for
some last questions or comments see if anybody has some
anything you'd like to share about that meditation or about this topic of Sangha
or this idea of let's talk about practice or something like that and if
there's any comment on YouTube we can reflect or hear read that as well
um
I just I think this was so sweet thank you it was it was very nice just I mean
very sweet to just be here with you guys in this way tonight so thank you it's for me I love that we're talking about
Saga and we created this great great little group here and it makes me happy kind of at this it's very nice
any anybody want to make any comments because it's not needed but if you want to say anything more Ben Jeff anything
you want to say before we end
great
um I I had this idea maybe we could dedicate the Merit tonight and
um I would like to wherever our microphone is Let each person name whatever
beings people issues they want to be included in the
dedication of the Merit of our time together
I think it's it's funny I don't I don't know if this one's and then sage has the second one
um
maybe you'll start Jeff okay
yeah I'd like to dedicate this to all beings everywhere and especially
those that are suffering
I mean I I can't imagine or I would like to educate to accept to exactly what he
said to all of us and everybody who's suffering uh but there's a hell of a lot of it
going on
um there's a 22 year old woman who was killed among thousands of people that
get killed every day in Iran her name is maso amini and
what's been going on around the world is they're calling her name not just
her name not just to that particular person but they're calling it for
everyone who's suffering and everyone who's being
yeah so her name thank you can can you say her name again
thank you so I just want to say one thing that I don't know whether you know the
the slogans of this movement in Iran it's three words
I mean say them again son can you say them and translate that yeah of course
assign means women right zandigi means life yeah it means freedom
what was Freedom right I was already Freedom yeah that's it
that's all there is wow and I just and this woman inspired
Sage would you like to
um sure I'd like to dedicate the Merit of our practice to
incarcerated people by how people may our beings be free
and
maybe I'll just say all beings and maybe I'll just add a little relish flourish
on it without exception all beings without exception
and then will you do the
do you want to add anything Jordan
thank you [Music]
about around water cooler what happened
oh outrage bonding through mutual outrage
ously
[Laughter] so much as social media is all about
that right and so yeah yeah
okay well thank you thank you all for your practice and for coming here and
sharing this with us I won't be here next week but um I look forward to being here on third week
three and week four so I'll see you then