so good morning everyone and welcome to imc it's great to be with you all
um just a friendly reminder if you have a cell phone or anything else that makes noise kindly silence it or turn it
completely off thank you and uh most of you know that this center runs
totally by donation everything every one here is is
offering the donna freely at their own expense to get here so uh
if you're inclined to donate to either the cent the operations or the teacher
there's a donation box with the teacher's name near the front door there's an electronic kiosk
next to the library door and you can donate online as well so
we're happy to have matthew brent silver here this morning read his bio
matthew ben silver phd is a member of the guiding teachers executive committee
and the teacher's counsel at spirit rock meditation center he previously served as program director
for mindful schools and for more than a decade was core teacher at against the
stream buddhist meditation society he lectures at ucla's mindful awareness
research center about the intersections between mindfulness and mental health
before committing to teach meditation full time he spent years doing research
on addiction pharmacotherapy at the ucla center for behavioral and
addiction medicine and is interested in the unfolding dialogue between dharma and science
matthew is the co-author of two forthcoming books on meditation during adolescence
good morning matthew thank you martha thank you
thanks for having me thanks for the uh warm welcome um is this sound good yeah
okay thanks good yeah all right um
so uh yeah we'll sit i'll uh sort of lightly lightly guide us till the top of
the hour and uh then offer offer a talk
uh
so
like a nectar falling to the bottom of a glass of juice
we settle says take that on
and sometimes it's skillful to
stop right on a dime to begin implementing a very concrete
technique
to specify precisely where the attention is directed
and other times
a certain kind of openness just to see
how the nectar needs to settle
to see what needs attention what needs patience what needs love
and to breathe and arrive
so
just let everything remind you of the dharma
just forgive all phenomena
and rest
so
just forgiving thought and sensation and affect and sound
unentangled
so
marshalling the attention the spotlight of attention
takes a little bit of energy nothing wrong with
expending energy effort on this path
but then sometimes useful
to see what is effortless about awareness
dimension of awareness that you [Music]
can't stop don't need to direct
requires no effort to prop up
and we just rest there
so
this
so though the way i've uh approached dharma practice is less less
of the dharma as a set of answers and more as a kind of open question a method of inquiry
and talk is in that spirit
so many people these days seem kind of
ragged and
and people who care about other people seem especially
ragged weary
and the pace of the news seems uh
unrelenting unsustainable you know for a lot of people emotionally
and there's a sense and we're always warned against this sense when we have it in a moment of
meditation but there's a sense maybe deluded like it's hard to imagine
it getting better kind of you know there's some sense of like all these different karmic streams
converging in ways that make it hard to imagine feeling a lot lighter at least
and i was thinking just like there's a kind
of consumer confidence index you know of
like sort of economic expectations and attitudes among the public and what do
you think about interest rates or something what do you you know what are your buying intentions
um it's also kind of like a
humanity confidence index and um
our humanity confidence index right now is like kind of shaky
and there's a sense that we
maybe can't keep going the way we've been going
and uh we've been mining the world
the earth and now mining ourselves so this is a
kind of a notable quote from uh justin rosenstein tech
kind of founder who's concerned about
about these things he said we live in a world
in which a tree is worth more financially dead than alive
in a world in which a whale is worth more dead than alive
for so long as our our economy works in that way and
corporations aren't regulated they're going to continue to destroy trees to
kill wells to mine the earth and to continue to pull oil out of the ground
even though we know it's destroying the planet and we know it's going to leave a worse world for future generations
this is short-term thinking based on the religion of profit and all costs as if
somehow magically each corporation acting in its selfish
interest is going to produce the best result this has been affecting the environment
for a long time what's frightening and what hopefully is the last straw
that will wake us up as a civilization to how flawed this theory has been in the first place
is to see that now we're the tree we're the whale
our attention can be mined we are more profitable
to a corporation if we're spending time staring at a screen staring at an ad than if we're spending time living our
life in a rich way and so we're seeing the results of that we're seeing
corporations using powerful artificial intelligence to outsmart us and figure
out how to pull our attention towards the things they want us to look at
rather than the things that are most consistent with our goals and our values and our lives
at some point in in life we realized that the the kind of time
left we have the time left is
is less than what we've already lived and
can feel the same for societies you know like
have we hit a kind of apex point and feel like we're
in descent is this particular
generation the unique extraordinary fortunate and unfortunate inflection
point or is that just
the vanity and grandiosity of our generation
because um just like every person thinks they're special every generation
thinks it's special so maybe we're just being seduced into a certain
kind of grandiosity of this as a kind of inflection point
but it for people who care about people
it's intense and uh
of course i'm thinking about row and i'm thinking just more generally about the ascendancy of and the the way that greed
aversion delusion are dignified culture wide
there is a moment this is september 2020 and um
george george floyd was was killed may
25th and um a very dangerous
as is still an unstable political situation
and there were fires there was a fire big fire down outside fresno somewhere
and then up north and the air on the ground was okay
the air on the ground was good actually but whatever the atmospheric conditions
maybe you remember this day the atmospheric conditions were such that the the smoke was held
you know real high and had this like wild distorting effect on the light and
it was like dark in the middle of the day an orange
and that day i was at a buddhist teacher meeting on zoom as we all were
on zoom then i was at a buddhist teacher meeting
and it was grim yeah
very painful day and and there's a certain kind of collapse
that happens in the mind when
like the badness the different kind of points of pain in the body politic and
the world do not add up together they they're sort
of synergistic they mul it's not badness plus badness but blindness it's like
madness multiplied by badness multiplied again
and it's a distinctive phenomenology you know like that sense of the collapse of
the mind this kind of inward heart collapse and um
and there's no no space yeah zen master said hell
is no space
and two days after that i gave a meeting and then i gave a
a talk on the 19th anniversary of september
11th and normally that group is about
i don't know 125 people and it was double that that
day yeah and um and i talked about love
you know just holding on
i thought of the the tom waits song hold on
lyrics um down by the riverside motel it's 10 below and falling
by a 99 cent store she closed her eyes and started swaying
but it's so hard to dance that way when it's cold and there's no music
oh your hometown's so far away but inside your head there's a record that's
playing a song called hold on
hold on babe you gotta hold on take my hand i'm standing right here
you gotta hold on
one of the things that happens in moments like like that is a kind of collapse into a certain kind of nihilism
or desperation frenzy
and the buddha warned against nihilism felt like it was
though that was a consequence there was a potential risk
of opening to the contingency of all things
and maybe we intuitively know that it's not satisfying for our heart yeah it's
like once we've we've seen the kind of
poignancy of the human condition it's very it's hard to just
devolve into nihilism so then we want to act we move into the
more frenzy desperate mode but are almost immediately confronted with our
own nearly complete helplessness
maybe maybe suffering dukkha and helplessness are
kind of synonyms almost
i read that um you know people cry for many reasons but one of the reasons we
cry is is from a sense of helplessness
and there are tears being a kind of plea
a social plea saying something like i i need you
but now we cry for others and often feels like
no one's coming and all of this all of this this
portrait i'm painting can scramble us and
there's a kind of fire hose of negative affect you know that sense of just
spraying of negative affect in all directions
and then enter twitter
and kind of just like just grappling scrambling to try to find
a view that's satisfying to try to find an outlet for this fire hose of negative affect
and all of this can undercut faith and dhamma in the path
it makes us wonder maybe in moments isn't maybe it's not such a meaningful thing
or maybe it makes us wonder like is it self-indulgent to even care how i'm
doing is it's self-indulgent to even try to potentiate my well-being
to fiddle with the nuances of my own suffering as the world
burns and so we can get into this mode of
practicing where we're kind of trying to save ourselves and kind of trying to save the world and it's a form of
multitasking and practice is not
does not flourish when we're multitasking in it
and so we're stuck
so what to do and this of course is uh where i'm
supposed to pivot and give you answers
your laughter conveys to me that you know i don't have them you know
yeah but um it's worth interrogating the the view
that you know fosters the dilemma i i laid
out and to make a few suggestions
now um i'm always cautious about anything that actually
blunts the the force of what i've just shared i'm a little cautious because
sometimes the depth of that pain you sort of just want to
wiggle out of it in whatever way we can with kind of
vague platitudes or palliative measures and thoughts that just to help us
takes the edge off the intensity of the need and suffering
and then i'm very conscious of
my own [Music] fortune privilege social location as i
anytime i talk about progress i'm very conscious of that because
it can to talk of progress is can seem like it is uh diminishing
the meaning of the existing suffering yeah
the enormity of the suffering and so that that's an important
caveat but but many many things are getting better
and not to see that not to attune to that is its own kind of delusion
and so the global burden of disease
or the trends over the recent decades of human rights internationally
trends in terms of of of violence and um
trends in terms of uh extreme poverty
it's it's it costs more now to save a life than it did it's the cost is going
up and that's actually good news right because to actually intervene
in a way to save a life that otherwise would somebody would have died it costs more
because fewer people are dying needlessly
through that could be prevented through very basic interventions this is a good
thing that it costs more to save a life now
and so this perception that everything is always getting worse is is not
is not right and that's an important corrective to
us attuning to the kind of enormity of dukkha
um some researchers told you wheatley and dan gilbert and colleagues said um
did a series of studies where they they described a phenomena where when the
instances of badness grow less common
the concept of badness expands becomes more prominent
as there's a decreasingly less gross
yucky context the examples of badness become more prominent
so they write many organizations institutions are dedicated to identifying and reducing
the prevalence of social problems but our studies suggest that even well-meaning
agents may sometimes fail to recognize the success of their efforts simply
because they view each new instance in the decreasingly problematic context
that they themselves have brought about although modern societies have made extraordinary progress in solving a wide
range of social problems from poverty and illiteracy to violence and infant
mortality the majority of people believe that the world is getting worse
the fact that concepts grow larger when their instances grow smaller
may be one source of that pessimism
so we attune we attune to this yeah
and not just because um to to blunt the pain of the reality of
dukkha but because uh to not know that uh fosters its own kind of delusion as i
said
and with all that said you know i'm kind of pivoting between depressing uplifting
and we're making another pivot here
all the positive trends yeah that have enumerated that you can see in the data
that are very striking when you look at the data they are threatened by larger risks
and as i was starting like you know i was
saying like every generation think every generation thinks it's special you know like you always hear like oh
back when i you know or whatever things now or what you know
all these things right and so there is there is a certain kind of yeah like uh grandiosity generational
grandiosity that mirrors the egoic process of an individual
and so i'm generally skeptical of like pivotal moments hinge points you know
but but these couple generations may actually be that yeah
this is um toby award the threats to humanity and how we
address them define our time the advent of nuclear weapons posed a
real risk to human extinction in the 20th century the continued acceleration of technology
and without serious efforts to protect humanity there's strong reason to believe that the risk will be higher
this century and increasing with each century that technological progress continues
because these human generated risks outstrip all natural risks combined
they set the clock on how long humanity has left to pull back from the brink
i'm not claiming that extinction's the inevitable conclusion of scientific progress or even the most likely outcome
what i am claiming is there's been a robust trend towards increases in the power of humanity
which has reached a point where we pose a serious risk to our own existence
recognizing goes on to say recognizing that people matter equally wherever they
are in time is a crucial next step in the ongoing story
of humanity's moral progress our own generation is but one page
in a much larger longer story and that our most important role may be
how we shape or fail to shape that story this approach is animated by a moral
reorientation toward the vast future that existential risks threaten
to foreclose
he suggested that um humanity is is maybe in its kind of like
adolescent phase where we have a lot
of power and aren't sure what to do with it yeah a lot of
of power but are naive in important ways and adolescents like adolescent health
adolescents are like peak physical health and yet die
at much higher rates than you would expect
a sense of like yeah we're playing with fire that that does seem to me not to be
catastrophizing that seems real like and to worry
to worry is not unreasonable
and so amidst the vastness of suffering and the possibilities of the future like
what stance will i take what does this mean for my heart
how do i want to be informed by this moment
and we bump up against the the the kind of blessings and consolation of dharma
and the the limitations of dharma
and for us often say for for some forms of of dis-ease
the dharma seems to me like the only medicine there is for certain kinds
forms of suffering i can't imagine any medicine being adequate treatment
but that doesn't mean that the dharma is the medicine for all forms of dis-ease
in other words dukkha is an interdisciplinary problem
yeah and in a way if we expect dharma to
answer all species of suffering it may fail to answer those species it
can
and so we look to all the wisdom of the world
all the wisdom of the world to science and art and philosophy and
movement building and philanthropy and all of it
now as i engage with the world you know i want my suffering to be efficient
i'm willing to suffer to engage to avoid
the deadness of apathy or nihilism or whatever i'm willing to suffer i'm
willing to enter the public sphere and suffer
yeah but i want that suffering to be efficient i don't want to waste it
and as i look back on my life there are some patches of suffering that
seem totally necessary and onward leading and
important and generative is like oh yeah i had to suffer in those
ways and i know there are ways in the future that i will need to suffer that will be
the redemptive form of suffering the onward leading form of suffering and
i can also look back on my life maybe anybody can and see
patches and strands threads of suffering
that appear almost utterly meaningless and cyclical
and unnecessary unnecessary
it just didn't lead anywhere it didn't accomplish anything it was just me
circling in some kind of little vortex of confusion and pain and not knowing how
to break the kind of break it
and so we have to part of our dharma practice is becoming connoisseurs of our
suffering yeah and spending it wisely
engaging in ways that like we're suffering efficiently
not cyclically not uselessly
and so we consent to some measure of suffering we're not giving up on samsara
and we're we're also not we're careful not to suffer meaninglessly
and so i think of this to some extent in how we engage with media news
like what aspects of that engagement are like redemptive
important suffering and what parts are just kind of have that that cyclical
like just spinning the wheel of samsara feeling
and this is a place to inquire and to look like what am i doing to my mind
is it useful what can i actually open to what do i have to like blunt myself from
feeling because i'm so overexposed
and it's just this sense you know like when i actually read the paper you know it's like i don't you know my nervous
system like isn't really equipped to open to the enormity of suffering
of samsara all the time yeah and what does that do when i like
kind of open and kind of close to it
so we're careful in how we dose this how we dose our
the information but um we also find something to do
that anxiety needs to be bound you know it needs to
be bound to action you know that's that's part of what actually
um that's that's that's part of this picture in to my mind
and so some of the kind of compulsivity about news is a function of our sense of our
own powerlessness and it's like well okay if i'm completely powerless at least i can just
keep consuming that or something or speaking about that
and instead it's like no we just do something we find efficient ways to spend our hard
to spend our suffering to consent to some measure of suffering and engage
hopefully in efficient ways
and so we we
are called at times to give to give until it hurts time or money or effort
or something we actually like it it's a practice of
of like get and this is giving till it hurts this is not like some incredibly
mercenary manipulation to try to get donna from you by the way
i'm not a psychopath you know but no it's like we give until
it hurts you know and and it's like we sometimes we're in this
mode of like half compassion half equanimity and my experience it's like no no no a
hundred percent compassion and then a hundred percent equanimity
it's like we give and then we really rest we really firewall some parts of our life
and we really rest otherwise it's like this half open heart half equanimous you know kind of
sense of like recognizing are the limitations of our own wishes to control
samsara and that half equanimity half compassion is its own kind of fatigue
and so we we really [Music]
give we try to serve in ways that are meaningful even in the face of the enormity of
suffering we try to serve in ways that are meaningful and then we rest and we really rest
i think of the dharma primarily as a as a technology of freeing our own heart
bring our own heart of greeting delusion i think there are other
traditions of wisdom that are relevant for change at a collective level
nevertheless our dharma practice is relevant it endows us with skills that
are powerful for engaging the dukkha of the world
we we learn we learn to truly care about suffering
for the earth shattering poignancy of that to rain
down on us and just that
closes the kind of distance that we might imagine between ourselves
and someone on the other side of the world or ourself and someone in the distant future
the circle of uh of empathy yeah widens widens we know
we know how deeply we share the longing to be free from suffering
that is like in the bones that's in our bones
and we learn how to grieve well which is indispensable if we're too open
to suffering and to engage it if we don't know how to like open to the
rhythms of grieving and the the prospect of loss
the reality the inevitability of loss we get spun in many ways
we cultivate a deep patience a deep patience that these are multi-generational efforts
the parame of patience
we're learning to drain a egoic investment from our views
the ways in which our views become charged with egoic energy
and we think our self-righteousness makes us more persuasive but it makes us much much less
it makes us much less it is a form of clinging yeah
and so we can actually sense the moral force of
a view that is enunciated without clinging
and we're coming to terms with death
that is so crucial part of our practice
i'm part of uh i feel maybe a prerequisite actually for
engaging with the broader world of dukkha as a
constellation societal level because
when we have no freedom around our own death it distorts our engagement in many ways
it's like our own death is uh
it's mara's ultimate trump card yeah
and camus said something like make peace with death after that
anything is possible yeah
and so in this realm so much delusion so much
kind of fear and manipulation arises out of our own incomplete
relationship with mortality with the changingness the the loss of all things
and so we
find a way to serve we let go of suffering that is inefficient
and we rest
it seems like a good enough life to me
sit for a minute
so
now offer offer these thoughts for your consideration yeah
and uh it's an idiosyncratic path and um
you have to determine what to um what is useful what to pick up and consider
investigate and what to leave behind
yeah so thank you i appreciate the opportunity to uh
ask some of these questions together yeah they uh
may we live well you know thank you