okay good morning or day or evening
why don't we go ahead and get started for today so we'll begin uh meditating together
so please settle into your meditation posture
maybe just taking a moment to really feel the body and arrive at this place
front of your computer or phone or tablet Wherever You Are and just have a sense that you're here
and you're now joining this we can release whatever we were doing to get here
if possible letting go of things you're thinking about for later
today or things that happened earlier today
things you need to do or want to say
or just having a sense of being here with your mind and body as they are
if you're comfortable doing so or you can close your eyes
feel into the sense of the body sitting or standing or lying down whatever
posture you're in and we want to find some kind of balance
in the body when the body is stable and balanced
then that supports that same thing in the mind
so paying some attention to the position of
the head over the Torso
the shoulders balanced and soft
and poised over the hips
the place where you're sitting the body rising up straight from that
and generally softening when we have places of tension then we
can't as easily find a Natural Balance because things are being held
so softening the jaw the neck
shoulders down through the arms and hands
softening the belly and the low back
down into the legs and feet
so allowing the straightness of the central part of the
body to just be holding the rest which can
soften around it
connecting in with a simple object in the present moment such as the sensations of the breath
over the general sensations of the body
more sounds something simple that we can use as a
home base for attention
just inviting ease
in the body and the mind
this is a way of just letting go what's right at the surface and is willing to
let go we're not trying to make anything happen or judge that certain things shouldn't
be there we just invite some degree of ease
and then I'd like to suggest a certain form of practice
that you could try out or do this morning or whatever time of day it is
and if it doesn't work for you that's okay
I'd like to suggest What's called the noting practice or labeling
where when we feel or sense something in our
body and mind we have a gentle one word note of what it is so it
connects us to experience so for example
we might feel warmth and then the next Movement we notice
that you've heard my voice so the note is hearing
and then there's a thought coming through so it's thinking
notes are very simple just expressions of what's happening and
doesn't have to be different every moment you could be noting pressure
if your attention is lingering at the place where you're sitting for example
so it's very meant to be very easy a way of engaging part of the thinking mind
such that it's not running off the important thing about notes is not
to get hung up on them you make a note and then you wonder was
that the right note or you puzzle over what was that how
should I note that that's already it's already gone on the moment has
already moved on so make a simple note or if you can't think of one you can
just say something is an acceptable note
um the only note that I was not encouraged
to use is pain because pain is
abstract it's a concept and so we would look for something more
accurate and more visceral like hoeing or tension or heat
were stabbing something that conveys the feeling
Okay so what this does is it helps the mind to be clear
connected simply to what is happening
I'll have a little more to say in a moment but just try it out for a few minutes
foreign that
you put about 90 percent of your attention on the actual experience
and 10 or maybe even only five percent on the Note
so it's very light this is not an exercise in
meaning it's just keeping the Mind connected
as we notice how the mind is doing the noting
practice one of the things that we can notice
is the tone of voice with which we are noting
so is there some subtle judgment in the note is there some subtle wanting
climbing toward favoring things that are peaceful or
pointing out things that shouldn't be there it's interesting to hear which voice is
doing the noting and if so that's one more thing to note about judgment is
happening
it's particularly helpful when we can begin to gain some facility
and noting you know emotions and thoughts
so being able to Simply say sadness anger
or joy helps us to not be so reactive
to those response when they're happening
and also forms of thought like planning or remembering
we can just say thinking for all of them but sometimes there's a differentiation
into types of thought and again that makes it
less likely that will get on the train and go along with
them
but again keeping 90 to 95 percent of attention on the actual experience
foreign
worth noting is just one form of practice but I find that
it helps my mind to be deeply honest about what is happening in my own
experience and practice evolves
I think only when we are deeply honest about what's actually happening
when we have that level of honesty with ourselves then we become trustworthy
stewards of Our Own Heart and our own practice what's really only safe if we can be
really open about everything that's coming in the body and the mind
so we'll sit in silence for a while now and I'll invite you to either continue with
the noting if that was working or to move on to
whatever other practice you have but whatever you do to have a commitment
to being very honest about what's going on it's all fine
just as you sit here with the body and mind as they are
foreign
that seeing is loving
part of what love is is to really see
someone or something as it is to just be with that
so there's a way in which this deep honesty about
what's really happening in mind and body is a form of loving and hence healing
all the parts of our being so rest for a few minutes in the sense
of care that is present in this kind of
clear honesty
foreign
you know this simple honesty that we cultivate on the cushion
can serve us out in the world also the degree to which we have
the inner capacity to know our own feelings and responses and
thoughts that are coming up as we go throughout the day those help us to respond well
we won't say or act on everything that is coming up in ourselves
you know as we talk with someone else we have all kinds of our own feelings and
responses if we have enough mindfulness we can know those
take them in as data um and then choose
how to respond clearly and carefully to this other person
but if somehow we aren't willing to see everything that's coming up in us if we're blocking some
of our own experience that will distort a little bit how we interact with people
of course we all do that to some degree because we're not 100 able to see our
minds usually but we do our best and this is an inner form of ethics
and the more that we can be clear about our own experience then
the more straightforward and clearly we can walk through the world and that helps everyone
it also models for other people a direct and simple
and virtuous way of being
so may our practice support over more inner Clarity and
outer straightforwardness
foreign
[Music]
this week the theme is called meeting life well
I've Dharma resources and this is to meet life well both on
and off the cushion so we're talking about five qualities
upon which the heart draws in order to meet situations whether they are Duca
type situations challenging suffering or whether they're What's called nosuka
the opposite Suka type situations of happiness or ease or appreciation
and today we are moving on to the second one
which is virtue or ethical conduct you can choose the term within that realm
that works for you the poly word is uh Selah
Sila and
there's some classical language around this from the sutas so I'll just read it
the Buddha says here a noble disciple abstains from the destruction of life
abstains from taking what is not given abstains from sexual misconduct abstains
from false speech abstains from liquor wine and intoxicants the basis for
heedlessness so you can recognize these as I think the I think you can recognize them as
the classical language of the five precepts of not killing not stealing not
sexual misconduct not lying not intoxicating the mind or the body
so typically lay people would try to live by these principles
it's an interesting question though why why we are following the precepts or
some kind of ethical conduct in the world and you know some people do so I think
without too much reflection or experiential understanding of what is
going on with virtue or silo uh and and in cases like that
you know it's just following rules then so the encouragement we have here is to
view Selah as a practice and to actually investigate what is going on and you
know I'm sure at a top level we've all can see that it feels better and goes
better in our life when we you know engage in these kinds of behaviors but
there's even more to discover if we investigate what's going on with
uh living by these particular actions and it might be that until we do some
kind of Investigation in practice in a formal sense with virtue it may not go
deeply enough into the heart to serve as what I'm calling a Dharma resource this week which means something that we can
rely on to come forth when we meet the world especially if we meet a
challenging situation we want that sense of virtue and
understanding of ethical conduct to be rooted deeply enough that it's just what counts for
um so what happens when we do some investigation one thing that we'll discover is that
acting ethically is more compatible with mindfulness than acting unethically
wholesomeness is pretty easily compatible with awareness whereas
unwholesomeness has a way of obscuring the Mind in a certain way you can check
this for yourself so let's consider just the area of wise
speech for example so the precept for in particular only
mentions false speech but there are expanded descriptions in other areas of
the sutas and they expand the description of unwise speech to include speech that is false but also that's
divisive or that's harsh or that's meaningless sometimes translated as gossip but I
think it goes beyond that um so we'll discover for ourselves we
can just observe that when we're speaking well it's pretty easy to stay in attention and to stay grounded in the
body and to be relaxed and to be focused on the person that you're speaking to
whereas when we're speaking unwisely you know we're lying at that moment or we're
speaking harshly or you know not really paying attention then our our inner Vision literally gets
kind of occluded in the mind Narrows in and we don't we actually don't Focus as well on the other person I've noticed
that when I've been in situations of somewhat tension with somebody else if I
allow myself to get sucked into a sense of aversion or defensiveness I literally
feel my attention sort of drawing down and I'm not as connected with the other
person this is the effect of of actually an unwholesome pattern in my mind you
know it has this impact so most of us have a mindfulness practice if we're sitting here in the
mornings so that means that we value mindfulness in our life that's something that we're trying to cultivate
so in that case it would make sense that we would also be strengthening virtue in
order to support our ability to be aware you know when I'm mindful even if it is
a tense situation with someone else if the mindfulness is strong enough that in
itself is a wholesome quality and I notice that it's easier to be aware and then if I you know if I can in addition
try to say something kind try to say something honest about how I'm feeling something like that the mindfulness
stays right there and I can stay in my body so virtue and mindfulness are very
connected so this is a deeper reason to practice Selah than just following rules
or just doing it because teacher says it's a good idea or something
so then another discovery that we can make through investigation is that
virtue is a powerful condition for a kind of happiness that endures even when
conditions change so when we're acting and speaking ethically we experience
What's called the Bliss of blamelessness in the texts that doesn't mean that we're a hundred percent perfect but at
least we know that we were present and we did our best and so there's no basis for feeling guilt or shame or
disappointment in ourselves and the world really needs people by the
way who have a genuine positive regard for themselves not the fake positive of
denial or ignoring things but genuinely possessed of well-being and ethics does
this for us so again we have a deeper reason to practice ethics we want to
support this let's say loftier form of Happiness that's better than just just
sensual enjoyment so I want to expand a little bit on this
clear link between mindfulness and ethics one time when I was returning from a
trip I arrived at the airport at night and at that time I lived close to public
transit and I figured on taking the light rail back to my apartment and I
knew that at night the trains only ran about they ran every 30 minutes and when
I arrived at the station the train was there and so I hopped on before the doors closed so I wouldn't have to wait
in the station for half an hour at night but you can't buy tickets on board and
so I was riding without a ticket and I noticed that I felt some mild anxiety about that during the ride but I
did manage to get to my station without the ticket person coming to ask for tickets
so in a sense I got away with it but as I exited the train I noticed that
I still felt some tension even though the anxiety of getting caught was gone
and so I found myself walking to the ticket machine buying a ticket and then
throwing it away so that I I had bought a ticket for that ride I didn't think about that I didn't
plan it out it just felt natural as I got off the train so mindfulness pointed
me toward that particular action and I was willing to follow it to follow the kind of situational ethics of the moment
you know because there was you know there's no one making me do that so meeting life well can mean that when
we're not sure what to do how to manage a complex situation we can default to
whatever develop whatever ability we've developed to serve ethics in the moment
another Buddhist teacher I know calls this serving what is true
so rather than gaming all the nuances and possibilities just be aware be clean
in how you act or speak and accept any consequences of that as better than the
alternative of not paying attention so but what does it mean to be clean in
how we act and speak often we think it means keeping principles in mind right I read the five
precepts so rules to follow we have these rules to follow and then we figure out how to apply them how to follow them
and that's fine that's how we do it a lot of the time but in the moment this might be too slow
we can't take the time to go through the cognitive mind if something is coming right in the moment so we need something
embodied and it has to be strong enough that it can override any reactive emotions that are coming out like anger
or greed or Envy or fear and so how do we train in that
so one way is to trust this connection between mindfulness and doing the right
action or the wise action Joseph Goldstein said it this way see
what you do or we say see what you say in the case of speech as a way of
exploring Selah so this turns things around sometimes from how we often
practice ethics so you know what we usually do is start from the principle and try to practice
doing it so we start from the idea of not speaking falfully and then we willfully try to be true truthful
and that's fine but it can be a little bit forced at times or not spontaneous
enough um so an alternative is to simply speak as we normally do but be very clear and
precise with mindfulness as we do it and if we start straying into speech that
doesn't align with the situation that we're in we'll feel it because we're being mindful
so for example if we're if we're listening to a friend talk about a workshop that they attended and we get
excited because we've also attended a program on the same topic and then we
leap in and we start telling about our knowledge and experience you know we might have assumed that Our intention
was wholesome to connect and say something meaningful with our friend but we can feel in the moment that what
we're really doing is asserting our own knowledge you know the ego has crept in they're saying they did this workshop
and we say oh I know about that too and it's not quite you know it's not quite um it's okay but it's not quite in
tune so we can feel that if we're mindful so feeling in our body and mind can be
more powerful than if we had controlled our speech from a cognitive place
this is something from Ken McLeod who's a teacher in the Tibetan tradition
many people try very hard to always say the right thing there's a common misperception that we
can know how to say the right thing that we can have it in mind and then when we speak the words will come out correctly
this is the common idea of right speech and most of us fail at it over and over
again the words don't come out as we thought they would or if they do the tone of voice is wrong or something else
happens it rarely goes as we planned that's the point we cannot plan the
future we cannot plan our speech any more than we can plan our next thought
how then are we to practice right speech the most effective effort is to listen
to ourselves as we are talking this effort brings attention to our speech
when we do this we will hear when what we say doesn't fit the situation when it isn't what we intended to say or how we
intend it to say it we will hear with our own ears the different emotional patterns that take over our speech
we will hear how what we say doesn't fit with our intention or how it comes out of our confusion
and when we make this effort over and over again we will find that we begin to
speak with attention this is how we practice right speech
and we can do a similar practice for Action like what I did with the Light Rail ticket where I sensed my body
moving to the ticket machine to find the ticket and I thought yeah I could feel in the moment that was a correct action
for that moment so ethics or virtue becomes an inner
resource or a form of inner wealth or strength when it's freed from the cognitive mind and its focus on ideas
and ideals and Abstract principles virtue becomes embodied when we meet
life with mindfulness and the intention of non-harm and we let actions in speech emerge from that
so it's a training we won't be skilled in it immediately but it takes our ethics training to a
deeper level of Dharma practice there's a story from the sutus where the
Buddha is speaking with a prince named Prince Abaya which means Fearless by the
way and he asked the Buddha whether the Buddha plans the answer to Dharma
questions in advance and the the Buddha asks in return whether the prince considers in advance
how to respond to questions about the parts of a chariot and Prince of Maya says no I'm very skilled in the parts of
a chariot and once someone asks me about that the answer occurs to me on the spot
and the Buddha replies so too Prince When people come to me and pose a question the answer occurs to the
tatagata on the spot so he's saying that he's understood the Dharma so deeply that he can always come
up with an appropriate response so we may not be quite at that level ourselves but I would suggest that we
can try taking our ethical conduct to this deeper level through experiential practice and then it will become second
nature to speak and act in non-harming ways even in stressful situations
so then it's become a reliable resource in our heart so we have confidence and we have
ethical conduct as two resources and we'll keep moving on as we go forward
thank you so much