hello everyone hello from IMC in Redwood City
happy to think of
these greetings going out in so many different directions around the world and
and um and to have your attention from so many
different places all the way around so thank you for being part of this
and I sit here in this large room at IMC
that's kind of peaceful calm still I hear some traffic outside
and so regardless of how I think about you around the world
and regardless of how I think about or aware of the drama of the world
the challenges and storms of the world
I know it from this place here in this room that's calm and peaceful and quiet
so if you take a light
a lamp bulb put it inside a box small box and turn
the light on the light shines and the light bulb shines just as it does
if you expand the walls of the Box make it a bigger box
it doesn't affect the light the light is just peacefully just shining
if you expand it bigger and bigger and make it as big as this room here
the light just shines the light shines quietly without
defining Itself by how far it lights goes doesn't Define Itself by
what the light lands on there could be a lot of drama
in the room or there could be a lot of Stillness the light just shines
and so the light of our awareness the light of attention
it's possible that it can just shine on everything without defining Itself by what it's
shining on and that place of awareness then can
become the large quiet peaceful room for us or to say it differently
the um it can be a
still like a Stillness or the calm in the middle of the storm
and the storms around could be the storms that existed our
thinking it could be the storms of our emotions
it could be the storms the agitation energies of our body
and it's possible to know it with a light that's turned on that is
not defined by any of it it knows it but is not defined by it
and to so as we meditate that's one of the
possibilities here is to discover a still quiet place
that may be as small maybe is as big as a large room or as big as the universe
that's kind of like the calm in the middle of the storm where we turn on our light
and we sit here aware of what is
and it's a very different way of relating to thinking very different relating to emotions than usual if we do
we Define ourselves by it or get involved with it participate in it
think more about them react to them but the still quiet place
letting all things be but not defined by them so in this meditation
perhaps that can be your little mantra uh
not defined so whatever you're aware of whatever is happening for you that you can know
you can add or imagine you're adding no def no definition
not defining Yourself by it so sitting upright
in the meditation posture and gently closing your eyes
and without much to do more to do sit quietly
and be aware of what your experience is like
before relaxing or breathing deeply just be aware
be aware from the inside out your body
be aware the emotions
be aware of your thinking
and be aware
that the awareness of it all
is like the light that's turned on
that does not need to be defined by what it knows
and what it knows will change and shift but maybe the knowing
can be a calm peaceful place to come in the storm
so if it's possible for you see if you can
see if you can um drop inside
as deep as a place you know where there might be some
quiet Stillness
and allow breathing experience or breathing
to make itself known to that still quiet place of awareness
awareness doesn't go out but experiences comes to it comes to
awareness comes into that quiet place
being aware mindful knowing what's happening
like turning on the light so there's brightness and clarity about what is
but not defined by what is
an awareness which is not defined by the body
and knowing not defined by your emotions
and knowing not defined by what you think
and knowing which doesn't Define itself either
it just is
thank you
and that's still quiet place in the middle of the storm
denies nothing doesn't even have to let go of anything
place whether it's quiet awareness where we turn on the light of attention
to see clearly
and it's a world of difference to know
from a peaceful place inside
or to know while negotiating and
entangled participating in what is known
and then to again find a place within that's a still
quiet space may be associated with knowing
maybe a place that's deep within maybe the deepest place of Stillness
that you know
and then if you from there if you look out upon your life
the issues of your life your concerns
from that place of Stillness or peace or depth
does that provide a different perspective than the usual one for you
do you gaze upon things differently
understand them differently think about them differently
how do you see your life
when seen Through The Eyes of the peace Within
and to
turn that gaze from that still quiet place out into the world
not into the people you may encounter today strangers and
people who you know
and maybe from this quiet place within
You Can Be Touched more
by the humanity and suffering and joys of others
from that still quiet place you could gaze upon the world kindly
be still and gaze upon the world with kind eyes
may all that you think of all the people you know
may they be happy may all the people you know
friends and foe both may they be safe
may all the people you know
may they be peaceful
and may all the people you know may they be free
and in relationship to all the people you know
may you be free not entangled
in your caring awareness of them
[Music]
so
to talk more then this week on practicing with thoughts and emotions
the relationship between them and it felt important to as much as it's
important to see that there's an intimate connection between how we think and our emotions
how we emote and our thinking and that by seeing that connection it's
possible to find a degree of freedom that um
but more importantly I don't know if it's more important but another possibility
is to by knowing and seeing carefully the relationships the
entanglements the influence of one emotion emotions and thoughts and thoughts and emotions
at some point what becomes maybe strong is not the
emotions and thinking but the awareness of them but to be aware I mean I think I think
that thinking and emotions is often the place that people get hooked up caught
by stuck in reactive in but also it's a very common place to
somehow consciously or unconsciously to be defined by to know this is who I
am and some people feel it's very important to really be someone like this is who I
am and take a stand there and some people are very afraid of being
someone taking a stand and there is a third option
and that is to calmly and peacefully be aware be present be grounded be be
centered in the place where the light of awareness can shine
where we can turn on the awareness and see what's there see the emotions see
the thoughts that we have uh maybe even see some of the entanglements between them and our
entire entanglements with them but to
to be aware of it
from a peaceful place and that's one of the possibilities
through meditation is to become calmer than we usually are in daily life
and I say it carefully they're calmer as opposed to some high standard of how
calm we have to become but to be calmer or more peaceful and more subtle than we usually are
so that we have different eyes to see we have a different way of looking upon the
world and as we get quieter and Stiller we were less caught in the world of
thoughts less caught in the world of emotions even the ones that are beneficial
then the eyes conceived with greater clarity but and
we can see from a deeper place within where we have contact to wisdom to
understanding to perspectives to attitudes that we're not going to have available
when we're caught up in the in the thoughts caught up in our emotions caught up in defining ourselves
by it and thinking this is who I am
and uh and to have that New Perspective and to then from there maybe think about
our life from there see what emotional connection there might be
but it's the emotional connection that has a very different uh feel to a very different attitude very
different effect because we're not it's not doesn't come
from the contraction of definition doesn't come from the hooks of reactivity
it's as if that with there's a Wellspring or a spring within a vast
spring Within that um of wisdom of goodness of freedom
of peace that we can Avail ourselves of
to when we start we are no longer so caught in the world of thinking and emotions
and that also allows us to think and if and have feelings from a very different
perspective because many of the feelings we have many of the thoughts we have
can be very much rooted in definition and seeing this is who I am and this is
about me this is about me myself and mine but the still quiet place the the calm
in the middle of the storm is not you
it's not anyone else but and and whether it's you or not we don't
have to think about those thoughts we don't have to Define ourselves by it we don't have to grab a hold of it and and
feel like take a stand on it this is who I am
and this Freedom this peacefulness this calm in the middle of the storm
is tremendously useful because it'll it can allow
a different kind of thinking that's maybe that's not
um impatient that's not reactive that's not caring with it as much of the judgments
and biases and preconceived ideas that we might have in the surface mind
the surface mind that's been so conditioned and influenced by society and events
and the same thing with our emotions so a still quiet place within
a calm in the storm the awareness that is like a light bulb
with that when it's turned on the light
doesn't have preferences where the light lands it lands on
everything equally and just sees it that's all
so I hope that this week on thinking and emotions
has given you some New Perspectives to really look at your life and look at
yourself understand yourself that and certainly that's part of my Hope was that you would to is to provide
New Perspectives that would be freeing the New Perspectives that would be useful to break out of old perspectives
that maybe are not so helpful so I hope it worked somewhat for that
and uh so thank you for this week
and then a couple of announcements the uh I'll be going away uh next Thursday
for to teach back east and East Coast at the Berry Center for Buddha studies
and um and I've become a little bit confused exactly about um uh my the substitutes coming to teach
for me and at some point in that uh those two weeks Matthew Brent silver will come
and uh since I'm leaving on Thursday I might be able to be back the first days next week and and maybe megaler will
teach the end uh or something else will happen I'm not quite sure these next two weeks so
um so please uh just to be aware that there's a certain unknown at some point it'll be
put in properly in the calendar IMC calendar
and um and then a couple of things uh announcements that maybe it's a little
bit relevant for some of you uh way back in the beginning of the year we did this series on this Sati
patanasuta the discourse in the four foundations of mindfulness and I was uh struck by how meaningful
the instructions were on the different parts of the body the 32 parts of the
body 31 parts of the body meditation that we did a little bit and a friend of mine is one of the Bob
Stahl is one of the or probably the biggest proponent of this meditation
practice in our Buddhist scene and it does a lot of teaching of it's practiced it a lot
um it was kind of us the 32 parts of the body kind of a systematic way of
connecting to the body in a very deep way it's a it's a very important practice in therabad and Buddhism
so we invited him to come and do a class but it's through the Sati Center and so
if you go Sati s-a-t-i sati.org
you can find his class there I think it's maybe in September it starts maybe
it's an eight-week class and um I think there's uh information
about the Sati Center programs on the what's new section of imc's website
and the other thing that's happening in the beginning of October is I do a year-long programs for people who have
fairly established practice and practicing for some time and I think you have to have four years
of practice and a number of Retreats silent to be passing their retreats but
for those of you who have done that you might be interested it's a one day a month for about eight nine months and
this year the topic is meditation and the program is called deepening meditation practice
and you can read a little bit more about it in though again the what's new
section of imc's website which is on the front page of imc's website the Box on
the bottom right and there's applications for that for
both programs and and um so so I think the applications for the
deepening meditation program is this is in September 1st
so thank you everyone and um and maybe I'll be here Monday maybe not and and
certainly look forward to our next time together