foreign
if you're comfortable it will help me if you put a name tag on if you don't mind Jim
would you mind bringing a couple of name tags in the pen for anybody I think there's a couple people who didn't get
it it helps me I want to learn your names thank you
so um does anybody have any concerns about my taking my mask off
no
thank you Jim so this is the fourth week in this four
week series establishing a practice
um
foreign
she was right there I think she that was it yeah thank you
so just um is it Mila Mila Mila great
um so the four weeks we went through the first week um wise understanding wise intention
second week was mindfulness on and off the cushion third week was actions that
support Joy and this week is establishing and sustaining our practice with wise effort
and if you signed up for the prac the handouts it's all in there and I'll
email it to you yeah um
so I'm just wondering before I kind of go a little bit more into today's topic
if there are any questions or responses that are residual um
that I can answer for any of you nope
good all good and I have a question a different question since you don't have any for me
I have one for you did any of you focus on moments of
well-being or Joy this week and if you take in yeah
Corey you did perfect would you mind saying a few
words in the mic yeah thank you Sage
uh yeah just uh little things just um
usually on my walking commute to work if a car would
stop and as I walked past I would you
know give a little wave I kind of helped uh
try and remember that I did a little bit of uh an appreciation Journal as well so I
would write down try to do three appreciations for the day to try to
keep in those moments so I think it's a good practice I I I'm liking it
how um how is how how do you know you're liking it what are the benefits for you
uh uh well I guess difficult to say I think uh
I don't um
dwell as long or churn as long in the
uh uh bad things or or challenges that come my
way it just kind of there's this other presence there that is kind of a lighter
presence and allows me to um
uh just be um
generally more more positive about uh about about my days beautiful well that
seems beautiful yeah thank you Corey sure
anybody else I want to share any any and if not from last week when you were here at a
different time or any other thing from the the series that you've been doing that you found beneficial that you would
like to share or okay
great um part of the reason I ask about the
noticing the joy is that negativity bias is so strong I find
it that it's almost like people just pass over even that those practice like
you know um it's like the Mind loses interest so quickly
and the well-being it's like if you imagine doing the raft practice it's
like everybody before they even get to where you would have everybody sit around the table they're done right there's just but we could actually stay
with it we could actually spend some more time and say well what were the conditions that supported This Joy well
I was you know at the Sangha I had good intentions you know that various things
that we could start to really highlight for ourselves and
um so it's a mystery for me and I'm trying to I'm wanting to arouse interest in
this and and help people sustain so um I'm you know I have a lot of I think
it's so important that um which is why I'm lingering here and
um just really want to encourage you to think about how to help the mind take in
the good because it won't do it by itself not until we condition it in that
direction I also want to invite all of you to a
day-long Meditation Retreat this this Saturday from 9 30 to 4 30 there's
Flyers at the end of the the state the stage if you want to pick one up
you're welcome to come for the whole time and if you can't stay all day it's fine to come for part I'll be
co-teaching with kodo so if you did the intro series with us he'll be back and
co-teaching with me that day long um
so to start tonight I have a little bit of a quote
practice sometimes unfolds in surprising ways
it's actually never a straight line to any fixed goal just like life
is always a mixture of things that arise from times characterized by confusion
doubt discouragement to times of clarity joy and inspiration
keep practicing just keep practicing never stop practicing is sort of the
motto so it's not a straight line and uh
I've had this image of myself at times you know where there are times where it
feels like it's almost every step you could go this way or that way off the
path and it's it's sometimes it's just this constant you know attention to what's
happening to keep us on the path we yander off and we have to come back
but if we're really right here you can start to even see oh the mind is entertaining the compulsions the polls
and um you know so yeah yeah it's
not a straight line so
for me um one of the really supportive things to pay
attention to in my practice is my effort
I feel like um there's so much uh there's so so much so it's so Dynamic
working with effort um
no different from opening a jar right you know different can openers some are
easier some are harder some jars are easier some jars are harder if you do you know if you don't put in enough
effort the jar doesn't open if you put in too much effort you might break the jar you know there's effort in that and
and the feedback is right there the jar of the lid comes off or it doesn't right
um so that's a very gross kind of analogy
but the truth is is that um there's so much effort in in just in
deciding to do something and how much effort we put into it can really impact
our experience of something and the practice is uh
no different in fact it's um a really beautiful thing to start to
notice and and really think about like okay how much effort am I putting in to
being aware of my breathing and and then that will change over the
course of a practice period in five minutes the amount of effort that it needs to stay with the breath
can change dramatically right typically if we start the practice
with a little more effort to stay with the breath stay with the breath it helps us get you know established with that
anchor but if we keep putting that much effort in that we start with it's too much
effort after a while then we start to overwork and we're over
straining and we start to get tight so there's you know a certain amount of
effort that's needed to get started and then we need to back off
and then sometimes we'll back off a little too much and we'll start to wander and lose our focus and then we
need to notice that okay then maybe we need to kind of bring back a little bit more effort
so for me um there's there's that kind of effort
there's also the practice we're doing is an effort so choosing the
um anchor is an effort we choose an anchor right in this practice
and that's that takes effort in choosing the right anchor is an effort right it's
all like doing loving kindness practice is a certain kind of effort
so how were even the mindset or the tone of voice in the mind
is part of what affects the effort so I'm going to invite you all
Just Close Your Eyes for a second and in silence in your own mind I'd like
you to say your own name
just say it a few times and just sort of see if you can't notice how
it feels and what you notice in your body when you hear your own name
okay now I'd like you to um
think about somebody who adores you could be a pet
child grandparents somebody alive somebody from the past it doesn't matter but
somebody that you know really thinks you're you know they're pretty smitten with you
and I'd like you to imagine hearing your name in their voice
just a few times and notice what that feels like in your
body
okay and did you feel the difference
could you feel the difference inside of yourself
I see some slight nods yeah so this is a great kind of
um example of the subtleties that we can start to pay attention to with effort
the ways we can start to tune in to how we're bringing ourselves to this cushion
you know if we aren't careful we can bring the voice of an irritated parent
to you know the experience of sitting right to ourselves and then that's going to
have an effect our system will respond to that way of being spoken to right
so when we talk about effort and the practice we often use words two words
skillful and unskillful to describe
how habits thoughts decisions practices lead to you know suffering or
the end of suffering and so but this these terms you know
this term skillful and unskillful we really are tuning into how it's supporting our ability to be present
and we need to be seeing ourselves as our instrument
so the tone of voice the amount that we're encouraging ourselves the way the practice will we're like a bell it will
resonate and have different tonal impacts
so we want to look for things that are skillful meaning they support
you know our awareness being present wisdom being present
and uh our mindfulness
so we're using our effort as we grow this practice to monitor our inner life
Joe was talking to me earlier about you know monitoring how she's thinking right
in daily life and um and this so this is this is wise effort to try and monitor but then if we
over we're in the middle of life trying to work or talk to somebody and
if we're over trying to you know over efforting
what's what's going to happen for us we can't keep functioning because we're
over analyzing ourselves right so
and we use the effort to Monitor and
sort of check in on our intentions what are our intentions here
and then um I like to talk about um the feedback I like the word feedback or
outcome but I like feedback best is it's like that's the the resonance that's the
impact of what we're doing what is the feedback that we're getting from our effort are we not just doing something but
actually paying attention to the impact of what we're doing
so there's these they call them four teachings on four kinds of effort
and there's essentially you know two two parts of it one has to do with preventing or
stopping unwholesome or unskillful
experiences thoughts practices and the other is to grow or to sustain the
skillful so we wanna if if we're noticing a lot
of hatred come up and self-hatred come up or something like that
we have four you know there's there's stop the hatred
right and then once the hatred is stopped we want to prevent it from arising again
and so we can start with trying to stop the hatred and then preventing it or we can actually
turn away from the hatred and grow something that's wholesome some love or
kindness or compassion and then sustain that compassion that whole that
um you know skillful
so we don't always have to focus on stopping something that's unskillful we
can instead choose to grow something that's skillful just abandon essentially the unskillful
as opposed to trying to just repress or stop something
sometimes it works to just be like no that doesn't feel good I'm done and
there's just a stopping that happens it's a really simple really clear
sometimes it's really easy but sometimes I find that when there's something I'm
doing that is a problem for me I actually can reinforce it if I stay focused on it then start criticizing
myself for doing this thing and it feeds it more
sometimes if I'm practicing loving kindness and I'm so I'm growing and then
sustaining a skillful practice mind state
um I might find that I'm
maybe I'm I'm I start to do something unskillful at the same time like
um I don't know maybe I start to get interested in my phone
and um that and so that's not you know that's not skillful that's not going to
support the cultivation of loving-kindness or my practice so
that might be something that I I truly want to stop I might if my phone is Within Reach I might literally want to
turn it off or put it away and then it's sort of done right if I
can do something that's that simple it might be just really easy to to stop
when I'm cultivating or working on sustaining something that feels
supportive helpful
says trying to get the mind more interested in what is happening is wise effort
so helping us be curious and interested is wise effort so it's so there's so
much to it here right there's really it's a very rich territory
and curiosity is really supportive for the practice having a mind that's
interested really interested and what what it's like a you know a kid
who's really curious about what happens if I put two more drops of dye in this you know they're so engaged you know and
so sometimes I that kind of mindset where we really want to stay with it and
see and find it fascinating now too much of that is not good either
I think a lot of times it's almost similar to maybe the thing I was talking about earlier about noticing Joy
it's almost like we're much more interested in in the creation of the effort and the doing than in caring
about what happens like so much more of our pattern is to
pay attention to that the launching and not what it's really like to ride in the boat
so I think that we get in trouble with
ourselves with our practice and in relationships because of this as well
I think that noticing and sort of paying attention being attuned to this the idea
of a bell you know the resonance
and and feeling into the space between yourself and others is really powerful
important and within ourselves
I think another thing that can happen is that we can have a sense of wanting to
avoid like oh I hope that didn't come out the
wrong way right we say something or do something we
don't want to cause more difficulty and
and then there's a tendency to then want to kind of Turn away and deny and move
on so that we don't have to pause and take in what the impact that
we of something that's happened that didn't quite go the right way
so we there's a conditioning there it's back to this idea that we're not
staying tuned in to the impact of what we're doing because one it's not that important or two we
don't like what we don't want to we don't feel embarrassed we don't want to cause more of a mess or
but it doesn't always mean even we have to
say something but it is important I think it's important to to pay
attention even if it's just in ourselves to give
it some space to hold some space and so we don't always know how we're
impacting other people but we can notice how we're being impacted so maybe even
it's like oh well now I'm worried that what I said wasn't okay but they seem fine but I'm
not okay I got worried why am I worried so there's something there for us to to
see
so before I kind of go any further
I'm wondering what thoughts you're having about this what associations what questions
what ideas you might be having about effort in your practice and what
you're noticing is anybody open to sharing
hi Myla um the effort part I find that really interesting because when I meditate I
sometimes I'm really there and and giving it yeah
an even amount of effort and other times a whole half hour goes by and I don't
really know what I was doing I mean I catch myself in somewhere in there but I
love I like it's really important to um to put forward effort and why am I
sitting for a half hour if I'm not going to actually meditate and and focus on that anchor that you talked about
whatever it might be um and then when you were talking that's the one
thing uh um when you were talking about like the voices or
my thought you know I sometimes I have thoughts they obviously aren't necessarily always in line with who I
want to be or or how I might say something to someone but I've heard over and over again maybe
become friendly with it rather than go for the wise versus the unwise or and
so you know just today it was like oh yeah I hear you you know like and just
acknowledge it because it's coming from somewhere it's not necessarily what I want to do yeah but that made me think
about how I can respond to something like that if I'm aware of it at the moment yeah absolutely that's and and
um Myla um the sometimes that is the most skillful
thing we can do it dissipates everything right not give it much attention you
know just acknowledge and yeah I mean I could go on and on and say oh that again or you know whatever it might be but
like yeah hey I hear ya yeah yeah it's more like give it some kindness or love
Yeah and sometimes it's uh you know we'll play with it because sometimes
what we'll find is the response the response is what's going to tell us
what's next because sometimes you'll find then it grows because there's something that wants attention and you
know and then we might have to respond in a different way and sometimes it's just going to dissipate but this is the
thing to pay attention to is what is the impact of our effort what happens
and yeah anything else you want to share yeah but it's beautiful Reflections and
anybody else have another idea or thing about effort
yeah great and Rose
hi good evening everyone hi Tanya um uh sometimes I feel in terms of effort I could be a bit overconfident in
what I'm doing and then all of a sudden you know 30 minutes does go by and then I'm like wait what was I doing or I'm
not even really focused on or maybe I thought my anger was on the breath and then I stopped paying it stopped paying
attention to it and then like the following day at work I'm like well I I had a really good sitting
or what I thought was a good sitting and then I'm I'm All Fired Up and calling
home calling kids houses and writing referrals left and right and
I'm just like why why can't I be okay with this I
thought I would I was on track with my meditation and I guess my effort maybe
the voice that I was listening to was a one that was laced in criticism rather
than rather than one that was of of loving kindness you know
that's beautiful yeah
I'll tell another little story um and somebody else if you're thinking
of something great but um I one place I've been watching the impact of effort is swimming I'm a
swimmer and um you know when you swim
it's a whole different thing to try and speed up because it's all about moving
your legs harder and your arms faster but also pulling harder it's a very different thing than
pushing something right because you're the water the consistency of the water is really different and so for me
um there there is a concerted amount of effort when I'm trying to increase my
Pace when I'm trying to get myself to move up a bit that starts to happen but what I notice
is that if I'm not careful I feel like what happens so I love to swim I love
the water I love the light in the water the feeling in of being in the water the
smoothness of it the you know just there's just so much that I love about it and when I'm putting in a lot of
effort it's like a hood comes down over my head and I I stopped seeing all these things
I stopped taking in the light I stopped taking in the feeling of the water I
stopped feeling the joy of swimming and so there's this real Balancing Act
of needing to work harder while trying to open up at the same time
so I just shared that as another example of how we need to be mindful of our effort because when we're trying hard
it can for me it feels like literally pulling pulling a hood down over my head
in a way like I just instead of being open like this
and and I felt like that has happened to me in meditation too where I'm all I'm
doing is focusing on trying so hard I'm not actually really paying attention to much of anything other than I'm trying
so you know as we start to watch this we might be able to have a relationship
with a certain feeling that comes in our body when we're trying too hard
when we're putting in too much effort and conversely when we're not putting in enough
you know there can be yeah Corey
[Music] yes oh we should yeah yes yes this is such a
great yeah and um sure Brian do you want to go over and to
the heat thing or um it feels like people are getting a little bit cold that maybe needs to be no you're okay
yeah okay all right if anybody's getting cold Jim can just let Jim know and he
can bump it up a teeny bit but we're all okay right now I guess Jim all right okay sorry uh no it's okay uh yeah the
metaphor I've heard before is that of uh with one's practice um
uh that of tuning a guitar string yeah uh if it's too loose uh the note is a
little um uh sour or uh and if it's too taut
you know the string can break or so you want it in tune where it's kind of
humming along absolutely yeah there's a suit uh um all about this it's such a great suta
but yeah if it's too that you know the string gets really the sound doesn't
vibrate right it does it just if the string is too tight it's like trying to ring the spell when
I'm holding it it just blocks the sound from vibrating and
um yeah and if there's too much it's too slack it's like you know so yeah it's this is another
very beautiful simile for helping us think about the effort that we're putting in and where the where the
instrument we're playing here folks we're we're the instrument and we've got
to tune in to what the impact is of what we're doing yeah yes and Rose
great how do you thank you Corey that was a really great
point I just how do you know when you're too taught or it's too slack right I mean obviously
there's tension I know that great and then maybe apathy if I'm feeling like
whatever it doesn't matter I'll just move try to move on yeah like
that yeah yeah absolutely so watching the subtle the body tension is one so
you know you know we might sort of find ourselves completely slumping or just sort of
losing losing a sense of uprightness right
um now you know we're all bodies are going to look a little different so it's not like we're all going to look the same but we'll know our own selves right
but the other part is tension to like our shoulders are tense our Jaws
are gripping right um our gosh I don't know about you but
my my shoulders will come up to my ears or my eyebrows will get super tight when
I'm trying to concentrate sometimes and these are all this is all feedback that
I'm over efforting I'm efforting in the wrong way so we've we're going to have our own
conditioning our own body patterns that will give us feedback about over under
efforting and the tone of voice in our minds the
word choices the rapidity of the speaking in our heads the these are all
forms of feedback right yes yeah thank you so
[Music] okay so um in in general the things that you
know tend to be important to think about are relaxation is actually really really
important so we start sitting up and finding a good posture we start with
setting an attention and working to establish our connection with the the
anchor and we've got to it's like they say the bones are upright and then they'll let
the muscles fall off the bones let the belly hang out
so there's this combination of upright and relaxed
and you know for me another big thing is paying attention to my chest it's
important for me to open up my squeeze my elbows together lift my shoulders up
and back because this counters the Leaning forward with the computers and
the phones and then the body can breathe more easily it just naturally takes
easier breaths so this is a this is an example of taking effort to help with our ease
you know to help us relax in the practice is setting ourselves up physically before we come in
um the other thing that's really supportive you know I read that quote by um aside
but um trying to get interested is wise
effort curiosity interest that's very helpful like saying you know
I'm interested in learning about what's Happening Here I'm interested in noticing well what
happens if I start my practice this way and then oh well what happens if I start
it that way let me see what happens so that also helps setting the sense of
intention to notice right this intention to notice
um
and actually relaxation it's like another word for that might be
receptivity so you know how for two two braced
too much effort there's no receptivity and practice requires a lot of
receptivity there's a lot of Need for Attunement and receptiveness being
willing so that relaxation really supports that happening
all right um
so I'm just going to go over a couple other little tips that can help in practice and then we'll do some small
groups in terms of effort with thinking when
thinking becomes really strong one of the things that we teach um is to instead of staying focused on
the content of the thought notice the way you're thinking
thinking in words thinking in typed out words versus
hearing thinking in images memories
noticing if it's in color or black and white so start to just kind of one way is to
say oh this kind of thinking is happening right now and sort of see that as opposed to
attending to the content of the thought another is to just kind of uh grossly
categorize the type of thinking that's happening worry planning
wanting remembering just these very simple categorize categories that help us again
shift from the content which is a little bit like when you plug your your CD into
the TV the VCR hold these and it grabs it and it starts rolling it's kind of
kind of when we stay with the content we get grabbed and pulled into the story Into the movie more easily so this is a
an example of how to redirect your attention to know that you're thinking but without kind of getting carried
Downstream and then another example of a really
skillful practice when there's a lot going on for us in our minds or
difficult emotions is doing loving kindness practice is doing the phrases that um
you can do them for myself so for me I they can do them for somebody else you
or all beings or categories of beings and it's essentially four phrases may I
be safe may I be happy
may I be healthy and may I be at ease
and we just gently repeat these phrases over and
over in the mind and that can help settle things as well
I can also it'd be it's like that effort of arousing good States skillful states in
the mind and then sustaining them so that part of that effort of arousing
and sustaining all right
so let's do groups of one two three one two three yeah three perfect
and um maybe three to four so sage and Jim can join a group if they wish
um and I generally encourage you to get in a group with new people that you don't
know um and yeah go ahead and just
turn your bodies and make yourselves comfortable and get seated and I'll give you some more instructions in a minute
is
Okay so have you all said your names to each other great
great so
um I think I'll give you the option let me maybe just see I'll do a show of hands
I was thinking about having you do this one particular question in a repeating
practice a repeating way it's like one question and you keep answering that
same question over and over again letting whatever different answers come up
and the question that I had in mind was if I keep practicing no matter what if I
keep practicing dot dot dot so it might be I will
and you're going to have words to say or um something will happen you know just sort
of letting your mind free associate and kind of offer what would happen if
you keep practicing does that feel like where does that feel like something you
could engage with right now is that relatable question for you all
I see mostly head knotting okay
yeah if I if I keep practicing no matter what if I keep practicing no matter what
and so um one person at a time would share
and um can you each have group have a time
keeper great
two minutes per person so you're going to answer that same question for two minutes long
and so one person in the group who's not the time keeper can ask the question
and you just ask it and let them answer and when they stop pause and then just answer ask the same
question again and then just wait and and then at the end of two minutes you'll switch to the
next person and you might need to change roles okay is that clear great
okay begin
turkeys
about it
thank you
but
you know
or whatever relationships
pregnancy cardiac California as well
okay
you know whatever it is
foreign
Chinese
um
to have better experiences
I am um
[Music]
excited
foreign
thank you
again
did everybody get a chance great great
thank you thank your song members for their kind openness and attention and
Sage should I hit record now or you want to hit it or okay
so just for the recording the question was if I keep practicing no matter what
over and over again we're asking the same question to see what different answers come up
and um I'm curious if anyone wants to share how
that was what the what they learned or
hi it wasn't so much a little closer to
your mouth okay it wasn't so much what I was thinking it was after I it
was my turn and I looked back and I'm thinking oh my life is hanging by my
meditation practice I feel that my life has gone to miraculously change if I stay on this
path and so I was just splurting out till these positives
and then as I sat back I'm like I'll say if it doesn't happen yeah
yes and and then you know what happens when it doesn't happen exactly that way
and you keep practicing yeah thank you Joe
anybody else want to go
because it won't you know Joe it won't go exactly the way you think it right nothing does life is too
unpredictable so nothing else you guys I heard overheard a few nice things that were
very inspiring Ben okay so I mean the option of all the things that we said was just
like living a life fully awake
as opposed to asleep
well half sleep half sleep yes yeah oh Mitra wants to share thanks
yeah we all said really good things will happen if we keep practicing
so I think there's no there's no reason not to practice
and I think a little bit of those things are already happening like very little let's hear it
Mitra let's hear it oh just a little bit of kindness just I mean tiny tiny bit
nobody else would realize but I do I don't think you're the only
one that would realize me yeah beautiful beautiful
anyone else want to share anything that was surprising even that came out of their mouths they were a little bit
surprised by by what came out
is it still on okay sorry
hello okay I was driving across the bay bridge this morning and it was very crowded
and
I think the battery is out because it turned off so I don't think that was you maybe a different mic
hello thank you so um the only thing I was I was
thinking normally let's say 10 years ago
I would be zipping in and out of that traffic trying to take out any little
space in that road and maybe I'll get there five minutes
faster maybe not I don't know but I would try my damnedest but I just sat there wow and I thought
imagine these are all your brothers and sisters on this road
and you just that's all they are beautiful then anyway so thank you
practicing no matter what that's beautiful
okay so um let's do I was going to do guided
meditation love and kindness practice kind of give you an experience of that
and I'm wondering if you want me to save some time for
some Reflections afterwards or you'd rather have a longer meditation
so I mean I can say five minutes four four minutes
um and do a little longer practice so um
people want that little longer meditation or you want a little more
extra time for feedback and comments so if you want more more meditation
raise your hand if you want more time for feedback and Reflections raise your hand
so one two three three okay I got three hands up from the second okay so how
about we do 15 minute meditation 10 minute um right okay
great so here we go we're starting with the
effort of finding our bodies in this present moment so move around a little bit
you know adjust your posture see if you need to stretch a little bit
and invite your awareness to come inward come inward
start to feel the support of the cushion or the chair
floor feel yourself maybe giving
your weight to your bones and to the chair the cushion
and see if the breath doesn't rise up right in the middle of it
so we talk about finding an anchor that helps us stay here
most frequently we use the breath but you can choose a different anchor so
whatever your anchor is breath sound sensation
taking a moment to be curious and interested about how you're
experiencing your anchor at this moment and this body
at this time
and if you're having a bit of a challenge connecting with your anchor
you might try taking three longer slower deep breaths just some big nice deep
breaths inviting a relaxation and a letting go with the
exhale
so remember the sound of the voice that you chose for
hearing your name earlier the one that says it with care and
acceptance and kindness see if you can find that voice in your
mind and your body and whether it's in your own voice sound
or in theirs offering the phrases to yourself
with that energy that heart
remembering that this practice of loving kindness
it's a practice where we are not trying to make something happen
rather it's all said with this may I or may you or may we
so it's almost like an invitation that we're dropping into our own system
to the universe so we'll do that with that voice of
kindness of care
and you can start with offering it to yourself and if you find that it's
really uncomfortable then bring to mind somebody who's so easy to love
and imagine there them there in front of you and you can offer the phrases to
them
so what we're doing is starting where it's easiest for us
and so this is an example of effort and then paying attention to the impact of
our effort so if we offer to ourselves and we notice there's resistance and
difficulty we're noticing and receiving the impact of our practice
and then maybe shifting to something another easier being for ourselves
tonight and the phrases start
may I be safe
just taking a moment to hold that idea of safety safeness safe enough
maybe noticing in this present moment if there's a sense of safeness
how do we know when we're feeling a sense of safeness
what happens in our bodies when we feel safe enough
may I be safe
may I be happy this is that sort of Happiness that's
not dependent on other things sort of a simple
simple happiness just a sense of
ease or Joy that's so subtle sometimes
maybe bringing to mind an experience of feeling just a contented happiness peaceful happiness
may I be happy
may I be healthy as healthy as I can be
just connecting with that feeling of health and vitality well-being
may I experience well-being
may I be healthy
may I be at ease may I be at ease
and what does ease feel like
may I be at ease
now we'll repeat the phrases and you can take a moment to decide if you
want to continue to offer the phrases to yourself
or maybe to another human being you know that could use some support care
was having a hard time maybe somebody who's easy to love
a pet maybe all beings in the world may be
connecting with what it would be like for every single human living being
so I'll use the word we for whatever we is and you
may we be safe
may we be happy
may we be healthy
may we be at ease
may all beings everywhere without exception
be safe be happy be healthy
and be at ease
[Music]
so we have um you know we have 10 minutes
I had a little fantasy and that fantasy would be pretty simple
I think that actually the only person that would be a little hard to reach would be or no but that we take the
microphone and we pass it from each person
just you know go and you can say whatever you want to say as we wrap up this four week series and we'll be
starting another one next week called let's talk about practice and
um so you know what do you want to give to the Sangha to yourself
um if you want to ask a question fine but um Sage maybe you could start and then
pass it to Ben yeah so um I think what I'd like to give
you this first of all is just gratitude gratitude Tanya and gratitude to all of you it's
been wonderful practicing together thank you so much for
teaching I hope to apply it and to get to what if you keep practicing
without exception someday soon
and maybe say your name this has been um
um I've attended many different classes not as much as Mitchell but some
uh over the years and
[Music] um the effect of each of each class is very subtle
um and you wonder well what did I learn
then as you live your normal life you begin to see Snippets little bits of
pieces bits and pieces of which any kind of makes you hopeful that
maybe I did learn something
great and then just make sure you get animals behind you yeah
I feel the same I feel it it's
it's subtle but it's adding um and I want to thank you for these four
weeks and something happened today
um when you said to hear the voice of a person
um I think I don't know if this is going to go away but something in my heart
changed I don't think I ever said my own name or heard my own name
like this before and uh
I heard it in my dad's voice and it changed everything yeah it just
changed everything I how I feel about the whole world changed
when we did this loving kindness I don't think I ever felt so much
and today is four years since he passed away oh but I don't think that I just um
hearing his his voice thank you
thank you Tanya thank you everyone for allowing me to feel safe and welcome I'm
just grateful for the two months that we've been I've been cultivating and
establishing and I just hope to continue on in this journey even though there can
be times of such self-doubt I I have to remind myself that
it your patience is is something that I have to practice and sitting just
sitting and being with the breath and and just not allowing myself to
be you know over you know what do you call it like the boat in the water you
just completely carried out yeah carry it out and I I can drop the anchor Yeah because sometimes I'm holding it yeah
and I'd rather be swept away by everything and I know I I know there's a better way to live life and just many
things and I'm so grateful to everyone to you and I'm excited for the for next
week great I'm so glad you'll be here on Rose
I would like to thank you for for the teaching for sharing the knowledge um it's it's pretty useful there's a lot
to to learn and a lot to apply so uh as I don't know says patient is
needed patience is needed to to to absolve everything and to apply
everything so thanks again for sharing and thanks to the other four participating
uh yes
uh thank you for um everything and
um the the inner voice is something uh that
I picked up this time and um I'm I'm learning
um what uh uh that that that
it could use some softening so um and that was a a
the distinction between first um calling your name and then like
imagining somebody that's um likes you say your name uh it helps
me realize that and um I think that pervades a lot of uh
my being in the world is that inner voice so it's a really important
um Focus focal point to
to study and and I guess you start with accepting and
then I don't know move on um just um
noticing is is where I'm at right now so I think that's good
Corey Myla hi
um I didn't know what to expect and I knew I was coming on the last night I thank you all for uh you know accepting me in
tonight and I got the feeling that there was a real sweetness here and uh
a nice Sangha you know and um I I benefited by it tonight
um I've been here many times but in person only twice recently so I'm looking
forward to the all day on Saturday and thank you for sharing so deeply tonight
um and uh what else I just feel like there's just so much
like a Common Thread in in why we end up in meditation and what we want in life
as as human beings so it was great to share that with you all thanks
hey everyone I'm Richelle um thank Danielle for teaching the class um thank you uh
the the community it was very nice getting to know everyone and hearing
your thoughts as well I think for me the series has been um
sometimes challenging but also it has been very useful in actually forming
advancing the meditation practice especially in the sense that
um certainly I'm more observant of many of the tools that you know we
discussed here in states of mind that we discussed here like the inner voice like the different types of resistance that
we experience in trying to be mindful and a lot of conditioning which is very
subconscious and it pretty much like affects everything so
it's been useful yeah it's been very um good to expand my practice thank you
thank you
yeah so this is my second week here it sounds like class is over or the
session is so it's a four week series and so next week we start us a different
four-week series Diana Clark and I will be co-teaching uh like we're calling it
let's talk about practice and we'll start actually talking the first week we'll be talking about Sangha
um and we'll cover Sangha and we'll cover um
I think it's I think we'll talk about wise effort again and mindfulness and
concentration so one topic per week but it'll be structured very much like this
we'll move through the topics I'll have discussions and guided practices so
just each month kind of shifting a little bit what the theme is or how we're going
about it great yeah so this is yeah my my first time you know doing this in a
group setting um I like it because when I'm here there's
nowhere else I need to be other than here there's really not much else of a distraction
um even just listening right to the teaching is sometimes I catch myself wondering it's
like okay wait wait you're here go get back to it so yeah definitely just getting started but I want to
get more into the practice of you know just being present so this has been a good start for me I
think great
um hi I'm I'm Joe I am just so glad that I find my way
back here I I first came here in 2015.
and I don't know what happened but I just
looked into it a couple of weeks ago could make last week I love Tanya I think you're a fantastic
teacher and I feel very welcomed by everyone so thank you
and yeah I just love my new Thursday evenings thank you
yay wow well may the benefit that
um you all shared come in deep and may you appreciate and
Savor that benefit and share it and it's it's just gonna be shared by in
so many ways you know just by if you hold it dear you can't help but share it and may that
continue to be shared with all beings so that everywhere on this planet people
experience the benefit of this practice and I appreciate your sincerity your
engagement you know this is a beautiful Sangha thank you for being here and I
hope to see you all next week