so hello everyone and warm greetings welcome
and some of you have been commenting a chat i see that it's cold
where you are and sometimes when the weather is
warm or cold in between there's a way of
using the temperature of the place where it's meditating as a
reminder to be involved in the sensory body to be connected to the body in some
deeper way where we're sensing and feeling it sometimes when it's uncomfortable the
weather it's easy to be in the control tower
you know a little bit upset with what's happening or not liking it and an alternative is to
kind of enter into the sensations of cold or warm
and rest in them and feel them receive them and there's a some occasionally a very
different way in which the body receives warmth and cold
if the mind is not resisting or reacting to it but the mind is helping us to
feel it and sense it in the body and that's kind of the theme for this
morning's meditation is um a kind of sensory awareness exercise
which the buddha's is pointing towards and that is to
have a sensory experience of the breathing it means to
step out of the control tower of a lot of thinking and analyzing judging and trusting
that we don't have to do that trusting that instead we can rest ourselves rest attention
in the body as it's being experienced as as it's felt
the sensory body and um
and not only does it uh in being grounded in the sensory body
is a protection from being wandering off in wayward thoughts
it's also a little protection from being excessively self-concerned
which is naturally enough and certainly appropriate enough at times but it can be overly done it's nice to
take a vacation from self-preoccupation
and so this dropping into the body and feeling the body's experience for some people can see this it provides
them with that vacation from self-concern at least for these minutes of the meditation
and finally there's something very special about sensations
that we experience sensations are the meeting place
or the synthesis or the dynamic kind of experience that arises
when the mind is connected to the body
the body has sense nerves all over it that can be triggered
stimulated to give a sense experience the mind is what knows that
awareness is what knows that and the meeting of the body and the
awareness the meeting place of the body and mind is in the sensations themselves
and the sensations occur where the sense nerves reside
and so sensing our capacity to sense
and sensations uh are like two two sides of a hand they
can't really be distinguished in experience
and that's the meeting place of the mind and body and we're trying to in this meditation
practice to have the mind and body be together working together
if the mind ones are under often thought or in commentary discursive thought
then the mind is somewhere else besides the body but when the bot when the mind is
they're connected meeting with sensations with sensing then they're working together
and one way today that we'll talk about dropping into that is by relaxing into it
so to assume a upright meditation posture
and sometimes by being careful
with your meditation posture the body
begins to support you in being aware through the body
in intentional posture
has a tension in it
gently closing your eyes
and as you inhale sense and feel
what happens in your body with a deeper inhale
and on the exhale a longer gentle exhale
relaxing the body
breathing in and breathing out
and it's a little bit of a ritual to take some deeper breaths at the beginning
a ritual of being reminded here this is the body
this is the place to be during these minutes of meditation
letting your breathing return to normal
and as you exhale relax different parts of your body
but as you relax them see if it can be like a relaxing into
the sensations of that part of your body almost like you're resting in that part
of your body maybe beginning with your belly
on the exhale softening the belly and resting
softening the belly and then softening settling into feeling more of the belly
on the exhale relaxing your legs settling into your legs feeling the more
as you relax
breathing in and exhale softening the shoulders
and feeling the soldier the shoulders more as you relax
on the exhale relaxing the muscles of your face feeling those muscles
feeling your face as you relax
and if there's any tension or pressure associated with thinking thinking mind thinking muscle
as you exhale relax the
mind and feel whatever sensations are associated with
that tension and pressure or what replaces it
and then open your awareness to that place in your body where you most easily experience the
body breathing
and as you inhale receive the sensations of inhale
as you exhale relax into the sensations of exhaling
as you exhale relax whatever keeps you separate
from the sensations of breathing
relax into the sensations of the body breathing
perhaps floating on the changing nature of those
sensations
if you're intimate with the inhales you'll probably feel more than one
sensation as you're breathing in
one more than one sensations of inhale
and probably one more than one sensation as you exhale
it can be two or three or a kaleidoscope of sensations that come and go
are fleeting as the body goes through the motion of
breathing in and breathing out
as you exhale and feeling the sensations of exhaling
see if you can relax into them relax with them
settle further into your body breathing
relax the thinking mind
relax into the sensations of breathing
and have the sensations be where the mind and body meet trusting
that staying close to that meeting point is valuable
and for a couple of more minutes see if you can
be continuous in your awareness of the whole length of
breathing in beginning middle and end
the whole length of breathing out beginning middle and end
really staying connected like the mind is holding hands
with the body breathing
and as we come to the end of the sitting
learning to stay true with the breathing meaning
learning how to stay attentive to the breathing
is a life skill where we also learn to then develop the
attention to all kinds of things in our lives
including an attentiveness a presence that we can offer to others
we can listen better without
quickly as inserting our ideas and thoughts
hear people deeply
we can take time to see and feel and sense situation we're in before we assert
ourselves into it
and this ability to sense and feel and see and attend
is the basis for wisdom to living wisely
it's also the basis for living kindly
because to be wise in buddhism
goes hand in hand with being friendly and caring
so may it be that whatever ability we develop to
be mindful to be present to attend
with attention may it serve us
to contribute to this world
so that we contribute our care our love our kindness our compassion
our friendliness for the welfare and happiness of all
may all beings be happy may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
so this practice of mindfulness sati developing awareness establishing
awareness begins with a breathing
now we know that not breathing as a meditation object doesn't work for everyone
so there are other ways of practicing mindfulness and some people will establish
awareness not so much with breathing but with the body more generally
and the um uh
maybe maybe ignoring the places in the body where breathing occurs because it's
somehow compromised it's a difficult place for some people but
it's also a classic and uh primary focus of meditation and buddhism
a teacher in japan told me that everything you need to learn about buddhism can be discovered through mindfulness of breathing
and or i'd kind of prefer to reword it and say everything you
need to know about buddhism will be revealed through practicing mindfulness of breathing but it's actually true that
for any engaged mindfulness practice whatever the object is whatever the way of practicing is
mindfulness has this capacity to reveal everything we need to know for the purposes of freedom
so um but right now we're doing mindfulness of breathing
and um and the emphasis now is to experience it in the body
the word is the big word in poly is pati
verity patti sam verity and it's um it is uh
means to experience to feel uh in a brief in a reflexive way in a
subjective way your own deep subjective experi feeling of what's going on but not feeling in
the english word it's meaning that sometimes it has um where how i feel is really how i
um what i want or what i'm thinking about it or my attitude
about something here we're talking about something simpler uh we're feeling is the sensory
experience we're having independent of our preferences
and and we're learning to be close to that simple with that
and using this sensory experience as a way of cultivating some degree of
concentration stability which also serves the purposes of
protecting us from wandering off too easily into distracted thoughts
and so to have a a a place where the attention gets established rooted this is where we're
going to be um and of course the mind wanders away
and then rather than being upset with that take it for granted the mind will wander away
but that what we're developing here is what we're practicing here is a rhythm of uh
just like there's a rhythm breathing in and breathing out there's kind of a rhythm of coming into the present moment
with breathing and then wandering away and then coming back wandering away
and coming back and you're not really in charge of the wandering away
but your role is the coming back and if you think of it as a rhythm as a
flow then you maybe do it more harmoniously rather than jerking the mind back or
rather than taking time out to be upset with the fact that you were distracted just there there there it is and you
kind of get into the sense of the rhythm okay and you're not going to participate with
the mind being distracted if you have a choice and but what you're
doing is bringing it back to the breathing and then to stay close to the sensations
of breathing which are the meeting place of the mind and the body and we want to bring the have the mind
and body working in harmony and working together that's part of the unification practice
of what meditation of meditation the unification that gathering together so
all of us all of who we are begins operating in harmony rather than being
working at cross purposes so if the idea is to be in the present moment in our direct experience
and the mind keeps wanting to think about something else then we're kind of in cross purposes with ourselves
in this uh exercise we're doing now around breathing the task is to come back to breathing
and there's this is a also a very common down through the centuries kind of
practice is to offer a little bit of a
of a dedication a commitment to staying with the simplicity of breathing
so there's some strength there that uh with time overrides the tendency to wander off in
thought and so the rhythm begins to slow down you're less wonder
you're more you're less often going to wander off you're more going to stay with the
breathing and also you're going to come back more quickly to the breathing slowly this changes and you could more
and more hear and and so offering some strength some
commitment okay this is what i'm doing uh is a way of not offering a lot of
energy fuel to our thinking mind and you know it's it's a slow process
slowly slowly we begin to switch the orientation switch the
commitment of the mind from being committed to our issues in our life
to being committed to in terms of meditation practice to just being here in the simplicity of breathing
it can be hard sometimes for the mind to appreciate that this is valuable that it's we're safe we're going to make
our life better and everything just by staying simply with the breathing when we have important things to think about
but in fact this is one of the great ways of making ourselves safe because we're learning how to drop into
a quieter deeper place within that's a source of wisdom source of
better understanding and a source of um of a shift of
identity a shift of how we understand ourselves that uh is sometimes a much better place
wiser place than the identity that's supporting distracted thinking
and so we're coming in and so this training to come in for landing
with your breathing just being with the body as it breathes and um and then the instructions is um
at this point is in the elbow in the text it says
breathing in one experiences the whole body breathing out one experiences the whole
body and um and there's two meanings of this experiencing the whole body
one is that it is experiencing the whole breath body the whole duration of the breathing
and the other is you're actually experiencing the whole body beyond just experience of
breathing for now i'd like to emphasize the first that as we're cultivating
continuity with the breathing it's possible to have continuity
within the inhale so there was a time in my life where i did the check
checklist approach to mindfulness so i would knew i had to be mindful of the in-breath and so i would note it as
in and as soon as the mind has recognized that this was an in-breath then it was vacation time and my mind
would wander off because i did my job i just checked it off in and then with the out breath out
and what i learned was that rather than just be checking it off and being done with it
it's uh staying present for the whole duration many years ago i took a massage class in
college and the instructions was as you're massaging someone
always keep a hand on their body so there's always a continuity of contact
and so they're not surprised if you take your hands away to get more oil or something and then put it back is a little bit surprised or
something or you've lost contact and so the same way with the
breathing stay in touch with a full duration of the in-breath
and the beginning the middle and the end and as you get more intimate with the
experience you'll feel a kaleidoscope of sensations as you breathe in maybe there's a
beginning of a lifting of the chest or expanding of the belly or beginning of a tingling on your
nostrils and then what happens to those sensations how do they morph and change
just in the course of the inhale and
and then same thing with the exhale stay and touch now sometimes we sit down to meditate and the breathing is short and quick
and uh and so you just kind of ride it like the bronco writing in the rodeo you just ride the
bride the shortness of it coming and going and maybe relax the best you can on the
exhale but as meditation gets calmer the breathing tends to get slower and longer
and then that's when you start feeling and sensing savoring having an intimacy with all the physical
sensations that come into play as you breathe
and it helps if you uh are not measuring everything through the perspective of
your preferences and whether it's comfortable and not comfortable or whether you like it or not like it or
whether you think it's good or it's bad that's belongs to the control tower it
belongs to a way of separating ourselves from the experience and if you get bored with the breathing
that's also a separation from the experience you probably won't be bored unless you're kind of pulled away
from it the idea is to come into it and be really close and intimate with the experience
and and just feel the whole inhale and the whole exhale
and if you get into that then also doing the same kind of delicacy even
to experience the transition from breathing out to breathing in and breathing in to breathing out
so um so what i'm describing today
i'm not suggesting that it's easy but it's kind of the direction that it's possible to go
to settle in and let the mind become quiet and really develop this sensory awareness
and sensory awareness is one of the forms of awareness forms of attention in the toolbox the
buddha is offering us in doing satipatana and doing this mindfulness practice
and so to cultivate develop and hone this tool
the tool of sensory awareness is really fantastic for the purposes of mindfulness
so i would encourage you for you know until we meet again on monday
to um spend the spend the next couple of days
um studying being curious about the sensations involved in your
breathing take little times out through the day maybe even a minute or two maybe in times when you're waiting for
the traffic to move or you're waiting for something to happen standing in line in a store
and use that as a time to um to really um
just be curious what's happening with your breath what's how is your body experiencing the experi
the process of breathing and get intimate with that and curious and wise and and start becoming familiar
with a range of different ways in which breathing is experienced and then we'll continue with this
process next week and and then at some point expand it into mindfulness of the whole body
as we're breathing and and uh and go through all four all these
different steps of the first exercise and mindfulness of breathing
so thank you very much i have a couple of announcements
the first is that i'm going to do something a little different for next
monday in that the broadcast of this youtube
same time and same place on youtube however i'll be at our retreat center in
santa cruz and so i'll be teaching from the meditation hall there
so you'll see a different place and there'll be a different buddha statue
than when we get there so
that's just for one day i'll be back here on tuesday and then the other is that
imc is offering a day-long tomorrow day-long meditation retreat
on the four great efforts this is one of the important teachings of the buddha about
the kind of effort or kind of engagement the four wise ways of engaging uh that
there's use or four ways of engaging that
you know essential to all forms of this meditation practice and mindfulness practice we're doing
there's a kind of a um it's a it's a orientation to
how to engage wisely so it's a day long with meditation and
teaching and other things being taught by um three teachers here from imc who are
in the current teacher training that we have all three of them have been teaching for some time and are wonderful teachers and
should be a wonderful synergy of the three of them teaching together and um
and um and you'll find out more about this there's a link to it now and someone put
in the youtube chat but you'll find more about it also in the imc website on
what's new and also on the imc calendar so thank you
and i look forward to being together on monday