how's the volume can you hear me okay through the speaker okay
you did yeah so um they say they can hear me okay
volume it's loud enough it doesn't sound very uh no it doesn't I
don't really hear it um there we go is that better okay
yep okay let's see how's Diana sound
how does this and it's yeah
how does it oh this is a definitely louder maybe it's a little bit too loud thinking that
because then I will try to speak really quietly and then that doesn't work so well yeah I think it's still
yeah can we make turn it down just a little bit there we go there that I think that's a little bit better I guess
I have to talk non-stop so you can figure it out I think this is it has it for you guys is it too loud
okay I don't know if anybody's on the other side of that camera are we getting any
comments okay
are there meditation centers down in Mountain View in Saratoga
there's one in Mountain View yeah the Shyla Catherines is at a church I'm
not sure the name of the church but and I think she also has something in Saratoga she is like on Thursdays in
Saratoga on Tuesdays in Mountain View or something like that I think so there used to be a different
person different oh yeah oh I don't know
actually I don't know yeah we're like friendly neighbors but
we're not like the same organization
did you used to come on Mondays or Thursdays okay
and there's one in San Jose I know that's further south
you know I'm sorry I can't tell you but like I've been there but uh forget
Jelani is the teacher and I think if you go to our website
I think there's a link on our website to her songa or her contact information
yeah Shyla Catherine you can Google that name
that's the Mountain View teacher okay and possibly Saratoga it used to be in Circa together I don't
know if it still is and then forget Jelani
I think she pronounced it Jalene jalane okay
there's a lot of meditation in the Bay Area there's a lot so whatever you're interested in you can find I think
pretty much
okay so somebody else arrived so this is a good sign if there are more students than teachers
but it's okay if there's not also all it takes is one student that's right
hi Anne Rose a small night glad you're here
hi come on in
we'll start with a guided meditation so I'm just going to wait a few more minutes and just see if a couple more
people show up or just let us relax and and also if there's any other questions
or comments people want to share you know is a great time anything that your
practice coming up in your practice or anything else
I think I'm gonna get a soft food to sit on great
remind me your name Iris
okay and then well
John John and Rose I'm Tanya Weiser
you have like the best uh family name wiser I just love this name this is so
great wiser and this is the Diana Clark
but we could say that maybe both of our names wiser like you know being wise
clerk is derived from clergy so kind of you know a teacher or leader or
something like this so spiritual yeah so both of us have a we were meant to do this I don't know we
just made this up but I like it John
and well Iris and Rose
and Richard and Richard
so um tonight the focus will be on concentration practice just
um sort of what is concentration meditation how do you do it some of the real simple Basics nothing complicated
um and so you know we'll like I said we'll start with a guided meditation
and um I think I'll just say first of all maybe let me ask when I say
concentration practice what comes up for you what are your associations and if
you don't mind and Rose you could get the mic and help out with the mic just make sure you speak into the mic this
will help me help you hearing a little bit about your associations and relationship to this
idea so you have any thoughts to share on Rose yourself
okay I would say for me for concentration as I've been doing this practice has been like noting my
thoughts and then just knowing and not getting lost in them too much as I'm
as I often do so like oh I'm noticing feelings of frustration or anger or
uh just sadness or whatever and and just just being with those feelings
while I'm sitting and also on the breath and and also not getting mad when I'm
when I get lost in thought and I can go back to whatever anchor it is so I think
concentration for me is a host of things but uh I know if I'm doing too much then I'm
then that's also a problem that I have because I'm straining and
and that's I don't like that feeling yeah thank you Amber Rose thank you do
you have anything John that you would like to say about your thoughts and associations with concentration practice
nothing particularly okay
ah good idea
uh for me it's just something that I'm focused to do or just purposely focusing myself to do
something okay great and Iris any thoughts from you um maybe you have this idea of what
concentration practice is and it kind of brings me anxiety because
I guess I normally practice open awareness and even doing that it's so it's hard for me to kind of even just
focus on my breath consistently so the idea of concentration practice where maybe I associate it with longer periods
of focusing on the breath um that seems really hard okay yeah yeah
if I can't share a little story about this that um there was a time I was on a
long retreat and so I was gone for a couple of months and I came back and I
had to take care of something at the bank and the bank person wanted to know like
why didn't I take care of this earlier I'm like well I was out of town and you know I don't didn't have access to email
and all this kind of stuff and then they were perplexed you might imagine these days it's not so common to
be completely unplugged and um so I said well I was on a Meditation Retreat and
this person said ah really did you do like astral projection were you like in different places at the same time and so
I thought oh this might be what a lot of people think about when they think of concentration or doing a lot of
meditation it's all about I don't know superpowers or something like this so I
just wanted to share that story that's great and so is that the kind of concentration practice we're going to teach here tonight
well actually I'm teaching it right now because actually my physical body's in another location and I'm like a
translocator I thought you were in a you know reference yourself on YouTube no not that
nope sorry yeah so
um I I had this idea for guiding you that it's a good maybe a little
different than normal um because I want to kind of just explore a little bit
what our relationship is to concentration and different ways we might connect with it
um and before I I start I'll sort of say there's two what they call there's two
different forms of concentration practiced and one of them is kind of a
kind of a you have your breath you're aware of your breath and then oh a thought comes up so you know you're
thinking and then there's a sensation and you're aware of a sensation so you go from the breath to a thought to a
sensation in in succession right but you're aware of each thing so it's I've
heard this described as serial monogamy
so we have intimacy with one object at a time
but it's serial relationships right so that might be uh the more of the open
awareness kind of um concentration where we're it's just this this close connection to each thing as it comes up
and the other kind of concentration is where you might have an intimate uh
ongoing connection to one object like the breath
um so they're both they're both ways that
we can become concentrated actually and they can both lead to very deep states
of connection and seeing into our experience and settling in the mind and
calming so whatever way it goes for you
great and um
part of part of what concentration isn't is struggling
so as much as you can let go of the idea that you need to try and make something
happen and you need to be in conflict with and struggling to make it happen or
upset about what's happening as much as you can just forget all that the better
so with that as the introduction let's consciously find a posture
that we would like to meditate in
so remembering this idea of kind of a there's an uprightness if not
at least in the body to some extent also in the mind an uprightness an interest
a commitment to showing up for our own experience for witnessing
experiencing our present moment experience so just
you know how would we be attending if we believed that what we
were doing was really important that what we're doing right now is
important so just sort of okay yeah this matters
and then taking the moment to rock your posture a little bit lean forward and
back and you know a little bit it sort of helps you find that centered space you know if
we move a little to the right a little to the left oh yeah here we go right in
the middle and same with forward and back because
we can be a little too far forward or leaning slumping a little too far back so just rocking a little bit here and
finding that like uprightness
and you'll all have your eyes here closed which is supportive for
concentration practice you know but if you need to open your eyes
it's okay to have a very soft gaze just just a bit of in front of you
resting the eyes not really looking but just resting the eyes
okay so feeling this sort of arriving in
this posture in this uprightness
like all you need to do right now is to feel sense feel into
your present moment experience
being curious about what this body feels like in this moment
what this breath is like
maybe take a few longer slower breaths
with that exhale you can invite a sense of letting go of the day's stress
of any over efforting
[Applause]
oh Richard did you put push record I did not should I push
okay so just that deep breath in followed by
the exhale
and this idea of resting our Awareness on this experience we're having
sort of letting the awareness of what's Happening kind of follow and be with
whatever is most clear in your experience
to me this feels a little bit like one of the things I love to do
which is in a warm ocean on a beautiful day is to float on a raft
like one of those air mattresses where the water is warm enough but cool
enough where you can just let your body
rest on the raft and just float there
being supported by the ocean feeling the
subtle movement in the water usually in that situation small waves
maybe receiving the sounds of the water
in a way where resting our body on the ocean letting
our body just follow the flow of the water
in the same way we can let our awareness rest on our experience here the breath or the
sensations in the body there's a certain surrender or letting
go into the experience
like letting the experience be what it is we can't really control the ocean right
we live our give ourselves to the intimacy of that experience
so if we're working with an anchor in our practice like the breath
it can be this feeling of just feeling that
resting on the exhale resting on the inhale
breath after breath
and it also can be resting on a sound we're hearing
sort of like oh yeah that that truck you could hear the car and then the sound Fades away and you
can kind of rest into that space too
so again this idea that we don't need to struggle if we get caught and thinking
at some point when we realize what's happening we're already back we're resting again right
there oh right here into whatever you can
sense in your present experience
sometimes if we have Minds that are active for
some reason at the moment there's two things we might try
for having a hard time settling resting on that raft
one is that three-breath Journey just following intimately an inhale
followed by the exhale three breaths in a row just that's it a
small short little period of being very connected
and then we can just do another three breath Journey after that
after taking one of these three breath Journeys you might just notice
what that felt like what's the impact of just just that one little intimate
connection to three breaths
and if it's a one breath Journey instead of three no problem
every moment matters it all counts
you know that feeling you have when you're really relaxed
and you can hear people talking or maybe the phone and you just don't really care
it's a you're just so content resting
relaxing that things can be going on around you
and you can hear them and they come and go and you just it's okay you can wait
imagine having that feeling right now
that being with your experience however it is right now
it's just good enough content enough
giving into it resting in it
so whatever those thoughts that come up in your mind or plans or remembering
it's like oh yeah okay hmm yeah breath
hmm breathing in and breathing out
and with whatever else you're aware of it can just be going on together
is it possible to just have the breathing be in the Forefront and the other things
happening in the background or to have the breath just breathe in and
through the sounds or the sensations or the thoughts
practicing in this way doesn't mean we're suppressing or rejecting anything
instead we're just simply prioritizing being aware
being with
foreign
to ask yourself now what can I notice that's different between the inhale and the exhale
do they feel the same different
does the breath feel the same on the way in in the nose as it does on the way out
just getting a little closer
a little more connected
noticing the temperature of the breath
is it smooth or rough
sometimes with each exhale I can just feel a little more letting go again
eat deep in my back my shoulders
the end of that exhale there can be this little feeling of Letting Go dropping
maybe the breath gets a little slower
maybe there's a pause between the exhale and the inhale
and maybe not just being close
resting on
whatever you're aware of
the moment I'm going to ring the bell
but I want to invite you to stay in your meditation for a moment
let the sound of the Bell be part of what you're aware of
see if you can just hold your awareness until the sound is
fully gone while staying in your meditation posture
[Music]
foreign
minute Diana will talk a little bit about concentration
is it okay if we ask if there are any comments and Reflections about your
experience with this meditation what did you notice how was it for you
thank you Ann Rose please oh well I was uncomfortable in the city
you know I try you know when I'm ambitious I try to sit and on the floor
because normally I wanted him sitting on the in a chair um and then I was like oh I'm
concentrating on trying to get too comfortable and then my leg was falling asleep and then I'm like oh this is not
what I wanted I'm like wait just get up and move and I did and it was cool I
just was I really liked the sensation of focusing on what the breath felt like going in
and I never thought of it like that because sometimes when I'm focusing on the breath I'm like okay I'm breathing
in I'm breathing out but what does that feel like I I like that it was nice
thank you thank you
I thought I was doing a good job concentrating and then all of a sudden I
just faded out and I found myself leading over one way or another and I
thought well that's not so good and I write myself up and said oh can we stay
in a balanced focused position and they say I know I'm leaning over to Psy again as a
it's a little difficult for me to do two things at the same time I think so my
mom just tries to go to a place where it quiet and then it's hard for me to start
counting breathing or I'm not familiar with that in fact I don't even know why we have to do it three times rather than
two or one so I was just struggling with that because I was pretty comfortable
um where my mind was but then I had difficulties in following you know what
you were saying something about breathing which at some point I just stopped listening I guess with a lot of
respect yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah but that worked for me because I'm not really familiar with that three times or
two times so great thank you foreign I think earlier in the meditation you
said something about imagining like a lazy Sunday where you don't have to like do anything or you don't care that was
really helpful because I think I realized that with thinking I naturally kind of try to resist or judge or change
it so that was really helpful and then I think I noticed that as my
thoughts kind of went away weirdly enough I get I guess it's like I have a
lot of thinking energy and when you remove the thoughts the energy just kind of comes out which is a very interesting
experience so yeah thank you thank you
maybe I'll just add the uh Tanya when you said like floating on a raft I
haven't heard that before that was fantastic also I was like I just felt really great like this relaxed floating
it was very nice so thank you
so is concentration practice not really what we kind of normally associate
concentration with okay it's more like a concept I'll talk about oh okay in a little bit uh yeah yeah I'm
going to talk about this Okay so I think it was very helpful Tanya that
you asked us well what what associations do we have with this word concentration in Iris you had said well I kind of it
was a little bit like stressed or I don't remember exactly what word you said but for me in my ear my shoulders
go up towards my ears like oh I'm supposed to focus so because of that I'd like to suggest
that we use another word just because concentration it has this baggage that
goes along with it we have this big Association of whether it's supposed to be so the poly word is samadhi and I
like this samadhi has this kind of like this relaxed
feeling about it and it turns out that that is really important in fact integral to
concentration we might say so samadhi if I were to Define it I would say it's
probably not what we often think about this word concentration but instead it's like the mind and the body feeling
unified kind of like feeling collected feeling in harmony
and with a sense of well-being so the sense of well-being is integral
as well as one way we might think about samadhi is like non-distraction so just
kind of like collect this sense of collectedness but we often think of it as something
that the mind is doing that the mind is you know right on the object
and it's very common that we use the breath as subjects we don't have to but that's very common
so but but I want to highlight that not only is well-being really important but
the body is really important to for this uh for kind of like this collectedness
this Wellness and then I maybe I'll also mention that
so often it's we have this idea okay I need to be concentrated or I am
concentrated or I'm not concentrated but I think it's much more helpful to think of it as a spectrum
like sometimes we're really really distracted just can't keep things
straight at all and sometimes there's this sense of settledness and in this
tradition there can be an extreme sense of settledness it can go really far on
the Spectrum so instead of having this idea I've concentrated or I'm not
concentrated because sometimes when we have this idea I'm not concentrated then there's like and I should be right is
this little beating ourselves up or or then I have to try harder and then we kind of get tight and strain and strive
and that's not the direction to strain and strive or beat ourselves up
does not help absolutely it doesn't help in fact it goes the opposite direction it's a form of Destruction
so it's really helpful because this is how it actually is it's just a spectrum
so just to notice am I moving towards more settledness and well-being or am I
moving away settleness and well-being I think that's a really helpful way to
consider this as opposed to this binary yes no am I this way or not
so how maybe I'll add one more thing about
um concentration or samadhi here is it's not only about collectedness and
well-being and I'm using this word well-being purposely to be very vague
because we find it we find our way into that in different ways
for some people it's just a kind of a quiet sense of contentment
drinking hot chocolate for me when I was a kid that was like something that I loved you know so that kind of a feeling
and for some other people it's really
a big giant like Wahoo it's my birthday you know that kind of a Feeling
so just well-being wherever uh however you experience that
so not only is it well-being than this collectedness but the third element is
that when this happens the mind is able to see things a little bit more subtle than we can see in our regular way in
which we're practicing we can start to see things that aren't so obvious when
we're in our regular I sometimes called like Street Consciousness when we're
just going down the street type of thing and one way to think about it is if
mindfulness is like awareness and we can think of awareness as like a
flashlight or maybe even a telescope
that looks at something it brings attention to something and highlights it so that we can see it
and samadhi is we can think of it as like the tel uh
tripod that's underneath it so then this beam whether it's a telescope or
flashlight is then steady steady on whatever it is it's seen and
because it's steady it can see things that otherwise you can't see for example
if it's a telescope right you can't see things so well on a telescope if it's jittery so this allows it to Be steady
so an obvious question is well what is the difference between mindfulness and the samadhi thing like how is the
meditation different what what what's the relationship between them
well one way is that mindfulness which I kind of like we know we have this object
which is very often the breath pay attention to the breath the mind wanders the mind wanders it's planning it's
dreaming it's doing whatever it is and then it comes back to the breath the mind wanders and it comes back to the
breath with mindfulness practice we're holding everything in kind regard so if
there's a an uncomfortable bodily body sensation we could just put the flashlight of
awareness mindfulness onto that uncomfortable body sensation hold that with kind regard
until it's no longer compelling and then come back to the breath with concentration practice
we have this object the breath we just stay with the breath stay with the breath one breath Two Bros three breaths
ten bazillion breaths however many and then we have a kind disregard for
the other things we just stay with the breath and it's
not that we're shoving things away it's not that we're insisting that they be different but we just kind of like this
kind disregard maybe it's like okay I hear that sound but I'm just gonna let
it go I'm not gonna get tangled up with it and get mad at it or anything I'm just gonna oh there's a sound but I just
stay with the breath stay with the breath so that's one way we might understand
the difference between mindfulness and concentration whereas mindfulness might have the breath and then the sound and
then bodily sensation and then come back to the breath with a concentration smartest breath
breath breath breath that's we're kind of putting
but he's asking like why the breath and why
not something else focus on maybe a positive image a positive
sensation and something else you know why the breath well what point yeah yeah
this is a good question like why the breath so it doesn't have to be the breath we this is
the most common for some people this doesn't work maybe they have you know
trauma they or they have asthma or something like this and just to think about the breath is really uncomfortable
but there's a few things that's helpful about the breath one is that uh you can
tune into the sensations to the experience of it
because I was mentioning earlier how the body is involved so it's not just mental
even though we use this word mindfulness it feels like a misnomer it's really like body fullness or so so
the breath is something that the body is doing and because the breath has this
movement it's a little bit easier to pay attention to because it's harder to pay attention to
something that's static if something is a little bit moving then the mind is a little bit more interested in it for
example Tanya and her guide meditation could have said pay attention to the beginning
middle and end of an exhale and that's a way of kind of like getting
a little bit more intimate with the experience or what's what does it feel
like to have the gap between an inhale and an exhale so these are ways in which
the mind can you know kind of like tune in and maybe like touch the experience
more um closely but join us well why not a
positive image or something just um like we absolutely you could do like a
candle flickering or um some people do loving kindness practice we're not going
to talk about that so much today which is about phrases and like sending
will wishing to other people and to ourselves so it definitely can be that but I would say for concentration can be
like the candle flame or loving kindness phrases or
um all kinds of things are probably yeah visualizations and all these types
of things mindfulness practice is more just about the bodily experience the
actual what's happening and
I don't I don't have experience doing mindfulness with uh like uh imagining
something the problem is that we're trying to stay in the present
moment and the body is in the present moment like of course it is where else could it be
but the mind not so often is it in the present moment it's always planning or
remembering or fantasizing or rehashing a conversation
or you know something like this so to our life is actually happening in
the present moment and this practice is that really helps support our life so to be in the present moment is kind of like
mindfulness so one way to think about
this is that um concentration
naturally arises if we do a lot of mindfulness if we just start doing
mindfulness and we do it a lot concentration naturally arises what does
that mean to do it a lot well there's two ways we can think about that one is for longer durations that
when we sit then we just sit for longer durations and of course right we just
start to get settled eventually it happens provided you don't have like body bodily pain because that's
distracting and you often won't get settled or provided that the environment
supports you that if the neighbor's dog and gets joined the whole
chorus of something else or you know it provided the environment supports you and your body supports you just sitting
longer settledness and well-being just start to happen so it goes towards concentration
so that's one way to be like sit more you'll have some concentration
a second way is just to be regular with practice you know to meditate every day
meditate daily even if it's just for five minutes you
know meditate longer you'll have a more concentration more samadhi
but this kind of regularity of practice is really helpful really can make a
difference so that's the second way you could do it longer and then the third way you can do
more mindfulness is to do a day-long retreat or a week-long retreat or
something like this so that is to meditate for very for a number of hours in one day
and of course because the body cannot do that cannot just sit still for so long then you do sitting meditation and when
we do it here at IMC we do this on Wednesday mornings it's um
City meditation and then walking meditation so you can move the body
and maybe bring the energy up or bring the energy down and then go do sitting meditation again and then on Retreats
you can do like then walking and then sitting so sit walk sit walk so this alternation just to help take care of
the body otherwise it's too hard to just sit for that long but you can do walking meditation in a
way that really can support this collectiveness and this sense of well-being and the sense of Harmony or
unification that can happen so does it have to be in the seated posture
for some people they do lying down but then the you know meditation practice
soon turns into sleeping practice which is fine right because I mean makes
perfect sense this is what our minds and bodies are used to you get horizontal you close your eyes you go to sleep
right those are the only times in your life that you're horizontal with your eyes closed usually so it's definitely
uh something that has to be practiced to be able to do mindfulness laying down
so what are some other things to like think about if
we want to have this sense of unification and well-being there's a number of ways that we can do
to really support this and it encourages that um
things that we're doing off the cushion off the cushion when we're not meditating do you have an impact on the
mind of course right there's only one mind so the same thing that is maybe
watching Tick Tock videos where I don't know how long they are but they're short
right and so one after the other after the other after the other in the mind's like stimulated like okay so doing a lot
of that you know the mind of course is going to have a hard time settling down
or maybe there's a way in which there's a
part of like this kind disregard that I talked about so we're with our anchor I
could use this word anchor so I'm suggesting it's the breath but as John pointed out it can be other things
doesn't have to be the breath we can use this word anchor that
um while we're with the anchor we could have this kind disregard for other whatever else is happening but
that this kind disregard requires a little bit of like this letting go of like okay I'm not going to get tangled
up with that sound I like to use the neighbor's dog barking because that's if that's part of my life
experiences I have a neighbor whose dog barks on occasion that's
so there's one way in which we could just sit there and be fuming right it's like I can't believe it why don't they
let the dog out this poor dog and and then they always do this and you know maybe the dog needs some blah blah right
we can just really get tangled up with the what I say tangled up I mean like lost in thoughts
but there's a way in which um we can let go
of his stories we have about it like yep we could follow that thought train and
think for 20 minutes about how the dog should be otherwise or we cannot
just kind of let go like oh I'm lost in thought okay I'm just going to let go of that so this idea of letting go is not so
easy initially might be something that we need to kind of like cultivate and practice
so this is something that we can do when we're not in the meditation posture it's just practice
letting go and so what does that mean
it means there's a number of different ways of letting go of insisting that we
have to be right you know letting somebody else like they may be saying something and we don't agree maybe we
don't correct them or maybe we don't insist that they have to know what we're doing right we do this in a in the
settings that are appropriate or maybe we let go of wanting to have
our preferences if the for example you and your partner want to do something and your partner wants to do something
different maybe just kind of let go of your preference at that time so just these things that we do in our
daily life really help settle the mind and the Heart instead of always trying
to get one more thing so this practice is not about acquiring
it turns out by letting go all these beautiful things naturally
arise we do not have to go chase after them we do not have to make them happen
but they're just happening with this Letting Go including this samadhi this
concentration letting go of the things that are that are distractions or insisting that things
are different so that was a it's kind of a little bit about samadhi
we have time maybe just for a few questions but I kind of threw some a lot
of information out that way are there some questions or comments
um does this mean you don't explicitly practice concentration or like
if you naturally do a lot of mindfulness meditation eventually as you're doing a
meditation you reach concentration is that kind of how it works or do you like explicitly do like concentration
practices yeah yeah thank you Iris this is great um both sometimes you can say specifically I'm going to do
concentration practice okay and that would mean uh you know just like staying
with the anchor and I would say you talked about you do like open awareness practice and you can definitely have concentration with open awareness it's
uh takes a little bit longer sometimes I practice this way it takes a little bit longer to settle but the subtleness
tends to have a little bit more stability when the when the Mind settles if you're doing open awareness practice
so yeah and sometimes it is true right if you just do a lot of mindfulness it'll just start happening at a
concentration okay thanks okay
just quickly so you start with mindful concentration and eventually that will
take you to the I guess
mindful meditation and then that takes you to cons
[Music] Ole the concentration
yeah you know what I mean yeah yeah so that that's one way and that's a very common way but you can
intentionally do some concentration also and that is to just really stay with the
anchor stay with the anchors stay with the anchor and have this sense of collectedness and well-being so this
allowing the sense of well-being to arise while staying with the anchor with the
anchor with the anchor or it's a lot of letting go I have to say
too I don't know Tony do you have something that you'd like to add here
um
I think I'd like I to me I really resonate with that idea of letting go
um and I kind of kind of mentioned it in the meditation sort of that feeling of being so relaxed
that it's sort of like it doesn't matter anymore what's happening around you
you just don't have you don't care enough you don't you know you said the kind disregard which was a really fun
way of naming it another way is so it's like it's almost
like also this idea of letting go there is a phase in which it is a very
active process where we have to try and help ourselves
let go of something no let go of the ice cream or you know no let go of worrying
about later but the more we let go
the less it's actually the more automatic it becomes the more
it becomes like instead of having to let go of something it's more like I don't
want to pick up anything yeah it's just like it's okay it doesn't
matter you know it's like just sort of like it's just too much work to pick up
something else it's it's you're too relaxed to want to get up
you know um so I think that it changes
and I think there's in the beginning there is this you know anytime we start to sit there's more of this Active
Energy to helping ourselves stay with a breath helping ourselves let go of the thinking
to come back to hold the posture but after a while it's like
um things like the in a snow globe right if you shake it up all the little
snowflakes are swirling around and and you set it down
and slowly the snowflakes come to the rest come to rest at the
bottom of the snow globe right and there's almost a similar process that
starts to happen for us that things just start to come I like
the word resting to a place of resting we're just sort of intimate with
whatever settled intimate resting and then
what will happen is like picking up the snow globe you know we move the
snowflakes get stirred around and maybe it's a thought or a pain that comes up
and it does the same thing it stirs the mind again and you know sometimes that might be a
lot but sometimes it might just be oh and then it's uh it just comes back to
rest again
and I'd say you don't have to worry about concentration at all you don't have to
you can just do mindfulness just and there's some people maybe I'll just
add this list some people have a propensity for concentration and some people have propensity more for
mindfulness just different minds are different so not this isn't necessarily
that's something everybody has to do or everybody wants to do or something like this it's just a recognition of
something that will happen if you do a lot of mindfulness practice
there's something one other word that I've used that I like which is there's uh intimacy
a sense of connection intimacy with with your experience and that
um and that happens in mindfulness too when there isn't um
there there isn't contention with what's happening and there also isn't
engagement with what's happening right entanglement with it there can just be a like walking with
your good friend and there's this sense of connection and intimacy between you
um and I think that there's a way in which that our our mindfulness can
grow in this intimacy when there's this lack of contention
and this lack of engagement but but not meaning
disconnected makes sense
yeah okay
yeah Iris um if you kind of have a hard time
letting go is that where kind of like the mindfulness developing that relation
first will kind of help you let go easier or how do you kind of help let go
easier
this is a great question and you know and we're us we're saying oh just let go no problem
definitely this is like a skill I I would say it's right something that people definitely have to develop
so there are a few things and one is uh maybe like in our daily life to
recognize when there are moments of contentment and so we tend to be dismissive of when
everything's okay we rather just don't even ignore them we kind of but there might be times when you're sitting in
your car and like everything's fine you're just it's fine or you uh just finished a meal
everything's fine you know these scents of everything's fine so this cultivating
a sense of contentment allows the mind and the body and the
heart to recognize oh there it's um
it's there is possible to have this sense of okayness without always looking
for the next thing so sometimes we just have to reassure
this mind and heart that yeah there are these times during the day when things are okay
and again this is not necessarily easy because you know our habit is to notice oh that's a problem I have to fix it oh
that's a problem I have to fix that and we get rewarded for fixing problems and you know in our professional life our
family life this is what we do so this is kind of a radical thing that we're
suggesting here so I offered one thing do you do you want to offer something for
yeah I like I like the idea of let be
another approach to letting go is oh just letting it be
I don't have to do anything about this I don't have to change it I could just let
it be and everything is gonna the itch is gonna go away you know the irritating
sound is gonna happen and then not happen and
then happen again and sort of a again it's a non-contention a
little bit to me not having that sort of just willingness
to let things be the way they are in you know in meditation
um is a letting go and it's easier than this idea to me
letting go has a very active feeling to it which there are times we need we
might need to kind of make a decision that might be another way to put it
I need to make a decision to stop arguing with this
and then we decide that and then we have to remind ourselves and remind ourselves and then slowly as we keep remembering
that we're not going to argue with this anymore we it just Fades because we're not
engaging it anymore it fades away and that's that's kind of one way that
we let go so letting go sometimes very active but
also can just be a very allowing letting be
thank you both ideas are very pretty new to me great seemed very helpful okay
great your questions were awesome for me the idea of letting go is to
actually end up winning so um I Let Go
because even though in my mind I'm losing because well you know the person who
wants to upset me you know it's it's gonna think that upset me
because I'm not reacting to that in my mind is I'm winning because
I can continue doing something different yeah so yeah absolutely I guess there is
not a lot of altruism I'm seeing things in that from from that perspective but
it works for me because I'm willing to lose because I'm actually winning yeah so that simplifies the you know yeah and
other things which is really there's so much wisdom in that to me that's when I
think about the first Noble Truth right which is that they're suffering it to me this is the way I would talk about what
you're saying which is I'm going to suffer if I keep fighting with this person I don't want to suffer
so I don't care let them let them win because I don't want to keep suffering
in that way and so I win that way I win because I'm not going to add to my
suffering they can think whatever they want
that's right that's right that's right I agree
and maybe if this is okay I'll say some other things that are supportive for letting go or for concentration and that
is just simplicity mm-hmm and in all the different ways that it
can show up in our lives just not being too busy not being in a place
that's too cluttered not you know just Simplicity of course that just helps
things to settle right when there's a certain about a simplicity
and I talked about also kind of like somebody having this sense of well-being but just some kindness right just in our
daily life just practicing kindness towards ourselves and towards other people that feels good of course it does
so these are some of the things that can help support meditation practice in general and maybe a samadhi practice in
particular so
can you use the mic for the recording thank you so much oh I'm sorry
um I think a meditation is sort of like a mental uh massage
you know if I've uh if I'm physically uh tired after exercise
I could get a massage and basically the masseur will unknot all my muscles
you know and boy that's that's really relaxing and I and I noticed that when when I had meditate I had the same kind
of feeling it feels like your mind is just tangled up with worries planning and all this other
stuff uh and meditation just simply taking those Tangos away just like the tangles
in your muscle and then and it's very relaxing
yeah relaxing and this uh word Tangles a great word and this is a word that shows
up a lot is like to untangle the tangle this uh kind of like the Buddhist literature has this expression to
untangle the tangle
I think um one other thing that might be worth talking about is
um just to maybe invite you to think about moments in your life
right it doesn't have to be formal meditation where you could you felt that sense of
contentment ease the untangling the the the resting just whatever you
were doing you you know with the Buddha it was under a memory of being under an
apple tree as a child while his father was working in the field it inspired him to practice and
brought him to Liberation remembering that experience of sitting on a summer
day under an apple tree watching his father working in the field relaxing
that it was very pleasant you know collected feeling of well-being at ease
contented for me that memory is of times on boats
and floats in the water with the water with the sun with the warmth with the sound of Chess
I could spend hours laying on the bench in my father's boat or floating on a raft in the lake
just I was so content and comfortable and um so I wondered if you have
memories experiences that you could describe and and that can help you connect with that
feeling if you'd be willing to share
go for it in Rose well to keep in mind with Simplicity as
Diana put um like washing the dishes and the song starts playing and then I'm
like not that I want to wash the dishes but then it's you know just if I'm gonna wash the
dishes I should wash the dishes like take nocton would say and and it's just like even if I'm feeling
really bad about something like I have been recently I just this feels nice or
this is a nice I'm like it doesn't you don't have to go on a spa day yeah to to
feel contentment it's it doesn't have to be so big it could just be so
something like that beautiful beautiful thank you
do you have an experience virus
um I guess I like the idea of Simplicity yeah um and I think your med your
instructions really remind me of like Sunday afternoons when I don't really have anything on an agenda
that just feels really nice yeah great
I have great memories of um I like cooking I mean I have learned how to
cook you know especially since from South America so I usually get together with friends family and just you know
spend time cooking and enjoying life so those are moments that yes and you know
connect me with I guess the positive parts of
everything beautiful yeah so with cooking you know you have
to pay attention to how you're holding the knife and the vegetables and the pressure there's so much mindfulness
happening you know and the smells and the colors to look in and that's very present
moment right very present moment not having to head off and do a bunch of things on your Sunday you know you just
there's this resting in the experience of the dishwashing you know that's
there's something really where Intimate we're connected or you know sort of in
open to being with this moment in this way that
is so nice so nourishing brings the well-being
yeah maybe I'll share something too is that um my mom and I used to
make like greeting cards together and it was just something very sweet we would
just be sitting at the kitchen table you know cutting or I don't know stamping doing all this kind of stuff but it was
just very nice like we had this little project that together we were doing and it was very sweet so this idea of kind
of doing some activity that requires attention but it's enjoyable and nothing
else needs to happen yeah
so are there any other comments or
questions any other Curiosities and Richard maybe you could check and see if there's anything on YouTube a question
or a comment welcome to happy happy to hear from anybody on YouTube and
I hope the idea here is to invite you to not get tangled up
with the idea of concentration the tangling up around it won't lead to
the opposite of concentration or samadhi
and maybe I'll just share that for me it was a turning point in my practice when I realized oh well-being is a key here
somehow I felt like strive and I just had to really strain and huff and puff
and it turns out that the certain amount of um for me I wasn't feeling well actually
and during a retreat and so I was lying down in my room and meditating
I was just having a little bit of knee issue so I just had to give my knees some rest and it was something about
just being horizontal that was just a little bit more a little bit less efforting a little bit
more comfortable at that time and it allowed like oh some concentration to
happen and like oh this is what they've been talking about oh I see so
maybe I'll say this that some of these deep concentration States
when they arise it will be a surprise it will always be a surprise because if
you're really really really striving and straight and you're not going to get there so it just arises as a surprise just at
that so you don't have to be trying super super hard but at the same time we have been talking about letting go and
contentment and simplicity and kindness and well-being it is a skill
in terms of it is something that we kind of have to train the mind and the body to do to you know keep on coming back
don't follow the distraction just keep on coming back to the anchor for the breath or whatever the anchor is
that you're using and we've learned lots of skills in our lives we learned to tie our shoes most
likely drive a car or ride a bike or right we've learned lots of things so
this is just one more thing that we can learn
yeah yeah Cyrus
thank you have there been times where you've kind of like lost a bit of motivation or like interest in practice
and like uh if you're like motivation kind of Ebbs and flows and you've
reached a point where you're like uh not really feeling that motivated um has that happened to you and like how
do you work with that great question Iris great question
do you want to go first or no you unless you want me to yes yes
right we're only human right of course this happens and I've gone through phases like this is crazy I don't know
what I'm doing I'm never gonna do this again like and then you know then I do
so what helps uh having friends who
meditate and sometimes I'm using this word friends really lightly in terms
maybe it could just be Associates or colleagues or so it makes a huge difference to be with a group
so whether it's online or in person so that takes a little bit of effort right to log on or to go to a place but that
can really make a big difference to as a support
um and there's often sometimes maybe I'll offer this and maybe some other people have some ideas too the second
thing is it can be helpful to check in with or reconnect with why we started
meditation in the beginning and like oh I was having these
difficulties or I wanted to do something and it might be that what was initially motivating us as uh as lessons of some
of the difficulties or something like this or but it's not uncommon
for why we're like maybe to start because we're having
some degree of suffering in our lives and I'm using this word suffering to go just like stress all the way to
you know this just receiving a very scary diagnosis and you have limited
time to live you know the whole range from just mildly stressful and irritated to you're going to die unexpectedly and
you know it but um it could be that when we became practice then it's not uncommon that we
catch a glimpse of something and it points to maybe we're not even sure what
it points to but it touches the heart or touches the mind in some way like
whoa what was that and it kind of like I feel like we want
I want to touch it again or understand that better or something like that so that's not uncommon
so just maybe if that has happened to kind of like connect to that like what
whatever that was even if you don't know what it was that kind of something but
you know maybe you have some things on the hour you know I was thinking um I was
thinking about that feeling of you know not being very motivated and how when I think about any time that I
still got myself to sit down even if it was for five minutes I I don't think it ever made me feel
worse and I can pretty confidently say I always felt better
and and so um maybe it's getting disenchanted with the
discontent or the the doubt and being sort of like well okay but I'm
gonna I mean literally for me for a long time it was really only five minutes
but I kept that five I kept sitting for that five minutes if that's all I could do that's all I could do but that five
minutes for there was about a year where it was a lot of five minutes it's
but boy did that that year of five minutes sits leave an impression on me
really impacted me so
I think um maybe even if you took two minutes when your mind says why am I doing this
and saying well let me sit for two minutes and see why am I doing this and discover Anew each time
um because that two minutes will make a difference
any other maybe one one more comment or question or we can just move to
dedication of Merit at this point but I guess I'll just say I really
appreciate the questions the reflections the engagements
uh well I have to I'm very grateful for IMC and for Tanya and you Diana the
Monday sittings and these Thursdays have been have been revolutionary from my mind
that's been kind of in its own Battlefield and so
um the yesterday in terms of concentration and the surprise element I realized I I came to see it be to to
meditate because of my anxious and you know overthinking and all those things
and just stuck very stuck and
Then I then I came to this conclusion when I was on the phone with my sister like oh wait I notice what I'm doing
when I'm feeling really anxious and it's just either with my speech or what I'm
saying and whether I'm gossiping too much and I'm like and I never would have I never would have been aware of that
had I just taken the time to just be still and it was really surprising and
that was that was last night and I'm like oh my goodness and even if I received bad news
and I wanna hold on to that forever I don't have to and if I'm like striving
to change it or fix it and that's usually it usually doesn't work for me
um doing something differently and it was just so I'm just very very
grateful truly so much I there's I have a long way to go but yeah a five or a
ten minute sit in the morning and in the evening for me has been I I can't imagine not doing it anymore
because it's to not take that time for myself so that I could be better for others or at least
more mindful in what I do is just I I thank you
and thank you for highlighting that we don't just practice for ourselves we practice for others
this is how the world becomes a better place right it's when people are more tuned into what's happening with them
and sensitive to what's happening with others and beautiful
segue to dedication of Merit so we don't just practice for ourselves
we practice for really ideally the benefit of all beings without exception
and so one of the things I've been doing on Thursday nights is to help us you
know all beings is a concept an idea sometimes we have certain beings in mind
that we know are suffering or could use the benefit of our practice and
so I want to invite anyone to share anyone you want to name to be part of
this dedication of Merit any group any person any being any animals whatever
whatever um you want us to bring to mind
so is there anything you would like to specify
I guess from my perspective I just wish all of you everybody here everybody here
lots of happiness and I'm very happy that I'm here to talk beautiful
thank you Emmanuel
this is [Laughter]
thank you for being being willing to use the microphone even though it stresses you out because it's amazing people do
listen to these talks and we hear about it now I remember when
I was a student too hearing other people oh my gosh was this Lifesaver like oh
they're just like me they have the same questions I do makes a big difference yeah so I know it's weird to hold the
mic but it is speaking of for the benefit of all beings
it really it's amazing what happens and you hear people talking
about what they heard and it's really a gift
so made this practice our time together the things that you've shared that we've
shared may it be a benefit to each other to all of our others in our lives and to
all beings everywhere foreign
[Music]
thank you thank you thank you all wishing you a wonderful rest of the evening
and tell me what what uh on next week what is happening next week
um next week is the first