greetings greetings friends greetings sangha
whatever time zone you are in good morning good afternoon good evening
lovely to be with you in practice together at this moment in time
so for today this week we've been exploring the
refrain of the sati patana sutta going through each statement
step by step together and exploring it and um
i'll say more again about the context uh during the uh brief darmet afterwards
and i'll put up the uh diagram again just just to give a refresher
and for the guided meditation i'd like to just mention very briefly
what the statement the sentence is um that we're working on with today so
so the statement this the next part of the refrain we're working with today
is um mindfulness that there is a body is
established in one to the extent necessary for bare knowledge and continuous
mindfulness i'm going to read this again because this is going to serve as the
inspiration actually maybe it will help to read the whole refrain just for context so
the whole refrain in this way in regard to the body
one abides contemplating the body both internally
or one abides contemplating the body externally or one abides contemplating
the body both internally and externally we did this
a couple of days ago the next sentence or one abides contemplating the nature of arising in
the body or one abides contemplating the nature of passing away in the body
or one abides contemplating the nature of both arising and passing away in the
body we explored impermanence yesterday now here is the next sentence
or mindfulness that there is a body
is established in one to the extent necessary
for bare knowledge and continuous mindfulness
read it one more time or mindfulness that there is a body
is established in one to the extent necessary for bare knowledge
and continuous mindfulness so there are many keywords here which i will expand
on later in the dharmat and during the guided meditation i'll
invite i'll invite you i'll give invitations based on these particular keywords here
that there is a body extent necessary for bare knowledge
continuous mindfulness these are of course beautiful poetic but they're not just poetry these are direct
instructions that the buddha is offering so until i'll just read the last sentence
which we'll bring in tomorrow and put it all together
the last couple of sentences one abides independent not clinging to
anything in the world that is how in regard to the body one abides contemplating the body so
so without further ado let's let's practice together
formally ah arriving arriving in our seat
arriving in this body
here here
as always let's start
by relinquishing by releasing thoughts preoccupations
what is not needed releasing preoccupations
relaxing into the body relaxing into the body
and taking refuge in this moment in time
in our hearts intention in our goodness coming together to practice together
taking refuge
and the goodness within possibility for awakening
the teachings and the sangha buddha dharma sangha
ah let there be brightness let there be brightness
this sense of alignment maybe sitting up a little straighter if you're sitting
not tightening still relaxed
but a sense of alignment verticality
in our heart body and mind
noticing there is a body there is a body
aware there is a body
awareness can there be awareness with this phrase with dropping in
there is a body
not so much here is my body or what is this body oh
there's a body there's a body here
there's breathing happening here sensations
there is a body
notice how the use of this mental labeling very light
can bring recognition [Music]
sanya recognition [Music]
what is here present
and support sati mindfulness
and clear comprehension of what is here
simply there is a body
established in awareness
here not entangled
but spacious
knowing clearly knowing clearly knowing there is a body
not to analyze not to be entangled
just simply this awareness
knowing there is a body
this reflection for the purpose
of continued awareness continued mindfulness
bare knowledge bare knowledge
and continued
awareness light touch
there is a body there is a body
a mental note
a linguistic note
if you notice there's entanglement in the mind
the linguistic noting technique there is a body there is a body
ah establishing re-establishing
sati awareness mindfulness and continued
continued recognition without entanglement
analysis simply knowing clearly knowing
there is a body
simply barely knowing
continuous mindfulness there is a body
there is a body so simple and yet profound
and for the last moments of this practice period together
whether there were many moments of fair knowing clear comprehension
continued mindfulness or just one it's okay
letting go relinquishing releasing any judgment
you showed up you did your best by just showing up and planting seeds
we're cultivating goodness individually and collectively
in the world for the benefit of ourselves
and others let us trust in this goodness and this goodness co-created
and offer it generously generously and with humility
our goodness the goodness of this body this heart this mind
and all of us collectively in this brief period in time that we're
alive this flash of lightning that is our life
offer this goodness offer this goodness
from our practice today to all beings everywhere especially to those
in the war zones those feeling unsafe threatened
fearful offering offering our care
to all beings especially those in difficult situations
may all beings everywhere be safe may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
thank you for your practice
greetings greetings dear friends
global friends it's such a delight
to feel your presence all over
the world in various places there's just a sense of brightness and gladness
that's arising for me right now um feeling trusting you're here we're all
practicing together just i feel connected to you as if
as if i see you in your in your homes you're just all here
connected connected through this this invisible thread of goodness and
intention coming together coming together to practice so beautiful so beautiful
i'm so touched thank you yeah so
[Music] so today we continue
our fourth day of exploring the refrain of the satipatana
so just to remind us [Music] of the context
i will share this screen [Music] just a bit of review
so the sati patana sutta the four foundations of mindfulness
sutta which you've been practicing studying with gil
systematically over the past many weeks and continuing
to practice for the next few weeks so the suta has four sections so looking at
this and this is drawn from the book sati patana the direct path to
realization by pico analia a wonderful book wonderful book it's actually it's
it's his thesis is his phd thesis that he did on on this um
so looking starting from the bottom structure is there's four parts there's
the body you see on the left side there's the body there's six part six teachings to it
feelings which you practice with guilt last week feeling tones or vedana
there's mind mind states often translated as and then there is the
dhamma so these are the four foundations for establishments four ways to
establish awareness through these these ways through these establishments
foundations and each teaching each of these
teachings and i trust you can see my cursing each of these many many teachings in
these sections go into detailed descriptions as to how to do
the description how to do the the contemplation you know
postures lists the postures or say corpse and decay
as a cemetery contemplation stages of decay the many stages to go through etc
and at the beginning there is a definition which i shared at the very
first day i'll touch into it today again and the refrain repeats after every section so the
refrain sati patana sutta the buddha offers the refrain 13 times
as if to say hello are you listening i'm going to repeat the refrain
13 times and as i said earlier
i thought oh refrain you know sometimes the sutas are very repetitive like okay okay i want to get to the main teaching
whereas actually the refrain is so important as we have been exploring
today this this whole week together okay
so so today we want to focus on the third
statement as i read it earlier um so just to bring bring us up to date we the
first statement has to do with internal external not just internally as we
associate mindfulness to be just internally just internal long-term no internally
one abides contemplating the body internally one abides contemplating the body externally and one abides
contemplating internally and externally we discussed that we practiced with that
and the sense of [Music] impersonality of oh internal external
can can can pop out yesterday we worked with the second statement
arising passing or rising and passing and the significance of of contemplating
impermanence which is a doorway which is necessary for awakening
um one cannot awaken without a deep appreciation
contemplation of arising and passing really rocking getting impermanence in
every way not in just one way not in just one phenomena but in every way all
phenomena internal external the perceiver and the perceived
all aspects of experience the long list of satipatana teachings that's why the
buddha keeps repeating after everything after everything right
it contemplating say impermanence after breathing after
postures after activities anatomical parts like it's all impermanent it all
arises and passes away everything feeling tones mind states
hindrances ac everything it's it's pretty radical teaching you know it's
applied to all of these and today
we turn to this third sentence which relates to the previous two sentences so
kind of building up the third sentence or mindfulness that
there is a body is established in one to the extent necessary for bare
knowledge and continuous mindfulness okay there are a lot of key words here okay let's let's decode the significance
of this so and and in the guided meditation i
brought in there is a body there is a body we dropped it in and by the way just to say uh let me share this screen
one more time uh the the refrain of course after this the
fee after the like this refrain after feeling tones it says the contemplation
is that there is a feeling tone not that there is a body or after the mind would be
uh contemplated that there are mind states so
so that there is a body repeats in the body section and then the refrain for
feelings mind dhammas to substitute the word feelings mind damas for the word
body in the refrain just to be clear these ones don't say there is a body
they say contemplating that there is dominance just to be clear when you read it of
course you'll see as you've seen so
so what's the significance of this practice that there is
a x there is a body there is dhammas there's
feeling tones but i'm just going to continue with the body here just to have a specific instantiation but just
again you can apply it to all these other foundations
so so first um mindfulness that there is a body so this
is a uh what's called a mental label or a mental note or or
rather a linguistic note this is the way that the suttas and this is common
actually many places in the suttas for example in the anapanasati suta that
one knows i'm breathing i breathe in long one knows i breathe in short like one knows
like oh yeah this is a linguistic like it's a linguistic device
and this is often in the tradition in the practice it's called mental noting but mental
kind of i i like linguistic or lexical noting because mental somehow i feel
like we have to note it in our head but but lexical i think is a better choice of
the word or linguistic note so i'm going to use linguistic note
so it's a linguistic note as we practice with together oh there is a body there
is a body you drop it in drop it and you bring it up and the idea here is that um
it's [Music] it's a skillful employment it's a
skillful use of verbal knowledge so the practice doesn't mean that you have to
relinquish all verbal knowledge uh but actually concepts can be helpful
for the sake of knowledge and continued mindfulness as it says in the rest of
the sentence and in fact i think what i'll do is that i will put this line
in chat so that you can actually see this and follow this this line of the citra that we're talking about here we
go so so there is a skillful use of of
linguistic noting for the purpose
of bare knowledge and continuous mindfulness this labeling this label actually can
strengthen recognition can strengthen as you might have experienced yourself today in our
practice can strengthen recognition and clear comprehension it kind of brings it
back together if the mind is distracted and and lots is arising oh there is a body there
is a body and again it's not that this it's my body this oh it's there is
a body there's a sense of objectivity there's a sense of objectivity there is a body there's a sense of spaciousness
that can arise ah there is a body and yet
the this is not an end to itself this this lexical note we don't keep
repeating it as a mantra we don't we don't attach to it it's only again as
this beautiful line in the sutta says to the extent necessary
so important to the extent necessary for bare knowledge and continued mindfulness
like ah yes here and you might have noticed it i
hope you did for at least for a little bit like yeah there is ease like oh yeah there's kind of it's easier there's a
body i can there's an awareness of it and there's more continuous
mindfulness awareness clear knowing when this lexical
labeling is used another significance of this and i'll
wrap up quickly is that
yes labeling is not a means to an end uh it will be let go of when it does
establish awareness um so and it also connects this clear
knowing here in this sentence where knowledge and continuous mind it connects to what we discussed about the
definition on monday with sam paganya with clear comprehension so this mental
note can bring more clear comprehension which i really hope you you experienced
and lastly to say this idea of this use of concept here
this concept using this mental this this keep saying mental
lexical note we are using concepts in a helpful way and another thing to say
the object of this practice is not to get rid of concepts to have an empty
mind this is a misperception sometimes people think oh yeah the point is to
empty my mind no here the buddha is actually instructing us to bring in to use
concepts skillfully in order to establish what in order to establish
bare knowledge and continuous mindfulness so this is a very important point here
with that i'd like to end by thanking you and inviting you if today
um as you go about your daily life take this practice with you
there is a body when you are distracted stressed perhaps ah there is a body and
again it's not my body it's like oh there's a body there's a sense of spaciousness
uh healthy lack of attachment like oh there's a body wow how amazing there's a body that's
one thing that was coming up for me this morning sense of joy actually can arise oh there is a body wow
and continuous mindfulness the mind can really engage and relish the light
in in continuous mindfulness so so please take the practice with you
through the day let it be with you support you thank you so much for your practice and looking
forward to being with you tomorrow as we bring it all together
be well take good care