I'm bringing your awareness in Word to the breath moving moving through your
body
moving through the abdomen
the entirety of the in-breath the entirety of the out breath
aware
and you don't need to make a project out of breathing it happens on its own
it does not need to be effortful at all
relax soften the body
let go of any tightness or tension and just receive the breath
receive the entirety of the breath in your abdomen and your whole body
Let It Be nourishing Let It Be soothing
calming grounding
oh my God
receiving the breath and the forceful Act
but as if each breath was a gift the receiving a gift
of kindness that keeps this body alive
functioning
relaxing receiving
each breath
okay
then if though to rise you notice the mind is now
entangled in a plan for the future memory from the past it's okay it's all
right it's okay no need for self-flagellation
noticing what this thought the scenario the story
is
and smilingly releasing releasing
thank you but not now I see you but not now
and inviting the Simplicity of this present moment
just sitting privilege of just sitting and being
breathed a moment of Refuge
taking Refuge
right here right now
each moment a new arrival reconnecting with the breath
in the abdomen the lower abdomen
your whole body
foreign
spaciously kindly
feel like you can open also your sphere of awareness
to include the sounds Sound of Silence in the room
sound of my voice
the sound of your breathing the noises
that arise and pass all the sounds
spaciously spaciously thoughts too are like sounds
arise and pass
just as we don't need to get entangled with
every sound that arises and passes
every passing car
we don't need to get entangled with every thought that arises and
passes
receiving relaxing receiving it all
unmoved upright rounded sitting like a tall mountain
taking refuge in this moment
in your heart
The Sound of Silence
please experiment with wearing a smile
and see how
a smile can shift the space of your mind your heart in
this moment giving yourself kindness the gift of a little smile
see how it might shift the landscape of your heart your mind
the half smile of the Buddha
and as we bring the sitting period to a close
offering yourself a gift of kindness appreciation
for having showed up as well as you were able to
not judging comparing what happened or did not happen
during the sit whether you were distracted or sleepy or
emotions were coming up no problem you planted seeds
of presence spaciousness
and now kindness you did the best you could
appreciating
your wholehearted intention the goodness of your intention
and offering your goodness trusting there is goodness here
co-created In This Moment together offering our goodness the Merit
of our practice to all beings everywhere
as a gift wishing for all beings to be safe
happy healthy have ease may all beings everywhere be free
including ourselves
[Music]
so good morning
it's good to be with you in person as I was sitting
this morning the reflection came up for me that um
it's been two and a half years since I have sat here and taught in person
two and a half years away where did that go it seems like it was yesterday I was sitting here with people and teaching so
just an appreciation just an appreciation of being back together in person and
um it's also an appreciation for this miraculous
human life the mystery of it time passes where did it go it's always
now and we're often so caught up with what
is happening in our minds with the challenge we're dealing with but it's the magnificence of it all
magnificence the chance of being human being alive having
this precious human birth with all its difficulties and challenges but such a gift
to be human to be with other human beings even if they Annoy Us and push their our buttons it was but what a gift
really what a joy what a joy
just really appreciating that so for today's reflections
I wanted to um talk about
the unexpected power of random acts of kindness
so if you have listened to uh
Buddhist talks before um you would have probably heard at some
point about the three poisonous roots of unwholesome actions and the three
poisonous Roots being greed hatred and what's often translated as
delusion or confusion or ignorance which is by the way the root of the other two
so greed is pretty easy to understand wanting more grasping more and more
hatred is easy to understand pushing away hating ill will and that that
delusion or confusion often confuses people like what is that deluded
well one way to understand it is in um
not knowing any better and not knowing any better not just with our minds but with our hearts
another way I like to think of it is um cognitive bias
in the most radical sense so in Psychology there is this idea of cognitive biases that we have
there's for example the recency bias what has happened the most recently we
think oh yeah this is oh yeah yesterday I was sad oh I'm just going to be sad for the rest of my life well you don't
remember the last week you were really happy with joy right there's a reason to say bias we have so many different
biases biases psychologists have have
studied them but I like to think of our cognitive bias
this this delusion as a radical really the most fundamental cognitive bias or
perception bias the perception that greed will make us happy
hatred is a good thing or somehow it's going to make us happy and and
so really the the delusion or the confusion is the root of the other two
is this cognitive bias not knowing like really what really makes us happy
and what really serves what really helps us wake up
another way to understand these three is by their opposites in in Pali the language of the Buddha
there's the um the prefix ah that is put between whatever word you put it in
becomes negative so
so agreed non-greed generosity
generosity being the opposite of it hatred the opposite of it love loving
kindness and delusion or confusion or this
cognitive radical cognitive bias of of um not
knowing what leads to Freedom ease Liberation the opposite of confusion
wisdom wisdom okay
oh so to think of the to consider the
remarks I'm going to offer today about random acts of kindness in this context
of we don't really know we have a cognitive bias and that's what I want to
talk about today we have a cognitive bias serious delusion
of not knowing how much actually random acts of kindness
help us in our Liberation in our freedom in our happiness in the free in the
happiness of others so that's the the framework
so also
I'll bring in a bunch of studies in in my Dharma talk today and that's what I
usually like to do be having a background as a scientist especially when there's studies that that
corroborate what we already know to me that is so interesting to me that is the
Dharma because Dharma is learning studying the way things are and science tries to
do the same thing studying the way things are learning discovering the way things are so
finding um a lot of confluence
so so there have been a lot of research in the
past many years done on how
acts of kindness practicing loving kindness meta
the the Brahma viharas the the four practices of the heart compassion Etc
they um they lead to more happiness for us when we become Kinder
we become less stressed in all the ways that all these practices
are good for us so I'm not going to go so much into that today because there's there's a lot there but what I want to
focus on today is our understatement our under on underestimation
of how much are small acts of kindness actually make an impact in the world
and that's what the some new research that has just been published which is so
interesting so so here we go and then and there was a recent article in the New York Times on
September 2nd uh the title of it being the unexpected power of random acts of
kindness that reported on this so through pointers for you
for later so this this paper was published recently in the Journal of
experimental psychology and I love the title of this research
paper a little good goes an unexpectedly long
way underesti underestimating the positive impact of kindness on recipients
I like the the paper already so they did the scientists did a bunch
of different experiments um and in so many setups basically
um the um
there and and as I mentioned their premise was that yes um we know that the Performing act of
kindness already increased the happiness um in the givers and receivers but but
but the givers systematically undervalue undervalue the positive impact on the
recipients so so they set up these different experiments they
um had a setup where they had on a college campus they hired students
offer classmates a ride from home to campus or bake cookies or or buy someone
a cup of coffee and in in that experiment again ever everybody
all the people who did these acts of kindness they didn't quite they and they had them fill out questionnaires how
much do you you know from zero to ten zero being really insignificant very small to 10 being very large how do you
predict that the recipient's mood would change from negative
what kind of an impact it had on this on the scale and also what impact would it
have on their mood and and systematically consistently people would
underestimate the impact of these simple acts of kindness random acts of kindness
and then they did another experiment um they had this this is actually a very
interesting one so they had a um in they had they recruited 200
participants um in Maggie daily park I think it was
the big Park and they had a control group of 50. and these 50 people simply received a
cupcake for being part of the experiment for just showing up they received a cupcake
and then they had another 50 people um
that um 50 people who did not receive a cupcake
but they raided how the people who received a cupcake how they would feel so they're they're having this really
complicated setup of trying to figure out how people are estimating right how other people are feeling about these
impacts of kindness so it's a very interesting sophisticated setup
and then they had a third group of 50.
a third group of 50 that um they were that they were told that
they could give a cupcake away to a stranger and they were asked to rate both their
own mood for doing this act of kindness as well as the recipient's mood for
receiving the the small gesture so so it turns out
that the people who received the cupcake they were impacted but the people who
received a cupcake from someone else so let me say that again so the people who
received a cupcake as and participate just that because they have participated in the experiment
their impact on them the change in how they appreciated the how happy they
became was less than if they received a cupcake from a random stranger
because not only did they receive a cupcake so the people who received a copy were already happy but if you received as an act as a random act of
kindness you felt oh Somebody went out of their way to do something kind for me
and so the impact of the random act of kindness not only is it bigger but
consistently people underestimated how the recipient would feel receiving the
random act of kindness so there's a lot of do you hear there's a lot of different conditions here a lot of
measurements they're doing but the point I want to make is that
um the people who received the the the random act of kindness
they considered the gesture to be significantly more meaningful because
somebody did something nice for them
so we tend to underestimate we tend to underestimate the impact of our small
acts of kindness or small quote unquote small random acts of kindness
on ourselves and how it actually improves our own happiness and and
well-being and freedom and they'll talk more about that and how it impacts
others there's another study where
people that were another experiment where
simple researchers did a study on simple acts of connection like texting your
friend or picking up the phone and just a simple call and again in that study
also they had they asked the people who were just sending a text to a friend how
are you thinking of you right we do this right we do this but maybe we don't do it enough
we don't do it enough so they they asked they recruited almost
I forget uh thousands of people I don't have in my notes anymore but I was looking at it last night I recorded
thousands of people so this is a pretty statistically significant study and they asked
people to estimate the impact on the recipient and then they asked the recipient how how their mood was shifted
how appreciate how much they appreciated how it brightened their day to receive this random text of how are you thinking
of you and again and again statistically significantly people
underestimate how sending a text to A friend is going to
to have an impact how it's going to improve their mood their make them happy
make them feel cared for increase that sense of connection so we have this
radical radical cognitive bias this radical delusion
let's put it in Buddhist terms we have this radical delusion
about our impact or rather lack of a better impact and on others we
don't really realize how powerful we are how powerful we are
just how powerful we are
some researchers think that maybe for example in the case of texting
with a friend reaching out to a friend one reason for it is a liking Gap we
have again this delusion or this tendency to underestimate how well-liked
we really are oh do they really want to hear from us we underestimate how well-liked we
really are take that in for a moment
this underestimation of how much
people care about us and how happy they become when we reach out it seems very
simple but it's really through recognizing our power not just with
friends and texting Etc but with with the Ripple effects in the world
So speaking of texting while I'm on that um I recently was was quite sick I
actually had covered a few weeks ago and I was quite sick and
um and what a gift it was to be so sick and have a high fever and have friends
send texts and call are you okay what do you need even if I was I was too tired and sick to respond to them right away
like I don't can't even respond but it was just yes yes the sense of connection
being cared for and and perhaps the friends who sent didn't
realize how meaningful that was for me this sense of meta feeling held in meta
that probably really helped me recover oh yes I'm not forgotten people are texting calling asking so let's not
underestimate our power each and every single one of us has so much power
power of kindness and we can do that
there's so much that as
that can be taken away from us and and I'm thinking of those of you who might
be familiar with um a man's search for meaning
this amazing book written by Victor Frankel who was a psychologist who
was who went through the Holocaust survived the Holocaust and
um he wrote This Book
remarking and observing that so many people had so much taken away from them
they had their belongings taken away they had their
um their family their friends they had so much taken away
but many people still they well the one
thing that cannot be taken away from us is our choice is our choice how we think
how we feel and how we act in the world is it with more
kindness or is it with with greed hatred and delusion so these choices cannot be
taken away from us all the things can be taken away but the choice how to be in
the world how to perceive and how to act with kindness cannot be
taken away from us
so
so the hope that that the researchers have with this study and and I have with
bringing it up is that by by realizing by appreciating how much
our acts of kindness in the world actually make a difference for others
um that we become more open to to be kind to to
exercising our powerful kindness there's a little story actually that I
would read and I trust I bet we have our own stories every single one of us I bet
we have our own stories but in this New York Times article it starts with a little story I'll read for
you in late August Aaron Alexander 57 sat in the parking lot of a Target store
in Fairfield California and wept her sister-in-law had recently died and
Miss Alexander was having a hard day a barista working at the Starbucks
inside the Target store was two the espresso machine had broken down and
she was clearly stressed Ms Alexander who had stopped crying and gone inside
for some caffeine smiled and ordered an iced green tea and
told her to hang in there after picking up her order she noticed a message on the cup
Aaron the Barista had scrawled next to a heart your soul is gored golden
your soul is golden I am not even sure I even necessarily
know what your soul is golden means said Miss Alexander who laughed and cried
while recalling the incident but the warmth of that small and unexpected
gesture from a stranger who had no inkling of what she was going through moved her deeply
of course I was still really sad Ms Alexander said but that little thing
made the rest of my day how many of us have had our day made by
a small random act of kindness just I know I have
I know I have so many stories so many instances
um one just randomly came up I remember some time ago I went to have my blood drawn and having
my blood drawn for a test is not my favorite thing in the world I have to do it often and it's just like oh still
feel strange and and um this this person at the blood the
phlebotomist was so nice was so nice
he made my day he really made my day I was so happy I didn't feel unhappy that
I was sick he just made my day I was just like coming out of having my blood
drawn lots of vials like wow I feel like I had been graced I had been touched by
Grace with just this person being kind going out of their way to make me feel
comfortable so many examples so many instances of
just kindness random acts of kindness everyday kindness can completely change
people's lives there was another story I read um some time ago and this was
um someone who was quite depressed and and perhaps even
you know thinking you know Hanging On by thread and they would go for a walk every day and
every day on their walk they would see a neighbor who would just give him a big bright smile big bright smile the
neighbor and later they reached out to the neighbor and said you know that big
bright smile you gave me every day on my walks it kept me going it keep me going
that there was kindness in the world that there is goodness in the world it just that was the threat that kept me
going so that just uh
on not underestimating the power of simple acts of kindness just a smile
we underestimate that's the point I want to make today we
underestimate nah now science says
with these studies we underestimate the impact we have on each other the impact
on how we have on each other so so that's one aspect of what I want
to discuss but there is another aspect of it so we underestimate two ways we
underestimate both the impact it has on others the gift
that we make for others and we also underestimate how much of an impact it
makes for us completely underestimate
so so another research paper I want to
bring in which talks about that other side is one by um
um Michael Norton Professor Michael Norton from Harvard Business School and this was a 2008 study
which showed up in Science magazine um
and the title of this is spending money on others promotes happiness
who would have thought right and here again I won't go through too much detail
but they they have it's a very interesting and sophisticated setup they have lots of different setups and
um and basically what they find is that
maybe I'll just talk about one one of the studies that um
they um when they ask a group of students how much you know if
um how much they think um spending the money on themselves versus
spending the money that or so in this study they're giving a bunch of giving group of students some money five
dollars twenty dollars so this is not a big amount of money it's a small amount of money it's just a token right it's
buying someone a coffee right it's not a lot and and they um they ask the
students okay what do you think how much your happiness would increase if you spend it on yourself versus you spend it
on others and again we have this delusion of thinking spending the money on ourselves makes us
more happy and sure enough when you actually spend the
money on others it makes you happier it makes you happier than spending it on
yourself but of course I mean again there's a lot of detail I'm leaving leaving out
is there is the self-care that we need to take care of ourselves etc etc I'm
not talking about that but that extra level of oh do I get myself a gift or
somebody else a gift that that turns out it makes us happier
to make other people to be generous with others and again this is this is the um
the delusion we have because if when I tell you we're like no I don't think so like yeah I want to spend it on myself right that's the delusion we have but
actually when we do it when we actually do it and we and then we get asked the level
of gladness happiness is is more so
so if you're feeling down if you're feeling unhappy
the fastest way to to get a jolt of joy
gladness is to do something nice for somebody else
to do something nice for somebody else so if you're at home if you're feeling
unhappy or stressed oh poor me poor milk will reach out take your phone perhaps
reach out to a friend how are you how are you doing I heard you were sick or you're having a hard time Reach Out do
something kind for someone else both you're underestimating how happy it
makes them and you're underestimating how happy it'll make you and also this
the sense of social connection
so in row so Rose by Any Other Name so to I've
been talking about loving kindness right practicing loving kindness today
about loving kindness and it may not necessarily be just sitting on the cushion and wishing you're wishing
yourself well or wishing other people well which is beautiful loving kindness is a wonderful wonderful practice
I love practicing it I love teaching it during happy hour please come join us every day of the week 6 to 7 P.M online
and and some people say well I don't have the time to come and join happy hour or sit on the cushion and practice
loving kindness no problem go out into the world you have so many opportunities
to be kind for random acts of kindness in fact um
I saw this this is a fun one um a grammar in Florida in Tampa Florida
started a smile and wave Challenge on
their next door I think you're from next door is this app is this a community
Forum where each neighborhood you can send email or posts to your neighbors
you're nodding so many of you know what next door is so so this this person in
Tampa Florida started the smile smile and wave challenge so
so um and got the whole neighborhood just
everyone you see smile and wave smile and wave and she said she had she got
about 75 percent of people to smile and wave back and that was that 25 that she wanted the help of everybody else in the
neighborhood to to reach to just smile and um and it's it's a it's a nice quote
that she says if someone doesn't have a smile then give them yours if someone doesn't have a smile then
give them yours especially nowadays if someone doesn't
have a smile give them yours
so we underestimate our power we underestimate our power for for good
no need especially if you ever feel powerless
you're underestimating your power your impact your likability you're underestimating
so much impact you have
the Buddha says practitioners people knew as I know the fruits of
sharing gifts they would not enjoy their use without sharing them
nor would the taint of singiness obsess the heart even if it were their last bit their
last morsel of food they would not enjoy its use without sharing it
if there was someone else to share it with
AKA 18. so
kindness loving kindness which is intertwined with generosity in Buddhism
really it's the generosity of the heart that when we feel like okay we we have we
have so much to share every single one of us has so much to share so so of course you know this idea of of
um random acts of kindness doesn't mean now okay now all right now do I have to go learn bake you know how to bake
cookies or buy everybody coffee no it doesn't mean that whatever is part of
your wheelhouse part of your what you naturally do if if you love baking cookies sure please do that but maybe
maybe you have the skill of of listening again reaching out or or whatever you
already have in your Wheelhouse in your skill in your um your bag of skills that's what you can
be generous with you can be kind with you can have an impact
you are you're already so wealthy each of us is so wealthy in in the ways that
we can be kind a couple of other things I want to say
before closing one is also and um
the Buddha and the sutta of a persons of integrity's gifts
he says there are five um
there are five ways that a person of Integrity gives a gift
and what are those five a person of Integrity gives a gift with
a sense of conviction with a sense of conviction
a person of Integrity gives a give attentively
especially like this one actually I like all of them so with a sense of conviction like a sense of conviction
right giving the gift giving and an act of kindness with conviction
attentively so it's like you know if you're giving someone a gift you don't give them a gift like ah you're looking
elsewhere like you look at them you you give it to them you give it with both hands now with just one hand like oh
here I have I have a gift for you whoops still I go here take it look at there
you give it attentively right there is a way to to honor another one with an act
of kindness or or a gift or generosity the third a person of Integrity gives a
gift in season a person of Integrity gives a gift with
an empathetic heart I love this one empathetic heart and the last one is a
very interesting one the last one the person of Integrity gives a gift without adversely affecting themselves
or others so this is an interesting point here
also so an act of generosity kindness not to adversely affect oneself and
others so to keep that in mind
so I want to close with a poem by
la nusa lamaris it's called small kindnesses
I've been thinking about the way when you walk down a crowded aisle people
pull in their legs to let you by or how Strangers still say bless you
when someone sneezes a leftover from the Bubonic plague don't
die we are saying we sometimes and and sometimes when you
spill lemons from your grocery bag someone else will help you pick them up
mostly we don't want to harm each other we want to be handed our cup of coffee
hot and to say thank you to the person handing it
smile at them and for them to smile back for the waitress to call us honey
when she sets down the bowl of clam chowder and for the driver in the red pickup
truck to let us pass we have so little of each other now
so far from tribe and Fire only these moments only these brief
moments of Exchange what if they are the true dwelling of
the Holy these fleeting temples we make together
when we say here have my seat go ahead you first
I like your hat
what if they are the true dwellings of the Holy
these fleeting temples we make together
what if what if these brief moments of of Exchange
these fleeting temples we make holy fleeting temples
we can all make them together
and the last quote from Helen Keller believe when you are most unhappy
that there is something for you to do in the world believe when you are most unhappy
that there is something for you to do in the world
so long as you can sweeten another's pain life is not in vain
let's just sit together for a minute the word settle
d
thank you all for your kind attention so let us make today a random act of
kindness day both all of us here together in this Hall and all of you on YouTube
let's together have the ripples in the world
of random acts of kindness and if you do you can send me email
take care be well be kind