so uh so welcome welcome folks
um yeah it's good to uh good to be with you
um
yeah that's um go go right into uh the silence
so maybe you um
Begin by relaxing or maybe you begin by
um becoming sensitive more sensitive
to goodness
to the goodness of your intention goodness
of the Sangha
what is good in each of us
part of practice is becoming a
moved by goodness so maybe that's a good way to begin
help us inhabit this moment more fully
just settle in in whatever way you settle in these first few minutes
yesterday I was meditating outside
and uh in the distance someone was practicing
bagpipes and when you're meditating
bagpipes are very very funny
and you may not have the benefit of bad wipes in your sound space
but there's something to hear so maybe
well explore outer sound and then inner sound
so first just anchoring attention to this soundscape
the ambient noises of your space
because we tend to subtly image
the the objects uh
from which sound emerges
then we image those in a kind of uh location
in the theater of our own minds
the sense of um
spaciousness
the openness of our mind
to just listening for sounds will will tend to focus on
near sounds the beginning of sounds
loud sounds but here we honor
sounds from the distance sounds
that are faint sounds when they end in
addition to when they begin
it's as if we allow the sounds to run
through us like uh a gust of of wind that is not
trapped inside of us it just blows through
nor hope and our fear
trap phenomena
or grasping and aversion what we like just like
about the sound or that traps the phenomena in the headquarters
of self and we chew on it
but instead in our practice
we practice
vetting sound
run right through
in this uh awareness of the soundscape we can also
include our own verbal thinking
Julie we just call it thinking
and usually we don't hear it in the sense of knowing thinking
as thinking we don't hear the phenomena
of verbal thought
we are just identified with it and obey
and so now they awareness it feels almost as if it's
poised perched listening for the arising of auditory
thinking
and it's generally true that audit the the awareness will
disrupt auditory thinking the presence of awareness
means that we can't be fully identified with the content of our thought
but we listen as we can for the words and sentences for the
chatter for the embryonic auditory thoughts
the thoughts that seem to beg us to think them
so now we're vetting the the uh attuning to the
soundscape as it runs right through our own heads
in a way we we practice uh not treating
thoughts as some special species of sound
but uh in the same category
as the the birds
the garbage truck and the neighbors
foreign
this summer summer before uh September 11 2001 was reading I remember
reading a book um that um it was called
um I think happiness death and the remainder of life and um
what I remember about it was the the basic premise is that life is lived
under conditions of too much too much
capture something important too much
energy in our system and we need to discharge it too much
coming at us we're besieged by samsara
by this realm of existence too much I want to get done too much
I need to worry about too much to let go of too much
and it strikes me that maybe maybe too much
is a is a kind of synonym for dukkha
in the sense of too much necessitates if we're to be happy we we need to find
ways to turn down the dial on our nervous system
[Music] and it's over stimulation the sense of
too much and the the Dharma is a kind of
dialectic between um between peace and what I spoke about
yesterday purification between uh tranquility
and letting the world rush into our heart and um
and without Tranquility the Letting Go the purification the opening to Duke uh
all of it feels like too much and you see how
desperate we are to dial things down in some way to
um yeah to turn down the nervous system and
kind of seek out that that Cocoon of unconsciousness where we're not being
stimulated in a way that creates the sense of too muchness it's kind of yeah
cocoon and um
and so we we do a lot to kind of like
create that Cocoon of unconsciousness
to insulate ourselves from the intensity and um
and I'm sympathetic to the the impulse of doing all that we do
to dial down the nervous system but the Dharma Dharma celebrates a kind of
Tranquility that is alive rather than dissociated it's not the the
the peace or seclusion of the the infinite
scroll but it's a kind of alive form of Tranquility
and so part of the Dharma and part of Dharma pleasure is
um learning the the ways that we come to rest yeah way as we come to rest
ways that our Dharma practice allows us to
to rest and so we rest
in a number of ways we seek out spiritual friends
with whom our heart can relax now we call that Sangha
it is soothing it's soothing or so
so porous and just to be around
people trying to to live a life of wisdom and care
um that's not trivial that's not trivial that allows us to begin to relax some of
our vigilance were were
um were reassured by by the the lineage
that that so many of so many have come before us
walk this path profitably and um
there's uh there's a certain kind of soothing in knowing this
I remember on the first night of a retreat uh Michelle McDonald was
teaching and she said something like the first night of retreat I think it was a two-week or ten
day Retreat or something she said the first night of retreat is um
is all about reassurance yeah and then she repeated the word you know
and said something like just that word reassurance
something in his lungs for that and you can kind of feel the room just let down a little
we learn practices ways of of um directing our attention maybe we say
meditating but not just meditating but we'd learn ways of attending that naturally brings
a soothing and um
some of it is as simple as just attending to phenomena that bring calm stability
on a suit uh when when one's mind is possessed by restlessness overpowered by
restlessness one not cannot properly see the Escape from restlessness one does not properly
understand one's own welfare nor that of another there's unrest of Mind frequently giving unwise attention to it
that is the nourishment for the arising of restlessness
unwise attention to the sign of restlessness
so what aspects of experience what signs are useful to attend to what brings a sense of
seclusion protection tranquility
and as this process unfolds and we do start to settle and we can start to
settle even when we're not quote concentrated you know it's like can start to sense like oh yes something in
you is resting even when
there's a lot of discursive thinking and then just to rest there is is very
healing because um life doesn't feel like too much
in that wrath
and we rest in we rest in a certain rest
maybe we say in the truth of The Human Condition
um in a sense because we've
we've deeply contemplated um
a Nietzsche impermanence uncertainty we've deeply
contemplated dissolution and and death
um change doesn't come as such a shock to
the system in a sense maybe we say that we
we pre-grieve all of the inevitable losses of Being
Human yeah and that's different than fretting about
it all but we we sort of pre-grieve
Leonard Cohen said um I I don't consider myself a pessimist I think of a
pessimist as someone waiting for it to rain and I feel soaked to the skin
it's said that um that anxiety is the intolerance of uncertainty
anxiety is the intolerance of uncertainty
but were already soaked to the skin
there's no uncertainty
the famous Parable that uh Jack cornfield recounted and in his
encountered with Arjun chav uh holding up uh you know holding up a mug or something and saying like uh uh this
this cup is already broken yeah because I know it's broken I can enjoy it now yeah
cup is already broken I know it's nature nature is the break
and because I know it's broken my heart won't break when it does yeah
the corollary uh of uh that this cup this cup is is
already broken um the corollary there are many
corollaries of that but um
that includes that uh this cup is already broken
um already dead yeah this land is already
gone all is already lost
and um
that doesn't flatten the heart yeah but um
actually um
can create some sense of of rest because we're not gaming out some Sarah
anymore we know how this story ends and there's
a certain measure of Peace we pre-grieve the inevitable losses
of Being Human and uh
then we can rest more deeply
and also love more deeply
to offer this for your consideration
um will uh have another optional meeting this
evening on uh on Zoom um it's uh
at seven o'clock tonight uh Pacific time and uh the the link is
just on on uh that website
um uh yeah matthewbrandsover.org
chatted it in okay um okay uh thank you uh thank you all
um uh yeah
yeah I wish you uh wish you all a good day and and if you like um come on by
this evening Pacific time um um
and uh we'll sit a little bit and check in see how your day was
and um yeah I can try to answer any questions
so okay thanks so much