there so hello dear sangha
hello welcome good to be with all of you so
so so to be in this world of ours at this time at this point in
what's happening geopolitically etc etc so
there may be there may be some heaviness of course of course it's hard not to
have heaviness [Music] paying attention to news and what is
happening so [Music] during this evening's happy hour
practice um i want to continue
what we've been paying attention to last week in different ways addressing
addressing sent the need for stability the need for
peace the need for groundedness so that there is stability
internally to hold to meet the challenges of the world we did
equanimity practice last week we also did calming the energy body
with the breath many of you seem to like that it's a sense of bringing home we did joy
practice on friday again as a way to support us in challenging times
um all of these practices and compassion and practice of course um
both equanimity and joy practice can be support can be support for a compassion practice
so what i'd like to invite us to engage in tonight is
is more of a slightly differently this attending to
the energy body in terms of establishing calm
establishing centeredness establishing [Music]
groundedness which can both hold joy
and sorrow it can hold both but it there needs to be a stability
there needs to be a sense of equipoise equanimity uh
to hold whatever there is instead of toppling over especially when the news in the world is so challenging
and difficult and heartbreaking so that is all the framing that i think
is necessary for tonight and let's just settle in and practice
together so
so let us arrive let us arrive
together as a sangha as a community
and individually in this body
in this moment in time [Music]
turning the gaze inward attending to whatever is arising in this moment here
in this body as if you are taking stock greeting
yourself sensing sensing internally
what's happening in different parts of the
body can check in popcorn style
just no getting to know oh yeah maybe the head is a little tight
shoulders hands might be cool or warm
maybe the feet are tense maybe the sit bones are relaxed or whatever
whatever is happening in your body take time
take time
and knowing what's happening in the body doesn't mean that we judge or
we push away we just know oh this is what's happening
hello dear body
let me get to know you
is it possible to release
to relinquish thoughts entanglements that are not helpful right
now as you take refuge in this moment
taking refuge in your intentions and the goodness
of your intentions for being here practicing aligning
aligning how you spend your time with your values
taking refuge in this goodness
just this moment just this moment of cultivation
is enough
maybe bring awareness maybe bring your awareness to the heart
center area on the center of your chest
let there be a sense of gentleness kindness
as if you were with your hand gently caressing
holding the middle of your chest caressing or physically or in your mind's eye
okay sweetheart it's okay it's okay
softening
letting the breath be natural
not so much that you are breathing but you're being breathed
you're being briefed let yourself be breathed
as if the breaths these gentle breaths are coming through the heart center
the middle of the chest
expanding contracting [Music] bellowing ever so gently
the rhythmic motion of the chest and the abdomen
calming soothing
the calming soothing of the energy body the body inside
energetically releasing
letting yourself enjoy enjoy be healed
be calmed be soothed
by the rhythm of the breath the chest heart center the abdomen
bellowing through the body
ever so gently happening on its own could be very shallow that's fine let it
be shallow
your day doesn't matter
breath might be slow slow slow
each breath calming calming the body
each breath a lullaby
reverberating through your whole body calming
the entire body
slowly slowly
uh
as thoughts arise as they will arise not a problem
no need for self-judgment or criticism simply notice
oh this is what i'm thinking about right now this is the thought that has arisen
for the sake of this practice release not that there's anything wrong with thinking
for the sake of this cultivation bowing to the thought
releasing thank you please come back later if you're important enough you will come
back
letting there be a an enjoyment of the breath as if it's
lapping of waves waves lapping
upon the shore of the body
the whole body
slapping waves calming soothing
moving through the heart center the abdomen the whole body releasing
relaxing centering
there's a gentleness an expression of meta an expression of
love is this gentleness
of the lapping waves through the body
filling the whole body with ease with metal
not overpowering but gentle caring
responding to whatever is needed right now
can you just be calmed with this loving gentle energy
these lapping waves of the breath
your heart be calmed soothed held
and your whole trunk chest and abdomen
be soothed calmed the lapping waves
of the breath gentle gentle ever so gently
can this gentle lapping waves of breath
filled with meta can these waves radiate
fill the limbs maybe your shoulders
energy this calming energy moving up from the chest
feeling the shoulders the neck radiating down the arms to the hands
moving up through the head
braiding radiating down from the chest and the abdomen
down to the belly lower belly
filling the sit bones
the waves calming the upper legs
pouring into the knees
the lower
legs and feet radiating down
through the feet and upwards
from the top of the head in all directions
this calming soothing energy of meta not contained
not limited
to where the skin ends but further out as if we're sitting
it's expansive sitting
spacious no boundaries
of these waves lapping inside outside
reserve this container greater than our body
we're sitting in sitting in this container filled with lapping waves
gentle gentle metal
lapping waves of the breath filled with mental kindness
benevolence
this whole container that includes our body filled with menta
with care for this being who is me
and the sense of ease
of course this care this meta radiates outward this whole body
is a body of meta gentle gentle caring
just being in the world it radiates kindness
touching others doesn't have to be forced
how else could it be a body filled with gentle meta
will impact others
with matter
let the energy body be calm [Music] calmed and radiate
with the breath with the meta filled breath
let this calm calmed nourishing [Music] lapping waves of meta
be healing grounding
let yourself enjoy
letting there be equal amounts radiating inside
radiating outside this meta
calm this peace radiating through the entire world
as a gift you are offering gift of your calmness
your stability your peace offering that to the world
with care
may the fruits of our practice
be of service be offered freely to all beings everywhere
our calm our care our stability
for ourselves and others may be of service in all beings everywhere
especially those in war zones may they have peace and ease
may all beings be free
thank you for your practice everyone
we have time for any reflections any questions
you may want to share you can type in chat if you like or raise your zoom hand
if you type in chat if it's typed to me alone i won't read your name just the comment
so it's private and if it's typed to everyone i'll read the name also
so any reflections you like to share for the benefit of everyone in the sangha
any questions and also acknowledging that this practice
can be quiet and very calming this energy body practice so
you may not be moved to speak bill says wonderful session nikki thank
you you are welcome and thank you for your practice
another reflection wonderful deborah says i really appreciated the image
of the lapping along the shore of the lake was i the lake or the shore oh i love
that question was i the leg or the shore or both
love it love it thank you deborah that's lovely i love the image
vicky says very calming indeed i love the waves too thank you you're
welcome and thank you vicky for your practice
kathryn i see your hand [Music] yeah just
today is a very difficult day for me to settle or find
ease but i've been doing this practice now long enough to
to take refuge in the knowledge that that changes and to just keep practicing and and have
much less reactivity to the difficulty of settling in this
particular session and so i i feel really grateful for that
that i can come as i am and accept myself as i am
thank you for that gift that gift of reflection catherine indeed
indeed knowing that it's impermanent it comes and goes causes and conditions arise and
sometimes it's easier to settle quote-unquote sometimes it isn't and yet to hold all of that
with kindness and acceptance just as you said and beautiful to have that to have
cultivated that acceptance and care no matter what that is meta yeah it's
not reward oriented only if you settle then i will love you no i love you either way
sweetheart it's okay yeah thanks for bringing that into the space catherine
okay couple more reflections wonderful way to go off into the evening
calm and centered very grateful nikki you're welcome megan says the wave imagery made me
think of the disney movie moana she is called to enter the ocean and
embarks on a hero's journey it's not easy there are waves and storms
but she follows the call oh i love that reflection yes heroes journey through our breath
yeah i love that thanks for that reflection megan love the imagery
jerry says you mentioned that we need to reach out to all in war zones but we are
not in this world with the potential wars of
i'm not quite understanding the question jerry i think what i meant to say is this
radiating out uh the radiating out of care
to everyone and offering the calm so i'm not quite sure where the question is i didn't quite get it
may the lapping waves shore up our body and one last reflection thank you nikki
i feel strong enough to hold both joy and sorrow yet light
like a snowflake yet light like snowflake almost free
from gravity yeah yeah
jerry is clarifying are we all not in a potential war zone oh of course we are everything can oh yeah of course
everything can change in any minute not to make us anxious but life is just what
it is it's life is anything can happen at any moment you can be hit by a truck it could be war
could be anything so and yet and yet can we stay calm can we
stay centered in the middle of the the waves the waves of the ocean
support is supported by the internal waves of calm
so i'd like to invite us to turn into sitting together maybe just in silence
maybe we just hold space silent space for one another or
maybe share um [Music] and one last reflection this is from julie
on youtube thank you for a beautiful soothing meditation a great reminder to come back to the heart space at all
times yes yeah yeah
so thank you all danke
so i'll create the breakout rooms and again take care of yourselves take care of each other just maybe
there's just need to hold space for one another um
maybe not much needs to be said or maybe something needs to be said it's all
it's all good so i'm going to open the rooms
in a moment and uh yeah take care here we go
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed everybody's back and we just have
a couple minutes if any last minute reflections especially from being
together in the groups if you like to share
the floor is yours
going once going twice
okay seems like there is a feeling of closure hope you enjoyed um
yeah yeah sounds good i i see a um
request to have some guidance about how to behave in the group i think that is important
they often do say to please take care of yourself and take care of others and speak from your own experience not
speak about other people's experience please please do not do that
and the person who privately messaged me i would appreciate if you stay later and tell me if their issues are rising
because i really would like to make sure this is a safe place for everyone and that people don't drop out
because they don't feel safe with someone you know talking about their experience etc or anything else that's happening so
please do stay and help me help support the community
and deborah says i told my group that during the meditation i found myself stay stay staying instead of go go going
ah yeah it's is it a question or is it a a
statement i wasn't quite sure deborah i think it's a statement
but maybe i will just leave it leave it as that and i don't see your hand either or
so maybe oh statement yes okay sounds good debra we'll let that sit we'll let
that stand as it is so let's um bring our evening to a close
thank you so much everyone thank you for your practice for your dedication
[Music] cultivation both for your own sake and the sake of all beings everywhere may
all beings be free including ourselves
thank you and good night