so hello again and warm greetings on this beginning of the
week and we're continuing with the sati petana suta the
core buddhist buddha's teachings on mindfulness mindfulness practice
and this practice um aims at developing a great clarity of
awareness a clarity of of awareness a kind of a lucid awareness
that's very stable and very simple and allows that somehow in that clarity
and simplicity it sees things clearly in such a way that
liberation is within reach and so it's a state of mind that's
settled some would say concentrated composed
very present and very clear very attentive to the flow of experience in the present
moment and the text is all about the different exercises you can do
to build up to that quality of clear attention in the present moment
and many of us here in the west have learned certain aspects of this text
especially the ones that emphasize simple mindfulness non-reactive
mindfulness and in simple recognition of what's happening as it's happening in the
present moment and sometimes we get the impression that's all we're allowed to do
but in this text there's other practices to be done or can be done
that contribute to developing the mind overall so the mind be can have the stability
and strength to remain in the present moment and see clearly
and surprisingly one of those
things we develop is our capacity for imagination a kind of
the word that we're talking about right now pacha vekati vekati
is um can also mean to review with the word
view implying kind of a seeing so whether that reviewing is more mental
consideration thoughtful brings something to mind or whether it's
bringing evoking the imagination to visualize something that depends on the individual
practitioner but in a variety of ways and situations the buddha kind of relies on or calls on
very simple acts of imagination he does that when he evokes metaphors
for practice and um and we'll see now in this next exercise
there's a i'd like a beautiful metaphor um and somehow the evoking that
that what happens with him when we imagine a metaphor that speaks to something about what the
meditation is going to be about it kind of evokes those parts in our body and our mind and our hearts perhaps
so it comes a little bit of surprise that imagination has a role partly because other places the buddha
clearly is critical of how we get caught in fantasy and
and false imaginations but he uses a different word for that
and he has this word a couple of words he uses that are more positive for that probably mean closer to visualize
than simply imagination and and so this next exercise is used as
this and so as a way of introducing it for the meditation today
i'd like us to engage in a simple act of imagination to support the meditation practice
so it's not to imagine anything that's not present so you don't have to worry about being
taken off on some journey someplace with imagination but it is evoking the imagination to
support being here so um
taking a meditation posture lowering the gaze
relaxing the eyes relaxing the gaze
if it's comfortable closing the eyes
and in a way that is comfortable for you taking some deeper breaths
maybe three quarters full
exhaling no longer than you normally would but not so long that it's a strain
a delightful exhale
letting the letting the breathing return to normal and just hang out for a bit with the
rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
and if it's easy relaxing the body as you exhale
and then imagine yourself
sitting in meditation
maybe if you have it
easy ability to visualize visualize yourself sitting in meditation
it doesn't have to be exactly as you are but in some way that
the imagination the visualization the reflection
has some nice feeling to it nice quality
maybe your you might also imagine in your mind's
eye with your eyes closed the place in where you're sitting
letting your mind gently roam around left and right up and down
imagining visualizing the location where you are
and then again within your place imagine yourself
in your meditation posture
imagine that your body is beginning to relax
whether it actually relaxes or not is secondary
to simply imagine maybe you remember a time when the body
relaxed deeply and you imagine that that's how you are
now
imagine the relaxed way that you're safe here and now
surrounded by these few minutes with safety
imagine what it'd be like for your body to really feel itself in a safe place
what would relax in the body
and imagine what it'd be like if in this imaginary meditation session
you felt content at ease
imagine the breathing what it would feel like to breathe and sit here
very contented at ease with all things
maybe visualizing yourself meditating this way
imagining a feeling of contentment spreading through the body
whether you're content or not is secondary
to the imagination that you are a gentle imagination
for people who have a hard time visualizing or imagining
imagine that you're visualizing imagine that you're imagining
so it's a very light touch imagining you're sitting here
in your meditation posture breathing in a content way
imagining what that would feel like
and now having spent some time imagining
let go of the imagination and let your awareness enter into your
body as it actually is
becoming aware of your embodied experience
as you exhale calming the mind
calming the thinking
centering your awareness on how your body experiences breathing
so
okay
and as we come to the end of the sitting notice if there's any ways that you are
calm or calmer more peaceful more settled
from this meditation or if you're not
do you have more clarity but how you actually are
simple recognition or a deep recognition
one way or the other sitting quietly in your meditation posture
not moving notice how you are
and to whatever degree there's a sense of stability
or stillness or non-reactivity to the world around you
imagine yourself being stable non-reactive
not closing down imagining that the people of your life
are coming into your view that you bring to mind those people you
might encounter today whether they're strangers or acquaintances or friends or
family neighbors
and see if you can have them be present in the mind's eye while you are non-reactive while you are
stable and steady maybe peaceful
imagining that you offer a stable attention sense of presence
non-reactive presence
and from this place this way do you have access to any thoughts
or imaginations how good it would be if these people could be happy
safe content peaceful
free
imagine that's possible and wish that to them
they be happy may they be
safe may they be peaceful
may they be free and may this good will
well wishing for the world spread out into the world through the
day and may each of us live
for the benefit of this world may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
uh
so in this um journey through the 13 exercises of the
buddha's discourse on the foundations for awareness for mindfulness
we've come now to the fourth exercise which is um
a mindfulness or a reflection on
parts of the body so all along we've been
doing mindfulness of the body developing a awareness that's embodied
being mindful of ourselves and postures and being mindful of us ourselves as
specific activities we do now that focus is on
um bringing more specificity to this mindfulness of the body
by becoming aware or mindful or focused on 31 different parts of the body
and and the way that the the verb that's used for what we do the activity
is a kind of i think of it as a rich word with connotations
that can mean to visualize to uh to see in the mind's eye it could
also mean to review or reflect on something which has a double meaning in
english as well where the word view means to look and the and the reflect has also the
kind of the meaning of association with seeing when we see our reflection in them
in the water for example in the mirror and exactly what kind what how the mind
is engaged in considering this is maybe depends on the person who does
it some people have a very strong ability to visualize and some people don't some people have
strong ability to maybe conceptualize uh what's being discussed
without actually seeing it there have been times where i had done visualization practices and
and um i never really felt i was particularly good at it being able to visualize
but it made a huge difference to me when i started imagining that i was visualizing
so it's i mean visualizing itself is a use of the imagination but somehow when i imagined i was doing it then i was
able to kind of kind of get into the event get into the
ideas that are being you know held up in the imagination
and um it was also very for me was much lighter touch because uh in the mind because when i
visualized that i found myself working too much but when i was imagining myself visualizing then there was no work in
just imagining it it was just kind of like more of an effortless place for me
and so exactly what this word reflect review imagine
visualize how it should be interpreted as maybe into very individual
and you're allowed to do that because this practice is about what supports you to develop clarity stability insight
and a certain freedom and and so and so what we're seeing here though
is that the satepatana uses a variety of different mental capacities
all for the same purpose of this lucid awareness that's being developed
and and so it's a as we do as we start learning these different capacities and recognizing in
which situation different ones of them are useful so to review some of the verbs that we
talked about so far one is to know like no we're breathing
the other is to experience to feel the whole body
and then there's the to relax or calm the bodily constructions
and then there's to know uh the different postures we're in and then there's to be have full
awareness or full comprehension while we're doing activities so
and then also we talked about in the refrain the capacity to observe to abide and
observe and now we're using a different mental capacity that a reflection or
visualization for something different people have different strengths in these different capacities
but they're all ways of engaging the mind now the 32 parts of the body
actually 31 parts of the body the text has 31. the later buddhist tradition
added the brain to the list and so there's 32. but
in the text it's only 31. and this is a cherished practice
for new monastics at least cherished by some um often in thailand and i don't know
about other countries when a monastic often when a person ordained as a monastic
this is the first practice they're given to cultivate these this practice on the
they do the 32 the 32 parts of the body and this has a variety of different
functions um one is that um you're supposed to memorize the list
and be able to recite it kind of with ease and there's something about the act of memorizing
uh doing the memorization and then do reciting things from memory that engages the mind in a very nice way
or hopefully a nice way there's something about the heightened attention that's needed to memorize
something the heightened presence that is beginning to train the mind or or
support the mind in having this heightened a certain kind of heightened attention for breathing
for present moment experience the the there's a kind of overlap between the kind of focus present moment
attention needed for memorization and the kind of focus attention we need to practice mindfulness in the present
moment and by memorizing we're learning something about a slightly activated mind or energized mind
that doesn't have to be tense or stressed but that shows us something about how to
be present that's not too laxadaisical not too complacent or not too lazy or something
like that a kind of clarity and intent intentness uh when you memorize that there's an
intenseness in what you're doing so in memorizing the list and then for monastics there's a lot of memorization
especially as a new monastics and some of that is not just to memorize the text so you can chant them
but it's also training the mind building up the strength of the mind
that supports also mindfulness practice this heightened
capacity of lucid awareness so the 31 parts of the body is
is engaging the mind the way that helps it get concentrated and concentration is a
very important part of mindfulness practice overall and so here we've kind of started with
mindfulness of the body and now we're introducing something that for many people supports them to get
more concentrated and to take the 31 parts of the body meditation seriously to develop that
concentration so that when we continue with the satipatana that we're supported by this
more concentration the second thing that it does is it this 31 parts of the body
meditation it it we get a different orientation of how to experience our body than what we
commonly do kind of unconsciously subconsciously carry around in our mind when we uh because of our culture
advertisements popular society family experiences we often have a self-image of ourselves
in our body which is a biased that's partial that's only has you know
this is not kind of the full picture of what goes on and not a few people have negative body
uh self images that they're troubled by their body or they're overly focused in their body or
they have positive views of their body and they're focusing on making themselves beautiful and just right
and so there's a whole focus on the body that is a multi-billion dollar industry
in this country maybe around the world a focus in the body that causes a lot of suffering a lot of stress
and and it doesn't really and it supports a certain kind of attachment or clinging
or grasping or fears aversions all kinds of things happen around how we
view the body and now this practice now is breaking through that to offer a
separate way of experiencing the body that is maybe a little more concentrated
has a different orientation perspective on the body and breaks up the solidity or the authority of these old body
images that we're burdened with or or which gets in the way of the mind settling deeply down into
some the alternative way of being in the body from the inside out
the third thing this these uh meditation on the 31 parts of the body does
is that there's a way that um it's they're said to be unclean these parts of the body
or unpure uh and uh and if we focus on them the theory is if you focus on the body this
way that it breaks down not just the body image we have but excessive
attachment to the body and
the and
so for people who are very attached to the body uh seeing it this way these unclean things
um can break the attachment and the un one way of understanding that the way that they're unclean
so a lot of people in the west are very resistant to this idea to see the body is impure unclean
and in fact many you know those who have seen the inside of the body sometimes it seems quite beautiful to see the parts
is uh imagine that um person that you cherish and love and everything
and um you find their hair and your food your their pubic hair in your food or their
snot or you find that uh you know their skin sloughed off a lot
and it's in the stew that they made or fingernails are in food i think for many people the sense of
like body parts are beginning to appear in my stew is little bit like uh repulsive even
it's unclean it's not it's not quite right you don't want to eat it even though it's beautiful when it's on the other person but
you know something doesn't seem right about you know eating it if it's in the stew
and so it's maybe something like that that there's some perspective that's not unhealthy
that if we're attached to the body can help free it it is using the imagination
if it's needed for this purpose so uh the 31 parts of the body
i'll give the list and then i'll post the list for you so you can have it you can cut and paste it if you want and
and some of you i would encourage you to memorize it uh the list and see if you can
you know learn about this heightened attention that is useful for mindfulness that comes
from memorization so head here body here nails
teeth and skin flesh tendons bones marrow kidneys
heart liver diaphragm spleen and lungs
um bile uh phlegm
pus blood and sweat and
fat tears oil
saliva snot
the fluid of the joints and urine
so i think that oh no i left one out in the middle there intestines
large intestines small intestines contents of the stomach and um
feces so sorry i didn't do it all on the list but
that's that was that's a list and and um
and so that's the topic for the next two maybe three days and we'll practice with it and explore it and hopefully you'll
understand how rather than being a distraction from mindfulness uh you begin appreciating the wealth and
the richness the the range of what how the mind is engaged support the
direction of the mind becoming lucidly aware and present the movement towards freedom
so those of you incline memorize it and it's memorization this kind of memorization supports concentration
and also supports the practice of it um so um
thank you and