there so hi hi everyone welcome to everyone joining
on zoom on youtube on an audio dharma asynchronously
later in time lovely to feel your presence to join the
sangha so nice just so lovely i've already my heart is already warmed up
with the hellos that um even though it seems like we're just
saying hello but it's it's an expression of human kindness that we show up
we show up and we say hello we say hello we say hi maybe we smile maybe we wave
human kindness everywhere just showing up with our heart
so see the theme for tonight is hello human kindness hello human kindness
it's actually um i'm borrowing this phrase from
a health network that's local here in california and i've seen their ads previously on various billboards and
buses and i thought huh how interesting hello human kindness and
and today just came up for me it came off for me hello human kindness ah
it's kindness is everywhere so if we say hello the same way that we show up and
we say hello and we get seen we get recognized we can we can also
recognize human kindness in so many places it's all around us it's within us
we can recognize them ourselves so
we often we often don't see it our minds focus on what's negative what people did wrong
what we did wrong and all the um ill will
not to say that yes wholesome intentions and then turning our minds towards the
wholesome always and and noticing what's unskillful is important and yet it is important to to
notice kindness so so let's do a little exercise
first look around wherever you're sitting look around the room where you are just take a look
okay now [Music] if i say
notice the color blue now look around
see where you see blue places you hadn't noticed before because
you were not looking for it ah there's more blue than i realized here look at that
a lot more blue
now what if i asked you to look to notice the color red
yeah ah it's actually kind of nice to notice
right to notice these colors these vibrant colors jumping out which i
hadn't noticed they're there before i do this with so many colors but the
point the point i want to make is it's here there there's so much in our field of
vision especially visually there's so much in our field of vision that we don't pick out for so our minds are
everywhere we don't we're not uh paying attention to colors but the
same way there's so much that we're thinking about and planning and and all
regretting that we don't tune we don't tune to human kindness we don't tune to
human kindness and it's all around us there's a vibrancy
it's like the vibrancy of these colors i'm going to choose red such a vibrant
color one of my favorite colors all around we won't notice the
vibrancy of human kindness so so the theme tonight is hello human
kindness both within ourselves outside inside tuning into it as if
we're tuning a radio maybe we don't hear it at all at first maybe we just had a really long hard day
and let's tune into the channel of human kindness ah letting our hearts be nourished
by this channel so that's the invitation for tonight and i'll give some guidance some
invitations and feel free to adapt them to
whatever works for you whatever is needed right now and um just one more thing to say for those who might be new
we always start with um [Music] settling landing the breath the body to
stabilize and calm the mind then then i open up to
the invitations so so without further ado
let's uh let's begin let's begin you need to shift or move your body
with kindness ask what this body needs in this moment
ah so that it can settle and be happy as happy as possible sitting for the next
30 minutes of meditation
so arriving here
hello body hello body hi
how are you what do you need dear what do you need
in this moment
let's see what answer arises
hello breath hello
body alone yellow feet
hello any tension
in my neck shoulders
forehead my jaw
my arms my hands ah
my chest
hello my heart whatever is arising whatever emotions
are present here i can release release around them
release a body [Music]
let go of the out breath make space
foreign
and if thoughts are arising the mind is moving from
the body to thoughts it's okay it's all right
hello thoughts hello thoughts can you say hello to
thoughts with kindness and those thoughts
can we say hello to the breath of the body again calming soothing this breath
as if this breath is a gift of kindness from the world
[Music] from the universe this oxygen
that keeps us alive
the right mix of oxygen and nitrogen
in breath
entirety of the upper
let there be the settling in your body
breath intertwined
with kind awareness
now i'd like to invite you if you would
as you stay embodied in the body with the breath feeling the breath in
the abdomen lowering the center of gravity
bring to your heart not to your head but to your heart space
someone who recently did an act of kindness no matter how small
and feel it in your heart space the kindness the goodness
the generosity of the act and not to think about it analyze it why
they did it or other motives no not
get heady just feel the goodness with your heart
hello human kindness this relishing in frosting
receiving it with your heart letting it land the goodness not getting in your own way
i don't deserve it too big to this to that none of that just
simply see what happens experiment
experiment with letting yourself fully receive this act of kindness
thoughtfulness care
whatever it might have been
so if you're breathing into your heart center letting your body relax
with this gift
no feeling of obligation just receiving receiving
is the biggest gift we can give others is to receive their kindness
graciously practice gracious receiving in this moment
maybe the words or the feeling of appreciation gratitude
or thank you these words bubble up
to your height
hello humankindness [Music] hello
nice to feel you
and gently opening up your heart wider
maybe there's another act of kindness thought from this care
maybe a phone call a friend or family member
i thought about you hello humankind
letting your heart open to appreciating that now
and you can open up if you like to another act of kindness
maybe somebody is making time for you has made time for you
sharing their resources their skills
their presence
their care
hello kindness hello
hello
and you can open up your heart just
allowing these kindnesses these gifts to arise
not so much going out and searching for them but letting them come up if they do
and if not then staying with the last one just staying and relishing
appreciating this is not a thinking practice it's a feeling it's an opening the heart
and letting kindness goodness arise
and appreciating relishing as the visitors who come and knock on
your door you open the door you say hello hello kindness hello human
kindness you don't go out searching all over town because no need
i'm gonna knock on your door just hang out be relaxed and spacious
in your heart space
you see sit with these so many kindnesses not from
just yesterday or today or earlier the week but maybe earlier in your life
arise so many gifts of kindness hello human kindness
not to think about it again just rest
best to take it slow so the mind isn't jumping from one thought to the next
stay stay
for a while with weather rises
and now you can continue in this way
or let's turn around and allow yourself to relish
your own kindness
appreciating your own kindness
maybe we start with you to yourself
as if you're a beloved other maybe you're feeding yourself
something healthy wholesome
or resting when you need to rest
or being gentle with yourself when you make a mistake
or if you feel sad you're kind with yourself you let
yourself be sad and feel the emotions
so many ways we're kind we can be kind to ourselves
it's choosing one
maybe you refer to yourself in terms of endearment
maybe you care for this body [Music] by brushing its teeth washing it
hello kindness
what if we saw these as acts of kindness not as
these boring things we have to do but if we saw them as acts of kindness
shifted the frame
now if you like opening up the door
and inviting to others
acts of care generosity thoughtfulness to others
letting yourself relish yeah this is kindness
hello kindness hello human kindness
maybe you're recently supportive to a friend
let yourself relish kindness
lastly you can also add welcome the door open
the door and welcome to acts of kindness you witnessed
can you appreciate someone doing for someone else
let them brighten your heart
acts of generosity care love
hello human kindness hello
so much kindness all around hello kindness
hello hello
as we near the end of this practice period
let all these acts of kindness everywhere to you from you
from others to different people all this kindness all around
requesting through the world beautifully beautifully
let it fulfill your heart
with gladness hello human kindness
all around through me
as an expression of my being [Music] those of others
more and more inhabiting living more fully into human kindness
may all beings everywhere no kindness
their own those of others
may kindness goodness
prevail in the world
may all beings be free including ourselves
thank you for your practice hello hello
humankindness so we have time
for reflections for questions comments what arose for you what did you notice
any aha moments perhaps to share for the benefit of yourself and others
as a gift any challenges to it's all welcome
and if you type in chat if you type to me privately i won't read
your name so it'll be private comment it's type to everyone i will read your
name you can also raise your zoom hand especially if you haven't
spoken for a while i'd love to hear from you reflections
hello hello what did you discover in this practice
plasma please hi um hi
a lot of the stuff that came up in terms of
when i was thinking of um you know kindness from me
and i was like oh this is things that are manifesting as a result of this practice that was
nice to see oh sweet that is so sweet thanks for
sharing that fosu so if i heard that correctly just realizing that many of the things that
are manifesting is as a result of this practice you're doing the the mental practices coming to fruition in acts of
kindness is that did i hear that correctly yeah pretty pretty much yeah yeah oh that's so beautiful yay yay
wow to celebrate that and as the buddha says whatever you um
you uh ponder you you reflect and ponder upon frequently that becomes the
inclination of your mind so as you ponder upon kindness that becomes the reflect
your inclination of not just your mind but the inclination of your heart and your body in acts of kindness yay
oh i celebrate that it's beautiful thanks for sharing that fossil and it's so true
so true rad i see your hand please
hi hi um so
yeah i feel like this practice was really um
really good for me at the moment because i've been having
like a really difficult past month i've been having like housing issues and
having to move like every week and stuff um
and yeah i guess i just realized um
yeah i think kind of when you're in that sort of situation it's really hard to receive
the kindness that people show you because you're kind of in that headspace of trying to figure out
um yeah it's like well what if it goes wrong or no like i don't need that i need this and
um yeah it just really helps um when you said to just drop into the heart and the
belly and just like receive it there rather than being in the head um
and even just the intention that people show to like the amount of people who have
offered that i could stay with them and stuff um it was yeah really um
heartening yeah oh thanks so much for sharing that
that is so beautiful to turn as you and and as you were saying of course it is challenging and
it's difficult moving frequently takes a toll takes a toll on the mind and always planning and new environment and as
you've shifted and receiving so much kindness oh my goodness i my heart feels
full feeling the goodness the the generosity of people who are supporting you and
offering you to stay with them how beautiful is that hello human kindness
how beautiful ah thank you for sharing that that is so sweet
thank you yeah that's lovely and i don't know if you wanted to say
something else i saw your hand moving your welcome yeah i just i guess i just wanted to add
um i was thinking about that um because i heard this
saying the other day of someone talking about joy and they were like you know there's no such thing as perfect joy
because as humans we're always feeling more than one emotion at any given time so
that thought sort of came to me as well like there's no such thing as perfect kindness either um but
to just receive the kindness that is there along with everything else exactly yes it's it's
just receive what there is and and that was another invitation i was giving at the time i was suggesting to feel into
the heart space not to analyze oh yeah this is a little kind it's a little thought you know it's a little selfish
it's like just just let go of all that just tune into the channel of kindness
and in that way actually now i'm going to suggest something completely different in that way you can feel into
the perfect kindness of it right if you if you really see that aspect it's like
earlier when i was suggesting look at look for the color red like well yeah there's a lot of blue and yellow and
maybe it's not pure but just i'm just gonna look at the red oh and it's beautiful it's perfect it's like oh my
heart my heart gets filled with joy so that's another
practice to bring in thank you for that radha beautiful graham from youtube says there is so much
kindness in the world that i take for granted uh thank you graeme for that
beautiful insight he has so much kindness and then we turn towards it and jerry says
it was a struggle to drop the unkind words and actions of others but then the kind actions dominated beautiful that's
lovely yay let the kindness prevail beautiful yeah
so so dear friends um let us transition to
to uh small groups practicing together um
with receiving and sharing simple human kindness with each other
this is a sandbox and especially if you've had a hard day or week or month just nice to just feel
into this this simple grounding practice and the invitation
for the practice is the groups will be roughly size of three
and each person listen carefully each person will speak only from their
own experience it's an i statement this is what this practice was like for
me or you can be silent when your time comes you can say pass and you say just one nugget if you have
five things to say you only say one of them then after you've said that
then you pass it on to the next person or the baton gets passed on and the next person will speak from their own
experience and then the next person from their own experience you don't ask questions you don't direct you don't
manage you don't work as a facilitator in the small group you just show up with your
own kindness sharing yours your own experience and receiving those
of others just stay close to your heart to your own experience okay
only i statements yes clarity yes so this way we can keep the
container safe for everyone not transgressing okay and again the way
you can show up with kindness tonight might just be holding space and being silent and really listening to others
maybe that's what's appropriate for you so so hello human kindness
whatever you'd like to share about this practice for you so creating the rooms
and uh here we go opening them take care of yourselves
take care of each other here we go okay
the rooms are closed everybody's back and we just have about a minute well actually not even
that but maybe just a quick comment if somebody who hasn't spoken has a quick reflection we'll fit it in before we
close any takers anything that revealed itself to you in the rooms
that was surprising richard what's up richard
hi quick i've been coming here for a long time
and i i've been waiting all this time for this feeling this feeling of meta to
overflow and warm my heart but
reflecting uh know every time you know when i just talk to people neighbors and people in
the building and whatnot there's simply just a genuine friendliness
and i guess that's so my meta has been here all along i just didn't know it
that's it richard oh my god i am so glad you raised your hand to say this
i so appreciate what you said that's exactly it that's metta it's been here
all along it's been waiting for you hello richard
i've been here all along ah thank you that warms my heart
that's profound thank you
thank you richard and thank you everyone for your practice for your kindness for
extending kindness to yourself to each other
deep bowes of appreciation so let's dedicate the merit of our practice may all beings everywhere
may they be free may they know the kindness that's
all around through all the kindnesses in their lives with their neighbors friends family all the
kindnesses all the meta overflowing may all beings be well may all beings be
happy including [Music]
thanks everyone